99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment in California and
Around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
You were listening to 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Lange
Wireless
Suning
My name is Erica Everhart and I'm the creator of the site you are listening to Los Angeles
And you were listening to Chicago you were listening to New York you listening to Montreal
And you are listening
To San Francisco
Azure color
Last year after the Giants won the World Series
I was out in the streets of San Francisco checking out all the different celebrations going on
And when I got home I was looking on Twitter I saw other people are posting links to
What's happening in their neighborhood people out
Lighting bonfires and
One thing that kept coming up was
Hey check out the San Francisco police radio on
Soma FM
So I started listening to it
It was cool and got bored after a couple minutes and started putting on some of my music in the background
And something about that there was like a Synergy between
The police scanner and like the music I was playing
That really sounds cool I want to find a way to share that
Oh that's right
And since it came online on March 6th 2011 I've spent what might be considered an indoor
Amount of time listening to
You are listening to
Some people think it's
Peaceful some people think
It's creepy I think it's mesmerizing
And it's elegant is in its Simplicity show me load the page there's a little Javascript file that pulls in an audio stream from Radio
Reference.com they provide the police radio audio
A playlist from SoundCloud which is music sharing site which has been screened by Everhart so that the playlist only has the
He's dreamy ambient soundscapes that complement the police scanner audio and also loads the background images
Coming from Flickr those are three main parts and they're all
Coming from site other than Maya and only possible because each of the companies provide
Simple web API application programming interface
You can create something new that might not be what the Creator intended
The design is being made by these sites the thing that you are listening to is exploiting
Is a relinquishing
A little bit of a control of their data in order for that data to spread across the web in ways that they
He never could have imagined
In this way outside an independent developers like Everhart can act as a kind of
R&D Department
Radio reference and Flicker and SoundCloud and the artists offering Creative Commons royalty free music on SoundCloud
Well did not imagine misuse of their content but they do have an API they just created a shareable architecture
Sure that Taps into a remix and culture
Or new ideas can flourish
Since the site is launched and
It word gets around it's been very popular
I've been contacted by lots and lots of artists from SoundCloud
And they all want to be part of it they all think it's cool
And they're asking me can I have my music included on your site
You know they're not getting anything out of it they're not getting paid there's no royalties there's nothing like that
But they are getting exposure I think these are people who
Posted their music out there because they wanted to share it with people
And now they're finding their sharing with lot more people
So
It's kind of like a virtuous
Cycle I got Square
I created something
I'm not looking for anything in return the artists are getting something out of it
SoundCloud and radio reference are getting something out of it because there are
More people are becoming aware of their services
Surreally at zero cost to me or to the artist
We're all building something together that kind of enhance is everyone
Designing for openness allows others to answer the questions that you don't have the answers
Did the greatest power maybe that it allows others to ask the questions that you haven't even thought to ask
99percentinvisible was produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco and the center for architecture and Design
To find out more
Enterprise it podcast
For the 99% invisible
. org
Hey guys it's Roman Mars again and we're done with the
Radio portion of 99% invisible Ron to be
Podcast bonus content of the show
Fat people
I seem to be pretty happy about so I'm going to try to keep doing this if I can add another question for Erik everhard
What about future plans
And he brought up
Are old radio piece that I did until we're going to listen to his answer about these Revolution and things he wants to do
Weather
You are listening to
Then he going to mention something very special to me here at the end of this clip
Eagle
Moving forward I'd like to find a way for
People to be able to contribute to this
Some experiment with more apis more
Servicesonline that allow people to
Share audio post their thoughts in their writings about stuff
And then I want to find a way to be able to integrate those into the site into the audio stream
So then ultimately Maybe
You can choose between
Police radio or
Maybe like the audio equivalent of Twitter what did you have for breakfast what was the last thing that you watched on television before you went to bed
Because I think it's all those things mashed together would create an even more interesting kind of
Mashup of experiences and sounds
Textures
I was looking at your website
And one of the things was
The Sting radio net
Which
That kind of I'm like oh look someone's already done this and it with different technology 20 years ago
But that kind of was right where I was aiming which was like
Be able to take people's little short
Snippets of speech
And just throw it in there and see what happen
So that thing you mentioned radionet which is by Max neuhaus
I was obsessed with especially
Inta 2005 I was working for the Third Coast International audio Festival
I had to track Max new house down
And interviewed him about his various public engagement art projects on public
Radio that he did decades before and so here's the piece I did for the program ReSound and so the voice
You're going to hear is the host of ReSound
Gwen Max I
And I'm and you're going to hear me talkin in pinot it's a
Was that six years ago so a little looser
It's a little you know it's not a perfect radio story
Anyway I hope you enjoy it and doing it at the other side of this piece
Basically
Radio is a one-way medium
We talk
You listen
Sure there public radio call-in shows that are meant to sound live
But more often than not
They're highly edited and reproduce
I hate to hear that
But it's true
The different brief moments in the history of the medium
Which Airways really were a free-for-all
Wheatley new forms of sound were born
Max neuhaus make sound work
Neither music nor events
He coined the term
Sound installation
Is Beni engine hide all sorts of new ways
The thinking about experiencing sound
A producer Roman Mars
Trent new house down in Italy
That Roman is responsible for the sound
Ivory sound
All music
Voices odd sound effect
Did you hear in between pieces
And that
I can tell you
Is no
Small desk
But when you actually hear Roman
On the air
Caulking
You know it's because he's become obsessed
What's something
To the show I create these mixes the sound collages
Comprised of layered elements that relate to the themes of the program and one of the elements in this mix.
Right now when I use a lot but to be able to hear it
Turn down some other stuff let's take down Transmissions from Saturn I don't know if you recognize those those are transmitted
The Yankee Hotel foxtrot Willmar
And the music
Right there
That's radio net
For 2 hours
Displayed on 200 National Public Radio affiliate stations
On a beautiful Sunday afternoon
Decomposition
With ten thousand contributing musicians
It's a sound entity really
I'm getting ahead of myself
What unit is part of the continuum
Broadcast works
By Max neuhaus
Starting with public Supply one
In 19
IMAX new house work with sound
Is an artist
And doesn't it
Sometimes even
I have done so for most of
My adult life so the last
Almost 50 years
I was asked to do an interview radio interview
WBAI New York
And I thought
Rather than doing an interview why don't I try to do work that way
For the radio
This is a knife
66 at that time there were no radio call it shows for the idea of connecting the
Telephone Network to the radio station
Which I wanted to do
Make it to a space out of the radio
Gastritis
Was unheard of and it was difficult to do in fact the engineer was so sure that we would have
So
So many bad words broadcast
That he refused to consider
Project accept an interview
So he said in the end he would put the
A microphone in the studio for 2 hours
And what
I put into the microphone was up to me
So I got 10 telephone lines installed into this
WBAI Studio
And built a kind of
Rube Goldberg automatic
Answering
System
Because they're
Waxing machines
Which allowed me to
Trauma
Homemade box I'll make mixer
Control
Pick up the phone and mix
Which I put into an amplifier and put a loudspeaker in
Front of his maker
When it came time to go in the air
Do it on the air
Call Oxford 7
Or Oxford 79526
Depart of public Supply
Give me a funny kind of parties that everybody that wasn't
Seeing each other everybody was listening
The word describing now is kind of a life
Was a wild
Live sound collage
People
Also hearing their own voices
On the radio was
Startling thing at that time
Not many people had type recorded So hearing your girl voice
Was
Revelation
Turn it it quite excited yes I mean
It was raw
Swearing
WPA
Do a couple iterations of Max new houses Publix
Supply including a Peabody award-winning broadcast on wfmt insha
Chicago with colors voices
Activated special
In addition to coming through
You clearly so that
What they were saying could I
Be understood
And what do people say when they're given the opportunity to be on the air for the very first time
The answer is
Kind of the same
Hi Mom hand-waving Goofy's or two things that they do when they're given the opportunity today
Years later a fairly new and compared to
Today
Much more experimental NPR
And OfficeMax the opportunity to do the exact same thing
Nationwide
Which brings us back
Tu radio net
National Public Radio prevent
Radio net
Alive Nationwide composition
By Max neuhaus
Radionet is B the music
In the case will be using
The National Public Radio Network
To actually generate a piece of music from
Found
Sewing material found in by
Anyone from anywhere
I think the most important thing for the listening to realize is that we're making a piece of music
And all one really has to do is listen with an open mind
NPR now invites you to become part of radionet dial any one of the following telephone
The point I was really fighting
Music could be made another way of this idea of really
Activating ale public in inventing their own music
You know it is from Mars
Radionet sounds different from Publix apply for a number of reasons
New house took advantage of the NPR distribution system of the time
Kafka round robin
Connected all the 200 station
This was normally used was that a station would feed
Program tell the other is by breaking into this round-robin telephone line
And sending it around the loop
Five cities
New York Dallas
Atlanta Minneapolis
And subdivided the networking
Each point having its own
Automatic mixer
Selected fractions
Of the sound
Toe beans fat in
By the phone call
Join the broadcast
Sounds phone into each City
Pass-through itself mixer
I started losing
With each cross country path
Each sound mean another layer
Overlapping itself
A different pitches
The Graduate
What is the activation of an entire continent into a sound transformation box
I was literally 1500 miles wide by 3000 miles long
5 ins and outs
Emerging in Washington DC
CarMax new house at
And mix them all together
Employment
5 headed animals
But it didn't
Spin off into a massive
Feedback loop
It was fantastic movie
I need to go from
1 station
20 mile radius 2
Continental
Amazing
What was NPR steak
Because it was live
Never heard it before
Imagine
It was risky and they were really in shock after
Is over
They didn't
Want to do it again
They were really terrifying
In the beginning there
Terrorize people because they are afraid to speak
One minute
30 seconds
Panic
Semi-regular
He's really quite
Pizza Hot
To listen to
But still 2 hours
For them
Primetime Sunday afternoon
On New Year's Day Sunday after New Year's
Attic really
But anyway I
I had them and they had me
If we were there for two hours
What day is it
Nobody talkin about a Repeat Performance 1978 is like God
We live through it we could have to cover I have to somehow but
They were in shock
NPR
Rihanna was definitely
A moment in time along with public Supply
But do you think they're
Tigger
Lessons for radio
Shoot Lee radio did take this idea
And it shaped it to fit it
Have you ever called a joke
It's on the other end of the spectrum at least
Two-way in a trillion
Jania
But out of call for college
You get
Immediately
What
Certain people who are willing to call in or thinking about
Even though it's it's very
Gold
Did moderated and that I think is very positive
I don't need all this work is that at the time Max neuhaus
Furbabies compositions
From being recorded
Who's idea was that
They existed as entities
That any listener should be able to modify
What they're hearing by contributing to the composition
Something that
Couldn't happen
It was a music
Courtney
He was very strict about the
No recording
Was to be married
Annie's best I can tell
Not one engineer
WBAI wfmt
Or national public radio
Listen to
Which is the only reason why they're available to be heard today
Because you can violate a lot of rules
You can turn a one-way medium like radio into a two-way communication device and synthesizer
You can put people's voices on the air unmoderated and unfiltered
But under no
Circumstances
Can you stop
A radio engineer
Recording a sound producer
I'm in Mars talking with sound artist Max neuhaus
The next Evolution Max neuhaus is broadcast work
Called Oracle
AU
Racl
And it's sort of an online version of radio net
But it's 24 hours a day and anyone can play
You can find a link
On the recent page
Thirdcoastfestival.org
Tell us the story of radio Net10 Max neuhaus and Max
Died a couple years ago I think he's just the greatest and so I'm really sad that he's gone
I have a link to IMAX new houses website as well as the Third Coast International audio Festival
That I work for 4 to 2 or 3 years
And other great and they have a program called ReSound that I helped work on for a long time
The website is amazing and they're just a great group if you want to stay on top of all the really amazing
Things in radio you should go to thirdcoastfestival.org
All right
That's a sale for this week
I'll talk to you next week with lots of cool stuff
I guarantee it
Take care
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
2 days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had something
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Every takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast.,