99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment in California and
Around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
If you were standing in the crowd for any of the presidential inauguration from Andrew Jackson
Dwight D Eisenhower
You have seen the solemn oath of office taken between 24 tall smooth columns
The East Portico of the United States Capitol building
When the columns were installed in 1824 the Sandstone slabs themselves that made up the column
Even before they were erected
What considered so important
But they were transported from the Potomac River to Capitol Hill
My human power alone
No lowly mules were deemed fit to moveset synchronoss
But they didn't have quite the same standing in 1958
They had been taken off the east
Restaurant when the front was
Extended
They were stored on along the Potomac
Crated
Slowly disintegrating
After the renovation of the Capitol The Columns all got the boot
The notion was horrifying to Ethel Garrett
And she conscripted her friend Betty Ray Elizabeth Sea Ray known as Betty Ray
And sometime in the 1970s they made it their mission to get the columns back on their feet
I thought this would be very simple
I mean who would say no
Do that people said the way they still belong to
Congress after ten years of meetings
Appear before various committees
More meetings
Have another meeting fundraising had to appear before the national
Capital Planning Commission Architects and surveyors
But we offer
The Columns were moved from Storage
From the area along the Potomac
They were put on trailers
And
Draft
I was in a band
Steal things
On mattresses old mattresses
And they've been brought to the National Arboretum
The Arboretum is a swath of greenery nestled in among the warehouses in gas stations at the edge of Washington DC
It's where the old Columns of the US Capitol still are today
When you're walking up to the columns located on a high area
In the meadow are there
Arboretum
Their Majestic they're huge columns
Courser free-standing they are really Majestic
And there's only one way to
Describing it
Majestic
I could I could see them approaching from the field and actually pretty majesti
The consensus seems to be that they look pretty Majestic
It's pretty spectacular that's radio producer Jess schreibstein
Taking of columns at the National Arboretum
On the crest of this very small hill
AR
I want to guesstimate a couple doesn't call him
Weather is Chrissy Moore
She works at the armory
So they have Corinthian
Tops
On these columns and
They're lined up
And a few rows
Very tall
I understand why people think that they're from Grease
Or from Rome because it actually looks like
Some old Greek ruins sitting on top of the hill definite
Distinct Granger about it
That you won't see much outside of Washington DC
Independent of their grand presentation The Columns hold a certain power
Even if they don't
Hold the roof
But not all of the old East Portico had a champion like Betty Ray
My directions say
Go downhill Into the Woods
Go down towards the bottom of the hill there will be no Trail don't worry keep walking
Several miles away from The National Arboretum
Where there's no visitors center there no commemorative black
Philadelphia trail that goes up into a ravine
And you go on that trail and then it'll large
Concrete bridge
Take the lower Forks to pass under the bridge
And then there's a clearing on the web
And here in the middle of the woods lies the rest
The capitol's East Portico the parts that didn't make it to the Arboretum
To the right of us
Are basically
Stacks and stacks
Comes
We almost could have walked right by I feel like
Who's our next
To some buildings Ellis
You know
Part of some building materials but if you look at it
More closely you see at the RX
Discover it in
This place is 100 square yards
Busted up architecture Maryland
Stone and granite and decapitated heads
Corinthian columns weathering in the snow
But it's arrangement
Oddly intentional the debts of
Building carefully stacked 12 15 feet high
With Wells and kasim spanning between
Is it just going to leave them here
Super sad the physical manifestation of the parts of history that didn't make
The car
Texas
Leaving here without the Rolling Meadow and historic backdrop
The ruins still managed
To be Majestic
I think if I discovered this when are the kids out of felt like I discovered the Lost World
Atlantis
This episode of 99% invisible was produced by me Roman Mars with Sam Greenspan and Jess tribes done with help from a
Melissa Lee and John Asante
The four of them have their own fledgling podcast called whisper cities learn more at whisper cities. Org
This program is made possible with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity at the project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco
Center for architecture and Design
More including cool pictures of big columns at 99percentinvisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com