99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
My friend Julia Barton that's me
And the editor of
Made in Russia
Unsung
And Lawrence apparent that sounds exactly like the building's door bus
No matter how hard we try cut out Lawrence
He denied
But maybe that's okay because I Dobbs new book on Soviet design is an omage the stuff of ordinary
Mary Soviet life
Cigarettes drinking glasses subway token machine
And it might be hard for Outsiders to see
What does seemingly random collection of Soviet consumer goods have in common
But I don't believe there's something that unites
Did you find this aesthetic you first need to realize that most of these items for
Rip offs of Western sources of varying
Qualities
They are imitation
By the way Lawrence the parent is imitating the door buzzer
One look at the items in this book even though they are Shameless imitation
You'll see the
The Soviet stuff
Unmistakably
Soviet
Take your Soviet soda machine in those
Carbonated drinks came not in bottles
But straight into a communal drinking glass
Something chained to the machine
In the excruciating Soviet arcade games were designed by the committee on amusement
Most Americans haven't even seen these artifacts but in a way we are responsible
Bass Crudo goes back to the kitchen debate
In the 1959 The Roosters what was successful American exhibit
In Moscow
Counterpart
Vice President Nixon showed Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev around the exhibit
We stopped in front of a model Suburban home to address an audience
Before New American color TV
There are some instances where you may be ahead of us
Chapel in the
Development of your of the rest of your rockets for the investigation of outer space
There may be some instances for example color television
In order for both of us
For both of us
My God I said that this bike cruise ship
Bombay
Send the recent success of Sputnik
The Soviets were humiliated
Buy all of Americas
Stuff
Cruise ship decided the Soviet people needed stuff to
But with a huge struggle for the Communist Party to switch Soviet factories from producing
Tanks and rocket
Gigaset.
And hair dryers usually the way it worked was you know some party guy with wood
Come back from a foreign trip and then
Bringing you know a German radio
Give it to the engineers make
And then they would just reverse-engineer at 2 and then they would look around for you know the guy who draws well
Can you draw okay if you do the logo and that would be the logo that
Would last for the next
40 years
Assistant produce a lot of strange stuff but sometimes the Soviets been better than the
Take the unbelievably cool magazine
Bow down before the glory of
12 chromosomes are supposedly based on something cruise ships all while in the United States a magazine with a record in it
I don't call it the original podcast
Taxi South Lake Public Radio
There would be an article in the magazine and then
Conscience
This could somehow illustrate the art
The sounds of the
The Foresters
Where or false
Songs of
Up some far-flung tribe or is this
What started happening over time was
The people who make this man
Had access to
Or something
Unbelievably awesome for the Soviet Union which is you know vinyl
Breast
They started slipping in a little pop music
Is it going there
It was the round tear out discs in Krogers or that gave Russians their first non bootleg recordings of everyone from Barbra Streisand
Send to Pink
Floyd to Michael Jacks
The main thing that unites the designs and made in Russia
They're often the only disease
Micah light off didn't pay
Pick from shelf loads of
Say different
Dat recorder
Most Soviets had one
The Vistana
The BK Electronica personal computer
Probably made Russian
Can hackers
The best in the world
Through its sheer awful
Nobody had any other choice
Far be it from me to
To suggest that this is actually a good thing
But it certainly simplifies
How to know another because
If you grew up in the Soviet Union interview
You're my age or older I already know so much about you
Including the song I put
To the bed at night
Do you know if you grew up in the Soviet Union
It it's just seared into
I can I can sing it
I think it goes
Booster
Gross gif
Used skis
This theme from a children's puppet show aired every night at 8
15 on Soviet television
You can't really
Call the crude animal puppets
Icons of Soviet design
But I don't put them in his book anyway
Step
Because of their bright eyes and worn out for
Krisha the pig and
Lapochka the bunny represent a lost universe
11 time zone
Closed off from the rest of the world
Making their own stuff in their own way
The tired toys are sleeping now
That's how we song
Goodnight Roman
99% invisible with produce this week by Julia Barton one of the great radio reporters and editors
She's also part of the
Oberlin College
Public radio conspiracy
She added a few of my pieces when I did some stuff for weekend American I swear every single piece I've done since then has been bad
Because of my contact with her
No kidding
You can find her at Julia Barton. Com
Buy me Roman Mars you can find me
Right here
All the time
Tell my kids I love them
This program is made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
The project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
Define a wink to Michael eye drops made in Russia unsung icons of Soviet design I'm very fine book
If I do say so myself
Or do you want to look at some pics of
Dove cool silver
Catch the 99% invisible
. org
Spokoinoi nochi glass
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com