99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Chicago
Is next do you want to stand out as a skyscraper in Chicago you've got your work cut out for you
At this corner
A zillion billion x
Never
Looked up at this building the Hancock Building there's the Sears Tower
Willis Tower
Yeah I'm not going to call it that
And then there's my friend Dan weisman's new favorite.
In the South Loop
A couple days ago I was at the cultural center
In Africa map
Chicago architectural landmarks
Billions of buildings
How is everything
And this building is not on it
Even if a building is designed by a prominent Architect by this guy everywhere
Who made the DC Metro
He's a big deal and even if that building has only three sides like a triangle from above
Like a grilled cheese sandwich
Cut in half diagonally
Irregularly Place long vertical window slats to like a
Punch card or a Scantron car it's still hard to stand out
As a skyscraper
In Chicago
I remember the first time I noticed
What is that building someone there was like
My name is Jack heart rate
I was the project manager
Campbell
Correctional Center
Which most people know at the Metropolitan Correctional Center or MCC Federal Detention Facility
Stay
When you're waiting to go up on trial in the federal courthouse
Just like two blocks away when it was built nobody much like the idea of a federal jail downtown
Didn't want this building built in the loop right across the street
The club called the Union League club which is one of the kind of fancy Elite
Clubs
In the city
If it were like we don't want prisoners you know mooning us front the windows of the jail
And it doesn't seem like it's going to be really good for
Property values so there was a lawsuit actually
Did they are legal misfortune
Had to bring the suit in federal court to the only people who are going to hear the suit
We're also the only people in Tonawanda being built
Are federal judge
And I think it took them about
12 minutes to get things kicked out of the Court it was impossible to get a judge that was
Favorability
The Architects and Harry Weese is group or tickled by the prospect as well in the building said
I think everybody in the office figured that you had a certain number of unindicted criminals in the city
Some did it got caught the MCC was just the people who have got caught
And because the Architects took it seriously that the inmates were innocent until proven guilty they thought
Places we can you know somebody look at this problem how do you make a a really small space
Cozy
Harry startup view this from the standpoint of the accommodations on sailboats
Furniture was all built in so you could really do pretty nice furniture
Built-in hardwood Furniture has he's really clean line the bed
CVS pictures
You know tonight
We built rooms to scale in our office and my chill
Used to come down and take naps and that they loved the Interior Space it was you know kind of
Manomet Pleasant the Cozy
And those narrow slit windows I mentioned earlier
Those are floor-to-ceiling windows to let in as much light as possible
But they're also built just narrow enough at 5 inches
So that they were within the federal guidelines of the time
And not need bars
It's not a bad Flex Tuesday
Hotel
Well we were doing a hotel at the same time and
This was better than
The hotel as far as the building furniture and all of that
Show me the hotel
Dan is a reporter tenacity like you wouldn't believe
But he just couldn't get the warden to let him into the MCC to see if all these beautiful Harry Weese Interiors
And Designs were still intact
So I called around
Thinking like who gets inside is
And I ended up talking
To a guy named Phil Kerrigan
If you would into the facility and talk to a random
Bunch of the tdz
They would be
I guess that that
Description
Or
Would it be one
Wolverine
Cut your throat
That is not the case
Phil Kerrigan has been going to the MCC for over 10 years
CC
And he goes and visits guys who don't have anybody else to visit them
Got to stop
It's
Very drab
Gunmetal Grey
You know the physical
Physical
Show off
The cells
Describe this
Knight's Tale
Hardwood built
Furniture
Gone
The bump shirt
Steel
Gutierrez truck
Dogwood
Have sunlight
The widows
Boston
Doesn't love love
Stephanie Inn
The gods of change
But none of them have
Are the timed and talk with Robert brugman who wrote a book about hearing
He was pretty bummed out
There's something about
Despacito
Harry Weese
Brilliant
Architect
And it seems like it's one of his signature
His concept
Exist but you know
He's going down all of the country
And that's true of them almost all Arkansas
Is a minor matter
The inside of a place
It was never meant to be public
Changed
It is after all not Hotel
Even if the warden had let Dan into the MCC it wasn't the MCC that he wanted to see
That matter
Wasn't the MCC that Harry Weese wanted either
99% invisible with Bruce this week by Dan Weisman and me Roman Mars this program is made possible with
Support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in Sanford
Francisco American Institute of Architects
Sysco in the center for architecture and Design
To find out more and see the punch card building for yourself go to 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast.,