99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
From the point of view of physics
It would seem a little less
Funny new ways to create new buildings with new technology has been the bread-and-butter of the Leading Edge architects
Since there have been
Leading Edge architects
Today my friend Nate dimeo hey Nate
Has the story of one of those men
A man who
Time on the Leading Edge was brief
But dramatic
Made it the creator of the Memory Palace the History Podcast that is all about being brief and dramatic
This is the story of visionary Daredevil architect Bradford Gilbert
Bradford Gilbert at Spanish Square close to the ground
23 he took a job is the architect for the New York Lake Erie and Western Railroad
Who's 1878
As an older man Central Station
Central location
The places you waited to get places where things actually happened
But buy ticket for Manhattan or St Louis Arch
Can you can find other Architects building more impressed
Thanks
6 + 8 + 10 story structure
Mammoth blocks of stone and brick and wrought iron
Made for the kings of the modern American Insurance in
The emperor is of import
What's an export
John Noble Stearns made a lot of money importing
Silk anyways looking to make a lot more in real estate
He bought some land in a prime location
850 Broadway
But there was a problem
Dwight was only 21 and 1/2 feet wide
There are rules that dictate what you can build and how
Rules of physics and rules of men who sit on various bureaucratic boards and body
And those rules dictated that if Stearns wanted to build one of those 10-story towers that were all the rage in 1888
You need to build walls of stone and brick
That were five feet thick
That was no for an interior that was only 11 ft wide
Play stuff you need for a hallway a few for a bathroom
Couple fur coat closet another for some filing cabinets in an umbrella stand
He asked me the quintessential modern Titan of American industry
Torque in a dark cell better suited for a dark ages Monk
During diastole the best dark
Extra solution
They all told him it couldn't be done
Everyone except Bradford Gilbert
The in-house architects of the New York Lake Erie and Western railroad had a theory
Hundreds of tons of cars in cargo we're hurtling over
Everyday
What if you turn one of those bridges on its head
What if he built a bridge up
Instead of out
Hold strength if he did this
The walls wouldn't have to be fine people
They could be just dine in
20 foot wide office
Places that would create
Quintessential modern American Titan
Reverend stretch out of blacks
Volume 8 is rent check out to John Noble Stearns
Architect
Came in from all over the country
To watch the tower building rise
Deport over Gilbert's blueprints
Gilbert and Stern
Beg Gilbert to change the plan
But he refused
He said he was so confident in his design
Good movies off
2 floors of the building
You would have the farthest
The first stiff Winds of a hurricane blew into Manhattan on a Sunday morning 1889
The tower building stood
Nearly complete
People lined the streets to watch it
Men pursue the crowd
And began to climb
When Bradford Gilbert reach the top of his Tower
The wind was whipping through its skeleton frame it more than 80 miles an hour
He called out to the center of the building
Pulled from a bag
A rope
With the lead weight attached to one end
You tied the other two a girder
You toss the way down through the open floors below
When you called his way back down
He found the lead weight
Hang in there
Stocksdale
Held up by a building that wasn't going anywhere
4 years after
Gilbert could Fitness Penthouse office in the still-standing tower
And stretch out of
Watch a whole city
Stretch ever higher
Taking his idea
In building on it
99% invisible is produced this week by Nate dimeo I'm your host Roman Mars
This program is made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San
Center for architecture and Design
To find out more and get a link to Nate Tomatoes brilliant Memory Palace podcast
Go to 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had so
Something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com