99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If I was a flower growing wild and free
Honey bee
Two teenage girl named Juno is walking down the
The street with a half empty 1 gallon jug of Sunny D City
Cris beverage in one hand
She passes a tree and everything becomes animated
It's kind of a Lo-Fi on
Polished Xerox
Copy animation
Inspired by punk rock music flyer
How long did you have that
Main title music
It's still there isn't
Yeah I think so
You know what they're using it at some commercial
These days
When I heard it it was I just got flashbacks
Crazy
The title sequence immediately establishes Juno's quirky worldview
Liberty store
Months
Yes
Has a title designer
Very important that the music that you use in a sequence is something that you love that you really enjoy working with because it can be
Ross otherwise
My name is Garrett Smith and I am a film title designer Gareth and his partner jenilee did the titles for Juneau and Upland
We are among others my name is Ian albinson
And I am the founder and editor-in-chief
Art of the title
A website that curates
Title design
Inside is awesome it's a completely different
Set of people that
Do the work that do titles
People don't always realize that
And I always seem to be always surprised that I was some actually thought about this
Paid to design into work on Sunday
Yeso
Connected to the
Fundamentally a title sequence is a presentation of a legal document to the audience
A list of names of the crew and actors in everything who are associated with a film and then there's be more interesting in
An artistic reason
But I don't seek
Establishing tone and perhaps a storyline but there are rules what you're doing in studio film
The designer or the company will gets a
A document that's
You know maybe 10 to 15 pages long if you just read out the text
The title sequence easily on a single page but of course it says 15 page document
And besides title
There is several paragraphs
Text about how each title needs to be
Be treated like maybe in some sequences the lead to actors require their names
Bigger than the other titles
And they'll actually list in the
Exact percentage size that it needs to be bigger than the other titles in the sink
Set very specific and it's in as a designer it gets very frustrating and challenging to deal with this because
It feels very limiting
To need to have every single title in the sequence be exactly the same size
When it comes to Innovation and influence and title design there are two words you need to know
Saw
Bass
He was a major Benchmark in terms of realizing that you could have good design in a title 6
Saul Bass
Came along
It was a designer that started to work on more promotion for films and then started to
Bring his illustration and Design
Style
2 oz
Ethicon number
Pieces if the title sequences of Saul bathroom immediately
Spring to mind do yourself a favor and Google
Anatomy of murder
The man with the golden arm or psycho or
Vertigo
So good what I love about
Some of his earlier title
Princesses if you look at them they're basically animated film post
But a lot of that solve a style faded away in the 80s you know the 80s
And the 90s
He started to get The Branding idea with films
And so a lot of
Title sequences
Once a much title sequences but we're just over the logo the song
You're creating a brand
Back to the Future
Where's it's a very iconic logo design and you have a lot of that
I late 80s and early 90s
You didn't see as many
Complete opening title sequences
Beetham stand-alone or servants good with the song
Which is not done very much
These days
Nuts have been a lot of films where there's just a big
Logo that you see on the
But then we hit the second major
The movie Seth its titles were created by Kyle Cooper instead of reintroduced the idea that
The title sequence could be its own thing
What is what
Bastard
Yunnan decades earlier
The title sequence of 7 works as both a standalone vignette and is a vital introduction to the grimy and obsessive
CEO of the movie
Serial killer in 7 doesn't appear until two-thirds of the way into the film
You really get to know the killer right here in the first 2 minutes
How Cooper took us inside his head
The most memorable
Title sequences are really ones were
You know there's a great movie after if 7 was put in front of some
You know terrible movie that no one saw it wouldn't have moved on to influence generation of title designers
One of the in Albertsons favorite titles
Sequences is another couch
Cooper creation
The island of dr. Moreau
Who's the one that
Check the in in the head and made him start noticing titles in the first place
But if you were smart
You probably didn't see
The island of dr. Moreau
And you don't know how cool the titles
But every human on earth over the age of 20
Knows the name of Gerrit Smith's favorite titles
The TV title sequence for cheers I can watch that
Endlessly
I remember liking it before I was a designer had anything to do with design so
I was trying to put my finger on why I like it and of course the great theme song on
Makes a big difference
But it also just has lovely typography very simple
Lovely typography and
The
Editing of the sequences fantastic is it just captures the entire tone of the television show and in 30 seconds to
Tears is a montage of historical drawings and photographs
People enjoying themselves
In bars
And what they do
Underneath eats of the title cards for the ACT
I actually find Historical image that does sort of
Suggest that character in the television series
The reason I enjoy it is warm
And friendship
And that really comes across I think of that title
There are a lot of fans of film title design out there was trying to figure out why that is and I feel like film title design more than
Other sorts of
Design has a bit of a longevity
Because it is committed to film
Is it a lot of design
Is
Commercial or Prince and it kind of
Is designed to exist for a week or two weeks
Anton just
Vanished from the face of the planet where is Bill design you really do have to think about what is this going to look like in 25 years
You hope that the movie you're working on is going to be one of those movies that's going to be seen many years from now you know and it has a kind of hold up over
Time
99% invisible was produced this week by Marilyn Mars with
Support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7
Local public radio in San Francisco
The American Institute of Architects in Sanford
And the center for architecture and design for videos and links to all the titles we talked about in this episode
As well as a kick-ass Montage of Kick-Ass titled edited together by Ian albinson
Go to the website is 99% invisible
. org
I want to do a little social media outreach
Before you go
If you could go like this show on Facebook that would mean great deal to me
Because
There's this other project
Actually really Noble call the 99%
And I just want to get more fans
There's like a thousands of thousands and thousands do you like on average like
And 12000 are you listen
Weekly
And I
Can I have a
Almost 700 fans on Facebook so I think we can do better
Okay that's one
The other one is
If you would take the time to review
Fish show in iTunes
You would not
Leave the impacted has it you're like a Nielsen family
But you get to choose yourself
When you
Reviews up in iTunes that represents Millions
Of people at school
Razee
The rankings I go up instantly
When I get one review in iTunes
So
If you could do that too
Your five stars
Very popular
That would mean so much
Alright thank you 99 percentile
We'll talk next week
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com