99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% into the
If you're standing on the sidewalk
The New York Financial the
In the shadows of glass skyscraper
You definitely don't feel like you're at the seaside
But had a few blocks south and suddenly you're at the edge of the continent
Looking out at the water
That's pretty sure Emmett Fitzgerald
There are ducks and seagulls
Ferry boats ready to take you Island top
Writer Paul Greenberg moved into an apartment down here over a decade
And up until that point
Like a lot of New Yorkers I didn't really pay that much attention
To the Sea
If I want to go to the ocean I would go to
Marthas vineyard Long Island
But then he started noticing all these Maritime building
Like the old Fulton Fish
Where fishermen used to sell their catch to rest
I certainly was her to confront with the fact that
New York Manhattan is really a very buccini kind of place
Greenberg actually writes about the ocean for a living
His most recent book is called American Cash
And he started to research the relationship between New York City and the sea
But then in 2012 something happened that made that relationship impossible to ignore
Hurricane Sandy
Crashing on shore
Winds now at 90 miles per hour and this
The storm is so big so bad
60 million America
Ken's will philia
Power just take a look out here that is the Brooklyn Bridge and look at how those
Are whipping the river around
Hurricane Sandy storm surge inundated neighborhoods throughout New York City
See water poured into the street
Putting out apartment buildings and filling the subway tunnels
Greenberg and his family waited out the storm in their tent floor apart
We sat there in the storm hit and things started to rock and roll
Then everything went black Sandy knocked out power across lower Manhattan
The day after I immediately wanted to get a sense of what it was like
So he walked down to the water
Passed a bunch of bars and rest
And when you
Peered in the windows
It looked as if there'd been a horrible bar fight
Because the water come in
Flooded up to eight or nine feet
Have thrown all the chairs and tables up in the air
But as he surveyed the damage Greenberg also started to notice things about his neighborhood
That he never had
Turns out that Broadway and I live on Broadway
Is it Ridgeline
It's the high point between east and west
And when
Hurricane Sandy hit
Lower Manhattan
Safer and safer and dryer and dryer
Closer You Are
Broadway
He says the storm forced New Yorkers to see the relationship between their City
Much more intimate way
Nothing acquaints you
With your city's topography like
Living in the eye of a hurricane
And feeling that water flow up in and rise up and literally start to swallow the city
Sandy took the lives of over 100 people in the United States and cause upwards of fifty billion dollars in damage
Who's the second most expensive storm in US history
Are the reason why the storm was so destructive
Has to do with climate change
Scientists have calculated that because of sea level rise driven by climate change
Sandy flooded in additional 27 square miles
Unaffected 83000 more
Then it would have otherwise
There is a wake-up call here
And there's a lesson
He learned
This is Governor Andrew Cuomo
Speaking in the storm's aftermath
There's a reality that has existed for a long time
That we've been blind
And that is
Climate change
Extreme weather
Call apus
Do well in our vulnerability
It's undeniable but that the
Frequency of a
Extreme weather conditions
It's going to be a
Rethinking
Redesign of how we protect
This metropolitan area from this increased
Frequency
Architects and Engineers are looking at different ways that cities like New York and redesign their interest
To prepare for more extreme Storm surges
There's talk of floodgates
Massive sea wall across the entire Harbor
But Paul Greenberg says that
One of the Soul
Solutions for New York's future
Might lie in it
Will Sasso New York
In its natural state was set up
To deal with big storms
New York was built at the mouth of the Hudson River
In that fertile Estuary environment was filled with all kinds of marine life
1 Majestic creature in particular
Shape the landscape
Decimated probably in the trillions
Avoid stirrers surrounded New York City
Before European colonization
We now think of as the New York City Harbor
Was a veritable oyster Kingdom
Some scientists think it contain nearly half the world's oysters
And they were an important part of the ecosystem
Oysters are filter feeders
And they help keep bacteria levels in check
And in addition to their ability to filter the water
Oyster student huge amount
To buffer the city against
Storm surges
Because oysters are kind of special
They are unique among
Mollusks in that they build in three dimensions
So there really architects in a sense
Oysters like to grow on top of other oyster
Actually since the chemical basicness
Oyster shell
And they will see directly on top of other waster so you get these aggregations these clumps that build build build
Belt eventually they build up into massive complex restructure
Kind of like coral reef
Oysters really are
The coral reefs
List of temperate zone
Oyster East covered over 220 thousand acres
The Hudson River St
And sometimes they grew as high is 20 ft tall
Like coral reefs they cut down on Coastal erosion
And we're home to all different kinds of fish
And just as coral reefs help protect many Tropical Islands from Hurricane
Oysters protected New York City
They broke up large waves before they could crash onto the shore
Below the surface
The rough texture would increase friction
Slow down the water
And so annoyed her wreath
Spread out over many miles
Well actually
Seth the wave energy of waves passing over it
Most people don't associate New York City with oysters today
The back in the 1700s
They were what New York was known for
Oysters
We're absolutely Central to the identity of New York
You know if somebody were to say I'm going to New York that would say Enjoy the oyster
This is Mark kurlansky
Author of many books
Including an environmental history of New York City called
Big oyster
Kurlansky says that before colonization indigenous Lenape
People a lot
And when the Dutch arrived in the area
They found an oyster Paradise
You could just walk down to the shore anywhere
Certainly in lower Manhattan
Where everybody was living but
Anywhere
And
You don't break off a few Isis
And that's exactly what they did
Everybody in New York
Oysters
It was said that the only thing the poor people ever got to eat with oysters and bread
But it was also something that rich people
How do unusual in food history to have
The rich people food in the poor people food be the same at
Same time
Oysters were sold in Street carts and Bar
But also fancy restaurant
And they were served in all different kinds of ways
I was there were lots of things they were like oyster loaves
Send
Oysters with different kinds of
Sauces and they were oyster stews
Discarded oyster shells piled up in
Huge Mounds outside of shocking houses in restaurants
They were so plentiful
That Builders began using oysters as construction material
Shows were burned crate lime ground up for Mortar
Were used to pave streets
Prince's Pearl Street in lower Manhattan
Call Pearl Street
Originally paved with crushed oyster shells
The demand for oysters was so great that it eventually out
Scripps New York's Bountiful Supply
The Erie Canal and the railroad opened up new market
Well nature could not produce enough oysters for the all the place
Shipping
A lot of places it was more than the natural bed
Provide
By the mid-1800s New York natural oyster population had been depleted
Humans had nearly eaten the city's protective shellfish barrier out of existence
But that wasn't the end of oysters in New York
When I started to run out of oysters in New York city seed from the Chesapeake Bay
And they planted these baby oysters
On Long rope
Strong in Rose throughout the shallows at the harbor
Farming oysters works
Quite well and it is kind of the next launch
Magical staff
Need more oysters than grow there with nature you just grow some of yourself
Oyster farming continue throughout the 19th century
And by the 1880s the city was producing over 700 million oysters per year
But there was a problem lurking in the water
4 years
City had been dumping industrial pollutants and sewage straight into the harbor without a second thought
It didn't seem to register with people that dumping raw sewage on a food supply would be unhealthy
It seems sort of intuitive to me
They didn't really they didn't worry about that
That is until the early 1900's when New York was hit with deadly outbreaks
Cholera and typhoid
Public Health officials were able to track the disease is back
The source
Turned out that most of these epidemics are coming from
And so one by one the city started shutting down the Oyster Bay
Which was really upset
Setting for New Yorkers
It was huge
Front Page News every time they closed
Oyster Bay
And there be all these articles
About how we have
To do something about this
We're losing
Heritage
Lucy hair oysters
We have to stop this
I think somehow
Didn't get it stop
New York closed its last remaining oysterband off the south coast of Staten Island in 1927
Water quality continue to deteriorate until oysters
Could no longer survive
Water was so acidic it would actually actually through the shelves
By the middle of the twentieth century New York's world famous oysters were all but gone
Leading the sea bottom bearing
And the City
Exposed
Pollution continues to be a problem in New York but in 1972 Congress passed the Clean Water Act
Which regulated the waste being dumped into waterways
And little by little water quality in the harbor has improved
Now oxygen levels are high enough
Sports shelter so theoretically
We could have shellfish again
Throughout the day this is Paul Greenberg
In his book American catch
She documents several different groups who are working really hard to try and bring back the New York oyster
There are a lot of obstacles in their way including
FDA rules which makes it really hard to plan toys
And the fact that they're just
Isn't enough wild oyster larvae in the water anyway
The biggest challenges is actually an architectural
Because
The physical landscape of the harbor has totally changed
We've been dredging the harbor
Turn over
150 years now
I went
From an average depth
20 ft two places where
Now it's more than 50 ft
And the bottom looks very different
Right now our Harbor has a
Flat Muddy Bottom
But you know if you were to look at say 1850 1880 this would have been
Extremely kind of rough ER
Three dimensional mosaic
This is Kate orff
She's a landscape architect and founder of the firm skate
Beast in Manhattan
And she is the author of the new book towards an Urban Ecology
She also just became the first landscape architect to win a MacArthur genius award
An orc says that a flat Muddy Bottom just does not work well for
Oysters
There's no places are very few places for oysters to grab onto and to attack
Right now there's some oyster larvae floating around out there
But they don't really stand a chance
Any oyster that
Lands on the bottom of the base bed will then immediately be covered with soap
Do we need to
Lift those oysters off of the bay floor and we need to provide substrate for these creature
Pictures to attach onto
That challenge gave orphan idea that spawned one of my favorite portmantos
Oyster tecture
The concept was to build giant Nets made of fuzzy Marine rope
And Elevate them off the seafloor
They would then see the net
Oyster larvae and let the oysters grow from there
So it agglomerates in the sense of becoming a mega structure at Scales up out of
Very small organisms
With a relatively small architectural intervention you could have a new piece of protective interest
An artificial oyster
Which in turn would
Filter the water
Slow the water and create a safer relationship with that water
Kate orff debuted her oyster texture proposal in 2010 as part of an exhibit at the Museum of Modern
Art called Rising currents
And it was a speculative
Check that sparked a ton of conversation
But it was never actually built
Did Hurricane Sandy brought new attention to sea-level rise and open new funding avenues for Coastal resilience projects
In 2013 the federal government launched its Hurricane Sandy rebuilding task force
States in architectural competition
Call rebuild by Design
Escape
Kate Works Architecture Firm
Submitted an oyster Centric proposal called living Breakwater
Receive $69 at funding and will be carried out for the governor's office
The storm recovery
Nailscape is in the process of Designing artificial oyster Reef break Waters off the south coast of Staten Island
Staten Island was particularly hard hit by Hurricane Sandy
This is Gina worth
Another one of the Architects from scape
Explaining the choice of location
And the wave action from The Surge
Landed right on Staten Island and really dramatically impacted
The plan.
Staten Island was also one of the epicenters of New York historic oyster economy
So it's it's not the first time
That people have been trying to
Cultivate and expand oysters within the bay
You know hundreds of years ago they were doing it for food production and today we're trying to do it for a more robust and resilient
Shoreline
The design has evolved a lot from The Original Oyster texture Proposal with the Marine rope
The plan now is to build a necklace of offshore Breakwater
Out of large Rock
A special material called Eco concrete
Which shellfish like to grow on
They will then see the breakwaters with oysters
So they grow into reefs
Much like a natural oyster Reef the living breakwaters are designed to slow down the water
And break up dangerous waves
Before they reach
The shore as the oysters grow a really help
Add fractions the water column and and break waves
The living breakwaters should reduce Coastal erosion
Build up Beach
And make storms last names
Modeling by scientists at the Stevens Institute has shown that the breakwaters could have reduced the height of waves during
By 326 ft
But they won't keep flood water out of Staten Island all together
And they're not meant to
Breakwater's let the water through
We can reduce the wave action we can reduce the intensity and the velocity of that water
But we live in a coastal Edge
And wants to design a way to make that Coastal Edge safer and healthier
Both for humans and for marine life
In addition to reducing waves and filtering the water
The living breakwaters will provide
Some of the habitats that oyster reefs once did
Staten Island historical mysteries were filled with all these nooks and crannies were juvenile fish like to hide
With the help of marine biologist
The architect's design pocket
It's within the Breakwater structure
They call them Reef Street
So within the reef Street
Juvenile Fisher able to come into these kind of underwater canyon
And feed in the street
And shelter and hide from predators in the structure
Where says that as a landscape architect
I think your clients are usually people
But we're also trying to think about who are our underwater clients
Who are the fish species that might use the system like
If you are a fish swimming in the water
What would look like a safe
Play like a totally different mentality to have when designing than what a person looks for
Construction hasn't begun yet on the physical structure of the Breakwater
But some of the oysters are already growing
Nightwish is growing over here
This is Asia Salgado
A recent graduate of the New York Harbor
On Governors Island
The Harbour School runs a program called the billion oyster project
Which aims to restore oysters throughout the harbor
And in the process teach young New Yorkers all about the Marine
Asia is standing next to a tank
Filled with white shell
Soaking in carpet water
They're actually leftover shells from rest
So we'll go around and we'll collect
Shelf
Different
And on the surface of every shell
There are little oysters growing
Utilities big brown dots over yeah
Those are always
They look like little blobs
Brown jelly
But if you get really close
You can see the beginnings of an oyster
You can try to tell on this one this one has like stripes on it that's how you know what that's like it's
Don't shout slowly growing
I want to gets bigger obviously it'll look like one of you show
But
Getting there
Chloe
The billion oyster project is an official partner on the living breaker
Meaning that millions of little brown balls of Goo grown by Young New Yorkers like Asia
Will soon be protecting
Staten Island
The governor's office of storm recovery is scheduled to begin construction of the living breakwaters in 2018
The billion oyster project will work with local high school
Schools on Staten Island to monitor oyster growth over time
Add healthy Reef can grow very quickly so and we're very optimistic that by say
2025 we would have a pretty
Robust
Teresa stump going
Kate orff says that even if they're successful they aren't going to return the coastal environment
The way it was before
No
Can do that
The creating something totally new
Part ecosystem
Part info
North hopes that they Inspire other living infrastructure
Projects
But she doesn't think that oysters are going to save New York
Climate change
There isn't any one solution
To a problem so immense
Funplex
Researchers at the organization climate Central recently ranked New York as the most vulnerable city in the United States
What's the sea level rise
With / 426 thousand people living in zones that could face serious flooding by 2050
When you start projecting out further than 2050
Scale of a problem becomes hard to fathom
I mean it's really hard to frankly to be optimistic
We're on track for pretty rapid sea-level rise and you know can we kind of come together
Gather and
Proactively see this is an Urban Design opportunity
And not
A force that just died
Displaces thousands of people with
Economic means and who are less fortunate I don't know I think it's going to be a real challenge
Orsi's the living breakwaters project
As a step toward a healthy relationship between the city and the sea
But to protect New York and other coastal cities in the long-term
There are going to be a lot of other interventions that will need to be considered
Any new development on Coast
Lifting existing buildings up
And eventually in some places
Retreating literally from
I'm flood-prone areas and an
Can we have those hard conversations
I certainly hope so
I hope so too
Because New York is a city by the ocean
And the water
Is only getting higher
Oysters aren't the only non-human architects
And that gives us a tour through the extraordinary Builders of the animal kingdom
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again
Again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Because I'm in the studio with Emma
Fitzgerald
PSN in the Beast
You talk with Paul Greenberg and he
Talk about oysters
Behaving like Architects as they build these massive structures
Shoreline
Migos thinking about other types
So architecture that is not made
Spyhuman
I mean I think I feel like
Architecture
And then the other building and structures and buildings is sometimes
Thought about is something that
Separate
Humans from the beasts
A lot of my favorite artists
Pixar
Weight on stomach
Is a lot of different
Samples of Animal Ark
But let's
Trial try to do a couple from from different Animal Kingdom so to start with the mammals
We've got to go with
With beavers
What are some of the most obvious example but they really are
Pretty special architect
First of all they build PC
Incredible houses
The Lodges out of sticks and mud and they've got you
ESchool underwater entrances
Mi amor amazingly they completely re-engineered
The landscape by cutting down trees with their teeth
Damn
Is that
Essentially will turn you know what's a river
System into a peaceful Pond for them to live in
And and I was sort of looking into this and I found this one scientist
Think that they've discovered the largest beaver dam in the world in Northern Alberta
Canada and its its
Which
Is a larger than thin
Yeah human dance with large gray Hoover Dam
Set this was built in / many / like multiple generation
Sounds of beavers Vino different families contributing to the
Misfits mask
Sedan to create sort of a little Beaver Paradise up there in in Alberta
Why would think
Generations
Remarkable
Switch
All right so moving on to Insects their tongues of great examples of Android architect
But I'm going to go with
Termites
S1 termites bill
Giant Mounds out of mud
All over the world really in a lot of dry climates
Africa in Australia and South America
And and you can get your shoes they can be upwards of like 30 ft tall and mmm really why
He's really really really large structures
And if you think about that relative
The size of a
A termites body it's like
Even more impressive
Tall structure
Interino for a termite that's
If you serve scale that up
2R size
It would be something like close to a mile high so they really are
Building
Incredible
Dylan Sprayberry
My favorite thing about
Termite Mounds really does
They exist
Really to provide ventilation
The termite colonies The Colony exists even under ground and spreads out beneath
You know over a greater distance than it's just
The termite Mound
But if you get really really hot underground
Especially in these dry climates and so they'll build this structure upwards and
It's super porous
Senso
Cool breezes
Catch
And it's
Built in such a way that it ventilate
The entire colony
Keeps them and it helps them regulate their temperature
Which is just a pretty amazing
Is level of innovation for a tiny insect
They been digging and just live in
It really is a purpose-built solution to solve
Yeah and their end anytime
Of different animals and obviously it's like
It's not it's not like a single person who has an idea like solution to a problem is like
Evolutionary solution of an adaptation that they developed over a long period of time
Walkable to me I don't know either
That's amazing
Alright so this is our last one is is my my personal favorite really does feel like the Artistry of it but
There's this bird in that lives in the forest of New Guinea called the vocal cup
Bowerbird a bottle cop is my my personal favorite
And it's totally unassuming looking birds like a little brown
Looks kind of like a sparrow
So this is unassuming bird but
The male bowerbird in order to get
Attention
They will spend
Several years
Building these elaborate
Structures called Bowers
And there really aren't there like they're so beautiful. Like these
They're like these beautiful fat
Tents
That they
If they construct using little twigs and sticks
But they're so carefully done if you came across one
In the forest you would like you wouldn't even consider that a bird made that it looks like
It was designed by like
Little Ferry architect or something and and yeah the end and then off in the
Carpeted with a Mossy carpet
Front
Locked up with
Chew stick
Set the entrance
And and then decorate
It in these crazy ways will go in and get
Flowers
Build little piles of flowers
Fairies
I'm all kinds of especially things that
Colorful to add color to the Bower
And then it's
All of this is all of this year's of
Of me of building work is all just
This one moment when they're attempting to catch the eye of
Female bowerbird
2 hour look
Athena will come in there might be like more than one of these Bowers in it and I
Given part
The fluorescence show like
Decide who her favorite architect is
Comforters
Alright well thanks for giving us a guide to animal attacks
Yeah my pleasure
Visible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald
Mix anti production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is the senior producer
Percocet is the digital director
Marissa team includes Delaney Hall
Avery Johnson
Darren Massa and me
Menards
We are brother did 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia
From PRX
An independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all a pot
By the mall at radiotopia. FM
We are supported by the Knight foundation and listener donor
Kitchen whatever they can to keep us making the best audio in the world
You can buy the show enjoyed discussions about the show on Facebook
You can't win me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
When Instagram Tumblr invited to
But if you were thinking I need some more 99p I in my life
We have all the old episodes available and new articles about
Top design every couple of days
Our beautiful website
What's 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com