99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the early 1950s Sam Moore and his family left rule Arkansas looking to start a new life
They planned on moving to Chicago
We were on our way to Chicago with all I worldly possessions and I dog spot
And we start off in my Granddaddy's 53 dynaflow Buick
And got the same Lewis and ran out of gas
And instead of continuing on to Illinois
Where's family just decided to stay
They settled in a middle-class area called The Ville
St Louis was segregated and the bill was one of the only African-American neighborhoods in the city
The residence of the best of it
Metro Porter Zach Dyer
Black owned businesses thrived in the neighborhood became one of the most prosperous African American communities in the country
Do you mind if we just roll the windows up
Just for that recording
Okay I turn the air on
Seymour's dad got a job as a bricklayer
And help build some of the beautiful stately brick homes in this area
He was a great break that he didn't quite a few jobs around this town I shall see some of my dad's work
Oh wow really
Beautiful homes
Triple break three-story two-story buildings
I will cost
A million-dollar soon to duplicate
The driving around the Vail today
We're more has lived for almost his entire life and is now the alderman
Neighborhood looks very different
We pull up in front of a couple of old houses
Hold on one sec
How many days to build a look at that building
You can see clean through it
From the street the building facade look normal
It's a two-story brick home sitting on a white Limestone base
Rounded brick Arch his friend the first-floor windows
Had just around the corner and you can see that the entire sidewall is Miss
The bricks are just
Gone
You can see straight into the room
Each with a different wallpaper
We call him doll houses because you can look inside of them and see what's going on
Ramona little girls play with the doll house and put the furniture and you can see it
Jan in the wall
In the past 50 years the city of St Louis has lost more than half its population
Vacancy has skyrocketed in the Ville
Another neighborhoods on the Northside
Entire neighborhoods here are just green pasture
Punctuated by the occasional dilapidated building that slowly surrendering to the landscape around it
Alderman back in 2007
He started to get calls from his constituents complaining about these collapsing building
To discover why they were falling down
I figured it was probably just because they were so old
But didn't notice that something was strange about these so-called dollhouse
They were surrounded by piles of Broken Bricks and debris
But something was missing
I often wonder why
I never saw a whole brick
If the buildings were falling down into piles but there weren't any holbrooks
Nose piles
More knew it meant someone was taking them
Salvage bricks
Are valuable
There's a market for them just like there's a market for the copper that gets stripped out of old homes
A pickup truck full of old bricks could be worth upwards of $300
But these bricks weren't being salvaged legally
There was or not legal demolition
Project stay with death
Bricktown
I miss that was happening on a massive scale in Morris District
Why have 1242 empty buildings
And 1700 vacant Lots
So out of the 1700 bacon lines I guarantee you that
1200 mosto
Despite these being vacant houses
All of this brick theft is a problem
When a building's bricks get stolen
The house usually can't be resold
It also takes money out of the pockets of illegal demolition worker
And it stalls Redevelopment
Because you can't sell a building
You can't guarantee that I will be there next week
But there's also something
Intangible that's lost with bricks
The bill has been home to famous African Americans like Chuck Berry Tina Turner and the opera singer Grace bumbry
I remember the grace bumbry house
That house was
Stole
News column old Wagner building but
A lot of our history was taken away and stole as well
Brick theft has been going on all across St Louis since at least the 1970s
Whole buildings whole blocks whole parts of neighborhood
Being stolen
Card off illegally
Cancel
How and where in the United States can somebody steal a whole building
And not get caught
St Louis history with a break starts back in 1849
The boat fire on the riverfront
Jump into the city
Hundreds of wooden buildings along the river burn the ground
Devastation with the city government to order that all new buildings be constructed with fireproof materials
The city happen to be sitting on top of a high-quality clay
As well as the coal that would be needed to fire the Kilns to turn that clay into brick
Well I can show you a couple of these different kinds of bricks and
Andrew Wiles executive director of the landmarks Association of St Louis
Behind his desk
You got a giant frame tutorial map of the city back in the late 1800s
The landscape is dotted with evidence of the Cities once-thriving brick industry
It's covered with mines and smokestacks
You'll see
Some smoke stacks and you'll see
You know some
Derek set up a winches setup over over Minds
I'm some pit mines you also CDs
Beehive Kilns they look like big lips
The red clay industry was so big that folks were even digging mind and their backyards to get this.
And all this new industry attracted others
St.Louis
In the decades to come waves of migrants from across Europe and the southern us
Lock the city
It was a Boomtown
So it's for The Perfect Storm
Of materials
Labor
Command industrial innovation
That can bind to two mixing Lewis into this brick producing
Powerhouse
St Louis was home to the world's largest brick manufacturing company
Millions of bricks were exported across the country to build skyscrapers in Chicago
And other buildings across the western and southern United States
Bricks for cheap
And plentiful
Anatman
But even modest working-class homes in St Louis
Could have one of a kind brickwork
But not just blank facade
Do they have this for
Corbelling extensions
Recesses
And ornamental Bricks Built into them
Pressed flowers art designs
String courses
Things like that
But even as these beautiful brick homes were going up all across the city
The conditions for the city's eventual semi abandonment
We're also being put in place
In the early nineteen hundreds St Louis was forcing its black citizens to live in segregated neighborhoods when the practice was
Found unconstitutional Realtors began asking homeowners in St Louis to sign something called Raceway
Corrective deed covenants the homeowner and future homeowners property to African American
And other minority groups
Here's calling Gordon a history professor at the University of Iowa when realtor has assessed properties for sale
High in St Louis in a well into the 1960s one of the standard items on the assessment form was
The nearest negro Community or the degree to which Negroes had invaded Orange
Treated funda neighborhood
And is Invasion a word that was used in these documents
Intrusion by invasion
Not only were African-Americans blocks
Certain neighborhoods by these racist deed Covenants
The city was also bulldozing black neighborhoods
From massive new projects like the Gateway Arch
This was the age of urban renewal
Increasingly
We are seeing large-scale demolition is the first step in building modern cities
In this jet age events move fast
Faster indeed than we sometimes realize
Study
As we clear away the structures that block progress
In the 1950s white residents have started to leave the city entirely
The departure was facilitated by the recent development of the highway system and by the GI Bill
Which gave white veterans easy access to home loans
While largely denying black veterans the same right
White flight was happening all over the country
In St Louis was no exception
That's why it's rush to the suburbs the City's population declined and its tax revenues Plumbing
By the 1970s
African Americans with the means started moving out of the city 2
We lost over half a million people
In the city since 1950 so we have a huge problem with vacancy
Andrew Weil again from the landmarks Association
And
At the same time
The neighborhoods that are vacant were built of incredibly high quality materials
Find incredibly durable material
Most of the brick that's being stolen in St Louis is a hundred or hundred twenty years old suits
It's really at the beginning of its lifespan
Bricks can last for hundreds of years
The Fallout from Decades of racist housing policies in disinvestment in the north side
Who created communities with a bricks themselves are worth more than the homes they support
The only reason these buildings
Can be still on his because
They are perceived
To have no value
So
If the building is perceived to have no value and there are
Eyes watching it
You know it's the perfect opportunity for a
Disappear
By the time Sam Moore and become Alderman in 2007
Brick theft had already been going on for decades
I've been much of an effort by the city to stop at
Some more sand out to figure out
Who was stealing bricks
How
To start
He did what any gumshoe would do
He went on some Steakhouse
That was some Steeler bricks and follow them to the Brickyard where they sell them and wonder why
What does City's a tiny legal
Organization like that of a business by Brick
These Bricks leaves have found that abandoned houses represent remarkably easy target
So easy but sometimes people are coming in from as far away as Las Vegas
It's not actually hard to tear the buildings down
People go about it in a few different ways
So the guy get up at 6 in the morning
And
Get on a bicycle
And take a screwdriver
And pick him out
67 bricks out of the wall
Rare / wall
That's all it takes
Make a hole in the wall
Sliding metal pipe in the hole attached to a chain
Give yourself enough clearance
Impulse
Instant demolition
The thieves had figured out how to steal bricks even in busy areas
They just take out the back wall of the house
Hidden from View
This is a busy street so what they did was
It took the back out of this one
Look to your right
Oh I see now
You're right
So literally like the whole building is
The back of the building is gone and there's a tree that's growing up in it
Do you write the whole building it's just there's nothing there in the back
There are various ways to steal an entire wall a brick
Some people run a cable through one window and out another
And attach it to a truck and pull
Or they've used backhoes that were contracted for other legal demolition jobs
They would drive him over in the night
Knock down an abandoned house
And then return later to steal the brick
One of the more drastic methods of stealing bricks
Involves burning the buildings first
The fire destroys the wooden supports holding up the building and weekends the mortar between the bricks
And the fire department arrived to put out the fire
They're high pressure hoses off a knock down the walls and even clean the mortar off the brick
Michael Allen is a preservationist who used to live in North St Louis back in 2008
Theft was at its worst and dozens of buildings were being stolen each month
Bad person work with some neighbors reported up buildings that were imported
Sweetheart waiting for the city we
Nailed shut the doors to keep people out of them from setting the fires inside
And then meal baby
On fire
Didn't seem real
Driving out to go get groceries
Spellings of Adams Dolan
Send otherworldly
Stealing the buildings is backbreaking work
Dangerous
Hit a couple times we have found people
Upside down in the rubble baby got caught
The Brits call them and kill them
Eventually Alderman Moore
Set up was sitting in his car and watching all this happened to his neighborhood
So he started to confront the fees when he would find them
People been wanting me man sound they got gun they don't like you
You need to stop run up on people so ask
I took his advice I stopped riding a bull
More eventually realize his interventions weren't making much of a difference anyway
Brick that is classified as a nuisance crime
Kind of like breaking windows in an old building
Carries a maximum $500 fine
And up in 90 days in jail
Given the amount of money that can be made selling stolen brick
A lot of people figure it's a risk
Worth taking
2 Min what makes used 4X so special and desirable is the
The color
This is Barbara Bach
Xi'an Century used brick is a brick yard in St Louis
And so when they tear the building down you'll get like this mix of colors of oranges and reds
And it's really hard
It's been really hard for New Brick manufacturers to duplicate that
Book says her Brickyard is scrupulous about only buying legally Salvage brick
Typically buy from just a handful of trusted vendors
Because we're legal
We have to know exactly where it comes from
So
If we don't we don't usually have people showing up at our yard with just a pal you're trying to sell a pallet
Starbucks has their other brick buyers
That aren't as careful as she is
There was a guy in St Louis that people were he was buying brick
You know after hours
1 in the morning you could get a shopping cart fill it full of brick
Go get money and go buy your drugs and he was doing a huge business
And then
Please shut him down
Book explained to me that the supply of Legally Salvage bricks is driven mostly by city-funded demolition
So when the city runs out of money to tear down old buildings
More brickyards are willing to turn a blind eye
The brick acquired illegally
And so that's when it gets
You know tempting to
Police car
Bastille brick and sell it
Because they know there's
A lot of demand and no Supply
Some of the Breck whether it's weekly salvaged or not
Goes to building or renovating new homes in St Louis
The most of it heads to another part of the country entirely
David said most of it goes to Louisiana
And we saw some in Florida we sell some in Mississippi we sell in Texas
So there's
You know Southern markets that really love our brick
I'm 63 years old I've been doing this since I was 18
And I've seen in her just about anything you can think of in the brick business so
Gary McConnell Owens McConnell brick in Baton Rouge Louisiana
And he's been buying salvaged brick
For decades
When demand was at a time
Who's getting boxcars full of used brick from St Louis
Newbreak might sell for around $350 per thousand
Old Brick
On the other hand
Logo for almost 2 times
For example we sell St Louis brick for 675 1000
There are a few reasons why there's such a high demand for salvaged bricks in Southern United
States where McDonald's from
For one thing
1960s and 70s
As neighborhoods in St Louis we're starting to hollow out
A new style of architecture in the South with creating a market for used brick
We had an architect in
In Louisiana named a Hays town
And he was the first
Person that I know of and I was
A kid back then but
Started
Designing houses using Salvage material
Town with influence by Antebellum Southern architecture
Course you know where down south
We have plantation homes
All those old old plantation mansions and
Stop
The brick were actually made on site
My Insite workers living on the plantation
And they would
Make the brick
And put them all these houses so when Mr town
Hiss hiss
Reputation and his flare was to replicate
Some of these old plantation home so
The only way that you could do that was
How to use antique
Brick
Towns designs called for used brick not just for the facades of homes
Respect for the flooring
Courtyard patios and pool deck
Even today
Some neighborhoods in Baton Rouge require all new construction to use reclaimed brick
Demand for that weathered look has gotten so high
But only the wealthiest homeowners can afford to have salvaged brick
Lyrics
Expecting that
Have
Salvaged brick or
You know
Old Brick floors or pine beams or pine flooring
Any kind of antique salvage stuff they're expecting
To see that in those upper in houses
Aside from this desire for an antique look
Is another reason why so much use bread from St Louis is headed to the Gulf Coast and out west
It's because
Not all bricks
Are created equal
The exterior layer of brick
The face
Produced in St Louis is fired in such a way that it helps it withstand the freezing Winters in the Midwest
Interior brick is softer
Can't stand up to the elements
In the 1960s and 70s St Louis home builders in the suburbs who started using reclaimed brick from the city got a
A nasty surprise
Brick facades
Were crumbling away
If you're going to put used brick on a new home
There has to be someone at the demolition site
Separating out the face brick from the interior
That's something demolition companies can't
Or won't pay for
The easiest thing for them to do is just ship all of the bricks down to warmer climates
Or even the softer ones can be used on the exteriors of buildings
To me there's something sad about the beautiful old houses Own St Louis being torn down to build beautiful old
Looking houses
Somewhere else
Barbara buck
Who runs the St Louis Brickyard agrees
You know there are just times when I'll go to a building that I know is coming down
And I just feel
So sad
Because I think about the family and I'm very sentimental I think about
The family
The live there I think about the family that built that house I think about the generations that were raised in that house
But she's also practical
Mini houses can't and maybe shouldn't be saved
We don't have
The population we don't have the jobs to support those houses and everything has a life
Spent
The worst of the brick theft is over today
Some of the Brickyard that had a history of buying stolen bricks
We're shut down with the help of city workers
Local activists and representatives
Like ornaments and more
Brick yards in St Louis
Are now required to photograph whoever salesmen Bragg
Along with the Demolition permit for that job
Now the question is how to reinvent What's Left Behind
I'm doing I'm doing a brick interview
Brick interview you know I'm the big man
Jacksonville
More shows me some of the things they're doing with the vacant Lots in the neighborhood
We pull up next to a fence decorated with life-size portraits of old Negro League baseball players from the 1930s
Behind the fence is one of Morris projects
An urban farm
This is called the vilard today who got about 50 fruit trees in it
Regarding tilapia fish
And catfish forgot to hatchery in there we got chicken
Got to work
And there's new housing being built in the jail to
But not the same kind of stately homes that the neighborhood used to be known
It take a million-dollar bill to mow houses over again
So
We want makes you so now I think they look good and it seems it has the neighborhood
More shows me some of the new houses
A traditional brick home in this neighborhood would have been made with walls that were three brick
Mystery
Ounces look kind of like the old one
Up close you can see that there's something
It's not a whole brick
Overlook clip-on gadgets
Is niacin is a flat surface is about 3/4 inch thick
Souvenir of a
Power brick
The clip-on Brick Works just like siding on a house
It's a slice of used or manufactured brick attached to the wooden frame of the building to give it that look of a
Brick home
These homes with their brick veneer are far cheaper to build and will likely be the new face of the Ville
They're not as ornate as the old turn of century houses that used to define this neighborhood
Therefore debility gets more people to move in
To lower the vacancy rate
And that's what counts
Better to have a neighborhood full of life
Even if the brake is fake
Replaces dollhouse
With real houses
A lot of cities were ravaged by fire in the mid-nineteenth century
St.Louis reacted by building everything with breath
But when San Francisco burned down it use brick in another novel way
Biblical extra story about that
After that
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds game
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptom
Comes come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
So a lot of other cities were also hit by fires in the mid-1800s
St.Louis
The 19th century was a very dangerous time in San Francisco for example in regards to fire
People came out for the gold rush
Lived wherever they could and would Shack
Pants even on wooden boats in the shallows of the Bay
It was a disaster waiting to happen
Agricola said he's here in studio with me now
It's not about how
Fire
Shaped San Francisco's architecture and Amherst
In 1849
The same year that St Louis suffered from a severe fire that
Ultimately turned them toward Fireproof
Brick
San Francisco was also hit by the first of a series of seven
And 2 years later
One of these destroyed an estimated 2000
Three-quarters of the city of the time
And Casino
The reason why there's a phoenix
It's because all these fires
Fun facts
What are things that very clear
Is that serious, did not go the route of St Louis there are not a lot of brick buildings in response
The fires of the
Bright 2
Brick was expensive on the bay and the climate doesn't really require the installation or benefit
From the thermal Mass
The brick provides
So why Lucy was actually rebuilt using wood
But they did widened
City streets to slow.
Spread of flames
And the funny therapy
Firefighting
Jersey Evening Post
Range of fines for any citizen who stood by and didn't he
Put out teacher
To make reservations
Regular citizen to be involuntary firefighter
I don't know if that would fly today but
And these fires
They also led to the creation of this Underground
Sister
System around the city
Which provided water reserves are firefighters so they could
Tap water
Closer to blaze
The importance of these
When actually realized until about a half century later
You mean for the Big Show
Quake of 1906
Exactly
Water mains broke
Rubble prevented firefighters from reaching parts of the city the fire is a burning for
Thousand
Most of the City was destroyed
But in the aftermath San Francisco said about it
Expanding its auxiliary water supply
Reservoirs pump stations fire boats
Earthquake-proof cisterns
Using concrete and steel
All which were designed to help
In emergencies when conventional water system
Doesn't sound like a very good solution to but it doesn't sound like
Building with wood
Was a good idea
Masonry is better for fires but it's
Not as great an earthquake
All that being said
Did have a role to play
Walking around the city of the day you can spot where the CD cisterns are because they're marked out on the surface
With big circles of brick
On San Francisco streets
The brakes aren't actually part of the system but they do indicate where the sis
Western is
And visitors and new residents always ask about
Huge mystery what are those
Circle
Outlines
They are almost as big as
City Street
Yeah they spent basically from sidewalk to sidewalk
And they hit that something much larger below
Ultimately the visibility making these systems easier to spot in a crisis
In the middle of these break circles are these little manhole covers that provide the actual Acts
Being spun around the city these many reservoirs can function independently
Earthquake damage cuts off one area from another
And in total there about 170 of these spread around and they have
Combined capacity of
10 million gallon
Elias
And so if you're walking to see
You should really look for
Write an actually wrote an article titled the coating rings on our website which
Talk more about the history
Has images and videos but most importantly
Has a Mac
So you can actually help these down yourself
I'm nice and that website
99 pi
Hi. Org
99percentinvisible with police this week by Zach Dyer edited by Delaney Hall
Bixente production by Sherif Youssef
Music by genre
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital director
Running out the team Savory gentleman
Emmett Fitzgerald
Karen Mazza
Roman Mars
We are project at 91.7 kalw
San Francisco
Produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX an independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all app
Podcasting
Animal
Radiotopia. FM
We are supported by the Knight foundation and listener donor
Kitchen whatever they can to keep us honest
And keep us working hard
You can find the show into a discussion about the show on Facebook you treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you're thinking
I need more 99 Pi my life
We have all the old episodes available in new articles about design every couple of days
My beautiful weapon
It's at 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com