99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When do movies come out most of the praise goes to the director and lead actors
There's so many other people involved in a film
And a lot of them
Our designers
There are costume designers and set designers
But also graphic designer
Working behind the scenes
All of the graphic object
That you might see in a phone
And I do mean
Every single
Object
Interesting bits
Lettering on it and a thing with patent on it than anything with illustration on it and most things made out of paper
This is Antioch
My name is Daniel
Anaheim
Designer for
The film industry
Over the course of her career Atkins has design all kinds of traffic
Telegrams
Vintage cigarette packaging Ops glasses
Books
Any kind of chocolate box food packaging and labeling passports
CIA
Identification card
And with all of these objects Atkins needs to choose or design the lettering and make sure the
The paper is
Just wright
All these small design decisions
That contribute to
To creating a cohesive visual world
For the fountain
A scarf designs film already have two main priorities when we start designing any
Proper set piece
The first is to set the. And the second is deceitful okay
Patient so that when the audience start watching a movie they know immediately where the story is being told and when it's 2
But I think the other thing that we have to do is we have
Also try to tell the story of hand as well
With graph
So for example
If you see a sign in the backgrounds of a New York Subway scene
It says Walk Don't Run
You can bet any seconds after you see that the characters are actually going to start running
All the graphic design you seen a film has a job.
It's moving the story forward
Easy background signage seems to have a kind of a subliminal message
It's always put there on purpose everything that we put in front of the camera
Is that for a reason
I met Annie Adkins at the aiga national design com
And I interviewed her on stage and I just
Loved hearing her talk about a work
So I asked her to
And today
We're just going to run
So let's start at the beginning
How did you get into this
My very first job was on a TV show called The chutas which we made here in Dublin and Ireland
About 10 years ago now
And I went for an interview
For the job as an assistant the art Department
But when they sell my portfolio they realized I came from a graphic design background
They said we're actually looking for full-time
Graphic designer
On the show
Gradle
Pieces
And I couldn't understand this because
It didn't make sense why they would need
A graphic designer on a show that was set in a. Before graph
Designer
I confirm this advertising background while we were making
Logo design website
Magazine layout
And there were none of these things in
The cost of
Henry VIII
But then I learned very quickly when I started the job.
Just because
They weren't any graphic designers
In the 15th Century doesn't mean that wasn't graphic design is just that at that time it would have been the craftspeople who are the designers
So
For example
Hannity 8 forms to chop his wife head off
He's going to need a death warrant
And if he needs a death warrant
He's going to need a calligrapher
Because at that time
It would have been the calligrapher who is responsible for the layout
The Royal Scrolls and documents and also the
Style at the light
So you become the graphic designer for the
15th century
Yeah
Exactly so now it's the graphic design is Rolling Stones a day to try to imitate both across teeth would have done weather.
The
Ironmonger all the Glazier
All the stone Mason
Talk us through the process like how do you begin how do you know
What your job is going to be what does it mean to
To be a graphic designer on
For certain
First of all I never know what my next job is going to be so I can't really
I can't really prepare myself and I can't really learn every skill that I'm going to need
It's like I don't know if my next job is going to be
Sex in Victorian London or if it's going to be on a spaceship
200 years in the future
So what happens is I got the call I arrive on sats I set up my tool cast I sit down with the scrap
And they go through the script on by mock house and a thing that sounds like it might
A piece of graphic
Design
And while I'm making this list which we call a script breakdown
I'm also beginning to research the periods
All the genre all the
The storyline that I'm designing
I do that for about 6
Six to eight weeks prep and then shooting starts during that time
Time is always against me and I'm
Stuff out
How often are you making stuff
Right before someone else
To hold it on
Film
Will we try to get everything made if it's a prop then we tried to get it made at least a week
Before it's shots on
Because inevitably going to be some
Changes that need to be made
When I was working on the Grand Budapest Hotel I had to make a notebook for a fine to start to do stuff
Andrew stuff is very
Precise character
When refunds came in for his costume fitting
He had his notebook and all the other props that he needed
The first character
And he just noticed that they would no lines in the notebook could give him and made him a notebook with
App like pages
Question. Because is Khartoum so precise he thought maybe it would have
It should have lines in it
So we took the truck back up to the studio and we remade the notebook
Send it back down again with lines and I was fine
But then
After the film came out and I started doing some magazine interviews about
Designing graphic props
I use this is my
An example because I thought it was quite interesting and quite a good example of
The level of detail that react
You going to
But of course all the gentlest head was that
I was saying that Ray Fiennes are some kind of Diva
So actually I actually stopped using that as an example of because that's not what I was saying at all you know
It's really it's his job to make sure that
The props are rice and this our job to make sure that the props arise and this is just the kind of back-and-forth the everyday biking.
Let me go straight when making things for phones
So when you're doing that script
Breakdown
What are some of the keywords that you're looking for that indicate that you have work to do
In that scene
That always stops me in my tracks
When I'm reading a script
Would be the word of
Because offices are just absolutely full
Of paperwork
You know like notice boards
Filing cabinets
Covered in all kinds of paper whip
So that's a huge that's a huge step for the graphics
Apartments
There are lots of scenes it
Have a very low volume
Graphics not really like
You can kind of skim read
Sexy
Do you have a
Liberty have a pulled out a newspaper I'll start looking in the mouth
So funny
Let's talk a little bit about so once you get
The list of things that your have to work on you begin to research
What those things are what they are like
For this phone
And
Could you describe what the research is
Dislike
So I start my research I do a little bit of research online
But I find that looking things up on the internet can be misleading
Trick of the reasons
Festival
Nobody really ever labels anything property online like if you find if you find a beautiful vintage map
Tan Tumblr that's absolutely no way it's going to tell you what year is From about the dimensions of it are
And then also it's really difficult to judge
By looking at pictures on a screen
Scale of things and also that extra things
If I have to make a telegram
For example
I really need
To go to a flea market
Cast and find an old hologram that I can hold in my hands
And then I know what kind of paper to make it out of Amino X
I'm so I do a lot of my research
NC markets in junk shops buying old pieces on eBay
Rating my grandmother's elastic
That kind of thing
What are some of the other sharks like so you do everything by hand when it
Would have been done by hand
What is it
Take-two makeup
Paper love
Cold
You know you're making it brand new and handing it somebody
How do you make a
Cement feel real
The aging process
For Prague
Is a little bit of a tricky balance
Tightrope
Because
The pieces usually should have been brand new at the time
At the time that the show is Seth in
When you're making a. Drama
A lot of the time audiences needs
See a little bit of beijing
To really believe
That there in the.
You know it's like we need we need to see the cracks in the converse of the oil painting
Because that's how we see it in the gallery
We need the paper to be
Off-white so slightly yellow
Because that's how we look at all.
Commence now
But if you go too far in that direction
Then all of a sudden everything looks a bit like
I do not like an old pirate map
Rice
There's a tricky balance and it varies from show so show some directors and production designers wants to go for real kind of CP
You look and everything
And then other directors
Wants to
Really work with the colors that they would have used at the time which is one of the reasons why it was so
Wonderful working for Wisconsin because he really
Like embrace
The the colors of the periods
Instead of doing that whole sepia-toned thing that we do a lot of
The time before waxing
Some kind of
Drama
Right
Is there another I want to get back to
Grand Budapest
Hotel and West Anderson
Second butt
Are there other examples of
Things that
You
Researched and you know what is accurate
The time for example of something being new when it was
It's actually new
But
You're balancing that against
Expectations of what
Want or expectations of
Of the story
So that
For some reason the accurate representation is not the
Proper representation for
Thing that you need
What to do in that story
So we try to start every single prop that we make for a film with a real historical artifact
That we can
Coffee bicycle
And that means that we we're making things that feel really authentic instead of
Like a movie prop
So what example would be newspaper design
Newspapers to use the Lost info because they're really
The really good storytelling
Advise if you need tell the audience that there's a war being fought
You can show a newspaper headlines thing that the Bull Run
Rather than she used to say she seconds possible sequence which is going to cost
How much money million dollars
So we would start with the real reference of a newspaper
Actually a lot of the time in
Particularly in England
In the beginning of the twentieth century the broadsheet papers didn't actually have
Newspaper headlines on front pages at all
The front pages were covered in
Small Lots
Advertising local businesses
Awesome things for sale
So what I do when I start a project is I'll talk to the director in the production designer about this scene about bring them there
Information and tell them that this is actually what a newspaper front page was like
And then they make the call
Whether they want to stick with historical accuracy
Or they just want to ignore that
Designed the newspaper
To suit the story that that's how they
The line that gets bandied about
Fill knots Papa
And it always goes something like
We're not making a documentary about 19th century newspaper layouts
Telling story
Is there a part of you that
Really enjoys it when it's really accurate or is it
Do you
Get more pleasure from it just
Being really good in serving the story
The best way possible
You get the most excited when you can just going to marry the two
It's exciting
To study real references
Because what I find a lot of the time is that
The truth is more info
You know like if if I started a prop with just a blank page in illustrator
I wouldn't be able to create something as interesting
As water is actually being designs before me ride like my imagination can't compare to the collective imagination of
Hundreds and thousands of craftspeople that have
Gone the family of the last
Hundreds of years
So it's interesting to look at something real
And then develop it with the director and the production designer to suit the story because then you can make something the feels
I'm sick but it's also
Interesting visually
Until when I'm watching you work
And movies
You put a lot of time into
But
Do you want me to notice them
Or do you want me to
Kind of ignore them
I kind of feel the
If the audience is looking at my pieces of graph
Design
Then this film isn't necessarily worth
Congrats to the attention of the audience should really be on the drama that
Unfolding between the car
Like the drum the drama between the humans
I think you should notice it but only subconsciously
Like we are building a world
Under using graphic design
To do that
But the pieces is so fleeting I don't think you should really
Register
Everything consciously
When I watch things that I would come back with my m
Mosa
I'm always very keen that she notices everything
I made that I made that and she's always like boss
This is a conundrum of almost
Design that
The best stuff
Is meant to work in
Do its job
But kind of not be noticed in is there a
Estate of mind that you
Gotten into where you can
Except that
Or is it
Just come naturally
I've never felt
Shih tzus in anyway. My work
Doesn't get
Screen time
I only have a feel
Thrills when it does get a little bit of screen
There's something thrilling about
Having your way
Shown on a cinema screen
I don't know what it is
When I worked in advertising years ago you know I would design Billboards but I never got really excited
Driving past a billboard that I designed where is
If it if I'm sitting in the cinema on something gets like a
Fraction of a second of blurry
Screen time then just some reason I'm really excited by
I don't know what that is I suppose it's like the whole
How Hollywood star system thing getting to me
It's fair you give yourself that enjoyment
I'm peeing on a movie
Screen
Have you ever
Really labored over something that got caught from a scene in that
The pain you at all
Yes you will come things all the time that you put a huge amounts backed into that just never gets seen
An adult on the
On screen or by the camera
I'm actually say that most of my work
It's like the
There are people who see it
And the people who see it all the actors and the director
And it's really like it's really exciting to Bill say for example a street scene
And put up all these then
Street posters in shop front signs and hunting signs and pieces of like. Advertising
Amazon CV axles arrived on SAS in the morning I'm taking the surroundings and really you can see them feeling like that
I've been transported to another time
And then
You know they go and they do that right thing and I I hope
But maybe
As film designers contributes little bits to them really getting in Spyro
Yeah
Have you ever had an instance where
An actor really fell in love with a
Proper something that you made
I remember when we were shooting Grand Budapest
That was a prison scene
With Harvey Keitel and Ray Fiennes
Ray Fiennes was admiring the prison escape map
Harvey keitel's character ludvig
A drawn
Gustav
The character played by Ray Fiennes at Maya's it's autistic
Promise
Remember when I read that script page being really excited because
It's very rare that
Characters in The Script admire a piece of graph
So I need
I knew that this is going to be a big one for the graphics Department
So we may as we made his prison escape map
And dab it was thrown up on the back of a piece of packaging paper so we also included
Packaging labeling post
Thompson
Frankie moxon
We really went all out song
Jason Mewes
These pieces for this imagine
Country
And the Empire zebrowska that was it created
When Harvey Keitel arrived over from LA
To do the scene
He suggested that he and all the people in the
All the other actors
In the scene
Actually go and stay in the prison it was a real person that we were shooting in
Don't stay overnight in the prison
I'm take these props with them so that they could get into character
So that was really fun the thought of them all going off
To this remote prison in the east
Germany in the middle of February
In the snow
I'm taking the props that weed made
How to get into cars
If you were to pick up a script tomorrow what would you read in the script
That would make you really excited
To make that
I like designing things fast you have to design as a character in the film rather than as a graphic designer
Example of prison escape map
It's not really a graph
Set designers jobs traditionally
Designer
Stride
Set the prisoners job to draw it out themselves so you really haven't get into character and try to figure out
How that character
What tools they would have used
To do it you know what
But they've had access to Pennzoil charcoal crayons
What kind of paper with Dad
Access to and what would that style be like
What's that you mention that
You've the most part you work
Isn't noticed in the
But with the
World of
You know streaming video and the internet where people can pause in and discuss the graphic design of things
You know people do notice
And
Probably notice
Mistakes
Yeah
Is absolutely full of continuity errors
On the loss of them are about graphic
Pieces
So one example is
When jumping is at the gas station
The calendar on the wall says October 1932
Vchos Oktoberfest
12/19 + 26
Sundays
In 1932 those dates fell on Wednesdays
When we made the calendar we didn't think to check the day's against
The dates of 1932 but then we didn't think anybody else would either
I can read that kind of thing thank
You know the Titans
But that right
And when I look back at the pieces that we made I see that yes there is never that
The next job I went on to it would have been Spielberg's Bridge of spies which was a true story
We made a lot of
A lot of newspapers without phone
And I remember speaking to check the dates against the days because I want some
To get it right
And then eventually the prop Master said to me you know what I think we just going to leave the dates off
Because
It wasn't clear the sequence of these things going to be shown in on he says you know if if you leave the days off altogether nobody
Look fresh
But if you put something bad that's wrong then it might jump house
We went with no dates in the end suppose mean
So when you were doing the design for the Grand Prix
Best hotel
There was
An error
I called him after we do a bunch of the war
And it was only little pink cake boxes and
From the fictional bakery called Mendel's
Can you tell us a
Halfway through the chute
Wisconsin section says I think there's a spelling mistake in the Mentos bulk
And I said
I don't think so because
Take such great pride in my spelling and grammar
And he said that has two T's and patisserie
I looked at the box and I realized that he was right
And of course
I had a blessed.
Suicide never gone through
Spell check
You know it's a word of French origin I really should have double-checked that I should have triple checked it and I just didn't
And at that point we had shot
So many medals boxes
Wichita I think
2000 of them
And it has to be fixed in post-production
Which is great it's it's great that we have the option fixings and post but it's it's a kind of a lengthy process because you have to
Change
Whatever it is 25 frames per second
I am so it can be quite expensive as well
So that was embarrassing
Since the film was released the mendl's box is kind of Taken on a life of its own it's kind of become a bit of an icon
Come to the film so
People that people are selling them online and people making their own fake boxes and selling them and trying to pass
Real props from the movie
But I know when I look at them
But it has two T's and patisserie
Then
It was really in the movie
If you have to see a box with two T's in history
You should buy it
And these were really iconic looking and therein
IOS movies
Pink Accu
And so
They're really up
Very active
Part of
Of the scenes at the ran
Yeah they're what we call a hero prop
Superhero props
Is any profit cats
A bit of screen time or has a kind of character of its own
You can generally tell what a hero prop is because it will have a description in the script
Like a lot of things that we make
Can't even mentioned in the scriptures
Like
It doesn't it doesn't office scene
And it's just assumed that we will know what's address instead of
Festina the script won't go into details about notice boards and fighting cops
But a hero prop will always be at least
Names and mentioned and sometimes described
When we come back we'll hear from Annie about when the most difficult
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
Got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast oh my God
Black podcast
Soda follow up on this conversation next week
We're doing a whole episode on the design of fake money
The movies
And the challenges that profits on his face
Creating a currency that
That's a look real but not so real that they get busted for counterfeit
The preview that story
I asked any icons about her experiences
Designing money
So most of the time when I have to
Create currency for movie I'm really recreate
Because most movies are set
The real world
So I'll find vintage banknotes and I'll scan them
And reproduce them
There are problems with the
I think I was a shelf you know doesn't
Let you do this it tells you
It's it's an eagle that you can get around it with a
A little hot
And then for things like Grand Budapest Hotel I was creating a
Fictitious currency because it was
Fictitious Empire
So
That was
It's in the sense that I didn't need to worry about legal Terrence but it was really tricky because
Designing a bunk gnosis
Really difficult I'm sure it takes
People months in years to design banknotes and you know we had whatever it was
Fortnite
Brother legal considerations
When you're designing banknotes
Well yes you needs you need to get it past legal clearance
So things have to be changed slightly I mean I haven't actually made any Malden
Money because I've never done a contemporary movie
But I have designs things for example for the CIA and the FBI for true story
So we wanted to use the real logos
Of course because we want everything
Feel authentic but that doesn't get pastelitos parents so you have to do things like
Flip the eagle on the Department of State logo
You know you know in the the American seal it's an eagle holding things in his claws
Yeah like terrorism
Yeah you have to change what the eagle is holding him which way his head is facing
I guess this ain't the same
Currency as well
Do you want to hear a lot more about the dangers of Designing prop money
I have to do is listen the next week's
99percentinvisible was pretty so sweet by Emmett Fitzgerald in Avery trufelman
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer
Costa is the digital director
Running of the team is to review Civ
Delaney Hall
Turn master
And me
Roman Mars
We are product 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX an independent collected with the most Innovative shows in all a podcast
Fun Mall
It radiotopia. FM
We are supported by the Knight foundation and listeners
Ford owners
Who pitching whatever they can
Keep us doing
You can buy the show enjoy discussion about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi Oregon Instagram
Tumblr and latitude
Did your thinking
I need more 99 Pi my life we have all the old episodes and new articles about design at Cartwright's
Every couple of days
Beautiful beautiful website it is at 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com