99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There's a scene in the buddy cop movie Rush Hour 2 starring Jackie Chan
Docker
That takes place
Las Vegas casino
In the scene Jackie Chan character is in the unenviable predicament of having a small bomb stuff in
Inside his mouth
The villain
I hate it when that happens.
Thai Dish of
Onto the floor of the casino
About to explode fortunately at the last minute Jackie Chan's partner protector
Tucker removes the tape from Chan's mouth and transcripts the bomb on to a nearby roulette
Where it goes off
I did
So in that scene where the roulette table
Explodes money flies
Everywhere
Best producer Elizabeth nakano
And to create the scene and a bunch of others in the movie filmmakers needed a lot of money
Fake money
We had produced a billion dollars of $100 bills
Which is quite a bit of money in
14 pallet loads
Of $100 bill Solid 4 foot by 4 foot Cube
That's Greg Bilson Jr
Is the CEO of ISS props that company that provided all the fake money for the movie
And he says while we were filming Rush Hour 2
Something
Strange happened
A couple of men showed up to Dalton's office
Well when they showed up
They were saying that they were from the Secret Service and provided documents
Indicating such and I thought it was being punked I didn't believe that it was a real situation
Just two officers at it got very serious very real very fast
The Secret Service was in Greg Wilson's office because during the filming of that scene in the casino
Some of the fake cash
Had gone
Missing
Some souvenir speakers and Extras grab some of that money put it in their pocket and it subsequently started turning up
Is counterfeit over the next
Few days
People were trying to use the fake money as real money up and down the Las Vegas Strip
Which meant that Greg was being accused by the Secret Service
Counterfeiting
This is a serious charge
People who counterfeit money can face large fines and even jail time
Which is made the use of prop money in movies
Really complicated
It's over the years
We have pretty strict laws around the reproduction of US currency
Can be traced back
The mid-1800s
Around the time of the Civil War there was a ton of counterfeit currency circulating in the United States
Some people say anywhere from 1/3 to 1/2
All money with
Fake
The federal government wanted to give people faith in it
Currency
It got serious about cracking down
Counterfeit money
Reproductions of US currency became illegal
Including photographs
Money
Along with the law that criminalizes reproductions of money and enforcement agency was formed
The Secret Service
Yeah those guys with the earpieces black suits
Tech president
Those guys
Today the agency falls under the Department of Homeland
Security
But I didn't start in 18
65 the Secret Service was part of the Treasury Department
And it's only job
Was to fight counterfeit
Secret Service agents operating from field offices throughout the country
Evan constantly fighting the criminals who make folding money
As well as those who passes to the public
Asthma film put out by the treasury Department in 1945 called
Doubtful dollars
And accepting money it is well to remember that file not Falls
Grainger.com
Counterfeiters are stranger
Learn to know your money and train yourself
Examine the bills and coins
Okay so
The ban on any photographic representation of money was in place for about
Century and this was a problem for advertisers and talk
By the letter of the law they were specifically barred from taking
Pictures of money
The law was written before the invention of motion pictures but when movies came along
It was generally assumed that filmmakers would follow the same rules as photographers
No money on camera
I'm so in the early days of Cinema when money was needed in a film producers had to get
Creative
That's a scene from the 1943 Hitchcock film shadow of a doubt
And if you watch a movie and look closed
You can see that the bills in the scene aren't American dollars
There Mexican pesos
God entails
I'm glad to see that you're a man of understanding
The most important
Me
Austin Powers
I remember seeing it movies all the way from
The twenties in the thirties and forties up into the 7th
This is Peter Huntoon he's an author and expert on America
Concurrency and he says you can see pesos in a lot of old movies
The reason for this is that after the Mexican Revolution ended
Around 1920
Regional Mexican money that was created during the revolution locked value
And whistle for cheap
The notes from the Mexican state of Chihuahua or punch
Sophia Health power or some of the most widely used
They were absolutely gorgeous because they were multicolored
They had gold backs black Print
But the idea was is that these things look like
Money they were real nice looking
And so the studios bottom up
The studios weren't trying to pass pesos off as American dollars it was just all they had
Nobody's ever fooled by it if you see this
Does that money go by in a movie you know whether it's American or not because of course you'd see that a block away
In the second half of the 20th century the government began relaxing restrictions on the rules around photographing currency
And it eventually became legal to film real money
And real money is great for scenes where you need close-up shots
Like this scene from the 1995 movie Dead Presidents
But I can forgive me for this one
I'll tell you what man
This kind of money
In this scene
Or of the characters have robbing armored truck
And are splitting up the cat
The camera pans slowly over stacks
But it can also be risky to have real money floating around on Sat
Especially if you need a bunch of it
It's a lot of producers prefer to use fake money
These days the government does allow for some reproductions of US currency
It's just not very clear how real
Fake money
Can look
It depends it's it's very subjective if it's the same size as a current US
Currency note
And it's front and back and it's made in the likeness of our US currency
Then we view it as counterfeit
That's Trent Everett
I am an assistant to the special agent in charge for our criminal investigative division of the
Secret Service
And I currently oversee our counterfeit operation section
Over the years prop money and movies has begun to look more like
Actual money
Sometimes
Too much like actual money
Some companies did and still do turn out bills that run afoul of the law
Because to look good on
Screen fake money has to be pretty close to the real thing
He's moving companies like to have things look as real as possible and then that's where they start running into issues
Some people make bills that are the same size as real money
But with one or two small design changes like maybe it's as in dog we trust instead of In God We Trust
What has Benjamin Franklin making a weird face
Order of bills that look exactly like a real thing
It's up there stamp the small disclaimer
All of these would probably be
The Secret Service
Remember Greg Bilson from Rush Hour 2
He thought they had made their fake bills look different enough from the real thing
There's probably 25 or 26 separate things that are not but a real $100 bill has on it
But it was still too close to the reality for them to accept
Wilson had to turn over all of his prop money to the Secret Service 2
And then They confiscated and destroyed all the electronic files that were used in creating this money
Feel so lost a lot of money
Not just a fake money but the real money it took to produce the fake money
Thousand dollars just a Paper Stock alone to buy
Enough paper to produce a billion dollars worth $77,000
In the end all Bilson really lost with money he didn't have to go to jail
These days he mostly trying to avoid using fake money at all it's just too hard to please both the Seeker
Service and the movie producers
It's not worth it I'm not going to break the law for a TV show a feature film or a producer that I don't even
But movies are definitely not the only way fake money is making it into the marketplace
Is Trent Everett again from the Secret Service
That's not
But it's just leaking out of production companies
But that's being sold on the Internet or anybody can purchase it
You can actually buy prop money right now on Amazon
Steven on Prime free two-day shipping
So of course
We ordered
The producer Katie mingle opening up the package
Okay so it's a little stack
About half an inch thick
It does look
A good bit like money from a distance
It doesn't
Feel that much like money though it feels like just regular
Paper to me
Benjamin Franklin is making a really strange
Face
It's like they took his mouth
Shrunk it
And it says for motion picture use only
But yeah let me see if I can pull any of my coworker
Katie has about ten hundred dollar bills in her hands which she's going to say a fan sent us in the mail
Note with all this money in it
Who did
Deer 99ci
Love your words
Pictures of summer
Special lion
People
How much money is it
Real
It doesn't
Promotion
Picture use only
Shut up
Okay so Delaney could see it was fake as soon as it was in your hands
But from a couple feet away the money does look really convincing
Antron Everett told me they're actually investigating some fake money that looks
A lot like the stuff you guys bought from Amazon
Currently we are invest
Instigating the motion picture note that has been popping up all over e-commerce sites
But it's two-sided it is similar size it is in the likeness of a $100 US
Notes
And the only difference on it is that says motion picture you saw me
So don't be surprised if some secret service agent show up at the 99 Pi office
No charges necessarily brought on the person for purchasing it
They just aren't legally able to possess it
Okay just for the record
Personal purchases
Katie Mingle
Am I in
GLE
Given how difficult it is to make money that looks real but
It's hard to imagine who still wants to be in the business of
Creating and applying fake money for the movie
But there are a few people still doing it including RJ Rappaport
I'm rich
RJ Rappaport
And I'm the president of RJR props
We are a
The props house
4 film
Television
Music industry
Commercials and the entertainment industry
When I visit RJ at work he shows me around a huge Warehouse
There are all kinds of different props
Hospital bed a prison style
Futuristic machine with lots of knobs and buttons and control panels like this
Blue light spinning across
Circuit boards and
And flashing LEDs no sportsmanship
Hardee's been in this business for years but he still seems so excited by it
It's almost like he's a kid playing pretend
All the perfect toys
Princess if somebody had to
Disarm this
Is the missile control system
When we step into the room with the prop money
It's like seeing a bunch of movie cliches
There are Stacks and stacks of bills wrapping paper bands like they just came from the bank
So I noticed you also have a briefcase of money is at 1 hole prop that you give out the briefcase with the stacks of cash
Entire
Crop ready to go
And we have other briefcases like this
Just a black leather
Briefcase
And this is a brown leather briefcase
Sometimes we feel them
Take drugs as well
RJ says it took three years of back and forth between him and the Secret Service
Rihanna design for prop money
That kind of guidance isn't something the Secret Service normally provide
By the way
RJ managed to finagle an exception
We work with the Secret Service
And we went over all the laws
All the updates
All of the changes
It's it's a very tedious process where
You just doing original artwork from scratch
RJ says when he makes bills that are blank on one side he can make them pretty realistic
Otherwise you have to be really careful
John Deere a ton of Hoops
And even then sometimes the Secret Service will end up asking you to destroy
Everything you made
It's so much hassle that ironically there's no money in it
And it's not a big money maker
No joke intended
It's not the way that we
Make a living
It's really not
This is really just
Hey
Service that we do
For clients
And we know that
They're going to come back to us for something bigger and better
Then we'll make a living online
RJ has supplied money for a bunch of popular movies and TV shows
Like the Netflix series Ozark
Okay
Money laundering 101 suitcase with 5 million bucks in it
In this scene is a montage include cash on the glass table cash running through a counting machine
And cash in a suitcase
The IRS won't let you buy anything of value with
TV and movies are full of characters who come across suitcases full of money
It's a fun plot device
But behind all this cash is someone like RJ
Who is been through a meticulous design process and years of back and forth with the Secret Service
Because for the film producers
There's no such thing
As easy money
You know what's not on US currency
A dollar cinema
Kurt explores the origin of the S with a line through
After that
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
IPic
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info slide podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
So I'm in the studio with digital director
Kolstad and as we mentioned earlier
Windows really strict anti-counterfeiting laws were on the books
Movies use pesos
What's the standing for US currency
But the idea of seeing
Circulating
In the United States
Wasn't actually
All that new
Krazybee
Yeah in fact from the late 1700s
All the way up to 1857 pieces for legal tender in the United States
Around the same time that Congress officially approved their use
The dollar sign started to
Well nobody's really sure who first designed the dollar sign
There's a lot of them about how it came up
Some people have speculated that the s
With the double lines those two vertical lines over it is actually a you superimposed on an S
At the bottom of the you remove
Oh so it's supposed to be US citizen
US currency
Right and that's an appealing.
Theory
Makes the dollar sign seem distinctly American like a national symbol
Leafly fault
I guess that's one
Hypothesis on what's your
Favorite version of
How the dollar sign
Well there's this rather epic theory that the dollar sign traces back
To the pillars of Hercules on either side of the Strait of Gibraltar
This famous Strait is effectively a threshold between the Mediterranean Sea and the Atlantic Ocean
And according to Legend the flanking pillars were once inscribed with the Latin words non plus Ultra
Translate says nothing further
So is in
Once you leave Mediterranean Sea
There is nothing beyond their just
The endless
Write this is the end of the world as we know it and that motto
Ended up on old Spanish currency
It was later changed from Christopher Columbus reach America
I actually dropped the non part and then it's loose Ultra
Meaning further Beyond
Reflect this new realization that in fact
There was a lot more to the world out there
And I'm Spanish coinage the model was shown on banners that rapped
Flanking pair
Corny pillar
So you have this kind of s shaped Banner
That wind down around a vertical column
Turn the words with a pillar and a banner wrapped around it it looks like
Single line
Pretty much and it's a fun story but the prevailing theory is actually
That the dollar sign was never really about the new world he wasn't something distinctively American
In fact it all comes back to the Spanish peso
And their plural abbreviation which is
PS
At least before the pizza is getting a lot of use
In
American businesses in the 1700
And the idea is that
As it was getting written down over and over again on documents
Puppy started to order
The s
And the crew part of the
You just got dropped over
So you end up with something that
Looks like the single bar dollar sign
That vertical line going up to now
Let me know today
And so that is
Thought to be
It is thought by many to be the true story and that is what the Oxford English Dictionary Clayton
You know we may never be sure
99percentinvisible with Bruce's sweet by Elizabeth nakano
Edited by our senior producer Katie Mingle
Did the temperature in and Mick
John real compose the music
Brooke Holsted is the digital director and the Restless staff includes Delaney Hall
Avery
Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Mapreduce
On video route
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
This show is part of radiotopia from PRX a collective with the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
Sticker loving listeners
Just like you
If I 99percentinvisible angel in discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we did me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pio
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Do you want to read an article about car-free cities or see our video about biomimicry that we make with bok
You have to go to our website
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com