99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars this show would not be possible without our advertisers
Don't worry I'm not about to read some pass right now I just want you to consider the way Wii U
Advertising letter podcast risen radio hosts myself included read out messages from our sponsor
Play pre-recorded commercial Rush Limbaugh
More comfortable than ever
North stop extinguisher yes the fast-acting snore spray
Working back to where audio advertising began the Journey of how we got to now is fascinating
Organist a podcast from KCRW and Sweeney's recently featured a two-part documentary about the surprising and straight
History of radio advertising as heard the years of Clive Desmond a radio producer in podcast host
Who has worked extensively in the ad industry is account of the evolution bad spots jingles and voice overs
All add up into a story of his own journey and it starts when he was a boy
I grew up
Bungalow-style house
In Buffalo New York
There was
Beautiful radio in the kitchen
Was always on
1959 when I was two and a half
I began listening
My favorite station is WKBW
It was a top
40 station
So there were three or four commercials
It's been a free song
Listening as intensely
Yes I did
Soon discovered that all radio commercials worth
They were like pasta
I came in different shapes
There were monologue commercials
Dialog commercials
Interview commercials
Musical commercials
Are you into my tiny tender ears
I noticed all commercials had one thing in common
A certain lack of authenticity
The radio voices spoke with a cherry make-believe tone
One that said
Everything's great
This was a tone
I have never heard real people speak in
Except for one of our neighbors
Mrs. Cunningham
What's an optimist
But then one day
Least expected
I heard a radio commercial that featured a little girl
Marsha
What's your opinion of all the vitamins and minerals in moscow
I never showed them
You can't see them but they're there
It says so right there on the label
Power Ranger
I'm sorry Marsha
Okay
Anyway I don't care about Spider-Man and things
How do you say by Kristian make my milk taste so good
Like milk with chocolate in it
Well Bosco's good for you
I know
Send letter since I was like Clash of Clans and vitamins
I just like the taste good
Looks like you foolish
Monster storage Mart
But kids are smarter
Little girls voice
Add a powerful effect on me
Because she sounded is real
Is the girl who lived in the Bungalow next door to us
A few days later
Sitting in the back seat of the family car we drove past WKBW in downtown Buffalo
I peered out the window at the station and wondered if the Bosco syrup girl live there I mean
The girl in the commercial be on the radio like that
All the time
I haven't yet learned about the Wonders
Tape recorder
Well I sat in the car
Pondering the whereabouts of the Bosco syrup girl
375 miles to the South
New York City
Was the man who made
Bosco syrup
Radio commercial
Is name
Tony Schwartz
Does a radio producer and audio archivist
Tony Schwartz specialized in recording commercials with real people instead of recording actors trying to 4
Trey real people
Which meant
Bosco syrup girl was a real child and not a 35 year old actor playing a child
Schwartz's production philosophy
To avoid the use of any music or unnecessary sound effects
And when he did work with actors
Sports directed them not to sound like actors
In this way
Tony Schwartz was radio advertisements first
Modernist
A fire breaks out on the first floor of the two family house
The woman quickly leaves to call the fire department
Torn two people died upstairs
Overcome
Buy smok
A man smoking in bed starts a fire
Leaves the bedroom brushes to a phone a door before the fire department gets there
The door rest of his house burns down the door is there one single act that could have been.
Help prevent this needless loss of life and property close the door should these people have done
Close the door you know that a door
Is one of the best pieces of firefighting and life-saving Equipment has the door
And if you leave a room that is on fire close the door you simply
Close the doors the door will help stop the fire and smoke from spreading to quickly close the door
This life-saving information is brought to you
By this station
And a New York City Fire Department
After I turn 9
Every summer I was ritually shipped to California to spend time with my cousin
In San Francisco
Like most children
I was fond of Saturday morning cartoons
The more cartoons I watched
The more familiar I became with the characters
And the more familiar I became with characters
Fox Popeye Bullwinkle
More notice of their specific voices
But there was one voice I like most
Perhaps because he sounded so
On cartoon like
You may know him as Pete Puma
Junior bear
He appeared in Sylvester and Tweety
The Bugs Bunny Roadrunner hour
Ren and Stimpy
Stuart Little
And I go Pogo
Among hundreds of other shows
But when I was a boy
Using radio commercials to
His name
Stan freberg
Honda Odyssey 1966
Sleek Paragon a different breed of chow mein
You'll see it instantly in new bean sprouts with crisp aggressive water chestnuts
Talk about extras you want bucket bamboo shoots power onions you got it mister
In the 1966 trunking chow mein outside to you notice the Revolutionary starting
Round cans right away wrap-around labels more pick up in the two cans taped together that's standard
Equipment dog piss baby look at the way she handles
In the bottom can
Independent vegetable suspension and in the top 10 where the action is over 27 cubic inch
Succulent Chongqing sauce loaded with high-performance chicken Step Up
To the tune to chow mein
The 1966 Chongqing
Noodles optional
I didn't know who Stan freberg was
How big a role he would play in the evolution of Sound Radio commercials
But whenever I heard his voice
Got my attention
One night
Driving over the Golden Gate Bridge with my uncle Owen
Stan freberg voice
Pop
Of the speaker stunts I asked my uncle
Could you watch
Turn that up
Radio
Why should I advertise on radio
There's nothing to look at no pictures I seen you do things on the radio You couldn't possibly do on TV
That'll be the day alright watched
Okay people and now when I give you the cue
I want these 700-foot Mountain the whipped cream to roll into Lake Michigan which has been drained and filled with hot chocolate
Royal Canadian Air Force will fly overhead towing a 10-ton maraschino cherry
Which will be dropped into the whipped cream
Returning a 25000 extra
Is alright to the mountain
Leaderboard
University
Okay 25000 Cherry next Drive
Now you want to try that on television
We're already was a very special made
Because it stretches the imagination
Television stretch the imagination
Who listens to radio
Was part of an advocacy campaign sponsored by the radio advertising Bureau of America
To encourage clients to buy more radio time
Apparently radio was going through a sales drought
Nevertheless
Stan freberg was the main voice of the Epic radio commercial
That's what caught my attention
Deering Freiburg Commando 700 foot mountain of whipped cream being rolled into Lake Michigan
While the Royal Canadian Air Force code a giant Maraschino through the sky
It flipped a switch in my imagination
Is nothing happy for
This was bigger than the Bosco chocolate syrup girl
She was still pretty good
To a nine-year-old
2 weeks
Feels like a year
That was more than enough time for me to untether myself from The Familiar sounds of Buffalo
And absorb the subtly different tone and tempo
California
Two weeks on the west coast and cleared my mind
I'm ready for the next phase in my radio commercial Journey
After my vacation ended
I was sent home to Buffalo via the scenic route
I spent most of my time in the observation car with the new transistor radio my uncle Owen had given me
Is it going away present
The radio
Model named Juliet
Was about the size of an iPhone 5
It was an inch deep
And came with a leather cover
Airsoft
The Lamb's Ear
The most importance
You had
An earplug
The earplug look like a piece of automotive technology from the Balkan Wars
Brown and round is a walnut
Attached to the radio by a coiled wire
Listening with the ear plug was a new experience for me
Was like being in
A radio cocoon
Station after station
Commercial after commercial
I slowly began
Overdose
Timeade
A disturbing discovery
The more I listen
The more I recognize the sameness of all the stations and commercials
After hours in the second chamber
A group award
I wanted to hear
Something new or something different
2 Days Later
After passing through the American Heartland
The train had a one-hour layover in Chicago
My plan was to stay on the train
Listen to the ballgame
And read The Amazing Spider-Man number 38
During the first inning
I fell asleep
I have a dream
You can call it
Is now
I am in Chicago
Belize might rain season go outside
I'm walking through a secret tunnel
But I have to be careful
Because it was dark
I don't let to a theater
Suddenly
Bud Light come on
The lanky man in a black suit blocks of a few steps onto the stage
Impose a greasy Sheaf of papers
Instaread
A small jazz band
Get to work
Behind him
Want you to know that I love my baby
And my baby loves me
Short time ago we went out together
A place called ferret
Double rainbow
The Rhythm was they having stillborn held my babies and she gave me a list
I knew we were in the same key
Everything is beginning to swing
The quiet years later
I would learn that this combination of writing and music that was called
The word jazz
The Pioneer who created
Was a man called Ken nordine
Then
I heard a train whistle
I woke up
Nice nap
Back into reality
In the beginning
Nordine was simply a writer and a performer
A lot to say
To supplement his meager income
He began making radio commercials in the world jazz style
As we pulled out of Chicago
Nordine commercial played
My Juliet radio earphone
Heaven's head open
I heated The Voice
I could be
Think with your tongue
About lemon
From the first smack
Your tongue can tell the lemon
Something else
Something so subtly obvious
Buy something so obviously sad
Yet
There was a feeling among yesterday's times
The something else that is lemon wasn't getting its just desserts
But that was before the sheriff labor but
Nothing secret about slavery but accepted gives you a perfect Lemon Jelly dessert every time
Best thing that's happened to 11 since trees best thing that's happened for tongue since please
Play Everybody's what makes this lemonsoda lemony lemon
Reward your family with the sheriff jelly dessert Meyer lemon not all
Jellies are created equal so ask for share of jelly dessert
The lemon dessert radio spot was like nothing I'd ever heard
But it was just
What I've been searching for
Nordeen have created something fresh
My seemingly came
They didn't have much hope
Did anything else like this would be coming down the line
Perhaps I was too young to see
Nordine was a harbinger
On the last Friday of the summer of 66
I arrived in Buffalo
But I wouldn't be there long because that night at dinner
My father announced the family
Is moving to Toronto
As long as I had my comics
Giulia radio
And uninterrupted access to my favorite Buffalo media
The move to Toronto meant little to me even be a good thing
As a child growing up in the sixties
I can't say I love jingles
In the 60s
All the jingles I heard word reiterations of Jingles from the past
Sure
It was cute as a basket of puppies
For the most part
Nothing more than tuneless mindless junk
That was until the summer of 1967
Very strange things begin to happen in the universe of the lowly jingle
67 The Beatles record Sergeant Pepper at just come out and popular music suffer.
Massive disruption
Guitars Barnyard sound at Illusions to Lewis Carroll and stockhausen
Sergeant Pepper's land with a bang
And so big what's the batting Sergeant Pepper's that jingle producers on a mad scramble to copy the new
You sound
One of my neighbors
Went berserk
At a barbecue one night
I remember more telling my mother
This is the biggest thing ever
What am I going to do
How can I compete with a goddamn Beatles
My mother
Looks solemnly at her freshly manicured fingernails
I said nothing
Beatles course
I've always been badgered to endorse products the being the Beatles it was not to be
Is a Beatles wouldn't make a triangle there were plenty of musicians who would stay
Still giddy from the success of their single white rabbit
The Jefferson Aeroplane accepted an invitation to make a jingle
The invitation and by way of Levi Strauss the clothing company who are anxious to draw attention
Line of white jeans
It may take a second or two to grasp what you were about to hear but it's a jingle all right
Summer of Love Triangle
Listen to the way Grace Slick summons the spirit from a pair of white jeans
Jefferson Airplane
Beyond the shadow of a doubt
Strangest wrinkled to come out of the. Was a spot
Remington electric razor
It was produced by Frank Zappa
Teaming up with an unknown singer Linda Ronstadt
Zappa produced one of the most magnificent liad jingles
History of radio
Can you play something
Dania
Of course
Senior Management at Remington
Rejected Zappa's bingo
I don't know why
Because that was jingle is a one-of-a-kind creation
Rihanna
It's a strange shaving itself
Over the next three years I adjusted to my new life in the Dominion of Canada
I went to school
Stumble through the nuances of Canadian English
And because Buffalo was only 35 miles south of Toronto across Lake Ontario I could still pick up
My favorite Buffalo stations
While exploring all the Radio Toronto had to offer
CBC cfrb
By divine intervention
My father igadget free
Acquired an enormous 72 track reel to reel tape recorder on which I learn to record and edit
When I was 12
My voice began to break
My future
I was going to become a voice-over actor
In radio commercials
Maybe
If I was lucky
Beyond TV commercials 2
One step at a time I warned myself
One step at a time
My voiceover nom de plume
Chris Christensen
Reading into the Sony tape recorder as Chris
I practiced every day
I read copy from a magazine ad
To make my first radio commercial
Experience
In 7th grade
Add a friend to intentionally dress
His hair
I look like Andy Warhol
His name was Taylor Reed
Taylor's father mystery
Account executive at the ad firm McCann Erickson
Erikson's biggest client was Coca-Cola
On weekends when Taylor's dad have custody of Taylor
I would often tag along
And the three of us would hang out at Mr Reed's office
Ed McCann
One Sunday
In February
Mystery took us into the boardroom
Sat down
And he explained he had a top secret radio projects show us
I wanted our opinion
Penny press the button
Curtains closed the Lights Went Down
We sat in the dark
And waited
Voice
Such Angelic purity
Pierce through the silence
The hair on the back of my neck stood up
I'd like to buy the world a home
I'm Spanish and whoever lost apple trees and honey
July 3rd
I'd Like to Teach the World to Sing
After the new coach angle plate
Mr. Reid said
So what do you boys think
We gave the thumbs-up
Boy
Are we right
The simple words and Melody of the new Coke jingle suggested that the clearest path to Utopia
Through the mouth
Of a coke bottle
Bill
Apostrophe or not
To this day
I'd like to buy the World a Coke
Remains one of the most popular jingles in the history of radio
When FM radio came on the scene I put my Juliette portable transistor radio in retirement
Acquired a new portable Panasonic radio with AM FM reception
And stereo ear plugs
The new radio was smaller than a paperback get bigger than the Juliet
Every Saturday and Sunday night I would lie on my bed in the dark
Autauga lacrosse the frequency band on my Panasonic
In search of new things to hear
About time
I was very excited that I had discovered the concept
Of irony
I was always on the outlook for tiny ironic moments
To test my new capacity
I need detection
My solitary weekend listing parties
Typically went something like this
Saturday night
CompTIA wgr radio
Buffalo
Tuned into Larry King
Copic the Vietnam war with actor Jane Fonda
You always be
Honorable moment
An Army Recruitment ad produced by Ken nordine yes the same word Jazz Ken nordine I'd heard in Chicago
Played right after James delivered a rousing speech about the hypocrisy and Evil
The military industrial complex
You're a failure
James without a job with no future
Majority of opportunity swings open and success
Wakes you have a ghost of a chance
Don't despair
You're still young there's still time
Who escaped from a dreary future
Choose your own job training in today's Army
Say goodbye to the evil eye
Sunday night 8 p.m. CHUM FM Toronto
Show
Firesign Theater radiopublic tonight athletes in action
Heaviest show you'll ever see
Surreal stream-of-consciousness comedy radio show
Produced in Los Angeles that often made coded references to recreational drug use
Usually
Marijuana
Memorable moment
The Canadian Department of Health was a key sponsor of the Firesign theater show
So during commercial breaks blisters were bombarded by endless rounds of anti-drug PSA
Lexus weird contributions during Indian classical musician
Ravi Shankar
This is Ravi Shankar travel around the world
I seen that
TNT + searching
What it means
Shrek and peace happiness and spiritual awareness
Find a cation light fixtures
Without using any tracks
Killian once you have the elixir of life
You don't need her tricks to make your life more meaningful
In highschool I was a loner a real Holden Caulfield
But I managed to avoid most of the humiliating pitfalls of adolescents with a Rapier wit
Stolen from George Carlin
And because
I was always wearing earphone
After graduation I took the radio and television Arts course at Ryerson University
Rice owls reading weather reports on the student radio station
CFR app
On sunny days on chilly days I would call for work
I was a real barrel of stupid Collegiate labs
After my freshman year with Roger Stone
I got lucky and landed summer jobs a boy Friday at at Toronto recording studio called
Morgan Earl sounds
I was the lowest rung on the ladder
My daily duties included vacuuming
Picking up my bosses dry cleaning
Cataloging tapes
An endlessly restocking mid-priced wine for our clientele
Of attractive Ad Agency creative Department workers
These were the beautiful people and now I was a monkey
Morgan Earl sounds specialized in making two things
Radio commercials
Engine coils
On any given day I hear an amazing Cortez radio commercials with a voice
Catherine O'Hara Eugene Levy Rick Moranis and John Candy
They come on we're paying you to say Dorval Circle huh Harlan. As easy to get to as a
Easy route number one
Harlan Auto at the doorbell
Easy route number to take the prince, that the source is full of
Do the Winners Circle
It store Valsartan you say that
Best in General Motors car sales and service
Choice
Are you having problems at home or something you can't read the script
I mean it's right there
As easy to get to cuz they are to talk to at the Winner's Circle
After two days on the job I was shocked when one of the senior producer has invited me into the studio
The witness the production of a radio commercial
Blisters
Will never set foot in a recording studio
Here's how it looks
The recording environment is comprised of two rooms Studio
And I control row
Studio soundproof and contains microphones and headphones for the performers
The control room
As a variety of speakers recording devices and a mixing console
Which allows you to edit
How to assemble the recorded material
There was also plush seating
Includes leather-bound sofas to catch the occasional spilled drink
In those days
The control room era was Richmond the unmistakable Aroma of Ampex 456 recording tape
Kohl's campfire smoke
And styrofoam packing peanuts
Are asteroids everywhere
Strewn around the road like sleepy domestic house cats
Where the Coterie of writers producers and client Representatives
Given the often experimental aesthetic of the time
Excessive Second City and Saturday Night Live
Many commercial recording sessions relied not on Scripps but on the improvisational Talent of the performers
I remember being at more than real one night
Watching Second City record a commercial
We're not coming federal election
Here's an outtake
What do you have to do to get people involved in politics
I sure we could rent buses for them and force them to go to these meetings
I think
What do you think we have to do to get people involved in politics
I think we should have send the more letters
I tell them what's happening and
Make them read them
Excuse me what do you think we're going to have to do to get people involved in politics and good government wash if they don't go to the meeting she attacks
Just talk some real heavy
Hit him where it hurts in the pocket
I think
Political party
Should be parties
I think that's what people are
Attracted to fun
And you make politics fun
And you got a lot of
Great things about working at Morgan oral
For the out-of-town guests
Henry Winkler
William Shatner
And Alice Cooper
I'll stop by for one reason or another
Familiar face at the studio
San francisco-based radio Raider interviewer and genius
Mouse Sharp
Mao specialty
Is the man on the street radio commercial
I spent one day
Operator assisting now recording some commercials outside
Piles fedora
Mao
Is one of the most fascinating and charismatic men
I have ever met
Of the many lessons mom taught me that day
The most important lessons in fact was
How to talk
With complete strangers
Malka talked almost anyone
Because he knew the power
A kindness
Well this is a mouse sharp along with Randy Anderson and of course in the background you hear the people of California
Chanting for valbrun to defeat the Rival chip you can hear them as they sing Bell by Bryan Bell by brand
Brian in the background man you're out here and you can hear these people if you think this is going to be good for sales
It's the new thing it's new anything you understand what they're chanting
Potato chips a dog what does it sound like
I mean it's incongruous so in summation you think it's going to be a good year for Bell brand potato chips as long as they stay
So I think it's going to be a good year for betabrand
Regardless of the chanting because their product is so good
Now what else do you want from me
If it's it's 12
Did you notice the pint-sized musical flourish at the end of the Bell potato chips pot
It's called a tag
Tags belong to a musical genre that began as an experiment for a waiting breakfast cereal in 1926
Abuse
What began as an audio experiment for a waning breakfast cereal in 1926
Wood
Over the next five decades become a distinct Musical 4
Call
A jingle
Although I was exposed to thousands of jingles in my childhood
To what you've already heard
Who'd have known there was a creative jingle explosion
Just around the corner
Shingles have been around since the beginning of radio
The 1970s
We had Peak
Jingle
But since they fell out of fashion so long ago
This might be a good time to review
What actually makes a jingle
A jingle
Shingles always have a catchy Melody that's easy to sing
They must be earworms
Brewing their way in and staying there for days
Lyrically
Some Jingles try to create a vague atmosphere of desire in the listener's imagination
Other kinds of triangles
Play to The Listener with more specific Appeals
Underlining the virtue of a product's price
Speed
Sexy news
Or mouth-watering ingredients
Traditional jingles
Come with the chorus of singers
Repeat a catchphrase or tagline near the end
What did jingle really does
Is bind an emotion
To a product
Service
By Design
Ingles bypass the analytical lobes in the brain and instead
Stimuli
The nucleus accumbens
For pleasure centers
Once you hear it
A jingle creates an itch that you can't stop scratching
Between 1970 and 1980
Add companies produce thousands of shingles
And for good reason
Change was in the air in the 1970s a new generation of very sophisticated
What is a jingle jungle and couldn't help and write music that appeal to their generation
None of this came as a big surprise to me
Because in many ways
I was one of them
Growing up on a diet of Steely Dan
Joni Mitchell
How could I not have them
Fake dr pepper
The first time I heard be a pepper in 77 I had to pull over to the side of the road
Randy Newman and Jake Holmes wrote the jingle which begins with a startling statement
I drink dr. pepper cuz I'm proud
I used to be alone
In a crowd
What
A dr. Pepper bottle to cure for alienation
Let's take a sip
MC
For me
Be a pepper
Was an Awakening
Listings for calling radio stations requesting to hear a hit song
Power of this fact
Wasn't lost on me
At 20 years old
I began producing radio commercials
Can I join the musicians and actors Union
I began writing
Play the singing on jingles
Reading to Union newsletters
I discovered the Toronto was a hobbit wrinkle innovation
What does a real spider of the universe
Was
New York
40 seconds
So
Like thousands of starry-eyed kids with a dream
I moved to Gotham City
Department
And hit the pavement with my demo tape in hand
As luck would have it
I was still working
I was a writer and a producer
I work for ad agencies and sound production companies
I listen to As radio ad shortened from 60 seconds to 30 seconds
I gasped a great tivity was off and crushed
Find increasingly Powerful Beast
Call market research
Despite the many obstacles
I was always in the studio doing what I loved most
Making radio
No matter what place I am or era I'm living in
One thing has always been clear to me radio commercials are never the main course
What's a complimentary basket of garlic bread you get at an Italian restaurant radio commercials
Order the rapper
Something you expect and sometimes take the light in of course I'm like today
Complimentary basket of garlic bread
The very first radio commercial was written and produced without a known format
Fallout
No one knew how short or how long it should be
But if it would work at all
And what if anything would happen after it went to air
August 28 1922
Wef radio in there you are
A man called
Mr. Blackwell
Stood behind Mike and urged unsuspecting listeners to leave Manhattan
The family-friendly tree-lined streets of your health
May depend on it
Enjoy
Jackson Heights
Friendly environment
History doesn't say what happened to Blackwell
The response to the radio commercial was overwhelming
Because within days
The Viking Apartments
Omar Thorne Court Apartment Homes
Golf
All of this
Because of one simple radio commercial
The Hawthorne radio Caracol spread
Every Station in New York understood the potential
Crushed
Finally
Way to make real money
Radio Embrace commercials
Radio commercials became a mainstay
The radio experience
What began as an audio experiments from 90 years ago
Eventually became a worldwide industry
Billions of dollars
Brilliant
Silly
Thought-provoking or moving
The Humble radio commercial
Became the fuel
Allows radio to play the news
Music
Stories
We've been listening to
Ever since
For the organist
KCRW and mcsweeney's
Onclive
Desmond
This was just an edited version of part 1 of Clive Desmond's two-part personal history of radio advertising
Do the rest check out the organist from KCRW and mcsweeney's
There's a link on a website or on the subject of the sound
Radio changing our lives I wanted to share a clip of me talking about my first favorite radio story which is
Isn't a radio story at all it's from a movie that's right after this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of May
Handmade sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another room in a voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
See, go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flash podcast
So my friend Chuck Bryant is 1/2 of the Charming Josh and Chuck of the original nerd out on Tiny details podcast
Called stuff you should know
It's probably the first podcast I ever listen to and I still love it
Meaning does Josh and chocolate are just so great spend time with
Chuck has his new podcast it's really fantastic it's called movie Crush
Where he might people he likes to talk about their favorite movie of all time
And I went on to talk about Jaws
Belle Isle of Jaws
And so does Chuck actually and my favorite scene is when the Shark Hunter Quint
Tell the story of him being left in the water after his ship that USS Indianapolis
Was sunk in World War II
So here's a part of that monologue
Japanese submarine slammed two Torpedoes into our side gif
It's going back
The island of tinian the lady just delivered the bomb
Hiroshima bomb
Eleven hundred men went into the water
Michelin down in 12 minutes
Didn't see the first job for about a half an hour
Tiger
13 footer you know how you know that when you're in the water chief
Tell by looking from the dorsal to the tail
What we didn't know
What about mission of Ben so Secret
No distress signal has been sent
They didn't even list is overdue for the week
Very first black chief
Conclusion
Sweet formula shows into tight groups
Satellite gold squares in the Battle Lake nuc in a calendar leave the Battle of Waterloo in the idea was
Jack is the nearest man that many steps pounding hollering and screaming sometimes
Sometimes he wouldn't go away
Sometimes that shaggy looks right into you
Smile into your eyes
You know anything about is Shaggy's gun
Lifeless eyes
Black eyes like a doll's eyes
Soca
Music of me talking to Chuck Bryant
About that scene
On with the crusher
I love
Radio
So much
I love the storytelling radio
It is still like my ideal form
And I think of Quinn story as the first
Radio story
I ever really loved
If yak
It is told
Just perfectly
Like right like you could almost see it
Like
Storycorps music starts
It starts you remember some teenager going oh my God
Can't believe
Is it perfectly told natural
I think I just think the radius or I would cut it out and put on the radio in Heartbeats
Perfect
And it's funny cuz there's all this stuff all this
Rate activity you've already had the adventure music playing
You know in the barrels and shooting it and everything that that moment
So riveting
That's my favorite moment in the movie
I mean one of mine for sure and
The backstory there for that scene was that that was not in the book
Spielberg brought in the Great
Screenwriter and filmmaker John Milius
To write that monologue
And then apparently Robertshaw himself to who was a playwright went in and
And did some rewriting on it and kind of worked with Milius on it
You know Justin's up being
Like one of most iconic monologues
Movie history for sure it is so good and it's so naturally moves from one scene to this car comparing to the other
Weather and
In the fact that I've thought about this a lot it's like
Because it's get called out because they're comparing scars and Brody says
What's that on your arm
And it's at its
The removal of the tattoo of the Union Indianapolis right and
And I think about that all the time like
Remove it and like what is going on in his head that he would remove it instead of keep it there
And
With every part of his character that you get in other ways
That seems like this extreme moment in his life
That you have no knowledge of it just have this little tiny peek into
And I love that part of it too
I never thought about that
That is super interesting that you would
Annette Annette
The old Sailors don't have tattoos removed
Yeah yeah exactly to like that the level of
Trauma or whatever he was trying to get away from or whatever it was like it was
Clearly something that haunted him
In a way like it was not an adventure story to him
Yeah what what happened
And
This is something else I guess you don't really know it's an incomplete narrative but I've tried to fill that
In my head lots of times and I never come up with like what I think is the answer
But it
They may have to do with it
I'm trying to get away from it end
Vim willingness his willingness to talk about it that moment
How close is Garden in the short amount of time but also
That he senses that the Peril that they're in
And wants them to be really aware of what
You know what's about to happen and what about to happen like
Having two most immediately after work like they start start starts knocking into the boat yeah
In the next scene
Yeah it's funny I never really thought about it but it's almost like
Quit knows this is the last time I'm going to tell the story
The whole episode with me or any of the other Great Gatsby
Talking lovingly about their favorite movie
Go to movie Crush. Show or search for it wherever you listen to podcasts
99percentinvisible is Katie mingle Sharif Youssef
Sean real quick. Delaney Hall Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Meza and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all a podcasting
We are supported by the Knight foundation and listeners just like you
You find 99percentinvisible enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Instagram Tumblr invited to
Did you want to see the latest video we made with the Box
About controversial shared spaces
You have to go to our website
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast.,