99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When somebody gets in the car wreck
Examine exactly what happened is there any accidents working right now Joe
They're called police officers
Talk about reporting.
This is New York state trooper Frank Bandera and riding shotgun with benjiro is Stan
Elkhorn from the investigative reporting podcast
Rubio long last spring
Add to see the paperwork
Open
Reporter's right here
In the past 50 years the car crash death rate
Has fallen by nearly 80%
And one of the reasons for that drop
Have to do with this accident report form
It's where Bandera writes down the weather
Draw a diagram of the rack
Identifies its primary cause a whole list of possible
Things but there's a million
I mean try to cover the bay CA there Animal Action connect
Play ideas Crossing Road
I tried to tell my wife
Safest thing to do
Slow down
As much as you can without
Beyonce
Drive straight through tiananmen
Really yes
As We join the Long Island commuters on the Southern State Parkway
Call comes in
Over the radio
This turned out to be just a fender bender
But if it were one of the more than 30,000 fatal car accidents that happen each year
Staying here for now
The information gathered on the side of the road
Weirdo from that accident report form into a federal database
The fatality analysis
Recording system
Anyone can use this database in car company safety Advocates and Regulators are combing through it
Constantly
Looking for patterns that help them understand how and why people die in car wrecks
Which then helps designers and Engineers GradeSaver vehicles and roadways
The data and forms all kinds of design decisions around car safety
Everything from speed limits to mandatory seatbelt
But this culture is heavily regulated data-driven Auto Safety engineering it did not
Always exist
In fact at first automakers tried to
Keep data about car wrecks themselves
They not only resisted making cars safer they argued the very idea of a safe car
Was impossible
Story starts in the early 20th century
Car ads didn't talk about their safety fee
They talked about
Styling
I'm the richest player of its new fights with rear fenders right up to its bold but elegant new front style
The new Power style Chrysler emphasizes the forward look
Power in motion
Looks like it's still moving
Stop spam design
Chrysler safety director actually compared to Cars 2 women's hats
Saying that quote
They have to have special attractiveness
And sometimes that you can compromise
Function
When safety was discussed
It wasn't about the car
It was about the driver
Unfortunately there are drivers amongst us
Rockport Sports
Within 25 years of the first known
Fatal car crash automobiles had become the leading cause of accidental death in the US
But all those deaths were blamed on the quote
Nut behind the wheel
They are the wrecks
Who caused the accident that Meme and Q
Another words cars don't kill people
People kill people
The whole notion that the machine could have some sort of impact
On the likelihood of you
Surviving a car crash
Wasn't even on the radar
During the first half of the
The 20th century
This is Amy gangloff
Historian who studies Auto Safety
Safety-wise how would you
Characterize the cars
Compare them to the
Large part they were deaf
Traps
Get seatbelts and airbags the first cars had windshields made out of regular old plate glass
If your head went through it
You could get stuck
Wood shards
Glass pressing into your neck
But before someone could come up with a safer car
Someone had to come up with the idea that cars could be safer
Getting off traces bad idea to a self-taught scientist
Computer Haven
You tell me
Alex of the Haven being interviewed
The project really started in 1917 and 18
When I was just fine
That's the Canadian Air Force in World War 1
When he was just like
24 hours away from being commissioned
He had a horrific plane
Accident
I ruptured my liver
I left my conscience
I rupture my gallbladder
While he was in the hospital he had his kind of moment of his epiphany
He concluded that there was a sharp knob on his safety
The belt that I'd probably led to his injury
Until we started thinking that perhaps we can package human beings
Better
Not just an airplane
But also in car
The Haven started by crash testing objects dropping eggs onto padding
From higher and higher Heights
He found an egg could survive a 100-foot fall if it landed on a 3 inch thick rubber mat
Benny turn to human beings
Tracking down the people behind actual newspaper headlines like
Girl falls 10 stories lives and tells a bit
Any marines that we are just like eggs
We can survive seemingly unsurvivable collisions if
The impact of spread out
Tell her time and space
Like when you fall into soft dirt
Or get thrown into a seatbelt instead of the windshield
Finally he turned to what was actually happening to people's bodies in the most prolific source of high-speed collisions
Cars
Do that
He called up hospitals
Corners and police officer
Most of whom
Thought he was nuts
Why was it supposed to be
The crazy
Well
Is a very
People
In those days
Feel
If you get in a crash
You're going to get
When your not hurt
What they called a Jesus fact
The Havens crazy theory was that would happen to people's bodies in a car crash
Was not just luck
It wasn't something you couldn't calculate or change
It was a predictable product of the car's design
It seems so common sense now it's hard to even register it
What is the time
It was revolutionary
And in the 40s and 50s to Havenwood prove it was true
In 1953 he partnered with the Indiana State Police for a year-long stay
Their photos and
Reports from doctors in Corners able to isolate which parts of the car where the most dangerous in a crash
And there are things that we don't even think of me
Like hard unpadded dashboard send
Steel knobs with sharp edges
Stuck in people's skulls
Yeah he's
Diagnosing exactly what's causing the injuries inside
The car
And then what does he find what exactly did he find
Is causing
Busby's injuries
The steering column
The steering column itself was not collapsible
So if you had a front-end Collision the steering column with push up
And might even push
Sprue somebody's chest
Like a spear that might actually impale somebody
The solution was the now ubiquitous collapsible steering column
A technology that saved 79989 lives as of 2012 according to 1 governor
That's more than anything except the seatbelts
But collapsible steering columns wouldn't become standard equipment in till 1967
More than a decade after results of the Havens Indiana study were published
Because car companies just did not want to deal with his funding
Car companies for very paranoid about having a discussion about safety
In the 1950s because of discussion about safety was pretty much going to guarantee the people start thinking about the day
Dangers of driving
And it's just not fun to drive when you're thinking about a knob getting embedded in your skull
Steering column being jammed in your chest
I mean one of the things that you to have an is definitely looking directly at is
Our mortality
And it's kind of the analysis of risks in general require us to think about something that a society we
We rarely if ever want to think about
Better for society to think about it
Would take more than an academic research
It would take politics
I want to have my name so you remember where I am
This is Joan Claybrook
Joan Claybrook would eventually be in charge of Auto Safety
United States
1965 she was a political novice
Coming to Washington for the first time as a fellow for the American Political Science Association
And I I signed up to work with a member of Congress
Atlanta Georgia
And
He was concerned about
Kids in this neighborhood
Man killed
In car crashes and he is very unsafe at any
Speed unsafe at any speed was an unlikely bestseller by a car safety obsessed young lawyer
Name Ralph
Nader latest book and that's the first time that I realized
The car design was
Crucial
Can your survive on a car
Crashing
The book took research by people like you to Haven and turned it into a scorching indictment of the Ottawa
Mystery issued car companies actually patented safety technology
Including the collapsible steering column
I just want using it
I got to know
Because I was one of the most
Williams audiences play all the things you want to do
Behind the scenes Joan Claybrook work
With Ralph Nader on a bill to regulate the Auto industry for the first time
Neither would give testimony in front of Congress
It sounded like a grad student reading is overly academic thesis paper
Just for flavor here some from 1960
Mr frenetic activity
Deserve their corporate employer
These lawyers
Became Afflicted with a tunnel vision
The brings with it
The Familiar lawyer malady known as
Retainer a stigma
Warren and that sound
The Auto industry was
Terrified of Regulation
Andolina
And that's why the Auto industry
Heritage jumpsuit
Trail near me
I got some dirt on them in
Try to discredit
This was when the greatest cell phones in American political history
General Motors didn't get any turn on data
The word got out they were trying to undermine him and it made General Motors
Just
Terrible
And that's what they did and that's what made him a national hero
I gave a lot of power
In just a few months the car companies
Had helped energize a movement to regulate
Car companies
And that movement
Succeeded
Distinguished
Members of the Congress the administration
Friends
On September 9th 1966 President Lyndon Baines Johnson addressed more than 200 guests at
At the White House Rose Garden
Including Ralph Nader and the President of General Motors
What they heard was a president talking about cars in the language of Public Health
Are yours now we've tolerated a raging epidemic
He called it
Highway disease
A disease that have killed more than three times as many Americans as all our Wars
Despite our technological advances
We were failing
Secure it
In this age of space
We're getting plenty of information about how to spend Menen
Space
And how to bring them home
Yet we don't know if
Foreshortening
Baltimore auto accident
Cancer caused by faulty brakes
Bye-bye soft shoulders
Are by drunk drivers are eaten by the deer crossing the highway
And with that
LBJ started signing bills
Traffic safety act will ensure safer
Better protected cars
In the event
That bill created a new federal agency
What's now the national highway traffic safety administration
It had the power to make car companies install seat belt
Collapsible steering column
And to set up those crash database
And in case that wasn't enough this bill to create a powerful government agency to regulate what were then some of the large
Largest companies in the country
It passed with nearly unanimous bipartisan support
The 60s
Sprayberry
Different time
Thank you
Technologies that were mandated in the 1960s like seat belts and collapsible steering columns are still saving
Thousands of lives each year
But the car crash death rate has continued to drop decade after decade in part because of
Smaller sudler design changes
And understand how those changes happen
You have to go back to the government databases of car crashes
The ones fed by police officers like Frank Bandero and use-by safety engine
Mike Matt
Tumblr
Matt brumbelow is an engineer at the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety
Poor iihs
Honest SKS bolt a car headlight
And a giant paper book of federal regulations
Federal Register
Define pastime
About 10 years ago Matt was looking at that government databases
Fatal crashes
Government-run website
Sifting through the data he noticed something
People dying in head-on crashes
In cars that were rated safe
In head-on crash test
A lot of these crashes had a distinctive look
The passenger side was okay
The driver side look like a giant had destroyed the corner of the car with a croquet mallet
Pushing the bumper
Past the engine and the wheels off
Be there completely off for push
Way back towards dock
Did it take some
Set a time to recognize or was it like a man
Fairly immediate
He immediately recognized that this was a kind of crash
These otherwise safe cars
Hadn't been designed to withstand
Switch to math
Was an opportunity
We can probably do something
Sing about it
Something like designing a new crash test
Test IHS has been doing since 2012
I went one of these crash test for the BMW X1
And in the hours before the main event it's kind of how I imagine it would be backstage
Team of people running around making tiny cosmetics
Tweaked star
Except the star is a compact SUV and instead of hair and makeup
There are sensors and instruments
And huddled in one corner of the room Engineers from BMW
Tibbetts Creek
Make sure you're doing everything right
No they drink always everything
Portrait
Butt watching
Closely
Because BMW has a lot riding on
An earlier model got a marginal rating on this test
One step below acceptable
So BMW redesigned the car
Always design for the new requirements
Should have seen your requirement from the IHS
We have to redesign our cause
How car is doing these tests
S'matter
2 car buyers
And so it matters to car makers
These days safety cell
And it justifies an incredibly rigorous technical process
What are you doing
Seat belt sensor tape so it stays
The breeze long These Bars
What's the movement of the
Belt
This is Tyler Ayres
Dummy
How many sensors
Right now at least for my dummy is 39 total
39 total
Tyler measures that crash test dummies position
Down to the millimeter
266 NE fingerpaints the dummy's face
Half pink half blue so we can
See where hits the airbag
Kindergarten
You're pretty much I said I got a job at the circus
Paint clown face
Let's walk out of here
When we walk into the echo ecrash Hall
It feels like more than just a test of a car
It feels like I'm watching the whole cycle of Auto Safety in action
You got the new and improved redesigned X1
And you got this meticulous data-driven evaluation
39 sensors sending out 10000 samples a second
For the 17 seconds it takes to drag the X1
To a speed of 40 miles per hour
Destroying this car
In the hopes that maybe its next incarnation
Can be even safer
A couple months later the rating would be announced
The X1 went from marginal
Too good
And it was named in iihs
Top safety pick
And this change started with Matt brumbelow the safety engineer
I found a need for a new kind of crash test by going through government crash date
Any terms of doing the work that you do
How important
Are these
Federal databases
Real world car crash
Yeah there
Real
Crash data
We're just be guessing
Biersbach the Centers for Disease Control put out a list of the greatest Public Health achievements of the 20th century
On the list are vaccines
Fluoridated water
And
Motor Vehicle Safety
Decade after decade
Cars keep getting safer
Because Regulators activist and the automobile engineers
Keep looking
How drivers get hurt
I'm finding more things to improve
It's a never-ending process
It always begins
With data
But it is not a universal process
It hasn't happened in all Industries
The odds of dying in a car crash have dropped by 80%
The 60s
The odds of dying from
A firearm
Have actually gone up
Have you been listening to this
Maybe you've been drawing parallels
Between cars
Encon safety
If so
You wouldn't be alone
When pundits get together to talk about the latest mass shooting
The hook Virginia Tech Columbine the list grows somebody
We can bring it up
An interesting analogy and it's actually quite telling legal expert Michael Waldman
You know we
Affected who could drive
We lifted the drinking age to 21 for
Stop eating so people wouldn't drive recklessly we put in airbags we change card design
In other words we changed
Cars and made them
Safer and
You know the question is are there ways to do that also
With guns
Other pundits will rightly make the point that cars and guns are very different
What is designed to help a person get from point A to point B
And the other is specifically designed
To injure or kill
But people in the public health field that's kind of beside the point
Guns are a major cause of death and injury
And whether or not those deaths and injuries are in
National
Researchers want to know whether or not their prevent
They want to know if a change in gun design
Oregon laws about gun ownership
Or some other Technique we haven't even
Thought of yet
Could cut down on the more than 20000 gun suicide
And more than 10000 gun homicides that happened each year
Some experts think the first step could be to treat guns more like ours when it comes to research
For example
Public Health Professor Stephen Terrace
It's called for creating something that does not currently exist
Comprehensive database of deaths like the fatality analysis reporting system
But for guns with data about the victim and the perpetrator
Whether they've been drinking details about
The device itself we don't have those data with regards to gun deaths
So now even though the number of
Motor vehicle related deaths and gun deaths in the United
Stage are approximately the same every year
We have data for one we don't have data for the other
Starrett used government crash data
Tell look at airbags and child restraint laws
But then he shifted his Focus to guns
And the difference was Stark
Instead of just downloading government data did the gatherers own
Corners and police
Like a gun safety Hugh de Haven
Only 50 years later
It was hard
It was expensive
And some information like
Specifics about the guns used
He just couldn't get
There's been a culture that
Built up
Around guns
Not collecting
Information
Where is the exact opposite
Has occurred
With regard to
Cars
If you had to boil it down
Is there one big thing to point
That explains
That difference
Well yes
There is one big thing
And one powerful thing 2.2
Referred to as the NRA of the National Rifle
Association
For every chapter in the history of Auto Safety
There's an opposite chapter
In the history of gun safety
Usually written with the help of the NRA
We're Advocates of Auto Safety sued car companies
Advocates of gun rights made it nearly impossible to sue gun makers
Congress created registry of drivers and then made it illegal
Create a registry
And for each of the hundreds of millions of dollars that the federal government spends each year on Auto Safety
Siri search
Gun violence research
If Penny's
And Scatter it knows all of this
All the people I talked to he was also the most hope
Which I found kind of
Hard to understand
What lets you still be
Optimistic
Looking at all those
You're trying your best and
You're doing a fairly good job
And making me
Sink into some swamp of despair
But I'm afraid you're not going to
Seething
And that I'm not going to do it
And one of the reasons that I'm not going to do it is because
I understand something about
How Public Health made progress over the century
He points out that it took more than 50 years to really reduce smoking in this country
And even though some 27,000 lives are now saved each year by Technologies.
Like seatbelts and airbags
It took decades to get people to even pay attention to car safe
Progress in public health
Just takes a really long time
There's hardly any examples
In public health where someone came up with an idea
Everyone rallied around the flag saying that's a wonderful idea let's implement it immediately
That's not how it works instead it's a fight
To collect the data to identify what we can change and finally to make the many small incremental model
Vacations
But eventually save tens of thousands of lives
People tend to think the car itself as a critical factor in keeping them safe on the road but car does not
This is one piece of the puzzle
The engineering of things people might crash into on the side of the road
Play say less obvious but nonetheless critical role in Road Safety to
Are some cool examples of that
After this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
To engineers and designers have done a lot to make car safer
And we hear about their work
The public statistics and vehicle advertisements
But there's another less
Visible Dimension to rotate
Which involves the
Better Vehicles often crash into
And I'm here with our digital director crackle dead
Let's talk a little bit about that
Side of the equation
We tend to think of
Post
And support things like
Streetlights and telephone wires and road signs as being robots by Design
Have to be to stand up to the elements right
But sometimes those same supports actually have to serve a really
Function
Which is
At the break in just the right way
And I get hit which helps minimize vehicle
Designed to stand up and be started
But also to get knocked out
So how does that work
Popular type of solution is called a slip basis
Basically instead of sticking a whole pole into the ground
Which could do a lot of damage
It's hit workers assemble a pole out of two pieces
First there's a low-post
The top plate that just
Sticks up slightly above the ground
In another post
Is attached in both of that
And that
Upper pole is the one that holds the
Exactly most what you see is that upper pool
Any idea is that when a car hits that are proposed
It will then break away for the Lord post and cause Wells Fargo vehicle and let starts with I
Annie's awesome mix fixing a post
A lot easier after Collision because often a new top post can just be
It's all that happened
The old base that just got left behind
So the connecting bolts
They snap from the force
Of the car hitting the upper post
Similar Buck stays intact and that's
Really
Clever solution texting pretty simple when you think about it
But how did you even learn about
That's because you know you see them
They eat that's not obvious
Yeah they're they're everywhere and I'll be honest I never noticed them before
And looked at me interested in
Wrote in about the
And then I start again about the lady called my dad who's the physicist answer key with him about them and ask him about the Four Seasons
Play it how it all worked
Really hooked me was this one particular Breakaway sign post that Tom
Send a photo of
Rather than a pair of flat plates like that first one I described
Where the upper and lower post
Seedo connect to answer to this plant intersection
This example
Angled
Okay so you show me the picture of this when the plates are angled
Up
In the direction of
Travel yes exactly
In this so-called
Incline slip base system
It does something pretty remarkable
So instead of shooting just sideways
Is like the normal post
Top of the post actual
Please put up
An out-of-the-way
So the angle plate
Sims 4 broken toes upward rather than just
Fast forward video this on our website and it shows a car hitting a signpost
And then the whole time. Is over the car and then lands behind it
At least can work great if you know the kind of
Direction of travel right the directions
Acted so for example along the right-hand side of her
Right
So they're flat and their angles the basis for individual post but
There are lots of other types to write
Oh yeah there's a lot of really need to re-issue
Spike on some roadside sign for example they have liked to post supporting the one on either side
And1 Breakaway post
I'm freaking closer to a lame can flip out of the way while the other post
Actually hold the sign
And therefore the vehicle can just pass like most so doesn't even break away to the bottom
1/2 kind of collapses exactly
Peyton Place
And then there's have a bigger version of this on telephone poles
WeChat hinges all the way up
Top so they can actually break away at the base
And it should have been just crashing on the car they they just kind of swing out of the way and the other post take up the load
Of those lines on either side
So the telephone line
Hold up the rest of the telephone pole once the pole is broken away
Whole system down on top of you
Just crush your car
That's amazing
Emojis aren't looking for them you start seeing these Breakaway systems just all over the
Send the droids in the mechanisms very there's a lot of difference
Subtypes butt
Usually if that connection to the ground in one form or another
Kurenai also recently worked on a video with
Kristofferson Fox
Media about improving traffic safety
By removing signed entirely
Urban designers call it a shared space approach
And it's a very data-driven but also
Complex and pretty controversial
So you can check out that video and also see images and videos of brakeway posts in action
On our website
What's 99 pi
. org
This show is produced by Stan Alicorn and edited by Delaney Hall mix and Tech production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Delete mingle is our senior producer recruit Kolstad is the digital director
Progressive staff includes Avery truffle
Emma Fitzgerald
Aaron Masa and me
Roman Mars
Thanks for the medical center archives of newyork-presbyterian Weill Cornell
Put the audio of you to Haven
History came to us from the podcast reveal
From the center for investigative reporting and PRX
If you want more deep reporting in your ears you should really subscribe to reveal
Every week
They're working with investigative journalist around the country and around the world
Expose wrongdoing hold people accountable
And Estelle Greatsword
Like how the town of Kermit West Virginia ended up with 9 million Hydrocodone pills
Or what the pizzagate pedophilia conspiracy theory tells us about Russian trolls
Find reveal on radio public or apple podcasts or wherever
99percentinvisible is a project of kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from prxz collected by the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
And listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoying discussion about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at room in Mars in the show at 99
API org run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But our true home on the internet
Is 99 pi
Daughter
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com