99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
At some point in your life you probably encountered a problem in the built world
Something that was poorly designed and effects was obvious to you
Maybe a door that open the wrong way we're poorly painted marker on the road
I know this is kind of stuff all the time even more so now after creating the show
I'm sorry if you do too because you listened to the show
And mostly when we see these things
Wii Grumble on the inside
In that
Do nothing
There are all sorts of reasons for inertia
We don't know how to fix
It's not ours
Fix
We could get in trouble that's producer David Weinberg
You might notice these little design flaws
4 years
Silently
Human
Until
One day
He calls me instead
Okay we're doing at
It was early Sunday morning August 5th
2001 Los Angeles Califor
Richard ankrom and a group of friends were on the 4th Street Bridge
Of the 110 freeway
They were about to commit
Give me a high-profile dangerous situation
Natalie can I get arrested I could kill somebody
Really
Was terrified of that
But let's back up
About 20 years prior
Richard ankrom an artist living in Orange County was driving north on the 110 freeway
As he passed through downtown Los Angeles
Who's going to merge onto another freeway
Dye I-5 North
You missed the exit got lost
For some reason
It just stuck
Years later when Richard moved to downtown Los Angeles he was driving on the same stretch of freeway where he got lost at
Decade before
We looked up at the Big Green rectangular sign suspended above
I realize why I missed the exit
Because it wasn't
Adequately signed
Bad wayfinding
The exit for the I-5 wasn't indicated on the green overhead sign
There was even a big open
Space where there should have been a blue and red Interstate Shield
And above that
It should have said north
It was clear to Richard
Caltrain
California Department of Transportation
I made a mistake
Sir Richard and artist and sign painter decided to make the Interstate 5 North Shield himself
In the place he thought it should have been all along
High above the 110 freeway
You would call it an act of Guerrilla public service
I would like to do is to be
Public servant
Ord
Or actually to show
What you can do with artwork
You can put in plain sight have a functioning working thing for everyone to use
Richard started by studying LA freeway sign
Holding a Pantone swatches
Perfectly matched
The paint color
Did dangled over Bridges to measure the exact dimensions of other signs
And most importantly
He downloaded the Necronomicon of California road signage
Batkid
The mutcd
The manual on uniform traffic control devices
Quote to provide for uniform standards and specifications for all official traffic-control devices in
It's not a beach read
I have a lazy Sunday afternoon
All aspects around line so
People can
Bid on projects
Richard wanted his sign
To be built to the exact
Specifications
Caltrans
Which were designed to be read by motorists
Traveling at high speed
Chill with
The five on it
3 ft
Roughly High
And why
Less than eight
7 inch barrel
It's still pretty strong
And above that it cuz the word North
And that was
I will. 14in
By 5 ft
And again I use the same typeface that we
Was there in the same signs I tried to match
Closest I could so
It wouldn't be obvious
Caltrans
Richard's brand new edition
Had to blend in perfectly with the existing signage
Which have been collecting dirt and smog
Decades
I sprayed the whole thing with a
Right then glaze
Gray
Can Knockdown
After he finished it Richard sign his name on the back of it
Black marker
Painter signing a canvas
Then came the next phase of the project
The installation
Cheap land
The Precision of a bank
Ebody disguise a white hard hat and an orange vest so he'd look like a Caltrans worker basically looked at
Deportes as best I could
Animated decal for his pickup truck meant to look vaguely official that said
Aesthetic
Deconstruction
The night before the insulation
Richard drove out to the site
Kids movies
Supplies to the be easy to get to the next morning
Randolph Utah
He took me to the
The spot
Xiaomi
Stashed
Okay we're basically here
Right now the it isn't that fit but it was a lot thicker and I had
Play sweet but I not trade stash the ladder and the sign
After he hit his things
He climbed a tree
I just sat there
Don't do everything
I just heard calm myself down by being there and hang around with it and I
Richard was worried that he might drop the sign
Onto the road below
Drivers going 60
B+ miles an hour would have no time to react
Something landed on the road in front of them
Or Worse onto their car
That was a scariest
Saying about
Somebody got hurt
Project
It would have defeated the whole
Idea
But despite some reservations
Richard was
Pretty confident
Call the Whole Thing Off
And
He gone too far to turn back
And that brings us back to the morning of August 5th
Richard did not act alone he asked several friends to film the insulation from different Vantage points
Amy inoue was one of the friends he Enlisted the film
We did it
6 a.m. or 7 a.m. on
Sunday morning
It was tense
Because
We all thought we were going to
Richard had chosen the Sunday morning to put up the sign knowing that there would be little traffic and The Morning Light Rising above
The skyscrapers would be just right for filming
What he hadn't anticipated was that Caltrans at also picked that morning to do work on the same stretch
Batch of Highway
Yes they happen to be doing some other work
On the freeway
Just south of
When they saw the Caltrans workers
They thought about turning back
But I had surmised after all this is a pretty large city there be more than one sign
My assumption was that think the other guy was too
Richard Park his truck
When everyone was in position with their cameras
You went to work
The hardest part was getting over the razor wire
With the ladder
Once he was up on the catwalk really 30ft
About the highway
He started screwing in the new sign
Careful not to drop any
Screws
Cars below
Halfway into it
We just
Felt like okay
Lincolnway with it or what.
The whole thing took less
30 minutes
As soon as it was up
Richard pack up his letter rushed back to his truck
Blended back in the city awesome
I think we all went out
We're super relieved in
Really happy
Only a small group of people knew that the Interstate 5 shield with the word North hanging above the 110 freeway
Was it work
He didn't stay to us Don't Tell Em
So our friends all knew about it
Happy
But it never
Tweaked-out
For a while
For nine months
The secret stayed within a small community
And then Richard sprengeri
Repeat the story
What the hell Gary why can't you be cool just be cool Gary Richard Secret
Without the Caltrans
And the Press from the fake magnetic sign on his beat up blue truck
Work order proclaiming rush but it is against the law to Capron says it has no plans at all without charge
Cards Against actually found out what happened
Apparently they sent a crew out there to inspect
Richard was hoping to get it signed back from Caltrans after they took it down
He was thinking you would hang it in an art gallery
But Caltrans didn't take the sign down
The Caltrans inspection
Cuz that's really that
Define elope
Cast of how am I
How good the artwork is
It stayed up for 8 years
9 months and
14 days I believe
It's not exactly
Pretty close to
Interviews about the incident with other news organization
Caltrans didn't exactly
Dawn Richard's handiwork
They were pretty kind about
Here's the Caltrans spokesperson
At the time he did a good job but we don't want him to do it again
And in fact you did such a good job that I'd like to offer him a job application
More than eight years after Richard sun went up
He got a call from a friend who noticed some workers taking it down
Richard contacted Caltrans to ask if he can have his signed back
By the time I tracked him down
It already been crushed
Bale
Going for
Who knows what it turned into
You could be a waffle iron
After Caltrans took down Richard sign they replaced it with a brand new one
But this time
Incorporated his ideas
Into the new design
They out of the 5 north and The Shield
Not only
That's fine
What to do additional one
Up the road
A little epilogue
Richard's highway sign is a happily Ever After Story the sign work
People appreciated it
No one got hurt thankfully
Even Caltrans was really pretty nice about the whole thing
There's another gorilla sign story out of New York City a group that calls itself the efficient passenger project has been hanging
Find in New York subway station
To tell people
Where they can board the train to make the most efficient transfer
The project is not at all affiliated with the Metropolitan Transit Authority
But the signs look just like MTA sign
Black with white helvetica lettering
They say things like
Bored here for best transfer to the 4 5 and 6 train
Board here for best transfer
F&M trains
It's the kind of knowledge that you build up over time as a regular Subway Rider and this gorilla sign maker is offering
To everyone
I know some of the plot of the signs
Not all New Yorkers are
These are secrets some say
People should have to earn unbalanced the cars they say leave signage to The Experts
The MTA for their parts
Is taking down the signs
As fast as they go up
MTA spokesman Kevin Ortiz
Told us in an email that quote
Posting of the signs
Is considered
An act
Vandalize
Point being if you decide to undertake an act
Guerrilla public service
Just know
It may not be received
That sucks
There been a bunch of fascinating extralegal Public Service intervention since we are this story a few years ago
A Roundup of those
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
Does routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
The efficient passenger project isn't the only group that's gotten ambitious with modifying New York City subway signage
99p ice Kirk Olson is here to talk about a similar intervention and some other creative works of gorillas
Thank you actually led me to the story of a Rhode Island School of Design Sue neighbor Ryan Murphy
Also took up the challenge of Subway signage
And his project was pretty simple but also pretty clever he installed a bunch of signs
About exits at eye-level about 5 feet up
On stair risers
Daddy was that train passengers looking at the staircase from below could then figure out if those steps would take them
Where they wanted to go
Stair risers are basically the flat front of a stair that you see
From the front
Yeah so think you walking up the staircase it would be
Right in front of you and you just have to look at it and be like oh yeah that's the exit I want to be able to get a more easily find a way
The system is a lot of real estate that signs to Havant
Occupied all that much
Ashley and of course
Like the other sign project has got taken back down and clearly the empty is not particularly open to gorilla
Snopes there they're not have you covered a bunch of these on the website over the years ohyeah Super entry Buddies
Kinds of gorilla public service
And those unpaid activist who do them
Creative people who see everyday problems as Civic design Opera
And mostly of course there were cats removed
But in some cases these projects actually lead to something more permanent
Kind of like the highway sign that David talked about in our peace
Exactly end up here in Northern California there's another group called
The San Francisco transformation eejit
Which is of course a spoof on the city's Transportation agency
And their crew has illegally built a number of gorilla bike Lanes around the city
And often they just kind of Barclays out with ordinary orange traffic cone switch
So you can just pick up and haul off
Since I get taken away with a mainly due
Is highlight
Design problem
With the current
Yeah in a lot of cases
But in late 2016 they decided to create a protected bike lane on a stretch of road along Golden Gate Park
And they use what are called Soft
Or see if hit post
Which are fut High
Bezel reflectix
And these provide a visible and physical presence but they're also easy to knock over so they don't really pose a danger to
But instead of just taking the post
Style and the city did something pretty remarkable
They agreed to run with the idea and it's all protected van on that same spot
Legal reasons I couldn't just leave up the post-credit
Same idea
I mean it seems like a pretty big win for like a really small group of people that are activists for bike safe
Yeah it was totally a 3-point shot for these guys at the transformation
But there are three goals of one drawing attention to unsafe conditions
To increasing safety for cyclists and pedestrians and three getting the city on board with more rapid and effective safety
And so this is I mean we talked about ones that happening
California
Rena Ware particularly Rowdy bunch of
Leftists in such a mean does it happen another places
Yeah it does not totally unique to California and
Cruising your cabinet install gorilla bike Lanes
Ellen Seattle there's this group called The reasonably polite seattleites that actually made a lane
They got taken down with initially
He was like really nice about it
Politely offered to return the post to the installers and then finally they actually agreed that
Just put that girl away
Backup
There's activity andele there's activity in San Francisco activity in Seattle is this a West Coast liberal thing
It kind of seems like there's a lot of that I talked to you earlier this year
Call the San Francisco Public bench project
2nd and everything isn't so much about Road Safety is it is about just making the city a nicer place to live by installing free
Free benches
So I contacted their founder 499 Pi feature and he said
Basically like he's been on boards and committees he's worked on promoting public space but he really finds his
Building benches to be more rewarding and over the past 40 years he's actually installed
Or 70 benches around the city
And he keeps improving his design as he goes to
It's so how does that work as heat
Never gets permission to do emerges doesn't Rogue no matter what
Make them cheaper these loopholes in the city codes which allow for sidewalk Furniture if you can of meet the right guy
Criteria and you don't obstruct sidewalk so you have found a gap
To put them in
In most cases he requests a bench for a specific spot
And then they agreed to keep an eye on it
And then if the community feedback is positive the bench becomes the
Does permanent picture of the neighborhood and he also offers tablets instructions to anybody who wants to can I DIY this and
Take up the mantle
Okay so it's easier to beg for forgiveness than to ask for permission
3 got interventions and built spaces like roads and sidewalks but
Activity related to Green spaces to
Indeed there is
The freeze Guerrilla gardening covers a lot of ground but essentially refers to any active planting where people
Aren't supposed to plant
So give me a garden without a permit would be a sort of simple example
And these can be about
Beautification activism food production or a combination
Does Little League Grassroots reaction to
Top down urban planning
Yeah a lot of cases it can be pretty small-scale and incremental like filling in vacant lot
Where to get a nicer Greenery
I'm you can find actually recipes and design instructions online describing how
To build water called
Seed bombs
The typically are balls of clay
You know compost and maybe a combination of local or Regional wildflower seeds and people
Petoskey
Bombs Over fences and obedient
Is better hard to access Newton Billy be able to get to the
And not all the interventions are just about
Beauty really they're they're trying to create something functional on the environment
Yeah I'm into this group in San Francisco of gorillas grafters and their idea is I mean
We have a lot of greenery but it's mostly
Is they don't want fruit creating messages attracting animals
And these guys are grafting fruit bearing branches on the trees in the city
To try to provide like local food source
Wow
And they don't care about the food messes and stuff well I think I think that their idea is that you know the good outweighs the bad
So far these interventions have been about creating a better Urban environment for the public good
But not every single one of these sign changes are doing it
Solely for other people's benefit
Oh yeah I know know there's there's definitely examples on the other end of the spectrum and there's a guy in particular who just died
HIPAA news
From China who got caught
Painting
An arrow in the middle of the street and it was broad daylight
And you know there's a turn arrow there already but he pointed this forward Arrow because
You know he wanted to make his commute
Basically
Pretty clearly self
Act
So we took a turning lane and turn it into a optional go forward and turning lane
And then he got fired
99percentinvisible was produced this week by David Weinberg his show below the 10 is an ongoing series from KCRW that tell
Intimate stories about the people who live in neighborhoods south of the 10 freeway in Los Angeles
Check it out
99percentinvisible is Avery Chapman and Fitzgerald reviews
Delaney Hall Aaron Mazza composer Sean real senior producer Katie mingle digital director
Ted and Me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We're supported by the Knight Foundation
Sticker loving blisters
Like you
Even the show enjoyed scussion about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
The real 99p ihq is that 99 pi
Daughter
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com