99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm roaming
It's the end of the year and time for annual Minista
How many stories are quick-hit stories
And we're making pitch noise from someone in the audience or something interesting we saw on Twitter
What is the cool tidbit
We found in our research.
Stucker heads
Season 1 come out
But they didn't
Whiterun
Episode treatment for whatever reason
They're also this great opportunity for
Price to get to know the
Non-scripted version of
Define people who work
Work on this job
And if the person who can stay interview though
That is my favorite
We have some real
Turmeric
Love stories of mysterious iceboat
Stream Bruins suck
Dresses steampunk violins in a little
Update
Couple of the notable City Flags open redesign
Can be fun
First up is senior producer
Katie Mingle
Okay we're going to start out by meeting
Denise
Hi my name is Denise Boniface
Am I own Optimus diving in Rocky Mountain House Alberta Canada
Yasso Denise is from Alberta Canada where she owns scuba diving
Anthony
In Alberta as you may know is not a
So is your scuba diving
And Alberto you're doing it
Clear cold air dark there murky
It's kind of creepy to
So there's this one leg called
Trisha surrounded by mountains it's right in in a mountain valley
Very very remote
If you find the right spot on the lake
And I've about 30 feet down heel
You find a ship
It doesn't really look like except it looks like
Iowa Lumber that's all broken up and
Laying there
And then there's a lot of refrigeration coils
What are the refrigeration costs for
We're going to get to that
Okay for now so
You make your way down sort of through this murky Darkness
Like pile of
Lumber and debris 868
Hey girl and gets excited
It's pitch-dark but if you shine a light on it
Read it
And Denise
House Reddit operations how to cut a secret world project involving
Special built January to April 1943 with a prototype
More information contact with Canadian parks
Westchester
Wow
So there's like a hyperlink
In the bottom of a lake www.
What is a QR code
Yeah it's okay so there's so many things about this pack that I love I love that it's
The bottom of the lake Isle of
The part where it says for more info contact the Canadian Park service because it's cuz you could just
Stumble across this wild
Like strolling at the bottom of a Canadian lake
Actually I asked Denise that and she was like yeah you you could because there's a lot of people to tighten this leg
But of course the most intriguing part of the plaque
Is the part about the sea
Secret World War
To project
Involving the use of ice
In shipping
So what was it
So okay so in the early
19/4
During World War II
German submarines
U-boats
As they were called
Or basically wreaking
Havoc on Allied ships in the Atlantic
Ocean just
Thinking then left and right
And So eventually this person named Admiral mountbatten
Goes to Winston Churchill and he's like
We have to do something about this
And I think I know what the solution is
A giant Unsinkable
Aircraft carrier sized ship
Made of ice
And actually turtle is intrigued like it sounds like one of those
Farfetch'd ideas that the kind of gets flooded during times of War but never actually gets billed
Except for this
Really did get built or at least
A prototype of it
God built and that is the Shipwreck
At the bottom of
Patricia Lake
And that's what
The plaque commemorates
Wow
So what in the world made
Admiral mountbatten
Think that an unsinkable ship
Should be made of ice
Yeah
Sole
What the hell
Reply so that was a big
They were actively looking for alternatives
And then the second thing is that they they hopes that this ice ship would be
So dense
And it would basically be induced
And what made them think that ice would be indestructible because it doesn't
Seem like that
Bright
Oh it actually it wasn't just play nice
If they weren't they're going to build these ships out of a mixture of
Of ice and Sawdust
Kampai
Named after its inventor a guy named Jeffrey
Sophie mix
Serve water and wood chips together and then
Frozen and maybe ice
Really really strong
And so this guy Jeffrey Pike he
He invented not only by creeper
Came up with the idea of building a ship out of it
And then he got that idea
To Admiral mountbatten
So the ships will be built from blocks of
I treat and then there would be sleepy pipes
With coolant running through the hole
Keep it up
So that's that's the refrigerator
Are quails a Denisa the bottom
Anti crease really was
Dislike
Credibly strong and then
Mixture then there's this
Amazing anecdote in the story where Admiral mountbatten
Who is not the inventor of high-grade but
She's like the main kind of
Evangelist for this idea and he was so
Hype about it that he brings
A piece of pie feet to a meeting
This is a meeting in which they were trying to convince
The Americans or the British were trying to convince the Americans to
To get on board this
This crazy ice ship
Plan
So he brings a block of Pie Face the meeting along with a regular block of ice
And at some point he does this demonstration where he
Shakes out his revolver and he shoots
The regular ice
And it's
Splinters into a thousand little pieces
And then he
He shoots The Patriot
And the bullet bounces off the pykrete and actually sort of ricochets into the leg of one of his car
Successful actually
Play take Claritin total success and and they're all like thumbs up like Greenlight Full Speed Ahead
And yeah they did they decide to go forward with this crazy plan Winston Churchill signs off on it I'm not sure what
What all Americans
Sign off on it but they
American said we'll help you
You do this and then I guess at some point they also got Canadians involved because they
They end up building
This prototype on this little late
In Alberta
Mike Patricia
I named it project
Habakkuk
After a Bible
And I think the verses
Pretty interesting Cemetery today cuz
Behold ye among the Nations and look
And wonder marvelous
For I am working a work in your days
Which you will not believe
He told to you Bible verse
We are building a crazy thing thing
And habakkuk apparently was the name of the Hebrew
Prophet witch
I certainly never knew
Prototype itself was built by Canadian conscientious objectors
Didn't know what they were building and who had opted
For alternative service jobs
They were like giving this
Job and not really told that it actually was
Abortion before the war
In just a few months they built a prototype of this ship but it ended up being harder to build and then more expensive
Then they thought and by the time the Prototype was ready
The Warhead kind of moved on like they were figuring out how to build the atomic bomb
They figured out how to mask
Produce smaller aircraft carriers
And in the end they basically Scott the project and ultimately let it sink into the bottom
Aflac Patricia and
As we know you can
See it there today
The coolest thing about diving the habitat is being able to stay that you don't
Like its it is cool to Diamond that's nice
But today but too many times it's not that interesting
Yes apparently like if you build a ship out of ice if I just sort of like
Turns into nothing
The bottom of the ocean
Once
You've seen enough
That's fine that's awesome
Special thanks to Debbie Schneiderman who sent in the tip
Project habakkuk
Jesse send it in response to the mini Stories episode that we did last year
So if you also have a mini
Suggestion
We do read them
Reaches to the contact
At 9 p.m.
Next up producer Emmett Fitzgerald
All right
Are you ready
Yeah you should just start
I don't know if you're going to do
This is a story about a ruin
Probably
The most
Famous Bruin maybe Roman Colosseum
Aerocool
Nyurban
I've never been
I've also never been but you can you can picture
In a white
Columns
Kind of Dusty
Denuded of all life and it just looks like a classic ruin
White and brown hawk
I think that's like yeah that's part of it image we have of ruins but I was on Twitter the other day and I found this kind of amazing thread
Read the future all these paintings from the 19th century
The Coliseum is totally green
It's like this
This greenhouse covered in Vines
Plants and plant life and it was a thread put together by this guy named Paul Cooper
Cheese Annapolis
Standard PhD researcher at the University of East Anglia and he studies the history of ruin
And he says that you know it until the middle of the nineteenth Century the Coliseum was totally overrun with plants
Shrubs and Vines
Growing everywhere and then like always
Artists and Poets were right about the Colosseum is this
Verdant
Greenhouse Charles Dickens
Arches overrun with green
And in 1850s this British botanist a man named Richard Deacon decides to do
Botanical survey of the Coliseum
Cataloging all of the plant
Growing on them
What will he find a grave
Are you doing, growing around on the crumbling ruins
So that's that Paul Cooper that's the total fertility the twitters right exactly
And he told me about all the
The different plants
This guy Richard
Confound 56 varieties of grass
Cypress Hills Harley-Davidson
Incredible variety
What comes out of Dickens book
Is this incredibly poetic description of
Scrolling landscape
But
Variety
Describes how it sits down
Cool and in the lower case of the Coliseum but the dryer and woman on on the top light
Microclimate
Steffes biodome of overflowing life
Specifically the some of the plants
I was so rather that they did not see occur anywhere else in Western Europe
And so
Deacon sits down and tries to start of workout
How these plants ended up in this one spot in this like iconic cultural spot is but it is sort of a botanical
He comes up with the hypothesis
Let me
These clowns must have been brought into the Colosseum
On on the phone or even the stomach
Of the animals the Romans brought into the arena to fight
Brahmin Friday
Gladiators May brought in
Giraffes and other kinds of African Wildlife for a ceremonial hunts inside the coliseum in the theory was
She has plans to traveling on the backs of
Host of other animals that move around that we've moved around the world
The bat might be there.
The cause of
5 what brought
These plants are the call
But so great
It's a little hard to
It's a cool it's a cool story
And
Paula Cooper
Really likes
Animal hunts
Proving humans can reach the level of civilization
Complete Dominion
Triumph of the wild and destructive nature of the natural world
But what's the Buried and in the fern and Gatsby's animals
What is natural seeds to ultimately going to
Innovate and climb over the household magnificent ruin
So how did it happen that
This
Inadvertent
Microclimate
Almost Greenhouse
Become the dusty dry ruin that we think of today
So in 1870 Italy gets unified under a secular democratic government
Take control of the city of Rome which I previously been in the hands of of the papacy
And this new government is really trying to say
Create a set of rational scientific modern Italian identity but they see that is really rooted in this ancient
Roman history
Until they care a lot about these old ruins like
The Coliseum and projecting a certain Italian this to these buildings represent
And the plants don't
The ruins
Hyundai
And even if the time there's some real pushback from scientist from the Botanical Community who say you know stop this is this like
Special micro ecosystem filled with all these
Totally unique
Plant species
Italian
Buff list and countess
Amazon TEAS test
Poetically
Archaeological cupidity
Oculus go
Staples
What's the time
Electronics
You got into the
The ruling party
The ruin was completely stripped and excavated
I completely cleaned witches
Unless you unfortunately that the state we find in today
Socially about whatever you think is
Proper thing to preserve I mean do you preserve it is true
The Vines were destroying the room in
But what is the cost of removing all the vines
And
What is the
History represented in the natural history of the things that are there
Cooper says that when he sees these
These beautiful paintings of the Colosseum
These rare plants travel there are potentially on the back
Interesting questions about
About what state
We should preserver ruining is it just
The rocks that the only thing that we care about our stories
Embedded potentially within other aspects of
What's there that
Tallinn
Parts of the history
Yeah it does make me sad to think that we've lost
The Romantic potential
Abyss
Site of this incredible ruins overgrown with Greenery
Buried stories hidden in these different layers of History
I don't like the floor growing up to take you to ruin can tell a huge part of the story
So
Talking to pollen and then you have seen the Twitter thread that he
Together and then later turn into an article at a really just made me think about
Historical preservation in Ark
Archaeological preservation really
What gets
To be a part of what lives on and what
We choose not to leave
But doesn't make the cut
Who's in the spaces
Always plants
In the story of the built world is not just
The things we build its all the stuff around it and it
It could be that natural flora and fauna
Effects
And there are still some plants in the coliseum in NC
Make decisions about what
The pick
The space and so it's smooth
Even there even more kind of
Outliers
So then the rest of the
Adult environment
Little bit of greenery in a gray
Concrete world
So a while back nine ipi's digital director Kolstad started researching
Story about
Sackcloth
Dresses
The type of DIY clothing
From upcycle of flour
And feed sacks
And we considered it for a full episode for a while but current had a connection to this
That made it even better
As a mini story
Homemade tack cloth apparel group really popular during the Great Depression
But as I was looking into it I thought the idea seems familiar somehow
So I called it this is story and I know to see if maybe she had told me about them when I was a bit younger
Okay
So
Can you
Tell us briefly
Who you are and what you do
I'm Sally Gregory CrossFit I'm a professor at the University of Minnesota
Where I teach courses on science in American culture
So my mom was born in Michigan during World War II
And her dad worked in Detroit at the time
My father was shipped overseas
So I call people from Michigan she refers to the shape
Of Michigan as looking like I
Gloved hand
And refers to it as the Fillmore the where it is in the hand right if they're trying to tell you where they are from
Expensive toilet there hand in Lake Point to part of that
Unlike other places in America
People in Michigan
To deal with shortages
In the late 1920s
Going to World War II
When I was a little girl my grandmother did most of the spelling for all of us
And so the fabric that she used for
But she would pick out by going to the local General Store
My great-grandmother would buy sacks of flour and then reuse those fat
And the flower stalks became on the fabric store
These dresses
Any other guy picture
Socks
Butthole rice or something which are
Terrible burlap
Style socks like what was the fabric like finely woven because it was
Need to hold flour
All cotton fabric
These days we think of flower is being something that comes in these smaller 5 or 10 lb bag
Made a paper
Back then it was a different story
So did the flower companies know
That people were using their flower socks
An upscaling them
As dresses
Yeah I've only started to figure this out over time
And they start to adjust their designs accordingly it's actually you think that would wash back out so you can have this clean white
White cloth and others went the other direction with it and they design these pattern
25 flour sacks with dancers are jockeys are bunnies are
Flowers are other interesting things in my mom's grandmother would sit through those options and
Bring home pay rent from the store
Cheap learn quickly
I didn't like
So I think she avoided pink Fabric or pink flowers on fabric
People that time also turn sax
Quilts curtains even diapers
Informers reused
Livestock feed bags to
Matt Patrick was rougher
But it still work for things like tile
Experience
Eating a piece of that
Apparently my
Great-grandfather had a feedbag Hebron like great-grandmother meet him for doing really dirty work
Like to dirty even for work
Helping out cows in labor
Are you really didn't want to wear even your ordinary work clothes because it was really a pretty bloody mess
Wow
So you could buy
Seed by a sack
Of feed for the cows
And then
That's
That's pretty crazy
That's what I recall
Tow companies across caught on to the sack fabric Trend and they realize they could boost their sales with nicer cotton and
Depression worse or the fashionable patterns
Along the way
And some manufacturers
Even sponsored National sack cloth dress making copy
She actually said
This quote that I really liked that it was part of the fabric of life
Is living in rural America
Ultimately these designs they evolved
Beyond just being Look fashion
I think is really fast
I so want to go to a fabric store and buy velvet
Are wool or linen
Was going to the General Store pick out your fabric
Because no matter what
Even if you're wearing
Crestmont Ave cycling
Do you want to look at you want to express yourself
Stuck at Universal thing
In some cases they fight about you
Bring him home
And I'm breathing the same family get out
Because of wearing the same patterns of Cyclops you could actually tell who is from what family by
Buy another pattern that they were wearing like a Tartan like I killed for something
So cool
This is been really great I love talking about this
I love the fact
My mom's a historian
That is just so interested in these things
Personal histories 2
Thank you so much for him
I'm talking about
Well I think 99% invisible
Give my best to Dad and I'll talk to you soon okay
Okay love you too bye bye
Oh I love it
Everyone who helped me get set up with all this
She was like okay you can you can cut any part of this you want that you've got to keep
She knows what she's doing
Alright thanks so much
Quieres to listeners who was an all the way to the end of the show
You're my favorite
When do the end of the show
You may have noticed
A new production credit
Since we started using
All original music
How did your voice on here why don't you actually introduce yourself and what you do with show
I'm Sean real and I'm the composer for Adderall the music
Until you have a Mini Storages that use your first money for it so it's my first
Radio story ever so there we go
Okay well congratulations so it's what's your
So it's the late 1800s and people are just starting to consume recorded music
In the process of recording at this time is
Kind of hectic and I like to imagine
A lot of fun but maybe
Maybe more hectic so
Before they use microphones and Studio sound was captured by these big horns
Which were made of like mainly brass or copper
And these recording horns
Would collect and focus
Sound Vibrations
Into this little diaphragm in the diaphragm would vibrate a stylus
They cut a Groove into a wax disc
Should I be picturing these recording horns pretty much like
Phonograph
I don't fashion photography that plays out to one of these
Yeah it's like the same thing it's
OK Google
Side part of images
Same backwards
The forwards for the problem with this process was that these recording horns were limited
In what sound frequencies they'd respond to
So certain instruments like
Tubas and French horns were which were also made of brass
I'll get picked up much louder
10 string instruments
Guitars
Violence
So now it is
We record every instrument on its own track and do a lot of leveling after-the-fact but
Back then they had to record whole orchestras with just one or sometimes
If they were really fancy of these like thing recording horns in a single room
And then they just make copies of the disc that they recorded on there was no editing
If there was too much French horn or if an opera singer like
And blew out the recording what their falsetto
You'd rather just go away and you do it again
So in order to get a balanced mix
I'm Different instruments and voices
Sound Engineers would arrange
Musicians
All around us
Studio add berries
Distance
From the recording
Sometimes they do have
Louder instruments like french horns
Pointed at the back wall away from the recording horn and the musicians would be watching their conductor like anime
And they put pianos on top of platform so that you know like the mallets and chords that are inside would be lined up
With the recording horn
And this one's on my face
They'd sometimes put a singer like on a little
Trolley
So that
An assistant coach
Wheel them closer to the horn for quieter vocal passages
And will them away during loud ones
Chaotic is like a Rube Goldberg recording of an orchestra
But the string instruments were the hardest to record
And because of that like stand up bass parts were often just
Play it on tuba instead
And a lot of Engineers
Didn't want to deal with
Recording violin
Very few recordings with violins on them before a certain time is that true
Well there were actually a fair amount of recordings of viola
But
He was part because of the engineers going through all the
Was troubled see these elaborate session
But also because of this
Okay so can you describe what you're holding
I'm holding Astro violin witch
My bandmate founded
Does novelty music shop and it's
It's got like
The neck
And
Like head and Bridge of a violin and the strings
But instead of like a body it's just got this like
Wooden rod and then
Dislike
Huge horn
Yeah it's coming out of it
A violin with the body that has the
Thinking that resonate that goes up against your neck when you play a violin that's all gone and then instead
Is this
Bisley a trumpet
Sitting on your pointed folded back into itself in the sound comes out of the end of the of the trumpet
Just like how recording was like
The gramophone back
Backwards this is also the same concept
Of the gramophone
Vibrating of the strings
Goes into this diaphragm that's down here by the bridge
And it vibrates the sound
Which cats
Projected out
By the horn
Wow that's amazing
It looks really
It's like
It would be the centerpiece of a steampunk Orchestra basically yeah there are there are
Steampunk bands
Bat that uses
I would love to
That's awesome
In a way
In its native state like in this room it kind of sounds like
Like an old recording of a violin because it's going through that diaphragm and Hornet has a little bit of a
Electro-acoustic
Sort of seeming processing
Yeah that's part of it is that like the reason why recording sound that weighs
Because that's what
The old recording horns were like
Able to pay
Pick up and so what this was doing was actually
Amplifying
The frequencies that
Like the recording horns
Right toe is sore design
To speak to
The horn that is doing the recording in some ways like it's the it's the analog to match on the other side of it
To make it even better.
Another thing that it did was it actually like
The horn
It made the sound more directional because all of these musicians had to like
Funnel their sounds like into this like one
Christa corn in the corner of the room it was really helpful
When you can have a violin that would point it sound directly at the horn rather than like just radiating out into the room which is like
What the resident body usual
Every little while it was a big deal on the recording industry
These designs replied all kinds of instruments Pro guitars Joe cello through mandolin Stroh ukulele
Please and actually a lot of instruments that
Like weren't under the Stroh name but there was just a lot of
Different instruments like from different companies that
Utilize this design
Instro is the brand name
Lasko is the name of the person who invented the first
John Matthias Augustus Stroh
And so were they all manufactured by the company that was destroyed company or is it just a design that was
Excuse by anybody
Astro violin company in them
They kept manufacturing them even pass
Astros death in 1914 his his son picked up
Where you left off whenever a lot of articles that were speculating about where it fit in
To the broader world of music I like this one in strand Magazine from 1902 that I found
I was pushing
Hard that these instruments were the future
But what is a great importance
Is an entire absence of
This is a point that's so Lopez will value highly
Immediately it is finished
And it will produce marvelous tone and quality of sound
The original violin has been a cherished item
The spirit of invention
Respect no one's prejudices
Amazon actually phone up that all
Fighting underneath with Chara
Kind of a relative to the straw violin
It's okay I see you have one but what would happen to these instruments in the in the larger world
Soho round 1925
Electric microphone technology made its way into recording studios
Broader ranges of instruments
Became more possible to capture
Soba spot of items
Events no longer like
You know made the same practice
Soda straw violin company slow production and then finally shut down in 1942
Can you tell I'm sad about it
And a lot of people write about them is kind of like the silly flash-in-the-pan thing but
We're a really valuable tool for the beginnings of the recording industry in
Without them
There are a lot of Records where violins
Wouldn't have been is present probably
Studios or I wouldn't have bothered
To record them at all
So after they were necessary because Recording Technology
Advance
Did they just come fizzle out as an instrument
Are there actually still around
You can find them and why do you send folk music from Romania Myanmar
Shakira yeah destroy violin player is part of her 2010-2011 tour
Resonator guitars
You know those ones with like the partly metal bodies and they got kind of like
Nice designs
So those are the same technology
And one of the inventors of the resonator guitar
Visited the stroll Factory
Like in its heyday
And there are a number of articles
Say that
Eustis designs off
What he saw there
So it's still lives on to this day and what is it that you mean you said you're a little sad about it but why are you sad what is it
To do for you what do you enjoy it
I think what I feel sad about is that okay
It's so different than a violin and like
The Strand magazine art
This is
Like better than the violin and of course you know like
Violins
Around headband
Prolong timer like
Know better than
How many sexy kind of a little bit more limited range by definition
Senna violin
But it has a really kind of
There's something nice
That sound it's a different kind of range of
I just think that like
It's wonderful to have like
Cool well thanks
Sprinter distance to Bistro Vineland
Thank you Roman
We're going to take a quick break and I'll catch you up
A couple of notable stories in the history of flag redesign
Catalyzed by the TED Talk
I gave a couple
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
IPic
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info slide podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
So in March of 2015 I did a main stage TED Talk
Talk where I talk to
About the designer flags and
Mini city flags around the country were
Particularly awful
And I performed it live
Collider podcast
And
I used the voice of
Icelandair extraordinaire Ted k
Explain his by Design Prince of
Is total blast
And what's great is that since then there have been over a hundred flag we designs in the US
It's been fun to watch people engage with their civic symbol
The new way
Burlington Vermont had an open call flag
Aqua design contest
To replace their coat of arms Style
And the competition Was Won by twin 12 year old brothers Owen and Lucas Marcus
It's a white
Green and white zigzag stripe on a blue field
Very
Congrats guys
A particular note in the flag redesign world is the flag of Pocatello Idaho
Pocatello was voted the worst city
Flag of North America by the members
North America
What's the West Coast
And it was kind of the punchline
APA TED Talk
And after they heard about the talk
Invited me up
The Pocatello to Spur their flag
And it couldn't have been nicer and more gracious
But a fantastic time there
Breakfast with the mayor CBS Sunday Morning came to Pocatello to do in national news piece about their redesign
I think
Even though I
I was having a little fun with them
The city came away from the experience
Really excited and enjoy the attention
And best of all
After a year-long effort
I got a new beautiful flag the new flag is called mountains left
And it has three red
Symbolizing three local Mountains on a field of blue
A blue line at the bottom
Representative
Portneuf River
And at the top of the highest peak
Is a Golden Compass Rose
Representing book
Bus transportation
Is a fine fine
I hope to see it
Everywhere
I'm up there
If you're curious to see a picture of it
But we'll also have a picture of it on our website
At 9 p.m.
. org
Well done
Is it real
Going to take a little break until 2018 but I'm going to put some surprise 99
Guy stories in feet
I know you'll day
So you can buy
I'm happy New Year will be back in 2018 with another mini-stories installment
Between the rest of the crew and I
See you then
99percentinvisible is Avery Chapman
Emmett Fitzgerald
Sharif Youssef
Delaney Hall
Aaron mattes
Composer Sean real
Senior producer
Katie Mingle
Digital director Court Coast
And me
Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On Radio Road
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from Price Collective the best most Innovative shows in all Apopka
We are supported by the Knight foundation and sticker loving listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoy discussions about the show on
Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi Oreck run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
The real 99p ihq is that
99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com