99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things find out more at 21st century.
Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When people critique
Cul-de-sac
A lot of time there actually critiquing the suburbs more generally
The cul-de-sac has become a sort of like the mascot of the supper
Mike Epps Suburbia had a flag
It would have a picture
Have a cul-de-sac on it
I can still remember how strange that words sounded to me when my mom told me we were moving from the city of Atlanta
To the suburbs of Denver
And that we'd be living on one of these
Things
Hey that's pretty sure Katie mingle do my work this week
The cul-de-sac is a French term literally meaning
The bottom of the back
Or the ass of the back
So it's no wonder the French themselves prefer to use the word
Empath
Another fun fact the plural of cul-de-sac is actually culs-de-sac
But Katie and I have agreed that it isn't possible to refer to them this way
Without
Sounding like a couple of aspects
I've always felt a little embarrassed by my Suburban roots
By the cul-de-sac especially
Which
With its uterine shape and having the words
Sock in it
Give me the feeling that I spent my early years coddled and sheltered
In an asphalt womb
Living on a cul-de-sac
Has come to symbolize
Got everything that young hipsters or
People who are
I don't see Suburbia as the American dream
I've come to despise and it's taking on the symbolic role
That's Matt Lassiter
And I think he just called you a hamster
Yep I think you did
Epitomized Suburbia both in it
Busting the myth of the
Going to happy nuclear family American dream and in the way that critics
Condemned it as a
Facade
That teaches a history of the suburbs course at the University of
And the great age of the cul-de-sac is the 1950s and 1960s
Matt says that by the 70s and 80s our faith in the nuclear family and in the Suburban American Dream
Was starting to break down
And it's evident all over Pop Culture
Like in the 1980's classic
E t
At the beginning of the film
We learned that Elliott's parents are
Divorcing his father is down in Mexico
The car with him
Girlfriend
Is Mom's there alone in the family sitting around the table
And they're very sad
Maybe you ought to call your father and tell him about
I can't
He's in Mexico with Sally
And then et qualms
From outer space
You almost like a savior figure
To bring happiness back to this
Sad broken
Suburban family
And I think it's really striking in the film The Way That
Elliott can
Confine
Freedom
And excitement
In the suburbs by riding his bicycle
Note to the end of the cul-de-sac and then beyond Into the Woods
In the kind of magical
Friends
Where the subdivision
Stops in the
And the wilderness
Again
E t
Is devastating to me and I get last year's point about ET providing the escape hatch
3 horrible oppressive cul-de-sac but I also think you can't deny the fact that the kids in E.T
Ruled the neighborhood
I mean the boys outmaneuver the feds on their dirt bikes
It's a great place
To be if your 7 years old and you want to ride your big wheel
Out in the street
But it's not a great place to live
I would argue if you're 14 years old
And want to get out of
The neighborhood
And you don't have a car then you start feeling
Trapped cul-de-sacs do tend to be iced
Oscillating
They aren't connected to other streets
And they're far away from town centers
But even though cul-de-sacs are experiencing a backlash right now
They were themselves part of a design backlash
Against Urban living and the traditional grid pattern streets
That make up most cities
We think about
The cul-de-sac Bass
Subdivision
And it's obvious
Which is the urban grid pattern
But if you go back before World War II there was a third alternative
Which was the early Garden suburbs
That had curvilinear Street
But they were designed
The fit in with the landscape
To create buffers
Between the houses
To integrate people into Park
Send
Lakes and other natural features
And so it was the opposite of the grid pattern but it wasn't
The
Cul-de-sac
Bass
End of the road
Dead end pattern
Are the streets almost always came back around
The other Street
It was when the suburbs became mass-produced
The war that the worst aspects
Suburban design began to dominate
Little boxes on the hillside
Little boxes made of ticky tacky little
Whether or not you buy the idea that cul-de-sacs
Psychologically oppressive or stifling to the freedom of those that live there
They have some real quantifiable design flaws
Great Lake imagine me a garbage
Butter or streak
Instead of driving down one Long Street
And collecting all the garbage from that street and then
I'm taking a right under the neck
Street and so on
You to turn around and all of these
Cul-de-sac
Over and over again
It takes more time use more gas
They're expensive to maintain some governments
Like the one in the state of Virginia
Are starting to ban them
In all new develop
Chicago.
About speeding cars
Wait here we go
My mom
Hey Mom
Hey honey
Research about
I guess I'm wondering
You love to call the
Because it was
Place where
You know you were allowed to go out there all hours of the day and night and play
Be pretty much unsupervised
Oh she sounds nice
She's the nicest
And it's true I did love the cul-de-sac
I didn't like school and I didn't fit in there but none of that seemed to matter on the cold
The cul-de-sac it was all about ghost in the graveyard and signing the guts to launch off the skateboard ramp
And that was a world I shined in
My parents they always seem like they live there too
Just for me
And after I moved away
Eventually they did to
Now my mom and dad live in a new development that urban planners would refer to as
Mixed-use
That's shops and houses and restaurants all mixed in together
I love it
They live right above the gap
There's a library within walking distance
My dad helps little lecture series and their condo
And I like that as they get older they won't need to be dependent on a car to get what they need
It's perfect for them
The frick kid
When they play
The one family that I'm thinking of who live up
Fifth floor
Their children are pretty young and they have talked
They go to different parks around the area
Going to parks with Mom and Dad doesn't sound nearly as cool as taking over an entire Street every night
What type of suburban development that's organized
Around the needs of
5 year olds or 8 year olds or 10 year olds
That's the last straw use that we shouldn't be design in our neighborhood
Exclusively around the needs of 5 year old
A new studies are showing that as gas prices rise
People become more ecologically conscious
We're already seeing a reverse fight back out of the suburbs and into cities there are even fears
Where's the suburbs will turn into Ghost Town slums and ghettos of the future
I really give ghost in the graveyard a whole new Edge
99% invisible was produced this week by Katie mingle from the great Third Coast International audio Fest
I'll look it up
And me Roman Mars
With support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity it's a project of a alw 91.7 local public radio
Show in San Francisco
The center for architecture and design and the American Institute of Architects
San Francisco
Annette Moore go to the website is 99% invisible
. org
Everyone is roaming again and
During this little section the podcast last week
I asked you to
Have you the show night Tunes
And maybe told like it's over on Facebook
And I was
So overwhelmed by the response it was so sweet and
Kind and generous in
I think we got Alex
60 or 70
More views
Last week
Because of that
Call out
And over a hundred more people on Facebook so thank you so much
Why can't I mean it was just amazing
Who's more successful than I ever thought possible self
If you did take the time to review the show
That was really sweet and if you haven't yet
I'm happy just to have you as a listener but if I can put you over the edge to write a review
That would be fantastic to because
I swear
Those reviews kept me in the top 50 ranking for Arts podcasts
All week long and it wasn't because
I got some huge Spike
In download so just because of your reviews that's how it work
It was amazing
Thank you so much and was so sweet to read a response to his really really
Beautiful
And the funny thing is
99percentinvisible is now on
Stitcher
So
Check it out
On Stitcher it's like an iPhone app that
Chains together podcast into a little playlist
And it's actually works really well and
Fun
And I just wanted more people have a chance to hear it and maybe
Get new ears soaked
You used to chirp like the show
Let's do it again maybe it'll go up the rankings there too and new people find it
All right
Thank you so much
I'll talk to you next week
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden 2 playlist
Like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of thing if you
Days ago Wesley Stern in actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found
I'm dead in my private gym crossed inside a high-tech weight machine even
Worst the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to file
Find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com