99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is part 2 of the 2017-2018 mini Stories episode
Where I interview the staff and our collaborators
About their favorite little design stories
I don't quite fill out an entire episode
For whatever reason
But they are cool 99p iStore is none the less
We have underground tunnels
Alarms mysterious filing cabinets and gold
Tiny tiny
Amounts of gold
Prepare to be very interesting
At your neck
Barney
Let's do this
You start with who you are
Okay yeah so I am Delaney Hall and I am a producer and Senior editor
OnStaff
What is your story
Well first I'm going to introduce you to
2 Peter suckers
Play my levels are okay
And I try to not pop my peas
I get excited I'll try not to talk too fast
And the stuff that Peter gets really excited about the stuff that makes and Papa's Pizza and Subs
Is language because he's the editor-at-large at Merriam-Webster and he's a leg
Photographer
Lexicographer is a person who compiles and edits dictionaries that's the old definition
The Great
Samuel Johnson lexicographer in London
Mid 18th century
Darius Amos Lee
Define lexicographer as a harmless
Drudge
And Peter actually said that they use that term affectionately now as like
I kind of
Badge of honor they like to be called harmless drudges
So don't worry about insulting them if if you want to use that term
Merriam-Webster well from his description it sounds like they work in an office that is very very
Be quiet silent basically
And it's filled with these massive steel filing cabinet
And I've kind of been imagining it like that scene in Raiders of the Lost Ark at the end where the man
And it's pushing that create through a huge Warehouse
Instead of stacks of enormous crates is filled with metal filing cabinets
And those metal filing cabinets are filled with index
As far as I know it's the largest body of collected evidence of any language in the world it's
15 or 16 million
Index cards
With a word in context
Wicked full bibliography so we know
Who wrote it and where was published and when
And so that is the work of lexicographers are the keepers of that word history
And for a long time before computers came along this is how they did it with
These massive systems of filing cabinet
Is the
File for the fin for the foundation for the pronunciation editor
Is the file for our dating editors who who do the etymological dating a Place full of file cabinet
But this isn't actually a story about how the Merriam-Webster offices are filled
Was filing cabinets no it's not it's a story about 1
Special filing cabinet Ventura office okay so here's where it gets really interesting
The 1-day Peter was wandering through these endless rows of filing cabinets and he came across
Is one and one of them simply said
Backward index
And so he opens up
The cabinet that says backward index
I realize what it what it was which was
Are all of the head words of the unabridged dictionary some 315,000
Separate index cards
With only
One word on them and it was
Edward
Typed backwards
Is a bad word that use the entry in the dictionary that's the first
Word with the word in question
This index is like imagine all the words in the dictionary
But
Typed backwards and then organized
Alphabetically
Okay
Why would you do that that is the question because
Utility of it is not immediately obvious at least not to non lexicographers like you and me
Repeater
The harmless Drudge
He kind of got it
Lexicography is an extreme sport
This is kind of a radical
The practice of collection and of archiving
And so to a certain degree this is
Maybe the the
The weirdest example of that kind of archiving
Abbott made a kind of sense to me
To really understand why it makes any kind of sense you have to think back to when lexicographers
First started compiling
The backwards
Which was in the 1930s it turns out
Which was a time before computers and
All of the search possibilities that they allow
In the pre-digital era
How else could we have known that there are four examples 500 words in the dictionary that end in ology
Yeah yeah you're getting it that's because with a regular dictionary just
Organized in a regular alphabetical way
A word like ecology would not appear next
To a word like technology because one starts with
Lydian once
I got it okay so with a backward index all the words that end in ology for example be grouped together
So you couldn't actually look up ology words you would look up
Y g o l o r word
Can yuan
Exactly yeah yeah
Kind of kind of ingenious
And there are actually a lot of other examples of of why this is useful
There was no way that they could know
For example how many words in English
Made with a compound like
Like you know block like clock like rock like sock like chocolate
I'm or how many open compound that is to say two word phrases
Found that use Pony so Highland Pony Shetland pony Welsh Pony that kind of thing
And then it gets a little deeper those
Words that are related morphologically like a ethological lithological ornithological
Particular sequence of letters basic rhyming
Sequences
Sleepy weepy sweet pea I'm forty shorty snorty
And in fact this backward index was instrumental in the creation of Merriam-Webster's 4
First rhyming dictionary
Oh yeah yeah yeah they're still they're very popular
By reading words backwards you can start to see
You kind of pattern psychology pattern or the
Logical pattern or destroy me better
The kind of lexical detail that we can get into by looking at the language backwards
In a normal way
In 3004 there were computers but does Peter know anything about who actually made this mystery is filing cabinet
Yeah so after he discovered it he started doing some research
And exactly
Who invented it is still a bit of a mystery he figured out that it dates back to the 1930s
And there's some evidence
That lexicographers work done it up until the 1970
So he knows how long it was
Actively being compiled
Co-founded the project
Was
A kind of favorite pet project of this one editor
Name Philip go
He edited Webster's
Third unabridged dictionary in the 1950s and it sounds like
He was
Barry
Rigorous Andrew lorient
Who is the famous
I'm his organizational
Skills and enforce
Making the dictionary apparatus that is to say that
The things that that we use as kind of code in the dictionary things like
And what is a bold-faced colon mean what is a light face
Metallic semicolon mean
When can we use commas so there's a rule for everything
And and so it was really go
Systematized
All of that
Key made a rule book for us for the editors
That was followed to the T
He was really really strict
I'm a very kind of innovative in its way and also kind of Proto digital because when we finally did this
Digitized dictionary recognize how very regular the
Apparatus was
Sogo
From Peter's description that seems like he's thought about the dictionary with the logic of a computer program
Hammer butt
Before computers were a thing
And now that computers are thinking you mentioned about an index
Propel out in the 1970s with makes tons of sense
Indicators must have really changed the way let's confers of the distant really works
For one thing they have made
The old-school backwards index totally obsolete dream Webster website there's an advanced search
Search function where you can
Type in ology
Or phobia pulled up all the words that end with ology
Are phobia
So easy we haven't
So easy to do really do
And then computers have also allowed lexicographers like Peter to see
Other kinds of
For example
Well my favorite that we talked about in this interview is dysfunction on Merriam-Webster's
Website
Which is called time traveler
I'm by which you can
Reorder the dictionary in chronological
Order as opposed to alphabetical order because ultimately alphabetical order is
A random it's arbitrary
But chronological order isn't because English develops in a very particular way all the words for the other words for exam
Apple about
You know a train travel in train tracks and Kohl's and engines they all come at a certain time
All words that have to do with repeating Firearms they'll come at a certain time when I'm going to the words that
I entered the language regarding the law that are derived from
French
They are coming up at a similar time to reorganize in the dictionary in in a
A digital way
I'm turned out to be a way to sort of
Turn the dictionary to a three dimensional
Search
A rather than just simply a list
We can go in in in Greater depth
Amazing
Cool love the idea of the time traveler
It's such a good way to older now at Jenna certain way and it's sort of like the backwards index was an early
Pre-digital attempt
Add achieving that kind of thing
Three dimensional
Search
I'm so cool oh thanks
Yeah thank you
We got to know Vivien Leigh when she was a finalist in the radiotopia podcast Kant
Her show billing is she is premiering this year
But she's also going to do a couple of 99 Pi stories
Including this
How many store
And she decided
Do you start
Big
So I want to start with
Nuclear accident
In US history
It's okay go ahead
How many years there has been a vigorous debate in this country about the safety of the nation 72 nuclear energy
Power plant
Activate is likely to be intensified
Because of what happened early this morning at a nuclear power plant in Pennsylvania
So you probably heard about this before because
This is big news
But back in 1979 there was a partial core meltdown at the Three Mile Island nuclear power plant near Harrisburg
Cooling pump broke down
And the plant did just what am I supposed to do
Shut itself off
94 some radioactivity had escaped
We have to report
A bunch of communities around the reactor ended up having to evacuate
A lot of people out they should have been freaked out there
Freaking scary
In the aftermath of what happened
The president ordered a commission to investigate what happened and there's a
This big post-mortem report to try to understand what
And what
It's kind of complicated because a lot of things went wrong
But Three Mile Island was
A classic cascading failure type accident
So essentially
A relief valve in one of the reactor units got stuck in the open position which caused all the
Going to be released
So the coolant run out of the core and it started to overheat
And in the end it ended up being a pretty minor mechanical breakdown
But what they found out was that it was actually human error that made the whole situation worse
Humans make everything worse really do they really do
But
The plant operators
See and they can hear that something was wrong because all these lights are flashing and alarms are sounding
But it wasn't clear exactly what was wrong
Because all the alarms are really
Fusing and just made this
Situation worse
Because I went to
Same time
That would have hindered
Communication
At the very time
When they need you
Communicate
And who is that
So that's Judy edworthy she said he's psychoacoustics and alarm design at the University of Plymouth
And she told me that Three Mile Island is actually a really common case study when it comes to bad and ineffective alarm design
Is very well-known
Having hundreds of alarms going off
A short period of time
Until happens
Alarm design really matters
Yes it definitely matters to
And there have actually been other major accidents were alarms that were supposed to help people respond to emergency
But instead they made the situation worse
Like the Deepwater Horizon accident in 2010 would cause a ton of oil to fill into the Gulf of Mexico
I didn't know that had anything to do with me
Oh yeah yeah
It turned out that a bunch of the alarm systems on the Deepwater rig and actually been inhibited for at least a year before the
Because Transocean
What is the company that ran the rig didn't want false alarms to wake up the crew while they're sleeping
Three alarms
Too easily triggered
And so they just turn them off
They didn't upset
The operation of the ranch
To visit going to stop
Professor Edward a think about a lot
Yes yeah she thinks about the best ways
It has an alarm so that they can accomplish what they need to do
And whenever big concerns is that humans are just bombarded by so many alarms in our everyday life that we just
Start tuning them out
Or treating them off
Cuz I think the whole world's have to serve along today
Just so used to alarm just going a whole lot of time
Under almost
Digital backdrop to allies
She says that the average person probably hears about a hundred different types of alarms a day
The distal the time you send it to cash register
Speak to me away
Shunyi
You had called
Turn ons going off
Everything
FANUC
And so people just start tune them out and they lose track of which alarms are important and which
If everything in the world is beeping we kind of forget that those beats are trying to point out actual problems
But another consideration is
Set alarm tones Ben cell should communicate something about what the problem is
How does that
So
When you think of an alarm sound
What do you think of
Well I think of
Bracing klaxon
Beeping siren high pitched
Alarm alarm in upsetting all have like one culture
Reference point for what an alarm should sound like
Because like in the olden days we didn't really have much range in terms of
Alarm
In the past
Alarms
Metra Lombard
Pushing son pushing a through an object like a
The klaxon
Pitching
Taco Bell
Wesoo cities arcade noises
Like bells and whistles and sirens and klaxons with
Auditory alarms
Because that's just what the technology of the time allowed for and we got used to it
So
Judy made actually was kind of funny point which is that we have such a narrow idea of what an alarm should sound like
That it even shows up in futuristic Sci-Fi movies
Sci-fi film
Oh so wonderful things happen in the film
But when you put alarms both and I just the same alarms that work
We just used to
So I come in the film
The Martian
They can do it just want to listen good malls
But the counts on veteran loans
Digital sound
Esl which was possible you can make
An alarm sound like basically anything
You can use music
Some people use
Tunsel sequences of melodies
You can use
Sounds of the sounds of real object to real things that we tend to
Research thesis
But really love just metaphors
And I love this I love the idea of auditory icons and
Metaphorical sound is just really interesting
So what's a good example of an auditorium
So
Hospitals are notorious for having these terrible sounds
Because the sheer amount of alarms that are
Ashley going off in
All hours of the night
And I'll just eat some towns that are kind of variations of each other
Soju Design This NuTone
It's meant to be used when there's a problem related to a patient's medication and
This is how it works
What you might do is dance
An alarm by using
Coming out this
Attention
There's a little bit
Attention grabber
And then something metaphorical
Oh so you can really tell
What it is kind of
Choose medication in your head so you kind of already
Know what the problem is before you even address
What we what we find is over to icons
The very very easy
Can you just tell people once
What they mean
And then there was ever understood it
So instead of some generic an alarming alarm sound
I could literally mean anything
Which is what happened at Three Mile Island you can imagine these
Auditory icons that kind of communicate exactly what the problem is so you work there wouldn't be this confusion about trying to decipher
What is One Tone means
Except for a 3-mile and when there's a hundred things going wrong
It would sound like
Preschool classroom and rattles
But that becomes the sound design challenge of like
How do you
Prince which one you hear the loudest in
In what order do you hear
That's worth it
Which you know is really
Cool concept to be into
Yeah yeah yeah you basically have to rethink
And environment from the top down
In terms of what it sounds like
Thank you so much
Thank you
Since your voice isn't heard as much on the air want you say Who You Are
I'm sure Jusuf
I am what did you settle on technical producer
Make things sound good
That's awesome
I need to make things sound good
What kind of story do you have
Yesterday I have I believe it's called a mini story and it is about alchemy
It is a the idea of
Turn it using chemistry to turn lead into gold
Yeah basically or any other base
It was this loony idea that folks in the Medieval ages were obsessed
Sweat turning base metals
Lead and mercury into gold
Which of course is preposterous nowadays
But there's this time when Alchemists were these like really dope people back by Rich folks and Powerful folks
Including King Henry the 4th of France
A lot of Catholic monks practice Alchemy
Even Sir Isaac Newton was super into Alchemy he apparently wrote about it more than physics
Optics
So for a long time hundreds and hundreds of years
Lacrosse team
Tire world
In the Middle East in Europe
There are these blurred lines between science and Alchemy
I'm back to Alchemy can actually be
Be traced back to
The Arabic alkemia which means
Chemistry
Because apparently Egyptians
Since we're pretty big into Alchemy back in the day especially
Italy during the holidays
X in Alexandria which is where I used to live
So shout out to Alexandria
And so Alchemy was really big thing and it is still
Really prevalent in pop culture today like I don't know if
Minecraft
Based on a cursory Google search
I think there are some Alchemist characters involved in the oast
Examples for my child who doesn't Harry Potter
The whole first book is about the
The Sorcerer's Stone
The British version
The Philosopher's Stone
Which is this thing that turns Metals into gold and also
Apparently
Makes people immortal
Which is like Voldemort was all about it
Anyway that's all to say that this idea that you could design
Kind of design gold from other metals
It was a really big pseudo-scientific West
For a really long time
But that'll sort of went by the wayside when Modern Chemistry started to become
Its own disk
Atoms neutrons and electrons and all that stuff sort of started
Taking cold
Well the ironic thing is is that
With modern chemistry it is actually possible to create gold from other elements
It actually happens in nature like when a neutron stars collide
And it can happen in Labs if you have nuclear capabilities or like a particle accelerator
Which brings us to Maryland
In the 1960
There was a physicist there named Judith temperley
And there with a nuclear reactor she managed to turn
Mercury
Into gold
Well she actually transmuted it which
Is the technical term end as I understand it means she modified the nucleus of
1 elements
Until it had
The same amount of protein
Gold
Should I do a quick chemistry lesson I mean
Chocolate chemistry
Elements are defined by the number of protons in the nucleus
It's like hydrogen is number one in the periodic table
Which means it has one proton in its nucleus
Sodium is number 11 has 11 protons Meadow on
I'm so the idea was that
If you got an element
That
Had you know
Close to the number of protons is gold
Yeah I'm then maybe like with particle accelerator youku
Add protons to weatherstrip protons away but to do that you need
A huge amount of energy
Because if you
Collide
2 positive things the witch
Are than they were
Bounce off
Ready to party
Accelerated
And Mercury is number 80
On the period
Gold is number 79
So they're very close
Right so she was like okay cool I'll put mercury in there which has 80 protons
I'll try to smack one of those off and maybe one of the protons will fall off and I'll be left with gold
And she did that
I think successfully converted
One atom into gold which you know great that was really great job and she proved that this ID
Do you have that was really crazy but was
So obsessed over for so many hundreds of years
Actually sign
Play possible
I'm a man in the 1980s
This professor named Glenn T seaborg who was a nobel-winning chemist at Berkeley
Made even more gold
Transmitted the same way
Except this time he was bismuth which you know unlike Mercury isn't poisonous
And it was also pretty close to gold on them
I think it was
Kirkland's number 83
Compared to a gold set
Find some smack some carbon into it using up
Particle accelerator
And he managed to create several
Thousand
You know when both
Cases
Love and results we're sort of invisible
Like to the naked eye
So it doesn't seem like a
The best option
Referred
Creating wealth
Xiamen
Especially considering that you need
Particle accelerator do if a child care
Pretty expense
Sensitive Bell
Solace
CenturyLink West becomes possible
But in the end it's pretty impractical because
You really have to spend way more gold than could ever be made
Creating a
Gold atom out of business
Yeah I think
Seeburg Economist told the Associated Press at the time
That in order to create an ounce of gold using his process that he did in Berkeley
It was he
One quadrillion dollars to create an ounce of gold and I had to look up quadrillion
It's a one with 15 zeros after it and at the same time the going rate for gold was about
$560
Not the most cost-effective but
Pretty cool that we did it
Thanks so much
Last but certainly not least is the longest serving soldier in the 99 PIR me
Avery trufelman
Answer the question
So how long have you lived in the Bay Area
I moved here in
So are there any
Tourist
You still haven't been
Oh
Yeah
Alcatraz Pier 39
Lombard Street
Oh yeah I've never driven down on bars really
That's so funny that you would love them
Live there for my childhood and adulthood
Are you tired
And I never ever went to the crown of the Statue of
Now it's too late and it's the kind of thing that I've always told me to do
And it's
You know just kind of a typical thing that locals have a very
Different experience of their town and their city and visitors
Does by and large they don't see the attraction
The vast majority of our visitors
Are from out of town
Overwhelming majority
Play about locals doing tourist activities in any town around United
Many people do not go to The Tourist
In their town this is Dina jerrion he is a tour guide in an area of downtown Seattle called
Pioneer Square
Very touristy
And he works for a company
Bill Speidel Underground Tour
As the name suggests
The Torah allows you to
You descend some steps
And find yourself below street level
Like literally underground under the ground
I lived here
Ford
12 years before I knew
Safe to say
Easley the majority of people live in works at in Seattle do not know
They don't know
As we look around up above there
All of the sidewalks you see up there all of those sidewalks are Halo
What does it mean that the sidewalks are Hollow
Explain that we have to go back to 1851
To the founding of Seattle when the first White settlers
Arrived back then the land look
Completely different
Topographic
It was
I mean shockingly differin if you look at a map
Seattle is this tiny little Peninsula that used to sometimes flood into an island.
It was
Not the best place to establish a city
But
Some young white guys went ahead and established it
Pioneer Square quickly became this little logging town
Tiny wooden houses
And the logging Mill
That was the original Pioneer Square area and that's
The dock was
That's where the song
What business is work
This is history and allenstein
And he says even after the settlement the town would still flood sometimes
And this man plumbing was impossible
Toilets were at
Sea level so the problem is every time the tide came and it would blast water through
And so these toilets erupting with water
Sound off.
Stupid places establishing Town it was a bad idea
But the settlers decided to grin and bear it
And they put up with the many faults of their little city
As long as they could
Could continue to sell its Lumber
Until they accidentally burned the entire Earth
Even when the great fire hidden 89th at
That burned down that started in Pioneer Square that burned down was that area Because by the
This time
Wooden buildings have been built up
In 1889
The great fire had Seattle and it is pretty much
Levels downtown
Town it's just a
Asteroid
But miraculously
No one died in the Grapevine
So the city actually sees this as an opportunity
Saddles like okay this is our big chance to get the town above sea level and we
Start again
They thought well let's live
Grated over let's
Pack up the streets so that there
11 feet higher in the air
Yeah and
That way it is
It's a little more stable
But the business owner has already started building the city didn't want to tell the businesses in Pioneer Square
To wait until the project was done to rebuild
Because raising up the streets with this really ambitious project
I was going to take like 10 years to do so you can tell all the businesses in your town to take a 10-year hiatus
The Pioneer Square businesses
Where is that when they rebuild
First I should do it in Brick and Stone not would my no lesson and then secondly
They should add another entrance
On their second floor
And slowly in increments
The city raise up the street
5 to 11 feet up
Around business
So they built their businesses
With an entrance
On the first floor
And an entrance
On base with a second-story
For the eventuality that the street would raise to meet at
We're raised up and then the sidewalk and the building were lower than the street
So for example if you wanted to park your carriage
In the street
And then
Leave your carriage and go into a store
You got to actually go down steps
Stairs reedem ladders
Storefronts
Basically the sidewalk at this point wasn't really joined that Second Story
But the street was there but the sidewalk
Yeah the sidewalk was still down at the old
Athletic
Yeah first level
It did not happen
Once it happened in increments
But yeah and then the street was above it
So
Eventually the city connected the raised
It's to the new 2nd Story entrances
With a new sidewalk
I just covered up the old sidewalk
Incredibles hollow space
Between the old sidewalk
Anakaren
Once
The streets were graded level
Then
Businesses move to the Opera that the Second Story
And that's where their storefront
Later became
So all these
Original storefront
Worthen
Covered over Underground
And that's what
Became Underground
Seattle
So the underground was rumored to have a lot of
People speculate
About its life is speakeasies and gay clubs and Pat's for Espionage or smuggling
But honestly for most of its existence it was
Abandoned
Forgotten are used as storage space by the shops
What's the weather in Pinehurst
But then in the
Most of the businesses started to leave Pioneer Square
And the area became kind of down and out
And said this was the sixties everyone is like great let's just turn down all the old buildings in Pioneer Square so we can build more space AG stuff
Lego Space Needle
The space-age the future
People are looking
Forward than they were.
The past
Except for a man named Bill Speidel
So build it was a
Columnist
For the Seattle Times
And he had an interested
In history
A lot of it was because he had a lot of contacts
Like contacts with direct descendants of the founders of the city
Bill Speidel new people who were the sons or grandsons of the founding Pioneer families
Galilee young history
As far as White Settlement goes
Here in Seattle really it's
Three generations
It's away if you
And through these Old-Timers their stories the rumors
Speidel hears about these underground kind of tunnels in downtown Seattle
And he eventually learned about the raising of the streets in this house
Spaces between the car
Current sidewalk and gold sidewalk
In 1965 Bill Speidel Underground Tour with a
Officially born
And he use the tour as an opportunity to show seattleites that they had history
And I had a historic district but they were ignoring
And they thought they didn't they thought they were this young City
This got the ball rolling on preserving Pioneer Square and by 19
It worked because it became a a National Historic District
Nancy is still listed as day
Bill Speidel passed away in 1988
But today if you go to Pioneer Square you will see
Hordes of tourists roving around in groups of 47
Taking Bill speidel's Underground Tour
They trying out these massive Torres everyday a hundred eighty eight people come through every hour and
One time I went
There is never this woman
Translate inventory in real time on her phone into Chinese I mean they're from all over the world
I'm at or very much continues and Bill speidel's original style it's a lot more dedicated to
The fun Ben facts
Lightest eye exam dad jokes
Drunken debauchery on the Rays Street
In the first year of construction Alone 17 men
Walked out of bars tried to cross the street
Fell to their death stepping from the street to the sidewalk below
Bill Speidel said that was it working away because that was early Seattle's original one step program
I love that joke
So it's a lot of
Unverified stuff and a few exaggerations but honestly
It's true with a lot of tourists detours they kind of turn into this giant game of telephone
But in this case without Speidel Legends and dad jokes we might not have
At all where this piece of Seattle history
Notorious no better than the local
Since literally thousands of you asked
I'm going to tell you what I think
The redesigned Donald Trump
Presidential challenge coin
Right after this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is from
Frustrating it doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
You might not remember
December 22nd 2017 is a particularly notable day
But I will always remember it as a day of the world first song
Donald Trump's
Redesign
Presidential
Challenge coin
Now if you were unfamiliar with challenge coin
Please turn your hymnals
Two episode number 156
Text 999 gold coin
And you know everything you need to know
But if you've been here awhile
You know
I know about challenge coins
And I care about them deeply
Inside if you didn't serve in the military
There's a good chance you learn about challenge going to the first time from 99% invisible
This show is don't challenge coins radiotopia so my association with John Lithgow
Is strong
And because of that
I was forwarded
The December 22nd Washington Post article about Trump's garishly over-the-top challenge coin
By about
9000 people
So am I other podcast
What Trump can teach us about con law
We take the tweets of Donald Trump and we use them
As a jumping-off point to learn about the US Constitution
If you haven't heard it
It's a really fun show and it's not nearly as snarky and angry as you might think
Plus my co-host on that show is
Hello professor and a friend of mine her name is Elizabeth Joe
And she's super smart and
Delightful to listen to so check it out
When things we discuss a lot on the show is that Donald Trump
Has a tendency to subvert
Constitutional norms
And if you're into Trump you can actually
Appreciate that Tennessee I know I totally dig people
Pushon rules to achieve the things
I want
To achieve
Anyway with the redesign of the presidential challenge coin it's clear that Trump also likes to break the norms
Taste
Good design and tradition
The new Trump challenge coin dispensers with the presidential seal
And replaces it with a similar-looking eagle image
But the head of the Eagle at 23
The directions for some reason
And it has Donald Trump signature
Across the bottom
Instead of e pluribus unum
It says
Make America great again
And it says Donald Trump again on a ribbon that extends below the traditional circle of the coin
It is twice as thick
Is the most recent presidential challenge coins and instead of the muted colors befitting a dignified office
This coin is gold
Burberry
Very
Cheap-looking
Goal
In terms of taste I consider this new coin and imp
Events
I will personally draw up the articles of impeachment myself just give me a call
However
I also must consider this from a design perspective
The key question in design is
The Thing You Do
What it was designed to do
In that sense
One could argue
But the Donald Trump challenge
Is perfectly
Design
It completely reflects the taste and style of trump and his presidency
In every way
Is in your face
Non-traditional
I fundit unbelievably ugly and tacky and I don't like the ribbon protruding from the bottom of the circle
But it's
Much like the man himself where is his
Wide shiny ties that come down
Way too low
So just like I didn't really get the red Maga hats I can't argue that they weren't
Effective icon for did the job they were designed to do
Turn away
You kind of have to admire the new coin
And judge it
What it is
Sinbad
Limit to how far my 10 Rocky will extend because it is
It is really awful it is
Awful to look at
In every way it is just
It is it is
It is so
99percentinvisible is Avery trufelman
Emmett Fitzgerald Sharif Youssef
Delaney Hall
Turn Massa composer Sean real senior producer Katie mingle digital director Kurt Kolstad and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco introduced
Fun Radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight foundation and sticker loving listener
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we did meet at Roman Mars in the show at 9
99pi or run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
The real 99p ihq is only at
NPI
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com