99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Summer time in New York
Year is 1902
And II and wilhelm's printing company in Brooklyn has a
The problem that's producer Emmett Fitzgerald
They're trying to print the popular Humor Magazine judge
And it's really hot and there's a lot of humidity and they're having trouble
Getting the
Thanks to set properly on the page this is writer Stephen Johnson
Author of the book how we got to now he says the problem isn't so much the Heat
But the moisture in the air with warping the paper throwing the print out of alignment and so they hire a
Young enterprising engineer
By the name of Willis carrier to solve this problem and basically pull the moisture out of the air
Inside the printing plant and carrier developed the system that pumps air over cold metal
Coil
And it works it pulls moisture out of the air and the magazines are printed more efficiently and and that Banks
Don't run
But
It has a side effect of as it's pulling moisture out of the air and also makes the air
A cooler
And so of course
Everybody wants to have lunch in the room with his new machine
It's like wow this is so nice
Because it's so much more pleasant
Carrier had invented air conditioner
And began to think that maybe his new technology could do more than just keep paper dry
Maybe it's
Something could actually be harnessed in the service or just human comfort
The first install system in textile Factory
Tobacco plant
Other industrial workplaces that require low humidity
Is it really catches on in a very different
So before air conditioning the last place you would want to go
What's the crowd into a movie theater with a thousand other human beings on a day when I was 95
Degrees out right that would just be
Completely intolerable
The movie theaters really struggle to sell tickets
It's during the summer months
So carrier approaches a bunch of theater owners all around the
Country with an idea
I'll install a new machine
That turns your place of business
Into a crisp
Cool Oasis
It won't be cheap but you'll make up for the cost in summer tickets
And that's exactly what happened
Peter owners advertise their chilled air and people came out to air condition theaters in droves
Yes you lucky people just sit back for a moment
Relax
I noticed the delightfully clean
Cool and refreshing
Atmosphere is scientifically air-conditioned theater
This advertisement
From the 1940s shows a bunch of
Theatregoers wearing fur parkas
Isis
Ripping
Spinner
Suddenly movies went from being the last place you'd want to be on a summer day to being actually one of the nicer
And this whole tradition of having these big movies to come out in the summer
Became pause
Summer blockbuster
But air conditioning would do a lot more than just
Create the summer
Blockbuster
It would dramatically change what people in the United
It slipped in the design of our building
And homes
But the air-conditioning Revolution didn't happen all I want before World War II
Wealthy Elites had air conditioning systems installed in their Mansions but mechanically chill there was still seen as a
Luxury something to be enjoyed at the theater in your own home
Willis carrier wanted to change that
In a 1929 speech he said
Air conditioning and cooling for summer may become a necessity rather than a luxury
And we will look upon present times as marking the end of that dark age in which there was but relatively
Little cooling for human comfort
The big transformation for air conditioning
They really arrives after World War II
Is like so many stories of Technology really a story about
Miniaturization of
Something was really big and shrinking it down
Early AC systems were massive
Way too big for an individual home but by the late 1940s
Carrier and other companies were selling air conditioners that can fit in your window
But they were expensive
And it wasn't clear at first
That people would buy them
I think advertising
Play a huge role
In the increased use of
Air conditioning in the residential sector
And what's really interesting is that the advertising really played on the role of women
And their social status
This is Gail brager
She is an architecture professor at the UC Berkeley College of environmental design and an expert on thermal cup
If you look at the advertising in the 1950s a lot of them showed
Women dressed like
Beaver Cleaver's mom
With the pearls
And the gloved hands and
Dressed well
And it was really trying to associate on social status
With air conditioning
If you have air condition
You can live this life of leisure
And you wouldn't have to sweat with the toil of housework
Is that also played on the idea that
With air conditioning
Homeowners could take him
Control over nature
Mydesert 110 by day
Cool enough to need heat the same night
Here's an air conditioning commercial from the early 1960s that takes
Place in Palm Springs the maximum test for air conditioning
What system works best
Let's ask the owner of this desert show place
Miss Dinah Shore
Hi
With my year-round gas air conditioning by arkla
I just touched the thermostat
Delightful Cooling
Uncomfortable heat in every room
Humidity control dust and pollen filter
My indoor climate is always perfect
Is very compelling
The Advertiser
And I think that really played on
People adopting air conditioning more
Into the home
In 1960 13% of homes in the United States had a c
By 1980 it was up to 55%
Today is close to ninety percent
In just a few decades
Is air conditioning went from luxury to necessity
Just as Willis carrier predicted
Has had a serious impact on how and maybe was profoundly where we live
All of a sudden there parts of United States that had
Historically been
Really unpleasant to live in particular during the summer months
That's only because of these home air conditioning units
Are now
Places to live
Population of States like Arizona and Florida
Bloated
Adduction of of home air conditioning
Really arguably one of the largest migrations
The people in the history of the night
States moving from the north
To the South On To What We Now call the
The Sunbelt
If you could air condition your way through the summer than living in the middle of a desert or a human swamp
Was no big deal
In just 10 years
Tucson
Went from 45 to
Some people
The 210,000 people
In the same decade
Houston almost doubled
And Florida during the 1920s had only a million people living there
But fifty years later there were nearly 7 million people in Florida
This Mass migration was so significant it changed the political
Increase population in States like Florida got more votes in the Electoral College
A lot of these new Southward migrants were conservative retirees
They tended to vote Republican
You begin to build this
Can a Republican
Sunbelt Coalition that didn't exist
And that Coalition is really crucial to Reagan's
Successful bid for the presidency in 1980
They were obviously a lot of different factors that led to Reagan
Can selection but
I think that
Had air conditioning not been invented Reagan might still have gotten elected but he would have required a different
Political coalition to make it pop
The population of the Sunbelt boom with the Advent of air
But it's not as if no one lived in these places
Before AC
Knows who did that developed lots of strategies
To beat the Heat
Including forms of vernacular architecture that were carefully attuned to the climate
Vernacular refers to traditional architecture that develops in a particular place
And it's often driven by local environmental conditions
If you look at traditional buildings in hot climate
Show me the elements are going to be
Be different
If you're in a hot dryer hot humid climate
In the desert Southwest
Houses were traditionally built with Hefty material
Like Adobe and stone that can absorb heat
Is soaking up the heat during the day
Keeping it from getting inside
And then releasing it to the colder air
At night
Homes in the southwest also tended to have flat roofs
And small windows that can be closed up during the day and opened at night to let the cool area
However in the humid Southeast the vernacular architecture try to maximize shade
It was screened in sleeping porches
Breezeway
It's between rooms
And cupolas in the roof to draw cool air up through the house
You tend to have much larger Windows much larger operable windows to the
Tire
Passage to be opened up
You might have much larger shaded
Porches and balconies so there's a lot of outdoor living
And so you can you can look at the architecture and
It says something
About the place
On demand cold-air freed architects
The challenge of Designing a home that was unique
We Suited
The climate around
And as we got
More of a chemical systems and the power to
Heat and cool
Buildings through mechanical
Call systems
Architect started relinquishing
Control
Oven bar mounts
Conditioning to the engineer's
Air conditioning systems were expensive
Home builders made up for the costs by cutting down on
Passive cooling features
And little by little the local Architectural Traditions rooted in the climate
Gave way too tightly sealed mass-produced
Tractor
So a house in
The Southwest
Might look
The same as a house in New Orleans which might look the same as a house in Minnesota
And whether you were in a hot humid hot dry or cold climate I think architecture
Really lost a sense of place
The rise of tract housing had to do with more than just Erica
It was influenced by the development of the highway system in the suburbanization
American Life
But AC enable the mass production of affordable homes that could exist in many different climate zones
Air conditioning didn't just
Change residential architecture it revolutionized the design of skyscrapers
Schools in office building
For air conditioning the only source of cool air with the outdoors
So offices usually have high ceiling
Lots of windows
People could open
And so all offices had at least one
Wall that was exposed to the
You might have Courtyards in the center of building
So that even the built those spaces that
Weren't on the street
Would have access to the air and light on
Inside
If you look at the floor plans of many mid-rise buildings from the early 20th century they often have these
Irregular shapes
It look like letters when viewed from above
So we sometimes
Just called them alphabet building
Thanks cuz they be in the shape of
E&H and I and O
But with air conditioning buildings could fill up the entire lot with offices.
Inside the core of the building nowhere near a window
Air conditioning also changed facade design
4AC address the issue of
Too much sun
By providing appropriate shadings or on a
Facades were carefully designed to avoid too much sun coming into a space
This is Lisa Hashem an architect who spent her career studying light in architecture
Discovered air conditioning all of a sudden we could have these continuous glass facades
Because we would solve the problem
With power conditioning instead of
Facade design or building design it was just Brute Force Power
Will air conditioner weigh out of all of these
Design it
Now this wasn't all a Bad Thing many modern Architects were happy to see the problem of thermal Comfort to the edge
It meant they could focus
Aesthetics
And so it was incredibly empowering
Architects to be able to relinquish that
With a c they were free to design the Sleek hermetically-sealed last hours that became Hallmarks of modern
It's safe to say that without air conditioning we would not have many of the Great modernist buildings of the 20th century
Oh absolutely not
But as a consequence the modern built environment in the United States is now totally dependent on air conditioner
A lot of our buildings would be uninhabitable in the summer without AC
And all that cool air requires a lot of power
We now use as much
Electricity for air conditioning as
We used
For all purposes in 1955
This is Stan Cox
Author of the book losing our cool
He says AC consumption has continued to rise
Vim 1993
The 2005
The amount of electricity used for air conditioning doubled Nationwide
One of the big reasons was that houses
We're getting larger
And virtually all of those newly constructed ones
Were getting central air installed in them
The larger the home the more space needs to be filled with cool air
It's crazy to think about it to me that
Hohhot
Day here in Kansas
There are
3000 square foot houses
Being kept at
70 degrees
All day long and all the occupants are off it at work and school and so it
Not cooling a human being at all
In all that air conditioning might be keeping our buildings cool
Let's make in the outside world
Hotter
The additional
Greenhouse emissions from Air Conditioning in the United States
Add up to about
500 million tons of CO2 equivalent
Per year
He says that's more than the entire construction into
Including the production of materials like concrete
So what's up
Very
Significant amount
In fact in 2010 when Stan cockroaches book
He says the US was using as much energy for air conditioning
Has the entire continent of Africa was using
For all purposes
And all of these structures that require massive amounts of energy to key
Keep cool
We've been
Boarding them to the rest
The world
Including really hot places
It's like Dubai
What American has been fantastic
Cost of boarding Dental design in art
Is making a brine Annex
Sporting Good
However a lot of it architecture is non-responsive
To the conditions of The Middle
This is manit rastogi
An Indian architect and co-founder of the firm morphogenesis
Space in New Delhi
He says that a lot of the buildings in Indian cities
Is today
Look like they could be buildings in other City around the world
Sealed up glass towers that require a lot of air can
But India also have a long history of vernacular architecture design.
People cool
M Rastogi started looking back at some of the
These old buildings
And thought
We used to do this really well
Not so long back
Why are we building differently today
Rastogi has devoted his career to designing functional modern building
Borrow passive cooling techniques
Traditional Indian architecture
And require very little
Play Fanny air conditioner
Like it design
The Pearl Academy of fashion
So the Pearl Academy of fashion
Is on the outskirts of Jaipur which is essentially a desert climate
Went rastogi started working on the Pearl Academy
He looked at Old Indian buildings
In hot dry climates
Inspiration
He studied Old Fort
Sun Palace
The see how they stayed cool
And he was particularly impressed by a feature called the battle
Stepwell
Bellies are traditional Indian stopwatch
What's found in many old Palace
They're basically pools of water dug deep into the ground beneath the building and surrounded on all sides by descendants
Intricately carved
From Stone
The cool temperatures from underground combined with the evaporative cooling of the water to lower the temperature
Picture in the palace
Rastogi decided to put a modern take on this ancient architectural feature in his building
So we created about your step brother
Across the entire site
3 meters down into the ground
And we recycle all the water
Into that stepper condition allowed for
Evaporative cooling to come up and cool the side down
The top of the building is insulated using earthenware pot
And the sides of the building reboot
Locally manufactured jollies that keep the Sun out but let the light in
The Jolly is a traditional Indian architectural feature it's basically a lot of screen filled with all these
Any holes
What's that letting diffused sunlight without too much heat
Let me put a whole life together
And when the project finished
We were getting temperature to 29 degrees
When the outside temperature was 46 degrees without air conditioning
In Fahrenheit that's 84 degrees inside the build
When it was 115 degrees outside
It's still hot
But doable
Turn office building that doesn't actually sound all that doable to me that sounds way too hot
Yeah I think so too but rastogi says that for someone used to living in Jaipur India
Pretty Pleasant temperature
He says thermal Comfort is relative
Standards for what constitutes thermal comfort
Is where I think the whole problem
Sort of sick
Architects and Engineers around the world use thermal comfort
Set by the American Society of heating refrigerating and air conditioning engineers
Historically the standard
Dictated a relatively narrow temperature window that all building should be kept
The only way to be certain that a building can meet that standard all year long is with lots of air conditioning and heating
But if you've ever worked in an office you know that some people are always hot
Well others
Katie
Are always cold
You will never
Achieve a static environment
Where hundred percent of
This is architect Lisa hatchimal
There's a huge amount of individual variation in what people
Experience
And what they prefer
Are thermal preferences vary based on age and
And sex in the climate that were used to
But the whole goal of conditioning buildings is
How to create a static indoor climbing
One temperature that will hopefully be the least unpleasant the most number of people
Galebreaker cost
She and her team at UC Berkeley have developed new thermal
Allow
For a wider range of
Buildings
Breaker doesn't want to get rid of air
All together but
She thinks we can be more intentional about when and where we
Our
Environmental conditioning systems
Think about Heating and Cooling
Spaces
Rather than Heating and Cooling
People says we don't need the key
Cool corridor
Words to the same degree as
The parts of an office worker
People spend most of their day
And she says we can save enormous amounts of energy
By letting the temperatures in buildings fluctuate over a wider range
And giving people more tools to heat and cool themselves
To do that it's going to take a combination of high and low Tech approach
A window that you can open right by your desk
Is a great personal cooling device
A sweater
It's a pretty good personal heating device
But also developing low-energy desk
Foot warmers
And the chair I'm sitting in right now
You might see these dials
This is a heated and cooled chair
And this to me is
The ultimate form of a personal Comfort System we call it
PCS
Because we're all going to feel something different
And we could
Be sitting in the same environment but one person maybe feeling warm one person maybe
Feeling cool
And would you like to sit in this chair okay we're going to switch places
You going to stay the night for a while
People are getting more and more used
Heated seats
H&R cars
So why not have
Heated and cooled
H&R office that I'm going to Rich
Reach over internet
Cooling
Okay and you should feel that pretty ugly
Yeah wow
It's blowing air
Cross your back your seat
Oh it's so nice that I have sometimes
Had when my back
Reducing our Reliance on air conditioning
Is Austin frame as a loss
Giving up comfort
But neither deal-breaker morally to hedgehogs
Back in the seventies heschung wrote this beautiful little book called thermal Delight in architecture
And then it she argues that we should think about a perception of temperature as a sense
Just like any other sense
Temperature can causes
Discomfort
But I can also give us a lot of pleasure
Where the light
The feeling of a warm fire in the winter
Or Cool Breeze
Hot summer night
Or sliding back into your heated chair after a trip outside
She wrote about
How thermal experience could enrich architectural design add a new dimension
And it requires
Change it turns out the physiologic
The only way we can have that
Is to actually have some kind of variability in our lives
Deal breaker has done studies on thermal comfort in buildings around the world
And she's found that people actually prefer
Naturally ventilated building
Planes where they can open windows
I feel a little bit of control
Over there around 10
Turns out that not only do you
Tolerate that you actually
Prefer a wider set
Of conditions
Today the average person spends
It's about 90% of their time indoors
And Gilbert doesn't think we should live so much of our lives
Thermal monotony
Imagine life
If we ate
The same food
Everyday
If we didn't have changing weather
And everything was the same all of the
Time
Beauty terrible
But that's essentially what we're trying to do in our building
Towards the end of my conversation with Gail I reluctantly offered to give her chair back should we switch
Did you vacuum near me
I like my chair quite a bit
You should
Special things to architects
You have asked and I are going to talk about
Terrifying incoming missile false alarm in Hawaii
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
So a few months ago thanks in
Pretensions
With North Korea
The Hawaii Emergency Management agency started doing ballistic missile attack
But the other day
Someone was in the shade
Test alert
And apparently
Chose the wrong option from a list
A very confusing options
Easier to give
So at 8:07 in the morning
A message went out
Two cell phones in Hawaii
Ballistic missile threat
Inbound to Hawaii
Seek immediate shelter
This is not a
Within a few minutes
Officials knew it was a false alarm and started doing damage control
But natural Stand Down alert wasn't issued until 8
More than half an hour after it all
Okay so some officials in news outlets
Are calling to the prison
Set off the alarm
Three fire
Wall-E Touhou steam
Colbert joked around about
But the opposite
The Agency Inc
Boy in question
Was reassigned
You keep him in that job
He's the one person
Planet Hulk
Will never ever make that mistake again
Do you know
Design Guru Don Norman
Also thinks
The focus is too much
The person whose basic argument is that if it's that easy to screw up
There's a design problem
Fax and I think it's safe to say that we
MPI
Are members of
Don Norman amen
And
Really there are a number of Zion
It was really easy to make this mistake and send out the alert
It's also too hard to retract it or issue
Correction
And then there's this lack of detail on the method
Like where to find shelter
Oregon telephone numbers or links to websites that might
How people get update there more information
So people panicked
Many fearing the worse
Call loved one
I mean this is a very
High stakes
Design problem
A lot of solutions are being foot
Summit call producing more friction to the process to
Slow things down and help avoid accidents
Knocking balls adding steps
Options like they have right now
In favor of more clearly differentiated buttons
With you.
Different button sizes
Colors
All of the goal of making the
Test initiation
Easier and more obvious
When sending an actual alert
To already there fixing some of these issue
She was like creating a Panthers and out of Correction more quickly
From here on out a second step
Confirm again
Easy solutions
I think his Focus
Too much
On human error
Retracting kneeler
After the fact
Taking the design
It's totally true the process really
Amiri designer
From start to finish
And some of these changes
Are the words like having longer messages that also have emergency
Lynx
And numbers
Even though
They need to actually pass the system or offense
People are familiar with
Know how to react
During this accidental alert was discovered to
Number of emergency siren played
The wrong to Norge
Filled entirely filled both as a false alarm and as an actual
It's the rib Sunny ended up being a false alarm
But that still seems just unnecessary
Westerly High
Yeah but I think we can all agree
That we need to Leo
Oh definitely that guy
I just hope
His name Never Comes
Me too
Alright thank you
Thanks
You want to eat you out even more about alarm design
Be sure to check out the mini stories for episode from last week
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Till
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is the senior producer
Pickles that is the digital
Beretta team includes senior editor Delaney Hall
Sharon Massa in me
Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
Imbue
Downtown
Open
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia
TRX
An independent Collective the most Innovative shows in all a podcast
Fun Mall
Radiotopia. FM
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
And listener Donuts
To pitch in whatever they can to keep us making the best audio in the world
You find the show enjoying discussion about the show on Facebook even tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 PSI or run into
Instagram Tumblr invited to
Did you think
I need more 9 p.m. my life
The old episodes available in new articles about design every couple of days
Are beautiful
It's 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com