99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
And this is Scott McCloud
My name is Scott McCloud I'm a cartoonist and author and I've been making comics for a few decades now
Probably best known for non fiction Comics especially book called understanding comics
Where I explain how Comics work in comics form
Also done fiction work and I have a lot of different interests and I'm very easily
Scott's book understanding comics
Which is 25 years old this year
Is a seminal deconstruction of comics as an art form and mode of communication
A little cartoon Scott jumps between panels of the 215 page book explaining how pictures and words and
Combination
Create a new language for telling stories and describing the world
The book was the culmination of a bunch of ideas that have been swirling around Scott's head
4 years
Everybody knew or they thought they knew what Comics were and it was a very limiting idea and I see video
Go games and other media dealing with the same problem today maybe than podcast is that dead people have
Had this idea the comics were just
Four Color
Cheaply printed
Cheaply made
Comics Batman almost all superheroes are funny animals
But they were disposable entertainment
That night of the writing nor the art was anything that was going to last to be significant
I need to know I saw a lot of comics that
You know
Conform to that definition I mean there were certainly plenty of Bad Comics out there
To me it was just an art form it was an art form that was capable of so much more and I felt like
The first step was wiping the Slate clean and trying to
Approach it from
Almost there clinical value-neutral sort of standpoint where she's like what what are the essential elements
Any essential elements of comics or just putting one picture after another
And substituting space for time you just saying it as you move from one space to the next you're moving for one moment to the next
And that idea to me had just Limitless applications and it drew boundary around a continent
And two possibilities that as far as I was concerned we'd only just
Began to explore
When you wipe the Slate clean
Started with
Anew definition, or at least you know a refined definition of comics
Can you rattle it off the top of your head what the definition was from the book
You know
My mentor will Eisner head use the term sequential art night and I said you know for the most part most 90%
I have the time you can just say sequential art people get it
But then right away they'll say things
Well what about animation and sequential art
So I had to come up with the longer definition that erases many loopholes as possible and what I came up with Wiz
Juxtaposed pictorial in other images in deliberate sequence
Just for fun I got that you know like like
Really narrow it down
Just in case you didn't fully absorbed that definition it's
Juxtaposed pictorial and other images
In deliberate sequence
Some people thought that
You know we had to stop calling them comics and start calling them juxtaposed pictorial and other images in philibert Seacrest
That's it you just you do that once and then you go back to calling them comics
People put a lot of value on label
And and a lot of folks
You know they got all up in arms that although they're calling them graph
Novels
Kaiser putting on airs
No no no you can call it, except
If you want
I was just saying that
That you know comic Sweeney
To allow the words take on new meanings
And every art form has different modes of
The dress right you can read about something in film comment and then you can go to
To be Academy of Motion Pictures to
CD awards ceremony
And then you can go out and see a movie the next day
You're using these different words has different ways of
Illuminating
The different functions the different styles the different
Moods that
That come out of that art form
But
It's okay you can still call the movie 2
You can still call them
What term do you like
I Like Comics because actually I think it's fairly dry I think that
It's been a long time since
People thought that all Comics have to be funny when I was growing up there
Everybody assumed that all Comics were muscle-bound guys in skin-tight suits beating the crap out of each other
So
So we'd already lost the original meaning
And that that render to Justice try little bundle of sticks
Collection of phonemes
That you could pretty much stuff any mean
And also it's quick
It short two syllable
So if I were to pick up a comic book or turn to the comic section of the newspaper
Are there certain things
That you could teach me like how to decode comics in a certain way that
Like guy you tell me like all the artist is trying to do this when they do this what a little of take-home
Facts about
Decoding comic
Well the first thing of the universe
That is if you're looking at a comic strip
Comic book
Graphic novel
There few things everybody has
To do whether they want to or not these are the
Obligatory
Decisions that they all make
And where the first decisions they make
Is choosing their moment
No matter what
You're breaking the world into Moana
And it's a non-trivial problem as an engineer with
I'm not son of an engineer
And
Eat up because
If you think about it any kind of narrative that you want to tell
Can be broken down
In an infinite number of ways
You know I could do a 10000 panel graph
Novel
Of me taking a spoonful of cereal from a bowl
And just lifting up timeout
If you want I could just break it down by microseconds by nanosec
Or I could do you a 2 panel sequence
Of the entire history of the universe
Big Bang heat death
You're done
So that means that you you can slice up anyway you like and yet if I asked you
Hey what did you do yesterday
There's a part of your mind that immediately
Leverages this tremendous
Neural horsepower
2 deciding what matters
You know we have these wonderful saliency filters that choose the moments quite natural
And Mouse cartoons choose them
Pretty naturally they know once I have a story to tell they know what moments matter
But they have to make that decision even if they're not making it
Consciously
And then from that point
You have to choose the
The angles
What's the framing
How close are you going to get to that thing you want to show how far away are you going to
What angular
Is it going to be warm side view Eagles View
Are you going to have to establish the Same by plant way back
And then all those decisions about
How you draw the
How do you draw so it's recognizable how do you draw so it's a
Expressive how do you draw it so that
It's visually interest
How do you balance out Dynamics versus
It's Clarity Olive
And then of course the mixture of words and pictures and the way it flows and it's just
It's an endless series of decisions but these are decisions
We all
Make whether we do them cons
Through every medium has its strengths and weaknesses
And your mind we're the best kind of ideas that
Comics are best at conveying and it may be what are some ideas for
Hardest to convey in,
When it comes to visual explanations I found it, it's a really good at
The intro
When you getting time to a really granular level like for instance if you want to choose Comics to it
Explain the latest
Congressional
Budget bill or something like that
That can be a problem because they're time-intensive
So long time to
Put them together and something like that is better intact
But if you wanted to explain
In a particle physics
Swore
Some you know engineering
Principal or something like that something that's going to stick around
It's a Wonderful entry
Almost any subject
And I've done a bunch of things like that
That I recently did a
A comic explaining
Kubernetes which is
This was for Google it's it's a way of
Orchestrating containerized applications if that's something you're
Planning to do tomorrow
There's a comic going to explain how to do that
So what I'm able to do is I'm able to lay out the map
I'm able to give you a sense that
Yeah this is what the neighborhood looks like this is how everything is interrelated
This is the shape
Of the subject
Comics really good at that
But the flip side of what Comics are good at
It's tricky because
I'm always reluctant
To say that the medium is inherently good at something because that immediately Beggars the
Question as you've already asking what what's it maybe not so
And the thing is whenever I think Comics are not capable of something
Somebody always proves me
Wrong listen example of that
Would like hard math you know but some people have actually given it a running like where they use in comics to it
Explain
Mathematical Concepts something that I thought would probably
Dino Dan on starter
And it turns out.
You can give that a try
And
And of course when I began
It was all superheroes it was all suspect
Sensationalism
And there were many people who felt the comics were inherently good at that
But pretty soon into my
Career even before I became a
MyCareer formerly
I discovered Japanese comics
They were doing comics about everything they were fishing,
Thermage on comics
There were comics about Romance
Answer comics about ninjas
It didn't matter they could be about any
But if you grew up in America you might mistakenly think
The medium was somehow built somehow
Inherently constructed in such a way
That
The love affair between comics and superheroes
Somehow inevitable just like in in 1962 somebody could think that
The love affair between
Movies and
Mpix
Espectacular music
What's an F
Wasn't
There's nothing that said that movies had to go in that direction it's just that
Just the cul-de-sac
The bay window
But I love to look at when it comes to this roof everyday objects at people very familiar with
Is I like to look at that man and
To recognize that they represent choices and maybe their choices so long ago
That we
Forget that they're even choices so
For example I was
Thinking about
The speech bubble
In the comic books
And realizing
That is if you really think about it
And
Other things like that that aren't these little revolutionary
Visual representations of things
That you could ever walk us through maybe who did them
When did this change
When did it go from being in the Box to being in the bubble Lena lick words
Anything about
The evolution of
Comics that
Represent these revolutionary little punctuated
Equilibriums but are so built into the way we perceive the world that we don't even recognize him as choices
I'm going to pull up 180 here and say that
Actually this is a good example
What's something that maybe isn't
To the medium is kind of an epic
When when you do something I'm one of those usually the first evidence is that it happened early
And speech bubbles happen as early as certain European broadsheets
And they are speech bubbles
There's no question about it
You know I could show you something from 1600 1500
Where are there in the shape of Scrolls but they are dialogue coming out of people's mouth
So as soon as you start squaring off things into panelboards which they were also doing in those days
Rectangular paddle board
Yeah you start to have that
Restart an speech
You can even save sort of equivalent things in things like
Pre-columbian
Germanic script
Some of the stuff I think there's some dialogue in the bayou
Tapestries
So yeah this was going to happen no matter what
Because
Dialog speech it's part of life
And anything that
Purports to represent life in any kind of art
Citic narrative medium
It's going to have to account for that and in some way shape or
Perform
That's it I think it's it's what
It is kind of what will eyes are called a desperation device
Bison in a sentence
Because we have a soundless medium
For most of our history
We were kind of stuck
And it does feel a little bit like a hack
I think there's a little part of
Every cartoon has heart sinks a little that
That we have to use the
Shape with voiceover in in movies
Yeah yeah
Yeah it feels
Feel like a cheat like you should go to show it and not tell her
It does it feels like a cheat and I think that's that's why
I think what Comics are
Silent when you have the silent
Sequence of some cartoons do nothing but I like
Most of us will do them
Occasionally it feels more like pure
Comics you know there's that little purest
Gene in each of us.
Rebels a little when we can dispense with not good news for writers
I love this term silent comics
It's so strange the Absurd it but I totally totally makes sense that it's
It's strange that you have this
Unitymedia
Presentation
That still feel so multimedia that we think of it as having sound and time and
Adept
Exactly we it's very easy to forget the
The comics is
This is relegated
It's just one of the five
Traditionally Porsche that's beginning to change a little
With various mutations online and one
Not that
Yeah it's it's strange because it didn't really doesn't feel that way it does feel multimedia and that's of course that's partially because
Many feel that it's this
Agglomeration of
Abortion pictures even though that tends to be true I don't think that is the essential
Show character comic
I just think of that out that is one of
Comics auction
But you can if you get some other comics
Scholar in here
To argue with me
Wetlands are certainly the most visible but
The other ones
I do find very interesting I talk in understanding comics about
Things like Sweat Beads and how you can
See the evolution of written language even in the
Pictorial symbols
And the fact that a sweat bee
Toriel symbol
They gradually drifted so that rather than a little sweat beat on cheek
You would see a sweat bee drawing beside a face
So that it began to emanate
From the face
To the extent that it became a symbol that simply
Indicated the interstate and now you can find manga
Where robots will have sweat bees
On the mend it's simply a signifier
Of emotion
And in a lot of ways.
Drift this exact same drift
You had too many
Pictorial base written language
Especially in the Far East wear
Something would begin as simply a drawing of a chair or a drawing of a horse
And that over
Decades or even centuries
Of writing they would
Become more and more abstract
That's exactly what
So if you were give you no
25 year
Post understanding syllabus
The listeners of 9 p.m.
What are the essential
Comics
Maybe it'll that show a change in form or something and kind of like what they are and
Just a little description of like
What is this doing that is particularly remarkable
All to you
If I just had a
Fu
I probably start with Chris where's
Building Story
Witches
A giant box like a Milton
Bradley gamebar
Which has comics in a million different shapes
Because at that definitely sets the mind going
I would throw in a couple of crazy webcomic
Where you can go in any direction
I would
Had at least one silent,
Jim Woodring
I would include
Persepolis
Because I think persepolis really was a tuning fork for a lot that came after
In what way
What do you mean it in terms of boys as one of the beautiful things about Comics is the way
The comics can offer you
A very intimate and credible voice from somebody who could just be making it up
But you know that they're not
This is something that Comics journalist Joe Sacco
Took advantage of he would do things like spend
Months or even years in a place like Palestine are the Balkans
And he would
Talk to people interview them and then he would do these painstaking drawings of the area
And you realize as journalism
You could doubt everything he's telling you but you don't
You know
That a human hand took the
The time to make this
And with that labor-intensive
Devotion
Came truth
If something very convincing about
Even though
It's a lot easier to fake something in a drawing that in the photograph
You know
That it's true and that that was true of persepolis
What's 2 is that
Marjane satrapi's experiences
In a round During the Revolution the war with Iraq
Coming to Europe to all of these things
They just feel so credible so personal
And
They open a door
To another experience
Movies can do that books can do that
But
The the contact with
The paper that the notion that human hand
It makes it more intimate
It makes it that it did their entire world
Is seen through their lines
And that's that's
It's really exciting
Anything else in the syllabus that weekend
Just throw in there though the arrival by Shaun tan
A wonderful book it looks a little sore like a kids story book
Set up like a Chris Van Allsburg
Beautifully Illustrated silent story
Witches
Kind of surrealistic
Meditation on what it's like
To be an immigrant in a strange new place
Shaun tan moved from Malaysia to
Australia
When he was just a kid and he
You really makes
You understand what it is to go to such a new
Alien place
He doesn't
Beautifully
But also
Really terrific
To approach comic
Without words
To pick something without words
For your first encounter
Because then you have to recognize
The degree to which
Pictures art
Pictures
AR meaning
They're not just illustrations
The pictures do the
You know it's still in popular culture because of all the
In the Marvel movies and such that
The superhero is a dominant form in comics
Is there something that
You
Find that you enjoying them like ways
Is it something that's lost to you at this point
What is your feeling about
Right now
I've lost some of the joy that I had when I was first reading superhero comics
But I still
I like the medium I think the medium has an important
Part to play in comics culture
But
Still I'm I'm kind of happy that we're becoming a little bit more like
Japan we're starting to see more genres
Come in one of the big revolutions Now isn't
Kids comics
The best-selling cartoonist in America now is Raina Telgemeier
Best comics for kids
And those Comics don't have any superheroes in them too
Her biggest one with smile which
Just about
When she was a kid and she lost her two front two of her front teeth and hat
But it's just fantastic stuff
You know we're seeing much more diversity
Just got a wonderful crowdfunded book called
Bingo love witches
Two women of color who
Who fall in love is
Kids
You know in a bingo parlor and both of their families
Just don't approve and they don't really
Until they're old
Far Cry from The Amazing Spider-Man
But some of the things we love the most about Spider-Man I got to say we're just the small moment
The everyday moments the real Moana
So there was maybe that was a seat of that
Even in those days
I know you're interested in graphic communication in the World At Large Beyond comic
How did
Understanding comics in Oliver thoughts
You put into
This as a study
Change the way you decode Graphics in the World At Large like what is something that
You could point to as an example of
That ties to this medium
That you could help
People like decode as they're walking
Diversity
Well
Let's look at fire safety signs oh my God
It drives me crazy
If there's there's a really classic little
Messed up fire safety graphic you'll see it
All around the
Country
Off and on the inside of hotel room doors
Which is
It's got two different little flames
It's got this
Little tiny elevator and then it's got this very big
Guy who's
Going
Right-to-left down the stairs towards
Flame in about to trip over the elevator
All they did was they found the symbols and they filled the available space
Buddha symbols
It didn't even occur to them that the way the guy was facing
Or the relative size of the guy in the Flames the guys much bigger than the Flames to Flame someone
And why are there two of them
You don't like all of these things
They didn't consider it at all
Because they weren't thinking that maybe
Every visual decision has
Every visual
Collateral meaning
Until I started remix in these things and turning the guy around and changing the size relay
Changing
The proximity and making sure that
Each individual element had its own space to breathe
And I was able to come up with like three different alternatives
I think
Work better
I'll probably go on a crusade to fire departments around the country
But now I see I see these things everywhere I mean like
Maps for example
You know
90 degree rotation is hard
Mental knife
2 degree rotation
It's very hard
Actually upsets me when I see
Before plants telling you how to get out of your burning building
And they're rotated they're not in the same orientation is the way that you're standing
Because they have one
Map orientation for the whole building right on the map they print right
But you know you are building is on fire
You're going to die any minute now
And you've got to stand there and kind of just sort of Imagine
If you were facing the other way any return this way and way which hallway is that in there this
I should be clear as day
Here's the thing
I think that
Good visual communication should speak
Imbecile
What I mean by that is that
There are many
Kinds of
Visual communication
That
They're clear enough
You can figure it out
You can piece it together
But they still kind of Mumble as they walk away
Like the bike path sign you know it's
All it is the bike path signs are everywhere right it's just a
Picture of a bicycle
And then the word bike
Empath underneath
The bicycle
And
Oftentimes
Biking path are separated
And there's more space
Between bike
And pass
Then there is between the words biking path and the wheels of the Bison
Nobody will be confused by this
Everyone on Earth
Knows that if they can read English
Dino that says bike path they know what it means
But I say it's still up
Socks on every
Damn one of them
Because
Because what it does
Is it violates the rules of proximity
So that it's like
The word spike in path are married there are a couple
And that there is
There is infidelity going on there because they're flirting with the wheels
Right and they're creating this visual grouping of wheel and
And word
That's completely irrelevant to the message
Nobody will be confused by this
Ivy my wife just tells me Let it go let it go it's fine they needed from the state needed from for the little boat
To go and that's all it is they just they were just making room for the bolts Scott
Just
Just let it go
But but I am telling you
Instead of just saying bike path like it was supposed to
It's saying
Bike path and you're like
Wait what did you say and I said I said bike path that's like no no no after bike path what did you say I didn't say any
Anything I just said bike path
Mama
There you did it again he said no matter what the hell was that
It's like it's
It's killing off
Irrelevant
Visual information and I see it
Everywhere and it's driving me nuts
Is there an analog and comics where you feel like
There has to be a type of precision in the presentation of the narrative
Or do you allow for a little bit more mumbling
That's a good question because I think in comics
People embrace the mumbler
People embracing imperfections
In the cartoonist line they actually fall in love
With the things that make a cartoonist
A little clumsy
A little crowded
A little strange
Because
Those are the things that only they do
And there are certainly there are Craftsman in comics who know just how to make it singing
And compose it
With great precision and orchestrate the line so that
There is no mumbling so that there is no noise
And I love them too
The imperfections I think
Are part of what people
Are drawn to
In my medium
It is an imperfect medium because
It is
The creation of an imperfect species
And the idiosyncrasies
Of cartoonists like
And I'm saying
Robert Cromwell
Charles Schulz
These are the things that
I don't know I think people
Come to embrace
What is a person obsessed with the second the world of visual communication relate to close family members who are
Blind
Ask a question and get a really cool dancer from Scott McCloud
But after that
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound make
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size 14 but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
I got. Info stock podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast oh my God
Flash podcast
You really taken the world with
A lot of attention to
Visual cues and in graphic
Interphase
And you happen to have a blind father Eva blind daughter
How is that affected the way you perceive the world
And even like
How you relate to them
The condition that that
Both my father who's been deceased for some time and my daughter have is
Is called stargardt's disease
It's an inherited condition in swarm of macular degeneration so they're their central vision is
Wasn't easy
And
My daughter being 24 living in Portland
Wearing Doc Marten boots and listening to
Aeroplane Over the Sea on vinyl is is
More than happy to tell me the ways in which I'm ableist and
And the different problems in my focus on visual communication because there are people for whom visual
Communication has
Increase of your limit
And we've had some wonderful discussions about
Accessibility
Just very recently actually
A bit of an epiphany when I was talking to her about this
Her name is Sky and sky and I were talking about
Accessibility and I had
Didn't complain Ivan B no bitching about
One of
Some bit of bad design that affects
It affects me and I realized that
We were talking about the same thing
Idea that there is
It is a human right information as a human right
And
Between the information
And the person you can use that information I think we're talking about fire Maps actually in the recent fires here in Southern California
And the limitations of the different displays that went out
Problems of typography problems
The size of the type Sky tried looking to see even though she wasn't in our area
She was up in Portland but she was looking to see where the old neighborhood do you know where the fires were
And she couldn't
She wasn't able to access it
And I realize that I come up on obstacles and trying to access that information and she had come upon Ops 2
Trying to access that information
And it really illuminated the fact that though they were different ops
Testicles that the principal was
The same
That
Bad design
Is
Committing the same mortal sin
As
A lack of access
For those with disabilities
In fact
Really
At the end of the day
We all have disabilities we all
Cognitive limits
We all have limits of our senses
And
In a failure to recognize the multiplicity of barrier
It's stand between us and what sometimes his life
Saving in
Information
Is an urgent
Public Works
It needs to take place
The other aspect I should mention
You know where sky is concerned is
People with stargardt's.
It's very interesting cuz I
I've run into others with stargardt's
In my travels
If you ever see somebody with sunglasses on
Maybe a dog
And a cane
And walking
Very fast
Cmake infuser
You may wonder why is this blind person walking very fast
Well as I've been studying visual cognition one of the things that's come up as often
Flow
And this notion of
Dewayne which we perceive depth
Not just by stereotypes
Two Snapchats by combining the
Images in our two eyes
But also in the way in which the entire visual field moves by as a
The different speeds
Nearest things like when you're on the road for example and you noticed it
The telephone poles are going by faster in your field of vision then say a distant house
Distant Mountain
Or even just the furniture in your
You're looking up
What what you're doing if you're building a deck
Map
Of the whole visual field the whole visual world
And you're doing it
With motion parallax
Fox rather than
Stereopsis
And this is this helps give you a sense of where you are
Lil Skies peripheral vision is fine
She sees the car coming around the corner
She just can read
She's lost percent
But the faster she moves
The faster she walks
The mark
Complete
Picture of
The world that she lives in is
And so you'll see that on it and a lot of people think that people with stargardt's
Sissies and other forms of maca
Degeneration
I think they're not blind at all
But now they're just
They're seen with
A different part of the
That's amazing
99percentinvisible is Emmett Fitzgerald who helped me a lot with this interview Avery Elementary
Use of term as a composer Sean real
Kolstad and me Roman Mars we are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Reduced on radio Row in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most in
Innovative shows in all of podcasting we are supported by our listeners and that matter so much X
You can find 99percentinvisible into a discussion about the show on Facebook you can't wait to meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99 pi
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
The real 99ci HQ is that
99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com