99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Off the coast of North Carolina
There's a stretch of islands called the Outer Banks
Picture a narrow ribbon of sand that runs along the coast for 200 MI
These islands are three miles across at their widest
Only 200 yards at their narrowest
And there's one part of the outer banks that used to be especially treacherous for ships
It's called Cape Hatteras
That's reporter Gordon Katic
Of a podcast called
Cited
The Cape is known for choppy seas and strong ocean currents
Since the 16th century these waves have caused a lot of shipwrecks
Over a thousand according to the National Park Service
The area has become known as
The graveyard of the Atlantic so many sailors were dying. In the late 1700s
Congress authorized the construction of a giant lighthouse
It would eliminate the dangerous passage and make the Outer Banks less deadly
The lighthouse went up in a small town called Buxton North Carolina
Right near Cape Hatteras
And the people of Buxton they love this lighthouse
Generations of families there helps maintain it
But you know this what your grandfather did it's what your great-grandfather did
This is Danny Couch he's descended from English Pirates
And his family goes back nine Generations in North Carolina
Today Danny leads tours of the Outer Banks
Gordon went last summer
We got three Maritime symbols in this country number one Statue of Liberty number two
Golden Gate Bridge in the number 3 the granddaddy of American lighthouses 282
Bathrooms on the right
We believe anything you need on board
It is pretty Majestic
Got it
Red
Basinger
Delete all
Black and white spiral e
Paint job sort of like a
Black and white candy cane
I see some people on top
Observation deck
There's a crowd of people waiting outside
Park ranger is standing near the entry
Buddy ask because this is all a national park
This is the tallest brick lighthouse in North America that you all are about to
How to climb today so
Hope everybody's ready
It's hard to overstate just how important this Lighthouse is to the people of Buxton
There are three Lighthouse gift shops in town
Practically every business here has a lighthouse in its logo or its name
Like the lighthouse View Motel
Or the lighthouse Sports Bar and Grill even the churches
Like the Lighthouse Christian Assembly
But back in the seventies it look like Buxton might lose their beloved lighthouse
He was getting closer and closer threatening to swallow it up
And people were torn over what to do
The lighthouse
Leave it in place and try to defend it against the forces of nature
Next 30 Years the people of Buxton fought in intense political battle over this decision
Is the kind of battle we can expect to see a lot more of
As sea levels rise and threatened Coastal communities around the world
It all started with a scientist who had a radical idea about what to do with the light
An idea almost nobody like
Let it fall in nothing is so important that a can't fall into
Why don't you introduce yourself
Oh yeah I'm I'm a horn trophy I'm a retired
Marine geologist
Two started out in the deep sea and ended up
On the beaches
Orange County is a professor emeritus at Duke University
He typically wear short-sleeve button-up shirts with
Two or three pens in the front pocket
And she studies beaches
But there aren't any beaches at Duke
Because Duke is right in the middle of the state
So in the 1980s or would pack his students into a bus
Maddie
All the way to the Cape Hatteras Lighthouse
It's usually a pretty exciting place
The average wave height
Cape Hatteras is higher than anywhere else on the East Coast except possibly northern Maine
Oren would tell his students at the waves at Cape Hatteras don't just calmly roll onto Shore
They slam into
And spray up into the air
Paula student stared out into the water or unexplained
These waves are washing away the beach we're standing on
And soon they'll reach the lighthouse
The shoreline of the Outer Banks the entire Charles and the Outer Banks is
Is a routing and partly
This is simply a matter of the ways I think of way at the continent 90% of the
Azar roading
Some very very slightly and then some very quickly
The beach in front of the lighthouse can a road fast
The rates vary wildly from decade to decade sometimes the coast loses 50 ft air other times the beach
Actually gain sand is an erratic natural process
Good morning says climate change is also part of the story it's speeding up the erosion process
4 decade a bunch of different government agencies have been fighting back against the seat
I tried barriers to slow the waves
Put down a wall of sandbags
Even tried this thing called Beach nourishment
That's just a fancy way of saying pumping a ton of sand onto the shore
Other
Inventive ideas to
They put in what they call Seascape
It was plastic
Strips of plastic that floated
Strips were supposed to act like seaweed
And keep the sand from washing away and here it was a very cheap way to stop a road
But it didn't even
Begin to work
In fact none of that stuff for
The Decades of fighting back against the waves the ocean was getting dangerously close to the lighthouse
Less than half of football field weigh
Basically we would stand
Besides a lighthouse
And see
How this
Precious historic
Structure was due to fall in I mean it was easy to see where
A good storm
Would have
Taking out the lighthouse
Is it wouldn't have to be a wind blank or storm but it has gotten to that stage
And so 1974 Oren wrote an academic article
He said we tried pretty much everything
Texas lighthouse
Time to give up
Hero quote
It is difficult but necessary to come to grips
The ultimate result of living with nature at the shoreline
And then he started telling the people of Buxton to let the lighthouse go
Which made them really mad
The whole idea of
Letting things fall in with was absolutely
Outrageous of course we're going to
Defender
Corps of engineer Colonel said
We're not.
Hold up our hands of slink away
Most North Carolinians did not want to see the lighthouse fall into the sea
In 1981 photographer and conservationist named Hugh Morton
Started a group called save the lighthouse
School children across the state raised money to support the group
And they recruited prominent North Carolinians like University presidents
Business Leaders and politicians
The tour guide from the beginning of the story
He became the local representative for Save The Lighthouse
In terms of uniting political philosophies and
You know contradictory elements of
Society developers and environmental
Everybody
Can rally around the Cape Hatteras Lighthouse
And that was
Essentially yes
What was going on nothing else mattered
It was to do right by
The lighthouse
What's in our heritage in disguise
Eventually Danny settles on one big idea
Build a solid concrete wall
All the way around the lighthouse
I think you can pick and choose your fights with Mother Nature you're not going to win all up
You got to pick a fight
But you can win
That was a very common attitude in those days
My idea was to
Live with nature at the shoreline
Warrants at the seawall would be
Extremely expensive and ultimately counterproductive
Busse walls
This is one of the more controversial things that I was saying others to that's a wild destroy Beach
Orrin had Maps
Diagrams of
East Coast
And they showed that seawalls made erosion happen even fast
He argued that that's exactly what would happen at the light
A wall would make the beach smaller
And smaller
So now you're a Beach Community without a beach
With the seawall plan the lighthouse would eventually become a walled Island out in the water
Not ideal but even if you were fine with that
The wall probably wouldn't hold
Oren said it's hard to imagine building a seawall strong enough for the waves at Cape Hatteras
Lots of big storms at the cape
Half the size of the lighthouse the storm server top over the C11 and
Top of a lighthouse
Then one day or met an engineer Named Dave fischetti
Dave Sadler
People don't want the lighthouse to fall in
We don't want to see wall
But there's a compromise
Nothing can be moved
It's around 200 ft tall
About one and a quarter million bricks in 4800 tons
But believe it or not
Engineers have moved bigger buildings
This presented a pretty good opportunity for Warren
He could use the lighthouse to test something that planners call
Managed retreat
The idea is that
As sea levels rise
We won't be able to defend every Coast with a giant wall
Instead we're going to have to make plans to abandon certain areas
And move some things out of the way
Foreign thot
Buxton could be convinced to move this big light house
It might show that managed retreat
Is doable
So she and Dave fischetti along with one of Orrin students
Steve bush
Form their own
They called themselves the move the lighthouse
Committee
We met together alive and reproducing
Blizzard of papers
Documenting things about a rosian to think about moving buildings
Mainly aimed up at the media
Why did you why did you care so much to spend so much of your time
I guess I guess I got emotionally involved off
I wasn't going to let that Lighthouse fall in spite of that first article online
So now you got these two groups
They both want to preserve the lighthouse
But they're debating how
Ultimately it's up to Congress and the National Park Service
Because this is federal property
So the two groups are trying to convince the Feds that they have the better plan
The town of Buxton flatly rejected orange move ID
A local magazine did a poll over 90% of residents wanted to keep the lighthouse in place
Many were offended by the very idea of retreat
Hugh Morton said retreating from the shoreline would be quote
Cheating man's historic battle against nature
And it would make Buxton the laughing
The coast
Danny's group stats
Save the lighthouse
They feel confident they can win this fight
I didn't like these Outsiders telling them otherwise
It was a situation of
Yashow again with a local people
Kind of
Claim ownership of that and how dare somebody with some out-of-state plates come in here and want to tell these
For dwellers on these shifting lonely Sands
What to do with their lighthouse
I mean we are we're not afraid to pick a fight we're very independent people
Danny told me a story to explain the tension between orange group in the locals
He said there was a Duke grad student who would drive down to give talks in Buxton Danny remembered meeting him
And he proceeded to waltz into a gas station that I was running at the time Filling Station automotive repair shop
And we're changing out us semi tires for a for a
Tractor trailers and stuff and Eagles
Search wagon
Finger
Don't you know that this Lighthouse we're going to lose this lighthouse
And y'all are obstruction is y'all are you are
Not y'all he didn't use he one day y'all
You said you were holding this up you're holding this project up
Standing there would like a tire iron in my aunt
Boren and his group has serious credibility problem in Buxton
And they understood why people like Danny
Where it's at
Of course ofcourse we were outside and we were from
From Land far away in Durham
Did this ever give you pause
I suppose so
Going into the community and thing
Hey I know the truth
And after I felt that there was a
The pit of arrogance
And Napa
What was the choice
I didn't know anything about her
How you deal with people I guess in in this sense
Hi understood sometimes
That I was
Speaking over their heads are facing things that they that they did not
Understand that did not want under
And there were other reasons
People didn't like orange group
Many words a lighthouse was so big and so old
That it would break
If you try to move it
I just had strong feelings about the location of the lighthouse
They said it would lose historical value in a new spot
And then there were also some big money interests
Business owners and real estate developers thought a move would hurt their bottom line
If you own something with a name like
The lighthouse View Motel
People move a lighthouse out of you
Throughout the 80s and 90s there were lots of scientific committees commission studies and reports
They all decided that moving the lighthouse was the best idea
But that didn't do much to convince the local
Except for these two local Lighthouse historian
Bruce and Cheryl Roberts
Bruce
Nice to meet you
How you doing
Yeah she'll wasn't around when I met Bruce
She was busy working on a new Lighthouse book
My wife does most of the writing in
I take
Pictures of lighthouses
I'm actually photographed almost every
American lighthouse
Recent Cheryl have basically turn their home into a shrine
4 lighthouses
I got over a hundred Lighthouse books
There's a bunch of miniature lighthouses scattered about
I see countless Lighthouse paintings and pictures
And in their study there's a giant
3 panel room divider
It looks like one of those Japanese screens
Only it's got the Cape Hatteras Lighthouse painted on it
There is something about a lighthouse iPhone
Especially
Back at the time of the controversy
Bruce and Cheryl were writing a book about the Cape Hatteras Lighthouse
That's when they started to do some research
We had read the reports
The White House would be lost in
We talked to some of the other scientists who have studied
And made an interesting discovery
The scientist told them that the lighthouse it's on yellow pine Timbers
They're submerged in a pool of freshwater
It's a strange design
The Builder who constructed the lighthouse knew that if he kept those beans in freshwater
They be preserved
And his plan had work
For over a hundred years
Here's the problem
The ocean was coming closer and closer to the lighthouse
The ocean is filled with microorganisms that could degrade the wood
If the salt water seeped into the foundation
The beams wood rot
And that was the reason that
Channel 9
Realized that
If nothing else happened Lighthouse will begin to tip is that what Foundation was eating away we actually
Went and talked to several of a scientist who it's on the study
Saying it had to be moved
And we got convinced that they knew what they were doing
This was a
Huge gap
14 move the lighthouse
Bruce and Cheryl weren't technocratic Outsiders
They were like us finale
I never seen you look
Like it or not
Scientists are actually right
Then in 1996 two major hurricanes hit North Carolina
Hurricane Bertha
Hurricane Fran North Carolina and Ocracoke Island and Hatteras Island or under an evacuation map
Mandate
Hurricanes are becoming more frequent and more intense
And this created a new sense of urgency
So 1997 Congress started planning a potential move
17 years after save the lighthouse formed
And after almost
Two decades of debate
A public meeting was held to discuss the move
It was organized by a US senator from North Carolina
As well as a state senator from the region
It was April 1998
About 400 people filed into an aquarium
The largest building in the Outer Banks
Children are busting from every school
There were 11 news crews their reporting on the event
The people of Buxton new the fate of the lighthouse might be decided here
Today they had their move it or lose it signs and then the others are like save not move
Guy came up to me grabbed me by the arm said here's your sticker
And I looked at it and said move it or lose it all out on that damn sticker
Politicians and their aides watched as people got up to testify for each sign
Every time somebody said something
That was beneficial to their side they would a corrupted cheers like you were some of the Roman Colosseum
And what about your gladiators
And Bruce who was there along with Danny
But the crowd was clearly against the lighthouse movie
I think I felt
We were going to lose
Bruce went back home feeling defeated
He was convinced Congress was not going to fund the movie
I think the back
That your tube I heard the phone ring back in the office and Cheryl
We're back in
North Carolina state senator Marc basnight was on the other end of the phone
He said
Before the meeting I supported moving the lighthouse but then I saw just how unpopular that was
And now I don't think I can do it
And
I said wait a minute
Here's Cheryl
Do you know about that
Foundation
And the danger
Collapsing
He said no
Bicycle Denmark
You should not be making a decision
In this matter
You need to listen more to the facts
Cheryl told the senator about the
Pine boards in the saltwater
She told him if we don't move it the lighthouse might just fall over
And he did he say
What's a tariff
Hour hour and a half
And she want them over
He had to know
Scientific
This was the critical moment Cheryl got the senator back on board and he urged
Congress to act fast
A few months later Congress funded the Moon
In a last-ditch effort the local County sued
But they lost it was a stinging reminder that even though it may have felt like buxton's lighthouse
It wasn't
Skip Along to the federal government
Began on June 17th 1999 journalist swarmed
Boxden
Because nothing like this has ever happened before
No one had picked up a 4800 ton Lighthouse and moved it over half a mile
People called it
The move of the millennium
Make sure they know we're Romo tape from the truck when you're hearing tape from a documentary made by a local TV station
Already there have been 1,800 visitors to the park this morning that's about double what they usually seek
Coming here this time of year
The Park Service put in Orange fence near the base of the lighthouse
Antorus lined up along it
Local sold them t-shirts and hotdogs at everyone waited and
Brian what do you think about the lighthouse what do you think about it
Big
It sure is big
How we going to move that
Can I pick it up
I'm sorry but
It is heavy
The process was pretty simple
First the engineer's cut through the granite base
Satellite house
Banana Splits 7 giant steel beams underneath it the beans created a New Foundation
A grid under the lighthouse
The pressure at 44 under the steel grid and using hydraulics
Who sing up onto a track leading to the lighthouses near home
Ajax the engineer's for all ready to roll
They pulled a giant lever
I know Lighthouse started 2-inch former if you were there that day in the crown
This all would have looked inside come after because the lighthouse moved
So
Can you see if you couldn't even tell
The Rangers had to put markers along the track
Just so you could be sure that it did in fact
It's just going real
And you're lucky to be
The end of the first day
The lighthouse it only move 10 feet
This whole process would take weeks
My word is still going out
Slowly
Bruce remember showing up one day near the end of the move
Decide Danny coming towards him through the crowd
Danny told him
They're moving it too fast
I'm limestone.
What
What's wrong with Lily get too fast
Is his look
Every restaurant is
Making money
Kerry Hotel smoking
Money
We have never had friends like this ever before
If you can just slow it down till September
We'll all be rich
Slow Down slow down slow down
Orange
At the lighthouse in to its new home
It was again 1600 feet from Shore the exact same distance it was in 1870
For the sea
Wash the beach away
Before the move the people of Buxton felt something terrible and undemocratic was happening to them
These out-of-towners were destroying the heart and soul of their Island
The community fought hard
And they lost
But in a strange way
Things actually worked out for them
I look back at this you know after this is all said and done
Was moving that Lighthouse the right thing to do
Yes it was
Daddy got a ton of Business from The Tourist
Is repair shop in gas station had never done so well
So he's had a complete change of heart
And he's not alone
In fact most people think that the move was the best thing that ever happened to Bucks
Something as Monumental as moving America's lighthouse
Put us on a national radar on an international radar
And people started thinking about the Outer Banks
It was a raging
Success
Danny doesn't look back now and see the movie as a cowardly retreat
He sees it as a testament to human ingenuity
Is all makes orange
Hopeful
Is if Danny can change his views
Maybe others will too
They'll I think the moving the lighthouse was a
The profound event
In terms of our response to sea level rise
I think the Cape Hatteras Lighthouse
Is kind of a good example
We're going to be doing a lot in the future
If you can move a 3000 or whatever it is
Tongue
Lighthouse you can move a lot of colleges
But it's not just lighthouses in Beach cottages
There are thousands of miles of vulnerable US coastline
The Battle of Buxton is just a preview of the tough choices will have to make
We have three thousand miles of Barrier Island show and so whatever happens
Cher
Is also happening in Galveston
And also is happening and Myrtle Beach and then
Jekyll Island Georgia
And they're all going to be
Asking for money from the FED that we need money we need money we need to nurse the beach or we need to we need help.
It ain't going to be there
That's why Retreat is important
But the year 2100 at least 500 us communities will be at risk from sea-level Rise
Including major cities
It's like Miami and New Orleans
That's according to the union of concerned scientists
And then there's the millions of people in other parts of the world
In countries like Bangladesh
Guilin
Better already being badly affected
People get this worked up
About a lighthouse
Imagine how hard it will be when we start talking about moving entire cities
How can you do that fairly and in a way that doesn't devastate communities
We're going to be fighting this battle over and over again
And after all of this the Cape Hatteras Lighthouse will probably have to move again
It might last 100 years at its current location
But some scientists say
Maybe even less than that
We've another high-stakes story of a building being rude but this time
All the people were in it when it
But after that
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
Sometimes moving a building is about preserving historic architecture or
Cultural heritage
But a 99 Pi fan named
Tomorrow solorzano notice about unusually high stakes moved
What happened in her hometown
Guadalajara Mexico
And cripples to this
To talk about it
So back in the 1950s City officials in Guadalajara decided
Why didn't major app
More traffic
And a lot of buildings were just demolished
There is a problem
There's this one 1700 ton brick structure occupied
By the Mexican Telephone and Telegraph
Mismo Kalahari lantigua
Compania telefonica
Eataly grafica
So
Why not demolish
This building along with the rest of it
Will it would have been more expensive
But it also would have knocked out Regional telephone service for at least a week
And that's where Jorge
He's a civil engineer
The dean of the city's University and he has this idea to move the building while leaving everything wired up
And keeping the operators at work
Inside it
I've been pretty nervous
Reassure The Operators and make them feel safe
So his wife Esmeralda
Agreed also go into the building while it was being moved
And she even took along their seven-year-old son one Jorge
Assassin's path on butt
Here's this
Webley clip of his widow talking about the move on television
Ian Thompson
How smart are horses
Yadira Nostradamus gnosis
Yeah
El Menor
So she says
She and her son
1 Jorge went inside the building to gain their trust
And they didn't even feel the tiniest movement
When they moved the whole building and all the Opera
That's so cool
Yeah
Basically
It all went really well
The building was slowly shipped about 40 ft
Switch new location
And
The other people inside didn't feel a thing they kept working
And the whole boob has done just five days
No Interruption to phone service very critical and Lead it on a budget around $100,000
Which was a fraction
Of what it would have cost to demolish the structure and then build
Into this was about
About 70 years of the building
Is it still there is it along this new widen Road
It is
San Matias Ramos
Has a pretty unique Memorial
Statue right outside the building
If this life-size figure of him
And actually positioned it so it looks like he's physically pushing the structure by hand so cool
Yeah and next to that sculpture of course there's a plaque dedicated to his civil service and Engineering Junior
Yeah it really is a special thanks it tomorrow for a city
Really need story
And you can see a video of the move and images of that
Cool statue of matute Ramos on our website it's 99 pi
. org
10% invisible was producer Suite by Gordon khattak and Sam Fenn of cited
F c i t e d
Academic citation
You stories about research and higher education
Yvonne at work at sided
Bill Evans
Stavros album 80s
Thanks also to WRAL TV for letting us use their documentary The Cape light
Away from the edge
You can find a link
Go program
On our website
From our staff is Beast
Personality by Delaney Hall
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by xiaomi
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital
Russell staff includes Avery Trucking
Edmund Fitzgerald
Taryn Masa and me
Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw
Cisco introduced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland Calif
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
Your supported by listeners
Just like you
And if you support us in the last Drive
These are exciting
Divine 99percentinvisible into instructions about the show on Facebook
He treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99pi org
On Instagram Tumblr
Turn right at 2
We have more visual design stories
Videos to
899 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com