99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Going to build a wall
Going to be real
One week into his presidency
Donald Trump sign an executive order to begin building a wall between the US and Mexico
Trump says it will be quote
Impenetrable physical
Tall
Powerful
Beautiful
Southern border wall
Campaign slogans are easy
Reality
Harder
Joe richman radio Diaries on this episode with the help of radio Diaries
I'm going to tell a few stories
About the physical border on the southern edge of the United States
And what happens when instead of people crossing the border
The border crossing
Go Richmond
We'll take it from here
In 2006 President Bush
Signed a law to begin building in 18 ft high fence along a few key parts of the US Mexico border
The project went by different names
Operation gatekeeper in California
Operation Safeguard in Arizona
Play Texas they called it operation Hold the Line
Today that fence looks like a somewhat random dotted line
The entire border
And the Border fence is always been controversial but it's based on a very human impulse
To have an actual physical barrier that marks the imaginary one on the map
It's a simple idea
And like most things that turned out to not be so simple
Hello
Hello this is Pamela Taylor
So can you tell me where you are right now
I'm in my living room
I'm looking out the window
I shaved my front yard
And Beyond.
Is the fence
It is huge iron
About 20 feet tall
The paint was put in there by Homeland Security
Pamela Taylor is 86 years old
You may have noticed she has a slight British accent
But she's an American citizen
After World War II she marries an American they moved to a small Brick House outside of Brownsville Texas
That's the house she's in right now
Which has been there for more than sixty years
At that house is technically in the US
But for the past 6 years
It's been on the wrong side
Defense
We are on the Mexican side
The fences in front of my home
So let me just go over this
Many people think about the Border fence they just assume it's on the border
The Rio Grande river is illegal border
Between the US and Mexico
But the Border fence doesn't follow all the natural Contours about River
If they follow the river it would be a winding fence
Whereas now because a straight fence
And therefore they did not need to install that much fence
And in the beginning
We were told this fence was going to go right through my living room
Luckily the ended up building it
About a mile North
Today Taylor has about a half-dozen neighbors need exact same situation as her
Down the road there's also a farm
Ana Golf Course
All on the Mexican side of the fence
We've gotten used to it now
We just can't go on and
A measurable about it
So how would you describe
Where you are living
Well actually it's a no man's land
And I firmly believe that I shouldn't be paying taxes
A no-man's-land between two countries that's what our next story is about
The United States is not as big today as it was at this time yesterday
President Johnson and president Diaz ordaz of Mexico mad at the border today
Ended an old dispute
The Rio Grande River has been the border between the US and Mexico ever since text
Is became a state
The problem is Rivers can move
That's exactly what happened in 18th
Torrential rains caused the river to jump its banks and go south
All of a sudden the Border was in a different place
What that meant is the Texas have gained a square mile of land
Was called the Chinese all
Names of the scrubby desert plant
The crew there
The Chinese I was a thorn in the side of us Mexico relations for a century
And then finally 50 years ago
The US gave the land back to Mexico
About that time thousands of people and moved to the Chinese at all
I made it their home
And that is where the story
Begins
My name is smiley okay me at 3
I grew up in the chimney selleria during the 50s and 60s
I live one street away
From the river
Which was the division between the two countries
The river was just
More like a highway that you have to cross to get to where you needed to be
There was a baseball team on the Mexican side and then it was a team on the El Paso side and they were just
Signal each other through crystals on and they would cross
That was just
Life with the river between us
This is an interview
Is part of the Chinese style oral history project
Mystery
Could I ask you to describe the neighborhood
Yes they were a lot of tenements
And a lot of
Small
I hate to say checks but that's what they were
They didn't have any
Electricity no running water
But you built one room and then you build another room and that you built another one room after the other state
Baby, just
Better off
Money
Is Victor Guzman Garcia
Garcia Clan goes back to
About 386 years
In this area
A lot of Mexican interior thought that the Chinese are switch
Basically just a square mile of land
They thought it was us largest California
And that is probably had oil and two holes
So
Every time there was an issue between two countries
A Mexican would have course bring up these Chinese on
My name is Paul Kramer and I'm in a store near Vanderbilt University researching the history of atomic solid
In Mexico the Chinese are represented illegally occupied territory
But in the United States every two Americans had even heard of it
And then the 1960's that'll change
No really unexpected way
And this is NBC News
This government
As promised
Has maintained the closest
Surveillance
Of the Soviet military buildup
On the island of Cuba
Within the past Cuban Missile Crisis and specifically the fact that Mexico does not cut off its ties to cast
The Kelly ministration becomes very concerned that Mexico could be vulnerable in the Cold War
Suddenly there's a real willingness to remedy
The Chinese all dispute
To use it as a kind of bargaining
Until the big question is
The residents of this tiny patch of land
What's going to happen today
It's the letter from the international boundary and Water Commission to mr. Luis Rivera
Dear sir
We advise at the appraisal of your property would be undertaken as soon as practical
Preparatory to a position by the federal government
The song
S Kids R Kids
We were eavesdropping
And we heard there was going to be
Removal
We remember our fathers stomping around the kitchen same way they know they can't
We were Mexican by heritage
But we understood that we were American by nationality
People were given a choice of
Going
Back to Mexico
And only one man that we know of
Actually accepted
To go back
Everybody also
No
But we all have to be out
October 19th
This is an interview with we wood
Former government real estate appraiser
Settlement
How did most of the people feel about leaving their home
It was mix
There's one case
Is that I can recall
And this lady
I had a very nice home
Better than the rest of them in the neighborhood
And she's not going to let us in
She couldn't speak English
Enough to get by
And she told me that she was not going to give her house to those goddamn next
Nginx
Nothing go to hell
And I will keep my house and I will
Get my guns out and I will fight
And the day when it came to move
The United States Marshal
Pick her up bodily
And put her in a car
And put her furniture in storage
My name is Angie Nunez
It was a very big disappointment
Because they did not pay for the house
They paid us for the land
My father had just built
For extra rooms in our house
We had Central Heating
Keven Hatfield the bricks
Meat special
Adobe
With the hay
Because the house was going to be that much thicker that
Warmer that
Nice whatever
And we had to leave all that
One by one the family started moving out
What was left behind were empty
Shell's of homes in
Windows are all boarded up and then yellow ribbon was placed on them so that we couldn't even go into the bank
So it look like a crime scene that is yellow
Tape all over
Until the only family left was hours
Hours
Historically was the last
And I remember my dad said
Don't look back
You are forbidden
Aztec welcome at the US Mexican border for President Johnson
Gustavo Diaz ordaz
Arriving together just have to let century-old border dispute
I remember
Thousands and thousands of people
On top of the bridge and everything
And I could see Johnson I could see him sitting at the table and yes or Des
Senor Presidente
It'll stop sneezing America
Jansen
Pretty much the whole of the White House with congressman and senators and everybody was here
This was a big thing
An unpredictable River
Has been converted into a control source
Of water
For Mexicans
Are Americans alive
C4yourself
By December 1968
Mexico and United States
Jointly sponsor
The digging of a cement lined Channel
That will
Make the river go where
The authorities wanted to go in terms of maintaining the boundary that they want
After speeches the two men walked over to press the buttons that would detonate a retaining wall about a mile away and send
The water down its new channel
At the appointed time the two presidents
Approach this black box it's been set up on the bridge
Which has these two Redbox
And it supposed to hit the buttons
And detonate
These explosives to release the mighty Rio Grande into its new channel
In fact I smoke nothing happens
And so very quickly ignition sueldos the Damned
And release the river completing the ceremony
The second hundred years but it's finally done Mexico has its piece of scruff land back their bracket as
What to do with it and the river is once again the international boundary it cost 40 million dollars
Let's write it this way
Jack Perkins NBC News El Paso
Well I'll show you
The river is now
Encased
And cement
That poor thing
It's about 5 feet across
It looks like a muddy creek
Where we used to go out with wide sometimes they had
Quite a bit of water
And that would Ripple across
There's only so much control a man can do on a river
Sooner or later
I personally think that river is going to do what Mother Nature has Tata to do
To move
Well I woke up
This morning
Do the door let it go
I found that I was living in Old Mexico
Well I was born in America in El Paso
The song you're hearing right now is called the Chinese all Blues written and recorded by Bob Burns and the teakwoods P9
A year before the Chinese all was handed back to Mexico
This story was produced by radio Diaries that's Joe Richmond Nellie Gillis
Sarah Kate Kramer Ben Shapiro and Debra George would help from historian Paul Kramer
Radio Diaries is one of the founding members of radiotopia and one of the true gems of public radio
I implore you to subscribe to their podcast
We we pour your own guy
They produce many historical documentaries but they specialize in giving recorders to Ordinary People
With extraordinary stories and turning their audio Diaries into Unforgettable radio they busily one
Every award in journalism and when we started radiotopia
So honored that they wanted to work with us
The brave Diaries is not part of your podcast diet
You are missing out
Find them at Radio Diaries. Org
Rent radiotopia. FM
At the tail end of 2017 our own Avery Kauffman took a trip to the border for sale
Look at the architecture of the border wall and the new border wall prototypes
We'll talk to her about what she found
Right after this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms but oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
Build That Wall
Truly after Trump took office in March of 2017 US Customs and Border Protection put out a request for proposal
Asking private companies for designs of a wall that would divide Mexico
In state
There were two different requests for proposals or rfps
1rp was a wall design made of concrete
The other was for a design made of quote on quote
Other materials
They were to be between 18 and 30 ft tall
From the submissions they received Customs and Border Protection selected 8
And turn them into prototypes
That's October our own Avery Chapman went down to see what they look like
Well I'm glad you're okay
I found myself in a crowd of reporters
From writers in the guardian and Univision and fox
We'd all been given hard hats
A neon yellow vest
We all piled into an air-conditioned van
But we were brought out to a construction site
Cameramen unpacked and hoisted their video cameras like great mechanical carcasses
Anchors applied fresh makeup and did warm ups
And then we swarmed around Roy Via Real
All of us jostling to get our microphones in his face
First name is Roy Roy last name vital
V i l l
A real acting Chief Patrol agent for the u.s. border patrol in the San Diego sector
He was showing us these eight prototypes
New border wall
Between the United States
And Mexico seven of the eight have been completed and the 8th when should be completed by the end of the
These 8 Simple rectangles
Border wall are massive
Each is 30 ft tall
It's striking in person
If they were actually formed into one continuous wall
They block off the mountains in the distance
By now you've probably seen pictures of these prototype
Bar made of concrete
Four are made of other materials
What is bright blue
One has molding on the side to make the
Concrete look like cobblestone
Half of them around and tops to make it harder to grip
MMD determination of of the ultimate design is based on
Testing evaluation
We have three specific
Requirements
Which are looking at the Subterranean ability to dig underneath it prototypes
Penetrability
The aspect
Being able to breach
Some way to grade the Prototype
And scalability
The setup of the eight different prototypes only look like a design competition
So I asked Via Real
Will there be a winner here
Olympia winner
Ultimate the winner is the US government is going to be us in that this is going to enhance our portion
Nicely played
Conceptually what we may have is we could have a singer design that is going to be
Utilize it then some signal on the border or we have a combination of the designs
Pair together and then applied
Different areas along the border
It's not exactly clear what will happen with the Prototype
Customs and Border Protection never specified if they were intended
For the entire border or parts of the Border
Or to fortify existing walls
Because of course the part that Trump didn't mention in his campaign is that over one-third of the u.s. Mexico border
Is already covered by a wall for a barrier from time
So now we are here in this Administration which ran on the platform to said I'm going to build a wall and everybody clapped
There's already 650 my wall in place
This is Ronald real professor of architecture at UC Berkeley and author of the book border wall as architecture
In his book he writes about the long history of the border wall
It has a long life
It's been around for some time
It's evolved from
Stone Cairns these are Stones placed along the border to save where the Border was
Because it's just a frontier originally real says no one knew where that borderline
Actually was
An engineer's from
Mexico and the United States
Went to this kind of no-man's-land Frontier Zone
After 1848
Just figure out where to place
Is demarcation Stones piles of stones were put up in Lego monuments
Fences were constructed mostly the fences work truck to keep cattle out
Is there ranches on both sides
Eventually
Some of those fences
Became more aggressive especially between the cities
Particularly
Between San Ysidro
Tijuana
In 1990 the Army Corps of engineer came to that Tijuana border
They brought over 40000 carbon steel corrugated
Each plank 12 ft long and 1/4 inch thick
These have been made for the Vietnam War
Portable Landing mats for helicopters
Annies helicopter landing mats were turned up on their sides
Into the first official border wall
More and more Landing mats were added and today they're over 60 miles of this Landing mat wall
And then in other parts of the Border other kinds of walls and fences work
I'm different
All varying based on the topography
Pedestrian fences that allow for visibility on both sides vehicular fences that are meant for cars not the
Cross in his book railless over a dozen types of border wall
And this is here in the Algodones Dunes
California floating fence
Snakes over
Huge mountainous Dunes
And has these mechanical buttress
But keep it from sinking into the sand
Dutch designed to be lifted
Placed back on the dunes
Otherwise
Just let it go it just sinks
Amazing
The border wall is already a building project with significant weight behind it
Is unfettered bylaws that regular building projects
Have to abide by
And that's particularly because of Easter
Secure fence Act
Passing 2006 back when George W Bush was president
The secure fence Act of 2006
Was created
So that it could
Usurp
Any other law that existed
In the United States
So any environmental
Protection laws
This is more important
Any Native American heritage
This is more important any Wildlife Act
Secure fence Act
Is more important than any of them
And so
The wall can be constructed
Inhibit
Which brings us back to those new prototypes that are being considered
And the Press junket I went to back in October
The border is very dynamic
Fluid Dynamic there is
Climate
Some form happening everyday
The prototypes will help influence
Beef
The future.
Future development of our border infrastructure system
When they request for proposals went out
Architects for like
What do we do
Number of architecture firms submitted some designs for border wall
And other Architects admitted blank sheets of paper to waste his time
Ultimately
Customs and Border Protection didn't choose
Any architects
At all these prototypes
Like the vast vast majority of
The Delta environment
Bridges
Tunnel Towers houses
Does airports luxury apartments in prison
Or mostly made
Buy General country
These giant construction firms
Are very practical
They safely arrived
Huge structures on time
And on budget
Their goal is to
Jacquee's the club
Which in this case
Is the US government
They prototypes were manufactured
Her by 6
Companies
Do you mind walking us through these companies are
I'm going to defer that to mr. to sell cuz I don't know them
Route to say I was the spokesperson for border
And he wasn't quite familiar with the construction companies either
The best he could do was read them off a list
Glpa North Augusta
Cadel
Sterling
Kwwr Fisher
Sand
To be fair at the time I didn't know these companies either
I had never heard of them before
But I've lately been in one of their structures somewhere
In one of their tunnels or airports are office building
The companies that made these walls are
WG Yates & Sons from Mississippi
Open North America in Israeli company based in Maryland
Caddell Construction Alabama Texas Sterling Construction of Houston
Kwr construction from Arizona and Fisher sand and gravel from Arizona
Now
Because of the wall prototype
People know these companies
And they're talking about their relationships today
We separate return from the border I went to an Oakland city council meeting where they were considering passing an ordinance to forbid
Contracting with any of the companies bidding on the border wall
How to take my colleagues and fans for supporting our resolution on the border wall to make sure that
None of our tax dollars are spent
Being invested with any contract or any business
That is building
This divisive wall that will do nothing to make us safer other municipalities
Around the country
Including New York City in LA
And even floated on the state level in Arizona California Illinois New York Rhode Island and Wisconsin
This is a Prohibition on the city of Oakland
Doing business with contractors
Build
Trump
Border wall
And the City of all countries have absolutely nothing whatsoever
To do with it
But they're also critics of these kind of ordinances
Luxury Smith
Representative from associated general contractors or AGC who stood up at the Oakland city council meeting and testify
Behalf of the contractors Freedom of Choice has any policy or regulation that prohibits a contractor from bidding a
Construction project because contractor should be able to choose which projects they wish to bid on
Without fear of reprisal or discrimination but the ordinance passed
Companies entering contracts
City of Oakland
Say to build a tunnel or a condo complex
Will be required to declare that they are not
Part of border wall construction and do not plan to be
And this goes beyond those companies already involved in the Prototype
Because new Border Construction is happening
Separately
8 prototypes
On the San diego-tijuana border
When I talk to Customs and Border Protection people
They're thinking is that you know
He's the president this is what he wants
So we're going to
We're going to follow his
Orders
So they're going through the motions
Buildings prototype
But when it comes down to it that's not going to work
That's Melissa Del Bosque
A reporter from the Texas Observer
And according to an article she published last year there already plans in motion for the First new section of the border wall
Which will run through a wildlife refuge in South Texas
It will be built by Michael Baker International
Construction firm who was not involved in the prototypes at all
The proposed design will be a levee wall
Which is not among the designs in the prototypes
Pictures of the prototypes what should we make of that
I don't know I think they're going to
Sit there like Stonehenge probably
You just view them as a symbol
Yeah
Yeah totally
I don't think they mean much other than
Filling his campaign promise
So whether or not these particular prototypes on display will ever actually be built
There will be more walls
What will happen is what has been happening for decades
And it's not
Special to the Trump administration at all which is that
Some walls are going to be constructed
Because this has been happening to many presidencies
Republican and Democrat
Professor Ronald Rael again
And so I imagine that's what's going to happen
There's going to be some walls built
Rail has been studying the various border walls for years
He's come to believe they're ineffective and inhumane
So we first saw the pictures of Trump's prototypes
He thought of the famous saying show me the 20-foot wall in 21 foot ladder
And so real got to work on a simple Act of protest using his skills of an architect
Based on the images of the wall prototypes
He drew up some designs for ladders
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery truffelman and radio Diaries composer is Sean real
Senior editor Delaney Hall
Digital director career goal stat senior producer Katie mingle rest of team is Emmett Fitzgerald
Turn master and me
Roman Mars special things this week to Dexter Walcott Ashton ham Patrick McAndrews James hurt Peggy deamer
In the rest of the architecture Lobby
Group of concerned Architects doing work
Find them at architecture. Shalaby. Org
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco are produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Or one of the founders of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
We are supported by our listeners
No keep sending me pictures of your freshly applied sticker badges
They make me very happy
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoy in discussions about the show on Facebook you can meet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99
MPI or one Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But all people of every nationality are free to hang out at our place at 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com