99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
You've seen a logo that Tom Geismar has design
You probably someone today
Xerox
Mobile
NYU
TBS
Univision
The Boston public transit systems Mark is a t in a circle
Tongue guys Marta.
But his work and that his longtime business partner Ivan tramiah poop
What's the weather in May 2017
Is truly fused into the DNA of moose
Modern logos
To see today
Whether they design them or not
In 1961
Logo for Chase Bank
Poppy design
The blue octagon with the square in the middle was introduced
It's still used everywhere
Consider when the first of its kind in the US
An abstract Dynamic shape
Representing a giant company
The logo was a real CJ
For Chase
Belle Chasse at that time it was really Chase Manhattan bank because it was the merger
Two giant bags
Chase National Bank in the back of the Manhattan company
And
They had a logo which featured a map of the United States
Globe of the world
The wording Chase Manhattan Bank in a few other things
It was quite a
Credit mix
I meant they were
In the process of building the first modern skyscraper in the Wall Street area because of Avi
Financial firms for moving up to Midtown at that point
David Rockefeller was in charge of that process though he was only 13 command at the time
At the bank
And
He fell
That would be appropriate to have them also and modern
Contemporary looking mark
For this new Leaf
Form Dutch
Basically you're merger
Least of these two Banks
And we discussed with him the idea of maybe we could just do something abstract because no one had any idea of
A symbol of banking dollar sign
Chase was so big they were going to be either the number one or number two I don't remember
Largest
Bank in the country they had advertising in the newspapers every day
Turn around
New York metropolitan area that you couldn't miss
Their branches they were everywhere so
The idea that you could establish something
Don't you be abstract as their mark
What channel is the Red Cross or Mercedes
Chevrolet that mean there are some around there were some of the time
But not many at all
And that was the idea
We can do that
Stop for something
That was bold and that would be recognized as representing the bank
And so how did you come up with the shape like what were the drawings like what were you thinking when that shape was
Applying to Chase
But we weren't something bold something to stand out something that could be reproduced
In various materials
Something that could work at a small size
Turn up the time is very important also that's something that could work in black and white in the newspaper
There was no color printing in newspapers at that time
Something that could work on television but also in a letterhead or a formal announcement
So we
Try to keep all those things
In mind we looked at a number of different designs this particular one
It's also quite similar to
Old Chinese coins
They were rectangular they had a hole in the middle
And someone in that was
Helpful in terms of rationalizing
Why that particular design
And so
In Rockefeller was
Turn on your side in this but
Did they expect something quite so
Dynamic and radical in Revolutionary or they expecting something more akin to the
Map of United States and the globe and the world banking
Word on top of them what were they expecting
Well you say they David Rockefeller certainly went along with this idea but the two
Do people above him
John McCloy the chairman and George Champion the president
We're pretty shocked
Women that when we showed it to them
Championship why can't we just have a picture of the building
Or the sculptures were going to have out front
Panda
We tried to persuade him that was a bad idea
Helen McCrory eventually said
David we've given you this project
If you want this
For the
Retail Bank you can do it but I don't want to see it on my letterhead I don't want to see at my office
I don't want to see it I really don't understand it and don't like it
Soon thereafter they adopted it and
The bank went ahead and did it and it was only
6 months later
That we were down there and ran into McCoy in the hallway
And
Barry was with a tie with a symbol on it with cufflinks with the symbol on it
With a pin in his lapel with a symbol on it
So it was a great lesson to us because
Suddenly someone who couldn't understand it
As an abstract design
Now really accepted it
As a representation of
His his company
So you mentioned the lessons of McCoy
Employee
On board
With the mark
As soon as it became the mark of his bank
Expand on what some of those lessons are and how you
Use them to think about your work
Today in and how you deal with client
Well I think that's a big lesson
And we learn then was that
What people react to is not the more but they react to is the institution that it represents
So if you ask people
Yo what do they think are good marks
They will
Almost inevitably
Mention
Companies or institutions or whatever that they think highly of
So they'll often say apple and others that they think highly of
Dilemmas never say Imran for example
Even though Enron had a very
Good
Mark
Designed by a famous designer Paul Rand
Nothing to do with the quality pretty much it has to do with what it represents
So the chase logo with something that's from the ground up
A brand new invention
It's also done an umbrella I got a patient's and
An update since
Was one of you talk about the PBS logo which is something that
I think a lot of
People are familiar with
What that process was like and then what you were trying to do there
You're very often we will try and build on something that's there if it has real real value
And in the case of PBS
There was a
The problem
That
They and the station
Where is public broadcasting stations
At the time people presumed it was the public broadcasting system
The way CBS is the Columbia broadcasting system it's on
At CBS you know they have a number of owned stations and whatever
End of the issue was that actually
The stations
Had complete responsibility for raising their own funds
To keep in business
And PBS is not a
Conglomerate that supplies funding and someone
Verizon programming
But not finding any people misperceived
What PBS was in there and their logo
Was a very clever
PBS where the P was a person
Service silhouetto of a man
And
The idea was could we do something
That makes it clear that does public television
Not some kind of
Network
So or I thought was actually at the time to take that P
That they had out of the PBS
Turn around 30 gave me lobotomy
And
Pick some up a bit and then repeat it so that was the idea of multiple
People is in
That was public TV
But that was the whole reason to do it but again it got filled
On something that existed
A part of the letter so it was no great
Radical change
At the time but it was something more appropriate
And something to solve a problem
To how do you
Steer a client to select
Name of the shape in the idea that in your heart
You really know is the right one like how many options do you give them but I'll need variations do you present is there a psychology
In presenting a logo
2 group
Will today
We do want to prevent
Options we almost
Almost always do
Because there is not necessarily one right answer
For these issues
It's just you're having to make a decision and go ahead with it
But we you know explain what the pluses and minuses are of the various options
And you often have a favored which we try to push if we had
Butters
There's not necessarily a computer
The obvious
Right
Answer
And when you have a favorite.
Give me state that it's your favorite or do you just presented first or presented last is there a
Engagement ship in this at all
There may be a little bit but not
Not that much and we don't usually state
Which one we favor for showing options
But we encourage them to ask us
A later and we try to also get there
Take out in one of the first things we say
Actually when we're before we presented anything is it's never love at first sight
So it's your thing is if you can imagine what it might be like it actually use
And that's what we try to show when where showing
Designs
Have to be marks
What it might look like in various appropriate to kind of use
So I see the chase logo on my iPhone it works really well as an app icon it is that a coincidence or something
Has made it indoor over 50 years in in in Brooks on a tiny screen as well as a
Trinidad and other tie tack and everything
Well it is a coincidence but it happens to work very much in our favor because we've always tried to do things
That are very clear very simple and that can be reduced to a small size
So suddenly today it's a it's a requirement
Really have almost every Mark that has any kind of social exposure
And it does work well
And it just happens I think maybe our approach was the right approach and we were lucky
That it certainly applicable today and looked like a lot of work we get
Today is because people have
Mark's that can't work is it at
So has the approach
For creating marks
Changed over 60 years in
Because of this or there are there other things that
Are more fundamental in the in the change in the work that you guys do
You don't actually hasn't
Change that much at least our approach to it hasn't changed that much
Is that say mention we try to
Really
Get down to the basics
Sing a basic Mark that can identify
Whatever the institution is that we're identifying in a clear way
And we have three criteria really which are the basic criteria
That one is that at
Be appropriate
You would do something
Sports team that would be quite different for something you do for a bank for example
It'd be appropriate to
To the client
In to enter what they do
Second one would be that'll be distinctive
That
You can see it you can remember it you can recognize it
Maybe you can doodle it
Quickly after having seen it a couple times
Set that it that it will stand out
And be recognized
And then the third thing is just that it works in all kinds of sizes
Different materials and so on if that's appropriate and it often is
So if you can meet those three
Criteria
Then we're doing pretty well
How do you balance
The concept of being appropriate
Towards a certain Institution
And it being abstract enough
You know be this empty vessel that
Rapport meaning into
Well it doesn't have to be
An empty vessel that all it doesn't have to be abstract
For banking that window
We couldn't think of anything that's good
Trappa lyrics persons banking but that's not always the case by any means
I mean if there is something
Real that's appropriate than you try to work
Understandable
That's a lot easier for people to understand the other thing is that once we did the Chase Bank
Mark
Thanks rollover infect people over started using
Making abstract sense because they didn't have anything like the exposure
Dr. Chase
That kind of thing only works really well if you
I'll have enough exposure that people come to recognize it
Brian
Rhino that makes
Example I know that
Your
Group is responsible for a lot of
Aquarium logos and those are
You know that they have nice shapes to them in their abstracted in certain ways but
Waves and fish and things that you recognized as the things that that it represents as an aquarium
Yes and I actually will those aquariums
They will have different emphasis in terms of the concept of the building and and the
He said that since I won
And so we're even trying to represent that obviously fish
And water are
Key part of all of them
But summer about the oceans and summer about
Freshwater and so on
You talk about
You know how you decide
Nearest
In the very beginning stages
Of working
The client
Whether or not you're going to
Do some kind
Wordmark
That uses
The company's name or
Something more abstract
Pictorial
How do you
Make that up
Well that's what was the key decisions
We don't surely make the decision
We we might show you both options for example
And what the pluses and minuses are
Proposed
Two things that depends of course and put the name is to begin with
But generally if the name is is short and I shorted me maybe five letters or something
Annie's distinctive
Then
We would start with the idea
Making that word
Distinctive
I'm doing a lot of work for a lot of technology companies recently added
You know what they're
Doing is pretty hard to understand and serve you very hard to represent in any meaningful way
You know it's not as if they're
They're harvesting apples or something that you can do Annapolis
Whatever
It's extremely difficult
Go to work
Find something that's a
Appropriate
Meaningful but also
Distinctive
And if so is there a certain thing that you listen
For when somebody describes
Company describes what they do
That is a
Key into your process of beginning to design something
For them or is it too stiff
Every time
Well we go through a whole process of trying to interview a lot of people
Really trying to understand the culture
And what they do obviously
And to understand the competition and Racine with
Against and
Really together
Pretty in-depth
Understanding
Of what the situation is in
In the process of doing all that
And interviewing people
Muffin ideas funny
Some funny places come up
Might be just a wisecracking
Conversation or something but that's where a lot of the ideas come
Sue in 1961 you can introduce an octagon and have a pretty simple
Be bold and be assertive with Chase
Because Chase is so big
Now you know doggone it's closed off you can't put an octagon out there
As an abstract marched
You know for a company
Is it harder
Have a bold graphic
Simple today just because of the number of
Shape sorter
Just limited in the world
Well it is hard
Chester there are so many and now with
Little icons and emojis and whatever is just so much so much around so yeah
Yes it is it is difficult
What we do now is before we show anything
To our clients we
Have
Done a preliminary legal search
So
We try not to show anything
To a client
East Pass
The initial with
Knockouts
Search
Because we don't want them to fall in love with something and then find out
MLB can't use it
Have you ever fallen in love with something and found out you couldn't use it
Oh sure we just don't show it
I mean very much and one of the one of those
Complications is of course the things are registered
Has marks within a certain area of business
For example I want to wake up a week if it's
Red star
So what I mean obviously represents China
But it's also Macy's
Is San Pellegrino it's Heineken
It's it's many different things and they're all doing it legally
They will have the right to use it
Another so
It's not quite so simple
So you might have something you come up with it maybe similar to something in a very different field
And you have to register the mark in particular
Yeah whatever area business here in
And so then there's
That decision to hear do you
Go ahead presuming it's going to be okay because there's not going to be confusion because you're in a completely different
World
Or not
Has this method of
You know introducing things to the public
That's really change
Extend
The time. Would you been work
How do you approach that now in in what do you think of
The Serta Bloodsport of
Introducing logo is in
Reactions online
And that kind of thing
Well are you sure recommendation is don't say a word
Just do it
I think if you look at more broadly I think people are much more
Visually aware
Today
You're always looking at their phone they're looking at
Icons of looking at apps
They're looking at all these things in and so it's much more part of the
Culture so
I think the desire to do something good
Which sperm are going to be was certainly a positive thing is part of that
The idea being a Critic is
Is another part of
But I think overall
It is great that people are much more
Conscious and aware I critical
Of these things
Tom Geismar is the co-founder of Termite & Geismar & haviv
If I mentioned at the beginning the show Tom's longtime partner Ivan chermayeff died in December of 2017
They work together for 6
60 years
Expanded text version of this interview will be included in a new book about the firm
Don't be published by standards manual in May 2018
Bobolink
Coming up an extended preview of a brand-new radiotopia show in the producers of criminal
Criminal
What day you ask me
Is my personal
Favorite podcast I cannot praise it enough
Guava short story and preview of their brand new series
But after that
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
And now a preview of a new show in radiotopia
From the makers of criminal
Generally speaking a lie about
5100 eggs and these are laid in a in a
White silken sack
And
After the babies hatch
The mother
Just about immediately lays another set of eggs and and these are what are known as trophic eggs these are exit
They're never going to hatch and they will serve as food for the spiderlings
This is doctor bill shut professor of biology at Long Island University
Associate in Residence
The American Museum of Natural History he's telling us about the black lace weaver spider
Spider is common in the United States
You've probably seen one before you probably have one somewhere in your yard right now
They're hard to describe because they look like a spider
Brownish black in color
Summon the spiderlings hatch
They are the immediately set about eating the the eggs
All the trophic eggs that their mother has late now spiders and a lot of other Arthur
Pods animals that have an outer covering that have their skeletons on the outside of their bodies like shrimp or Lobster
We're scorpions or insects it's the only way that they can grow in size
Is to shed their outer that system is cuticle
So after their first molt that pretty much out of food
So they've gone through the
Trophic eggs that their mother has produced
And that's when they do something really
Kind of strange
The mother
Basically thrums on the web drawing a baby's to R
So it looks like she drums on the web it and and they are attracted to that vibration of the web
And they swarm all over her spiders are all about vibration
She basically does as she's plucking on her silk and attracting the youngster
First to come to her this is Doctor Linda Ray or
Associate
Cornell
Inter specialty
Is the social lives of spiders
They respond to the movements
And move in
Quarter as a group and start feeding and evidently they eat or within the hour
How does she get them to eat her do they just know this instincts really that
They noticed instinctually
What they do is it is basically inject this enzyme Laden
Got juice and.
And break down the inside of her body
It's almost like they slurp a rock through a straw
Like a protein milkshake
Eating her
Yeah eating her alive
And then they
They will hang out for
Another
Three four weeks together so there's a mass of these baby spiders and then they'll disperse from the web
Hot to become adults
It is
It is just natural
Yeah I would call it parental Behavior
That to a degree that we would consider to be extreme
They turn out to be just awesome Mother's
The ACT
Inducing the young to come to her and start
Feeding on her is absolutely intentional
She is inviting them
She's asking them to do this and this is her sacrifice for her youngsters
This happens every day These Quiet selfless Act
All around us
And we have no idea
We've been making Criminal
For more than three years
When we began
We set out to explore stories about crime
That went places
You might not have seen coming
We thought we try our hand
It's something new
A subject
Is enormous and varied
And arguably over
Posed as crying
Criminal
Isn't going anywhere but
World's going to bring you this new thing
A show about people
Not spiders
Dealing with the inescapable nature of love
And how a simple Act of love
Isn't always pretty
Or Grande
And doesn't always make things better
But can change the course of it all
Incredibly excited about the stories
And we hope you listen
Is love
You can subscribe in apple podcasts
Or wherever you get your podcasts
And learn more
But this is love podcast
Dot-com
99percentinvisible is Emmett Fitzgerald who help me edit this interview
Avery Trucking Mentor reviews of turn master composer Sean real senior producer Katie mingle senior editor Delaney Hall
Digital director Kurt Kolstad hanmi
Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
Radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are apart of radiotopia from PRX
Collectible the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported
Wireless
You can find any 9% invisible enjoin discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars in the show at 9
NPI aura
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to do you want to learn the difference between the rounded rectangle and a mathematically
More complex
Much more pleasing
Oracle
Never look at app icons the same way again it'll bug you forever this is our gift to you
Go to 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com