99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1933
A group of Architects boarded a ship called the SS Patrice 2
Set sail from Marseille France toward Athens Greece
On board were several of the world's most famous
Modernist Architects and artists
Erno Goldfinger
Le corbusier
Alvar aalto in dozens of others representing more than 15 countries
There was a silent film made the voyage that shows grainy shots of The Architects on deck of the ship
In short sleeve white shirts and sunglasses
Cigarettes in their mouths their hair blowing gently in the breeze
Listen to lectures
One of the Architects wrote in his journal
We eat and drink copious
Demerol half naked
The Architects were on the ship for the international Congress of Modern Art
Commonly known by its French acronym
Cm
Bet senior producer Katie Mingle
And I'm going to hand the story over to her now
So yeah The Architects were on this
Boat Trip
Oracia meat
More specifically they were there to talk about how to plan a better City
The members of CM thought that cities were too congested
Too noisy in polluted and chaotic
And they thought that some of these problems could be solved by separating out the
The functions of
The city into distinct zones
So as separate everything everything housing working Recreation
The traffic
Separate all the kinds of traffic so pedestrians the cyclists cars
The trains
It would mean the end of congestion
That's deaf
Planner
Hey must been a bunch of years working for the city of Amsterdam as the head of the urban planning department and now he's
Teaches at the University events
I love cities
The idea of separation of
Functions wasn't brand new
Bahama says The Architects from CM wanted to take it really far
The Living Spaces would be in high-rise apartment
So that the ground level was open for recreation
Collective spaces
Live in the sky play on the ground
In fact
Cars with drive on elevated roads so that pedestrians could have the ground all to themselves
There would also be separate zones for industry and shopping
We're old European cities for winding cluttered and polluted
These new cities
It would be linear open and clean
Everything in it
Proper place
It should be kind of smooth
Lies machine where you're very comfortable
Modernist also saw this new kind of city as more egalitarian
They wanted to get rid of slums
Create beautiful housing that everyone could afford
It was a beautiful image
I knew it
I knew alternative for living in cities
That's the American city planner Oscar Newman in a BBC documentary called the writing on the wall
What's a people
Give him a few
If you happen to be the other buildings but
Get them of you
Give him space down below free the bra
Socrative
But in the 1930s
That's all it was
A great image
Because the world was in an economic depression
There was not much to do in the 1930s
Because it was the crisis there was no no building anymore
I never got the second World War
It sounds cynical but
In effect
They were rather lucky that so many cities were destroyed in the Second World War
Sounds documents that they day almost celebrated
Destruction
So that was a lot of work to do in 1945
And they were really excited
But it wasn't just that the Architects had a lot of work
It was an opportunity to start over
To build cities the right way
From the ground up
And that was all that was their idea from the start
So dear everything down
Let's start again
The CM architect cease to this opportunity
The famous Swiss architect and CM member liquor Boosie a published a book
Called
Leila shot Dothan
English
The Athens Charter
The book outlined exactly how to build new cities in the way vrchat
MCM had talked about
On the boat and became a best-seller
Le corbusier traveled the world talking about these modern ideas for
City building
And governments liked what they saw
Mostly because of the price
CM proposed
Affect very cheap building
Concrete the modernist Building Material of choice with inexpensive
I'm building identical apartments in high-rises was
Cheaper and required less land than building stand-alone home
Ross what all the
The government's need it after the second world war because
Oh you are + poor
And so after World War II
In cities all over Europe
Buildings and housing developments were rebuilt with CM principles in mind
Almost everything
Are in Europe
We built a lot of modernist style apartment buildings
Here in the US
Northeast building project
Post-war Europe in the United States
Weren't usually pure encapsulations of
CNN Le corbusier plan
Most places took some ideas and left others
But the city planners of Amsterdam in the Netherlands wanted to go further
They wanted to build a new area
Right outside of Amsterdam
It would be a CM blueprint
Perfect encapsulation of these modernist principles
They would call this place
The belmermere
Show from the center of Amsterdam I think you could
Take a bike and within a half
How are you are in the balamir
That's Touch Radio producer Chris Byam reported the story with me and like a proper Dutchman
He rode his bike out to do interviews many times
That's a bummer mirror
I always take my bike
So you'll hear him asking questions and
Occasionally speaking in Dutch
The Builder Muir area covers about 6
Square kilometers or
2.3 square miles
I think you can walk around for a day
Is really big
Today the belmermeer is also in
Extremely diverse area
There's something like a hundred and fifty nationalities represented there
All your car goes in Ghana says on the
The area has changed a lot from the original design
And it's had a bunch of different chapters over the years
Including some really tragic one
So let's start at the beginning
First can you introduce yourself
My name is Peter brand I'm an architect
Amsterdam
And I've been alone for a while I've been educated in delft University
How much in debt
Functionalist
Modernist
Addition
That means
That is you know gif
Thick concrete
Blocks the that was our
Paradise
When he was a young man to Brown was hired
To help plan the belmermere
It would be a brand new area right outside of Amsterdam 400,000 middle-class resume
And it would technically be part of Amsterdam
But it would be built from scratch and designed to function almost as its own City
A city of the future
True to the tenants of modern
The Belmont
HDI ptosis of old modernist
Thinking it's a dream come true for you oh definitely yes I was not even 30 years old
Jordan 25
We are going to present the world
Who is the new
Far-reaching
I did
YouTube
I started to understand
This is going far on this is really
Unusual
It was like a fever everyday every moment
In.
Directions
The brown worked on a team with a bunch of other planners
And the head of the team was an architect named Siegfried Nassif
Yeah you a secret nothing was a lot of really idealistic
Personality
Believe that
How we built in the 19th to 18th centuries was good enough
Let's do it
All over again a new and bigger and NM better
This is Dan Decker
I'm a writer and I wrote a book about
That developer
The Bell Marissa
A shorter way of saying the belmermere
You hear people use it a lot
Anyway Dan says there was never any
Question that the Ballmer would be made up of
Tall concrete housing Towers
But the planners did choose to arrange them in a sort of unique shape
Which was shaved off of owning
How do you say yeah
Adwords
Honey,
If the buildings were laid out in the
Hexagonal grid of a honeycomb
It would allow each
Department to get a good amount of
Sun per day
The modernists were crazy about sunlight
That was a huge part of their Doctrine
Better than your predecessors
If you could bring more sun to all these dwellings
The apartments at the bilmar Were Meant For The Middle
A new apartment was designed to be better than another
Image of Man Behind
Belvidere bus
Egalitarian
The basic idea behind it
Was
That
Everyman
Is equal to his neighbor
The modernist idea to
Keep all of the functions of the city's separate was also strictly follow.
Dahmer
Housing would be up in the sky and Towers while the ground would be kept open for the people to congregate in green
Green spaces and endure Collective areas
The idea being discussed
Philosophy help each other grow in life
Make better people proposed Apartments be built on the ground level up
The building
An acid was completely
Horrified and appalled saying
The ground is for everyone
Should not be inhabited
Bye
Private people
The Browns has any suggestion to stray from the original principles of modernism was
Completely shut down by NASA
No
Stop we're not going this direction
We'll stay in the party line
Boss like a religion
Any any subversive
Alamo
Lost
But potentially big danger
To the house of cards
What we call in the Netherlands
Actually moved
Do it flat
I was so much
Involved
In the modern movement
Modernism
Advise No Doubt
That I would
Like to live
In the middle of
The brown was not the only person who wanted to live in the middle of it
Advertisement stupid
Take me to paradise
Modern apartment Towers surrounded by lush green grass and trees
Hey it's comparable with this but living in Central Park
Even going to be better than Central
The park
Of course people wanted in
Each building was managed by a different Housing Association
Underwear waiting list
An interview to be accepted as a tenant
The Brandon is spice moved in in 1969
I left on the 9th
Florida three bedrooms
Living room
On kitchen
Beautiful bathroom
I had a balcony
Off
Substitute white
12 meters long
Advisor
Paradise off a balcony
Surrounded always lived in small apartment
Noisy cities
Now he was on the 9th floor
Up in the clouds tons of light
And he loved it
He talks about his first year at the Belle Mer like it was a religious
Experience
Very much
An everyday
Shankly feeling you you.
You know all the old days
Daily
Hostility of a city
Wasn't it cool
And silence
Aaron life
That brought you deeper into
Yourself maybe
But there were also
Pretty immediate
Problems
A Metro was supposed to connect the bilmar with Amsterdam
The construction was delayed
For a while there was only one road out
The area and it was dirty
The designers have also plan for shops
To come to the belmermere
Those didn't come right away either
There was no where to buy groceries
If you didn't have a car or didn't want to ride your bike 30 minutes
The Amsterdam
That came a kind of driving van
Every Friday or
Maybe twice in the week
To sell
A bottle of milk
Very very primitive
Eventually the roads did come
And true to the modernist idea of separation of functions
They were elevated above the ground
Sort of weaving in and out of the
High-rises
I remembered you could drive
With your car
And then have this specs
That she loves you
Of the Ballmer is seeing all those high rises around you
And then driving 70 80 km
Is an hour
Judas cityscape
Wow
It was amazing
That's decimal again who you heard at the beginning and he says yeah it was amazing
But it was all so disorienting
Is always problematic to find a way
Where am I
Which
What's that building is this
Where am I going you could not find Center
You couldn't find the center because there was no City Center
No Town Square
Just identical concrete buildings one after another after another
Visitors were constantly getting lost
And they can just pull over and ask for directions
No one would walk
On that level
So you would never encounter someone
That was no way to ask
How can I
Today Show this address
And on the ground level the promised greenspace didn't come right away either
Green takes
Time to grow underground says in the beginning the landscape was like a desert
Blow in the desert
You would also not anchored
Uncle to someone
Because
Hoot book
Through the desert
But I liked it
My wife liked it
Because
Did she wants with me
Andre Burrell Young
And that is a state of pioneering.
Many people
Like
What we are saying to the designing team because you live there I would
Hell
My superiors
These planets like nothing
It isn't working
And he would say
This is
You have to wait
This is because it
Snap Fitness
Jet
And soda Brown waited
Other residents were not as
I remember
This kind of
Old elderly couple
Okay now we going to this paradise that has been promised to us
Anywhere
After 1 year
Completely
Disillusioned
The waiting list disappeared really fast
Desperate people that starts with the Shelf
By the early 1970s the Belle Mer was being built much of the world was already turning against the massive
Concrete apartment towers that modernist had pushed for in the thirties and forties
Nobody builds
These kind of structures
Set a timer anymore
It America in St Louis stay with you were tearing them down
Today is demolition day at pruitt-igoe door Wrecking Company looks blowed the supporting columns from and
11 story vacant high-rise
Who died Co in St Louis had also been an experiment in the modernist principles of cm
It was different than the Belle Mer in that it was never meant to
To function as a city unto itself
But it was similar to
Made up of 33 high-rise Towers surrounded by lots of Green Space
The architect had envisioned rivers of trees running between the buildings
Lego was completed in 1954 and just 15 years later it was so overrun with big
Vacancies in drugs and violence
But the city chose to
To tear it down
The current Secretary of Housing
Has the side of the road I go west inspect a disastrous mistake
That's the city planner Oscar Newman again
Quisiera is that it was all the common spaces
The pruitt-igoe that led to its downfall
Rivers of trees the architect had envisioned
Garbage
Father and rivers of trees inside of the building the interior spaces were vandalized heating equipment torn apart
Harvest Road everywhere light smash
Windows broken
Newman believe that if there was a lot of space in or around a building
The residents couldn't literally see from their own windows and watch over
But that space was vulnerable
What's a crime
The net result of all this
Quality design
Bison facts
Production
David environment of fear
In 1972 Oscar Newman visited the belmermere
And he gave it essentially the
The same diagnosis
They can seize an empty comment space
This would become breeding grounds
For crime
Even members of
VMware turning against
The Belle Mer
The famous Dutch architect and CMM baraldo Van Dyke went on national TV in the Netherlands and cried live
Literal tears over what an awful concrete monstrosity the bilmar was
Yeah yeah I cried
Yeah
More buildings went up
Massive concrete structures around 400 apartments in each
First there were a couple of buildings
Then there were four
Then five
That was no
Brake no stop
Eat
9 building
You should have said stop
Building more
Units because they'll be
Standing empty
No one said that
Not even me
15 buildings
I'm going to start counting in fives
Because they're
Too many
20 building
5:30
Dish contractor's Pat contract
Years and years of
Continuous building
And they just did
And that was
Like
Oil on the Fire
31 buildings in all
13000 departments arranged in hexagonal block
Soda from above
The belmermeer looks like a massive
Concrete
Syfy
Honing rod
Honing
Grat
Pornographic
In addition to all the buildings there are also 13,000 storage spaces on the ground level
31 parking garage has hundreds of elevators and staircases and common spaces
And 110 km
Or 68 miles of indoor ground-level corridors
There was so much space
And not enough people to fill it up
OverWatch over it
But there were still people who needed housing in the Netherlands
In fact there were thousands of newly-arrived citizens
We traveled
Cross the Atlantic Ocean
I'm a tropical land in South America
And they needed a place to live
The story of the belmermeer took so many twists and turns that we have to continue it next
Why the preview of that episode
Right after this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Next week on the show with the story of the belmermeer continues
So here's a bunch of
White guys
Decide to build this area
India people is the city of the future
Where
Spandex jackets
This was the idea when the idea of the belmermeer fails to live up to the reality
Thousands of apartments in MD
And new people take them over
He said we need houses
Let's go get the house
But the bilmar mirrors newcomers aren't welcomed with open arms by all the old residents
Besides it was
It was like
Inferno
Really
The lift didn't work
They threw that refuse over
Over the balcony either side of those blocks at Advance
Like a ghetto
And we make something
And a tragic accident
Strikes the belmermeer
Didn't let anybody go inside a gate
So you lost everything you lost everything
You lost everything
The only thing we get this our life
99percentinvisible was produced this week by our senior producer Katie mingle and Chris Byam
Special thanks to Frank wassenberg
Jean-Louis Cohen
Bodak Yellow
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real Delaney Hall is the senior editor
Kolstad is the digital director
Russell staff includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald turn Meza and me Roman Mars
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
Radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX
A collective of the best most Innovative shows in all about
We supported by a coin carrying in
Sticker plastered lizards just like you
Irvine 99percentinvisible enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can get me at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But if you want to explore more of the corbusier's modernist vision for houses and cities
We have links to three articles coming out this week and they're all really really good it's on our website
99 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com