99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
What you're about to hear is the second part of a two-part series
Part one was last
So if you haven't listened to that yet
Go do that now before you hear this one
Purple rest of you
Here's a recap
It was a beautiful image
Underwear
A new alternative for living in cities
But the people who give him love you give him space down below free the ground
After World War II
Modernist Architects offer people a new vision for urban planning
The so-called city of the future
Or people would live in high-rise apartment buildings and cars with drive on elevated road so that the ground could be
The open for recreation
Housing shopping and traffic
Would all be separated out into distinct zones
It would mean the end of congestion
It should be kind of smooth
Lies machine where you're very comfortable
These new modernist ideas for Urban Design were used to some degree in developments all over the world
But in Amsterdam
They took this modernist idea really
Far
HD apoptosis of modernist thinking it was the best
Two bills
The city of the future
But in the late sixties and early seventies as the first residents moved in
The belmermeer was not living up to its promises
The waiting list disappeared really fast the desperate people
You should have said stop building more
Units because they'll be
Standing empty
When it was completed in the mid-seventies
The belmermeer or the Belle Mer as locals, for short
Was a massive expanse of 31 concrete Towers arranged in a honeycomb pattern
13000 apartment
And many of them were unoccupied
Just sitting there
Totally empty
Senior producer Katie Mingle
We'll take this way from here
There are so many planes that fly over the belmermere
It's a route to the airport airport schiphol airport
Producer Chris buy a Mojito reported this story with me I'm only asking questions
Speaking in Dutch and waiting for planes to pass
Is he toxic
Ball out of the Belle Mer
If Chris was standing outside the Belle Mer in the 1970s
YouTube heard the same thing
A lot of planes
Many of them would have been coming from across the Atlantic
Termination on the northern coast of South America
Call Suriname
It was like a sport
That's Kelly Costner he lived in Amsterdam in the 1970s but he's originally from Suriname
I'm a Dutchman
But in my heart and in my soul I am super animes
Beautiful country with very special
People
Define metastasis tropic
That tropical climate is part of what attracted the Dutch to Suriname back in the sea
1600s
The Netherlands colonized
Is part of South America
As well as a handful of islands in the Caribbean
And for a couple hundred years in these places the Dutch used slave labor from Africa
To grow tropical crop
Like sugarcane
Slavery was abolished in the Dutch colonies in the 1860s and many years later in the 1950s
These Caribbean colonies including Suriname were incorporated into the kingdom of the Netherlands
All the people were given Dutch citizenship
And allowed to live in whatever part of
The kingdom they wanted
I'm so Gillie Costner and his family chose
To move across the Atlantic
I left when I was
6 years old
This was 1960
So Gilly was already living in Amsterdam
When in the 1970s suddenly a lot more people from Suriname started moving to the Netherlands
5000 people
Sometimes maybe I exaggerate a little bit
Unlock
3000 at least
Every month
A movement has started with in Suriname for independence from their former Colonial rulers
And people got
Scared that the upheaval would be bloody
And the people lose their ability to live in the Netherlands
They talk while we have to go now if you if you wait too long week we have to stay in Suriname
That's Dan Decker who wrote a book about the belmermeer you met him in the last
So it was The Exodus
Surinam eventually did become independent in 1975 and around this time it's estimated that
More than a quarter of the country
We're about a hundred thousand people
Move to the Netherlands
Before the government was ready to show cause
Housing problems in the Netherlands and
Dade
Didn't know where to place all those people
Of course there was one place with housing available in the 1970s
A brand new development
Thousands of Empty Apartment
The belmermere
Kelly Koster was already living in the belmermeer when the major migration from Suriname started in the night
1870s
And he says that the apartments were nice enough
Large modern
But the outside was not
Pretty
Big and ugly
It was like
They created a monster of Frankenstein
At that time there were several Housing Association
It managed the different buildings at the Belle Mer and even though they were having trouble filling up the apartment
With white middle-class Dutch people
Some of these associations
Quotas on the number of surinamese they take
Lieutenant
The housing
Corporation the Ballmer which set
Are we only want 10% of Syria time using our Flats
Gazelle
It would be K mighetto here
How is that legal
Panther Lake anti-discrimination laws or something
Are we talkin about the seventies
Different butts
The West wasn't any regulation in that way and that was racist and without a doubt
But there were already a few surinamese people living in the Belle Mer
Including Gilly and a guy named used
Madre
My Drake is no longer living but Gilly remembers him well
Math today
Dish guide
Statue of Liberty
Dewey says that magic saw all these people coming in from Suriname being squeezed into tiny flat
Downtown Amsterdam and he's supposed to live
He also saw that a building
Close to his house was
Almost empty or at least
30% or 40%
So magic organized the group to squat apartments in one of the building
Kelly was part of it
I was in the pussy to squat the houses
Break open the kitchen window
Sneak
Can you put a chair in it and from that moment
Process to get you out of the house
Ultimately a lot of the squatters were given legitimate leases
An overtime more and more surinamese Dutch
Move to the Belle Mer
Not just a squatter
What is regular tennis
I have never seen an idiot In Harm's Way so many black people were living in Coppell square kilometers
To be young
What's a really great
It's am really grateful for that. Because
You know we
Play all music
Loud
Because other synonyms people were used to
Heading music
Julie talks about his particular building at
Ballmer really fun Lee
Cuz there were a lot of artists and musicians there
The guy he knew used
Projecting movies from his balcony to the wall across
The courtyard
And people could sit in the summer on their balconies and watch Laurel and Hardy
The wildest Artemis were finding homes in the Belle Mer there were still some white.
People who live there
And they weren't all thrilled about the newcomers
They were that happy day
A lot of people from shooting Nam
Arrived there with their own style of listening
Making more noise
Oh my God that was like
Invasions
Of immigrants
From the West Indies from
Suriname
.
Invade it
The Belmont Manor
Because
That wear lots of
Empty Apartments
That's Peter Brown that architect you met in part one of the story who helped design the belmermeer and was
Living there in the 1970s
It's stigmatized the area overnight
An immigrant
Area
But the thing is the surname he's weren't technically immigrants
They were Dutch citizens would grown up speaking Dutch and learning the history of the Netherlands in school
Decapoda all the cities ever figure knew everything about the Meadowlands
And it's all said they would be welcome in the Netherlands
But when they arrived here
They didn't
Cell death welcome and Dede Alsace also saw that
What did the people in the Netherlands
Didn't know anything about tsunami
In any case when the surinamese started moving into the Belle Mer
Peter Brown saw them as
Well here I'll let him say
These poor people
We're coming out of the Jungle Day by not used to live in high-rise
Sophisticated
Flat buildings with central heating on
Miss refuse Chutes and they couldn't
They couldn't
Understand the sophistication of living in such a
Machinery of a building they threw that refuse over
Over the balcony
Advance
Like a ghetto
What about Mimi was never
But again
People called it the ghetto
Yes the rib problems adapting to the system
Yes we have to find out
You can go with 12 people in an elevator
Yes we've had to find out that you're out of the balcony
A serious and in phloem.
People living in some apartments 20
People
So what to do apartment 20 people
Julie doesn't really dispute that the surname he's Dutch had a different way of living than the white
But he points out and I think rightly that the belmermeer was failing before the surname he's showed
So here's a bunch of
White guys
And working with physically separated
Spandex jackets
This was the idea
The idea fell apart Gilly says when no one who could afford to live in the Ballmer actually wanted to live in the
I must be out of my mind
White Dutch people didn't want to live in the Ballmer and so it increasingly attracted the people who couldn't afford
Ford housing anywhere else
Or who are being Des
Discriminated
Elsewhere
Overtime thousands of Gabe's
People move there
An immigrant
Places like turkey Morocco and Ghana
Who came to the Netherlands for work
But the fact that the bomber had become undesirable
The people with the means to live elsewhere was really disappointing
Are the people who designed it
Who thought they were creating a better kind of City a utopian Paradise
People with lineup
To live in
In the late 1970s some of them are still working on
The project including the lead architect
Siegfried nothung
Here's dandekar again who wrote a biography of Ness
What's a big disappointment from a really big
Didn't want to give interviews about it's even with his best friends he didn't talk about the Belle Mer
And then one day in 1979 NASA just
Quit
Not just working on the Belle Mer
But quit being a narc
You walked out of the office
I didn't even say goodbye to everybody and never came back
The Visionary behind the belmermeer had given up on it
But there were still a lot of people living there
And their story was far from over
1980 the Metro train connecting the Palmer to the rest of Amsterdam finally came
Five years later than planned and a shopping Center opened up nearby
But still the Belmont didn't fill up
At the highest point vacancy in the 1980s
3200 Apartments were sitting empty
Or about 25 per
Percent of all units
Because of vacancies in a vulnerable population that couldn't always make rent
The Housing Association that controlled the buildings was broke and couldn't do routine maintenance
The place was
Falling apart
There was heroin
Real decline of the Belmonts start of the whizzer heroin that came to Amsterdam
In the 1980s
Heroin use was at a peak in it
Amsterdam and when the government decided it had enough of the heroin dealers and users in the city center
I push them out
And they found
Perfect place to go
20 minutes away
The belmermere
It was full of vacant apartments
Neglected common spaces and various other good places
Hide
Maybe fish
You can say your name
Sadis bio
That's because you're a survivor.
Talking with Chris out of the Belle Mer to hear a live there as a kid and she says there were a lot of heroin users who hung out on the
The top floors of her building where there were more vacancies
She was constantly afraid that the elevator would accidentally take her up there
And I stepped in the elevator I was always
Praying like
Please don't go up
One day when Tahira was around 11 she was playing outside with her little three-year-old brother when she noticed that he was
Carrying around something strange that he
Picked up off the ground
A heroin needle
I mean I was small I didn't know it was
A drug needle
I went to a mother and I showed her
And she was like
Okay
This is the limit we're moving
The hero's family did eventually leave the Belle Mer
Lots of other families did the same thing
The turnover rate was high 40 to 50% in some buildings
Other numbers weren't great either in 1987 the burglary rate in the Belmont
Two and a half times that of Amsterdam and almost ten times the rest of the Netherlands
And over half of the bombers residence
That's where they can move crime in 1988
The belmermeer have been talked about during it
Conception as a city of the future
But by the 1990s it would come to be known as the quote drain of Dutch
Society
Over the years various small measures have been attempted to help the Belle Mer
Maintenance security cameras subsidizing runs
But nothing seemed to work
Finally the government decided they had to do something dress
Maybe it was time to demolish some of the building
But before they could start
Something horrible happened
On October 4th 1992
Left Amsterdam schiphol airport Bound for Israel and almost immediately lost two of its
They needed to return to the airport for an emergency landing
But
They never made it back
It's hard to make out but about 15 minutes into their flight
Pilot can be heard saying going down 1862 going down
From an altitude of about 4000 ft
Flight 186 to nose dive straight into an apartment building at the belmermere
So can you tell me something about the 4th
October 1990
Tobias 1992
Soviet together with friends
At home
When we fell in love
Loud names
That's Susie ampofo an immigrant from Ghana was in the building when the plane hit
She and her friends
Escaped but she never saw her apartment
So you lost
Nathaniel has everything
I lost everything
You lost everything
The only thing we get this our life
Many people didn't get their lives
It was a Sunday night at the Belle Mer and so a lot of people are home having dinner or smoking cigarettes on their balcony
It was an
Phil is
The deadliest plane crash in the country's history
The official record says that 43 people died including the three crew members on the plane
But the number may actually be much higher
A lot of undocumented
People were living in the building and it was hard for the government to get an accurate count
I'm so nobody knows exactly how how many people
I'm dead
So what did change
After
That's Chris talking with you
Urban sociologist who worked on the renewal of the belmermere
After the plane crash the city waited a couple of years to make any major changes to the Belle Mer
People were traumatized and needed time to recover
But eventually a massive renewal began which included tearing down many of the original high rise
Apartment building
It was decided
To tear down 1/4
And so they started taking down building
But not all at once
Buildings came down over about 15 years
One after another after another so that people could be relocated
And the buildings weren't dynamited like the infamous housing project pruitt-igoe in St Louis
They were taking apart Story by story to avoid the imagery and metaphor of a neighborhood being blown up and for sale
Bacon
Because they weren't just going to tear down the belmermere
They were going to redesign it
Make it better
And that's what they did
Are we going to see a street with
Small houses for
Here on the water side with
5 story high building
Eventually a lot of the high-rises were replaced with smaller building
Between 1 and 5 stories
Shops were relocated to be closer to the housing and the 31 parking garages were mostly torn
Down because no one was using them
For much besides drug dealing
Even though the original designers were sure the car would be the primary mode of
Transportation
For people of the
The future
City of the future
We all come in by our without cars
Instead of parking garages the redesign made
Places for bikes because
Let's be real the Dutch are ultimately way more into bikes
Bicycle song
Very important
Inn in Amsterdam
And you want to put your bicycle in a safe place inside
Some people do Drive
Cars of course but they tore down the elevated Road
Now people drive at ground level
The funny thing is we're now standing at
That's one of the original Flats
A car is moving
Impossible no cars in this kind of areas was strictly forbidden
We are looking for mixing finches instead of
Taking them apart
Mixing functions or mixed-use development is happening all over the world
We seem to have come a hundred and eighty degrees away from the modernist idea of separating
Now Urban Design is focused on creating neighborhoods
That have shopping and Recreation and housing all mixed in together
No car needed
And we realized something else
About cities
It's not a machine he's not a machine
That's city planners desk
Hey Ma you heard him in part one of the story and he says yeah people want their Apartments to be quiet
They want their cities to be safe
But they don't want the city to be a well-organized
Machine crowded cities congested cities
Mixed-use
A lot of improvisation
And a lot of stupid things
People love it
Yes people seem to love that they love the chaos
Fastidious
Yeah of course because
Life is chaos
You want a piece
Otherwise life is boring
Also
People realized they didn't want to live in humid concrete structures
Almost immediately after the belmermeer was finished
Another neighborhood in Amsterdam was also redesigned and rebuilt from the ground up
But not with concrete
But bricks
It's
What they want
And I remember it was very expensive
Building and bricks update water breaks
Give the people brick
Yeah give them breaks
Nice
And it's feels warm
But this this modernist
Kohl's kitchen architects
Aesthetics
It's not what people really
In this way the belmermeer and maybe a lot of modernism
Was architecture for Arctic
That was probably always part of the problem
Yeah Yeahs Aragon
Is very active
Impersonality
Didn't you better
Andy Woods
Take care of
And build them homes
And they would show them how to live
The redesign of the belmermeer area did not make this mistake
The community was heavily involved at various levels
And the physical environment was not the only thing that got attention
Programs were set up for job training and education and special housing was opened for
A heroin addict
Now the belmermeer is a nicer place to live
It's not perfect but
It's much better
My house welcome
Even to hear I moved back
His family left after her three-year-old brother was found playing with
The heroin needle
Living room
Open kitchen
This used to be close
Tahira actually lives in one of the original high-rise
Apartment buildings
The outside of her building was repaired and on the inside all of the apartments were gutted and sold completely
Empty and Bare Bones
For the buyer to remodel however they wanted
In Holland we say Bluetooth straight and Tran
Black sweater
Is in this apartment
Making it financially possible for
For people to become homeowners instead of renter's has also been up
Priority of the redesign
There's a growing black middle-class there now
The bummer is still one of the most
Inverse areas in the Netherlands
Over a hundred different nationalities are represented there
Including still a lot of surinamese.
We created the Belmont
It is
Today we created it
We were never the problem
And we made something from it
Julius Wright
The surinamese Dutch really are the people who stuck with
The Belle Mer all alone
After the white people left
And the lead architect asserted it
And the public declared it the drain of Dutch Society
The surinamese and later immigrants
From all over the world
Raised families
Open businesses
Immediate future
Ferocity that didn't have one
Coming up Kurt and I talked about one of the design strategies for making the Belle Mer a better place for everyone
Right after that
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Is Katie discuss the Dutch are tackling the redesign of the belmermeer in different ways
Import they're trying to figure out
How to go from
A one-size-fits-all approach to something more individualized
Sort of this ongoing Urban experiment and talk about that remodel the belmer building that terrorists
The Bayou
Featured in the piece
Recently moved back into
Right so that building that to be removed into there's actually talk of demolishing it
But a few years back Consortium of Architects and developers pitched a plan to revitalize it
But instead
They got approval and they went to work on the exterior and
Common areas
Started sandblasting The Conch
Facade and renovating the halls and elevators
And they also move the storage up from the ground level to make that first floor livable
But the actual private Living Spaces were gutted
And left unfinished
People moving in had to start from
And when you say unfinished him what are we talkin
No shower
No kitchen
Nowruz at all basically
Total blank slate
And lead of the project
Cool spot
Hughson being touched
That sounds like a rough
Situation to move into a special you're not a do-it-yourself inclined at what is the appeal of An Unfinished
It's partly about flexibility
And sustainability like there's less waste when people you know
Don't move
What a big driver is affordability
Developers often add premium materials and fixtures to justify higher prices and Baton turn prices
To some buyers out houses
People can make their own decisions
About how and when to finish their homes
Presidents who want something more luxurious can have that
But others can pick more Spartan Ops
Or just you know add incrementally as they have the budget to do it starting with the basics and working the right from there
So causes mange
How much more affordable are these
From what I read
Those bilmar units were put on the market
Around 1200 Euros per square meter which is
Cheap for the Netherlands
And really cheap compared to Amsterdam where places can cause
Multiple times.
In this kind of DIY housing
This is something that is actually a larger trend
Absolutely there's a British nonprofit for example called naked house
Which is also working on strip down home
They clean their houses will actually go for 30 to 40% less than other homes of similar sizes on the market
So yeah that's a pretty huge potential saving
And part of their design strategy is to build in some double Heights
The idea being that people can build them out over
Time
And traditional floor space
When they need room decor
So you move in and
Your bottom floor is
Yeah
Yeah you get this kind of mezzanine level so you got this nice I want space but if you really need that floor space you can add the floor joists easily and it
Turn all outfit it's that easy
Reminds me of the story we did into a
Half a house
That we did about a year ago
Yeah exactly element all
As used
A similar approach in Chile
Basically they frame and roof
The house on both sides
But they only enclose one side with exterior wall
The open half can then be built into overtime and even those faces that are initially enclosed
Are there bones
They're missing
Basically everything except for the kitchen sink on painted drywall
Unfinished floors no appliances
I think there's a real intellectual
Appeal to this kind of approach
But it's definitely raised some questions and empiricism
It has in some of those are very legitimate
One of the most common is that
To make the place livable in the first place
DIY home buyer will have
Refuse them their upfront savings
To purchase materials database
Ml generally be paying retail rate
Because they can't tap into the same economies ask
Fat Developers
Pause some people of course
Don't have the skills or the time to work on their own
But you don't for people with more time than money or would you experience building things these kinds of DIY
Why options can really make housing more accessible
They give people choices to
Build things out that they want
In their own time at their own
In this exact
Opposite approach
Set the modernist
Originally doing what
With the Belle Mer making everything the same in attempt to be
Their version of egalitarian
Yeah I mean
Turns out one size
Fits all approach
Doesn't actually fit everyone equally
Rap-up
Tie into this
Two part episode of the Belmar can you describe what you tok
Yeah so basically this set of Articles traces the career of Le corbusier that famous European architect
To co-founded the international Congress of Modern Art
And the first piece explores his early houses designed to be quote machines for living in
II that covers his utopian radiant city which is all about this sort of separation of Funk
And idea
And the last one tok
About
So this mixed-use
Units of habitation
Vertical micro cities that
Actually got built around Europe and For Better Or
Possibly worse
Le corbusier helped lay the conceptual groundwork for the bilmar
Understanding each other build projects
Can kind of show you how modernism
Simply. Indifferent
So if you enjoyed your trip to the Belle Mer and ones I've even deeper into modernism functionalism and Le corbusier
Be sure to check out the articles on 99 PA
. org
99percentinvisible with Bruce's week bar senior producer Katie mingle and Chris by Emma
Special thanks to Jean Louis Cohen
DotA
Anne Frank wassenberg Tuesday research on large housing Estates was invaluable
To this series
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Sean real Delaney Hall is the senior editor
Kirk Olmstead is the digital director
Russet that includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Aaron Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Produced on radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
Divine 99percentinvisible enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can't wait to meet at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
I ordered my Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Wheely 1 education on modernist
Electrical said be your guide with his articles on corbeau
They're on our website
99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com