99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the late 1920s the Ford motor company bought up millions of acres of land in Brazil
They loaded boats with machinery and supplies and ship them deep into the Amazon rainforest
Workers cut down trees and clear the land and then they built a rubber Plantation in the middle of one of the Wild
Places on Earth
Orange rubber development on the river is an Enterprise of historic proportions
Acres of jungle are being converted into a highly modernized Plantation
Capable of producing rubber on a large scale
The plan was to harvest the Rubber and ship it back to Detroit
It would be turned into tires and other parts
Scoreboard cars
The Henry Ford
One of this community what she called
Fordlandia
To be more than just a huge Plantation
He wanted it to be a kind of industrial Utopia
He paid his Brazilian workers good wages
At least for the region
We tried to build them the kind of place
He would have loved to laugh
Which is to say
A small Midwestern town
But in the middle of the jungle
Deep in the wilderness this model community of self-sufficient
Has its own Powerhouse electric lighting
Telephone system
Phone machine shop completely equipped with modern tools
Laboratory for processing Rubber and ice plant in the fire depart
Go to church you had Hospital leave at a power plant
You have a big Sawmill that's Rodger Webber
Who's the host of a podcast called mismatch
And the story is meditation of one that recently aired on his show
And so he wanted to
Who creates
This
Village
For the workers down in fordlandia
And well it's easy to look at him as some greedy imperialist
Capitalist very easy
He actually felt that he could help
These people
Provides free medical aid for the employees
Later than outdoor luncheon is served
Followed by tempting Delicacies
Then comes the afternoon round of golf
Play it on the plantation links against a beautiful jungle backdrop
Today the Ford plantation is a successful Enterprise
A tribute to skill in science
The new weapons of the 20th century pioneer
But the reality is that fordlandia was not a successful Enterprise
Nor was it really a tribute to skill and science
It was a colossal
Expensive and tragic mistake
It took Henry Ford nearly two decades
To give up on
It's a parable of arrogance but the arrogance isn't that Ford thought he couldn't aim and conquer the Amazon
Greg Grandin
He had his sights on something actually much bigger he thought he could tame and Conquer capitalist
Industrial capitalism
Ford wanted to export his brand of industrial paternalism to the Amazon
Hey workers well
And provide services
So that they stayed healthy productive and most importantly
Loyal to the company
And and that didn't have
In the early 1900s
It's a couple of decades before Ford set out to build fordlandia
A massive shift was underway in the rubber industry
4 years Brazil have been the world's main supplier
Rubber pretty much all of the Rebel with the one at some bicycles at 1
The condoms that
Gaskets
The valves
Winter tires
All came from Brazil
And the way rubber was cultivated was very labour-intensive
Rubber tappers would go out into the dense jungle
And find rubber trees
They would slash the trees and then they would extract the latex
The floor on the side of the trees
They would boil
Innocence this Milky
Fluid and turn it into
A large balls of rubber
Which they would then
You try to sell
Passing it on this kind of very decentralised chained up until it wound up in warehouses
Manchester
Warren Detroit
Rubber stoppers would work part of the Year tapping Rubber and they were part of the year
Growing
Other sustenance crops in order to survive
This is the economy
Lasted four years in in Brazil
But this economy could be brutal for workers at the bottom of the production chain
As rubber plantations grew they struggled to find enough workers
Some robber barons started enslaving indigenous people in forcing them to tap trees
Even the workers that were being paid didn't make very much
The so-called latex Laura.
Set the top ruin normally wealthy
Living in palatial homes in gilded cities in the jungle
This system all started to change because of a British Explorer named Henry Wickham
He come to Brazil to seek his fortune in the Amazon
And then in 1876
Henry Wickham
Managed to steal
Thousands of rubber plant
And he sent them back to England and eventually they want to the English colonies
It was technically no law at the time preventing the X
Sport of the seeds
Wickham had applied for an export license under false
Pretenses
He smuggled be tens of thousands of
The seeds back to England in the hold of a steamship
Each seed was about three quarters of an inch long
Is entire seed cash
Weight over 1000 lbs
He may not have known it at the time
But his act of Bio piracy
Would totally transform the rubber tray
From England Wickham's rubber seeds travel to various European colonies like Malaysia Sri Lanka and Indonesia
The trees thrive
Tropical environments where no blight or bugs had evolved to eat them Growers set up plan
Plantations with rubber trees planted in dense rows and these new Colonial plantations ended up
Possibly outperforming the traditional Brazilian rubber Tapper
Say run 1910 Brazil head by that we're pretty much lost its control over the
Rubber industry
Meanwhile the new European robber barons were talking about setting up a kind of cartel
Danelle dominated the global rubber trade
And they realize that meant they could set it prices
Which made a certain American industrialists control freak
Extremely nervous
Henry Ford was used to controlling
Everything
Will the Ford Motor Company in the in the 1920s pretty much
Controlled
Nearly every
Raw material
That went into the making of a motor car
Glass supply in the wood Lumber
Everything separate
This looming European control rubber cartel represented a big threat
A rubber prices went up
It could make the tires and gaskets and Tube is more expensive
2 Ford wanted to create his own rubber Supply
What is problem is that rubber doesn't grow in the US
So Not only was Henry Ford vulnerable bit but Brazil was vulnerable
That's why the nation of Brazil basically gave him this huge
Tract of land about the size of Connecticut to try to start his
Rubber plant
Brazil was placing a big bet
The betting on Henry Ford wasn't the worst idea
You look at a guy like Henry Ford and all he had achieved
With the Model T
The $5 day wage
They're looking at a real opportunity
And who better than Henry Ford to come down there and then
Restore the former glory
Of
How controlling the rubber Market
It was a boondoggle from from the very beginning
Ford Company shipped in supplies on the top of ghost River
They brought in American managers and hired a Brazilian Workforce
Then they started clearing the land to build
Portlandia
The jungle courses is just a very challenging
Place
And right away
Things started to go wrong you have four
Example the workers were trying to clear the land
Baby working out their bare chested
And would be suddenly covered with biting ants
Hornets and scorpions in even worse they would reach in and suddenly a pit viper
Pepperwood bites
The Man Killer's
So they were they were dealing with a life-and-death struggle year
Eventually the workers managed to clear the land and build a town in the middle of the rainforest
Bored at a very particular vision for this town
He wanted it to feel like these small Midwestern Town T associated with his childhood
He grew up on a farm
He believed that there was a
A kind of healthy connection between
Between Agriculture and Industry
Is this crazy as that seems he he saw them kind of intermingling
And
He really brought these Boyhood memories of the farm into his adult life
Justice nostalgic
Yearning
For a bygone era
This Nostalgia was for a very narrow slice of America
Small town mostly white in there
That was Ford's model for fordlandia
Even though he was importing it into a very different cultural environment
When you go to fordlandia there's an uncanniness to
Familiarity
It doesn't seem exotic
Isabel
Company event setup plantation-style rubber feel
Lots of trees densely planted
The style of the colonial rubber tree plantations in Southeast Asia
They started recruiting even more Brazilian workers from the surrounding areas
A lot of them were excited to work for 4
Ford was promising something they'd never really had
Free healthcare
Free education
He wasn't a guy just running roughshod over that area he felt he could improve
The wives of these
Workers
And this wasn't just for being benevolent
This was bored being straight
T check
Back in the US he discovered a few paid his workers well and let them work reasonable hours
If you didn't
Totally exploit them in other words
He could dramatically reduce turnover
And that's what he wanted to do in Brazil
In a sense they're trying to apply lessons from the factory
To a plantation
That's exactly what they're trying to do that's Matt Anderson
The Henry Ford museum being interviewed by Rodger
Try to run a plantation in South
America
As though it were
Industrial facility here in the Midwest
I'm bringing the time clock had to workers work 8-hour shifts
Clock on clock off Fiserv
Cafeteria style
Set for the world so forbidding
What he was trying to
Part of the problem for cultural
Neil people down there were used to living a different way they were not used to the 8 hours a day
The factory clock ship that were used
Usher and Yuna
United States
And part of that we would very good reason
The climate there is very different there just 250 miles or so from the equator
Temperatures routinely get well over a hundred degrees
He's during the heat of the day they were used to going into work
In the early morning hours
Before the Qibla kicked up taking a break for several hours in the middle of the day
Me coming back at the end of the day today
Started to become clear back in the state for that created an industrial system will workers connect before
Where to buy the products they made but in the Amazon there wasn't really that much to buy
Society within the Amazon so they didn't actually need
The high wages that Ford was promising they would work a few weeks or a few months and then they would disappear and they would go
Go back into into into into the jungle to to to work that plots to 2
Produce their own food and maybe they come back the following year
And this would this would drive the Ford managers mad
Solve the problem of turnover in Detroit
And the problem of turnover in the in the middle of the Amazon at the top of his River just
Proved insurmountable
The cultural disconnect also went beyond just work.
Henry Ford and very particular ideas about how Society should be arranged
And what people should enjoy
For example
He loved square dancing
He met his wife Clara at a square dance
And so he figured well
We got this big hole down there and in fordland and so let's play some square dancing
Music
A dress pattern
Surprised you know it wasn't all that popular down there who would have thought
Ford was also a teetotaler
So even though drinking was legal in Brazil
Gibbeted alcohol in Portlandia
Again you have Henry Ford trying to
Impose his will thinking will it works for us in America
Although a lot of Americans of the time didn't think the prohibition work
But he was
By golly he was going to make it work in Brazil
Ed couples balance board
It turns out he wasn't going to make it work in Brazil
Some Savvy entrepreneurs set up a bar and brothel on a little island near fordland
They called it
The island of Innocence
Fred Couples ladies Jane
And they were technically outside a Ford sovereignty of Fords
Control when they couldn't do anything to stop it
And then there was the food
Henry Ford was a vegetarian
Can an early advocate of healthy eating
And so he wanted them to eat
Whole wheat products and he just felt that this was going to be better for their health
This actually LED
To a riot
What happened in 1930
Workers resented having to eat the exact kind of food that Henry Ford told them to
But the other problem was that
It initially serve lunch the workers restaurant-style
With Waiters
Open somebody got the idea
What should we have the assembly line
In the
The United States so
What's helped them eat cafeteria style
What's more efficient weekend
Keep track of things well
The workers
Absolutely hated that approach
They felt like they were
Being treated like cogs in a
In a wheel and suddenly went on a rampage
And the town was was
Practically destroy that one of the first targets where the time
Which they smashed to pieces
Yes the managers actively write the manager said to flee on boats and
And intelligent
Because of because of the fury of
What is uprising
End and it was the time was eventually retaken with the help of
Brazilian security
And and then rather than give up Ford recommitted
Port even more money into enter trying to realize
This Midwestern ideal
At this point forward was only a few years into this Portlandia experiment
And it wasn't paying off
The company dust cap
Money it's the Rubber Plantation
Brandon said there always seemed to be a way to justify the project
In the 1920s it was going to be a symbol of what industrial capitalism
Bring
Took of the Backwater of the Amazon
In the 90
Dirty's during the Depression to be
Becomes a symbol of how to survive the downturn
Amazon
Who was going to say no
Henry Ford
No one really had the gumption the determination that this
Bravery perhaps the challenge for dummies big decision
Because
Yeah he was a tough fellow more and more as the years went by he got set in his ways and that was it his word was
What is going to happen
But fordlandia was up against insurmountable challenges
More than the time
More than the square dance
More than the way meals were served
The real problem
Was Boggs
The insect
Fungi
That were the rubber trees natural predators in the Amazon
Ford hadn't really bother to learn anything about botany or Agronomy before embarking on his fordlandia
The experiment
He didn't trust the expert
I could have warned them
What he was getting into
In fact he didn't trust
Experts at all
Kingdom and the idea of
Exports of slowing
The progress of of an idea
And his experience they could go to the factory floor
And maybe they had a problem with a widget or a wagon and they would have trial and error
And they would just figure it out
Need some
Buddy with the title
Or an education and some specialty
Need to tell them what to do
That was part of the problem with this that I thing
Ford bought into his own kind of invincibility is own price
If you will think Unity
You could just go down there and take
This kind of rock
Jungle in
Turn it into an industrial Enterprise Al working industrial Enterprise
And I think his
His eyes were bigger than his stomach soda
Because Ambitions got ahead of his
Disabilities
Because he wasn't willing to listen to
The experts wasn't willing to bring them on board
He was in
Far far to DP over his head
The problem was that rubber trees have never grown in the Amazon in the way that the Ford company with trying to grow them
Intense plantations with trees planted in Tyro
This growing style might have worked in the Southeast Asian plantations run by European
That's because the bugs there hadn't evolved to eat rubber trees
In Brazil this density ended up creating an environment
Were Native bugs that fed on rubber trees
Thrive
What Ford was basically doing with building a giant incubator
In which
Which year did the bugs and the
Blade and the fungi that feed off of rubber
Was able to grow exponentially because the trees will close together
For example there were these caterpillar
We're very fond of rubber tree
One of the predators of a caterpillar
Spray tan
Chipotle near me
The managers would send out
Battalions of workers to
Pek the caterpillar
Play even gathered all the caterpillars together and end in in buckets and then pulled them together and then had a huge bonfire
But within a few years guess what happen
It wouldn't the caterpillars Warren actually
Eating the leaves from the bottom they will leave from the top
You couldn't actually see them and so therefore you couldn't pick them
Again and again they replanted the trees
I need to have them killed off bypass
This went on for years and then decades
It wasn't until 1945 the Ford finally decided to shut down fordlandia
That point Henry Ford had turn the company over to his grandson
In fordlandia with a
And within a few months
He sold it back to the Brazilian government
For like $250,000 and then it was over
Henry Ford died a couple years later
And after all the money and time invested
Weirdly
He never even visited for Atlanta
He orchestrated all of it
Right down to the square dances
I miss home thousands of miles away
In Michigan
You're part of it maybe he was just afraid of going and
Qingdao
Tell you there in person so dusty
I was reading the reports the memos
Knew what was happening or what wasn't having the fordlandia surprised you didn't want to
Reckon with it personally
Fordlandia is still a town today
And although a lot of the old buildings are now falling down
People continue to live there
Is Dwayne Greg Grandin has visited twice
That's two times more than Henry Ford ever did
For those of you keeping count
Brandon made the day and a half long trip up the top of those River by boat
You just turn you just come around the bank and then all of a sudden you see this enormous
Enormous saltwater tank
Back in the day
The word Ford was
Written on the wall
The tank and end
And you could see the outlines of what was fordlandia is still there it's now
Brazilians are moved in
And taking over all of the houses
But you still get a sense of what
Look like
In the 1920s in 90
In thirties
Salinas casa
Emma Frost
My house is very close
From my house we can see the water tower
It's Antojitos Sosa and she's lived in fordlandia since 2009
Jim Kimball missing
Blessings kilometer
We can see it
Water Tower
Beautiful
It's historic it's a wonderful
There aren't many jobs left in the area for the 2002 habitants of fordlandia
Most of the economy in the region now revolves around industrial soybean production and cattle ranch
There's a little bit of Tourism to
Which people like Sosa counselor
She works at a hotel in town
We receive people from all countries
They search for the history they are curious to see in person
History
What is left
There are few things yet
He comes to the Village
The big houses
Cool the symmetry
The hospital
Hospital
People come to see what's left of Fords
Crazy vision
American style town in the middle of the Brazilian jungle
Be culturally insensitive and paternalistic boondoggle
For all its faults
Still created good paying jobs
Sports workers
424 flight
Henry Ford was very audacious at the time
2 best of Fortune in Brazil
In a foreign land
I think he's very interesting
Sebaceous
Americans are bear like this
It was school he did that
As a time he created a lot of jobs for Brazilians
People from all over Brazil
Migrated to here looking for a job
So is it wasn't there to see all the ways fordlandia went wrong
Bird the history represents a time when this sleepy town was the focus
Of a massive experiment
Buy world famous industrialist
Now with its crumbling old buildings
Portlandia is a different kind of Lost Civilization than you'd expect to find in the middle of the Amazon
The Midwest
Fantasyland
Returning to the Jungle
Do you know I host introduce another show
About the Constitution Twitter and Trump and it's actually really fun it's called
What Trump can teach us about con law
And this week is the last episode of the second series of that show
And I'm going to talk about it
With my co-presenter Elizabeth Joe
But after this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another room in Brawl hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
So I host another radiotopia podcast called
What Trump can teach us about con law
An idiot I invite over my friend and neighbor Elizabeth Joe to teach me a little about constitutional law
Using tweets from Trump
As a jumping-off point
Holbrook sample
The episode coming out this week
Starts with Trump's tweet about giving guns to teachers in school
And then we use that premise
To look at the Fourth Amendment and
What it says about the use of deadly force
By the government
Usually the government employee that would
Potentially use deadly force
Is a cop
Teacher
But the world has gone crazy
Presidents have always pushed against the constitution in different ways to forward their agenda
The reason why Trump is such a good foil for these
Types of hypothetical
Discussions about the
Institution
Is because
We have this unique
Window
What he's thinking
Because
Of Twitter
We've never had would have direct access to a president
Thoughts his ID his moment
My Moment thoughts on
Every piece of news or policy which may only hold for the next
5 minutes but nevertheless we get a snapshot into what he's thinking
And that's been important because this is been a norm breaking presidency
It's almost a tired phrase now to say this is abnormal I mean
The abnormal has become normal and in some ways that's been the Genesis
And Trump has definitely changed the way that Elizabeth teaches cost
At UC Davis
When I Survey my class and asked like what would you like to talk about
The semester will try to address some of those things
Donald Trump related they all are no basically
Whatever the topic is
Can he do that
Is he allowed to do that and I think that's been what's really remarkable
So yeah it's very different to me
Student ID
The teacher of
It's very different just to be an American today to think about what what's normal in terms of
Expecting certain kind of behavior out of an American Prayer
That's totally true
We're using in Cypress
About the concert
Anyways
And that seems to be going on Beyond
Is that a silver lining that you
You see in all this
List of people are actually talking about the
Take pleasure in the
Yes but has to be the one silver lining the people actually want to learn about how the government works
And
The people are slowly discovering that despite the fact that we have a constitution and we have
So many Supreme Court decisions on a variety of topics
The real thing that was always binding us the cookies and the glue for society was norms
That the Norms actually make
Our shared experience of what government should be possible
And when those start to unravel
People are understandably nervous
So that's been a
Big learning experience for all of us
Do you have a greater sense
That we are dependent on Norms
Then you did
18 months
You're absolutely mean it's it's showing us that
You know what we need is as kind of collective faith that are institutions
Our Collective faith in what the President should and should not be doing
And when that starts to come apart I think that that raises new kinds of questions for how we got to think about all of these
Offices
Westland institutions Congress the president how log works
But we should think about chords and we've never really had this kind of
Ultimate question that you want what is this song mean
In the very very beginning
When we started
We talk.
Only 5000 words
What's the scaffolding that
Be interpreted in
The ways
You kind of wish now.
But they were
More words of the Constitution that it was a little more exact
No I don't think so because I think there's a mean one of the reasons why so far anyway our system
Has been remarkably resilient in my last day
Is because of the flexibility and the doctor
You know if
They we had spend specific
You can't use muskets
And every person should pay
You know
$1 in taxes would be a very different document and probably we would have abandoned it a long time ago
But it's the open-endedness of it which kind of shows the genius of
Original framers
The show that
They were writing a document that was supposed to last
Astro long time
The problem with that is that we end up arguing a lot about what that means
And so that's
Thrilling parts of constitutional law or had been
And now sometimes it's becoming a scary
So if you want to take the chaos of
Unhinged tweets and
Endless political news
Channel that into learning the Constitution
I welcome you to join me
The fellow student
What Trump can teach us about con law
Can Trump fire Mueller can Trump pardon
What does it mean when Trump questions the legitimacy of judges
Can he even sees the necessary land to
To construct a border
Elizabeth show Explains It All
What Trump can teach us about con law
We collect Trump con law for sure
Find it on Apple podcast
Radiopublic
Wherever you download Pocket
99percentinvisible was produced this week by our senior editor Delaney Hall mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer
Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
The rest of the staff includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman
Thanks to Roger Weber and Zagros
The host and producer of the mismatch
Legrand Media Group in WDIV Local 4 in Detroit
We adopted the fordland used
From that thanks also to
Paola muda production and translation
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a founding member of radiotopia from pra
Collective of the best
Most Innovative shows in all of vodka
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
You can find a show enjoin discussions about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit
We have all kinds of pictures of fordlandia
And they are weird and definitely worth the gander
And 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com