99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We wanted to do a story about gerrymandering for years
Once you take it as a given
We want to live in a representative democracy
The next question becomes how are we best represent it
We need to divide ourselves into groups
From what basis should the lines be drawn
Basic geography is a place to start
But there are always exceptions and nuances that make defining voting districts
Solium on Geographic boundaries problematic
I think of this as a design problem
Maybe the most important design problem of democracy
Our friends over at 5:38 recently drove deep into this topic with a six-part series that examines gerrymandering
In different states around the country
It's called
The gerrymandering project
It turns out each state that they profile is dealing with representation and gerrymandering differently
The states are really acting as the Laboratories of democracy that US Supreme Court Justice Brandeis said they were
We're going to spend the whole episode this week
Flooring that series and playing scenes from four different episodes
About gerrymandering in four different states
Our guide along the way will be the host of the gerrymandering project
And producer at 5:38
Galen druke
Thank you for being here going
Hey Robin thanks for having me
So this might seem like an obvious question but
Just laid out for us what is gerrymandering
Gerrymandering at its most basic is
Drawing district lines to achieve a specific
Golf
I think the most
Common form of gerrymandering that people are familiar with
Partisan gerrymandering which would be
Drawing lines in a way that Advantage One party over another but you could also draw lines to protect income
Cummins or you could racially gerrymandered
Dilute minorities voting power
So there's more than one kind of gerrymandering but at its core it's just manipulating lines with a goal
To implicit
In
The idea that
A gerrymandered district is manipulated
Is that there's some natural way that a district should be drawn and that doesn't seem like it's running how do you really determine
Natural state of a district is
Yes you're right
There is no redistricting plan
That is
Blessed by the grace of God you know there are not Rivers
Streams mountains and Reed Ithaca
Often times people will just refer to something as gerrymandered when they don't like
The result or if it looks
And who decides how District
Rescheduling
General Lee
For the most part state legislators
Come up with maps that have been approved
By State Governor
And
In some cases states have overhauled the process to give the power to an independent Commission
But for the most part at State gov
The party in control can achieve
An advantage over the party out of control
Is my packing and cracking their voters
Which would mean in some instances
Putting a lot of that party's voters in one dip
So is to make them waste a bunch of there
Because
Theoretically any vote over 51%
Would be a wasted vote it's not helping to elect
And then on the other hand you have
Cracking which would be
Dividing up that parties voters so that they can't reach
51%
In any one District
Forcing them to waste votes in another
So in the 538 Series game looked at four different states that are either currently dealing with or have recently
With the question of gerrymandering
Tape and talk a little bit about each of those States
We'll start with Wisconsin
So just a little background Wisconsin Republicans one unified control of the state government
This was a particularly big deal because it happened to be a redistricting here
It was the first time in decades that a single party and had total control of the state government as the state read
Andrew is political maps
Republicans took advantage
They drew maps that Democrats allege
Are very favorable to Republican candidates
This obviously didn't sit well with the Democrats and they filed suit
For a long time anti-gerrymandering activists have been trying to find cases that they could bring before the spring
Court to try to get a ruling that this kind of political manipulation
Is unconstitutional
Violates either the First Amendment or the 14th Amendment
And one civil rights lawyer in particular a man named Peter oral
Started digging into the Wisconsin case and uncovering details
He found out that Republicans had drawn these maps in a secret office
And that Republican lawmakers had signed secrecy agreements not to discuss the shape of the new districts
The Earl didn't know the extent to which Republicans have gone to secure a partisan advantage
Will it Galen take it from here
Earl and his partner
Still didn't have a full picture of how the maps were drawn
A detail that would be key to their case
Should I continue to dig deeper
And I noticed the email records from some people
Didn't match the email records from the people they were communicating
And that raise suspicions and we began to
Demand more and more information
And the court finally ordered them to turn over that hard drive so we can friends see if we look at
So the attorneys hired a forensic Examiner
He was able to determine that
Hundreds of thousands of documents have been deleted
A wiping soft
Prior to that hard drives being turned over to us but they were able to uncover the deleted.
Including a number of spreadsheets
And those spreadsheets are what really told the story we were able to see every iteration of the mat
As they went from the Baseline
To the man that they finally adopt
The map drawers used years of partisan voting data to design maps that strongly favored Republic
We found out that there was a professor by the name of Keith
Daddy from the University of Oklahoma
Who have been hired by the Republicans
To develop a very sophisticated multivariate
Regression analysis of partisan performance
Based on on boats
In the Assembly districts
From 2006-2008 mm
And they actually
Downloaded this proxy
Into the
Software that they were using to draw the maps
So when the man throws moved the lines on the software they could see how it affected the partisan lean of the district
In real time
The three Republicans who were responsible for drawing these Maps
Declined to be interviewed on the record
And then
They think they kept upping the ante and how many republican seats they were guaranteed
The map that ultimately came up with was designed to elect Republicans
259 of the 99 assembly seats with just 49% of the vote
With a minority of the Statewide vote
They had accounted for in effect
The largest swings between Democratic turnout and Republican turnout
During the preceding decade
The plaintiffs are now presenting those spreadsheets to the Supreme Court
As evidence that the Republicans
Set out to disadvantaged Democrat
The moment that we realize this was like it was like I was Eureka moment and the rage they anger
That I felt
The hours
Bat
These
People
Would Commit This level of a crime against the Democratic process was
Which is astounding
At that point
We decided we were going to do something about
I mean the sound
Completely pernicious and
COTA bus
What is the defense against that's like what is the actual argument that can be made is this a smoking gun
So the most blunt argument
That Wisconsin Republicans will make is that
Partisan gerrymandering isn't illegal
State legislators have been drawing Maps
That Advantage One party over another for like over a hundred
Year
And so
They're basically saying
This is a bit
Hypocritical you know why are Democrats all of a sudden outraged about
Partisan gerrymandering after they've been doing it for years
Themselves
Democrats in the case will respond and say you know this is
Civil rights issue when it's gotten so far out of hand
That the Supreme Court does
Finally need to step in
And
Then the Republicans will say
Okay if the Supreme Court is going
Stop in
Then you have to have a very clear standard of what is and is not
Fair in drawing Maps
And ultimately that's a really really difficult line to
Because
Judicial
Branch doesn't really want to get involved with drawing
Every line on a map
I mean you could see why they be reticent to do this but this is up to legislature
For sure I mean for conservatives on the court who
Strongly believe
That judicial overreach is
A threat to in our governmental system
Yes. That would be terrible if
Courts around the country
Basically
Drawing maps that were supposed to be drawn
By mistake
So if they are going to wade into the
Issue they want to be able to have like a very clear standard
For what is and is not fair and then get themselves back out of the
The process so that State Legislature
And follow the
Guidelines
Anthony Kennedy has made it clear in the past
That
He does not like parties
Gerrymandering
Keys Radisson however
Awaiting into this for that exactly
He doesn't want chords across the country
Repeatedly
Getting involved in this issue and dry mouth
It's a weird is that Wisconsin situation currently stand
We are waiting for
The Supreme Court heard oral arguments
Last fall
And
We will have a decision in this case
Baijiu
You know the decision in this case could be a pretty big
If the Supreme Court sides with the Wisconsin Democrats
That could mean that there's a
Whole lot more
Court cases
Following the same model
Saying that
The maps in those states are illegal and need to be
So Wisconsin is a pretty obvious example of partisan gerrymandering
But now we're going to turn to North Carolina where legislators have drawn lines with race in my
The Voting Rights Act has been interpreted over the years to mean that
States need to draw Maps
That don't dilute minority voters and allow minority communities
To elect candidates of their choice
North Carolina
That meant in the early 1990s Maps were drawn
So that certain districts would favor African American candidates
It works
North Carolina elected black representatives to the US House for the first time since reconstruction
This was a huge success for the African American community
It was also good for another group
North Carolina Republicans
Do understand why
Through this
Black North Carolinians overwhelmingly vote democratic
My packing these voters into a small number of District
For black candidate
Likely win
The legislature also diminish black voting power in other District
Around the state
Alone Republicans to dominate the overall political landscape
Escape the state
Different people in North Carolina have very different opinions about this
I want to play some tape now from the North Carolina episode of the gerrymandering project
Illustrate
Super complicated dynamic
I have never
Personally been one that think that increasing the numbers
The black caucus
And
Congress for example
Necessarily equated to a plus 4th Ave
American commune
Derek Smith
A political action chair for the state NW
They can ensure that African Americans get sent to
Legislative bodies and that looks good on Election Day when they can stand up and say look look at what we did for you all we help kitties
Eva Clayton
And Mel Watt
Into Congress
In the 1990s
But on the whole
The effect was
But that was when the state began to shift towards
All republican-dominated caucus and that happen all throughout the South
He's in favor of African-American voters
Influencing various
I've always thought that African-American voices that
Numerous
And loud enough and active
And
Many different places
Lynn to the likelihood
Policy decision
Will consider after
Americans more than they do
And white and black Democrat
Can form coalitions to elect minority candidates
More easily than they were once able to in North Carolina
Smith Point store famous exam
President Obama is a classic example of
If we can fuse together on a common interest with your face
The governance for the good of all
Doesn't matter your race
Reggie Weaver of common cause tends to agree
An argument has been made that yes it in in justification of racially packed districts that
Minority candidates would would not be elected any other way
There may be some truth that I don't know
To me then the answer
Isn't
2Pac districts in weekend
The minority voice in other
Area
He says that that won't get at the root of the problem
What I personally more incident as you know why is it
Yeah why is it that
Kaiser Permanente me I'm going to have a weaker chance in a
Purely
Better District just along parts of Asia why is it nothing but that gets too deep requested that we are yet resolved
I'm at the country about
I'm about race
Less emphasis should be put on race when drawing District
Is not a universal
Again here spam stop
Who worked in greensboro's 12th District office
What it was first one by Mel watt in 1990
Until the playing Ground is level in America than we will always need at Menard to test
Insofar the playing Ground is not level
Stubbs is unsure that African-American lawmakers
Will maintain their rank
If these districts are dismantle
And academic research
Suggested that could cause a ripple
The presence of minority lawmakers
Can boost voter turnout among minorities
You can also increase their trust and engagement
With politicians
One study
Done after Democrats began drawing down the black populations in minority districts
Mm
Show that Minority members of Congress
Are more likely to advocate for their communities priorities than white members of the same party
Realize most of those Monarda districts
Were created after the 1990 census
When they were
Hardly any minority representation across the country in
In Congress
So even though they're safe now you have to understand
Why they were created
Case in point
Visit the Civil Rights Museum
Ingrained
My name is Cassandra Williams and I would like to personally welcome you to the international civil rights Center
And Museum
When you arrive at the Voting Rights Act section of the news
There's a striking installment
Now we look at this list of the wall here you see African-Americans elected to federal or state
Patricia Locke
It's a Florida ceiling list
Showing the date African-American lawmaker
Elected from each state of North Carolina
In the Years
Right after
The Civil War during Reconstruction
We see that there were four black men elected
Represent the state of North Carolina in the house
House of Representatives
But then
We see
About a hundred year Gap
Before mrs. Clayton
With select
Did you represent
North Carolina
In state after state
Across the South
That 100-year Gap
Persistent
Same Gap
In South Carolina
We said in Alabama
Florida
We say
1871 and then another hundred-year Gap
Is there we can see it in Georgia
In Louisiana
From 1875 and then not until 1991
In many states
Batgap only ends
In the early 1990s
When states were forced to draw
Majority-black District
So it's easy to understand
Why the conversation about majority-minority
Can be so contentious
Unemotional
If the law favors unpacking minardi District
Could become more difficult to ensure that African-Americans are elected
The same rates
But they happen
Example North Carolina State Legislative map is currently being redrawn
Unpack the majority-minority desk
The chair of the legislative black caucus
Angela Bryan
Is likely to lose her seat in the reader
Actually regret
I losing my district and the coalition
That have been formed in that District I regret that
At the same time the gerrymandering is
Luther Barnes
She says it's for the best
I'm convinced
That even if people like me lose out to have a firm foundation
Upon which we are doing this redistricting we will be better off over time
This is the episode that most
Broke my brain I think I don't know you putting it together but there is so many
Interest that have to be balanced in so many interests that I
Really support
Want to have happen
I know it's it's
Crazy
How many values you have to juggle to draw these lines
Yeah and I mean
This is really
Even just
The tip of the iceberg when it comes to
All of the interest
That you have to consider
Drawing a district map
This is a really difficult conversation especially for Democrats to have
Because on one hand
You know they want to have the best shot at winning majorities that they
Can
On the other hand
If we are going to no longer have majority-minority
That might involve amending the Voting Rights Act
And that's a really difficult conversation for
Because as a platform Democrats
Support
Enhancing the voting power of minorities
Can we talk about this in value of competitiveness and and that brings us to the State of Arizona in twenty eleven
They tried to give power to draw Maps over to an independent Commission
And a big part of the goal was to increase competitiveness and elections
Can you describe what the thinking was an end and why they create commission to preference this button
Guitar value
Yes if you ask Americans they love competitive
You know of course from their eyes
Complicated but in general competition is a Americans value like what's more
Competition
In mm
Arizona
Through a ballot initiative meeting that just Arizona's all across the state
Voted on this
Single item saying do you want to create
An independent commission to draw the state map
Take the power away from the state line
And
Arizonans voted yes
And so for the first time in 2001 an independent commission through the maps and then for a second time in mm
An independent Commission
And in doing this you know
The
Drafters of
Ballot initiative
Had to basically say these are the criteria for drawing the maps that this independent Commission
Have to follow
And uniquely in Arizona
One of those criteria was competitive
In fact it's the only state in the country that
Wires
An independent commission or even lawmakers for that matter
To try to make this right
What's compatible
Invite competitive you mean that
I depending on
The candidate
Maybe I don't know
Equally likely that a Democrat or Republican to be elected I mean I need to find competitiveness in the kind of
Monkey world
538 we Define competitiveness
As
Within five points of the national average in a presidential election
Show
Basically a district where you would expect
And so
VSCO
Very controversial very fast can you tell us what happened
So at the time in 2011
Republicans control
Both chambers of the State Legislature
And
You know they were not all that interested in enhancing
Competition because it happen
Mission would mean probably a better chance that Democrats will take some of those seats away from them
Then on the other hand of course Democrats
Water copter
At the heart of this was
One woman who was the independent charity
The commissioners
Five people to Republicans to Democrats and one independent chair who ends up being
The tiebreaker
If you listen to the episode you can decide for yourself whether or not that's a good song
Ultimately this independent chair calling Mathis
Became
The focal point of
All of this
Disagreement
Between the two parties over how the district should be drawn
And
Things actually
What kind of scary for her
Okay so we're going to play a little bit of the Arizona episode of the gerrymandering project
Which deals with these maps that were drawn to increase
Competitiveness
And this thing starts in a public hearing
About the map drawing company that the independent commission chose
Let's all rise for the Pledge of Allegiance
I pledge allegiance
To the flag
Of the United States of America
I want to see right now for give me
I'm not going to use nice
Because I am so upset over this situation
The best way to describe it I think is it was like a beehive
All kinds of people were there and
The way they were looking at me I could just tell
They weren't happy with me
That's calling Mathis
It was June 30th 2011
And she was chairing a public hearing of Arizona's independent redistricting
The group of citizens tasked with redrawing Arizona's political boundaries
It was a packed
Room
Standing room only my husband actually was there and he went and stood in the doorway he was concerned frankly for
The safety of all of us
Cuz it just seemed
Like a heightened level of in
The commission had just decided which mapping company should draw Arizona's new District Lines
What are the boundaries that help determine who you vote for
And Republicans
So slanted have your votes been against Republican
If there is no question what the goal this commission is
But what can we expect when the independent is not really an independent
She's married to an activist Democrat
One after another each of the
People who filled out the request to speak forms came up and
Prettymuch berated me mostly
There are many
Mapping company
He's out there
Sorry I am
So upset
That you could have picked
That are non
Who article
Why didn't you
The mapping company had done work for Democratic campaign
And Republicans blamed math
Choosing a bias company
After attending the last two meetings my feelings are that this is a predetermined process
With one agenda
Remap Arizona to improve Democratic representation
What were you saw
After the the mapping insulting was appointed was a lot of pitchforks and torches here in Arizona
Because I think the public really knew at that point
That the mapping wasn't going to be
You know I told this commission was
Supposed to be
Non
Partisan
Damn it you can't get any more parts
It was scary
A few weeks after the mapping consultant decision
A sitting state senator
Had suggested
Reported in the press that
There was a Target on me
And
And that was scary
He said quote the gun is loaded
And it's just figuring out what
2 pointed out and when to pull the trigger
According to the yellow sheet report
A political newsletter in Arizona
Antinori told the Press
The time that he uses military analogies
Because he was in the military and that he wasn't targeting anyone
When people talk about targets and guns it's
Not
Something to mess with
Only six months earlier
Malthus's congressional representative
Had been shot to the Head
At Point Blank
I was in Tucson when it happened
And
Anybody who was in Tucson
Remember that day very well because it was
Was a dark
During a constituent meeting at a grocery store in Tucson
Congresswoman Gabby Gifford
I need to another p
Rashad
Sex diet
That unfortunate
Awfulness occurred in January of 2011
And I was sworn in March of 2011
And so this was that summer
After that and
It's just
It's hard to talk about it
Mathis says she and her husband bought plywood
What at Home Depot
And boarded up their bedroom
And I
Ended up
Kind of making our bedroom at least a safe Zone because we just felt
Kind of like
It'd be nice to be able to sleep at night
And not worried
Somebody was
Looking in the windows are going to do anything
They also went to the
Justice
In Washington we talked to some folks at doj and
And they had
FBI person sit in
Their safety concerns would continue for years
In 2012 with litigation still ongoing
Their house was
A year after that
The commission's office
It was broken into
And the computers of all the commissioners
Stolen
We don't know
If it was related to redistricting
But
That did occur
NASA says her mother
But I never
Was going to quit I just knew that if
If you quit
You're giving into that's exactly what they want you to do
Really intense
So what happened with these
New competitive maps that were drawn in Arizona
You know the story
It ends up being
The most
Intense
I think redistricting
Process
Probably the country is
The governor and legislature impeached
Mathis then she gets reinstated ultimately
Babe
Pasta Maps
And
They did end up enhancing
Competition
In Arizona
During the 2016 election there was one District
Arizona
That voted
Hillary Clinton for president and voted for a republican in the house
And there was another District that voted for
For Trump as president and voted
A Democrat
That's pretty rare in
Dehydrate these days where we have a very polarized political environment and generally
Democrats and Republican
Live together so it's very rare that we
See those kinds of voting
So yes
The districts that they set out to create
As competitive Def
Do function outcome
But of course
The path to getting there was a very acrimony
I mean
When you went there and
Did this story I mean what did you think of competitiveness as of value when it comes to drawing
Soup
It's a complicated one
When we look in American polity
Text because you know we say we want competitive
Shenzhen
Inferi competitive elections make lawmakers more accountable right
If you're basically guaranteed to win your primary when your general election then you're not
.
Accountable and
If voters don't have options then do you really live in a representative democracy
At the same time
Patterns in
The ways that American voters have
Clustered
Make competitive difference really hard to achieve
Republicans and Democrats don't live in similar areas
And less and less American voters
Switch back and forth
Between parties
From want to watch
And so
You
Really have to kind of
Work at creating competitive
Districts
It's okay
The last date you covered the gerrymandering project
Is California
Lake Arizona they also started an independent commission to redraw District
But they did it for a slightly different reason
Here's a clip from that episode
What caused California to creative
Did not have to do with the same old partisan type of Jerry
It is much more to do with protecting thing Compass the way they draw the district lines is to protect the incompetence
That's
Well I'll let him introduce
I'm Arnold Schwarzenegger and it was governor
Of the State of California from 2003 to 2011
He back redistricting reform as governor
And has since continued to advocate for
I'm a big believer that you must
Terminate gerrymandering
America
When you look at the district lines the way they're drunk they make absolutely no sense to anyone
But it is all designed
To keep Democrats separate from Republican
Best strategy for drawing
Created an environment in which of lawmakers felt entitled to groups of Voters
They saw it's beneficial to
Without much regard for existing communities or geography
In Los Angeles for instance Koreatown was split into three or four districts
The Filipino American Community was split into
Kathy Fang is the national redistricting
Of the nonpartisan group
Common cause
She's also its executive director in
California
During the 2001 round of rediff
She testified to the legislature
About how the line should be drawn
To keep Asian communities hole
As we traveled up and down the state we were hearing these stories about people feeling for the first time the
Prince of
Talking about their communities
Fences during the process
She got a call from a democratic assembly /
I had received a phone call
From a legislator from San Francisco
And it was my first time talking to
You know assembly person or a senator
And as a Young attorney it was quite exciting to receive this phone call
And
This person called me
To essentially tell me Kathy
You're not going to put another in Asian in my desk
I asked her to identify the lawmaker
Carole migden
She's out of office now so I guess I can say her name
It brought me to tears
Because it was a realization that
We still have
A lot of racism in this country and even in a very blue State like California people
Come to power with a sense of entitlement
That allows them to
Make
Decisions about excluding People based on race
In order to protect their own seats
When reached for comment
Carole migden said she did not recall the conversation
Any idea it was clear that the legislature was not interested
Did in considering public testimony
Like fat
What we found out was it after 4 months of
Public hearings
The legislature went behind closed doors and Drew the line
That
They are always intended to
The California Senate passed the maps on September 12th 2001
And the assembly passed them a day later
While the rest of the nation was rocking from
This terrorist attack but it happened and there was essentially a media blackout
Quite honestly there was
A real moment of reflection about
Whether or not our democracy is functioning
Their incumbent protection plan was overwhelmingly
Successful
The deal that was passed
In 2001
Made California's map almost impervious to change
Only one incumbent
Lost re-election in a general election
Between 2002 and 2010
California has insulated itself from the political volatility
Facing the rest
Country
Few of the races were even close
Ua265
US House races in California
Only 14 of them were decided by less than 10 points
Just 5%
California's Congressional elections
Competitive
I always said you know that the Soviet politburo
Edward changeover
Then our system here in California
So what happened in California like how did they combat this problem of income and see them
Incumbency bias
Californians
In the. From you know the early 2000s to 2010
As you may remember in California we're very very
Chat with the state
I mean at a certain point I think their approval rating
Was
At 10%
And
So you had
Governor Schwarzenegger and activist
Really agitated
Against the law
And so between
Common cause
The organization
And other non-partisan and partisan group
As well as the governor that kind of
Got together and bats
A again
A ballot initiative like in Arizona
To take the power of
Drawing these different Maps
Away from the state legislature
And to give it to an
And so what is the basis that they that they independent commission Drew their Maps
Show
Where is in Arizona we had one of the criteria was competitiveness that was not the case in
One of the main criteria in California
Was
To respect and Empower communities of Interest
And that relates to
Kathy fangs experience with the Asian American community in Kyle
California
And the way that she saw them basically being disregarded in favor of it
Combat zone
Electoral priority
And so what the
Independent commission did in California was a traveled around the state
And listen to members of
Communities basically say
Basically Define their own communities of
That could range
Anywhere from Koreatown
To get a one example is
You know a group of people who has horses in LA or
You know one example was even like the soundproofing Community around LAX
The LAX airport in Los
That's interesting Enzo how successful were they anyway what did they what did these Maps end up
Resulting in one of the complications with this
Way of mapping is that it's hard to tell whether or not people are being sincere about what they can say
Center as their communities of Interest
Like
Political consultant came in and
Basically organized people around
Communities that may have been disingenuous in an attempt to influence
The map drawing process for partisan reasons
There is good reason to believe that they were successful in some
Cases
Ultimately though
I think California was
Pretty successful
At appeasing
Both sides of the aisle and getting a relatively
Fair map I mean if you look at different
Statistical analyses of
The vote percentage compared with the seat chair
California's maps are pretty fair to Democrats
So what are your takeaways from all this reporting you got you were steeped in this for months and months and months and what did you come away with
Indeed I was
Trophy
If we look at the four different examples
That we've just
First what you don't realize is
That
All of these different priorities so
One being
Fairness between the two parties
To being
Fairness in representing minorities
Three being competitiveness in elections
And for being respectful of
Communities as they exist
On a map
You'll start to understand that these things do Contour
Star situations in which
Enhancing the opportunity for minority candidate to get elected
Could pain
Republicans add an advantage electoral
So ultimately the people who draw Maps
How to make
Difficult
Value chart
Often times the people who draw Maps only care about part
Right and so you know
That's basically the maps the way that maps have been drawn
For a long time
Play for going to reform the process you still have to be
Off Lease Auto
About the values that you want to prioritize amongst those for
And which of these four states do you think
Is doing the best job
If you look at California that is the place where
You will talk to both Republicans and Democrats
To say that
The mapping process overall
Westfair
And you know they're obviously Democrats Republicans who will disagree with that
But it was a rare example
In the months that I spent
Reporting on this
That you did come to some bipartisan
Agreement about the success
And is this a function of it
Being drawn by an independent commission is this what the success really points to
I think that's part oven times Americans distrust
Partisan legislators to
Put aside their partisanship in order to do what is
Quote unquote
Fair
Obviously
The people who wrote
The ballot initiative in California
Looked at some of these
Examples in other states
They you know they're already been around everyday
In Arizona the other states to look at
As well and
Think about where other states may have
Gone wrong
Try to correct
You know you said that
Of the American states are Laboratories
Democracy
And
A result of different states
Getting to tryout litigate vote for
Yo draw maps how they want to
Is that we get to see the results of a whole bunch of different
And I do think the people in California were very thoughtful about the way that they wrote the law.
So what do you expect will come out of Wisconsin case
The million-dollar question
Honestly I have no idea
But I can tell you
If Wisconsin Democrats win this case you will read in
Plenty of newspapers Supreme Court and gerrymandering
And I can tell you right now that
That will be sick leave
Ally
Because
If the Wisconsin Democrats win What will what it will actually do is start a very long process
Determining what ultimately
Is fair when it comes to
Partisan advantage
In drawing map
Right
I mean unless the Supreme Court says
You know you have to use this statistical model and has to be within this percentage of baba baba baba blah blah
Which I have no reason to
Then it's going to start a process
Of a
A lot of different lawsuits that litigate this in different ways that ultimately try to land on
What is fair
And you know what it could be
We never really land on anything I mean
That's what's happening with the Voting Rights Act right now is that we don't have a strong
Conception
Of what is fair in how much
The cluster
Minority voters together
Right
That could end up happening
With partisan
Gerrymander
And you can say that's all worth it and we need to have that debate and
You know
We're happy for all the lawyers that are that they're going to be employed for the coming decade
Off of all of these lawsuits but it's a conversation we need to have
But you know
Even if the Wisconsin Democrats don't win I don't think there's a conversation about gerrymandering goes away because ever seen even now in
Pennsylvania
There are a lot of different Avenues
Is to litigate this
And so
No matter what the decision is
In the Wisconsin Supreme
I can promise you that this is going to be a conversation
So why don't we just have computers draw District Lines
Will Galen hasn't answered
Fabulous
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another remedy for all hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek out go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Tequila told me that when the gerrymandering project came out when the biggest questions they got from listeners
News about algorithms
Why not take this
Whole process out of the hands of humans
And just use an algorithm to draw totally random boxes on a map
In some ways
You could you just
Write new laws saying that we want an algorithm to draw a nice neat shapes
On a map
Probably the area where you run into the most trouble is the Voting Rights Act
Which specifically requires that minorities not have their votes diluted enter sometimes
Just drawing Maps
Randomly according to shape
Could potentially violate the Voting Rights Act
On top of that whether or not we're talking about a minority
Community
Often times people want their community in one District right
If you're going to have a representative you want them to represent
Something
And so if you have an algorithm that draws the map randomly
People might not feel like they've been grouped together with their community
An algorithm cannot
A hundred different
Community meetings and listen to people talk about
Where their Community is
If you work at
California
Independent commission website
One of those like
Commonly house Prussia
Why doesn't an algorithm
Algorithm can't listen to community property
Galen is not against using algorithms and redistricting
But he says they don't change the fact that drawing lines on a map forces you to make difficult choices
You still have
Program the algorithm
To prioritize
Certain values the same way that you would have to
Construct a legislative body or an independent commission to do that
So you know in the program you have to say we want District to be compact
Or we want
Districts to respect existing Municipal boundary
We want you algorithm to make the district
Competitive
I mean still itches like algorithm time value so I don't understand how it's all that all it really seems to
Potentially solve is
Calling Mathis doesn't get death row
Right I think there are plenty of people who will tell you that algorithms
Have
A place in this process
And yes it can make this process
Easier and potentially Fair
But it's not a silver
Galen true
Post of the gerrymandering project
Podcast mini-series from 538
Chadwick Matlin was the editor of God
Keep bacteria Ava and Alice Wilder contributed to the structure
Did you enjoy this we really really encourage you to go listen to the whole series
Baconator so much more detail and it was completely fascinated
15538 also put together all these incredible maps and Graphics that
You can play around with to try to understand
Different District in priorities and how they impact the shapes of the Mavs
Adobe links on a website
I-90 I. Org
99percentinvisible with Bruce's sweet by Emmett Fitzgerald mix and Tech production by Sharif Youssef
Music by genre
Can you mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital director
Delaney Hall is the senior editor
Press the staff includes Avery trufelman
Turn master and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective but the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
We are supported by a listener
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we meet at Roman Mars and a show at 99.
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
We have more visual design stories and even video
At 9 p.m.
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com