99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment in California and
Around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1998 Dr Gary Kaplan the CEO of Virginia Mason Medical Center in Seattle
Received some bad news
About as hosp
It was losing money
But voices David Weinberg who's doing our reporting for us today
So back to the story
Is that loss is at Virginia Mason Dr Kaplan start studying how other hospitals are managed
We started scouring the country
Looking for a hospital with a management system worth it.
And if you're anything like me when you hear the phrase
Management
System
Part of your brain begins
Shot down in another part of your brain prepares itself
The hearing a lot of
Either complete nonsense
Or common sense
Tarted up with unnecessary jargon but really all you need to understand here is that
Dr Kaplan was looking for a hospital that have processes and procedures
Or better than what it was already using
But he never found one
So instead
He ended up in Japan
At a Toyota fact
Yep
The automobile
I think about
This is a very smart physician who goes around the country
Looking for a great manager
System and doesn't find
Charles Kenny is the author of transforming Healthcare
A book about Virginia Masons journey to adapt
The Toyota production
System to healthcare
He doesn't Dr Kaplan told his staff they would be changing everything about the where they operate
And the changes were based on a car company
And that the doctors and nurses should refer to their new teachers as sensei
Response
Was not pretty
There was a lot of Anger from
People within his organization
Led by the doctor
And this whole multi-year overhaul started with a ball
A blue your
The staff met with a Sensei and he took out the ball blue yarn and a map of the hospital
And he told the staff
To trace the path a cancer patient would take
On a typical visit
For chemotherapy
And then the yarn when
Cross tattoo
Couple inches and then it maybe went up
5 in
To where they'd have
To get their blood drawn and then they would go up
To the 14th floor and on the cardboard that was like maybe 4 in
Which is above that Joellen is a nurse manager at Virginia Mason
To come
And see their doctor which was in a different location was so big on our board that we just had to keep wine
Finding it around itself that sucker Henry Otero creating kind of this circular maze like
You would wind a yo-yo when we looked at it we were amazed
At how far patients
Travel
We were asking oncology patients who are
Their oxygen carrying capacity
Password is compromised
Because the chemo
Therapy
Destroys a lot of red blood cells so that makes him short of breath
And here were asking patient
Things to do this who are short of breath.
To begin with
So is this
It was appalling
To us and I think it was
That mapping of the flows of medicine and the patient understanding the patient Journey was
That I
Eye-opening moment
That you realize
You don't really know what
What's going on the blue yarn told the story of what Virginia Mason was doing wrong
We just didn't we couldn't conceive of it intellectual until we saw
In the story it told was not a good one to dr. Otero thought he was providing exceptional care for
They basically came into my
Exam room
And they laughed
And I really said I'm a great doctor look at this great care I give I see them I send them out and
Another day just mess
Feel like temperature
Great experience of having care here
Then he saw the twisting path of the blue yarn
Oh how awful it is for them
How awful it must
Speed to really
Weight everywhere along the way
And that I was contributing to that
And that
It became an intolerance
Spell 82
I couldn't accept it anymore
Six months after that first meeting
Doctor Mecklenburg the hospital's chief of Medicine
Let a group of staff on a 3 week trip to Japan to meet with a
And so they pulled out the schematic essentially an architect's drawing
Various parts of
Virginia Mason Medical
And
The Sensei kept pointing to these areas
Saying what is that and
Dr Mecklenburg
I would say well that's a waiting
And this happened over and over
Again
The waiting area and as this was happening
That's a waiting area
The sensation
To him to be getting increasingly angry
And he says to Mecklenburg
Why are there
So many waiting
Areas
Throughout this
Who's waiting
What are they doing what are they waiting
Dr. Mecklenburg
Says those are patient
They're waiting for us
And the sensei
Long pause
Looks quite
Furious
Looks directly at Doctor Mecklenburg
Front of Mecklenburg steam says to him
Aren't you ashamed
And Doctor Mecklenburg said at that moment he was
He was absolutely
If I told you to
Picture
A waiting room
You probably picturing a doctor's office
This is what we are trained to do when we go to the doctor we are trained
To wait for to a sensei
He's been trained in the Toyota production
Waiting is a form of waste
The number 110
TPS
Is to eliminate
Waste
The staff completely redesigned the cancer center
And they hired an architect who had first-hand knowledge of cancer treatment as a patient
You've designed the journey differently to really
Be
OceanFirst
The new design put patients on the outer edges of the building
Nice rooms with big windows that let in natural light
And provided views of the Puget
It sound but in order to give the patient these rooms they had to take them away from the doctors who had their off
Offices there
Do you want something that really
Was difficult for me because
Play I think we're always in the right direction with
The patient
I think for others who may be didn't go through that process
They saw it as a takeaway
You know I had to Great office the great win tonight putting me in this cubicle you know and I'm on the guy does all the work you know
You know what your night
It shouldn't have
The big office some doctors were so angry that quit
Dr. Otero
Did everyone who stayed realizes
It was the right thing to do for the
When I go there and I see them there and I see them looking out and I
II
Recognize that's a much better place than be gratified that
Decision was made
And
It's totally worth the right
Decision it's not even a question
Should have doubted relocating patients
It was just the beginning
Today the new cancer center has been dubbed
The cancerous
Spa
It was designed to
Create an environment of
Healing
So it has
Real pretty pale yellow color we use colors of nature
Nature cell
Yellow for Sunshine we have brown
To stimulate
Ingrained
Stimulating
And we have a water wall there's two of them
Actually it just so you don't think
But this new manager
System resulted only in
Natural
Colored walls in
Big windows
The whole reason why this blue yarn was unspooled to begin with was to save the hospital money
And it did
And it also
Made it a safer place
From 2007 to 2009
Virginia Mason was so much safer
But their insurance
Expensive decline
Astonishing 37
2%
While simultaneously increasing the number of pages
Retreated
All without having to hire any Edition
And yet some people
Still scoff at the idea of Toyota in
Inspired manager
I was on a boat once
And someone said to me so you are you guys still building Toyotas in your basement
And that was that was a real
I mean I was
Send it
Because I knew that what we're doing here is a really good and I said to him
You know you can say what you want
Make fun of what we're doing but we're trying to do the best
This complete upheaval of the medical industry
Stemmed from a single thread of blue yarn
Became especially poignant
When the staff visited Japan for the first time
Ansan exhibit at the Toyota his
History Museum
It was an automatic Loom
That was where the team learned that the Toyota production system was in fact born quite literally
From a single thread of yarn
Might have even been blue
Toyota was originally a textile
In 1902
Sakichi toyoda invented a selfie
Correcting Lune
I would stop
The thread was broken or woven incorrect
That this the museum is a story of continuous process Improvement
You start with backbreaking work on a manual Loom
That is producing defective product
And you put in the first components of ergonomics
Putting the person sitting up in
Instead of sitting on the
The floor then you start making automatic lamps and improve the Machinery then you start developing mistake proofing into the prom
Process that if any of the weave or the West
Breaks the machine stops
Improve the machinery
Function is time goes on
Speed and velocity
I see that at Virginia Mason we're still just we just gotten off the floor
Sitting on the chair
We got a couple of mistake proofing things in the iron and we someday we might be an automatic Loom but that might be 34
40 years from now
But
We've got a long way to go to mistake-proof healthcare
Do it in a cost-efficient
Manor
99% invisible which produces Wheat by David Weinberg
With help from me Roman Mars
Who's made possible with support from the lunar
Making a difference
With creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco the American Institute of Art
Architects in San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
Define Atmore go to the website it's 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood we're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of thing if you
2 days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com