99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Fairhope
Grace
Human Madewell
Set float in the air
4 over 100 years lighter than air aircraft have fascinated us
I have this recurring starring role in our dreams of an alternate reality
Of a future that might have been where cargo and passenger is Traverse the globe
Civilized
MDOC elegantly
In the morning Towers on top of Art Deco skyscrapers
In real life it was likely a blimp emblazoned with the Goodyear logo
A blank is a non rigid Airship there's no structure inside the balloon is just a balloon
The shape is maintained by the pressure of the lifting gas inside then you had a little cockpit in engines and rudder
Outside that big balloon to make it Fly today's blimps are basically cute PR novelties
But for around 100 years
Lighter than air aircraft
We're seriously proposed as the Perfect Design solution
All kinds of problems
Even though none of these proposals actually happen
People just
Couldn't give up on the promise
Veriship
In the 90s there was a company called sky station
Play raise some
4.2 billion orally solicited it to put 205
50 + 10 equip the airships to deliver internet service
This is Bill Hamid
He's the engineer guy on YouTube and an Airship enthusiast
The 80s that was the British Antarctic Survey
Go to the South Pole
I'm so pretty soon enough professor
Suggested Tangled electrical wires
Zappos onedin chemicals in the seventies they were supposed to help developing nations using a hive
Hybrid blimp to Usher those nations in the 20th century no no need for roads they need
Railroads and tunnels and bridges which is to lift stuff in the 1950s and 60s
Nuclear powered airship
What's with unlimited energy and an unlimited capacity for work
Propose
In the twenties and thirties they were to fulfill Imperial Ambitions both
Germany
And the British
We're looking for that
Any Americans to
Imperial Ambitions in the Philippines
All those failed attempts to realize
Full potential of air show
It was those Imperial rigid airship
Have we developed in the 20s and 30s
That came the closer
To actually changing the world
Airship
You have a metal frame
And the house has gas bags that lift this year
Those gasbags are arranged in the metal scaffolding like
Peas in a Peapod
And it'll cloth cover is stretched over that emmacloth cover is not airtight it protects the gas bags from weather
Underneath the fabric cover are not trust Gatsby
Because it's not a pressure vessel
They're able to build things inside the airship
Like crew quarters dining rooms lounges
All built into the metal framework
So people move around inside the thing that you might think of as the balloon but it's not really
Emmett structure enables an Airship to travel faster little blimp
Because the force of the wind for example with the form the nose of a blimp
And it also allows
The ship to be built much
Much bigger
You may be heard the term dirigible which is the French name for an airship
Where is zeppelin
Which is a German company that makes airships
Zeppelin is like the kleenex or bandaid of the airship
The proper term is generic and boring as it sounds
Is air show
The most promising most
Opulent rigid Airship of its time 1920s here was Britain's r101 B are there
Stands for Ridgid
The rise and dramatic fall of Britain's last great Airship is the primary subject of Bill hammocks new book
Call
Fatal
Flight
Weather alert
When it comes to the dream of airships dominating the sky's the catastrophic and very public Hindenburg disaster
May have been the final nail in the coffin
It was the crash of r101
That built the coffin
R101 was supposed to connect the global British Empire
Who designed to fly from London to Karachi in 5 days
That's 10 days faster than by sea
Taking a plane that distance
Took 16 days
Because planes had to stop so often to refuel
Airships could also carry 3240 X the cargo of airplane
Airships just made so much sense
For an Empire whose reach
Exceeded its grasp
So Great Britain build r101 and r100
Which was
Its sister ship that was supposed to go to Canada and back
As the first two rigid ships in a fleet
That would give the crown dominance
Over the skies
To match its centuries-long dominance
Of the Seas
Intercept is conceptually quite simple but it's still an engineering Marvel
It's a gargantuan cigar-shaped math equation
On one side of the equation and wait on the other
Minimizing the weight of the airship
Was always a challenge
There's a rigid metal framework and that is one of the most difficult Parts because
That have to be lightweight yet strong yet r101 was supposed to match the sturdy luxury of a high-end OSHA
Matthew's pictures white China
And with royal blue and silver salt shakers and crystal glasses
Small butter dishes but to allow for those essential refinements
Everything else could only have the thinnest veneer of opulence
Because they needed everything to weigh as little as possible
One person described it when they touch the ceiling is like a piece of
Stage scenery
All the walls were actually fabric
The pillars in the lounge word made from Balsa
Covered with metal
The tables were also Balsa
Mermaid of the lightest cane
What kind of an illusion the the solidity of a ship because
You just couldn't have
Ford the list
Tons and tons
On the other side of the equation is left
You get Lyft from pumping in gas that's lighter than air
In the case of r101 the gas they use
What's hydrogen
Will flammable hydrogen seems like a very poor choice
It was for a commercial airship
The only choice
Use hydrogen instead of helium which is non flammable
Because the purpose of a ship like r101 what's a transport
Cargo
And helium is both heavier and provides less lift
When hydrogen
What you're interested in is
The payload that you can
Lips so
If you
Track all of the
Wait till you have to lift a rigid ship
Gasbags
Water
The personnel
I'm in a ship like r101 if you filled it with helium
You would not have enough
Lyft Lyft
Flammability of hydrogen was indeed a concern intercept
But find engineers and crew were habituated to it's dangerous much like we're habituated to the danger zone
Combustion engines today
They felt that you just take
The proper precautions
What engineer production don't light a match and look in your gas tank in your car
When you're driving around with something highly flammable all of the time right now
Proper
Engineering Solutions in control
You're the reason why helium wasn't an option on Commercial airships
Was the cost
Helium at that time was produced in the USA
It comes from natural gas that
Required
Expensive distillation plants in most of the helium is in
Places like Kansas City
Oklahoma and Texas
So they would have to pay for it to be imported into Britain and said you can make hydrogen on-site
Very cheaply
Almost 1/100 of the cost of helium
I was never really
You know an option never really
Considered the gas bags that contain the hydrogen
Are their own engineering Mar
It's interesting to me as an engineer.
Think about
The materials they had to make these
Gasbag
Because you have a problem in that hydrogen
Wants to permeate the small molecule that likes to go through things
So you need something that's very strong
Videos
Impermeable to
Hydrogen
Or largely impermeable
Adidas lightweight
And so they tried things like rubber gelatin glycerin
Viscose
Synthetic
Fabric is coated with latex
But they all failed one way or another like to viscose if you crumpled it up
You could not
They use in this
Stuns me to this day the intestines
Dachshund
It is specifically the oxygen test with a very fine membrane is called the cecum and it's
Straighten flexible
And hydrogen seats only slowly through it
Ox intestines are nearly the perfect material except
Or the size
The cecum of an ox is about
30 in by 6 in a square foot
And yet one of those gas bags if you laid it out your
30000 square feet to create one of these gas
You would use 50000 of his entrails Orso
Factors of over a million and a half oxygen test things are needed
To create the 15 gasbags
Sure I would have won if they delivered from
Slaughterhouses
Argentina leave some of the the animals
Barrels of these guts and then they would scrape them
And go through this long process to prepare them and eventually to glue them together
And answer your question 50,000 Ox intestines even One Secured and treated to make them into gas bags
You kind of steak
They did they did apparently if you were up in the Airship you would smell you know what kind of an animal smell
A musty smell also because the clock cover didn't allow light in
Or 101 in a few test flights in and around its hanger outside London
Great Fanfare in fact
Bill Hammack surmises that the
Focus on PR and Fanfare rather than
More rigorous and deliberative test
Lead to the tragedy that was about to come on the ships first
Attempted flight to India in 1930
Good left
October 4th Mets
6:30 at night
Most of them work the well as reports
Somewhere observers and somewhere Diggity
Capital Crossing linode traveled across
Channel into France and
It was easy bruising wind
When sulfuric acid
The ground speed is only 30 miles per hour or so
I need a few minutes past to it was about 40 miles are 64 kilometers
North of Paris
Any kind of chop to the Tribune are flying about 1,200 feet but
Moving up and down a couple of hundred feet
And the top cover ripped open
The top cover was weak it was one of the weakest parts of a ship
Then at that point
The gas bags which are made of these very thin intestines were exposed to rain
The rain
How did the gas bag
There was a decrease in
Maybe drop to 500 feet or so
And the control car and no one knows why today signal for the engine power to be cut off
Corset locked Holden hammock
Looked at that point
And it drove nose-first the ground it slid into a Grove of Hazel and oak tree
Burst into Flame
There's some debate as to why it burst into flames
Bill Hammack thinks the fire might have been caught
Buy calcium phosphide flare
That book kept in the control car
Those ignite when water hits
And of course that ignited
Hydrogen
At that point just everything became chart only six people
Survived it
The ground was littered
With
The universe sad everyday things I mean soup
Spurline Bouchard shaving brush
Kind of cigarettes
Peking Wok
Pens
Plums with a
Juice leaking
End
Then
He was very quiet
And all you could hear
What's the hits of the rain
Hotmail
The wreckage had barely cool
The British government halted their Airship program for good
It was almost immediate
R100 had flown
Go to Montreal and back
And it was in the shed
It never flew again
Play eventually steamrolled
R100
Sold some of the parts
Prescribed sold Summit
Even though our 101 was completely destroyed in the French Countryside
The burned remains did float in the sky once again
At least for a little while
Well the wreckage of that ship
Was cut up into pieces
Shipped back in December to Grapevine
And went to
Somebody who will
Take scrap metal
And then
Apparently
According to a newspaper account
It was sold
To the Zeppelin company
And they use
Is part of that metal
Because of the Romanticism wrapped up in airships
The flexibility when it comes to moving huge cargo
Unified that requires very little
To support their operation
Hope that airships will make a return
Has never gone away
When I get a question it's going to come back and with new material
From the reason why they don't come back is this
Fiery disaster fill Legacy which I am
Perpetuating right now
What politician won
To vote in an Airship intend inhabit crash in somebody's about ghetto didn't you know about
The Hindenburg
I would not this isn't quite fair if you look at me like the Graf Zeppelin which was
The contemporary
R101 it
Predecessor to the Hindenburg
It was in service for 9 years
Across the Atlantic
144 *
16000 flight hours
590 flights 13000 passengers the first
Aircraft
Ever
To exceed 1 million flight miles
Answer
Navigated
The globe
In just 21 days so there is
You know another history back
Necessities things can be made and can be made
Well
At this point the airplane has had a Century's worth of development in
Efficiencies
Speed and safety
So that the need for the airship
Has been largely eliminated
The past is precedent
Some enterprising engineer is in a room full of venture capitalist right now
Trying to convince
.
Giant airships other solution
To some pressing world problem
In the meantime
The Airship will continue on in science fiction stories
Asda
Quick and easy visual cue
That work in a world that's a lie gars
But somehow
More wondrous
What are the most memorable pieces of audio of all time and my favorite video by the engine
Junior guy
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
. info
Flat pocket
When the Hindenburg crashed and burned in a New Jersey field in 1937
A reporter from Chicago radio station WLS named Herbert Morrison was there is real-time Rihanna
Disaster that was unfolding in front of him
Became one of the most memorable recordings in broadcast history
Couple people on staff here at never heard it before it's totally shocked me
So I wanted to play here
You might not be able to make out all the words but
Morrison's emotions
Through loud and clear
Comparable
That radio recording was later paired with newsreel footage of the disaster
36 of the 97 people on board the Hindenburg
Died
When you see the footage
Airship
The fact that 61 people survived
Seems like
America
As I mentioned in my introduction to Bill hammock on YouTube he's known as engineer guy
And I would be remiss if I didn't point you toward his fantastic video on the ingenious design of the aluminum beverage
Which is for my money
The greatest video on YouTube it is 11 and 1/2 minutes
Everyday design and Engineering Glory
I love it
Here's a little audio sample
Why is there a tab on the end of the can
It seems a silly question how else would you open it
But originally cans didn't have time
Very early steel cans were cold
Pretty obvious reason
You use a special opener to puncture a hole drink
And hold of it
In the
Pool tables invented
The know
You can find links to build videos and his book on the r101 on his website
Baidu.com
99percentinvisible is Avery Chapman Emmett Fitzgerald Sharif Youssef
Turn master
Composer Sean real
Digital director Kurt Kolstad
Senior editor Delaney Hall senior producer Katie Mingle
And me
Roman Mars
We are products 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Mapreduce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We're part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
We are supported
By our listeners
IQ
You find 99percentinvisible into in discussions about the show on Facebook
Can you tweet me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi org one Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
We have very fun pictures and diagrams of airships on our website they're even more amazing than you can picture in your
Add 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalize Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com