99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
August 24th 1814 March 1st and only time Washington DC was occupied
By outside forces
United States with two years in the War of 1812
Be taken on Great Britain which was then the greatest naval power in the world
And things weren't looking great for the American troops defending DC
As producer Vivien Leigh
British forces / took the city
Set fire to Historic American landmarks including the treasury building
The Capitol building
And even the White House
The beach became known as the burning of Washington
But then a freak occurrence which in any other situation would have been a total disaster for DC
Saved the city
Dark clouds begin to form
Which turned into thunder and lightning
Which then turned into a full-blown tornado
Headed straight for the British who were setting fires around the capitol
A number of British soldiers
Chris were killed by Falling debris
And the fire is extinguished by the rain
The British retreated back to their ships which had been severely damaged by the storm
Thanks to a simple Act of weather
The occupation of our nation's capital was over within a little more than a day
The storm that saved Washington was just one of countless times that weather played a crucial factor in war
Napoleon's Army was interviewed by Russian forces but by a Russian winter
And during World War II
General Patton famously distributed
250000 prayer cards to the Army
Enlist as many men as possible
Pray for an end to the Rain
The battlefield has always been at the mercy of the climate
But there was a time and US military history
When we did more than just pray for advantageous weather
We try to create it
Fighting communist guerrillas in South Vietnam continue
Videos of slug line
Pictures from the swampy Mekong Delta show government troops trying to ferret out the
Beginning in the 1950s and continuing into the 1960s and 70s
Do us became deeply entangled in a war between North and South Vietnam
North Vietnam was supported by the Soviet Union China and other communist allies
South Vietnam was supported by the Us and other anti-communist allies
And the Vietnam War
Or as the Vietnamese called
The American War
Was unlike any of the United States had ever engaged in
Or
Tradition and our heritage and our
Education in our history all prepared us for a different kind of War
Then we had to fight in the lake
This is General Merrill McPeak
Former Chief of Staff of the Air Force
There wasn't a Frontline
And we weren't facing a enemy at least of the beginning
That was equipped with tanks and flamethrowers and
High-speed you know computers and so forth
It was a total Miss mismatch
That's from that standpoint it was us against the
A guerrilla Army that showed up occasionally and then disappeared vanished
Spent the next day
No months looking for it and then it showed up Suddenly and then was gone again
That gorilla Army was the Viet Cong
Communist Sports
Allied with North Vietnam but fighting primarily in the south
One of the vietcong's greatest advantages
Was the Ho Chi Minh trail
Supply route that ran from North Vietnam
Two parts of Laos and Cambodia into South Vietnam
Hundreds of thousands of North Vietnamese troops
Used it to infiltrate the South
Weapons and supplies
Travel through an isolated region full of rugged mountains and dense jungle
The trail itself is made up of dirt paths in handmade tunnel
Along the way there were hidden bunkers
Barracks
Even hospitals cleverly camouflaged from above
It was a engineering Marvel that wasn't a single Road
It was a network of Amazing Frog
The covert trail system dramatically shortened the journey from North to South Vietnam
Many more troops more weapons and more North Vietnamese
Pork be made available to Communist forces in the south
And the key thing was that's how all their supplies
Sa Supply both the Viet Cong and also
Their own forces
I had to come down that trail
This is Lieutenant General Ed's oyster
And in order to cut off the supplies with your course very important for military operation
We had to close this Trail by various means
The US military tried disrupting the trail with
Bombing campaign
Am I plowing the jungles to strip the land
They also use deadly chemical defoliants like Agent Orange
But none of these
It seemed to work
At least not for very long
So whenever we punched a hole in one part of it
They simply moved over to
I know a bypass
There was only one thing
Significantly slowed the flow of supplies and people on ho chi Minh trail
Rain
The reality was that
Because of the nature of the trail
It was affected by heavy rainfall
So they had the same problem of course as we did in terms of trails that were
Very very
Marty
What the rain
The mud would make the trails difficult to navigate
And so during one month since
In the middle of the war
Somebody
Certainly not me
Came up with the idea of let's see if we can increase the rainfall
Enough to stop vehicle
Qatar traffic
The Department of Defense design it
But they should try
Control the weather
This was the beginning of a top-secret military project called operation Popeye
The goal was to actually create more rain in Southeast Asia
They artificially extending and intensifying the naturally-occurring monsoon season
The monsoon season typically lasted from April to October
US military believe that if it could extend it
Buy a month on either side
It would create a huge strategic advantage
Humans especially military humans
Have wanted to control the weather for a long time
Because pets who up
Traditional out rainmaking ceremony
This is Jim Fleming
He studied the history of human attempts at weather and climate modification
He doesn't think very highly of our abilities
Turns out that if you do a rain dance for up to two weeks it'll probably rain and then you can take credit for that
And consistently enough it'll rain and you can claim responsibility
Funny says that in the 19th century after the Civil War
A theory begin to develop
That major military operations Were Somehow disrupting the clouds and causing big rain storms
We could shoot Cannon
Fireworks
We could sort of imitate battle
Imitate battle in order to create rain
The federal government actually attended this in Texas in the 1890s
Special
Department of Agriculture funded it
And they had a weather bureau Observer there
The locals love
It was during the monsoon season
It was a really good chance was going to rain anyway
This kind of experimentation continued from the 1890s into the early twentieth
Century
It only accelerated after 19
Weed enter the Cold War era
And we just invented the bomb
And that technology made people think they had power over nature
Those are heightened are paranoid that other countries were trying to develop their own nature controlling technology
Like the Russians
Before the space race with the Soviet Union
There was a kind of weather race
We thought they might get ahead of us
And if they had a nefarious purpose they might be able to change our weather and climate in
Possibly caused
Unlike another dust forward or drought or something if they really could do it
So there's a great rush to get into this field again
Driven by military
Concerns
There was a lot of money being poured into scientific research on whether
A control
And while many of these experiments didn't yield very promising results
One actually did
In 1946
The weather
This remarkable achievement happened in Schenectady New York
Are the offices of General Electric
Yep
The same company that made your dishwasher also invented weather control
GE was where scientist and Nobel Laureate and Irving Langer was working in collaboration with a colleague
Vincent Schaefer
Who developed a technique of dry ice put into a cloud that would make it super cool
And force it to be
Conditions to go below freezing
A little bit of ice in the cloud
Could cause a cloud to play shade or creates snow
In case you didn't quite get that here's a quick lesson in 8th grade cloudphysics
Clouds are essentially just tiny droplets of water
Suspended in the atmosphere
When the right conditions occur
Water molecules in these clouds will condense together and become heavy enough
The fall to Earth as rain or snow
And that's what Schaefer had figured out how to do
He figured out how to create the conditions in the clown such that it would produce rain or snow
In parallel with that breakthrough there was another guy doing instrumental work at GE
His name was Bernard or Bernie Vonnegut
The brother of author
Kurt Vonnegut who also worked at GE in the PR department
And it's interesting
You can actually see the ways that GE influence some of vonnegut's writing
Kurt was on staff at GE
Writing a history
Reports when he was also working on novels
Play Cat's Cradle
In which the
The mad scientist kind of like in Irving Langer person develops Ice Nine which
Messes up the environment
Ice Nine was kind of like cloud seeding on steroid
It's clear that Bernie and Kurt
These two brothers
Chris were uneasy about some of the brakes
If they were involved with
And I think you'll see some of Bernie's concerns
Reflected in Kurt vonnegut's novels
Which are pretty much
Against the militarization
Of nature
The Bernese work at GE actually helped lay the groundwork for that militarization
Along with linear and Schaefer
She made another credit
Call Discovery
He found a new weather-related use for a compound called Silver iodide
It had a hexagonal structure
Like a snowflake
And he found that if you sprayed it into a cloud
It would trick the cloud in the glaciated
And so
Armed with a Nobel Prize winner
A technique to super cool cloud
With dry ice
And a technique to trick a cloud with silver iodide
They really felt they had
The basis for chemical cloud seeding
GE was understandably very proud of their discovery
And so they
Officiate a great big press release it said we can control the weather
But shortly after claiming responsibility for a storm that caused 8 inches of snowfall in Upstate New York
GE suddenly realize that they might not want to be known for controlling the weather
Especially if that weather was destroying people's
Property
Munster lawyer says know you better
You better keep that quiet because there could be too many lawsuits
Given the risk of negative public reaction and liability
Weather modification research continued
Quietly
Scientist board how it could be applied to Hurricane intervention in drought relief
Course
Warfare
Langmuir himself
Was excited about the military applications of his research
And I think he wanted to have a kind of a gigantic militarized
Hurricane is multiple h-bombs
And credible
Destructive power if you could
Directed
Against an enemy
Sole me was making these kind of plants
And so were our political leaders
Was nuclear weapons now in play
The US was
Forward
Imagining how we could give ourselves an edge and future Wars
This is from a speech that vice President Lyndon Johnson gave in 1962
LBJ or Bond film
You decide
By the time rainmaking had made its way to the Ho Chi Minh trail in Southeast Asia
It wasn't a new technology
It was still a closely held Secret
Operation Popeye was a Navy program
Admissions were flown by air for
Force pilots
And as Pilots were given limited information about what they were doing
I never even imagined
That group was doing until
We got over there and
Showed up
For the briefing
They told us what
This project is about
This is Brian Heckman a former Air Force pilot
He belongs to the 54th weather reconnaissance Squad
They contributed to the 2602 cloud seeding missions flown during operation Popeye
Looking for clouds
2 seed
When they found the clouds of life
The flip switch to ignite silver or lead iodide flares
Anyway to see if the cloud produce rainfall
There were times when we left an area
That we have been working
And it was obvious that
There was a lot of rain storms going on
Operation Popeye at form an object
To turn the roads to mud
Cause landslides
Lights along roadways
To washout River Crossing
And to keep roads muddier for longer than usual
It seemed to Heckman that operation Popeye was working
But it's really hard to know for sure
Cloud seeding at the time and even today
Far from an exact science
At best a military could measure three things
What's the average rainfall for that area was
What's the estimated rainfall would have been
And what actually fell after receiving mission
But they couldn't collect
That much data
Like enough to really rigorously analyze the outcome
Hughes Plumbing again
The rain is completely a variable
You have tremendous
Temporal variability
Spatial variability
And that means that statistics are not robust about
Your particular intervention did to that
Particular
Rainfall
And even if they could make it rain
They couldn't precisely control where that rain landed
One official described accidentally dumping a ton of rain on the American Special Forces
Still the program was deemed effective enough to continue for 5 years
M1967
But the biggest problem with operation Popeye wasn't so much the lack of quantifiable success
What's the many ethical concerns
Weather modification
Especially in the context of War
Resalat of thorny question
The military Justified the program by arguing that increasing rainfall to Grandma and wash out roads
Wood preferable
Baltimore bombing
But the reality is
The US military still dropped a lot of bombs on southeast Asia during the Vietnam war
Over 7 million
Tons of them
So many in fact
That to this day
The government of Laos is
Still trying to clean up all of the undetonated bomb scattered across the country
Here's General Merrill McPeak again
We dropped more bombs on Laos than
And we did on Germany and Japan all together in World War II
Show the tonnage of of
Bomb dropped was enormous
And the heavily-used
Parts
Of the Ho Chi Minh trail
Look like the face of the Moon
It was just a lunar landscape nothing but dust
But just as it's unclear how much rain was generated
Popeye
It's also unclear if Popeye actually prevented the military from dropping more bombs
Or if they die
Did both
And messing with another country's weather system
That has potentially bigen unpredictable consequences
You don't necessarily know what the long-term consequences
Is it going to be of rain make
This is Jacob Hamblin
Astorian at Oregon State University
Especially if you're doing it all night
A long-term basis
And there are documented
Cases in which weather modification may have caused
Set alarm
Silver iodide sprayed into
The clouds can be toxic
Sick to humans in concentrated doses
But it hasn't been shown to have negative health of
Effects when you
McCloud CA
Nevertheless
Cloud seeding may have caused other prom
In 1947
Irving langmuir research
Estima GE
Tried to break up a hurricane by dumping a lot of dry ice into it
To see if it would collapse
But instead it changed the trajectory
Became stronger
Did you get the Georgia coast
One death was reported as result
Hurricane
And in 1952 the British royal Air Force was conducting cloud seeding test in lynmouth England
And may have accidentally caused a devastating flood that kill
35 people
It was this kind of ethical ambiguity that ultimately ended the US military's entire weather
Annotation program
In 1971
Jack Anderson reporter for the Washington Post
Published an article revealing that the US was engaged in covert weather Warfare in Vietnam
This report was corroborated by information leaked
Paper
The following year in July of 1972
Seymour Hersh reported in the New York Times about operation Popeye
Within two days of the story's publication
The entire program was officially ended and all cloud seeding missions
Stop
When the program was finally Declassified and it came out that the US had been secretly engaging in hostile weathermen
Population in Vietnam
It was dubbed
The Watergate
Weather Warfare
But they really should have called it weathergate
This led to a kind of an embarrassing the tremendously embarrassing moment for the for the US here's Tim Fleming
Just perceived as a big mistake
It's just an embarrassment
Try to
Intervene animations weather like that
Research money for weather control rapidly disappeared
And in 1977 the US signed an international agreement called the environmental modification convention treaty
Orin mod
For sure
How long did the Soviet Union and many other nations
They agreed to ban modification of the environment
Pravda purposes
The treaty outlawed causing earthquakes and tsunamis
Steering hurricanes or tampering with the ionosphere
It also banned any other widespread long-lasting and severe damage the environment
But there are questions about whether the end mod treaty was even that relevant
Missouri easy to ban
Environmental Warfare
The reason was easy to ban is because you're not giving up anything
Because those things no longer work considered to be
Important parts of the RC
They were developed during a Time
When
The US wanted to develop a lot of different weapons
But by the time you get to the
If there was going to be a war with the Soviet Union
It was going to be a noob
Clear war was going to be a war in which thermonuclear weapons were used
Intercontinental ballistic missiles were probably going to be used
And so Hamblin believes that giving up environment to Warfare
Was more a gesture
Of global cooperation rather than an actual step towards the storm
After all it's hard to find something that can cause more widespread long lasting or severe damage to the environment than nuclear
Their weapons are not banned
Real Madrid
You could argue yes sir it's progress but
I would encourage us all to take a more cynical view of that and
And see that it was signed for very political purposes and really gave
Virtually nothing
The military interest in weather control had run its course
The cloud seeding is something that still takes
Place all over the world for another reason
Money
Major percentage of the economy is weather sensitive
From agriculture to energy to insurance
To the travel industry
More than 50 countries openly have some form of weather modification program
China attempted to use cloud seeding to clear skies over the Beijing Olympics
There's even a company in the UK that offers a wedding package that includes cloud seeding
Can be used to burst rain clouds and make them
Disappear
Company claims they can guarantee a rain free wedding day
And that will only set you back about $150,000
As the conversation shifts away from the Cold War
To the present a threat of climate change
People are starting to talk about the use of geoengineering to fix the problem
Suggestions have been thrown around like
Brightening the clouds to reflect radiation back into space
Or spraying reflective particles into the stratosphere to cool down the planet
People propose giant space umbrella
We're even trying to change the orbit of the Earth
So that it's
Slightly farther from the Sun
Changing the weather is one thing
But changing the climate on a permanent scale is next level modeling
Many people are highly doubt
The geoengineering can be used effectively
Play to stop the warming of our planet
Anything we try would be extremely experimental
With unknown consequence
That's the main issue do we have a right to mess around with a right to Tinker with things
Anilao things just happen
What is the free market or some some go engineer who wants to
Try some new trick
Do we have the right to do that when we going to have global
Weather systems are so complex
It's pretty much hubris to think we can intervene in predictable ways
But as long as the stakes are high
Whether it's a war
Are you now
Fate of the planet
People will probably keep
Keep trying
Kirk Olson and I talked about the unintended reuse of bomb fragments in Southeast Asia
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
So as we mentioned in the story the US military has described their efforts at cloud seeding
In and around Vietnam
Has this alternative to bombing
A way to muddy up the trails with rain instead of dropping
Deadly explosion
But in reality
Us airplanes dump
Tons and tons of bombs in Southeast Asia during the Vietnam War era
Minions
Exploded on impact
Tactic requested is here to talk about
The ones that didn't
And the unexpected ways
They were reused and incorporated into the built landscape
In the 1960s and 70s
Is the US covertly dropped
Hundreds of millions of bombs
More bombs were dropped
In Europe during World War II
In the wake of this conflict which
Can be called The Secret War this small Asian Nation
The morbid
Distinction of being the most bombed country
Per capita in world
And it still
Holds that
It's hard to wrap my mind around the counter
Hundreds of millions a how is that even pause
Well a lot of the devices that got dropped work
Cluster bomb
Basically these consist of hollow metal shells that open up on the way down
And deploy hundreds of smaller explosive
Omelette
Which are about
The size of tennis ball
And the US flew over 500000 missions into Laos
To drop these and other types
Explosives
So the larger sell the big bomb is released the casing and it's his little
Bomblet seen inside the bigger shell that would
Spread out
Explode when they
Well they were designed to at least
But they actually had a really high failure
Is many is 1/3 of those bombers
Didn't detonate
An impact
Leaving the country littered with
Close to a hundred million unexploded device
And when the bombing finally stopped and 19
Les oceans were left to deal with the aftermath
So the begin cleaning the landscape but they also started collecting the shells in the scraps
They found
And putting them to use another
And you mean the bigger
Outer shell casings or these little bum
Little bit of both and other types of bombs to but those big hollow metal shells in particular yet they turned out to
To be really useful at least
The ones that were relatively intact
Some of the larger ones have been turned into things like
Canoes
Other mid-sized ones have been lined up
Form the walls of buildings or used as spilled flick
Tap houses off the ground
Orchid pots
Plants
And even the really small scrap can be melted down for other purposes
Is like making jewelry or silverware or cowbells or
Other things
And overtime
Finding recycling the shells in Scotts is actually grown into this unlikely National Industry
So around the Laotian Countryside you can see tons of Bombshells baked into built
This story has this patina
Of this uplifting swords to
Usher story
Really
Horrifying Legacy
But they have to deal with
These deadly devices that we dropped on
Yeah it's
It's really very sad and
Aside from the people who
Who died
Initially even those bombs were dropped
Tens of thousands of people that actually died
Duda detonations in the decade since
And even now hundreds of people are injured or killed
Each year
Explosion
Sometimes
Gather up
So they've been cleaning up for Renewal since 1970
We three are they anywhere close
How to clean up on
Not really
Non-profit organizations that are working on this problem actively
Still have to make that it will
Will take decades or even a Century II
Clean up the rest
And it's this Legacy in Paris
That is caused
Over a hundred Nations to get on board with this convention of cluster munition
Which is an international agreement.
To make or use or
Transfer cluster
And I take it the United
Is not one of the countries
That signed on to the convention.
Cluster munition
Correct the US military clearly didn't take away
Is some of the same lessons that other countries did from
What happened in the Vietnam War
Well it's
Fastening to see how people in Lost
Managed to make something useful out of these devices
Still this
Really tangible through four basic reminder of the horrors of
War
A few years back photographer Mark Watson encountered this phenomenon
On a journey through Laos
You can watch a video of the Riu samples that he found on our website at 99 pi
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Vivian Lee edited by Delaney Hall
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by xiaomi
Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Katie mingle is our senior producer Russell team is Emmett Fitzgerald
Avery trufelman Taryn Masa and me
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
We are supported by our listeners just like you
You find 99% of Des Moines discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars in the show at 9
Epi or run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But do you know what's better than all of those things
Our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com