99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On the University of Pennsylvania camp
There's this
Gorgeous old library
Which is the School of Design library of Fine Arts in architecture
It was designed by architect Frank
Furnace
Looks like a red brick and terracotta Palace
Producer Avery trufelman
It's got these leaded glass windows in this very elaborate roof
Articulated with lots of pointy
Ornaments
And a two-story rotunda reading room
According to its website it is a Seminole Library design
Expressive function
While merging the imagery of
Cathedral
And
Railroad state
It could be the sad for any number of scenes in Harry Potter
It's a National Historic Landmark
It was completed in 1890
So you may know the furnace library at that pandas
A wonderful 19th century
Building
This is Denise Scott Brown
Who studied urban planning
And then taught there
And at my first faculty meeting they were
Considering whether architecture schools should
Supposed to plan to demolish
The fiendish library
This is a 1961
Architects for variant
Tearing down old buildings
No one would dream of touching it now
But then I was a rebel and saying that
And there was a big debate
And the deed was on the other side he wanted it demolished
In 1960 Architects. We should be getting rid of old
Really architecture
Sure and constructing new modern efficient buildings of glass and steel in concrete
Denise
On the other hand
Was kind of over modernism
Nothing she didn't like glass and steel in concrete
She like the buildings themselves
She's just getting tired of the philosophies behind modernism
She's tired of Architects
Imposing their Sleek utopian Visions on people
Without first asking people what they wanted
It was
Stupid Innocents to say we don't have to listen to
Two people they don't know what
They want
We can tell them what they also want that we will be so good for them
And so in her
First ever faculty meeting
Denise took a stand
Imagine her
In her late twenties
Red hair and an accent shaped
Buy a childhood in South Africa and an education in London
She battled the dean
To convince the rest of the faculty
This old library
Should be saved
That there's something to observing and appreciating the architecture that's already around us
And she won them over the whole
Psycho she finally agreed with me but not
Before a lot of arguments
And
I'm sure all of that this young man came up to me and he said
I agreed with everything you said
And my name is Robert Venturi
And I said
Well why didn't you say something then
Robert Venturi
Another young faculty member
Didn't want to admit it at the meeting
It wasn't cool to be in Texas
Extravagant old buildings then
Inventory was already kind of an out
He was struggling
The people that would say well he shouldn't be there he's not like he likes history
He didn't go to Harvard while he went to
But you wasn't from a fancy family
And yes he was really into historical architecture
Ann in Denise Scott Brown he found
Kindred spirit
They began to share ideas and research
They were both very into mannerism
Which is a late Renaissance style of architecture that has a lot of complex decoration and exaggerated visual tricks
Not unlike the furnace Library
It's a labyrinth
Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi work clearly on the same page
They taught courses in conjunction with each other
From 1960 to 65
Iran 1 series
Listen here on the other
And we
Camden together
Collie get pain was so bold as to suggest
Denise
You should marry Robert
But it wasn't like
Denise was actually a young Widow at the
She lost her husband in a car crash
Pretty recent
She wasn't interested inventory that way
At least not yet
We were good friends
Don't forget I'd lost a husband I was a very sad
Person
Denise did
However
Want to take her friend Robert Venturi
Two very special place
The place she considered the ante modernism
A place
The most of her colleagues in architecture and urban planning looked at with
Stan
Las Vegas
Fabulous
And what happens in Vegas
Never really stays there
Together Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi
Define lessons in Las Vegas
That would spur a new chapter
In architecture
To this day architects
And turn their nose up at Las Vegas
Las Vegas is still a very
Controversial topic among architects
Typically dismiss the city
This is Stefan Al
Practicing architect and author of the book The Strip
Las Vegas and the architecture of the American dream
Everytime I tell my colleagues I study Las Vegas and I get a few frowns
From architecture perspective
It's a city that's known for neon
City known for candle decoration
Casino for kids
Exactly the opposite
A what
Conventionally trained architects
I would like
But people love Vegas
Last year there was about
45 million people that visited Las Vegas
And that was 10 million more than the City of Paris
To be clear here we're not talking about downtown Las Vegas
We're talking about the Las Vegas Strip
A long stretch of road flank
Bike Casino
Yeah so a lot of people don't know that this trip is actually not built in the city of Las Vegas is actually just outside
Site outside of city limits
And as a result developers are not as much restricted by
City zoning laws work
City Council
And they have more
Leeway so to say which is why the Vegas
Strip is never one static thing
It goes through radical changes
Almost every decade
Since the whole stretch of the strip is geared entirely to what will bring in the most Taurus
Is design for what's popular at a given time so I'll make as much money as possible
As soon as
One of the buildings is no longer profitable or as soon as they realize they can
Actually build a more profitable building that is worth for them to implode the previous building and build something new
And this is how biggest is always be
Constantly remaking itself depending on what tourist want
It's designed and redesigned over and over again
For its visitors
The very first Casino Hotel complex on the Strip was called El Rancho Vegas
I had a western theme
Literally part of the advertising was
Bring your wine
Western boots in your usn outfit
How you can wear your hat
In the 1940s
Western movies were popular
And the western themed made gambling seem a little more
Patriotic
Rugged
What cowboys did
Do you got to have gambling in a wild West Town
A real authentic
Wild West Town forever any Cowboys in Las Vegas and so it was from the very
Beginning Las Vegas architecture was
Where you could call
Fake and then in the 1950s as the
Fake Western fat got tired out
They traded it in for fake mid-century Suburban glamour
It really turn gambling into a Suburban vacation
There were all these glamorous bungalows
Kidney-shaped pools
But they all look more or less the same
So then came the sign
Starting with the Stardust Hotel and Casino
Big horizontal sign really big
Over 200 feet long
It looks like a giant explosion and their mind this was also. In which we see the space race
Start to begin up the ante on the competition between the hotels on the strip
And more massive hotels popped up with bigger and bigger sign
And it was a really kind of sophisticated technology that went into these structures
It was only because
The competition was was so intense and it was so much at stake
By the 1960s the Las Vegas Strip with a cacophony
I think eating Neon
All these huge jarring sign was calling out over each other
That's what the strip look like
When Denise Scott Brown first encounter.
I've had a cold shiver up my spine
And I said Is This Love or is this hate
I said I don't know
I said foot rabbit anyway before it goes
She first visited Vegas in 1980
C5
After she had left pain to take a job at Berkeley
Unlike the modernist
To it ignore a messy place like Las Vegas
Denise found herself
Curious about it
Given her background and urbanism in planning
She was interested in observing the
Habits
Las Vegas was
A place people voted for with their feet
They went there in droves
They really showed they liked
They even spent money to be in it
The 1960s trip was the exact opposite of what modern architects
The world should look like
It was loud
Garish and dazzling
It was full-blown populism
And this is what Denise loved about the strap
She knew she had to show Robert Ventura
Bob was the only person I invited to Las Vegas cuz
It was the only one interested
And then he just adored it
In 1966
Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi spent 4 days in Las Vegas
Marveling at it
When Bob and I
Went to Las Vegas
I'm have this wonderful time together bad
Xiaomi he became a much more relaxed human being
We took photographs we drove the strip we had music on Wii
Jobs in the desert and we took pictures of each other
You look at the joy and the faces of those pictures and you see what's happening
You can google pictures of Denise and Robert grinning on the strip
Yeah
You can really see it
We fell in love
5 years of working together
It happened in 4 days
Vegas
We were in a bar
Antoni we held him that's about all that have
And then we began to get more and more fond of each
After a little back and forth
He's got brown eventually move back
Back to the East Coast
And then
Montana Tech
I just said to hit will you marry me and he said yes and yes and yes
Robert Venturi and Denise Scott Brown got married in 1967
Get together
Yeah
But even though she was on the other side of the country
Denise wasn't done with Las Vegas
Not in the least
Anarchy changde Neeson Taken great pains to include the elements of observations
And what better spot to observe
In the strip
It was the epitome of
Brawl
Allowed advertisement
Shopping Center
It was
American culture
Steroid
Extreme cases usually up uricase
I think if you look at
Scientific study
It's awesome down that's right let's get the most
Stream version and then from that
We can
Nerd with the principals where I look for them in other places
She and Robert Venturi resolved to bring their students
The strip
So they can see it themselves
Venturi and Scott Brown plant a 12 week long Studio studying Las Vegas for 13 students
10 days of this course
Would actually be spent
Itself we will all puts up at the starter
Scott Brown inventory got comp rooms for them and all the students
Took full advantage of the freedom they had off campus
We didn't notice when we went into their
The smell of marijuana
Because I just didn't know that
Out in the field under Denise and Robert
I
The students did a lot of watching
Many many photographs
So which were taken from
From reclusive millionaire Howard Hughes helicopter
He made available and always use
Leatherface helicopter
That was very useful because very good pictures
And with the nieces help
But students finagled their way into the grand opening Gala of the Circus Circus
Kiss Casino
And they had got themselves dressed up
They went to the thrift
Shop
In Las Vegas
In the midst of all the fun
The students were still really engaged with the labor
A truly looking at
Students observe traffic patterns conducted interviews
And made maps and diagrams
Basically all the things architecture students would normally do
To observe Athens or Rome
But
Like this time they were sitting in drawing sketches of parking lot
We had a set of topics
Many of them were patents of distribution like
Where are churches in Las Vegas compared with New Haven where our wedding chapel
People did distribution map
Denis compared the strip
To a Bazaar
Our Marketplace
Built on a scale for cars
The market is afoot Marcus and you Caesar
The actual Goods in the window of the
You smell them when you arrive on the market
Put on the Strip instead of the sights and smells of items for sale or the merchants hollering and peddling goods
There are signs
Call out infection to you
What's the anatomy of a big Las Vegas sign that has its high reader it slow reader
How does that feel
In relationship
Small side where all of them put on the side
How do they draw you in where do you see them from
And it observing the strip
And the way cars and people navigate it
They found that Las Vegas
Worked
The sign served their purpose
Strip was navigable
It functioned in the midst of its apparent chaos
Like there would be an Arabian themed design for an Arabian themed Casino
And then use advertise the evenings performers in big lights
Everything was spelled out very clearly
In a way that was a
Appealing to people
And so
Robert Venturi
Anthony Scott Brown
All the maps and notes
Observations
Today in the Student Center
And together but they're teaching assistant and co-author Stephen Eisenhower
They put it all
In a book
A book published in 1972
Cold learning from Las Vegas
What happens next everyone reads that book
This is architecture and design critic Alexandra Lange
And she says learning from Las Vegas challenged architects
To take the architecture of Vegas
What they called the architecture of the American Highway
Serious
And that it too has a structure
And it too has lessons that we can learn from
And so let's stop being snobby and only
Kind of talking about architecture within architecture and look at what's actually out there in the world and what we can learn
It's not just saying hey Vegas is cool it's saying here's a whole approach
To the world that we actually live in
And truly everyone studying architecture read this book
Why do they catch on because people were searching for a way out of the dead end
The dead end of modernism
And this book written by kind of the coolest kids in architecture
Seems like it might be that way out
By 1980
Learning from Las Vegas becomes a text assigned in every architect
Is that
Is a huge deal because it means American architects
Can't ignore
The built environment
That's all around
Although Venturi got most of the
The credit I never get the famous all it's Robert Venturi and what's that wife doing hanging in there
But learning from Las Vegas to Rives from Denise's
Experience on the strip
Which she then invited Venturi along for
Not to mention Denise's background in observation
Planning and her believe that spaces should be designed with
Digital architecture needed to say something to the maximum number of people not just two people
Who were educated
In the themes
Architecture
Venturian Scott Brown loved the historical elements of architecture that anyone could recognize
And so they say you know what
People love houses with Gables people like their Banks to have columns out front
So let
Do that
Columns can signify that a building is important
Since they're associated with banks and government
Wrangler roof means that the building is a house
It was elements help people to understand the building
Architects should just go ahead and add them
Denise and Robert put some of these ideas into
Practicing their own
One of the more extreme examples is their design for the Children's Museum of Houston
They put these oversized Greek
Columns in the
Front with signal Night at the Museum
Because it's a children's museum
The Columns are Brite canary yellow
The Columns hold up on massive sign that says Museum in Big Red Letters
You don't have to wonder if you've made it to the right
It's pretty clear
And they did this for adult museums to freeze off of in Seattle Art Museum
A sign on the top of the building just says s a.m.
Seattle Art Museum
It is very big
I mean not all their buildings a giant overt signs on them
But the point is Robert Venturi and Denise Scott Brown we're not
Raid of signs
Do not afraid of color
No we're not afraid of
Historical motif
Their work
Inner architecture and writing
Is about making sure buildings were accessible and understandable to as many people as possible
And this morphed into one of the most controversial movements in architect
Postmodern
Post-modernism
Buildings to be communicative deeply meaningful and fun
Although the problem is a lot of designers
Focus on the Fun Park
So some postmodern architecture
Takes
Kind of the Jazz Inus
Vegas
Takes the colors take the Neon
That becomes one form of
Post-modernism
A lot of Architects and designers were just like
Oh cool now we can use neon and bright colors and big science
Xiamen historical Styles and details
Just for the fun of it
In other words it became part of the ascetic
The 80s
Bright colors
Gold shapes
This is what a lot of people mean by NF
Betika post-modernism
Just kind of goofy without substance
It goes in all of these different directions and I think
Denise Scott Brown really hate
Some of those directions because they don't have their interpretive
Quality.
They brought to their version of
Modernism
Andaz postmodernism became sillier and
Sillier
It strayed further and further away from what Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi were originally trying
Need to do
It became hard for clients to see how deeply intentional and thoughtful their work was
It wasn't like one Triumph to another after they wrote that book by any means
We probably
Had more work if we hadn't done all this
Their books they're building Champion places like the Las Vegas Strip
They're definitely times when they didn't have that many clients it was very difficult for them
To get work
Ultimately postmodernism's popularity was short-lived
What happened with post-modernism is it really did not last very long as an architectural movie
It has basically it
Tenure
Approximately 10 year Heyday you can
And say kind of early 80s early 90s and then it just goes really out of fashion
Clients
Sort of revert back
Two wanting things that look modernist
And architecture
Revert back
To its previous form
People go back to wanting faceless building
In shades of grey and black
Made of glass
And if people want it
Las Vegas will deliver it
Eliza published
The book learning from Las Vegas and Las Vegas becomes known as
Maybe took the birthplace of
Postmodernism
Celebrating signage and moving away from
Boring modernism this is actually when
Las Vegas turn
To the opposite
As ever Vegas was ahead of the Curve
The strip had already started to revert to corporate modern
Even before learning from Las Vegas
Was published
In 1967 the state of Nevada passes
The corporate gaming
Which allows big corporations and hotel chains
To own and operate casinos
Became a casino operator but on the Las Vegas Strip
And they
Built following their own aesthetic which was
Corporate modernism and it was precisely this
Style of architecture.
Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi lamented
That's a big iron
Of course this isn't the end of the story
The strip after all he's always Reinventing
Responding to what consumers want
The big glossy Towers continue to rise
Until
Steve Wynn's. A giant erupting volcano
In front of the Mirage Hotel
This brings in the Disneyland era
When Casino started to build a crazy expensive
Attractions
Treasure Island which had a big sinking pirate ship the big Cinderella Castle Excalibur
Let's call it vacationland
Fake Venice with fake canals and gondoliers who sing to you
Paris with a fake Eiffel Tower and then in the New Millennium Vegas welcome to a batch of new casinos
Designed by big-name prestigious architect
They're trying to appeal to Millennials by making Vegas look like a cutting-edge city
$15
And soon without a doubt
Strip will shapeshift again
This is all just to say
The Vegas Strip is in such a constant state of
Flux a renewal
Barely resembles a city that was chronicled in learning from Las Vegas
Almost Doesn't Matter that Vegas is
Changed
Postmodernism is an architectural movement with a short one
Has Denise Scott Brown herself is often said
Learning from Las Vegas
Is not about Las Vegas
Use critic Alexander Lanigan
Is to use
The tools in the critical tools like they are writing as
Critics of the American landscape
To apply to your landscape your own situation
Learning from Las Vegas
Has helped Architects open their minds
Reserve judgment
And learn
From the everyday built environment around them
If you do want to observe the changing ever-shifting state of the American landscape
Still no better place to see it
Las Vegas Strip
Every time I go to Las Vegas I see something new and
If you if you want to stay ahead of the curve as an architect
It's good every now and then to
To visit Las Vegas
Denise Scott Brown went back to Vegas a few more times
When is many of these changes
But it's been awhile now
I haven't been there recent
And what items
From the Disneyland theme park
Arrow was that they were very talented
But you do
We have always turned on designing a casino that's was nothing
2.4 Oz
But don't say no one else does
Easy stir Damiano sauce that school celebrate
Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi are still together
And now they live back in Philadelphia
Just a 30-minute drive away
From the red brick Library designed by Frank Furness
A wonderful 19th century
Mannerist building
Chaba Thai
Regeneration just made it into the architecture Library Network dream of touching it now
In 1986
Robert Venturi and Denise Scott Brown worked on the master plan
The restoration of the Furnace Library
The very building
That brought their life
And their ideas
Together
It's everyone's favorite architecture game duck or decorated shed
Right after this
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
IPic
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info slide podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
We're back in the studio with Avery Drummond
With a little addendum
To be learning from Las Vegas tour
This is one really famous take away from learning from Las Vegas
We didn't cover in the story
Because
Kind of eclipse is the rest of the book
Architects Tennessee
You had only one finding the dock on the Declaration shed we had 10 15 or 20 finding
And they have made to have ribs
The stuff well enough and learned how to use it
I'm one of those people
That
Love the concept of the duck versus the decorated shed
Just because as great name
I mean you can we can cut this out if we need to but
Should I give a shot of what I think it is and Vinny correct me
What's the definition of courage
Severe two types of building
There's a duck
Which is
A
Building with the form that represents the thing that's inside of it
And then there's decorated shed which is essentially a box
With a sign on
More or less
It gets so that's that it that is what it isn't Siri but then as you apply it to the real world if you look around looking for
Production decorated sheds
Yeah everytime I teach the deck in the decorated shed I have to
Think I'll and reread it and I profit
SRI Reddy
Strangely difficult
The design critic Alexander Wang is going to help us out a building that
Is a box
That could contain anything
And it has a sign out front
That indicates what happens
Inside so yeah pretty much a decoration that is pretty much what it sounds like
It's a simple
It's not a cereal box but it is a simple and generic building
With a sign or decoration on it
Like the Stardust Hotel
Which cities are staying at
That was a facade a mile long just
Blazing
Neon
And we woke drawn the back
I'm box at the back of this building is
Flawless decoration
Then Walter gropius ever dream job
And we call that the shed
So decorated sheds are actually quite common if you think of like a big box store
If it goes out of business in another business
They just changed
The sign and it
Completely functions
I think that the interesting thing
About
Learning from Las Vegas and Scott Brown inventories work
Is that what they're basically saying is like decorative Shades or not
A bad thing
That is one of the main points learning from Las Vegas is trying to prove that signs are really efficient
Way for building to communicate so we will getting this model of the shed for the place
But I was
Walking down
Architecture building
In New Haven and I looked up and I said you know
It's called No decoration but the whole thing is a piece of
Decoration
Which brings us to
The duck duck
So that's the idea of the whole building being a decoration
You know what
Call Duck I don't
Does actually there's a famous building on the side of the road in Long Island
Literally shaped
Like a duck and it's old duck
And it's sold duck eggs
Of course it sounds awesome.
And it doesn't really matter what
The shape is inside this route for old activity
I guess I'll know that even if it's shaped like a duck a lot of buildings
Shaped like the very thing they're selling that's
Pretty rare
There's one outside of where I grew up
Which is one of the reasons why I know
It resonated with
What is it
In
I lived for a stretch of my childhood in Newark Ohio
And outside Newark Ohio
Is the
Starts with an L basket company
I don't know what it's called
They sold
Baskets and they had a building
A big picture
I'd like one of those
Rare like
Pure forms of duck
That's so cool but that's the interesting thing is like
Frank gehry building
Things can technically be.
Frank areas like mr.
Because those are
Statement buildings that are not
Decorated for sale if I don't have ornaments on them
But they are built out as an entire piece of decoration in and of themselves
Looks like with Gary has he
Crazy
Curved metal Exteriors
That forced the interior is to accommodate it
So it's it's kind of counterintuitive cuz you
Would be inclined to think while modern buildings are sheds
Because they're very minimalist
But yeah there's an argument to be made that a lot of modernist architecture was very preoccupied with making
What they called the heroic and original architects
People like Paul Rudolph
And the brutalist
Made a building
It looks like
Did all kinds of crazy things to try to express what it did
Inside
But actually often made in a room that were unusable
Balconies and nobody would ever hang out on
But that's not to say
That ducks are bad
Sunbathing should be.
You know
I was sunbathing should have ducked like parts of them but was inside is less important than the outside
Airport buildings that need something on them to make them
Show from the air
Edward helps out
Do that job special but they better have a big red checkerboard pattern feather
No plane will fly into
It's for a while when we went to give a lecture and you should be someone dressed like a duck on the stage with
Text pictures of nice sign of kind of something
So
I guess you're pretty much right
What do you think anything
It widened my scope of what a duck
I can see why
Even if your
Really smart like I was your delaying
Is way smarter about architecture then than me or
Anyone in the building
You would kind of have to look it up
Like his Maybe
The Apple
Campus
IDOC
I mean I think there's a case to be made that
Are there any others
Edge cases that we could talk about
I kind of think like other hotels on the Las Vegas Strip you know
Like
Some of them really walk that line I'm picking for
Particularly of like New York New York
Hotel which has this
Play Books
Like the skyline of Manhattan
And I can't tell
If that is like
A front on a bunch of buildings you know it's hard to tell
What is the sign and what is the shape of the building when you get to the Vegas
And that mean the best form of nipples of both
I looked it up afterwards and it is the Longaberger Basket building that's in Newark Ohio
And it doesn't even look
Look like a giant picnic basket
It is no longer owned by the Longaberger company but
Fruit plants are
To preserve it
And all of its magnificent
Darkness
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman
Mix anti-corruption by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Delaney Hall is the senior editor Kurt Kolstad is the digital
Katie mingle is our senior producer
Crystal team includes Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me
Roman Mars
Special thanks this week to Adam Nathaniel Furman
With fact-checking
Bigram heishi
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective with the best most Innovative shows in all of podcast
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 pii
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
We have an explainer of a duck versus the decorated shed that Kurt wrote up on our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com