99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Oprah Winfrey's hair is an amazing and ever-changing
Object of design
Quick Google image search of her and you can see it in a dozen different styles
But there's a consistency to
Brand familiarity
I'll give you took over his face out of all those Google Images
So that all you could see was a series of pictures of hair
You still know it was her
And even though she's done weaves and braids and all sorts of styles
She's also a natural
Meaning she doesn't use chemical relaxers
Try to straighten her hair
I'm not actually something over and I have in common
That's producer Lila Day from the stoop
Which is about stories from across the black diaspora
And since I'm white guy with very little hair
I'm actually going to hand this one entirely over to her now
Oppa gets most of the credit for her amazing natural hair
To one person
Andre Walker hair for 18 years and I've been through some really good styles
Add a couple of bad years
The same person who knows your hair doing it all the time
Andre Walker first saw Oprah on her talk show
Am Chicago back in the 80s
I thought she was fantastic
And I was watching her show every morning
And I thought you know I want to get to know her so I sent her some flowers one day
Saying I'm dying to get my hands in your hair
Please give me a call
He didn't have to do much convincing to get the job
She called me the next day
And I'm thinking oh my God that was easy
Andre travel the globe with Oprah as she became one of the most important media figures in the world
He gave her basically every hairstyle imaginable
Chin length
Bob very layered and spiky that was one of my favorites
Flippy we did
A cover with an afro on her Magazine with the
Huge afro wig
That was a very popular God I can go on and on and on
Puppy on Oprah's hair Andres known for something else
A system that he created back in the 90s
To Market his line of hair care products
The system categorizes natural hair types
And it's come to be known as the hair chart
Andre Walker hair takes your Nash
We've never gone for
The hair typing chart consist of for hair types
Within each of those categories there are different
Subtypes
Types one is for straight hair
Takes two is for wavy hair types
3 is 4
Curly hair and type 4 is
For kinky hair
Go for the goal
By Andre Walker
Revolution for Kinky-Curly and textured hair
Andres hair chart shows each type of hair drawn-out and labeled
From bigger loopy curls to super tight course
You can actually cut off a small piece of your hair and compare it to the drawings on the chart
To figure out which one you are
What's considered before B
So I'm on the kinky or end of a cross back chair
M4 Andre it was all about selling his products
If your hair is like this you buy this product if it's like that you buy this other one your hair will feels so moist and touch
Hatchable you don't know what to do with you
Obviously
I found Andres chart after I decided to go natural
Like a lot of black women I spent years putting chemical relaxers in my hair to straighten it
It actually never even occurred to me not to relax my hair
Until I was living in Cuba where relaxers were hard to come by
And so one day in Cuba
I just decided to do
The big
Chop
To cut my hair and let it grow back natural
It felt like a big deal
For a while I didn't even know how to manage it
Sometimes I felt frumpy with my short tight hair that I couldn't even come through
I put on bright red lipstick and big hoop earrings
Anything to get through what some people call
The ugly face
All of this was a big change
Not just the hair but how people reacted to me
In Cuba I went from being called mulata which is more of a mixed girl
Negra which is black girl
I you look Negra now
But somehow I'm naked I didn't feel like a compliment
I felt pretty lost
So I turn to YouTube
To find a community of other Nacho
And there was Andre system being referenced
All over the place
What is your
Karyotype
To be like most
Frequently Asked question
4C hair is a beautiful
Creation
You Found Me
And it's most beautiful when you take care of her
The front portion of my hair is
See
Hundreds chart
Has gone Way Beyond his own line of hair care products
It's become the go-to way for many of us
I understand and talk about
I texturize my hair
But not everyone thinks Andres categories are a good thing
In fact I'm not sure they're good thing
But his chart
Has definitely got me thinking about a complicated relationship African Americans have with her hair
It's a complicated relationship
That goes way back
Thick kinky hair was considered a sign of health and wealth in parts of Africa
But in America
Skin tone and hair texture
Was used to divide enslaved African people
Light skin and straighter hair could mean more privileges
Like working in the house
And not in the field
This idea of good hair
And bad hair
All developed during slavery
Your hair was the closer it was too white textured hair
The better it was
Ayana Byrd is the co-author of hair story
Untangling the roots of black hair in America
And she says the common belief back then was
If you had straighter hair you probably had
More
White blood
Someone who didn't have straighter hair
After slavery ended
These racist beauty standards hang on
In the early 1900s
Some people try to straighten their hair by putting oil on it and then wrapping it with
Heated flannel
Mother's Reven wrapping their children's hair
I've been causing Burns
A lot of hair damage
Black churches in certain cities that would hang a column on the front door
And if your hair is you couldn't calm your hair with that then you couldn't worship
At that church
In the 1920s
Hot cam for used to treat in hair
And then came a hairstyle known as The Conch
You can see it on famous jazz musicians like Cab Calloway and Duke Ellington
The Conch was the name of the style
But it was also the name of the relaxer itself
Which was made with a harsh chemical
Cut sodium hydroxide
Rely
And it's essentially just ate away at your hair and your scalp and cause a lot of serious Burns
And they were not safe
Some people made their own conch
Sometimes with two white potatoes and egg and Red Devil brand lye
A combo that left many Scouts bleeding
The conky eventually went out of style
But relaxers made with sodium hydroxide continued on and became more and more popular
The wash-and-set and under the dryer with a magazine
Became up very common image in Black salons
But then
In the 1960s
Something different started Rising
The Civil Rights Movement brought on the beginning of a new shift
It was all about embracing black
And this man embracing your natural hair
My mom aunties they all do the big chop
Heading out the relaxers and wearing their afros
Loud and proud
Does rabbit hear myself all of us were born without hair like this
And we just wear like this
This is an interview from 1968 with former Black Panther
Kathleen Cleaver
We're told that only white people were beautiful only straight hair light eyes
Light skin
Beautiful
And so
Black women with try everything they could straighten their hair lightening skin to look as much like white women
Dickinson's changed because black people are where and
White people aware of the two because white people now one not perfect they won't wigs like this
Isn't it beautiful
Natural hair and afros were everywhere
From The Fluffy froze of the Jackson 5 to White celebrities like Barbra Streisand
Copying from
Was the first time that the relaxer industry
The chemical relaxer industry is really taking a hit
Financially
And not as many people were chemically
Straightening their hair
Instead of straighteners
For the first time people racing products that were meant to
The compliment their natural hair
Like Afro Sheen
Which gave the afro a bit more shine
I made it glisten like a Halo in the sunlight
Even if I froze continue to be an important Style
In the 1980s
A new chemical hairdo was on the rise
Sexy
1 2 3
A Jheri curl created a bigger looser curl pattern
It was a turn away from the political statement of Afro
The Jheri curl
Was all about fun
So the ads really shifted away
I from having anything to do with
Black culture and community building and black identity and some more to just
Neon colors
Partying in Lake
All of the advertising for Jerry curls more about the 2nd Precinct
This fun
Ez2go Style
Although nothing about the Jheri curl was easy
Jerry curls were the most product
Heavy
Hairstyle
That I think any people have ever known black people white people doesn't matter like to have a Jerry curl you had to have
All that activator in
It's so much stuff and you had to use it every single day
The Jheri curl was a very
Moisturize Style
The activator that you had to put in your hair everyday with drippy and greasy and your pillow would be
Be stained with it
Wearing a shower cap in public was
Fight normal
I know all of this
Because when I was a kid
I had one
When a Jerry curl fade it out regular old relaxers were still an option
And I went back to a relaxer to
Then in 2009 Comedian Chris Rock produced a documentary called
Good hair
After his daughter asked him
Daddy how come I don't have good hair
In the documentary he refers to chemical relaxers as creamy crack
Because they're applied in a white paste and even though they're toxic
Some people
Can't seem to
Quit them
In one scene he shows just how harsh the chemicals found in many relaxers can be he needs help with this camera
Who demonstrates how sodium hydroxide can eat through just about anything
3 years
Skin the chicken is your skin
So it'll go from
My brown skin
Down to the white meat
Right wow
Now you realize this goes in people's head start
Yeah people in black people
Black women
Some men
Morris Day
Prince
Put sodium hydroxide in their hair
To straighten it out
Why do they do that
Tulip White
You talked about UC
How is some head come in
Tighter than it may be like a 3/4
Do you mind
Got another Dingle Smith
And I'm with her and her Salon in Boston
Which amazingly is called
Girlfriend
Hook me up salon
Everybody was saying girlfriend you hooked me
That's how I came up with
Smith tells me that even though the Chris Rock movie brought up some deep-rooted stuff that we need to talk about
It also did actually affect her business
People used to come in every 6 to 8 weeks to get relaxers
Some women would spend well over $1,000 a year on regular treatments in salon
I think the Chris Rock movie
Had an effect on all that
For a minute I was bad at a cousin
Why because it was affecting my money
Everybody
Started
Going
You're mean so
Impact on me with me having chemical client
Goodnight and creamy crack
Today black consumer spending on relaxers is down 30% since 2011
And this brings us back to Andre Walker's hair chart
All of these newly natural people
I getting on YouTube for advice
I'm discovering the chart unbeknownst to me I was on the internet one day and
Pence
List by reading some bloggers and they were referring to
Andre Walker hair typing system in like
Did I do that except the one I wrote about in my book
These days Oliver YouTube their people referencing Andres chart
Which remember categorizes hair from 1 to 4
When a being looser curls
M4c being the tightest
I'm just going to be braiding my hair
So I can get
My Afro
To be like rounded
Into the front
Their videos on the best creams for a 4B twist out
Or how many times a week you should wash your 3B hair
Order
Protective styles for your 4C hair
At first I found this all really helpful and positive
I mean it's great that more people are going natural
And it's great that there's a system to help them to do it
But then a few people started noticing that even in this new online community of natural
A lot of the videos were just reinforcing old bias about straighter hair being better
The videos often instruct women about how to go from very kinky hair to less kinky
Straighter hair
So like from a 4C to 3B without using chemicals
But still implying that
Straighter is better
Serenity hair like vest
Terminating a campaign
But you do see
Sophie bouncy curly hair
An old hag campaign
Are people that myself. You had that I literally cannot get my hand through it so I'll problem is unlocked
The same
We should be given room to speak
That's a plus one flower
A popular blogger
Who makes a lot of Straight Talk self-care types of videos
People like ourselves
You don't have hair that grows downwards our hair grows
Even if my hair
It feels the slumflower and others
Like online natural hair talk
Is mostly about how to transform what we have into something else
Something a little looser
That's not what our hair naturally does
And they're using Audrey's chart to do it
There has been a lot of criticism against a lot of natural hair websites
But they focus too much on quote-unquote 3B hair as opposed to 4C hair
And that the tighter
Your crawl
Pattern is and the kinky or your hair is the less represent it you are on the site
One woman I talked to said the chart feels to her like a modern-day pencil test
Which was a test used in apartheid South Africa
To figure out if someone was white or black
If you put a pencil in someone's hair
And the pencil fell out
The person passed
And was considered white
Skywalker says he just wanted to make a variety of products for different kinds of hair
It wasn't all his intention to create a hierarchy
People have asked me why did I label
Straight hair is number one in kinky hair is number
For I also asked him
But my answer to that is
It's going from zero texture to highly textured so going from one
Being straight to for being the kinkiest
And I've had people
That have been very sensitive about that
Because
They thought that I was given kinky hair
Left
Important
By putting it in number four
And giving straight hair more important by being number one
But that just goes to show you how sensitive
You know hair is hair and texture is
You know for a lot of people
It's true
It's so so sensitive
And even though a lot more women are going natural
There are still so many who just don't want to
Maybe they like the way their hair look straightened or find it easier to manage
Or just don't want to deal with other people's reactions to their natural hair
Pocket girlfriend hooked me up hair salon event voice of some guy
Says she isn't the least bit concerned with Andres hair chart
Because she doesn't want to go natural
I don't know that
Look
I feel is not for me
There's just this
Should I say fear
Or discomfort
You know I'm not going to show up to an interview with braids
Or fro or anything like that
My hair is going to be
As straight as it possibly can be
Because as much as
I like it or don't like it
We still live in a society where
Our hair is not accepted
For what it is in
You have to
To play the game to win it
There is
So much racism and colorism and years of painful history Tangled Up in all of this
It's deeply personal
And for those of us who have decided to go natural
It would be nice to see the hair conversation shift away from how to change our hair
And more towards how to manage the natural texture we were born with
Because my hair
It's still a crown
No matter where on the chart I land
Clima de decodes The Proud Lady symbol
Right after this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sand
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
Things we love to do on our show is decode little symbol
What's that you see out in the design world
And you're here to tell us about the
Our lady symbol
What is the Providence
The Proud Lady symbol
Is a symbol of this
Black woman
What day is longlac
Behind her and her head is how proud
And you can see the symbol on the back of some hair care products
And I actually grew up seeing symbol everywhere I just thought was part of you know
All the brands
But it's actually not that has a very sweet
Okay what's the point
There is an organization called the American Health and Beauty Athens
And they were founded in the 80s after a lot of black hair care products were kind of getting lost
Lost in the consumer Market they were big corporations like redlon and Johnson and Johnson
And they were sort of taking over the black hair care business so they created
The Proud Lady symbol
To let people know that it's a black owned business
Oh okay so what do you what do you have in your hand there
Pink therapeutic conditioning hairdress I haven't used it yeah you say use less words when I was a kid but there's the
Probability symbol right on the back near the barcode
And yeah it says and really tiny little writing what you said
If I can stay at
The Proud Lady 100% black owned
That's great
To this day do you look for that and
Make your choices based on that I never have you know and it was just doing this piece that I was like all that symbolize
I went to the hairdresser when I looked for it
Over and over and over and over again
And I only saw it on a couple of products and I also
I don't know if it's it's obviously not used as much as it used to be but I kind of missing that symbol
So if you want to make informed choices
Look for Brown face she looks Brown
99percentinvisible with Bruce this week by Lila Day from the stoop mix and Tech production by Sharif Youssef with help from senior
Predator Delaney Hall
Music by Shawn Rio Kolstad is the digital Direct
The rest of Team includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald
And me
Roman Mars
The soup podcast is stories from across the black diaspora
Hosted by Lila day and her not bomb
It's conversations about Blackness that aren't talked about enough
Like is it
Appropriation
African American
Where African clothing
What it means when
You sound White
You can subscribe the stoop wherever you get your podcast
99% invisible is a product of kalw in San Francisco in produce
Radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX the collective at the best most Innovative shows in all of podcast
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
You by 99%
Stop showing Facebook you treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi or run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit
2 but our true home on the internet
Is 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com