99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Coffee east coast of Mainland Canada
Is the island of Newfoundland
The island is as far east as you can go and still be in Canada
So far east in fact that it has
Stone time zone
Half an hour later than anywhere else
If you seen a photograph of the island
Is probably the one that went viral last year
A small village on the eastern coast
In the foreground are Rolling Hills in a couple of houses
In the background
A gigantic
Iceberg
Float Spa
On the choppy blue sea
Yeah icebergs Float by occasionally
But that one was
Actually scary bear
Anais pronunciation of Newfoundland by the way
A lot of people say Newfoundland
And it's a bit of a sore spot without locals
Betty's Newfoundland native
Luke Quinton
And I want to take us to a different part of the island
To a little town on the northeastern side called
Gander
No Looking Back eyes are all the 20 years old
Condors how do I change
It's Christmas Eve 1972 Indian Blackmore's working
My name is Ian Blackmore and I was
Photographer with the gander Beacon after I finished
High School in before I went to college
Contrato
Ian's co-worker Gerald vokey was an editor on the same local paper
He's going to help tell the story
It was Christmas Eve
And their mother was
You know getting things ready for Santa Claus
Gerald was home that day in 1972
His family is getting ready for Christmas and he wants to get his daughter out of the house
So they decided to go hang out at the local Airport
As you do when you live in a tiny town in Canada
Airport is the best thing around
Also this is not a normal Airport
But we'll get to that soon
You never knew what the airport being up there who am I
Come through at any given time
Regardless of our the day or
Night or whatever
Kevin Gerald got to the Gander Airport
He started asking around
Astrid idiot
The security there you know what was going on
And they said that
Fidel Castro
It's here and I see why
Fidel Castro was there in the airport and he was more or less just
Hanging out
I had dinner with a
Yeah in the dining room. Shirley traditional fatigues
Women's combat boots
Spring fatigue snow metals or nothing just
Said playing uniform
Turned out Castro had a pretty long layover
So at some point he basically says
Give me a tour of your town
He wanted to see the town
Sew-in in Gerald and Fidel Castro all pylons and cars and go driving around the little town until they come
Come across a kid
Sledding there is a young fellow with his
Dog and probably another friend there and they were taking turns going down on there
Bog
Course mr. Castro decided that
That book that arresting and figured he might
Siwa
Thing was and how it worked
Nothing at cameliard snow
Castro gets on his sled and starts down the hill
Annie Blackmore snaps a picture
I got ahead of him before he started on the slide down so I was in position for the catch him on his way.
Photograph
Ian Blackmore's photograph of Fidel Castro sledding with end up in time Maggie
And the amazing thing about this anecdote isn't how unique it was
For Gander
But he'll totally normal
The gander airport was used to hosting really famous people from all over the world
It wasn't just a tiny airport in some Tiny Town
It was a very large very important airport in some Tiny Town
But before we hear how this place came to be
I want to take you inside the airport
Because it's an incredible building
Okay Airport
Beginner airport you such a mid-century modern Time Capsule that I actually think I could bring up some Lounge music right now
This place is straight out of an episode of Mad Men
Mad Men with
Newfoundlander accent
If you follow me across here
Over on the
Capron Jerry cram is a commissionaire at the gander Airport
The job is part fixer
Part security guard
Jeriel probably be the one to give you a tour
If you ask her ass flooring is all from Healy
Right here is what we called the
The birds of welcome
Jerry's pointing at a bronze sculpture of seven birds that greets you when you walk into the lounge
The blue and the gray Furniture is all from the late 50s early 60s
The international Lounge of the gander airport is this big area space
Super high ceiling
And when you walk in your immediately a wash
In the orange glow the 1950s
Vinyl chairs and couches are arranged in U shape seating
They were designed by famous mid-century designers like Charles and Ray Eames and Robin bush
The gander International Lounge has been called the single most important modernist room
In Canada
Even the bathrooms are their own amazing time
The women's restroom especially
Jerry calls out a warning
So that we can go in
We're good to go
This is not a gross airport bathroom
It's beautiful mid-century luxury
There's a row of swivel chairs in front of a counter and a wall-sized me
It is two showers because he has
People used to shower
At the airport
There is two showers in this way
As well as
But now you can say you were in the washroom
Aternos being on June 19th 1959
When is International Lounge of the gander airport opened in 1959
The Queen of England herself came for the opening
And yeah the townspeople hobnob with her to
A lot has happened in this Airport
And the story of how it came to be and what it's become is really also
Story about the history of air travel
Finance
Because the shortest way
You've got to look at it on the glow
Is a trace a direct course from New York to Paris
You'll see that it takes you right over nothing
Remember Lindbergh
In the 1920s before Gander exist
Newfoundland grassy Fields were the jumping off points for transatlantic Daredevil pilot
Amelia Earhart Alcock and Brown Lindbergh all of them
Because it was so far east
It made sense to start there if you were worried about getting across the Atlantic with enough fuel
Eventually the British government which control Newfoundland
The time
Started to take note
Maybe there is something to this whole air travel thing
In 1936 the British shows what was then basically a patch of woods on the Eastern side of Newfoundland
As the site for over a million square yards of runways
By the spring of 1938 the gander airport was fully operational but the massive runways were mostly on you
There just weren't enough
Planes in operation that could actually survive
Crossing of the Atlantic Ocean
It was a very very risky
Attorney
In the two decades before the war
Only a hundred planes across the Atlantic
50 others had tried
And fail
People that died
In the 1939 World War II began in Europe in Allied Force
Wanted his many fighter planes if they could get their hands
Americans and Canadians have been shipping planes over by boat
But that wasn't working out so well they were being torpedoed by the Year by German submarines
Rare finds Denver actually making it over
Can UK
That's historian Informer air dispatcher Dean call
And he says to get planes to the UK the British had to come up with a new idea
They would have to put up what we call a bladder inside it was a
Spare fuel tank basically
To give them enough is enough fuel to make Crossing
Process of flying the planes from Gander to Scotland
Began in 1940
And was called
Eureka Math
The first Crossing was 7 playing
And it took place in a freezing night in November
The pilot had to fly in the dark
Because lights could alert the Germans
Miraculously all seven made
But that was just the first day
Over the course of the war 20,000 planes were brought to Gander to be flown across the Atlantic for the war
Some days are being hunted airplanes that would go over
Churchill's even quoted at one point in
Refer to Gander is the largest aircraft carrier in the North Atlantic
I guess it was the turning point of the war really trust for Britain
Jenna was making history even though at the
The time there was no actual town
Gander say there people living between
Intersections of runways
That's where the
Americans are the Canadians in the British had built
Morton Buildings
Printables of former aircraft
Controller at Gander
History of the airport
And he says the early town of Gander was basically just a
If you live in court
Right next to the runway
I will show you in a hundred yards or so or even closer than that
And I made a hell of a lot of noise it was a those aircraft
Because the gander airport started as a military operation
It wasn't until the war was over and civilian air travel began
They decided to build a separate Town away from the runway
And then in the late 1950s the Canadian government built that fancy International Lounge
At the airport
In 1958 just a year before the new Lounge open
Jets like the de Havilland comet in the DC 8 rent reduced
These planes could make the long Trek across the Atlantic without having to stop and refuel in Gander
But they took a while to go mainstream
And 4 years
Gander served as a stopping
For international travel
These are the Glory Days of candor
When celebrities from all over the world would wind up stopping through on their way to or from the state
The Beatles first step in North America wasn't in New York
It was in Gander Newfoundland
The gander airport became by far
The hottest place to be in Gander
Oh yeah used to go hang around up there and watch the
What's the people coming in on the plane
Escalator
It was a hotspot
John beard grew up in Gander
Everything revolves around the airport mean that was 1 in
It's a quieter place now than it was in
In the 1960s air travel was still pretty exclusive
A lot of North American tourists
Still travel to Europe
Bicep
But celebrities and heads of state from all over the world were paying big bucks
The fly
And many of them were stopping and gander
In that beautiful mid-century modern Lounge
A lot of famous people who came to the Gander airport tried to go unnoticed
But some really one of the cocktail from the bar
If they were in the airport bar they probably were interacting with the
People of Gander
Security
Pretty Wings back then
To say the least
I'm at the
Marilyn Monroe
Bob Hope
Kings and queens of Summer berries country's king of Jordan
King of Saudi Arabia Mikhail Gorbachev Macho Man Randy Savage
I met President Bush
That's the former mayor of Gander Claudel
The Queen of England
Flu
With Prince Philip
On a chopper
The locals also love to tell a story about Frank Sinatra trying to cut in line
The airport bar
Getting told to go to the back
But it wasn't just a scene of people drinking cocktails on their way to London
By the late 1960s most commercial Jets could make it across the Atlantic without needing to refuel but gander
Was still serving an important role in international travel
Especially to communist country
Please who couldn't fly to the US or use at their space
Gander was D major stopping point between Moscow and Havana
But this occasionally invited defect
Seeking asylum in Canada
And in particular the fair number from Cuba
That's Gary vokey Gerald Loki's son
And he said sometimes people would get off their plane coming from Cuba or Bulgaria
Or some other communist country and seek Asylum
Not that this was easy
Vokey remembers witnessing one incident in particular in which a woman from a Cuban
Attempted to escape down the lounge escalator to Canadian authorities
Well the Cuban flight crew tried stopper
They had lady hold buyer fees
The Canadians Hatter
Ahold buyer Huebner arm
So she was upside down
Going up the escalator
And
She had a dress on her dress was back over
Riverhead
It nearly turned violent and it was
For me as a kid it was one of most iconic things I've ever seen
Residents of Gander life was also about living alongside people from all over the world who work for the airlines
Aeroflot the Russian airliner had over a hundred and fifty crew in-flight planners in Candor alone
Gander
In its day
Was
A lot more multi
Cultural
Then a bigger cities in Canada
Did the Brits have people there Germans had people there tours
Canadian military
Cubans and Russians
Everybody Mingle
Particular Cubans were famous for buying find bicycles and then shipping them back to
Back to Cuba
The airport turn cancer into an amazingly diverse play
And Beyond
It was a portal from the town
To the rest of the world
There are stories about local people with the right connections shopping on last minute flights
Cuba
And Europe
In New York City
Just by clearing
With the captain
And maybe it was all those trips to New York that prepare the people of Gander for September 11th
As much as mention we have a breaking news story to tell you about apparently a plane has Jeff
Crashed into the World Trade Center here in New York City at
Happened just
A few moments
Testing my wife's sister
Had the news on in the morning
He said it looks like an airplane
Crashed in the
What are the buildings in New York
In the morning of September 11
An unprecedented decision was made to close all American airspace
Hundreds of flights were diverted to land at airports in Canada
I was only going about 10 minutes from the town manager called me and said that
You better come in
We may be getting some playing
As the plane came in one by one
The people of Gander gathered
Outside the airport
What to watch
Well I'm quite remarkable actually because you would see airplanes airplanes aircraft
Miles and miles and miles in the distance
Esl lineup
Tallinn
So it was quite a remarkable scene
38 planes and nearly seven thousand passengers ended up in Gander
They called the stranded visitors
The plain people
When people weren't there just for a few hours
They were there for three days
And they got nothing
The passengers weren't allowed to take their luggage so
It arrived in Gander with nothing but the clothes on their backs
After each passenger was registered with the Red Cross
A loose network of volunteers from Gander and nearby communities
Provided thousands of hot meals
Toiletries and prescriptions
To the plane
Bus drivers who were on strike came back to work to drive them around town
It was a job I was born
Howard job fair how our people came
Truancy
We are here we are here to help you
Until you're ready to leave
Gander has 500 hotel rooms
7000 new gas
The population of the little town had nearly doubled overnight
It's a residence
Stepped up
Mental people in
And yes there was people took people into their homes
Even though we were told
Not to do that because at that time
They didn't know how widespread that this terrorist attack
Would they
Do they have no food
Some of the stranded passengers ended up forming strong bonds with their hosts
At least one marriage is reported to a Combat Evolved
And a bunch of friendship
One group of plain people who stayed at a high school
Stardust
That's not worth over $1000000
The passengers organized all this on their flight home
After they finally got cleared to leave Gander
Even today we still have people come back to visit people in people's homes that stayed here we have people in Gander that goes to the
U.s. 11-story is where the famous because the Broadway musical come from away
In which the gander mayor Claude Elliott
Is the central character
Andres just five or six of us from the community that
Portrayed in that place
Represent this whole community
Well he's not like me I mean I'm beautiful okay about tetanus
American
I understand
These days the gander airport is pretty quiet
Do people
It's never quite as packed I guess it wants
I know
That's Luke injury cramp
Inside ear
Are we still getting International traffic today
But they're nowhere near the extent before they had to stop somewhere to refill
Refuel
But now you got the planes that can go on without
Have him to stop
St John's the capital of Newfoundland has the Island's major International Airport now
And aside from a few daily flights
Gander traffic is mostly military planes and emergency landing
Between the military base the air traffic control center in the airport
Gander has found ways to stay afloat
A few years ago
The airport Authority was thinking of tearing down the international lamb
I'm building something small
And much much uglier
But there was a huge outcry from architecture enthusiast
Around the world
Full disclosure I was one of them
In the end thanks to organizing by people like Luke
The mid-century Time Capsule that is the international Lounge was saved
And Jerry cram promises it will stay that way
Party words
Mark my words but I'm not always going to be around either so
And so as long as Jerry cram is round
The international Lounge stands as a kind of Monument to a bygone era
Mine was luxurious
When you didn't have to take your shoes off to go through security
When actually
There was no such thing as security
When the bar in your Airport terminal
Was open to anyone
Ticket or not
And if Sinatra cut in front of you in line
You just tell him
Please
Wichita
What do those big numbers painted on Airport runways really mean
Kurt Kolstad will decode them for you
Right after this
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
So a few years back the Oakland International Airport changed
Two of its Runway number
27 peking 28 +
29b
99 guys on Kirk Kolstad lives in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
And he's here to explain why it was really important that they make that change
First though you have to understand how
Runway numbering work
Airports around the world use this Universal system
That's based off Earth's magnetic north
So basically you
Figure out the
Magnetic compass direction of the runway up to 360 degrees
Then you round that off to the nearest
10 and then drop the zero at the end
And and then you have your number
I can see you in for the sub numbers one
236 instead of
All right that's it and each one way as a complimentary number to that goes in the other tracks
And that's of course I 180 degrees difference
So Runway number 18 is the flipside of wrongdoing number
And so on sofa
And if you see letters
That actually means there are multiple runways
Running parallel to each other
So Alice for the left
Are for the rain
And if there's one in the middle they use letter C for a center
So
By necessity
If it was 18 L the other side would read
Pixar
Okay I'm going to make that don't make sense
No it's not obvious to me why they do use
Compass directions rather than just
Then bring them one two and three
Will you do with all the high-tech stuff that guides plates fees.
Magnetic directions serve as a kind of backups
Help planes land in case something goes wrong
Also make it easy for pilots on the ground to double-check that their Runway and compass
Online before they take off
They know they're in the right place doing the right thing
Do it all else fails
You can use a compass
It begs the question
Why
Do the numbers
Ever change
That's the really crazy part
I knew that
The planet's magnetic poles reverse every few hundred thousand years
But they're also be smaller but significant ships going on
Constantly
And we tend to think of North in terms of true north
That is no single point of the top of a globe or map
Compass reading of magnetic north differs from one place to the next
And
It moves around all the time too
By the flows of the Earth
Molten metal outer core
And when those cumulative changes are big enough
Then the airports have to repaint the runways or the numbers don't make sense anymore
Gradle could just be
It goes from point for 2.6 and that tips in the other direction
Right
Around 3
And these ships happen even faster closer to the poles so airports that are really part of the North or really hard as a child
Actually have to make these changes more often
I just have to keep an eye on this for their own sake because if they're traveling on a plane they want to make sure these things are right
And it turns out it's a huge project magnetic monitoring stations all around the world
And satellites that also help keep track
I was actually just talked to my dad about this
He's a geophysicist
And apparently the poles may also Rivers entirely again soon
It's hard to say
And when that happens it could actually cause problems for the world's electrical grids
Among other things not to mention causing entire repainting of airport
I need when you say soon what do you mean by soon should I be
Prepping right now
Well if you look at the historical record we're actually overdue already but it could still be thousands of years
Soon in get out geological time can be pretty long in terms of
Ceiling tile
Buyer can the soup is what your say
I mean well if you want to geek out with more about Runway fonts and other
Flight related design details you can find Kurt's article on our website
It's 99 pi
. org
99percentinvisible with Quentin and Senior producer Katie mingle mix into production by Sharif
YouTube music by Shawn real
Delaney hall is the senior editor kurt kohlstedt is the digital director
Dresser team is Emmett Fitzgerald Avery trufelman Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all
Paula podcast
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible and join discussions about the show on Facebook he tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99.
Yeah I work on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But you're always welcome over at our place at 9 IPI
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com