99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The laugh track was ubiquitous on television sitcoms
But nearly 2000 it began to disappear
What happened
How do we get from the rock is canned laughter of The Beverly Hillbillies
To be silent slide
Joke every 20 seconds of 30 Rock
The Curious story of the laugh track starts with one man who created the laugh track as a homemade piece of technology that took over the
The sound of television
And then
A lot of fashion with the rise of a more modern sense of humor
What happened to the laugh track is just one of a cultural Mysteries that are being explored on slates new monthly podcast
Decoder ring
Here presenting the first episode of decoder ring
Call Black Box
Is host
Willa paskin
Eight-years-old
You come home from school
Turn on the TV and watch the Pink Panther show it was 1982 and Paul was watching the show
Syndication on WGN Chicago
Some channels are versions of the last track and some are Persians without
I always watch the ones that had the laughter
Because it was
I guess it's a child of this community
I said all these people watching with me and
They sound like adults
You don't sound like you
He left the show so much that you would tape it but he didn't have a VCR
Who would use a tape recorder when the only captured the sound
Even though the Pink Panther show has very little dialogue
What you been listening to
That's mostly what the pink panther sounds like
What I was doing was allowing myself to hear the last rather watch the show
Visually
Like watching shows with your eyes closed
Yeah basically start
Who are these people
Laughing
Why are they laughing the same Waters
Pause early encounters with a pink panther Foster a lifelong interest in last track
Paul lives in LA and works as an account manager at an insurance company
These are passionate last track hobbyist
Paul taught himself everything about laugh track
How they're made
Who made them the difference between them even how to make them for himself
The Monkees is a great
Show the think of cuz they killed the laugh track halfway
The second season
One of my goals in life
History of the laugh track
And not just light up
Try to add it as it was
Using those same laughs
It's really a very strange obsession because there so few people use
Until it too but I love Rico
I love Iceland
These clips
Putting them on anything
What are the shows that Paul Tinker around with is the ABC sitcom Modern Family
It doesn't have a laugh
Sepulveda
I just never did not like me before
Thomas Davis gym teacher
She's a teaching what doctor Seuss's to Medicine I think she don't like you
Modern Family premiered in 2009
But even had arrived just five years earlier it would have sounded something like that
From the 1950s to the early 2000s sitcoms had laugh track
.
And then when last tax free shows like Arrested Development and the American version of the office made it to network TV they mostly just
Most it come today don't have one
Except for a few big heads
Like The Big Bang Theory and reboots like Roseanne
We talked about last night's now it's mostly to make jokes about them
Phone towers going up and every show have a laugh track
People didn't talk about them very much
They're kind of a c
Secret so few people knew about it were disgusted
Everybody hears that everybody is aware
Why won't anybody talk about it
Today
We're going to talk about it
Growing up I never thought much about the laugh track one way or another they were just always there
Does a TV critic iWatch laugh tracks become contentious and deeply uncool
It's always fascinated me that something we barely notice for so long
Technically maybe even kind of like
Become so annoying to so many people so quickly
What changed
Why do they exist in the first place
Do we just realize they were really lame and if so what took you so long
Translate magazine this is decoder in a show about cracking cultural Mysteries
I'm play TV critic Willa paskin and every month I'll take a cultural object idea or habit
And try to figure out where it comes from
What it means and why it matters
Today
What happened to the laugh track
Imagine it's the 1950s you've just gotten your very first television set
A waste of time and it's a size of Euro with wood paneling and a couple of tiles on the side
You set it up in the living room and you call him the whole family and you turn it on
Too late now
The ladies and gentlemen
I must
The Jack Benny Program
Original hit radio show
Is there Easter Bunny a one-time Vaudeville performer and comedian as a version of himself
Radio
And now that show from the radio it's on your television
Even though you've heard it before you've never seen anything like it
Before when you watch a performance it was in public with an audience
And now it's happening in your house
Think about how strange
I knew that
And then listen
You hear it
Something recognizable
Something reassuring
Tells you what you're watching
It was my sponsor who didn't have the nerve
That's almost early TV comedies recorded in front of a live audience often times and studios in New York
By the early 50s as a TV industry moved away from New York and into Hollywood
Executives wanted to move away from the traditional approach of broadcasting what amounted to live stage shows
They wanted to shoot comedies on film
Comedies that weren't live
The still sounded like
The solution to this problem
And the person who came up with the solution Charles Douglas
Charlie
Douglas was a mechanical engineer would work on radar for the Navy in World War II
We knew his way around audio and electronic
In 1950 the Hank McEwen show
I mostly forgotten series from NBC
Have used a rudimentary last
Dubai 1953 Douglas I developed a better way to insert a laugh into a show
You've ever watched an old
The time is almost certainly heard his work
Now we lift up the dryers
And see how their hair turned out
I asked Ron Simon curator of television and radio
Paley Center
Formerly the Museum of Television radio what he knew
Charlie Douglas
Took the concept of just adding laughter probably from a
Transcription desk
Create a machine that could do it
Any creative
Little box
Using laughter from
Marcel Marceau
From the silence
And critiquing
That could then
Be injected into film,
Make it alive
Experience
Douglas and Port over these last and his kitchen table night after night
You splice them into analog tape realistic can be played on a patented device Douglas had built himself out of household appliances
Oregon Park
Vacuum
The devices at 3 ft tall the shape of a filing cabinet
Very heavy at slots for 32 rails
Wichita Old Town last
It was officially named the audience response duplicator
The became known as the last
And that's life
Spell the goofy 50 style Laff
Weird machine that's closer to hefei steampunk that it is
Modern electronic
Technology
Like an adding machine where you just press the
Style
And laughter would happen
Eventually would evolve into more of a
Typewriter thing where you
Punchkees
Glassbox could chuckle
I could laugh with side release
It even had a real controlled by the foot pedal that was just hitters
Tiny little one person last
It's most sophisticated the Box head
320 last
Play One Life at a time by pressing one key
Pressing multiple Keys together to play a bunch of laughs at 1
Sofifa something was remotely funny Tara let's have this guy laugh right here
Any just have that going
Maybe he come back and watch it
So you know what that could that wasn't Place funnies or as
Is the producers going to want it so maybe he would add a second sound like this
And then he would add it all together and mix it together so you hear the full product
Three separate Clips overlap
What what happened was the producer or the director would come back and see his work
And so you know what that could use a much louder laugh can you give it a louder to fall and issei are at Short Hills
So you throw supplements just like that
Because why foxes were patented and Handmade by Douglas
Does anyone can make or use one
There are only a handful of working models at a time
And he basically had a monopoly on the process
By the 1960s almost all sitcoms were single-camera shows filmed without an audience and tricked out with a rockstar
Charlie Douglas laugh
The boxes apply lacquer for tens of thousands of episode
Set the television
Tens of thousands
Even more
Everything from The Munsters Bewitched The Beverly Hillbillies Gilligan's Island
Mary Tyler Moore in cheers
For decades or sound with ubiquitous
But that wasn't want to talk about his device
Douglas whenever he went to a show
Wood covered over end
No one would actually see him at work
There is something you know embarrassing
It was certainly part of his
You know not want to talk about it really actually talk about
You know how the last sausage
Actually me
Douglas Harvey ever gave interviews or spoke about his work
1966 piece from TV Guide titled the Hollywood stinks and his last box
What's the Sphinx is Douglas
Describe the mystery surrounding the man and his device
The author wrote
It's a laugh box should
Start acting
Strangely the last boys we lit into the men's room
Locking the door behind them
So no one can
I mentioned the name Charlie Douglas and it's like Cosa Nostra
Everybody starts with
The most taboo Topic in
Baby
I want to see hear that every knock on the last track that you've ever heard
That it's fake and it's corny that it's cheating that it's not funny that it thinks audiences are dumb
People been saying since the beginning
And that's part of the reason for Douglas's silence
But listening to Douglas's wife
Kiran Paul try to recreate them it changed my thought about them
I've always prided myself on being open-minded about the last
Funny show with a funny show with or without one
Even so I always thought of them as automated mechanical
Not at all
They're crap
Charlie Douglas played his laugh box like it was an instrument
Literally
But why people think it was just a bunch of laughs thrown into a tape machine summer
Pushing the button
It was an art
He took it very seriously
Cheers on the Charlie's laugh
It was used in the late 60s and 70s
Including in the pilot for math
You hear the laughter telling off at the end
I love that
It tells a story in a single laugh
There's a joke but one guy in the audience
He doesn't get it right away
He does Split Second late and then he last a little bit longer
Hear it listen to it again
Charlie Douglas wasn't at the sound engineer
He was a psychologist
Dropping the last track is that it's fake laughter from a fake audience
But that's not quite right
Doesn't represent a bogus body
It represents an audience of one
Charlie Douglas
He definitely Goose laugh a producer's instructions
Large extent he and the people who work for him follow their guts
It's incredible that one man's taste and sense of humor or so important and pasting an entire type of Television comedy
But it's true
So how did the last active in Era of TV come to an end
How did the laugh track go from being a tittering companion
I think we need to think about the laugh track
Not just a habit or an object
But an idea
An idea about why we laugh
I'm going to get you another idea about laughter later on but this first one
I think it makes the last track of the 50s and
Take these make a lot more
Here I want you to listen to something
How many people wants that was really funny
That menacing sequences from the okeh laughing
Okay okay eh
Is the name of the record label that released it in 1922
It was recorded a few years earlier in Germany
As the sound of a cornet being interrupted by a hysterically laughing woman
Was joined by hysterically Laughing Man
That's it
It goes on for 2 and 1/2 minutes
2 1/2 creepy creepy minutes
Play 1922
People thought it was hilarious
The okeh laughing record was a huge novelty hit
There's speculation that sold over a million copies
It's bonded in tyermanii genre of novelty laughing record
Blastrac it's a version of the okeh laughing record
Trying to make you laugh
Just by listening to other people laugh
What's funny must be the laughter
Because it's not the joke
There is no joke
But this particular approach to humor it's not that popular right now
Define someone to defend it I had to talk to one of Paul's friends
10 Glen
He's an art historian by training
But he's also a devoted laugh track enthusiast
Kampala in the same Charlie Douglas Facebook
It just wouldn't be funny
And it was
Scratch
Yes yes parley
It's not funny
Right
That's funny
I found this
What does a tree falling in the forest make a sound send Cohen a sitcom laughter a genuinely perplexing
Is a pie in the face funny if no one laughs
Is an episode of Friends funny
That's what I wondered after coming across this video
Posted on YouTube a friends without a laugh track
Where is the waitress I'm starving
Buffet man
Here's what I went all my money back
You can hear what the rhythm of the show was supposed to be
How the pacing depends upon their being laughed
Without it friend sounds weird and unnatural
If there's no audience laughter it suddenly starts how hot it is that the characters are trying to make each other laugh
Friends need to slap
To be funny even if some of them are fake
Has anyone seen Richie
She's upstairs not doing the dishes
I'll tell you something you don't I'm not doing them this time
The transition away from the Laff trakk started slowly
In the seventies with Norman Lear sitcoms like All in the Family
Comedy started to be taped in front of a live studio audience again
The audience is last would be smoothed out edited or boosted
This is a process called sweetening which Douglas had done a lot of and still happens all the time
But already it was of the last sound borealis
In the eighties and nineties some shows like The Wonder Years the Larry Sanders show and the days and nights of Molly Dodd
Started to experiment with dropping the laugh track
The TV's biggest hits
Shows like Jerry Seinfeld and friends still had them
By the late 90s with the rise of cable and on Laff tracks animated series like The Simpsons
Even the network started contemplating making different kinds of comedies
Setting up a collision between the old idea about comedy and the typical way of doing things
And a new idea about comedy
A new way of shooting a TV show
Cotton a collision
Aaron Sorkin Sports night
You're watching sports night on CSC so come on back
We're out
1997 Sports
His first TV show
ATC
It was a comedy
Behind the scenes of an ESPN style Sportsnet
Sorkin and the director
Tommy schlamme
Wanted to shoot it like a single-camera
If I had four walls the camera moves
And they wanted to shoot it without a laugh track
ABC
Not so much
They wanted to do something different
But not that differ
Here's Mommy
The economics of television and certainly half-hour television
Was so massive
Shows that I've had traditional
Laugh tracks
If they were really very nervous about giving that up
What did you feel like the last recommend about your show
Base town of a
Situational comedy is the laugh track
I think we're familiar with it I think it sort of
Resonates in a certain way
But I think it is kind of establishing a conceptual idea about a show
That is saying it's not real this is a theatrical presentation I'm there with this group of people were all laughing it's fine
That was not the idea of the way I think Aaron wrote or what I think Sports night was about
Here's a clip of the laugh track from the sports night
Yeah but the point I'm making is but I can't who is this I'm Jeremy Goodwin
Are you here for the associate producer job or I could really feel
Filled with the laugh track was holding the show back
Sportsnet is fast
He doesn't want to pause to wait for the audience's laugh
The last have to be shoehorned into the rear brakes and Circumstance dialogue
Play sound even Faker than usual
Dispatches from a whole other Sensibility
Will you be here starting to happen with sports night is the last track changing from background noise
Impediment
It's actually keeping Sports night from being is funny and fast
Swimming is good
@the could be
After its first few episodes
Sports night stop being taped in front of an audience at all
And the laughter got even fainter
Here's a clip from an episode at the end of season 1
Yes
Hello
You're breaking up
That you're not there. There's nobody there at all yet I'm still talking
All right
First second season ABC let the show dropped a laugh track entirely
What was canceled at the end of that season anyway in mm
Just ever so slightly ahead of its time
The last track free British version of The Office premiere in 2001
In 2003
Arrested Development started airing on Fox
In 2005
American adaptation of the office started airing on NBC the first huge hit without a laugh track
That same here
Everybody Loves Raymond won the Emmy for best
Comedy that's the last time I said
Sitcom with a laugh track has done
The end of the last track
So what changed
I want to talk about another Siri about laughter that's different from the pie-in-the-face theory I mentioned earlier
Isn't a fundamentally social activity
Because everyone else is doing it
Something deeply wonderfully individual and idiosyncratic reaction to the quality of the joke itself
Representing is a TV writer Andy secunda
Any songwriter on the current ABC sitcom The Goldbergs which doesn't have a laugh track
What is fresh out the 2004 UPN sitcom love incorporated
About modern-day matchmakers did
But that's not fair I have a dream too
What's your dream
Top ten thousand more dollars
I'm talking about $10,000 to help improve The Human Condition
Condition very much
Before working on love incorporated Andy has been a writer for Conan and a teacher and performer at The Improv Comedy Powerhouse up
Upright Citizens Brigade
Alternative comedy snob
And coming out of the New York scene
Already was
Show with a laugh track
Other than Seinfeld
Is
You know
Passe
A dinosaur
But it didn't have the clout to keep love incorporated from having a laugh track
The show is performed in front of a studio audience
And hatsune real life
Dennis sound editor came in to sweeten it
Boosting and manipulating all of them
Is a relapse replaced by Alaska
But anyone use that last track in the typical way
So I guess my take was
Well
Since we're doing this anyway
Why don't we just decide what
Give me I was with like if we'll it's going to be
This creation
This false thing
Why go half way just make the whole thing of
Train the audience that's watching at home
How much attention anyway in my head in other words anyone the last track to reflect what was really funny
He understood how the laugh track is
Supposed to work
It is supposed to make people laugh at what other people are laughing at
What do you want to retrofit it to account for the secondary of laughter
Tell audiences hey
Some jokes are funnier than others and you should laugh at those
In 68 his boss wouldn't have it
But even so you can see
He may be skeptical of the laughter of the crowd but he believes in the objective quality of
The joke you may be able to get a big laugh
Ativan audience and B
Not that great a comic
I mean a lot of comics with argue well if you get a let get the laugh
Then you are a great time at
Cuz I'm a snob
Any may be a snob but his perspective has become White
This is how a lot of people think about comedy Now
Me included
Some jokes are better than others and you can't tell simply based on what got the biggest laugh
Especially when that last comes from Alaska
For decades TV was ruled by the idea that laughter is socially contingent
Debackers idiosyncratic and individual
This is a big transition
For some viewers the last act into stop encouraging laughter
Started inhibiting
The last track
Broke
Play shows of artifacts have been almost entirely cut out of the crib.
Conversation
Do they still have their modern-day Defenders and uses
Especially in the revivals of beloved shows that have laugh tracks
Like Will & Grace
Netflix's 2017 reboot of Norman lear's one day at a time a show about a divorced cuban-american better
Urine with PTSD
Raising her son and teenage daughter while living with her mother is great
It's smart it's Charming it's clear and it has a laugh track 2
She has to
To have a quinceanera
How else would we know the day that our little girl becomes a woman
You missed it
Well I was in gym and ironically happened at first.
So I'm just
Podcast for doing about the last rocket
I'm wanting to talk to you guys
Because you do a great job as laugh track
That's Gloria Calderon kellett in microwave
The showrunners of one day at a time
There right there shows filmed in front of a live audience
I was the
Mike and Gloria say they're sound editor cuts down on the Oz
And the more excessive whoops Rita Moreno and even trims down to laugh
But they say there's no sweetening in their show
I said it was a laugh track
Like
Why does that bother you so much
Some people just don't like
To hear other people laughing cuz
It feels like they're being told what to do
But part of that comes from
I think feeling like the laughter is somehow fakely adidon
Mike is right that is how some people feel about the laugh track
That is a false advertisement
Trying to sell you a bad joke
As I was a good one
And sometimes that is what the laughter
So I asked why it was worth risking that kind of reaction
Police about a shared experience
So I feel like it's an opportunity to experience a play in the comfort of your home but you're experiencing it as
You are a part of a community
We want them to experience the emotions audibly
You know like it's there
There is something about that that's the crying too by the way
For Gloria and Mike last night as a reminder that other people are there
Watching with you even when you're all alone
Just like it has been from the very beginning
I want to go back to that scene from earlier when you turn on the TV for the first time and saw the Jack Benny Program and it was so new
Strange
When you heard the audience laughing it was a cue that you should laugh to
Yeah but also it was a sign
Sign that you weren't watching alone
Blackhawk was trying to bridge the bazaar new distance between the audience and the performers
Between the audience and other members of the audience
The thing you have to remember and this is so different than now
Did the lack of trying to overcome a defective television
Which of the unlike Vaudeville in the movies you watched it all by yourself
Now that the fact that you don't have to go anywhere or interact with anyone while you watch it
That's one of TV's biggest selling points
Unlock Rocket help us to get to that point
For a long time the laugh track seemed permanent but it was really more like training wheels
Something that taught us this new scale of watching and laughing in solitude
Mother stuck around way too long but it did its job really well
The late 90s and early aughts
When the numbers of shows on cable start to Skyrocket
The TV audience began to fragment
We were totally ready to move from one theory of laughter to another
To embrace the idea of ourselves as individuals with idiosyncratic comedic taste
Who did not need or even want the Laff tracks lame chortled approval
To know it was
These days it's the last track that seems weird and vestigial a sound from another time
Unless we're specifically after the theatrical communal throwback experience of a show like one day at a time
Black is always been a tool
I'm nearly 70 years after it was invented there's nothing to fix
Watching TV alone isn't the weird activity watching together is
A multi-camera comedies with laugh tracks of faded out
Single-camera comedies without last I've only gotten more and more adventurous
Bingohall upheaval in what constitutes a
The comedy.
Most well-regarded comedies
Like Atlanta and girls and transparent are more funny a JC
Laugh out loud funny
Thereafter that big big laugh
Making people laugh is really really hard
One shortcut from decades ago was the fake that laughter
It's not to worry about whether audiences are laughing at all
My littlest
Probably be my IBS
I medium baggage should be that I truly don't love my grandmother
You don't love her at all
Start with your biggest baggage Bay
Converging
How do you say
You know they're not laughing
Audiences are finding makeshift ways to watch community
You're looking for the present-day technological equivalent of the laugh track
Look at social media
Sitting on your couch
Reading Twitter while you watch Atlanta or a football game or The Bachelor
Those tweets are signal about what's good and what's interesting
Sometimes they're just the shows best joke
Books tweeted verbatim
Often those people make you laugh
Spell definitely
I'm feeling like you're watching
Learning history of the laugh track
Thinking about it as a way to foster a feeling of togetherness it really made me wonder
Solo binging with headphones on or the person in the very same room as you watch as something else
Really better than gathering around one of three channels
Politely putting up with canned laughter
And one of these experiences that you definitely get to decide what's funny fears
But you really are doing it all alone
I think this is part of what drives laugh track aficionados
Tinkers with laugh tracks and add them back into old episodes of The Pink Panther or the Monkees
Recapturing the spirit of a different time
A different way of watching television
Icompanion
I asked how his favorite Charlie Douglas last was
He had one of course
He got right to the heart of it
It was basically a deep man's laugh
That was used
Sparingly and then it started to get used more regular
Sounds like this
Let me hear that with my sister would say there's your friend
Even listening to decoder ring
Hosted by Willa paskin
Decoder ring is a brand-new podcast
Translate
It was produced and edited by Benjamin fresh
You can find out more about the show at slate.com Dakota rain
Gator podcast
You don't like it
One of the shows in radiotopia is The West Wing weekly and the co-host that show with Joshua Malina who starred in the show
Fortnite one of my favorite television shows of all time
And excited as the Tipping Point moment of the laugh track so I asked him what it was like to act in TV show
I was slowly turning down the laugh track over the course of the series
Wechat conversation
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms but oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
Joshua Malina is the co-host of radiotopia is The West Wing weekly podcast
With risque Sherway
Joshua is also an actor on the side he recently wrapped up a 7-year run on Scandal
He was also on The West Wing
Because big break in television has Jeremy Goodwin on another Aaron's working creation Sports night
It was a strange and beautiful half hour comedy with strong dramatic elements in
The rapid-fire dialogue that people would Embrace more fully on The West Wing
But as was mentioned in the documentary you just heard
Sports night marked the beginning of the end for the laugh track
I asked Joshua if he was aware of that Dynamic at the time
It was always my understanding that Erin
Objected strenuously
To the inclusion of a laugh track on Sports night
And for that matter to the inclusion of a live audience
In the studio as we filmed what was essentially
Single-camera
Comedy so it was kind of being forced
Into
A hybrid
Of which iron did not approve
And did you feel the tension of it be neither fish nor fowl when you are
Acting in it
Yes I think as a performer and that somebody coming from a theater background
And perhaps somebody is a little bit
Oven 1/8 ham it's hard to ignore
The presence of 90 people
In a room where your
Making a show hopefully for millions of people to watch at home and there is
Something different between a performance
Four camera
And a live performance
And so
While be priority ought to be be home viewing audience
I found it difficult not to play to the people who are in the room with me
Flight very happy with my performance in the pilot
It's large
It's possible one can detect
My playing
To be live audience and perhaps I should have toned it down a little bit
Sophisticated and I sense that you are
At least 20 minutes
As the
Laugh track itself
Was slowly muted
I think
Maybe my performance got a little bit smaller little more finally realized
So I think I need to go back up a little bit understand so there is a live audience
For the first season or what was the setup actually
There was a live audience
For I think as long as there was a laugh track
Tommy schlamme and Aaron Sorkin finally outwitted ABC simply by dialing it down a bit
Episode-by-episode until it was gone
So they never
They never
One of the explicit argument about a laugh track ABC never said fine get rid of the laugh track
They just got rid of it so slippery you know it's that thing I guess where you boil a frog
It was a you know de facto they have gotten rid of these laugh track by the time
ABC you seem to notice up my memory is that that was somewhere around episode 7 or 8
End
Having disposed of the laugh track we dispose of a live audience
It was already a weird situation to have the audience there when we were moving around trying to make our
Single-camera comedy
And so there really was no
Existential point to the live audience once the laugh track was
Removed
It was one of those
We're instances why I think that a lot of us who grew up on television the laptop
Heart of sitcoms
And this was a very different sitcom
Did you feel the sense of this tension
As an audience member as well as up as a person crafting this
Yes
I'm not a big fan of laugh tracks
All together
The Golden Age of TV if the shows in black and white and feels like a theater piece anyway like The Honeymooners looks like
Like they're putting on a play
It kind of works
And has heard of an old-school resonance for me
Certainly for what we were doing
Wait
Was creating a piece that included
Elements of comedy in drama
It just
Felt
Weird as we're making it when I watched it
The that that
You know sweetens
Super artificial
Laugh track
I think there's not
Elevate The Shadow
And so over the course of the first season while the laptop was being
Bow Down
Surreptitiously
Did you
Intuitively know to change your
Performance slightly was that communicated to you in some way
I don't think it was made explicit I think
I just settled into the natural rhythm of acting for the camera I think the best piece of advice I got as a young actors
Learning how to act on film
Was
I always remembered that the camera can read your mind
And
That's a very different piece of advice from you to make sure your performance reaches
That person in the last row of the balcony and said they're just there are baked in
Inherent differences
Between a live performance in the performance for Cameron sowinski audience was actually gone I think I just settled into
Okay we're making it TV show
You know did that
Cameras going to get in
Really close
When it needs to
And
Startled let go of the idea of
Trying to
Project
Anyting
So what do you think of sports night being this
Pivotal moment in
Laugh track history
The situation with the laugh track
And ABC versus Aaron and Tommy
Reflected
Very significant
Misunderstanding on the networks
Part
Of what the show was
End
So I think it's just one
Offshoot of they're not quite knowing
What they had or what to do with sports night
And I think we're we're very used to sing single-camera comedies and we're used to seeing
Television shows that
When might have difficulty classifying as a comedy or drama I don't know why this is such a
20 years ago now we're a little bit more sophisticated
As an audience and we understand
That much like Life TV shows can have moments of drama and moments of Comedy
But I think
At the time abc didn't quite know how to handle
What Erin and Tommy were giving them
And Randy
Dia de la track
Was reflection of that
Tension
Like a lot of things though the first guy to the wall
Gets the bloodiest
Right and then
We've all benefited from that fight because
Have West Wing in
30 rocking
All these things that I think you could
Point of this moment
And go
The
Pyrrhic victory of sports night
Made it so that
All this other great TV happen
As well
Do you understand
I think it's for science is complete to class like I loved it so much I appreciate that this
Strange little object
It
Fought a battle that really changed
A lot of Television that we admire today feels like a platitude to say that anything was before
FaceTime work
That's why we didn't do better because we were before our time but I think it's actually an app
Phrase here and I do think
Aaron Sorkin and Tommy schlamme in terms of
The material that Iran is writing in the way that Tommy was
Filming it
I think they were truly a little bit ahead of the Curve
And did ultimately take a little more time for
Audiences to come around for this type of material
But I agree with you that we did
45 episodes
We got a couple seasons and I feel happy
That was part of it and proud of what we ultimately put out
Joshua Malina is the co-host of The West Wing weekly and addictive
And rigorous discussion of the TV show The West Wing trust me it's great in the community they formed around the pot
Comcast is just like this
Warm embrace so proud to have them Park
The radiotopia crew
99percentinvisible is Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald's reviews of Taryn music composer Sean real
Digital director Kolstad senior editor Delaney Hall senior producer Katie mingle and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX eclectic but the best
Most Innovative nicest smelling shows in all of podcasting
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
Confine 99percentinvisible and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars in the show at 99
NPI org run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But I bet even the most dedicated of you hasn't heard every episode of 99% invisible
And you can remedy that
I downloaded them all
Right now on your favorite podcasting app I recommend the radio public
But they also live beside words and videos and pictures and a bunch of other design stories
899ci
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com