99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Imagine you're in a hospital room
Waiting to hear the results of a test you at
The doctor comes in
Apps
You might Sense on some level what's about to happen
I got the results back
The muscles in your shoulders tense up
Your hand suddenly feel clammy
They found a mass in your descending colon
Biopsy
I see if it's positive
And then you get some very bad news
Results came back that is invasive adenocarcinoma
And what that means
The cancer is basically untreatable
Then after about 10 minutes a timer goes off
And the encounter is over
Okay when take a deep breath
That was not actually somebody being told they had terminal cancer
It was part of an exam for Med students at Rush Medical College in Chicago
I do remember that student and I thought he did a really really nice
PetSmart para who played the patient he went the whole day being told by medical students that he was dying and then
Henry acting as if that was actually happening
Is CS difficult it's a it's a long day
About a long day
The little Like A demented theme park
Job
But as difficult as it is Mark is playing an important role for Med students like Rd Missouri
It's never a good feeling to break bad news to patients but I understand that
No matter which field I go into or which specialty of this is something that we all will have to
Andorra some point
In medicine bad news is defined as any information that drastically and negatively Alters a patient
Outlook for the future
John Cecile is a radio reporter and part-time Medical School videographer
TXU set up cameras to film that encounter between Mark and Hardy so that RT could be evaluated
On his communication skills
And I was really surprised by how calm and compassionate already was
Many doctors struggle with Breaking Bad News
I've heard stories about a doctor leaving a voicemail to tell a patient she have cancer
I heard another story about a doctor who used a sports analogy to deliver difficult information
As in it's the bottom of the ninth and there's one out left
Breaking bad news is as delicate a procedure as a knee surgery and there can be serious consequences if they
Things go wrong
If the patient doesn't understand their diagnosis or
What the next steps are
They could end up making an informed decisions about their treatment
Which is why many medical schools now offer training
They bring an actor's to help
Students learn how to navigate this
Critically important and very high-stakes moment
A moment that most of us will experience
One way or another
But that's not the only connection between acting and this particular facet of Medicine
Goodbye
It turns out one of the first doctors to recognize this problem
He wasn't just a physician
There's also a comedian
And he actually Drew an attic
Experience to transform the way that doctors break bad news
There are ways of doing this they're always of Breaking Bad News
His name was Rob Buckman
And his very unusual life prepared him perfectly to tackle what might be the hardest part
Of a very hard job
In 1968 Rob Buckman was on stage in London's West End
Striptease
I think the essence of it is that it was a
The strip routine that you might have expected a female burlesque.
To come out and do with rub it in this extraordinarily physically unlikely
Guys
Going through all sorts of
Gestures getting his head stuck in his
Pullover
This is Pete Atkin and Russell Davies
Two of Rob's best friend
They were all students together at Cambridge University
And they were all members of the footlight
A theatrical Club
It was a big deal to be in the Footlights then and it still is today
The group has turned out tons of famous comedians like half the comedy troupe Monty Python and more recently peep
People like John Oliver
The Footlights put on reviews each year that featured comedy and music
And back in the late 60s
Rob strip routine was a highlight
He did
Take it
Absolutely seriously hate
Came out and did it as if
People were meant to be
Aroused by this routine
Play with your moving as watched as if this was especially in Russia
Ocala FL
Except taking off your watch like will do
There was no real punchline to it was there except
Except that he had a flower painted on his stomach
And that was robbed that.
Robert going to Cambridge with the intention of becoming a doctor
My day he said he medicine and two classes in Biochemistry
By night he wrote and performed sketches in the Footlights Club room
House in the second story of a local fish shop
He slept only three or four hours a night
After Cambridge Rob went to a teaching Hospital
And it turns out that he answered medicine just as a big shift in medical culture was happen
One that changed the way doctors thought about their patient
Around the same time Rob was on stage in London West End doing a strip routine
His name dr. Elisabeth Kubler-Ross was working on a pretty radical project
She was spending time with dying patients at a hospital in Chicago
Listening to their stories
I just sent them listen to dying patients
I'm try to be their spokesman
You can only sit and listen and hear
What they say
They teach you nothing about dying but about living
In 1969 Kubler-Ross published a book based on her research called on death and dying
You know the five stages of grief
That's where that come
The book became an international bestseller and brought conversations about dying into the home
Google Ross also encourage doctors to speak more frankly with their patients about death
She said they needed to stop tiptoeing around the subject
Which is what doctors had done for most of the history of modern medicine
The original code of ethics established by the American Medical Association in 1847 sed
It wasn't the role of doctors to make
Quote
Gloomy prognostication
Instead they should be Ministers of Hope and comfort
Doctors were afraid that disclosing a bad diagnosis would actually be damaging
They could even drive patients to suicide
This attitude remained unchanged through much of the 20th century
In the fifties the word cancer wasn't used
Dr. Walter Bell is a psychiatrist and a professor at the MD Anderson Cancer Center
It's part of the University of Texas in Houston
There was a lot of deception that went on around
How sick people really were
You couldn't talk about the patient died so you can imagine
Nobody
Really was able to say goodbye
In 1951 the Journal of the American Medical Association actually published methods for deceiving cancer pain
Patients and their families
They recommended giving evasive answers or using confusing euphemisms
Like calling cancer and ulcer
Or an infection
The same article recommended that cancer patients who learn the truth of their diagnosis and reacted badly to it
Be given lobotomies
And this attitude was
Pervasive
In 1961 a survey showed that 90% of doctors prefer not to disclose
Cancer diagnosis the patients
Despite another study showing that the vast majority of patients wanted to know the truth
But then things started to change
In the 1960s doctors develop effective treatments for cancer
The two big advancements for chemotherapy and radiation therapy
The
Research just exploded
Patients have a lot more to hope for
And around the same time palliative care emerged as a concept in medicine
We began to
Realize that
Controlling pain and other symptoms
Could give people a peaceful death
The modern palliative care movement together with hospice
Has
Really made death
Less fearful
4 people
These developments along with the work of Elisabeth Kubler-Ross all started to change the way our culture talked about death and
Dying
And it was in this context
That Rob Buckman became a doctor
A Doctor Who's totally irreverent take on medicine
Would ultimately help him transform the field
Rob's work in the Cambridge Footlights got him noticed by the BBC
Was still training at the doctor he wrote and performed on radio and TV
In 1978 he and his writing partner or given their own comedy program
It was called
The pink Medicine Show
I think medicine show was like SNL or Mad TV but all medical
It was actually a lot of comedy about medicine at this time
Especially in Britain
Doctors were seen as the stodgy and distant authority figures so they made a good Target for satire
One of Rob's recurring characters on the show was a malingerer
A guy pretending to be sick
Who keeps showing up at the hospital with different ridiculous excuses
It's a bat mug
Bowels
What's the regular
Every morning
I don't wake up till 9
Rob success caught the attention of another Footlights alone
Mostly we lost a lot because he was funny
We was one of the
Half dozen people that I spend most of my time laughing
That's John Cleese
You know Monty Python Fawlty Towers
A Fish Called Wanda the James Bond movies
I think he's in one of the Harry Potters anyway when I reached him he was getting ready to go on Safari
Well I'm off tomorrow for 3 and 1/2 months
Simon the usual stage of wondering what I forgotten to pack
In 1979 John Cleese was producing the secret policeman's ball
A comedy show that benefited Amnesty International
Any ask Rob if he'd appear in a sketch with him and Michael Palin
The old Monty Python been known as
The Cheese Shop sketch
How about it
Yes it's a very silly python sketch in which a man goes into a cheese shop
To buy some cheese and it slowly becomes obvious
That they don't actually have any
Any cheese in the shop
Parmesan
As the man puts
Seems to be shopping toddy uncontaminated by cheese
The whole time this ridiculous exchange is taking place
A Greek Bouzouki band is playing in the background of the
The shop and there are two guys doing a weird dance
With their arms around each other shoulder
One of those guys
Was Rob
And there's a certain point my character goat soap
Irritated by the lack of cheese
The tide turned Snapchat
At the Greek goddesses
Then stopped in slang.
Rob's appearance with Monty Python mark one of the high points of his comedy career
If you look close that you might notice his face looks pale
A little puffy
That's because after finishing his medical training and establishing himself the comedy
Rob
Country Way
Really sick
Soon firsthand what it was like to be a dying patient
And this role reversal
From Doctor to
Stick person
Would transform how he thought about his work as a physician
And the process of Breaking Bad News
April 1978
I contracted a very interesting and very rare disease
Interesting not just
Because he defected me and turned me from
A doctor into a page
But also because it's one of a group of disease
In which
The body's defense
The body itself
And in which you become
Literally
Euro
That's Rob
From a TV documentary he made about his illness
As he was becoming sicker
It's called Your Own Worst Enemy
It began
Very simply and very mildly
With pain
In my right wrist
And when I move my wrist
It Creek
Rob had dermatomyositis
Very rare autoimmune disease
The disease causes your body to malfunction and attack its own muscle
The Robb wasted away
He developed these rashes all over
His body
At one point I couldn't actually put my hands behind my head
Because so much of the skin was inflamed it was like wearing
A leather jacket that have been shrunk in them to you
Encased in
Rob was married at this point and had two daughters
One of the more poignant moments of the film captures Rob trying and failing
To pick up one of his girls
He talks about how weak and vulnerable
Bully fails what happens
Is very very simply
The color
Trains out of everything
It's the same scene
It's the same family as the same house
But
The color the things you enjoy
Have simply
Play the tone
All film is about the
While Rob condition was so bad that his doctors thought he might not make it
And the experience of being that close to death was profound
Years later he broke all and especially important encounter with one of his Physicians
And I was sitting on my way
Very altruistic and I had all kinds of problems with the skin and bowel trouble
And I was feeling lousy
He said you got miss you girl. You go the other you look skinny but the muscles
It must be awful for you
I am sorry
It must be awful
Fall for you
I'm sorry
I very nearly burst into tears and hugged it
Because he gave me
Permission to feel
The doctor was telling Rob that it was okay to have feelings about being sick
But the negative emotions were a valid part of the experience
The doctor was paying attention not just to Robbins physical state
But also his emotional state
And while this might seem obvious
It wasn't especially common for doctors to
To do this back then
This moment was simple but important
It would go on to become the Cornerstone of Rob's approach
The doctor-patient communication
And then little by little
Rob started getting better
He was having blood plasma replacement therapy
And a new drug he was taking started to work
The last 4 weeks
Something like
I can drive my car
I can
Straighten my elbows
I can dress myself I can put any kind of sucks on even really sucks by May of 1980 Rob's condition had
I turned around
I can go for walks in the park with the kids and don't feel too bad about it and I can stay awake all day
I watch television in the evening or whatever like go to bed at midnight and then live
Normal life Med going back is incredibly intense work schedule
He was more successful than ever training as a specialist in oncology which is the branch of medicine that deals with cancer
While simultaneously co-hosting a popular TV science show called
Where there's life
Where there's life returns as doctors Miriam stoppard and Rob Buckman explore such topics as cosmetic surgery
Unwed mothers and the nursing
But that intensity wasn't good for his marriage
He and his wife ended up getting a divorce and in 1985
Rob move to Toronto
To take a job at a hospital
In Canada ROM had to restart his life completely
It was there he would end up making his most lasting contributions to the field of Medicine
He started studying the way that doctors communicated with people they were treating
Specifically
He was interested in how doctors interact
Dying patient
Because he himself had recently been a dying patient
This is from an interview he gave in 1999
The great thing about
Being able from my point of view
Was that I found out that I could tolerate mean I did
But I didn't come
I didn't have my hero by any means but I wasn't a different person
His big realization was that doctors didn't need to hide information from their patients and tiptoe through tough subject
Sick people could withstand a lot
So when I recovered
I was thin able to say okay I've been on the phone
And I stayed the same
No I can be brave when talking to the patient
He walked in my room like
A breath of
Not fresh air I was sort of like a
Wind
Is huge energy
Exploding into the room and I've never actually
Met anybody quite like him before
I think most people haven't
Dr. Patricia Shaw was a cancer researcher at the same hospital where Rob worked in Toronto
She goes by Pat
Patton Robinette in the most dr.lee meet-cute scenario imaginable
Why didn't you ask me
Crisco
And so we came into
Kisimi
And that's how we really
That's our first conversation
One thing led to another and they got married in 1988
It was around this time that Rob started writing more
He had a large piece of
Solid mahogany
They brought with them from England
And
His favorite spot was just sit at this desk
Cache of computer
So even though he's really busy
At the hospital
He's been a huge amount of time
After those hours
Working in a study
Rob wrote a book
Called I don't know what to say
How to help and support someone who is dying
It's kind of like What to Expect When You're Expecting
If what you're expecting is that somebody close to you is going to die
It's a very Frank but easy to read book that covers everything from
Basic listening skills to the sexual needs of the dying to survivor's guilt
And then in 1992
Rob published the most important book of his career
It was titled
How to break bad news
The first medical textbook
On the subject
When Rob Buckman
Wrote the book on how to get bad news it was from his
Experience as an oncologist having to give it
Several times a week
That's dr. Walter Bale again
He was also studying doctor-patient communication when Rob's book came out
He understood that
Bad news was a series of steps that could be broken down into series of steps
Walter and Rob would eventually write a set of guidelines based on route
Book
They called their strategy
The spikes protocol
Spike's was an acronym
That's good for setting
Reception invitation
Knowledge
Emotions
Stratagene summary
It's a mnemonic device that doctors can use as they prepare to give bad news
And then during the actual conversation with the patient
So that it doesn't
Fly off the rails
Eden worried that it was sounded too I don't know Spike
We didn't even
Think about it because it was so elegant
Everybody remembers that
Soon Walter and Rob were giving presentations on spikes at hospitals all over the world
They made videos for medical schools which demonstrated have spikes could help doctors navigate these difficult conversations
And some of the videos robbed
Performs improvised scenes with actors
Explain patience or family member
Just like you heard already doing with Mark at the beginning of this episode
Not real but
Really intense
Here is the six
Step protocol
Which has the robbery in Allegan
Threatening acronym
Texas stencil
Getting the physical context write
Sit down relax
Eye contact
If the patient is either angry or crying
Wright-Patt perception
Assessing the patient
Perception of his or her medical
When you got back chest
When you found that lump in your breast
What did you think
Quiz
Then comes the pivot of the whole interview
When you ask
The patient
What he or she would like
I
Invitation you want to know the exact results of the bones kind of know what is going on is that the kind of
Where you'd like me to handle the information please
Giving the medical facts
Belk Wilson
Cumberland microscope
I can't tell you what it wants
Give me information in small chunks
Whois check
That the patient understand what you are saying
After each small chunk of the girls was malignant
In other words of the law
I have cancer in my lung
4 ml
Acknowledge
Name the emotion
But the patient is expressing
If this is obviously a great shock to this is difficult this must make you feel overwhelmed
Your ability to empathize with the patients emotion
Is the single most important characteristic
A good
And supportive newsbreak
Insensate
Indivisible
And then
S
Strategy and summary
Why we do from here
What we do from here this is very important
Whatever it is that's going to happen next
Make It Clap
As you can hear from those scenes Rob with master
Breaking Bad News
He was calm
Present compassionate and clear
And not just because he been a patient
But because he been a comedian
It's the ability to put yourself in your audience's shoes
And understand
What makes them
Check right so if you're comedian
You want to know
What you can do
To make people laugh right
If you're a doctor
You need to put yourself
In people shoes
And imagine what they need
In order to make sense out of
The process of giving bad news
Even though Rob had recovered from his illness
It has taken a toll on his body and he had health problems for the rest of his life
A case of shingles left him paralyzed on one side
Your difficulty dressing himself in Wok
He couldn't drive a car
And that was
Pretty devastating
Again Rob's wife
This insult leaving him with his permanent episode I think was
Really really damaging any other hard time coping with that
But in his typical robway he kept working on his many projects
In 2011 he flew to London to film a series of health videos with Terry Jones
Another member of Monty Python
Then he got back on the plane to Toronto
Afters light Garden
You didn't arrive any wasn't answering his
Text messages
Wasn't too unusual he's travel so much flights
. delayed
I went to bed
Panda boat midnight
There is a knock on the door and there was a policeman at the
At the door
Doctors aren't the only ones who have to break bad news
Talk to bit of nonsense and then asked if I was
Mrs. Pacman
And then eventually got caught around saying that the prophet passed away
Robert died in his sleep on the plane from an undiagnosed heart condition
He was only 63
It took Pat a long time to get over the shock
There was
So much boo
Missing Rob there is so much about having to deal with the realities of what happens when somebody dies
And even though Raab himself had talked openly about death and dying
Even though he'd spent years writing books that encourage people to be frank about the
These subjects
He wasn't actually ready for his own death
In real terms you know like finance and insurance and all that kind of stuff
What was there was hard
Even though it's 6 years later and it still makes me
Bacteria thinking about it
Beyond Rob's death
Spike's has endured
It's been absorbed into the mainstream of American Medicine
Just recently the American Society of clinical oncology started recommending that doctors use a protocol
Call when giving bad news
Therefore spikes is a good example
And spikes is taught in many medical schools in the US and Canada
As well as schools in Europe
Asia and South America
You remember Artie the medical scene from top of the show
He has spikes navigate his encounter with Mark the actor
Yeah I think if I hadn't had this beforehand I would have been
Completely lost I would not have known
Can I where to go next
Spike's isn't the only set of guidelines for Breaking Bad news and it may not apply to every bad news situation
In some scenarios like an emergency room
Doctors might not have the time to be that delicate
And time is one of the main things working against doctor's as they try to do their jobs
Thoroughly and compassion
These days the average physician visit last
About 21 minutes
More than half of visits last
15 minutes
Charles S
It can be really stressful to try to convey necessary information in that amount
Time
Especially if somebody is freaking out because you know
They're dying
And throughout the course of their careers many doctors will have to break bad news over and over and over again
It's emotionally exhausting
Spike's helps doctors do what they need to do in the limited time they have
It turns the awful task of Breaking Bad News into a clear and simple set of steps
What it really is
Is a protocol that can help doctors be more like Rob
At least the person he tried to be
Open honest
An empathetic
Cheers John Cleese
I think it takes empathy
How can you talk to someone
Whether it's a group of people or a single person how can you talk to them if you don't have
Lymphocytic feeling of Bay City
Who they are
What they know already and what they need to know
Rob's funeral was held in Toronto
The same Minister who married Robin Pat leather
Honda service
Before Rob died
He requested that this song be played as people exited
What a day for a Daydream
I want to record a message
Which is played
Ask the people are leaving
It's just me and I got to say
Thank you so much for coming
Unlike the rest of you
I don't have to get up in the morning
I'm going to
That message wasn't actually played at Rob's funeral even though he choked that he wanted to be
But you'll hear more from Rob and from Monty Python's John Cleese
Right after this
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife isn't another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flat pocket
So I'm back to the reporter John Basile to talk about some of the remarkable
Beautiful pretty much unseen comedy that he found while he was reporting on Rob Buckman
But we can fit into the new story itself so
Is a little extra bit for you Monty Python fans
So are you a Monty Python fan
I would say it went to a Monty Python face
Efface in junior high
You find them and you think
I'm really special for liking this when no one else liked it cuz it was just on PBS
Add that was my face why I watched all of them and
I love them but I haven't kept my Phantom alive
I'm a huge Monty Python fan and when I started reporting the story had no idea there was any connection between Robin
Monty Python so
Finding that out was like a big deal
Found all this rare stuff
That hardly anybody has seen like stuff I got from tapes that Rob's Widow pulled out of storage
Like Mike what would give me example so right around the time Rob was writing how to break bad news in the early night
90s
John Cleese got in touch with him and he had this idea for a series called videos for page
I said it always seemed to me that it would be a very good idea to make
Videos for people who had just being told by the GP
That they had some sort of medical problem because when you told that you always get anxious and then
Absolutely the worst time
To take in information
The idea was to make a bunch of videos describing various medical conditions in detail so that patients with
Weather conditions could replay them whenever they needed a refresher
And almost all of them start with this little sketch that kind of
Deuce Breaking Bad News
And some very beautiful music
90s CD-ROM music
Or I don't owe
What's my problem leg ulcers
Leg
Chris plays a patient inquiring about his condition and Rob the doctor precedes to lay some head
Heavy medical jargon on him
What exactly are leg
Is the consequence of tissue hypoxia
Ischemia
Stacy
Evidence
Proximal varicosities and incompetent
Cost you loitering
This food
So as Rob's talking
Increasingly confused and upset leans in
Squints looks over his shoulder
By the time the camera lens and close up his face is slack and his eyes are wide with Terror
Are there any questions
Naruto
Yep
Then I'll see you in
Bye-bye bye-bye then please gets up and walks off stage revealing to the audience that he's on a set
Hasn't happened
I haven't
Dr. Tisdale
Really told me that
Sometimes it can feel a bit
The time I get home
I always realize that I haven't
List of everything that the
Always something
I should have asked
For some reason didn't
And that's
Exactly
Why we've made this
So then the rest of the video is just Rob going over the conditions slowly and in painstaking.
Detail
Lego Elsa is what happened
When the skin
Over a part of your leg count Grove
They made almost 50 these videos on everything from breast cancer to something called
Glue ear which I've never heard of
But they ran into a problem
A major problem which none of us had anticipated and I'm not entirely sure no one could have anticipated
And what was the problem
We set up all sorts of schemes
Couldn't pretty shift that we could never find a way of getting people to give us
12 of 13 quid
But 25
Minutes
Lecture
People
What's the pay
So that's why you never seen them
But now you can see them on our website
Yes you can you can see one of those videos and can also see
Footage of Rob's
Strip routine from the Footlights days
And stuff
Right so Rob Buckman also work as a videos with another member of Monty Python the Terry Jones can you tell me a little bit of
About those
It was literally the last thing he ever did he died on the plane on the way back from working with Terry and London
And these videos you can see online already there called the top 10 tips for health
The goal was to provide practical tips for staying healthy although really
When you're watching it just feels like you're watching two old men Goof Off
Here's Robin Terry in Drag
2 old ladies
Actual law.
No ice
Straight off the wall
Did you recognize the spam lady voice roaming
This reminds me of one of my favorite sketches
Michele watches
Piston engine what you thought that's what it was about
That one I know by heart that was good
Video series they actually
Directly make fun of Breaking Bad News
Type 2 diabetes
Nice
I said
Buhach
Type 2 diabetes
Is the Robins
I think I saw in the cinema the other day
At the diabetes 2
The Terry Jones is still alive but unfortunately he's suffering from dementia so we were able to interview on
He dropped a really close though Terry actually wrote Rob's obituary in the guardian after
He died
I remember when you're putting the story together
When you got the interview with John Cleese I was just shocked that he was to be that he talked to you
How hard was that to to manage
Oh man so actually got that interview through Rob's daughter Joe
Joe Bachman is a screenwriter in Los Angeles and
She participated in the interview to I think it
It meant a lot
To her you know Rob's death was so sudden that I kind of got the sense
From his family that the wounds of Never Fully healed
Ferjo the chance to hear John Cleese talk about her dad in such glowing terms
I think it was really meaningful
For her and any parent and it felt really good to be there in
To hear that
That's so nice
What's the weather that happened
Yeah Rob's family has been really great and supportive of the story but particularly Joshi was really my part
Partner in crime
Helping me with the police interview which is obviously get and then also
Helping me get some of the archival you heard in the
A story that's so great wall thanks to Joe Buckman
Hangzhou
Shout out to Joe
99percentinvisible was pretty so sweet by John fasil edited by Delaney Hall make some tech production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Kolstad is the digital director or producer is Katie Mingle
Russell team is Emmett Fitzgerald
Avery trufelman
Taryn Mazza and me
Roman Mars
I think the staff of Rush Medical College dr. Mary Mulcahy and Dr Miriam stoppard
I think one more time to Rob's family
Joe Buckman
Dr. Patricia Shaw
Jamie Buchman
Dr. Joan Van Den ende
We are products 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Are supported
Meijer listeners
Just like you
You find 99percentinvisible in discussions about the show on Facebook he tweeted me at Roman Mars and the show at 99
MPI org
Instagram
Tumblr and Reddit to
The only place you can see videos for patients
With Rob Buckman and John Cleese
Is 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com