99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The state of Utah has about 3 million people
And a third of them live in one Valley
Surrounded on three sides
By 7000 ft mountains
Into the northwest
Buy a great
Salty lake
The valley is home to the state capitol
Salt Lake City
And a bunch of other small cities and towns that overtime
Have grown together into one big Mass
What are the towns amid the sprawl
Isabel
Okay
We are in Midvale Utah
Producer and the Fitzgerald recently took a trip to Midvale Utah to visit a mobile home
I am standing up
Side of the
Applewood community
Applewood is a small mobile home Community for seniors
You have to be 55 or older to live there
About seven acres
56 Lots
It looks a lot like the rest of suburban Midvale
It's at the houses are smaller and closer together
It has its own little road
With its own speed limit
10 miles per hour
The very quiet community
Except for that weed wacker
Houses are in just a few
A few feet apart
I'm the Bell
Nice to know there are in really good shape
Olive Garden. Front of you
Wechat
Hello
This is Charlene stovin
She convinced me I needed to come visit Applewood after one phone call
There's something in my voice on the phone that attracts people
I can get on that phone and I'm not bragging but I can get anything I want
I don't know
Charlene's home is immaculate
She has spotless white carpeting from wall to wall
And all this modern furniture that's been carefully color
And it's really spacious
She says that when people first walk in
They seem surprised that a mobile home could be so nice
Jose
Ja
It's a manufactured home and it is built stronger and better than 90% of visual tracking
Books hard for people to get past this tunnel vision of
Trailers in trailer trash
Mobile homes don't get a lot of love in our culture
They represent a lot of the affordable housing in the United States
Drop the 90s
Mobile homes made up about two-thirds of new affordable housing
Charlene bought her mobile home or manufactured home in 1994
She was divorced for kids were grown up and out of the house
She wanted to buy her own place
But you couldn't afford a tract home in the suburbs
When I thought I was just excited to think
I can actually now have a beautiful home
That I can afford
Does tract homes I can afford
I had to borrow money
And the loan on the borrowing of the money plus the pet fee
Which less than what I was paying
Tarentum Park
But when you buy a manufactured home
The structure itself is only half of the equation
Then you need to find a place to put it
Angeline found what seems like the perfect spot
A small quiet mobile home park with an empty lot
When we moved here I moved here February 1994 thought I'd died and gone to heaven
I have a little
Beautiful backyard and I plan a little bit of the garden
I love tomato on my cucumber
I want just a little bit of crayons
And this is just enough
That's perfect
But it wasn't actually perfect
The same Dynamic that made this housing situation great for Shirlene
Also made her vulnerable
Because the mobile home was hers
The land underneath it
Wasn't
Part of the Paradox at the heart of manufactured housing is that
Precisely the thing that makes
It's so affordable
That also makes this
Reighley NC
Secure form of housing
This is aster Sullivan
A sociologist at the University of Colorado Denver
Who studies the relationship between poverty and housing
She says that about a third of mobile home owners live in Parks like Applewood
Where they rent a plot of land for their home
She called this Arrangement halfway home ownership because it's filled with all this uncertain
Residence Inn Park basically live at the whim of
The property owner
Where the property owner has the majority of Rights
In that community
So they are subject
Too often times
Foreign Shawty maintenance
Ever-increasing rents
And eventually
They can be subject to
Park closure and Redevelopment with very little notice
One Day in 2011 and found a letter we all received this letter
You're right
It's not going to
$89
Per month
And in six months
It's going to go up another
$89
The owner of Apple that taking good care of the Park and Campground slow and affordable
But there were new owners now
Who can afford a TI and then another 89% unlimited account
Are you kidding
They managed to negotiate the increases down to $70 each
But still in a six month. The rent for each lot went from $320 to 460
And rumors started swirling
That the increases might just be the first step in a plan to force them out
Shirleen started digging into what was going on
And pretty soon she discovered that the new landlords had submitted a plan to the city
To build a 3-story apartment
Right on top of Apple
Then we understood why
They were trying to
Financially
Invictus
But Charlene wasn't just going to up and leave
She got to figure something out
Owning your own home has long been seen as a Cornerstone of middle-class stability in this country
Home ownership helps you build wealth and as long as you're able to pay your mortgage you don't have to worry about getting evicted
That security is kind of Why We Buy Houses
But that security just isn't there for many mobile home owner
Including Shirleen still open
And the rest of the community at Applewood
Bring it back to their story in the second but to understand how a mobile home owners ended up in the precarious position
End of owning a home without land
We have to go back to the early 20th century
And the dawn of the automobile
People
Add cars for the first time in
Could go out and explore America by attaching little trailers to the back
Of their model T's or whatever cars they had
This is Andrew Hurley
History professor at the University of Missouri st. Louis
He says that the first trailer owners were wealthy vacationers
Tin Can tourist
Trailer happy as can be
But then came the Great Depression
When migrant workers started Living
And trailers full time as they travel the country looking for work
And so there were thousands of it
Generant individuals and Families
In search of work that
Didn't really know
One day
Or if they would be coming back to
Where they had originated
Han Solo trailer
Was something that they could
Attached to the back of their
Car
And just take their home along with them
And
They started the site these homes
Together in
Basically what became the first mobile home park
These Parks were really seen as a
Major
Drain
Unlocal resource
Writings of the timer for two bees as trailer slum
This was the beginning of a kind of classes trailer stigma that is still very much around today
But the event that really solidified the trailer as a viable form of American housing
Was World War II
American industry has met the challenge of Horror
American factories have achieved The Impossible
American mass production is delivering the goods
Is the war got underway
Factories popped up in all these remote parts of the country
But because
They had been undeveloped
It was no
Housing
And
There was no capacity to build a new housing
Because Construction
Materials
Upward prioritized for war production
So the government bought thousands of trailers to house the wartime Workforce
But this was always supposed to be at
Temporary solution
When the war ended the expectation was that people would give up their trailers and move back in the conventional home
That didn't happen
Trailers continue to be an affordable housing option for people who didn't have the money to buy a home in the expanding
Suburbs
And a lot of these mobile home owners rented pads in one of the many mobile home parks that were popping up all over the country
Esther Sullivan says
These parts continue to spread throughout the 60s 70s and 80s
As the government was investing less and less
Public housing
So just as
We've increasingly
Slashed the budget of Hud
And the production of affordable housing
Weed scene
Incredible rise
Manufactured housing and specifically
Manufactured housing mobile home parks
To fill that Gap
Mobile homes were never really able to shake off the stigma that began during the Great Depression
People just did not want a home parks built in their backyard
In fact
Cities use all the tools in the urban planning tool kit to render mobile home parks
Invisible
For the last half of a century
Planning and zoning laws have required
That Mobile Home Park
Walled in
Fenced off
Visually screen
Landscaped out of sight
So that
The average
Citizen in a town or city
Might not ever know that a park was
Locate
Where was lo
These Parks were often built on marginal land on the outskirts of cities
Bill's mobile homes are legally classified as a form of transportation other than housing
They can be built on land that wasn't zoned residential
So separate them
From
Residences and single-family homes
More often Place mobile homes in
Commercial or industrial zones
As well as in hazardous places like
Floodplains or substandard lamb
Cities develop and expand mobile home parks become valuable proper
I can be bought up and redevelop into something more profitable
A new apartment building
Condo complex for a Walmart
Almost any other land use
Is
Prioritize
Ice over a mobile home park
In
The decision
Of local city councils
And in the eyes of Developers
And the Redevelopment of a mobile home park
Means math addiction
Mobile home park residence
Which brings us back to Midvale Utah
And that little mobile home park for seniors where over 50 manufactured homes were on the verge of being a dick
To make way for an apartment complex
I asked everyone I met at Applewood if they consider the possibility of Redevelopment and eviction when they moved in
I just hadn't thought about that fat
This is Beth Durfee
She moved into Applewood with her husband Russell a couple of years ago
The fact that I would have to remove my home or leave my home and
Having to move out I never thought that was possible
Until they told me
That it was
A lot of people including many developers assume that if you evict a mobile home park the residence
I got their houses and moving somewhere else
But the truth is
Mobile homes aren't really mobile
In the mid-twentieth century the mobile home industry split into
One branch continued making travel trailers and RV's
Well the other started manufacturing houses designed to be lived in full time
These mobile home started to look less like trailers and more like conventional single family houses with
Multiple rooms and hallways in in for bathrooms
And they got harder and harder to move
The term mobile home is more or less in the snow
Ended
To be mobile except when it is
First transported from the factory
And installed on the side
And if you try to move it again
It requires specialized
Trucking and Hauling at Great expense to homeowners it can cause between
5 + $15,000
First to move one of these
Moving can also cause serious structural problems
It can damage the home so severely that it becomes unlivable
And even if residents of Applewood were willing to take that risk
Had a spare $15,000 lying around
Finding a new place to put their home could be next to Impossible
Because there has not been any new manufactured
Home
Community
Built
Utah
For a long long time
There's not that many spaces
In any of these parks to put
56 homes
This is Charlene stovin again
She says that if she got evicted she would probably have to abandon her home
And move in with one of her kids
But some of these people have no family
Or their family so far away
Where would they go
Charlene was determined not to let that happen at Applewood
And she talked to some local community organizer to advisor to start a homeowners assoc
So first meeting with a carport I can't remember which Powerpuff Girl one of the car parts are we all met
Decided this is what we needed to do save ourselves
Interested
Of course
And I thought okay what do I do now
I'm clueless
But she kept asking people for help and little by little they started rallying people to their cause
The residents started a petition
To save a boy and got over 2600 signatures
Charlene testify before the mayor and the city council
And told them
If we allow this guess what
You're going to have
Homeowners
That will be
And what are you going to do with it
Homelessness is a huge problem in Utah right now and it's been exacerbated by a housing shortage
And apartment complexes are going up all over the Salt Lake Valley to try and meet a growing demand
Charlene says that's good
You need the apartment
Displaced people in order to do it
Charlene in the other residents of Applewood fought for several years to stay in their homes
There were a lot of twists and turns and late nights in a whole lot of emails
But eventually
After a lot of public pressure
The development company gave up on the project
He decided to put Applewood up for sale
Her that she remembered an organization that she thought might be able to help them out
I was called
Rock USA
Yasso Roc stands for Resident owned communities
And we help homeowners in mobile home parks by their communities as Co-op
This is Paul Bradley
The president of Rock USA
Which is based in New Hampshire
Bradley began organizing mobile home coops with the New Hampshire Community Loan Fund
Back in the 80s
They even got legislation passed in New Hampshire that gives mobile homeowners a first option to purchase the land whenever
Close up for sale
Today about 27% of the
Manufactured home communities are Mobile Home Park
In New Hampshire are resident owned
Now so that's a hundred and twenty-seven or so communities
Bradley thinks we need to build more affordable housing but he also wants to protect the affordable housing we already have
Right now mobile homes represent the largest source of unsubsidized affordable housing produced in this country
Bradley says that if we can help mobile home owners by the land beneath their parks
Then the risk of mass eviction disappears
And so in 2008 Bradley launch Rock USA
Effort to spread New Hampshire is cooperative ownership model Nationwide
So far they've been really successful
National network of just over 220 communities 14000 homeowners
And we're operating with coops
15 states
When Charlene called Paul Bradley things were not looking good for Applewood
The land had already been sold to to new Developers
44.8 million dollars
But Charlene Paul approach the new owners explain the situation
They talked about how difficult it would be to move their homes
And ask if the new owners would be willing to sell the park to the residence
And they said
We didn't realize you you wanted to purchase the property but if you if you want to and you can do it within the next
Couple of months will sell it to you
Otherwise if we're going to
We're going to own it eventually we're going to close it down
Buying a mobile home park worth at least 4.8 million dollars
Seems like a very tall order for the residence of Applewood
Individually no one in the park
Even come close to getting a mortgage for that kind of money
But together as a co-op the financial picture was different
Rock USA was willing to give the residence of very low interest loan for 3.6 million
They would still need to find some more money though and so they went to a low income housing form in Utah called the Olene Walker house
Housing Loan Fund
So there I am again
Pleading
Mycase
And Gloria who is the director
Sad
I thought about this the last 3 months
And I've decided
We need to help
These people
We need to give them the money they need
So between it all we finally come up with
5 million that we needed
And on February 9th
Resigned
So we own
After four and a half years of fighting for their little piece of ground
Bland officially belongs to the Applewood Homeowners cooperative
To pay off their Collective mortgage the residents agreed to pay $60 more a month than they had previously been paying in rent
It's going to be a challenge for some of them
But the monthly cost be stable from here on out
Worried about eviction
We can breathe again I got to worry about losing our home and everything would have had in it
Or we can order home
Fieldease
This is Russell Durfee who lives in Applewood with his wife Beth who you heard from earlier
He says that at their age
They're just happy to have us
Secure place to live
We're getting so old and feeble
But we don't know how much longer we're going to live so I want to go grocery shopping or dare
Everybody Green from
Red Hawk rifles
Charlene is also relieved but completely
They own the place now
I got caught up to run
And bills to pay
Before it was
Fighting
To gain
The land
Now it's a whole different
Set of pressures of Jessie
Getting this running smooth
And the coop is a different ball
Because now we're in charge
It's up to us to make it work
Otherwise we're in deep
Deep doo-doo
But they aren't on their own
Rock USA is helping them structure the coop
And deal with the finances
And of course
A Cooperative Applewood means Cooperative living
There are lots of meetings and elections
Committees
Archimedes
Where's the community rules
Where's the finance committee there is irritation committee there's a major
These are officers were trying to get organized
Russell Durfee says he's not well enough
Participate as much as you would like
But you went the first general meeting of the coop and he was really impressed
They asked for volunteers to be president vice president
4/4
And every and every position they had volunteers
Didn't have to
Coke people
Servant leader leader
Automatically wanted to do it
Russell says they have lots of different skills and
Decades of experience here in Applewood
And their talents
Example is a retired engineer
Are secretaries going to automatic she was
Secretary for a police
I asked how she could
Prosper
Lymph node about to get all the notes down in Fort Worth
I did it for many years
The coop is going to be a lot of work
But at least for now people are glad to be part of it
And to finally own the land under their home
Together
Esther Sullivan the sociologist we spoke to for the story has a new book out later this year
It's called manufactured insecurity
Mobile home parks in Americans tenuous right to play
Cherokee lived in several mobile home parks that were undergoing eviction and study the impacts
You can find a link to the book on our website
99 pi
. org
The ever-evolving design of mobile homes and the concept of mobile home skyscrapers
Right after this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
When Emmett was reporting the story he discovered all the different names for these things
And that they were used interchangeably but also had different meanings for different people
Turnpike trailer
Manufactured home mobile home
And Coco said is here talk about the rise of the term mobile home
And how that design evolved over time
Right and Emma was telling me that
But when he was interviewing people for the story like everybody was just using a different term for sort of the same thing and put this actual
Turn mobile
According to Stewart brand
Really excellent book
How buildings learn
Was actually coined by a man named Elmer Frey
And I helped build a verify that
Independently but Frey did play a big role in popular I think it is nothing else and he's this really interesting character in love
40s he started a mobile home manufacturing business in Wisconsin
And he sold a lot of these 8 ft wide homes
We also lobbied to be able to transport 10-foot wides on public Road
And what is the big difference between an 8-foot wide home in it
Infant White
So if you think about a typical mobile home at the time
The real limitation is that horizontal to me
You can make one that stuff in the feet long fence really hard to fit in
Balls in hallway
It's too thin
So if you add a few feet of width
You can certainly subdivide space
Create rooms
And connecting the outside chords
So now you can walk
Pastis fully-enclosed individual spaces rather than always stepping through one room to
To another
That means you got privacy and you can fit a Pamela more comfortable
Sabillasville to make one
Expand on site
Become wider
And then of course he got your double wides in your triple wides designed to be joined together
And as you make these leaves
It sounds like mobile home is already coming
Less and less mobile
Actually
Exactly is Pennywise in the 12 I've gained popularity they were increasingly created to just be shipped out sat down and lived
Do you know the US Department of Housing and Urban Development this post
The problem a lot of these relatively new mobile homes were not being construct
The same standards as normal Lotto
So in the mid-1970s Congress pass
Mobile home construction and safety standards
Which basically was to make sure that
New manufactured homes will be more energy of
In disaster resist
It's a one of those regulations due to the industry and the mobile home housing stock
What would you hide code set standards for things like safety and durability but also heating Plumbing ventilation
Air conditioning
Electrical systems
All those things you normally associate with Regional building codes but that didn't
Always apply to mobile homes
Federal sampling this is where that manufactured homes distinction comes in
Predictably of course some people
In the business of producing prefab homes work exactly pleased with the added layer of regulations on sick
First year of the new rules deadly the better Design interior Construction
She mentions her brains book how buildings learn which is all about the ways that buildings
Evolve and adapt over time
It seems to me that
And whatever you call these types of homes
Trubisky
Pre-designed self-contained and they're not really designed to change
Yeah in a way that's true they don't have to change over time you know the factory build it ships it out
That's down plugs it in and it's
Good2Go
Brandpoint that these initial modules are actually rich with potential to
As he puts it
A small unit can become the quotes
Seed around which a larger home grows
So for instance an owner might build a shed roof
Taqueria port
Men eventually in clothes that on all sides to create interior space
Super Sunday
Can't afford a house right away
A big house
This kind of base model approach
Allows owners to build out on their own terms
Let me have the time and the
Of course this is also tied up in that increasing in mobility of
Manufactured housing
Right once you start expanding this thing
Are the staff
And so what about Friday the original mobile home popularizer with a builder and seller of these kinds of structures
What was his reaction to the
Shift from mobile homes to these
Immobile manufacturer
So he ended up exploring some pretty extreme ideas in the 1960s and 70s
Well heads over here developing standards
Free
Is actually proposing skyscrapers for mobile home
And one of those early plans was to rectum
Is two spiraling Towers in Milwaukee
It was hundreds of parking spaces
For portable dwelling
And those Powers were also at restaurants and shops
Community spaces
Above and below the parking fee
Living areas
So maybe you stay for a few years parking brake
New job
NH place you'd be living in a walkable downtown and that's reminiscent of Ready Player one where the main character lives
Stacks really Stacks and stacks of mobile house yet don't really look
All that night's exactly know I mean they're they're really kind of not very appealing and
Frankly the Prototype that frame made the sort of they were just a couple stories tall and they
Basically look like that
Weren't that appealing and they didn't work that well
But his larger vision of he's really tall towers was actually pretty interesting
Things you think about
You know if it worked out his so-called skyscraper terrorist could have brought mobile housing right into the heart of City
Combined Mobility with Urban density and I really
Unprecedented
Will you can see pictures of phrase proposed skyscraper Terrace and other vertical mobile housing designs on our website it's in that
Api.org
99percentinvisible was pretty sweet by Emmett Fitzgerald mix into production by Syracuse
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Beretta team includes senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery Chapman
Turn master
And me Roman Mars
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99% invisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Fun Mall in radiotopia
Tok FM
You by the show enjoy discussion about the show on Facebook you can't we do me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you're thinking
I need more 99 Pi my life
What we have all the old episodes and new articles about design every couple of days
What are beautiful website
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com