99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Delaney Hall
Filling in for Roman Mars
In 1997
A curator named
Catherine Otto
Was learning her way around the Smithsonian National Museum of American history
She was new to the job
She specialized in medical science
And there was this one storage
In the building where she work
It's like that classic
What you
Think of it as a dark
Dusty sort of scary mildly mysterious storage room in a museum there were drug charge
ARS air was parts of
Of mannequin bodies laying around but the weirdest thing was
There was this
Wheelchair that had
Go-kart Wheels it was completely customized had a Recaro seat
That was used in Porsche
Cars
Bank of tripping over it and finally I'm like what the heck
The Catherine. Started asking around
Where did this wheelchair come from why is it in storage
And no one at the castle
Which is what the staff called in the main Smithsonian building
Could really tell her
Nobody
Completely understood
Who had owned it had been left
At the door of the castle with a note pinned to it like an orphan in a bass
The note said this was
A chair that belong head Roberts
We think it should be at the Smithsonian
Ed Roberts
I didn't recognize the name
Not yet
If you live in an American city and you don't personally use a wheelchair
You probably don't pay much attention to the small slope
At most intersections
Between the sidewalk and the street
It's just a ram
A cut in the curb
Through the country now
Just about any place you find sidewalks
That's reporter Cynthia gorney
60 years ago when Ed Roberts the owner that wheelchair was young
The sidewalks at most Urban intersections ended with a sharp drop off
That's enough to stop a person in a wheelchair from reaching the next block without help
And the story of how the first widespread Urban curb Cuts came to be
It starts with a movement
The demanded Society see disabled
People in a new way
Which was Central to that move
At 10 so we're the hundreds of people who helped drag his wheelchair up Constitution Avenue
Middle of Washington DC
So we could end up at the Smithsonian
Insisted it was a piece of American history
Ed Roberts grew up in Burlingame
Near San
Who is the oldest of four boys and he loved the play baseball
But one day when he was 14 years old
He got really sick
With a fever
Within a few days
He was in the hospital
Zona Roberts
It's Mom
She's 98 now
And within two days of that he was in rush to an iron lung because he couldn't breathe anymore
Chinese own
It had Polio in a damaged his respiratory muscles so much that he needed the iron lung to stay alive
Iron lungs aren't made anymore but back in the day they were these full-body respirator
That encased polio survivors in metal up to the neck
And pulled are in and out of their lungs
Is polio wrecked a lot more than his breathing
You left him paralyzed below the neck
He could move two fingers on his left hand and that was it
Is paralysis permanent
Parents survived is high fever did not present this as good news
He said
Well how would you feel
If you had to live in an iron lung the rest of your life
I don't imagine you've ever been in one I've been in one and it's not a
Very good way to live
In order to escape the iron lung once in awhile and taught himself on his own a technique called frog breathe
That's a deep sea divers trick where you go poop oxygen into your lungs the way a frog does
Polio survivors whose weekend breathing muscles not strong enough to inhale that needed oxygen
A person could get out of the iron lung for short stretches of time
You swallow air
Like that
Swallowing
And then you can breathe
And they kept telling him to stop at that was not good for his body and of course he kept doing it because it kept him alive
An ed was determined to stay alive on his own terms
Here he is in a 60 Minutes interview from night
Probably
The people around us
Think about your own life
What's tenacious
But everything was hard
He was asleep but the Frog breathing let him leave it for a while during the day so he stayed in school
Fast once a week
How's his family
They were helping the world that wasn't built for a person in a wheelchair
Ed's brothers or his dad would help lift him into his chair
Drag the chair out of the house and then list the chair over curbs in up and down stairs
Or if they'll know we are alone
She would Rangel strangers
God have to give somebody help me
Get the chair up the stairs
So it would be
Somebody in the back of somebody on the framing
Get it up or sometimes it would just be me
Graduated from high school then from a local community college
The Berkeley in 1962 the University at first said no he was just
To disabled
And where can I safely live
But she still used every night
Wouldn't fit in a dorm room
Until finally somebody suggested housing him as a campus
Hospital
Patients room remade into a living space for ED
And all his equipment
Is Ed Roberts
To type 1
September 15th
In a series of oral history interviews much later
Add remembered what it was like to
To start as a
Berkeley
Do you remember your
The day you moved in the car
What it was like
Gary
An attendant would we led the each class
And then Edward recruit a classmate
To help him take note
Aragonite
Appliance usually find a good-looking woman
Give a woman a piece of carbon paper
She would take notes during a lecture and then she give the carbon copy back to Ed at the end
Are custody people
Valle Verde
It did so much studying and reading
That's a mouse want he used to turn the pages of books started pushing his teeth out of shape
So campus officials saw this experiment was work
Newspapers wrote stories about that
Is Mom still like to make fun of the headlines
Helpless cripple goes to college. That's one we all love
Quadriplegic student moved into a makeshift Hospital dorm
A young man who'd been paralyzed in a diving accident and was initially told he should just get used to Life as a shut-in
Then a few more arrive
Both to live in the hospital and to find lodgings off campus
The word started to spread
Something unusual was going on at Birth
These students had profound and visible disabilities
State paid special attendance to half their wheelchairs up staircases and intellect your Halls
You couldn't miss the new presence on campus
And don't forget
This was the 1960
Edwin to Berkeley
That's the story and Steve Brown
He has a genetic syndrome that among other things makes his bones break easily
So he's a sometimes wheelchair user and a co-founder of the institute on disability culture
So the 60s were a time of lots of protests and lots of Reform and lots of
Change
Very technical historical term it was in the air
And it was
In the air
Disabled people
Improvised dorm in the campus Hospital
Those rooms turned into the headquarters for an exuberant and irreverent group of organizers like Ed and Hales
Zuko's son assertive guy with cerebral palsy who communicated with a board in a pointer strapped to his head
They call themselves
The rolling quads
And like a few other coalitions of disabled young people around the country they started using a new kind of language
To talk about their knees
It's in REITs
The radical idea that people with disabilities
Had civil rights
The right to education jobs
Respect
Inclusion in public life
Distant right into the Revolutionary Spirit of the 19
Sixties and early seventies
And the Berkeley disabled students
Had
Berkeley reputation
At that time it was
An explosive
The place
Destiny human
Who had Polio as a kid back in the 1940s and has used a wheelchair since then
She was a young New York disability rights agitator when she moved to Berkeley for graduates
Was our responsibility
To break down The Doors
And we had a lot of fun
Because
It was much easier to organize
A demonstration in Berkeley
Then in Manhattan
You know so we could get
Wheelchair Riders to come
The city hall
Is a pretty large number
Notice she said wheelchair Riders
With a d like bicycle Riders
It doesn't really have the same feel as wheelchair-bound right
And disabled people from other parts of the country
We're coming to Berkeley
Charter School
Flexwork
To be a part of
A disability Vibrant Community
I was
Instantly attracted
To them and what they were doing
Debbie Kaplan broke her neck in a diving accident just after college
What you decided to study law Berkeley admitted her
And it don't come work with us
I mean
Two people in the disability community
We
Hung onto each other
Because we all had this
Idea about who we were
Nobody else around us
You know I mean
Everybody else was
Stuck in
The standard way of thinking about disability back then
Charity
Public welfare and
Disability memes
You can't do anything
You know Jerry Lewis Telethon
Inaudible English opium now
20 hours
Coast to Coast
You know that
Okay
Now let's see if we can get the people out there to love you too
The Jerry Lewis Telethon was the late comedians annual Marathon fundraiser for muscular dystrophy
Mug for the camera and brought in celebrity
Singers
And spent a lot of time smiling down at
Cute well-dressed children in wheelchair
The rising generation of disability rights activists
Hated it
Well we just wood
Fringe
Every Memorial Day weekend
Knowing that all these people were watching
Jerry Lewis
Squeezing money out of
People
Bye
Dramatically
Playing up
The most
Horrid stereotypes about disability
That
Having a disability is a fate worse than death
That we should be pitied
That if we
Do anything we are brave
Yet
Really not
Real people
I knew that be the only other time I saw a disabled people on TV wear during those telephone
This is Lawrence Carter long
He's communications director for the disability rights and education defense fund
Lawrence was five he was a literal poster child for the United Fund charity
Because he was born with Cerebral Palsy and he was cute
That was on the side of buses
I was in fundraising Appeals
And everybody we open up the checkbook
It wasn't
Until I got a little bit older and when I was
College and I thought wait a minute
What's the subtext of that in the subjects was what you don't want to end up
Like this poor kid
Do you think
Give us some money
As an adult Lawrence would go on to study the way disabled people work
Portrayed in the movies
And on television and generally in the public consciousness
What became very clear is there were certain narratives that got told
Often
You know that
Disability was something that we were to be afraid of
Disabled people were robbed
And
I remember 1972 there was a controversy around the Jerry Lewis Telethon where Jerry Lewis said
The man upstairs goofed
And I think the man upstairs group
He made a mistake
And I thank you for people like myself
And all these lovely people at the bloody phone here
Shoe repair that go
Ring that Bell in my mind from
Is that what people think of me
But I'm one of God's
Mistakes
The rolling quads and Ed Roberts in particular or one big antidote to the
Jerry Lewis Telethon
Ed flirted with women
He got arrested in college for peeing outside a bar
He told dark jokes about quadriplegia
Like when the doctor told him he was going to be a vegetable
An ed replied
Fine I'll be an artichoke
Tough and prickly on the outside
With a tender heart
Adjusting counselor was pronounced dead the beat
Very aggressive
Electric County his response
Well if you were paralyzed from the neck down. You think aggressiveness would be an asset
The nature
Eco of access
Of being included Mathew hats
In some ways force yourself upon the world and say
We're here hey hey hey
Because the tenancy
The programming
For the rest of the country even year in Berkeley at first was
See that
You're going to make those normal people uncomfortable
Roberts was in graduate school at Berkeley the disabled students were noticeably unmistakably
Part of the community
Even more so because somewhere zipping around in power chairs which had been invented to help wounded veterans and we're starting to be more of a
Available to the General Public
It got really interested in power chairs when he first watch another quadriplegic try one out
And now he had one of these new portable ventilator
Attached to his wheelchair
So even though he still use the iron lung at night he could stay away from it for a lot longer
And
There was a girl
To do that as well
Had.
APK
They have my attended pushing me around
For the power chair a person like Edward still need an attendant for some things
Emotion now
Not to go on a date
I learned how to drive a power wheelchair
In one day
But think about this
For more than a decade you've been able to get around because somebody's behind you
Pushing your chair
And now you're under your own power
Get to leave that wheelchair attendant behind
But you still have to contend
If you're trying to get across
Street
End
There are no curb cut
6 inch might as well be Mount Everest
6 inches makes all the difference
In the world
If you can't
Deck over that curb
These guys can only roll independently once they could get over the curb drop offs on the way
Yeah they could go hunt for a driveway
But that's dangerous for somebody in a wheelchair
Driveway send you right out into traffic
The whole point of a marked intersection
Is it it shows you
This is where it safe
Lacrosse
Departure writers actually
All the wheelchair Riders needed what we now call Curb cuts
Those slopes at the corners that make it easy to roll between sidewalk and Street
End
Here's where it would be great
To be able to tell you about the inventor of the curb cut
The clever person who
Who first thought of cutting metal ramps
So people could roll into intersections instead of having to step off
But
Nobody knows who that was
All we know is that they were not a standard feature yet at most intersection
9 Berkeley
Not anywhere
Back in the 1940s and 50s
A few communities across the country where people had tried to make parts of the built environment more accessible
There was a coach in Illinois working with disabled soldiers who badgered reluctant officials at the University of Illinois
Like she is fighting for us
Until finally the school set up a rehab in education program on its most important campus
With Wheelchair Sports and wood ramps into buildings
But by the late 1960s and 70s this new wave of young disabled activist like the rolling quads
They weren't going to wait around
The occasional enlightened college coach
They demanded
They were insistent
They didn't wait for
Her permission
You still hear these stories about the rolling quads going out on Commando raids at midnight
Guys in wheelchairs with their attendance using sledgehammers or jackhammers
The bus stop curbs
Builder on ramps and force the city into action
The story that the word midnight Commandos
A little bit
Exaggerating
Exaggerate
He said
1970s he was a disabled students attending at Berkeley started rolling quads fellow Traveler
He says maybe a few of them got impatient maybe they did go pour a few ramps themselves
We got a bag of tools
Concrete
And
Mixed it up
And took it to the corners
Would most
Is the route
So that occurred on I'd say
Less than half a dozen corners
Did any of these runs occur at midnight
Yes they were all done in
Under cloak of dark
It may have been against the law
Right
And so you can call them Commando raids
Do whatever
Those Commando raids never happened on a grand
Scale
Instead most of the progress made by The Rolling quads was
A Little More lyrics
A little more how real change often
Made
One day in 1971 the rolling quads show up at the Berkeley City Council in a
Posse
Roberts who has a poli-sci grad students
Zukas the guy with a pointer in the word board whose learn Russian and is finishing a math degree
And all their friends
Disabled and not
When you picture this remember that Berkley's council chambers are not very big
Really
What kind of stone to see
The whole lot of people in wheelchairs
We only until the council
Meeting
And saying that they
Wanted to have
Curb cuts
On every street corner in Berkeley
Because they needed to get around and they want to be able to get around by themselves
That's funny Hancock
Who was a Berkeley city council member and then the city's mayor before joining the California State Legislature
We were on a stage
Just I remember so we were elevated in the people in wheelchairs were down below us
Looking up at us
I'm just looking into their faces
Realizing the effort that it
It took for them to be there
I meant they were
Requesting something that had never been done to our knowledge anywhere on Earth
Was an overwhelming sensation
But realizing that it's something that we could do
And
Should do when what do
Until they did
The world's first
Widespread curb cut
City council minutes September 28th 1971
Declaring it to be the policy of the city
The streets and sidewalks be designed and constructed
So will take circulation
I handicapped persons within major commercial areas
The curb Cuts be made immediately at 15 specified Corners throughout the city
The motion
Cherry unanimous
By the mid-1970s the disability rights movement was growing and spreading
Groups with the rolling quads sort of attitude or multiplying around the country and even world
And 1 adjectives with pretty much key to the new movement over the next to deck
Independence
For everybody in this Crusade the physical fixes list was ambitious
Things that had to change in the built environment to make a real Independence possible
Not just crypto
Wheelchair lifts on buses
Ramps along side staircase
Elevators with reachable buttons in public building
And accessible bathrooms
Service count
Slow enough to let a person in a wheelchair be attended to face-to-face
Respectfully
Not pure down that from way on high
So they got to work
Are tired
They're uncomfortable
But their Spirits are soaring
San Francisco's hdw headquarters now is in its third day
And 125 disabled and handicapped are pledging they'll continue the sit-in through tomorrow night if not longer
Disability rights protesters hit Federal Office Buildings in 11 cities at once
They're pushing the government to act on long-neglected rules protecting the disabled in all facilities taking Federal money
The San Francisco protest turned into a month-long sit-in
With steady news coverage
People in wheelchairs
Taking care of each other and refusing to leave
Wheelchairs
The sit-in worked
Images of the grown-up disability demonstrator uninterested in pity kept
Accumulate
Disabled people in Denver staged a protest demanding curb cuts
They already blocked traffic until City Transit officials promised
To put in wheelchair left on all the buses
Now a couple guys in their own wheelchairs lean over for the photographers
Concrete curb
Holding sledgehammers
International University for the deaf try to appoint a president to like every other so far
Is not deaf
Angry students boycott classes and shut down the campus until their candidate becomes the college's first death press
And in 1990 when the sweeping Americans with Disabilities Act gets hung up in the house of
Disable demonstrators in front of the Capitol building weed their Wheelchairs and crawl up
The marble steps
Make sure that that bill get
Where were you turned on the television
That was the image that you
You saw that millions of Americans saw
We're disabled
Growing up
Stairs
Capital not asking
Not begging
Demanding
To be apart
Open Society
Going where everyone else had gone before
Lady wasn't the First Federal legislation designed to remove barriers for disabled people
But its reach was unprecedented
Access and accommodations for the disabled in all places open to the public
Businesses lodgings
Transportation employment
Anytime qualifiers
To be sure
The Ada required only what was
Quote-unquote reasonable
Employers
Builders
And so on
And there was a lot of argument about that word
Reasonable
What is the bill signing ceremony in 1990
President George HW Bush spoke with emotion
About the recent fall of the Berlin Wall
Which divided communist
East Germany from the West
Note that will he mention
And now I signed legislation
Which takes a sledgehammer to another wall
One which has
Why is the Cavs score
Too many generations
Separated Americans with Disabilities from the freedom naked blimp
But not grass
And once again we rejoice as this barrier Falls
Proclaiming together
We will not accept
We will not exist
Excuse
We will not
Tolerate
Discrimination
In America
The guy UC Berkeley officials once thought was too crippled for the University finished his master's degree taught on campus
Co-founded the Center for Independent Living disability service organization that became a model for a hundreds of others are
Around the world
He also married father to son divorced
MacArthur genius Grant
Whole California State Department of Rehabilitation Services
He was 56
An international name and Independence for the disabled
When a heart attack kill them
I was
Disability resources in Charlotte North Carolina
It's one of those programs based on the Center for Independent Living Model
Annie 1995
Julia was at the annual March and meeting of the National Council for independent living in Washington DC
And he died a few weeks earlier
Any special memorial for him was now on the sketch
We were camping marching down the the main street to the Capitol
They were going to put
Ed's
Wheelchair be at the front of the March
The Marchers follow the empty wheelchair which was being dragged
Until they reach the Senate Office Building
Speakers got up to honor His Life and Legacy
And Senator Tom Harkin from Iowa
Gave the eulogy
And he said you know when Martin Luther King jr. past they built
Statues
In honor of him
Robert Hawkins
There's a better way to honor this Warrior for another kind of civil rights
Not going to tear down barriers in his name
And every curb cut
Is
Memorial to Ed Roberts
And sometime later after the Marchers have gone home or back to their hotels
Ed Roberts attended push the wheelchair the rest of the way
And left it on the front steps of the Smithsonian
Cheers beautiful to me
That's Katherine.
The curator at the Smithsonian National Museum of American
She's the one who found as wheelchair in the storage
Is chaired now remains on permanent display on the smithsonian's web
It's all banged and dinged in the imprint of him
There's a
Big battery cage in the back it's all customized he has a bumper sticker with a statue
YouTube Liberty on it it with the
In big letters yes
!
But having Ed's wheelchair at the Smithsonian does not mean everything is now okay
As anybody in the disability Community will tell you
Every broken bus wheelchair lift every
Temporarily out of function Subway elevator
Every Uber driver who won't take a wheelchair every open manhole cover or car blocking the sidewalk
Most of the New York City subway system which city leaders years ago decided was just too complicated to make fully excessive
The built environment is still littered with barriers
Crickets are common now
But they're not at every intersection
Even in Berkeley
And when it comes to attitudes and Prejudice
Assumptions about what people with disabilities
Can you do an achieve and enjoy
We might
Accomplish
Full inclusion
We
Have managed
To make it easier
By and large for people to get into the building
What have we done the work
It's going to make it easier for them to get the education
Forgive them to not only have a job
But have a career those things
Don't yet exist
How many people
Even in
But here's what hits you when you go into Lawrence's office
It's in a building called The Ed Roberts campus
And they're actually about a dozen other disability rights organizations in that building 2
The police rolled over an entire block
Berkeley
And every single thing about it is designed for
Everybody to use
Inside like a great celebratory piece of art is this huge orange spiraling rap
It's two stories high
It's one of the ways to move between the first and second floors and all around the ramp the curved walls are lined with giant
Photos of demonstrations over the years
So if you're listening to this while walking
And you happen to reach an intersection that's got a curb cut
Maybe a bumpy one
Let's blind people feel by Cain where the Sidewalk Ends
BB guns
You might
Hold up for
Just a second
The most important thing I think people can
Realize
Is
That
By noting
Stopping pausing
Paying attention the next time you walk down the street the next time you try to cross
History
Say a little thank you
If you will
Crewcuts haven't just been helpful for wheelchair Riders
But also for people pushing strollers and shopping cards
For elderly people who use walkers
For bicycles
And this phenomenon
Has come to be known as the curb cut effect
Roman Mars will be backed
To talk with reporters Cynthia gorney about it
Right after that
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
So I was out of town the last
Couple weeks on the radio.
Okay East Coast
Store which is why Delaney filled in for me at the house
But I did get back in time to pull Cynthia gorney
The reporter on the story
Into the studio to talk a little bit more about curb cut
In this newest idea that
You'll sometimes hear about
Disability leaders and designers
That's called
The curb cut effect
So what's the story with the idea what is the curb cut
Term gets used
To describe
Pics that is made to help
Particular disadvantage
In this case for example
Putting ramps
Sandy sidewalk curbs
So that
People who roll
Because I have to
Can
Across the street
Safely at an intersection
But it's got much wider applications because it turns out that there are a lot of them
These fixes you do
Having helpful ramifications for a huge group
The GI Bill for example after World War II designed specifically to help veterans
Wide-ranging population in the United States the home building a Suburban communities Etc
And so who's the first person to apply the curb cut metaphor to this idea
Nobody knows who came up with the term the curb cut effect at least
Let me rephrase that I don't know who's out there surely knows
I was not able to find out
The idea however has been around for quite some time
And the
Most interesting example of
Recent times that I learned about came from Steve Brown the disability historian we heard from earlier
She told me that at one point recently
While he was doing a radio program about his work and disability history
Phone call from his own parents
You said we'll see that was all very interesting you were good on the show but
Don't you remember that back in Kalamazoo Michigan by the way
We had some purp cuts and Steve said what and it turned out that in the 1940s
In Kalamazoo
Disabled or injured veteran
Stop watching other disabled vets
Struggling up and down the Curves in Kalamazoo Kalamazoo turns out
Apparently at least at that time to have extremely high unusually high curbs because of river flooding
This guy
Talk to City officials into just in a very few Corners downtown
Cutting ramps into the curbs
People started using it and they got so interested in what was happening that they decided to study it somewhat formally and see what effect
It was having
And so Steve told me
The officials commissioned a report
So it's
Said
Set the curb ramps not only help
People in wheelchairs
Thank You For The Music crutches but
Women
Pushing strollers
Send Delivery Man with the deliveries in bicycle
And then it kind of
Ended with something like it was creating freedom of movement for everybody
Examples of
That were devised for people who had certain Savanna Jazz but really benefit Oliver
Okay you're going to really noisy bar you're watching the basketball game
You're following it
With the captions
You're experiencing the curb cut effect
You're trying to get into a building your hands are full of packages
You use the special electronic button or the button that you can
Just hit with your hip
You just used
A thing that was made for somebody who
Can't push the door or in the earlier example
Somebody who can't hear into examples like this all the time without being aware of it and it's
When I started working on this story
Whenever I would say to people curb cuts
They would
General especially if they were under the age of about 60 and had not been around Berkeley when the stuff I'm talking about what's happening
Show me those things that are in the sidewalk so you can put your bag or your stroller
That's correct
What was the strangest most unexpected
Carpet effect that you
Found in your research
So the football huddle
Turns out to have been invented
At gallaudet University the National University of the deaf
For students who couldn't hear
Because gallaudet in the late 1800s early 1900s
Had a football team
They had to figure out a way to communicate with each other so they got in a huddle and we're signing to each other
And therefore became the huddle
Yes it's true
So I looked it up
It is true
They were signing because they were playing other deaf teams
And they got into a huddle
Because I didn't want the other deaf teams to be able to read there signs every team in the NFL uses the football huddle
Let me see which animal wouldn't have thought of that because
Across the field you could talk openly
Appreciate hearing teams
And they couldn't hear you in traffic
So this is connected to a bigger idea that
Adding a lot of designers Maybe
A lot of other people know, Universal Design so how is this all connected
The person who is generally cited as the father of Universal Design
Although it's not clear that he actually invented that term he's
To cease now Was An Architect named Ron mace out of North Carolina
He himself was a wheelchair user
And he did a lot of very influential writing
Message being look
We shouldn't be thinking about just people in wheelchairs or just
People who can't
Seorj
Here when we design
We should be thinking about
Designs that work for everybody regardless of their Mobility their ability to their ability to
Hear their age
And there is among architects who are Advocates of Universal Design there's a set of set
Seven principles which are
To elaborate to enumerate here but they're very straightforward
They should be easy to use
They should be widely accessible they should use the best of the best available materials
And so
The
Curb cut
Has turned out to be a classic
Example of Universal Design
Because anybody who rolls
Uses it
Mostly I think that people think of Universal Design in the physical space
Case with like
Nice grip handles for people who maybe our arthritic & Crewcuts next
The next Frontier of Universal Design is in the virtual
Because the Internet is
The place where all of us are leaving for more and more of Our Lives more time how is Universal Design being applied to
Virtual
World's pyside from the football huddle
Will start being started for the deaf my second favorite phrase in all of this reporting was
Electronic curbed
Wow
Which is the term that people who work in Information Technology are now using to talk about
Ways to make that technology
Accessible
Available to people who can't see
Chad here
Can't use a mouse in the old days
Can't type on a keyboard
And Debbie Kaplan
The
Person who had originally been involved in the Center for Independent Living that we met earlier in the program
Does this this is her specialty now she works on accessibility of
Technology Information Technology electronic
Yeah those of us who
Thought for
Accessibility of the built environment
When we realized that
The electronic environment was
Getting built all around and end
Becoming more and more
Apart of
Of daily life
We realize that we needed to get involved
Quickly
How did they get in
I think that some of the earliest
Problems that they wanted to address were
How you make
Computer information available to people who cannot see
You cannot hear
Who can't use a keyboard
So
A lot of the work
Mapreduce
Ends up being a factor in our daily life
Siri and Alexa can recognize your voice
Because of technology that was originally designed
For people who need to be able to address
A computer in that way
There is
Program that
Let the record show I will never use that allows
Your email to be read back to you while you're driving your car right
Comes from the kind of technology that was developed
By people working on electronic curb cut
What was originally thought of as
Something just
For people in wheelchairs
Ended up being just taken for granted by everybody and
Used in ways that
Weren't even originally anticipated
Faded
For the benefit of
Many many more
The older than originally
Auto
And that's true for
The things that we do to make the electronic environment
Isabel also
So now that Universal Design and the curb cut effect isn't pretty
Widely-held
Uncontroversial opinion of how design speed on WOW
Where are we in the state of
Design about world or the electronic world
I would so to sum it up
In my own experience of learning about this
Bye
Describing a little bit about my time with Debbie Kaplan
At the time that we were meeting with each other that we live just outside Washington DC
And
Spending an hour with Debbie Kaplan is like a
Crash course
The advances and ongoing challenges
Of disability fixes
At least in the United States and we are more advanced than most Societies in this
Disregard
So Debbie Zinn attorney she's actually an old friend my husband and I have known her for many years
She has a very interesting job working on electronic curb Cuts information design
She lives in
A community that has been designed with Universal Design principles
Accessible to everybody
Pictures of Handy power wheelchair that gets her everywhere she needs to go we were there in the winter so you go down
And then ice accessible elevator with Debbie
And you go out in the street
There are curb cuts
In Silver Spring
So so
On the sidewalk is people who left their bicycles on the sidewalk now here where we are in the Bay Area
People leaving these new scooters all over the place every time I see a scooter now I think of people in wheelchairs
Is right
There was snow and I said I turned to Debbie at one point and said well do they make an extra effort to calm and clear the snow
No for people who are in wheelchairs who catches Dart around at the way somebody on foot and she looked at me and just burst out laughing
I said are you joking
So
We've come a very long way and I think anybody
Who is presently or about to be
Grappling with disability
Will understand how long away we still have to go
It's not just about
Universal Design principles in the making of things
We have to incorporate that into star behavior in our sense
Courtesy towards one another
Precisely precisely
Thank you so much
Thank you
99percentinvisible with Bruce this week by Cynthia gorney
Edited and guest-hosted
By Delaney Hall
Mixing Tec production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real producer
Director Russell team includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald
Tarun mathur
And me
Roman Mars
Please put your hands together for the newest members of 99 PIAA Joe Rosenberg and Vivien Leigh Joe did the brilliant piece
Broadcast a couple years ago and Vivian reported the crazy history of lobotomizing weather and
In that mini story on alarm design
They both joined us
Full-time Sophia walking around downtown Auckland New Zealand
Special thanks to asada Iman for the audio from the documentary
We shall not be moved
504 sit-in for disability rights
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99% invisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most innovative
YouTube shows in all of podcasting
Find mall
That radiotopia. FM
You can find the show and go instructions about the show on Facebook you can tweet challenge coin news to me at Roman Mars and the show
No and then I bi org
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you're thinking
I need more 9 p.m.
We have all the old episodes including the First episodes by Joanne
Ambient air and new articles about design every couple of days
Qunar beautiful
Beautiful website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
Maven
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com