99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars in the Arctic
Ocean there's a cluster of islands called svalbard the island are technically part of Norway but they're much far
Farther north than the mainland like way way up towards the North Pole the landscape is icy and mount
Turn on one of the icy mountains of svalbard is a very curious thing of all
The entrance to the Vault itself is striking a man-made obelisks sticking out of a glue
Glacier on top of a mountain
Yes the Vault itself is inside a mountain that's been brought Johnson from
Podcast endless thread showing which Ben and his co-host Amory sivertson tell stories that they find on Reddit
This week we're featuring one of those stories
So I'm going to have this one off to Ben and Emery
The story is actually been posted a few times by different redditors
But it's about people who aren't necessarily Reddit
Olga Marie Hager
Do you think Marie haga is already there been
I don't know but she definitely knows how to talk
Two interviewers
Do you want very short answers medium answers
Marie haga is a former Norwegian diplomat
He was a member of parliament in that country former minister of energy
Her current job is to manage one of the world's most important vault
Maybe the most important vault
In the world
Let me take you on a little tour
You open these metal doors
It's like something out of a science fiction novel
And you walk 130 meters into the mountains tunnel
The walls are covered in snow and ice
They look like they're made out of snow and ice
There's this big chamber
That I normally called the cathedral
It's painted white
It's not the ice crystals are
In this big room UC City doors
These doors
Lead into 3 volts
Vaults within the vault
What's inside
Precious treasure that is
Stored on permafrost a reindeer covered islands in the Arctic Ocean by bunch of Norwegians
Behind the iciest vault door at 0° Fahrenheit
Boxes boxes boxes and boxes of seeds
Seeds
Inside of these metal envelopes
500 seeds
Per envelope
The seeds are from all over the world
And I mean all over the world
Every country
It's part of something called the crop
Trust
The crop trust is like this massive backup for the planets food crop
There's only one back up in this is it
And it's all thanks to a Russian guy with a crazy story
Don't worry that's coming
Right now how about a list of seeds in the backup
From Marie Hagen
Whose official title is director
Of the crop Trust
So we are concerned
To safeguard the 3000 varieties of coconut
So are the four and a half thousand varieties of potatoes
The 35000 varieties of corn
925 Silver right is a wheat
Or the 300,000 varieties of rice
Best to mention some examples
There seems to be kind of a Noah's Ark
Aspect
2 best
That is actually a good description it is kind of a Noah's Ark of seeds
And it is mint
At to be
Backup if things go wrong around the world and unfortunately things do go wrong around the world
Occasionally
Once a decade small bird staff
It's supposed to take new seeds into the vault
This is going to happen just a few weeks after this episode comes out
On February 26th
Marie Hager and her team will disarm the bolts alarm systems turn on the lights to the tunnel in
Into the mountain
Unlocking Krieg open the vaults big doors
And put more seeds
Inside
Any country that wants to store seeds in the vault can do it
For free
Emery says in the vault
There is World Peace
South Korea's seeds sit next to North Korea
There are seeds from Iraq sitting in the frigid sign
Afghanistan
Syria
Seeds from Ukraine sit next to seeds from Russia
It's almost like this is the one thing
Whole world can get the
Protecting our food supply
In case of an emergency
Like a big emergency
This single back
This planet's worth of crop diversity living in relative
Keys under a mountain
Spirit of this has its origins in World War II
The global existential crisis
Like no other
Svalbard Story start actually not too far away
In Russia
The guy you could call svalbard seed Vault grandfather
Was a man named Nikolai vavilov
I don't know what the crop dress my organization would have been without Boblo
He really
Explain to the world back in
The early nineteen hundreds
How
Globally are fully interdependent when it comes to the crops
The crazy part of Babel of story though is that this man a giant in the world of crop genetics
Was thrown in a Russian Gulag for his scientific
Principles
In a bunch of is devoted co-workers had to fend off rats in Starvation to protect his life's work
The richest
Seed supply the world had ever seen
Hidden away
Underground
In its own vault
In what is now the city of st. Petersburg
It had a different name
Leningrad
And Leningrad
Was Under Siege
Okay
You know how people say so-and-so wrote the book on x
Well agricultural ecologist ethnobotanist in Franciscan Brother Gary nabhan
Wrote the book on a Russian botanist Nikolai vavilov
12 ft life was from a very well-educated family
In Russia
I think every one of his siblings became a scientist as well
The book is called where our food comes from
Retracing Nikolai vavilov
Cuesta in the famine
In the circle of life Gary's book shows that this Russian botanist in geneticist story really begins in fan
Hammond just like it ends
Grew up in a. Where
Russia and Eastern Europe had suffered one famine after another due to
Inclement weather
Causing crop failure
These famines that she grew up with
How serious were they
They were of Epic Proportions from the 18:6
These are night there were
Major famines who killed over a half million people in Eastern Europe in
And Russia and so he grew up in the smell you
Tolstoy
Babylon's upbringing around these horrendous crop failures and famines leads him to learn a ton about plants
In botany
And as he is doing his work as a botanist in the 1920s he starts to get into this idea that
Collecting the plants or the seeds
Preserving an understanding crop diversity around the world
Might help fight off crop failures
Because he might be able to breathe
And find certain strains that could resist bad weather and dust
Shannon
There were people with their eyes on the same prize earlier on in
History
Thomas Jefferson for example
Collected
Are seeds brought back cuttings or plants to the Americas
Elolf was the first one who had
The education in what we would call
Evolutionary biology
How plants adapt to different climates
Conditions
He answered of this
Humanitarian
Set of values
That underscored the way he did science and
Certify
Remarkable way I mean he really was a superstar
Up there with Charles Darwin and other people that we could mention
So we've been talking about Nikolai Babolat
Cool by many measures is one of the Worlds
Seminole plant
Geneticist
But also a scientist who has a very pointed reason for his work
She doesn't want any Russian really any human
To die again because of fan
Overtime this remarkable humanitarian way of doing science games Babel off a lot of follower
Both in terms of the science
And his altruism
In over his career vasilov does something that's
Pretty incredible
He and his team of scientists together hundreds of thousands of different kinds of seeds from 64
It takes over 100 different expeditions to do that
He's like Russia's Indiana Jones of seed collection
And he's super charismatic
He's handsome he's good at raising money
But he's not without his
Detractors
Everybody famous has some hater
In Babylon has got a problem
Eye problems name is trofim lysenko
I think I'll start out as a student of Babylon
Babbel app encourages him
But then listen kid gets into this weird pseudoscience
PepperJax the idea of genetics
And he becomes this like Auntie science-based agriculture guy
Which is little odd because he also becomes the head of the Academy of Agricultural Science
Wisynco doesn't like Babylon
Their Rivals now
And lysenko Gainesville
The ear and the favor
Stalin
It's August of 1940
You can almost guess
What happens next
Davila
Without on another collecting expedition in the caucasus
Found what he believed was a new subspecies of wild wheat that could be very effective because it was so
Drought tolerant
And as he was coming back to his vehicle
Several black
Unmarked cars from the KGB or its
Its predecessor showed up and without
Talking to any of the other
Doesn't scientist on the expedition
Bevilacqua scuttled away
And disappeared
From public site
So Babylon is thrown into a prison in Leningrad AKA Saint Peter
His family doesn't know where he is
His colleagues don't know where he is
But they have a mission
Babel ops mission
Preserving and studying the world's food
Killing off hunger forever
His mission has a headquarters
It's this building at 44 person Street in St Petersburg
Kiss staff
Sort of
Came together they adored this man and said we can't let anything happen to this collection we don't know what's going to happen
And so they put
325 of there
Staffers
On duty 24 hours a day
And sealed off 18 rooms
Because there was another threat
About to hit
Saint Petersburg
The siege of Leningrad starts in 1941
A year after Babolat disappears into a ghoul
This prison is a stone's throw from his family home
Battle Ops family members passed by without even knowing he is right there
In prison
The siege of Leningrad is unique
And that it last
Almost the entire War
Nearly 900 days
The city is cut off on the North By The Finnish Army in the South by the German
And at the time it is one of the most destructive attacks on a major city in known history
Constant bombing
Lack of food and water
People actually rush into the craters after bombs drop
Because water gathers in the crater
That's how they get their water
And through all of this people are starving to death in letting go
Everyone
Russian soldiers government officials
Also the families of the scientists who are protecting
Secretly protecting this massive seed bank
They're putting the location of the bank in the fact that it is full of food
Seeds rice legumes
In the metaphorical vault
They're not
Telling anyone
And they are really freaking out by the way
Because Hitler is rumored to be really focused on capturing the seeds in this feedback
As part of his world domination f
So it really is a high-stakes mission
So think of it you're starving to death your family is
You up for staying in this
Very
Powerful
Lee position
Well guarded building
And your weight is going down your immune system is going down
And it's one of the curators said
When someone asked him was it hard for all of you to try to keep
Defending the seeds
When you could have eaten them to improve your own personal health
She said
Well it was hard to wake up in the morning it was hard to get on our feet
Because we are so weak it was hard to get our clothes on
Because it was cold
But it was not hard.
Protect
Proceeds
Tell me the story about the
The p
Collection curator
Alexander skilken
Took care of peas
Peanuts and other legumes
And he was one of the ones
Who died in the
The first year of the effects sofa
Starvation with
Seed envelopes in his hand
We we know that other people
Died of
Diseases carried by rats
They were trying to
Exempt from eating the seeds
Erase collector name
Dmitry Ivanov
She died within
Just a few feet of 1000 packets of rice
It just by boiling up water
Cooking the rice could have saved his life
Overall
12 scientists
Died protecting Babolat slice work
During the siege of Leningrad
Most of starvation
As for Babble Of after a year-and-a-half of eating frozen cabbage and Moby Flower he also.
Died of starvation
He never made it out of the gulag
But the seeds survive
And so did the mission
The svalbard seed vault in Norway is a direct descendant of a Velociraptor
And that building in St Petersburg is now the Babel of Institute of plant
Industry
You visited the seed vault in St Petersburg few years back
What was that like for you
In my years of doing
Science
I've only
Wet
Twice
And one Swiss
In Hawaii when I saw
15 different endangered
Species
The last individual
Of many of those species all sitting on one table
Anna nursery and there were none of those species left in the wild
I felt the same way when I saw the wall
A photos
Of those 12 scientist
Russian scientist
Who gave up their lives
Sago seeds
I
I was Brokenhearted
Where did you see in their faces
The best
That any of us
Can hope to be
On behalf
Our fellow creatures
Thanks so much for talking with us
Thank you bless you for your good work
So Amory
Let's go back to Marie haga forum
Whose team of scientists recently opened svalbard seed Vault on that
Frozen island in the Arctic
Ocean so here's a question
If he's Country Store
Seeds are for free
Who's playing that song bird electric bill like like who pays for the seed Vault to exist
Great question I asked
To Murrieta
Our organization is
First and foremost funded
Bye
Government
But increasingly the crop trust is trying to work with the private sector
Ann Marie give me an example
We have address developed a conservation strategy
For coffee
Coffee happens to be very climate sensitive
And that is why we think
Badsha the major coffee companies over the world
Who get involved in lava rock
And also contribute to finding it
I for one am very glad that the organization trying to protect the world's food crops from a doomsday scenario
Is also working on keeping
Coffee around
Yeah I think we're going to need
Coffee after the
But for Murray of course
It's bigger than coffee
You know I
Considerate
A great privilege
To work on something so fundamentally important
As safeguarding the diversity of crops
That
Job is really about
Safeguarding the bases
Knob and
Tomorrow and forever
There are other seed banks in the world and our very own Emmett Fitzgerald is going to tell us about one of them
God bless
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Fox podcast
Okay so we're back with 99 Pi producer Emmett Fitzgerald and he's with us because
He was actually looking into doing a story on Babylon
Artio while back and it didn't pan out for a bunch of boring reasons
So when I heard the endless thread version I was like what
Play that one because we love the story
But you actually done some interviews on the subject already
Yeah and as I was researching it I found out about this other seat
Back this one is based in Syria and it's run by an organization called a
Carter
And that stands for the International Center for agricultural research in dry air
Areas
And I actually spoke with
Former director of a card at muscamoot Sula
My name is Mohamed Salah
I'm the former director general of the International Center for agricultural research in dry areas
And just like Nikolai vavilov when Mahmood was a young plant scientist
She said off on on his own seed collecting Journey
And where did he go
So she went through all these Central Asian countries places like
Jordan Lebanon Iraq
Turkey elected in Afghanistan
In August
And at that time Afghanistan
It was a peaceful country
That was a beautiful country
Ubf mountains of pistachio trees in Afghanistan
Mahmoud drove all over Afghanistan in this little Jeep looking for in a wild lentils
Chickpeas
Pistachios
What you're talking about
Inspired by Nikki literally following in Babylon footsteps
Or at least
At least I was trying
Like that time
I had the map
Very low where did he go so I was trying to follow the routes but rule Afghanistan
Extremely mountainous
Too mountainous
For the Jeep
Turned out we would love to go
Does certain areas without going on a
Back of a horse or a donkey
You know because
Those areas are so narrow
Sost
But to be honest with you even in 74
We could not follow what very low bid
In the earlier years
And that's why you really admire this man
You know he was certainly a remarkable person
So what happened to all the seeds that collected
So those seeds were the beginning of the year card at collection
And a cart of basically works with farmers in dry parts of the world and then one of the ways that they help them is by cancer
Serving and also breeding drought-tolerant varieties of different crops
Collectible huge variety of C
From Farmers all over the Middle East
East and North Africa
They've got one of the world's largest collections of drought tolerant
Including
Thousands of varieties
The barley and lentil and fava beans
And 4 years this collection was stored in the facility in Aleppo
Syria
Which I can see the problem
Right and when violence broke out in that country in 2011 the plant scientist
Starting to get worried about the
And so they sent some collective The Collection to other CB
Banks around the world
They were creating
Duplicate
The Collection you know in order to safeguard
All that material and then and then eventually they were forced to it to level up
But we got the seats out
Before
The staff Polly had to abandon the research station
This is
Harry Fowler and he's actually the founder of the svalbard global seed vault which
Suite we heard about in DMs
Spread peace
And Fowler end up
Calling up my mood and an inviting him to
Store some of the Carters
Seeds up in up in the Norwegian Arctic
We got them up to svalbard
When it became clear that those researchers were not going to be able to go back to their insta
Esthetician
Leggett re-establish themselves in Morocco and Lebanon date they ask for their
There's a collection back so they could re-establish their
Receipt Bank
This is actually the first time that anyone had taken seeds back out of the
Svalbard seafall
And they use those
Lucy is that Pepin store there in that
Tunnel in the mountain
To create two new seed banks
One in Morocco and one in Lebanon
So it's almost like they had this external backup hard drive their computer
At unit something happens to the physical computer you've still got all the data in this case all the seeds with
Backed up somewhere else
To start anew
Seed bank somewhere else
Yeah yeah that's exactly right that's
Analogy that a lot of people use and you know
There are seeds in a Carter's collection that you can't find anywhere else
So the consequences of not having that back up could be
Catastrophic
You know in the past this would likely
This kind of event
Would like
Likely have led to Extinction
And in this case I think it's pretty clear that
That would be the
Extinction of something terribly valuable
2 world agriculture
Because you can imagine that drought and Heat
Tolerant varieties of wheat
Barley went
Is Chickpea in
Weather going to be in high demand and that's
What's the place you got to get
Sweetest name to hear a story
Of the seed bank
Not just being this
Potential
To save us
Really
It was used
As it was meant to be to take him seeds and then send them out into the world
To stop
What could be a potential Extinction of a species it's kind of stomach
What an action
It's interesting as people refer to it often as the Doomsday vaults and there's this kind of
This kind of expectation that it's it's just waiting around for the Apocalypse
Casinos that we could then use the seeds
Regrow Mina restart our civilization or something but but Fowler actually see that is having a much more active role
What is this kind of like
You know this her backup hard drive for others
Seed banks around the world so that if you
If you run into trouble you can
You can store your receipts there and then and then take him out when he did again
It seems like
They're truly inspired by wawel off
Work
Yeah yeah I mean obviously like at the turn of
A veterinarian of the early 20th century was
It was super
Concerned about food security for Russia and then the idea was like
You know we got to have
Are are genetic diversity
Protected and then obviously people people are going to die
For that
Went with the idea that that Russia you don't need this season
The other side of the war I think
The challenges are different obviously today and then and more Global potentially but
But when you think about it
The importance for all of us
Are genetic diverse
Inspiring in a lot of these people work
Continue to be inspired by vivalavi E everyone I spoke with was was
Thot meaning
Referred back to him very fondly so much so that they literally followed in his footsteps
Tried to call Brian that he did on unkind of centers of diversity
Cities around the world in and how he thought about seeds
We're very much like ahead of their time and people still
Refer back to him and then his his ideas have relevance
Today
99percentinvisible was preached this week by Ben
Brock Johnson in Amory sivertson mix and sound design by John perotti and Paul Vegas
Play music by sculpture production of WBUR Boston
NPR station in partnership with Reddit
Iris Adler is executive producer of endless thread Michael Pope is the advisor and Reddit
Formartine senior producer Katie mingle senior editor Delaney Hall and producer Emmett Fitzgerald help bring this one home
The recipe name is Avery Kaufman Joe Rosenberg Vivian Lee Shreve Yusuf
Sean real digital director Kurt Kolstad and me Roman Mars
11 of us now
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On Radio Road and beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
10% invisible is a member of radiotopia from PRI
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasts
You find us all
A radio Topia. FM
Ubuntu Show entrance questions about the show on Facebook you can treat me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit too but you want to link and want to learn more about endless thread the show we featured this week which is very
Good I hope you enjoyed it and I hope you subscribe to it
39 pi
Ductwork
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com