99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment in California and
On the globe Define transformational Solutions quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
The 2009 feltron annual report from this moment every encounter you have
Another person encounters
Each mode of transportation
Like if I walk through the door I'm writing down the name of that store
Total locations
Reported 200
I just want to know every single place that I go Nicholas Felton AKA Beltran
That he would interrogate at the end of the year designing pie charts and bar graphs are used to create a can
Insights infographic that tells the story of Nicholas Felton year is it going to be through the lens of like my favorite 80s
And more is going to be through the person I spend the most time with
With one person
What do you think
He calls the beautifully designed result the feltron annual report
About this report that is the voice of freelance journalist Nate Berg he interviewed Felton in New York for
Easy to understand in the sort of graphs and pie charts that we've gotten used to seeing all over the place but
Presenting stuff directly got out of my own life to
Restaurants I go to last year how many beers did I drink
These are all things that I do and I'm the data ability to
Presented
Help Scott a connection between two
Essentially strangers all the easy dismissal criticisms about Foursquare check-ins and Twitter should be pop
Walking into your mind right now they all boil down to this why do I care about what you have
For breakfast this morning
And I get that
But if anything happens when you take
What you had for breakfast this morning and * 100 of its quotidian equivalent and multiply that
* 365
He's doing exactly what everyone else is doing but he's just doing it no more purposeful way it's not only
That he wants to track what's happening and come
See how his life changes over time but presented in a way that's digestible to himself and
Other people of even strangers what Nicholas Felton creates with all that sprawling information superficially resembles a
Corporate quarterly report but it's the most beautiful version of that you can possibly imagine true work
Consecutive exclamation marks use
2008 was pretty boring year
Travel very much of the highlights were like first ice cream of the year
But
Elaborate
Peter design work but took weeks to create
Thousands of dollars to produce to document this like one tiny memory that would have been totally lost otherwise.
It's my favorite way of telling stories now it's a
Way of making things that are
You are invisible
Or too large
To be comprehended
Making them visible
Rather than the abstractions
Looking at tables of numbers
They're pretty
Compelling and memorable ways
Revealing
Invisible stories
It puts more focus on the the little things that make up most of your time your life isn't really that trip that you took last summer
Countable times that you can walk down the same way to get your office at one house on the corner of
What that crazy dog you know how many hours of your life that you spent listen to Hotel California on the radio
I have to break in here to say this is where a normal public radio show with
Play the song Hotel California
I am your friend
And I would never
Do that to you
That's the beauty of this kind of representation as you can take something and represent
Millions or even
Billions of action
Reduce it to
Something
Consumable
Verde zero
Average beers per day
Seroquel
Nine9
Dalton has been doing this in-depth self-reporting since 2005 but the end of 2010
His father died
Answer the 2010 annual report took on a whole new scope
He took kind of that same approach but applied it
You know on a much grander scale to
Someone's entire life
The life of his father
2010 feltron app
Report I didn't want
My 2010 report to be
The story of my father's death
I think his death is the least in
His life story
Items catalog
So
I wanted to make something that talked about his life
Passport stamps
It's like writing a biography about someone
A different format
Rapsodia Amore valid one
Rooted in
The facts
Life is like a direct translation is very little
Very little my opinion
Pictures up in here
Further back
Evacuation
That my opinion
Postcards
Photos of Gordon
In record
Percentage of photos
Joseph Gordon wearing a tie
18%
It's his life story so
Bookended by his birthday
Sadly by his death but
One of the things I want to remember about him and I think it's
Part of his story is
That's the day he died
What the weather was like
Is the next
Statistic
Not trying to be shocking about it
But it needs to be in there
Want to have a little
Repose
At the end
Absorb
The end of his narrative
Last day
September 12th
I didn't want to dwell on
Sickness or
That his Spirit fading I think that's in there if you look at a lot of the grass you can see
A decline in in meals out its
It's kind of foreshadowed throughout the document that
The spring in his step
Miss diminished in his last few years
My challenge was to trying
Take that idea of a biography
Put it in a new
A new form that I hadn't seen before
And yeah but you have to give up on
Not seeing him
Smile if not seen him in motion not hearing his voice or just listening to one of his joke
But
That's part of the aggregate view that's part of this
Is grander scope that I was going for
Weather on September 12th 2010 49.8 degrees Fahrenheit and overcast
99% invisible was pretty sweet by Nate Berg and me Roman Mars
You by Nate Berg work at Nate Heisenberg. Com is it also mention you're the voice of data in this piece was done by
What a lovely and talented mrs. make Mars
The show 99percentinvisible is made possible with support from a lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
Define Atmore including links to the feltron website in the annual reports what you really do have to see go to
The 99% invisible. Org
Everyone it's Roman Mars again I just wanted to welcome a bunch of new people at the 99th percentile because
ITunes has been featuring the show on the big banner in the iTunes podcast or so thanks to them
And they were so great I think we've got a bunch of new people
Thanks for that little quote from Dad of amrod of Radiolab encouraging people to check out the show and the
Prime placement
So thanks for checking us out and I just want to let you know that all the old episodes of 90% invisible
They're all pretty good
Summer better than others but they're all pretty good and
Thrall will call Evergreen in the radio business so
They're not paid any certain day that information isn't too older doesn't get deprecated very fast
Does downloading Mall check them out
And I hope you enjoy them
I want to thank all the folks who've already done iTunes reviews I put a call out for these and we got
Cons of them hit allies in Lee close to getting 300 ratings and reviews
Which I'm really psyched for and you wouldn't believe how much they out they just they help
Tremendously in it's just very very kind and very sweet and people were running very very nice things
Thank you so much it's been fantastic
All right I think that's it for this week so
If you want to get in touch you can always follow us on Facebook
I put some stuff there that it always put on the Block so maybe you want to join on Facebook
You follow me on Twitter if you like your
90% invisible news
Peppered with a bunch of nonsense for me and my personal life that's at Roman Mars
Or you can just leave a comment on the blog that would be fantastic I love to hear from you all right
Take care and I'll talk to you next week
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero in
Any movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I
Had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com