99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the early 1940s has the war effort ramped-up
And maybe put out a proposal
Chairs they needed a chair that was Fireproof
Waterproof
Lightweight and strong enough to survive
Torpedo blast
An engineer named Wilton C dentist designed a chair he knew would be perfect
A chair made out of aluminum
Wilton Dinges developed a method of process
To take this aluminum
And bend it
Weld it and grind it and he treated
All of these elements are all invisible but
Part of making something
This super strong
That's Greg buchbinder
He knows this chair inside and out
It's the the most indestructible chair on the planet
Wouldn't they just proved Us by taking his super strong indestructible aluminum chair up to the 8th floor of the Excelsior Hotel
Hotel in Chicago where the Navy was holding chair auditions
He Pruitt
Out the window
And hit the sidewalk and found several times
Retroactively terrified by this post right
Someone ran the chair back up and it was it was
Completely perfect
Undamaged
The Navy was impressed and they gave Wilton dingess a huge contract
In order to fill this contract he opened a huge Factory
He called his business the electrical machine and Equipment Company
Amica
That's my fellow radiotopia and Benjamin Walker
Host of The Theory of Everything
Benjamin reported this story
Over the next few decades
Amoco ship
Hundreds of thousands of these
He's 1006 Navy chair
The US government
Factory
Hanover Pennsylvania
It became
Standard issue for all worship
Battleships aircraft carriers
Submarine
It's aluminum
Silver
Modern and minimal not too many floors
It doesn't even have arms
Just three slats
Coming down from the back
The top is art
But it's squared off a bit on the side
It's a utilitarian looking design
Except it has one slightly unexpected enhancement
There's a divot
Receipt for your butt
In the 1970s
Amica was purchased by a California businessman named Jay bookbinder
That's great father
But by the 1990s
The company was losing a lot of money
So Greg took a trip to the factory
To check on
When he got there things look really bleak
Primerica
It was
Skeleton Crew
The guys were we're just waiting for the company to close
The government contracts
How long dried up
Greg started to think
Perhaps this place should be shut down
But then
He overheard a phone call
Between the office manager Paulina
And a mystery customer
She was on the phone you just know we will not ship your chairs you should you send this money first
Slam the phone down and X
Alina who is that she sold some guy Georgia
Anime
She had no idea who that was
And I started look through the file cameras of who we were shipping chairs to
They were shipping chairs to designers like Giorgio Armani and Terence conran
It's tip entrepreneurs like Ian Schrager
Wealthy tastemaker
I discovered the beauty
Indestructible Navy Surplus chairs
Brake suddenly realize
The emeco could sell to what was mostly an untapped Market
I just felt right at the time
If we can shift our Focus from government sales
Focus on Architects and designers
That would be an opportunity for us
To take this thing
And turn it around
Greg buchbinder definitely turn things around
Today emeco makes new chairs with Architects and designers like Norman Foster
Frank gehry and Philippe Starck
And the original 1006 Navy chair has become one of the most iconic chairs in the world
You've definitely seen it before
All kinds of movies and TV shows that can be seen in The Matrix and Avatar
Upholstered version shows up in the dark knight when Batman interrogates the Joker
It's the chair museum team set in prison
And police station
It's also a go-to chair for fancy restaurants and art galleries and co-working spaces
It's everywhere
But not all of these chairs
Are emeco chairs
A lot of them are knock off
Sex
How can you tell if they're real curves see the bottom slot
Last month Benjamin walking around New York City showing me both real and fake in Macau chairs
Like the fancy Diner filled with wheel emeco chairs near his apartment in the East Village
Nice chairs in wood
Full of people
They look wealthy
Then Benjamin took me to his place
Show me his collection of real and fake Emma coats
First knock off
That's kind of excited about if you lift it up you'll see that there's something immediately wrong
Benjamin Walker is obsessed with the real and the fake
What makes something real and when does it matter
These are questions he's exploring right now in a mini-series on his show
The Theory of Everything
And for 99percentinvisible I wanted to look at the real and the fake
As they relate to the design of chairs
In America today
Most people think of design and shape the average consumer doesn't realize the design is so much more than
To understand what a real Amoco is
You need to understand
Not just what it looks like
How It's Made
There's 77 steps we go through to produce the Navy chair
That's why I took a visit
To the factory
In Pennsylvania
The first step
Actual sheets of aluminum
This sheet
Is the Sheep will use to make seat bottoms from
One of the most distinctive elements of an emeco Navy chair is the butt shaped divot
Legend has it it was modeled after the derriere of Betty Grable
A famous Hollywood actor
The 1940s
But there's absolutely no evidence for this plan
Growing up and friends would come over to our house and get the giggles about
That's Jay buchbinder she was named for her grandfather Greg's father and she recently started work
Working at Amica
Oh man
Now we're off to welding
I didn't see much automation at the emeco factory
Just a number of very skilled craftspeople
This is walter white now he's
Routing holes into the aluminum extruded
In order to accept crossbars that go into the two
Dennis case the famous
Vertical slats
The back of the emeco chair is curved like an upside-down U
And the three vertical slats come down from the top of this you
And made a curved crossbar
The three slots don't go all the way to the Sea they intersect with the crossbar 3/4 of the way down
Turn the most distinctive design elements of the immigration
Okay so now we're going over into
Are Department three witches grinding all the whales have to be ground down except 3
The original chair they made for the Navy had a lump of welding I need to join
But when the fancy designer started working with hammock out they found all the welds to be a little crude
So emeco ground down
Except for the three welds where the vertical slats meet the arch on the back of the chair
We leave
These three Wells on the back
Hazard signature
After the chairs have gone through all this heavy work
They go through a series of water bath
There's a total of 5 bass 1 2 3 4 5
In order to
Perfect
This process
After 5 salt baths in a 9 and a 320 degree oven
This aluminum chair is 3 times stronger than steel
Turn of the opposite of planned obsolescence
Many of the designers who work with them ago
Want to see this elaborate process and make the trip out to Pennsylvania to meet the workers
Like the famous industrial designer Philippe Starck
Visit was filmed by Greg
I was obliged
Call myself
I miss you
Because
Like a sister
You make
Scripture
I just got a new refrigerator you reproduce
Description
Everyday by Android and biceps
It's a beauty
That's why
When you see
Yorkshire
UC
According to Greg when designers visit the factory
I Come Away with a deeper appreciation of the workers and the value of the chair
Beyond its shape
When I take it architect
The one thing that they always say is
You should charge more
For this chair
A lot of Architects must have a pretty big chair but
Because emeco chairs are not inexpensive
Anew 1006 Navy chair will set you back
About $550
But you can get an emeco look-alike chair
For a lot less
There are several websites
That have
Listings from vendors of
Thanks
Counterfeit
Chairs
That's Madison BookFinder
Greg's wife
Cheetahs price for the company
But she also has this ritual
Where she wakes up every morning and scour the number of e-commerce sites
Perfect
And those sites are house
And eBay
Amazon
And
Alibaba
We have very good luck
If it's any
Exact
Copy
I can get those off and
Heartbeat
When companies don't comply with their requests
To take down the look-alike
Amoco can take the company to court
This is what happened in 2012
When Restoration Hardware started selling the naval chair
They even knocked off a name
So when
Someone is a
A counterfeiter
That's typically the kind of things they do in order to give their
Product
Fake authenticity
Restoration Hardware settled with Amoco
Before the case went to court
Greg's also got another big box
Like Target and Ikea to knock it off with a knock off
He can do this because he has trade dress protection
Trade dress protection is designed to protect consumers from the look-alike imitations of name brand products
He's not pressing the function or use of the product
It's just the dress how it looks and for emeco
That means the chair shape
That shape belongs
2 m Koh
Nobody can reproduce that shape
So
Having that
Kind of protection allows us to be very aggressive when when we need to be
But I'm at a lawyer
Christopher sprigman who doesn't think Amoco
Deserves this
So consumers in the marketplace when they look at this chair
Unless they are real furniture aficionados
They don't think oh this is Amica
I think oh that's a chair
Right or that's a pretty chair that chair would look good in my living room
I don't think that the shape of the chair is distinct
It's a it's an office chair design it's been around I have pictures of it from the twenties and department stores in office
If the cigars litigation I think I would have
Clear
Trade dress protection
Is really hard to get for design Prada
And Christopher sprigman building
If a macaw
Ever does end up in court
It risk
Losing this production
What really bothers Christopher is companies like emeco and Herman Miller and vitra
Turning to the law to take knockoffs out of marketplace
To the extent that that succeeds these designs become
The territory of the Rich and no one else can access them
But I just wanted
Put a fine point on this so this is a family company that's their business and I understand that they care about that
But let me just
Say that out there in the world are a bunch of consumers who want to
Furnish their homes
This is a country where not everyone is rich
If you want to be
Stylish and have a house that's nice and you don't have a ton of money
You might buy knockoff chairs
In his book The knockoff economy
Christopher makes the argument that these kinds of protection
Given to expensive things like
Chairs in clothing
Is actually bad for consumers
Because for most people
Knockoffs are as close as they can get
To the real
One of the things that's real about them is
They're there for
The rest of us right they they they bring the rest of us into
The world of the artist right they allow us to participate in the fashion world even if we can't afford the stuff
That is paraded on the runway
They allow us to participate in the world of
Industrial design
Furniture kitchen appliances
Does etcetera even if we can't afford
The super expensive
Browns
That's democratizing
I think it makes the country
You prettier and more enjoyable
But for Greg Amico knock-offs
Also make the country the whole planet worse
By filling landfill
What's with garbage chair
Oliver product is engineered
To be made
For the longest life possible
Anak office is
Is Shirley made to be
Seoul
Used
Thrown away
Great Clips
Probably still make nice chairs for less money
But it takes
77 steps to
Make a torpedo proof chair
Torpedo proof chair
Will last 250 years
The goal is to
To produce something
Where it has the least impact
Environmentally
All the way through
And has the longest life
To me that's the very best kind of product can you do
Greg genuinely cares about sustainability
I spent just a few days with him but I know he thinks food tastes worse when it's served in disposable
And that he travels with his own silverware
This is why he wishes he could use the law
To go after
The lookalikes
And the almost
Looks like
Like the popular lightweight aluminum Delta
The chair from Crate & Barrel
I showed him a photo of his
What is this a fake
Absolutely Frank
What they've done here is they
They put instead of three bars on the vertical back they put
4 bars
Instead of having a
Horizontal
Or
Towards the bottom they take these
Or vertical bars and bring them all the way down
The seat bottom
But
It's the same
Tube-shaped it's bent the same way the legs are the same configuration
The seat bottom has the bomb dipping if the front legs have the taper
This is May 2
Look like anime
Chair
We have a good look after dental work
Amazing
Benjamin took me to a Crate & Barrel in Manhattan to show me the chair in question
I think we have to go in this room I came in here looking for the other day
And look what these bastards did with us knock off
Of the
To The Crate & Barrel chair is different enough to avoid a lawsuit
But it retain those signature welds of the emeco chair
To give it that handcraft
To feel
But even if they mimic the wellness according to Greg
There will always be one key difference between the emeco chair
And this one
It it won't last it's not designed to last as long as our Cheerios
Greg is fairly certain
It wouldn't pass the original test
Turn off that 8 story building
Of course
There's really only one way to find out
The helicopter noise to the helicopter
Now that I have you on my roof on the 7th floor with the knockoff
Crate & Barrel
I kind of
I think the ultimate test is throwing it off
See what happened
You're on your own for that when you do that on your so there's no absolutely not
Let me hear what happens next
You're going to have to go to The Theory of Everything Everything me
When it's here is designed specifically to be affordable and that becomes expensive
And then affordable knockoffs are created
Which is the real chair
Percocet and I talk more about fake chair
After that
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is from
Frustrating it doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
Charles and Ray Eames were to America's most influential modern designers
In the mid-1900s they made all kinds of architectural products graphics
Films
Some toys
And
Furniture
You probably seen their iconic lounge chair it's very distinctive features of molded plywood frame set on a metal base
And it's usually top
Black leather upholstery
There are plenty of knockoffs of this chair and it's matching ottoman is here to talk about another chair of their
I'm more utilitarian Jared like Emma goes that also get
It's copied a lot
Charles Eames once said that their 1950s lounge chair was designed to be soft and cushy because he was sick of people
Complaining about how uncomfortable modern furniture
Answer those complaints were pretty understandable
In response to what are the other best sellers
Design a few years earlier
A series of molded fiberglass
Best Chairs
So I know this one and you probably encounter.
I kind of think of it as the school chair it's a
Has metal legs that you can stock up and
Is this mean seat pieces
Molded into a curvy L shape
And then there are various account
Arms are no worms that can have different legs different thousand faces all I kind of saw
Buyers could pick a base for the home or pick one for the office you have something more minimalist or something more stylish
But the chairs weren't just designed to look nice they were also meant to be affordable and functional
So they were low-cost easy to master
Mapreduce
Easy to move around easily
Keep clean
Actually the first prototype was built for an international competition for low-cost Furniture Design
Which was hosted by
Museum of Modern Art New York City
And so did it actually win this compass
Actually no second place
You know $3,000 a piece or so
Jury reportedly like that modular approach but they may have taken off points
Because the Prototype was made a stamp
Still and that's a tricky
Inexpensive material to work with
Takes these
High pressures and high temperatures
24 Mass
Actually switch
2 fiber reinforced plastic
And because the chairs are made up of just a few pieces they were easy to assemble
And that sounds a lot different from the 77 step process
That's great the aluminum Navy chair
Really is and that Simplicity is by Design
But these different areas do actually have something in common
Knock-off companies love to make copies
And according to One Source I found one of these molded Eames chair variants
This one that has what's called the Eiffel Tower base
Which is the son of
Four legs with these criss-crossing middle connectors
Is actually one of the most copied
Chairs in the world today
But if they were designed to be affordable
What is the incentive
And make copies of them
YouTubers that are officially licensed by vitra
Actually self
Over $500 emeco Navy chair
Given the same quote that Victor has up on their website
Getting the most of the best
To the greatest number of people for the lease
And maybe the real ones really are much higher quality
Einstein
Bill seems really high
And so are these copies illegal copies license
David Woodward
Deal with them
Will it varies by place
And in the UK for instance
Suspicions were originally protected up to 25 years from the date
Of creation
In 2016 they change the rules
Onexton coverage up to 70 years after the death of the
Creator and
Of course that shifted the legal status of a lot of modern classic
But also
Arne Jacobsen egg chair beast and Rose
Barcelona chair Le corbusier
Lc2 sofa
It sounded good cheese
Class table vitra the company that owns the rights to the molded Eames chairs
Really push for this chain
Which is not
So when tears went from being protective
For 25 years after its creation to 70 years after the death of
The Creator
What did
People say
Only UK a lot of people saw the news and rushed out to buy replicas
Ahead of the new laws taking effect
And when all this started advertising a pair of
Retro style Eiffel chairs
440 lb it went viral
Never opinions on all sides
Some argue that these very ghetto reprehensible knock
Eames Originals
But this one architect and design critic who writes The Guardian defended the copies
Asking
Isn't this exactly what Charles Eames would have
What do you think Charles and Ray Eames would have
Settebello
Obviously we'll we'll never know for sure
Give them their design philosophy
I really
Just keep wondering if maybe they'd have seen these affordable copies
As more real than fake and some cents
Because Max accessibility was a big
Part of the original design intent
So I guess it just depends on
Maybe what themes
Valued more
The shape of this chair
Or
What was made to do right and it comes back to this question two of you know what makes a design is it the shape of the thing is it the
The function
Doing what it's designed to do
Hibbett
If it's not too expensive
In that case
It is failing to do one of the things was designed to do
99percentinvisible with Bruce's week by Benjamin Walker and Andrew Callaway from The Theory of Everything
As I record this I still don't know
Benjamin actually threw that chair off his roof I don't know
And I don't want to know
I want no part of it
Until I hear it for myself
I'm Benjamin Walker's Theory of Everything
Mosey on over there for answers
From our team senior producer Katie mingle shape the story
Sean real me the music
Tariq Yusuf
Made it sound good
The rest of team is digital director Kolstad senior editor at Delaney Hall Avery Troutman Joe Rosenberg
Vivien Leigh
Emmett Fitzgerald turn Masa and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia
From PRX
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all Apopka
Baidu mall
And radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Did you want that link to The Theory of Everything
Any of our old episodes and new articles about design
That go up every few days
Head on over
299 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com