99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On a March afternoon in 1996
Toronto rap
There's a brand-new team in the NBA at the time
Playing the Chicago Bulls
Jordans
The Bulls were the best team in the league
And the Raptors
We're pretty terrible
36000 fan showed up that day
And the Raptors actually beat the Bulls
But it was a mostly meaningless game at the end of the
Season this is reporter Whitney Jones
What's the weather is going to be about this game isn't who won or have a team
Who's played
But the way they look
There's the Bulls were just classic NBA
I've had the same logo since 19
They're wearing their red away jersey
Basically like every Chicago Bulls jersey
It's red with the word bull was written across
The front and black and white letter
It's simple
Classic
But then there's the Toronto Raptors
The team is wearing their white home uniforms which have Jagged silver and black pinstripe
As if they were
Cut by slashing Raptor Claws and then across the whole front for the giant red.
Basketball playing Dinosaur
Who himself is wearing sneakers and a uniform a totally different uniform
And he dribbling a basketball
And that was just their home uniform
The road jerseys that you're even more fun
They were bright purple
All this including the Raptors name had been inspired by the Velociraptors in the wildly successful movie duress
Beihai Park
But these jerseys got compared to a different
Much friendlier 90s dinosaur
Dinosaur
That's now known as the Barney design because
Their Road uniforms
Purple
This is
Paul Lucas
Uniform obsessive and writer of a column an ESPN called yunnan
It's it looks so cartoonish conservative
You look at it in
Like really that's a professional
Top-level
Team
The Raptors jersey may have been particularly garish
But it wasn't the only Jersey of its kind
The 90s were this insane decade of NBA uniform design
Reduce some of the wildest jerseys that have ever graced a basketball court
Design the likes of which had never been seen before
And haven't been seen since
Like the Atlanta Hawks red and black Jersey with a fierce-looking hawk swooping in across the entire front of it
Holding a basketball and its little Talent
What are Milwaukee Bucks green unit
With a giant picture of a purple stag
Call Lucas called this one great
Hemingray in the sense that it was
So awful it was great
They had this you know this person
Garish purple and green color patterns
Ridiculous butt
It definitely all these designs
Definitely
They pushed and extended
The idea of what a basketball uniform could be or should be
And many of these designs can be traced back to one man
I'm Tom Brady
I joined the NBA 1990s League's first creative director
Tom group in Chicago
Sketching Andre sketching the logos of his hometown Chicago Blackhawks
Another classic Pro Hockey
Comes love for sports and eye-catching art
May this new NBA game
Dream job
My first day at the NBA was just
Filled with excitement
I'd always been a big sports fan
And I loved
Design
I studied graphic design
Cheer Columbia College back in Chicago
So when I walked in the door in June of 1990 I kind of had a pinched my
Cuz I really didn't
Believe it was happening
Before Tom O'Grady join the League most NBA jerseys look something like that classic Bulls jersey
It's simple two or three color schemes with the team names across the front
There might have been strike here or there may be a cool font but that was about it
And they weren't designed by designer
The process of Designing team uniforms is mostly left up to
The team equipment managers
Because they were responsible for getting
The players outfitted
To play the game
Mostly this consisted of the equipment manager
Flipping through a catalog
Choosing a designer like
The right colors
It was not a sophisticated business
Let's say that
They were happy just to get Uniforms on the players back
But that was all about to change
Because in 1988
Charlotte Hornets introduce a radical new idea
The color teal
In this archival news footage from 1988
Hornets player Kelly tripucka stands on stage in front of flashing camera
Any rips off his teal Tearaway warm up
To reveal the Hornets new uniform
Teal was not a traditional NBA jersey
Not NBA red
It's not NBA blue it's not self
Fix screen if not Lakers yellow
Tom O'Grady had nothing to do with a teal Hornets
But he took it as a sign that the league was ready for Boulder design
It was I was at the kind of a leap of faith
Fridley to say you know this is not really something we've seen before it but as an expansion team will probably let you have this one because
Maybe there's something we can learn
It turned out fans love
The teal Hornets Jersey
It looks fresh
Indifferent
It was really very popular they soon became
Known as the Man of Steel
In all sudden
The Charlotte Hornets have gained great recognition
Before they never played the bass
When Tom O'Grady was hired as the NBA's first creative director two years later in 1990
He wanted to push Jersey design even further
Not just the colors
But the designs on the uniform
Until the early nineties there has been real limits to how Wild you could get with these designs
Because all the details
The numbers the names and the logos had to be sewn on
To do any kind of complicated graphics
Would have taken a massive amount of embroidery
And all that thread would have added additional weight made the Jersey hotter to wear
But soon after Tom O'Grady join the NBA he would get some new tools to work with
Computer programs like Photoshop and illustrator
Helped him dream up new logo designs
And was a new technique to get those drawings onto a Jersey
It was called dye sublimation
Sublimation changed everything
Sublimation is a process of printing dye directly into the fabric
No for the first time you could design something in Photoshop
You can make it big and you could add a bunch of different colors
Then with sublimation you can basically print that design straight onto the material
Without any embroidery or extra weight
So
It allowed us to start to take things we would never normally even
Consider doing
On a Jersey
And we started doing more outrageous uniforms
The stuff because we could
We can
So we will
Comes first big design was for the Phoenix Suns
We're celebrating our 25th year in the league
They were moving into a new Arena
They wanted a new look
Soto met with their team owner Jerry Colangelo
Gary is great he was a fellow chicagoan so as soon as he heard my accent he's like
I think we're going to get along you know I think of Chicago guys kind of get this here's what I want to do
I want to have a logo that's going to last for the next 25 years I don't want to have to change
I want something futuristic
The classic
So Tom and his team started on the Suns redesign
They come up with this big basketball that's also a son
Aziz long red to orange gradient sun rays coming off
And then they print this
And a bright purple background under their New Jersey
It's not exactly what I would call Classic but it is bold
Definitely both
As luck would have it the Phoenix Suns made it to the NBA finals last year
And the whole country got to see that bright purple jersey
With its blazing basketball Sun
All over national TV
We got exposure that uniform that
Was
Priceless
That changed
Everything
For us we were able to do
Things with uniforms that we could not imagine even two years before that
Like a teal Detroit Pistons jersey with a flaming horse head logo
Wear a pinstripe Houston Rockets Jersey featuring a cartoon rocket
With an angry face on it
Over the course of the decade 2/3 of NBA teams got new uniforms
With new logos and new colors
There was a lot of teal and purple
3D lettering and oversized Graphics were everywhere
We look back on and see Wild
Some of the stuff
Capri Outlander
That's okay cuz that's what was happening at a time
The technology let us go wild
Atoms boss NBA Commissioner David Stern
Gave him the freedom to keep pushing the designs further
He said you know if this is what selling any of you telling me this is what's going to
Work at retail
Count Me In
Before the 90s the NBA wasn't doing much with merchandising
If a fan wanted to buy a jersey they had to pay the full cost of a genuine stitched
NBA game Jersey
Sometimes over $200
With all these popular new designs
Tom and others at the NBA got thinking
Why don't we
You know have a
A jersey that we can sell for about 2
45 to $50
That looks similar to the game Jersey
And we saw this business explode
Me know in 5 years
It went from a
Almost like
Baseline of nothing
A multi-millionaire
Our business largely on the jerseys
We were designing
The Arab outlandish NBA uniforms reached its apex in 1995
Wechat Jersey we talked about at the beginning
The one from Toronto
One that some people call the Barney design
We were told directly by the team owner at the time John bateau
I would like to Happy Meal box of uniform design
We can look at in public like what
Did you mean by that
He said I'm not going to wear this uniform forever aventino
Kids don't eat out of Happy Meal box
Forever but if you going to get the kids into your
Store
You're going to win him over
Happy Meal design isn't a term yet
Making it 1 right now
The goal was to convince hockey loving kids in Toronto
That they should care about this new basketball
And so we crazy
Purple uniform
What these Jagged Edge cloth Pinstripes that look like a raptor come and ripped it
And then I slapped a big dinosaur right in the middle of it
And they made it red
Because
Canada
You wanted red wraps up to represent Canada which made all the sense in the world
I don't know how much sense it made
MoDOT Jersey it sold
I think it was the top-selling expansion team logo we ever did even today
Sales are through the roof
Before they ever played a game
Before the team had even signed a single player
The Raptors were seventh in the league in merchandise
What is the nineties came to an end
Change was afoot
And stuff was about to get a lot more
Boring
By the early 2000 the NBA
I become a booming Global industry
And Wealthy business people were suddenly interested in team ownership
People like Howard Schultz who turns Starbucks into a multibillion-dollar business
In 2001 Schultz about the Seattle SuperSonics
And he came into the league with a whole laundry list
Changes to make
He wanted to replace the Hip Hop
You here in the arena on Game Night
Jazz
He wanted his team to stick to the fundamentals
Best flashy dunks in Showboat
The favored team basketball over individual Stars
Who's actually really bad for his team because it pissed off their actual Stars
Also Schultz
Hated the sonics 90s lock
Have been designed
Another Bernard Powelton
We were able to take this kind of basketball spinning around
Space Needle and kind of Heaven
Superman fonts in
Added Ford sonnichsen
In there and they change the colors from green and gold
The dark green red and a metallic bronze
Old Howard jazz instead of hip-hop Schultz
Was not a fan
So we hired Seattle design firm hornall Anderson
Completely remake the sonics graphic identity
Jersey's warm-ups logos
Everything
So so damn excited
This is Andrew Wicklund
Who is the lead designer on the
What
The sonics look like at that time too and
A lot of other teams frankly that have been rebranded in the
90's show
Yeah it was it was
Can the candy store
The directions were given was clear
Immediately go back to the old classic green and gold color scheme
And do something iconic
Howard's words
Where I want this to be something
That nobody would ever want to change I want it to be
The Chicago Cubs the New York Yankees
Is the Green Bay Packers
Those are
Solid shapes simple shapes they are
Simple color palettes
Simplification
Is it strength
By the start of the 2001-2002 season
Everything was in place
Green and gold
No 3D anything
No giant logos across the chest
Do uniforms look like an update to the ones that started wearing in the late 70s
But if Howard Schultz was committed to making the sonics and iconic franchise with an iconic look
His commitment didn't last very long
In 2006 he sold the team
The new owners move the sonics
To Oklahoma City
But Schultz's aesthetic Vision Ripple throughout the league
Throughout the odds one team after another
Slowly return to the old color scheme
And lost their big graphic Jersey
Even the Raptors look has completely changed
This year the two main jerseys were red and white
And they just say raptors on the front and a symbol font
No crazy claw marks
No dinosaurs
Here is Tom O'Grady egg
They're just there's nothing to them
There's a zero there lifeless
And I don't get it
Say what you will about Tom Brady's jersey
But they were not
Lifeless
Is designed are mostly gone from the NBA now
They live on
Blog post
Listicles of people's favorite jerseys from NBA history
Who are their least favorite
In their 2015 list of the ugliest basketball jerseys of all time
Sports Illustrated wrote quote
Toronto Raptors cartoon dinosaur logo
Is one of the worst
In all sports
Thankfully
It will soon be extinct
What time does it mean when people call is designs Garrett
Or even ugly
He's proud of that Raptors
I was meant to be provocative it was meant to be kind of eye-catching
We could have taken at start out with you no 72-point have vodka that says Toronto and a big number on the back and call it a day
I think that would not have been a memorable Identity or no
A great way to introduce a new team
Sentence for Newmarket
And if people are still talking about it
Then he did his job
Right
I'm fine with the criticism
About people thinking it's the worst thing ever because
It certainly is certainly says Hey and I'll
We noticed that we have an opinion about it we have a strong open
We remember it
I think that's
That's great
And the Raptors original plan to hook kids with the Happy Meal of NBA jersey
Love it or hate it
You could argue that it worked
Today Toronto has a loyal fanbase
Head over the past five years I've had some of the highest attendance numbers in the league
And as for those bold 90s jerseys
They haven't actually gone extinct
Entire company
Mapreduce retro jersey
And many of the designs, Grady and his team came up with
Are really popular
I want the top sellers
Its a bright purple jersey
For the jagged claw cut pinstripes
A red dinosaur
Dribbling a basketball
Because Oakland Warriors swept the finals this episode about basketball jerseys the season by Justin
I hear but I have good news for you
It's time for the World Cup and we have the perfect design nerd World Cup conversation starter
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
So most major sports that involve a ball
Including
Basketball and baseball in American football
They went to early periods in which
Actual ball designs buried
A whole lot
But in general the shapes in the materials and dimensions and the basic look
Have all become standardized
Overtime
You know in the NBA you've got a big brown ball of a certain exact size
With thin black lines
Major League Baseball
A small white sphere made
With exactly one underneath double stitches are veterinarians and then in the NFL ever
Uses the same brown prolate spheroid white stripes
Plated
Very narrow pressure range of around 13 PSI in trouble
Active measures
Hampton sequestered before the game
What is Kirko said I'm talking to he's our digital director and we're going to talk about a type of ball that is
A bit less consistent it continues to change year after year it is the socket
In 1930 at the first World Cup
The two teams competing in the final game couldn't bother you
Sophie's actually stepped in and had them alternator
Between two different balls
Using 1 teams picked for the first half
And the other teams picked
The second half of the game
Going forward FIFA rule that they are
He just one ballpark
Make census of the two balls in 1930 look pretty similar they looked on like volleyballs and pretty rough-looking and you could see
See the laces around
Send it to
Yeah and those are pretty typical for the time and for the decades after most balls about. Follow the same
Basic model long strips of leather
Is together into a rough sphere
Most were of a single solid color to usually
Neutral Browns yellow
Oranges
Stop lights bulbs and I grew up with didn't look like that it was made up of
Very uniform patch work
High contrast
Black and white
Geometric shape
A map of Europe
That classic soccer ball that's
Very recognizable
Basically iconic at this point
That's if you do an image search on the web for soccer ball icon
That's exactly what you'll find
So how did this become deejdesign everyone
Will soccer balls first started featuring this
Distinctive pattern of pentagons and hexagons
In the 1960s
Then he got really famous when fee that use a virgin made by Adidas
For the 1970 World Cup
They wanted something high contrast
So the gameplay would be easier for viewers at home to follow on black and white television
The so-called
Telstar ball
Was an instant
The name Telstar is a portmanteau of the words television and star
Because it was meant to be the perfect soccer ball for televised games
The name was borrowed from the Telstar communication satellite
Which was white and spherical and had black solar panels
A lot of substance
Have continued to use the same basic approach of alternating darks and lights
But the designs
Have really evolved to over the years
Official balls went from having 32 to 14 to just eight panels or fewer and son
And this isn't just cosmetic
Those different number of panels
Change the function of
Yeah they affect the shape and how the ball performs on the field and make a really big sort of structural difference
So can you tell me about this year's ball
Yeah so this year Adidas
Urban Design these balls
Since 1970
Telstar ball
They're back again
And this time they're actually bringing back the Telstar
With the Telstar 18
How similar is the Telstar 18
To the original
So it does have black and white but this news
6 panel design
Actually also features a digital grid pattern of the grave
Pixels that fade between League
Well the original Telstar could be
Easily distracted into a logo now or shrunk down to an emoji
This one has too much detail for that
It seems more designed to sell the latest cool looking bald and actually work
Is an icon
What is crazing mean if they keep changing the design and forcing professional players to deal with
Different shapes and weights and aerodynamics
Over and over year after year that's
That's crazy to me
Yeah it's been a big source of controversy
T2
Ahead of these World Cup competitions
Some players complain about having to figure out how to avoid this new ball will actually behave on the field
And it kind of makes you wonder if we should just
Stick to one basic uniforms
Structural design
Figure out what the best Geometry and materials and then you can make superficial changes
Teams that look but don't touch
Function of the ball
But meanwhile I'm For Better or Worse
There are a lot of different designs
There and you can see a ton of them on our website
What's a 99 p i
. org
99percentinvisible with Bruce's sweet by Whitney Jones and Emmett Fitzgerald
Whitney is the host of the show pitch who's next season is coming out on Audible
End of this month on June 29th
Are mixing tank production was by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Senior producer Katie mingle and Joe Rosenberg handle the added
The rest of team is digital director Kolstad senior editor Delaney Hall
Vivien Leigh Karen Meza and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Confetti streamers
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all the podcast
Fun Mall
And radiotopia. FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi or
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But I have a few follow-up episodes for you if you want to really dig out about sports uniforms
Find episode 111 featuring Paul Lucas of uni watch and Jesse thorn of NPR's bullseye
Talking about baseball hosiery
Seriously
It's great
Did you want more from Whitney Jones and pitched
Check out the episode we do put them on REM out of time
And how it may be the most important political album of all time
Because of its Packaging
Episode number 124
Newborn both on Apple podcast
Store by searching are beautiful and functional website
99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com