99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Back in the late 1980s
When Louis guy was a little kid growing up in Columbia
His brother didn't have babysitters
They had bodyguards
His parents would send them to school in an SUV that was accompanied by another identical as UV
Which was a decoy
Because that meant if one of the vehicles was attacked
It would be a chance we would not be
That's Lewis
Are life is strange in many ways back then
My brother and I had our own bedroom
But every night our whole family would sleep in the same room
It had a door to the back patio and a ladder ready to use in case we need it to
My parents made it seem like we were just having a slumber party
But the real reason that Louis's family took these precautions is that Lewis's dad was a captain in the anti-narcotics
Unit for Colombia's National Police
Pablo Escobar
Notorious drug lord
I declare war on the police
On the whole Colombian state relay
It's become a typical day in Colombia three more judges who quit their jobs after being tracking
By the murderous drug cartels
The government has imposed a curfew in nine cities
In the heart of cocaine country including
The cartels Capital Medellin
Today the
The late 80s and early 90s
Esqueleto supplying 80% of the world's cocaine
And environment surrounding the drug trade have gotten really bad
The epicenter of the violence was minnijean
Escobar's cartel was based at
And they control
13 bombs have gone off and Midian since the weekend all aimed a government owned Banks or state liquor stores
Marine became the most dangerous city in the world
In 1991 alone around 6000 people were killed
The murder rate was almost 400 people per 100 thousand residents
Which to put things in perspective
That's three or four times more than the most violent cities in the world today
But today me the genie is very different
In just 30 years
It's changed from being the bloody cooking capital of the world
Into a place that's often described as a model
It's no safer than many cities in the US
And amazingly
What are the things that helped to pull the city out of the vile
What's a whole new approach to urban planning
Including a major overhaul
Best cities public transportation
Lewis's family experience Colombia's many changes
Louis is now a journalist
Annie's going to help us tell the story of what happened
Along with Maria Elena HOSA the host of NPR's Latino USA
She covered the violence in Medellin back in the 1980s
And she went back again last year to explore the city with Luis
Alright so funny
So we are here in downtown Meridian
You were here 30 years ago
What was it like
Yeah I know I remember that when we
Came to this
Circular Park
I just remember walking here
I'm feeling very afraid
Feeling very afraid because
Everybody knew that at any moment
Anywhere a bumpkin
Our story today is a collaboration with
Latino USA
Marine sits in a valley surrounded by steep Green Mountain
In the cities early days
The mountains were undeveloped
During the first half of the 20th century the city rapidly industrialized
More and more people came to Medellin for manufacturing and textile jobs
And it began building homes and communities of the sides of those mountains
These informal settlements became known as camunas
The community really thought of as separate from the rest of the city below
Both because of their geographical distance from downtown
And also because it would neglect
By city government
Didn't receive the same Services as other neighborhood
Public transit
It would take more than an hour to get from the farthest camunas to the city center
People in the community essay
I need to go to Marine to run an errand
Even though they were technically living and Maddie
But as the manufacturing economy boomed
And look the other way
Until the hills above the city were crowded with houses
Stack on top of each other like colorful box
But by the 1980s many of Columbia's manufacturing jobs are moving overseas
And is manufacturing with tanking
The drug trade skyrocketing
The Medellin cartel began recruiting young people mostly young men
From the kimonos
These were young people who felt disconnected from the water City
And they didn't have a lot of other options for jobs
American Odyssey
TV
I was quite a stir Escuela del Barrio La Paz
El Lugar donde nacio
This is Manuel espinazo
He says that back in 1989 he live two blocks from where Pablo Escobar grew up
And his group of friends had to make a choice
To be seduced by the drug trafficking life
Where to continue studying
You were having to make that decision am I going to be
Going in suddenly making Fast Money dealing drugs
Or were you going to kind of you know becoming something else
What what did that look like
Amigos que aparecen con Moto con Carro
Completa Para
Started seeing friends with motorcycle
Golden knights Club
They talked about working for the narcos for a few months to get fast cash
They have money to party on the weekend
She got the
Hand soap bubble bath
By this point Pablo Escobar have been running the Medellin cartel for more than a decade
Forbes Magazine had recently billionaires issue
With a provocative headline
Presidente Don Pablo
And that wasn't a huge stretch
Through his network of informants
Escobar control module managing in other parts of the country
He cultivated a Robinhood Type image
Building housing and soccer fields in the community
He was a hero to some of his friends
Johanna konta
Bluebird
Monroe said she plays soccer on a dirt
And the games would end at sundown
But one day
A rich man came to celebrate the construction of a new lighting
Volume to play at night
And guess who the man was
Periscope live
Monroe says that Escobar was very different from other rich man
Because he was generous
He was a benefactor
He was also becoming in many ways more powerful than the 11 states
To try to solve this problem Colombian law enforcement began relying on militarized policing tactic
Increasingly violent clashes started happening between the cartel and the police
Law enforcement will go into the Kahuna's to try to control the drug trafficking
And sometimes they'd end up killing young men from those neighborhood
Then after years of conflict between Escobar and Colombian authorities
The US started its War on Drugs
And passed an extradition agreement with the Colombian government
That meant
That if or when Escobar was captured
He could potentially spend the rest of his life in a US prison
The violent Imaging got a lot worse
It may have been a bomb that blew up a plane in Columbia today the Boeing 727 of Avianca airline November of
1989 the Medellin cartel bombed in Avianca aircraft
Mid-flight
Killing all 117 people on board
The cartel was trying to kill a Colombian presidential candidate
The bombing of flight 203 with the deadliest single attack in decades of violence in Colombia
Two Americans were among the Dead
Counting been President George HW Bush
To offer support to the Colombian forces in their search for Escobar
With additional American resources
The operatives trained to capture Escobar Mountain doesn't have real
But he had so many informants in the government but he kept on getting away
And he retaliated
Dominican cartel when I'm a killing spree
The ship Columbia
Especially managing
To its foundation
This was when the city became the murder capital of the world
Sandra Reina Stacy was total chaos
She's a sociologist in mini Jean
Who started the armed conflict and how it affected the city
Regular assassination
And fight among rival gangs
Denver car bombs going off all the time
La Casa de papel
She says that a sense of fear to cover the streets
There was a feeling that anyone could die at any time
Medellin cartel members are police office
Anyone
Public spaces that had once been Lively started emptying out
To maintain control the cartel imposed a curfew
Escobar's men with rose leaflets from Ellicott
Ordering people to stay inside past 8 p.m.
The violence felt indiscriminate
I did not describe a terrorist like a long black night
Love you Missy Misdemeanor
Of Escobar's top lieutenant
Only four are left alive today
And three of them are still in prison abroad
The only one who is alive and in Columbia today
Is John Jairo Velasquez
Also known as
Or Popeye in English
Ciento ochenta en el ano Mas importante
The year 1999 was the most important thing that was a war
That's Popeye Pablo Escobar's right hand man and top assassin
He served 23 years in prison but he can still vividly recall the most intense year of the conflict
Fighting in the streets we are killing police officers and having shootouts in the
Streets block by block car bombs are going off in managing
Popeye would eventually admit to killing over 250 people
And for this
He had help
Used to operate in the camunas getting to know the young man who lived in those impoverished and ignored neighborhoods on the outskirts
Parts of the city
Then he'd recruit them and train them a sicario
Or Hitman
Escobar and his top leaders like propane
I figured out how to exploit the geographic fragmentation of managing
They knew the kids in the camunas didn't have a lot of opportunities
And so that's where they focus their effort
Even though he can't resist recruiting in a way
Talking about how exciting it was to work for Escobar
Meetup powerscore amigo
Pablo Escobar for us was not a boss or a friend
He was a god
I recorded a video Never
We would eat up a table with him
We were in his orgies
We would die for Pablo and would go to prison for him
Demolition cartel was a big
Family
When Maria in xhosa Louisa's reporting partner with a younger reporter
She came to Medellin to cover the conflict for Rolling Stone and other news outlets
And she remembers getting threats from the cartel
Popeye tells her that yeah
She was being watched
Made a loud message characters in potassium
Yeah that's right
The boss always notify the journalist
You should thank God we didn't kill you
Risk of us killing you because in a war you have to shoot
Everyone
Zero Maria
Let's be honest
We were at War
I'm worried that my father also fart
As a captain for Colombia's National Police
Because of his father's rule Lewis and his brother had to learn things in most little kids don't have to learn about
Like when Louis was five or six years old there was an explosion at a mall next door
It was strange because it was so close to our house
And I remember asking my mother if it was safe to return to the mall
My father left it on to narcotics unit and join the National oil
He was the head of security and Logistics
FRAM oil pipeline being built through dangerous
Territory
He went to both Norco control and
Infarct territory
The farc
Short for the Revolutionary armed forces of Colombia wear a leftist guerrilla group who took up arms against the government in 19
N64
By the late 80s
They were the largest Rebel group in Latin America
And at the same time as the Medellin cartel
They started drug trafficking and kidnapping
To fund their war against the state
One weekend
While my mother and my brother and I were out of town visiting my grandmother
Turn on the TV and saw the breaking news that the farc rebels have attacked a pipeline where my father was working
The news anchor said Rebels had taken hostage
In one of those hostages with my father
In the past when he was with the National Police
My father had fought the same fight insurgents and they knew who he was
Their enemy
Plus
My father was easy to recognize
Standing Tall at about 6:43 slim with an arrow pride and elegance that made him stick out in the crowd
So in my mother's house on TV
She said she knew my father would die
The farc rebels eventually freed elderhostel
But it kept my father
They held a war Tribunal
And then execute
Right before his death
My father was able to leave a message that would later get passed on to my mother
He told her that she knew how to be strong
They have prepared for this moment
It was not her duty to races
And get ahead in life
And that he was sorry
He was sorry that I'm at right now
Suddenly
How old are you
It was almost 6
Machinery was paid for by the military the National Police
The whole ceremony
Surreal
And remember like at the funeral home
And I kept messing like when he's going to wake up
So why it's over it's over like when is he going to wake up and play
Just like my family
There are many other families in Medina where morning
The same year my father's dad
In 1991
The city's murder rate
The cartel created fear to the idea that violence can strike anyone
Anytime
Around the same time Escobar made a deal with the Colombian state
Yes traditional Colombian citizen to the US have been prohibited by a newly approved Colombian Constitution
So that possibility was now off the table
Escobar agreed to surrender to authorities and to stop all criminal activity
In exchange for a reduced sentence and preferential treatment
Including no extradition
To the United States
And he got very preferential treatment
Escobar was locked up in his own luxurious private prison
But Bill specially for him
He was called to like at the door
And it featured a soccer field a bar a giant dollhouse
A jacuzzi and a waterfall
Then it became clear that Escobar was continuing to orchestrate criminal activities from within the prison
Authorities made plans to move them to a new location
But Escobar escaped before they could
There was a man hun
December 1993
Escobar died in a shootout
But even before Escobar died
The city had undertaken an ambitious new project to try to figure out
How to pull Marine out of a drug-fueled violence that affected the city for so long
Grand Prairie
Tambien
This is Sandra arenas
She says that it was during the worst of the violence
That means you got to figure out the formula for its own transformation
What happened was a national government sent policymakers out into the neighborhood submitting especially the Kahuna's
To hold public forums and to meet
People from all across the city
Peking Palace photos even related comunitarios
Los jugadores
Adina says this meetings were attended by Community leaders
Teachers religious figures in public service
Akademiks artist
And everyday citizens team
Is initials for dispenser
Colossians Sarita
Arena says that in the Forum
They figured out that the city needed to reclaim public spaces
Places where people to meet up and talk
Many of these spaces like parks and plazas
I've been abandoned because people were afraid to be outside with all the violence
People also said the city needed to invest in community group
They were already lots of artists collectors and Community organizations doing important work in the community
They just needed more support
And finally the city could no longer neglect and ignore the camunas on the steep hills above the city center
Those neighborhoods needed to be integrated with the rest of medine
City needed a modern Metro System
Transporte publico Imaging
That's Natalia castano
And she says that the public transportation system became a way to create a sense of inclusion throughout the city
Castanos anarchist
And she helped to implement some of the ideas that came out of those early Community meetings
In 1995 the mini Metro opened linking parts of the previously fragmented City
The richest southern district was now easily connected with the poor camunas to the north
In the moment
Los active building
Natalia says
They were living in the time when violent attacks
Car bombs and assassinations were common
And obviously
Dimetra infrastructure
Target
The drug cartel Hitmen were part of the conservative managing culture
And many of them are cats
So the city came up with the idea of placing a statue of the Virgin Mary
And it's one of the metro state
They thought it would be a reminder to keep things calm and peaceful on the train
To complement the Metro
The City built something else
An Innovative system of cable cars that went right up the Steep Mountain sides to link the comunas to the rest of the city
And this made a huge difference
It wants taken people in the community over an hour to get to the city center
Now it took more like 15 or 20 minutes
Before
People in the community used to say I need to go to managing to run an errand
Now
The feel like they were part of managing
Like they belong
There was other investment in the communitu
City built Big public libraries
Parks soccer field
Job training centers in health clinic
And they poured money into already existing artist collectives and Community organization
Natalia says it's because the city had come to realize that
Odell Beckham Una
Does neighborhood
Happy neglected and underserved in the path
And wait Marines big innovation was to Taco crime and violence not three more policing
But to urban planning infrastructure
And social programs
The invested in neighborhoods that have been the most isolated
And where the cartels had previously had the most success recruiting members
And the city started to change
Commute times dropped soccer field state lit up into the night
The city of some bills inviting new outdoor spaces and the streets became busy again
And along with all these changes
The murder rate plummeted
By 90% from its peak in 1991 to today
The approach to urban planning that developed in Medellin has now become known as social urbanism
It was a Grassroots approach
Not a top-down one
And people all over the world now look to Medellin as an example
How to do this well
Of course there were other reasons the violence decline in Medellin
Medellin cartel was dismantled the economy was getting stronger
In a series of progressive mirrors kept building on each other's work
Urban planning and public transportation did play a big role
But yet I wanted to see this change for sales
So we better wait
Comuna 13
Historically
One of the most violent and stigmatized neighborhoods in the city
Comuna 13 is a dense neighborhood built on a steep Hillside
And now running right up to the middle of
Are these massive
Outdoor escalator
What is an escalator doing in the middle of a
Outdoor
Community
And there's another escalator
Wow
Just the notion that you're writing escalators
Up a hill
Literally and it's taking you to the top of the city
On escalators that are Outdoors
But you're also seeing it everywhere you turn there's art there's a huge mural Arts at every turn
Off of the top of the escalator
Boosie huge paintings
And kids breakdancing and beatboxing
30 years ago this neighborhood was a dangerous place
Please would have been afraid to come here
And now it's flourishing
The art and color interests
From all over the world
Yeah
Foreign tourism has gone up by
By 250% in Colombia in last decade
And many of those tourists are coming
Actually because of the Cities drug trafficking Legacy
It's something the locals
Call Norco Torres
Even Popeyes cashing in on the interest in this type of Tourism which is only been Amplified by the hit Netflix show narcos
He leads drug-related tours of Medellin
Taking people to sites around the city
Like Pablo Escobar's grave
Hey guys were you emojis city services
I'm here with Popeye. Killer
And it's good that Medellin is safe enough for tourists now
But there's also something uncomfortable
About knowing that Popeye is now profiting off a glorified version of the city's violent past
The city has a complicated relationship with his kind of Narco tourism
When the main Narco tourism sites is a place called if you seal Monaco
It's the building compound for Pablo Escobar used to live with his family
Interests
Love to visit at
Benin's current mayor
Federico Gutierrez
Says that there are actually planning to tear down at fucl Monica
No I won't tell you more later
Yeah you almost a construir en parque in ornithology
He says that he makes plays they're going to build a park in remembrance of the victims
Not to hide the history but to transform it
Because part of healing is not forgetting
You have any idea when we do.
Anil Kapoor
He says that the terrible things that took place in the city can't be forgotten
Because that's what made the city hit rock bottom
And hitting rock bottom
Is what eventually make people come together again
Society
It is undeniable that many in today is a different city
They're still massive inequality and drug trafficking
They're still criminal gangs that control parts of the city and sometimes extort people and businesses
But it's way more democratic inclusive and peaceful
And it was 30 years ago
And today you can take a trip across town that would have been impossible a few decades ago
In the morning you can get on the Metro downtown in a station decorated with Virgin Mary statue
You can ride up into the Kahuna's on the outdoor escalator that carries you pass murals and beatbox
And then
As evening descends
Not worrying about any curfew
You can hop on the cable car and Float back down the Mountainside
The slopes of the Communist off me behind you in the Twilight
The lights of the city center becoming clear as you draw closer and closer
Its streets and shops and buses
Bustling with life
People from all over Medellin
From all over the world
City
Finally
Connected
We'll talk more with her Porter Lewis guy out about the complexities of Narco tourism and his decision to return to Columbia
After years of living in the United States
Plus extended preview of a brand new radiotopia show called zigzag
After this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Fox podcast
We're back with Louise Gallo we reported our story this week
In the late 90s about five years after his father's death
Louis and his family left Columbia and move to Seattle
Louis decided to move back to Columbia a few years ago
And we want to hear more from them about what it's been like to return
We were especially curious about his reactions to the Narco tourism
As someone who has
That's a very present
Don't connection to that history
So we called him up he was traveling in Spain when we don't talk
I mean I want people to come to Columbia I want people to visit the country
Tippecanoe understand the plays a kid
Get a sense of what it's really like
As opposed to what they see on television
So I think it's a positive thinking for more people are coming to Columbia
However
People coming only to see that part of Colombia
Hannah perpetuates the stigma
And perpetuates
Toilets that stereotype
That
But many of us
When I move move on from
And it's problematic because like many people who are coming
Enter Colombia into managing in visiting does the spaces
Define this Narrative of
Pablo Escobar
The violence of you know the drug bosses
You know a little bit seductive and entertaining
Wet'n'Wild the same time
That same narrative the same
History
Was our reality of the time right it was all reality was our
Our daily lives
And all that suffering was real so he wasn't just like
You know what TV show it was
Realtor
And
Is it hard for you to see the ways that
People like Pablo Escobar
Popeye
I've been turning these sort of
Glamorized
Figures
I see why this narrative entertaining for many people
Because it's kind of like
This Man created an Empire out of nothing more or less
But at the same time
Yeah they're good time
Get that they are responsible Pablo Escobar and Popeye
Are responsible for the suffering of
And a dad send you know the killing and the terror
Yeah we digest I can Overlook that
You know I can buy
You might be entertaining for a TV show for a movie
By in real life
These guys are psychopaths
So given all the suffering that you've seen and experienced with a conflict between the cartels and the government and
Fark
Is the leftist guerrillas who
Murdered your father
Why did you decide to move back to Columbia after so many years away
I decided I decided to go back to Columbia because it was around the same time
Thus far
And the government
We're finishing up
Signing their peace agreements
So there isn't a piece of cord that they were finalizing
And I went both as a journalist but I also win Colombian Vino victim of the violence
And yeah I just wanted
Maybe come back and he'll both collectively and and you know them personally
And I wanted to be part of that crucial time in our history
Where you know 50 years old
In over 50 years
Apostolate where you know we're coming to an end
In the longest-running conflict in the world was coming to an end
There was a concert that you went to that was a celebration of the signing of the peace Accord and it
Sounds like it was a really significant moment for you
Can you tell us that story
So
I say this moment you know crystallized for me last year
When I was I went to a concert celebrating the
Define the signing of the peace Accord in in Bogota
And so they had a concert in the main square of the
And not the concert we know most of everyone was wearing white
I'm waiting you know why
White balloons
Elevating me another piece of cord
However
I saw other people wearing red shirts and waving red flags and friend I was with
The president told me she might confirm that
The people right wearing the red shirts
Warning signs fart
Urban militia numbers
Set a remembers of the fart button thing that would like the bullet
And then you know the concert
The the lead singer from this
Columbian rock band outfits
Called everyone
To hug a stranger in the name of Peace like to hug somebody you did not come with
And then
Right next to me was his young man College age
And he was wearing a red shirt
Approached me
And he was young he was drinking I would have been pay
Which is the Colombian liquor
So you approached me and offered me a swig of his I will get the bottle
And I took a drink of it
And then he came and gave me a hug
And I. Moments you know I just like when they realize they
Wild
Miss this person
Is
Or was part of
Love the fart
The same group had killed my father
Bye
You don't like it very emotional there were people in tears that were people
You know very moved from happening
And I realized that moment you know like this is
Aspen you peaceful Columbia
That was reported Luis Gallego recording himself on his iPhone
In Spain
This story was produced by Luis Gaya edited by Fernando echeverri and Marlon Bishop
Research assistants on this episode by Tom Collins
Production help from Sayre Quevedo
A program today was a collaboration with latino USA if you don't know them they're great podcast and radio show Within
An inside look at Latino life
Culture history in politics
It's in English and it's not just for Latinos there is something for everyone
We were brand new show in radiotopia it's called the zigzag
It's graded by manoush zomorodi and Jen poyant used to work together on WNYC note to self
Agon independent.com podcast
And their own podcast company in their own way
And we're going to follow along in real time
As they build it
Scratch
When they were raising money for their company they looked into investment and grants
And found those traditional path unreliable and require them to give up too much control
So they're trying out something completely new
Here's an extended preview
Early on when we've been talking to everyone we need to figure out like really should we start our own company I am
Met with a friend of a friend who actually advised media startups his name is Josh Benson
And then Josh call me back
Because the more he thought about it
Since we had our first conversation
The more he thought that actually
Then I would be a great fit for this other start-up he was working with
It was kind of hard to explain but the gist of it was that this group of techies and journalists
We're building something
That would throw good journalism a life
Help it survive in a world now driven by
Free Facebook news feed
They were called civil
And thanks to the generosity of a multi-billionaire
They had money
Actually had grants to give out to journalist
Proven track
No strings attached
The journalists would own their work
All they had to do was contribute to the Civil platform
And the way they were making this media fantasy come true
It was something called the blockchain
Jen and I had heard of the blockchain you may have to
We weren't entirely sure how it worked or what it had to do with journalism
And like most people we pretty much
The most popular cryptocurrency that had made the people who bought in early really really rich
According to memes
Attempt to compel them to buy Lamborghinis
Why the hell would we want anything to do with
Research we started to understand
Black teen was just the technology that made Bitcoin possible
But it could
Maybe
Do so much more than just make some dudes Rich enough to buy Lambos
The movie Red
The more we felt like actually the blockchain could be a second chance for the internet
It's over the last few years we've seen that the promise of the web
Information and access for everyone
It had been totally perverted
But the blockchain
If it really got off the ground
Could do things like protect people's identity
Help get eat faster to natural disasters
Sustain the poorest population
Maybe even help protect democracy
And save important struggling industry
Like journalism
Either big promises
After hearing what civil was doing with the blockchain
We were kind of stoked
Josh
Hi
Went to see Josh Benson our blockchain Matchmaker
Is wework office on 23rd Street
Please make yourself
Cuz I just think you guys are going to be obviously like a super interesting and attractive proposition to bunch of places
It's like we know some people who are doing interesting things
Podcasts in French
It's just like we're thinking about all that stuff
Because why the hell not
Weird crazy
Blue Sky opportunity at the moment and so we just
Once we left the meeting
It was no need to play it cool anymore
Jen and I want
Just give me three words
Right
I mean I'm scared
They like
It sounds too good to be true but like
It's perfect for us
Can I help with this
Launching
How to be super fun A beautiful concept to help and support journalist doing good work
Incivil wanted us
Especially when we told them what we do with the grandpa
Make our first podcast
One then actually explained in normal non-hardcore taking language what the hell the blockchain is
Because here's the thing listeners
That Grant civil gave us
It was half real money
In the other half is a new crypto-currency
But they call Sybil tokens
These tokens have no value yet but after they get auctioned off to the public
They could be worth quite a lot for nothing at all
Join the news and Jen in zigzag Isaiah for big issues of women
Tech journalism and capitalism
Tell me a fun Journey
You're finally going to understand the blockchain
It says 1 and 2 are out right now episode 3 drops this week
Do you want to be my friend
Download it and listen to it and follow along with me and let me know what you think about it on Twitter
No idea if it's going to work or how it's going to end
That's why it's fun zig zag from radiotopia
Find it a zigzag pod.com
Radiotopia. FM and whatever length
Nordstrom
Alongside the amazing team at Latino USA our show was produced in edited this week by senior editor Delaney Hall
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Sean Rihanna team is senior producer Katie mingle digital director.
Joe Rosenberg
Avery trufelman
Vivien Leigh
Turn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Von Maur
Radiotopia. FM
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 PIR
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But on a website me a pictures of cable car has an outdoor escalators and colorful camunas plus links to Latino USA
Sake and zigzag
It's all there
And 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com