99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Producer Katie mingle dad retired he began walking a lot
He's always been a walker but with all the new time on his hands his walking to Ghana Forrest Gump Ian
Fervor
He started doing these really long multi-day treks through the countryside
And even though he's American he mostly prefer to walk in the UK and backed over the course of several years
He walked the entire length of Great Britain
And I'm one of these many trips
In 2003
I was walking through
Beautiful
Rolling Hills and wooded
Area and their work
They were just literally hundreds and hundreds of pheasants and Grouse along this Trail and you'd Walk Alone
They would fly up in the air
That's my dad
Jim Mingle
I walked and walked and
It got later and later and I realized I couldn't get back to my
B&B where I was staying
So I decided I'd
I would hitchhike that
Hitchhiking is dangerous. But go on
I stuck out my thumb in
I pulled this Jeep
I hopped in
And there was this guy sitting there all dressed
In search of traditional Tweed outfit there was a funny cap and
There was a shotgun
On the rack in the back with you
Never ever saw
And Breton
And we got to talking and he
You said he was the gamekeeper for
Madonna and Guy Ritchie
My dad have been walking through Madonna's
State when he was picked up by her gamekeeper
Which is the thing a lot of wealthy landowners have in England
Person who manages the hunting activity on their land
Rates of this game keeper drove him back to
To the village where you staying and drop them off
I know his story doesn't end with him meeting Madonna
I wish you did too
And I asked about Madonna how he liked this game freak keeper like
Working for her and
He said he loved his job and he thought Madonna was too
Just wonderful
What's your favorite Madonna song
I just like the idea of put on I've got very good at remembering
Now that we've established that
Madonna is wonderful and my dad cat name is
Single one of her songs
You might be asking yourself
As I was
Dad what were you doing in Madonna's backyard
I was walking most of the time across
Private property I was walking from
One field to the next climbing over the fence where they are through a gate
And
I'm going on in this was
This was
Permitted
It's true my dad walked the length of Great Britain and was on private property a lot of the time
Which is different obviously than the way we do things in the US
If you wanted to walk across this country you'd have to do it on a combination of
Public trails and Roads and you certainly couldn't cut across Madonna's
Property
This right in Britain
To walk through private land is known colloquially as
The right to roam
In the movement to win this right was started in the 1930s
Buy a rebellious group of young people dressed in Army Surplus shorts and hiking
Curing cannabis rucksacks and canteens
They called themselves
Rambler
Rambler is one of those
Quaint Old English words
Time from really
But it means walking or hiking
In the country
Seaside this is Rollie Smith the rambler / journalist
To says his rambling forefathers and mothers were
Toiling away in the factories of 1930s mansion
Leicester Manchester was a very grimy town
A very
Dirty
Smokey a horrible environment
A product really of the Industrial Revolution
Outside Manchester it was one of the most beautiful parts of England an area known as
As the Peak District
So if you can imagine Factory workers in Manchester and Sheffield could actually see the
He's inviting boys from their homes and their workplaces
And they will until I have to walk on them
It hasn't always been this way
Hundreds of years and idea of the comments that existed in England
So the commons
They were
Integral part of
Medieval life for the ordinary
Villager in England
That's kind of Jonas author of this land is your land how we lost the right to roam and how to take it back
All the way
But the peasants
Statue in Rio rights on these common land
In this feudal system
Kings and Lords control of all the land
In the manner grew enough food to support itself and its tenants
The Peasants lived on the land sometimes without written leases but with assumed rights to use it in exchange for vert
Service
They could
Graze their cattle lumbar they could draw water they could
Collect could use it for a whole bunch of
Purposes
That began to change in the 1400s
When will Prices rose across Europe
Landowners wanted in on the profits and in order to graze sheep more efficiently they needed to fence off
And that's when we begin to
Asia.
Enclosure
Landowners clear the entire Villages of people
Making them homeless
Put up little stone walls and hedges to Mark the boundaries of their property
Accounting called works
61 Villages were wiped out before the year 1500
Over the years Parliament created more and more laws
How to keep people from using what was once common land
It all wrapped up in the 1700
There was
Nearly 4000 acts of parliament between
M18 7
That's a sixth of England that went from
Common lab
Enclosed
Private
Property
Destroying people's livelihood sin
And way of life
People are so desperate to continue hunting on this once
Common land
But they came at night and covered their faces in
So it for x
Camouflage
They became known as the blacks
In 1723 parliament passed
The black Act
So this black Act
It created
50 offense
That were
Punishable by
For people who are accessing
Westland
Delete the death penalty
Trespassing was done away with
But the land remained closed
To the vast majority of
People
In the 1800s Britain industrialize
And people found themselves indoors
All day
And unable to find places for recreation
England did not have a national park
System at this time and the trails that people could access we're extremely Limited
People long to be in the Hills
They walked where they could and trespassed where they couldn't
They climbed over fences and tried to stay hidden from the game
Keepers
And all over England
So-called rambling Club
Started to form
The forest rapper
The Midlands Institute of Rambler
The Manchester rambling Club
Tons of bees
Walking group
In the late 1800s and early 1900s
Forming to fight for access
And walking right
They often times head
Socialist sensibilities but the heart
There was a lot of for walking
In a belief that it was their right
Access was no longer a matter of survival as it had been in the days when enclosure begin
It was about Recreation
And getting away from the polluted industrial cities
Which brings us back to polluted industrial 1930s mansion
Rambling Club
Call the British workers Sports
Federation
The British
Workers
Sports Federation
And in this group was it
Automatic Rambler named Benny Rothman
Stucky middle
A very Broad
Grand and great sense of humor
A man of the highest
Principles
But he was exceptionally short it was about five foot nothing is Wayside
Really actually got to know Benny later in life
He was a man who I very much look.
240 short
So one day back in 1932
A few people from Benny's group tried to take a walk in the Hills near Manchester
In that beautiful mountainous area near the city called the
Peak District
And I will chase store
Buy a group of game capers
And when they go back to their camp
Betty Ross
Osman and others
Set you know if there was enough of us I couldn't stop
So Benny and the other Ramblers came up with
What's an idea
Let's get a huge group together and walk on to this mountain called
Kinder Scout
Which was the biggest
And this Peak District it was called The Forbidden
Mountain in this area this was
Guarded by
A whole bunch of
Gamekeeper
Are these words
Intimidating
Telescope
Apps to identify trespassers from
They carry these big sticks or clubs
That they would sometimes use
Xiamen trespasser
The British workers Sports federation did not keep their plans
To trespass a secret
They gave an interview to the local paper saying
We feel we cannot any longer submit
Being deprived of the beauties of the countryside for the convenience of the landowners
Wherever we claim we have a just-right to go we shall trespass in Mass
And Sunday will be the opening of our campaign
Not everyone was on board more conservative rambling groups in the area wrote editorials denouncing their plan
It would hurt the cause for expanded access to the country song
One editorial argued that trespassing was fine
It should be done alone
Or would just one or two people
Quietly
Neely
And successfully
The police were well aware of
The plans to trespass
The Kinder Scout and Benny rothman's role in all of it
And on the day of the event they tried to serve him with an injunction
Keep them from going
The police know he was coming
Mini arrive by
Bicycle
And they all expected him to
Hang out at the train station
Rothman makes it to the trespasser
Vines about
400 other people are there too
Mostly young people below the age of 21 a lot of men but some women too
They're wearing
Old army top
Multicolored
Sweaters
Khaki shorts
Warren work boots this is kind of the standard hiking
Garb of the day
For whatever reason they carry these
Enormous
Rucksack
They're considered like the thing
To do at the time
Lake often Wilburys
On the head
So is a very very Motley Crue
Pink
This Motley Crew of hikers gathered with their Berets and rucksacks at the base of the mountain
Anthony Rothman gave a speech
About taking back the rights they lost during the enclosure acts of the 17 and 18
Any emphasize
The trespass on Kinder Scout
Was meant to be peaceful
And with that the group set off up the mountain
The other thing they did was sing
They quite often sang when they went a trembling
And then they were singing songs like be internationally and
That sort of thing
About course
Show their political leanings
As well
Communist
The Ramblers were in a good mood to say hi
The saying and talk
There was some police behind them keeping an eye on things and having to keep up with the pace of the young walkers
At one point a group of gamekeepers approach them wagging their sticks
And a small scuffle into
One gamekeeper going to rolls over and hurt his ankle that's the extent of the
A scuffle
Eventually the Ramblers made their way back to
The bottom
The trespass have been
Success
They openly walked on Kinder Scout and no one has been able to stop them
And it probably all would have ended right there
With nothing much gained or lost on either side
If the police hadn't decided to make some arrests
Arrested at this time trespassing wasn't even an arrestable offense
So the police came up with another charge
Assembly
1 Rambler got off
But the rest were convicted
Prison Center
This is from
2 to 6 months
But when the sentences were handed down by the judge
But actually United the Rambler schools
And I also this was terrible you know
Just for walking on the moon with paper being sent
Suddenly there was this huge amount of awareness and the general public about walking rights
This was like
National
Item at the time
Sympathetic
Set in motion
Change
Transformers power England
Facts about private property
It's been described as
One of the most
Successful
Acts of civil disobedience
Ever in the history of this country
The whole thing is even memorialized in song
There was a guy on the trespass name Jimmy Miller
He eventually became a pretty well-known folk singer in England and changed his name to you and McCall
And you and wrote the song
Based on the mass trespass
School to Manchester Rambler
Another word
You're not going to ask me to sing it on you
Kayak
Yeah
I really want
I can sing the chorus
I think you should get a recording
Really
I'm a rambler I'm a rambler from Manchester
Stowaway
I can o my pleasure. Moreland way
I may be a wage slave on Monday
But I have my freedom on Sunday
I
The day
ESPN
For the trespasser
In this country and then
It'll be played at my funeral
Nothing
After the trespass
The rambling groups continue to push for expanded access
There are more tests
In 1951 when Britain opened its first national park
It was in the Peak District for the Kinder Scout trespass 2
Place
This was no accident
Years of negotiations between the Ramblers
And the landowners and legislators in the area and pave the way
But it wasn't until the year 2000
But the Ramblers got within always wanted
An act of Parliament that opened up
Huge swath
Country
Where people could roam free
The countryside and rights-of-way act
And that opened up
Mountain
More
Stars are just kind of fancy English words for
Unimproved grassland
And now
We do have the right to roam in Open Country which is what those lads
A1932 Worth Fighting For
The 2000 act opened up about 7% of the land in England and 21% in Wales
On which you are free to roam meaning you don't even have to stay in the trailer
You can truly just
Wander around
And 10% may not sound like a lot
Between that and other designated Trails where there are more worst
You can now pretty easily walk across England
Just like days.
Smallfoot
For my dad rambled across Madonna's
Property she actually sued to keep
People from wandering around out there
The government ended up allowing her to close off a lot of her estate but did keep some small amount of it open
Ramblers
Madonna wasn't the only person with concerns about Ramblers
When the countryside and rights-of-way Act passed
A lot of land owners
Fear the worst
You know everyone was worried about
People sniffing glue or the countryside in people
Tractors at work
Fornicating like this was all in the newspaper that people really worried but
None of that stuff
Turned out
To be
True
In addition to Britain a bunch of other European countries also have partial right to roam
Systems
Meaning some but not all private property is accessible to walkers
But then there are countries where the right is even further expanded
Norway
Finland
Sweden
Sweden has this thing called
Alamance
Which means every man
That's right and this means you can walk
Silver cowpasture this means you can walk through the woods to Spain
You can access virtually the whole
Countryside
In the United States we have a system of national and
State Park
But we don't have any rights to wonder through private
Property
And in some places
You might even get shot
The idea of opening up private land to the public
Seems almost on America
But this wasn't always the case
Yeah this is kind of like a
Forgotten chapter
Of American history
Americans
Sewer unenslaved
We have the right to roam
From
The colonial days
Up until the Civil War
In the early days of this country
It was common practice to hunt and fish on private land if it wasn't enclosed by a fence
In fact the Pennsylvania delegation to the Constitution
Even tried to get this enshrined in the Bill of Rights
That's how I
Important this was
The early Americans
Nearly a century later
In an 1862 essay entitled walking
Henry David Thoreau wrote that he feared that one day quote
Walking over the surface of Gonzo
Shall be construed to mean trespassing on some gentlemen's ground
The state may have come even sooner than throw fear
Kennel gouna says our concept of private property begin to
2 Chainz just a few years later
After the Civil War partly because of the end of slavery
This is the isn't Louisiana
Legislature
After the war they passed this resolution
Acknowledge the end of the war and they also do something else
Criminalize
Trespass
Now why would they do that right after the Civil War I think I know
They did that because now you had a whole bunch of
Free and independent
There were other reasons as well
As Native Americans were forced onto reservations
Land grants to the railroads and the Homestead Act of 1862
Turn gray
Swanson public land to private ownership
And then
Team Barb Wire
Fences became
A lot cheaper
So you could put fences up for livestock
Suddenly a whole bunch more the country
Isn't close
You haven't diverse
Certified
Economy
So people are no longer
For hunting
And fishing
And Gathering
As much as I used to so when
People start chipping away at access rights
You don't have
An impassioned
Group of
Proponent
Access ride
But kennel goodness thinks we should be fighting for recreational access in this country
Where a lot of our public land is concentrated in places that are hard for most
People to get to
For instance Alaska has
329 million Acres of Republican
That's 41% of all public
You look at the five states
With the highest percentages of public
That's Alaska
Nevada Utah Idaho
Wyoming
All this all this land is in
States where there aren't that many people
Guinness believes a right to roam system could help connect all these disparate pieces of
Public land
And give us a sense of ownership
I think if we bring in a system
Like the right to roam
You know we're still going to look at the land as if
It's someone
But I think we'll also begin to look at it as if it's
Sort of hours
And for what it's worth my dad agrees
He says there's something really special
About being able to walk wherever you want
I thought the whole concept of being
Able to
Walk respectfully across
Private land
Was
Extraordinary and it was something that
Just doesn't exist
We have a lot of public land where you can
Walk in the US but
The same very different
So many routes and trails
To choose from
Felt like the whole country was open
To you
These days if you ramble across the open grasslands of England or Wales
To see the remnants of enclosure
Stone walls and fences
And you also see
Things meant to help you get past these barriers
The Styles which are step ladders to help you get over fences
So called kissing Gates
What are v-shaped openings that
People can walk through
Livestock
Cannot
Because the fences aren't there to stop you anymore
You just hop over
And continue on your way
Some places go beyond a right to roam an offer free shelter
To a weary Rambler
We visit Bobby
Up next
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's omigod. Info podcast
Oh my God. Info
After England and Wales began implementing their Countryside and rights-of-way act
Scotland
They decided to take things a step further
7 mm 3
They passed their own Land Reform Act
And it did a bunch of things but
First and foremost
It codified a long tradition of public Acts
Basically if people are respectful
Have other people and property
They can roam even more freely on private land up north
And it's part of a larger ethos about accessibility exemplified but he's a little building called body
Original phenomenon that Kurt Kolstad is here until
So historically Abbasi was typically a small cottage
For Farm Workers
But World depopulation led to a lot of these being abandoned
Two Travelers who saw they were empty
Started spending the night
To the first time I ever encountered the word bothy
Was in Stirling Scotland and I ate at a place for lunch called but coffee body which I think is not these
Sort of things but it's kind of like us saying that I ate a Pizza Hut last night
Broader Association of these old
Old tall buildings on farmstead
But yeah it is now it's sort of grown to have this larger meaning of also these places
Hey I'm saying it
Delta probably don't you
So bodies can be found across the British Isles but especially in the Scottish Highlands
Father publicly-accessible most are still on private property
And the owners
Just let Ramblers sleep on their land and Buffy's that they own they do
Overtime a lot of these landowners who actually really embrace the tradition
Leaving building's unlocked and open for you
What is a community effort to their volunteers who help take care of and manage bothy
Please do the mountain bothy Association
Which is a Scottish charity
He's mostly As like small dark stone Cottages angled roof little chimneys
On rolling grassy Hillside says that's the image I'm going to complete that about right
There's actually pretty settings in the architecture
Summer Inland others fell on the beaches
Sonny's sweet things like post offices or schools
And there's this one out in the coastal Cliffs of Sky called
The lookout
That was actually built to be a coast
That has these big windows and he's a really awesome panoramic views
And it comes with binoculars Wildlife identification charts and this log book for people who want to watch
The Dolphins and the whale
There's No Reservations use ramble opinion
Stay in one of these
That's the idea
So you have to find them first
Wasn't always easy to do
For decades it was mainly a word of mouth system
And then a few years back
The mountain bothy Association started putting Maps app online
Making it easier for
People that point out there
Nature you get views
Free
Where do you sign up I mean that's pretty
Will you don't have the beauty of it but I should warn you
These can be pretty minimalist set times
Some have sleeping Platforms in stoves and little libraries things like that but they don't
Typically have
Running water or much insulation
It is a really impressive system and
A great way to repurpose old buildings that are not otherwise in use
And it works especially well in Scotland
We're really remote places can be accessed in part
Thanks to really permissive
Roman laws
How do I know I'm staying at a designated bothering on someone's land
Rather than just
Accidentally sleeping in their garden shed
You know I'm not
Sure
I didn't see anything about this when I was reading about them
Wonder Lake if you did just accidentally started right
That was sort of the origin of it
Is this A system that unique to Scotland
Not entirely
The US and Canada Australia New Zealand and actually a lot of northern European countries
He's also have their own verse
That said in many places there even more rustic
And they're often owned and operated by government agencies and set up on public land
Right and we have a much more divided system he republic versus
Private land
And when it comes to private property
You really have to watch out for those no trespass
Driving signs and
Keep their warning
Exactly
While in Scotland people really can just go out and wander
In the truest sense of the word
And if they happen to come across a coffee along the way
They can just walk right
And listeners combine images of bodies as well as links
Maps and other information about the body Network in an article that Kurt does published on our website
It's at 99 pi
. org
99percentinvisible with producers week by senior producer Katie Mingle
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by genre
The other 99 Pi Ramblers
Are digital director Tripp Halstead senior editor Delaney Hall
Joel Rosenberg
Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Jim mingle who gave us the idea for the story
And Kate Ashbrook from the Ramblers Association
Which continues to fight for walking rights in England and Wales
We are a product of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia
Beautiful tiara
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all the
Coupon Mall
Radiotopia
FM
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can't with me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Play invite you to ramble on over to our fertile land of design store
Write 99 pi
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
A treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com