99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the beginning was the word
And the word was
Well actually there was just one word long endless
Just years
Text
In Europe
Add no spaces between words
There was nothing at all to guide the reader
That's Keith Houston
He's returning 99ci Gaston author of the book Shady characters
Have to find the boundaries between words would have to work out where
Sentences and clauses began
Intended on the road
Sometimes it's never-ending string of letters would execute what was called an ox turn if the first one to text read from
Not to write the line below it would read from right to left with the characters themselves drawn backwards
The point is reading was hard
So
There was a librarian
Alexandria the third Century BC called Aristophanes suggested that
Readers might want to use the adults but you're very easy to insert between letters
In order to help them
Remember where the pauses where
The system didn't follow strict rules of grammar
It wasn't about demarcating sentences
What about rhythm
It was initially a kind of stage Direction it was
All about the performance of the text
So
Point halfway up the line was it a short pause
I'm going to the bottom of the line is a longer pause
The point to the top of the line was longer
Kind of like a.
Aristophanes little dots form the system from which almost all Western punctuation stems
A partial thought
Followed by the shortest a, a fuller thought was calling a colon in a complete thought
Appirio toes
A.
More punctuation Fallout
Medieval scribes gave us the earliest forms of the exclamation mark
8 century
Alcuin of York an English scholar in the court of Charlemagne
Quietly introduced a symbol that would evolve into the modern?
Ever since
We've Ended our sentences with one of these three more
?
.
!
They're called
Anna Marx
An exclusive Club
Really heartbreaking
That's 99 Pi producer Joe Rosenberg
Today
Story of the punctuation mark that almost
To join this exclusive cabal
In the new Merriam-Webster's Collegiate dictionary the 11th Edition
There it is listed
Among the various punctuation marks
The interrobang
This is Penny
Amoxi talking about interrobang
It's the real thing
You could use it right now if you wanted
But still just a baby
The story of its invention
What is exactly means
Just a little over 50 years
Paisley husband
You can say Martin was an idea man
He worked in advertising executive
Cocktail brainstorming and Madison Avenue glamour go right ahead
1950s and 60s Martin wrap some of the biggest names in publishing such as Barron's Dow Jones and the wall
And we ate dinner out most evenings and Martin got some of his best ideas
Jot it down in the back of the gold envelopes is everybody did
The Martin wasn't
Glamour
You want to sign
What is typography
Martin was constantly reading books
Punctuation on typography on English usage and so forth
And when you died we had a separate apartment with about 250
Small printing presses
Yes
Tell him this High some of this high and then we had
A really
Big one which took a full-page newspaper
And you actually have any you have any
Yeah
About 20 of them
I know but they're little
It was at this intersection
Of typographical notary and Madison Avenue Moxy
Ben Martin case Spectre had his big idea
It was the spring of 1962
This was the Golden Age of the advertising
Still true today
The Advertiser
Vistaril
Car wash
How many licks does it take to get to the Tootsie Roll center of a Tootsie Pop
Question
Can you hear me now can you hear me now
Any questions but excited question
Questions like
Of course
How
Did you indicate the question was exclamatory
Writing
How do you make it clear on the
Peach tattoos with a question
Tweets about placing
?! Back-to-back
Spectre saw that in this case
The ancient model of reading still hell
If you wrote an exclamatory question the reader was still expected to work out the nature of the sentence do contacts
Not punctuation
Then we were having dinner one night when he came up with a solution for it
The interrobang
Spectre was the editor
Typography magazine
Can the March April 1962 issue
An article titled making a new point
Or how about that
He proposed the First new end mark
In English language
300 years
Wiki interrobang
Spectre collapse the? And the! Into a single glyph
The two marks instead of being placed back to back
For now conjoined
Sharing the same. The bottom of the line
With these sharp birth
Slash of the exclamation point
Nestled inside the sinuous curve of the?
Luther Burbank means exactly what it
It's not the question
Expresses surprise incredulity
Which also makes it useful for rhetorical
Most of which are
It turns out
Also
A news article inspector was already envisioning exclamatory / rhetorical advertising slogans that could take advantage
Image of this Newmark
Such as
What
Refrigerator that makes its own ice cubes
Although Penny prefer
Who forgot to put gas in the car
Which is not really a question
Becker provided a few alternate designs for the
Interrobang
The readers of pythons also wrote in with proposals for alternate name
Kratom
DentaQuest
Tara point
And my personal favorite
Perogative
Oh I like that one that lets me use that one
Sorry romantic
Can go with that one
Spectres original navestock interrobang
Interra for interrogate
And bang for
The proofreader's word for the exclamation point
Traditionally printers didn't use the term
Nation point
Comedian copy with somebody you're never going to say! You say bang
But when she came up with the idea and you talked about it
How serious fuzzy
Oh he was very serious
And you really thought that
People in advertising would hook onto it
So what happened to spectres in bed
It really is in the dictionary
Waiting to be used
Why haven't we seen more interrobang
It's not easy to Advanced
Punctuation
That actually sticks
That's cute Houston
Clear Keith loves me
The painting to say this
It turns out in inventing the successful Market punctuation particularly in Denmark
Is really hard
History is filled with far more attempts
Creating a
Pretty much all of which I failed
Anne Arundel by the
16th century
The perfect station mark this rhetorical?
Last about 50 years before
It disappeared
There's any Mark invented by a kind of renaissance man called John Wilkins who proposed on invert
!
Which seemingly from the day it was born based a string of bad luck
For example
Article praising interrobang appeared in the New York Herald Tribune in 1962
The writer read Martin's original piece in hypetalk
Tribune article
The writer called the interrobang
Scrooge
But unfortunately his article was published on the 1st of April
And took it as an April Fool's joke
Still our baby punctuation mark persevere
In 1966 a company called the American type founders of legendary design firm that created some of the most why
Widely used typefaces between century
Unveiled a new typeface called Americana
That included an interrobang
And then the company
Americana was the last phone thing actually caught
And so they did not cuss anymore
Interrobang
All was not lost
Near 1968-d iconic typewriter company Remington announced that their latest model typewriter
Heatran optional interrobang
But I wonder if perhaps
The fact that you had
To pay some extra money to get an interrobang key might have turned people off
Today interrobang is just
Barely hanging in
Is recognized by Webster
Medina creative
Rising number of computer
Even has its own character in unicode
Common directory of symbols
All computer fonts
But keep points out that it still hasn't cleared
Biggest type of graph
I think that's
To consider to be a real Market punctuation
Keep left the use of that thinking about
In other words a truly remarkable Mark of punctuation must be
Unremarkable
It must be by now
Banality is not one of the interrobang
Remington's brief attempt to get the key
It never made it onto any standard keyboard
And now
Is included in a file
Accessible only with a nested series of menus in selection
So when people do use it
They're deliberately going out of their way to
You so
Using it because it's fun
Keith is going on the document ever more outlandish examples of the interrobang which have perversely
Only made it stand out more further undermining its legitimacy
Quick Facebook search yields at least two bands named interrobang one Punk one brass
In 2014 in Australian cartographer in the state of Victoria
Painted an interrobang on the roof of his house
It's not visible on Google Maps
In 2017
The Minneapolis Star Tribune obituary for the poet J Otis Powell
Could always ended his name with an exclamation point
But changed it to an interrobang
Before his death
None of these examples are in the service of an explanatory question
They're there to be noticed
You sometimes see it on
Twitter
Someone will ask a question
Taiwanese with an interrobang
But then they'll stick in
Interrobang just make sure that you absolutely got the Joker that you actually
Salt River Tubing
So the banality
Isn't there yet still stands out
Emperor Keith
This is the Brass Ring app
Ordinary People
Employee interrobang
For no other reason
Beyond the fact
Descendants of ham
Hospital to use
Maybe then we can say that is made it maybe then we can say that it sucked
It's a real
Market punctuation
Just watch me
We'd only find a question
Have you ever seen any new truly honest
Your truly
Interrobang
So to speak
In an unselfconscious way
In
Hooks
In newspapers
I just don't know about
Perhaps it's a flying under the radar
However
Takis
I might know
Genuinely banal interrobang
Cuz it turns out
There's this guy
Frank Easterbrook
Cleavage
Chief judge of the United States court of appeals for the seventh circuit
We totally sounds like a judge
Annie's kind of a big deal
The court of appeals is the second highest court
Before that I was Deputy solicitor general of the United States
The solicitor General's office is the office that argues the interest of the United States in the Supreme Court
Just like Martin
The chief judge for the United States court of appeals for the seventh circuit
Is a type of file
Because when I started reading I noticed that some things were easier to read than others
I started looking in the back of the books
Because
That would be a line on my last
Paige saying
This book is set in
With that name that I face
Who designed
And that's stuck with me ever since
And now God help the lawyer who submits a brief to Easter books Court
In Times New Roman
The default font of our times
Does not fly in the 7th circuit
Times New Roman
The reason why Times New Roman
It has been a plague
Is the punch newspaper typeface
We were lawyers to use walkie-talkie
National rule of Appellate Procedure
Easter bread
Esoteric
Just
This courtroom is a proper place and Hughes
Everything
In May of 2011 Easterbrook was writing a ruling for a case
Case of Sears vs Crowley
Realized
Secret himself
I reached a point where I had
Written a rhetorical question in the opinion where I was tempted to use in all
?!
?
!
Debridement
He can start changing
Just to avoid indignity of
Bring all those marks back to back
You know he knew it would make his argument
But then judge Frank Easterbrook remembered something
An obscure Mark of punctuation that would allow him to keep the sentence
In all its rhetorical Glory
Just as it was
So
Out came the interrobang
What better place
I'm self-conscious interrobang to appear
The American legal
Appreciated at the time
MasterCard points and it was a printing error
And of course my clerks had this reaction when they saw they said
There must be some garbled hear what happened
And I told him know this is a real character it's called an interrobang
And they both immediately looked it up on Wikipedia where it
Has its own entry
Mr. Brooks latest interrobang into a dense paragraph of legally
Actually had to read the entire 8-page opinion
Make sure that he used it correctly
Sentence defy summary
But when I can tell you
Is that the Everlasting Joy of Keith Houston
Appointment of the interrobang
Is extremely bad
Just so matter-of-fact it's just it's just in there
There are no Pages before it in Pages after it
There's nothing to say hey I just use an interrobang
Johnny gives easterbrook's interabang even more awesome
Biereley wasn't showing off
Normandy publicized it in anyways
Still
How to administer one last
We kind of like
Chomping at the bit to use it where you like man I just can't wait for an opportunity
No I wasn't chomping at the bit to use
Where are you
Planning on using it again
If the occasion arises
Shortly after Easterbrook issued his opinion his quiet U7 secure form of punctuation with
Spotted by illegal blog
And added to the interabangs Wikipedia page
When we told Easterbrook this
He laughed
He said he never intended to draw attention to the interrobang
He just thought
The right Mark to use
From a typographic character you don't see all that much
The one that
And maybe see all too often
We revisit the story of the Octapharma
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad to take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Like the interrobang the octopus
Also known as
Poshmark or the pound sign
Is a special character that existed for a long time on the periphery of punctuation
But unlike interrobang the octothorpe
Took off and became something we use everyday thanks to new technology
Here's the story of the ox
It was originally released in December 2014
Every morning I wake up
Rollover
Pick up my phone
Intertwitter
Not proud of this
Just the way it is
Twitter always struck me as the social media platform that was the most like Broadcasting
It's an ongoing conversation
Angel bow
It's a lot like scanning to a radio dial
Which mainly comprised of the people they know
Telling you about their day
Reacting to shocking news making jokes
Sending around legs
I deleted Roman Mars by the way before and sometimes I tweet
Producers name is Avery droppleman
But if you want to find out about the show in general
Is a hashtag for it
It's
#990 eye of course is comprised of two vertical lines intersecting two
Two horizontal lines that looks like a Tic Tac Toe board
In the current Digital World the hashtag identifies movements events
Happenings Brands topics of all kinds
Hashtags help people gather that's incredible power to give to like individuals
As a character I mean awesome
It's got like this little typographic superhero story now
And this superhero story star is Chris Messina I'm Chris Messina the inventor of the hashtag
Designer
And translator
Translator
Human culture
That's probably a little bit bloated
I don't know I don't know
Chris was the first one to use a hashtag on Twitter
Before it was even called a hashtag back in August of 2007 when he was going to an event called barkcamp it's a nerdy thing
It's an event that you go to that completely unstructured and unplanned and the participants figure it out
So the participants needed a way of organizing
Which led Chris to tweet the very first hashtag
Even though at that point it was just a pound sign
How do you guys feel about using
Pound
Barkcamp
Four groups putting a pound sign in front of the word barkcamp helps the other people at bar
Pick out the word Barr camp in their Twitter stream and encourages all the other bar Camp distance to use
Barkcamp in their tweets
Invitation says some people got on board and agreed to use the pound
But most were like okay you go do that the pound symbol had already probated other corners
The Web Internet relay chat AKA IRC use the pound sign to represent chat rooms or Converse
Versation channels
There's another Haiku that also have these channels
So there was other stuff that came before me
But Chris was using bunch of pound signs throughout his tweets
I was putting
Pound symbol
In front of my words
If you were like I don't understand what you're doing
You're putting all this strange punctuation in
Stop and
It looks.
But the True Believers stood by the sign
One Twitter user called it a hash
Tag
Because hash is the British name for the sign
And these are being used as category
Tags
Anacortes directly but they thought it would never catch on the look clunky
Then a few months later in October of 2007
The purpose of the hashtag was fully realized
A friend of mine was down in
San Diego isn't even a traitor and he was using Twitter basically pulling all the stuff together around these fire that we're going
San Diego
He was fixing all of his tweets with Sans face Diego space fire
Switch to hashtag San Diego fire all one word and then other users would imitate him
And it worked
People trying to find out about the fire do exactly where to look on Twitter
And this was a moment where everyone went oh that's what these signs are for
Clarify
Hashtags were nothing that Twitter planned on and they coming to drag their feet on incorporating it
We kept thinking
There must be a better way to organize all this information
What's going through Twitter
I'm weak I'm looking for a week
Really found it
What the hashtag
Andy Lawrence
Let an employee at Twitter officially brought in the hashtag
The users brought in the hashtag what all I did was link
The hashtag
Twitter search
One line of code
Took me about 15
Ask anybody
That one line of code meant that when you click on a word with a hashtag in front of it you'd see a page with all the other tweets that
Also contained that hashtag word
And basically this help you round up everyone was talking about a specific topic
And now the hashtag is a tool used in advertisements
Social movements music videos memes TV shows and in conversation
#sometimes
Hey Justin what's up
W
The busy working has a rising grind hashtag is it Friday yet even Chris acknowledges how irritating
She said aloud
Mostly when I'm being annoying or ironic but I'm I'm coming to sort of except that that's the phrase
It's getting to the point where the hashtag is erasing the symbols other uses friend of mine
He is delivery guy showed up and was looking for a hashtag to a hope that most people who made deliveries
For a living
#SMH
We know it more
The number song
In the states it's usually called the number sign
Call the pound sign
In the UK is often called a hash mark
Epic War because of the way it looks and everything else
This is Keith Houston
He's the author of a book called Shady characters
The Secret Life Of
A punctuation symbols and other typographical marks
I've got a whole chapter on this symbol
Anna has a lot of other
Random uses as well as used in chess
To represent remove the results in checkmate
In proofreading if you see a hash symbol this means space should be inserted here
It's used on Swedish maps to mean a Lumberyard hash pound number sign lumberyard
Whatever you want to call it however you want to use it
The symbol traces back to ancient Rome
The term Libra Pondo
Mint pounded weight
The word Libra
I like the constellation
Weighing scales
Bounces
And pump
And Dairy Queen
Means to wait Libra Pondo
And these two names were interchangeable so Romans referred to this weight measurement as a Libra or a Pondo
So the word Libra was often abbreviated
Lowercase L lowercase b
Which of course
We still use
5 l
You mean 5 Libra or 5
Time is it
This is also why British currency the pound
Is represented by a stylized L for Libra
So the abbreviation lb becomes a thing
And oftentimes it was drawn with a little bar
Across the top
Both letters
Just to show that the L and the B were connected
Scribes
A writer is garbage
Peerless Saloon write faster and faster
Faster
Do the pandas leave the paper
Fort Douglas
Bar across the top
Answer this seems to have given
Rise to the pound symbol for hash mark or Lumberyard overtime the symbols meaning started it by 4
It was used like lb for the unit pound and also started to be used as a number sign
It had a lot of various uses
What is important enough
To wind up falling
Typewriter keyboard
Which is
Kind of that the keys thing is the thing that symbol had to do in order to survive
Symbols that didn't make it onto a typewriter keyboard got pretty unpopular
Like the interrobang the pilcrow
Manicure
4 things
Fast forward to 1963
The invention of the touch-tone telephone
Hi this is a bell systems new at Stone Valley
Rotary wheel
So unlike previous phones the numbers didn't have to be arranged in a circle on the dial anymore
Bell Laboratories a research subsidiary of AT&T experimented with a few different designs for the telephone keypad
They try to arranging the numbers into rows of 5 in a circle and a cross
Step pattern
But they ended up using the numbers 1 through 9 in a 3X3 grid
Can you put zero alone in the bottom center
Years later in 1968 they figured
Why not add keys to either side of the zero this would make the keypad into a rectangle
There's a few more options on the phone menu
To repeat these options
Press the star key
Because unlike rotary phones
Touch-tone phones allow you to continue to dial
After the connection has been made
So you could punch in extensions and navigate automated menus
Press 2
Originally Bell Labs wanted
Pretty shapes on the two extra buttons
That made prototype phone that had a five pointed star and a diamond
On either side of the zero Doug Kerr would have none of this diamond and five point star business
Because by that time a new thing and coming to the picture
The possibility of customers dialing directly from their phones into a computer for such things as checking bank balance
Cesare validating their credit cards or what have you
Doug Kerr wanted to make sure that the two new symbols will be once a computer could recognize
Ones that appear on a keyboard and we're part of the computers vocabulary
So there would be no uncertainty about how a certain button would be recorded in the data that went into the
Computer Bell Labs was pretty set on their star and Diamond idea so the compromise was an ass trick for the star in
In a pound for the diamond because
You know the
Center
How to look Diamond like I guess for a second AT&T was like can we at least call it a diamond
The call that symbol diamond
It's not a diamond at all AT&T didn't know what to call this button in their manuals
And this led to the creation of what some people including Keith Houston
Consider the symbols official name
The octothorpe the octothorpe
One day I was out with my
Engineering partner
And we got to talking about it and thought maybe we should come up with a new name this is like to work in marketing for AT&T
During the time
Ian is engineering partner look at the symbol
And saw that I had eight line sticking out of it in there
Tendentious autofit hair weave
The RP
In there too
Because it sounds kind of Greek ashamed
Davidson statue
They called it an octothorpe but that morphed into octothorpe with rumor has it came about because someone involved
Change the name to turn it into a tribute to Olympic Athlete Jim Thorpe
But no one really knows
G is it proper to spell it
Octave Thorpe rather than Thorpe
There is no proper
Doug called it an octothorpe
Lauren called it a knock
Dother buttock
Joe Thorpe
Seems to have the most widespread use
There with you is not widely
Originally the only reason octothorpe ever caught on with him Bell Labs was because Engineers thought it was funny joke
The manufacturer Western elect
Totally hated that name
And pretty much killed in the 70s
But today for a lot of type of fishing out
Octothorpe
Is the signs real
In typography
Is the name Hughes
You might think
Topographic nerds like Keith love it because it feels the most neutral and official
Been to this symbol whatever it's called
Doug Kerr and the other Bell Labs engineers
Really understood that we would be using telephones to communicate with computers
And this is exactly the same reason why Chris Messina chose to use this symbol
Back in that tweet in 2007
At the time we had
Blackberry Smirnoff
Neither Hardware base
Best keyboards
SMS because that's the way that I'm going to be publishing Twitter
Which left Chris only two choices the star with a pound
Whatever
It's
Probably one of the most dense symbols
And so when you're reading a sentence while you're reading a tweet
It stands out hashtags on promotional materials on other social media platform
Amazon protest signs
In your annoying friends conversations
And this is all probably going to sound
Sarah dated in like 5 years
For two years
Or maybe a few months
Hearing hashtag out loud I'm going to sound like someone reading a telegram
My office instructed to advance you up to $25,000 stop and Merry Christmas
Sam Wainwright in a telegram has on Twitter
Are speech changed to accommodate the machines
Changing our language to be more computer friendly
And what we're needing to do is actually invert the Paradigm where the computers become more friendly to Human
So we're probably not going to be using hashtags the way Twitter use hashtags
Forever
But this won't mean the end of the symbol itself
It started out on paper but then it leaped to typewriters computers and phones and it seems like it's probably going to stick around
Whatever we decide to call it
#Altidore
#basta Thorpe
#pound
#number sign
#lumberyard
#tic tac toe
#musical sharp if you really lazy
Part 1 of 99% Invisible by Joel Rosenberg in part 2 by Avery truffle
I'm interrobang story mix into production by Sharif Youssef with music by Shawn real
Music in the auditorium Episode by melodium lullatone Keegan DeWitt
And a few others
Is a full list on the side
The rest of the night IDI team is digital director Kurt Kolstad senior producer Katie mingle senior editor Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh
Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are brothers and 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Obviously independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all a podcast
Baltimore
Radiotopia. FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can meet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi org
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to be when all the old episodes posted that we don't even talk about on the podcast
Go to 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com