99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
Mars radio producer
NPR quiz show wait wait don't tell me or as the co-host of the now-defunct podcast how to do everything
Which I just loved is such a good show new podcast out right now launching this week and it's delightful
Delete weird well the show is called Everything Is Alive and it's an interview show
In which all the subjects are inanimate object
So I talk to things
So what made you want to do a show like this
Well a couple things like
One I think it's just like
We just sort of think this way like you know
I'd get up from a chair and
Think about
What a
Terrible job the chair had and liked
And like how the chair must feel about being sad on all the time and then I think
Producing for so long
You're always trying to get to like the
Primary source
You know
And my girls looking for experts
I thought it would be really fun if like
You know your
Putting the other piece about
Rainbows or whatever and like rather than talk to the
Physicist to understand rainbows
If you could actually talk to the rainbow
Tuff Stuff County idea
I know that was going to deny 10% invisible are fully capable of accepting that even the most mundane objects are
Infuse with great meaning and can say something about us as humans but
You may not be prepared for that object to actually talk so I asked me in for a primer on how to listen to everything is a lie
You know if I was talking to a candle say like a bedroom candle
Like it's not
Every candle it's not speaking for every candle
It is one candle that is sad on one night stand forever
And like
Been blown out by one person forever and has a relationship with that person they're kind of aware of their
Object communities like it knows more about candles than
We do
It also has like a very distinct
Lifetime of experiences
But the things that says are all
Actual I think I was surprised by that when I first heard
The episodes that I have the same flavor
Yeah
They know things
They know real things about their world
For the most part
They're the
Inanimate object version of the person at the party who like always has an anecdote for everything
They're very aware of history and
Stories of
What they are
So even though the situation is quite absurd on the face
When you hear a fact it's a true fact yeah
There's so much about
Personal life of the object
That you know you know isn't
Exactly real
When I'm telling a story about something real I don't
Yeah I don't tell you what like
And so
We're just letting the objects behave in the same way until
There's probably you know there's going to be some mystery and
Hopefully people will Google +
Figure out if things are real or not
This is everything is alive
Hosted by in Tagalog
Let's just start settling have you
Introduce yourself horse my name is Luis and I am a can of gotu Kola
That's a store brand
Go to go
Similar to
Coca-Cola similar
People call it a knock-off I've been called The Best of the worst
You know if
You want to get my honest opinion I believe in a blind taste test
Your average person wouldn't be able to tell the difference between me and a can of regular Coca-Cola but
Bottom shelf
We can describe the comfortably is bottom shelf I'm at peace with that literally on them
What's the time now
Well
There's a lot I want to talk to you about that dude need anything water anyting
Completely self-contained
I want to ask you about your time before you ended up in the fridge or in now
So you are you I take it were you were in a supermarket
Yep
And what where were you are going to Safeway
I was bought at a case
So there were 24 of us
We were all purchased together and actually
Our next
Residence was a bowling alley for a 12 year old's birthday party
I saw most of the rest of my case drunk at that party
I was not drunk
I was saved for later and brought home and put into refrigerator
And then forgotten about for a few months placed in the back of fridge
Sure
I froze in the fridge
I was in the very back and the temperature got very cold I didn't freeze all the way through but
I had a frozen couple of weeks
Pretty learn
You are slushy inside always like inside
And
I had a brief Adventure when they realize I was still in the fridge and they took me out for a road trip
I got to sit in the front
Seat cup holder you know
And I took a little
Fun road trip down to Florida and then back again
I never got around to drinking me on that trip then they put me back in the fridge and that's where I've been ever since
It sounds like you were almost chosen so many times
What does it feel like when your play at this birthday party
And
You're waiting for your moment
Rivers in the movie Jaws
Yeah
So you know the story that that Robert Shaw tells to Rob Roy Scheider and
The other guy
Anyway you know the story about the USS Indianapolis
Reason the water and the sharks are coming and
He's waiting to be picked off and he's waiting and having that long dark night and one by one is in his friends go
That's kind of what it was like for me
Irvine and on the one hand I was very angry at you and being sore being in this position to consume us
And then on the other hand I was also very angry how come you didn't want to consume me
Yeah
When you when you think about being consumed by human
Do you think about the human that you want to be in
If and when I'm finally consumed I hope I'm consumed by someone who enjoys
But I like to imagine that if you're drunk immediately that instead of be
Being a painful process there's the sort of first moment of release the can is cracked open
All of this internal fizzing that I have going on finally
Somewhere to go just for them to round out
Your external can we have that last moment where you're feeling to purpose and beginning to
Blend in with his human being and you become part of their story
Truthfully here's how I expect to go assuming that I am
Consumed I'm expecting it's going to happen
Blow the night we're not waiting for it and someone's going to open the fridge and pull me out and that'll be that
It would be nice to be poured into a nice big pint glass you know
Frosty mug would be pretty good way to go happy Pleasant you know
I doubt that's going to happen though they don't Reserve Frosty mugs for gotu Kola so that's just another one of those Facts of Life
How did you see jaws
The human being who lives in my house was watching Jaws they took me out of the fridge and kept me on the table
I thought this is at this is my big moment
Kind of part of me there was the Robert Shaw scene when he's telling the story of the Indianapolis and I was thinking boy this is just too perfect
This would be amazing
He was reaching for me was going to go for me and then at the last minute you know another human being came into the house and
Scolded him on not drinking soft drinks by pulling back in the fridge
Wow
Yeah I would have been perfect huh
Damn
I should ask you there there's a lot of talk right now about
Beebe health effects of stop suffering people tend to think of
Of them is very unhealthy
Sugaring
Do you feel unhealthy
Do I feel unhealthy
It's hard to say because I think if you were feeling the way I feel
You would feel unhealthy
Red
But I feel like me
I can't say that that means I feel good
But but you go back to your question you know on healthy drinks or not like
The new thing by any means
Have you ever heard of RAV4
RAV4 RAV4
All right I was so back in the twenties there was an energy drink with radium
Cold r84 okay
It energy idea was it just radioactive material
In water
They claimed radiatore give you energy and cured a bunch of
Thanks
They also implied
That radius or increased male virility
Raiders are also killed him people
So you people just drink
Radioactive material dissolved in water
I'm just looking it up here
Actually there's an eBay ad
There's a bottle of RAV4
For sale come on now currently $659
Got to be kidding me
Excelsior
This certified radioactive water was advertised as a quote
Cure for the living dead and quote Perpetual sunshine
It goes on
One guy who used it
Eben Byers
Died from radiation poisoning and they had to bury him in a lead-lined coffin that's what you get when you drink
Active material so they made a beverage which not only killed a man
But his dead body would have it had they not taken precautions
I killed all life around him yes presumably his dead body is still radiating the poison said he drank from ready Thor
In fact that the ad goes on
They exhumed him for study in 1965, his remains were still quite radio
Active
It didn't mention that the developer of radiator was not an actual medical doctor
Yeah that sounds about right to me too
Also the bottles in very good condition
So there's your original Power drink for you
How you got to
Did to me more about human beings that it does about soft drinks
To be perfectly honest
Are our willingness eagerness to
Find something that your chronic search for potency
That's my valuation of humanity
Chronic search for potency
Hello
And calling for Jeff
Yep
Hey Jeff you're you're the man behind the
Bygone times vintage right
Haha yeah I'm guilty
I noticed
One of your eBay listings
So you put up the RAV4
Tradutor
Yeah
Yeah is that is that for real
Oh yeah
What happened was I was at a flea market and I found
Ascent of about 20-25 of these
Okay
It was like a
Shipping crate or something
And
So yeah I have sold
A few of those
The end of the
Is it a reproduction or is it an original bottle
These are original
Original
Did you check them with a geiger counter
I have not I don't know
I just assumed they wouldn't have any there's no contest
Tilapia
But I haven't no I didn't
Geiger counter
I suspected something from the 90
Done gone
Maybe it wouldn't be gone
I don't know maybe they would I don't know
Capital Mall
Under a blacklight or something
Hope
Still
Actor that would
That raises the
Interesting questions
Did you know much about rathore when you
You know when you know now you know I got on
Fortunately now we have the internet Google is quite helpful it's really an interesting
Story I don't know if you've taken the time to to look into it but
Bats mating
Yeah I just I just heard about it it's
Crazy that we
We human now
I like the story about the guy who
Died from it and then they dug him up in the 60s in his leg
Lion coffee
You are still Radioactive
That's why I wear I feel like you should maybe get checked out your head think I will yeah I think I will
Really
Glass with holding his assets
Yeah radiation you don't want to mess around with I guess when it comes down to
Now I hear you
Hey I have to I'm driving and I don't want them getting on so busy at road now so I need to unfortunately hang up on you
Got it yeah be safe
Okay bye
Lewis one quick thing I want to ask you about I have in my life
Occasionally
Dropped a can of
Soda know you
I said I'm having you all it's awful experiences
Philip I mean obviously very shaken
There's a rush
I guess I'm a human being terms to be like a rush of adrenaline and for a while you're feeling just very
Reverse
Hyper after the shakeup
And then you start this recovery Saddleback to a neutral state but you have this awful kind of nauseous
City sleepy feeling after the fact
And you feel kind of
Dumb you know the shake up kind of like rattles you a little bit and takes a little bit of time for your intelligence to come to come back to you with an offer
Experience
Imagine two like we often after that happens
We will tap on
What would be your head
Don't
Doesn't do anything
There's no reason to do it it doesn't do anything to the carbonation all it does is Annoy Us in a very sensitive moment
Don't do that
You're listening to everything is alive on 99percentinvisible
This might be
Awkward to talk about but I feel like there's a hierarchy to sodas at least in terms of how humans think about them sure at the
Doctors you know Coke and Pepsi
And then there's 7Up and Sprite and then there's
Destino like your son casting
Great
Soda Fanta that are kind of at the
Bottom I wonder if that does that hierarchy does it mean the same thing to you
But let me tell you something I Fanta
I mean sure here in the US it's not the most sophisticated soft drink but overseas
Its huge
Vitapan euge
Fanta Fanta
In Thailand
It's all over the place if you walk down the street there you'll see half open bottles of fanta everywhere
Strawberry Fanta in particular everywhere just hanging out
Just like sitting on this
The street yeah just on the street because
Youmans there you Strawberry Fanta as an offering
Two ghosts
So they leave it out on the street because
They're giving it to go yes friendly ghosts according to local custom
Love sweet red soda
So if you leave it out it attracts them and they hang out around your house and protect you from
I guess whatever unfriendly ghost might come around
Who I guess don't love sweet red soda
Right
Do you know what it is about Strawberry Fanta in particular because of the color
So there's a theory that it's because I can't do blood offerings anymore until Strawberry Fanta which is another you know red
Viscous liquid will be the next best thing Strawberry Fanta among the sodas available to us looks the most like blood
Yeah which I personally don't see
Okay but you know I tok Thailand thing
We humans we think a lot about
Spirits or at least you know what might happen to us after we die do you as a cold
Do you think about that
The afterlife
Yeah oh yeah
I do not think that all the time yeah
Reaching that age myself are probably not to be around that much longer
You are a mean you are recyclable
Which opens up a whole other
Conversation
You know my my body McCann
Will almost certainly be repurposed
That leads me to you know ask questions of like well have I already been repurposed I don't know you could have been any number
Sodas or or anything else and airplane I could have been I actually when I was younger I used to have a return
Recurring nightmare
That I was there was a plane crashing
There's no trying to be
And in that it was nighttime and it was raining and there's a plane crashing on the beach
And I used to like to think that in a previous existence I was part of an airplane and this was some sort of
Memory that had traveled with me maybe as part of like a
Ventilation system on Board of Ed 747 or something
You referred to your your can is your body or your body is your candy
Is there
Equivalency between you know what humans talk about Body and Soul his is
That I'm sorry
I'm only saying because I wish I had the answer to this question is there an equivalence yes
Yes the body mind problem that youman beings have been dealing with since the days of Descartes
Something all too familiar to us cans of soda am I
Toucan
A my soda what does it mean to be soda and my part of the larger
Potion of soda out there am I just the individuated so damn isoda interacting with a can in like
Cancer
Being slowly eaten Away by the soda inside me I thought about this alot
Yeah
I don't have an answer but it's something to wrestle with all the time what am I fundamentally
What's the sodas gone like an remains but bye-bye me
I think
Who knows who knows these are the mysteries of permeate every level of existence
As far as I know
I have to say I think I think about the type of can you are with the pull tab
And then I think about other cans in the kitchen you know like a soup can I know if you know any soup can
And it occurs to me you are
So lucky
Because
You think about the way a soup can gets open
That
That I can opener to me
Seems like a torture device
It is let me tell you something else to I thank God everyday of my life that I was not born in a can of minute
Macaroni soup
I at least
I have lived a life I know where I've been
You know I'm not all of my dreams may have necessarily come true I may have taken a couple of bad turns here and there
But at least at the end of the day I've been witness to my own life
These poor bastards are stuck in the Soup cans
We talked about hermetically sealed
They lose all sense of time and perspective when you open a can of soup
When they wake up
I have no idea how much time has passed there like astronauts coming out of cryogenic freeze
They're all spaced out in the completely disoriented they don't know what's going on and their wake-up call is being
Torn open
Buy these damn can opener is what a nightmare of an existence
The Flash is literally busted open only to wake up into a world that they don't know anything about
All the rest of us stay away from the cans of soup and I'll be honest with you I feel awful about it but whenever I try to talk to a can of soup
They are weird
You mentioned that you're you're feeling like you're nearing the end of your life hell yeah
What do you feel older
And how very much I know for a fact I'm old I can look at my aspiration to it
Okay and it can I ask
How close you are T minus 2 weeks to go my friend
Wow
So what
But you could keep going on after that that's just
I thought it's not recommended
But I could
Desert C I mean I think about this with you because
And I'm sorry if I have
This isn't the right way to put it but it seems like your purpose is to be consumed by a human
And so you know we all want to serve our purpose we all want to be useful
And yet for you the moment of your youth is the moment where you are no more and I wonder
That's something you anticipate
With optimism or if it feels like
You know approaching me and it's a paradox isn't it is
On the one hand
I do surgery
Dread the idea of being consumed
All beings Endeavor to persist in their own being
Spinoza said that
I heard about that from a a cup of coffee
On the other hand
I guess on some level I still hope that
That I will kind of official Myself by being consumed do you know I think that dream is still is still very much alive
Know if I'm being perfectly honest with you
You know I do
I do sometimes fear that that moment has passed
I feel weird saying this but
I could drink you
Right now
Yeah
I mean I want
I want you I am thirsty but I also I want this to be a good moment for you
I want you to be read I don't want you to do it if you're not ready
Well
I'll make a deal with you
I've always said I wanted to go with my eyes wide open
I'm prepared to ended here if you promise me that even if you're disgusted by I taste you will finish the can
I will make you that promise
Is there anything you want to say
The humans you've encountered the Kansas
Encounter the
Countertops
You've known
I think
I think overall I would say life is a gift and a blessing
And I don't believe anything is but everything simply transforms into the next thing
I would say
If I can be a little bit soft hard and sentimental for a moment or two
It's a gift to get to be anything at all
Well maybe what we'll do in that just in the interest of Journalism is all
Drink about half
Animal check in again do you want to talk while I'm drinking you I don't
No
Okay
No I want to have the full experience
Okay I'll check in with you at the halfway mark
Alright so
I'm up
I'm picking you up
Give me one second
Okay
Are you ready
This I have to say feels delightful
I will am I guess
Cheers cheers to you with you
Here's hoping for the best
I mean
Your
You are delicious
Thank you
You're very gentle
This is
Trippy feeling I'm not going to lie
Alright my first report
Feeling very spacious inside right now if you got back I got room to be
But I'm also
I'm feeling the warmth of the tummy
Very strange thing I'm in two places at once spaces in my own body was feeling warm and securing your own tummy
All the sudden I find myself
Thinking about my body
I'm thinking about my body and I'm hoping that my body is a good place for you
I think so
I don't mind telling you my first impression of the inside of your own tummy you seem to be taking pretty good care of yourself
Yeah
I am seeing someone are you sweating saying some
I'm going to I'm going to have a little more
You go ahead and finish me off
Okay
Are you
Are you still there
Everything is alive is produced by Jennifer Mills
San Angelo
This episode had reporting from Patrick win and Timothy Jorgensen in the piece we heard the song sheets to buy the band Mountain
Their album Coral Louis was played by Louis kornfeld
Find out more at everything is alive. Com
I'll have a behind-the-scenes discussion with Ian and a preview of this season of everything is alive after this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here and then
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
What attracted you to tell the story of
Louis the
Generic Cola as the first episode of everything is alive
I think I imagined that a can of generic Cola wood
Maybe have a chip on his shoulder
It's always been compared to like the big guy you know
It's even been made to try and
Trick people into thinking it's Goku
Coca-Cola
You know it has its own identity
Maybe that
Makes it bitter
I mean that in the emotional sense not a new flavor sense
But because there's a relationship between generic things and non generic things that it would like
It would already have some personality that made sense
The conversations are like they're real interviews like we don't scrap them
We just like ask a person
Do a little research
Or like we give them research
And then I interview that I don't know and so like things where at
You know where there's a little bit of character already to the thing I think it's more fun and it's easier for the actor
The Voice app
I know Lewis is
An actor is the eBay guy in actor
No
Yeah
We we call them up
I don't know there was like there was a number on his
His Facebook page and
Yeah he's real he's okay I'll tell you that
Cuz he's a he's a very good character
Yeah that's amazing
Annie's fine though
I said I started to do a little research about like if glass would actually
Old radiation
And I actually don't know the answer to that but but I can pay for his cases
Can you tell people what to expect
In this season of Everything Is Alive we have a number of things were talking to or talking to a
Lamppost named Maeve
There's a bar of soap named Tara
Right now I'm working on an interview with Jake
Who is
A mailbox
A mousetrap
Who
Actually
She has to use a pseudonym
She's having
The Mousetrap is having a lot of
Second thoughts about what
She's asked to do
She doesn't she does not want to kill mice
She has a lot of other ideas about what
She could
Do instead
Given the form she was given
None of which
Are as good as
Mousetrap mousetrap
They're all really going to be different and we really
I want them all to be different things
They're going to be deep thinking objects and they're going to be
Superficial objects
And I think they're going to be unlikable object
They're certainly objects you don't like me
Very much
And
So
Yeah I mean I think our goal is is just that it be a
Diverse community of
Thanks
And I'm so
Do they not like you on principle or
Through the action of you interviewing them it's through me interviewing them
It's funny though like
I realize cuz I really I feel the same interviewing a thing as I do interviewing a person
I really do and sometimes it will be after the interview
Realize there was something I was afraid to ask
What was wrong with me
Like why
Why was I afraid of offending that.
I'll
Is there an Ultimate get for you that you're like working your way up towards
There is a yeah
Yeah you know I'm trying to take the things very seriously
But I do think
If the final episode
Of the shell
Was
An interview with an ice cube
Play Ice Cube
Sweetheart styles
Everything is alive is the latest show from radiotopia from PA
Lorax get it at everything is alive. Cam at radiotopia. FM
On Apple podcasts and radio public
99percentinvisible is a project of kalw San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
You can find the show endurance test about the show on Facebook even treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi Orrick
Instagram Tumblr and ready to put our true home on the web
Is 99 Pi. Org radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy
You know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to
Huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym crossed
Inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com