99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
And now 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The shipping forecast issued by the Met Office on behalf of the maritime and coastguard agency
On Monday the 21st of September
4 * everyday
Radios all across the British Isles
A BBC announcer begins reading from a seemingly indecipherable script
Viking north of Sierra
Southwest delete 5 to 7
Change my account
Raynaud Shaw's Madras or
Occasionally poor
Cryptic mesmerizing mumbo jumbo
Is the shipping forecast
UK's nautical weather report
Time to go fishing
Southwest 405 increasing 506
Occasionally 7 laser
Occasional reign
Madras
And that voice you hear reading it
Is Peter Jefferson
21 Peter Jefferson used to work the BBC for about life time and a half
And that one thing I did that was to read the shipping forecast
Peter started working for the BBC back in the 60s
He was an announcer which man he read the news
But one day they handed him a very different sort of scrap
It was the shipping forecast
Never thought that one day I'd be reading it
And when I was faced with it and lived to tell me
How would you go about reading it I was there
So he just read this
Word for word
Originally I was reading was wondering to myself
Hell is all this about
But he got through it
And from that day forward Peter Jefferson's job which he would keep for 40 years until he made a fateful
Steak
Was to read one of the oldest
Strangest
Most beloved weather forecast in the world
It going for
A hundred years now
Become a people regarded as poetry
This is Charlie Conley
Including attention all shipping a journey round the shipping forecast
Charlie is pretty into the shipping forecast
Forecast
Coming back to be saying this but
I have my alarm set every morning to go up for 25 5 in time for that early morning shipping forecast
Did Charlie is really into the shipping forecast
NCLEX test
The story of how Charlie's favorite radio program came to be begins in the 1850s
With a man named Fitzroy
It comes back to you Admiral Robert Fitzroy who was the captain of the beagle Charles Darwin ship
After a long tumultuous sometimes controversial career
It took him all over the world
Bob Fitzroy decided he wanted to find a solution to one of the most serious
Problems facing Sailors in the 19th century
The weather
By the mid-nineteenth century the amount of shipping around the world was absolutely phenomenal
Antique stones with blocks a and ships would be lost live
Chicago
Around this time people were just beginning to understand the connection between air pressure and storms
And fish woke up really interested in this because of the potential applications
Maritime
Fitzroy was appointed head of the new meteorological office
And he poured all his energy into the study of airbrush
Get a barometer
And he would use it to try to figure out
What the weather was about to do
And then one day
In 1859
A ship called the Royal Charter was sailing from Australia to Liverpool
Many of the passengers onboard were minors
Returning from the Australian goldfields
They were almost home
When suddenly
Huge storm blew up in in the RCN chase the ship out of the coast
Robert Fitzroy was sitting in his house in London at the time of Jesus
On the wall
So I knew that was a big storm somewhere
In the vicinity of Britain and Ireland
The captain of the royal Charter try to ride out the storm
But eventually the winds blew the ship onto the rocks
The Royal Charter song
And over 450 people drowned
Throw Fitzroy to this really badly because I felt responsible for this terrible disaster
They can want anyone
Fitzroy decided to devote the rest of his life to saving lives at sea
By predicting the weather
Which in Victorian times was pretty controversial because here they are they're very religious people and anything that kind of sounded a bit like
Prophecy was kind of heavy dragons in witchcraft as far as the victorians
Concerned
So we decided to use a synonym
4 prophecy
That didn't sound quite so Twitchy
He invented invented the term weather forecast to distinguish it from prophesying
Superstition in electronic thing
Fitzroy inventor of the weather forecast
Delivered his prognostications by Telegraph to the various ports around the UK
Signal flags were hoisted in the harbor to warn ships heading out to sea
Eventually his forecast for published in the newspaper
And well they were often ridiculed by readers at the time
They were pretty accurate
And they became indispensable
We're Sailors and fishermen alive that was saved as a result of Fitzroy anyway
And decades after his death
Fitzroy shipping forecast would expand its reach
And become a British spoken word love poem to the Sea
All thanks to a new technology
Radio the BBC
British Broadcasting Company calling
BBC was founded in 1922
And 2 years later
The first shipping forecast went out on the airwaves BBC Radio full
Map shipping forecast there have been many shipping forecast readers over the years
Biking Nova Terrace Southwest Southeast becoming cyclonic 5 to 7
Moderate or good
1969 Peter Jefferson join the club
When he first started he didn't understand the words he was reading
He was not a sailor
In fact he couldn't even swim
He didn't know the difference between a gale
In a cyclone he didn't know exactly where docker was
What time does the yolk White actress that said this is what it means
Peter learned that the numbers are wind speed
The directions are wind direction
In the random adjectives like good
Or poor
Are descriptions of the visibility
And all those Whimsical names are real places
Regions of the ocean around Great Britain
Names by the Met off
Some are named after Islands
Or towns along the coast
Summer named after Rivers
Summer named off to sandbanks
Was wonderful Rockwall
Which mm
Mitchell is a rock sticking out of the sea
Inhabited by seagulls nothing else I think
Sailors know how to decode the shipping forecast in over the years it has provided them with wheelie important information
But most people in Great Britain
Are landlubbers
They do not need to know the weather conditions around some seagull rock
Hundreds of miles from the nearest coastline
Still
There's just something
About the forecast
That appeals to them
The words and the I suppose the tone and the
Pace
Mesmerizing in a way
People just drive is everything from just very soothing to a sort of
Prayer
And maybe you can see where this is heading
Maybe as you listen to Peter
Your eyelids
Are getting heavy
And your thoughts
Are getting dreamy
If this is the case
You Are Not Alone
Peter discovered pretty early on
The people all across Great Britain
For tuning into the late-night shipping forecast
Just before 1 in the morning
Or something
Entirely different
From its intended purpose
Somebody once said to me
I love listening to you sending me asleep
Beijing Nights
Peter was loving them into sweet
Sweets
Oblivion
I took it to the backhanded compliment ready anyway
For the record
I hear this a lot to
You've told me that my voice puts you to sleep
It doesn't bother me
I'm sure you wake up in the morning and listen to every episode from the beginning
Really appreciate the craftsmanship
The quality journalism
Cut oneself off from the actual meaning it doesn't actually have that that time have a meaning to you
Dentist Chester American Voice
Speaking to you
Soothing way
On YouTube someone strong dozens of shipping forecast together into a 5 hour video
In the comments
Are all these people going on and on about how much the shipping forecast has helped
Cure their insomnia
I fell asleep to this almost every night
There's something oddly soothing about it
Yep bores the pants off me to sleep as well
Beyond
There's dozens of these comments
Love this
So boring
Bedtime story zzzzzzzz
And honestly providing a soothing bedtime story might be the forecast primary function at this point
Plenty of people still listen out at sea
But these days
Many sailors have weather radar on board and smartphones with internet access
I'm surprised actually that it still there
Because there are many other ways of getting that information rather than listening to the radio
And yet decade after decade
The BBC continues to broadcast the forecast
Every single day
The exact same times
Some music I know they change the time the shipping forecast spend thousands of people marching on Brookhurst
London
This might be a bit of an exaggeration
But the point is the British Bob the shipping forecast
And you shouldn't try to take it away from them
The goodness knows what might happen to be civil wars
Over his decades-long career
Peter Jefferson became one of the most recognizable readers of the shipping forecast
And his voice was a metronome
Sailors and insomniacs alike
Peter had all kinds of other responsibilities at the BBC
But you could never really Escape his association with the forecast
Not even at his own wedding
Am I then future wife and myself while I was outside the church we had these bank at Fords have lost again on inside
Fully went in on
The vicar was in there delivering what he called their wedding forecast in which he described their partnership as
Moderate
Becoming good
Which coast
A great deal of love laughter and when we had it before it was fantastic
And then one day after learning some bad news
Peter made a mistake
Aaliyah that died being told
A prostate cancer end
I don't think I should have gone into work that day cuz my mind was
Note on what I was actually doing it was on other things that you can put the Imagine
He stumbled over his words trying to transition
I thought I chose the mic
But I haven't found I said
Unfortunately
I followed it shortly afterwards
Peter was fired
I got a phone call from my boss and the shift of the next few weeks but after that
Thank you and goodbye
The BBC has consistently maintained they didn't fire Peter because of the slip
Camping around for a long time and they wanted to get some fresh faces in the building
Enough I mean I was thinking of stopping at a few months later anyway
Forecast Moscow on though
Panda.
The shipping forecast guy outfit on the real thing it is terrifically important
Insanity warning paper-bag weather
I'm just reminding people that we are Marathon people wear Marathon nice
This is Charlie Connolly again
He talks about the shipping forecast like it's a piece of literature
An Ode to Great Britain's relationship with the sea
National effects like the Canterbury Tales and Beowulf for the shipping forecast to be the equivalent
British national anthem
National Epic
We knew chapters written everyday
Four times a day
Buy bunch of meteorologist in office block somewhere
Buddy
Guy sitting at desk
Waste Paper bins next to make Browning apple cores in them
Then and it was texting them saying what somebody be human and then they producing this amazing stuff
Gyros
Every one of them
As for our hero
Peter Jefferson
Getting fired did not sever his connection with the shipping forecast
If anything
It made it stronger
It gave him time to write an entire book about
And he's got a new project
Lexus lost yeah right I go to an email out of the blue the email was from the popular meditation app
Calm
Comb produces what they call Sleep story
Meant to be listen to right before bed
And they wanted Peter to read the shipping forecast for them
Minnesota Twins
Imeca rather soothing bedtime story
Peter obliged
He read the forecast from his last day at the BBC
It was a pretty quiet day weather wise
No major storms
Much more slowly than I would normally
Successful
So successful that they hired him to read another of their bedtime stories
And this one has nothing to do with the shipping forecast
What they want me to do is read this very
Retarded
Legalese
Documents
Facebook send people to sleep and I think they're absolutely right
Here's a little taste of Peter reading from the eu's recent General data protection regulation
How many codons to the Treaty of the functioning of the European Union
Particular
Article 16 lateral it's pretty sinilangan stuff
Having regards to the proposal
European Commission
Having dogs to the opinion of the European
Economics
He may not be saving lives at sea
But Peter believes helping people get to sleep
Is a very honorable profession
As somebody who has huge problems
Fall asleep self
I hope that it does work
Cuz I know what horrible thing it is if you
Come get to sleep
German thighs
West packing Southwest
405 Precinct 6 at First National rain
Madras Oregon
White
Variable becoming southwesterly
Precinct 405 laser
Family Fare
Madras Google
Good enough for you
That's great
I was just I was going to stop you but then I got
Mesmerize finish
Peter Jefferson's book is called and now the shipping forecast
Charlie Collins book is called attention all shipping
A journey round the shipping forecast
You can find links to both on our website
Pri.org
You still awake
You are still awake dear listener
Stay tuned for more of the art of putting people to sleep with sound
After the break
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Okay so the shipping forecast became a bedtime ritual for a lot of people
Accidentally
In the same could be said of our show
About this week's episode might be a bit of an exception most of the time we're not trying to put you to sleep
But I'm here with you Ackerman who is the creator of a podcast called sleep with me
And the whole goal of his show
Does that help people doze off
ESO sleeping me is a bedtime story podcast for grown up
And the whole idea is
To take the listener's mind off of what's keeping them away
Wake
To disengage them enough so they can pay attention to the story or to what I'm saying
But where they don't feel the pressure to keep listening
And there's also the risk of like
Is this compelling thing coming at my show
A steer right around the compelling farts and I go into the Indian details
Is my cat a specialty
But
It is it's just like a bedside companion
That's meant to be there
In the my grip on The Listener ideal he's just loose enough that they feel like they could just let
Go my hand and drift away when they want to
I think that if you were to
Look up what a relaxation videos on YouTube there's a
Harp music or a whooshing sounds or people whispering or something
This appeals to the swerve the intellectual monkey mind
That is
Tripping wait you at your day and you create something enough of a narrative that people can latch onto
But it's loose enough
That people can also drift away from
And how did you come up with this as the way
To be that type of bedtime companion
Hellboy I have this controversial belief that I didn't want to bring up on the podcast but I call that kind of part of our brain
Brain brain.
Should I believe it
Then my brain and maybe other people's brains are populated by these little
Droid
In all these Droids that they serve these different
Purposes like at worrying
Thinking about the past
And none of them have sleep modes unfortunately
And I found said that
By just going to say hey come on over here let me tell you a story I hear to see your worrying about high school
And then when you spill. Lemonade down your shirt yet who I love I'm going to talk about it
A suspenders for a little while and Rainbow Stew
Suspenders in particular
And ideas
Even one party has to be like what is it I can picture rainbows
Suspenders
I've never had them but
And I do it's like so they could that suggest visual enough and just enjoy it enough
That you'll think about it for a few minutes and interrupt your train of thought
We're going to be like
Okay he's it's been 14 minutes he's still talking about rainbow suspenders
Lakers
Used trying to conceive try to make a metaphor about it
What's somewhere under the rainbow suspender
So they gay
And what we do here to question that just came up while I was recording this interview
Are there any leprechauns that have rainbow suspenders cuz they should
I really wanted to white people
Or make them feel some kind of delight versus bedtime that you feel so
Serious
An ominous
Even if I don't
Hit that goal
It's like
I joke I might not make you smile but maybe I can bring your face to a neutral
Two neutral level
It's like my over trying to overshoot
I can just get to the place where the people
Instead of laughing
Define
Oh yeah that's pretty good
Drew's approach the storytelling is quite unique but over the years he has tried to fall asleep to
Lots of different types of audio
When he was growing up
There was this comedy radio show called Doctor Demento and he like to listen to it late at night
Helping get to sleep
So when I was a kid and I had trouble sleeping
Remember I was telling this one classmate like I can't sleep at night and then Sunday nights are the worst because they started having anxiety about
School ever been at school a few days
And he said my other my older brother listen to this radio show is on Sunday nights from 9 to 11
It's a comedy radio show they play parody songs
And I turned into it and I guess one of the things I wanted in the in the Doctor Demento provided
Like this can be like an overused word or sound over-ambitious but like
It really is this idea of compassion
When you break up the word like is suffering with or suffering together and I'll dig documentary knew that but it was like dr.
They are with me
Sitting by my bedside scene
Hey the skunk stinks you can't sleep and
I really feel bad
For you
And
When I can't sleep I have this story about myself running through my brain about the past about the future
And I want to just misdirect people and say Hey listen to the story over here
It's a it's a nicer story you're not a character in it
And it's just here to keep you company in here sitting you don't even need to listen to it to fall asleep at like I'll just be here to tell you
Play the story
End
Pegasus of what I wanted as a kid 2
Haven't you been doing sleep with me for a few years what kind of feedback have you gotten from the listeners of the show
So
It was in the first leg a 8 months of the show
Occasionally the end that would make jokes like a and I think it was because I was new to podcasting in May
It was really afraid I would make you do that self-effacing jokes like oh no one's probably listening to this
At this point in the show
I got three emails in a row from people
Please don't say that like
I am awake
At the end of the show
And I'm listening to the show
To be distracted like because I'm not going to fall asleep
And it's painful for me to be reminded of that
And it brought me right back to that memory is like lying there
When I went to the doctor men told there was no hope of me falling asleep either
So that was one piece of feedback is that
It's pretty powerful and then it's like just getting feedback about what people are afraid of
And then trying to steer around that
Leica
For spiders and be like web-based being sore
For any other animals that are scary like Forest
Friends lake
I like stuff like that like tried as just a dream
Drive the car right around those trees Savannah crash into him
Mets Drew Ackerman host and creator of the podcast sleep with me
Take out soup with me wherever you listen to podcasts
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital director
Russell team include senior editor Delaney Hall Avery truffelman Joe Rosenberg
Vivien Leigh Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX an independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Lowe's in all a podcasting
Von Maur
And radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook
You can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But you want a bunch of other 99 Pi episodes but YouTube play
As you are drifting off to sleep
Go to
99 pi
. org
And now the shipping forecast
Issued by the Met Office on behalf of 99% invisible
For Monday the 23rd of July
The area forecast for the next 24 hours
West Viking
So the way for 5
Becoming variable 3 later
Slide
Mainely Fair
Moderate or good
East Viking Norfolk serie
West Sound at 0
Variable three or four
Slight Fair
Good
Eselfserve
Northwesterly 5 / 6
Backing Westerly for later
Moderate
Becoming slightly later
Fair
Good
40s
South Burien Southwest
Three or four
Slight
Fair
Good
Cromartie fourth time
Variable mainly south or Southwest
Three or four
Increasing V at time
Slide
Fair then rain
Good
Occasionally poor later
Duggar
South or Southwest three or four
Slide
Fair
Good
Northeast Fisher
Northwesterly five or six
Back in Westerly for later
Moderate
Becoming slight later
Fair
Good
Temescal Piedmont
Northwest
Three or four
Increasing 5 at times
Slight
Showers later
Good
Occasionally moderate
Bushrod Rockridge
Northerly or Northwest early for 5
Occasionally sex
Slight or moderate
Showers
Dondria first
Good
Grand Lake
North or Northwest
Four five
Occasionally 6 later
Slight or moderate
Fair
Good
Highland Park
Glenview
Westerly or northwesterly 3 or 4
Occasionally five except in Glenview
Slight or moderate
Bare then rain or showers
Good occasionally moderate
Elmhurst
Variable three or four
Becoming Southwest for 5
Slide
Fair then rain
Good
Occasionally poor
Alameda Fruitvale jingletown
Southwest Burien Northwest four or five
K-26
The first accept in Fruitvale
Slight or moderate
Rain or drizzle
Good
Occasionally poor
West Oakland
West or Northwest
Four five
Moderate
Occasionally slight later and west
Rain then Fair
Good
Lower bottom
So the elite four five
Occasionally 6 at 1st and west
Becoming variable 3 or 4
Slight or moderate
Occasional reign
Bald patches
Monitor good
Occasionally
Very poor
Jack London Square
Summer league during Northwest early for 5
Occasionally 6 at 1st and East
Then decreasing 3 for a Time
Moderate
Becoming slide or moderate
Rain or drizzle
Pain patch
Moderator good
Occasionally
Very poor
Chinatown
Cyclonic mainly normally 5 or 6
Becoming variable 3 or 4
Light or moderate
Bald patches at first
Moderate or good
Occasionally
Very poor at first
Beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Variable one or two
Vulgarly
Then Fair
Good
Becoming hella good
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com