99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
For the past few days Californians have watched as the car Wildfire has raged through the northern part of the state
The fire started a little more than a week ago
Fueled by dry brush
High temperatures and strong shifting winds
The fire has moved from a national Recreation Area
Into the nearby city of Redding
As of this recording six people have died 19 people are reported missing in thousands have a key
He waited the fire is only 20% contained
Wildland fires aren't new in California
But with climate change are fire seasons are becoming longer and fires are becoming bigger
And harder to fight
So the next two weeks we're going to look at the issue of wildfire
Some design Solutions
Just how complicated they can be to implement
The Santa Ana winds of Southern California are sometimes called the devil winds
They pick up in the late summer and early fall
Sweeping down from the mountains and across the coast are hot dry and known for creating
Dangerous fire conditions
In late November of 1980 as the Santa anas blue in it up to 90 miles an hour
Unknown arsonist with a fire near Panorama point
San Bernardino Mountain
Mets reporter Stephanie Joyce
Pushed by the wind the fire grew and quickly spread down the mountain towards the city of San Bernardino
Elizabeth city's been fired
Talking to a reporter and we had extremely strong winds humidity was somewhere
About 10
Another local fire chief said they called in all available resource
And still
It wasn't enough
There was no stopping the fire
All the conditions were
Just wright
+ 4
What we commonly refer to as a firestorm
In just a few hours
Panorama fire destroyed hundreds of homes
Killed 4 people
Was one of the worst Wildfire disasters in California history
The time
It was also the fire that would make a young researcher
Question or entire approach to wildfires
And conclude
That we might be able to design our way out of the devastation
Because
When was a few years out of graduate school
In a recent transplant to California
Time of the fire
He's working as a research scientist with a
The forest server
Studying fire Behavior
He was interested in how to Panorama fire and destroyed so many homes
Especially when there was such an overwhelming firefighting response
A Strike Team of entrances five engines and they had 20 strike teams coming in
Right away
There would be a whole block of houses on fire and they could not deliver enough water
So they were calling in
More hoses
And moving
A block down
42 block
Box down and losing that
And then moving
Further
And losing that
Two Jacks are listening to the emergency dispatch
Tapes from the day of the fire
Jack is a matter-of-fact kind of guy
Assignment
Rational
Not emotional
Almost 40 years later he's still chokes up when he talks about the desperation he heard in the firefighters voice
The teams are pretty hard to understand
But you can hear the emotion
It was pretty emotional
Particularly listening
The radio traffic
Just couldn't
He couldn't fight it
For those of us who mostly say wildfires on TV or in pictures of the paper
It's easy to imagine that a wildfire is like a tsunami of flames
Spreading across the landscape and destroying everything in its path
But Jack knew it wasn't that simple
Piece together how the disaster had unfolded
And so one of the things that I did was to look at
When the first
Call Kami on to dispatch for a fire in this community
Where was that call from
And where was the Wildfire at that time
Just get out of here
Just get out
Is Jack was listening to the tape
He started to notice a pattern
People were calling in about houses on fire
Long before
The fire front ever reach their neighborhoods
The Wildfire was
Still actually on the other side of the ridge
About a half a mile away burning up the hill
These houses were burning because of wall of Fire
Was racing through the community
They were burning because of something else
The Embers
As wildfires burn they generate Ember
Better lofted downwind ahead of the main body of a fire
Jack realized most of the houses that burned had one
Extremely problematic feature in common
As it turns out every house had a flammable Woodroof
The Embers were accumulating in the crevices around the dry wood shingles
Setting fire to the houses from above
Across the street in a development without wood roofs
Most of the houses that survived
And while that might not seem like a huge epiphany
That houses with wood roofs burned and houses without wood roofs didn't
For Jack
It was that detail that made him rethink the entire Wildfire problem
Because when you listen to other people talk about the fire
They weren't focusing on the wood roof
They were talking about firefighting
They were saying nothing could have been done
I just captain in the San Bernardino fire department
If we would have had as many as 500 units
Read along the whole Hillside there to protect those homes
I don't believe that we could have stopped that fire any better than we did on his condition
WeChat
The only thing that I feel is that what could have saved those homes
Would have only been an act of God
Jack didn't think that was right the problem wasn't the firefighting response
The problem was that the houses
What are built
To burn
And when Jack shifted his Focus
The fire to the design of the home
Suddenly he found himself wondering if we were framing the whole problem of wildfire in the wrong way
He wasn't the first to have that thought
But he was the first
To do extensive research
Exactly
How homes burned in wildfires
Some of that work put him at odds with some of the main firefighting agencies in the US
And nearly a hundred years of fire policy in Tradition
And even though his ideas are simple and compelling
They still haven't caught on in the way that he hoped they would
Maybe because fighting fires is as much a social and political problem as it is a technical one
Do you feel frustrated most of the time
For most of this country's history or approach to Wildfire has been driven by the sentiment
Fire is bad
Before colonization Native American tribe set fires intentionally to regenerate while playing
How to create grassland habitat for game
When Europeans arrived they brought fear of fire with them
And overtime in much of the country not only did we do away with the practice of setting fires we actually
He started to extinguish naturally-occurring fires to
In 1911 that became an official responsibilities of the newly-created for a service
Even got a name
The 10 a.m.
Is it the forest service
To put out every new fire on public land by 10 a.m. the following day
President Roosevelt
Civilian Conservation Corps was on the front lines of implementing
That policy
We fought those fire night and day sometime
You can see smoke
Clear the end of the world
The belief was that with enough water and Manpower
Firefighters could put out any wildfire
And a huge industry rose up around that idea
Agreed to employ tens of thousands of people
With hundreds of millions of dollars a year being spent on planes and helicopters and fire Crews
And for a while that Brute Force approach seem to work
What does early firefighters had an advantage
For millennia
Before the rise of modern fire suppression
Woodburn regularly
America
S4s
They would eat up all the fuel
Thyroxine low-intensity
Estate on the forest floor
As firefighters begin aggressively fighting fires
That balance started to change
With fewer fires burning
For it started getting more and more dance
On the forest
Did catch on fire
There's more material to burn in a fire burn hotter
And bigger
If I delete by suppressing natural fires
We created something that turned out to be much much worse
Here's Mark Finney
He's a fire scientist with the forest service
Fighting fire really has some
Unintended consequences
Or maybe even worse than the fire so
In Oxnard
Since the very beginnings of our fire suppression policies
There been people arguing that it wasn't a good idea to put out every fire
But it took until the 1980s for that idea to really take hold
By then it was also becoming increasingly clear
That we couldn't put out every fire
Especially as they got bigger and bigger
We're not actually stopping them we're just delaying them
Yeah there's a
The saying a fire put out as a fire put off
But even as the public in the 1980s started to accept the idea that
Fire was natural and necessary
And fighting it had unintended consequences
Not fighting it
Didn't seem like a viable option
Outside of remote Wilderness Area
Because how could you stop
Fighting fires
When they threatened
Which brings us back to Jack Cohen
The panorama fire
Once he started to focus on the home at the problem not the wildfire
He wanted to know what made some houses more susceptible than others
This was a question that I had in my mind a curiosity question what I'm trying to do is to ask
Establish a relationship between wildfire and Hondas
I want to know what that linkage is
How does this happen
In the Panorama fire
It had clearly been the wood roofs but in other fires there were plenty of homes without wood roofs
Hepburn 2
So Jack said about learning all of the houses potential weaknesses
All the ways it might possibly catch on fire
The first thing he wanted to know was how close the
Flames of the Wildfire had to be to a house
Frederick Knight simply from the radiant heat
Answer that question he did a series of experiments
Including one in the late 1990s in Northern Canada
Reset an actual Forest
Text on fire
Do you actually cut
Slots
M2
Affordable realtor
And then
Japan on fire
Yes
Glastonbury
What Jack found in the experiment
Was it an entire Forest
Could be on fire
30 feet away from the house
And nothing
It was fine
But of course Jack news at the flames and the radiant heat weren't the only threats to the house
There were also the Embers
He frequently found himself standing next to houses reduced to Ash
And next to them
Green trees
It was a Telltale sign the fire front never even reached the home
But the Embers did
Jack has a slideshow he likes to share with photos of burned houses
So this isn't going to be free audio
And it's like the optical illusion
The phase in the phases
At first
You look at the aftermath of a wildfire
And all you see is the
Destruction
But after a few slide almost feel the transition in your
In your eyes
I'm like the green trees shift into Focus
It's easy to see that the home
Is often the only thing that's burnt
When you when you see it
It's like a miracle you're like oh wow
So
One of the things that I always
Try to point out because
Everybody
That looks at news footage and pictures
Can readily observe
No trees on fire
And the structure burning
So he did experiment
To see exactly how the Ember
Setting houses on fire
He discovered Embers like to collect in lots of
Places
Like in the corners of wood
Gutters
Pine needles in an attic
Open phone
People evacuate during Wildfire there's no one around to douse The Embers
A smolder and set fire to the entire house
The more I thought about it
The more he came to believe the most Ember fires
To be stopped with some simple design solution
I mean you don't have to live in a bunker you don't have to
Cut all your trees down
Jack began to develop guidelines for Designing and Landscaping homes to withstand wildfire
He started by drawing a buffer based on a conservative interpretation of those Canadian fire experiment
He called it
Home ignition Zone
The home ignition zone is limited to the house and its immediate surroundings out to about a hundred feet
Between 150 and 30 seats in the House
The goal is to space
Trees to the fire can't jump between them
Has forced the ground
Between 30 feet and 5 feet
What was the landscape and design to the ground fire loses Steam
Removing fuels like tall grasses
Woodpile
Within five feet of the house
The going to stop
Fire dead in its tracks
With things like rock that
Well irrigated grass
What I found is that you don't have to be very exotic
About your design and materials in order to make your
The house is very resistant to ignition
Jack also came up with a long list of suggestions for preventing Ember fires on the house itself
From the big and obvious ones like replacing your flammable Woodroof
To the smaller less obvious
Like making sure your garage door has a
Tight Seal with a concrete
And removing decorative juniper trees
Which RX
Some of these ideas were pretty intuitive
I've been floating around for a long time
Many fire-prone communities homeowners have long been encouraged
The clear flammable vegetation in their properties
Send to maintain their homes in ways that would reduce
Stir chances
Catching Fire
Ajax experiments allowed him to put hard numbers
The people's intuition
Develop specific
Evidence based recommendations
For the changes homeowners should make
In Jack's experiment also showed
The windows changes were made
House was much less likely to burn
In fact he showed that was the meantime
Factor in whether a house was going to burn
It wasn't about the intensity of the fire or its size
It was really about what was happening within 100 feet of your home
And not let him to a further
Far more radical
You can have extreme Wildfire Behavior
Not control that
And yet still have houses
Survive
In other words we may not even need to fight fires as long as buildings near fire-prone areas
Are designed to withstand them
It wasn't that there weren't
Other reason
Just like fire
But Jack said there was no need to fight a fire
Is the only goal was to save houses
Not ruled out fighting a lot of force
So we have the opportunity to separate
The Wildfire issues from the home destruction issues
We can separate those
Which meant we could let more forest fires burn naturally
And finally break out of the Vicious Cycle of fire suppression that leads to the largest inferno's
Jack thought that he'd come up with a way to save houses
And let fires burn natural
He thought it was a win-win
1999 he presented a paper about his findings at a fire comprar
Events in San Diego
So I give this paper in front of a group of mostly agency people people with the forest service and
State Fire agencies
People in a position to change policy
And Jack says
They are.
Totally uninterested
Like no Quest
Jack is up there saying that it's really only what happens within a hundred feet of a home
It determines whether it burns
And no one seems to care
Except this one guy
Environmental Group
As I'm walking out he says
Do you have a copy of that paper
Ajax like
Sure
Here's a copy
A few days later a newspaper reporter calls
Asking about Jack
Talk
Check is an interview and the article comes out in a local
Wallpaper
And I don't
Exactly remember the headline
But it was something like
Poor service has its head up
Pataas
That wasn't the actual title of the article
But the story did imply that basically everything about how the forest service dealt with wildfires
What's wrong
Because remember the 10 a.m. rural had left us with this huge firefighting infrastructure
The forest service was spending hundreds of millions of dollars on planes and fire Crews
Was approving massive logging projects
Next on the grounds of thinning out the forest would help reduce the intensity
Wildfires in safe homes
And Jack was saying actually it would be way more effective if you just encouraged homeowners
Maintain retrofit their properties 9 in the morning I get a phone call
From
Region 6
Forest Service
The fire director of region 6
What do you think you're doing
Immediately
He was in trouble
He remembers the conversation
The director told Jack he was putting those big logging projects
In jeopardy
And not put the director in a sticky
Keep political
But in the middle of getting chewed out by the director Jack just
Double down he says
He knew what the data said
He knew the signs wasn't wrong
And he told the director of the logging projects weren't going to do much to save home
And I said well
You might have a problem
Because the research I've done
Doesn't indicate that that's going to be very effective
That was the end of the phone call
And pretty much
The beginning of
Adversity
For the next
Three or four years at least
I don't know I wasn't at a level to know whether was resistant
This is Shawna legarza
She currently the national director of fire and Aviation management
Forest Service
Jack was first promoting his ideas
She wasn't in manager
So she wouldn't comment on the pushback
The Jack says he
Effaced
She does say that over her 30-year career in the forest service
She's seen more and more emphasis placed on strategies like defensible space
Which means clearing your property of flammable materials
And she's happy
I believe that people taking my ownership
And their home and have a defensible spaces is number one service can do to encourage
Rich people to make changes
A lot of that work falls on local governments and individual homeowners
And even today
Not everyone is convinced that it's important to invest in the kinds of preparations that Jack recommends
Yeah you know so it's
It's kind of scattered across the country, communities don't believe a fire will ever happen
Weather out it'll never happen to me
And I'll never have to evacuate and so I went to keep my trees and shrubs right by my house and
Unfortunately time is telling us or showing us that it does happen
Fire has no boundaries and no preference for
Aware burn
And in the meantime the forest service
As a congressionally-mandated duty to fight fires
Last year the federal government spent more than two billion dollars fighting fires
Just a small fraction of that prevention and mitigation
Deference
Parkour culture views fire
Has primarily an emergency response activity
But if you treat fire only is an emergency response under emergency circumstances you're missing out on all the preventive
This is Mark Finney again
You remember he also works
For the forest service
He was on board with Jack's ideas
He also understood that there were huge challenges
Implement
The reasons why they didn't catch on
First we can't just throw a bunch of scientific papers on the table and
Have everybody reason to go out cheese thanks
That's what I needed now we have a different
View of how things work
There's too much history behind the idea that we've got to do something about fire
Whether it's effective or not we the public
Expect to see dramatic shots of airplanes flying over raging fires
Dropping water on them
But when communities put
Principles Jack articulated into practice
They work
There are several communities in Southern California built with wildfires in mind
That survived when nearby homes
Didn't
But those homes are mostly
Free Custom Design
Gated communities
Homeowners association
7/4 strict rules about vegetation
Home design
Making changes elsewhere is more complicated
For starters many homeowners may not even have
Space
To clear and Fireproof
It's expensive to replace your roof
Renters they may not have the authority to
Make changes to
Their homes
Remaining cases
There aren't incentives
For people to invest
Plus many homeowners just kind of instinctively get
Got the odds of being in a wildfire or extremely low
There are more than 40 million homes in wildfire-prone areas
And only a few thousand burn every year
Without someone compelling them to do it
Homeowners might decide is just not worth spending time and money
To change their properties
So even though Jack's ideas are
Pretty simple
They're not simple to actually implement
In the real world
DuckTales
The story about a friend of his
Descended modifying homes to make them fire
Assistant isn't Rock
And I said to him know this
Is much harder this is social science
And his comment is
OG's we're screwed
Jack's ideas have become more mainstream Overtime Bar agencies like the forest service
Now talk a lot about defensible space
There's more emphasis placed on homeowner responsibility
Jack also helped start the prominent organization firewise which promotes fire preparedness
Shawna legarza the forest service fire director
Does it be enormously destructive fires of the last few years
I've also forced people to think about how to make their homes and properties more fire
Resistant
And I think every year there's going to be more awareness about Wildland firefighting in
An evacuation Zone do you have defensible space or not
Just because of the trends every year
You know we saw it last year with largest and most devastating
A fire year and now we have this year which is larger and more devastating than last year human fatality
Firefighter fatalities
And with climate change the Fire season is only getting longer
When I asked the Garza if she could imagine a future like the one Jack proposes
The forest service would get out
As a firefighting
I think we're a long ways from that you know so I mean we're all bored for fired after communities and resilient landscapes
Sinper you know folks have defensible space or around around their structures
And I'm more healthy Brazilian national forest system slanted we're a long ways from that we are a long way from
The forest service is currently fighting several dozen fires Across the Western United States
When you're that busy running around putting out fires
Literally
It's hard to focus on how to prevent the
I'm from being so destructive
If in the first place
Jack retired from the forest service a few years ago
Feeling like all his research
Haven't made much of a difference in the end
When he's watching the news
Especially coverage of the past few destructive fire seasons in California
You've noticed there isn't a lot of talk about making homes more fire-resistant
Clearing defensible space
Instead
There's a lot about firefighter
Apocalyptic
Identify overwhelm firefighters
Did what they could no way you could stop a fire front like that
The fire
One of the very frustrating things that I had
Experience this past summer but you really from the California fires
Is the continued
Sounds
Of fatalism
Oh well there's nothing that could be done
Well
Know that
The bottom line is
That we can do something it just doesn't have anything to do with
Controlling the wild
This fire is now 45%
Watching news footage from the California fires
Something stands out
Especially if
You spend a lot of time with Jack
Once you get over the shock of
Racine neighborhoods reduced
The drama firefighters talking about how there was nothing they could do to
Stop the flames
Your eyes shift to something else
The green trees
Untouched by fire
Surrounding the burned-out home
We are really
In a battle with nature
That nature is more powerful than we are firefighters are battling the fire
Next week will be continuing to explore the issue of wildfire and just how hard Jacqueline's ideas can be there in
Implement in the real world
We'll look at one community in Southern California
Which has been threatened again and again by fire
Beaver preview of that story coming up right after this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sign
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another room in Brawl hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
Next week on the show we're going to look at just how complicated it can be for a community to figure out what to do when their face
But the regular threat of destructive wildfires
And to do that we're going to spend some time with one Community & Southern California it's called Montecito
It's right next to Santa Barbara
And Daryl Cagle has lived there since the mid 60
It's a lovely place and it's
Where I grew up in a
Very comforting to
To be in the place
That is so
Familiar
The hillsides are covered with Chaparral
The scrubby brush with yellow flowers
And the neighborhoods are aligned with eucalyptus
But montecito's beautiful landscape is also what makes the community particularly vulnerable to Wildfire
The Chaparral and Eucalyptus both provide excellent fire fuel
The Canyons that sit below the hills of Montecito
A cozy little spaces for fire can easily take hold
And the town so-called
Sundowner winds
Blow hot dry air from the desert
Up over the mountains and through the Canyons
Spreading that fire
This landscape
Fire is predictable
And it is inevitable
And coupled with a multi-year drought
It is becoming unmanageable
We had no idea that fires were going to increase
Insights in frequency like they have
Maybe it's like the
The frog in the pot slowly coming to a boil
It's just so
Getting worse slowly
For decades the residents of Montecito is it a kind of
Stubborn Pioneer Street that characterizes a lot of California
After fires they rebuild
Continue on with our lives
But that kind of optimism is getting harder to sustain as far as become more frequent and more intense
And as a community is force to reckon with rebuilding again and again
And again
We are entering a new time when
Because of the weather in the impacts of climate change and long-term extended drought that fires have reached
A new level of intensity that it's causing us to have to
In some cases change our tactics or strategies and to start to you know where we're re-evaluating our deal with this
More on that story next week
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Stephanie Joyce in our senior editor Delaney Hall mix into production by Sharif
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer of coal state is the digital director
Wrestling team is Avery trufelman
Joel Rosenberg
Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to kuow
And the Tom Culligan
For research assistants
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Sinhala podcasting
Dubai Mall
The radiotopia. FM
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99pi org
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But I invite you to bask in everything 99% invisible
And 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com