99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We are in the middle of wildfire season here in California
There are more than a dozen currently burning across the state
And so we're dedicating two episodes to this issue
Last week weeks for the work of Jack Cohen
He's a forest service scientist who back in the 1980s started to argue that instead of fighting fires
We should focus more energy on building homes that were better designed to withstand fire
He helped Define and popularized the idea of defensible space which is the buffer you should create between
Building on your property
In the grass trees and other flammable materials that surround it
This week we're going to spend time in one community
In Southern California
Which is frequently threatened by fire and is grappling with what it means to rebuild
Uber
And over again
When Daryl Cagle move to Montecito California as a kid in 1964 it was a quiet town
The kind of place where his single mother who worked as a school teacher
To buy a house
Montecito used to be a very normal neighborhood
Normal people with normal jobs could afford to affordable houses there
Montecito has changed a lot since
It's now famously home to Rob Lowe and Oprah
And not so many single mothers and school teachers
The housing prices of fun crazy and the demographics of town or just
Probably extreme
But it's a lovely place and it's
Where I grew up at
Very comforting to
To be in the place
That is so
Familiar
Nestled between the mountains and the Pacific right next to Santa Barbara
Montecito is very Charming
And very geographically isolated
I can see why so many celebrities want to live there
At Susie Cagle
The reporter for our story this week and Daryl's daughter
The landscape is this mix of desert and Coast with soaring Hills natural hot springs and cool doing morning
The hillsides are covered with Evergreen Chaparral
A plant Community characterized by scrubby brush
The neighborhoods are lined with fragrant eucalyptus
Montecito's beautiful landscape is also what makes the community especially vulnerable
To Wildfire
The native Chaparral covering the hills is drought and relatively fire-resistant for the first
20 years or so of its life
Then it dries out
Too rich
Fire fuel
Then there's invasive eucalyptus trees
The Shaggy Bark and flammable oils make them burst into fire balls
The heat up during wildfire
They look like matchsticks when they catch
And pieces of their bark
Fly off to start other places nearby
The Slender Canyons that sit below the hilltops of Montecito
Our cozy little spaces where that fire can easily take hold
Which it does when the town so-called Sundowner winds
Blow hot dry air from the desert up over the mountains and through the canyon
The region indoors a major fire once every 10 years or so
Dear my dad and grandmother moved to Montecito in 1964
Wildfire called the coyote fire
Scorch 67000 Acres just north of them
Heyburn 206 homes in killed one firefighter
My dad says he doesn't remember it
For this landscape fire is predictable and it is inevitable and coupled with a multi-year drought
It's becoming unmanageable
We had no idea that fires were going to increase
Insights and frequency like they have
Maybe it's like the frog in the pot slowly coming to a boil
It's just
Getting worse slowly
For decades my dad and grandmother and the other residents
Montecito exhibited a kind of stubborn Pioneer streak that characterizes a lot of California
After fires they rebuild and continue with our lives
My grandmother had been driven from her home in Texas by the drought in the 30s
AdSense
So many Dust Bowl refugees fleeing for a better life
So what was a little fire
But that kind of optimism is getting harder to sustain as far as become more frequent and more intense
And as communities are force to reckon with rebuilding
Again and again
Again
Are we going to deal with this
Rob Hazard is the Deputy fire marshal for Santa Barbara County
Anna 5th generation Santa Barbara residence
We are entering a new time when
Because of the weather in the impacts of climate change in long term extended drought that fires
Have reached a new level of intensity that's causing us to have to change our tactics or strategies and where
Stretched to the Limit all of our resources
13 years after my dad arrived in Montecito he and my grandmother face their first
Close call with wildfire
The Sycamore Canyon fire
It was July 26th
Young man flew his box kite into a power line on a warm summer evening
Causing a spark
Which turned into a fire
The Sundowner winds pushed the growing Blaze into my dad and grandmothers dense neighborhood
Wechat only just been built in the early 60s
They evacuated
We got a car full of quickly gathered mementos and the clothes on our back and
We drove out
And next morning came back in the house was gone
The house is burned completely
From the roof down to the foundation
But the foundation was fine
In fact the chimney was left standing in the chimney was fine
195 houses burned in the fire
Many of them like my dad's
Hargrove's made of wood shingles
Was cozy are gaps in between
Perfect for flying Embers to catch
Like
Kindling on top
Map of houses
The County Fire Marshal at the time reported watching wood shingles lift off of one burning house
Why do the air and land on another house with a wood shingle roof
He called it a wood roof
Conflagration
And was there ever any question that
Grandmother wanted to rebuild or
Was that just a given
Well she had
Fire insurance and rebuilding the house was covered and
She had a
The job working for the
Schools in town and
I don't think
There was much question about it
If there is an upside to destructive wildfires it's that they give a community of the chance for a design do over
Towns have a rare opportunity to modify the landscape and rebuild houses in ways that make them more resistant
Do disasters in the future
Do the fifties and sixties Montecito made a handful of changes to prepare for future fires
The forest service tore up some of the flammable Chaparral with bulldozers
And douse it with herbicide
Until fears over toxic chemicals and a growing environmental movement
Scrap the project in the 70s
Especially firepro neighborhoods the county began requiring people to build their houses with fire-resistant roofs
And walls
And with wide areas of clear open space around the
What's known as defensible
Space
Each new disaster inspires a new edit
When my grandmother rebuilt she changed the design of their house
Those nightmares wood roofs for now band
So she replace hers with concrete
I'm peeved over the tiny surrounding yard
They did what they could to make their space more defensible
But there can be limits to the effectiveness of defensible space
That's especially true in a dense Community where people have small Lots
We have paver sand
Neighbors have rights and neighbors want trees and you can only see her
Brush from your own land
So even if you're diligent about keeping your land carefully maintained
Your neighbor might have a propane BBQ
Are tall stand of lovely eucalyptus
And their house could catch your house on fire
In Montecito preventing fires can often prove more controversial than rebuilding after them
Describe fire set in managed by firefighters
Once considered an effective way to burn off fuel
In coastal California with its
Parts Chaparral
They're hardly done any more
The so-called controlled fires can easily grow out of control and Destroy Bible ecos
+ neighborhoods
In Wichita firebreaks are expensive to maintain
And ugly
This big stretches of cleared Lander meant to make space for fire engines hoses and hand tools
They provide firefighters with ready access to
The front
But residents of affluent communities don't like to see big scars across the Lush Mountainside
Even when it's for their own protection
So Rob Hazard and other County firefighters
Rtasks
With a losing battle
Fighting nature and civilization
Without control over either one
A lot of our discussions revolve around Well Community planning that's really where we need to be tackle
Plan our communities better we need to build our houses were
Durable and resilient and
Resistant
Combustion
We need to stop building in the in the Wildland
But the sad truth is that
Already
Dealt out our community
And we're only adding two
Adult communities grow and spread inland
They've gotten closer to what used to be considered wilderness
Now it's called the wildland-urban interface
Researchers expected a million new houses will be built in those High fire hazard areas of California in the coming day
Decades
As
Urban populations have moved closer to the wildlands
We get a whole new generation of people who aren't familiar with
The risks inherent with living next to the wild lands in Southern California actually Statewide now
The reality is there there really isn't a Wilderness in Southern California eat anywhere in the state of California we can have a fire
Start in a Wilderness Area and be in the back door of a major metropolitan area
In for 5 hours
The same time communities are encroaching on what used to be wildlands
Climate change is making wildfires more frequent and intense
It's a dangerous mix
The Way We Live Through Fire has stayed remarkably the same
What a community Burns
Local authorities wash to issue new building permits
And the California and the grips of a housing crisis that has only intensified since the 1970s
It can seem crazy or not to rebuild houses
Even though the threat of fire is now year round
There is no fire season anymore
My grandmother died in 1999
And my dad moved into the Montecito house
In 2008
31 years after the Sycamore Canyon fire
The house was threatened once again
This fire called the T fire
Was eerily similar to the fire that it burn their house down all those years ago
It swooped in really fast and it took out a similar number of houses
It was quite nearby and very scary
Like
Well
It burned a whole bunch of houses on the next Street a block over
And
Smoke was swirling in
And there were Embers in the air
Should have gotten out earlier
How tall
The tea fire destroyed 210 homes in my dad's neighborhood
His house survived and despite the near-miss
Again he chose to
How to say
The constant threat had made him somewhat blase
Like a lot of people in the community
When another fire sparked in the Santa Barbara Hills just six months later
The Jesus beautifier
He didn't worry at all
Sure you could see flames in the hills from his house
But they were to Canyons over
And everything that could burn between him in the fire
Had already burned anyway
But just this past year something happened that made people feel a new sense of danger
First
It was another fire until very recently the largest in California history
In Southern California are racing against the clock
From spreading it
The Thomas fire burn through nearly a thousand homes in cities to the South before the wind moved in North Des Moines
Want to see dough overnight in the foothills
Residents watch The Blaze in awe
Horror
We have a great on the morning of December 16th
The fire was raging five blocks away from my dad's house
It got so close that it 1 Point
Satellite heat map show the fire perimeter completely covering his house
It look like it was gone
And
I never seen all of the mountains behind
Burn like that if they weren't they were
Completely denuded
They look like
Desert mountains that
Don't have anything growing on them
A shocking thing to see
Persol
Large an area hole mountain range
The Thomas fire burned more than 280,000 acres and cause more than 2 billion dollars in Damages
Eventually burned into these still fresh
Scars from other recent fires and without Chaparral another fuel to keep it going
It simply put itself out
Only three houses were destroyed in Montecito
People in the town thought they'd been spared
But then the rain came
In the early morning of January 9th 2018
A storm pummeled Santa Barbara
Half an inch of rain fell on the mountains above Montecito
In just 5 minutes
ER doctor Steve Mills was up listening to the storm
He and his family had moved to Montecito just a few years
Before that night
Everyone went to sleep
And I couldn't
It was one of these things where you're in that throw half awake half asleep state
And
I heard thunder
What I thought was
NFL
Weird Thunder last for 30 seconds
I mean what Thunder rumbles that long
And then my brain finally turned on enough that I
Left out of bed
And
Okay
I was going to make sure he's okay and then as I walked by I look outside and there's mud at the door
House of been enveloped in a river of mud rocks and trees there was a dead body right in front of our house there was
A lot of number of them washed down
Extreme indoor area and it was
Frightening
This debris flow
Or what some people mistakenly call a Mudslide
Was the direct result of the Thomas fire that had burned the mountains Bear Just week before
It all goes back
The Chaparral
After the fire the waxy substance that coats the Chaparral leaves was left as a film across the score
Soil
That oily coating made the ground impervious to water
Serene slipped across it instead of soaking in
Is the rain skimmed across the soil
There was no Chaparral to restrain it
Thomas fire had devoured all the plants
Years Rob hazardous
And what that does
Completely strips the
The hillside of anything that can hold back
Soil Rock debris
To such an extent that you know
Any amount of rainfall
It's going to result in some kind of
And then unfortunately of course we know what happened we had
Rainfall intensities that were 10 been seen in hundreds
In this landscape flood is essentially the second stage of Fire
Rain came rushing down the hills into the town
As it flowed
The water carry mud
Trees and rocks off the steep hills
Even season rescue teams are shocked by the magnitude of the destruction we don't say this I mean it is complete
Devastation
I'm multiple multiple homes
That are completely destroyed
Boulders the size of small houses
Voted down several dense rivers of mud
More than 15 ft deep
Some of the debris flows reach speeds of close to 30 miles per hour
Boulder smashed into one house so violently that the gas man exploded
Unwhole residential blocks
They weren't houses to dig out under the mud
The houses were simply gone
Some homes were wiped off their foundations and vanished
Others turn into piles of wood in
And steel
My dad was fine but many of his neighbors were not
More than 400 homes were damaged or destroyed
About a tenth of the whole town
Hundreds of people had to be rescued by helicopter
23 were killed
2 or never found
Steve Mills and his family were lucky
By some measures
A few of their neighbors in their low-lying part of montecito's Flatlands ended up with Boulders in their bedroom
The Mills house is currently uninhabitable
And they're living in a rental while they make repairs to the property
They had 65 truckloads of mud and debris removed from their yard
Before they could even begin removing the mud and debris from under their home
Some of the people whose homes were destroyed have moved away and Steve's wife
Would like to do that too
She saw this
Mud
Damn and it was frightening and I
That sort of that leaves you marked your mind just learned a great sushi
Really doesn't want to live here
But for now they're in a protracted battle with their insurance company and they can't fix their house until that's resolved
So they have to say
Debris flows are technically floods but since they're caused by fire
California law mandates that they're covered by fire insurance
Which everyone in Montecito has
The financial infrastructure that takes over when physical infrastructure fail
More than government
It's insurance companies that seem to make the decisions about where and how
People can live in California
Insurance companies complain that their subsidizing for risky decisions
But for the most part
They don't stop and train people
They just increase prices
In California and even more
Exclusive
The place to live for everyone
The housing market is cold
Somewhat
Montecito is a whole remains desirable
If anything the value of every property that wasn't destroyed by fire or flood in the last year
I've only gone up
With the Chaparral bird out of the hills the whole wrist
Paradigm in Montecito has changed
As have the engineering challenges
Threat of fire is another 20 years off
The immediate concern now is when the next rain might come and bury the town in mud again
I mean to have that amount of intensity that follows up a fire that have
Select off the hillside you know that that's not going to happen very often does it doesn't mean it's not going to happen again
Of course not
More debris flows are inevitable in Montecito
They're how the whole area was formed hundreds of thousands of years ago
They're what carved those lovely canyons and created those pic
Tres creeks
Homeowners here have been landscaping around the boulders in their yards for decades without realizing how they got
Got there and what they meant
Now geologist are studying the area with new urgency
They found huge Earth shifting debris flows as old as 125000 years
And as young as a thousand years
This wasn't the first time a debris flow had flooded Montecito with a wall of mud and rocks
It's a regular repeating cycle
It's somehow everyone still manages to forget
In our area
We are very used to how to deal with
People know how to deal with
But it lulls them into a certain amount of
Complacency in it
How to deal with other emergencies
Dustin Williams is the elected County Supervisor who represents Montecito
As an unincorporated community
Montecito doesn't have its own political decision-making by
And it likes it that way
The town is voted on in corporation before and it's never passed
There's a classic California libertarian streak here
Which values private property rights alongside tight local community control and C
Support
So far
Santa Barbara County has made it pretty easy for the residents of Montecito to rebuild
They've developed a streamline review process and are mostly letting homeowners rebuild as they choose
Does Williams is just hoping they'll choose well
Moments like this
Do provide an opportunity for
Are people too
Soul searching, maybe it's
Better
If I either see if I can
Build outside of that
Envelope
Which is why we have
Provided more flexibility on rebuilding
Or make the individual decision to not read
I know everyone has to build with two threats in mind
Fire & Flood
You can clear brush from yards install fire-resistant
Exciting build concrete roofs in
Even by systems that will shoot flame retardant goo all over your house
You can close the crawl spaces above your foundation and lift your house up on pilings
But you can't make a home in pervious to a boulder smashing into it at 30 miles an hour
American Institute of Architects is Wayne in with design recommendation
Pants and FEMA updated its flood risk maps from 2012 to better account for the hazards that follow a fire
The best accounting can do
Is require people to rebuild Within These new guideline
Which golfer houses in the newly-expanded floodplain to be raised up
On elevated foundations or pilings
We made the decision
We're not going to tell people that they can't rebuild
As long as they comply with
FEMA recovery maps in the elevations
Map
But
That does not mean that rebuilding is a good idea and I'll
Gus Williams would actually like to see certain flood-prone neighborhoods
Stay empty
For the greater good
Annies considering Boulder steps local government could take
Eminent domain would empower the county to take people's homes and land in service of Public Safety
If the county could come up with the money
Well the majority of land out there
And this is a bit constrained on our ability
Improve the situation
Is in private hands
And it's in private hands with pretty high
Property
Which makes it very hard for government
Acquire land
Massively
Changed it
Equation
A single lot of land in Montecito can cause more than $1000000
And Das Williams would like to buy a lot of it
With the help of local philanthropy
Parcels near creeks would be kept vacant as Memorial Park land
And would act as a buffer
Creating more space between future debris flows and home
There are other bigger infrastructure projects that the government could try
They just aren't available to individual homeowners
Metal Nets could be installed on hillsides before a large storms
Dacatch chunks of the mountain before they reached
The town
And the 11 existing debris basins in the mountains
What's your kind of like dams designed to catch large rocks and trees flooding down the hill
To be expanded and modernized
Das Williams is working to raise money for those new bigger basin
The same people who don't like the look of firebreak
Seemed unlikely to embrace Stark concrete dams and oversized
Steel Nutz morning there beautiful Hillside
Venus williams has his way
They may no longer have a choice
My dad wasn't affected by the January floods
But his house sits right in the middle of historic debris flow
There's a creek at the bottom of his steep driveway and The Tell-Tale Boulders line has neighbors yards
I showed him the FEMA map that puts him in the red zone
He hasn't seen it yet
It bothers me to look at this map and see if the
Red area pointing into a creek
But for my dad the map appears to exist separate from his look reality
So far the house is made it through every disaster but one
By his account
Those are pretty good
Any other evidence
It's just isn't persuasive
It needs to burn down
Twice for me to get a
A sense of how often it burns down I mean
Turning down once I don't have enough data points
My dad's math themes
Dubious
But part of his personal threat appraisal seems to be an assumption that disaster build character
My dad likes to say he has a healthy relationship with the stuff he owns
Because he's experienced losing it all before
Plus he says
With climate change
Isn't every place
Disaster-prone
Why not at least stick with the horror he knows
It's app
Play Sia
Love
Comforting and familiar and and
You know I could move
Somewhere else in California and have an earthquake
Move somewhere else and have a
A hurricane take out all of all of middle of Florida I could move
TCU student death
Floods destroy the whole city did move to New Orleans have floods destroy the whole city
You know every place has their issue I've got the issue of a house that burns down once
Every 57 years
It's true that anywhere you go there are risks
Even halfway around the world we have a story about how Coastal communities in Japan Warren future Generations
About the risk of tsunamis
After that
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
But it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God.
Has Daryl Cagle noted at the end of that story there are risks associated with living anywhere
But there are places like Montecito where there is a persistent threat
It is important not
Colette the memory of
Disasters
Fade away so much that
People make poor choices in the present
Triclosan is here to talk about how people in Japan sent warning
Future Generations
About the dangers of tsunamis
There's this
Huge Old Stone
Sitting on a hillside blue honey Oshi Japan
And there's a warning card
Intuit which locals credit with repeatedly saving their clothes
Translated it reads
Do not build any homes below this point
High dwellings are the peace
In harmony of our descendants
Remember the Calamity of the great tsunami
So what happened that made
Their ancestor
Decide they need to put up
Well it started way back in the 1890s
Earthquake off the coast
Followed by a pair of really devastating tsunamis
Huge wave throws up over a hundred
And destroyed thousands of coastal homes
In the aftermath
Locals in on EOS Rebel
Then they got hit again in the 1930s
So that point they decided we got to move to town uphill
And they left behind this morning
So when big tsunami struck in 1960 and then again in 2011 the village set
Safely above the high-water mark
Assassin Amazing Story
Right there hundreds of these along the coast
Some of which date back over 500 years
Lincoln me really big 2
Summer is tallest 10 ft
Are they all really telling you where or we're not
The Builder they all like
About zoning regulations
Well not all of them some of them are more like memorials to pass disasters
Victims
Others just off of these blanket warnings to head for Higher Ground during earthquake
Escape the waves
And their cases to of towns ignoring worth
Specific warnings
The shore
Been facing serious destruction in a later tsunami
So do people still pay attention to these stones are they base
Historical map
As a prank
Good morning they're pretty outdated
You still in still get put up sometimes but more is Memorials than
Warnings
These days Japan has a lot of high-tech warning system
Really well marked evacuation
They also engineer better houses and put up seawalls protect
Oh as we saw in 2011
Those aren't always enough
So if you want to see pictures of these hunting
Evocative tsunami stones
You can visit our website
IPI
Thanks
When I say always
Like
99percentinvisible was Bruce this week by Susie Cagle and our senior editor Delaney Hall
Mix into production by Sharif
Music by genre
Katie mingle is our senior prom
Kurt Kolstad is the digital
Beretta team is Avery Chapman
Joe Rosenberg
Ella Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Terry Meza and me Roman Mars
Thanks to Tom College
For research assistant
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Produced on radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
The fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of pocket
Fun Mall
Radiotopia
FM
You by the show in joints questions about the show on Facebook you can't we do me at Roman Mars and the show at 9 p.m.
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
This week on the 9th
ATI website
An article about the great fire of 1910 that changed America's attitude toward firefighter
And the thousands of fire lookout tower
Powers that were built
Across the Nation in its way
Find that are
Only
And I and I
IPI
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com