99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
You're walking in San Francisco
You might not know when you're Crossing from the Western addition neighborhood
In the Hayes Valley
Or if you're in Portola
4 Excelsior
But you could be aimlessly wandering around any Western city of significant size including San Francisco or
Oakland
And you'll know exactly when you're in Chinatown
Those visual cues may be simple to pick up on but it turns out
The origin stories of Chinatown and the architecture and food that come from it
Are far more complex and interesting than you can imagine
We did a couple stories on this a few years ago and we compiled them together into this episode
I hope you like it
Stepped off a plane from Hong Kong and into the San Francisco International Airport
It was his first time on American soil
At 22 years old he had left his homeland of China and traveled across the ocean to build a new life for himself
Self and his young wife
In this land of opportunity
When immigrants first come to the US Census
And this is such an all troponin old stories that you expect
Yeah the streets are paved with gold
This is Bonnie toy
Jorge's daughter
She's also the author of a book about American chinatown's
Even today I changed
San Francisco gold Mountain
This is why you find your fortune in Sims
George toys very first stop in San Francisco he's very first stop in America
Like generation upon generation of Chinese immigrants beforehand
What's San Francisco's Chinatown
And he was not impressed
Two Georges San Francisco Chinatown
Fell out of date
All the things he saw in Chinatown these Pagoda roofs these Dragon Gates these flourishes that
United a signal China and Chinese notice there were things that he actually end scene in
Back in China Fair
Years and years and years and they were not used in that
Architectural vernacular back there and sell
He wondered how Chinatown in this
In a release supposedly modern America was
Why did it
Feel older than oldest parts of Hong Kong work
Looking grown up
Because it was designed that way
That's producer Chelsea Davis
For George soy and many other Chinese immigrants
San Francisco's Chinatown
And the chinatowns in alot of American cities
They don't look much like the China they know
Looks like a bit of a movie citic
It's a lot of contacts to anything else
Next to it on either side
That's filmmaker Felicia Lowe
She made a documentary about San Fran
Walking around Chinatown together
Past Bank of America ATMs guarded by gold dragon
Shops with neon lit names
Like Hart of Shanghai
Selling paper fans and plastic Buddha
And towering four-story bazaars
Crowned
With little to gota
But Chinatown hasn't always look
In fact before the massive earthquake that leveled San Francisco in 1906
Chinatown look like most of the other neighborhoods in San Francisco
Rosa brick homes
Done up with Victorian italianate facade
The only thing you recognizes Chinatown
Are the people in it
And
Chinese signs
American
Signs
Phil Choi a retired architect and historian of chinese-american
Culture
He grew up in San Francisco
And still live there
He says it's not like Chinese immigrants in SF had strong opinions either way
About their neighborhood
Victorian flourishes
Columns for porches
They just
Didn't have much Choice when it came to where they live
After arriving in America they moved into the old homes that white people had abandoned
And after that basically the Chinese
Didn't have
Time
Greeley
Pay attention to
The architecture
All creating
Chinese
Architect
The basic desire was to make a living
And making a living
Was easier said than done
If you were Chinese in early
Early 20th century
Since the 18th 6
Chinese immigrants
I've been a convenient
For Nationwide jobs
The result was Federal legislation like the 1882
Chinese Exclusion Act
Which bar the vast majority of
Chinese people from entering the states
And made it impossible for
The Chinese already in the US
Become new America
Can citizens
In San Francisco racist housing policies made it almost impossible
More people of Chinese Heritage to live outside of China
And when they did set foot out
Outside the 15 square blocks
So the Chinese Enclave
It was at the risk of physical violence
So the self-contained world of Chinatown
Served as a desperately needed Refuge
Or Chinese
But a 1906
That Refuge would be eviscerate
Buy a double whammy
What is that
Early in the morning of April 18th of that year San franciscans woke up to a seven point
892 North
Like it was the biggest quake in the cities recorded history still is but those violent Tremors were
We're just the beginning because the earthquake shattered the cities gas means
And the gas that we doubt somewhere it connected with a spark
The massive fires that resulted lasted for three days and destroyed about 500 city blocks
Chinatown was one of the first neighborhoods to go up in smoke
Neighborhood and without it
Give me something very dangerous
Situation
Andrea Davies is a historian at the Stanford Humanities Center
But before her career in Academia
She was in a slightly different line of work
I was a San Francisco firefighter for about 5 years
And so my first
Assignment was Chinatown fighting fires in that neighborhood later LED Davies to write a Social history of the ninth
She says that in the wake of the disaster newspapers pedal this feel goodies story but the SF
Earthquake and fire were social equalizers
That the shared experience of suffering United San franciscans of all colors and creeds
Man helping man and so on but while white man may have helped white man no one was out
On the Chinese
The racism against them only intensified
I call it hiding post-disaster
You could see this height and racism happening on at least
Two levels
First
With individual white Saint Francis
The built environment
Everyone in their place
And that's what gets erased
On April 18th
So
If you're an elite white Saint Francis
You don't have
The resident
Chinatown unless you go there
As
The Chinese are leaving their homes in desperation
They're being yelled at to get
And don't turn back
And according to Davies it wasn't just
Private citizens who are guilty of that heightened racism
Because the second place that the fire spur to flare up and racism
Wasn't how the recovery efforts were managed
The Firebird
Department
Did very little
In Chinatown
In effect
Underwater Manta
Until there
It's not wide enough
Is if you look
Cat Chinatown
Just Nestle right again
That's not pill
We're all the elite mansion
All the water goes
Advance America
To save Nob Hill
And all the dynamite
Goes into tray
At the time Fire Department
Would Dynamite buildings to keep
Spreading
But the fire department use the wrong kind of dynamite
In Chinatown burned all the faster
In the following days as the Embers of Chinatown cool
The Chinese found themselves
Homeless
A new Leaf vulnerable and hostile
The things
We're about to get worse
So many of the sea
Cities political and business
Slater's
Or actually excited about
Social equalizing disaster
Because of the Limited in Chinatown
Will never rebuild it
Before the quake
Many whites
Tina Chinese neighborhood
At the Camorra of opium dens process
Pollution and disease
In 1885
City Hall had prepared a municipal report
On Chinatown
And in that report
Page yourself
Of documentation
Listing all the houses of
Prostitution
And the number of gambling houses
And opium dens
Throughout China Town
This reputation for Vice
Had actually created a minor industry of Slum tourism
In China
Thrill-seeking white people
Could hire a guide to lead them through scenes of alleged depravity
It would be taken through dimly-lit building
Then shown opium smokers
Send prostitute
Gambling
Evidence suggests that some of these scenes may have actually been staged by the guys
That's themselves
And one thing that was
Definitely
Was a widespread rumor
At San Francisco's Chinese resume
Lived in underground tunnels
This is what they really peeling
That the Chinese live
Underground
And
Even today
People wants
Seeds
Chinatown
Underground
On top of all this
Chinatown was right in the middle of choice
Downtown
Real estate
The San Franciscan Elites
Had long wanted for white biz
In fact
2 years before the fire
Then-mayor James Phelan
A tired in Ark
Dr sketches
It's brand new.
The architect they hired
You may have heard of
Daniel Burnham
And in his plan there is
Burnham was a proponent of the city beautiful moon
In urban planning philosophy popular in the late 19th and early 20th century
And this idea of City beautiful
Racialized
This View
And the idea is
A more beautiful Urban environment
Crates
Citizen
We want a beautiful city of well-educated
Citizens
Everyone is
White and productive
And with China Town burned to the ground
City leaders seize the chance
Make that white dream or real
Within a week of the fire
City Hall created a committee dedicated solely to relocating China
The group included former mayor James Phelan
The one you would hired Burnham
To drive those revised draft
San Francisco
And so the minute
The city Goes Up in Flames
I'm not kidding I don't know
Is finished burning
And James feeling is
Telegrafi
Canterbury
Send more reports
Immediately get them at the hands of the city leaders and
Business Leaders
Here's our plan we can rebuild
Here's the proof
The plan for that
Perfect City
Who did the Chinese all the way to Hunters Point
A region on the edge of town
It's where the city slaughterhouses were
But it wasn't long before the Chinese residents found out about the
And I think they fought back very
Intelligently
They got china's Empress Dowager so she involve
She sent her consul-general from Washington to meet with San Francisco official
But the coup de gras
Was Financial
Four-decade
San Francisco had been a key hub for trade with China
So a group of the city's top Chinese business owners wrote to the current mayor in a line
Which San Francisco officials could easily understand
And so the on the business level of the negotiation was
Okay you don't want to
Come back we're not going down
WinCo Tacoma
We go to Portland
What is a panic of a loss
And that was a loss that city leaders couldn't take
Less than a month after the quake
The mayor dissolved
Committee to relocate
For Chinese Americans at this time
This was an unprecedented
Political victory
But they didn't stop there
The fire had left Chinatown a blank
And for the first time
The Chinese
For holding the
They were sick of Chinatown getting this bad rap for Vice
Sick of City Hall harassing them sick of visitor asking them if they lived in tunnels
Makeover for their neighborhood
And an American Born Chinese businessman named looked in Eli just how to go about it
The word was build me a pagoda
That's Felicia low again
She says that look Tennille I figured
Hey if porous are always going to come to China Town seeking a taste of some imaginary East
Let's give them what they want and so he was able to
Higher White architects
To create a Chinatown that looked the way
White people imagine Chinatown to look
Even though he knew
In his own mind that
The buildings in China didn't all look like this
Now looks plan might seem a bit counterintuitive
For decades
The Chinese of San Francisco had been harassed
That's precisely
Cuz they look and dress differently from mainstream White America
And he was the guy saying
Let's rebuild our neighborhood in a way that emphasizes our foreign debt
The cars are different from the rest of the city into the very face of our buildings
The Bonnie song
Whose father had been flummoxed by the look of Chinatown when he arrived in Sanford
Francisco
She says that the Chinese community of 1907
Saw a positive side
To that foreign this
And they also were pretty Savvy with the fact that people were interested
And they were interested in this exotic
Element
And if I could
Bill that in a way that was
Attractive
Instead of repellent
But that would be
Protective
For them
Look hired an architect named T Patterson Ross
And an engineer named aw Burger
These two men
Had never been to China
At the time The Architects
Where.
Trinidad
Traditional anything about
Oriental art
Because
Also at the time
The Orion was considered
Way behind the West
So
Culturally everything
Was looked down upon
Pain that's it
It's nothing to study about
Rothenburg runs knowledge of China was limited to a few images they've seen of ancient palaces
From the Song Dynasty
An architectural style that was already hundreds of years old by the early 20th century
But that didn't stop Ross and bergren from using their imagination
And how they use their imagination
They created
The sort of a Disneyland effect
Brinson's the sing cheong building was topped with a small structure that sort of look like a pagoda
Batchoy says that in China you typically wouldn't see a pagoda on top of another building
Pagodas there are free-standing structures
Not a decorative flourish
And secondly
In China dishware
Monuments for religious purposes of the religion of Buddhism
Here and it's San Franciscan for him the Pagoda instead houses in Monument to consumerism
Sing cheong became a bustling department store Hocking Asian art
Which it still is
To this day
But nonetheless the designers that looked in Eli hired created a striking building and other merchants
Rebuilding in Chinatown couldn't help but notice
Soon sing Chong's bombastic
Chinoiserie look happy Conde style for most new structures going up in Chinatown
The Architects were trying to reproduce Beijing in San Francisco
Tell me about a lot of the details wrong Taurus
They were wrong in all the right ways
Taurus love the new Chinatown
This was exactly the Westerner friendly version of China they wanted
Vaguely exotic
But safe enough for middle class white
Visitors began to flow into China.
And so did their cash
Antenna towns Pleasant new appearance was beginning to change
Popular sentiment
What's the Chinese people
American newspapers made it
Explicit that the neighborhood makeover was causing them to rethink their contempt
For the Chinese
And one newspaper the bulletin put it in 1909
Quote
Chinatown is one of the most noted places on the American colonies
We have held up to the public gaze
For too long
The racial grief
What separates the yellow and white people
The Earth and quote
Looked in Eli's
Plan had worked in Chinese communities elsewhere in the US were taking note all of the
Successive China towns that have Cam
In America
Take a cue from the take a page from this Playbook New York San Francisco LA Honolulu
They all sort of San Francisco again
She says visual style and tourist-friendly attitude that San Francisco's Chinatown had perfected
Soon began to spread was so successful
Still influencing chinatown's being built in our own time for instance take the Chinatown in Las Vegas which was
Created in the 90s
It also had the same
Pagoda roof lines and Dragon Gate like the same
Language sexual language
Same architectural vernacular was being used
To create
The newest Chinatown that was used to create the oldest Chinatown you know you outsmarted the devil
Basically there is a phrase you know that they called white people
Walkway which is the white
Devil
I think that it wasn't fixed
3 absolutely of course this architectural Revenge
Didn't instantly fix everything for the Chinese in San Francisco
They still faced plenty of legal and popular discrimination
For example they were still required by real estate laws
What's to live in China
And on a federal level the Chinese Exclusion Act
South wouldn't even be repealed until 1940
3 more than 30 years later
And even if they're rebranding
Chinatown help
To ease negative sentiment towards the
The Chinese
Philips Hue believes it may also have helped
Promote certain stereotypes
It continues
Super Bowl
Al forniss
And my I remember my daughter coming home
One day very annoyed
And
Upset is it
People look look look it's like they never seen a Chinese person before
By contrast look at the other traditionally ethnic neighborhoods in San Francisco Japantown or theater
Italian neighborhood of North Beach
Choices those neighborhoods
Start the Chinatown dead
Not embellish and embrace the ethnicity
Other immigrant groups at that time didn't face the same antagonism that the Chinese did
So only the Chinese were forced to cater to white people's fantasies
As a survival knife
That's the irony at that time
We have to promote our furnace to be accepted but even if chinatown's architecture
Is a somewhat inauthentic representation of the real thing
B'Elanna Torres don't realize
The fact that real people live there and that it is a place actually that is for poor
People you know I mean it is at its
Essence a place where people come to live when they first get here because they can't
Because they need the services that are provided there
Funny soy says this is true of all the Chinatown she studied they're all portals of entry for
New immigrants of
Particular class in a working-class immigrants
Don't speak English
In fact thanks to factors like rent control zoning restrictions and really active tenants rights group
Community
San Francisco's Chinatown has managed to remain a relatively affordable neighborhood for low-income immigrants
Ebony says yes Chinatown has been disneyfied and rebranded to cater to American tastes
Are there still an authentic
An important history
There's something about it that if you can serve read the skyline you can read the story
Story of
How this place came to be and also in that is Chinese
In that there's like there's is power in that
99percentinvisible West produces week by Chelsea Davis and Katie Mingle
Version of the story was originally broadcast in the public radio history program backstory
One of my favorite episodes and episode titles of all time
A sweet surprise awaits
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
This is still 99percentinvisible
And I'm still roaming Mars
It was the night of March 30th 2005 and the Powerball Jack
Crock-Pot with 25 million dollars
On TV the white ping pong balls rolled out one by one as the host announced the winning number
39 Powerball is
That's pretty sir Avery truffle
There's a winner in Tennessee
But the way the Powerball drawings work there usually some second-place winners
Guess all of the numbers
Except for the very last one
On average there are three or four of these players
But on March 30th 2005 there were 110 second-place winners
Was there a computer glitch
Number
Has someone compromised
This is journalist
Jennifer 8 Lee
Lottery officials are planning
Like something
So the next day as the winners around the United States came to collect
The Powerball officials
So where'd you get your number from
And each of them have the same answer
They'd gotten their numbers
From
Fortune cookie
They were different cookies in different states
But they all had the same fortune
And the same lucky numbers
Very
Lucky numbers
And so just remember
Made you realize like how
March 14th
Use in Chinese
Fast food
Become an American
Chinese food along with pizza and the Frankfurter has been adopted and modified to become
American Cuisine
Rooted in some good old-fashioned American xenophobia
The early waves of Chinese immigration in the 1850s
The new Chinese population work mostly As Miners and farmers and laborers
Can Americans as ever
We're concerned about these new immigrants
Taking away jobs
And it was actually only after huge
That the Chinese actually moved in
Can you feel
When was laundry again
Restaurants with Easter cleaning
Unless they were
No longer
And as their livelihoods depended on it
Chinese restaurant owners made up dishes to cater to American tastes
American face Eagle Lake
Things that are sweet and they're fried in
And that's how dishes like Chop Suey were invented
Chop Suey the name actually means assorted
Pieces
Like odds and ends
Chop Suey the biggest culinary joke that one
Chop Suey is not real Chinese
At all
It's as American as apple pie
And speaking of apple pie
Americans want to start because
We are America and we like
Antibody
Do you need a dessert and is Chinese desserts go there aren't that many options that the American pallet wood go for
The Chinese desserts like
There is a Mooncake
Which like taste and looks like a hawk
Tupac
There's there's not there's not a lot of stuff
And so around the 1920s the fortune cookie somehow enters the American Chinese restaurant culture
Where they came from originally is a bit of a mystery
But we'll get there
First let's make this
Perfectly clear
The cookies
These are not
From China I don't know why the Chinese
They don't need a fishing pole
Steven Yang is founder of Yang's fortunes Incorporated
In San Francisco
Chinese people in China don't eat
But Americans consume billions of
Which means great business for Steven
Because he prints a lot of the paper fortunes that go inside fortune cookie
If you go to any way I would have new york-boston shoes
Is there any way you can
I see my voice
Including all the fortunes for Panda Express
That's definitely Stevens biggest client
Stevens tiny Warehouse
In San Francisco's Dogpatch
Is filled with boxes
All stuff
Full of tiny strips
Fortune
Each box
Contains 300000
Paper fortune
Alpena Lotto
IPL live
See
And Stephen Prince all these boxes and boxes with only five other employees
And Lisa
Stevens daughter
Writes all the fortune
When I visited she was away on maternity leave
But she is written most of the companies 5000 unique Fortune
This is amazing because we think about it fortunes are deceptively difficult to write
The messages have to be really really generic because they could be for anyone
You can't write messages like you will meet a tall dark stranger because an eight-year-old could read that and be like
That
Why would we
And fortunes also have to be careful not to offend
Famously there was once a fortune that said lighten up and a lot of customers were like
Is this cookie calling me fat reduction
Americans like their Fortune
Sunny
So Fortune send of evade or just generally uplifting like tomorrow will be better or the fortunes
Arnab from quotation books
Just whatever Lisa can find
Stephen doesn't really care he doesn't breathe
I don't know why the American people didn't like it
They say they would do when they got a 14
After eating dinner with keeping the water
The keeper
Yeah that's true
Some people do keep the fortunes in their wallets
When I asked around it turns out a few of my friends do this or can recite their favorite fortunes from memory and it's crazy be
Because a lot of these fortunes are Stevens
Written by his daughter
Lisa
But there are a few ways to tell where your fortunes come from
If you get one with blue corners on it that was printed by a giant company in New York called wonton food
They make over 4 million cookies a day and we're responsible for the cookie that made all those Powerball
Winners in 2005
If your fortune has smiley faces on it
It was probably printed by a Chinese company
For the American Market
Of course
And if the fortune doesn't have blue corners or smiley faces chances are it was one of the many thousands that Steven
In all different colors and fonts
And sends the factories all over the country
Including the Golden Gate Fortune Cookie Company
Tiny Alleyway in San Francisco's Chinatown
The Golden Gate fortune cookie
Company is
Pretty tourist
The charges visitors 50 Cent a photo and doesn't actually have a very big cookie
Actually calling this place a factory is kind of an overstatement
It's just one narrow room
With most of the space taken up by three whole King fortune cookie
Versions of machines that were invented
By Edward Lewis
My father used to call his machine like
This fourth child
He had three sons and in the fourth was his
The baby one of Edward's Three Sons
Met me at the Golden Gate Fortune
Company news fortune cookie machines are pretty simple
Fix bottom round ABS about Iran
Conveyor belt
In a worker sits next to this belt and fold the hot cookies around the paper fortune
One by one
My hand
And
We pick them up as you see them doing here
Fold it and put them on a conveyor named learned how to fold the cookies when he was around eight years old
Aloha family used to have a fortune cookie company of Their Own
It was a whole life
Even during dinner
Wechat
Somebody eats
The other one work
That's how we did it
We used to call ourselves the prisoner
That was a famous saying
Help I'm a prisoner in this
Fortune cookie
Ming's father later developed the next generation of Fortune Cookie Machine
Fully automated version
Which also.
And because of this technology
Fortune cookies are widely available
A cheap enough that restaurants can give them out for
Free
No one in the Lewis family really question where the cookies originated
But it was a mystery that other people trying to solve
People like Sally Osaka
She knew they were not
Invented in China
What do you mean the Chinese fortune
Japanese
Sally osaki is
California born and raised
But her parents came from Japan in the early 1900s but I was a child
Fortunes
Used to be in Japanese
Rather than the Chinese character
And the cookies weren't something you get at the end of a meal at a restaurant
They coming back you know it and
Mostly I know who we got them when I was a child
Was we would go see Japanese movies
Sew-in Sally's California childhood but cookies were a casual snack
But if you chase them all the way back to their origins in Japan
You actually find them at a shrine
There you will be able to find
Is Japanese Bakers on grilling fortune cookie
Jennifer flute taisha Shrine in Kyoto specifically to try them
They're not like the fortune cookies we see in the United States
Bigger and Browner
And they're actually kind of like nutty Savory flavor
Cracker like but still there that same iconic fortune cookie shape we all know
There's actually an old Japanese image of a baker Folding It crackers and it dates back to 1878
Decade
It's before the first reports of American fortune cookies that I spoke to
Thought that
Fortune cookies
Designed to
Like a bell
In part because of
Bealls
All along
But then why don't we eat it after
Cuz I people are not eating soup
Xi'an
When Japanese immigrants were opening businesses in the 1920s there was no market for Japanese food
Again like a Chinese m
Before then
They Pander to American taste
Japanese
Families
Ran a lot of Chinese restaurant
And these Japanese families ran American Chinese restaurant
Full of Chop Suey and other Pho Chinese cuisine
Annie's Japanese owners with
Bro in a fortune cookie
For dessert
When Sally was a kid fortune cookies were still made in Japanese Bakery
Grace in both LA and San Francisco
And the fortunes were still in Japanese
And then something happened that completely disrupted
Everything about Japanese American Life in this country
And I don't know if you know that
The Japanese-Americans hundred
20000 /
During World War II
Sent away
I was nine years old when we got sent to
To the concentration camp
Sally and her family were farmers
In Fresno
They were summoned to a train station
And sent off to a camp
In Arizona
You had to carry whatever your day
That was a child
Enjoy that much
Pictures of small suitcase
And I remember my mother
Give me
Store
Account
Cuz she heard that
But we are going in error
Desert in Arizona
Are rattlesnakes and scorpions
Whatever yeah oh yeah gila monsters and scorpions and
Rattlesnakes Young
In the camp her parents were given jobs at her and hardly any money
Salary was
$16 or $18
For 4 years
From 1942
California's Japanese and Japanese-American community
He was marooned in the desert
Out of sight
Add communication
Out of
Including a lot of Japanese Bakers & Japanese restaurant
My recollection was that
After we came out of the camps
It was a Chinese fortune cookie
The Chinese actually
Commercialized it
And
Did all the Chinese restaurants that are deserve it
Thanks to Chinese business owners
And later
Edward Louie Fortune Cookie Machine
The Chinese American fortune cookie
As we now know it
Flourished
It's nearly impossible to pan the Americanization of the cookie to one specific Japanese-American Bay
Baker or Chinese American Restaurant
The transfer from Japanese cracker to American Chinese cookie was a larger phenomenon that occurred
Or less
Across California
And then swept the rest of the United States
And then the world
Except for China
They still don't eat for two
Part 2 of 99% invisible was produced by Avery trufelman this story was largely inspired by Jennifer Haley's book
Fortune cookie Chronicles which goes in the even more depth about the origin of American Chinese cuisine
Believe me throw away deeper depths to explore
Really fun read
Check it out
The great lullatone provided all the music in the store
Most of the 99 bi crew is on vacation or on light duty this week
Who's a good time to send them a note and tell them that they're great
We are caving in
Port Costa
Delaney Hall
Average
Emmett Fitzgerald to refuse of xian real
We are brothers 91.7 kalw
Yuan San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
90% invisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX independent Collective
YouTube shows in all a podcast
Aeon Mall
At radiotopia
Tok FM
Can you find the show in discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at
Roman Mars in the show at 99p or run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But did you know that we have a website and great and has all kind of interesting design stories on it
Well now you do
It's a 99 p i
Radio temperature
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com