99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It can hardly be
No language on Earth
Ever pretty
An apple
Ugly
Something very ugly
Some attain a degree of ugly
I can only be the result
Effort
Avena San Jose Airport
People who are
Tired
Lucky China
Landed in Vermont
Milan airport is the only
Of this otherwise infallible rule
Anoka Tech
Text have on the whole tribe
Designs
From Douglas Adams The Long Dark tea-time of the Soul
I think so many airports
We're not designed for the
And so
It is all fixing as you go there if there wasn't some great mask
So when it comes to the ugliness in general dysfunction of airports are a little bit off.
Improvement
An area of about the design of air
Airport she said to me
If all airports simply play Brian Eno's album music for airports over the speakers
Every airport would be better
My name is Alison Arias
And I read about design and
Annabelle
The New York Times
I say this to serve not only as an introduction to Allison area but also so that you'll know that she is someone
Who is Judgement
Is perfectly true
Antarctic Iceberg to said nothing is
More quickly obsolete than an airport built
Technology
Changing so fast
Anything at all airports are still trying to catch up to now the thing that forced airports to change the most
The fastest
Was 9/11
Security screen has come to dominate all aspects of airport design
We're going to focus on just too fat
The verses that because the unpredictability and time required to go through security you no longer dawdle on what is called the land
And side of the airport landside is basically a curb appeal part of the airport parking in store
Ticketing area so considered landside the wonderful lines that you have to wait in TSA
Play what you're also changing by the way most airports of course have had to make room for those lines so all of that in landside
So when do you want yourself to the pleasant experience that is security you are on the airside but people responsible for Bill
Airports
Really kind of followed the bus station model
Where
It was like a holding pen
We just got you here as long as we put you on Amtrak or put you on Greyhound and airports were so tough on that model T because he asked
Assumption was you were just passing through
Now the assumption is that you are absolutely not just passing through the assumption is that you were going to be staying
A while
So newer airports are designed with that in mind
And a good example of this new thinking described in a recent New York Times article by area
Is the new T2 terminal design by Gensler Architects at Sanford
Cusco International airport
T2 is the new
Terminal 5
American Airlines
And Virgin America
At Sanford
Beijing International Airport
And it's one of the
The first
Terminal
To be designed
The last terminal constructed the 42 at SFO
Was the international terminal that opened in December of two
It still feels pretty new
But you can tell right away
The trajectory of airport is on was going in a very different direction in the year 2000
Then what is prioritize today San Francisco International Terminal for example
Is all about
Ticketing area you walking answers
Massive
Amount of space it's open and Airy and actually pretty wonderful to experience but
In the new world of TSA
All that building doesn't make any sense
If you actually
Think about it you realize that
All the exciting stuff is on the land side
Eating your shopping apps that are all that
In the new T2 all the good stuff is saved
Security because as we all know everyone should
Russian today
I'm going to want to leave her at all
So while there is a very generous
Ticketing area
Did you giving way more
1000 mm
Coming to the gate
What's also different about T2 is that they're really incorporating the security procedures in the design from the get-go
When you look at security Now it often looks like the TSA
Just set up shop yesterday
With retractable barriers and then it spits you out to a couple of folding chairs
To put on your shoes in
Stole your laptop
The new T2 actually has what they call a recompose own which is
Like a lounge for putting your clothes back on after you get through TSA with
Sculpture in
Lots of natural light in sky lights
And once you are at that spot putting your shoes in your bowel phone
Jewelry my Roth back on
You can see everything that you're about
Retail
Seton Hall
I've never given much thought to shops or restaurants in airports but the thing I need not want
I need when I travel is a place to plug in my phone
Or laptop
And probably both
There are many many more Banks about let's cuz again you think even back to
Pre 9-11 which is now
About 10 years ago
Ubiquity of person
The walkmen
Great path music
At every age every soda
Traveling segmen
Worse
Airports.
I was in O'Hare recently
Sitting on the floor next to this businessman
We were huddled like hobos around
Single outlet in this 3 gate area
According to area human factors study shows that passengers want to stay within 250 feet of their gay
Gate and T2 at SFO addresses this anxiety
If your
Find a paper
Traveller coffee sitting down the restaurant
All the gates are visible all the time because of the open floor plan
What I heard a lot and talking to many many arcs
Express Airport
The top of the list
Letting people feel like
Hello there experience
I'm having a son
Where they're going and
Really should have designing so that all of the anxiety that comes naturally with that hoe
Process now is is alleviated
What is 6 * 10
So against of environments designer
Intuit where people's Hang-Ups are going to be
Keto Africa
Project
The noble goal is to try to design away all airport anxieties no matter how experienced The Traveler
Bruno's in 10 years I could be redoing the story and contrasting T2 against some new super Airport
That solves all the problems of usage that T2 failed to anticipate
No place to park my jetpack
Printing complex Perfect Design is a moving Target
But odds are your luggage will still be in murmansk
99percentinvisible was produced this week by me Roman Mars with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio and Santa
American Institute of Architects in Sanford
In the center for architecture and Design
You can keep up with Alison area for the opinionator blog the New York Times and I should mention that the Douglas Adams quote with the top
The show was right by Francesca Panetta who's the producer and creator
Of the Hackney podcast
Just consistently stunning and amazing and you should
Although it does have a dearth of Francesca
Voicemail
You probably heard more for here
What happened here on the acne podcast
Thank you friend
If I get all kinds of links go to the website is 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com