99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Most of the American West is owned by the federal government about 85% of Nevada
61% Alaska and 53% of Oregon
The list goes on and I've always been questions about how this immense swath of land should be used
Should we allow ranchers to graze cattle
What should the western land be a place where wild animals can roam free be protected
Or is it land we want to reserve for recreation as you can imagine there is no consensus on the answers to those
Questions but there are a lot of strong feelings
And over the years those strong feelings have sometimes bubbled up to the surface and manifested in protest
And even violence
In 2016 a group of armed militants occupied malheur National Wildlife Refuge in Western Oregon
They were led by a cattle rancher by the name of Ammon Bundy the son of Cliven Bundy
Perhaps you heard about it
Never really understood exactly what it was all about
Well today we bring you a story from long reads in Oregon public broadcasting reported by Leah sottile
And it's the first in the series they put together that looks deeply into the fascinating and even sometimes wonky details about
How the American West is managed
Why the Bundys are so angry about it
And the religious ideology that undergirds their fight against the federal government
It's amazing series that spins a good yarn but also resonates
So many aspects of current US politics
It's also about Land Management but she's really exciting for me personally
This is episode 1 of bundyville
Here's Leah sottile
By his own account Nevada rancher Cliven Bundy never wanted to start a war with
The federal government
He says that if they just left them alone out here in the desert
This would have ever started
If you want to see him as a folksy hero of a modern-day Western
You can choose to see him that way
Here's a good starting point
It's a random YouTube video
Inches a blonde haired little boy
Toddler
He's wearing a Dusty red Polo shirt
Blue jeans
Elaine stand in the dirt
Having just been knocked down
He's considering whether or not he wants to cry
Help you up
I hope I begs not broke his Cowboy hat-wearing Grandpa
Putter's away from Cowboys
Please come see how heavy is he got run over by horse and he's out there and going already
Nothing to it he says the toddler looks back at his grandpa
Points of the West
In the camera follows
Patch of bright green grass comes into view against the Nevada desert
The color of life
It stands out in place
For everything else look
Dead This Land is Our Land This land is a free land
This land is a place that we can enjoy
And you
That's Cliven Bundy as he'd like to be seen
Diesel farmer
Homesteading on a 260 acre ranch
Bunkerville Nevada
Just a few weeks after this video was shot
On the same piece of land
Cliven Bundy and his sons were anything but peaceful
Did raise the militia that was
Pointing guns at federal agents
What the Bundys called
Tyrannical government
Siri is onstage in Bunkerville
Whipping the crowd into a frenzy
Demanding that the local sheriff
Bulldoze the buildings nearby National Park
Does its surrounding Community might have free reign of the land
UK cronut
He says get the county equipment out there
What are those things down this morning
The sheriff Just Dance quietly on stage
He's got two stones hitch in his belt
The mob hackleton
He has more demands
The sheriff also have to disarm the Park Service Rangers
Bring me those guns in one hour he says
Where else
Luke Bryan Detroit
Depending on how you look at the way this is all played out
Cliven Bundy is either profit
Is leaving his people to Salvation
Percolator
Is lettuce follower straight to jail
Even death
How you see Cliven
Message just as much about you
Is it does about the Bundys
From longreads in Oregon Public Broadcasting
This is Bundy
7 part series about the Bundy family and how they're changing the American West
Leah sottile in a 2016 I set out to write a single breaking news story about the Bundy
But one story turned into several because every time I learn something new it would just bring it
More questions things that seems unbelievable would turn out to be real even when I wasn't
Writing I couldn't stop finding new pieces in this really complicated puzzle
Most people know roughly what happened in Nevada and Oregon if not this first episode
He's going to bring you up to speed and then we're going to dive into all the weird stuff that didn't make it on the Nightly News
Only come to light months and years after most people stopped paying attention
Because the Bundy story is bigger and Stranger than I expected
Forget about facts and laws more than anything else the story of The Bundys is about belief
Truth is figuring out which one of those things has more power if you
If you believe the Bundys then you believe the federal government is trying to enslave the American people
You believe the feds and you believe a remote cattle rancher is a domestic terrorist
So did the Bundys on the truth or is that the property of the US government
That's what I set out to find
Let's think for a second about all the things in history
I've started armed revolt against the government
Food shortages
Dictatorship
Widespread corruption
Where do reptiles fit on that list
For Cliven right at the top
Here's Aaron Wise
From the conservation advocacy group
The center for Western priorities
The whole reason that
Cliven Bundy has been
Breaking the law and running his cows illegally is because
His cows
Posed a danger to the desert tortoise it was an endangered species problem to begin with
Early 1990s
Populations of desert tortoise
Plummeting in the American southwest
The tortoises have been around for 15 to 20 million years
In the desert
But they compete with cattle for what little grass or is to eat out
In cattle usually win
In the 90s that land of the tortoise on the endangered
Species list
It's a common story in the West
Endangered species
Is threatened by ranching or logging or mining
Regulators and environmental is step in to preserve the animal
The group's go to court
And fight over this one Central Quest
Are the wide open spaces in the West
Meant to support rural communities
Or should they be kept for
Historically the people working the land have had to back off
Give up resources in old ways of life
Change with the times
Certain point the bunnies decided they just weren't going to change
They were done with Federal rules
We're in cattle here grazes natural resource office public land
And I abide by all of Nevada state law
But I don't recognize United States government
Even existing
The bunnies have been growing melons and raising cattle on their hundred and sixty-eight
And for decades
The family also paid the federal government for grazing permit so they can legally Ranch on the public land
That surrounds the property
Nevada ranchers the tortoise listing meant 3-4 months each year that they can
Greaser hair
The Cliven Bundy
In 1993 he started simply ignoring the ruling
Kept his cows on the land
You should know that the rates ranchers pay for grazing are like
$1 per cow each year
Ranchers by the permits because
Land is expensive
Majority of land in the West
Is actually federally owned
But Aaron Wise says that's one of the things that's Up For Debate in the eyes of the Bundys
Whether or not grazing your cattle on a piece of public land gives you any rights
To that proper
Cliven Bundy believes he is grazing his cows on his land
And he's going to claim it's not federal government land it's actually County Land
Ranchers in Clark County Nevada or eventually offered buyouts for their grazing permits
Help save the desert tortoise
Nearly all of them took the money
And their permits were retired
Everyone
Cliven Bundy
For more than 20 years
He fought in and out of court with the Federal Bureau of Land
You'll hear about the Beyond a lot in this podcast
Is the agency that President Truman created after World War II
To manage millions of Acres owned by the US government
Most of it in western states
The bunny said
That was unconstitutional
If you're around the bunnies and their supporters for any amount of time will hand you a pocket-sized copy of the Constitution
And I'll tell you about the favorite part
Article 1
Section 8
Let me read that lost to you that again this is Article 1 Section 8 Clause 17
Now it starts out that says Congress shall have power to Colors called The Enclave clause
And it basically says the government needs to get State permission to use land outside of Washington DC
The bunnies claim even when they have that permission
The feds can only build things like forts
Military dockyard
The problem with this interpretation is that it completely ignores the rest
The Constitution
There are other Clauses and long settled
Supreme Court cases
The government definitely can own land
We'll get into that later but it's also important to know that the other ingredient here is Sovereign citizen ideology
Sovereign citizens believe they are independent nations unto themselves
And when you're your own Nation
You don't have to abide by the country's laws
Federal courts aren't valid federal judges
Aren't real judges
Things like
Federal agencies
Don't apply to you
Cliven and Son Ryan
They flirt with these ideas
They don't recognize the US Justice
System
Cars and spent two decades in court fighting over his interpretation of this clause
Few people have even heard of
All the while
Is cattle grazed
Far far beyond his property on public land
Which belong to everyone
The cattle grazing so far from the ranch
Official surveyed his cows
They found lots of them are feral
Some didn't even have a brand
They were probably born wild
These fights over endangered species in land use
I've been going on for a long time
For two decades
Funny fart about those things in court
You just kept losing
By 2014
The government said Cliven had racked up more than a million dollars in fees
Funny cide differently
I would be happy to pay my grazing fees if I owed old grazing fees to the proper government
That brings us to the point of who does own this land
How does the federal government own
90% of the state of Nevada
I thought we were sovereign state
Buy I'm the manager of this land
Because of my my ride
Record says Cliven Bundy is trespassing on United States
Property
Just an aside
Cliven often refers to himself in the third person
Is this idea of trespassing that really set him off
Because he was giving this interview in 2014
Federal agents were indeed Staffing up
To take his cattle as payment
For his backlog of feet
Who is the trespasser
Who's the one out here with
Arms agency
Drowning my home in my rank import of
Courts of Clark County is Cliven Bundy doing those things or is the United States government doing these days
That was his Breaking Point
He refused to give them a towels
And I have spent 20 years
Legally clinically in the media and now it's time to get on the bar boots and I guess
Lakers fan
The bunny never publicly calls for an armed standoff implies that's his only option
It seem like it's down to We the People is if we're going to get it done
Building things like Malaysia
No I haven't called or anything like that but hey it looks like it's about let's go where at
By this point it was April 2014 and the Bureau of Land Management was coming to get clivens cattle off the land
Once and for all
People from across the country with all kinds of grapes with the government it picked up in the Bundy story through right-wing media
Many of them didn't know the first thing about raising livestock
They were just looking for a fight
One of them is James Yeager
About a year earlier a video he posted got a lot of
Attention
He was angry at the Obama Administration
Over proposed ban on assault rifles
These are the type of people who start flocking to Bunkerville
Jaeger became 105 in
Personal bodyguards
About 5 days after BLM agent showed up on Clements Ranch
There was really chaotic
They're protesters yelling at BLM agents
Agent of dogs
They're trying to let some trucks through the crowd
When all help
Breaks loose
What agent causes an older woman on the ground
And then all of a sudden Cliven son Dam and speeds up on Annie
ETV
Stop sit in front of the truck
Gets out
Trades words with the agents
Dog Snapchat in
Etekcity
Agent teaser
Kid rips out the taser prongs
It keeps yelling
That video goes viral
And it brings even more protests
Bunny Ranch
It's helped Along by this network
Right-wing YouTubers and bloggers
They're inciting their followers and in some cases telling them
Bring even more guns
The desert
Again I'm going to say it again
Anyone in the general vicinity you can get the Clark County Nevada
And show some support for our US Constitution our sovereignty
And stand in the face of tyranny
Nspl
Pressure mounts on the government to avoid a potential shootout
The further people the fact that there could be a shootout
I guess I'm driving toward Nevada
Malicious like the three percenters
The Oath Keepers assemble at the ranch
2 days after that video was shot Albanese cows in a pain underneath interstate
15 few miles from the ranch
People hop in their trucks and speed a couple of miles away toward the cattle
Mel Bundy is there on horseback
Holding the animals are surrounded
Avenue overpass
They're people pointing sniper rifles at them
Bunch of Clive & Sons
M&L Ryan
Are there two
They're telling me agents to let the cows go
And they do
Down along the banks of the lawn
There's video showing a group of people riding horses
Turn the American flag
Hurting Clements cattle back to the ranch
Ryan Bundy climbs a light pole
Endless hat
Sky
You might think the feds would bring charges in the days and weeks after the standoff
The bunnies had to fight a court order
Pointing guns at federal agents
But the government doesn't
They just leave
In the bunnies get what they wanted
Not by court rulings by compromising
The one by playing cowboy
Bringing bigger
And Morgan's to shoot out at the crowd it was like the old west
Where the Outlaws
Told everyone they were the heroes
And soon in the desert of Eastern Oregon they tried again
But this time the feds would be the ones pointing the weapons
Burns Oregon is a real sneeze and you'll miss it town in the remote Southeastern part of the
There's a grocery store
Some restaurants
A motel or two
People who live there drive 2 hours
To go to the mall
Costco
Everybody knows everybody and burn
They notice when Outsiders are in town
So in the bunnies appeared in late 2015
People took notice
They came because Ammon Bundy had taken an interest in a local ranching family
AR
Wonderful people
They are
Salt-of-the-earth
He's talking about Dwight and Steven Hammond
Father and Son Ranchers
Were convicted of setting fires
Public lands in the early 2000s
Prosecutors tried to get them sent away
For destroying government property
Meaning the land
Which carries a mandatory jail sentence
5 years
The judge said no
Find the hamster
15 months
Prosecutors weren't happy
They appealed the ruling
In January 2016
Cynthia Hammonds back to jail
Falafel fiber
Hundreds of people and burns were upset
All the March through town in support of the Hammond
They saw the burn as an effort to protect their property
The wildfires
Rage across the West
Beach summer
The FED said
One of the fires was actually started to cover up an illegal deer
Either way
Ammon Bundy saw a federal government persecuting a ranching family in order to take their land
It's crucial that you understand what's going on here what does he she was truly about
It's about our federal government
Taking over private property adversely
Or using the taxpayers dollars after they ruined the Ranchers
To buy it
It was part of a broader conspiracy he said
Government run amok
Predators
Any of the day can get control
The land and resources
So they can control for example the water
Then they can have
Full control over the people
To Ammon Bundy and his brother Ryan
The case was a chance to get cash
Controls the land back from the Fed
It was an opportunity to take a
Discontent over the Hammonds
Nurturing
After the protest March in Burns Ammon Bundy kinda snowbank in the parking lot
The town's groceries
He started making a speech know what's going on here and have seen it for many many many many years
Those who are ready to actually do something about it
I'm asking you to follow me and go to the malheur National Wildlife Refuge
We're going to make a hard stand
And that's what they do
Ammon Bundy picks up where his father Cliven
Left off
Under the cover of Darkness the bunnies marched a group of men to the malheur National Wildlife Refuge
The federal bird sanctuary 30 miles from town
They broke into locked buildings at work
Closed for the winter
And they quickly started to tell the media their version of events
They claim The Refuge was unlocked
And they waltzed right in
They said they had more than a hundred and fifty armed men ready to defend the Refuge law enforcement came
In reality
They only had a couple dozen at most
What was in a few days the militias showed up again
People from out-of-state flooded the wildlife refuge and dug-in
The band was back together
It was Bunkerville in snow
The bunnies dared the federal government
Just try to stop them
They held daily press conferences
Talk about how the government
Can't own land
But there were differences from the standoff in Nevada two years earlier
Many townspeople didn't buy the Bundy story this
Time
They posted signs
Crossburn
Militia go home
They held meetings asking the sheriff to turn off the power to the Refuge
Mother bunnies freeze
When the occupier is called for supplies
People from around the world sent boxes
Sex toys
This one was really funny and a bag of dicks
They called them
Y'all queda on social media
Vanilla Ice
Waist and waste their money on all this
People stop to send out here
But the biggest difference
Between Oregon and Nevada is at this time
Shots are fired
It happens on a remote Oregon Highway 26 days after the occupation started
An informant tipped off the feds
That the bunnies and other leaders of the Takeover are driving into cars
To nearby town
They plan to hold a meeting in the next County over
Lucy the sheriff
Who supported their cause
Federal and state law enforcement set up roadblocks
Ammon Bundy gives up immediately
Gets out
Hands up as Oregon State Police clothes in
But the people in the other truck don't give up
Occupation spokesman Robert Lavoy finicum is behind the wheel
He was once a model Rancher
Paid his grazing fees
To the federal government
But he converted to bunnies way of seeing things during bunker
I'm going to make the chair is waiting for
So you do what you damn well please
We're not going anywhere
You bet Dad are you coming out
What does do mean
What you're hearing is a video taken from inside finicums truck during that stop
Inside the truck with finicum was Ryan Bundy
19 year old girl named Victoria Sharp
And the person shooting the video
Shawna Cox
Depending on who you ask
What happens next
Is either an assassination attempt
We're Justified police shooting never have thought he says
Patience.
Lasers from rifles flash inside the truck
Officer shout to get out
It doesn't take long before finnicum hit the breaking point
Steps on the gas barrels around the curve Road
When he gets the roadblock he swerves at the last minute
The vehicle narrowly misses an FBI agent
And before the truck is fully stopped
Finnicum wechat
Someone fires two shots that hit the truck he stumbles through knee-deep snow
Keep shouting his hands are up at first then he reaches for his jacket
The pocket inside is a loaded handgun
He puts his hands up again and he reaches
And reach
Finally
Police to shoot him
He never managed to grab the gun
Police were shooting balls of pepper spray
Lavoy was bleeding out in a snowbank on the side of the road
Enforcement had been trying hard to avoid a shootout
They waited 26 days for the bunnies to leave the compound and the roadblock was on an isolated Road
Are the bunnies can call for backup within days of Memorial pops up world
Lavoy had died in the Bundy crew were talking about it like an assassination
Who's the ultimate example of a tyrannical government
Ammon and Ryan Bundy were arrested at the roadblock and went to jail in Oregon
Cliven Bundy was arrested days later
As he got off a flight in Portland
He was coming to help his son
Instead he was indicted on a Litany of charges
Stemming from the Bunkerville standoff
Nevada
Prosecutors have been waiting two years
Spring this trap
It wasn't looking good for the Bundys
The malheur occupation had led to a man's death
And they were about to have to argue in front of a federal judge that the stand us were Justified because the Federal
Sermon on state land
But then in court
Things did not go as expected
The court case in the verdict
Bundyville continue
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife
Wife is another remedy for all hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer in composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flat pocket
Here again is Leah sottile
The bunny's legal fight took years to
Play out across Oregon and Nevada
And I was there for most of it in both States
Don't worry I'll spare you the monotony of actually sitting through a federal trial
Not nearly as exciting as the movies make it out
The trials are when I really started to understand the power of the bunnies belief in their own story
For years they talked about fighting for freedom and some of America's wildest places
Places
Few people in this country have been to
And then
For two months in Oregon in 2016
And a month in Nevada in late 2017
The bunnies were forced to argue their case
Urban areas they despise
Las Vegas
Portland
Liberal enclaves the Bundy said we're ruining the lives of rural Americans
It's worth talking for a second about the Las Vegas Federal Courthouse itself
It's that far back from a long Palm tree-lined Road
Treatments front doors
You've got to walk across this massive concrete Plaza
Later I found out that's because this is the first building to comply with blast-resistant codes put in place
After the 1995 Oklahoma City bombing
That was the work of an anti-government
Extremist
Name Timothy McVeigh
It left 168 people dead
Orchids
The bunnies
To have been labeled
Is anti-government extremist
People have called the Oregon occupation domestic terrorist
And within their ranks of followers
You will find people who agree with what Timothy McVeigh did back in 1995
1 Bundy supporter a guy named Gary hunt
Talks about McVeigh like
He's the first one to actually take an active action against the United States government was a government building
And in that respect he is the first Patriot of the second American Revolution
Not that I agree with it from an objective observation
I give him credit for
Doing what other people have talked about
McVeigh murdered 168 people
19 of them kids
And some people within this movement see him as something of a hero
I think about that when I'm standing in this long line of people waiting to get into the courtroom
Apple trials
In Oregon and Nevada
Their homeland security officers with dogs walking around looking for threats
Before they walk through the metal detectors
All these bunnies supporters huddled together in a circle
Take off their hats
Pray
And then I wonder why it isn't afraid of them
Because the government is telling me to be
Because they're actually violin
Once I make my way into the courtrooms and the trial starts
I'm surprised
I thought the bunnies with Flounder in the city
Instead
They thrive
In downtown Las Vegas
The bunnies come alive with the atmosphere
From the lobby outside the courtroom
A Neon Cowboy flickers on the corner of Fremont Street
He's in the saddle a Topper giant rearing Bronco
The family seems like they feel right at home in Vegas
A rebel and having an audience
The first day of the trial
Ryan buddy pulled up to the courthouse in a white stretch limo
During the trial in Portland
Riders on Horseback Gallop down busy city streets
Tailgate party with hot dogs and burgers fills the sidewalk
The creative circus everywhere they go
Even in court
As a trial starts
Prosecutors and the bunnies only agree on a few things
First
What happened at Bunny Ranch was important
Second
Cliven Bundy is a lot
Grazing fees
They just disagree on who he owes them to
Cliven centamin and Ryan brought armed mend Oregon
2 years later
Take over the malheur national Wild
Was it a protest
Armed occupation
Beyond those points
It was like I was watching the national debate over alternative facts
Fake news play out in a courtroom
1st and Oregon and then in Nevada
Attorneys for the government would tell the jury these cases were simple
Describe the bunnies as a menace
Issaquah Ivan and his sons trespassed on Federal Land
Stole from the American people
Used intimidation
Stop federal workers from doing their jobs
It was all there in the evidence they said
Salmon and the others on video
And they did
We have
Basically taken over the Malian National Wildlife Refuge and we're planning on staying here for several years
Prosecutors talked about the main charge in both cases this idea of the Bundys and their followers conspiring to
To keep federal officers from doing their jobs
It showed a lot of maps they talked about things most urbanites probably don't care much about grazing permits
Water rights
The FBI described how they picked up evidence of The Refuge how they put in a baggies
Consign it to lab technicians then the technicians with lauded why did I come to court today
The jurors look bored in the front row I watch this one woman not off
And not just for a second the judge's clerk had another awake she giggled to herself
Prosecution had presented its case as if the details were going to be picked apart by other lawyers
But they weren't up against lawyers
Ryan Bundy was acting as his own attorney
When he stood up to present his case
He painted a very compelling picture
About life out west
He talked about him and his brothers as children
Waiting in the waters of the Virgin River
Sunrises
Moon Rises
Chasing frogs
Hunting rabbits
Running across a desert dog that
The Kills
Ryan talked about a family living in an unforgiving land
Finding Beauty in Solace among the Desert Shadows finding life in a place where so many things cancer
Survive
Talk about jackbooted agents armed for war
Federal snipers surrounding the Nevada Ranch
Cliven Bundy said the FBI mounted cameras to record his every move was a story about a tariff
Cornered and needing to defend its way of life
For his side of things the woman in the jury box
Wide Awake
Starbucks I certainly did not see this result coming I think it did
Kevin Sally is a portland-based defense attorney who watch the Oregon trial play out in 2016
He says prosecutors had to decide how to deal with a bunny versions event
What are the choices you always have to make as sort of a lawyer when you're when you're facing kind of a counter argument is
How much do you want to
Engage and thereby sort of dignified at argument as opposed to sort of
Dismiss
Oregon prosecutors didn't engage the Bundy version of the story
Even after a man talk for days and Court about the Constitution
About how he believes it's illegal for the federal government to own land
Legal Scholars laugh at
Prosecutors didn't touch it
I may well have done the same thing
Because if you if you think that your opponent's argument just really really weak
Then you're arguably doing a disservice to your case by time
He'll bring it up and elevating It And discussing it
So they hid it away
Didn't want to talk about the Bundys disproven views on the Constitution
How many years did been working the land
3 days talking
Telling jurors his family's way of life
Under attack
When it came time for the prosecutor to cross-examine him
They questioned him for less than 15 minutes
Nevada
Prosecutors hit away other things to
Didn't tell defense attorneys the cousin was right about guys with guns camping out near his property
His family was being recorded
At one point
FBI agents disguised as a film crew actually infiltrated the Bundy family home
All of these government Miss stats
The dismissive tones
The evidence they had because they said it was irrelevant
It all came across it
Arrogant
You could hear in the prosecutors voices
Etsy felt like they had a slam dunk
They were right
The bunnies were not
Not couldn't be clearer
In the end Sally says
That seemed to be the government's down
But the more I thought about it. You know it also
To some degree kind of
Presupposes the answer
What a lot of this case was about Italy some people's mind which is
Citizens going to have a right to a
Subject and disagree with
What the government
Does with land of the considered to be its own
You're so one Oregon juror
Grass to remain anonymous
Phrase the defenses message
This case is about the death of
Rural America
It's got me thinking
If
If your Farmers don't have the ability in this area to prosper in those venues in which they're going to raise
Logging or animal stuff it's
Got me thinking a lot about time
That message about the death of Rural America
It worked
At malheur there armed men patrolling a government
Facility
They took their guns of a fire tower
Doug battle trenches in case the FBI try to come in but in court
The fact that all those things are illegal
I didn't matter
The Bundys one
In Oregon ammon Ryan Bundy were acquitted by a jury
Nevada
The case never even got to the
Obituary
The judge declared a mistrial
Because prosecutors withheld evidence from the defense
Evidence that actually might have made the bunnies look good in the eyes of the jury
Like how it really was surveilling the Bundys
And prosecutors didn't mention that FBI threat assessment
Determine the bunnies themselves
Unlikely to be violin
I came into the trial skeptical the bunny world
But after listening to expert after expert explain why Cliven and his sons were wrong in their actions
Wrong for their beliefs
I can tell you
At times it's tough to tell which side of the courtroom is actually telling the truth about what the family did
Because the truth about this family
About the movement they Spark
Isn't that simple
It's it's a steak that's what your dinner that's where I'm headed
And God bless America today after having been arrested two years earlier
Cliven Bundy walked out of jail in the first days of 2018
Cowboy hats back on his head
His legs
Free of shackles
You raised a fist in Victory
Protesting or County Sheriff
Even the question of whether it was a standoff was still up for debate
Everything wasn't bunnies eyes have no contract with the federal government
Jurisdiction over this matter is federal government have a supposed to have an army that comes against me
He called out as he had in 2014 for people to stand up to the government
It happened on Bundy right they stuck their guns down our throats within days of getting
Out of jail
Ivan was on the steps of the Sheriff's Office
Out loud speaker
Making demands
Just as he had done in 2014
That's when I realized the Bundy story is hardly over
We're not done with this again we will definitely tell him
The truth
After the trials it felt like the truth was even more difficult to figure out
People traveled from around the country to see the Nevada trial
Journalist
Critics
Bunny sympathizers
Environmentalist
They came to see the wheels of Justice turn out long-desired answers
About what this is all meant
To understand what the Bundys actions mean about the teacher protest
But the future of the American West
Say something definitive about the movement the family tapped into three years prior
Play Mistral doesn't settle any of those questions
Is anything the proceedings raise new questions for people on the fence about the Bundys
Everything they stand for
Is a bunny sad loss
Their occupations will be a footnote to the fight over public lands in the West
Their story would be about a fringe Uprising that fizzled out
But because of the government's missteps
The Bundys Court victory
Reviews on who owns the West Bend legitimised
Least in the eyes of their followers
So if you want to know what the fight over public lands in the west is going to look like going forward you have to understand the bun
How they think
How did thinking Seducer
Is there followers
Understand the Bundys you have to trace their long and twisted family tree and understand the history
Backroom deals by politicians trying to undermine the federal government
It's a story of white supremacist
Nuclear weapons
And a little-known book that explains the Fringe religious beliefs behind Cliven Bundy's whole movie
Next time on bundyville
I dig in the client's past
And I find some answers
20 bill is a joint effort by Oregon public broadcasting and loan rates and was hosted in
Ported by Ward winning freelance journalist Leah sottile it is produced by Peter Frick Wright and Robert Carver
30 minutes West Productions
Ando BB's Ryan Hass
I highly recommend you subscribe the rest of bundyville and read the print Pieces by Leah on Long beads they are riveting
You can find it all at long reeds.com bundyville
Word search for bunny tail in your favorite podcasting app
99percentinvisible this project of kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Can you find the show in joints questions about the show on Facebook you can't we do me at Roman Mars in the show at 99ci org
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to put our true home on the web
IPI
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com