99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Is it daytime talk show that airs on CBS called
The Talk
It's kind of like the view if you've ever seen that
5 female hose sitting around the table discussing current events
And when it returned for its fourth season premiere in 2013
They came up with this.
Called Secrets week
Over the course of the week each of the five co-hosts
Took turns revealing one of their deepest
Darkest
Juiciest
Secrets
Because who doesn't love a good Secret
That's our newest producer Vivien Leigh
For example
We learned that week that Sharon Osbourne had a fling with Jay Leno
Metro State secrets
More interesting was a secret from one of the other co hosts
Julie Chen
My secret dates back to when I was
25 years old
And I was working as a local news
Border
In Dayton Ohio
Wait Chantel.
She been paying your dues as a reporter
But what she really dreamed about
Becoming an anchor
But when she approached your news director about the possibility
He gave her some
Be back
Because of your heritage because of your Asian eyes
Sometimes I've noticed when you're on camera
And you're interviewing someone
You look disinterest
You look bored
Because your eyes are
Art are so heavy they're so small
I hate people
Yeah
But Chen who's Chinese Americans found herself wondering if
Maybe he had a point
Reached out to a prominent talent agent for some career advice
And he actually took it a step further
He said
I
Cannot represent
You got
Plastic surgery
To make your eyes look
Bigger
And then she admits to the audience that she did it
She got the surgery
A procedure called blepharoplasty
For people who are not of east or Southeast Asian descent
Blepharoplasty is usually done to lift loose or sagging skin around the upper eyelids
Is caused by aging
Just Google Kenny Rogers before and after 2003
But for a lot of people of Asian descent
The surgery is more commonly referred to as
Double eyelid surgery
About having visions
Included
Are born with with
Called a monolid or a single eyelid
Which means that there's no visible crease on the eyelid skin above Lashley
This is what Julie Chen had before
The double eyelid surgery a decreased
So instead of the skin of the upper lid running smoothly from the bottom of the eyebrow
Straight down to the eyelashes
There's now a small indented fold in the skin
Just a few millimeters wide
That runs in a horizontal Crescent above the Lash line
This crease suddenly changes the eye shape in a way that makes the eye itself
Appear slightly larger
The simplest method doesn't even involve any Cuts just a few stitches along the eyelid
How to create the crease
John got the surgery in the mid-90s
But she kept it hidden from the public up until 2013
And that day
Which tells the audience about it
It was surprising to me to hear her sounding so
I didn't want to show you what I'm really demonstrate like
What my news headshot
Look like before I have this
Elasticsearch
I mean if you look at the app
After
That
The eyes are bigger
I look more
Alert
More Express
What's the name of that response
Sharon Osbourne saying fabulous
What is a serving to me
Double eyelid surgery is one of the most popular procedures for Asian-American
And hearing such a positive reaction it really is no wonder why
The hopes of looking fabulous or more expressive for the same reasons why people in my own family have had the procedure
Done themselves
In this ethnically specific surgery may have its roots in Asia
But it wasn't Asian doctors who popularized
It was popularized by a white guy
The US
He thought he was doing Asian people a favor by helping them look
West Asia
But before we get to him
The origin of double-eyelid surgery itself
Dates back much further
19th century Japan
Beauty standards will always vary from culture to culture and even within the same culture overtime
Double eyelids are seen as a beauty preference for a lot of Asians and asian-americans today
But that wasn't always the case
There's actually little to no record of double eyelids as an aesthetic preference until something called the Meiji restoration
Before the 1860s Japan practiced a policy of isolationism
And limited their contact with other Nation
But during the Meiji restoration which
Took place from the 1860's
Do the early 1900s
Japan opened up
Begin incorporating a european-style banking system new kinds of Scientific Technology and western style
It was also around this time that the first double eyelid surgery was performed by Japanese surgeon
It's easy to find like woodcut images or pictures of
The 1880s 1890s of a limited number of Japanese female patients are having I changes
This is John demoya
Professor of medical history at Seoul national university
He says that as Japan's contact with Western Nations increased
So did an appreciation for double eyelids over monolids
And it seems to be the case with a lot of Asian countries
Pretty places in Asia where there was a heavy contact either with the British Empire or with
Broader
Basquiat use the word American Empire
Tanabe places where blepharoplasty has 10 to pop up
It's these moments
Where Asian countries begin developing relationship
Swith Western Empires
At Double eyelid surgery becomes more visible
Prior to and during the Vietnam war and post
Korean War
But while blepharoplasty may have already existed in Asia is here and there
It didn't really take off in popularity
Until the Korean War
Korean war is technically still ongoing
But the actual fighting between northern and southern forces lasted from 1950
Pizza 1953
By the time the Armistice was signed dividing the peninsula into North and South Korea
The impact of the war had left South Korea
Pretty relying on help from Western Nations
What happened obviously created a certain path dependency in the sense that much of the aid was coming
From Western countries
This came in the form of food construction and importantly
Medical Aid
Which is how an American doctor named David Ralph Millard
Ended up in South Korea
He's a military doctor he's gay
He doesn't arrive into Korean till the war is winding down or just after
Millard he graduated from both Harvard and Yale then served in the Navy before settling on reconstructive surgery at this
Specialization
He studied under Harold Gillies
Father of modern plastic surgery
Who's known for repairing the bodies and faces of World War 1 and World War II soldiers maimed in battle
Where does the word I don't wanna say normalcy but he wants to restore some sense of a face that actually resembles a
A human face
Millard was stationed in Seoul in 1954 where he served as Chief plastic surgeon for the United States Marine Corps
It was his job to provide reconstructive medical assistance to those suffering from disfigurement caused by War
Burns or simply by lack of medical access
Millard was a fan of old Westfield grown up riding horses and learning to tie knots
Spinning ropes
Idealizing manly Western Stars like Ken Maynard and Buck Jones
He ended up bringing this kind of cowboy Goodguys savior mentality to his work in some strange and very little
Federal Way's
The first became well known for doing cleft palate surgeries on children
It is autobiography which he titled saving faces he tells the story of his first cleft palate patient
In South Korea
Millard I've been looking for someone to test a new method on but he was having a hard time finding a willing subject
We couldn't find a volunteer you decided to rustle up one and sell
This is before institutional review board exist
He's largely self authorized
Millard brag that he spotted a 10 year old South Korean boy with a cleft lip and ran back to grab a lasso that he kept in the foot
Foot Locker
Yes you heard that correctly
Lard-butt a lasso over 6000 miles
South Korea
I do not like where this is heading
He lassoed the ten-year-old and perform the surgery on him
And in case you were wondering
No he did not have parental permission to do this
Backing away historically
Probably today could not do
Medi the things that he did
Where someone else looking in and actually reviewing his work from professional stamp
As crude and horrifying as Millard methods could be
Is work in class
Pallet repair did get him respect in the field of reconstructive surgery
But he would soon become famous
Or maybe infamous
Another procedure entirely
Blepharoplasty
Or the double eyelid surgery
Millard was the first documented surgeon to perform this procedure in South
Korea
On a translator
Covetous in an essay that he wrote about his time overseas
Called oriental peregrination
Meaning Oriental Journeys
Depicts a Korean male translator
Who is
Coming to him because he wants to look different than he looks
Millard recounts
Quote
A slant-eyed Korean interpreter speaking excellent English came in requesting to be made into a round eye
Unquote
Interpreter then tells Millard that has
Does translation work relies on his relationship
American
Similar traits
Quote
He felt that because of the Squints and a slant eyes
Americans could not tell what he was thinking
Consequently
Did not trust him
As this was partly true
I can send it
Quote
Which sounds
Familiar
It's basically the same feedback that Julie Chen got 40 years later
People couldn't read her
Russians and audiences wouldn't relate to her
Stereotype of the inscrutable Asian has a long history in West
People from Asian Nations as
Perpetual foreigners who are just
Two different to assimilate
He shows dramatic before and after pictures of the translator
It is clear that he thought the work he was doing was more than just cosmetic caption
Backwards I said something like
Now he's frequently mistaken for Italian or Spanish
Morgana say that the translator
Kidspace totally transform now and European looking
Plans to go to the United States
Study for the ministry
Swimming
This is where people get angry at Millard not only enough for whatever his ethics are in terms of
The medical stuff but the cultural assumptions were you thinking
Completely transform this man's life
And his body is react
Surgery
Over the course of his year in South Korea
Mark continued
Performing blepharoplasty
Christian others
Specifically South Korean sex trade workers who are trying to appeal to American GI
Describe a woman's desire for eyelid surgery to be for
Economic reasons
Millard blepharoplasty offered a solution to a cultural disconnect between east and west
It was only those with Asian features who were expected to change their bodies
What's the population of East Asians growing in the United States
Millard speculated that double eyelid surgery might be useful at home in the US to
Gi's were bringing home Japanese and Korean Brides
And Millard thought that plastic surgeons could help them integrate into American society
He definitely saw himself in like to see himself as a
An advocate of the surgery
I don't think you could possibly though I've been to
Dissipated Howard
Will get picked up in different ways
According to the American Society of plastic surgery more than 12,000 Asian-American
Inside double eyelid surgery in 2017
Procedure has become completely normal for both women and men
And given the racist history behind the person
It makes sense that some people in the US are vocally critical about it
Who says look eyelid surgery
It's fake it's anti-asian you're erasing
Ethnic markers
It's not so much about necessarily just a droopy eye it's also about wanting to look more Caucasian
10 story has prompted a backlash
Some critics accused her of selling out
But not everybody buys this Narrative of selling out
The Western media pretty much
Distantly has a pitying or condescending attitude about
How Asians
Do plastic
Surgery
This is euny hong
A journalist and author of
The birth of Korean cool
She says that the reaction to Julie Chen double eyelid surgery was a perfect example of this condescending attitude
People are accusing her of being ashamed of
Erase
I've been ashamed of having Asian eyes and I was kind of gobsmacked
Because
You know I can a person's body should be there
Business
Calling can speak from personal experience because she's had the surgery done herself
She says
It was no big deal
The procedure doesn't take very long at all and might even be something like 20 minutes
Punk says that stigma around double eyelid surgery is distinctly American
American Media tends to assume that Asians are getting plastic surgery to look
Caucasian
And in a multicultural
Society like the US
Where racism is a daily reality
It could be hard for us not to interpret people's motivations through that lens
But Hong says the attitudes about plastic surgery are different in South Korea where blepharoplasty was first
Popularized
Will the procedure might have originated with the desire to look more Western
That isn't necessarily why South Korean people get it anymore
The history of double eyelids
Surgery might have been motivated
In kind of
Racial hegemony or something like that wanted to impose
Western beauty standards on Asian Spot
As with a lot of things including
Cuisine and art
It can have a certain origin but it always
Gets adopted and localized
And
Friends of completely
Taking the ball and run with it
The surgery has taken on a new meaning
Now we are a really focus all we really focus on making Beauty
Instead of making Western faces
Dollar South Korean plastic surgery at Seoul national university
Change the same reason they did back in the 1950s when Millard was around
Today they're aspiring to their own uniquely South Korean standard of beauty
Which has been shaped by complex
Cultural factors
The late 1990s South Korea suffered through a financial crisis
And the international monetary fund or IMF
Stepped in and completely restructured and modernize the economy
The country has since recovered and is now the 11th largest economy in the world
But the job market has become so competitive
But getting a job can still be incredibly hard
People do whatever they can to compete
So you're your appearance
Is 1
Of your
Thesaurus
So you have to kind of develop
Your appearance
You have a better job
And better future or better Park
And the South Korean government has also
Fully embraced
And encouraged
What's the plastic surgery industry
Governmental effort
To promote
Korean plastic surgery
So
Plastic surgery
Israel as
Korean culture has been kind of
National income
Sorry for the Korean government
The South Korean government has lifted a ban on medical advertising and revised immigration rules to make it easier for
Foreign patients to get long-term medical visas
And now medical tourism makes up a huge portion of the plastic surgery industry
People come from all over the world
Have work done
And South Korea
And
Of course many South Koreans get plastic surgery to
Eyelid surgery is still the most popular
Procedure it's so common that a lot of young people in South Korea will get the surgery as soon as they're old enough to
Like a gift when you graduate high school before you go to the college it's
Carnival
Laptop
Gift set
This is Geo a photographer who spent time documenting the healing process of South Korean plastic surgery
She's witnessed many of the recent Trends in Korean beauty culture affecting both women and men
So
Basically you have to have a chips on my baby looking face
Which is lighter
And you says that many people also want a sharp
Narrow chin
The overall effect they go for isn't necessarily
Caucasian
It's almost
Pixieish
You definitely have to have a very sharp
V Line
Chin with no jawline we slept very straight in there which outlines
But they tend to cut out those
The cheapest complete look
Requires a lot more than double eyelid surgery
Which is fairly easy and low-risk
Jaw reduction surgery is much more invasive in dangerous
Of course any surgery has its risks
But this one involves slicing out a significant amount of jaw bone
I could lead to complications like nerve damage or chronic jaw pain
One in five South Korean women have gotten some form of plastic
Surgery done
And if you look at women ages 19 to 29
That number shoots up to 1 and 3
Uses women face such immense cultural pressure to conform physically
It can be hard to resist
You should 5/4
Your own Beauty you shouldn't follow the idealized beauty you shouldn't be
Scrutinized by the culture
But it is
So hard
Nearest Summit
Easier and peace
To be popped
The car charger
What is critical as your feels about some aspects of the plastic surgery culture in South Korea
She does wish the rest of the world
But just stop
Being so
Judgy
Because whether you're a Korean woman
Trying to meet your cultures exacting beauty standards
Or an Asian-American woman like Julie Chen
When the choice between changing your appearance
Or hobbling your career prospects
You're basically damned-if-you-do
Damned if you don't
The art of making metal facial prosthetic
4 soldiers injured during World War I
After this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting to special episode
What's from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how our soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flat pocket
So we talked a little bit about how War accelerated the development of medical field
Like reconstructive and cosmetic surgery
It also drove the growth of
Aesthetics
A field at the intersection of
Medicine
Art and Design
NPR producer Vivian Lee is back to talk a little bit more about
That feel
Lake with reconstruct
The surgery the development of
Prosthetics really Advanced during World War but
Specifically a branch of medicine called Annabelle
Pathology which deals with
Customized Prosthetics
People with missing or malformed parts of the body
Especially for the
With a really rough time to be a soldier be
Because technology like
The machine gun
Had advanced
To make killing people and injuring people
So much more of a
Yeah you hit the nail right on the head
And you're given the nature of
Trench warfare
Soldiers with needs
Pop their heads out of these trenches
Sapphire off rounds or two
Dance
Making their faces vulnerable so
It's made facial injuries really common
But it was also this moment
History where medical treatment was starting to get a lot better which is
Good
But you also had men suffering from
Terrible headphones and then surviving
So you have a lot of soldiers
They're literally getting shot in the face
But they could now survive
Really horrifying in of itself
It also made it hard
For soldiers to come home and have
Normal life
Nudist
Figure meant exactly
And reconstructive surgery was
Beginning stages so you had things like
Skin grafts
But there really was nothing
Do in terms of
Surgery for someone who had
You know their jaw
Take it off
Keeping cold with her
Used to be
So anaplastology picked up in an aesthetic way where we can see
And this is a really interesting intersection between
Art in medicine
Rate so you need to be able to recreate a human face
Which takes a lot of artists
Talent and that's where artists like Anna Coleman Ladd came in
Should an American sculptor who lived in Boston at the time a lot of her
Pre-World War 1 artwork involves making like
The bounding nymph
And happy baby sculptures that you'd find in fountains
And she founded something called the studio for portrait masks
In France which made
Facial masks
For veterans with severe injuries
To the face
So how did an artist
From Boston
Go on to found this
Studio in France
Really locked ignition
She moved to France with her husband because
Cuz he was a doctor with the American Red Cross
And while she was there she right about this other sculptor and London who's making these facial
Pieces for veterans
So she got funding from the Red Cross
Do something similar in France
Not so cool
So what type of work goes into making
Each mask
Would take about a month now
To make ladwood
ACH look off of pictures of veterans before their injuries
To try to match his clothes sleep
Possible what they look like originally
I'm in the process involves you know taking a
A plaster cast of their face
Basis
And then she
Shape the mask itself out of the things she
Sheet of galvanized copper and B Skagway
You up to half a pound depending on
How large the injury was
And they were held
Face usually using in a string or wire
Sometimes they would use
Eyeglasses
Keep Monica
They wanted eyeglasses
Copper
Amazing
It seems like it takes a lot of
Krave interpretation to make the right type of mask
Can a metal right yeah that's what made these
Specifically so special
She would have to
The hand paint
Each of the mass directly
On their faces to make sure that their skin tones match
And matching the skin tone is
Especially tricky
Because you know
When you're outside
Healed your skin will change depending if you're in this
The sign or if you're in the shade
So she would basically need
To split the difference
Between the two colors to make sure it wasn't
Extreme in either condition
And she'd also you know either use real human hair or slivered tinfoil to create the eyebrows
Or a mustache
And my favorite detail that you would do is
You know it's the mask
Had to cover
The mouse
Of the recipients
She would leave
Modafinil it's just wide enough
4 of a cigarette
Guess at that point
Smoke up enjoy life
They do anything they really were just cosmetic
Chew food or see again
But you know for someone who had already suffered a massive
Facial injury that you can really mean a lot
It's such an interesting work
I mean in the pictures
Really stunning
It's hard to describe these
Because when you think of a half
Pound
Copper mask on someone's face
Probably doesn't sound like it's going to be very realistic
But there's this video Vlad fitting these masks
Veterans and it's
It's amazing how transformative they are witches
I see them in
And you can see for yourself on a video that we have up on the website
99 pi
. org
Thanks babe
Thank you
99percentinvisible with this week by Vivien Leigh mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Percocet is the digital director
Beretta team is senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery Chapman Joe Rosenberg Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are project at 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a proud member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Podcasting
Dubai Mall
And radiotopia. FM
You can find the show in discussions about the show on Facebook you treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But you can get all the tools to decode the secrets of the built world
Vat19 IPI
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com