99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Over the summer a new movement started to gain momentum
The movement to ban plastic drinking straws
It's now legal for Food Service businesses in Seattle
To provide a plastic
Stronger than you
Cancel
Santa Cruz is among 28 others around the
California and Hawaii or even exploring Statewide policy environmentalist a 500 million
Plastic straws end up in the world's oceans every year
Harming wildlife
The argument against
We consume
Tons of plastic
Not much of it gets recycled
Most of it ends up in landfills in oceans
Reduce a little of that way
But like most issues these days
There's been a lot of disagreement about
There's been backlash from few directions
Gluten conservatives
The lapse war against wait for it
Straws
Creamy rice
Is this idea that we are holier than thou
But people with disabilities also spoke up because some of those folks
Actually need straws in order to drink
That it might take away
Their tool of Independence
And there's even disagreement about the actual number of straws that we throw away
You hear the number 500 million
Floating around
Apparently that number came not from a rigorous study
But from a precocious 9 year old science project
9 year old
Even the environmentalists could not agree on whether the straw ban was a good thing or not
Everybody got to have their thing the real problem is cars the real problem is building the real problem is have you seen China's admission
You know the real problem is too much nitrogen and
You know ocean is it if
Application in energy and environmental problem
Is probably more important than flask
This is journalist Alexis Madrigal
He wrote a great essay about pasta
6 drawers for the Atlantic and he's going to be our guide through all of this
Because he says
That when you zoom out from the controversies of today
And look at the iPhone
History of plastic
They can tell us a lot
About America
Tell me about some of those bigger things that emerged when you looked at the history of plastic
You know I used to do this quite a bit like just take some little object and just
Trace its history you know you can look up
The patents on Google and you can
Search around for another company is that made it and you can see it
Technical Evolution you know you can just look at it like the way you would look at the development of any
Technology
But the thing I was soaked
Crazy about the straw
Who's the richest
It's so many of these like real
Crew major trends
In the way that the
The country worked
The straw is there for the invention of American industrialism for Organization for Public Health
Perform for like the suburbanization of the country
Fast food
And now of course the culture works like it's there for all of them
And to tell me where it all began
Did someone invented the straw or was it just always there
So you know there's even like
Scientific studies
The show that orangutan
Looks like we'll collect the straw-like thing is cool for doing straw like stuffy nose
Burlington version
But in nineteenth-century America
They see the straw with Rye
Literally no grass.
This hollow tube
And you know you dry it
Cut it into shape and that's what what happens that was the straw
Travis Tritt
Around this time they're also straws made out of more durable
Like metal
Glass
But then
Along Comes this guy
1888 Marvin Stone
He creates what was then called the artificial straw
Any artificial straw is basically paper dipped in some kind of wax
C substance
Paraffin
And that becomes this new standard
It wasn't just that it was artificial is also that it was
Disposable
This was basically this
Incredibly cheap
And it's incredibly busy
Disposable and hygienic
This wasn't something that came from nature
He was in fact
Produced
To a standard you know this wasn't patent straw
And the fact that this straw was hygienic and produced to a standard was important
His drawers are becoming a tool in the emerging Public Health movement that was happening in cities around this time
You know the reason public health is emerging at this time it's because people in American cities are just like dying all the time
Name of communicable diseases
A lot of illnesses were spread through dirty drinking water
Understand why this was such a big healthy
Guess you and white straws would eventually help to solve it
You have to understand how
Public water fountains worked at
In a lot of
Places in the city but work places in in in public locations
The water fountain wasn't
Like what we think I'm not like this little thing with water bubbling out of it or like
Depressed little button water comes out
It was just kind of like water that was sitting there or if a little
Tap and you would actually fill a cup that was attached to it
And it's drink out of it and it be like
Chain or whatever
Soyo
A bunch of different people would all drink from the same cup
We actually did an episode about the
Early water fountains you something called
The common cup
And it became one of the main targets of the public health campaigners
There was acting like one
Kansas doctor
Who started to like push
This campaign against the common cup
At the tone of this campaign
It's intense
Maybe they literally would show
The Grim Reaper taking a drink from the common cup with like a little girl
Next to him
Drinking from the same cup you know
Do you want Public Health reform or some kind of Reform you just need to go for the throat
Is it going to kill your children
Acquiring straw dispensers in certain public spaces in the case of the common cup
Strasbourg way to avoid actually putting your mouth or somebody else's mouth in bed
But it wasn't just
Public Health reformers that contributed to the rise of
There's there's two things there's a public-health Mania on the one side
And on the other side there's the development of
Certain bubbly carbonated beverage
Club soda and
The soda fountain
Occupies this really important place in kind of late 19th century early 20th century
For 1
I'm most of the public places where you could go have a drink or saloons and saloons were primarily gendered male
Urban women
With increasing freedoms in the city
Wanted to place to go
And many urban women were also involved in various temperance
Movement
And again
Saloons they're serving booze there and soda fountains become this kind of
Clean
Healthy alternative
So they're all these various
Transurban ization Thrice the soda fountain
The temperance movement the rise of Public Health
They all helped lead to the
This booming
Strong industry
Yeah and it's amazing see if you look at their
The Battle Creek Enquirer Enos Mall
Paper in May of 1924 they actually
List out how would how far did this go
How big was this boo
And they say do to the Yankee Mania for sanitation
The output of artificial straws has increased from 165 million in 1901
24 billion
A year
A manufacturer pointed out yesterday that laid end-to-end the straws would build an ant
Subway
16 times around the world
At the equator
Into 4 billion straws
In context
Talking about America is 114 million people
At 4:35
Strasburg
A lot of stress I mean I do I can't I sleep
I'm probably like a hundred year kind of guy
By the 1950s and 60
The strong will become less and actual driver of important
Football change
And more
Kind of insignificant object surfing along much bigger trends
Friends like
The rise of fast food culture
For businessman named Ray Kroc
Took over a little restaurant in Southern California called McDonald's
He was a paper cup sales
Which meant that he was also a straw salesman
So he works for the Lily toilet paper company
For a long time
15 years
Going around the Midwest
Selling
Straws and cups
The soda fountain
Amazing
Here you know what he he wrote
A memoir which
We keep radeberger shop and he called his Memoir grinding it out
Addiction tell you a little bit about him. He like moonlighted as a
The Pianist
But he was a Salesman like
Kind of one of those like
Really doesn't feel like a
21st century story like it feels like a like a
Weird story
But Ray Kroc
In this Memoir grinding it out
He describes papercut
What kind of disposable you don't hygienic
World
He was like
They were Innovative and upbeat
I sent from the out
Paper cups were part of the way America was headed
She was right like that was part of the way of America was going like every we were going to throw away everything we throw
Phones
Throw away computers we throw away couches
So Croc
Becomes a central figure lease in my story because he should have Kinect
This paper cup industry
To this greater concept is like disposability
In America
Selling all those cops brought Ray Kroc in
Contact with soda fountain
And he eventually went into business selling milkshake mixer
This led him to Southern California
We saw the first McDonald's in operation
He bought his way into the small company
Announce did the original owners
This is crazy
McDonald's goes
From base like a hundred
Knight Rises to a thousand and then just like keeps on going pure like kind of
Dick growth
The American public are basically
Beast
Eating
People
And it works
Day after day after day after day
People just want more of it
I can't give them everything they like
But this one thing I sure can get
And you have with
Place with the rise of fast food and suburbia
In the amount of
I have wrapping basically for food
You're getting your food in a box
And that's just
Hadn't been the way that things were
Patricia Lee Dunn
Select the Plastic industry at the same time is growing up because of this disposable
Can you talk about this transition
From paper straws to
Yes
When is inter
Everything about Plastics
1950 the world is only producing like one and a half million times
Classic which of course is a lot but it's not
He's nowhere close to somewhere where we get I mean by the late sixties that production has grown
Tenfold
Don't really kind of in the fifties into the sea
60s were decent people are going
Is there an object
Maybe it should be plastic
Chairs become plastic and plates become plastic and just everything kind of if you can do it you can do it in plastic
Pental quartz straws become part of the
1970's and 80's plastic straws had become ubiquitous
They were every
And while straw design continue to evolve slightly
The more dramatic changes were happening in the straw industry
At this point
Both in our economy
And also in this artifact
Straws history
It's really the mechanism
That organized
The factories
That become the most interesting
Object
And those mechanisms are basically Financial capitalism beginning to really move away from
Being about
Family businesses
Organizing production
You know at these kind of local levels or Regional levels
And it really becomes
Every
Thing
Is just a money waiting to be made through financialization
By financialization Alexis is talking about a big Trend in economics that's been happening over the last few decades
Our manufacturing sector has been shrinking
While our financial sector has been expanding
Which has big implications for who ends up making money
Long straws and a million other consumer goods
The slice of money that's going to the people who provide the money as opposed to provide the products
Is growing and that has really important consequences for how things get made and who makes them and
Where are the factories are located and how many people are employed in the culture of work and
And all these things
To tell me what happened to Maryland
This is one of the country's biggest troll makers
What would happen to them around this time
Maryland cup
It just sucks
Classic American story
Right
Owned by these brothers the Shapiro Brothers
They started out as like
Bakery and Anna turn into this
A bakery services provider and then they start making
So
After they make straws they make
Cups after they make
Cubs tickets
Partners from
And it remained basically family-owned
But eventually
Show the original management is gone the people are aging
And they decide that they're going to sell the company
They sell the company to another company
Call Fort Howard
Hard-charging
CEOs and their
Yeah there's a great story in the Baltimore Sun
Where they describe going to the sales meeting you know the Maryland cup Executives like I'll show up
The new bosses are there
And he literally probably had a flip chart
WhitePages flipchart it said hear your old values and they were service quality responding to
Customers
Are there parallel you literally like
Flip the flip chart to the next page and it said
New value
Profits profits profits
Damn that's quite a PowerPoint do you know
Maryland cop had been a very profitable company with a highly family
Oriented kind of culture you know the boss has a dress up as Santa Claus you know turkeys to all
Everybody at Thanksgiving and you know that kind of like
Paternalistic
We are all one big family company thing once they go into Fort Howard it becomes
I truly just kind of like work we're going to have to make money so
All these people get laid off they cut pensions
Did you all this stuff that's basically like the plot of Tommy Boy kind of speaker with his movie with Chris Farley
Ohio
Sowinski Industries has an offer on the table to buy us out
But if you realise Callahan has been family owned
Since Tommy's great-grandfather laid the first brick
And I'll be damned if that's going to change on my watch
But it's played out many many many many
And
In the end what ends up happening is that Fort Howard itself then
Is bought by private-equity firm
Who then goes and combines a bunch of different paper cup and disposable Goods companies
Into one kind of
Larger entity
And then spins it out
Loaded with a bunch of
And this is kind of a classic move that happens in private equity
Because you can borrow against these companies
Pay your investors and then spin out this other company that that is like soda floating in the ocean like
With rocks tied around its feet right
So operationally like from the from making cups and straws and all this stuff they're still making money but because
To pay all this debt
They're like deeply in the red
I have to lay off people
Have to close factories
And it is just
Classic story
I've kind of like vulture capitalism
And
The fact that
Straw like this
Stupid straw dislike empty vessel
Somehow also is tied up in the financial of America
Just said something to me every single goddamn thing is tied up with this
Kind of system of production
Can Banning straws really make a dent in our ecological problems
No it's not it's up to the scale of the of the problem
Line I see what all this stuff cuz obviously
It's hard to connect
Gala 1888 patent to the
Artificial straw
To financial capitalism in its current form
Here's the through line as I see it
The country has shed manufacturing job for decades
Straws contribute tiny share
Two environmental disasters that
Far beyond it
Mini economy continues to work on this way the concentrates wealth for the richest people
Yeah the sodas that are even like passing through
The Shroud and the people's stomachs are contributing to this obesity epidemic that threatened sexy roll back the public health reform
That actually got people's life expectancies to grow and previous eras
And there's this
System
Now that's attached to the straw
That helped to create you know disposable products
And then disposable companies
Disposable people both the workers who work within the system but also people who just have to live with all of these cries
Places that have been created
Structures far beyond
Their control
Is it was almost like
So we can all see that
Going on around us
Only when you focus down on like the most
Anything
That you can
See that massive structure
Temperature away
Arguably the most significant technological achievement of the 20th century
At least according to one of the descendants of the inventor
History of the Bendy straw
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Voice technology tok
To us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God. Info
As Alexis mentioned earlier
The Maryland cup Corporation got bought out and then
It's buyer's guide
Bought out in Solano
The capital is fast food chain
But before Maryland cups sold their family business
They grew in part by acquiring a
A revolutionary
Key patents
From another
Kirk Olson is here to talk about
That other family-owned business
They bought out
Flexible straw
The first of the contacts
As Alexis pointed out we'll never really know when humans first started using straws
But there's this Sumerian to about 5000 years
And I would still there these figures who
Appear to be drinking from straw
Sure enough when they found this ornate drinking
Precious stones
Really fancy and it's really old
It's probably not the oldest draw that
Ever exist
Digital this one we found
You may not even be close
It's expensive materials aside it's still just a straight to
Precious sure but otherwise not that different from a modern grass
Azure paper
Elasticsearch
So in a lot of ways
Straw design hasn't fundamentally changed for
Thousands of years
Or at least it didn't
Until the 19th
And that's when the f***
Yes
And as The Story Goes
The inventor Joseph E Friedman took his daughter to get a milkshake
Steak in San Francisco
At a sweet shop unbiased
But as he's watching his daughter struggle with this normal straight straw
He thinks to himself
Hey you get off maybe there's a better way to do this and it's like the classic
You see a problem you fix
It's a problem that this guy wasn't a
Strong maker by trade how did he die
Create this New Hampshire
Start out with this
Simple existing paper straw
How many slots in a metal screw into the neck
How many wraps dental floss around the screw
So that
When I tightened it down it creates ridges
And these ridges allow the things
You know like an accordion
Till you just use the screws threading
To provide the groove and then
And he's really clear about this tune the patent application is like
I didn't invent the accordion I didn't invent the straw
All I did was I combine this idea flexibility with this you know Street
Tube for drinking out of
So he MacGyver's this thing into existence
Does it
Revolutionize the industry by the way what does it do
It actually took
A while for these Flex
Which is kind of shocking
Because his brother oldest soda shop and yet somehow
It takes him 10 years to start selling these things
Taking other jobs on the side he needed to work as a real estate agent
Circuito live and he also got cash infusions from his brothers invest
Business
Got some business help from my sister Betty Who
Finally 10 years later they get their first buyers
And it has nothing to do with kids
So who are the first people to buy
Winter beanies large hospitals
Which if you think about it makes perfect sense
Steak-Out
Injured patients disabled patients
People lying in bed to a trouble sitting out
And so these Flex straws which argued openable disposable sanitary
They're just perfect for this Hospital
And from there of course they go on restaurants
Kids juice boxes and all that but they start out
Hospital
It's a really
Interesting example of Universal Design
It's really taken by a community that needs it
And then everyone realizes hey these are kind of nice for us
You know as we mentioned before there's some movement
Ball plastic
Straws banned
Do they still have a
Place in society
Minutes really debatable it is
Still being debated
And some people are saying hey luck let's go back to these paper bendy straws that worked right that's what Freedom was
Inventing with in the first place
About disability rights activists are saying
Hey you know that's great for some people but they can also fall apart and not that durable
There's also an argument that okay well then we should use reusable one
Eco-friendly life
Glass or metal but those are hard to keep clean
They can break
So there issues with all these different type
Pipes in for a certain demographic
Who really needs them
There's a strong argument
Freaky thing around play
Plastic Bendy straw
You can see pictures and patents
Freeman's original
Let's draw an old vintage print ads for them to their
Light bulb
It's on our website
It's a 99 p i
99percentinvisible with Bruce's sweet by senior editor Delaney Hall based on the story disposable America by
Alexis Manor
Written for the Atlantic
Mix anti production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Katie mingle is our senior producer
Kurt Costa is the digital Direct
The wrestler team is Vivien Leigh
Cambridge
L Rosenberg
Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are brother go 91.7 kalw insane
Cisco introduced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland Calif
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
A fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all up on
One Mall
Radiotopia
I found
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi org
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit
But you can listen to and read
More stories that use everyday objects to tell the story of the whole world
Pi
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com