99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
About eight weeks ago one of The Producers here at 99 P I ordered a book
Our office received
A lot of books
But this one
This one was special
Everyone wanted to read it
Okay so first of all it's booked beautiful
Master producer Joe Rosenberg
Where's the catalog from 1908
The great price maker
Sears and Roebuck mail order catalog was omnipresent
Early 20th century American Life
In 1908 when this particular issue came out
One out of every five Americans were already subscribers
So this come with the Amazon warehouse
Who were the country
For free
Didn't have anything dark desire delivered directly to their doorstep
Serious
Paris awesome pipes
Headstones
At its height
Sears catalog offered over 100000 items on 1400 pages
4 lb
Today
Does 1400 Pages provide us with a snapshot of American Life
The first decade of the 20th century
1596 our new Williams special single-strap buggy harness
Shearing machine menstruation products have definitely evolved
The Sears catalog tells the tale of a world
Itemized
But starting with this very issue in 1908
The company that offered America everything
Began offering what just might be the most audacious and in some ways most necessary
Item level
Wait these are houses
On page 596 subscribers would come across a drawing of a house
2 stories
9 rooms
Gable roofs
Enterprise $1,700
$1,700 for the house
I'm like no way tonight
Sears modern home program offered complete
Mail-order houses
It would be home on
I would come to be called
Kit homes
Exactly provided catalog
Between dozens of different designs
All you had to do was select your preferred model from the catalog
Fill out the provided form
Sending the check
A few weeks later everything you need would arrive in a train car
It's door was secured
The small red wax seal
Just like the Sea on the back of a letter to the king or something
It was to be broken
Throw for the door to this box
Car and you're looking at
Framing Lumber
Cedar Shakes
That's Rosemary Thorne
An architectural historian and author of the houses that Sears
She says that that train car also came with every single door
Every single door knob
Old way ironing
Beer Kitchen
In the mantle for the fire
And then you would begin the process
List of dutifully loading it
Either onto
Your your mule in car door
Model T
Plumber came precut
Giant Ikea
Along with
Instructions
If you provided the foundation
Sears promise
That working without a carpet
Only rudimentary skills
You can finish your Sears mail-order home
In less than 90 days
Claire Rosemary says does instructions also came
Weather warning
Do not accept anyone's advice on how this house should
Rebuilt follow this
Instruction manual and do not.
DV8 Sochi old wise
Carpenter
Buy and sell
I want to do that way and
Sears is warning you up front do not live
Listen to that man
Sears were going to ship out some 75000 homes across the country
In doing so they helped replace the idea that each new house needed to be built from scratch
The promise that new homes could be standardized affordable
Within Reach of every family
Long before the Advent of housing developments in the modern suburb
It was the Sears kit home that gave Americans their first taste of 20th century domestic life
But it's also a chapter of housing history that was almost lost
Sears not the first company to offer Keno
First mail order catalog
I can't dominate mail order
Is it founder Richards
What's that thing that so many people would claim to be over the course of the 20th century
Very few actually War
Did you just did
So many things and one is it one of my favorites
Is this
Sears knew that most Farm households would have both them
Montgomery Ward app
Sears Roebuck catalog
The household
So we purposely made his
Catalog
Just a little bit less wide and a little bit less tall in the Montgomery Ward catalog
Knowing that when The Farmhouse wife was tidying things up she would naturally put the Sears Roebuck catalog on
Top of the Montgomery Ward catalog I love that
A 1907 Sears and Roebuck was selling this been equivalent of 1.3 billion dollars
Merchandise
American family every year
It's around this time Richard Sears saw a weight cell even more
Most American families were still living in multi-generational housing
The reigning Paradigm of the middle class
Was the Victorian home with its many little rooms
Giving up children uncles and grandparents
Sears looked at this idyllic scene of families living in Harmony and saw
A wasted opportunity
Why should newlyweds move in the old homes with old things when they can move into new homes
Building with new things
From Sears
And that's
Sears modern home program
It was a hit
Basically after the end of World War 1
The influx
Veterans triggered a need for more housing
And there's literature that said if you really love this
If you really want to do right by America
Bye
Build a house
That's when kit homes
Really took off
Sears cut lumber for almost all of these
Right order
Giant Mills situated across the
The large
In Cairo Illinois at the Confluence of the Mississippi and Ohio rivers
Covered nearly Forty Acre
MSU variety of homes it shipped out with Stager
That first motorhome catalog at over 40 models to choose
Sears Will Go On.
Different designs
Every house in the catalog had a name
Fitting its architectural aspirations
So if you always dreamed of living in a California mission style home but you couldn't actually move to California
You might consider purchasing searzall home remodel
Other styles included the craftsman style Winona
The Dutch Colonial Martha Washington
They range from everything
From what I would call a hunter
Cabin
Literally a to
2 room house for
2 or $300
To the Sears Magnolia
2009 Hyundai
Square feet
Two full bathrooms UPS
Stairs 1/2 bathroom
From downstairs to
Fireplaces
A den
Even had servants
Squirters and service
Private bath
Sears even offered a 6 classroom School House
Complete with an auditorium and Library
Mostly it was hot
Big
Beautiful
Empty homes
Just waiting to be filled with things
In fact if you look at some of the old floor plan it'll feature the living room the dining room the bedrooms but then it will say
Place for grass
Spot for a piano plays for
Tufted chairs and so
Kind of showing people
How to stuff their houses with stuff from the Sears Roebuck catalog
Consumer Supply
There are Tales of first-time homeowners
About what you might call a turnkey operation, catalog
House the furniture
Little things arrested
Sunnylife
Awesomesir
In part because the company used is considerable marketing Savvy to make it clear
The building your house was going to be easy
The pre-designed home
You didn't need an architect
And with the pre-cut Lumber frame you didn't need a carpenter either
You can treat it like any other consumer item
Sears even have his add in front of the catalog
Jotaro decimal
What is Sears most popular houses
Side by side
When was built from scratch
Using ordinary building materials
Uncut stick Lumber
Weather
Retrica camera
In the ad the house with the stick Lumber sits unfinished
People are collapsed in the front yard exhausted
Precut Lumber
They're sitting on the porch with a mint julep you know having
The time of their life
Forget hire contractors Builder Sears home
Many did not
And I have heard
Many stories about
Family
Receiving their kit home
And calling on neighbors to help them come out
Start the process
Building the house
For many families these for their first homes with things like Central Heating
Inflation
In some neighborhoods
Sears kit home by the only house on the block with electricity
Annie 1911 Sears began offering competitive mortgages to their customers
Which also helped people in neighborhoods of color again around the practice of redlining
And redlining
Just meant that the bankers in the mortgage
Lenders would draw a line around neighborhoods where they would not loan money
So Sears
Didn't do any of that
And that enabled immigrants
Men and women of
Color and single women
Who would otherwise
Never have a chance of becoming a homeowner
Have indoor plumbing for the first time
Then the company discovered
Edited made a mistake
Probably sound
All 2
Familiar
From the beginning Sears had made sure their mortgage policy was like everything else in their catalog
Obtainable
Application form was only half a page long and almost everyone who applied for a mortgage qualified
Meaning of the average Sears homeowner was also in debt to Sears in the Roaring Twenties when interest rates were low
Sew-in liquidity High
It wasn't a problem
But when the Great Depression hit
Things got ugly fast
The end-up foreclosing on tens of thousands of very own customers
It was a
Emotional Devastation we all know the Great Depression
Was horrible for so many reasons
Losing a home that you had built
With your own two hands just seems like such a
Twist of the knife
For Sears it was a PR disaster
Best Mary remembers talking to someone in 2003
Describe has Sears have foreclosed on their grandparents home in 1931
Very same home
Sold them a decade earlier
And he said for two generations
Our family never patronize Sears ever again
Those are strong feelings go from 19
After years of declining sales
Sears would finally closed its modern homes Department in 1940
A few other kit home manufacturers ones that hadn't sold mortgages
They survived
But the Sears kit home boom was over
Then came World War
And with it
The next
Modern housing boom
Between the rise of the suburbs
And a prefab home
The homes
So many of us
Live in today
Most of the Sears homes the Alhambra the argyle the Magnolias
Ends up being sold to new owners who didn't know what they bought
I didn't care to know
Despite the high quality of materials
With Decades of
Comedian associated with companions over and above quality
Don't want to admit they live in a home
Elephants ears
A lot of them end up being renovated beyond recognition
Many were torn down
Others were simply abandon
And ask her where to find the ones that remain unfortunately after World War II
During a corporate house cleaning
Sales record
Search were destroyed
Phillies records are the records are missing
Turn somebody's burnpile all that stuff was
Disposed off
So the only way to find these house
Today is
Literally one by one
Weeks after I interviewed Rosemary
I want to see some of the last remaining Sears homes outside of Cairo Illinois
Town of Sears largest male in 1 stud
I got there only sign that there's never been anything there with the name of an overgrown back road
Sears
These are the two tiny houses to Sears rodessa models
Next to each other
They were the cleaner odesza models from that original advertise
2 homes being built
One fast one slow
Side by side
Now they weren't so so shape
But somehow they'd outlive the mail that built them
Sears Roebuck Road
Stop take a look
30 seconds later
A man wake me inside
Go to your room
They're just noise they don't mean no
They try to scare you off I think
Guy Parks greeted me wearing an old mechanic's jumpsuit
He settled into an easy chair in the living room
He told me that he lived on and off in Cairo since the 1950
Eddie first laid eyes on this route
Every 35 years ago
In the house was derelict
I mean it was
The roof was leaking
The windows were broke out
It was still safe
They withhold
Guy ran into the owner little while later
How about I tell you the place
Can you fix it up
After the hell I can't buy nothing
I saved $2 on my last check
He said I'll make it where you can buy
He said 1500 SLT for 15
I thought you meant that was an awesome and I would give that farted. In shape
He's on talk about a hundred
Okay you wait right here
So guy went out came back an hour later with the cash and bought through Adesa for $1,500 on the spot
Eventually by the rodessa next to it to
Between
His son lives there now
Nightsiders but I'm dumb enough
The last man everything I made for the next 5-6 years on this place
Try to make it right
You know that it was a
Sears home
Does a man live down on the corner
He work for Sears
You telling me story
Call
But he always told me the bad stuff
Guys neighbor told him that job at the Mill I've been
Hard dangerous
As a lot of males in the air
It wasn't uncommon see employees missing finger
Sears Mountain Home Department closed
Where can I purchase the plant in Switched making crates for bombers during World War II
After that they tried making their own kit homes under a new name
Ultimately they couldn't hold on
Canal closed in 1955
They didn't make very many homes after that I think this
One down and the little yellow house was
Probably the last one they built
It was just a little
A little shotgun house
My wife's sister lived there until she died
Even guys house isn't very serious anymore he's replaced a lot of the original parts over the years
Front door
The only thing in this house is
In this room right here this original was at front door
Sears door
4 series of race riots got to downtown Cairo 19th 6
I had nearly a hundred other Sears homes
Namibia last third of them are left
Skywatch this arrest
Abandon
Reduced to Rubble
Anna
The downtown just get going down
Going down going down
You can say every month or so they'll be another business gone
Tennessee
Find there was nothing down there but
Derelict buildings
Falling down
Anna
Sentinel event
All that done
Doggone definition
For a long time by parx's little rodessa and its twin
We're just two of a small handful of Sears homes that have been located and identified
When guy bought his house of the 75,000 kit homes that Sears built and shipped
Maybe 5% have been properly documented
Moose at undiscovered
If you lived in a Sears house chances are
You didn't even know it
A little over 20 years
One woman took a big step towards change
Although
As she herself would be there
Crestwood met
She didn't really mean to
It's pure Serendipity then I ended up
In this field
This is Rebecca
And no she doesn't live with you
But she does live in a town on the other end
A little Western Chicago
On the Fox River
It's called Elgin
And unlike Caro Elgin was not known for Sears homes
Rebecca first got there in the mid-90s
Almost no one there herself included
New with a Sears house was
Then my partner died in 1995 and I was
Doing everything
Because
It help
And that's how Rebecca ended up at the local library
Or she having fun a book about see ourselves which contained old
Catalog images of the various models
What you mean nothing
Capital One bitterly cold day in February
1997 happened to be lying on the dining room table
And it picked it up and I said oh haha I wonder if I can walk around my neighborhood
That would be really funny and so I picked up the book and I've said about walking in my neighbor
How many were you real
I wasn't expecting to find it
It was really kind of fun you know I had to go I had a mission
I forgot about the
Alarm clock
Time 15 minutes
I was walking down the street
And
I saw this house and I instantly knew it was
Sears
Right there after almost zero effort
Sears house
Makeup looks paused
What's the book
The house
The book
Craftsman style
Tapered porch column
The Avalon model
Then I said I wonder if I could walk around my neighborhood and find another one
And so I did on walk after walk
Rebecca Katz
Finding Sears models the Mitchell the Crescent the Vilonia and it was the Betsy Ross the Osborne
Text ICE one street that has the sunlight model and one side of the street and opposites the star lights
Starlight right across the street from each other
Rebecca wanted to confirm that these were serious homes so she sent a mailer app asking each resident to go and inspect
When did most discovered beams bearing a special stamp with a part number from Sears
Others found shipping labels from Sears on the back of attic baseboards
Two others managed to find their homes original series blueprints
Rebecca is not even done
There still more houses waiting to be investigated
What is the total number of houses in Eldon MO
At the moment
I think we are at 237 Sears houses in about a hundred from other companies
What's more
Most of the homes Rebecca found
Look like they were
Straight out of the catalog
They barely been altered since the 19th
That's why she was able to find something
Because the homes
Still be recognized
And there was a specific reason why
When the Elgin Watch Factory which had employed
A quarter of the Town closed in 1960
Before
Elgin entered a localized recession
Experian
From the renovation craze of the 60s and 70s
Instead Elgin Sears Home simply sat
Through the decades
Untouched
Has anyone ever went out the back at the closing of the watch Factory froze the houses
19 time
Oh yeah we we talked about that
Stuff we love it
We love it
The study of the Elgin homes
Along with your two other research
Makro store
Architectural history
What helped launch what is become a Sears house hunting movie
Turkish Chief passion in life is to scour the way
Try to find as many kittens as pause
Equity Rose
Some people do crossword
Word puzzles
Some people do jigsaw puzzles
I guess I look for Sears home but I actually listened Dale and Wendy
Andrew
And Nigel and Cindy
Look for soup
Those names form part of an elite corps of the Sears House Hunters
In a team if you will
And like any proper 18
Each member has their specialty
Rosemary Hunter the rare Sears Magnolia the three-story Colonial Mansion so far she says
They found 10
Their walkie specializes in kit homes built by Sears biggest competitor Aladdin company
Reminder much is the numbers down
He's currently working with about half a dozen people on a database that would list
Every single tear
Meanwhile Nigel Tate at 19 is the youngest member of their team he's found over 1000 kit homes
Without even leaving his desk
Uses Google Street View
Mostly they hunt for houses the old-fashioned way chasing down Clues patrolling the Mean Streets of America
Together and Andrews up in front and he's got his computer and he's writing down addresses and Dale is driving in
Wendy and I are in the back seat
It's for the camera and everybody's looking out the window and somebody says hey
Although they're not exactly bounty hunters
And so I'm getting out and I'm taking
And this very
Large
Three man burst out the front door he has a baseball bat in the
If we get in the car
Takeoff
Educational next episode
Rosen Rebecca thank the bay and other house hunters have
Help identify nearly 50000 kit homes from Sears and other come
The next time a ragtag team of researchers armed with cameras laptops in an old Sears catalog not senior
Your door and ask if they can take a quick tour of your basement
Don't be frightened
They're there to help
And who knows
You might even be standing then
Undiscovered model
Have you ever seen a few years Schoolhouse cuz I saw that they offered
That one year
Oh yeah I've been looking for that a long time
Good Lord I've been hunting that thing down like it's my
My job
Sears homes on the only Sears architecture. In the landscape
Kurt and I talked about the Adaptive reuse of massive Sears buildings all across the u.s.
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Use the fork record that join the team at 99percentinvisible he and I started corresponding by email
Among other things he sometimes sent over story ideas
And one of those was about an old Sears building he moved into in Minneapolis
It's not a serious home it's
Tessier's plant
Huge
City Block size Warehouse
Distribution center and Retail Store
Yeah when I was really young
I used to actually go shopping list
12 story Art Deco Sears
I go there with my parents
But for most of my years in Minnesota it was just an abandoned building
I used to bike
4 miles along this overgrown railroad track
Ran past the building
A trench and
At the time that B complex
Ominous presence that you just kind of slipped passed on your bike
Can I get to close to you
So you basically don't
Engaged
It's not really something nice
If you go up to you just
Psychopathic Eckley city blocks so it was really kind of between the parking lot in the
Building was just this big empty
Depressing city
And then suddenly you know I move back to the Midwest years later
And this place is
Totally transform
It been renamed the Midtown Exchange
And it was full of all these little shops and eateries on the main floor plus offices
Apartments and condos above
And those old realtrack that I'd like the long have been cleared and paved
Turn into this Five Mile Greenway
Which was really needed service ready-made Rails to Trails
And I got really interested in this. Just as a building but also as an urban phenomenon right like how they turn the
It's nothing into something
So I naturally being architecture
Started digging into the history of stairs
And what did you find in your
And your research
Well for starters
Richard Warren Sears himself
Was born in Minnesota where he actually started selling watches
Channel 1800
10 overtime he moved operations
To Chicago and start growing out this larger mail order
And basically became the Amazon of the early 20th century
And in the 1920s
We started branching out even more adding retail outlets to their distribution centers
All the way from
Boston to
Can you show me pictures of bees they all looks
Surprisingly similar even though they're like
What's scattered across the entire us
There's some different brake Styles but they're all kind of boxy that big windows
And other details income including
These really great
Distinctive Art Deco style
Powers Yeah
Yeah they look a little bit like Castle Towers or something there a big giveaway
If you're ghetto
Hunting these concert series build
The function to they basically concealed these huge Waters
Is that didn't serve the floors below
And yeah what's you know you have the tower is in the other details
You can really easily start to spot
Other Towers
Another city
A lot of that commonality traces
Back to this one
In particular
George Coleman
He did a lot of work for
Serious
A mansion for the company president but he's mostly known for big
Stihl commercial
Among other things he worked on this really big early plan
Administrative hub
Four Seasons
But this is not the Sears Tower
Chicago Willis Tower it's something else
About actually can many decades later but amazingly it was only like half again as big as this
Really old complex
Knows about
The old complex was built a bit West of downtown and it was about
3 million square feet
The company boasted that it was the largest commercial complex in the world at
And it's been multiple blocks
Covered existing Street
Could actually blocked off city streets and I had to get special permission of course from the city to do that
In the place basically function like a city within the city
Had some power plant
It had its own
Corporate employee based Fire Department
And it even has its own radio show
WLS
Short for
Worlds large
Store commercial radio station that sell great
Yeah I mean
Sick of basically buying airtime
Giant it's America's biggest retailer
And they just kept expanding to they kept following kind of where the country
If you took down at first the
Did mail order where they serve rural populations
Then they added these mixed-use plants
With retail outlets
Surf City
And then if people moved out to the suburbs
Going to the shopping
Today obviously serious is not doing quite as well
And a lot of that complex in
Chicago for example has been torn down
But some parts are still around and some of you
Including that Central iconic
Because it's really hard
To reuse
A million +
Where feet inside of
Yeah it's incredibly difficult almost impossible to find a single corporate client take that on
I am so like the one in Minneapolis for instance it had to bring in all these different stakeholders he's our local hospital
You get to see onboard another developers so that you know there was a plan to make it next
Start
These buildings also has some advantages to 4 adapter
Yeah they're built of 30 Concrete & Masonry
And they get a lot of light
On all sides because they have these huge windows
And so when you wrote me years and years ago it was in part a story about how cities are we using these
Sears
Buildings
Yeah and that's what really fascinates me
It's it's not just you know that they're being reused but it's the story that they tell about the different cities they're being used in
So in some ways it's like this big Urban experiment
Put
These different box
But all the time of the same sort of similar in size
You spread them out across the country and you abandon them
What happened and it turns out that you get these very City specific stories of
Abandonment and reuse
Tell you something about these
Okay so what are some of your favor
Discover in Seattle
Famous for its coffee
There's an old plant south of downtown
Has been transformed into the headquarters of Starbucks
And the Los Angeles plant is being renovated right now for a long time
It was basically down to just the retail
Store on the ground floor and the rest of the building
Was empty
Of course even an empty building when you're talking about Hollywood
Has a function
You can rent it out for filming
And then a lot of cities are to follow the Minneapolis example
In Boston was the first one to do it where they just said you know we have to bring in a bunch of different programs to make this work for us
Theaters in sports complexes
Daycare centers
And Memphis and Minneapolis North
And so there's a little
Sears building
The Uptown
Oakland Uptown is you drive up Telegraph far away from beautiful Downtown Oakland California chords
A little one and what it would they use at 1
So that place is really small
And call the telegraph Lofts
Basically they're looptworks
Southern residential units
Which is probably the thing we need the most in the Bay Area
Oh yeah yeah if there's
Is there empty buildings to be used here
I would hope
Could just turn them all into Morehouse
FEMA director
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Joe Rosenberg mix and Tech production by Sheree
Yusuf music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital director
Russell team is senior editor Delaney Hall Avery trufelman
Vivien Leigh
Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
Special things to the Riggs family and the other Sears homeowners of Illinois
And to Matt domeier for driving our producer Joe Rosenberg the entire length
Illinois
Twice
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from pra
Max up your sweet independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
At radiotopia. FM
Do you find the show in discussions about the show on Facebook you can do to me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr invited to
We have lots of pictures of old Sears catalogs and the Adaptive reuse of Sears buildings on our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com