99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The year was 1982
Turn on the Eastern edge of Pennsylvania
Small city of Allentown
7 a.m. radio station called wsan
4 years in broadcast country music to the surrounding Lehigh Valley
An area known for malls Manufacturing
And Mack Trucks
But the station was about to undergo a complete identity change
Was
Coming off being a country
Station
And becoming a nostalgic
This is Ned Teeter
He was a DJ at wsa in at the time
He says that as the station transition to Nostalgia mini big band soft hits from the 50s
They wanted a gimmick to hook new listeners
Something to lure people to the sweet sounds of The Andrews Sisters and Perry Como
So
You had FM radio stations play music with really nice fidelity
You had us play music so
You had to be a little bit
Different
So
You know they're shutting up and playing the hits
Or injecting something different
Indoor ER sound in this contest well
That was a little different
Picanto
Wsan decided it would launch a good old-fashioned endurance contest
Reminiscent of the pole-sitting stunts and dance Marathon
Popular in the 1920s
Precision security local sponsor Called Love homes
Austin donate a prize
Single wide modular home with $18,000
$18,000 is
And then they devised the scheme
Wsan had a billboard in Lehigh Valley Advertising the new Nostalgia music format
If you get three contestants
Do I send a 30 ft ladder to the billboard platform
Weber State on that platform the longest would walk away with the new home
Wsan called it that you'll love to live with us contest
Air1 radio station wsan challenge their Lehigh Valley listeners to see who could stay the longest
30 feet of Bubba Highway intersects
It was supposed to be a way to get people to know we've changed our format
Look at our billboard
That's what this was supposed
About what
Wsan have grossly underestimated just how much people would endure
For a little Economic Security
I don't know if it is
Is this law of attraction or what but
I mean for the in the weeks leading up to the
Contest
People are asking me all you're out of the army been away what you going to do I said
Going to be in this contest
This is before they even threw my name
This is Dalton Young
One of the three contestants that would have been truly be chosen by wsan
He was 22 years old at the time
He just been discharged from the Army and the month before
He thought that sitting on the billboard above a highway it sounded like as good an option as any
Not good at that
Unemployment
Outrageous Dalton was so dead set on competing that he turned in a thousand entries
He carefully read the submission rules and realize that there was no specified limit to the number of times a person could submit
And it turned out he wasn't the only one who read the fine print
And have a lot of time on their hands
Here's one Kistler with his wife Sue
Amazon employee and heard about the pill work on test stand
Wasn't working
Something to do
Ron's not the chattiest person in the world
But what he lacked in conversation he made up for with determination
We heard about the contest
Gansu and deliver over 4000 entries
Directly
The wsan station
I know you were trying for 4,000
4004 so that's what we send in
Ron and Sue have been dating for a year before the contest
And they were looking to move in together
This seemed like the
Perfect opportunity
Get a place of Their Own
And I thought was a
Quick and easy way to get a house
The last of the contestant was Mike McKay
He died in 2006
Back in the early 1980s
He was the only one of the three contestants who was married
He was the only one who had a job
But even still
He couldn't afford to buy a home
Make a sentence in astronomic
47000 entries to WFAN
He use a rubber stamp with the phrase
I need a home
And then cut out and signed every piece of paper
Is submitted so many times
The first 10 entries
Pulled by the selection team
We're his
Yeah my first impression of Mike was that he
Full of Bluster
Again Dalton Young
You know if you could get past all the Bluster got a big heart and I
He's a really nice guy
Between the three of them
Dalton Ron and Mike submitted 52,004 entries
And this sounds like a lot until you consider it to
How many total entries there were
The station receive over half-a-million submissions
We had
Miracle on 34th Street right these bags of postcard
Hertz on the conference table
Spotify
There was a reason they were getting so many entries
Around the time the competition launched
The country was slogging through the worst recession it had seen in over 40 years
Good evening
I'm speaking to you tonight to give you a report on the state of our nation's economy
I regret to say
But we're in the worst economic mess
Since the Great Depression
The recession began in 1980 when the FED raised interest rates to try to fight Rising inflation
Pendragon all the way through 1982
Companies cut their spending to try to cope
And hundreds of Steel facilities and manufacturing plants closed
Including some in the Lehigh Valley
Places like Allentown where wsan was located or hit particularly hard
You got to remember the
Ground Zero the rest
Blue Collar town
Steelcon
Mack Trucks is threatening to leave Champion spark plugs and closed
The national unemployment rate was the highest since the Great Depression
Interest rate skyrocketed
20% in 1982
If you were a blue collar worker and didn't already own a house at this time
It would be incredibly tough to get one
How many people the idea of spending a little time on a billboard for a chance to win a home must have seemed like a
Pretty good deal
Before looking for better times better days
That's a big part of this this is kind of like a Rust Belt Fairy Tail
The contest officially started on September 20th 1982
Dalton Young
Ron Kessler and Mike McKay ascended the billboard to begin their stay
Cowering behind them with an advertisement
Station Reading Unforgettable
1470 wsan
Here's Dalton
It was raining that day I remember was kind of drizzly and
Crappy little bit damp and cold
And I'm in Irish traffic blown by throughout the day planes flying right over head because it was right near the
Lehigh Valley Airport
This was supposed to be about 30 days
Event
This is Jean Worley
Another DJI wsan
And one of the contest organizer
Officially is Jean world
But almost everybody around here would call me early world
Theme from 2 in the morning
Worley said that besides some local coverage when the guys went up there wasn't that much fanfare around the contest in the beginning
Even though wsan had launched the contest as a kind of promotion
They didn't do the best job of promoting it with other media Outlet
It was going on
People just
Portmanteau
There was
Mention on the other radio stations that they might have listened to
Weather articles in the newspaper
Wasn't anything on the TV news that they watch
Become additions on the billboard were pretty bare-bones
Each guy had a small tent
Radio
A landline telephone
Chemical toilet
Which is kind of like a tiny porta potty
It was almost like camping
Only you were 30 feet in the air
Surrounded by freeway traffic
Entrap
We made the guys comfortable we didn't torture own
Everything going on in there
The billboard platform itself was about 8 ft
By 48
And it has been divided into three
Cool sections
My waist high partition
The organizers at wsan wanted to contest the last long enough to draw some attention
But not
Forever
I figured that by discouraging interaction between the contestants
They might keep the whole thing to a reasonable length
And we didn't talk
At all
I don't know what we said hi to each other
But even if the guys weren't encouraged to interact with each other they still had plenty of people to keep them company
From a distance
The contest requires that the guys have their own support team to deliver food and to handle cleanup
Each contestant had a pulley system so they could raise or lower supplies in buckets or entrees
Dalton's friends and family stop by all the time to chat from Below
Mike had his wife
And Ron's parents made sure he got everything he needed
And got rid of the things he didn't
Hirsute Cussler
What his parents did a lot too
As far as bringing food
Is that was in charge of
I'm doing that
The Purge on
How is his job
Sue and Ron were dating at the time and suva's did Ron every day except one when he was up on the billboard
Strangely enough
The contest might have even made the relationship stronger
Well that's all we can do is talk so
We got to know each other
A lot better
In that time cuz
We talked everyday and
On the phone or with me
At the bottom of the billboard
Aside from the essentials each contestant was allowed to bring a non-essential item with them
Mike McKay brought a guitar which he learn to play up there
Ron Kessler brought a copy of American Rifleman magazine
Hampton
Yeah I had some nunchucks up there in fact I think I got them
As a
Deferred my birthday maybe it was
As you can imagine there was little room to do anything
And even less when Dalton has nunchucks out
But there wasn't much
Duke.
Do drawing Kistler on his daily schedule
Yeah I wake up I was having for breakfast
What's the radio Hangout
Have something for supper
What's traffic
The routine was mind-numbing
Days quietly crept by
Benmont
September wake up have something for breakfast
Tuber what's traffic
November is the radio
But if they were listening to the radio in November
They might have heard a new song
One that would help transform their sleepy lives up on the billboard into something much bigger and stranger
The song was by Billy Joel
Weather
In November of 1982
The song Allentown
Started climbing the Billboard charts
And it happened to be about the very town where wsan was located
The song painted a vivid portrait of the economic hardship working-class families were going through at the time
He was talking about companies like Bethlehem Steel in the Lehigh Valley
Shutting its doors in eliminating nearly 10000 jobs
Because of the song
The city of Allentown became a kind of stand-in for all the suffering rustbelt towns in the Northeast and Midwest
Here's Dalton young again
Yeah I think he was talking about the economy and it just happened at this contest
What's going on at 8
You know I wasn't
Stated that the office is this
This contest is because the economy so bad
Yeah we're going to try to get somebody at home that might not otherwise have one but
Yeah they both
Seem to work together really well
People started paying attention to Allentown
And the conda
81 days on the billboard for Mike McCabe
And as this media coverage expanded stories about the contest started to hit National newspapers
December 9th 1982
An article appeared in the Wall Street Journal
And the response
Was immediate the phones were ringing
Constantly all the line here's Jean early world
Wsan DJ and I have no idea what they're saying except
They're talking about people on a billboard some other time we can
Off
The air
Some information was gathered that said
The Wall Street Journal did a front-page article
Suddenly this little AM radio station which only had about a 50 mile range
Was peking a lot of interest
Allentown Pennsylvania has been receiving International publicity
No kidding from all over the world
M&L before social media
Really even before the internet some stories just did that
And you
You didn't even really know
How
This is Betty Morris the staff reporter at the Wall Street Journal who wrote that article
Where's didn't expect the story to catch on like a dead
Because of her story Dalton Ron and Mike
We're Fielding questions from People magazine Rolling Stone and Phil Donahue about their Extended Stay on the
Don't even remember getting calls from Japan New Zealand
France the landlines that they had up on the board
The French magazine
Rihanna story
In France about
The contest in
For whatever reason they put
Each of our phone numbers
So all the sudden
We're getting like
150 calls a day from
French people
You
Have no idea when you're writing stories which ones are
Are going to
Hit a nerve
I mean it was interesting to look back and see
All those
All that Paparazzi outside the billboard later
But looking back Betsy Morris understood why this particular story resonated
Then President Ronald Reagan had referred to America as
Shining City upon a hill
But life was so hard in that shining City that
Three men that can find themselves to a billboard for months
All for a chance to win a home
There was something dystopian
About it
I mean the American dream was really shaky at the
Name all the guys in the billboard never said they felt excluded by the radio station
An air of desperation did begin to
Seep into the contact as the months went by
How long do you think you'll be here
Call Maybe
I don't know
Depending on that mostly try to run that by me again
Probably 2 years
Mini you're 9 months
I'm down for summer of 84
Some summer person
They asked us how long we would stay up there and I said
Two or three years
Then I really mad at you and I was I was just
That wasn't just bravado but I figured okay
In order to save enough to get an $18,000 home
What would I be willing to invest
Time
Two to three years
When December and January arrived it started getting colder
Lowest recorded temperature was 0 degrees Fahrenheit
So the guys were getting portable heaters
Keep them from
Dying
Huge snowstorm shut down the entire city
They didn't stop the contest
According to Dalton
It was a welcome
Change of pace
You know for me I was a piece of cake enough for that whatever 24 hours or
However long 48 hours till I dug everything out it was
It was peaceful
You know it was just so quiet and so peaceful
What was great
Actually given everything the guys were going through
The isolation
The weather at the border
They were holding up surprisingly well
Here's an interview with Ron around the same time
The temperature has dropped to zero emotional 24in
You must be talking to yourself but I know how you doing psychologic
Oh I'm fine
Get out
Don't run and sting happening
Something
Happen
Was one morning there's a guy out talking to Ron and Mike stranger that Dalton hasn't seen before was down below the billboard
Chatting with the guys
He casually struck up a conversation with Dalton telling him that he was also a veteran
We were talking about our experiences in the military and some of the party and we had it done at 9
He asked me if I got high
Yeah I thought of that point of some sort of a bond you know
Aishwarya Rai
I mean he was on a billboard for 6 months
Ask me if I could get him some and ice
Tomorrow I got a little like
Departwest
Play stuck in a cigarette pack and drop it
Dalton Lord down to join
And the stranger thing to him with a $20 bill
I said look man
You don't know I exist I exist I thought why don't you know
Twenty bucks twenty bucks I'm not going to turn it down you know
Get a phone call early in the morning and probably be
Before 5
This is my Christ
Executive director of the hgf
The company that was funding the contras
He remembers getting a call from a contest organizer
Zane have a good time telling the boss this while I got busted for drugs Isis what highlights of how can it be selling
Drugs from urine
30 feet up on a billboard
Apparently the strangerhood solicited
The pot from Dalton
Have been an undercover police officer
Cuz Dalton accepted that $20
He was arrested on drug charges
It made the front page of the
The Philadelphia Inquirer at I think
The same day that the Reagan announces missile defense
So marriage Reagan's missile-defense system and theirs
There's adult being busted on the
Turn on the front page
Dalton was knocked out of the competition on day 184
I'm probably the only person in history to be arrested
It's on fire
Billboard
And yes there were plenty of rumors that don't have been setup
Maybe one of the other guys were poured into the police or maybe one of the contest sponsor is
Speed along the end of the canto
None of this was actually
Proven
Got it
It's really really
Fishing
Run Mike both descended from the billboard to testify in court
Add breakfast
Quick shower
And then went right back up on the billboard to finish out the contest
Rodger Dalton's arrest
Competition felt
Different
Here's Ned Teeter again
On the wsan DJs
We have this contest
And
These people be coming
Every man hero
It's a great story
It's heartwarming
And then over two joints of marijuana Dalton get
Hold off
I think that's one thing
I think that's when things went from
How is this thing going to end
By this point the competition has become a huge annoyance for Town officials
The town commissioner even describe the contest as a hemorrhoid
And wanted it stopped
Officials here at Town Hall equally disillusion with a contest
I've contemplated sending the housing inspector to evicted contestant
The billboard has no Plumbing or smoke alarm
And the town's already sent them bills for residency
Teatox listening to billboard
The Ron Kessler and Mike McKay had dug their heels in deep
Neither would come down unless they were coming down to a new home
Decision that received more publicity than it ever needed
At this point is it become a burden
Wsan had the attention of the world
But nothing to say
We were radio
Marketing maven
Ron and Mike lasted 2 months Beyond Dalton's drug bust
Before wsan cave
And realize that enough was enough
When it became obvious neither man would quit and both threatened to stay forever if necessary
The station declared the contest a draw
And lured them in down by offering duplicate prices for each
They had captured the attention of the region when they came down today
On June 7th 1983 Ron and Mike both step down off their respective ladders at the same time
They've been up on the billboard for 261 days nearly nine months
When an entire time they had taken only one shower
I'm really happy with the fans
The station had received some criticism around the contest
People that accuse them of exploiting the guys
So wsan actually up the prizes to try to repair some of the Damage Done their reputation
Ron and Mike both walked away
With a modular home
Chevy Chevette
Ana free vacation
This wasn't supposed to be this
It wasn't supposed to be the big International global
Almost year-long thing
The men reacted very differently and their post contest lines
Mike tried to recreate the fame he had when he was up on the board
That never really happen
But when he died in 2006
Is obituary still referred to him by his preferred nickname
Billboard Mike
He was the guy that you would say
This was my high water mark this to find me
I think that
That Mike McKay was the one that loved at the most
Steel of being billboard mic
At least he made off better than.
I got 6 months probation in it
And $100
Course I do if I fell
Ron Kessler
Quiet determination the other hand
Probably gotten the closest to that rustbelt fairytale ending
Cansu married shortly after the contest end date
They lived happily in their two bedroom modular home for 20 years
Raise the daughter in it
I moved on with their lives
At the end of the day you've got
Three guys that
Did something crazy
Try and just get a little bit ahead of the
I mean remember these guys weren't looking for a mansion or a Jet Plane
We're just looking for a start
A very special thanks
Pat Taggart and Frank petka episode was adapted from their fantastic feature-length documentary billboard boy
What's available right now on Amazon and iTunes
What happens when you take away all the Billboards
They did it in the city in Brazil
We'll talk about that
After that
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
Cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
But it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
In Allentown a single billboard became a much bigger sign of the times
What started as a simple radio promotion ended up shedding light on a larger economic and housing crisis
Decades later
Something similar would happen in Sao Paulo Brazil
But this time it was about the removal
A billboard
Words that reveal
A bigger story
Percocet is here to talk about
So in the early 2000s
Littered with
That's including around 15000
Billboards
It is this visual pollution got worse people became
Increasingly frustrated you know it
Private companies be allowed
Basically brand Publix
Space
The bear comes along and proposes a
Clean city law
To get rid of
All kinds of
Business Signs posters
It all had to go
Even handing out marketing Flyers industry
Illegal
So extreme
Businesses must not have been happy about that at all
Yeah they really weren't I mean this was a city full of ads and suddenly
But this proposed law have a ton of Publix
Support
And predictably Business Leaders fought
Corporate lobbyists are you better be bad for the economy would compromise
They also tried to scare people with the idea that public tax money would be needed to remove all this
Supporting infrastructure you know that the poles in the scaffolding
Around these billboards
There is even an argument that Commercial Graphics were useful as we fighting
Helping people navigate the city
Bus at night you were lit up signs would make us any less safe
And so on
So I guess some of those arguments make some sound
But
They all seem to be rooted primarily
Absolutely
Timothy end
Business Advocates loss
The law passed in businesses were given 90 days to comply or to start paying fines
Until the ad started coming down and suddenly the city did looked at
Enter some old architecture was uncovered
Pulling down All Those ads
Also revealed some
Other hidden tasks
What kind of things
Stripping away huge billboard alongside major roads
Sprint students ended up
Entire Shantytown neighborhoods that have been visually fence
Lights off
Bayat
And then I'm beside the factories where they were these Billboards covering up Windows
Removing them actually revealed immigrants living where they were
Essentially they weren't being paid enough to afford
And the absence of ads in general right like sort of the decolorization of the city
Put a lot of focus on crumbling
Fracture ICD-10
The spotlight
So what about all those concerns from Business Leaders about
People not be able to wayfinder into dark at night
And it turns out that yes people can still find a way around cities without ads
And a lot of building owners ended up repeating their facade
So
A lot of structures ended up looking better and worse think of any
So this all started like a decade ago
Is Sao Paulo still
Totally add free today
Samantha Baxley been allowed back out
But it's
How much more controlled than
There's this
New awareness about how things look
Super example there these interactive search engine ads at bus shelter
But let Riders look up the weather where they're going
And
Part of the deal is that marketers have to actually take care of those bus shelter
So kind of like that. The highway program you put a little ADD
As long as you provide
Something good for the community
Technology twist
And I was actually just reading about something else that the current mayor proposed last year
His ideas to reintroduce
Exactly 32 billboard
Each one for one of the 32 main bridges that run around the city
Any idea there is that marketers can advertise on these only if they agree to
Tua maintain that bridge
Peach cobbler
Like the bus shelters they have to use
Some of the visual displays based
Actually show useful
Like traffic updates
The time in the
Very cool
See how I said he goes about
Selectively reintroducing advertising once they start with a
The Clean Slate
Yeah it's something that you know most cities
Just aren't like they just never ever ever get a chance
And tell you when you do you want to be deliberate and you want to make sure
For the public good it's a really great experiment a set of watch unfold
We have some pictures of these in the website oh yeah
Quite stunning
I get out at 9 p i. Org thanks
99percentinvisible
Bruce's sweet by Vivien Leigh makes intek production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real Katie mingle is our senior producer
That is the digital director of senior editor is Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald turn Mazza and me Roman Mars
Thanks again to the boys team who are just delightful to work with our movie is so fun to watch but we're boys is a
Available on Amazon and iTunes additional info is available at billboard boys.com
We are Brotherhood 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio Row in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX fiercely independent Collective of the most innovative
YouTube shows in all of podcasting fun mall at radiotopia. FM
Facebook me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi or run Instagram
Tumblr and Reddit to we have pictures of Ed field and add freeze El Pollo at 9 p.m.
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast
Dot-com