99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
For most of his life Sam Anderson didn't think about Oklahoma City much at all
Sam is a journalist he lived in New York City for a long time
In Oklahoma City just wasn't on his radar
But then in 2012
He was assigned to do a story
About the Oklahoma City Thunder
The city's new basketball team had just gone to the NBA finals
And they had this amazing Trio of young Stars Kevin Durant
Russell Westbrook
And James Harden
They were all really different players
We could really different temperaments and styles
There was something kind of
Magical and Unstoppable about the way they played together
Suzanne got on a plane and as you was flying to Oklahoma City to meet the guys and to write about their team
He was reading a book about the history of Oklahoma to get more familiar with
And it was talking about the origin of tornadoes
And it was saying that tornadoes are caused
By this Collision
Three separate
Very different weather forces
You got kind of dry air coming from the desert you got this
Cold Arctic air coming down from Canada and you got this warm
Heavy Hot golf
Air coming from the south
And they all Collide over Oklahoma in a way that those forces don't Collide really anywhere else in the world
At that moment Sam had a realization and he wrote it down in the margin of the book
Harden Durant
Westbrook
Which was the three big basketball stars in the Thunder who were a similar
Trio of
Strangely clashing forces
That basketball I've never really seen before so
In that little leap like I was noticing
This dematic Echoes between
Things about the history of Oklahoma and things about the basketball team and the kind of civics of the modern
These kinds of connections everywhere
The history of Oklahoma City started to seem so into woven with the Contemporary life of
The place and he's fascinating and unexpected ways
He decided he wanted to write
Hoboken
Not just about the basketball team but
About the city itself from its founding which was
Really very weird event
To the present day
The book is called Boomtown
Is one of my favorite things I've read in the past year I think it'll go down in history as one of the great pieces of narrative nonfiction
So today we're dedicating entire episode
To my conversation with Sam
There's so many interesting chapters in antidotes in this book but I wanted to focus primarily
Aliens
Scene founding of Oklahoma City
In the bed
That's known
As the land run of 1889
Understand that story
If you go back to
Just a little bit further to earlier in the 1800's
When Oklahoma wasn't even a state yet
Is a place known
As Indian Territory
The US government was kind of using it as the spot on the Great Plains
Medical
Force
Indigenous peoples into
To make room for
American settlers as they took over the country so
Got dozens of tribes that were forced into their all the Trails of Tears lead to Oklahoma
So that's what it was in the 1800's
Then during the Civil War
Couple of tribes in Indian Territory made alliances with the South
Rather than the North
And as punishment after the war
The federal government strip them of their land
This left an enormous patch of unoccupied space
Right in the middle of the territory
Roughly half the size of Connecticut
It's a fairly big space
And
Suddenly just had nobody in it and everybody referred to this patch of Indian Territory
Has the unassigned lands in 18 60s and 70s white settlers from the surrounding areas like Kansas
Texas started making illegal raids into the unassigned lands
The leader of this group
Known as the Boomers
Was a guy named David Payne
Apparently it's incredibly charismatic
I mean the pictures of him he's quite striking Yeezys
Really intense eyes in this kind of
Beautiful hair he looks like he could be
So you ride around Kansas
And get up on a wagon and
Shout out these speeches to the struggling Farmers about how
There was this patch of America that
Belongs to the American people that the government wouldn't let him have it and he managed to convince
Many many many people to buy into his vision of Oklahoma's is kind of sacred Holy Land
For white settlers in the middle of Indian Territory
And this is the beginning of
The scheme that was the land run which
You talk about is being the craziest way that a city could possibly have been born so can you describe
What are the ground rules
Of the land run and then how did it start Oklahoma City
Yasso modern historians looking back
Basically all agree that this was the worst way you could ever start a city
Even within those confines it went very poorly
So there really were not
Many rules I mean so the government finally says yes all right
You can have the unassigned lands
Anybody who wants a piece of it
So we're going to do
Come lineup
At the border the unassigned lands this is a 300 mile long
Circumference
In most places it's not marked
Where does Marcus like a
A stack of rocks or creek or something
So come line up around this border
April 22nd
And at noon
We will give a signal
And anybody who want some of this land
Can Rush In
Wooden Stakes
Claim some of this territory if you're out in the country you can have a hundred and sixty Acres
If you're in what's
Designated a town site you can have a smaller
Patch of that town site
And that's pretty much it
Even the basics of this
Is amazing because
Who decides what Nunez in 1889
You know I'm saying
Yeah right right there's not like a standardized atomic
Clock somewhere
I can set off a digital precise signal
So people had to kind of figure out for themselves
What noon was
And people came from all over the world to set off like a real movement
Around the globe
You had people in Europe
Like
Coming to the Liverpool and coming to Hamburg to like ship out to get to Oklahoma you had people
Putting classified ads in major newspapers in Chicago New York to let's meet up and form an alliance and
Make a plan and go to Oklahoma and claim some land
For the day itself you had something like a hundred thousand people
Show up to line up
At the border and make a run
So noon strikes
Maybe at different times for different people on the 300 mile border
What what happens next
So noon strikes
Quote-unquote noon
In some places there are
Soldiers giving the signal so everyone has to wait
Up north the soldiers are
Have this long rope that they pulled across part of the border that people are held behind
Down south there's a river that people are sitting on their horses like in the middle of the river sort of sinking in quicksand waiting for
The signal
And then
In some cases they fired guns in some cases they blue
Bugle
And they're off
And you had you know rich people poor people people riding the
The family wagon
Your people on racehorses that they just bought like the day before you add people riding broken down mules there were people in fights
Physical therapy
But
And they just burst across the border and start racing in this land is rough it's like
I'm either of their
Dry creek beds all over there Buffalo wallows were buffalo
Roll around
And
Immediately these wagon start hitting these ruts
And just busting a nut Vehicles intended for
We know rough Riding High Speed so these vehicles are busting apart and people are flying out of them at rolling across the Prairie
Getting up and running forward
It's just wild I mean people shooting guns to speed up their horses and accidentally shooting each other
Horses are dying of exhaustion
I think it's just about the wildest seeing you can imagine
And this is
Complicated even more
By the people who really cheated who started way before noon
And they became known
A progressively at first
As the Sooners
And the suitors are still part
The modern-day mythology of Oklahoma even today
Yeah right I mean Boomer and sooner are words that you'll hear
A lot
Oklahoma
Carroll College football game it's actually a thing that the crowd yells back and forth
Boomer Sooner
Right University of Oklahoma football team is actually called the Sooners it's this identity that Oklahomans really embracing it
I know you'll hear that like on ringtones in people's phones and stuff so
Yeah there is a real through-line in the identity of Oklahoma
So the Boomers were the ones who agitated for the opening of the unassigned lands
Sooners were people who
When
The date of the land run was finally set
Managed to
Cheat
A lot of them happen to be Boomers as well because the Boomers felt particularly entitled
To this land
Because they're the ones who did the work
To get the government to allow them in so they kind of resented all these other people who were just showing up the last minute
All kinds of ways to
The cheat I mean there were
There were stories of like
Hot air balloonist
Hovering over Oklahoma
Just before noon so that you could just touch down on his favorite spot when the bugle was blown
I mean there were many many many camps of people who were hiding out in this kind of
Goalies in
And along creeks
He's kind of sooner
Champs
But the federal troops would come through and disperse in the weeks leading up to the land run in and they reassemble
William couch who had taken over the Boomer movement
Was one of the main cheaters and he was deeply connected the railroads and so he and his
Businessmen cronies
Actually went in many times is incredible picture of him and one of his associates standing
In what is now downtown Oklahoma City
I was just then this absolute empty scrubby grass
Prairie
A month before the land run
Mapping out how they wanted the city to look
And so
When the signal is given
Theoretically should have taken people
Maybe an hour plus to get there because it was 15 miles from the closest border
And yet the moment the bugle blue
You had people including William couches cronies
Leaping out of the bushes jumping out of train cars
Falling out of trees
This mythological origin story where people just suddenly appear out of the landscape
And the soldiers don't know what to do cuz there's so many of them in there just planting tents all over in hammering stakes and William couch and his crew
Have a whole team of surveyors who have all their equipment their chains and poles and everything in there laying outside
As they have mapped it in the months
Proceeding the land run
Part
The labor of making Oklahoma into a real place after this was adjudicated all of that cheating
Who cheated and who didn't
Who deserve to keep their land
2 didn't
Because they
They settled the land as settlers not as city builders exact
But you didn't
Account for the things that make a city function they really just
Flooded out their own land for their own private use
Such a little is such a nice little metaphor in a way for
I don't know the American experiment the American temperament
Exactly you had
Huge wave of people rushing in
I mean waves from all sides
And what everyone was thinking about was
I need to get mine
Got a
Anchor down in this place so that whatever comes of it I'll have my peace
So there was no Central planning there was no foresight whatsoever
And so
By the end of the day on the site that would become Oklahoma City
You had
Something like ten thousand settlers
And they had claimed
Pretty much every single patch
Of land
I mean they were like it was just like
Tent flaps
Tent flap almost
You didn't have
Any of the negative space
But you really need for a city to work he didn't have
Streets you didn't have a lease
Other than the part of the city that had been mapped out by these cheaters and they managed to sell certificates to own
Phone Lots
On the land they had plot it out
But otherwise it was just a giant
Absolute mess they could never
Going forward function as
A place where humans live
Huge influx of people
Clean different parts of the land and this is done day one of the founding of Oklahoma City
What happens
That first night
See you this incredible chaotic recipe
They all managed to
Claim a spot
Found some spots you know there's
There's five separate settlers
Claiming that they were there first so you have all these disputes
All kinds of activity
When the sun sets at night
You get this kind of General relaxation everybody stops
Jogging
4 plots
Everyone stops their work
People kind of relax
And look around
Andres
And
Again because this was so recent we have all these eyewitness accounts we have news accounts that were reporters on the ground
So we know things like
Centipede crawling around everywhere because of course the whole ecosystem has just been shocked
Intuit agitation by this injection of humans into it for no reason
And
So you have this incredible scene of just tents as far as you can see
Masses of
Brand new people have never been to this place before most of them
Most of whom have no connection to one another at all
And
The one story that really stand out from that first night
Sometime around 10 p.m. or midnight
Accounts vary a little bit
It's quiet it down
And then a voice suddenly calls out
Silence
It's a man's voice
Is a realist
Really strong loud
Low voice
And what he calls out
Very clear in the night air but also totally inscrutable
Ojo
Here's your mule
Everybody kind of looks around
Every story about what that means
It might have been a reference to an old Confederate song or maybe the people in the camper
Talking about thing that actually happened that night
There was a guy named Joe with a neighboring lot
Smule had wandered off
This guy found it
But what happens is more interesting than whatever started because
Within a few seconds another voice Echoes that one
The dojo here's your mule
And then somebody else that goes it
Somebody else
And soon it turns into this life
Absolute
Bizarre party
Of everybody in Oklahoma City
Shouting so here's your mule over and over and over again
It's just resonating over the whole town site
And they say actually it was so loud that the federal troops
Who were stationed about a mile away for the night
Heard it and they started calling it back to
MN settlers on the outside of town heard in they started calling it out too and so you just have this cacophony of people shouting Ojo
Joe here's your mule
Some people say that it's spread that night from settler to settler all the way a hundred miles north
Back to the Kansas line where this hold message begun
Was the first night
This is kind of the moment that you cite is when
You that although settlers kind of become a town
I mean psychologically
It's hard to put yourself out there but
It's got to be the craziest day of everyone
Life
You know they've been through it all kinds of hardship
Hunger and thirst
Everyone is armed
The teeth and everyone's arguing and you don't know if you're getting a good spot or a bad spot
Your Wagon broke and you almost broke your arm and you know etcetera Etc
And then suddenly at night you get this bizarre
Sort of communal
It's almost like a sing-along or something you know
And yeah so all these people who are completely unrelated to one another
Arrived at this new and strange place in this kind of
Tidal wave
Selfishness
You know
Or something participating in this
Community Awakening and I
I feel like that must have been this
Incredibly intense
Bonding experience
That started
To help this very strange collection of
People become
An actual
Collective
Do we go forward and and become a real City
A video Joe incident
On the second day of Oklahoma City's existence
Two different leaders emerged
It was William couch
Who was the de facto leader of the Sooners also known as the cheaters
He had plotted and schemed in order to enrich himself by selling landscape gets in this one part of the city
And then there was Angelo Scott
Put come to Oklahoma during the land run
He was a hyper educated lawyer from Kansas
Who was this
Very high-minded and decent guy who did not approve of the cheater faction and their lands games
So he said about trying to create some order
Chaos
Loss of this new city
After oh Joe here's your mule after the chaos of that first day
Everybody wakes up
Everyone has been able to sleep
And they look around
And they realize
Oh my gosh this place
Is a mess
There's no room
To fit in an alley between these
Private properties
Angela Scott is one of the people who steps up and says well
Let's figure this out
And he gives actually in the second bells to
Three kids and puts them on little horses and sends them riding all around Oklahoma City ringing their bells and saying
Come to a big town meeting
And
Thousands of people come
Angela Scott steps up onto the wooden crate
He kind of lays it out for everybody says listen
Here's Where We Are
Our town is chaos
We have one faction of people
QR
Trying to impose order on it
By cheating
He says one of the ironies of the places that they could have had
Absolute peace
If they had adopted this
The cheaters plan for the city but it would have been on the basis of absolute fraud
How to figure out
Some other way to do it
Lewis God helps organize an election in which a Citizens committee comes together
The job of that committee is to go around the whole town
Educating every lot figuring out who can stay and who can go and what land needs to be seized and turned the streets
Alleys in public spaces
It's like this ad hoc
On-the-fly town planning
And so they went lot by lot by law
And work their way their Way North
Until they reached the
Southern edge of the cheaters
Part of town
And waiting for them there were
Men
Holding Winchester rifles
Who said
That's fine that you've done that
Down there
But I think you better leave this part of town alone
This could have been the moment but the city teetered into Civil War
Instead
Angela Scott organized another Mass meeting
And it came up
The compromise plan
So in the end they had to do something that was really abhorrent
To someone like Angelo Scott into a lot of people
But it was the only way
Two kind of Stitch the city together without
Actually breaking into violence
So what they did was
These two different plans the the citizens committee plan down south
And the Boomers plan of North
Part of the problem reconciling them was that they been laid out at slightly different angle
This meant that even if they try to stitch these two parts
So tell him together
It would be very difficult because the streets
Wouldn't match up
And so
The compromise they settled on was to build
What they called jog
Which are these kind of diagonal Street
The connect
The two different
Secrets
And Angela Scott called them
The scars of a bloodless confit
And
So essentially just imagine Walking Dead
Street
And then you come to an intersection and you have to
Turn kind of 10 ft to the left
Keep walking straight along that street
Is a nightmare for traffic it cause traffic jams forever
Act
You can still go stand on these drugs in the modern Oklahoma City street grid they have not been
Ironed out
Up the street grid
It's amazing they could still see it through this day two people know why it is the way it is
In Oklahoma City
I think most people don't
Probably know it's just kind of there funky little downtown
When we come back after the break we're going to talk with Sam Anderson about his favorite research discovery of a
Is entire career
I think I could write 800 books
Never make another Discovery as amazing and improbable
As operation Bongo so I'd be delighted to tell you the story of operation Baga
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa Model X
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black Box
So if you remember the thing that took Sam Anderson Oklahoma City to begin with
It wasn't the history of the land run
It was
Nike basketball team
The Oklahoma City Thunder
For many decades
Oklahoma City
Had not been considered the kind of city that could support
A major pro sports team
And yet suddenly
In 2008
It had this
NBA basketball team and got it was
By taking it
From Seattle
Oklahoma City Thunder used to be
This great classic NBA franchise called the Seattle SuperSonics
These lovely green and yellow uniforms and some great Superstar players over the years
And so I had to write this history of the taking of a professional team from one city to another
And in the course of writing that
The question occurred to me why are the Seattle SuperSonics
Call Dad
I grew up at this time but I never thought to
To question the name
So I started researching well where did this name come from
This let me down the rabbit hole
It turned out that Seattle have gotten its basketball team back in the 1960
Exactly the same moment when the United States was trying to launch its new futuristic world-changing program
Commercial supersonic flight
This is the idea that airplanes wood
Zoom around the world traveling faster than the speed of sound
Boeing which is based in Seattle
What's at the center of a lot of that development
So you got this program
SuperSonics program and you got this brand new basketball team
And in this great moment of
Civic
Sports
Synergy
They name the basketball team the Seattle SuperSonics
So that was a nice story and I thought cool
What happened to the American Supersonics
Program like I never
I've never flown in a suit
Supersonic jet
Dummy anyone I know has either so
Why did this not happen
Rabbit hole
And this is what led me to operation Bongo
If you are trying to launch a nationwide program
Of SuperSonic commercial flight where everyone's going to be whipping around the continent and the world in a matter of
You know minutes or hours
Then you have a lot of things to worry about there's all kinds of engineering problems
It's very expensive etcetera Etc
In addition to all of that
You have a very serious potential PR problem
Which is
When you break the sound barrier
Famously
You create this gigantic
Rumbling down from the sky to Sonic Boom air molecules actually get Crush
Crushed and then as Bay
Kind of
Expand again
Thunderous noises actually exactly the same
Mechanism that makes thunder
BFA
Boeing had to ask themselves
If we are raining down
Cacophonous booms
For the citizens of the United States
Thousands of times a day
Is everyone
Going to go crazy
And
They figured well
In order to test it
We're going to have to find
An actual American city
To be a guinea pig for this program
In Oklahoma City raises and it said we can meet up
Yeah that's my jaw hit the floor I couldn't believe it Oklahoma City raised it and if I have the Chamber of Commerce who's this kind of
Shadow government of business
Powers in the town
Raised his hand and said yes yes
A lot of money and
Probably most importantly this this mile-long super sonic Runway at the airport so they Oklahoma City which is all
Always trying to overachieve as a city
Would suddenly
Going to be in Pole Position
Finviz
Worldwide New Movement of SuperSonic flight
It didn't go through no citizens were asked the government approve of it the city government
They just said
Pick us in the FAA said
Yeah let's do it
In 1964 in February
The people of Oklahoma City or awakened
First thing in the morning by
Sonic boom that just comes out of nowhere Thunderclap out of a nice
Clear
Sky
And
Did you know there
People's houses are shaking and glasses are breaking and stuff like that no one knows where it's coming from
And that was the beginning and this was
This was officially known as operation Bongo
And it was set to go for 6 months
With eight times a day on a regular schedule
Within a week there were
Over 600 official complaints to the city from citizens because he's booms
Where real problem I mean their list
They're published list of the damage that it did to people's houses and it's like
It's like
How plaster walls were cracking
Ceiling fans were falling out in in
Injuring children at school
Like some I talk to somebody told me his
Fishbowl
Exploded
Some stuff is really an intense
Experian
Of course I didn't know why was happening and so
Wow
Finally the city council had to figure out what was going on and said to the Chamber of Commerce this has to stop and the Chamber said no no you don't understand
This is our chance.
To become a major American city
And in Toledo a worldwide movement
I saw this city
The city government stepped back and they let it go on it went on for 6 months
There was one day off
On Easter
And it drove the people nuts they did this systematic polling of the citizens
Were they asking all these questions about how they were feeling about the
Apocalyptic roaring coming from the sky
Constantly and
Turns out people really hate it
This is heartbreaking
Official document published at the end of
The experiment
Full of grass all these graphs of
Of the misery of the people of Oklahoma City just kind of rising and rising and Rising throughout the six-month.
And it was
So bad that
By the end of it
Killed the supersonic program
The prototypes for this thing it was just unworkable it was just it just couldn't happen
On any large-scale
The people of Oklahoma City
In the
Seattle
SuperSonics program
And then
40 years later
Till the Seattle SuperSonics and turn them into the Oklahoma City Thunder
I mean it's just that it sounds like the most made-up thing of all time I could not believe it when I
That's amazing
99percentinvisible with produces sweet by Delaney Hall
Mixing Tec production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean Rihanna
Katie mingle is our senior producer of coal state is the digital director
Wrestling team is Avery Shuffle
Joel Rosenberg
Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
Full title of Sam Anderson's book is
Boom Town the Fantastical Saga of Oklahoma City
It's chaotic founding its apocalyptic weather its purloined basketball team
And the dream of becoming a world-class Metropolis
These truly great go get it
We are products of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
AM radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX of fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Sinhala podcast
You can find them all
I radiotopia
Nfm
You can find the show enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook can you treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
YouTube Asking All the Glory of everything 99% invisible
And 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com