99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Anyone who has had kids knows that they go through obsessive phases
I can last anywhere from a few days
To several years
I went through a lot of phases growing up
Best producer Emmett Fitzgerald
There was a brief train phase then in preschool I was obsessed with farming equipment
I could list obscure European tractor Brands off the top of my head like an old
Italian wheat farmer
But I think my most intense obsession
Like many kids
Was dinosaur
As all the certain that I Would One Day become a paleontologist
I don't know exactly where this dinosaur Obsession came from but I think
Part of it was just a dinosaur
I had all these books still with Incredible drawing
Colorful dinosaurs leaving around roaring and tearing into one another
I fell in love with the artwork in those books
At least for the time being part is the only way we experience dinosaur
We can study bones and fossils
The barn the invention of time travel were some Jurassic Park Resurrection scenario
We will never see these animals with our own eyes
There no photos or video
Which means that we want to
Picture how they look
Someone has to drama
Hello
I'm Doctor Robert Butler
Known to the folks
North Texas as Jurassic Bob
I dig bones
Dinosaur bones
Bob Barker is one of the most famous living paleontologist
He also happens to be a very skilled paleo artist
He thinks the two go hand in
Aren't
Is very important in teaching Natural History signs maybe all signs
Teach everyone art
And everyone music to patterns
I like Bob a lot
When I interviewed him in a studio in Boulder Colorado you show our orally
He brought his own snacks
He's got snacks
He's got coffee and simatai
Free range apple pie this is so River of this place
Just so well
Boulder
Cage-free apple pie
Once we got started with our interview Bob said that like me he got obsessed
Two dinosaurs in dinosaur art
Pretty early on
How I got a hook
What's a piece of Journalism
From 1950
3 Life Magazine cover story called
The world we live in
Annie's pictures of dinosaurs and whatnot
The cover image was the head of a long neck dinosaur sitting in a swamp
Munching on grass
What is stegosaurus in the background
Staring off
In the space
It was this article about evolution
After
2 hours without Life Magazine
Announce to my startled parents
Mom and Dad I want to grow up in
Invertebrate paleontology
And dad had no expression
And Mom smiled and said that's nice dear
It's a stage alive grow
But unlike me dinosaurs weren't just a childhood
Good face for grass
Bob
By the time he headed off to college
A career in vertebrate paleontology was
Still The Game Plan
But it was kind of a strange time to be entering the field
In the mid-twentieth century American dinosaur science was in a bit of a rut
Dinosaurs were considered big
Dumb
Cold-blooded
Evolutionary failures
Dustin
Extinction
And that stores affected how they were painted and drawn
Most of the paintings of dinosaurs
They're not
Losing
Interacting
But each other
There's no spark of intelligence social life
And their bodies were like
Poking masses of Flesh
The white brontosaurus and Diplodocus
The biggest dinosaurs Illustrated they were like Giant
Gray
Vacuum cleaners
With very very short legs and they were slowly
Pulling themselves
Across the landscape or
Sitting neck-deep
Ineffective
Swamped
Dinosaurs were often drawn sitting in swamps like on that Life magazine cover
The thinking was they were so large they couldn't
Possibly hold up your own body weight
And if they were drawn on land they usually drag their fat tail behind them
As they walked
That's where we were
In the early 1960
Dinosaurs were sad
Cold blooded dead-ends in the history of life
But paleontology was about to go through a spectacular and
Unanticipated u-turn
And a young Bob Barker
Just off to college
Would find himself right in the thick of the app
Freshman year
The Yale geology Department took me
Bunch of other freshmen
Today
The trip out west was led by one of Bob's professors at Yale
A paleontologist named John AUST
And among other things we dug up
4 wraps
They were a new species of raptor
That Professor Austin named Deinonychus
Terrible claw
And the bones were found really close together
Assimilate
They live together that were pack maybe intelligent
But what really got Professor awesome excited was the anatomy of the skeleton
After studying the fossil remains back at Yale also concluded that
Swamp creature
Nippon fleet-footed
Agile and extremely active
Ocean began to argue that if you really looked
Did the anatomy of many dinosaurs
They look less like Mom brain lizards
And more like super atleta
Like birds
And his student Bob Bakker found this idea really compelling
Members looking at a skeleton of a different dinosaur called
Ready to look like a roadrunner with a long ponytail
But wow
Just spoke
Sylheti
But then you read the text books and I'm supposed to believe that
As an undergraduate Bakker dissected modern animal
In an effort to better understand dinosaur musculature
He concluded that the old stereotypes about
Stupid sluggish dinosaurs
Didn't hold up
They weren't slowing
Sloppy
Now this idea wasn't totally new
Packer says that for decades going back as early as the mid-nineteenth century
There have been people saying that dinosaurs were
Smart active
And bird like
But
These
Facts
We're forgotten about really sweet
Dropped out of textbooks
So Bakker decided to publish a paper in a Yale Journal
And his editor says
I know what you should call
The study and I said what
She said you should call it
The superiority
Dinosaurs
Yeah
They weren't The evolutionary hasbeens
They weren't dead ends in the
Flow
Of darwinian process
Top-of-the-line big beat everybody
But convincing people that dinosaurs were actually totally different than they had been depicted the past 60 years
It's going to require more than a few good academic papers
The really change people's minds
Sometimes you gotta show
Instead of tell
And remember Bakker was a skilled illustrator as well as a scientist
And so when John Ostrom wrote his
Definitive paper on Deinonychus
Deus Bakr to do the illustration
And I positioned the bones as if
Kids Raptor
What's running
In the picture of the Raptor is nearly parallel with the ground
Is left leg springing forward it's right leg curl
Highly against its torso
Preparing for the next drawing
Potato is high in the air
It's beautiful
And kind of terrifying
Ostrom put the picture right on the front of his paper
And it quickly became an iconic drawing
No one has ever seen anything quite like it
DACA is like a renegade
This is Darren Naish
Paleontologist based in the UK
He's got like a flamboyant
John Bushey bed
Android from the late sixties when he's in a stocking stuffer this stuff
He's he's drawing these agile active
Dinosaurs
Docker finish up at Yale and went off to graduate school
Where he continued to speak truth
The Slowdown dinosaur establishment
Hero academic and popular articles about how impressive dinosaurs have been
Any Illustrated them all himself
He drew dinosaurs bounding across
The prehistoric landscape like
Track and field stars
With live muscular bodies
Safe from the storm would have been drawn as like a Godzilla type animal dragon
Style on the ground
On the back of you got this thing shown with massive
Bulging muscle
And Packers athletic dinosaurs became a model for other paleo artist
So when my Deinonychus
Drawing appeared
Some
Artist younger than I
Okay
And we can do it
Artists like Gregory Paul Embrace this new exciting vision of dinosaurs
They started giving their dinosaurs vibrant colors
Occasionally feather
Really emphasize their bird nests
Images of
Colorful dinosaurs were everywhere
And they helped fuel the revolution that was taking place in paleontology
Throughout the 70s more and more paleontologists got on board with Ostrum and baugher's theories
They found new fossils and footprint evidence suggesting that dinosaurs have been warm-blooded intelligence
And birth like
This. Has become known as the dinosaur Renaissance
A moment when we totally rethought all of our assumptions about these incredible prehistoric animal
Indi Rene
Thanks art
Was a huge part of its success
I think that
Part of the
The reason
That was on soles of Darkness overnight
Baca
Drew in so many scientists in the 1670s boss because it was accompanied
But brilliant visuals
If anyone missed out on this Scientific Revolution and still thought that dinosaurs were
For slow and stupid
That ended in 1993
The dinosaurs in Jurassic Park are very
The dinosaurs of Jurassic Park 1990
Dial the dinosaur
Dinosaurs
And when that movie came out the whole world got to see these Fierce athletic creatures
Running through kitchens in
Eating lawyer's office
The toilets
And once you've seen the dinosaurs in Jurassic Park
You can't
I think it's cemented the notion of athletic
Dinosaur
This is John Conway
He draws dinosaurs for a living
I'm a title artist which means that
I
Door and paint
Prehistoric animals
Conway got interested in paleoart after reading Bob Barker
And in the early part of his career
Super lean muscle
But after a while he started to feel kind of funny about it
He says all the dinosaurs look like they had been
United suction
Pack your pack your clothes and you put the
Vacuum cleaner on it and you suck all the air out
Shrinks it down
That's what about dinosaurs
Putting skin on them and then vacuuming a
Anything
There was in between that
Skin on the muscle
No paleoartist weren't just doing that to make their dinosaurs look all cool and buff
They were trying to be accurate
I am Poppy
The generation
Ohio law office
The crew up
Young age when we first start
To think that it really mattered
Set things right
And to get things right you want your art to be rooted in real scientific evidence
And the piece of evidence resolved in the skeleton
Paleo artist wood base the shape of their dinosaurs on an accurate skeleton
The bones give you a pretty good idea where the muscle should go but soft tissues likes
Fat are much harder
That usually doesn't survive for millions of years and fossils
So without any evidence of it
Paleoartist tended to be pretty conservative about how much fat they gave their dinosaurs
Which makes
Total since you're not going to add something that you don't have evidence
But the result was that all these dinosaurs look like they went to the gym three times a day
And drink protein shakes for every meal
Done, it says
It began to feel as though paleo artist had replaced one Orthodoxy with another
At some point
I thought
We can't just keep doing this
This is
No
Interesting in many ways
And
Is it even right
Is this conservative approach really getting people
The right
Notion about what dinosaurs looked like
Just because fat didn't survive for Millions
Beerus doesn't mean that a dinosaur didn't have it
They are animals After All
I don't have time
And I have it all over the place
And some places I have really big fat Reserve
Which changes shape Valley dressed
Thunder score this point Conway asked me to consider a thought experiment
If we reconstructed
Magnanimous
Slightly reconstruct dinosaurs
What would they look like
In other words
If some alien paleontologist from millions of years in the future
What's the try and draw a modern animal
Isaiah well
Or a camel
Just from there fossilized skeleton
How would it look
Well if you actually do it
The month animals look
If you drop a
Bowhead whale for example just from the skeleton
Without a lot of fat or blubber
It looks kind of like a giant
Tadpole
Bulbous head
Along
Snake like tail I mean
You take away all that stuff and you not left with much Leo
Because why else that shape is defined by fat
Dinosaurs also had fat
And John argues that it would have changed their shape pretty dramatically
Who knows somebody even had humps
Like animals
You could take one of my cement dinosaurs
That dinosaur could have camel humps
And we wouldn't know
Right
Cuz you can't tell from a camel
Back to the house
Pumps
There's not really anything that
Brontosaurus could Adam sweet
Mount scientist do sometimes find dinosaur fossils with the sauce
Pocket tissues intact
And when they do
They can completely change our image of the animal
Dinosaur Apatosaurus for example
Used to be depicted in a
Standard shrink wraps kind of way
Colleges found this amazing
Full body fossil wear lots of a
Fat and
And the different soft tissues have been perfectly preserved
Turns out
Fleshy outlawed around the body was
Coextensive it was quite chubby creature
Is striping light up ice all over the body
Drawing of the top of the tire without a hundred long curving
Quills the good kind of like fluffy porcupine
You out a lot together that's that's a creature this
We we just
Would not protect
Based on
Just finding buttons align
In recent years fossils have been found with
Fat and
Frills and thick coats of feathers
Way more than anyone have predicted
Every time we discover something likes
It's weird
And I caught me thinking
So if all the ones we've discovered so far
I've turned out to be pretty weird
What does that tell us about the rest of them
There are
Bizarre
Possibilities out there that no one's looking
And
I thought well I'm going to
Stop drinking
So John began to try something new with hazard
He started
To speculate
He started drawing pudgy dinosaurs and dinosaurs with humps
Quills
Weird skin flaps
And that was my rule
It was
How far can we go what's the
Most outrageous thing I can do
That we know we don't know isn't true right
It's still within the Realms of
Possibility of snow.
John wasn't just making stuff up out of thin air
It was like there was a standard conservative dinosaur at the center of his drawings
Linn County
Cover it with more speculative Elliman
Wasn't claiming that every drawing
He did was perfectly accurate
But you wanted to show people that dinosaurs as a group
Probably had a lot more weird variety than we think
I'm sorry to get the overall picture dinosaurs ride
I think you need
A healthy dose of speculation in there
Conway says that dinosaur art
Should always reflect the latest science what we know for sure
Who will never know everything
And I think the speculation
Isabel
What extra
All of
We is beautiful in the world
Back then
The wheel just never know about
Urolithiasis
Took us to bring back some of that real
Magic as a prehistoric whale that was suddenly there
John eventually decided to give the world some of that magic in the form of a book
Teamed up with Darren Naish and another paleo artist named memo kozma
In Publix a slim little paperback
Call
All yesterday
All yesterday's is
Still with dinosaurs that look very different from what you're used to
There's a triceratops
What's covered in spines
How much is Soros with
Skin that camouflage that against
Forest floor
And if there is unisaurus that is so covered in feathers that looks like a haystack
Next to each image the artist describes why they drew it that way
The camouflage dinosaur is drawn that way because
The artist reason that It's oddly proportioned body might have made it vulnerable
The Predators
And in need of some kind of defense strategy
All yesterday's was a big hit
And it helped Spark
A little movement for more speculative paleoart
We talked about the old yesterday's movement as like it's the new frontier
All the way we should depict
Prehistoric animals
Darren Naish says it's more acceptable now to draw a dinosaur based on a hypothesis
For example horned dinosaurs like Triceratops have these
Surly large nausea
Confuse paleontologist for years
There been a few different hypotheses but
Bored by scientist
And one of them is that the dinosaurs
May have had inflatable
Nos balloons
Cuddly elephant seal hooded seal inflatable
Couches
But just
Would have looked weird and grotesque in Australia
Expressive very real possibility
No 20 years ago if someone were to draw Triceratops with nose balloons
They would have been laughed at
But I would say that
What we called you yesterday smooth
That means that it is now quite
Reasonable for an autistic
I've shown my Triceratops
Rejoin excitable nosebleed
Does this reason
And you could say
Nikon S2 specs
Justifiable
Site
Set the time being.
That doesn't mean Triceratops
Definitely had nose balloon
But by drawing it that way it's like the artist is asking us to keep an open mind
Because even though we know a lot about the prehistoric world
More and more everyday
The science is always changing
The past is always a moving Target
Tell me what is not just about drawing dinosaurs with
Stripes and nos balloons
Illustrators also depict dinosaur Behavior
Which may have even a greater impact on how we imagine extinct animals
Moron
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another word for all hearing
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Hello this is Emmett
Back
With ramen in the studio to talk
A little bit more about Taylor White
Dinosaur
Kieran's like the look
Of their physical bodies right there
Another
Pretty important
Issue with us
Is dinosaur Behavior like
If you're going to draw a dinosaur
Try doing something
And feel like when you think of what are the dinosaurs usually
Doing
Usually the T-Rex is
Tearing someone apart
Usually the
Brontosaurus
As we mentioned was
Stanija swamp with leaves
Car hanging out of its mouth or it's probably
Eating another dinosaur attacking another dinosaur eating dinosaur is probably
Being attacked or like a running away and some kind of way eating a plant
Whatever you
8 of the dinosaur is what you should be depicted doing at any moment of
Which like you know I mean in some ways it's not just a dinosaur thing like if you think about
Nature Documentaries we'd like to depict
Action
Totally
The last time you saw a cheetah
Doing anything other than
Running down a gazelle and like biting its throat but like she does do a lot of other
Thanks a complex life
End in the back like a real a real point that way through with
Art fair for people like Darren and John who who are in our our pieces like
They think
Alive
Of a lot of animals
Including dinosaurs are a lot less
Action-packed
Hit it feels like when you are just looking at the yard
Opening their mouths involving
The camera all the time to not just kidding and farting
State doing
Things living animals
Do that like United moving around and sleeping and
And finding food and being boring office
The time
Why didn't you mention this earlier
Of all the dinosaurs that we don't associate with that kind of like
Boring activity like Tyrannosaurus Rex total ranks like
Free high
Like it up all the ones you said you would
Action
Violence
Absolutely
It's always chomping at something that's its role
Even the end of Jurassic Park is role of two in the movie by chomping a dinosaur
Right right
And so when
The book all yesterday's they've obviously wanted to put
Tyrannosaurus in there
And John based his T-Rex painting
On this one skeleton is kind of famous skeleton and scientists have nicknames
Stan
Stan is quite an aggressive looking Tyrannosaurus in a waistcoat
Quite a large
Long
Scary looking head
I'm so sad is traditionally depicted doing very nasty things to other animals
But John is also like pretty adamant like that's not the whole truth if I was like who this creature was
They probably going to kill something
Once every two weeks
You know they spent the vast majority of their life
Asleep
Probably
With a great big full belly just sleeping on the ground
And say that's how I painted it
City of that picture in the book
The buck
It's almost like a
Cute
It's very cute
It's like slightly curled up with its little tiny T-Rex arms up by its chin this is like one of John's like favorite pieces
From all yesterday's in
And he and he called it
Sleepy Stan
What an infected mean this picture
It doesn't even show his teeth
When sleeping which I don't think I've ever seen a T-rex picture
Without it burying its teeth right which is a stunning to think about that I've never and I've been now I as I see it
I know it's true I've never seen one without his teeth being
Peanut Bean
Chao and how long they are
Probably ripping into Flash
But yeah we just we don't show
Tyrannosaurus Jess
Relaxing and that's what they did most of the time
Bright
Pretty good life
Sleepy Stan
That's awesome
So if you flip run into
Like the back of the book just one more thing that I want to show you some
This back
Section
Of the book is actually called
All today's
The idea behind
This part of the book
It's sort of the actualization
Thought experiment that John Conway asked
Stuff to do right where
You know you're imagining up
An alien paleontologist
In the future who is trying to piece together what the
The Contemporary world the animals of the
Contemporary world
Look like based on fossil evidence
Right so this
This picture I'm looking at now is that
Is a manatee
But it's a land of grazing land herbivore
Fred read the can you read the description they have there
Says a solitary Manatee is shown grazing and it's Mountain Home
We only know the skull of this enigmatic herbivore
Basically like in this case they're saying like you saw it with this animal maybe we only the only thing we ever got was
From that you're trying to make you like all this looks a little bit like a cow skull
And it's totally common and dinosaurs that the only find one for the section it's very rare that we find full of skeletons to tell you everything about
Pic of a manatee skull intro enough you would think
That's a
That's a cow and even if you do find a full skeleton
And there are other things
You wouldn't have a trunk so as evidence of this elevator just the snub-nosed
Weezer such a thing
Oh my God that's so true right there like a camel the same way that we don't message me when necessarily know that a camel
What had humps Yuan
Know that an elephant had drunk
Which is like such an iconic weird piece of anatomy in the world
Open bar but it's not it's not
It's not there and therefore it doesn't look at all like an elephant and it just looks
I'm and I really like it really sells especially with these
A speculative imaginings of modern animals really sells the idea of it a lot
All right
Baby go I like I like their texts on some of these still like
If you breed the swans it like in a two swans or seams are long site like four limbs
Which they must have used a spear small prey items
One of them has just caught a tadpole one of the mysterious fish of the past
Oh it's so perfect really they really embody this like this like you know this is futuristic
He's trying to piece together the world that we currently live in now is making these kind of conception
Will leads from evidence to
The obtaining a real picture of what
The world actually look like
But they're still have wings doing their best it's not like making fun of them
It just has to
With limited information we have
This is what we create right and really shows
The limits of that information
That's so cool
It's such a good idea to think the
This way it dislodges
The iconography from your mind to be free
I got something about him and lots of ways and that's that's really
And it really sells it when you see
The modern animal
Defected in the house for traditional
Granite dinosaur away. I got kind of love on it
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald mix into production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Can you mingle is our senior producer Kolstad he's the digital director
The rest of Team includes senior editor Delaney Hall
Joe Rosenberg Vivien Leigh and me Roman Mars
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX an independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in
Noah podcast
You can find mall
And radiotopia
Nfm
You can find the show enjoin discussions about the show on Facebook you can't read me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi org
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you're thinking I need more 9 p.m. my life
We have all the old episodes available in new articles about design every couple of days on our beautiful
Beautiful website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com