99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Katie mingle filling in for Roman Mars
In the early morning of September 20th
A category 4 hurricane hit the island Puerto Rico
You heard one official saying the island
Is destroy the power lines are down
Street art
Possible many roads are flooded
Maria was a beast of a hurricane the strongest one that hit the island since 1932
The wind was blowing 155 miles an hour which is very close to being a cat
Curry 5
And it didn't just hit one stretch
The coast
Actually moved across the whole island ripping up everything and it's
Airbrush everywhere
Trees down
Power lines down obviously everywhere going to be the tire Island
In the dark
That's Daniel Alarcon he spend some time reporting in Puerto Rico after the storm and wrote an article about
Audit for Wired Magazine wake up they go out of their houses or apartments they'll
Look on the street
The survey the damage and
And
Start
Trying to make sense of what they're seeing in front of them you know
And one of the people out there that day driving around in a state of
Shutterstock
Was a guy named Jorge Bracero
Please God let a video that or he took the day after the storm
Cheese from the capital city of San Juan and he told me he was just
Totally caught off guard by how bad the storm was
They've really became
Obviously known for everybody around that we were in deep trouble
But it wasn't for a few days when Jorge actually made it into work that he fully grasp
Scale of the crisis
Do you worship prepa which stands for Puerto Rican Electric Power Authority
It's the public utility that provides electricity for nearly the entire Island
I actually arrived at the power plant I noticed that I was one of the
The few that actually made it cuz
Most people live inland
When he gets there he makes his way over this big computer screen that shows
The outline of Puerto Rico and inside of that
A bunch of lines
Kind of like a big connect
The dots with each line representing a power line
And every blinking line
The whole island was blinking
Every single line was down
Every single line in the island was down
The trajectory of
Maria was
Almost as if it has been designed by
An evil genius
The weight cut across the island
Such that it
Essentially
Struck every major transmission line
The scale of the destruction to the power grid was hard even for Jorge Bracero to comprehend
And he knew that day that he would spend the next
Several months
Helping Puerto Rico recover
Through his work with prepa
What he didn't know yet
What's the thousands of people would come to count on
Him
Specifically him
To help them get through their year in the dark
Jorge Bracero is one of those people who you can tell you're going to like just by seeing a
Picture of them
He's in his late thirties with short brown hair and a beard
And he just looks like a nice guy
I think it's something about his eyes
Danielle Alarcon describes him as
Delightfully nerdy
He's a guy who
Will
Sit and explain to you
How an electrical grid works
You know like
And continue to explain it in my new detail even after
It's clear that you like
I no longer understand
Talking about
Jorge has worked for prepping for 13 years and his job there is a grueling one
He's responsible for operating
Story tall boilers
These boilers are cheated by 20 giant burners that Jorge also looked after
And so he's
Constantly hiking up and down these
Stairs that
Service the different parts of this massively tall equipment
It's
Extremely hot
Everyday just smelling off
Petrol
And Diesel
And
It's extremely exhaust
Sometimes you just hate it
When Maria hit
Or he and his wife Charlotte rode out the Storm at her
Her family's house
They weren't hurt
But they were surrounded by devastation
And they found out some really sad news
Charlotte's best friend who was pregnant
I've gone into stress induced early labor at the day the storm hit and lost the baby
This was particularly frightening to them because Charlotte was also pregnant
It was the most the most tense I've ever been in my life
What if Charlotte also went into early labor
What is the baby was born but
Couldn't survive the post Maria world with no electricity and temperatures routinely in the 90s
Because
When you sleep at night
So unbearable
Serious that the amount of heat in the air was so so brutal
Did you think I'm just going to get naked outside because I can't contain
This damn Heat
So I'm thinking a newborn can survive this
Jorge even considered trying to get his wife off the island
But eight months pregnant they don't allow you to fly
After the Storm Jorge and Charlotte Bounce from place to place staying with friends who have generators
At home
Jorge fretted over his wife
Send baby who is coming ready or not in November
At work things were even more stressful
The first priority was to get power to hospitals and water treatment plant
Aarhus power plant was one of seven major plants
On the island but all of the others were down and without those to help
His kept crashing over and over again
Dead
It would connect as many hospitals that we can but it just wouldn't hold it
Could you describe this like a tug-of-war
The power plants are on one side and their Giant
But the consumers are on the other side and they pull hard
If one power plant goes down the others will have to work harder
And they get tired
Sometimes to the point of
Collapse
After Maria there was only one giant power plant on Jorge side of the Rope
And on the other side hospitals and water treatment plants
Which were pulling like crazy
Every time there's a collapse you have to reboot everything just went down the drain and you have
How to restart from Step One
With just one plant that was constantly collapsing they had to triage
Is like
I only have one power plant that just got fired up
And I only have enough power for one
Of those two hospitals right there
Out in the field things weren't any better lines are down all over the island and there weren't nearly enough workers
To fix them
Eventually support would arrive from the US Mainland but for the first week or so Puerto Ricans were basic
Glee on their own
You know we only had 230
Power Brigade bats
All we have
For the company for the island
And that is not enough
That is just not enough
They're about three workers in a brigade so that's 690.
People give or take
As a point of comparison as Florida
Prepared for Irma they had 16,000 workers on call
Before anyone paying attention it was no surprise that prep I did not have the resources to respond to this disaster
Again here's Danielle Alarcon
Before Maria
The island
Was in a terrible economic state
A decade or more of economic stagnation Puerto Rico a u.s. territory and popular getaway destination
Try to avoid a default on its staggering that it would be the
In the decades before Maria businesses has left the island in droves as the US government phased out a c
Series of tax breaks
To make up for all the Lost Revenue to the Puerto Rican government began borrowing money in the
The form of bonds
Year after year issuing more and more bonds kind of hoping things would turn around
But things did not turn around
By the time Maria hit the government was in the middle of an enormous debt crisis
And in the course of that River was not spared
And prep has settled over the course of many many years
With a lot of debt
9 billion dollars in debt
Or I could never could have not that sounds like a lot can I look at my article cuz I'm not sure
Daniel actually had to stop and check his notes while we were talking to make sure this was right
Wow
Yeah I know that's it that's it that's insane
Because of cost and because of dad they're constantly postponing
Maintenance
Like for example in the mainland us the vegetation is kept mode so that there's basically a rose
That runs underneath the power lines
That's called right of way right and you're supposed to maintain the right of way
To make it easy in an in the case of
You know some disaster
To access
The Fallen Towers
So in Puerto Rico that doesn't
That doesn't exist
When Maria hit prep ahead been limping along
Now they would have to deal with one of the biggest crises the island has ever faced
But there was another problem and it was a big one
It basically had no strategy for communicating with the public
Didn't have a presence on Twitter or Facebook
Their the Twitter feed was
Alba dead
The Facebook page was not exist
There was no communication saying to people where are the brigade's working everything was kept hush
Hushed
Just to prevent conflict
And with little actual information from prepa
TV news stations just kind of made stuff up
Which made Jorge went to
Bros television across the room
There was a political analyst and he was saying
He was what he was saying was wrong first completely wrong
And not only that he was
Inciting more fear
And Desperation rather than comfort
And I spend the night
Just screaming at the TV my family was
Nodejs
Tell me the
Be quiet
Dad action right there is basically what you know it just gave me an epiphany
He felt like people need to hear what's really happening
I decided to become the news Outlet
Portuguese tarts
One man campaign to educate
Puerto Ricans about
Electrical power
Keep do it on his Facebook page and he wouldn't ask
Commission
Update October 30
Reshare please
Spread the knowledge
Didn't 9
All because of broken boiler
It will take days to repair
What's in 40 megawatts
Leon Focus posts are very technical and very specific
Starter relay test
Everything will be good
Turn it on and it will be at such-and-such line
You know working to restore such-and-such wattage to such-and-such Neighborhood
That information was basically for company use
So I decided to start
Leaking that information to the public
Every night Jorge would come home from a 16-hour shift at work
Hang his smelly clothes out on the porch and start writing
Update October 31
85 + 6
I was spending around for hours
Just riding and calling calling friends on the field
And asking them for to validate the information I never revealed any sources that I had because I was afraid
For any backlash that it would get
After he gathered all the information from his sources in the field
Or he would type out these
Extremely long post
Sometimes a thousand words are more
With his
On an iPhone
Update
November 3rd
Turn the man
993 megawatt
Cell service with so spotty that sometimes you have to drive to
Define a signal
His wife Charlotte who was still pregnant
Would be like
What are you doing
My wife would be angry
But then something happened
People started responding
More and more people started sharing Jorge's posts
Post of his we're getting
You know thousands of a repost and you know hundreds and hundreds of comments and he switched at a certain point for my personal page
Do you like a fan page
That was my wife's idea
And it was important so I decided to close everyday
Update November 4th
I wanted to give
People information but he also wanted to show them that people were actually out there working on getting their power
It was just a really difficult problem
How to fix there's a basic problem to the grid
Which is
The majority of population lives
In the North
Sebastian like a rectangle
Across the middle
Is a mountain range
And the majority of the population lives
Above that mountain range
And the majority the power is below.
And servicing the towers in the mountains was not easy that involves
In some cases you know
Flying a tower in by helicopter and then dropping it in and then guys hiking in and I'm trying to set it up
On top of the difficulty of the work probably just didn't have the supplies it needed
Remember Marie was the third in a series of devastating hurricanes That season
Harvey's Ranch
Keep coming son returned here today and reveal the devastation left
Goodbye Irma
The once-powerful
This hurricane
Triple whammy meant that all the things Puerto Rico needed were in high demand in other places
So we had no materials know anything
Like basic stuff
Lack of supplies of like
Not having enough Nuts and Bolts
You know
Screws
You know I time at guys who were finding stuff in the grass and they're like on can I use this and this stuff is like 60 years old
Has prevented the slow work of restoring electricity
Puerto Ricans who could afford them relied on generators for power
There were so many that the noise of them drowned out the natural sounds at the island
The sound of the cookie cookie cookie cookie like that sound
I've been replaced by the sounded like me which is like
The horrible horrible like a rumble of
Hundreds of generators
Meanwhile in post
After post on Facebook
He did his best to
Explain why things were moving so slowly
I think he did a good job at that critical moment people
Yeah this is the reality of
The grid that we have
Will great that was flawed even before
Maria came in
Andretti
But if you scroll through Jorge's
You'll see that they aren't just technical information
He's also encouraging people to be their best selves
And look out for each other
All I'm thinking is like
Do you imagine
If you had one committed that has power and the community next it does not
How dead people are going to start you know
Baton young lashing out and start feeling resentment and jealousy
There's going to be riots in the streets
Can you
Can you read one of these
Little pep talks
That you wrote
I'm here I'm going to send you one
K Domingo
Yeah
Let me
Play kitchen
You could read that may be first in Spanish and then
You can tell us what it mean
English
Yeah it says
Bob and Dave
Seattle
Mira La serie
Add yellow Cocina El Dorado Casino
Not that would be nice. Solo
Atonement
What it says is
I know that next to you everything is
In darkness
It's going to light up
If you already powered up
Healthy A1C meat
Do the best thing that you can
Make ice
Cook
Cleaner clothes
You are not forgotten
You are never alone
This moment will pass
Angels brought back
A lot of memories
Overtime for his post earned him a kind of celebrity status on the island
But yeah I went to go see a comedy show
And
And he was mentioned in the comedy show
And everyone
Cracked up like an entire theater, like hundreds of people
These owls of recognition in like
Applause and people doubled over laughing because it seems like everybody
Was checking
Everyday one word he said was saying
It's the first time in my life that I became a meme
140 meme was an image of his face on one of those Latin prayer candles
They would say don't let this candle burn out if you want Power
Another meme referred to him as
Fake beard
I had a very very rough beard
I didn't come down so these
Start calling me saying beard you know
Just caress his beard if you want Power
By this point for his bosses knew what he was doing and whether they approved or not
They sort of had to go along because the public was on his side
People were stopping in the streets
Thank heaven when they do see me on the street at now they give me a hug because
I'm not I'm not usually a handshake guy
I'm more of a hug guy
On November 14th 2017 who his baby was born the healthy baby girl who they named Leia
Amazingly Charlotte's mom and dad had just gotten power the day before
So when they left the hospital the family went straight to her parents
Air-conditioned house
Their new baby girl
This was the first Christmas in Puerto Rico since hurricane Maria devastated the island local engineers
Half of the island had their power restored
But the mood was Grim
So many people have lost friends or relatives or had their homes destroyed in the storm
Many people were still in the dark
No one felt much like celebrating
Still there were moments
The blackness
A local musician Rewritten the song All I Want For
Christmas
So that instead of all I want
For Christmas Is You
It says all I want for Christmas
Is loose
Which means light in Spanish
One line in the Rewritten song even name-drops Jorge pleading in Spanish
Jorge Bracero
Please give me what I want
Okay I'm sending you this
Songs
All right
On Facebook
Oh my God you have the video
Will Smith singing
Eventually the woman who wrote the parody song reached out to Jorge and they made a video of the two of them singing
Together
Yo te quiero para me
Capital Tri-State
Ask me sueno
Lose
Oh yeah this is
Is great
I'm going to watch this again later on
I forgot I almost forget about this
By spraying around 85% of the island have power
Still there were thousands of people who did in
In the spring I visited
A kind of old folks home
Up in the hills
And at the bottom of the hill there was power
But there there was no power
And they just couldn't understand why
And they were just beside themselves and just
Desperate
And
The sense of being forgotten
You know
Holy continued with his daily updates which lines were being fixed
Where the brigades were headed next
The team a irrigates and the American contractors
And to keep up a sense of momentum he also shared videos as new places got power
Like this one where an elementary school in the town of Puerto Nuevo finally gets electricity
The video was taken on some
IPhone from the hallway of the school
Kids are running by with their arms in the air going completely bananas
The teachers are jumping up and down
Just pure joy
It made me so happy
See it
That I figured people would be happy
Etsy at 2
Every week it seemed a new town was celebrating I started telling people
But
Soon it would be their turn just remember that even if you don't have power right now you will have it in this is going to be you
I've been restored all of Puerto Rico it's been nearly 11 months since hurricane Maria
And took out
Finally in August of 2018 prepa announced that the entire Island have been reconnected to the grid
It was six weeks before the year anniversary of Maria and just in time for the next
Hurricane season
Peppa meanwhile is arguably in a worse place than it was before Maria
There's been a lack of steady leadership over the last year with five different directors cycling through the position
At the helm
One guy lasted you know
Like a day there was a sense of a rudderless ship
To be honest sense of an absolutely vital ship
4 years a weird funeral have been in place that recipients of disaster money couldn't replace anything
Staying with a different
I eat more expensive thing
For example wooden post can be replaced with stronger metal posts
So Puerto Ricans didn't actually get the opportunity to improve their infrastructure
That's the same grid they had before with a population that's
Significantly more vulnerable
Antonio's Estes Park can't be overstated
Puerto Ricans were traumatized
Maria
It's not just that they went through
This
Storm and then went through the aftermath of the storm
It's I think
For a lot of people
It's what the aftermath of storm told them which is essentially we don't care about you
You're not you're forgotten you don't matter
The depth of this wound is
Just
Adjust
Very very deep
Now propose in the process of
Privatizing
Basically selling itself off piece-by-piece and hopes that a private company or various private companies will
Be able to deliver a better service and the government
Has
But a lot of people are skeptical
Jorge Bracero is still working at prepa
Still doing the hot exhausting job of maintaining a 15-story boiler
You'd like to stop doing such hard physical labor
You'd like someone to put them in charge of social media
Put his other talents to use
I'm up for it I would love that but so far
They haven't
Hurricane season was in full swing when I talk to her
So of course I asked him how he was feeling about that
When people ask me is like I'll be ready for a next hurricane I'm like no
We need a break just give us maybe two years
Just give us that time that window in which our people can keep working keep working key working so that
Can hold a little longer
Climate change and everything that comes with it is a reality
You know hurricane seasons are going to get longer
We're going to see more you know and that's
That's pretty scary
Freddy told me he thinks Puerto Ricans could survive another hurricane if they had to
Another year in the dark event
You wouldn't worry as much about the island devolving into Anarchy
As he once did
He saw the best of people after Maria
Let me think they could do it again
Just please
Please
Not this year
Bracero was not the only person in Puerto Rico to take matters into their own hands after Maria
All over the island people were stepping into new roles and figuring out DIY Solutions
But one time that Daniel Alarcon visited took this
Really really far
The people actually said to hell with meaning on prepa
We're doing this work ourselves
Daniel tell us that story
After this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flask podcast
So it seems like all over Puerto Rico people were
I'm taking matters into their own hands
Tell me about this town you went to the basically took it upon themselves
To get the lights turned back on
Yeah absolutely
In this one town called San Sebastian de Pepino
They took a pretty radical step witches that they
Took volunteers intermed turn them into lineman and created their own
Kind of unofficial Brigade
Connect and reconnect
San Sebastian to the great amazing
The mayor he's a Charming guy with a rhetorical flourish in like knows how to give a speech in
And make a statement end
I had no choice like it was more dangerous
Leave my vulnerable population without electrical power
Because a lot of people are older and sick and would have died
Without
Power
I got tired of waiting
They start doing the work on their own
Which is
Super dangerous
But how did they even know how to do it like today
They watching YouTube tutorials or less well as it happened before the storm.
Bought a couple of decommissioned
Prepper truck
With the with the buckets that dries
They bought them so they could cut brush
The hurricane comes and they're like well we've got the trucks
And they had one guy who had
It worked as a lineman
And another guy who knew a little bit about it and it's say okay when everybody we need help with
This brush so we can get to that line enough to that
Electrical pole over there and then everyone would take out their machetes and help through the line in the new go and
And and do the work
They
Had their whole town connected
Day weeks before
The other towns
So the other areas around there
And this was just
Okay like they didn't get into
Trouble like they did Pepa know what they were doing
You know
They couldn't officially sanctioned
They were certainly you know they had to coordinate
Cuz I couldn't be
Energizing a line well
You know Pepino Power Authority guys were
Connecting it to symposium
Power Authority it sounds so official was this an official body or
Is this just a made-up
Name
Filipino authorities
Completely an informal
Made-up thing
Pepino means cucumber in Spanish
I guess it sounds less official when you know it
Cucumber
David Jimenez the mayor is
You know
Play on
It worked
One of the results
Is
It was a law proposed after all this
That was going to loosen the restrictions for
Mayors
And local local authorities to do the kind of thing that he did
Just a final note it actually wasn't a lot that got past it was more of an agreement between prepa and mayors of
Cities that basically says
American do the work of connecting people to the grid if they want
And prepa is not responsible if anyone gets hurt
99percentinvisible
Reduce this week by me Katie Mingle
And reported by Daniel Alarcon
Was adapted from an article Danielle wrote in Wired Magazine called
What happened in the dark
Nexen Tire production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Delaney Hall is a senior editor Kurt Kolstad
The digital director
The rest of the team includes Avery truffelman Emmett Fitzgerald
Turn mother Joe Rosenberg Vivien Leigh
And
Feels like there's
Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Cindy.
That's beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Yeah I'm trying to make it a thing
99% invisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX and independent Collective of the most
Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Trip
You can find the show and join the discussions about the show on Facebook
You can tweet at me at Katie mingle the show is at 99 PSI or
Braun Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But if you want to see the amazing Pepino Power Authority logo
Yes it involves a cucumber with a hard hat on
Or if you want to print out a picture of seat beard
Put on your altar next time the power goes out
You'll find all of that
And more
99 pi
. org
Radio temperature
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com