99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It's hard to overstate just how important record album art was to music before we
I downloaded everything
Our experience with a record or CD used to be visual
The design of the record cover was your first impression of what was to come
I would stare at the font on the cover and pour over the liner notes the first time I put an album on it why
Was a ritual I'm not saying that error music was better it wasn't it was just different
BR on the records try to encapsulate the essence of a band and then that Essence was transferred to you because you were a
Fan and it became part of your identity to
At least that's what it felt like
Albemarle would certainly important to my friend and reporter Shawn Cole
One certain album
In one certain band in particular
The Roman were you ever Devo fan
I was aboard evil appreciate it I don't think it was really a fan like I listen to unlike the songs I heard
I remember with it when I was a kid
I remember that you're not a devotee
I remember the wren
Hats
NFL
Particular memory of them
Doing a cover of
I Can't Get No Satisfaction by The Rolling Stones on Saturday Night Live
Really weird yes
This story is about that
Devo album the one that they were promoting on that Saturday Night Live performance Yousaf
More specifically it's about
The album art
App that record
Because the story of the image that ultimately ended up on the cover of that record
Is this
Crazy rabbit hole that I fell down
Before we get there I just need to cover some some things about Diva that you might not know
Do you know where the name comes from
I do not
So a lot of people think of DeVos this really silly you know not even jumping around
But they were actually very serious and had a very considered
Philosophy
And that was at the
Human race
Is an estate of D evolution
Devo
So their songs are all the songs are mostly about corporate control and
Blind Conformity and they were actually visual artist
Before they before they wrote any songs
It wasn't the early 70s in Akron Ohio
So I talked with one of the founders of Devo Jerry Casale
And who says like back then they weren't they were mostly trying to figure out what
Devolutionary art
Would look like
You know cuz we were very very enamored and put off at
At the same time
Bye
Pop culture
Like the lowest end of like add graphics
Terrible TV commercials
We were kind of drawn to kitsch
And occasionally they
Would go out shopping
Fourchette
So
Walking through the Kmart
Nope it was the predecessor to Kmart it was click
And this is Mark mothersbaugh is another member of the band
This is probably the point to mention that this was more than four decades ago and and not everybody's memory is is
Declare independence department store
Department store we were looking for supplies we were
Collaborating on a
Visual art piece together
And
Walking through the sports section and there's V6 practice golf balls in a
Clear plastic pouch
Sealed shut at the top with a
Cardboard display head took a new picture this its like that display had
With a hole in it that that hangs on a hook
Yes I can picture it kind of like the rocks
With bags of generic candy at the gas station
Like a clear bag full of candy and it just says
Gummy bears at the top
Alright so
On that
Display head
Is an illustration
Of the smiling face
Chi Chi Rodriguez
And who was Chi Chi Rodriguez
Chi-Chi Rodriguez is one of the most famous golfers
In history
He was like
I don't know what you do Rodriguez was like he was he was he was like that he was like the the Elvis of golfers he was just like
The Big Show
I saw it and I just loved it was a picture of him
In front of a golf ball to his head's kind of Halo to buy a big golf ball
Kind of imitating
Something that I'd already been printing which was
Human heads in front of the Moon and
It made us laugh
Wee chuckle
We have to have that
Intercourse golf
Was almost symbolically like the most lame
Kind of
Leon bourgeois
Pursuit that you could
Have especially that time
Unless your parents are rich you didn't get to
If we ever imagined our self on a golf course it was probably as a caddy how boring it looked in on TV
Was Chichi because
He didn't
Fit
With the rest of the golfers at all
He wore these loud
Pants and
Bright shirts in he had this
Famous hat that only he wore which at a
Specific hat band
We don't have my hat
So did they buy those golf balls
They bought the golf balls
Mark
Used the Chichi image in a Manifesto he was writing about being a quote on quote
Spud boy in the rubber town of Akron
But other than that
Nothing really happened with it
Until
We were already putting out our self-produced single
You still
Oh I like that song
It's it this is my favorite one is so it's it's like this kind of jokey Anthem celebrating
Like literal stiffness like uptightness
Talking about televangelist politicians and how if they are
Somehow and I don't really remember the moment but
We had
The idea
I'm putting Chichi on that cover
And so they used that picture of chichi
On the cover of the 45
The Sing-Off
And it was like this
Commentary on on on Commercial as a Min Pin or obsession with selling
And in this case selling plastic golf balls
And the Americana of the
The golfer
Toby stuff comes out in 1978
And
Yeah they're still not famous there
None of this obscure art rock band
But then about four months later
Diva gets
Their big break
Warner Brothers sign the Bantu there
First full-length album
Gordon Jerry
Is where the real D Evolution begin
We've laid that whole thing out
And working up
This moment
And then comes the real Devo twist
Only a corporation could provide
In other words what we're talking about we become part of
They're about to be
On top 40 radio and broadcast on the TV screens at Middle America
What was that
First record call
The long title
Called question
Are we
Question are we not men
Answer we Are Devo
And this is their first major label album
So Mark and Jerry than the other members of the band are there like that
That picture of chichi work so well on the single let's just stick with it you know it's kind of our brand now let's just put that on the on the cover of the full-length
And this is like a picture of Chi-Chi Rodriguez the original picture from that
Thing they bought at Kmart
They just took that lifted it directly
And put it on
So they had to California
IMovie montage Beverly Hillbillies whatever and
Warner Brothers
Q and their this is like the process back then but then maybe now I don't know but like they're heading from
Department to department at Warner Brothers you know dealing with all of the new album things that need to happen
We're told to go see I think Rick Serena was his name and he seemed to be an okay guy in the Arctic
Ways ahead of the Arts
I was creative director at Warner Brother records he seemed to like what we were up to that one band that I pray
Appreciated the most was Devo
I love the fact that they just never took anything very seriously do you remember that first meeting with
Maryland you are remembered have a Polaroid
We showing the image
He Chuckles
I thought it was clipart
Yeah she does look a lot like clipart
And I guess I never asked
I only found out that it was
Kim sometime later
Well I guess what it is I just wanted to do vote for you
Absurdity
I mean you have to think about what was going on back
In the day
Artwork
Album covers
Has had rules
Attached to it
Most of them
Albums were delivered to little mama
Pop music
Stores all around the country
Let there be sound
Kid would come in at 4 after school and his job was to open up the box of records from
Warner Brothers Are
Columbia what not and then rack
Right
So the one thing that they
Told all of us in the art Department
Just don't screw that up
A rock band has to look like a rock band country western has to look like country western
They better have cowboy hats on otherwise they get Miss racked and then if people can't
Find them in the rack
Of the genre they're interested in they don't buy it
DeVos case the music was so unusual that it could have something
Completely absurd on the cover and make
Make sense
So even though it makes no sense
That a picture
Of a flamboyant golfer
Stolen from package of golf balls
As is the mascot of Devo it does make perfect sense because that's who
It was just like
Pick something impossible and and react is just psyched like he loves
He loves working on this
There you know it's there doing all the little designing things and giving me like
Font
Getting getting everything ready
He laid it all out
Spectre colors
You know did the whole series thing where they give you
A transparency that amaka
Right
And we approved
And 10 about two days later
Who get this call
And it's a big crisis
The car was from the vice president of business Affairs for
Warner Brothers
David Berman
Who was the guy that you would cast in a movie about the music
As a villain or is the hero
Depends on your point of view
He was very smart very good at what he did
Played Hardball
The first communication is
I'm a golfer
And I'm a fan of golf
I know she
I've met chichi
You cannot use Chi Chi Rodriguez
Status
Completely and totally false
This is David Berman
I told you not everybody's memory is Crystal Clear regarding the story
Not only have I never I have never seen chi chi
Other than a television
I'm not going to make fun of them
Friend of mine never met him I never spoken to him
Get this company sued
That part is accurate
Does David Berman about maybe being sued
Yes he did play hardball
But he says his objection was purely illegal
Shirley
In California laws crystal clear
You can't use somebody's name or likeness for commercial purposes without their permission
Had nothing to do with my being a golfer other than
Because I was I knew that it was clearly Chi Chi Rodriguez
It wasn't the fact that he was likable
Equipment Rory sabbatini I would have done the same thing
Wait who is Rory sabbatini
He's a golfer
But nobody likes Rory sabbatini
Why does nobody like Aurora's cavatini
I don't know
Also Rory sabbatini was born in 1976 and would have been 2 years old when this Diva record came out but anyway
This all came as a real
Blow
To the band
We're dumb fight in Creswell
We don't know what
Curse words
Giving up
Let's just right Chichi letter and ask his permission
But in the meantime you know
Corporate gears are rolling in money has been paid and
Warner Brothers is expecting a product
Sol Divas like
Let's come up with a plan B
And they had this idea that actually involves another piece of The evolutionary are
The artist rendering of what the last four presidents would have looked like
Had you combine them
The Ford Nixon Johnson and Kennedy all of their faces
Mashed
Together
Mark mothersbaugh I just had the pictures lying around
Neurosis
It is bizarre face that had John Kennedy's hairline and it had
Lyndon Johnson's ears and Richard Nixon's nose
So the band brings that image to the Warner Brothers Art Department
Why couldn't we just
Beauty chichi
So that it isn't Chichi anymore
So basically like it was like building a mr. Potato Head Toy like they grafted
Johnson's ears and Nixon's dos Chi-Chi's head reverse the mouth
I should I should actually I should say that the David Berman from was in business.
The time he doesn't remember the image being altered
So I sent him the original Chichi image from the from the golf balls and the Potato Head collage
I was just so he could
He could compare them
Looking at it today
I wonder why I proved it cuz to me it still looks like a chicken
Obviously I must have
Interior strike Salt Lake
About three weeks later
A letter comes back from Chi-Chi's Representatives
Yes Chichi thinks it's fine
To use that image
He just wants
Records
Christmas time
To give out to his friends and family
He wanted to say his friends and family look like like I'm going to record
Right
He like that
And this is Mark mother
So it was at that point it's like we couldn't go back
It would date already printed the cover so now we had this
Mutilated
Potato face
For an album cover
And it didn't really look like the handsome Chichi anymore so I'm sure he was quite so
Surprised when he got a box of them in the mail all our efforts were in fact
What it looks like in the end
Is it Devo hit meanly trick
Chi-Chi Rodriguez
And put out something made him look hideous
It was you. Was a mess
They did send Chichi a couple thousand dollars
Also as well as the records he wasn't
The total loss
For him
But then they just then I never heard from him
Celine ever
Got his take on the album art or even
The songs on the album or anything like that which is
My reigning question and all of the
I really want to know if Chichi ever listen to that record and what he thought of us
Yeah that would be the big
Hello
Hello Gigi Rodriguez
Yeah who is this
Hit Sean Karrueche at a country club
Naturally
In West Palm Beach Florida
He's in his early eighties now still handsome still plays golf
Professionally
Does a lot of philanthropic work through his
Foundation annual charity event
It's really an honor to talk to you
It is my honor to talk to you Johnny
It's Sean but that's okay
It sounds like the best Johnny I love him so sweet
I love him
Chichi says he remembers getting this letter
And he says he did give out those records to his friends and family
Did you notice when you got the record that it didn't quite look like you that much
What it look like me and I look at the plushies it look like me a little bit
At least 1/2 look like
But I don't know anything about them messing with his face
And he had no idea that they were worried he was going to sue them
Show them
Well anybody that worried about somebody showing them
That they show people that they think that people are going to sue them
I thought it was this young people trying to make a career out of it and I could help him and that's it because I
I like to do something good every day of my life and I want to leave the the Earth better than I found it
So even young sort of
Avant-garde Punk musicians you want to hell
Yeah
Did you listen to that record
Yeah I listen to it one time
Just once
I put away that you didn't like it
No I
Nat King Cole
Dean Martin was my favor
Cuz music is not supposed to Rally up
Music is something to bring you down
So the most important question
Answer
He did he did not like it right and like it but as I was talking to that there's like a
A kind of Greater question here
Which is like
What did he think about
His face
Mutated version thereof
Being on the cover of this apocalyptic
Weirdo
Art rock bands
First record like the diet like did that make sense to him
And it's
Because because
Chichi
Knows he's
He knows how much he stands out and how
Outlandish
PS
None of that is lost
He said it's it's
Purposeful
Golf
Gulfshore business and
When you're a space you got to
The people that show and that's
Nashville time
Oh so that is the similarity between you and Devo
Yes
So in a way it really makes sense that they used you on the cover of their record
I think they were geniuses
I need takes a genius to recognize another
You guys sound almost
Diabolical
Me and Chichi
The bottom of a volcano
Planning
One could argue that
Again Jerry casali
What we were put through
By David Berman
Actually
Achieved something here better than just
Using a found image
Corporate interference
Plus the faces of Four American presidents who prosecuted the Vietnam War
And it's aftermath
In this wonderfully dandyish golf legend all of this together
Yeah it's more DeVos in the original TGIF
Is it that's what I'm saying
Devo and action like
Do you need an example of what
Talking about
Here it is
So this whole story takes place at the beginning of his career end
They go on a play for decades and extremely famous
They were just nominated to be in the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame
Yeah
Do they think about Chichi as
Part of their origin story
Cinemark Melrose Park
I really I don't think anybody ever tried to measure
How much
That album cover had in the sea
Excessive Devo but
It could possibly have been
The Tipping
Stone that Duchess like a
The chance to
Have a public career so
Just in case
Thank you chichi
Yeah
Story's not over
One more diabolical Devo twist
Netgear start casali
I have to say that now.
That I'm a senior citizen I completely changed my
Attitude about the game of golf
You did not really
Yeah I like it now
I really has changed
So much from Those Days Inn
Who got to play it and how it's played
I mean those guys really are athletes
I never thought I would hear a member of Devo say that
I know
I hear that here's a
EE
Hideous Secret
Unfolding right now
I really like
Professional football
We are done the NPR Sports show only a game special thanks to Gary Wallach
Story
Hugh Brown who helped Sean Cole with the research
Around the time Depot with putting out their first singles in the mid-1970s a music teacher in Canada
Dazn DIY records
With a bunch of his Elementary School students and the result
With a haunting and uplifting Outsider Art masterpiece
That story
After this
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
In Canada in the 1970s
The music teacher named Hans finger recorded 60 of his Elementary School students singing in a gymnasium
He pressed a few vinyl records of those recordings and handed them out to parents
The Langley School music project was little known until a record collector named Brian land found one of those albums in a trust
In the year 2000
Lynn shared it with some people and eventually
Bar None records gave it a proper release
The records cover featured a collage of black and white pictures of the students singing strumming guitars
Playing drums and clapping along
The album was called innocence and despair
The rediscovered recordings were a hit
Salon music critic Steven Hyden wrote
The gloomy title innocence and despair is no lie
The echoing yelping Renditions of this feel good music
Gives off a powerfully aching melancholy
It's the sound of you
Frozen on tape
As it fades
Probably away
Here's the music teacher from the Langley School music project hans fenger
Talking to Katie Mingle
In 2010
Before I was teaching in Langley I played in the heavy metal band
It never occurred to me to be a teacher I wasn't really good student myself
Kids were okay but I wasn't all that gushy about them to be honest with you
I knew nothing about kids music I knew nothing about teaching I knew nothing but everything you know I'd hair
Jared attitude weight 98 comes off I went to Langley and
I started teaching
I was having to pee dippy
Reading of philosophy at all about teaching the head.
I can't really say I thought about it a lot
I know I had a lot of ideas about music
But sitting out about teaching
You know for me I mean I've been playing in bands since I was like 11 or 12 years old and
It wasn't like anybody taught us
It wasn't even like anybody said oh oh
This is the way you do it or that's the way you do it we just
Certificated and I've been doing music like that since I was a little kid
So when I went in to teach music it never occurred to me that I was going to teach anybody how to read notes
Or that I was going to teach anybody how to pass a test
The only thing I ever tried to teach children is really
It's just to fall in love with making music
But that was always my goal
I just thought songs I knew
And and and I was very good to David Bowie in those days that was variant Iggy Pop
I was into a fill soul Phil Spector records Brian Wilson
And it wasn't until much
Later
Did I realize that
Songs with thematic
You know I had gotten a teaching job originally because I was with my girlfriend and she was having a baby and I needed a job
And by the time I got this job we're breaking up
And I think that
In the back of my
Mind
You know I was feeling like a little bit lost
Contrary to what people think a lot of kids aren't that happy
They'll have troubles they got problems at home
They can feel lonely.
Isolated
And the music
Can contract that feeling into them
The weather in Northridge
Completely literally understand the words
I'm not sure sure that's so important
But I don't think Sheila when she was singing Desperado
Reading knew what a lot of those references were about
But you certainly captured the feeling of the song
Why don't you
But I know that
Disney
When I heard other school choirs in
Vis-a-vis so different
So weird
Any good to know how to sing
I never thought of it in terms of its special cuz it was good I was out of interns it was special cuz it was different
Oftentimes habitat 69
Kids in my class
And it'd be all over the place because there's no room and we have instruments
We had no equipment so I brought in all the equipment for my band
Which were used Marshall amplifiers in
Bass guitars and all kinds of things are kids supposed to really like that
Said it wasn't much room in kids room
Practically on top of one another and
I just saw
Arrange them according to height
I always felt like with my music teaching that I always was an outsider music
Teacher you know I mean
I never I never really put
2 pages in a lot of
Music
Teaching events and all that kind
The stuff I was always like those little Island.
To myself you know people always uses this term
Like thinking outside the box and all that but it's
I think
For me I didn't even know there was a bomb
You know I mean
It does have the sort of the Children of the Corn
Hyatt does it does have that feeling well I think we were kind of like a little call
It became kind of a
What type of an underground hit in New York
Tony Visconti who is David Bowie
Producer had heard it and
I think he thought it was a New Wave band
New Jersey
I couldn't quite believe it was a bunch of little kids on some Farm country in Canada
Yeah I have students
Facility music to this day
They're always in touch with me I jam with some of them once in awhile
I felt that the whole success of this would you really vindicating kind of
Experience it made me feel really like
Wow I can't do something
So it was great I mean when you know what I'd always taught by students in a really positive way and then
When somebody suddenly is positive about what you doing like that and it gives you a great feeling
Arun Katie mingle talk to Hans finger of the Langley schools music project in 2010 for the show ReSound produced by the
Third Coast International audio Fest
You want to hear Innovative documentaries from all over the world
You must subscribe to the ReSound podcast
And here are some fun facts
I worked on ReSound Third Coast for 3 years and during that time
I heard Delaney Hall at lintern in 2006 it was her first radio job
Delaney took over
And she hired
Katie Mingle
Eventually took over the show herself
No we don't work here
If you like us
Will take ReSound
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Shawn colimit Fitzgerald and Katie mingle mix into production by Sharif
Yusuf music by genre
Tripp Halstead is the digital director press the team include senior editor Delaney Hall
SoJO Rosenberg Vivien Leigh and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX independent Collective
The most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Von Maur
At radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show endurance custom about the show on Facebook even tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
I need more 99 Pi my life old episodes
And you are told about the sign every couple of days
Our website
It's 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com