99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Ivy Myers grew up in Brooklyn and married a guy she'd known since they were kids
Their first son David was born in 1968
By the time David was to
I be noticed something was different about him
David's face with twitch
He sometimes made involuntary noises
His arms flailed around out of control
So he can barely feed himself
He was very disturbed
By the other kids would make fun of him
David's teachers often got upset with him in class
So you can imagine the
Torture that he went through
One Sunday morning David with eight
Abby Watkin try to read the funnies
But he couldn't keep his head steady enough
That's producer Dan Weisman
Host of a new podcast about the cost of healthcare
Called an arm and a leg
Watching David struggle with the comics Abby was ready to cry
She put off doing the dishes
Sat down and picked up another section of the paper
End
2 total coincidence
It was an article about a teenager who had symptoms
Just like David's
Facial tics
Weird noises
Flaming Lips
I stood up and I yelled for my husband and I said you have to read this
This is what David has
Abby and her husband brought the article to David's pediatrician
And the doctor agreed
This story described exactly what David had
This condition will sound familiar to you but
Time most people even doctors
I've never heard of it
It was called
Tourette syndrome
Speaking to doctors many doctors after that
They said they never heard of it because they simply
We're not talk very much about Reggie season
The medical school
Back then
When so few people heard of
Direct was considered a super rare
It just seemed bizarre to me that I got a diagnosis out of a Sunday newspaper
From there a b sound a special
Eventually turned her on to a potential treatment for Tourette syndrome
It was being tested out
Clinical trials
Well
It wasn't being tested for Tourette's
The drug company was mainly hoping to Market this drug
Schizophrenia
The particular drug had been made available in Europe
For a while and taxes
New it worked on Tourette's
So David got in on a trial for this drug with the hopes that it could be approved in the US
It turned out
It works really well for him
But
The drug trial
Didn't go as well for schizophrenia
Which was supposed to be its more common use so the drug company decided the market wasn't big
They just drop the drug entirely
It's so good company she'll suck no
They wouldn't do it
They wouldn't make the truck they wouldn't sell it
And this is how Abby learn to term that would define the next few Decades of her life
Orphan drugs
Orphan
Drugs
As Abby learned
Drug companies weren't interested in developing treatments for rare conditions
Because the big money was in drugs with tons of customers
Antibiotics
Drugs for stuff like diabetes high cholesterol
They just didn't think selling a drug for Tourette's would be a big moneymaker
So promising treatments like the one that have been working for David
Became orphan drugs
With no Pharma company to raise them
To keep yourself from going nuts with frustration
Abby Meyers joined at the Tourette Syndrome Association
It's pretty small
Immediately invited her to join the board
And
Ask her what you wanted to be in charge of
I sure did that want to become the fundraiser or the arranger of special dinners or anything
Do you like that
And I wasn't the doctor so I didn't want to do the research end of it
That left Lobby
And advocacy
Spreading awareness
Abby started figuring out how to do that
She found a mentor
Her name with Margery got
Marjorie was the Widow of Woody Guthrie
The iconic American folk singer who wrote the song This Land Is Your Land
Woody had died in the 1960s
Huntington
Another rare disease
She was on a mission
Pharrell life
Which was
True
Find the answers for Huntington's disease
Marjorie was
React
By the time a d Myers started lobbying
Everybody connected with rare diseases new Margery got
Marjorie
Marjorie would be talking with Scientists or Pharma exec
And they be using technical jargon
She say please talk to me in plain English
I'm just a house
And they would
And when experts couldn't hide behind technical jargon Marjorie Guthrie would pin them down put them on the record
And use their words as ammunition
Branson
Experts to explain exactly how promising a proposed drug might be
Why they would sell it
And all of that
Would be in there and you're in plain English
So when Abby started meeting with government officials
She introduced herself the same way
Just a housewife
She figured it wouldn't be a bad thing to let them
Underestimate her a little
I found the people
Boys22
Think about a woman as somebody's just trying to raise her kids
She's just a housewife
By June 1980
Abby and Marjorie and their allies
Got a California Congressman to hold a hearing to call attention to the problem
Orphan drugs
This was their big chance to finally have a national audience
Different Pharma companies on the spot
To make them face the patients who were waiting for
Maybe this hearing could really changed
Well
Nobody from the pharmaceutical industry showed up
Also
Hardly any elected representatives showed up
Well no Republicans at all showed up
Maybe one or two congressmen stuck their head in and sat down for 5 minutes and then left
The gallery was pretty empty to
It was like nobody was there except
The very very last row in the room
A young man was sitting there
And I had no idea who he was
And the
Turned out that he was a reporter
For the Los Angeles Times
It was a local store
One of the people testify
A teenage boy with Tourette's
Was from Los Angeles
It resulted in a very short
Buried in the middle of the paper
Nobody was likely to see it
Except somebody did
If you're old enough to have watched
TV in the 1970s
The name
Jack Klugman instantly
Conjure a raspy voice
Baijiu New Yorker
The sitcom The Odd Couple it was huge
Jack Klugman played a middle-aged slob whose roommates
Houdini
Christmas present I forgot to give it to you Merry Christmas
Assorted cheeses
When that show ended Jack Klugman got his own brand new TV show
Kind of detective series
He played a medical examiner
Call Quincy
The Quincy show which was nice entertainment about a doctor who looks at dead bodies
Decided
Who the murderer was
It was like a precursor to CSI and it was kind of a big deal.
World of forensic medicine and after that little story the Los Angeles Times came out
Abby got a call from some but you said
He was a producer on the Quincy show
She was skeptical
Thought you said yes and I mrs. Santa Claus
But after a few minutes on the phone
She realize
The guy was telling the truth
He was a producer for Quincy
Any happen to have
Fairly rare disease himself
In fact
Who is dying
Optum cancer
And so he
So this whole say with orphan drugs
Is
Beautiful story and I'd really like to do an episode
Of Quincy about it
His name was Maurice
Klugman
He was Jack Klugman
Brother I mean these things happened in the movies that what happens with real people
And that's what happened
The episode actually got made
It happened and in the episode a teenager with Tourette's dies under suspicious circumstances
Turns out
It's not exactly a murder
But by the time Quincy figures that out
He meets another young man with Tourette's
And get
Obsessed
Problem
Orphan drug
Is Quincy
Document that kids death
If you got a disease that happen to have a low incidence
Don't count on the pharmaceutical companies
That's why they call them orphan drugs
Merrick
Chores for rare diseases that no one wants to adopt
Listen to go before Congress that supposed to deal with all this drug bill it still being considered
They should have suddenly goes from a mystery
To a policy drop
Quincy it goes all-in on the orphan drugs
He lobbied Pharma companies
The FDA Congressman becomes a total policy nerd
At the big finish the kid with Tourette's after a
Pep talk by Quincy
Gives a blockbuster speech at a congressional hearing
I'm thinking about
The other victims
I might just have tourettes
But anyone who is unlucky enough
To have a disease that never made it to the top 40
This Congressional hearing was obviously fiction
But it got a real-world response
When that show was broadcast
Jack Klugman receive
Thousands and thousands of letters
And they didn't even open up they just
How do you spell exactly will like
Santa Claus facts
And they stuffed animal into them
And they sent all of those
Sex
Tumi
The letters were from people with rare diseases and people who just wanted to do something to help solve the orphan drug problem
This kind of publicity and support
Abby and her friend got another Congressional hearing
On March 10th
Real-life elected officials heard testimony about a real-life proposal
To create Financial incentives for Pharma companies to take on Orphan drugs
On hand to give that proposal a boost of star power was Jack Klugman himself
The actor food Washington and testified in this new Hearing in Congress this time it was packed
People just sat down on the floor in the aisles
Because Jack Klugman was in the room
I'm telling you Jack Klugman was a big deal in those days
An orphan drug bill passed the house but
It got stalled in the Senate
Where Abby heard a single Senator was secretly blocking a
It was rumored to be Orrin Hatch
So Jack Klugman and his crew swing into action
They do another episode of Quincy
One single Senator is holding up an orphan drug bill
In the climactic scene Quincy confronts that senator in his DC office
I choose to keep going against this
And you should be ready for the reaction
I won't be in a reaction
I play this course too many times
Or maybe the rules have been changed
I'm just take a look out there
Window shutters
Senator glances incredulously toward the window
Doctor Quincy
Ben both guys turn
Walk
Solemnly over
Is huge picture window and
Out in the street
Big demonstration heading straight toward the Senator's office
Camera zooms past the two men that focuses on the action outside
There are
Hundreds of people lock them in wheelchairs
Colorful signs with slogans like
Now is the time
Vote for the orphan drug deal
Can
In a direct pitch to be fictional Senator watching through the window
We need you Senator Reeves
The sequence Wingers
And lingers and lingers these extras
Are all actual people with rare diseases that Abby Meyers and her colleagues recruited
Except
Not actually in Washington they shot it in Pasadena or the weather was better
The fake March on Washington
Totally work
The fake Senator on the show
I cannot support this bill but I won't stand on its way
And so did the real life senator
Orrin Hatch
There would not be an orphan Drug Act if it was not for that episode of Quincy
The orphan Drug Act
Pass the Senate
President Ronald Reagan signed into law
The fake March on Washington
Became in some people's minds
A real life event
People will say to me that March on Washington was wonderful
There wasn't the March on Washington
But you know it was on TV
Abby Meyers went on to help start a new advocacy
The National Organization for rare disorders
She ran it for more than 20 years
These days
When people ask her about her Legacy
This is what she tells
Be careful what you
Wish for
It might come true
The orphan Drug Act of 1983
Created Financial incentives
Pharma companies to develop drugs to treat
Orphan conditions
Urine Drug Act basically says
Once the FDA agrees proposed treatment
A rare condition undercurrent definition that means that affect
Fewer than 200 thousand people in the US
Ben
Developer qualifies for special goodies
That includes subsidy
Actual taxpayer cash
Clinical trials
And
A big prize at the end
First drug company to get FDA approval
For certain kind of treatment
Market
Exclusivity
Basically
No one else can Market an equivalent drug in the US for 7 years
Which means that during that seven-year period the company gets a chance to make money off this drug even if relatively few people
Music by setting a higher than usual price
You know if you have a drug for
High blood pressure
It's probably half of the United States needs blood pressure medicine
But with a rare disease you're not going to make money if you charge your normal price for those
Amendra companies realize that if they had a monopoly
It didn't have to charge anything that would be remotely considered a normal price
They can charge pretty much whatever they want it
Especially if the insurance companies were paying for it
It took Pharma companies a few years to catch on to how good a deal the orphan Drug Act be
But by the 1990s
Things were definitely rolling
One rare disease drug came out in 1991 with a price tag of 150
$1,000 a year
It was
Huge money
Biotechnology and Healthcare companies
This is Joshua Sean
And he's one of the many entrepreneurs
Who took advantage of the orphan drug policy
His path to the big Pharma money let through
Las Vegas
It was great
Just how Wild West
This new world
Could be in 2003 Joshua shine started a company called Lev Pharmaceuticals
And this company had just one mission
A single thing it was going to do
Lev Pharmaceuticals
Was going to Market a drug for a rare disorder called hereditary angioedema
Actually
The drug already existed
It has been used successfully in Europe for 30 years
But nobody had taken it through clinical trials in the US
I look like a good setup
It seems like a very good opportunity from its Inception
We saw a serious unmet clinical need in the US
To bring this treatment from Europe to the point where it could be sold in the US
Message Josh wish I would have to raise enough money for live Pharmaceutical
Which
Would be a lot easier to do
As a publicly traded company
And that's how they found
Fun City popcorn
Brightest on a typical path
Biotech companies
Fun City popcorn sold popcorn and nacho cheese sauce
The concessionaires all around Las Vegas
Malls
Ballparks
Skating rinks
Yunnan
Of course lived in Pursuit FunCity for their nacho cheese sauce recipe
It turned out fun cities owners were getting out of the popcorn & concession business
And they were game to try something new
FunCity agreed to actually merge with metformin
Bestowing on love
Their status as a publicly traded company
Which
Made it easier for love to attract even more in bed
But for a few months until they can get the paperwork sorted out
They had to go by the name
Funfetti popcorn
We felt we could
Overcome
Fun City popcorn than any other jokes that might bring up did people catch you about it
All the way to bank
Over the next few years
Lev Pharmaceuticals raise about 75 million dollars
To pay for the clinical trial that would win FDA approve
Of course Joshua shine still had to get the trials done and do it
Before anyone else
After all the orphan Drug Act
Is set up to give a monopoly to whoever gets to the treatment
First
Finishing second
Commune losing whole investment
It was a real horse race
So you could finish the trials
And shine one that's particular race
Yeah I'm very pleased with how this work out at workout most importantly for patients
And of course he's also glad it worked out for the shareholders
Please set up a company that we were able to provide a return
It was a
Big return
A 2008
A couple weeks before the FDA gave the new drug its final approval
Lev Pharmaceuticals sold for 442 million dollars
And within a few years
The new owner was making 400 million dollars
Back from this one drug
Every
Year thanks for price tag that made this one of the world
Most expensive drugs
More than half a million bucks
A year
Per patient
That owner
Sold itself to a
Still bigger company
44.2
Billion dollars
That Company CEO says that the company's entire strategy is to make money from the treatment of rare diseases
The orphan Drug Act and the crazy pricing that is its Legacy
Is this company's whole vision
For making tons of money
This is why I be Meyers has mixed
Feelings about her Legacy
35 years later the orphan Drug Act
Has been responsible for the most miraculous
Treatments
Many many diseases
But some of the companies that make
These drugs I put
Prices on number that is makes the drugs absolutely unaffordable
In other words it's like a ransom note
Thousands of Desperately ill people
Joshua Shine from left Pharmaceuticals has a different perspective
He says
It is hard enough to get money to develop these drugs
Even with
The orphan Drug Act incentives
2 payout
Drug by hugely expensive Isabella
And the failures
Far far outnumber the successes and without a system in place like you're the Drug Act
Of course it doesn't have to be this way
Abby Meyers and others have their own proposals for out-of-balance incentives with reasonable prices
It's a giant debate
If you look at a list of the most expensive drugs
You noticed two things
Unbelievably
Tens of thousands of dollars a month
And
They are generally for air condition
Insurance companies patients
Dothan contributes to the
Spiraling cost of Health
It's going to take more than a fake TV March on Washington
The fix the problem
If you'd like to know more about how the cost of healthcare has gotten so messed up and what we may be able to do about it
You just like really good storytelling
Check out Dan weitsmans new podcast called an arm and a leg
But more about that show after the break
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black podcast
Dan Weisman is a journalist based in Chicago you may remember that he reported a couple
Stories with us over the years about the reversing of the Chicago River
And how the popularity of Billiards drove the development of plastic
And as we mentioned he now has a show about Healthcare
Called an arm and a leg
I asked him why he was compelled to create a podcast
About this particular subject
I've been interested in this topic for a long time and partly for personal reasons
I thought about
Going out of my own as
Reporter and said
Work for somebody else
For a while I want to do but
Who's going to buy the health insurance for a family
My wife
Classroom business
Unthinkable
And I found myself
1 jobs
Crap I might need
A new career
Which was really
Sad for me
Is this one thing
This kind of running my life and I I know I'm not the only person
Which is
Yeah the cost of healthcare and the need for
Health insurance
Expensive that
You just drives
So many decisions
For so many people
I don't see
A conversation about
Or kind of accessible conversation about
How do we get here
Or anything any of us can do
Annies
How did we get here the driving question
Or is it how do we solve it look where do you place the emphasis in the show
That is a super good question
It's a good question
I I think
Because of my disposition
They're like
Are some good stories in how we got
There's two
Good things about that in one is it
Understanding how we got here might help us
Understand a little bit
About how we could
Make people better
Innocent like
One of the things
Is it
Bee Company
Keep it like we're all kind of scared and angry and can
Refused
End
Telling some interesting maybe fun stories
Is also just a way to
Half the time to bring her blood pressure down
To the point we actually
We could like see our way clear to do
As you've been Gathering the stories
Is there an underlying theme that submerged
That
Surprised
Surprise me first was just from talking to
Gout
Doing the show
Every
Single person
I would talk to mrs.
I'd say pretty much remained
Will either write
Off the bat
Or as we get to talkin do you like oh yeah well
This is a story that happened to me
Probably the single biggest private life ever
Every
One of these examples in your pilot with your friend Peter can you describe the situation with Peter
Is a real estate developer
Ndk
Makes a perfectly good salary
Yeah you know the health insurance at my job
Just keeps getting worse and worse
And last year my deductible was like
$18,000
Person
Oh wait and did I tell you about when I had the kidney stone last
You know
I put off going to get help for as long as I possibly could
Cuz he was like they're just going to charge money not be able to do anything for him
And he finally breaks down his wife makes him go to the hospital
And they give him an MRI
And
He is kicking himself
And they told me exactly what I knew that I had a kidney stone
And that's why he was passing and I'm like thank you very much
And then
I get the bill
Well it was $6,500
Oh my God and you had it was all on you
It was all on me
It didn't help me in any way shape or form
And then I'm left with this bill
Peter one of the things that I find
You know offland
It's about the story
Is
A real estate developer you know
Your real estate
Negotiating with
People likes a contract resume most people would
Never thinks they were
Slicking up to 2
Is what you actually do for a living
And I can't negotiate this
And so if you want to hear that story and its entirety you have to subscribe to an arm and a leg
Thank you. I appreciate it
99percentinvisible with produces week by Dan Weisman and edited by Avery trufelman
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
The rest of Team includes Emmett Fitzgerald
Senior editor Delaney Hall Joe Rosenberg Vivien Leigh Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia by PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Rosendahl up podcasting
Von Maur
Radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show endurance questions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Instagram Tumblr invited to
But this week I think it's a good idea to check out Dan weisman's other than IDI stories
On our website just use the handy search function
And 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com