99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman numerals
If you look at the outer Hall of commercial ships
Down by the water like you might find a painted Circle
Bisected
They long horizontal line
The simple marking is called the load line
Or as I prefer
The plimsoll line
And not oversell it
But this elegant graphic design has saved
Thousands of Lies
Examples of design because
What I really like
In the world
When you can find a massive problem that definitely needs solving and with some thought
We consulted with something as simple
Has a circle with a line through it
That's what I'd like to do with my Korea
Best Tristan cook
And on a human factors engineer so that means
He said I look at the white
People interact with their environment
Text Debbie Harry
Tristan also creates an outstanding blog called humans in design
The massive problem that needed solving in the 19th century that Tristan is referring to
Was the huge number of British ships sinking in the ocean
Because they were overloaded and in disrepair
Sending hundreds
Emergency mental watery grave the problem was so widespread that these vessels became known by another name
Coffin ships
Coughing
Now overloading ships has certainly happened since there have been ships to overload
It was the introduction of insurance
Decorated the coffin ship
That still collect real time for ships that are over insured so they worth more money to
At the bottom of the ocean
Lara Floyd
Social boners would purposely overload older ships with cargo
Thinking that if the ships made it they hit the jackpot
British ships didn't make it
They still made a lot of money on the insurance claim
Insurance that people want quiet
Aware of the idea to buy
Sharing something you were going to
Changing affect people's
Behavior this is called a moral hazard
When people engage in Risky Behavior because they are not fully accountable for the consequences
Insurance is going to keep every
It doesn't
Ensure that changes your behavior become more risky or you haven't
Incentive
To do something
In the unintended consequence of insurance
Was that ship owners had an incentive
To sink their own ships
And send hundreds of souls to the bottom of the ocean
Tonight's famous
What is the one called ESS London that had 200
Thirtysomething people on board it was leaving a place and I'm not kidding
Called Gravesend in England
Theoretically headed for Melbourne Australia
The Royal wiper
Things like that
Was in a meeting
Hundreds in
Extol
I try to send back to what the port
This is where our hero British MP Samuel plimsoll
And the plimsoll line comes in
Dust off to that happen
Plimsoll
I said to the British Parliament
And he
Wanted to pause a bunch
New shipping safety laws based upon his knowledge of
This Disaster
But passing the safety laws was not easy for plimsoll because it just so happens that
Murderous
Regulation haidian Emerald capitalist and their friends
Sometimes
Serve as elected officials
The owners that didn't go next regulation
Oceanside
Actually a family Lodge in a trouble getting
Solomon took his case to the people
Play Saul write a book called a salmon which it was really Champion the issue and that
Went really wide and eventually due to widespread public support the merchant shipping Act of 1876
Text was passed
It required the simple elegant graphic I described earlier a circle with a long horizontal line.
Be painted on the outside of the hall to show the maximum loading point of the ship
The mark let a third-party know plainly and clearly one of us was being overloaded and at risk of sinking in rough
Prophecies
If you see that horizontal line above the water they're good
If you don't
Well
You could be song
It's just kind of really pretty you looking to look at that initially it's
Very
Geometric
And some form of the plimsoll line remains on ships to this day
Flight mode
Application site
In different Waters or saltwater or
Freshwater with different sorts
Starships
You're allowed to loiter
What's the different levels of it's just a couple of days
Levels on the outside
Personally I think it's a nice
These days
Is that
Different sight images
United States GPS
Drive themselves halfway through everywhere
But
When it gets down to it the thing that is
Is most importantly keeping a boat afloat
Is still just a circle with a line through it
On a towel
It's just a bit of paint
There been numerous poems and songs sung about Samuel plimsoll
Overtime his name is faded even though his mark on the world lives on
It's fate actually less known as a
Twin Soul line now I'm over the line but at the time it was
Was definitely known as a
Plimsoll line
But if I've done my job today you dear listener
Only call it
A plimsoll line
Because
It seems like the right and honorable thing
And besides
If there's an opportunity to use an eponym
Use the eponym
Just
Cooler
Are cars upon the ocean he struggles to defend
Successful Samuel plimsoll
Chinese the sailors
99% invisible was produced this week by me Roman Mars would help from Tristan cook and Tom Nelson
Curate the blog humans in design
This program is made possible with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity the product of kalw 91.7 local public radio in
San Francisco the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
To find out more including a link to the blog humans and design go to our website it's 99% invisible
. org
Life Is Life
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com