99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The city of Toronto has a special relationship
With raccoons
Or at least
They think they
You're not the only city with raccoons but we often act like we are
We like to think Toronto is the raccoon capital of the world
And were strangely proud of that distinction
But we really have no data to back it up
This is Amy Dempsey
The reporter for the Toronto Star
Do we have more raccoons and say Chicago or Vancouver
Well we don't actually know you can't count Urban raccoons they're all over the place
But who needs data when you can
Feel it in your heart
A few years ago when a raccoon died on Young Street
Torontonians named in Conrad and built a vigil around his body with
Flowers
In a framed photo
Cards
So if science ever disproved this idea
Of Toronto is raccoon Nation I really fear for Toronto I think we're going to have an identity crisis
Toronto's feelings about raccoons are not uncomplicated
Our relationship with raccoons is kind of a love-hate relationship
We hate when they destroy our grass and break into our houses
And yes they do break into our houses
Maybe worse than all this though
Was the raccoons proclivity for getting into the compost
What's the city started collecting for the residents
In green bins several years ago
From the perspective of the raccoon
These Campos bands were an incredible development
An all-you-can-eat buffet with the plastic and other garbage RT
Thoughtfully removed
And the raccoons will go to town on our stuff and just spread it everywhere
And you wake up
Look out your window and go s***
And then maybe you'd argue with your spouse or roommates about who'd have to clean it up
The green bins become a feast a veritable Feast For the raccoons this is Toronto mayor John Tory a few years ago
Go dressed in a blue suit in front of a row of Canadian flags if he's announcing a plan to
Step up the war on crime
In a way
He was probably nothing that represents more of a nuisance
In a big city like this
Dan of the feasting of the raccoons on the contents of
Set the green bins
End the war on raccoons
Started started with Mayor John Tory
They're hungry
And they're determined
But our job
Together with our private sector reinforced
I is to show them
That we are smarter
He said things like
We are armed we are motivated
We have left a nose
Stone unturned in our fight against raccoon Nation
The reason muir-torre felt so prepared that day was that the city was unveiling a new raccoon resistant green bin
Organic waste
During the same press conference the mirror held up new been victoriously
Ended up with reporters as cameras Flash
I would say it was 75% tongue and cheek
But there was also a hint of seriousness to it it was pretty clear
But he was confident the new green bins would solve our raccoon problems
Confident enough to stand in front of news cameras and say
Is not an option
But Amy was about to find out for herself
Weather defeat
Was an option
And spoiler alert
It was an option
Let's back up just a bit
This all started the way most things starting cities
With an RFP. PDF
Yeah they put out a request for proposals
Asking for a new generation green bin
And emphasizing
That it had to be rodent resistant
AKA
Animal resistant AKA raccoon proof
Please
The company that one
Was called
Rehrig
Pacific Dennis monestier with
Rehrig Pacific and I serve as the environmental sales manager
Canada
If the city of Toronto was in a war with raccoons this ladies and gentlemen
Was the General
In charge of a major front
And he took his role
Very seriously
I mean rehrig Pacific takes
New product development very very seriously and and there's a five pronged approach
Which we initiate
Dennis is in many ways
A classic sales guy
He wears shirts with his company logo he has a firm handshake
I found him to be
Extremely helpful and genuine
When he speaks about the green bin you can tell
He's really proud of it it's something that I'm very very passionate about not only being part of the design
Team
But I'm also Raisin in the city of Toronto so I know
What it means to me as a resident
Rehrig Pacific had a number of design criteria they were trying to meet with their green bin program
For example
Ben's would need to be picked up and dumped by an automatic on that reached out from the truck
The bandwidth need a lid that closed and locked to protect against raccoons
But the lid would also have to open up automatically when the bed was turned upside down and dumped into the truck by the owner
So we have to ensure that the lock itself disengages 100% of the time the container must
Function in extreme weather conditions
Ergonomics Easley open with one single hat we are looking at
You don't safety kids end up in the darndest places
Definitely don't want them in organic container but more importantly we don't want them locked inside the container Wheels limit
Nation of internal CashPoints any material that becomes trapped inside the container could pose significant risk
With respect to the X Factor for the residence
On top of the X Factor in the meddling kids
Rehrig Pacific had to think about Enemy Number One
The raccoons
Yes so we worked with an urban raccoon specialist to basic
Sickly understand
Raccoons likes
Dislike
Stair dexterity what they can and cannot do it was a local raccoon specialist by the name of
Suzanne McDonald's Dr Suzanne McDonald professor at York University
Study animal behavior calling her a raccoon specialist really downplays her accomplishments she is
A professor of biology and psychology
You have studied
Just about every animal you can think of
She may have studied every animal you can think of but in Toronto there's only one animal that matters
In Toronto everybody tour
I work in Vancouver lot and nobody talks about raccoons are there raccoons all the time
So she wasn't that surprised when we are Pacific got in touch as they were designing there been
And
Asked me to talk to them about
Are raccoons work and I did
Will raccoons are omnivores
So that means I can eat
Everything
Really good teeth theyll use them
They don't want to use them
They want you to go away
You go away girl my yard
They also get a taste for human food
So once they get a taste for that Indian take out that we've thrown out that they've enjoyed our men on
Like berries I'm not eating berries we look at them they look at us
If you would look at a monkey in the face that look away
But reckons don't they look right out of
They look right through
You know they have pretty good senses of smell they have pretty good vision
But touches their superpower
I'm very persistent
It will work in a problem for hours and hours and hours and they're pretty strong
Rehrig Pacific took all of this information and applied it
Is there been design
There was multiple generations of the design
If multiple photorealistic rendering
In the end they came out with a Ben they believed in
It's an olive green 26 gallon container
That closes and locks
We felt
Very very confident with the success of that locking
Mechanism and the container itself
So
The new green bin rollout
Took about 18 months from start to finish
People are waiting for their new green bins and people are getting
Really excited about these things before they were rolled out on my street
They were rolled out on some of the streets nearby so
People on my street would have to walk by and see
At homes near us
Had the new green bin and we didn't
And you
It's sort of be thinking on your walk to the subway to go to work like
The hell where
Where's my Ben
But eventually Amy did get a bin of her own
So on the list
There is
A dial
Like a handle
That you turn
And
When it's in the
Horizontal position is open
When it's in the vertical position
It's secure
It's locked
You actually have to turn it in a way
That really would make it
Difficult if not impossible to turn if you don't have opposable thumbs
And contrary to popular belief
Raccoons don't have opposable thumbs
Even though they can move the thumb like did it on there creepy little hands
Little bit
For a while everything seems to be going according to plan
It's like some people worried
The new bands with working too well
In other words people were afraid that without the green bins as a food source
Maybe the raccoons were starving
So the way I became involved in all of this was
That in January of 2018
A friend sent me a note saying that he believed the new green bins
Had eliminated the raccoon population in Toronto
He actually use the word eliminated
Is any Intrepid reporter would do
Amy decided to look into it
I wrote a quick email to
Suzanne McDonald our local raccoon expert
And I said
Hey
Could racoons be dying
She decides
They're probably hiding from the cold
But she says
She would have more information a few months she said after I measure more dead raccoons
So a five-course wrote back immediately and said
Can I come
Animal Control was collecting raccoons killed by cars and storing them in freezers for Suzanne then come
Man and measure them in order to track the health of the population
From year to year and I do this
4 times a year
When you go in July it turns out and you bring up Frozen raccoon carcasses and it takes a while to measure them
They start to melt
Oh dear God you can imagine the maggots and the
All the things
That's fine I mean Society
Sweet Polly push through
Suzanne wouldn't have results of her data for a while
But while Amy was there watching her measured dead raccoons
Chester
Do you think it's possible they could learn how to get into the new green bin
And
She shook her head no she said
You know she'd filmed them trying and not one of them could do it she just said they won't they won't
Directions won't break into the
Into these green Vans
On the Raccoon proof
Green vandalism video
That was
Then about a week later
This story comes out
The look see your laughs
So watch a zoom into it here
Basically
Local Toronto resident who
Has film the video of a raccoon
Opening
His grain bin
Ask if that little tuck are we going
And just like kind of winking at the camera almost
Really
This was not the only report of a band being broken into
Although it was the first to include video which quickly went viral
Much to the dismay
Dennis monast
From rehrig Pacific
For somebody just to come out and say all the container doesn't work
You know it's frustrating
The videos going to says don't tell the whole story
A couple of break-ins
Doesn't mean the design is flawed
The screw might be loosened too much
And if you just simply tighten it
A little bit
It might
Prevent the issue
Dennis is frustrated by the fact that
Sometimes when people have issues with their green beans
They don't call the city they don't report their issues to 311
Instead they sometimes
Call
Local newspaper
And then it becomes a story
I think you said something to me like
You know when your car breaks down you don't call the Toronto Star
You call the mechanic
I don't know if for some reason you know Toronto specifically that they loved it glamorize raccoon
The city for its part playing the handful of break-ins on user error
And the city's response was to suggest that these homeowners
Locking their bins properly and to emphasize they had only had a handful of complaints at a 400
Green Vans
The suggestion being that if Joe in Yorkville had a problem with his Ben
And maybe the problem was Joe
And not the Ben
So
Soon after I woke up one morning and walked outside
And saw that
My neighbor's green bin was on the ground and Arlene way
And there was
Food
Everywhere
So I texted my neighbor and said
Directions of garden into your green bin
She said you know what the hell kind of raccoons
Get into the
The green Vans now
This point Amy had been convinced by the city's argument
There was no problem with the Benz the problem was the users
But you didn't lock it properly
I still have the text message and when I read it I cringe a little bit
Thank you locked it properly
Caroline
But Amy didn't get to space mode for long
Two nights later
Her own been with Wonder
My
Husband and I get it
Group text message from Caroline
Directions of gotten into your green bin
At this point on Floors because
My husband is a person who locks
Thanks and checks locks
67 *
It seemed the reporter
I just become a character
Your Own Story
I'm thinking like first of all
Do they like this is so weird that they know that I was looking into the stuff
Am I being targeted
Amy Cole the city who said ma'am please you probably just have a broken handle
And they said some workers out to fix
And they replace the lid on my band as if
Caution
Even though they
Couldn't find anything
Wrong with it
She also wrote to the raccoon
Expert Suzanne McDonald who was
Because
She's always secretly been on Team raccoon
She wrote back almost immediately and said that
Is
Awesome
And she said
I'm going to I'm going to loan you a trail camera
And you have to see how they're doing it
So I get the I get the camera from Suzanne
We meet up at the zoo one day
I go to our local grocery store and I got a couple of chickens
Put the chicken in the green bin
Some of the chicken grease all over the grain bin
The first night raccoons did not come
The second night I went out
To the front porch actually with my toddler
We peeked around the corner
And my my daughter said
Then was down
Is a mess
I took the camera upstairs
And press play
On the video that I captured
It's almost as though the raccoons knew what I was doing and they were like let's give her a really good
Shah here
This one is going to go viral
Cameras pointing at
The bends
And then all of a sudden this
This mama raccoon
Come skulking out
And
She just pulled the bend down like
She gets out of the way like at this point you can tell she knows what she's doing when she's not going to stand in the way and get crushed by the Ben
No she's going to pull it at the exact right angle and it just falls down with like
And turns around and looks at the camera
As if to say
Watch this
And then she turns the handle into soap it likes it turns it opens it just like I would
And then they go
The key seem to be knocking down the bin
Which made the handle much easier to turn
When it's on the ground you can just kind of
Holonis
Like as if you're pulling a lever
You know you can almost bet your paws added or like pull it to the side
On August 30th
2018 Amy published an article in the Toronto Star with her video
And as these things tend to do in Toronto
It went viral
Thousands of torontonians watched
As the protagonist handily pulled down the Ben
Flashing her glowing eyes at the camera
Showed off how easily
She could open it
Amy got a bunch of emails and comments on the article
People saying that this was happening to them too
The city maintained
They were getting relatively few complaints overall
What Amy told them as monitor
Cathay pacific
But the raccoons were getting into the bin that his company designed
He decided to pay her house call
You know I personally wanted to go out there myself to
Inspect the container and to do some pork for testing on the handle itself
Some Heroes don't wear capes
Paper polo shirts
Company logo on the breast pocket
The date Dennis came over
My neighbor Mike came over
As soon as he saw this guy in my driveway working on the green bin
But Mike had no idea that
This is
The green van guy
It seemed like there was a gang of neighbors that came up all of a sudden out of nowhere and it was just like
All we have in a week we had we have some some problems with with the raccoons getting into our bins
Getting in everybody's been and he's just
Ripping on
The green bins
And the waste of money
Dennis took it all like a champ
He tightened up everyone's handles so they be particularly hard for little raccoon Paws to turn
But it hasn't solved the problem
Having accepted defeat
Amy nail keeps her bins tied to a wall so raccoons can't knock them over
And she can't help but Wonder
How soon
What this knowledge about how to open the Benz spreads
The rest
The raccoon Nation
Raccoons don't
Teach each other these things but
It's called social learning and even most monkeys don't do that
And so it's not like this
Innovation is going to spread across the city
Suzanne McDonald doesn't think most raccoons in Toronto currently have what it takes to get into the new green compost bins
That perfect combination of strength
Intelligence and determination
Amy just happen to encounter
An extra gifted one
We call her the genius raccoon because I think it's amazing that she did it
Suzanne finally finished her dead raccoon study
Toronto's favorite front of me is as bad as ever
She thinks that's because even though most of them can't get into the compost
They moved on to a different solution
Good old-fashioned
Garbage
Are raccoons are not starving to death that's for sure
She doesn't rule out that Anna for all future
We might end up creating an Uber raccoon
One like Amy's that can get into just about anything
She studied raccoons in cities and they are on the whole
Smarter than their world counterparts
Urban raccoons are constantly having new problems place in front of them to solve
And they keep figuring them out
And Suzanne and Dennis both tell people that the green beans were never advertised as raccoon proof
Only raccoon resistant
Nothing
Is raccoon proof they say
Which is a small concession that well the front of the line is holding for now
The war
Against raccoons
Continues
More raccoon news with our in-house raccoon correspondent Kurt Kolstad
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
If you listen to the show record
You know that Kurt Cole said has a background in Arkansas
But you also read the articles on our side
You probably also know
He's really into raccoons to
So when these two interest intersect
Say a raccoon going viral on the internet
Climbing up a downtown Saint Paul office tower earlier this year
All over that store
Oh yeah instant
Local news is there covering the story on the scene in Minnesota
But I'm out here
Actual building that the raccoon is crying
I got super into it
Asada material they started
Diagramming
The route
Raccoon totem
The top
So if you want like a
Like straight up
Kennedy assassination style deconstruction
That old saw that you can check out our website
Too far off
Curtis here today with a story of a different
Famous raccoon
From nearly a century ago
That eventually
Resided in a particularly famous work of American architect
The White House
Oh yes
History's not exactly
There's this one in particular that really saying that
Especially around Thanksgiving
Her name is Rebecca
In the 1920s
She was sent to president count
Coolidge
In Mississippi
But this raccoon wasn't meant to be a pet
The idea was actually that should be served up as part of the holiday
Which is not the most traditional Thanksgiving meal
You know I mean not
Today at least but a century ago
Wild animals
Much more common to see
Dinner plates
Meals with Docker turtle or opossum work
Typical minute some cases that were even Regional delicacy
And then also you know sending animals as food to the White House for the holidays was a
Pretty popular
To the president getting center right
Wasn't Maybe...
But
Him keeping him as a pet
Was out of the garden
Right I mean that's a little bit more unusual when we think about president
And that
Thanksgiving we usually think of that turkey
Keyparts lady would walk her around on a leash during the day
And then at night
Cheap curl up
Calvin
Slap neck
The fireplace
It's looking pretty good bad
Well yeah and that's one side of it the other side
Is that she was still a wild animal
NTB kink out of Infamous for chewing her way out of her
Enclosures
The colors they put on Earth
You caught the furniture in the White House
LV stories
Chase her around while she runs up trees
Yeah so she was a bit of a handful
Call too but
She got to hang out in the white house sometimes
Andres the time she got this
Little wooden houses
They put up for her on the side
So it would seem a little bit of a house
But she seems to have
Yeah she did and she live with the cool just for a while and then the first couple handed off to a zoo
Who is the time
Maybe Rebecca bit
Calvin because one day he
Came out with a bandage on his hand
But Grace leader wrote very fondly of this
White House raccoon
According to her Rebecca quote
Enjoyed nothing better than being placed in a bath
With a little water in it
And given a cake
Pick up soap with witch
In this fashion she would amuse her so
Self for an hour or more
So obviously if nighttime
Can iPads have anymore raccoon stories they should
You're at you on Twitter
But they're already
Yeah. That's the pile
Be well if you want to see some really lovely pictures of
The First Lady Grace Coolidge
Raccoon friend Rebecca
Open website
At 9 p.m.
99percentinvisible with produces Sweetbriar senior producer Katie mingle based on Amy Dempsey's
Epic raccoon story
From the Toronto Star
Greeley refill
LinkedIn website
Mixing Tec production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
This episode is dedicated to Kurt Kolstad who enjoys nothing better than being placed in a bathtub
A little water in it
Giving a cake
Exo with wigs
Uplay
Russell team
Is senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery Chapman
Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Joe Rosenberg Karen Mazza and me Roman more
We are products 91.7 kalw
Cisco mapreduce
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com