99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On January 7th 1998 an envelope landed on the desk of Larry Calloway he was a
Call messed with the Albuquerque Journal it was sort of a combination of it
Press release in a ransom note
And
A photo
The photo was a Polaroid of a cut-off riding boot with a huge Spanish
All in bronze
Can I read the note the new hinted that the bronze foot came from a statue of a man named Juan
Hyundai Oneonta horse it was part of a monument on the side of a rural Highway near where
They founded the first Spanish colony in New Mexico
Back in 1598
Larry figured this was probably a hoax
Visit Stan Elkhorn a reporter with the investigative podcast reveal there are collaborators on the story today
So he handed the tip-off to the news from and a reporter
Called up the visitor center at the Oneonta Monument
And Ashley is your statue missing a right foot
And he went out
You don't go in shock
Shutters gone
Onate is one of the world's lesser-known conquistadors
His name is all over New Mexico
They're onate streets onate schools
For decades there was an annual Fiestaware one lucky guy would get to be on yacht A
Complete with that cape and helmet
There's even a song
In parts of New Mexico
He's treated as a kind of founding father
But history is not all song and dance and wearing capes
He was a conquistador after all
The envelope larry gott
Also included an excerpt from a history book
On oneonta's treatment of New Mexico's native people
It described an incident that ended with onate sentencing a group of men from Acoma Pueblo
To each have one foot chopped off
If the symbolism of removing the statues foot was unclear
The note made it explicit
It said we took the liberty
Every moving on yachty's right foot on behalf of our brothers and sisters at Acoma Pueblo
We will be melting this foot down
And casting small medallions to be sold to
Those who are historically ignorant
The statue sculpture cast a new right foot and reattached it
The medallions never turned up
But the story stuck
You got picked up by NPR and the New York Times
I was a 7th grader in Albuquerque at the time
And what I remember is how the subject I found most boring history
Was Suddenly at this exciting mystery
Remains unsolved to this day
Who stole onate foot
And then there was the timing
1998 was the 400th anniversary of oneonta's arrival centenario celebration
And although this date
It would be theater parades commemorative stamp
In a second note to the paper these so-called friends of Acoma Road
We see no glory and celebrating onate Sports Centennial
And we do not want our faces rubbed in it
In other words the point of cutting off the statues foot was to spoil the party and the centerpiece of that party
That got a mention in all the foot cutting stories with a cuarto centenario Memorial being planned for our
Albuquerque's historic Center
The Proposal
Another bronze statue of Juan de onate
This one right in the middle of New Mexico's biggest city
But with all of his new attention on onate
The second statue wasn't going to get built
Without a fight
I still didn't see the storm that was coming
It was still in its infancy
Conchita Lucero was one of the organizers of the 400th anniversary celebrations in Albuquerque
And one of the most passionate advocates
For a new onate statue
Passion that goes back to her childhood
Growing up in 1950s New Mexico knowing almost nothing about onate
Or the states two centuries as a Spanish colony
When I was a child
At 10 years of age
I asked my grandmother who was the school teacher
I was reading the American history
Books
I said the dark people do anything
You know that's how I felt
She didn't know
New Mexico
All Conchita knew was that her Spanish ancestors it come to the states
Centuries before the Anglo classmates who called people like her dirty Mexicans
Are the Anglo teachers who kept her out of a leadership Club
And she knew that racism and ignorance of History
We're somehow connect
If we make you feel like the underdog
And we take away your history and take away your knowledge
You're starting from scratch
Conversations you don't know how to even participate
You just left the other guy
Put you down
Conceited thought if she could just search out her own European roots
It would help her fight back
None of this is uncommon in New Mexico
What people have been reaching back to their colonial roots and identifying a Spanish since 1800s
African cheetah retired she found a lot of like Minds in local genealogical and historical societies
She learned how to use birth and death and baptism records to trace her family tree
There was the occasional Native American ancestor
Which was most excited to find branches like the one that extended back to a Spanish captain
Who brought his wife and kids through the Chihuahuan Desert on onate is 1598 Expedition
She saw them as having transformed the region by bringing livestock and Catholicism in the Spanish language
It's start finding your family members and you were going well
I never knew they did all this
Did it change how you saw
Yourself
Yes
I never argued that one person wasn't as good as the other but sometimes you were made to feel inferior
And at that point
The inferiority left
And so it was that Conchita was on the cuarto centenario committee
When they met with the Albuquerque Arts board
To discuss the request for a prominent new Statue of Juan de onate
The man they called the father of the Hispanic culture
And our state
And who the friends of Acoma accused of destroying native peoples way of life
Was what happened to that, I brought up
No
And was it on your mind
Was it something that you knew about
I wasn't
As first in it as I have
Become
For people who don't know act come out
What is
What is that this is a liter or Tweety suazo
And Acoma woman who become an outspoken opponent of an Oneonta statue in Albuquerque
Alchemist the oldest continuously inhabited community in the United States
And it sits on the Mesa 375 ft above the valley below
Secures a postcard of a Komando Show people when she travels
It's a village built on top of a Mesa which if you're not from the desert is like a huge Rock pedestal
And that makes it just Towers over the flat empty plane below
All of it a hundred shades of brown from Light tan to defrost it's incredible
Detecting with radios you can have pictures
Help people visualize it cuz it's like no other place on Earth it's it's not it's beautiful it's
Desert Inn
Roxanne
Sandstone Inn
That's where I come from you know
And unlike the Dozen the Pueblos that disappeared after the arrival of the Spanish
Acoma
You still here
Each year tens of thousands of tourists drive an hour west of Albuquerque
And then take a tour bus up a steep road to the top of the Mesa
Just watch yourself
Don't get too close to the edge
If you happen to fall over the edge
This is the end of your tour
No refunds will be given
On top you can see buildings made of mud and sandstone
The tour guide say date back to the 1100
Think about it these houses
Happened passed down through the same family for almost a thousand years
So now we're going to be walking past some of the older houses right up here
All along that work their tables where Acoma artist sell their Wares mostly pottery
Sponsor me
But it's not just a tourist attraction
There are 15 families that live up top year round
And hundreds more like Tweety's
Google there for special occasions
Funeral
Death
Religious
Fiesta
We were always there
What did you know about the history of
Your people in that place
That we came from the underworld
On the back grandmother
Spider
We wonder
The Earth
And when we got to where I, was
We were told this is
But we're supposed to be
That's what I knew you know that
We've been there forever
Tweety also knew that when the Spanish arrived they did terrible
Cool things to our ancestors
But she didn't know the details
Historians know many of those details today because they were written down by the Spanish in letters and legal.
Documents documents to quote ographer skim the surface of events
And sometimes present onate quote as he wished to be seen not as things actually were
Which makes their description of what happened at Acoma all the more shocking
After 13 of onion taste men came looking for food and were killed when a state declared a
War of blood and Fire
In that most brutal account of the battle that followed onate soldiers killed hundreds of men women and children
Stopped prisoners and threw them off the Mesa and set fires that suffocated women and children
Who taken shelter in sacred rooms known as kiva's
They then rounded up 500 prisoners and put them on trial
Onate sentence those over 12 years old to 20 years of slavery
It was under 12 he separated from their families
Giving the girls to the church
And the boys to the captain who just destroy their Village
And then there's the most infamous detail
In a document signed by onate himself
It says
The males who are over 25 years of age
I sentence to have one foot
Cut off
Is cruelty to the innocent about, was one of the twelve crimes for which onion himself would later be tried in
Convicted by the Spanish crown
As punishment
You'll be banished
Permanently
On the territories of New Mexico
This is the history that Tweety and I and many other New Mexicans
We're learning for the first time
As news of the stolen foot ricocheted around the state
That was the beginning of it
That was everybody's first awareness
And at the same time
We were also learning that the City of Albuquerque was planning to build this new much more prominent statue
She has been
Passed out of
New Mexico
Forever
And now you want to bring him back and put him on a statue
Still mine bazzi
Kanye went from a banished conquistador
To a father of New Mexico that people wanted to put on a statue
It's a story for another podcast
But the simple answer is
He was first
The first to build a European colony in the region even if that colony was soon abandoned
He was among the first to bring wheat and sheep and Catholicism
And because every people needs a founding figure
Spanish New Mexico made Juan de onate it's George Washington
Even if he had been cast out forever
But it did not take long for the Albuquerque Arts board to realize that one de onate was not everyone's ID
Idea of a founding father
They could see you at another triumphant statue of him on a horse
Would be a bad look for the city
Some of the time the foot was cut off of the old statue on the side of the highway
They made a few changes to the plan
The memorial would need to depict
Not just onate
But also the peaceful settlers who came with him
And the Native Americans who preceded and survived them
And the exact form the memorial would take
Will be up to a team of artists
They had a team of two but right before the newspapers got wind of the missing foot
They decided to add a third
When Nora naranjo Morse got the call
She was in the place where she's most comfortable
Her Studio
I mean who would want to be here right in this
Studio with a fireplace in the rain
On the phone was the director of public art for the City of Albuquerque
Asking if she wanted to be part of a tri cultural collaboration
It would be the Hispanic artist who built the Statue that had its foot stolen
An Anglo artist
And her
At a white Indian artist from the Santa Clara Pueblo
The call was
So out of the blue
This was a public art project I've never done public art really
This was with other people I had been working solo
So I didn't really know I was listening
And did you say yes right then or do you remember how the phone call
I said yes right away because
I open my mouth and I said yes and then
Afterwards I thought oh
I wonder what this is going to be like
She find out when she showed up for that first meeting
An Institutional room with fluorescent lighting and a chalkboard
The other artists wield in a model of a statute they'd already put together
It was
Another triumphant statue
Onate
On a horse
And that's when they begin to talk about the granite pedestal
And
How I could use
It
Set the pedestal beneath on yachty's horses feet
Right
I felt insulted
I felt hurt
I felt marginalized
Hi
Didn't
Thanks
I could do
That
Although in
Myself
I was thinking
That there was a solution
That art could tell a story
That was true
Dora quite literally refused to put on yacht they on a pedestal
The artist went back to the drawing board
But now Nora was in the public eye
And soon she started getting calls from other Pueblo people
Who wanted her to leave the project entirely
In protest
I didn't do that
And when I refused I got some
I think people were disappointed
But I realize that
Buy me staying in the game
I would at least
Be able to
Fight for that voice that I
I think was so
Important
Not just my art
Voice
But the voice of these people that have gone to this
Incredible
Experience that changed their culture completely
And
All I kept going back to those things
The year of the 400th anniversary 1998 came and went
And there was still no plan for the memorial
But the city would not give up
All the attention and made the memorial a very public test of whether the state was the land of try cultural
Tell Harmony that claim to be
So every time the process hit an impasse
The city just threw more time and money at it
Hiring mediators in forming committees
At one point one of those committees came up with a plan that would have restarted the whole artistic process a plan Conchita
Suicide couldn't tolerate
It called for a memorial
Without
Onate
Focus on coexistence of
Hispanic
Then we said it wasn't our celebration
You know it's your celebration now it's not ours
You know you don't get invited to a wedding
You don't start telling the bride and the groom you should have had it this way or that way or
And that's
What what it was it was our celebration but it was your celebration
With public money and
Public space
That's in a in a city that has people up
All different backgrounds
The grant was for our celebration
Not for The Alchemist celebration for for anybody else's
As far as computers group was concerned the present of onate was non-negotiable
Which made it hard to negotiate
In the end
There simply was no single design that everyone could agree on
Eventually the artist stop talking to each other
Instead
They proposed memorial made up of two separate artworks
A series of Bronze Statues of Spanish settlers including onate in full armor
Enormous response
An abstract Land Art installation made out of the desert itself
Did gone from a small bronze statue to a memorial that would take up most of a city block
And cost over half-a-million dollars
Requiring the city to issue special bonds
Now the question was
With the city approve it
Conchita and the pronoun take forces Lobby the city council
Wow unyazi opponents like Tweety
Took their case to the people
You know finding out
Woohoo
Forest and who is in
And how do we target the people in that area for them to call their
Councilman in
That's the first time I'd ever
Done.
You know
Do it like becoming a
An activist for the first yeah
I was diagnosed
I've never done that
The statue
And also a highway the city was trying to build through at National Monument of ancient petroglyphs
Was making first-time activist out of a lot of Pueblo people
Rallied around something
Activists artists
Citizens and City councilors
We're headed for a final showdown
This is govt
14th and now from Government Center in downtown Albuquerque the Albuquerque city council
In a series of meetings but city council Auditorium was divided
Like a pep rally
Congress
On one side was the pro on yacht A Crowd mostly Hispanic people around canchitas age
On the other side was the anti on the outside group
They tended to be younger and more diverse Native Americans but also
Anglos and African Americans
And a lot of people or mestizo
Explicitly embracing their indigenous as well as European ancestry
The city council tried to give the two sides equal time to speak and an hour after
Hour of public comment they went back and forth
Bernard over the design of the memorial really they're fighting over something much bigger
And much more personal their place in American history
Our colony was the first
In what is today the United States of America
You can't pretend that we didn't come here 400 years ago
This is really a matter of denigrating
The Hispanic people of New Mexico
Do I have to stop
First of all sorts
Chicano
Hand
Unlike some Hispanics that are here in the audience
I didn't just get off the plane from Spain
Does not represent the best of my culture
You are not representing me
And I just want to say that I'm sorry
That you and a small group of Hispanics in this room feel like they have to slam another people's culture
In order to feel Pride
There were dozens of speakers but the leaders were women from Acoma
Like Tweety
I didn't know that the awful things that happened to my people
Happened to my people
I told the statue became an issue
I'm really tired of being used
Taurus
The only things that matter in this community
Unbreaking you
Don't do this to my people
People
Don't hurt him this way
It's not right
Thank you very much
Bass speaker IL Sanchez Davis
It seemed like most people were on Tweety side
But the city voted against the memorial
It wouldn't just be saying no to this statue of onate and the settler send
Sonora's landscape art
You'll be admitting that this whole very public process that
It dragged on for more than 2 years
I've been a failure
The Committees that Define iterations the debate all for nothing
So when it finally came time to vote
All those in favor please signify by saying aye those opposed
No they go to 722 to build the memorial
After the vote Conchita Lucero told a reporter
I think our kids will finally learn about their ancestors
Tweety suazo and
Other anti onate activists
Formed a prayer circle in the city council chambers and wept
We work so hard
And it just it just is
Didn't matter
It didn't matter what we said
It didn't matter what we
Do
Politically astute
Now
Tweety thinks what they learned was
But the right arguments Aren't Enough
You made the right decision makers
She's one of several anti onate activists who went on to get involved in electoral politics
She's now the chair of the Native American Democratic caucus of New Mexico
And this last cycle she helped raise money and get out the vote
For Deb haaland
One of the two Native American women who just became the first ever to be elected to congress
Today if you go visit the Finish Memorial
What you'll see isn't onate on a horse
It's a compromise
It's really two memorials
Crammed into one
The first
You can grasp without even getting out of your car
It's more than two dozen life-sized bronze figures
Men and women oxen and sheep
Trudging up a hill
Juan de onate is in France
On foot no plaque with his name and under the watchful eye of a security camera
May or may not be pointed at his feet
II Memorial right next to it looks from above like a huge dirt spiral
But from ground level
You really just have to experience it
It's a striking contrast to the kind of art
It's really in your face and didactic insist this is what I mean
I think that
Flex Pueblo thinking it's much more subtle
It doesn't articulate in the way we've become used to as
You know
Civilized people
Colonize people
When I'm at Nora naranjo Morse to get a tour
She just been picking up trash left inside her part of the memorial
She's holding a donut wrapper as we walked down a dirt path that
Spiral slowly downhill
Into the ground
The street disappears behind the berms of camisas and Juniper is on our right and left
Bennett Buildings
10 Oneonta himself
Until finally at the center of the Spiral
All you can see is the land
And water trickling across Iraq
And I'd like that very much
Because I think
That's what it was like a long time ago that's how I interpret the
If you sit low to the ground
You can almost get a glimpse of a world before Oneonta arrives
It's an Escape
But it's also intended as a confrontation
Between two
Totally different worldviews
Because it's you walk back out of the Spiral
This is what you see
The telephone lines the
Sculpture of Oneonta coming here looking North
The stoplight it's all there
And so you see that
In some ways when they came
They brought us great opportunity
But at such a high cost
The brutal colonization was
Forever
Affecting to us
And I
Sync
We should never forget that
She hopes her piece of the memorial will remind people of fat
But honestly not that many people come here
The memorial doesn't attract nearly as much attention as the conflict over the memorial did
I think that's why it's important stewardship
Not only to pick up the trash
But also to keep that
Story of life
Cuz they're going to be a lot more generations of people coming
Wondering what what is this
And that's where our story was going to end until last year
An old mystery re-emerged
Remember that first statue we told you about the one that got its foot stolen
Will promise to decades the foot thieves had remained in the shadows
Their identities unknown
And then one day Chris are the director of smoke signals and skins possibly be best known Native American filmmaker
Was at La choza
This great little new Mexican restaurant in Santa Fe
I was sitting there
Eating
A taco with
My business partner and
Someone came up to me and said
I have a story to tell you is I'm eating my taco and I said
Oh s***
Not another story
Add
You know I heard a few keywords but I wasn't listening that intently
And all the sudden it dawned on me I said wait a minute
You talking about what I think you're talking about
It was the guy who cut the foot of the first onate statue
Or at least he claimed to be a spokesman for the group who did the deed
And
The truth of the matter is that I
Could never verify it
Other than I believed it in the end
Chris believe the guy
In part because he was presented with a very solid piece of evidence
When Chris met him for a second time in a
Forest of pinyon trees
The unwrapped a piece of Black Velvet
To reveal something no one had seen for 20 years
Lo and behold there
Appeared
Probably
Inch-long
Bronze
Patina.
Boots
Of a Spanish conquistador
And I said to myself
Wow
Then I looked around and I said to myself where the hell am I and what the hell am I doing here
A few chunks of the foot have been shaved off
But they'd made a half-hearted attempt to follow through on those
Medallions for the historically ignorant
But otherwise it was still intact
And still have the power to grab people's attention
The Chris knows the identity of the foot thieves he is not revealing it
But he did talk about their motivations
You know the party involved is not
Speaking from an activist position
And doesn't
Feel like an activist this person feels like
Astoria
He wasn't trying to start a movement or affect policy
Just to write what onate did to Acoma men in 1599
Into the history of the colonization of New Mexico
That story still doesn't have a statue
And maybe it never will
But in the meantime the friends of Acoma
Holding on to on your Facebook
Most statues in the news these days or Confederate one we're going to talk to a journalist who's researched exactly how those MA
Monuments are funded
Happiness
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa's talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Or story about onate this week with a collaboration with reveal
Which if you're not already a fan is a podcast from the center for investigative reporting and PRX
Reveal is actually tearing another fascinating statues story this coming week at it comes out on Saturday
And we want you to subscribe and listen to the whole thing
So we're going to talk with one of the reporters involve to give you a little preview the story focuses on
Preterite monuments it was reported by Seth freed wessler and Brian Palmer of the investigative fund
Brian is interest in Confederate monuments all started in historic Cemetery he was visiting the place where is great
Grandparents were buried they're both enslaved and then self emancipated to the north
Brian's great-grandfather served in the United States Army during the Civil War
In the cemetery where they're buried is located in Virginia on a military base
There's a white section
And a black section
And what I saw was
On the one hand tragic and on the other hand
Enlightening the traffic part was that
This African American cemetery
Was not
As well tended as
The White Cemetery
Across the base
So that to me was a little bit striking
At the White Cemetery there's one
Graven particular.
That caught my eye I've had
A couple of Confederate flags
Around it
The inscription on this wooden cross a little plaque said to the unknown confederate soldier
So I thought wow that's really interesting
This
White Cemetery is being maintained
The black Cemetery they at least rate
But it was tumbledown and
It just did not look like it had any stewardship
I started wondering while why are such cemeteries
Black cemeteries
Historic black cemeteries
Why are cemeteries such as this in such terrible shape
And why are Confederate cemeteries
And monuments and sites
In such a wonderful shape
The obvious journalist thing to do then is to follow the money
So you noticed that there's a disparity in the care
Makes you realize that
A disparity in Keras reflected in disparity dollars
And that money is being spent
On
Confederate monuments and not being spent on
The Monuments devoted to the after American Experience in the African American history
And then you start
Chasing on the dollars and not only all those dollars being used
For the preservation and the maintenance of Confederate monuments
They are being
Used
What Confederate monuments
Devoted to this lost
Cause narrative
So can you describe with the Lost Cause narrative is to people who don't know it
So you make that important distinction
We
Looked at a range of sites
That tell Civil War history
You have battlefields
You have
Homes in all sorts of different places
And what they put on the walls and what their guide say
Is factual
This happened here this unit fought
That to us is
History that's acceptable that is educational that's perfect
What we did
Was we
We focused on sites where the historic
Historical interpretation
And what the people there say and what is omitted
Represents an ideology
Not
An evidence-based
Comprehensive approach to the Civil War
But what represents
Ideology that what
What perpetuates ideology so for example
Ones that
Either minimize or
Deny the centrality the importance of slavery
In the Civil War
The ones that pump out these loyal slave happy slave myth
And ones that deny any
Any Southern responsibility
For the war that that that you know they paint this did this picture of
A blamelessness
Vist us
Is corrosive
To democracy into our society and I think it's led us to
Where we are now politically info
So these these monuments that you are investigating
They didn't
Appear right after the Civil War took you talk about
When they showed up and what political purpose they were serving when they were erected
They didn't just spring up after the Civil War largely because the South
Didn't have the money to erect them
Our first major Monument here in Virginia
Was donated
By Brits Thomas Stonewall Jackson was put on the
Lawn of
Capital and that was funded by British folks
But
Monument building really had three main phases
At the the tail end of the 19th century
Beginning
Of the 20th century and then
Right around the time of civil rights
So
Interesting it's not coincidental
Into each of these things they take they came about overtime in these these moments of white people in power
Power
Really literally exhibiting their dominance through these
Statues in Monument
And which I think is really interesting to make this really good point in the piece is that
The current discussion or controversy over historic monuments
This isn't cringe
PC culture kind of thing all the way along
Just people didn't listen
Cuz they were mainly
Objections
By African-Americans
There is a history of
African American resistance
This sort of
Self glorification of white Elites
Frederick Douglass wrote about monuments w b Dubois wrote about The Monuments and they were saying No this is just
Ridiculous
And yet because blacks didn't have the political power to do anything
And because
The so-called mainstream media controlled by
White men
Did not
Write about these objections
It could find no traction in larger culture
People now in the 20th
21st century can with ignorance tell us well you never objected before
No it's that you never paid attention before
And we never had the tools to make you pay attention in the same way that you forced us
To pay attention to your myths and your stories by embedding them in public space
So you begin
Investigating these Lost Cause Memorial
How did you go about investigating how public funds were used to maintain and promote
A survey historic
Sites
Sodomy
Go about this first
We had to differentiate between the sites
It's that were
Doing
Real
Honest genuine historic work
And those that were
Promoting ideology
So we did a lot of our searching
On the web first
And we talked to people
In
The places
Where these monuments and sites were
And then we went
So we could go to the museum so we can go to the gift shop so we could talk to the dose
So we visited
5060 different places and we lost account
And then
Once we
Figure it out
Which sites we wanted to focus on
We filed dozens of open records and Freedom of Information Act
Requests
How to local and state governments and the federal government to find out
Where this money was coming from we looked at IRS documents
We looked at State budgets line by line by line
So
That was our our methodology
Insulted
So we just like at you going around to these sites with your collaborators set
Freed wessler
Incentive
White correct
Santa's wife
I am not
I am African-American
Will you ever separated in such a way that
You were given a different experience of these sites
That's a very interesting question because
We tended to report separately
I knew based on my reporting
With other white collar
With my wife who is whose wife.
We would be treated
Differently
So
The stuff that Seth heard
And the stuff that I heard
Very different and I think that's that's that's part of the story but it's also the frame of the store
We went to some of the same places like the Confederate section of Oakwood Cemetery here I spend a lot of time there
Seth visited
What people told him
Was alarming
What people told me you was supposed to be reassuring
They needed to get the pr
Engine going
For the visiting black person
But for a white person they could
Be themselves
As it were they could let their Prejudice hair hang down
And
That to me was
Towing
There are people who just don't know
The other part of this history the African-American strands that have been
Purposely erase
But then there are people who do know
And still they tried out these myths
Either to preserve their power to make themselves feel better
Whatever it is
That's a kind of intellectual dishonesty
That I think is really really Danger
And I think that's
We're trying to drain that swamp
We are trying to to
Eliminate
The gray area that people can wallow around in when they say well
You know this is a Heritage and they've been standing 400 years and if the black people want their own monuments
Then they should go build them
Well
A lot of these monuments
We're built with public funds yes there were private donation
Can certainly
But
Land was donated
Infrastructure was built
And money allocations came
From General Assembly
City council County Supervisors
So don't tell me
That
We should accept
Sites and statues
That were erected
In a violent
And anti-democratic atmosphere
When African-Americans were being lynched
African Americans could not participate
In the political process
I put these things up
Now that we can we're supposed to shut up
We have no time
Fake history
And this is fake history
We need to illuminate
Not office
Hear Brian Palmer and Seth freed wessler full story on Public Funding for confederate
Monuments subscribe to reveal
There is amazing in. Dropping tape in the story from some of their visits to memorials like Beauvoir
Which is Jefferson Davis home and Presidential Library in Biloxi Mississippi
And Brian said also do the important work of chasing down how much public money taxpayer money are money
It's being spent to maintain these sites
Check it out at revealnews.org
Or wherever you listen to podcasts
99percentinvisible was produced this week by staying Elkhorn and edited by Delaney Hall mixing Tech production by Shreve uses
Music by Shawn real
Can you please raise Katie Mingle
Kurt Kolstad is the digital director the rest of team is Avery Chapman Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh
Joel Rosenberg Karen Mazza and me Roman Mars
Special things to reveal from the center for investigative reporting and PRX collaborators on the story this
Thanks also to Ramon Garcia kunm and the filmmaker Chris are
Clearview the alleged but thieves for his film that is currently seeking funding so you should seek him out and give
Give him some
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com