99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Downtown Providence Rhode Island
In 1838 it was the home of the Rhode Island state prison
Notorious for its horrid smell
Gregory outward appearance
Reputation for solitary confinement
Later the land house the continuing education campus for the University of Rhode Island
After that
A dirt parking lot called
Ray's parking lot
Then in 1999
In a grand effort to revitalize the sea
And with much fanfare
The Providence Place Mall was open
Best Vanessa Lowe producer of the podcast
Nocturne
Amal casting 500 million dollars
What was known as a super Regional
A One-Stop shopping destiny
Housing everything consumers could possibly want or need
In a totally enclosed space
Partially funded by taxpayer money it's been 13 acres
Offered 1.4 million square feet of retail
And dominate
The riverfront
It was
The largest
Construction project in providence's history
Obviously this one building and
We
So does student all watching it
Get built
Michael townzen is an artist who live nearby when the mall was still under construction in the 1990s
The daily running route took him past the construction site
And Michael says that if he wants to go out he had an open mind about the
Project
He was cautiously optimistic
That would be a welcome addition to the neighborhood
Yeah yeah
Itsfunneh
Devotion
To a building like that doesn't really kick in until the skin gets put on
When something is in his Erector Set mode where you just sing the skeleton like I have a pretty full skeleton but as soon as
The Flash is there like
Not Freddy
Providence Place is going to be a big
Boxy Soccer Shop
Without much in the way of architectural nicety
And his runs Michael watched as that big box was slowly filled with the things that make them all Amal
As it's being built
I start to sort of
Do mental Maps
Spaces
Does that seem to store that's me a storage space that's going to be parking
But amidst all the construction there was one part of the building that kept catching Michael die
Weird space in the guts of the architecture that didn't make sense
It didn't seem to meet the profile of either sore space or parking space or store
Space Michael wasn't sure what the spaces for
It seemed to exist only by virtue of the Wold intended for the more legitimate spaces around it
But the result was this
Room
It was an accidental room
A remainder left over by the long division of the malls architecture
I've never seen anything like it
Maritime Iran
It was something I would never think about
Michael eventually put the strange room out of his mind he probably would have forgotten about it entirely
Except that 4 years later a second group of developers encouraged by the success of Providence Place
Set their sights even closer to Michael
This time they wanted to build right on top of the historic Mill District where Michael
And a dozen or so other artist lived and worked in an old industrial building they called
Fort Thunder
The developers had to use the computer algorithm to figure out where to place a new Supermarket so that it wouldn't compete with others
Supermarkets in the area
And I got to see this computer printout and it is it like a nuclear explosion map
The radius of each supermarket and their theoretical reach
And
Indy Blank Spot that was our neighborhood
They put an X
Directly on the building we were live
And that was just the start
The developers wanted to tear down all of the Old Mill
And replace them with yet more retail with little to no pedestrian
And it appears that they only Mantra they have is
If you see a space at
Underdeveloped
You have a
God-given responsibility to development
That it was basically like having
A complete stranger
Women thinking about it
And we think we want to knock your house down
And and make it a parking lot of it
It's cool with you
Normally this would be the part of the story we tell you that Michael and the other residents of Fort Thunder
Banded together to save their home in the face of the Relentless March of capital
But
No it's not that kind of story
When did they did save some buildings
But as for Fort Thunder
Or actual home
They came out with bulldozers and crane and knock that sucker
Are flat
Fort Thunder was gone
The reason we're telling you this story is because of what happened next
Because when I see something like that on my ho ho ho
Really game on Michael and his friend
And have lost their home and in their mind
It all started with that first mall that was the original see that development that has led to everything else
And so talk again of a mall related action call it art call it a stunt
Anaplan started to take shape in the mall
7 days
Live
In the mall and they said a rule for themselves
They couldn't leave and without a second thought of thinking about how unfeasible that is
For own well-being we really thought that we had to do it
And if this sounds like
Clark well yet I kind of was
But I secretly
Serious Clark
The four friends
They would eventually number eight
Wanted to assert that space is like them all
Long dresses much to them after the debate
To really do this right they would need to find a space in the mall where they can hide themselves away
And Michael have the perfect place in mind
You begin to search for that Mysterious Room that he'd noticed when the mall was under construction
All those years before was connected to a kind of crevice a narrow Gap in
In the building structure that eventually LED out to an exterior wall so one night Michael went to see you
Entrance to that crevasse had ever been sealed off
Amazingly it hadn't
It was small and sort of hidden
But there was still a crack in the exterior of the mall
So he and his then wife Adriana turn themselves sideways
And slept inside
And then once you're once you're at that point you are exploring
A system of
Caverns
Long weird
Vertical Caverns
And there are places where it is false
Down into the lower levels of the mall
So you've got about
A foot-and-a-half
A blessed we are looking into a black abyss
And then
This
Series of Chambers
Ultimately give you access
To this
Space
The room was tall and wide filled with the byproducts of the mall's construction from the years before
Broken two-by-fours
Screws and plastic zip ties
That hadn't even been worth removing
The space
Have literally been forgotten
And it was
Big
He was a big space
That
Serves no other purpose
That wasn't the storefront
I wasn't a star while it was just
Big
And it was
A
Thrill
Tube
Physically find it be like this is it this is what I remember
The room was in the guts of the building
The part that no one was ever supposed to use
Even really see
But Michael and Adriana saw that it could still be access
I multiple-hit an entry point
Including from inside the shopping center itself
If you know how to get there you could walk there from the Macy's
But as far as they can
Hell they were the only people who knew this really exist
It was at that moment but the friend scheme started changing
Initial planning to spend a week in the mall
But the way they saw it
They were sitting on 750 square feet of underutilized space
Monastic
What would a developer do
Because after all
If you see a space is underdeveloped
You have a
God-given responsibility to develop
So
When we decided that perhaps the absolute best thing we could do is just build a condo
Like that is that is always the you that's always the answer you're not sure what to do with the space
Just make it a condo
The new plan was no longer to live in the mall for a week
It was now simply to live in the mall
Days of time
Using the room
Is an apartment
Well that may sound like a nightmare to everyone but a few weird artist from Providence
Michael and his friends at work on this little project
The excitement
New homeowner
Step 1 of course was cleaning
They had to get rid of all that debris
It sounded like
Irritated I get a prison break movie we were literally filling up our backpacks
Swift Just
Dirt and grime and then
Brandon carrying it out of the mall and getting rid of it
And for every backpack full of debris they took out
They bring a pack full of something in
Gallon jugs of water for drinking
Cleaning
Clamp lights and extension cords for illumination which they plugged into the malls internal power system
Parts for an ad hoc kitchen
They even built a cinder block wall to hide the space from anyone else who might venture into the cavern,
Commence various other entrance
We went and got a door that was an exact mirror of the doors that use in the mall
So if you were to find it
Unless you're looking really closely
At first glance it just looks exactly like a
Like it had been built originally
Finally it was time to decorate anything we could buy at the mall we would low table came in on
On top of that
Probably perch with a television at our PlayStation
But
If you couldn't buy it at the mall we have to bring it in tomorrow that's for the large
Pieces like the China hutch for the
4 piece sectional couch
No but nobody looks
Twice that you brought
Pieces of a couch
Through them all
How did you get that in there
In broad daylight
We avoided the night
And sort of work for the ebb and flow of
The mall we were just
Heart of the hills the living organism of it
Pets daily activities
Amazing risky trying to furnish
A secret apartment with a nested coffee table
But anyone watching
It was just a person walking through a mall with the nested coffee table that they just bought at the mall
There's simply no such thing as a suspicious consumer item in a building
What is dedicated
Consumerism
Friendswood sometimes stay in the secret
Apartment for several weeks in a row just living
Watching television and making collages with shadow boxes they bought at Pottery Barn
Even cooking in the ad hoc
Michael remembers burning some waffles with waffle iron and wondering if
Smoke weed give them away
And when the eight friends were enjoying their secret apartment
They were enjoying the mall
Not at Shoppers
But as residents
Thanks to its late night movie theater the mall almost never closed
So sometimes it would just roam the building
With no goal in mind
Observing its many moods
There are times in that in
Haier building
Probably had maybe
10 people in it
Like in the middle of the night
Dippy security officer to be cleaning staff
And it's a really wonderful time because it's
It's like having
A public park
4 levels deep all to yourself
Tend
In those moments
There's a sense of
Ownership
I just feel really good
Weeks turn to months
And eventually years
Out of the emotional Rubble of Fort Thunder they finally found their ref
And all thanks to the mall develop
Quit accidentally provided a sanctuary
Ameriworld they were busy developer
But as the old saying goes
There Comes A Time in every man's life
Woody must stop living at the mall
Unfortunately
The seed got planted
Dad this whole thing was going to unravel
And that's because we had a we had a break-in
One day they came back to the apartment
Only to discover
That someone who kicked open the door and still on the PlayStation
Along with several other smaller
Including the art they had made
Photo
But it left a silverware
They left the TV right this is a very odd burglary
I didn't take the things of value they only two things that were like
Super personal
Michael and his friends were
They had managed to hide the apartment for 4 years
But now someone knew about the room
Someone could come back at any time
Who seem to be interested in them
So they change things up
They decided from now on they only stay there at night
When the chances of being caught were low
Never during the day
And crucially
I would double down on another rule they had since almost the very beginning
Don't share it
It with anyone don't
Physically bring anyone here wasn't involved in the making of it
It's a lot of my very
Very good
Ban best friends
Never saw this face
And I'm the one who
Took that rule and broke it
Michael is hosting a visiting artist from Hong Kong
Her name is Jaffa
He was driving her to the bus station on her way out of town
And we're driving
Pass them all I say to myself
What can it hurt
How could this possibly backfire me
Self
I
Brought her
Into the space
Her mind was absolutely blown and it got remember that this is at the peak of its
It's Bill.
Michael show Java everything
Couch the light
Television
They were just days away from installing a water tank
And a wood floor
In spite of the break-in after 4 years of work the apartment was on the verge of feeling like a real home
But
When we're leaving
I hear walkie-talkie on the other side of the door
Within 2
Feet of us
And with the door open
It's
Three dudes and ties
Anta sports jackets
And
I realized in that moment I internalize that
It's over
It turned out that the earlier break-in have been the work of two of the mall's newest Security card
Instead of removing everything
Did taking the personal items in hopes of figuring out who Michael and his friends were
Now that Michael have been foolish enough to come back during the day
They had their man
General Growth Properties the company that owned them all
Did not take kindly to the secret apartment
And its walls
You don't say
After being handed over to the police and interrogated
Java was eventually let go
But Michael soon found himself standing in front of a judge in Criminal Court
Charged with breaking and entering and felony tree
By the time I get to court
The mall is hired a lawyer
And
They launched into all these details about
The
Illegal things that I have done
And I keep my mouth
Shut
But
After they've gone to this laundry list of
Illegal act
They use the phrase
This gave mr. Townsend axis
To an apartment that
They had built
Over several years that had
The following things in it and goes on to Blythe
In detail
What department look like
Including the coffee table the television a copy of the game Grand Theft Auto
An 8-foot China hutch
4 piece sectional couch
Silverware for 8 with matching glass
6 ft decals
This player gives the more the judge just looks around and he's like
What's Happening Here
The judge
Hustle
Advisors
Klosterman and hearing whispering
Any looks that looks me dead in the eyes and he goes
This is not a criminal act
We're not sure exactly what it was
But
This is not a crime
When the judge was receiving a deep legal Truth at the heart of this case
Where Michael was just the beneficiary of an incredible amount of white privilege
Michael may never know
In the end he was slapped with a misdemeanor for trespassing and release
He lived on and off in a secret apartment for nearly 4 years
And it was going to cost him almost nothing
But that doesn't mean he got away entirely scot-free
Just before Michael left the mall the mall security team handed him a piece of paper
The same piece of paper they hand to Brawlers shoplifters and anyone else who has overstayed their welcome
In this most private
Public spaces
This is
Standardized
Manila piece of paper which has a map of the mall
It has red line around the whole thing
You have to sign it and it says you can't cross that red line
How to make it clear you're never coming back
Now
Over a decade later
Michael still live
Right near the mall
But his days are running anywhere near is 13 acres
Are over
And the biggest bummer for me is that
If I want to go to downtown
The
That you bring your bike
Through is
Do the center of the mall where bridges over the river
I'll have to bike around it
Eric biker Roundup
Diligently
I have never broken this rule
Seriously can never go back
I could never go back
The story was a co-production with a KCRW podcast Nocturne which is produced and hosted by Vanessa
Solo Nocturne is an exploration of the night and the landscape of the Unseen
With a link on the website and in the show notes
We go back to the mall
Specifically
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad to take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Now that we've sneaked into this weird public
Private space that is the mall
I thought it'd be fun to revisit the origin story of this incredibly intriguing location which Avery reported for us
A few years ago
We've all done it
You go to the store for a pair of socks and come out with a mega pack of soda
Go out to get shampoo and come back with a fancy razor
It's hard to stick to what's on your list
I challenge you to go to IKEA
And leave with only the thing for what you game
Just try to buy a lamp without buying a cutting board it can't be done
You absolutely knew this but retail spaces are designed to do this to you
Producer Avery trufelman
The store is trying to look so beautiful
So welcoming
The items so enticingly displayed in such vast quantity
That you cannot help
To be drawn in
And I'm drawn towards something you don't need
This is the Gruen effect
The Gruen effect
Or sometimes called the Gruen transfer
If that moment when you walk into a store and the design of the store is so overwhelming and
Dazzling
That you being mindlessly consuming
The Gruene effect is named
Victor Victor Gruen
The who was growing complicated complex contradictory guy
Jeff Hardwick wrote the biography of Victor Gruen
Who is born Victor grunbaum born in Vienna
In 1904
And he is Jewish in Vienna leaves
1038 good call Groupon
And makes his way eventually
New York City
Once a New York grew and made a name for himself designing shops and Retail spaces
And this was a particular challenge during the lean years of the late 30s
People had no money
I just wouldn't go into shops at all
The girl figured out how to lower people inside
Basically by using amazingly appealing window displays
Go into these window
Display area
Look at
Jewelry
Handbags
Chocolate
Venue.
Tempted and lured into
The store I mean that's the Gruen effect
Gruene argued that good design equals good profit
And he
Equate those
One to one
If you do more
People are going to stay there longer and spend more
Bruins started making storefront all over the country and he moved from New York to Los Angeles in 1940
Gruen was from the beautiful city of Vienna
Which is lined with shops and Greenery and places together
It's not how most Americans we're just riding around in their cars all the time
Cut off from the city in from each other
He knew this problem was even worse
In the suburbs
The suburb lacked what sociologist Ray Oldenburg calls
Places
I think of home as your primary place
Work as your second place
And that third place is where you go to build communities hang out
To Simply feel connected
Gruen wanted to give the American suburbs
That third place
Image
Abreva inconclusive communication with other people
Image of
Petting zoo possibility from walk to one place to another
That's archival footage of Ruin from the University of Wyoming
See image of participating in events outside of your own little house
Become a desired effect
Victor Gruen imagine designing an environment
Full of greenery in shops
An indoor Plaza
A modern for him
Island of connection in the middle of the sprawl
One that would only be accessible to
Because
Old man Victor Gruen hated cars
He Rants and Raves
Against cars
One technological event
Advent of the private car
It's means of mass transportation
Human life intense is Justice great
Effect of exposure
It's hard understanding with the tape hessney accent but what Gruen is saying there is
The threat of cars that human life in hell
Is as great as the exposed
Sewer
So gruhn's objective was to get people to park their cars far away from these third places
And walk
Stroll within them
Has grew inside his structure would be an architectural Panacea
It would remedy environmental commercial and sociological problems
With the creation
I'm a single building
And so Gruen presented his solution for America
The shopping mall
Good actually wanted the shopping mall to be more than just shops
You want some D mixed-use he want
Apartments
Send offices or medical centers attached to the shopping center he
Cases that have
Childcare facilities Library
Bomb shelters
Whole range of
Different
A function
Ingrown dreamed and wrote about the enclosed shopping center way before he ever built one
Until he finally land the commission
For the very first
Indoor climate controlled Shopping Center
In Edina Minnesota a place not known for the welcoming climate
Southdale represents an entirely new and dramatic
Retail merchandising
Southdale Center opened in 1956
And it was the mother of all shopping malls
Seriously
Bruins subsequent malls were all mostly based off this original Edina design
When he's doing the first enclosed shopping mall
Southdale
In Edina Minnesota
Gruen really emphasize
And what the media ends up
Celebrate
Is this massive
Center Court
This cord isn't closing skylighter
Store
Photoshopping cyborg
In fact the whole area in front of the stores
Is air conditioned and Temperature Control
A year-round climate of 72 degrees
For grilling
He's creating a
A Town Square
Southdale Center wasn't
Quite mixed-use
Migraine imagine
People didn't live in it
And something like a daycare center or app
Post office couldn't afford that rent
The Tell-Tale did have local shops of all kinds
And plenty of shopping
Southdale
Tomorrow's Main Street
Today
But from the outside
Southdale Center is not much to look at
I mean it looks like a mall
What does ominous Amorphis boxy shape
In designing the shopping mall
Ruin ended is Razzle Dazzle storefront and window displays
Southdale hardly has a
Exterior windows at all the moves away from the original concept that in some ways they're going to
Track
By being Austin
The drawn now is what's inside the mall
Congruent mind it should have
Pretty much
Blank facade no signage on it and then you enter that
Space and then you walk into the shopping center and that's that
Set of transformational Gruen transfer moment
Mold are designed as the sort of suburban pilgrimage sites
Which of course
You have to drive to
It's a commitment
You're driving 20-30 minutes your parking your getting out of your car your walking in
Good new that Americans love to drive
So the mall with his compromise
You had to walk and stroll once you're inside
But the customers could drive over
So he just hates
The automobile but he never will acknowledge
That he's creating the shopping centres which are
Largely
Only accessible through cars
Brewing with rice
Americans love
Driving to his balls he got commissions for them all over the country
But over time
Truancies that in erecting these malls
Is Tiny Suburban cities
He's helping to drain the real City
So for a while
Current shifts his Focus
Urban planning
B12
Urcp
Which because we have neglect
Enter Gruen ends up
Being involved in urban renewal project
Next wear
He draws directly on
The Lessons Learned in his
Suburban shopping malls
And proposes bringing them back downtown
Municipality Tire Gruen and Associates to make their downtown
Gruen turns City centers into pedestrian-only spaces
Full of public art and Greenery and line
What shops
He made plans for Boulder
Fresno Fort Worth Kalamazoo
Actually
His plan for Kalamazoo became the first outdoor pedestrian shopping mall
Open the US even had a concept to turn 5th Avenue into a pedestrian Mall
Close down 5th Avenue for a couple weeks as a test
What is City's downtown is not a mall
Not so easily quote-unquote fixed not so perfectly designed and controlled cities
We're going to become the pleasant sterile shopping environments That Grew and wanted them to be
After
The Riots of the 60s he is shocked into the taken aback by those and it was
It's very much I'm prepared
And I thank God that may have been somewhat of his reason for the retreat to Vienna
In 1968 from Los Angeles back to Vienna back to the greenery
You've been trying to imitate
But he could not Escape his own creation
There's a shopping mall that's being built on the edge of Vienna
And he points to that as how original Vision had been completely skewed
After being in Vienna about 10 years
He gives
The speech in
Paper where he says
I refuse to pay alimony for the
Bastard
Victor Gruen the mall maker
Became the foremost Mall critic
Meanwhile America's love affair with malls continued
Do you want to catch them all pretty girl like you doing sitting alone in the middle of this Monument to consumerism
I know I remember in my own experience
Growing up in New Jersey when the first Mall opened anywhere near me when I was in high school this is Ellen Dunham
Jones she's a professor of architecture and Urban Design at Georgia Tech
It was cool to go to the mall
But I mean literally it was air condition
My home wasn't air-conditioned my school wasn't air-conditioned
Today most of us are
Spending our days and our nights in completely thermally controlled environments
A lot of us are craving
Being able to
Be outdoors
In recent decades our tastes have beard away from climate controlled environments and away from the indoor mall
Mall construction actually peaked in 1990 it's been declining ever since
And by mmvi is really the last
Brand new standard conventional Mall
That's been dealt in the US
And a new product has entered the scene
I kind of shopping center that the icsc the international Council of shopping centers
Kohl's a lifestyle
Lifestyle centers started appearing
In the 90s
And they
Tend to be
Open air
So when you don't have that roof anymore
But you have a lot of boutiques and a lot more restaurants Lodo centers are malls the sky
Guys as main streets
And even though they're full of chain stores
Lifestyle centers are sunny and walkable and bustling
And kind of what Victor Gruen imagine
And some of the old style indoor shopping malls
Are being read
Arby's
Retrofitted
Into the Hispanic community centers
Like in Plaza Fiesta
Outside of Atlanta
A lot of the stores have been cut up into much smaller mom-and-pop
Small shops selling Western Wear selling quinceanera dresses Plaza Fiesta also has a steady
The events calendar
Performances
In this two was kind of what growing imagine
These sort of community malls are truly places together and spend money
In the Shell of the failed design
Most people architectural historian
Especially
Fake ruin was a horrible Act
And you know
I I can see where they're coming
Physics
Barriers of his building
Are uniformly boring
It's a grueling that wasn't the point it was the interior
That we're really
Point does fountains the cheesy statues
Elevator music piped in through all those speakers
Those are all part of the Gruen effect
And I helped turn shopping malls into spaces where we felt comfortable
Staying and spending time and money
A lot of the original indoor malls are abandoned now
Growing weeds inside
Website this becomes a graveyard of dead malls called deadmalls.com
Users can log on to submit stories of the Dead malls in their towns
There are around 450 malls listed are submitted as sort of oral history
In particular what
Interesting I think about deadmalls.com is
How to spell check
A lot of fishes and it does make sense
So many Suburban communities the mall became the de-facto Town Center it was really the center
Of social life other than the school
I would be very sad if all of them
Victor Gruen Smalls were demolished we should certainly
Work to preserve
At least one
The most famous Mall in Minnesota maybe the Mall of America with roller coaster at zipline at the
Aquarion water park
The most architecturally significant law
It's grandfather
Is it one that's just a 12 minute drive away
In Edina
Jeff Hardwick book is called Mall maker Victor Gruen architect of an American Dream in ellandemm
Adam Jones book is called retrofitting Suburbia
Special thanks to Claire dority
Part 1 of 99% invisible waves produced by Vanessa Lowe from Nocturne and Joe Rosenberg mixing Tech
Production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real part 2 was produced by Avery trufelman in early 2015
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital director the wrestling team is senior editor Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh during Mazza and me Roman Mars
You can find Vanessa Lewis hunting show Nocturne
At Nocturne podcast. Org
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com