99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The end of the year income. Com invisible
Linkedin.com invisible
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Is the end of the year in time for annual mini Stories episode
Mini stories
How do you spawn quicket stories that
Maybe keep that our research for another episode
Or they're just some cool thing that someone told us about it
You could be from a friend someone on Twitter. Relative
Avery's Dad this is something that we found really interesting
But it didn't quite Warrenton full episode in 2 months of hard reporting
But they're great 99 bi stories none the less
And my favorite part is we do them is unscripted interviews where I'm in the studio
People who work on this show who I like a lot this is the greatest team and all the podcast and I can guarantee you that
This week we have stories about 60s cult TV shows semi useless gadgets
Play Modern Christmas tradition
It's going to be fun
Up first
Is Avery Joplin
Okay
What do you got
I have for you
My oldest article of clothing
I've worn this my whole life
Okay
I can feel it soft
Is a soft
Gray t-shirt
I've been wearing that weirdo shirt since I was like three clearly
My parents gave it to me
AmeriGas remember went down to your knees
Will have why you took it out or no or maybe again or no
I don't think I have the agency to take it I bet you put it on me 45 years old
Least
25 years
This is my dad
The Giver of this shirt to me
I read what's on it
Yes read what's on it
Where am I
In the village
What do you want
Information
Whose side are you on
That would be telling
We want information
Information information
Get it by hook or by crook we will
We will
I got to get serious
Who are you
The new number two
Who is number one
You are number 6
I'm not a number
I'm a free man
I know what this is
What is it Roman this is a t-shirt
From the prison
And
My dad's going to help us
The prisoner
Was an extraordinary television series made I think a 19-6
And it was during the sixties when you have the whole James Bond
Secret agent
60s TV show about a British spy by Patrick mcgoohan
Mysteriously resigns and then
That evening
Is abducted
Define themselves
In this mysterious place
Called
The Village
The village is this odd little town
Where he doesn't know where it is he doesn't know what it is that it's just a very strange
Little place
To the Village
Like if it's very disorienting cuz it seems to be kind of removed
From all other countries in the world
They're like
Villas and townhouses are all smashed together
And it could be absolutely anywhere
And it's
Completely beautiful and perfect
Black
Superfly
Everything is relentlessly cheerful
And everybody
Has to get owned
Good good afternoon we're having a parade
So they're all kinds of mandatory parades and events and festivals and no one has names and everyone goes by a number and again and again the Spy
Now known only as number 6
I've no idea who imprisoned him in this relentless
Wesley Cherry place
Are the people are wearing puppies stripes
Shirts and suits with
White piping and they're wearing rainbow capes
Keds sneakers
But the greeting from everybody is
BC
Be seeing you
Which on one hand sounds
See you later
But what it meant was that
See you later means
We're watching
So the whole village is under constant surveillance
All the time
And in every episode the members of The Village or kind of break number 6 in the
Tell him to elaborate my games and challenges and temptations
Try to figure out why he resigned
And the Spy can't leave the village or giant weather balloon
What come after having smothered
And the show only lasted like
17 episodes or so
It was really crazy
James Bond
Meats
Doctor Who
On ice
Yeah the show gets weirder and weirder with each for dressing up
Is that right yes
It'll actually sort of went off the rails
Everybody just went crazy
Very last episode
Doesn't make
Any
Logical Song
That's completely crazy
But
At the beginning of this
Bonkers absurdist
Crazy episode
It was something that my dad
I'm truly shocked
At the beginning of the opening very last episode they reveal
The location of the village in real life
I just like oh my God
This place really exist
What the hell is this
The Village
Looks like a set
But it's a real place in for my whole life
As long as I have been wearing that
Weird shirt
My dad is wanted to go there
And this year
He finally did
You know it's in a remote Corner whale
It wasn't easy to get there
X-ray
After World War 1
Is it swelled architect name
Serve
Bertram
Clough williams-ellis
And he was kind of dismayed by how the UK was rebuilding after after World War one and all these gorgeous old buildings were
Getting
Torn down or they just weren't bothering to rebuild in the Beautiful
Classical style they were building
Burlesque
Concrete block
Ring and
So when he acquired this
Remote
Plot of land in 1825
In
Home country of Wales
He decided to bring
The beauty of the whole of Europe
Back to his homeland literally
And as a zealous would travel around the world he'd find a Colonnade or building or church
Or maybe the top two floors of a church
Dismantle it ship it to
To Port my running rebuild
British person
Portmeirion
And from 1925 to 1975
Call William Ellis Williams Ellis
Hunted for all these crumbling remains of
Castles and houses in Villas
Across the continent especially the Mediterranean
And rescued
Vibranium to this one spot
And the kind of fund it
Became a resort
I've never seen anything like it cuz usually you think of Hotel it's a building
But this is 35 building
In an isolated area
At each building
I mean besides the other restaurants
Supports like a miniature Disneyland
Except unlike Disneyland everythingfx
Play real like it's all actually old architecture
But apparently
I mean here I have his books
But you can even look at pictures of it these are my dad's my dad's literature
But it still looks quite Disney ask because it's all painted these bright colors
Yeah
It really does that mean it's like
I would have never thought it was real
From what I've seen of it
Yeah it's crazy it's almost like why would you go to the effort of doing it for real
It looks so fake
But it does remind me that when we look at
Old architecture
We
Expect to see the weathering of it and if you really do restore it
It is bright and shiny and odd and
Brightly colored in pink and
Bright yellows and things like that
Public clock Williams Ellis County
The step further cuz he added
You like adding stuff
You put in fake windows that weren't really very like
Pokemon
And he added stairways that didn't go anywhere just cuz he thought they looks
Teaneck
Aldi's wine teapot
He also kind of like
Turned it into this Tutti Frutti
Playground of
Actual
And the cool thing was
It was post-modernism before post-modernism looks like a lot of styles that we would recognize
Smashing
You know Colonnades on villazon Gothic clock towers
I'm painting it all bright colors
And so in a weird way I can mess up
Extra crazy in the 60
No one was
Doing that
Although
You may be without having gone through post-modernism you would just see it as this
A weird collage
Whereas we might
Now how the
Language of
Disney and cheesy post-modernism to apply to this thing like maybe it looks cheap to us because of our
Our lived experience of these things
But it might have
Just felt opulent amazing to somebody before postmodernism exist
How do you say that
Architecture critic Lewis Mumford wrote in 1964
Portmeirion is a gay deliberately irresponsible reaction against the Dulce realities of so much that passes
Modern Art
Hair today
Shocking no one has seen anything like it and Frank Lloyd Wright went to visit it
Gregory Peck came to visit
Ingrid Bergman came to visit
Brian Epstein from the Beatles
I would stay there George Harrison
You stayed there a lot of
British celebrities
Shuffle Joe there
Because it was so isolated that it was so beautiful and they
Treated everybody with a sense of
Discretion it was a place that we
What kind of separate from the rest
Save the world
And removed
Contacts
For your name.
Matter basically all the stuff that made it for number 6
I was there for the prisoner Appreciation Society weekends
People walking writeaprisoner costumes they were re-enacting I remember episodes
My dad was there for this thing called pork
Maricon
What does basically like a giant cosplay event for the prisoner
Where everyone they do parades and they pretend to abduct people and they the giant balloon
Putting around
Everyone's wearing striped capes
Mcad
Except my dad
You know it was a little
Little Matt's is a little to buy a
I enjoyed the spectacle I wasn't up for the life
What kind of coconut is my dad's
Favorite show
Who loves this show
And so for him it was kind of visiting
An old friend
Cuz like they tried to remix
The prisoner
Kind of recently
They tried to do
American version of it
It was Tara
Who's terrible
I don't know what else to say it was
Parable because
My dad says it just can't work without the main star and visionary
Check my device is the one who made it weird
But it also couldn't work
Without Portmeirion
I think if the prisoner were done in like a Star Trek thing
It it wouldn't work but made it so incongruous that you weren't
Natural environment of these beautiful old building
That's what I think made it even more horrifying because it was so pleasant
It was so cute and it was so Charmed
At Owasso analog
And so that's the cool thing about
The Prisoner and Portmeirion itself it's not trying to be too
Attributed
The past
Or a vision of the future
It's just
Kind of dislike
Amalgamated alter
Ternative reality but in a weird way in both cases
Portmeirion
And the Prisoner
They just
Turn into alternate realities that look like what we have
Today Casino
Postmodernism and Disneyland and also this like World of constant surveillance and
Constance Uranus
It shows that the
The sort of fantastic nightmare that
Mcgoohan was
Predicting
In some cases are certainly not technologically pasa
That's totally why I still
Where the shark
It is very soft that's awesome thank you April
Ksenia
Next
This is producer Vivien Leigh
So I'm just remembering right now that the first time you appeared on this show
Was last year's many stories before you were a staff member at 9 p.m.
Oh nice Ron so great so happy you're here and so what is your mini story as a
A staff member
So I'm going to start this with another question
So
You travel a lot right
And
You trouble with device
Okay
So have you ever been on the road
And one of your batteries
Runs out of power on the phone it's like 5 or 6 p.m. consistently that's the way it is
Right yeah oh yeah it's it's the rule as around the battery but how useful would it be
If I told you that there was an AC free
Battery powered battery charger
That would let you fully charged
That one battery
And all it needs
Are 12 batteries of the same type
Charge that one dead battery
That doesn't sound very useful that sounds a little
It's not useful
But at the same time
It's not entirely
Unused
That's true that's true it's not
Entire leg still use that thing
That monstrosity that you are describing a battery powered battery charger is something that
Actually exist
Wow and it's one example of something called
Chindogu
Which is the art of Designing nearly useless gadgets
Wow okay so what do you mean exactly by nearly useless
So I change okay with a very specific type of invention that
Sets out to solve
One particular problem
But it actually ends up causing so much more of an inconvenience that it's almost entirely useless
So in the case of the battery powered battery charger you'd
Technically solve your problem with having one dead battery but you make a much larger Problem by draining 12
Other batteries
So it comes from the Japanese word chin meaning weird or strange and dogu meaning tools
So strange 2
Another example
They're literally
Thousands of them
A pair of high heels with training wheels attached the heels so if you're just learning how to walk in high heels you have a little
Okay right there there's is done kitty litter box
So you can practice the art of sand raking while you're cleaning up cat, but do you want to know what my favorite
Absolutely need to know
Solar powered flashlight
Technically could use it but you wouldn't really actually use it
So where do these ideas come from does anyone actually make them or they just ideas
So you can probably tell by the name but it started in Japan with a man named Kenji kawakami
Meet Kenji kawakami
Japan famous inventor of the useful
Anixter
His Creations range from Umbrellas for shoes
Two hairs flashcards
Two chopsticks
With fans
Soquel, you'd study to Aeronautical Engineering in college
And he's always been interested in engineering and design and
He came up with the concept and started making his own creation sometime in the 1980s
But somehow we actually ended up in publishing
Which is kind of how
Chindogu took off
So what kind of posting was he doing was he's busy polishing these
Like these items so in the early 90s he was the editor of a Japanese catalog called mail-order life
Which is you know what one of those home shopping magazines and so there's this one month when he realized
There was some spare blank pages in the back so instead of just leaving the blank he decided to include some images of these
Unuseless inventions that he been tinkering around in his workshop with so you know they were for sale anything--but
So he had a solar-powered flashlight which I mentioned earlier and
Also a pair of I drop classes which are
Essentially a pair of glasses with funnels over the lenses
So you can just
Put eye drops in a funnel directly into your eyeballs like little holes Donuts
The other three years ended up getting such a kick out of them
But you know she started putting chindogu and every issue after that it's after a few years of doing this this American Dream
Listen translator named and Poppy I came across it
And he was like I have to
Spread this to the rest of the world and so the two of them together founded the international chindogu Society
Established the 10:10
Chindogu
Stewby's have rule so it was a what are some of the tenants to make it a truly a true chindogu
Okay so the first rule is that itching dogu has to be almost completely useless
So if you created something that's actually useful
You failed your done
The second rule is that it has to actually exist so you have to actually build a Jindo go
Wondering that's okay
You can't just make this
Hypothetical even kneel like that
A picture of the mail order catalog actually have to make the cat
Cool and
So the third was actually my favorite it says
Inherent in every chindogu is the spirit of Anarchy
And then it goes on to say
They represent freedom of thought and action the freedom to challenge the suffocating historical dominance of conservative
Utility I think I'm getting sold like a little bit of this is it
Is an exercise in Rebellion
Or
The Uber design
Product that is perfect
Text that had that does its job was great efficiency in his like
If I freeze you
Weirdo inventions that don't
Function but don't actually function well
Utility and Design
But that is totally true
Yeah and I mean it seems a little strange
To use absurdist design as a form of Anarchy but before kawakami got into publishing
Was actually a radical
60s and 70s and so the spirit of
Nonconformity and anti-consumerism there's something that's rooted in the concept of chindogu
A couple of other tenants that dictate
You can't sell the invention for money and you also can't patent it because it belongs to everybody
Supposed to be like the embodiment of design without the restrictive
Read materialism you can tell by the way that he talks about it like
I still use it kind of Purity he intended them to be fight like a fun way to change the world
I believe that if everybody shares my idea of changing perception for says
The world could change
One invention
At a time
Is it what happened to chindogu as a movement
Aldi's big lofty ideas
Right right you know just spread internationally their chindogu societies and competitions all over the world but kawakami actually ended
Putting a bunch of books out with
I'm useless inventions that he's made over the years or that people have submitted into the chindogu society
But since one of the tenants
I thought you can't make money from chindogu he actually ended up doing eating a lot of the money to charity
Awesome ice
But I actually have one of us book
Hear that was
Published originally in 1995 and can you
Tell me what you see
It is a camera
On a long stick
With a plunger
Porsche the shutter of the camera this is a selfie stick
Portrait camera
Do it yourself without a
I know that it is a couple
Target pictures with you in them
It can be embarrassing to ask someone to take a photo for you confusing if they don't speak your language even costly if the
Third-party regard your camera as a gift
With a 57cm telescoping pole your dilemma is overspending to three times its length
Companion in your environment
Your only problem will be that
All your shots will capture you in the act of holding a pole
Zoom feature of your photo album unless you really like poles
Image of flan selfie stick years before the
The patent for the selfie stick
It came out so I don't know if kawakami failed at making
H&L go
Or if we fail the societies because people are still using
Healthy snacks
I think we felt this is society
Thank you Vivian that's great thank you
So I'm in the studio with him at the church
How are you doing
Good are you
So what is your name
All right so many stories out Blue Glass
And specifically it's about this
Screen. In the mid-to-late 19th century
Blue glass with a light
Passing through a blue pane of glass
Could solve
Just about any problems deposit
We have
And this all goes back
To a civil war
General General Augustus J Pleasanton was a
Soldier in the Civil War
And he was a gentleman scientist
She did a lot of reading
So this is Jenny Benjamin and she's the curator of the Museum of
Asian in San Francisco
General Pleasanton and she says that you know
This armchair scientist
It really shooting from the hip and he had all kinds of wacky signs
You know that the blue color of the sky
There must be some inherent value to that color and that blue light
Why was part of like what
Facilitated the growth
The plants and animals in and biological
Prophecies
So he built Pleasant
And that is felt a garden nursery
In his backyard
With alternating blue Plains
Glass
And
He ran a quote experiment
I see how well they vegetables
This is like a greenhouse
Yes like a drink but I didn't want to use the term Greenhouse
Because
It was a blue house
NBC says quote experiment
Gentleman scientist
But basically he was growing grapes
Inside of this
Glass
House with a certain amount of the windows
Painted blue
You can kind of
Imagine what happens next
The story right now I think so
Pleasanton reports
Of course
That is plants
Through to incredible size
So then he expanded the
Created an Animal Planet
It was for pigs
And he claimed the pigs grow to enormous size and it was all because of the blue
A blue light
So great
Tok
What kind of rounds around the country extolling the virtues of
A blue light even got a patent applied for a patent for what
Cerulean process
But I love that
Is it really amazing
According to him he says
The patent officer came to his farm
And this is what he supposedly said
If my investigation should establish the Verity of your statements you have made the most important discovery of the sea
Transcending and importance
Even that of morse's telegraph
Wechat
Best furnished only means of communication with this
In places while your discovery
Could be brought home to every living object in the
Planet
Your patent would be one of the most valuable ever issued in the United States
Wow
By tentative price
And anytime any all about this
About me on how blue light but
Panacea
And it was touted as a cure-all
Write everything
Skin conditions
Your eyesight
Also
Baldness
Insomnia back pain
Serious
Ebates away with saying you know
This can do
Everything in the book
Was really popular
And had all these testimonials ended up people saying all this giant just like Jeremiah paraplegic
Child are or whatever
And so every two years at 1876 and 1877
It was suddenly this
Huge bad for all
They're blue eyeglasses you show me a pair of blue eyeglasses from this. At the Museum of vision
Blue wallpaper but the big thing was blue windows
Some people would build like a little sun porches
1 blue glass window Neil thinking that
You know if you
Could spend time
Bathing in the blue lights that that would cheer whatever railed you
And this has become known as the blue glass
Craze
And so when did the Blue Glass
Come crashing down when people realize it didn't work at all. Quickly
What is a couple years was going on there were people that were kind of
Poking fun the same way
People believe in pseudo-scientific things that were editorials written about the video
Installing Blue Glass all through their houses but the reels are nail in the coffin
What's this
Yeah Scientific American
It speaks to how widespread it was a Scientific American took it upon themselves to like thoroughly debunked
Did debunking every ass
Aspect of
This
And you know just to be perfectly clear about
There is there is no way that color
By itself
Or colored light is
Going to
Share your ID
Or any
Garcia.
So are there any of these blue Windows left like out in the world
Yeah I asked Jenny.
Are there like
Remnants of
Era that you
Be today like
Windows in buildings anywhere or
That is a really good question I don't know if there any building
Blue windows
Specifically because of this
But I bet it somewhere I would
Surprised
Chase them down probably
If we were to find this
It would probably
Just one
Blue
Window
Oh please tell me you found it well okay so one of the most comprehensive writing about this are
Era was by on the writer Paul Collins so he's so Gray
And she chapter about Augustus Pleasanton in one of his books and and
Chapter he talks about
About himself
Finding a window
A blue glass window when he was
Living in San Francisco until I called him up to
Deserve talked about that
With syrup
Thriller type of area
Glass paint
100% sure that this is from that era
Troy I know that might have.
Put the age of the house with such that it is
It was like the right era
For that to have been an original
In the book he talks about how it's been
Queen
These two gas stations on this one Street into the sunset in San Francisco
Google Street View
And so here check it out
So here is
The house
You can see
Yeah these two panes here
How do you say
He thinks that this little entryway on the house
Is this one of these
There's some porches
That's awesome
Yeah it's pretty until you know it's like
Older looking house on the Block
Looks like it could be from that era right
I'm for sure and so yeah I
Decided to
Go check it out
Can the Shell station the Chevron
What we can find
No
Oh no
It's gone the house is
God
So
It was it was gone the house had been turned into like a condo
So even that picture from Google Street View is out of date and the crazy thing is at that was from 2017
You feel any better
How healthy are you and I get there and blue windows
Torn down and now there's a
Giant
Box
The huge Clear Window
It's really ugly
Trying to reinstall Jack
About architecture
And buildings but
This one really looks
Terrible
And worst of all
Glasses
Clear
Clear glass
Yasso
The story
After a long search I still have not found a blue glass window
You know if anyone out there
Expand from that area that I mean
Plausible that
Someone out there has got one of these windows to get take a look at
Tell me awesome
Cool thank you so much thank you
AB next one more Christmas-themed many story you're going to want this for your Christmas party banter right after
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Our final many story of the day
Comes from senior producer
Katie Mingle
Really cozy in Herriman
It's not cozy enough to start a 3.5 box
So hot in here but just roll with me
Starting a fire in here right now though
We could go to
YouTube
And find ourselves a yule log
Jamaica YouTube right now
Just a tiny bit of History a yule log
Is an old term
For a certain type of fire that
People with burn
A Christmas would like us
Special log but now often when people talk about yule yule log the talking about
Like
Like this
Put on that
Oh this temper slendrina hours of crackling logs for Christmas okay
It's it doesn't start as soon as the fire starts crackling
Like it's relaxing
This idea of putting a fireplace on TV
So that you can watch it as if
You know you had a fire in your home
Actually goes back to nineteen
Cool and it started at this
Little television local television station in New York City called WPIX
And
And it was kind of the brainchild of
The station manager guy name
Fred thrower
And heat you know how people are always like looking for
For Holiday content
Migrate like we know this from working and radio
You wanted to give
Dwellers
The luxury and the worm
FAU walk fire
Didn't have fireplaces
So that's Chip arcuri he's kind of an amateur
Historian of this
Original yule log
The location for the first shoot
Are you organized
Gracie Mansion
Which was the mayor's residence
At the time the mayor was John Lindsay
And he gave them permission
To come and film
And
They did but there was a mishap where
Blue out
And it damage the very expensive oriental rug
So yeah this was this was like a $4,000 rug apparently and they really messed it up
Anyway they got their footage they put it on the air it was a 3 hour long broadcast with
Louis a loop of this fire and it would air on Christmas Eve and you turn on your TV to Channel 11
It started actually started with like
This little
Christmas time you know
Special message from
Someone at the station
It's the one that I found online it's it's
It's just striking because it's
How to put this in
Very
Jesus forward
Let's hear it
More than any other person in history
Jesus taught us to respect the godliness in ourselves
And give it expression
By doing God's work in the world
The gifts which we give this Christmas season
As symbols of God's great gift to us
Will pass and be forgotten
Wow
This is a secular UHF
Local
New Station
Sew-in then after that message
They cut to the fireplace switch
What's the governor's mansion fireplace
And the camera would kind of do like a slow Zoom
Start out seeing like
Whole mantle
And there was stockings on the mantle
It would slowly Zoom in to where you were just
Seen the fire
And then
For the next 3 hours they would play
Christmas music
It is classic Christmas music from the 1950s and 60s
So yeah so it's like a lot of orchestral kind of big band stuff like people like
The ray conniff singers
Fred Waring and the
Pennsylvanian Percy Faith
Percy faces the king of the yule log
There's nobody that has more songs in the program
Virginia log of Tombstone
I've always said that the program
If the program aired with a
Great video of a fireplace
Interior soundtrack
Not done very well
But it's paired with a great soundtrack
Chip loves
Christmas music
He at some point he mentioned his list of top 500
The songs that I liked was like I didn't even know there were 500 Christmas song
That's great
So you're basically grew up with this Yule Log broadcast it was a Christmas Eve
Tradition
Yeah he and his family used to watch it together even though they they actually had a real fireplace
He did actually watch it beside me watch
The actual
Program the actual footage
Yeah like you would kind of gather around and put it on a new doll like
Yeah oh yeah
It would be on one side of the room
The TV with the fireplace with
The other side
Real fireplace
And we're probably watching you log more than we were the real car place
Some New Yorkers love
This broadcast and eventually
The station decides they need to
Therese shoot it because the film that they shot it on his
Is deteriorating
Who's actually a 17c
Second Loop people Pepsi like
That's crazy so but you remember how like the first time they shot it they
Play like Brenda a hole in the governor's drug will he did not forget
Yeah
He would not let the back at Gracie Mansion because of the mishap at the rug
They need it
Location he wouldn't let them go back there
And somehow in this part is kind of lost to history someone
Found a very similar looking fireplace
And you'll never guess
Where was
They located at
Very close
Silver fireplace
California ball places
Palo Alto
And they refilled it in August of 90
During a heatwave
In Northern California
Bay area zone
Palo Alto California is awesome
Are fireplace
Yeah 30 years of service Palo Alto fire
Became V Yule Log at aired for 20 years it's
The classic
Yule log
Not to be confused with
The original
Yule log
The 1966 you logout was shot at Gracie Mansion that are for those first four years
Is the original
But it's not the class
Because most people
Don't remember
Original
Wow
So yeah this one this one aired for a really long time
But then in 1990 Christmas Comes
And chips
Turns on his TV just like you did
Every year
I mean turns Channel 11
And
It just wasn't on we're all looking for it wasn't on
Luckily for me I just
Had a feeling.
Love you forever and I recorded it
Add a recording so he was fine but the rest of New York was just out of luck
And people were mad the station got a ton of letters
Why did they take out there after 20 years
So the station got actually got a new program director
The new program director came in and
It's taking up too much
Marshall time you'll take it off
Scrooge heartless
So it's a chip and a few other people actually started a petition to get it back on the air they set up a Wii
Website called bring back the log
Dot-com
But yeah but nothing seemed to persuade the station that it was worth bringing back until actually 9
What happened is that
Terrorist attacks
Betty Oliver leveno
Was the president of the station at the time
Top New Yorkers needed comfort
Television
They needed something
Remind him of
Happier days
Oh yeah they put it back on and it still runs today runs
I believe it's an hour on Christmas Eve and then
You hours on Christmas Day
Chip believes very strongly that the best time to watch it is Christmas Eve and
The way he talks about it it's like
It's scared
Play spiritual for him it's like
Christmas Eve Mass
All the cards are sent to
Cookies are baked to get Saran Wrap
Relax and enjoy the solemnity of the bone
Tranquility of Christmas
For the crazy Christmas Russian Chris
Today
Nice
Is it the same Palo Alto fire did they film something new I believe they're still using that
That same Palo Alto
Yes that's chipper Curry he runs
Bring back the log turned into just
Biolife.com
He's basically the keeper of all things yule log
I'm Heaven helps the TV station add another hour of
Music
To that the broadcast because he has to
Huge Christmas
Record collector
And a shout-out to our own Avery truffle men who first told me about this
History on to her dad who I think
The yule log
We'll hear more mini stories from the rest of the 99 Pi crew as the
The first episode of 2019
But we will have episodes in the feed for the final two Tuesdays of 2018 even though they land on Christmas Day and New Year
I figured there's a good portion of you or traveling and resting but still need nice things to listen to while you might have some time
I'm off work and if you don't have time off work
Will still be here for
So stay tuned
And a Happy New Year
99percentinvisible
Is Avery trufelman
Katie Mingle
Curt.
Delaney Hall
Refusive
Emmett Fitzgerald
Sean real
Taryn Mazza Joe Rosenberg
Vivien Leigh
Sofia klatzker
And me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 FM kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com