99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Mesa
What Christmas day of course
No you haven't missed it it's Christmas Day and we're celebrating with two buns toys from The Illusionist
Show about language from Helen zaltzman
Illusionist is one of my all-time favorite podcasts
I'm not just saying that because Helen zaltzman is one of my all-time favorite people
It is a show about language but it is absolutely not just for word nerds
It is 99 Pi style storytelling using language as the lens to view culture rather than design and if you haven't discovered it
Yes you are going to love it
With two festive seasonal favorites from The Illusionist
Here's Helen zaltzman
The war on Christmas
When the thoughts
The poem the birth of Jesus Christ himself when King Herod ordered all the baby boys in and around Bethlehem be killed
In 1644 when Oliver Cromwell Puritans passed an ordinance prohibiting Christmas celebrations in English
In 1659 when the Massachusetts Bay Colony Puritans managed to get Christmas done for 22 years for being
Paganfest
What date in 1998
In person second largest city
Birmingham
If you picked up practically any newspaper at the time
You would have wrecked the Birmingham city council
Renamed Christmas
Winterville
Birmingham will celebrate the festive season as usual this year with Carol singing fairy lights and Street Entertainment
But don't call it Christmas
Council officials have renamed it
Wentzville
In the hope of creating a more Multicultural at
In keeping with the cities mix of ethnic group
Politically correct decisions cold Christmas festivities
Winterville cancel Christmas coolant Winterville
Birmingham Council claiming it was anxious not to offend those in other faith
Rename Christmas
Winter political correctness gone by city council Chief provoked outrage last night
Christmas festivities
Winterville political correctness judgment believe
People name is intended to avoid offending Muslims and other minorities
A municipal brainwave cold winter
Renaming the annual holiday and liking it to shopping rather than political correctness gone mad
The word Wentzville has announced the echo of Communists who banned any Christian connotation in eastern
Cocoa right now
Call Mom call Mom
I'm barely in Britain Christmas was banished
Now we sing Winterville carols
Winterville sweaters
We hung up on Winterville stockings for father Winterville to fill with wind will get
And when we turn on the radio we walked around the Winterville tree to these festive Tunes
Winterville
Winterville Winterville
Printable window vinyl window
Exactly what happened
Well it's about as true as most things that are being said about Winterville
Which came about
Tube on mic
Chubb
My name is Michael
You could say that
I was the one
Costa funeral is Wentzville
In the late 1990s Mike tub was the head of events for Birmingham city council
Salon point of view from my seat
Cancel
Pokemon seaward
Windsor
Festival
I thought it was a portmanteau of winter and interval
I must say to suggest
This Hiatus in the air
Between winter festival
Quite elegant
Until it became showtimes for War on Christmas with a side of political correctness gone mad
It started well enough with birmingham's first when to vote in 1997
Events run over several weeks
Attended by hundreds of thousands of people
Without complaint from the Press World Apopka
Play why the following is Winterville became coincident
Fox
Then Bishop of Birmingham Mark Center
911 calls his Christmas message
To the clergy of the diet
It said
I wonder what madness has in store for us this Christmas
I confess I laughed out loud when I was city council came out with Winterville as a way of not talkin about Christmas
No doubt it was a well-meaning attempt not to offend
Ready to say anything at all
Unsu
The papers github
On the 8th of November 1998 the Birmingham Sunday mud tree reported that the bishop of Birmingham
Had condemned the city council's attempt
To Rebrand Christmas
What happened
User
An interesting story
Kitchen Oakland City Council of council Christmas off
Do you like Christmas Wentzville
Nationwide
Pretty much the only person who didn't notice
Was Mike tub
I can take in any of the
Did the media
Chivalry at the time
He just didn't talk to me at all cuz I'm actually working 41 days Non-Stop
Day and night
Busywork waging the war on Christmas
Except
That wasn't ready what Miken the council would doing during the war on the wall
In this world only one side turned up to the battlefield
What's a media really the actually took it took it on
People like the Daily Mail
Just going to Google and Google went to go and just look at sea
Organizations who are homes
About 6
Because they've been led to believe
Bowie City Council
It wasn't
Christmas would never
41 day is like Festival
What people thought he was trying to Rebrand crisp
Pyside
Political correctness gone mad
But actually political correctness have not gone mad
Political correctness is not even being a fire
Because
The council's events
Was not trying to Rebrand Chris
It was trying to bundle together a whole lot of events
Occurring in the weeks before and after Christmas
Birmingham is Britain's second-largest City
Shave with a very culturally
Population
There's a lot of stuff going on
Particular that time of year
They decided to use the mulching by my window
If you like it does what it says on the tin
State Market
A major Festival
Time of the year cold winter
I'm the boss of the things that happen in winter
BBC children in need
Hanukkah
Eid on Christmas
Christmas lights Christmas Market
Capris
Apparel
It was so cool Christmas
Particular event which included
Christmas lights which song was about
Events of a Christmas
Caymans
Christmas Christmas Christmas
Unfortunately
People decided not to
Decedent
Say they've decided.
Today's Show the off to the warm Wentzville erupted in the papers
The council actually issued a statement that they would not renaming Christmas
I'm Christmas was very visibly a major part of the Winterville lineup
But which Story 6
The tree one that winter was a marketing and admin umbrella
What's a lie
The twin trouble had come to kill Christmas
Nobody asked you could see the
Is significantly more about the war on Christmas
The actual evidence
That war
Is being waged
Some people seem very eager for that to be a war on
So they can leave
Two Christmases defense
The Christmas has achieved cultural dominance Way Beyond the religious line
D'cost it as an underdog
Provides a cover for
Taking a puppet of occult
To create to maintain divisions in society
But Christmas is a pagan Roman Christian
Celebrated by people from oil filter
Tiffany
Including me
Ethnically Jewish
Christmas is not threatened by multi
Culturalism
It is multicultural
People don't want change
The schedule change
Ultrasonic sensor
Winslow was used
An example of a change gone too far
Because I misread
Waltz
The organizer
Trying to do
And they continued to mystery
Austin 1998 Birmingham didn't run Winterville again
But in the following years the Winterville meth was repeated dozens of times in Britain's national news
Invite in 2011 after running another set-piece The Daily Mail have to print a retraction
Saying that we did not rename
Will replace Chris
That's too little too late
Windmill had already become the byword for play
Political correctness gone mad
It still continues
Just a few weeks ago in the British Parliament
Shailesh Vara
The conservative MP for North West Cambridge
Tell prime minister
Theresa may minority communities
Should respect
Reviews on tradition
Mainstream Brittany and that means and that means Christmas is not Winterville
On Christmas trees
I'm not pissed at trees we can
Agree with him that Christmas is not winter
It's just certain people just
Knights who say what they want to say
As a marketing story it is very successful because the brand
Really clever
If you just called it and I Birmingham winter holidays
Noah
Absolutely
The bronze Bean soy misinterpret
If you had your time again
Would you do it differently
Good for you
Experiment
The public needs to be introduced to Mew
Cycling initiatives
Otherwise we're just going to let you know.
Is it going to do
Going to go buy that fried turkey in the window and settle in for another story from The Illusionist
Featuring a couple of familiar 99 Guy voices
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Here again is The Illusionist
Anthony 9% invisible
So we're in the parking lot of Cow Palace
Does a gun show happening at the same time
Does welcome Patriots
We are here for the day
Chisme
Katie mingle on Avery trufelman of 99% invisible about to enter
Victorian London
In the Cow Palace arena in Daly City
Just south of San Francisco
California
I mean
60s degrees
Not Christmas tree at all
The great Dickens Christmas Fair entrance
Giant portrait of Santa Claus
As you walk in the Dickens Christmas Fair has been an annual event in the Bay Area since 1970
Founded by husband-and-wife team run and Phyllis Patterson who previously had started the Renaissance
As in the backyard of that home in Los Angeles
The kids run the Dickens bad now it's held on five weekends prior to Christmas
And is 120000 square feet
Victorian London Festival
Wow
Midas
They did a good job
Okay so
It smells
Lake
Apple cider or something
Spice wifey
It started set up to look like an Old English like
Market
Yeah they're like storefronts
And right here there's a big old timey sign that says champagne and they're like barmaids
Serving champagne
The bridge of my God, and they're British flag
Everywhere
All along
The feeling
It looks like a film set
Straight
The streets are named things like Nickleby Road
Crocheting
Pickwick place
Fezziwig's don't party
Do you have a map
FODMAP
Eyewear on Nickleby Road
Right now
Charles Dickens house
Streets of throwing with people in different interpretations of dickensian costume
Compulsory for attendees but encouraged
Pepitas
Batman actually
What is baby
Put their donuts face
Rapping in a potato sack and brought them to the victims
The Dickens bad London is also inhabited by schools of volunteers and well reset. Costumes
Before the event they've been taught relevant history given vocabulary guidelines and chosen names from a selection of approved
Dickensian names
Oh yeah
Never lacking
Patrico family's neverlucky
Oh and their English accents
Which I thought were right
Until you hit the docks
If you go any further you're going to hit the gym
You don't want to hear
What courses at Emsworth
I don't know if you could having a little too much laudanum Avenue missing
Laudanum was not a controlled substance in nineteenth-century Britain
But it is now so the Dickens Fair doesn't sell it
But there are lots of places to buy T&L
Aero performance stages
The Fencing Academy
Shops
Lots of shops
Robin nuspine hattenbach
I
Been wanting
Bonnet
Haley
Shops selling victoriana such as corsets jewelry
Popeyes
And once
Write ik when I die
I don't really know where that come from Jenna has visited us before Xmas man
We talked about the history of Santa Claus and Victorian Christmas cards with dead mice and baking them
Greg knows a lot about history and a lot about the history of Christmas
So I don't seem to check a few things at the Dickens Fair
To see whether or not
Dickensian
Etsy magic wands
Dickensian but I may be wrong on that $15 each
Rolling over
What else is British
Stop someone just makes up that David Copperfield
A lot of commitment yet
This many people go there you know like play make-believe on best brand of scale
Yeah
Wonderful
Is Amanda Tapping
Desktop has no problem at 11 Mississippi area of
Additions and I Blynken both of whom were top hats aficionado
Happy Christmas
That's an American
Only happy
Happy Christmas dickensian Merry Christmas non dickensian
Seasons greetings with very very Victorian times has a merry Christmas and a happy Christmas and
Seasons greetings and happy Yuletide
Biblical quotations and lines from carols
Frankly there's no real wrong way to say
Happy Christmas or Merry Christmas in Victoria
August 8th completely inappropriate
Are there particular words or phrases that are like useful today
Bullets is wonderful
There's one guy that bought the bollocks bollocks guy
You know he's a sign that says you either bollocks you not bollocks
And then people like I like your bollocks
That's why he's in your box
When do babies not falling
Greg
The word bollocks
That's a good old English
Swear word
That's enough. Of my head if if they can't ever use the in his novel Pepsi did
I mean it's it's got a long history goes all the way back to Anglo-Saxon English
So
Festivals of quaint britishness than Publix is our standard go to
English insults
Acquainted
I think so isn't it
Is this one Ally where everyone is dressed up as like a beggar or a prostitute or I guess a
What is it
Artful Dodger is a pickpocket
Yeah
I pickpocket
And chimney sweep
I got a lot of people are fake
Mud on their faces
Here
Which is kind of a weird thing look like
It wouldn't be my chosen form of escapism on the weekend sure but
Being rich
Expensive
Kevin Hart
Boring things
To gamble and drink
Really funny
Completely underestimated
Terrifying
Daily
Stresses and strains of
That's not having a food of having
Sexual violence if you're a woman who is a sex worker
The diseases you know the infant mortality rates
The fact that children working in factories and
FML
Kickboxing on the streets
Cadillac of educational reform
There is an enormous
Canvas of
A sadness of human sadness
Which Dickens picks up on
But there's a strange romance to it
Which we
Seem to Revel in
What was the life expectancy
1820 whisper something like 40 years old
An hour closer to 80
The facts of course this is massive infant mortality rates
Alicia Brady High chance of having at least two children died on you
If you have a family of six or seven kids
Women
Frequently have very serious
Illnesses in childbirth
More often than not the thing that would kill
A woman would be complications from childbirth
Cement of course
Treatment for service being
Elite dangerous
Temperature
Traveling the world
I'm conquering things in a ruthless fashion
Little circles you have
Terrible diseases and no understanding of germ Theory until the 1850s and 60s
So they're horrible cholera outbreaks the people that understand what spreads Colorado there is
Ask Evie that race this entry that race
A typhoid
Just terrible deprivation there. People unable to feed themselves unable to have healthy diets
There is choke in the bread in the period of History where
You can tell I have an ear infection
A scratch on your wrist
Anything can get infected
So
It's really not a very nice time to be living if you don't have
Car lot of money and if you do have money you might
Still die young as
Happened to several of Dickens
Closest relatives
Okay let's go see if we can Pekin
We're getting close to
The house of Charles Dickens wear
He's writing you can see in the window hello my goodness
What is
Ray-Ban
Could be one of his 20 novels and novellas thousands of short stories all schools in place
But given the environment that is quite a high possibility that he's writing something about Christmas
A Christmas Carol wasn't his first Christmas Story
But it was such a hit
It's like Mariah Carey really sing all I want
For Christmas Is You
Each year off with that was precious A Dickens
Keep supplying festive material
His other Christmas stories
The Chimes the cricket on the hearth
The Battle of life
The haunted man and the ghosts
Spigen
Human rights
And household World switches his self magazine stories for the Christmas edition of the magazine
From July of each year
Mr. Christmas tree
Christmas dinner
There's a very
Side SA
Britain in 1851
The year in which four of his family members died
Code what Christmas is
As we grow older
Which is a kind of
Tribute to them through several cooling out
In defense of Christmas in saying Christmas is about
Looking forward and hope and hoping for better future
While the same time remembering those who
To come before
So he
Return to Christmas many times in his career
Great Expectations starts with a Christmas scene
But none of those
Match the success of A Christmas Carol
A Christmas Carol is by far and away his best
Is most defiantly
Popular
Animals
Influential Christmas Story
How many other books being adopted hundreds of times for film and TV
The popularity of A Christmas Carol has never waned
It was an absolute Smash Hits straight away
It was published on the 19th of December 1843
I'm by Christmas Eve it was already sold out
The next day the book was adopted several times with stage and reprinted and reprinted it has never been out
Sprint
Dickinson public readings of the day
Back in Britain in the US until his death in 1870
And
Beyond
Yeah where at where at
Charles Dickens
And where he will be doing a reading
Completely set up like a full interior
And there's like a swooning couch and a fireplace and a bookshelf
Tattoos all over the place
Pictures on the wall
Rugs
Full whole nine yards with exterior
Is it painted like
Sir Charles Dickens
Wearing a long black
Coat
Sending a 10
A wood podium
Reading dramatically
A Christmas Carol to a
Crowd that is gathered a costume to an encore
Awesome football
Sitting in his house
Very enthused
Gandhi on the podium
She's leaning into the audience
Food City
Optimum
A Merry Christmas
What do you know about Charles Dickens
Katie mango
Sew it all
I was in a production of Oliver one
But stick and is one of those off as he's what keep kind of night without even having Reddit
Some of his work sticks so much and cultural Consciousness the name becomes an adjectives
Kafka
Volume
Dickensian
What Kenzie and is a very very Broad
Idea other than incredibly
Avast canvas of what we think of his dickensian and even that we use it as it was
That what itself has
Send me different
Interpretations and meaning
Men with Muffin Top sideburns and stovepipe hats women with hearts of gold and tragically short lives
Open spending themselves while menacing adults look around every corner
Please help my mom some more
Christmas Merry Christmas
Christmas goose Christmas ghosts
God bless us everyone
Dickensian is quite a tricky word Ashley and I think we
Done with nasseri know what we mean when we say it
As a what kind of comes up
Public cpaps
A sense of squala a sense of people trapped
Disapproval Society where there is no safety net there is no fullback plan with children and
Young women couldn't
Suddenly becomes into a life of poverty or crime or violence
But the Kenzie knows I really should sum up
Some of the beautiful things some of the wonderful things he harnesses you know when we look at a Christmas carol
The way he depicts the street scenes in children
People
Singing and saying hello to each other the sense of community the
The shop windows
I filled to the brim with delicious goods and treats to eat on Christmas Day and toys in the window
Also a Bountiful
Visual iconography
Dickens country.
Both
Oh so quiet
Enrapturing entrancing
Visions of what the city and the community could be so dickensian tends to be
Quite negative but I can really
Should I supposed apply to all of the different
Atwells the Dickens created and some of those were all the Pleasanton lovely and some of those were
Robert Rule and dog
Be at Lakewood
Steeler Christmas
Chicken
Yeah
Written about Christmas but don't have festive Festival
What is Dickens get to be the adjectives why is he given credit for Christmas
I want to pick people up and say is
Dickens invented Christmas which is absolute nonsense
Of course he didn't
Chelsea Kansas Christmases
Perpetuated some traditions he
Child that he
Perpetuated and shed in his books
Singing feasting charitable donations
YouTube
Medieval chewed up Stewart Georgian whatever you want to call that so
Dickens
Is not the architect
He's a cheerleader
Three different professions
Maybe maybe Saturday mean they both build large structures
The Christmas carol landed at a time when there was a trend for nostalgia
The nineteenth-century zientara why you have many folks arrest
And antiquarians
Taking an interest in the old ways there is definitely in the 19 century this idea of
I miss College eyes post
The Chew today ribbing
It's at Halcyon dive
Just as we have the dickensian festival is in San Francisco and we look best victorians
The victorians looked back to the Saxons and the Normans and The Chew
As a kind of Glory Days of simplicity
The good old days of Christmas
What much more pleasant
Because in some ways Victorian Christmas is a reaction to industrialization
The trauma of
Enormous economic
Frost
People moving from the countryside into the cities of communities being broken up
Dark satanic Mills
A factories of trains in industry
Of the British Empire expanding and people being separated by
Huge geographical distances
A Christmas Carol was riding a wave of renewed interest in Christmas
Along with the Revival of older faster
Costumes that win new ones imagine that
The K2
Christmas cards with suddenly logistically Bible with the invention of the penny Post in 1840
Christmas trees
Became popular around
King George the third German wife
Starting in the late 1700 so they went completely new
But they wouldn't really fashionable when in 1848 Queen Victoria Prince Albert and their children posed in front of
Illustrated London news
And like when whatever Kate Middleton was sells out
Christmas trees became All the Rage so
Quad loss of traditions
Movie think of his Traditions now that we assume that the Keynesian
Dickensian exactly the same time
2q coincidence
And it's so much together
Andis Victorian Festival suddenly feels like it's this brand-new thing
But it's not it's a continuity with some extra additional elements
The capitalism rapsody flop Christmas is a commercial economy
Without parallel
Had been for a while
Toys for children which is a new market is just opening up
Dickens's main intention wasn't to cash in on Christmas
Emanated need the money
Though he had had considerable literary success the previous decade
Lately the serialization of his noble Martin chuzzlewit haven't been too popular and his income was looking dice
Kelsey had a growing family to support him was often bailing out his parents and siblings to
I'm Dickens did sincerely love Christmas
His children write about the reddish
Which the father praise the festivities
But that wasn't the primary motivation either
Instead his heart filming Christmas Fable was the cover story for a political mission
He's a man who had a tremendous
Political appetites on who was
Of the middle classes
And after class
It was always on the side of
The wagon Clawson
And this of course was largely because he'd experienced poverty as a child
Dickens was the second of eight children in a pretty close family
I'm hot but he considered to be an adult child
Until he was aged 11 whereupon his father regularly had financial problems was sent to prison for debt
Anna's was customer at the time taken his mother and younger siblings moved in there with him
Puryear Charles Dickens left alone
He had to quit school and work 10-hour days 6 days a week under boot-blacking fact
Does a family dead reunite
Experience
Dickens informing much beeswax
Complete collapse
He's a man who's always championing
Those who've had a less fortunate life
He campaigned against public executions he thought they were vile and Grimm
You know he campaign for the women he campaign for Beto schooling for children
He's a man who
Who uses his voice
The campaigning tool
In the Victorian era
Many people Duster
Industrial Revolution adopted in such huge societal and economic changes.
Welfare and Health Services has not been instituted yet
I'm Dickens was horrified
The poverty so many people was stricken by in 1843
Particularly The Temptations children when living in
On the streets in schools for the impoverished
Looking down mines or in factories is he
And he was desperate to make a palpable difference
As a journalist he planned to write a political pamphlet
Entitled
An appeal to the people of England for the benefit of the poor man's child
But you realize that not many people would read a political compass
They would however read his fiction
And as a spoonful of sugar helps the medicine go down
Dickens code to display for social justice with
They feel good Christmas ghost
That's a Dickens
And I'd like to run with right many many
Journalistic pieces and editorials and he would
He would use his power
As a journalist in an essay yes
But with A Christmas Carol he's using his power as a Sentimental novelist
To move people to action
To inspire them to be better Christians to be better British people to be better
Neighbors
Family members lovers friends
Play whack his colleagues set
It's a book about charity
It's a book about community and about
What happens
When
The ravages of capitalism
Erode the human spirit
The corrupt the heart of Scrooge
You know he was a man who once felt he wants cat who once loved
An ultimately over the years he's being sensitive
Gradually worn down by this
Victorian Age 2
Make profit
The economy industrial progress moving forward
He's lost his Humanity
To the point that his own family
I mean I wasn't really want to hang out with and they already know he's lost all reason to say
For his fellow man
A Christmas Carol is
An allegory
Every Christian allegory a deeply spiritual book
About
A man who has become lost
Finding his way back
To his Humanity
I'm taking this Mission did succeed
Somewhat
The book was credited with causing a rise in charitable giving and going to General State your fellow humans and employees
Lisa Christmas
But it couldn't
Totally transformed Society
Literature can remove us
But ultimately structural systems
All very hard to shift
And
Victoria.
Had many many
Yes
Of moving forward in the very small
Steps being taken with their children's rights
Education reform since all the rights of women in particular
The Christmas aspect may have overwhelmed
The place call message
Patience
Like Scrooged we're running a little further away with inspiration like bad Sunday but I tell you what
B&B original still works
Treat because
It's really read a book the characters leap off the page
It's really moving
Inspiring and you desperately hope that
Scrooge
Stays reformed
It's really funny as well
I think one of the disadvantages to the web dickensian is it it makes his wife sound like
You going to be studying the Christmas pudding boiled for 8 hours
But it's not a cozy. Piece
His book is a reaction
Three economic
Situation in the 1840s
Facebook is deeply Morton
And yet
His
Outlook his ass to choose his
Sense of nostalgia for Whimsy
Is a course
In many ways DP traditional
Is
Bringing it kind of
Fusion
Between Haifa maternity
Old fashioned
Old timey
Lovely Nostalgia Fuel and when we look back
Dickens we
Do the same
Bellisimas is produced by Helen zaltzman with music and production by Martin austwick
It is a member of radiotopia and you should subscribe to it immediately and thank me for the suggestion
Well link on the website and in the show notes
99percentinvisible is a project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco with produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are proud member of radiotopia from PRX a collection of fiercely independent and fascinating podcast
Radiotopia. FM
We had a really good year of shows and I hope you heard them all if you didn't
You can subscribe and listen to the mall
At 99 pi
. org
Radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
5 part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com