99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
Eric molinsky has reported a few episodes for us over the years and he has his own right podcast called imaginary world
A picture of a couple of times
Imaginary worlds has a very special place in my heart because
It is the podcast I listen to the most
With my boys Maslow and Carver
Because it covers all the sci-fi and fantasy subjects that they love like
D&D in Doctor Who and LARPing
In a really thoughtful and entertaining way
And like every great show
It's about those things
But it's really about who we are as humans through these worlds that we create and share
How early this year imaginary world produced the story about the thing that is most
Near and dear to my boys hearts
And that's the card game
Magic the Gathering
I just called Magic a card game but if you spent any time around someone who loves magic you know
It is way more than a guard game it is a way of life
I'm pretty sure it rewired my son's brains
I wanted to cover Magic on 99 Pi for a while now but Eric did such a great job with it it made more sense to share his
Persian and introduce you to another great podcast that you might not know already
Enjoy
You're listening to imaginary worlds
And why we suspend our disbelief
IMac Gilinsky
And this is not
My name is
Nat is teaching me how to play Magic the Gathering at the Brooklyn strategist which is the same game shop
Copperline play Dungeons & Dragons Fierce ago
What were DND is role playing game
Magic is very much a card game
And by the way magic is the shorthand that most people called Magic
Mostly call it magic in this episode
Simplest level there are two basic types of cards in magic
Enterprise magic is like any card game
You need a combination of luck and skill to win
And it's usually played with just two people
But it is not a generic
Deck of cards
Each of the cards
The creature
Or spell
Or magical artifact on it that you can use to attack your opponent
And some cards represent the source of your magic which our lands
The more land cards that you have the more magic you can wield against the person sitting across from you
And your goal
It's a knock your opponent from 20 points
20 points
Danceable
It's not
It's really really not
So when you play you always have 7 cards in your hand that you're taking from a deck of 60 card
But that deck of 60 cards or something that you custom make
Because the company that makes Magic the Gathering
Wizards of the Coast
Has put out over 10
Thousand possible cards to choose from
Over the last quarter-century
And there is a central mythology that unites those thousands and thousands of car
Because Magic the Gathering takes place in a Multiverse
And some of the cards represent
Plane Walker's the main characters of the game can jump from one parallel universe to another
No I always do that magic the Gathering
Was huge
But
I had never done an episode about it because I was kind of intimidated
Like when I used to go to the Brooklyn strategist to play D&D
We'd all be role-playing are characters like we're in some kind of medieval improv troupe
And then I look at the table where these people playing Magic the Gathering
And it was like they were speaking a whole other language
Now this year is the 25th anniversary of Magic the Gathering
And it amazes me the game is still so popular
Notice anything wrong with a game itself but he was developed by this mathematician named Richard Garfield in the early 90s
There's very little competition from video games
And now so many analog games and toys that used to be pretty solid
Are struggling to compete against PlayStations and iPad apps
In Magic does have an app
But the handheld card game is still the main focus
And they are not struggling to compete I mean magic the Gathering has been on an epic run each year is more Pro
Profitable than the last
Soy two questions about the game I was really curious about
First why has it survived the onslaught of Digital entertainment
And secondly
How do you create a sense of story and World building
Hidden non-sequential card game
Indus all that mythology in world-building make for better card game
Or is it something the players ignore when they just focus on winning
Well to answer those questions
I went
Straight to the top
The head designer for Magic the Gathering
Mark rosewater
I'm pulling out of driveway we all know what that mean
It's time for the drive to work
Okay by the way that is how he starts every episode of his podcast as he drives to the office outside Seattle
Talking about different aspects of the game
He doesn't get to a podcast
Mark is out there on every media platform talking about magic
Answering questions from players
He is a force of personality
Demarcus been with a companies
Mid 90
Just a few years after Magic the Gathering came out
And I have to say in all of my years of interviewing people
I don't think I've ever met anybody
Whoso unabashedly loves their job
As much as Mark does
My job is to come up with a really cool things that will make players really really excited
And then I could not talk about it for
24 month usually
Example
Last December we put out a particle unstable
Which is kind of like a humorous take on Magic
I've been working on this project for 7 years
And I did not talk about it
First seven years at the one I finally got to talk about people like while you're so excited I'm like
I've been waiting to talk about it for 7
Now what are the reasons why magic has stayed popular all these years is because the game never stops evolving
As I mentioned earlier the premise of the game
Is a 30 parallel universes called planes
In the frequency in which Wizards of the Coast has introduced new plants gone from every couple years to every year
Denounce sometimes twice a year
And you know in the beginning magic was relying and all the standard fantasy tropes that you would see in a game like Dungeons & Drag
But is it kept introducing New World more and more quickly they kind of ran out of those fantasy tropes
They've also had to be more creative in terms of what they bring into the fantasy genre
Like in one of these parallel universes
Everything's made of metal
Or another one of these parallel planes is like a steampunk version of India
But as Mark says
Set of cards
It's a very challenging way to tell a story
Not everybody sees every card and they don't see them in the same order
So what we've done is we tend to use our cards
To build the environment
To build the world
The Flash out the world
And kids at the story
And then we tend to tell the story through other means
Like on the magic the Gathering website there's a lot of extra material explaining what is going on in these different worlds
But eventually they decided to up the ante
On the design of the cards
So when you encounter a new deck
You automatically feel something
About this world
Without having to read the backstory behind it
We want to figure out what the emotional core of the experience is going to be
The mechanics aren't just about doing something throat making you feel something
And I really got into the idea of
We're going to go to a Gothic horror world and we're going to make you afraid cuz it's a Gothic horror world
Are we going to go to our Greek mythology world and you're going to be a hero and goat adventures and mix
Something of yourself
Now there are three basic elements each card
First
There's an illustration
Which is about 2 by 2 in
But there's so much drama
In the story going on in those little paintings
Men looking at them I get sucked in like it's a movie
The second element every card is the statistics
How old is creature
Spell
Artifact will function as a card
Didn't realize
How many different ways a card could behave in a game
I mean it is endless in terms of how many points you gain or take away from your opponent
Whether this card is better used on the offensive or the defensive how many times you can use the card
And the game mechanics aren't random
They reflect the personality of what's on the card
In the third major element debit card is something called
Flavor Tech
A few lines of
Poetic description
But even the flavor text got more ambitious over the years
How many words that can cram into a card
But how succinctly
I can paint a picture of a broad story
Beyond that one card
Back when I used to write flavor text one of the things was it was a lot like poetry
It was a lot like
How can I convey as much as possible in the smallest amount of space
And one of my favorite pizza flavor tax
There's a card at insect called
We went with I SeaWorld
Apple Ice Age
And there's a cardinal called lord wife
Which was this horrible monster
Abase
Loosely based on some North stuff the flavor text on it was
Hans run it's the little boy
Last words of saffi eriksdotter
And somehow just like this idea that
Did poor of this poor woman that like the last thing we learn about her is she scared to death cuz she knows how horror
And she is right
Because
That's the last thing she ever says
And as much as Mark loves to talk about the game there's one aspect that he's actually the most
Passionate about
It's called the color pie
And when I first read about the color pie just seem like that of an esoteric part of the whole game mechanics
But then I realized
It is the lifeblood of the game
It is the thing that makes you feel like you're actually wielding Magic
You play with the car
Because all of the cards
The Gathering
Are divided into five colors
Card reader White
Black
Blue
Red or green
In each color represents a different philosophy of magic
To white magic
It's about control
Order
And whatever works for the collective good
Blackmagic promotes ruthless individualism
Red magic is fiery and passionate
Blue Magic is brainy
Intellectual
Green Magic
Is in harmony with nature
One of the neat things about
The color pie that I love is
It explains motivations in a way that doesn't demean the motivations
Like what I think is really interesting the man that has made me think about life a little differently is
Nobody's right or wrong they just have a reason for doing the things the way they do them and it's like oh what is their motivation
What's you're motivated by this
Going to make sense you coming conflict with motivated by that
I can argue and I have
I can argue any color from any perspective
Like one of these I did for fun at cuz I'm a writer is I did an interview and in my article is where I spent a whole column
Each of the colors
Interview with the colors having the color explained
From their perspective
Why they do what they do
So how did this all play out back of the game shop when I was learning how to play for my instructor Nat
Each hole has a very distinct personality and gameplay
What do the colors you use tend to Define what does
Now it's my first game I played with a deck of cards where everything is red
The magic I was using was fiery and impulsive
That's my natural instinct when I play games
Which is why I often lose
Because going on impulse
Is my downfall whenever I'm supposed to be thinking strategically
Meanwhile Nat was playing with a deck of black magic
It's all about sucking away your opponent's energy and using it for yourself
They're going to take one damage
Brady dommermuth
Is a lead writer in the creative team of magic
Any says when he would work on developing a new set of cards
He always thought about how the story they're telling with the cards
Should reflect the experience of people playing with a car
Magic
Defies one of the most common
Ethos prescriptions
In fantasy
And by that I mean
With the basic moral messages
I love the story in Fantasy A lot of times is
Sure you're the chosen one and you're destined to save the world
But you're going to need
Your friends
Help you out
In doing so
Button magic
I felt like
In terms of the story in the world design that form needed to follow function
And in magic
The vast majority of games are played
1 vs 1
It's you versus me
Is my deck versus your deck
And either you're going to win or I'm going to win
Which to me suggests a different ethos which is
Sure of course you have to have friends
That's super important
But
In the final fight
When it matters
You're going to have to fight alone
In fact
He thinks that magic is often misrepresented
Is a fantasy game
Because traditionally
Fantasy has been pretty black-and-white and its morality
But when you play Magic the Gathering
You're not automatically a villain
If you use black magic
And you're not
Automatically the hero
If he is white magic
Magic the Gathering
Action reflects science fiction
Is a long history of being morally ambiguous
Mark rosewater have talked about that many times about how
Star Wars
A fantasy story in sci-fi clothing
Where has
Magic
Is
Sci-fi story in fantasy clothing
Right now
Baxter game shop
I use red magic
Richard using a deck of blue car
Spells and creatures are brainier
Trickier
And by the way
When you play the game you can play any combination of colors but since I was a newbie
Nat felt that I should just play one color.
I switched from red magic - Blue Magic
I couldn't believe how differently the cards work
And I felt like I was relying on a different part of my brain
And my teacher Nat
It also sweats
Black magic white magic and I felt like I was playing against a different opponent
So overwhelmed right now
So many every card has so many like
Levels to it
It's a very very complex game
But that's when I realized how story can come into the
Because to be a good magic player
You need to know why your cards behave the way they do
And to do that
Really helpful to go on the magic website
And read the lore behind your car
What are the personality disorder
5 years or so I believed was to
Make the cards reflect story events more aggressively
Cards do
You can effectively learn how the story went
In fact I'm lying I found us some magic players have created fanart
Or they imagined
What if Harry Potter
Or the Marvel Cinematic Universe
Rare cards in Magic the Gathering
Chinese characters that we know so well like Harry Potter
Worth or it's kind of cool to see how they could be condensed into a single card
Summarized with an illustration
A bunch of statistics about their strengths weaknesses and Powers
In a few Choice lines of flavortown
But when he was working on a creative team
Pretty dommermuth always kept in mind that magic
It's not a movie or book reverse-engineer to be game
It is first and foremost
Again
One of the challenges for me and designing Magic World the reasons why undervalued plot
It's because I think that plot and games
Are not friends
Your ability to self Direct
Your ability to make the choices that you want to make your ability to explore the world how you see fit
Or to choose the cards for your own deck
Or
Decide how you want to win the game
History of finesse
Perforce
Those are super powerful things
Plattsburgh
Tommy
And I learned in my second round of playing the game that this blue intellectual magic was a good fit for me
I avoided all my worst impulses
And I became a better strategist
In fact
Wheels with this issue of I take stinks of a damaged from swings of magosi to my to life
That little bit
So game over then
Oh my God I can't believe it
Yeah I'm definitely quitting at the Thai I'm not going to go for 2 I'm going to go for the best-of-three
There is more to the magic Saga including some growing pains and the strange pitfalls
Intense fandom
You're going to hear from a couple kids
When imaginary worlds on 99percentinvisible
Continue
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
From imaginary worlds here again is Eric molinsky
This Leo used to work as a graphic designer on Magic the Gathering
And this was a dream job for her but
It also meant a lot of scrutiny
When I had you know millions of people see my first expansion symbol are my first card frame design and then consequently
Complain about what they didn't like about it I'd remind myself that Millions
The people were playing with this thing I designs and see a some people R&B focal and not like it but it just shows how much they care
About the
They're playing
But
I can't sugarcoat it either I mean there are certainly some toxic players and wizards has
Bantam
Or at least
Been working on their terms of service in terms of what they can do
No overall
Liz loves the magic community
She even went on a Magic cruise once
Just moments like this
What she wants went to an event and sat down to play a game
The guy across from me while we're drafting ass
How I got into magic and I thought that was a nice question and you responded and told him
The answer
The answer is that she learned to play from an all-female group called The Lady planeswalker
Society
But the guy didn't seem to care
He just said
I didn't think girls are into Magic
And that was the end of the conversation
What is small innocuous comment
Like in his head he probably didn't even think it was anything
Play so remember it because it just made me feel even more a little bit like
Wow
Should I not be here
And
Back it went when you're already playing Cambria to 100% on your
A game in terms of your mind and strategy
It can
Be a hurdle to overcome
Is sci-fi fantasy spaces have become more inclusive over the years
It's been an ugly backlash
And video games
The Hugo book awards cosplay
Star Wars fandom
Any huge Community like magic the Gathering stop being immune to this problem
That's sad
The game is always gotten price
Since the beginning
For having diverse characters on the car
But over time the creative team realized that they needed to be even more inclusive
Alli medwin is an editor and designer who mostly Works in Magic digital division
And a few years ago an intern
Came up with an idea
What if they created a trans character
For new deck that they're working on
Realized
This is
What we want representation to look like
This is a pretty natural flow like this is
Not
Shoehorned and this is not
Tokenize this is a natural extension
Of already established
Things about
The setting
They brought the idea to James Wyatt
It was a senior creative designer on the story team
Turn out to be a personal project for both of them
Ali is trans
Although she wasn't out at the time
That's for James
My daughter is trans so I send I need to write this story
For her sake
Allie and James really wanted this character
It's called Alicia
To be a fierce Warrior
Impact
The car's official title is
Alesha who Smiles at death
An illustration on the card
Shows Alaska in full armor
Leading the charge with her Army of the maardu Clan
Want to thank the magic that I love about our game is that we don't tend to put boobplate
Honor women
So
You can't really tell
Water physiology looks like
James Rowe the backstory for the website
And the biggest plot points
They argued over
Was whether an antagonist
Should confront A Lash about her identity
There was some sense and I've heard some people say this since the story was published that
Maybe it would have been better if
Unless it was just accepted for who she is with no question at all
But we did end up with a character in the story who
Challenges her and says you're just a boy with doesn't know who he is
Which is a terrible awful thing to say
To my daughter it was really important that that was there
Because she wanted
Jehovah character
Come to realize
Eyelashes
Worth and value and identity is who she is
Funny little thing I remember discussing early on is
That Alaska was a good fit for the Marty for two reasons than one is that idea that they claim a war name and the other is the fact that
They don't use Blue Magic
Because in the World of Magic the Gathering
If you have access to Blue Magic Lewis
Personally about transformation and so it would actually be really easy to
Change your identity
Change your appearance change your body
And we wanted
Her experience to reflect
Better the experience of real trans people in this world
Without access to Blue Magic
I'll tell you what if I had Blue Magic
My life might have gone a little differently a lot of people size might have gone a little differently
My daughter has actually designed a D&D spell that will allow that
As a permanent transition
Nice
When they finally put the card out there
They were a little nervous but how the magic Community would react
But
There was so much positive reaction that I still cry
It was it was overwhelmingly positive
Yeah maybe one comment in 50
Was negative
The overwhelming majority overwhelming majority was positive
The creation of his character Elijah
Also had a big impact on Ally
I lived
I was going to call a stealth
For a long time
It is
I didn't talk about being trans I didn't let people know I
I kept it a secret without
You have to lie lying about it
I came out
About
Halfway through the process
And
It was that it was incredibly rewarding I was incredibly relieving
Without a Lusha
I would still probably be stealth which
Look I'm not going to say doesn't work for some people cuz it does
But it was a I felt
I hope it doesn't burden and the less she was able to save me from that
But Alexa isn't just a character in the story she's a character in a game
Inner game mechanics are cool
Michigan help you resurrect other cards that you've already used up
And that's something that Allie really appreciates about magic
The way game mechanics Inspire character development
Vice versa
It it takes to design and directions that
We wouldn't necessarily ever get to without
The desire to
Figure out how to express an idea
Through the mechanics of the game
I think that it would be possible to put
Different stories on all the way
I really love the stories that we've got but if you didn't have any story on on these cards
You'd be missing
Solve
Really
So I came into Magic the Gathering wondering two things
Why is this game still so popular 25 years later
What is the role of Storytelling in a card game
And I think the reason why magic has been so popular isn't just the story within the cards or the story about the cards
The brand new story that emerges
Every time someone plays the car
The real story of a game as what happens
Player
Embrey Dahmer muses
That is increasingly rare
I mean so many video games today
Behaving like 5 Hour movies
Give the player very little autonomy
In an era where
So many games are played
Alone in front of your PC or in front of your console
Magic requires this community requires the semen presents its
It's compelling enough in it
Mechanic Smith gameplay and systems
That it wants to
Hold onto your brain wants you to explore
It's
Complexities
But in order to do so
You have to interface with other humans
And
Because of that it ends up being this
Naturally viral thing
Where
If I want to
See if my new deck works
I'm going to have to find somebody to play it
In other words the magic of the game is real world human interaction
Real world human interaction
Is in short supply these
Well that's it for this week thank you for listening
Special thanks to Nat Bale Mark rosewater Alli medwin James Wyatt
Brittany dommermuth and Liz Leo
Magic has some of the best fantasy art
Out there and I am saying it
I asked Liz if she's any favorite car
I love the card hydradoodle
It's this Hydra but it's also a poodle and
All the heads
Are off doing weird crazy things and the flavor tax is less housebroken than housebreaking
That's good
Is it your car is really cute
Imaginary world is produced by Eric molinsky and Stephanie Billman you can find it at imaginary worlds podcast
. org
Global Link in the show no
So when it comes to Magic in particular
My boy Carver and Maslow always
Always have something to say
What do you say boys
Hello
My name is carver
And I play Magic the Gathering
My favorite thing to do is to try to find a combo
Or something like that
That is so good that it will end up
Destroying the four battle just to unbeatable
Princeton the copycat
The copycat combo
The person who found a way to make incident little cat
To attack for damaged by around Turn 4 and it was
It was ridiculously consistent as a tattoo and everytime you want it turned out
Said no one could beat it no one can find a way to beat it
And everyone lost
And eventually they found out it was so good that both cards need to be banned and taken out of the phone
Charlie
So that it wouldn't go on like this
Until your goal is to find another one of those
My name is Maslow and I also play Magic the Gathering
I prefer playing the izzet colors which are red and blue
I'd like to play a lot of instants and sorcery cards and I normally play a little too many creatures for
For that type of deck
The great thing about instance is that you don't need to wait around while the other people's turns
You can
Do stuff as long as you have enough Mana for it you can
Play instances on other people's turn
What's an example of
A type of innocent party
You can play
For instance
Get it
There is a
A card called Sonic
Assault and I normally would play this on the phone it's turned when they're attacking and I'd say
Before attacks results
Itap user creature named here
And that packs and is an added bonus
Take control of that creature takes to damage cuz that's another feature of the car
That was for a few old school Die Hard fan
Happy 2019
99percentinvisible as a product of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
We are proud member of radiotopia from TRX a collection of fiercely independent and fascinating podcasts fun
Radiotopia
Tok FM
Is brand new show next week produced in the house so stay tuned for that it's many stories part 2
Happy New Year
Radio temperature
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The bunny genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com