We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek out go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
When the country's leading providers of Auto in
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is part to the 2018-2019 mini stories episodes where I enter
The staff about their favorite little design stories and stories about the built world
That don't quite fill out an entire episode for whatever reason
But they're quintessential 99 bi stories none the less
We have stolen artifacts mythical Ali's detach US territories
Machines that bring joy to people's lives
50ft screaming monster that we will burn to the ground
You're ever in need of a conversation starter
The mini stories
Are our gift to you
Stay with us
Amfirst
Producer Joe Rosenberg
Imagine you're watching
TV show
Buddy cop comedies
You know the closing in on a suspect
Nine times Outta ten
Around the corner to get away from them
And Ali is that what you're looking for some kind of leading you on
Rookie cop is woken in the middle of the night
It's Been a Murder at the crime scene
Crime scene
Chalk Outline
That is definitely again and now imagine me for what
Is the complete the rule 3 in another episode
Criminale definitely
Asian crime procedural
Play Imagine like say all the roles and Ali my play and movie
Upset in New York
You sure like if your
You are a restaurant worker or a dishwasher you take out the trash in the in the back alley you're like having a
Secret rendezvous in the back alley totally like that's an alley is
Where things
Exactly
The point
Is that regardless of what's Happening
In film
All of these Ali scenes help
Esl audiences
Is on the same eye
But New York is a city of
Thousand
Each with its own
This one time from
Which is better
There are no
They can't be true it's hard to wrap your mind around because we've all been
Raised on this myth that New York has
And there are some in the Attleboro
But like if you spent time in
And you really search your memory you will not remember
At least not like a classic Ali
Between two Street
At the fire usually maybe at Beth like it was like a glorified
Right right I can't specifically remember when you're right but that seems amazing to me
Do I think there is
And then why aren't there
Is there a question
Right right what's up what's the first why aren't
And this is because
When the city planners laid out the grid for Manhattan North
Houston Street in
1811 and something called
Commissioners plan
They purposely did not include out
They figured that they didn't meet Ali's cuz I got the high frequency
East west
You're much closer to
Gather to each other in the north-south streets
Kind of obviated the need for
Shortcuts
Or anything else that might break up
They're wonderful
But also and this is probably the real motivation it was a way to maximize
Because this way without any Ally cutting through the blocks
Badlanders can squeezing more housing
In Orlando
And after that almost no alleys were built because
Why on an ally when you can own a large
And so the result is that today Manhattan
Best a dozen things you might call Ali
Weather all
South Canal
Oldest part of the
That's amazing
We know that you mention it
The thing I noticed the most when I'm walking in the streets of New York
Is the piles and piles of trash
Which
When I live in Chicago
That's putting me out
That is not on there
Streak
Chicago is like
The antithesis
Chicago
Mm
And it said it's so cute to the egg
But you know
It's weird people don't put this together including
New York
One of my favorite things to do is
Just like I always asked
People
When was the last time you remember
Thanks I'm going to get somewhere
The quickest way to get there would be
Did you take the alley shortcut
It's not it's not a thing
It's only when you pointed out to them that they kind of step back and go
So this is Nick car and he's a film locations
Route to work
In New York for many years
What's the world
Wall Street
Ghostbusters
The Smurfs movies
Ve got another New York
When your television shows turned into a movie
And he says disbelief that New York has alleys
Is like the bane of his
Hilltop
Newyorknewyork Ygnacio Valley
But you were to tell a director
That there are no alleys in
They look at you like you have two heads and think that you don't know how to do your job
So invariably eat reluctantly wines up
Showing them
The Duggars
HD film izle Ali's
In New York that look like how you want to look I taste like five or six
None of those five or six
Most of them are they privately owned
Expensive
Weather permitting issues
Logistical dispensaries parking constraints
Leaving only the one Ally just south of Canal Street and
Easter Broadway
And that is Cortlandt alley
Which is just it is the alley
And Courtland
You have to understand
It's the alley you've been seen
Yuri
Higher life
You just don't realize it so like let me see it let me show you some
It's got the fire escapes it's
Loading dock
I've got no brakes and
Graffiti and it's an alley
Really is it is like it's
The perfect Deli
This is
Yeah
Yeah I totally scene
Yes I've seen 300
And yet it's
So I can pick up such a degree that if you walked
Buy it
You weren't actually notice it
Because it would feel
So intensely
It was like you've been there you know like even if you'd never sets wooden
Take it for granted because you you have already been there
So I'm pretty sure that whatever the first time I said
I walk down that alley it might as well have been like
The hundredth time I walk down that alley
But you're looking to get especially weird because
The reason Cortland looks like the platonic ideal of a New York Ali is precisely because it's been used in Soma
Classic New York Alley scene
Steve Cortland this is perfect and has been into contributing to the
Fantasy of New York
Because when a director has location of mine
He has created the perfect location
And no location you ever find will ever match up to what it is right
Portland is what you picture
Did you like the pictures in his head and it's not 80% of the way there's not 900%
Of what he had
My status because people directors CA version
New York in the other movies
TV shows and then go and
What are we created when they do their own filming
Sad truth is that
Stereotype tickets perpetuated
Kid from
Movie two movies
Suny cortland
Forever caught in this Loop
To the point where I can see my cat
All it's used for is filming by
Basically
Everyone always
When I used to drive by mean I swear to God it was on
New Law and Order series
No pribadi
The alley every other weekend but the thing is
They all did it they all do it and still do it
Every
Every major crime show cop show superhero show anything that is filmed in New York headstone in Cortland like I would
I would say that with
100% confidence
Like even the one Ally
In Manhattan
Doesn't really function as an ally it's basically a film set
Hollywood
The degree to which it's like
Treated as a film set in Hollywood zeal
Pursuit of the platonic New York
Ali
Like a story often calls for an ally to be like
Double trash
Concept
Of course real trash and grime would be hazardous to the cast and crew of the first thing they do is actually clean
Would like pressure hoses
Disappoint
And then
Yuan
Buy movie trash
IMovie trash
Large plastic bags like trash bags
That are filled with
Approved
Logo
Sort of trash so it's like generic milk bottles
And cereal boxes
Each bag of movie trash is about 40 to 6
$60 a bag
So there's an industry just
Mally's look like look like Ali
What kind of interest me about all this
Is it I think with
Some cities
We don't really know much about
So they can
There might be like
Shades about San Francisco Chicago but no one outside of
Francisco like truly things
But New York
Perhaps more than
Any other City
In some sense it belongs
Everyone feels
The thing
Right because they seen it in a million movies
It is like
American city
How many people
Is the city
Level granularity
Uptown
Downtown
Like like there are more like
Household name
Totally
Now that makes sense
It's also kind of like you know but they don't
And the result is that at some point the idea of New York
As overtaken the reality of New York kind of takes cultural precedent
Human Mind of a lot of York
Crazy never rely
It's just sad because it's almost like an actor that's Typecast
Right looks like an actor that's being asked
Play the same old roll cuz he did that one roll really really well back in 1977 so keep doing it for another
50 years
Sync movies
Are just so much more interesting
When you print portray
The locations featured for what they are and let them be a real character
Instead of just a backdrop
2 at any point
And it's
Film history
Was it ever
Names are presented as Cortlandt alley
Almost
Never
Men in Black
3 hottest scenes
Where Will Smith is tracking down an alien and they actually do
At least attempt
Qid
Taco
Another south of Canal Street
So close so close
Well I tried
They did their best
Men in Black 3
Well thanks so much Joe
Thank you
Okay Sean
Composer Sean murray
What's the story of
Wolf first I want to ask you a question Roman so you've never done karaoke
I've never done karaoke how is that possible
I played
The singing parts of Guitar Hero that's almost karaoke
Cinnabar with
Strangers
I've never done that
Yeah doesn't count
So I want to tell you about the person who invented the karaoke machine
His name is Daisuke anyway
And
As you can imagine he loves music
I read this interview with him and I found out that
He started working as a drummer when he was still a teenager in high
School and after he graduated he was perpetually in a Travelin Band that did Cabaret music
9 years
And I think that's a really big achievement but
Hey in his interview he likes to
Zoe says
One night I realized that
No matter how much I practice
I could never be as good as someone with god-given Talent
And I was enough to change my life as a band man and after nine years on the road
Many tails and no regrets I want home it seems like
It was more than just his musicianship that
Took him out of Road life like it seems like
It wasn't really compensated fairly all the time and
People he was working with like there
Really they partied a lot and they drinking all their money away
ISO
He was 28
And living with his parents in Kobe Japan
After all that
Karaoke is kind of already like a social activity but it's done with live instruments so
They're like bars where
You have like a musician playing a single guitar or keyboard or something and people singing along
And this was one of those kids regular gigs when he was living there with
Parents
And he says
Playing the drums
Oh no he learned how to play keyboard
Yeah he says that he taught himself 300 songs
Switch
Once again it's just like
Humblebrag
Because then he says because then he goes on to say that
Cute like but everytime I try to learn more than 300 songs
I like I just would forget them all the time mixing them up
Wow so yeah that case is pretty down on himself okay
So he's working at these karaoke bars
And
He's got like a bunch of regular karaoke singers and
There was this one businessman who would always sing with him
The kind of changed everything this businessman was about to travel for work and he wanted to be able to sing for his colleagues on the trip
And I say recalled the business man saying to him
Your keyboard playing is the only music I can sing to
You know how my voice is and you know what it needs
The town good anti skate couldn't take time off work so he
Tape them self
Playing some of this guy's favorite songs
And it worked
The guy was happy
Paid
And I'm sure you can see where the
After his success with this businessman
Daisuke in 1971
Commissioned a friend to build a machine out of three existing machine and amplifier a coin box and an 8-track car
Car stereo
And he called it that you Kate
So a hundred Yen put in a hundred yen
Atwood machine with turn on for 5 minutes
So you could put on a tape of instrumental music and singing through a microphone
And, I want you to see one of these
Insider very beautiful images
Going to Slack
It really is beautiful
Yeah it's a cabinet it's red and white
It has
Gradle analog knobs
And
Place for the
You know the 8-track cassette what I would call the cart machine in the in the radio business that you
Press in there
And then a little
Back red cabinet on the right that stores
Little library of a tractor
Best buffets
Is that him smiling right next to it looking man
In every picture you smiling like that
So the music on these first 8-track tapes were they the ones that
Did did he compose those or how did he how did he get the music
So they were
They were popular songs and the
Thanksgiving recorded them with his band
Actually I guess
He recorded his
Band playing the songs he says that early on in the process they fired him from playing
Again poured a skateboard
So he just focused on recording and mixing the music
Which is really important part totally totally
No karaoke machine
Recording and mixing thank you Sharif
And it's funny to me because even though it was fired from his own van he was
A real Hustler
He got bars all over, to lease these machines from him
He got contracts with major record labels to use all these Poppy
Your songs
He didn't patent the machine no
He says
When I first made the Jew Gates
A brother-in-law suggested I take out a patent
But at the time
I didn't think anything would come of it I was just hoping the drinking places in the Cobra area
Use my machine
Most people don't believe me when I say this
I don't think karaoke would have taken off like
If there had been a patent on the first machine
I think that's actually a pretty fair
Assessment
You know it's a really nice and joyful thing even though I've never
This machine is really really lovely in it
Is it nice to think of it
Is it just existing in the world to make the world better and not necessarily to make
But money
It does make some people money
This other person
Did take out a patent on a LaserDisc karaoke machine
But he's not part of the
Right now
I know that's right amount of History yeah
Ozon
Besides I didn't build the thing from scratch the amp the microphone the 8-track player even the hundred Yen box machine all had
You think so yeah I don't know anything about that
About Patton especially Japanese patent law
Well I don't know about dabbing patamon actually I'm no expert of US patent law but
If you come up with
A new use
Or even own thing
And prescribed that you since I have the patent
It doesn't have to be three machines that could be one machine to do a search
A little something and change it
He totally had the right to it
So this is just more of him talking smack on himself I really love about this story on a whole is that he seems
Pretty okay with how all of this turned out
He talks a lot about
Just like
How glad he is
Is that this brought so much joy into the world and he says
I may not have the original patent some say I would have made 80 million dollars last year and that was a bad year
But I have good friends and a family I love
And I can't help but smile everyday
There were things some uppers
Yeah I guess the last thing
I just wanted to
Say that
Daisuke says
To honor karaoke
And his wife and daughter and three granddaughters
Get out of song book once a week
And
See who can sing the most
Songs before going horse with
Sounds
So crazy that's a way harder than I want to party
And yeah and there's more to his story
But I think it's better told from him so we'll put a link to that on our website
Nice
Alright then
And we should totally go karaoking sometime I think we could make that
Text
About a year ago our senior editor Delaney Hall move from beautiful Downtown Oakland California back to New Mexico or she
She grew up she now works for 99p I remotely and her mini story is about this phenomenon in the new city where she live
Santa Fe
The phenomenon is called
Zozobra
Does Oprah is a big deal here in Santa Fe
Basically
Every year
A group of people in the city build
This enormous marionette
That's named
Sosobra
And in Spanish is over that means anxiety
So he's like
All of the city's Collective sorrows
Embodied in this
Wow
That's amazing so what is he what does he look like
50 ft tall
She is dressed in a long white
He has he's very dark Angry Eyes they're usually
Rimmed
Green or black
And what happens is that
Every fall.
This group constructs a new Zozobra and about 50
50000 people
Gathering one of Santa Fe
Is biggest parks
Wow they burn them yeah yeah they it's a very
It's a very intense
Kind of pig feeling events
I mean basically the crowd chant
Burnham Burnham Burnham and he's he's set on fire and he is
Slowly engulfed in flame
And I assume they burn him so they can burn their Collective anxiety that he represents
Yeah yeah exactly
Please soak
Because
Because he represents bloom
It's this way that the
The city
Purges
Sadness
And
People get to participate in these interesting ways
And one of the reasons
Sosobrat is
The flammable is that he is
Stuffed with
Bushels of shredded
And where that
Paper comes from is in the week
Leading up to the burning
Anyone within
Excessive Gloom
Is
Encouraged
Rate down there
Gloomy thoughts
Sunapee
Paper
And to leave it in this thing called the
Gloom box
Which at least in the past has been located
In the office
This Is Us
One of the local news
Papers that people contribute
Police reports
Mortgage documents
It reminds me of other Thrift
Bonfire rituals like
Like burning man or something with a lot of people go to around here
Yeah I mean it's a soda has been around a lot
Longer than Burning Man
Turn around since the 90
There are definitely some similarities like
Those were developed by
Artists both events began relatively
Small like in someone's backyard around him
And then grew into something much
Bigger and I'm both actually drawn other Traditions they go back
Even farther
But one thing that's
Pretty neat about Cisco bat is that
Because he's a puppet
Capable of
Kind of rudimentary movement so
Arm swing around his jaw is hinged
So his mouth opens and closes
And he also makes
Sound
So I'm going to play
A little bit of sound of the event so you can hear it
Flailing at the same time
Yashow
Wailing his mouth is opening and closing
It's really it's actually really troubling event
To go to as a
Kid it is sort of seared into my memory
This is actually like the thing I most want to tell you about the
Because I
I recently learned just in the past year or so
That the voice of Zozobra is performed live
And there is one guy who's been doing the voice for about 20 years
And I learned this thanks to
This Gem of local reporting from
Koe tea
Action 7 News
Me
I see him as an old grumpy old man
The character that I get into
This
This is so bright you know
That want to get rid of him that wanted
Destroying the water burn
And
My
The way I play the character is I'm fighting
They live
Friday Michael Ellis
Take on the Persona of archillect
SRO for the 19th
Despite the title of old man Gloom
Just hope his voice battles several emotions
Sparrow times
Until sound like he's crying
Adamant
I'm not going to let you do this to me again
50000 should always know what is over
Is feeling not only do I want
The crowd to hear it
I want him to
And even after 19 years for Alice
The big night is always exciting
I'll sit down and have a sandwich
Dictionary after
After that
I've got butterflies
I won't have it
Until after it's all over
On Friday night
Those butterflies join all of him
Gloom
Vinsmoke
Yeah I just
I love this news clip so much I think it's one of my my favorites ever and
Is the combination of the reporters seriousness or maybe Mox
Serious Mass and then just like
The sublime Ridiculousness of what you're seeing which of course people can't see it but
To describe it
It's Michael Ellis
The voice of Sombra
Performing the sounds of Zelda butt
To this big
Empty baseball
Field
Which you know probably later in the night will be filled with 50
50000 screaming people but
But at the moment is just entirely
So good
So you get like a little taste of what my glass is about but what is he really like
Yasso
This was the only thing I could find on the internet
About him
And from seeing this clip I definitely wanted to learn
And so I looked him up and went to
To talk with him
And what
What I learned is that he was
Born and raised in San
And Michael told me that
You know Isaac
Kid
So silver was like this
Figure this monster
Almost seemed real life
5 +
That sense of realness was this thing
That the community
Continues to really play into
Cultivate
Throwing up bile
I remember
Belittle stories
Newspaper talking about how sober has been spotted
In the Royals in the east side of town
You would hear stories of
She
Being missing
The area
Things like that
Play into
Trying to make
Seem real
And so from there how did Michael actually become the boys
Does Oprah
So as a high-schooler
He started volunteering for
She would help with
Building the puppet
Like that and he just kept being involved
A little more each year
Eventually
He was asked
Asked if you wanted to help with the voice
I was just sort of a matter of hanging around for long enough
And so did Michael do it any differently that he had something special to the voice when he took over
Michael didn't have any formal voice acting experience he's
He's done various jobs throughout his life
Including working at Lowe's hardware
Running a DJ business
But he told me that the main thing he wanted to bring to soba was that sense of real
That kind of alive
But I was
Talking about Earl
And
To do that
He said he had to find ways to really emphasize
Which celebrity has grumpy old man and to see the whole event
Unfolding from
His perspective
Knowing that
Everybody wants his demise
They want to see it happen
So I
I do my best
To try to
To fight
With
You know with my voice
There are times when
Almost sound like
Scrying
He's going to be able to do to stop it
Of course in our conversation and I was like pushing to try to understand is there some
Salumi memory or
Experience
Did Michael Taps into in order to
Perform
I asked him about his personal
History
I asked him about some health problems he's had recently
But he said
Not really
When it's needed
You just got the red Aaliyah
Accessible grumpy old man right there
I guess
APS a little bit of that deep inside
So that's
That's the voice of Sabrina and I I really like thinking about the fact that when I went to see so so but I burn
Back in the 80s
It was Michael performing The Voice
Tell me if I take
If I take
Fiona Ma
My daughter next year that it will probably be me
Up next is our technical producer
Sharif Youssef
All right
It's a Roman if I told you
That I had another Maps
Story
How excited would you be
Okay cool if you can Master it all I know maybe
I made it here
Just go to Google Maps real quick
The main thing we're going to be looking at today is the border between the u.s. and Canada and pardon my eyes
Siblings I have some dental work
And I think we need to pay attention to his
49th parallel in the Pacific Northwest of America
I'm so glad that you're okay
Yeah and you can like
Probably
Maybe now can notice a little something that looks off
Are you talking about Point Roberts
Sticks out right here
Yeah
Point Roberts on that little peninsula
Tsawwassen peninsula
Maybe you can just sort of describe what you're seeing
So
Robertson Upper Peninsula off of
Bay Area Vancouver
It looks like it's completely cut off from the US
Except by water
You have to buy land you have to get to it
To Canada
It's got a few
Very very gritted
Streets
A couple
It is kind of like an exclave
But but not
Yeah it's it's a it's a it's a semi
Exclusives
Space but it is difficult to get into so innocent exclusive
So yeah
Point Roberts is actually in Washington State
Heart of Whatcom County
I first heard about Point Roberts
Scrum podcast
Call Scott
Podcasting yourself
Dave shumka and Graham Clark
2 vancouverites
Mario there
Cuz it's only 20 miles away or so in order to pick up packages because
Shipping across the border is actually quite expensive
I'm and also to get cheaper gas
It's also rumored to be the site of
Federal witness protection program
Like where they relocate
And I just happened to be in Seattle a little bit ago and I also wanted an excuse to go to
Vancouver and how do you pay for it so I decided to go
Should I just play some
Border
Crossing my first board
This is the Peace Arch border
From Washington signature
Exactly
I'm good how are you
What's a preposition today
I'm going to Point Roberts to report a story I was just like a weird little part of America that you have to go through like to ball
Border crossings to get to
Yeah yeah
I'm very nervous yakety hear my voice cracked lips
I think there's a there's an instinct that arises in every Arab
Crossing a border
Also funny story the last time I crossed the Canadian border
I was
Three or four years old going into the American side of Niagara Falls
And the Border guide
LinkedIn was like
Is everyone in this car American
And it has like I'm Egyptian she's American and
He's American in the back and I don't know I'm French I'm being kidnapped
Oh my God there's there's some decent ROM around the Canadian border
I'm sorry if I was a little
Scamp camper van
Nice
Okay
Are you making any stops image
9 between but I'm spending the night in Vancouver tonight
Have a good time
Thanks man
Unscathed
Yeah he was a very nice
Border crossing guard
Did ask if I had been arrested which apparently is a thing like if you've been arrested you
Can't
You have to get like
Special permission to get into Canada if you have a criminal record in the states
It's another 20 or 30 minute drive to border number to welcome to Little America
I just crossed the
Border entry point
Scenic Loop
Gateway
That sounds like something I would do
I like seeing it
And I basically immediately to my right after I cross the border there's a place that receives
Packages open 24/7
Automated retriever
Vacuum Brew Coffee Parcel Services
It seems like there are a lot of places
And that was the theme throughout
The entire time in Point Roberts basically any shop
No matter what it was
Selling or what it did
They offered to accept
Packages for you
It's good to be back
To The Familiar land of America
The gases in gallons
Oh maybe it's not
Hello interesting
Facey measure the
Gas in liters
Here even in America
That's nuts
Wow leaders yeah leader
So what else did you find these little differences that decides the leaders revelation
Yeah there wasn't much it wasn't the most
Happening spot
Free wood
It's about like five square miles of population
Of
Latest US Census in 2010
In the summertime it can grow to about three or four times that
Because a lot of Canadian vacationers come in I went to the post office
Closed
Cuz it's Saturday
Is there a
School City
I had saw that
There is one primary school I believe it goes up to grade
Three or four
And then everyone who is older than that has to go
Across for international borders every school day
I'm to go to school in Blaine Washington
Yeah and I I grew up in a fairly brutal place with long school bus ride so I very much empathize and feel for you
Any point Roberts School
Kids umbrellas
Driving down the main drag
Biggest little store in Point Roberts
Eventually I ran into Fair
Restaurant
Easter egg
Call The Reef Tavern
Happy that right
Reef Tavern is calling to you that's that's what we call you I don't know if people know that
And I at The Reef Tavern I had a wonderful server name
And he was just the absolute
Swedish
Person and told me about how people from Canada go to that restaurant to get medium-rare burgers
Because apparently the health codes in Canada are a little more strict about how what's the
Perms
Basically in Canada
I'm so the real
Bud connoisseurs go to Point Roberts journalist from Oakland California
So cool that you ran into the other Oakland guy yeah
What are the odds
And that's not even the weirdest part
Let me play you a little
Little something
Get ready to have your mind blown Roman
The point
Purple dust
Yeah you guys have the same catchphrase
Oh my God yeah maybe
Yeah I know I don't understand how
The stars of the universe aligned in such a way but she's supposed to go there I know
It sounds like a lovely trap
Did you ever figure out why the gas was in liters
I didn't do much soup
Sleuthing but my guess is mainly to Market to Canadians
Yeah exactly
And I actually at the reef
Tavern I saw two very lovely Canadians named Jason and Lisa
They had come in that very day to pick up a Guitar Loop pedal
I'm from a seller on eBay who didn't want to ship it across the border
Perfect
Yeah here with super, who is doing the
Totally Tan
Looking into the town Lisa saw that the average visitor spends less than 20 minutes
Only 5% of visitors
Scotty longer than an hour
Anyway we've never been here before
Cool thank you so much I'll give you guys my life phone number
Making friends making friends and coincidentally I showed them
Where I was staying in
Vancouver and it was basically right next to them
And they invited me to drink wine and decorate their Christmas tree
I'm and it was
Just A really lovely
Evening that's so cool
Did you ever get confirmation about the witness protection thing
Well I guess I could neither
Confirm nor deny it
I actually reached out to Gerald short the founder of the witness protection program and
And he responded back and he says I have no information on Point Roberts
Washington
I wish I guess you can take to be like anything you want
That's awesome
Nice Adventure
In the name of the show thanks for thanks for the expense
No problem
X-ray
Yeah
Thanks
Goodnight Berg Lawrence Borat Peterlee for helping tree
Workout without story
With one more mini Story coming up next
With the king of the coda
Kurt Kolstad
After that
You
You inspired Xfinity to create internet that puts you in charge
Draw your movie marathons are better when you can stream them all night
Video chats for Grandpa's birthday it should be possible from anywhere in your house
And when you can pause wifi before bedtime
Putting your kids to sleep
Gets a little bit easier
So Xfinity reimagined Wi-Fi in created Xfinity X5
Because for the best Wi-Fi experience you need speed
Coverage and control
This is beyond Wi-Fi this is X5
Visit xfinity.com
To learn more
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Make yourself and make it stand out with Squarespace
Create a beautiful website to promote your business publish content sell products and much much more
High Moon Squarespace sites Roman mars.com to Showcase my work
His links to my TED talk into radiotopia
Steven has a sign-up
For the 99percentinvisible Weekly Newsletter
It was really easy to make mad at myself
Which is how I know that you'll have no problem making a Squarespace site to
Christmas Bayside, invisible for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Easy offer code invisible
Call for 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
So every year the end of the year in the beginning of the next year we do these many stories
And
The funny thing is is that the many stories were so popular
That we began doing important time in the history of a car
Almost every episode
Is it always some story that Kurt has that relates
Do the story we just told
But this one we never found a place that I really wanted to tell him
The perfect opportunity last year the Ford Motor Company
Play big news in Detroit
And they said they were going to buy and renovate
Michigan Central Station
It was like a big train stations were like Grand Central Terminal type train station
Central
Much taller in downtown Detroit
Yeah it's really visible when you're coming in on the highway it's in like one of the most visible
Tallest structures on the side of the Sun
Baste still in Detroit
Bought this
And suddenly there is all this news around the fact that they're going to come out do this big press conference
And explain to the city what their plan was for this old building that have been
Deserted for so long
Big press conference
Someone anonymously approach
The Ford Museum
With this
Surprising artifact
It was this big round antique clock that used to hang really prominently on one of the walls of the station
Let's face it
Train passengers needed to know the time
Show the clock
Puge
It's been gone for very long time
He couldn't believe it when a secret approach with me
To get that clock back
Somebody must have really loved it and loved the train station cuz I took very good care of it
So somebody stole this gigantic clock from the train station and then they returned it when they heard
That the transition can be renovated
Yeah it's pretty remarkable and we don't really know much about the person who returned the clock and then maybe they just took it
Get to try to help preserve it maybe they were in the original Thief
It's possible they bought it or found it on eBay or inherited it only really know for sure is that
They carefully wrapped it up
And then told the folks at the Ford Museum where to find it
Play me where to buy it like they left it somewhere and they like
Like along side of the side of a building their pictures of this you can see it like he just kind of wrapped it up in like
Strapped it in Fahrenheit
The clock but bring a couple guys and a Truck
Wow it's felt so inspired to give it back and then I think this is sort of a Civic icon
Carlos this stunning massive Bozarth structure
It was designed by the same Architects as Grand Central terminal in New York
Mdid originally was that it would be the Grand Central of the Midwest
Wood handle all this passenger and Freight traffic
And be kind of you know
Is landmark in the city
Sleepy puppies
It's filled with all these beautiful details.
Marble walls
Vaulted ceilings copper skylights
And it's cute
18 stories tall so there are restaurants and shops and below
And then office spaces above
And so but obviously it's on hard time swimming wrong with the Michigan Central Station
Well a lot of things arguably but
The rise of the car definitely help drive it out of business
We're driving out to the suburbs in the city itself
Anesthesia
Found Odysseus
At first the office has cleared out
And then the shops and restaurants that closed down and then finally in the 80s
The ticket booth shut down
And basically the whole place was
They just abandoned it was left empty at that point
Yeah and there was talk over the years
Tearing it down but it had this statuses
Is landmark
And that
Protected from Demolition
You know they came up with
Attempts to try to reuse this like
Ideas to turn into a police station or a Convention Center or even a casino
And none of those panned out
So the building just kind of
Insulting changing hands
And the owners
Before Ford finally did do some work on it like they drain the basement and they added some new windows and they put up a security fence
Obviously that must have happened after the clock was stolen
Yeah yeah they definitely were aware that things are disappearing from the building and I had to put a stop to that
Explore it but
Along the way hundreds of artifacts
So the clock is really just one piece
Is the bus there is lots of little things taken from the story about imagine over the years yeah a really large bees that took you to
But definitely one of many things and returning it actually started this kind of bigger movement
Because once Ford have the clock in hand
They were able to put out a call and say hey it looks my return this clock
If anybody else has stuff
Maybe you can bring it back too and you won't get in trouble no-questions-asked leave it on the side of a building
It works
Doesn't the people have now come forward to offer up old station artifact
Plaster medallions light fixtures
Yeah in Fort actually has a wishlist to they want back things like the ticket window grills elevator transom
And all other clocks
Spiritual years
And basically you know anything that
That is sort of considered critical to the historic character of the building right in what are the other planning to restore it as it was
Really plan to do with all these artifacts
Well something's will probably go back into the building and others will end up in local museums
Acai benefits
What is that
Silly things can be used to model copy
These two rights if you have one planet
A bunch of other ones
Renovated building
Well that makes sense
Who is the idea that this thing is going to be like a
Passenger
Train terminal again or is it something different for tired snowhead
Sir famous International design firm to help them build out
A new campus
The calling at the
Corktown campus
Could be the center for Ford to develop
Autonomous vehicles and other urban road related Technologies
Central area where they can do like actual on the road testing
And the station itself is going to be
The heart of this
Repopulate actually restaurants
Coin shops
And above their going to be offices but also condos now is that for
Some of the people at its partner organizations up into the
B spaces
Have you seen pictures of the artifacts and and the renovation at all
And it's sitting outside wrapped up
And there a lot of historic photos that cannot show what was their what's missing and
Ford's plan for what this building is going to look like when they're all done with this campus
Oh yeah
Fart sounds good alright thank you
99percentinvisible is Avery truffelman
Katie Mingle
Delaney Hall
Sharif Youssef
Emmett Fitzgerald
Sean real
Turn master
Joel Rosenberg Vivien Leigh Sophia Tucker and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
AM radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are founding member of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
We are supported by our sticker loving coin carrying listeners
Just like you
Play 99% invisible influence questions about the show on Facebook you can meet me at Roman Mars and the show at 9 and 9 p.m.
At work on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
The real 99ci HQ is that
Diane IPI
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com