99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
Producer Liza Jager recently did something that will become pretty common with the Next Generation
No kids she has to Grandma
The shower or tattoo
Can you just describe what the tattoo looks like
What was the tattoo
My grandma is very tiny
I think it's maybe 5/8 of an inch
And it looks like a little hand mirror
Definitely
It's a little circle
And then a line going off to the side of it
And then there's our cross over that line because
My blood type is O+
It's a tiny tattoo of her blood type
And just under her left arm
Okay so do you think that you can just walk me through step-by-step the whole process of getting the
Tattoo
Well
It was pretty it was pretty straightforward all of the kids whose parents have to sign the slip
Weren't taken marched out of our classroom
And down the hall
And yeah this was in school
This happened in Lake County Indiana
It was 1952 and my grandma was 16
And at the first station that you came to the
Your finger
And squeeze a little drop of blood onto a little card
And
Determine what your blood type was
And then you proceeded
Inside the Library
Inside the Library Carol discovered a few makeshift privacy Booth setup and inside each booth and in Ministry
Waiting with a tattoo gun ready to draw
Tiny old Plus
Or a b or a minus
On row upon row of waiting students
And always in the same place on the Torso
Just under the left arm
It was sort of like it an inkjet printer they took
Seconds
That was it
My grandmother and the other students said they were part of an experimental program called operation tat
It was administered by the county
And symbol
But also kind of terrifying
The goal of this
Was
How to make it
Easy to transfuse people who had been injured and who needed a blood transfusion
In case of an atom bomb
At the age of 16 Liza's grandmother's body was permanently marked in anticipation
Of a nuclear catastrophe
In 1952 the cold war was in.
And the government was busy developing civil defense strategy
Things ordinary citizens can do to help protect the home front
And in this case the thinking was that in the event of a Russian attack
The tattoos would make for quicker transfusions if children were incapacitated or did another blood type
They would also have what they were calling a walking blood bank
So instead of having to extract blood from people store it and keep it cool you just have a cohort
Potential donors
Walking around with their blood types
Written on their side
And if you needed
Some
A Plus store
A B minus or something you would just
Check all these people and they will see you found what you needed to the person that needs
Did the blood into an immediate transfusion
That you were just sort of like lift up somebody's Iris
Yeah yeah I've got one here this is what we need
For my grandma getting this tattoo was not a big deal
But I'm not now
It was a totally normal day
This was Indiana nobody gets all excited
Student loan you took your turn you went back to class and finished your mathematics or whatever else you were doing that
The time
What is Trivial is it may have seemed at the time
Carol's tattoo was more than a weird little cold war Oddity
It was one of the smallest and most personal manifestations
But much larger idea
That deeply influenced how the United States
Fought the Cold War
The concept
Survivability
Enough canned food
Shelters
Fearlessness
And sometimes
Tattoos
The American people would be able to survive an atomic attack
And that it was only logical to prepare for it
Today if we remember anything about the idea of survivability
It's probably this
It's the angle
Song that goes along with this grainy black-and-white film that was distributed by the federal civil defense Administration
It shows a little hand drawn Turtle decking under his shell
He's teaching kids to hide under their desk
During the bomb
People make fun of Duck and Cover a lot
It's considered the number one example of the kind of cold war-era propaganda
It seems
Totally ridiculous now
Kitschy and absurd
And sort of
Unimaginably naive
There a lot of jokes made and I think ridicule of Duck and Cover and even today people joke about it and
So you wouldn't be protected at all it wouldn't make any difference
Susan Linde is a historian of science at the University of Pennsylvania who studies the Cold War
And she says it when we make fun of the usefulness of a tactic like Duck and Cover
Thinking it couldn't ever work
We're actually just wrong
Those films
We're in fact based on the individual
Experiences of persons who had been exposed at Hiroshima and Nagasaki
In September of 1945
Just one month after the bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki
US military Center
A team of American doctors and geneticist to Japan to interview people who survived the attack
They were looking to understand both the short and long-term effects of radiation
That program would eventually be named the atomic bomb casualty Commission
Or the ABC
It would also prove to be highly controversial
Because the researchers weren't there to treat the survivors
They were there to study by
And only to study them
And
The reason to study the survivors
Was because they
They were surrogates for future American populations that would be subjected to exactly this kind of her
Urban attack
In a future nuclear war
It was American lives not Japanese they were hoping to say
Understand who would survive and who would not want an American city was hit with an atomic bomb
So when the American scientists and Physicians arrived in Hiroshima and Nagasaki what they wanted to
To do first was to
Track
Down how many survivors there were
They were looking at lots of thing
Cancer rates irregular pregnancies
Heart disease
Also
Critically
They asked every Survivor the interview
Where were you
At the moment of the detonation
How close have they been
Because before the ABC researchers arrived
The physicist who developed the bomb had assumed that they wouldn't be finding survivors anywhere close to Ground Zero
What they called the hypocenter
But what became
Clear
Is it some people could be very close but weren't exposed to significant levels of radiation because they work she'll
And
Within about three blocks of the hypocenter at Hiroshima there were people in a basement
In a fairly large
Concrete building
Who survived
And further out from the hypocenter researchers discovered that people who had taken cover even momentarily
Didn't just survive the immediate blast
They seem to be healthy
So there's a very famous story about Nagasaki
Which involved
Young boys who were
Swimming
And they were diving off a
Cliff
Into a lake
And
At the moment of detonation
Five of them were up
Standing up on the cliff and one of them had just hit the water and went under water
And all five who were on that Cliff where dead of leukemia by 1950
And the one who'd been underwater did not get
Anyone who had been behind even a tree
Was more likely to be alive
Five years later than someone who had been out in the open
And the logic of this is that
The key exposure to radiation
The most important moment
Last less than a second
It's not that there weren't other sources of radiation to be avoided
But What mattered most
Wisdom shielded at the moment
At the blast
And during the Blaster that followed it was the people who were standing up who were most likely to be
Be killed by shattering windows or falling debris
People who have been lying down when the blast wave hit
Much more often
Survive
The lesson seemed clear
In the event of an atomic bomb
If you can stay low
Stay shielded
In other words
If you duct
Uncovered
You might just be okay
American Civil Defense planners had already begun to wonder
Is Duck and Cover could help the population of a city survive a nuclear attack
What else might work
They were studying things like psychology and group dynamics and infrastructure
To see how society as a whole might hold up under a nuclear attack
And the civil defense policies that emerge from this research
All stressed in America
Could survive
But only if everyone
What does the authorities but everyday citizens did their part
What's the knowledge of the first atomic explosion to die.
Are chances for survival will be far better than those of the people of Hiroshima and Nagasaki
If we act on our knowledge
Underprepared
Like practicing proper Home Maintenance
I am going to show you how protective measures can help guard your home
I guess the heat effects of atomic explosion
Bandera Grill
Unknown
Warning is flag still on the civil defense network
Panamera Target City preparedness kits as concrete of test
Does possible
Short of actual bombing
Even learning how to deal with irradiated soil
More detailed information
Get your free copy of
Your livestock
Can survive
And in Lake County Indiana
They opted into a little pilot program to indicate their blood type
With a tattoo
All predicated on the belief that
In the face of an atomic attack
Person
And a society
Might just survive
And my grandma
She says
She was pretty much on board
You don't have any particular memories of your first impressions of
The program
Yeah they were all positive I thought this was a good idea
Cheetahs for one thing it was a time when more people still trust the government
Well you're just coming off this big war
Which
An impossibly complicated in all
Parts of the world
And yet somehow it had all come out all right
And so you felt as somebody was in charge that knew what he was doing
Plus the place you lived in Northern Indiana was a huge Railroad
And it was a possible Target
She didn't know for sure whether the tattoos would help her survive an attack
But she also genuinely believe that
They might
They're worth getting
Because if people were injured in would not be able to be assisted because you didn't know their blood type is
That's a no-brainer just go ahead and write it
Write it on them
Remember this was a voluntary
My grandmother signed up for
And so did most of her grade
She wanted to do her part
To be prepared
Because
Who knows who knows you know in all of the in the Japanese cities that were bombed there had to be a next day what do you do
The next day what do you do to save as many people as possible
The unthinkable thing
When it happens
You have to somehow react
Do it
When I really listen to my grandmother this made sense to me
It made sense that people believe that the risk of an attack was real
And believe there was a way to be at least somewhat prepared
The problem is that not long after she got that tattoo
The premise behind it
Survivability
Stop making sense
Even his children were learning to Duck and Cover and farmer for learning how to protect livestock from Fallout
The very idea of what a nuclear war might look like
Mike was changing
And with it
Are chances of survival
In 1950s
Two years before operation tattoo
The Soviet Union had a grand total of 5 nuclear warheads
By 1960
They would have / 1600
Many of them thermonuclear weapon
Exponentially more powerful than the bomb on Hiroshima and Nagasaki
Susan Lennie thinks that civil defense tactics like the school tattoo
They might still opened in the event of a limited engagement
In which perhaps only a small number of cities forehead
So
It's not a blood transfusion wouldn't have
Mattered at all
But in the event of a global thermonuclear war
Destroyed the entire infrastructure of the United States
You're not imagining a still functioning Society outside of that
You're imagining that there aren't there are no doctors
To be rushed to the scene nobody can come from a neighboring
City of these children going to do
What are they going to do
Still government agencies like the civil defense Administration
Continue to promote the idea that the country could survive a full-throated nuclear attack
In part because the gospel of survivability
However imaginary
Still serves other functions
Sure imaginary things matter a lot especially in propaganda
Because
A lot of military and civil defense planners
They didn't just worried there would be a war
They were convinced
Warwick
Department of Defense the president
Congress
Reach the conclusion
That developing and stockpiling ever-larger ever more powerful nuclear weapons
Was absolutely crucial
To the security and the future
Survival
Of the United States
Which is why by 1960
The same year the Soviet nuclear Arsenal top 1600 Warheads
The United States
Had more than 18000
Those weapons were controversial
Almost from the beginning
In one week in June demonstrations took place in more than a dozen countries and 250 locations around
United States
There were always protest within 24 hours of the dropping of the bomb there were critics all over the world saying
Find that the United States should not have used
If this keeps up
Then where does it stop
Do we live under the Sword of Damocles forever
And there were theologians who said this is an immoral form of warfare What's Happening Here
Play some moral and that we are in faith must resist
And that made the logic of survivability
Doubly useful
Things like lessons in school and evacuation drills
And tattoos
Is increasing the acceptability of nuclear weapons
And increasing public belief in the idea that even if a nuclear war came
There would be strategies that would permit
Those who were properly prepared
To survive
And did it work
Like do people feel less
Scared
I think that
Some people did maybe most people
Because when you look at surveys of people in the 50s about nuclear weapons
People
Believe that they're necessary
And if your
If you believe it's necessary then you have to believe that it's also
Practical but it's not insane
You have to believe it's not insane
Fear that my grandma got her tattoo
15 thousand other Lake County residents also got their blood type check
Do the typing program
Finger prick
Kappa Blood on the card
Two-thirds of those people opted for a tattoo
But operation tat type didn't go far outside Lake County
Despite all the survivability fervor
It never made it beyond the pilot program
When I talked to my grandma though I can kind of hear it
The thing when he talks about
About the psychological impact of programs like
Did getting a tattoo
Make you feel safer
Yes I guess so
I thought that I had done
The thing that was available to do to help in case of a
A total disaster
I thought I had done the right thing
But maybe more importantly it was just doing something that made her feel better it was hard to
To imagine the bigger picture I didn't envision myself
Elf lying there in a doctor's coming up and throwing up my arm and saying aha
Just use this child with O+ blood
I never played that all out
She said she was way too busy
She was talking with her friends about boys or what they were going to do over the weekend
Daily life
The life she was living
Was much more attractive
Otherwise would go crazy if we had to deal
Intensively with all of these terrible threats
What's a certain amount of stuff
I can't think about that you just got to keep going and do other things
I think that's that's one of the great capacities we have
Today the legacy of survivability is hidden behind a new series of titles acronyms
And other obfuscating symbols
B tomic bomb casualty commission which study the effects of the atomic bomb in Hiroshima and Nagasaki
Who became the radiation effects Research Foundation
A joint american-japanese venture has continued to study the long-term effects on the survivors a bomb in there
Children nearly 75 years later
The federal civil defense Administration after several name changes
Was combined with various other agencies to form FEMA in 1978
It strategies have been adapted to deal with hurricanes or earthquakes
And yes
Possible nuclear attacks
And then there's the tiny Legacy of survivability Inked on the Torso of Carol fischler
Just under her left arm
Faded tattoo
It says o positive
But looks like a picture
The little hand mirror
Social Links professors Tracy Davis and Ann lauman at Northwestern University whose voices we did not get to him
Include but Who provided us with invaluable information during our research for the story
Up next
Shall we play a game
Joe Rosenberg and I play global thermonuclear war
Play with us
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
Okay so Roman do you remember the movie WarGames absolutely
Big deal when I was a kid
Oh yeah and I didn't and it's aged as you decided it's aged incredibly well
For those
Don't know it or don't remember it
Classic movies from the 80s
Where a teenager somehow single-handedly takes on the military and died
Compact genre and obviously
Stranger things has
A lot to it
Anyways in this case the teenager is played by a young Matthew
Free thirst
Accident
Quasi sentient computer Mainframe that runs NORAD
And once he's in this computer starts talking to him and it says free games would you like to play a game
List of stimulated
Dillard's the computer lights to play pops up and one of them is called global thermonuclear war
Wright brothers character is he a teenager he's like hell yes I want to play
But the computer tries to talk him out of it and it's like wouldn't you brother
And Broderick is like no
Thermonuclear war
And suddenly Broderick is present with this game map the world is laid out before him
You can start dropping bombs on cities
And see what happens
Intercourse things arriving there at hilarity ensues I won't spoil the movie for anyone
But when I first
Star War games when I was all about Anna 10 years old
I kept thinking man
Why can't I play a game called global thermonuclear war
Sounded
Well here's the thing
In doing some of the research for this story
26 years later
Kinda sorta founded
If this
Online simulator it's called
In which you can sing like the detonation of the nuclear weapon of your choice
At any spot in the club
You can see what
I'll get to it right out what's the address I need
Just Google in nukemap
Alex Miller
Here we go
Oh yeah
Drag the marker wherever you want in like at the Target or you can like tripe reset
Rights are used for statues which city that you'd like to destroy
I? Anywhere but there's
Do you have a preference to San Francisco
Well you know
I think it's only fair
I actually did the exact same thing as far as I can tell everyone that show this to like
They always immediately either nuke themselves
For New York
What will do Oakland
Enter the preset of a type of
Kiloton bomb
You can try a lot of different weapons real life
Choose from the actual usms Arsenal you can choose
Really tiny unicorn confusion weapons
Canon
Like a largest ever detonated
Hydrogen monster
Russian deli
Which Wich do you want
A listing of
Let's go for the big one so this is the Tsar Bomba largest USSR bomb tested at 50 Megaton
Guy looks like that
Okay basic options height of birth
Airburst or Surface
Cerberus
Explodes
About the city of Sandpoint
And I say Chozen airburst
50 megatons
Battery dropped pretty much right on Market Street
It's on 21st between Guerrero and
Not that any of this is going to matter cuz it's a
Beautiful red button it says detonate
Pronounce
Totaling up the estimated fatalities
At 1.5 million people
It has this inner blast radius that's all red
Right in the matter but radius that reaches all the way to Antioch
And then a
I guess this is like
Radio app
A cloud that reaches wellpath Sacramento
Yeah and
And actually with these big
You can see
That outer red ring is I believe like
Third degree
Yeah chocolate is pretty much
Going to take out the entire Bay Area
Sounds like what you expected
This is what we think of nuclear war
Look like
Total devastation
You don't even need to be
Close
People in the Central Valley might be okay but we here in Oakland right across the bay from SF
We're definitely
But we're actually valuable
Is if you ship things up just a bit
So I might run the exact same simulator
But this time I want you to choose the bomb called
Batman this was the bomb the United States drop
This is 20kg
There we go
All right
Okay
San Francisco is in trouble still
Are you talking about
70000 estimated
Fatalities
And
The
The air blast radius
It really reaches
You know only the 19th Avenue to the sunset
That's what I force you to that that's what kind of shocked me either original bombs that we think of Izzy's
Destiny Wednesday are devastating
Compared
Hydrogen weapon
Kind of shocking me
And he even like if you calculate like the Shockwave that would like break windows
That Shockwave
Doesn't even reach out
It doesn't even reach
Egyptian cuz what you what you start to realize if he's smaller
Boulder weather
Dance like a Russian
Nagasaki
They take out this big chunk from the center of a
It's just the shock everything outside the chunk
Is convent
We need to
What is an contacts in point out that in terms of
This is still an incredible catastrophe minimize
Those bombs were horrible and they killed a lot of people
But when you see
What some of the largest nuclear weapons the potential of them and
These smaller ones you realize that
This logic of survivability
It really isn't.
Right right so yeah and it's really
Helps demonstrate
This thing I always her just like we say in the story
Hydrogen nuclear weapons
Exponentially more powerful than conventional
But that doesn't really mean anything to me I was like hydrogen conventional whatever they're all bad
But in reality no
There is almost existential differ
Any amount of Destruction
Andaz
Life is grandmother puts it whether there's going to be a next
Deorro
Right
Consequences for how we think about
Nuclear threats
Because people get real fatalistic about the bomb they say things like what could you do there's nothing to do it's not
Not something I can deal with
It's not something I can do
So this is life Creator Alex
Sweater stain
The professor nuclear history
Stevens Institute of Technology
And also part of a project called Reinventing sibbald
He says
One reason he built the nuke map
Is that we're still basically holding on to this late
Cold War model assume you clear War at this
Mobile app
Why bother thinking about it cuz if it happens
We're all Dad it's like getting a rare disease
Why worry
And that becomes the
The excuse to
Totally check
And it's not just checking out of
If something happened to them but it's checking out for it being like a national policy
Checking out on treaties
Checking out on
You know what the president allowed to do that kind of thing
And I really like people not to check out and I think the best
Way to do it
Is to get them to think about this more realistically
Until what is realistic in the sky
What's not particularly like was not real
In the current geopolitical climate
Is Russia bigger than China obliterating United States and half the world
Thousands of
Even though that's you know the scenario that most people
Like to grab it
They have a hard time shifting into none of them were talking about
Two or three detonations from North Korea
Nation is not going to be dead and then if you do that it is a little stressful then maybe it should be right
Because you you suddenly see it like oh
We should have a plan
And this is where nukemap comes in
Does it really helps convey the
Proper size
Cuz if you select for you know a North Korean side
That is one of the APA
You'll see it is larger than the Hiroshima bomb
Marco's Rothman terms
Kind of damage it does
Compared to these large
Okay
So weird
Feeling that there will be a neck
Hence the need for a plan
That totally makes sense so given this
What is
Well the big thing in Alex's mind
Now that we are once again presented with the possibility of these Limited
Nuclear scenarios
We as a culture need to relearn civil defense
Is that there are civil defense tactics you can find on the FEMA website like right now
In case of a nuclear attack
Alex's work
With the Reinventing civil defense project is in part about how
We could maybe actively disseminate this information
In a way that everyday people won't look askance at it either
Is Big Brother
Normalizing you
If he thinks
The feasible fantastic
And so what are the big things he'd like to
Is
Either hang of it in a very crude way this way if you're really too close to the weapon the nothing you do is going to matter and it's going to be over very fast
If you're really far away from the weapon you're going to say what was that no matter what you do because you're outside
Picture of an in-between range
Hours at work
Ducking and covering in some situations
Is
Exactly the right thing to do
And this is for all the reasons that were laid out in the main
Which is avoiding direct exposure to radiation and heat protecting yourself
Structural damage and shattering Windows which you can see on these new maps North Korean size weapon
Even if you're relatively close to the epicenter you're much more likely to be in the zone of the Shockwave
Most likely not going to be in the all-consuming
Maybe the biggest takeaway from the nukemap simulator is what
Fallout
Because in this scenario where we survive from
Over here in our
Cushy confines vocalist
Actually we're not out of the
Prevailing winds come this way so we definitely have to deal with
In fact that's what
Presents the most danger to the most people in Houston area
The smaller one
I'll just a few weeks I'll be out of this feature
Which is kind of like Google Street View you can drop this little marker
Anywhere on the map and tell it whether you're indoors or Outdoors or
Basement
Basically tell you
How okay
Because you can see very starkly
Oh I'm stuck on the freeway
I mean absorbance of this much radiation in this case
However if I had just stayed at home
Then I cut it down to this much and if I go into a basement or someplace bigger while it's like basically nothing at all
You should run or shelter in place which is
Important
Right and you should almost
Always shelter-in-place tagline is get inside stains
Cuz even just being inside house
House will likely
Please save your life
But in this case it turns out there are limits
What kind of advice
However well backed up by data and
Nukemap
Human beings are willing to except
That's pretty when it comes to advice
Communication
And in fact
My colleagues asked people
They actually told them what the right thing to do is and then ask them what they would do in a lot of them are like I go get my kids
If there was a bomb went off or a fire happens when it's like so much better for kids just stay in school where they are
Am I impulsive
Totally true
Sadie you just ignore this and
Well I mean I'd rather them let them than me
That's for sure
But it would be really hard to fight the impulse to not run to them no matter what I knew in terms of Common Sense
I'd like to believe that I
Overcome that
Maternal instinct
Maybe once
But anyway
Latin for everyone the next time a computer program like math
Asked you if you want to play global thermonuclear war you should say yes
Absolutely nuke yourself
And it's actually the reasonable thing to do play at the simulation
Thank you
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Liza Jaeger in edit
Did by Joe Rosenberg
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer coldstat is the digital director
Russell team is senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery
Edmund Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are protected 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are proud member of radiotopia from PRX
Collection of fiercely independent and fascinating podcast
Fun Mall
A radiotopia
Ask.fm
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can do to me at Roman Mars and a show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Ratatouille
But you're always welcome to shelter a tarp
And 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com