99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There are a lot of beautiful places in California
Downtown Oakland for example
But Santa Barbara
Is like
Stupid beautiful
Yeah it's like
Economically picturesque California seeing here
A few months back we sent producer Emmett Fitzgerald down to Santa Barbara on a really taxing reporting assignment
Dallas
Beautiful sailboats
Pelicans
Two dolphins
Songs beginning with that
Through rough life
Here comes a wave
F clef
And it really put himself In Harm's Way for the story
But if you look out at the ocean from this Scenic spot
You'll see something else
Something
A little less
Conventionally attractive
Right on the horizon line
That one too
Three four
Big offshore oil platforms
They look like
Buildings out there floating in the water
Giant battleships or something
The prettiest people here
Don't love them
Those oil platforms off Santa Barbara are at the center of a complicated debate going on right now within the environmental community
About the relationship between nature and human infrastructure
Although they have been a source of controversy since they first went in the water back in the 1950s and 60s
I came to Santa Barbara in 1966
This is Roderick Nash
Environmental historian who moved to Santa Barbara from New Hampshire to take a job in history department at UCSB
And it didn't take him long to fall in love with his new home
I began to realize what
People have told me they said
Santa Barbara's like the American Riviera
It's kind of a paradise
The land of Endless Summer
But at the time he says there was a sense that this Coastal Paradise
Sad lucrative tourist economy
Was under threat
Massive oil rig
It's going up all throughout the Santa Barbara Channel
They were cries
From the people Santa Barbara saying
Not so fast let's let's think about the consequence
We look out at the channel this is the million dollar view this is this is what
How the economy
And the culture of Santa Barbara is about
And now suddenly but pretty
Offshore oil rig shop
Up there and we're not so sure that we're protected from
Spills
But at the time there wasn't a whole lot anyone could do
EPA didn't exist yet
Dor no major environmental regulations in place
And so the oil platform
Went in and they operated without any major spills
Until January 28th 1969
I was working on the
Fourth
Floor of the El Paseo building that Overlook the ocean
This is Bud bottoms
Local artists who actually passed away last year this audio is more video interview the bottoms did a few years back
Back where you describe getting a phone call from a friend who had flown into Santa Barbara earlier that day
He was flying over the channel this particular day
They saw a big blowout
Either there's oil
From Eddie V
Platform by crazy
The whole house. Here is black
Good morning
Union oil the owner of the platform in question had failed to build a large enough protective casing for one of its well
Loyal which was under immense pressure
Forced its way around the well and erupted to the ocean floor
1000 gallons of crude were pouring into the ocean every hour
Rodger Nash heard about the spill that same day
But he said it took a little while for the scale of the disaster to really set in
I can remember walking down to the beach
No change
No change and then I walk down to the beach one day
And it was a black tide there was oil
And
Suddenly
The postcard
Beaches
Santa Barbara
We're black
Crude oil floats on top of water
Until this bill was particularly deadly for Sebring
Birds that dive into the water to catch fish
You go in and your feathers are covered with oil and you can't fly
Can you fly
Shop help
Play on the beach
It was an apocalyptic
Although Nash has the most uncanny thing may have been the
Sound
The waves
We're very quiet
Because they were loyal
They had sort of a mushy sound
Because what was really breaking was
2-3 inches of oil on top of the water
We stood there and cried
I hear grown men and women
Sitting there crying because the beach was half their life
We thought it was all over for us
But as
Sad as the 1969 spill was
Bud bottoms was
Mostly just
Furious
I got so angry
I just screamed out
We got to get oil out
Heber call screaming get oil.out at work
Panda by boss
The next off and he said
Hey get oil.out Google
Good name
And so Google spelled gooo!
Name of a new environmental organization that has helped launch in Santa Barbara
And whose goal was simple
Stop all Drilling and eventually
Ghettos platform
Can we do you know it cuz the stopped oil drilling in our in our
Beautiful pristine Nostrand Santa Barbara
Google held rallies and marches
They organized a human blockade to prevent oil trucks
Sperm reaching the harbor
And there were more creative forms of protest
We said off bottles of little bottles of oil
Bar Harbor
Does every Harry
Government official there was
II see for themselves what we were dealing with
The oil spill quickly became an international news
In part because of the timer
This is the very beginning of the modern environmental move
Rachel Carson's Landmark book Silent Spring it come out to the few years
Before
The Apollo 8 spacecraft
What's orbiting the Moon
Sending back photos of the Earth
Looking like a blue green marble in the empty desert
Space
The first time people were beginning to understand that the planet was small
Fragile
And the humans were doing a great deal of damage
So all those images
Soil drench seabirds dying are beautiful California beaches
They went around the world
People looked at these birds
I thought this is Santa Barbara
The Spill was a galvanizing event for environmentalist
The first anniversary activist rally in Santa Barbara
And some of them went on to organize the first Earth
Saying
This is why we need it this is why we needed
I'll because of something like the Santa Barbara oil spill
The oil spill inspired Roderick Nash to start one of the country's first
Environmental Studies program
UC Santa Barbara
It also fueled debate in Congress and help rally support for some of the most important environmental bills in US history
The 1969 National Environmental Policy Act
Was followed by the Clean Air Act in 1970
The Clean Water Act in 1972
Any Endangered Species Act in 1973
Destiny with you
Increasingly as you look back at it
From now
50 years
You look back at it
You can really say
Holy cow
There was a lot of change
And the Santa Barbara
Oil spill had a lot to do with that change
The Spill catalyze a national movement
But there was still the question of the platforms themselves
Local opposition put a stop to most new oil exploration off California
The existing oil rigs have continued to operate per decade
Today many of those old platforms are reaching the end of their productive lifetime
And based on the original lease agreements
They should be decommissioned
And removed from the water
Carla Frisk is on the board of Goo it's
Still around
And she can't wait for the oil companies to be
Begone
Get to the interlace and be done
A Ninja Turtle
Equipment and go away
Get oil out
If you will
Yeah the name
Felt it all really yeah you don't have any doubts about what the organization's about right off the bat
Brisk wants the oil companies to return the Santa Barbara channel to the way it was before the platforms went in the water
A pristine ocean environment without any giant artificial structures
You go down there and that you would never know that they were there
Really what it should be
You know when you have come to the ocean
Petrified ocean
That's simple goal
The one that members of Goo have been fighting for
It would seem like it's time has finally come
What is one little hitch
These platforms
Are the most
Productive
Habitats
In the world ocean
Anywhere in the world
This is Milton love
I'm a research biologist
At the Marine Science Institute University of California Santa Barbara
Love is author of
Classic science books like
This is really the title
Probably more than you want to know about the fishes
Pacific Coast
And also the sequel
Certainly more than you want to know
About the fishes of the
Pacific Coast
A postmodern
Experience
It's a 650 page home full of fish facts historical anecdotes
And some of his original
Poetry
According to love it weighs 5 point
4 pound
It's actually a dangerous weapon in the wrong hands
And it feels cliche to say that a scientist just really loves
What's the thing that they study
But it must be sad
Milton love
Mustache
I have a two tattoos of fish
And one is available
How Cod which is a rock
But the other one is of a deep-water angler fish
Is it
Edison Place can I see it
Well hold on a sec
Take my shirt off
Without thinking twice he pulls off his shirt to reveal
Updating shoulder tattoo
If this big female angler fish with a tiny little male fish latched onto her side
So there
There is the
Female
And that little nubby thing
That's a bet
It's the real thing
Love grew up fishing on the beaches and Piers of Santa Monica
Do you study biology at UCSB
And eventually ended up back at his alma mater where he started up his own research lab
The love lab
But in the labs early days he had a really hard time getting grants to fund his fish
And
In 1995 I was at a
At a low point there was no question
I had no fun
But just when things were at their bleak
Love got an unexpected phone call
Iamsymphony says this is Lyman thorsteinson
I'm from the national biological survey
Which was a government program in the 90s
That aim to catalog and describe ecosystems throughout the country
And I swear to God this way
He said
If you had money
For research
What would you
What would you do
What does knockout signs usually works
Nobody
Nobody calls
And says I have money
It's the other way around it's a very dickensian kind of thing it's like you're the little bigger boy you come over and you go like
Pizza
Could I have $100,000 set please
Love thought about how to answer this
Surprise question
On something that have been nagging him since he first came to Santa Barbara
Back in his 20s love you to collect fish for local Aquarium
And one day he and his fishing partner took their little Boston Whaler out to the oil platforms
And started fishing around them
There is like fish up the wazoo
And
We could have filled up the
Aquarium with all the fish week
Ever since then he had wondered what was going on down
Who's this dude like
Offering me money and I said well
I'm really interested in these oil platform
Forms off here
Their large structures I'd like to know
The role that they play as habitat
4 fishes and he said oh that sounds
Interesting
And so funding in hand Milton love got a team together
Rented a small submarine
And began to study the Platte
The first
Dive I made in
In the submersible
Was it platform Hidalgo which is located
Just barely in
Central Calif
Written about
If you don't water he took the submersible all the way to the bottom
The pylons reach the seabed
I was like blown away I didn't actually know what
Expect
And there was a lot of fish
In particular schools of adult rockfish
Were swirling around the base of the plateau
And as he started making his way up the structure he saw a lot of smaller juvenile
And we're talking
Hundreds of
Thousands of these young fish
Bent the metal itself was
Covered with
Colorful invertebrates
Cstars muscle sponges
And these little crabs walking all over the struts
Yeah I'm ever coming back on Deck to the research vessel on
The hatch pops
Everybody's
You know all the lab is there and then
Crew the boats there and they're waiting for me to say something I said
Yeah this was like
I said this
Amazing
Place
That platform dive was the first of many that Milton love and the other scientists that the love lab would do over the next
15 years
Love remembers one dive in French
Particular from this.
Around a platform called
Gilda
One of his colleagues went down first
And when she came back up
She said
Basically
That was unbelievable
The scientists always videotape these Dives
Show people who didn't believe them
And so she played them the recording right there on the boat
She put it in there and we're going like oh my God
That's the most fish we've ever seen
Around the platform
Not every trip down with like that
All platforms
Different love status
Some don't have a lot of
It's always easier to hear
But often love found that these oil platforms were like a little Oasis of marine life
The ocean is a big empty place
An animal
Tend to concentrate
Around
Stuff
The only reason they're there is they like to hang out with
What's stuff
Many invertebrates need a physical object
The latch on
Rockfish want to hide in nooks and
Crannies
Just be around anything with a little structure
They don't care what the
Structures made out of
Pipe
NBA platform it can be a tiring
Iraq
Oil platforms are particularly popular structures with the fishes
Because they have a lot of surface area and complexity
And they extend hundreds of feet through the water column like a
Marine skyscraper
Rockfish live at different depths
Throughout their life cycle
Oil platform the sink
Affordable home
Profession of all ages
Younger fish tend to live
Higher up the platform
Time After Time Love was Finding
Lots of fun
There were so many
I started thinking like
What is this mean
Biologic
Like okay so we're seeing a lot of juvenile fish
But how important are these platforms really in terms of the overall ecosystem
The bottom of that love and his team looked at one particular species of rockfish
Boccaccio
Yeah I got a big mouth that's what it means
Italian boccaccio
Means big mouth
The boccaccio are heavily fished around Santa Barbara
Around this time the stock was so depleted
Did the government close the fishery
But would love to the survey of seven different oil platforms
Victor Solis baby book got you and then we were talking
A lot of
About 450 thousand
Put that number in context love called up a scientist
The national Marine
Fisheries service
Who is responsible for counting all the boccaccio on the bus
Coast
Name is Alex
So I said Alex
We estimated that
There were 450000
Baby boccaccio
At the 7 plus
Is that important
Cuz you don't like maybe it's not
I didn't know
So he had a model
Betty Hughes
So he plugged it in and he came back
Couple weeks later and he said
Well
That's 20%
Cabal the baby will catch you on the entire Passage
Rapid7 platform
And babies are particularly important
To rebuilding the overall population
I'm going like
You know what that seems like those platforms
Important
For rebuilding
That particular
Species
Still as Love's results were coming in
A lot of people were skeptical
Like maybe the rigs were just luring fish away from natural habitat
Lymphostatic
Totally valid
Concerned
Does happen
A lot of artists
But after years of studying these oil platforms details
Continent that at least for some species
Betta fish
What platforms are giving the overall population of boost
Preponderance of evidence
Is that for
8 or 10 or maybe 12 species of rocks
Fish
There are more of them in California
Because of all these platforms
Then would be here if the platforms
You're not here
And some scientist would go even further
A few years ago someone else tried to calculate just how biologically productive the platforms were
The most productive habitats are places like rainforest
Coral reef
But when the scientist ran the numbers
He found
That these platforms are the most productive
Habitats
In the world ocean
Anywhere
Now we we should take that with a grain of salt
Tons of habitats that scientists haven't
Studied in this way
But the point is
These are fully functioning
They contain all the animals
That you would expect
Tusayan
A myriad of Nach
Which banks
The question
Is it in the interests of the people of California
To blow up
A fully functioning rave
And destroy it
In 2010
The California legislature decided it was
Any past ad to 503
A bill known as rigs to reefs
Oil companies
To leave an oil platform in place
If it could be shown to have a net benefit
On the marine environment
The oil companies would still need to plug the wells and Lop off the top
The platforms that boats could travel over it
But they would be allowed to leave some of the structure in place
So far though
No one is made use of this pill
And the future of California's Offshore platforms is still very much up in the air
A lot of environmentalists aren't sold on the idea of turning Riggs
Winter wreaths
They have concerns about liability
Potential for future leaks
The original lease agreements specify that the platform's orbit
Fully removed when the oil ran out
There wasn't a loophole that said they could stay if they turned into beautiful fish habitat
To me it's breaking a promise
This is Carla Frisk again
From Goodwill promise was
These would go away
And now they don't want them to go away
Tell
Community don't worry we're going to clean up our garbage after we're gone and then
And even if you love fish and I really do love fish
Her frustration is understandable
Environmental activist in Santa Barbara have had to deal with oil in their backyard for the last 50 years
In 2015 an oil pipeline a few miles north of Santa Barbara started leaking right into the ocean
It was a horrible reminder of the 69 spill and the dangers of living with oil in
Structure
And now the oil companies are saying hey these giant structures in the ocean that cause you all these problems
They're actually good for the environment look at the research their habitat
It's not
Carla is not convinced the oil executive support rigs to reefs because of their concern for the rockfish
My feeling is that they're motivated by saving money
Save a whole lot of money by not pulling nose out
The rig
Is off Santa Barbara or massive
Infrastructure
Some of the largest oil Platforms in the world
Philippe removing them would be extremely
Difficult and avoiding those costs could save the oil companies
Millions of dollars
Under the 2010 rigs to reefs spell those savings will be
Split with a state
What environmental groups don't love signing off on a policy that feels like a handout
Did the oil in this
Especially because environmental groups are currently fighting
New offshore oil development
The Trump Administration is indicated that they want to issue new offshore oil and gas leases off California
California has resisted the plan but environmental groups worry that
If the cost of decommissioning go down and the oil companies can argue that these structures are actually good for wildlife
They could have an easier time building new oil platforms
Do offshore oil drilling is the worst case scenario that all
Not just
Because of the risk of future spills
Because if you want to stop the worst impacts of climate change we're going to have to start leaving fossil fuels in the ground
Milton love agrees that climate change is one of the biggest threats to the world's oceans
And so I asked him
What he thinks about the fact
But the oil industry
Probably likes his research
I have tended to avoid dealing
With the oil industry to the extent I can but obviously they read my
My papers
They like it
I guess I mean it
CEO comment
Go like this is great stuff
I love your stuff
Thank you thank you thank I'm not ready
But his findings have definitely helped oil companies make their argument
Stent
That
My findings
Bolster
The oil companies
Dispositions
That's just what happens with facts
The facts
Of Milton loves research don't mean that oil infrastructure is
Is good for wildlife
That usually is
I just mean that
A few instances off the southern California coast
Oil platforms have become useful habitat
For a few different species
A fish
He's not in favor of building new offshore oil platform
Or even building lots of new artificial reefs
But in this situation
The artificial Reef
Is already there
My view is once you put something in the ocean and it becomes
Habitat for animals
I don't think you should pull it out
Cuz like why should we punish those animals just cuz they have The Misfortune of
Settling out on a piece of Steel rather than on the rock
After all Rockfish are just looking for a little structure in LA
They don't care if it's a rocky outcrop
Worship rack
Orion oil pump
Social things to Kristen Hislop of the environmental defense center who also spoke to us for this
And also a big thank you
Did Janet Bridgers
From Earth alert
Kindly letting us use audio from her interview
Bed bug bombs
Coming up
Taking what we learn from offshore oil platforms
In applying it
Offshore wind farms
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sand
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
Think about doing
Astoria
Like this
We talked about The Accidental benefits
Of human putting stuff in the ocean
Is that you could
Possibly Come Away with the idea that
This isn't necessarily a good thing all the time that we should just
Dumb stuff in the ocean
Report that piece
To address this issue
Head on
A little nervous
About
With the peace you know you could kind of
Draw the wrong conclusion of like take the conclusion of
The peace like
It too far
Yeah if you start to think
A fish like
Together around
Stuff then let's just
What are the water and the crazy thing is
We have done this
We have built artificial reefs
A lot in the past and made a people have
Thrown all kinds of things into the ocean thinking that
This is going to be beneficial there has been
Old washing machine
Subway cars
They even sunk in Old aircraft carrier once off the Florida Panhandle
Became known as the
The great carrier Reef
Clever
And the results are mixed often will you put
Structure into the water it does attract fish
Support these
Sorts of projects artificial reefing are far fisherman because concentrates all the fish in one place
Play some music to catch and so an argument against artificial reefs is that
They lead to Arkin exacerbate
Overfishing
And that's totally a real concern is also one of the more egregious examples of a misguided
Artificial reefing attempt
That I came across
What happened in the 1970s were people dumped half a million
Tires automobile tires into the ocean off Fort Lauderdale
Ostensibly you know in the NFL to create
An artificial Reef
That seems like the worst possible substrate
To build a wreath upon
Completely and it was an abject failure it's like a 30-year
30 acre Dead Zone around there now it end and not only that but like
Delta Tires Leach stuff that was detrimental to a natural coral reef fish having come through the worst
Case scenario of taking this idea and going
Too far with it
So the lesson is that we should not dress till the ocean with our stuff
Absolutely not I do not take that weapon away from the store anyway
But we are going to put cumin in
The structure into the ocean
As humans were going to put things out in the marine environment we're building
Breakwater's around Harbors we're building bridges were building
A lot of oil platforms moving the future probably going to be building a lot of renewable energy
Twin platform for offshore
Wind
So this is Jeremy
Place he's a professor of marine biology at Cal Poly Pomona
That ran the numbers and Quantified how biologically productive the California oil rigs are if you remember that from the story
And Jeremy's
Argument is basically that you know with all of this infrastructure we should be thinking about
The impact it will have
On the marine environment and seeing if there are ways that we could design the structure before it goes in the wall
Water so that it has a chance
To become
Beneficial habit
So in the oil platform Astoria it was at
Total accent
Peking rapes but he saying that maybe
We can actually do some of this intentionally or maybe even do it better
With some intent
Think about how we could design human infrastructure
To maximize its habitat
Annie's particularly focus on the question of offshore wind
Which to me is this release date Apple because
Unlike oil platforms which are
Problematic when it comes to climate change offshore wind
Is this climate solution in this potentially
Important kind of solution out
Yeah we know that we're going to need to build a lot of these structures
The coming decades like if we want to avoid the worst case scenarios when I
Comes the
Climate change we're going to need some
Offshore wind
On and hopefully now these Offshore platforms
Start can be put into designing them and then once they're put out there we can study them and understand
You know the positive and negative that's going on and try to revise those overtime and
I'm and do the best we can
I would all the stuff for putting out into the marine environment
So is this happening anywhere yet
Does anyone
Actually designing wind platforms
With biological life
Priority
Yeah we're kind of at the beginning of this
But the place right now in the world with the most offshore wind is the North Sea in Europe
And
There are a lot of wind turbines there that are just
They're basically just attached to the seabed by a
Single pole
Doesn't have a lot of complexity that structure and one of the things that's really
Great about
Offshore oil platforms as if they've got some of that structural complexity that fish
Penta light show in the North
See one thing that people are doing is starting to think about like how can we add a little bit of structural complexity
2DS
Wind turbine
And you're up in the North Sea they're doing things to increase the complexity on a down at the base.
There's opportunities to create more complex habitats surrounding it with
Cory rocker
Different structures
To try to improve the habitat for fish living down there but you know off California that situation is actually really
Difference the ocean floor is as you go through out to sea on California drops off a really quickly and gets a really.
And so
Offshore wind turbines in California if they do come
Are actually going to need to be designed to
Float
There's a whole set of new challenges in terms of deploying
Is floating structures but a lot of them
Artist going to be underwater
Is very similar
Sort of structure to the top part
Underwater of these offshore oil platforms
Kind of where we're at right now is trying to
Studied official living on these offshore oil platform
It's kind of a proxy what you would expect
The fish are going to experience living off these floating wind platforms
So Jeremy is hoping that his research can inform the design of the structures if and when offshore wind becomes
Cereality
In California but you know
He's at he's a marine biologist is obviously focused on fish
There are
Huge engineering challenges and end design challenges with offshore wind and solar
MultiCare about
Fish is not necessary is not necessarily be the easiest
I think the
The economic and Engineering challenges
Are pretty great
With these structures
So
Initially at least it's probably hard to come in and say well then let's think about how he's going to be good for the fish
Ultimately that I think that's what we should be doing
At the end of the day we still we shouldn't get
Too carried away with these with these ideas or
Think that we can design perfect habitats and at the expense of natural ones I think that you know
Anytime a piece of infrastructure into the water it's going to be
Disruptive on some level and then that's always that's always true and we always need to be thinking about how to mitigate
The negative impacts that a big
Piece of human infrastructure is going to have it with offshore wind
Nothing that you are obviously very concerned about is
Is seabird
Buy the whole other set of of design challenges you how do you
How do you build these structures in a way where
They don't disrupt
Seabird habitat
But I think
The first step is like how do we mitigate
Disruption and damage and then you can start thinking about what are ways in which we could
Maybe actually have
Small benefits
Right
Designed to never replace
The concept of conservation
Total Innovation and design and impact is on should go hand-in-hand
And even though we can make a nice habitat
On the bottom of a platform
It doesn't mean that we shouldn't be
Protecting
The natural
Cinebarre
Just as much as we always share
You know like
Replace it.
Completely there's no but nothing you're going to design is is better than
What's in leaving nature alone exactly right completely end
Some of the most interesting
Work that's being done
In terms of artificial reefs that I think people do support is
Assisting about habitat restoration you know a place where we've done a lot of damage with some other kind of development is there a way
That we can intervene
Again when did some kind of design solution
But for the purposes of of trying to rehabilitate something that was already there
Which policies in which
We don't disrupt Greece
99% invisible impact design coverage is supported by Auto.
The Autodesk Foundation supports the design and creation of innovative solutions to the world's most pressing social and
Environmental challenges
Like coral reef
Conservation and restoration
Secor is a nonprofit Global Network of scientists and other interested parties
That is creating ceramic
Seating units sandwich look like
Little ninja throwing stars
I'm covered in Coral RV and are dropped off a boats
And take hold in the nooks and crannies of damaged reefs
And repopulate Diego Zoo
Are using 3D printing and rapid prototyping to determine the best material and design combination for this evening units
For example they learn that
It has to be rough enough
Attached
Smooth enough
It's not a good location for other organisms like sponges in algae
That can take over and crowd out the coral
Learn more about that project
From Autodesk
Redshift
Tells the story
The future of making
Architecture engineering
Construction infrastructure in manufacture
Autodesk.com
Slash redshift
99percentinvisible was pretty sweet by Emmett Fitzgerald make centech production by Sharif Youssef music
By Sean real
Kurt Kolstad is the digital director include senior editor Delaney Hall
Mazza Joe Rosenberg Vivian Lee and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful downtown Oakland
California 99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia
BRX in independent Collective the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting fun Mall
Radiotopia. FM you can find the show in joint session about the show on Facebook
You tweeted me at Roman Mars and the show at 99ci org on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you're thinking this episode will be even better if I was looking at pretty pictures of rockfish
You covered at 99 Pi. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com