99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Back in the 1980s
Cuqui Skinner was reporter with a newspaper called The Arizona Republic
Cover the drug trade and the Border
They spent a lot of time in different parts of Mexico
He was getting tired of traveling and a being a stranger and every place he went
He wanted to actually settle down in Mexico
How to make a life
That's when I thought about well
I would like to be part of a community
In Mexico
What was going on
Tokidoki move to Agua Prieta a town right on the border where he done some reporting before
Agua Prieta at 6 just across the line from Douglas Arizona the two cities are contiguous
One urban area that spans the Border
/ towering rust colored metal wall
Steve concrete ditch
A line of concertina wire
A mesh fence
Antioquia
He settled down and made a life there
Methrone Delaney Hall
He built a house
Married a Mexican woman
Continued mastering the slaney Spanish of northern Mexico and ended up having five
Aprieta became his
And the thing I like that I will put it that it wasn't prison Orient it all
It was very Mexican community
And I was very intrigued by the town for that reason
Keoki ended up scaling back his full-time reporting job so we could open a smoothie shop and juice bar
What better way to get to know this city then to have a business here where
People will come in and hang out and talk
You could listen in observing probably pick up a few good ideas for the occasional freelance story that came as way
He named his smoothie shop
El mitote
Wishing in Spanish
It means like a gossip spot or there's a
A Ruckus going on for example of sirens going down the street
Everybody kind of runs out to see where the
Where the cop cars are going
And that's like the where's the meat
And what what's going on it's a hubbub.
Keoki pick the name because on occasion that he'd been accused of being a meatball dedal
Meaning of nosy
Someone who
Prize
He wasn't working as a full-time journalist anymore but that didn't mean he wasn't a reporter at heart
He loved collecting bits and piece
Information
And asking questions
Figuring out what was really going
And so that's how I got
The name for my business
And
Stuck
It's stuck in fact to this day how many years later
I'll run into people that get a gas station and they'll see me and they'll yell at me in Spanish
Blonde
Gossiper
I don't know my name but they know I had them
If it's kind of perfect though because it's also where you first started to
See evidence of this big
Conspiracy that was going on
Yeah there was things going on there that
Wasn't hard to start picking up stuff
So that would eventually lead karaoke
To one of the biggest and strangest stories he'd ever cover
In other news today something that one Customs agents called something out of James Bond
The story involves the cocaine trade
El Chapo Guzman has been the most Wanted Man in Mexico
Marijuana cocaine meth heroin and murder are all part of his business
And an incredible feat of engineering and architecture
That would change the drug trade
Forever
It was 1989 when keokee first started noticing some new customers in the Juice Shop
Guys he haven't really seen before
They have a certain
Swagger
Attitude
And he says they often had bodyguards
Which is not typical for an outing to the Juice Shop
Keoki describe them as Sinaloa Cowboys
So just when you said you Sinaloa Cowboys would come in like what they look like what do they act
Real high-end
Cowboy boots
The Levi's the leather vest that the white hats
What they wear
Pickup trucks with Sinaloa plates
They all feel like they're Cut Above the Law
They double Park out in front of my place
No they didn't give
Give a damn
Everybody just kind of stayed away from him because they knew what was going on that these guys were
In town for summer
Some something
Back in the late 80s
The Sinaloa cartel wasn't quite Beast
Falling dominant criminal organization it's become today
But it was headed in that direction
The cartel controlled a lot of the drug trafficking Corridor that ran through the Mexican states of Sinaloa and Sonora
Then across the border into Arizona
I don't update distribution points like Phoenix and Los Angeles
El aprieta FL ride along that corridor
Can you get suspected that these guys in his Juice Shop buying their smoothies with hundred dollar bills
Were part of the cartel
He began observing them
Cautiously
From a distance
But he also wasn't above marketing to their sensibilities
And the big thing we hyped with them was a
We had drinks
That we called AR-15
I love that one
And then we had what we had Alfalfa drink
We hiked it as being real good for hangovers
So they would come in and drink fresh Alfalfa mixed with pineapple or whatever
You know they bought into my advertising scams you know
And that's what they would have
This keoki says is
One of the Rules of Order.
Even if the theory of trickle-down Economics doesn't really hold up in other places
It's in the works here
You're dealing with border towns and drug trafficking
Trickle down economics
Pictures of valid idea because
In Mexico
These guys don't hoard the money
It gets better
On stuff like big houses and fancy cars
Not to mention Brides the local cops and
Politicians
And businesses
It's where the narcos launder their money
In general Kioki set
Drug traffickers tend to be
Pretty flashy
But there was one guy that stood apart from the Sinaloa Cowboys
Text with their leather vests and high-end boots
This guy dressed more like a businessman
His name was Francisco Rafael Camarena Macias
And one day he offered keoki his business card and told him a little about what he was doing in town
Call in a claim to be a lawyer out of Guadalajara
The story that I got from him when he came into my juice bar at one time
Was that he was a contractor and he was
Going to build
Houses in Agua Prieta
Oh, then I also Tokyo
That he was pursuing some business opportunities just across the border
Enalaprilat is sister city
Douglas Arizona
And at that point I didn't know of
What the score was I thought he was pretty legit
It wasn't yet clear to keokee that, Donna was also in the drug trade
Enoteca mosto year for that
Become a parent to the entire city of Douglas
And by then
Madonna had already turned the little town
Upside down
Douglas a small about 14,000 people lived here back in 1989 when Camarena for showed up
It doesn't have a whole lot of attractions
One of the main ones is the Gadsden Hotel
First built back in the early nineteen
The area was more of a magnet
The Cattleman Ranchers
And Mining type
It has a grand marble Lobby
Annie's gorgeous
Tiffany-style stained glass window
They depict the surrounding Sonoran Desert
It's saguaro cactus
Ocotillo and creosote
Today that desert landscape is heavily surveilled
A network of towers equipped with cameras and sensors
Watch the southern border and all of Douglas
Pretty much 24 hours a day
Border patrol trucks with tinted windows
Cruise the streets
There's so much history here because this all started with
Mister Douglas
Are you already taped
Reported me
Is that okay
On the north side of town There's a shop called Douglas
Diesel it's a big Brick Warehouse
Ceiling stucco filled with
And it's owned by the sky
Gary James
Maybe we better just start all over
Well
First of all
What's your name and what when were you born
My name is Gary James I was born
131 51
Gary grew up in Douglas and his live here almost all his life
Kilz fixing service the semis and trucks that pass through the Port of Entry
Pulling clothes Electronics window blinds in car parts
Manufactured in Mexico
About 145,000 personal vehicles and more than 2000 trucks
Cross the border every month
So a lot of my business is
From
From Mexico I'm fact I would say probably
80% of my business
This is from
South of the Border
And Gary says that when your customers are people who work in the cross-border trucking
A certain number of them will have
Tiles to smuggle
When you have a foreign country that butts up to the United States
And the drug problem that we have in America
You're going to have these kind of transaction
All the time
In all kinds of business
And so
Many of times I know people coming in my shop
May not
B-Legit 100%
But it's still a business
I'm Legit
So I
I seldom depart
But when Gary first met Rafael coming rain out at a local bar
He says he didn't suspect that, Rana was involved in any smuggling
I remember him being dressed very well
Was very professional
Never look like he ever got
Excited or upset and never said anything that would
Make you
Question who he was
Doug's Diesel
Amanda was outgoing and social
And he became friendly with some of Douglas's most prominent citizen
That included the chief of police and local Justice of the Peace who owned a lot of
Actually bought a plot
Near an industrial part of the Border
I also bought the local businesses
The business was called Douglas Ready Mix
Sand gravel and concrete for construction projects
Madonna higher Jerry to Help Services
And so I was seeing Mister, Dana at least on a weekly basis
At least Gary
Camarena's business appeared to be above board
So the Douglas Ready Mix
Was actually bidding on federal contracts
City contracts State contracts
For all kinds of
Materials that are needed in
Road building a bridge building
And so it looked like a very very legit business
And I mean he was employing people in so
So we were all happy because at that point in time there wasn't much industry in Douglas are
Really right downtown
Real close to where all the
DEA and Customs people
Crustaceans
It's right under their nose pretty much
QT scanner is giving me the Douglas
In his 1973 VW Bug
Which has a
Flapping canvas roof
The bumper sticker on the back that says
Make America Mexico again
With the map showing the US territory
That used to be part of our Southern neighbor
Okay this is
This Warehouse Right Here Right Now the city
Has been using at the store
Some of their buses in their bands
That run around
Rat run around Douglas
In front of us
Is a beige Warehouse surrounded by a chain link fence
Madonna constructed this building for her
Ready mix business
Back in the late 80s
He stored his trucks and equipment and material
The Border fence is about a hundred Paces away
Mexico is right
There
I'm through the fence
Just over the line
We can see another proper
That used to be, Dennis
It's a ranch style home in a wealthy neighborhood Developers
Medina built a house on a vacant lot
Which he reportedly bought for $90,000
Cash
Was a little bit over and above
Market price to say the least
It raised some eyebrows
This guy was throwing around a lot of money
And then there was the enormous hole behind them
It was going to be a swimming pool But as time went on then realize it was starting to fill up
Erdogan
And so
One day I was in the neighbors told me
You know that big ole butt
Weltall filled hit
No pull head materialize
You know there was a lot of construction activity at the house
Swift trucks going in and out and Hauling dirt
And at this point
Because Douglas and Oliver Prieta are both relatively small towns and everyone knows everyone else
Rumors were beginning to circulate
Matilda
Okie dokie
People were saying that, Rana wasn't just building a warehouse on the US side and a nice residential home on the Mexico side
He was building some kind
Tunnel
That dirt that slowly refill the swimming pool hole apparently it has been dug out of a passageway that ran
Under the Border
US Customs official
Spin Douglas and then in Phoenix
Eventually received a number of tips from inform
They learned that, then I was using the passageway to smuggle drugs from his
Is home in agua prieta
Across the border to his Warehouse in Douglas
But before law enforcement could go into the Wii
The search for the tunnel
They needed to establish that the smuggling was actually happening
So they stayed out, Dan has Warehouse
Ameritas business was located one block away from the US Customs headquarters
This was later chronicled in an episode of Unsolved
It was very dramatic
Early 1990 we initiated 24-hour surveillance
Of the Douglas Ready Mix
Company
Forgot something
Agent steak.com brightness business for over 2 months
Yes, day
Law enforcement eventually followed a flatbed truck
That they'd seen leaving, Tennis Warehouse
And they trailed it to a property outside of Phoenix
Where they conducted a ray
Redo the farmer Camarena struct adenosine
Agencies over a ton of nearly pure cocaine
Street value over 100 million dollars
The cocaine have been transported inside of
Hidden
Beneath the trucks bed
The rain confirmed with the drugs that come from camarena's Warehouse
In May of 1990
Law enforcement rated Comer in his Warehouse in Douglas and his home in Agua Prieta
They heard there was a
The tunnel
But they didn't really know exactly what it would be like
The first reaction was like
Okay
A tunnel is it's going to be some little bitty hole
Gopher Hall at these guys are
Crawling through
This is Terry Kirkpatrick
He worked with the US custom services
At the time and he was there the night of the raid
First agent entered the warehouse on the US
Side
And in the middle of the floor
Was probably about a 2-foot by 2-foot great
Well that great just having to be the shaft leading down into the tunnel
Once they found the tunnel entrance in the Douglas Warehouse
Some of the agents headed over to Agua Prieta
Where they were joined by the Mexican Federal Judicial
They discovered that, Donna and his family had already fled
His house with them
No one was there
But there was no access to the tunnel they couldn't figure it out we weren't sure how to get into it either
The agents went into what looked like a recreation
With a pool
And when they pulled away the carpet
They could see there was something unusual about the
It looked as if there was a separate concrete slab underneath
The pool table
Kind of enormous trapdoor
Agent started looking around for some kind of button
Lever that might open it
And someone else has pulled out of jackhammer
And I just happened to be the one that took the Jackhammer start Jackhammer in the floor
On top of where the pool table was
As I'm standing there jackhammering it all the sudden it moved and
Started go up
And then it stopped
And so everybody kind of froze
We said okay who touched what
Well it just so happened that one of the
Policeman outside was trying to get a drink of water out of an outside water spicket
Return that spicket
That's what was a control lever
That allow the pool table to go up
Valve triggered the pool table to rise up to the ceiling on huge hydraulic lift
Like something in mechanics
Revealing a set of stairs underneath which descended into the tunnel
Same one they found an entrance to on the Douglas side of the Border
The tunnel was located about 30 feet underground
Once agent at the bottom
It was a package
About 270 ft long 4 ft wide
5 feet high
Just tall enough that a person could walk through slightly stoop
Pushing a wheeled cart full of bundles of cocaine
The tunnel had concrete walls and a curb
Concrete roof
It was a ventilation system and rudimentary lighting
So this wasn't just a gopher hole
This was clearly a sophisticated engineering
Jess
The
Complexity to this whole tunnel
Was something that had been
Unseen before unheard of
And no one I think in the United States government
Especially in law enforcement realize anyone it has ever existed
Will federal agents on patrol along the mechs
Mexico Arizona border said today that they discovered a major drug smuggling Ruth where they have never looked but enough
2 million dollars worth of construction
Discovered last night
Concrete steel reinforcing bars electrical Arizona five feet high 4 ft wide the length
Of a football field
Agency discovery of the tunnel was pretty much the biggest thing that had happened
And Douglas
Everybody
I was paying attention
I mean everybody
And we had
Congress people come out to Douglas Arizona
And you know America's Most Wanted and
Unsolved Mysteries and
We just had a lot of activity here for at least the first year
After the tunnel was
Discovered it was constant
I was just concerned
I hear the helicopters
Black Hawks Landing all the time will who is it today
Hillside Grand Central Station in that place
Keoki started reporting in between shifts at the Juice Shop
Gary cab service in semis but was also hired by the federal government
To help maintain and secure the warehouse site so law enforcement could come and go
The customer service undertook a massive investigation
And people started printing t-shirts and bumper stickers would said I saw the tunnel
And selling them to all the visiting politicians and journalists
And everyone
Government officials reporters law enforcement ordinary citizens of Douglas
They were all asking the same question
First Who provided the money to build
It was estimated to cost one to two million dollars to create
The project clearly had the financing of a much bigger operation
And the other question was
Who had the expertise
Someone with engineering Noel have been involved
Someone who knew how to build a tunnel
Undetected
Stretch the length of a football field
And ran under the massive border fence in concrete drainage ditch
But separated Mexico from the US
So right away everybody was talking like
Who invested
Who is the Kingpin
This operation
And of course his name starts coming
The name was Joaquin El Chapo Guzman
And eventually
As the investigation progressed
Someone else started coming up to
Anarchist
The arrival
Of the architect
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Right now in New York
Massive trial is underway
Joaquin Guzman loera
Better known as El Chapo is one of the most powerful drug kingpins ever to face prosecution
This trial is a
Huge deal for the US government
Which tried unsuccessfully for decades
Capture El Chapo and hold him accountable
El Chapo escape from Mexican prison
Not once
But twice
Before finally being arrested again
Annexed related to the US
Now when he's being transported from the federal prison in Manhattan where he's being held
The courthouse in Brooklyn where his trial is happening
He's locked in what basically sounds like a coffin
The drug lord is said to be locked inside a security capsule which is fixed to the floor of an armored vehicle
Protected Inside by a team of officers with automatic weapons and escorted in a commando-style convoy
Capable of repelling attack
In an effort to prevent an assault in a caravan and risk another Chapo Escape
Authorities are closing the Brooklyn Bridge while delivering him to court
Early on in the trial back in November
As prosecutors began to lay out the
Scope and scale
The Sinaloa cartel's operation
Jurors were given a video tour
Of the Douglas
One discovered back in
The footage released to the public doesn't have sound
But it shows agents walking stupid
To the concrete
Passageway
And it shows the concrete slab below the pool table
Floating up from the floor on its hydraulic lift
Under the leadership of El Chapo de Sinaloa cartel became known for their creative smuggling method
Especially their tunnels
The one in Douglas became a kind of prototype for many tunnels afterwards
And the person who oversaw its construction
Was a man named Felipe de Jesus
Corona beer batter
The tunnels really started with a guy named felipe de jesus corona verbera
Who was an architect
He graduated
From the University of Guadalajara in 1980 with an architectural degree
And there's not much known about his early life beyond that fact
This is Monte real
He was the South America correspondent for the Washington Post and he's written about transporter Tunnels for the New Yorker
And he says that while Raphael, do not may have been the
The frontman for the tunneling project
Behind the scenes it was code on Eva Tavares
Who provided technical expert
Corona beer peritonitis
We'll get into that a bit more later but he was convicted of conspiracy and drug smuggling in his own federal trial
A lot of what we know about him is based on testimony from natural
Stories that have been collected from contract workers who helped him with certain
Construction projects and also from testimony
From former cartel members
Cartel members like Miguel Angel Martinez
Worked as a pilot and later is a lieutenant for El Chapo
Before turning State's Witness
And entering Witness Protection
Back in the 1980s in mind
Martinez helped to manage El Chapo's business
4 time he coordinated cocaine deliveries from Colombia to Agua Prieta
When he testified against Corona
He described him as being
The only guy that he ever knew
Within the Sinaloa cartel who addressed
Chapo with the pronoun to
Instead of the more formal and deferential usted so he was
Considered a guy who just was very close friends and very familiar
With Guzman but I'm not sure
If anybody
Really has the story of how they met
We may not know that story but we do know generally speaking
LCM Architects come to work
For drug traffickers
Basically it's like in any business community
This is Yuan Grillo
British journalist based in Mexico City
He's cover the drug trade and the drug war for almost 20 years
Like if you were going to build a house
And you say you need knock text you my ask around
I need some Marketplace
If you have somebody coming up an offering
Are we good buddy
Will you might normally make
It could be enough for this
Basalt reviews
Because cartels are such extensive and elaborate operations they need many kinds of sub special
They end up hiring not just Architects and engineers
But also accountants
Lawyers
It expert
I need a musician to write ballads about the exaggerated
Exploits a certain Market
Many of these people are employed for one-off
Jobs
Like contractor
Do you have professional killers
The highest paid a wage
I'll pay for it
You have
People who have
Woke up
Anna paid normally per backpack they take over
Do you have people who have paid
2 Bill Tuttle
Until I paid for the job
According to Miguel Angel Martinez
The former cartel member
The architect Cotto never worked on a number of building projects for El Chapo before embarking on the Douglas
And his first projects were
Just kind of construction jobs
Within Mexico that weren't related to
Tunnels
He had built a couple of residential homes
For Guzman and he had to help design a farm with a zoo where Chapo kept some of his exotic pets
Mini designed a grocery store where the Sinaloa cartel had some offices up in the top
Floor of it
And all these projects weather at four more a home or a grocery store
At a certain
Flair
The one thing that all of those
Project had in common
Was that they featured hiding places
That we're all access by these
Hydraulic system
There's a playfulness almost
To the sort of systems that Corona verbera design
He was very creative in
Kind of developing ways to access the secret passageways that somebody who walked into it
House would never really
Guess
In 1988 Corona bedroom move from Guadalajara
To the Douglas Tower Prieta area with his wife
3 kids
And in the federal trial his defense team maintained that it was to work on legitimate project
They argued that like a lot of people in the area Corona berbera inadvertently got caught up doing business with people
HuHot cartel connections
But they didn't actually design or build the tunnel
They brought in an expert to testify that the tunnel look more like a work of a structural engineer and not an architect
The trial transcripts kept very detailed and jardini with references to things like control joint
And curing comp
Inlet structure
Eventos corruption in the area was rampant and it was Corona beer barrels Misfortune to be in the wrong place
The wrong time
And there is some evidence
Said there were other Specialists involved
The tunnel
A senior Customs agent told me that
One of the informants who tipped him off to the tunnel with a Mexican engineer
The engineer claims he been hired by the Sinaloa cartel to research possible tunnel locations
Create tunnel designs
Which were then handed off to Corona beer
That detail is hard to fact-check
But it comes from a credit
Source
Even after being convicted and serving more than a decade in federal prison
Corona verbera still denies being involved with the tunnel
Is attorney told us that he also denies involvement in any previous Chapo Guzman projects
We asked one of their better for interview but through a friend he told us that he's not willing to speak at this time
Despite pleading Not Guilty Crown a betta with seen at
Key tunnel locations
Including both the warehouse on the US side
And the residential home on the Agua Prieta
Decide
Number of local contractors in worker
Recorded interacting with him at those construction site
They described him as somebody that they would talk to you all the time who is always around
And it's
Funny a lot of people actually describe him
In glowing terms
Present there was a contractor who described seen the plans that Corona Barbera have for the warehouse
And
He kind of pause in his testimony said they were beautiful plan
They kind of respected this guy as an architect he kind of had this air about him
That people looked at him as somebody who knew what he was doing
But there were also a few signs that this wasn't an ordinary construction project
For instance the drains in the floor of the warehouse
One worker raised questions about their size
And the fact that they didn't appear to lead to a clear drainage system
This was because they were actually going to feed into the passageway the connected to the tunnel
And one of the workers said you know these trains they don't
There's something not right with them where does the water go he was kind of
Questioning
The design and crunch berbera
Basically said you know mind your own business
I'm in charge here
The Sinaloa cartel had handpicked the our Prieta Douglas border as a tunnel side
Review reasons
One thing
Hotel was already operating there
They had established networks in an established operation
And they'd already been moving drugs across the border
Above-ground mostly in Vans and trucks
With hidden compartments
And they were able to move about 3 tons
Per month
Across the border that way but
Guzman wanted more efficiency
And understand why El Chapo Guzman wanted more efficiency we need to take a little side trip
Miami
Back in the early 1980s cocaine was coming into the US not
From Mexico
But from Columbia
And a Colombian cartels preferred smuggling drugs into the country on boats and small planes through cities inside
South Florida
Like Miami Miami is the source that supplies two-thirds of America's drug habit
And the drug trade was helping to fuel a surge in crime
And so the Reagan Administration started something called the south Florida task force
The fight it looks like a war Customs agents On Assignment ready for combat I Spy
Cobra helicopters from the army with marijuana leaves painted on the side each leave a successful drug bust
Reagan's goals for the task force were very ambitious
Our goal is to break the power of the mob in America and nothing short of it
Winning the end their profits imprison their members and cripple their organization
But the reality is the harder we make it for Smugglers to get Goods across the border
The more money ends up getting pumped into the system
Militarizing our border over many decades
Hasn't ended illegal trafficking
It's just help
Professionalizing
The more you crack down on it
Sahara
Eoin Grillo again
The hotter it gets
Price goes up
The more the price goes up the more money is
The more money is made the more criminals want to do it
The Crimson attached to it
NR Witcher I'm O+ ization
And the Mexican cartels were about to get a lot richer and more powerful
Thanks in part to Reagan strategy of increased enforcement in South Florida
Because when the Colombian cartel saw that they were losing their product in drug bust in Miami they just looked
Two different border
Criminal collaborator
Sanya tattoo Mexico
Name is agreement made where they would pay the Mexicans
Take the cocaine from them
Mexican Woody had a big trafficking group Encino
Cool the kilometer to Mexico
Mexicans could take it and then take the United States and deliver it to them
At a price per kilo
Pun
What a negotiating
So suddenly
A lot of the cocaine that have been traveling around or over me
Mexico was now traveling through
Through it
And then across the southern border into the US
Which meant a lot of new money
Pouring into the mix
Can cartels
Border agents in Arizona like
Karey Kirkpatrick
Could see the effects of this on the go
It hit it was just like
Every car instead of marijuana
Had cocaine
Just like a thousand pounds at a time 4000 lb
We got over run so fast
And as the US continue to crack down on cartels in Colombia
Eventually opened up new opportunities for Mexican cartels to become more than just careers
Did eventually come to dominate the entire cocaine supply chain
So the big cartels are taken out in Colombia in the first Pablo Escobar
And the Cali cartel was taken down
And the Mexican cartels
Particularly
Personal loans
I'm telling you I was only like
12 for 30 years old back then
And my classmates and I we were like eight
I don't want to be a superhero like most kids
Around the world I want to be a troll traffickers pose
They do have pneumonia and they can do whatever they want
This is Miguel Angel Vega
Grew up in culiacan Sinaloa
Which by this time
I've been the epicenter of Mexico's heroin and marijuana trade for deck
What was the rise of cocaine Sinaloa drug-trafficking
Because we're getting even more powerful
And they go watch that happen
She was growing up
Some of his classmates became immersed in Narco culture
El Chapo was seen as a modern-day Robin Hood
Helping sharn the sinaloan economy with drugs
Some of those glass
Classmate ended up being
Drug traffickers and all I can tell you about that
Some of them are in prison
Or that much of the blood is still here in culiacan
No violent
Consider joining the Norcos Vega became an investigative journalist focused on organized crime
He's chronicled the violence and Chaos of the drug war
What is done so much over the years to destabilize the country corrupt its institutions and turn some of its mode
Vulnerable people
Into Asylum Seekers
By what seems like these body stuck in garbage bags police executed
Journalist assassinated
Are directly connected to the Wrath of the Sinaloa cartel
And big explains that a lot of this violence and Chaos was seated back in the late 80s
I'd only because the cocaine trade was being rerouted through Mexico
But also because the cartels were undergoing in in
Internal reorganization
Sensation
Whole generation of older narcos with leaving the scene
They were getting arrested
They were dying and a new generation was coming up
And they were dividing up the old territory
Forging new alliances
The rivalries
That generation included El Chapo Guzman
And enormously creative
Brutal and
Ambitious
He was like
Eager for power
Let's just a small the whole world
Was just
Conquered entire world
And that's
Like his ultimate goal
El Chapo had some new ideas
Like this tunnel in Douglas
Which According to some estimates allow the Sinaloa cartel to Triple the amount of cocaine they were moving across
Cross the border
So do you think
What role did this tunnel play in
Chapo
Becoming Chapo
I think was a big role
Piers keoki Skinner again
The journalist and Juice shop owner from Iowa
Nothing really launched him onto his career the climates couldn't believe how fast you got that cocaine to Los Angeles
And they kind of jokingly nicknamed him speedy
In addition to helping El Chapo make his name
The tunnel created a new kind of notoriety
For Douglas Arizona
Which had formerly been a sleepy border
Suddenly it was synonymous
With the biggest
Drug trafficking story of the early 90
And there were a lot of questions about how a smuggling operation of that magnitude
Could have happened without at least a few local collaborators
What's the date in one June 10th
The first cup
Sure
The Specter of a man who called himself Francisco Rafael Camarena
Still stalks the homes of the wealthy and influential here
Who entertained him and lavish Style
In the aftermath of the tunnels discovery
Keoki got to work
Read a series of articles for his old newspaper
The Arizona Republic
Chronicling Raphael, Dan has connections to various prominent
People not just in Mexico
But in Douglas
He was always out of the country club
And I'm making the right connections getting another right people here
Before you got this
Tunnel under way
I mean
It seems like there were a lot of implications in these articles about
Local officials
Profiting
From this whole scheme
But did anybody in local government ever
Do any time for this or
Anything like that
No
No nobody on the Douglas side
They're also allegations about how Agents from the customer service
May have colluded in the tunnels game
And while no one was ever charged
There was a lot of corruption going on within the agency in around this time
Here's Terry Kirkpatrick again
At that time
Corruption was so rampant that the US government started a blue ribbon campaign trying to stamp it out and we
We're so busy
Trying to work the corruption and trying to weed out all wrong with these inspectors
Because they were passing a thousand pounds in the trunk of a car right to the Port of Entry
It was just a lawless kind of area back in 1989
Senior agent in the customer service told me that the tunnel was probably in operation for at least 6 months
And he said that quote
Everyone
Dave had to know about the passageway
Route to be in regular use for that length
After the discovery of the tunnel El Chapo Guzman came up with new ways of getting drugs across the border Tactical
Cans of jalapeno peppers or inside coils of insulated wire
Both Francisco, Rihanna and Saudi pakoda naved badass led to Max
And it took a long time to get them back to unite
Coming in and was eventually extradited in 2001 and a couple years later he
He plead guilty for his role in the Douglas smug Lincoln
You received a sentence
10 years in Federal
Corona beer out with extradited in 2003 and tried in 2006
He was released from federal prison in September 2018
But that wasn't the end of the tunnel
The devil's tunnel was like
Prototype
Even though it was eventually discovered it was so efficient and effective
During the time it was an operation
But it paid for itself many times over
With a successful experiment
They proved the viability of under
Michelle
The tunnels after this one
They almost became a nightmare
That was one tunnel after another tunnel after another tunnel
Tunnel from San Diego to Tijuana they found it so sophisticated being called a super tunnel
Nearly seventy feet underground
Part of it through solid Limestone on the phones
Phone still work without specific information about where the tunnels are located
Or just plain luck
They're virtually impossible to find
Ron Claiborne
ABC News on the US map
Most Channel show up along the Arizona and California borders
In places where the ground is soft enough for digging but not so soft it will cave in
Some of the tunnels are pretty rudimentary but some like the Douglas tunnel
Are highly engineered and sophisticated projects with elevators and real cars
I told discovered in Baja Mexico last year
Included solar panels to power a ventilation and Lighting systems
Most illegal drugs actually come into the country through legal ports of Entry
That fact
And tunnels
Are two reasons why Trump
Probably wouldn't do much to stop drug trafficking
But the US government still sees tunnels as enough of a problem that they started tunnel task force groups along the boy
The groups exist solely to monitor investigate and prevent tunneling
The tunnels are notoriously difficult
Detect
And they keep showing up
I was in Douglas I tried to get in
Into the old tunnel
Which has been kept open for
Regional training sessions by the border
Keoki Skinner worked his connections
And got us into the warehouse where the entry
But the tunnel is dank
Anna maintains
And I was 7 months pregnant at the time of the visit
A city worker took one look at me
Probably imagined me trying to
To clamber down the rusty ladder in the dark
And then wouldn't let us in
After all
But if we couldn't see the architecture of
Drug tunnel
Then at least we could see the architecture the drug trade has helped
Spell
Across the border
So you see it was pretty nice neighborhood
Once again we're driving around in keoki's rattling little VW Bug
We're exploring the part of town where I will see you at this business
It's the neighborhood where, Donna's ranch home with the hydraulic pool table
Although that's now been converted into a community
And keoki point that a house on the corner
It's a nice place
With a wrought iron fence
The house is made of brick
This this is clean money this is Cattlemen this guy's been a cattle
Guy Rancher 44 years
Because keoki has lived here for decades
Just picked up a lot of information about how people make their money
As we go around the corner
Look at this place up on the right look at the
Columns on that place
Blood Money
Who's ever The Limited
The house takes up the entire block
It has enormous white Greco-Roman columns and a chandelier dangles over its soaring entry
Keoki says a local Narco
Let's hear
It's one of many
Extravagant Narco mansions
In the area
Puking out with local tours Italy
Bringing tourists and snowbirds from Arizona and other parts of the Southwest down to God
I said I'm going to show you what
Bad habits United States
Has built for us down here
All this money from
Drug consumption United States this is
Is how it's been spent
Down here these houses
And not just these houses
When you stop to think about everything that's funded
Directly or indirectly
Buy American drug consumption
To make your mind
The money find its way to the people who drive track
Or fly the drugs
The Hitman
Battle over cartel territory
To The Architects and Engineers who built
Channels for smuggling in the mansions for the Kingpin
I took a bribe the cops
Politicians and border patrol agent
So they don't turn their heads and look the other way
At this vast and complex system grinds along
And of course the money also trickles down into the rest of the economy
To the grocery stores in the clothing shops in the gas stations
Even the local Juice Shop
That sells the Norcos
They're AR-15 smoothies
99percentinvisible was produced this week by our senior editor Delaney Hall
Finish the story just under the wire
I think that's it I also think I was like literally in labor when I tracked.
Stop so if there's anything that doesn't
Works very well let me
And I'll do it again
Spy
You went above and beyond day congratulations
Enjoy your much harder job for the next 6 months
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by genre
Katie mingle is our senior producer occur Cole steady as the digital director Russell team is Avery truffle
Joe Rosenberg Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh
Turn mad that Sofia klatzker and me Roman Mars
Special things this week to keokee Skinner Andy Becker and the clerks at the US District Court in Tucson
Arizona
To find out more about keoki's tours of Agua Prieta
Google his name
Let's keoki Skinner
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Von Maur
And radiotopia. FM
You find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook and tweet me at Roman Mars and the show at 99.
I org run Instagram with Tumblr and Reddit to
But our borders are wide open 24/7
At 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com