99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Steve Burrows is a principal at an engineering consulting company Caldera
I'm Steve Burrows CPA and I'm a professional engineer
And when he saw the Great Pyramid in Egypt for the first time he reacted pretty much the way I imagine most people react
When you actually come and see something that somewhere in the region of 40 stories high
It was built for Thousand Years
You know you just have this
Incredible wow mount
But then that structural engineer brain kicks in every time you look at something you think
Festival how did they do that
Then I start thinking
How would I do
In a recent article in design intelligence he took those questions
Head on
As if a client gave him a brief to build something like the Great Pyramid today we got these incredible challenges
Why you doing something that's never been done before
So one of The Incredibles
Facts for me you was at the Great Pyramid still too
Tallest building in the world
The century
And as someone who in the present-day is hired to Engineers seemingly impossible structures
Ceebros thinks that the engineers of 2600 BC really knew what was possible and made most of the major
Decision
As a present a engineer
So some of the things they knew
Why
If they built on the Giza plateau
They could put stones that
To a certain pressure
On the ground
Didn't collapse beneath
You can look at other pyramids and see the previous mistakes that were made out to no
What the ground capacity was
I'm think about determine the size
Inside the Great Pyramid
Because if you're going to build the tallest building in the world
How tall do you want it to be
Or just a bit taller than the last till this building got to make a decision decision was made for them by
The quality of the ground that they were building up
So that was number one
Secondly they had
The Builder in the Pharaohs life
I'm pretty sure that somebody
You know I can tractor
Set
You know with the best will in the world we can only lay this number stands a day
Am I can only Assemble
This many men and assembling men to be the right wording here because and I totally miss this
Historical revision
But the consensus now is that
It was a rather privileged well treated class of Egyptians that built the pyramids
Not
Slaves
That blew my mind
Cecil B Demille is going to be pissed
Twenty thousand men can only lay this many times a day
On the ferry typically lives
35 years so
You know that many men sounds that many stones * 35 years
Means it's going to be this hot
So the ground Can Only Hold so much mass without buckling the workers can only build
So much an affair with Lifetime and finally
The material had to be delivered to the side in time to build the thing
And I would think
Depending weather
The Quarry wall
Relative
To the actual sites
Just chosen
Known ground bearing capacity
I'm so sorry
Heightened visibility
Cairo
They also I figured out
I can only get so many stones
I only have so much
Ontario off the quality
At the Quarry
50 Bros things that these
Practical engineering considerations determine the size of pyramid
Tight
The number of stones and ultimately
What we all marveled
Thousands of years later
It wasn't so much missed a class
Practical nurse
Another practical consideration that led to the pyramids longevity is
Material chemistry
There are other agent buildings that I'm not held up as well as the pyramids the buildings are sore
I'd lost it
Thousands of years
Perfectly well
Sorry it was pretty clear to me that
The Egyptians had a pretty good understanding of the material.
What they were working with
But it wasn't
100% perfect
For example
The first large mud brick
As I looked
Had Massive Attack
Cracks in the
He was very clear to me that they with thermal crack
What has happened is that they were used to building walls
But when the world turns a corner
That point becomes very stiff
And because the temperatures vary hugely between day and night
These materials least walls
Binding contract
When it contracts
Masonry will always break
Next to the stick
So every time there was a corner
Found a huge bus
Bicycle crack
So they clearly didn't understand
The thermal performance
Of mud brick
And that problem is exacerbated by the fact that they laid these mud bricks on a mortar bed
So they actually have two materials for building so they do
Mud-brick
And Malta
And by putting these different materials together
They thermally move at different amounts
I made crack
So somebody must have said
Well if we only use one material lay the bricks dry
Would they have performed better
And the answer is yes
And the pyramids
Are exactly that
There is only one material is used
That means
The pyramid st. Louis
I got very hot in the day and very cold at night
But the material throughout the pyramid is consistent
I'm so it didn't crack
Because they move together they effectively breathe
And because they breathe
To account for the
Changes in temperature
Able to last a long time without cracking and breaking up
This prompted Burroughs to think about modern building
Where we put so many materials together all the time steel and glass and aluminium
Concrete
Cementitious materials and pasta
And I saw you walking round modern buildings in
Looking at where all the cracks where
I know every crack is Italy joints
Between different materials
I'm starting to think maybe we could
Think about this a little bit more time if we did
We can actually make buildings last longer
Just buy
Thinking hard about those joints
Which presently we solve by putting
You know Dewey material in the joint to try and take up that feel movement
But if we just
Detailing back
In the first
They would last
Nothing
Galanga buildings lost the most sustainable AR
So long as I live
Materials we use in the long run
Longevity is probably the most basic route to sustainability in the pyramids are the poster children for longevity
In addition to chemistry
Adhering to basic principles of physics
Keeps your building around for Millennia with little or no maintenance
A pyramid is a nice stable shape
And I think they would have loved not but it isn't as simple as the way I was thinking about
If I had a bucket of sound
Can I put it on the floor
Then it actually nuts
What makes a pyramid shape
So intuitively
They never the thoughts is a stable thing to do
But actually one of the interesting things is
That the gradient of the science of
Is not determined like sand by snot
Natural angle of repose
You can actually make it whatever you want to make it
But you can see from the prior permit
It's from a step pyramid
On the bent pyramid the pyramids that preceded the Great Pyramid
But they were sort of going a little bit steeper
But they never never really got above
50 degrees
I'm cuz I think somebody felt that this is sort of
A maximum angle about which
You should never exceed
So get an empirically derived knowledge sets the agenda
If you put these things together
How much Stone you can get
The bearing pressure that you can put on the ground
I'm the angle
United determines the height of
The building and I'm pretty sure the simple mathematics in the world between the ark
Engineering contractor
Gave a practical limit
So what could be built
This exercise in using engineering principles to augment the archaeological data may give us some insight into why the Great.
That is both the oldest and the largest Pyramid of Giza
These people probably thought it was the limit of everything
It's the biggest bearing capacity it's a steep as they can go and it says many stones as can be laid in a lifetime
You can't do any bigger than that
What's the speed of light
If you like for building permits
I know it's no Revelation that the pyramids are well-designed
I'm not an idiot
But learning about these practical considerations from Steve Burrows just made me appreciate their Majesty in a new way
These structures are not
Otherworldly
You don't need to come up with crazy theories to explain them they are the product
Smart Architects and designers and engineers and skilled workers
Who played knowledge that was gained over time and passed down over Generations
And do that perfectly understandable and repeatable process they discovered
Their limit
I don't get me wrong
I don't ever want to see the tallest building we could possibly build
But I might like to see the one designed with enough durability
Flexibility
The last 4000 years
99% invisible was produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
Just got in the center for architecture and Design
Define armoire
Good websites 99% invisible
. org
Blichmann
Search
Windsor
The note
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Arts on the truth podcast. Com