99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
My boy Maslow's favorite color
Is red
My boy Carver is favorite color
Is blue
Cover
Okay with the color red
But Maslow
Hates blue
They're twins
And for those who don't know them well
Color they wear is how people tell them apart
These colors
We're not chosen for them a test
Happened is
Fundamental to who they are
When you're a kid
Your favorite color is
One of
Maybe five of the most important aspects of your personality
Records of Our Lives
The fervor for a specific favorite color tends to die down
But over the course of human history
Search for the brightest
Splash of color
Has been a defining feature of our species
Concert Sinclair is fascinated by color
How It's Made
What it means
Now defined
She wrote a beautiful book called The Secret Lives of color that I love so much
But I invited her in to talk with me and she's riveting
So this episode
It's just that
My conversation
Kasia Sinclair
All about
Secret Life
Color
How did you begin
Becoming obsessed with colors in
What made you want to write a whole book
The lights
Yes I'm lucky that I came from for a creative
Amelie
My mother was a
Florist
And I have
Very Vivid memories
The kind of messing around in
Flower shop when I was little and I would be given kind of like the office
Cuts to make little bouquets from
That was the beginning of my love
Ocala but I became interested in it
Academically
I bet you the best because I was studying 80
Centre women's history
And more specifically what women wore to masquerade balls during a
Century
And one of the things I loved about
Starting this very Niche topic
Is the fact that I go to read
So many journals and letters
About
What people will
Planning to Arrowhead wound
Parties in University
Full movies with ghosts
Really struck me time again
Was the fact that friends will using
Caller-Times
In these letters
And Diaries and that account
That was completely unfamiliar to me and I
We have to go and do an awful lot of research to try and recreate what. Color might look like and then sometimes it was a dimple
Ultimate yunnan
I simply wouldn't ever be able to find out exactly what
Color look like
And the fact that the color of a cobra hitches
Shifted you know I was in London
In the same city where the people were
We're writing it out and it really wasn't that long ago historically
And yet the color terminology
Chad changed
3D was completely the colors that was possible then
What colors the eye
Even recognize
Delete my mind instead of continue to be of interest to Menard
Will be fascinated by it
And I mean in your book you talk a lot about the relationship between language and color and
One of the most interesting things to me was how different languages
Divide up the color spectrum differently
Yes absolutely so if you think about a color wheel or we know if you think about
A microwave
Representing the colors we could possibly see
It wouldn't be in
Straight line it would be kind of in a random Blood on the areas where your blue face into green
Phenol red face into
I'm too pink or purple
The dividing lines the bit with different cultures
Define
This is raden and this is blue in this is purple
That can really change
And making changes on an individual basis and also on a linguistic basis soap
Various languages have divided up the Spectrum
Differently in two more or fewer groups through 7 in different ways surf example
I'm Russian speakers
Wordful darker blue on the word philosophy for example and some languages only
Need to buy the color spectrum
Instacart
304 grade
Right
I was struck by this in your book that
When the section on pink
That there's a word for pink
And there's no word for light
Yellow or light green
It's just it's so strange that has its own nomenclature
Yeah it's a real set of cultural Oddity I'm particularly
Your pink now play suction outside
Role in our culture basic
Associated with women and girls by good on l
Peru ceviche
We just seem to really love it in western culture comes up a lot
And you're right you know far more than you would think of say up a pale green or or
Or pale blue
I mean there's a sense that these colors is this kind of his Concepts but
Your book The Secret Lives of color
Is really about color in the material world
Girls about the pigments
Themselves
Until I kind of want to go through a few of those pigments to sort of tease out
These types of
Stories that we get an isbn number
We could just start with red
Because it seems to be the most universally loved
Color through history
Why is that
Yeah it's pretty interesting one so one of these questions that I
Get off keto without fail every time I do a talk about color
Is weather
Colosseum make humans have a set of real physical response
And quite often decide are is Connor
Phoenix Lights
Junk science you know like pink makes you calm will we know whatever and it's very hard to really pin down
Valid
Pontificator
Red is the color where
The most test
Happened on
The most active
Come back with with fatty compelling result
Yes
Redis have some form of measurable
Impact
That's why
You get it so widely across
So many different cultures
Because it does seem to
Make us one
Spawned
In this really elements way so one of the
Examples of faith
Is that
If you look at movie games of
Establo Osaka
Dipping plate
Since the Second World War
In the UK
Teams that are wearing red have one
When I fridge more than they then they should have done statistic
And there was another similar study done on the Olympics as well as you know the Athens Olympic Games
On a non-combat for today and again he had similar results
What does deceive mean
Incredible but also makes you think that you have ass play
Thought you should definitely make sure you was a team wearing red
Talk about how people made red in the ancient world
Show so I'm one of the dates of oldest pigments
I'm always red pigments that we know about is is hematite
Which essentially you can kind of think of like rusticity
It's on outside
You find it in in Oak Hills right ashoka's and
The chemical compounds which is made of really common
In the Earth's crust you get kind of red red tinted
Either geographically really widespread areas
So it's not surprising in a way that it's
Crop top in a lot
If I'm difference
Archaeological context
All over the world and then
China North America
North Africa Europe. Again again again
It's so Universal that it was dumped by a 1980s anthropologist
Just wanted to see if the two consistent
Markers of Chi-Chi human evolution
Along with to make a
How's the weather
Hematite red into making are the things that make humans human
Yeah
But hematite Sarah falls out of fashion because
We find
Brighter version
The one of the reasons why I love
Color is a subject
Yeah I'm just so fascinated by it because humans have always
Going to the most
Extreme
An extraordinary lengths
To get that hums
On brighter and more interesting Shades and that's really evident when he talked about red so yeah yeah
If they have this really white available
Weather
That you bacon
If they got famous anywhere in the world but that is not enough it's not bright enough
And so somewhere along the line
Someone that discovers that if you crush up
A type of apple
Scale insect
That can be found in in Europe called that is neither could become is
That you can produce
I really am quite vibrant
Reds
Die
And this was a highly
Mokena on clothing it was
Used to clean a status symbol and it was also very expensive and because
The finest of a cloth
And the expensive. I went together there's no point in having a really beautifully manufactured wood and cloth
And then thawing it a color is associated with poverty
I'm a particular type of
Very fine cloth
Cool Scarlet
Wisp usually tied with
Descaling sex will you see if she died this very vibrant red
And So eventually the name of the cloth
Scarlet woollen cloth
Became kind of synonymous with the red that was so often died and that's kind of how
The name Scarlett and the color red came together that she should have borrowed from a very fine wooden clothes
That's amazing
It is another red that you can help me pronounce this is like
Coach Anil how do you say
TTM
Scarlet Azusa made with a scale insect
This one rather than being European
Is very common in South and Central America
And was used
Very widely biotics
Antenna man in Kazan In the Intercultural again it was
Associated with
With relays and and Power
Positive
Taxation
Histamine away so when there was a vassal state
And the bottle States would be expected to
Give the rulers
Certain numbers of
All femcare chenille
Die all the dried bugs
Through every month or two months
Depending on how well fetus
Allstate walls
Highly valued in an embedded in the culture
How did
Discolor
Interact with colonization in trade
Around the world
Food colors and colorants
You haven't been one of those things that people go and take over the countries and
Exploit of the areas of the world
For either that very often natural resources.
The people desperate
Set the hounds on
And they can make an awful lot of money from back home
I'm so nakusha Neil was one of the
The Spanish word with the desperate to get their hands on in order to get
This red
Colorance
Back to Europe where it was actually many times stronger
Then the commies died that had been originally used to
I'm color Scarlet cloth cushionless is much
Stronger
I'm so it's much more cost-effective and great sums of money
Could be made and mermaids
In the Expo and in use of this die
And it took like 70 thousand bugs
Pound of
Coutinho right
Yeah I mean
In with all these dyes that are made out of animals or Animal product in this reality
The pool at creature that's involved in the making of the color really does get completely homity a very often it takes
An awful lot of them to produce not very much time
And often you find he died
Temping driven to the brink of Extinction
Because people are so Keen to get their hands on on the
Color
And do we still use insects
Like they used to make pigments today
Yes so there is a spot East Side
Particular color in it
Queen of consent a natural Reds
Colorado booster because it's
Nesbit really highly pigmented
Is been used in car
Food and Uso cosmetic surgery
If you were to look at your stupid yogurt to or something like that you might see that it's been colored with
Carminic acid
We might see it down as the color
120 and not
Is it in fact
Cochineal
Okay
Yes but if you think about it all the covens that they used in food I mean
Maybe
We're all different but you know if you replace
Amy 21-20 with another color and that the likelihood is that that color it might well be
An extra
From like a cult of sludge just learned a lot about that coloring come from so I don't know
Kotaro Oldsmobile
Turn the color pigment can be pretty rare in nature intensive
Require the wholesale Slaughter of an entire species to make it happen
Which brings me to
Tyrian purple
Can you talk about
Yeah so this is one of my favorite stories
From the Spurs
Because many people
Office automatic association between royalty and purple
And it's one of those kind of cultural thinks that maybe you didn't think about too much
Actually
The link goes really far back
Audit is based on this amazing
Purple guy
I'm cool tyrian purple again it's an animal-based
I colored it comes from
Two varieties of
Shellfish
That all Native to Mediterranean
And if you were to go in a nun find some one of these selfish
I'm back white spiny so you have to be careful when you picked it up
If you attack
Crack it open
You would
Seated as kind of a apparel
Blinds
Runs across
Steve
The back of the of the shellfish
Auntie
Gland contains feet in a single drop of liquid
Smells a little bit like garlic apparently it's very unpleasant smelling like garlic breath
Ons this
Liquid
Is
Phenomenal when it's
Exposed to the light if you want to rub it on a piece of cloth Express a piece of toast to the light
It would have Me Gently change color with tiny yellow and then green
And then blue and then finally purple
Call of Duty produces is very distinctive and very vibrant and this was to die
Beloved
By the ancient world
And became again because it's very expensive
Really appreciated with
Chihuahua and
Royalty
So again you get off of legislation
Dictating who
Katadyn called where it is a kind of famous
Story about the emperor Nero who 10.2 a recital
I'm so a woman
I'm in the audience
Wearing a tyrian purple gown and she wasn't either of their of the rights and cloth
What state has to wear it
I'm so he had her
Taken from the room
Whipped and told her lands confiscated
It's because he's so this is a real
A wave he's up in his own power because she was
Taking
The power bestowed by this
Color was supposed to symbol
Which is kind of amazing
Yeah
Back again
Like the full scale
Bugsby for shellfish
United went through went through horror
Because of humans
Decipher this powerful
Hillside United
It takes about 250000
Of these shellfish to produce
Just an ounce of dye
Anso people hunting these selfish
Extinction
Chicken and using so many of these shellfish
Absolutely amazed
Geographical features if you go back to some of the
I'm the areas of the world were producing this die in the classical era
The discarded shells who makes become conniff
Hills
Outside the town
I'm very often downwind of the Town who the guy works with associated downwind
Say that the citizens who ended up wearing it's a real purple gowns when people that buy the smell of the money fight
Until when did
Purple
You kind of lose
It's
Association has always been associated with royalty
When did it become
Acceptable for a common Folk
To wear at without getting wet
Tyrian purple
Both because the shellfish
And it became incredibly rat
Suicide because of political
Tom Wales
I'm around the Mediterranean
Which kind of really disrupted
Steve Emmanuel
Jeff of the die
3M public self need a large disappeared from from View
Proper kind of goes into a little bit of it
Define
Until the mid-nineteenth century
When I didn't
Kylie new purple dye was discovered completely box
Understood letter Revival
And what's that
What's that
Somd the new purple guy that was
Covered in the mid-nineteenth century is Kool Moe
And it was discovered by an 18 year old scientist who is
At home on holiday
And, using his his vacation time to
Try and find
A synthetic
Version of Queenie in which was a cure for malaria the time
A malarial a use for severely common in Europe newest tool to be able to
Juice is synthetic we need
Would be kind of a huge moneymaker if anyone you could
Discover it
But that's what he was doing you spending his days
You know what's on this
I'm in his father's office
On one of his failed experiment
He ended up with it is
It is test you
Was Ethel purple
Sludge
I think you know he definitely knew this wasn't cleaning
But I think
Possibly because he was interested in Alton painted in in his younger days
He decided to just throwing
This purple sludge away
Without a bit of water to it and then he would defend a piece of cloth
And what he discovered was that he had completely accidentally
Made
A really colorful stand very vibrant purple dye and this was
Incredibly moving parts of lead
To a whole
Revolution
In synthetic dyes
You know what the flip is the first synthetic are they could be manufactured
You're not using any
Natural component so no bugs no fetal snowquill shellfish
And I need just allowed
Purple to be worn by monk
Greatest sex
Society than ever before
Until the invention of Mo
Really just impacted being
Tire textile industry because
Cuz of this possibilities are opened up in order
Official dying inside
The right way to put it
Yeah so they already know you think it would be kind of immediate you think that either the whole world would very quickly
Call Nan if you'll excuse the pun to the value of this
Of this synthetic dye but in fact it took a while
Oh I'm the scientist who quotes and William parking
To persuade
M textile dyes
Did they switch the way forward because they were used to working with
Natural plant
I mean idea of a synthetic doll I was really alien teeth
And it was in fact in a his
Best
Only buddy Hawkins love you by accident
It's because
Keep
Just waited a couple of
Textile mills to use this died and one of them ended up
I'm selling a gown
Two members of royalties are princess Eugenie
I got on in this powerful and then
The real clincher
Was Queen Victoria wore a move down
2hat what if I do to his weddings
Andy Scottsdale greatly reported
In the Press
New color
And it became a complete
Fashion trends
So much so that year off. Queen Victoria had one this down
A substitute Rico English newspaper
Reported that London had become Afflicted with the move measles
So many people wearing this color
I think it was intrigued
Especially by
The color green in your book
Because
It seems like
It is this thing is so fundamental to Nature
It's everywhere
But
It was historically really challenging to make
Could you
Explain why that is
Yasso and Willow
Like you say we
We could look around the world and it seems like there's a lot of green
In Orwell
In fact
It's very difficult to make stable
Vibrant
Green colorants
Either is as pigments
Inpaint but also
In thighs as well
And there was some who
Blesiv adeptus and I'm very often the office to able to make
Vibrant greens with make them by layering various different colors on top of each other
Daya's would have to serve again what would serve several different eye colors which was
Either in the Medieval World The Mixing of dyes is really frowned on
Why is that
It's often because of Guild restrictions
Because they were
Very protective of that Guild skills
I'm so
Daya's
Guild doubt
With words
Indigo blue dyes
Was very reluctant
Tuesday work with yellow coloring
I'm so the mixing of blue and yellow.
Taqueria green what simple machine is is devilish already transgressed
Save in many ways
Amazing it is like something that you know any kid
With paint
Knows how to do
Almost
Yeah it is an old one and it's one of those things right
You suddenly realize how
A way you are for the people you're studying
When you're reading these these documents you're looking at these kind of debate surrounding it and then prosecution's you're the prosecution of
People making green cloth
Two artists were able to find good Reds and could yellows but greens were
Define how did they end up
Finding the right
Bright green turf
Painting
He hasn't said greens were Lucifer's some artists were able to create
Vibrant greens by
Using condom
Intermediary
Maison dinner with a real kind of trade skill it was a closely guarded
Secrets by some artist
Secret today I agree in their ability to create the
Peaceful colors
Put that on
Sweetie very many
Staples
Natural
Green pigments
Fitts Auto
Have access
Which meant that when they started being created in the
Unirush of of Mew
Chemicals in
Experimentation
In the 19th century
The creation of new greens that would take out really rapidly
How much
Stooped
Cast
Why she was contained
In these greens
In particular
A green called
She was Green
Could you tell us about the uptake of that and the horrible effects
Yeah so this was created by a
Swedish
Scientist
In 1775
And
Because there was
Death of
Bright green pigment
It's on the market in this was relatively
Cheap
It got taken up by artists
Wallpaper manufacturers and
Dressmakers
Incredibly quickly
Well within a decade it was kind of everywhere
One of my favorite stories is that
The writer Charles Dickens
Came back from a trip to Naples where he seen a lot of the screen
Being used
And decided that he's going to decorate his entire house
This is one particular shade of green
Peter from the basement to the Attic
I'm very lucky for him and fast
I have never ran into his work his wife
Dissuaded him
I said that she thought it was disgusting,
And he ended up not
Erasing his entire house
This particular
Drawfee
Emerald green
Luckily for us because it was
Discovered is pigment that was made
Live from off neck
Was really poisonous or could be really poisonous
It was found that
In samples of wallpaper that we know any few inches across
Contains enough off Nick to kill
Two adults one of the industry's
The screen was really
Popular in with the artificial flower industry because of Syracuse tips
Paint the
The stems and under the leaves of these artificial flowers
Goku's Matilda
He was quite young athletes 2018-19
Started working at a special flower factory and very quickly became very ill
A doctor in London that started looking into the causes of this because
You know she had a really disparate array of
Symptoms
And eventually
Discovered that it was the screen colorant but by that time it was faulty late it was
All over the country all over the world that was used in wallpaper and dress fabric
You know you name it
It was it was it was painted this
United off Nick Laden
Green but one of the most
Famous
Supposed
Victims
The screen
Napoleon
It was found
Couch off to his death
That was
Quite a lot of green in the wallpaper that was used to decorate his room
I just thought for a long time that this arsenic green might have contributed to his death
Subsequent
Task
About to be shown
Remember to find some samples of his hair
Throughout his life goodness and he knows how
But they test movies
I found that we had really high off Nick levels throughout his life
And it didn't rise
Suspiciously
Just before his death
I'm old I'm sure
Peter being in a room
Covered with with Asatru paper contacts helped his gun
Is Health one little bit
Strange things I think
You learn
Reading your book
Is
The place of blue
In history
How popular was blue in
So now it's one of the most
Popular if not the most
Popular color
Globally among men and women
And it
Conniff and seen as being
Inspiring trust and confidence in
All good things
And you kind of
You're tempted to kind of push.
Into history but in fact
If you look at the ancient world and I'm kind of really up until
14th century
Leucine
Unlucky
Uncouth
Unfashionable Associated the code of barbarism
Sticky in the west disses in West Des Moines West
It was only with the kind of the rise of the cult of the Virgin Mary
In Christianity
Because she was partly
Depicted wearing
Bibliocommons
That blue becomes assertive have this car
Cultural
Resurgence in in Western thought and suddenly became
Pretty quickly
A real
Carla decided to the picture wearing blue
Who made that decision to change the world
Yes it's coming around about the same time that because of the Virgin Mary was crying
Vu
Of this Petit
Takeda pigments
I'm altering which
Made from lapis lazuli
Was growing and being caught
Affected
And again because it was this really
Vivid
Color
I was incredibly
Expensive
It became a way of autists and patrons
A showing that Devotion to the Virgin Mary
By depicting her in this Redux
Expensive
Luminous
Pigments
It came from a very long way away and I even its name Ultra ultramarine comes from Ultra and Moravian
On the sea the people itself
Amazing me
Exotic connotation
And that became bound up with the coastal Edge Mary and the two kind of
Bounce.
Each other
Booty challenge
I'm in a funny sort of way
Could you describe
How old is Marine
Was made
Sure
So many people are familiar with with lapis lazuli which is the
Semi-precious stone is the color of the raw material for making all terrain at Conifer
I really am
Colchester
Please stay that use the law in injury and kind of looks a little bit like tonight
Skype is really deep blue
And it often has kind of Trace reserve of white and black clouds
Elusive
He often contained little pieces of Fools Gold that looks a bit like
Stars
Esri 3D Pisa
I'm in order to get from this very gorgeous
Semi-precious Stone
To a pigment
Takes an awful lot of hard work
Des Moines
Afghanistani Minds with the lapis lazuli I came from wearing
Creditview remote
Stream would have to be loaded on
Two donkeys and camels
Take it across
So creep to the coast of the Mediterranean put on ships
And they usually fat shop in in Venice
What you said of the
Supports where so many
Luxury goods
Came into Europe
And1
An artist who bought his his pieces
Pavlakis La-Z-Boy
The work was still
Awesome Ava Stein had to be ground down to a powder
And then I have to be purified those bits of fools gold and the white
Traceries I mentioned in the original stud hats those elements
To be removed
Because they
Tons the blue color
Adult
And the way that was done
Is the blue
How did blue stone
Would be mixed
With mastic wax
And then it would be needed almost like yourself needing a dough to make bread
It is solution of of lie
And as the door was was needed and the flakes of blue
Which I'm full out
To the bottom of the LIE solution
I need them be up to tip off the lie and you have blue bright blue sediment
The contender
Be used
App to create an amazing pigment
Ultramarine that was just beloved of artists
I'm in
Medieval artist and Artisan the Renee
Plus
Pigments that was used
During this time and very often when you see
Painting of the Virgin Mary she'll be
Swayze
Kelly Clarkson and usually doctor who painted
Using ultramarine
The root of one of my favorite
Kind of color facts
Which is that Tina will there now we think of
Pink is being
Musicals
Please
Is being for boys
In fact if you were to go back to the
Adjustable air force entry a century-and-a-half
It was the other way around pink and and was so seeing his pale red and was much more associate
Did with boys
And blue because it's a station with the Virgin Mary
Racine is the most feminine and dainty color
The process
Extracting and purifying
Colors seem so
So arduous in
It speaks to the desire for the end product
But they would go through
You such a pervert
Try to create it
YouTube identify
Like real human Pursuit
Of like
Basically
Food shelter in the brightest color imaginable
Going to be this part of ingrained in our DNA
Yeah we we we love
Shiny
Bright colors and we are prepared to do all sorts of
When wonderful things to you
Orange because I need to know once and for all
What came first
Set the color with app
Fruit came first
Yeah it's a freak came came fast and got it
Traveled across the Wild Roots its name and it's
Color with it
Which is rather nice butt
In the English language
Oranges called oranges
Eudoxie cool yellow red
Which kind of makes sense but isn't
Yeah
Is a bit long-winded
So what's up Broadway
About the color
I think people think a black is one thing but they're a lot stiffer
Shades of blue
Fox could you describe
What black is
Yes it's it's a it's a funny thing that he got into a paint shop wall
You know clothing store
You can find
So many
Hundreds thousands of variance
Of white
And we can call them
Cream ivory
Lots of different names for them
And yet we just have collapse
So many
Duffel blog
Into one
Fairy
Big overarching
Label
I'm in fact
Rock has many different
Subtleties
Thailand United as as white does
And yet we just don't we all
A vocabulary
O Block
Israeli
Cool
And it was what was one of the colors I was most worried about when I was writing the book I was like
Am I going to get to this one chapter and just have nothing to say
I found completely the opposite I found
I became
Frustrated I wanted
People of the past
To have been as
Excited about
Glock
As if they were about
Redsan
Please take it seemed to me that I was
Richness
But it seemed a shame
The we'd be nice to have the vocabulary takes it to do it just
Quotes when you talked to earlier about
Zod arrival of Mo
For the arrival of
Green
Into the world
How the world
Bloated with a
Excitement
And how
Amazing is I think of
Discovering Racine colorful
The first time
This the closest
Analog I can come to
Is when I saw Manta
Which almost breaks your brain without blockage
Can you describe what vantablack is
And and how you encountered
Yeah so I guess
He's pretty start with the name vantablack it sounds to the ferry space-age but actually it's kind of it comes from a useful
I'm acronym
Devonte stands for vertically aligned nanotube
Array
And essentially
Vantablack
Is
It's not really a color it's more of a
Substance
Absorb
Moonlight
Anything else
On Earth
And that is because of its structure because of these but Caroline Chu
Tiny tiny tiny Cinema
Carbon fiber
Delight
Get Skyrim sword
Between and amongst
These fibers
And count get out
Get trapped
I'm so very little light is reflected
What did they make
What it was created for, released
Specific
Episode
I was created for satellite guidance
The idea being that you know
Different satellite TV
Know where it is in
Space
It takes it an image of what it can
See if we're sitting in front of it
Then that can be kind of much. With a map of the sky and then do you know the song
Play what kind of know where it is
And the blocker that you can get the internal working
Around the
Have the camera navigation
The bet that because it means says Surplus
Destruction in the image.
Will be clear enough for you.
Bez effect for the satellites navigate
I'm so that's been this
God of creation of super Pacs
Yeah by -7
I'm very sad that people who walk we would stop by SoMo make soft light
A British company
What about of nowhere discovered a much
Blocka blocka
And Eva been discovered
49er Neva Flats about no point notes
I've sent
The visible spectrum
3D is uncannily block
And it's fall to dockets fall to light
Disobeying
Fruit to give on eyes any information about
The kind of environment within so what I mean by that is
When I first saw a sample of antibiotic it was kind of
Grown on two sample of
I'm on sub to a piece
Crumpled up aluminium foil
How many looked at the reverse
You could see all the different planes you could see the discomfort piece of aluminium foil
From the different planes of of light
I'm not give you information about where
Uy relation to the tin foil and
If I was composing an aggressive it
When it was turned over to expose the vantablack coated side
F****** what you sow
Was like a kind of a mistake like an
A black hole
Because
Your eyes aren't being given enough information
So
What you saw was
Even though you knew that this
Piece of aluminium foil was was 3D at your house
The Contours
You couldn't
Define that
Legacy West
A box
Hole
And that was in
Creatively on Sunny Place Mesa
Gmod seeing it in a storm full in a lab
Even though I knew exactly what I was going to see I went there expecting it and yes
Daily I couldn't quite wrap my head around it but it really short
Pipa Lite
Start today the scientist who is involved in his creation
And he said he was getting cools from people and soon after it been discovered
Telling him that this creation must in some way be associated with
The devil
Anything
That black gave back that little information to our eyes must
People are intrinsically evil
How much is an oz
Yeah and Olney Jack reaction
In fact you know it's incredible
But it's also
It totally
Harkins back to all these stories that you've told us
But these
Association is Primal associations we have with these colors
It sounds exactly like
You know the
Alchemist
Told that they can't mix blue and yellow or they're doing the work of the devil
Yeah maybe after all
I had a question about the design of the book itself
It's really beautiful
And one of the coolest parts
Is that you have a
The colored stripe
On the edge of the pages
That go with it
Story
But I couldn't help but think about how stressful it must have been
You know you have to be right on the money that you got the right pigment you know in the printing process
You up at night
Yes it did not yet but I'm not going to tell you which color is that gives me this still gives me take this life I have I like my
I had anxiety nightmares
About either people coming at me and say your
Sky blue is wrong or whatever it is I just don't know no
Get myself into so much trouble at the end what was say stupid is that the apostles the argument of the book is that there is no
True ultramarine
Colors of
Cultural creations and they kind of Shifting all the time
Tectonic plates
Color is not precise
Spangs it's changing its living it's constantly being redefined and argued over
And I'm not part of the magic over that part of why I loved it but it was a part of why
I'm it is infuriating and particularly when you find yourself
Definition of having to choose
MAA the right color feeds and every page of your book you end up
Finding the hole
Completely ridiculous then and then casting the Fatiha
Winston car in the fast life
Final story from Kelsey St Clair
About the color blue
An art forgery
And not
When we come back
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of sun
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights.
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
Most amazing stories of art forgery
Here again
Is gasia Saint Clair
Just after the second World War
A lot of people in Europe were being
Prosecuted for collaboration and collaborated with the Nazis
During the war
Whipping invest
Tasted and one of those
I'm was an art dealer
Cools and Van meegeren
Who has sold an overdose of canvases
The Miz and embarrass other
I autistic
To your Nazi collectors uneven
Kalafina Hitler's R&R collection
Itself
The prosecution should have began of this
Basaltina
And he turned around and said actually
You know you should be prosecuting me
You should think of me as a hero because
Far from selling out
You're amazing. Shown dolls to the Nazi
I was actually doing if I was
You're creating these
Masterpieces
From scratch I'm a Fool J
I was never selling for me is to the Nazis
I was just ripping them off
He made a fortune
Cheering
United States. Made
I think the modern figure is somewhere in the region of around 33
$1000000 the heat made
By selling these
Then I suppose it all wet
I found himself and it's really odd position
According to Kant
Proved he was guilty of forgery
In order to prove that he was innocent of
Collaboration
Honesty
Pigments that eventually kind of
Proof that he had forged these pictures
Which by this time we're in
Your Uber has the most well-respected
Art galleries all over Europe heat full dinner floor FIFA
Is the Nazis
The pigment that this will turn Don was
Cobalt blue
Because
It had been discovered a long time off
Ipomoea staff
And yet was discovered
To have been used in this one particular
Ephemere
Fake for me that he had created
And so he managed
Proof that he was
Guilty of forgery because of the presence
Cobalt blue
Where in fact
Kid meant to you
Ultramarine
What's a good
Well this is so much fun thank you so much
I enjoyed it immensely
My cousin is pretty great fun
99percentinvisible with Presa Suite by Emmett Fitzgerald
Music by Shawn meow
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kolstad use the digital
Director
Russell team includes senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery trufelman
Turn master Joe Rosenberg Vivien Leigh
Syracuse
Sofia klatzker and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Lowe's in all upon cast
Find mall
Radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show enjoying scussion about the show on Facebook you can't we me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Instagram Tumblr animated to
You can probably surmised
Joey's favorite color
At 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm Evan I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com