99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Let me give you these thank you
Learn
Ear plugs
Let me take you back
Back to a simpler time
The year
What is this
So this is recycle Central
To stay large
A recycling plant where we sort all the materials from the blue band the bottle
Cans with paper
In 2016 producer Avery trufelman was working on a story about garbage and recycling pickup systems its episode
But don't worry this is not a rerun
The story is different
Back then to that story in 2016 I took a tour of the plant
That's sort all of San Francisco's recycling
We do 600 tons a day here
That's Robert Reed the representative for San Francisco Recology
Which is the company that is responsible for San Francisco's recycling
Their trucks Roundup all the recycling around the city
And bring it
To immerse
Murph
Mrf
Materials recovery facility
At the Murph
The trucks dump all their cycling into a big mountain
And then the wild park again
This particular Murph in San Francisco
Has all this elaborate Machinery that looks like it's out of a Miyazaki movie
UCI recycling superstructure
Three stories high
Pretty shortly
The conveyor belt to start up or going to sort all this
Material here in the 16 different types of material
This three-story tall superstructure and the 173 people that were working on it
We're separating
Cleaning the recycling
Starting at the glass paper plastic
Separate
Is there a combination of
Hand sorting and Modern Recycling equipment
Modern Recycling equipment like
The optical sorter that can automatically separate different color plastic
Right here
The scanners looking at the materials as they come by and when it sees a
Clear plastic like a clear plastic water bottle
Hitler was a puff of air
Can you can hear it
Spencer the first 3 million dollars for this machine and it came from the Netherlands
And at the time
In 2016 when I was younger and things were simpler
I'm quite grasp
The simple fact
Actually recycling anyting
Do not turning the paper into pulp or melting down the plastic and appellate
The Murph workout
Simply sorting and
Cleaning all the materials
They were loading bales
Clean recycling onto shipping container
So they could sell them to millswood then pulp the paper and melt the plastic
And I was just like okay cool
And left well enough alone
I just figured all those Mills and plants would always be there
Wherever they were
Waiting to accept our stuff
How could I have known
But in the near future
This Global Recycling system
Would go off the rails
It happened right under our noses
And most people
Macleamy don't marry recently
Had no idea
The industry has been using the phrase the end of recycling as we know it
Kate O'Neill is an associate professor in the department of environmental science policy and management at UC Berkeley
And she kinda freaked me out
Yeah you know I would say for a lot of
Stuff that we turn to the recycling it's not happening
A lot of recycling is no longer
Actually getting recycled
The list of accepted materials are shrinking in some cities
Depending on where you live certain types of plastic are being collected anymore maybe certain kinds of paper or cardboard
In many communities
Barack Obama sister picking up recycling
Does in the general trash
Even if they do collect it
Without a hard time finding places to ship it
Instead of making money selling recycling recycling companies are losing money on it
Now that someone take it
Skip the store it yes because they lost their biggest buyer
The place America and much of Australia and Europe in Canada huge amount
Cycling
This magical land where your empty plastic bottles in Old Soup cans went to be reincarnated
Was China
They will taking most of the wealth
China has been taking most of the world scrap since about
2001 which is around the time China joined the World Trade Organization
That's only really ramped up selling Goods all over the world
In massive shipping containers
And
Rather than send the containers back empty
We sent them back
Filled with
Recycling
Which was actually really cost-effective
What's cheaper to ship
Trip from California to China than California to even Arizona potentially
And the system seemed to work well
Cities could subsidize their recycling pickup program
From the money they made
Selling these materials to China
And then they didn't need to process the materials themselves
Capitalism at work
We basically assholes we gave up on even trying to
Improve infrastructure here because witches
China
And it seemed like a logical
As long as China kept wanting to buy a recycle
But then
China pulled a move that no one saw coming
Operation National
Sword
A pretty aggressive name for a piece of recycling legislation
Basically national sword is China's ban on the import of foreign recyclables
It started in 2018
And a list of banned items
Steadily grown
It has the potential of banning all recyclable materials by 2020
We don't know if that'll happen or not
It's hard to pinpoint exactly why China got fed up with this system all the sudden
There are number of factors you can point to but a lot of experts think it's because
Abba movie
This Chinese documentary
Plastic China
Buy director wangjing
It focuses on this insanely cute little girl whose family works at a plastic recycling facility
She never gets sent to school
Because she's helping her parents watch her younger siblings
And sort through mountains
Shredded plastic
They're cutting up plastic melting it soaking it and turning it into a sludge
And then turning that into hardened appellate
The little girl watches her face in the grape last
Sticky water
And it's fish that have choked on plastic
This family lives with the shredding machine
They eat and sleep near it
Inhaling
The dust of microparticles that come off during the shredding Pro
Process
The fumes from the melting process is a lot of bad stuff that
And all the plastic
It's all clearly from Western countries
A little girl longingly cuts out shoes from a discarded European catalog
And gleefully plays with dirty old figurines of Mickey Mouse
It is
Absolutely heartbreaking
And it broke alot of hearts on the International Film Festival
Target and then it was also shown in China for a while and get caught in the internet there
The government start in Yankton
Chinese internet wehunt
Keep doing that
Really
Yes
Yes I believe it did
Causation or correlation it was after this documentary that China instituted operation National
Sword
China realize that they needed to crack down on these informal recycling plants
And don't say sufficient
Recycling systems
They want to improve their own domestic recycling rates
Center cities and towns
A lot of work to do
I need more than enough stuff to recycle without taking on more from other countries
So they decided to stop accepting our recyclables
What I mean
Turn up it's a good move for them
I think China was no longer interested in being
But never really wanted to be but
Felt like it was being seen as the garbage dump
You know it's not its responsibility to taken all about trash got a point
And so now here we are
Blinking into the cold harsh light of 2019 national sword has been in action for about a year
Here now
Some people call it a crisis I just don't like the word crisis by that's where we are
That is unless you are a dedicated reader of waste dive
Waste time is triplication we cover the the waste recycling industry
Just generally the future of what happens to the materials we buy and throw away
Cool rosengrant is the senior editor
And reading waste dive
It's like reading the news from the upside down
It's a parallel world where the things we do in the realm of the shiny and new
Are perfectly reflected
In the grimy and used
Because we systems are affected by so many fans
Local resources Global policy packaging and product Trends new material technology on and on
It's a whole complex system
Especially in the US
Super complicated so more complicated than it ought to be
In the United States
Recycling programs very
Depending on individual cities
Counties in States
We don't have a national
Recycling policy other countries
Dune the right away sir in the US we do not
So in the wake of national sword it's been up to
Each individual recycling program
Find new buyers
Wherever they can
Summer started selling the recyclables
Southeast Asia
Countries like Vietnam and Malaysia and Thailand
Others are finding domestic Market
At least for certain material
With a woman with plastic and paper mills you know there's there are places in the US
Descendants that will buy this material to making products
And so
With that in mind areas of the country that have an End Market and reasonable distance
They doing okay
And now there's a big push to invest more in domestic recycling infrastructure
Which is good
There's over a dozen announcements of either
New expanded paper towels happening in the US
But here's the thing
All these new plastic glass and paper mills will not save us
Because now they are getting so inundated with recyclables
That they're increasingly putting their own restrictions on what kind of materials they are willing to accept
And there's a good reason why all these places started turning away our recycling
The stuff we've been sending them was too dirty so much of what we
Throw into the recycling bin is filthy contaminated with liquids or food waste oil
And this kind of contamination just ruins material
So if you're the anal one in your house was renting the yogurt out of the yogurt containers before you throw them out you are right
You are doing it right
But most people haven't been doing it right
I've been pretty high in the Risen in the past 10 years or so
As a result a lot of the stuff we were throwing in the recycling bin was never truly recyclable material in the first place
It was just
Trash
A lot of time it just ended up in landfill or incineration
Operation national sword didn't create these problems
I just revealed them
And then through the back
Well
Mostly through them at the Murph
They're the ones with the heaps and heaps
Useless recycling piling up
Wondering where to put it
It's been a minute since we spoke last
Happened
Yeah so I check back in with Robert Reed
Representative of San Francisco Recology who showed me around their plan
Back in the good old days
The 2016
What's been going on
The lots of things
If you lose your biggest customer
It really upsets the apple cart
Read explained that now and it's new buyer's market
Mills are only accepting the most
Easily recyclable items
Which means the items that are almost
Perfectly
Pure
Clean those efforts underway to reduce liquids
In any food scraps
In recycling bins
It's a Recology has been investing more and more and sorting and cleaning technology to make sure they can keep selling
Which means
They bought more Optical sorters
As we speak we're installing
State-of-the-art
Optical sorters
In our plants
It came from France
They now have seven
High-speed computer-controlled Optical sorters
Big machines
Do the work that we don't want to do
But also the murph's want us there consumers to send them cleaner recycling which would make recycling
Less expensive and more efficient for everyone
We're doing things to encourage
The public
To help us
Make cleaner bales of recycle
And so we've launched a new initiative in October called better at the bin
All of us doing a better job at sorting are recyclable
We call this initiative
Better at the Ben
Recology postings
High production value videos on their social media and on better at the ben.com
To try to convince everyone to take these little steps to be better recyclers
A point hostel bottle or can get stuff in the recycling bin
The liquid can ruin the whole lot
Remember reduce reuse recycle
Somewhere along the way
We totally lost track of reduce and reuse and focused too much
On Recycle
Refuse single-use plastic
Plastic bags and plastic coffee cup lids don't buy plastic water bottles carry a metal water
Replace
Yes
This is 100% true
We definitely have got to get better about generating less waste
And cleaning what we do recycle
But this alone is
Simplifying the real complexity of the problem
For example at the end of the interview
Robert Reed pulled out a totally normal-looking tube of toothpaste
You can't recycle this container
Do you still have the metal on the inside the soft plastic on the outside the hard plastic neck
Can tap into residual toothpaste on the inside not to mention the
Four five materials here
Do they all go to landfills are in
And then he pulled up the small aluminum can
And I'm opening it up and inside there's a
Hake
Toothpaste
What's a dry cake
It last for 45 days
And at the end of those 45 days
You just drop another cake
Into
The aluminum jar
I mean can you buy them in the states
I haven't been able to find them in the states yet
This one
Was purchased in
France
This struck me as
Fairly ridiculous
How
Are we supposed to buy cakes of toothpaste from France that we don't know exist
I don't like shipping toothpaste across the Atlantic is exactly environmentally friendly
Again
Absolutely true we need to get better at using less
Recycling and researching what are local systems will except
Definitely
Like
We throw out a lot of junk
Because we are sold
A lot of junk
So much
Problem
Is about the products we are sold and have access to
I just getting fed up with the way that we talk about our pollution problem
Matt Wilkins is a biologist
You are a piece for Scientific American about our current recycling
We should not have to fight as individuals against this constant onslaught of plastic
Take for example the term litter box
You don't want to be a litterbug right
The problem
It's not the fact that we have this unfettered production of
Billions of containers happening at all times and no infrastructure to reclaim this
Materials
And that nickname
Litterbug
It was popularized in large part
My group called keep America beautiful
Lobbying group keep America beautiful
Founded by
Pepsi and Coke
And Philip Morris
Among others
Keep America beautiful was formed in 1953
Around the same time Vermont was creating legislation way ahead of its time
It would have made it illegal to bottle anything in a non-refillable container
Of course
The beverage industry was against it
They wanted to frame the problem of waste
A something that should be dealt with
Not by companies
But by consumers
You know
Schlitterbahn
Keep America beautiful was essentially a lobbying group
But it's masterstroke
In consumer Shaymin came in 1971
When they rolled out
A very
Persuasive
Advertising campaign
Yeah the crying
Indian ad
Was
Basically they're there is a Native American canoeing through like a pristine Forest which is apparently right next
Dual Highway
And he
He paddles right up to the bank of the highway and climbs out and then people are speeding by and then
Motorists Life as we had some with a bag of trash and then the camera pans up
There's a tear rolling down his
Cheek
The sad witch
Featured an Italian actor playing a Native American
Became iconic
But it's basic lesson wasn't exactly wrong
But the ad made it seem that
The longest consumer stop littering
All of our garbage Rosewood besaw
Which of course is not true
It let the corporations that we're making all those disposable items off the hook
Although to be fair this is not exactly their stance anymore
Only a few years after the crying Indian ad
Keep America beautiful change their tune
So they actively
Bought this legislation in a public way I think up until the early 80s
And then they kind of switch tactics
And have basically since then
Just been kind of getting in on the Earth Day push and
You're telling people to recycle and
Organizing cleanups and stuff
Representatives from keep America beautiful told me that
They now advocate
Recycling legislation
And that their corporate Partners want to do their part
Jesus
Especially in the shadow of national sword
Corporations and governments have had to acknowledge this
Scale of our recycling problem
A very public way
We are gathered here today to advance solutions to today's recycling challenges
That's the voice of Andrew wheeler
Former coal industry lobbyist and current acting administrator of the environmental
Protection Agency
In November of 2018
PPA convened a two-hour-long panel discussion
In an attempt to attempt to deal with the Fallout
National sword
We cannot tackle these challenges alone
Which is why we are thrilled to have representatives from nearly every aspect
Of the materials economy
Gathered here today
At this little round table
All the biggest names in the recycling world
From Waste Management to Walmart
Sad every day that you get Keurig and Starbucks and Coca-Cola Pepsi and Dr Pepper all in the same room together
And I'm really glad you're all here
Keep America beautiful is there
Culver's in Grand was also there in the room
Covering it for waste.
Tennessee Phi Beta be so flippant about that maybe it does
Happy quote
Basically each representative had like less than one minute to speak and everyone mentioned a million different problems with our recycling system
But
There was a butterfly
At the bottom of Pandora's Box
The common refrain at companies recyclers and municipalities alike
All mentioned
Consumers look for us to give them sustainable products
Design the right way
Yes dear listener one of the most important solutions to our recycling woes
Actually laying
Design
At the EPA meeting the representatives from Procter & Gamble talked about their award-winning container made out of plastic
Cleaned up from the beach
What we do with a head and shoulders bottle as we took the iconic white bottle
Will use plastic collected from beaches
And it became Gray
But we sold it that way and consumers bought it
Okay so this was a limited edition product
And I could you not
Is only available in France
Dammit France
But
Appointed
That kind of packaging is possible
These companies have the capacity
And the technology
Wechat ask for it
I think another thing that we can do is demand better design of
Everything
With
The end of life
Planned from the beginning
Matt Wilkins the biologist again
And better design Camina couple of things
Jessica means finding new ways to use recycled materials like that gray Head and Shoulders bottle
Or at the very least it can be making products
Really easy and efficient
To recycle
Everything should be able to
Break down into its composite materials and separate them
In a way that doesn't introduce impurities so they can be used to
And designers can and should visit murph's and Mills
They should know how their products and packaging sort
Weirdo
What is a breakdown
Or don't break down
Designers can also use biodegradable materials
Or materials like aluminum that recycle more easily than plastic
The ideal thing
Is to design products
Or even parts
The products
But don't need to be thrown away at all
The sound
And that you design
Things that can be repaired
Let your toothbrushes
Yeah
Cell phone
That you can swap components in and out of
The Berkeley Professor Kate O'Neill says yes
Companies have to design Greener products
But then the next step is that this shouldn't just be specialty items
That should be the norm
I guess people have the label on it so people who are
Environmentally conscious will buy it
Turns out it might mean the people who don't care what by
What do it seems like a kind of paradox where were saying like
You know don't blame the consumer there's a whole world of influences but also like it's up to us
To harness the power of capitalism
And to send the market to our our will as as people who
We spend money
Yep which also it would also seems like it's putting the onus kind of back on the consumer now
Welsummers that was a thing
Not just consumers but how we Act
The citizens
So listen
In the course of researching the story
I had various freak-outs
At one point I was defiantly tossing my aluminum cans in the trash like
Wake up sheeple recycling isn't real
True
Don't do what I did
Instead
Ask around
And find out what is happening to the recycling where you live
This is a system that has been kept deliberately invisible
For the sake of our convenience
We need to learn how to notice it
Really think
About how our stuff is made
Going
When we throw it
Away
Operation national sword could be a wake-up call
But only if everyone
Can hear it
Okay you might be skeptical that design can really make a difference and recycling but I assure you it can not just product
Design but systems design
Take for example Taipei
The capital of Taiwan
They became one of the cleanest cities in the world in only a few years
By using
Singing garbage trucks
MapleStory
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
At the top of the show I reference in episode that Avery reported back in 2016 we called it
Separation anxiety
People really loved it
So if you missed it back then here it is now
Enjoy
If you could recognize any piece of classical music
I bet it's this one
This is chi release
Written by Ludwig van Beethoven in 1810
Maybe it reminds you of piano lessons you took when you were a kid
In my town it was also the song the ice cream truck used to play
That's pretty sure Avery truffle
But if you live in Taiwan
And you hear a truck rumbling down the street playing Fearless
It doesn't mean it's time to buy a popsicle
It means it's time to take out your trash
Because this is what a garbage truck in Taiwan sounds like
This garbage truck song isn't just supposed to be cute and fun
Although it is also supposed to be cute and fun
The singing garbage trucks
Are all a part of a completely different way of thinking about waste disposal completely different.
That is from the way that we think about it in the United States
In the late 1990s Taiwan recycled only 5% of its waste
Today Taiwan recycles well over
The country is now among the world's top recyclers
And what changed in this. Has a lot to do with the way that the trash is collected
Okay Fearless isn't the only song the trucks play
In Taipei the capital of Taiwan the trucks
Also play this song
That's a maiden's Prayer by Polish composer tekla baidu zuzka Baranowski
In Taipei City the garbage trucks just alternate between these two song
Protectors to pledges to songs
Stop music.
Taipei City
Given the elementary school kids can sing the song
So we have brainwashed
This is dr jasmine Wang
And she grew up in Taipei
Since I was a child
I knew that every time when the garbage truck
Cubs
Now the singing garbage trucks are such a part of life it's hard to imagine a time before then
But that time actually wasn't too long ago
We used to have a lot of a big dumpster
So there was a lot of rats mosquitoes and
Despite that and it's not good for our house
Just a couple of decades ago type a residence through their trash into massive smelly dumpsters on the street
Garbage would end up in piles on the sidewalk and then Park
Food faster in the heat
It was just nasty
Then taiwan's democratization accelerated in the mid-1980s
And created this desire to tidy up
Modern country means being a clean country
And when you have foreign visitors coming and visiting your Capital they shouldn't think
This is Mary Alice a.
Charity East Asian studies at Wesleyan University
In Taiwan the
Pro-democracy movement
Got fully entangled with the environmental movement and so as all those things move together in the state
The pro-democracy and pro-environment
Agendas got on to the public
Consciousness
Also the environmental movement had a practical end
Taiwan was running out of space to actually put piles of trash
Because it's a small island and extremely popular
Small island
There's not that much space where does you're going to stick all your junk
Where is in the United States there has been historically a sense of the
Untamed untappd
Endless
Wilderness
And you could just
Throw your junk Into the Wilderness and it would go away and you wouldn't have to worry about anymore
Not true in Taipei
The big city but it's
Clean in the subways
The cleaning
Sores are clean in the sidewalk so clean and it
It's really Pleasant to be there
You never know that the city used to have piles of garbage littering the streets
Type A and A number of other Taiwanese City
Reduce the amount of trash by changing the way the trash got collected
Take a look at my garbage
This is my friend Aaron Newport
She lives in Taipei
Where the garbage truck comes five nights a week
EBay like after work
It comes Monday Tuesday Thursday Friday and Saturday
In Aaron's neighborhood trucks come twice in the evening
At 5 and at 7
Take out the trash like once a week on one of their
Usually once I mean it's kind of hard sometimes to find the time
To always be home at 5
5 / 7
Erin has to gather her own garbage and recycling and bring it out to a designated street corner and wait
For the big yellow truck to come
Frontier Park for the sound
MP release or maiden's prayer coming down the block
Basically this is a bindless system garbage can with system your trash goes right from your house to the
Truck ideally without ever touching the street
You just have to bring out your garbage
A special bag
I pay my garbage
Bill
By purchasing these
Blue tie dye
City garbage bags these official blue garbage bags
Pay city of Taipei
I eat is emblazoned with
I buy them from the convenience store across
The official blue garbage bags come in a number of different sizes ranging from 3L to 120
Lemoore garbage you throw away the Mortal costume
And although Taipei residents have to pay for their garbage by the bag
Recycling and compost
Are free
You don't need to buy bags for them at all
You can just take out your recycling in non-official plastic bag
And you can generate as much compost and recycling as you'd like
So residents are incentivised
Is to recycle more and throw out less
OS Aaron sort out all of her recyclables
The perfect
Categories
He said the cans
Cans and bottle so we have a few tea bottles
So in Taipei every yellow garbage truck is followed by small white recycling truck
Was basically a cart full of different bands
There's a bin for plastic bottles
Lowe's 1/4 glass bottles
Different Metals in cans
Papers and cardboard
The compost bucket for raw food waste
In a compost bucket
Cooked food weigh
Taipei residents have to sort their recycling into all these different categories themselves
Although in the white recycling trucks there are officials and volunteers
Who can help instruct you about which item goes where
So Aaron her housemates and I got all of her bags of trash and different kinds of recycling sorted out
And then we walked about a block down the street to wait with the rest of her neighbor
Who are all clutching official blue garbage
Quite a lot of people gathered
Genesis Maybe
Larger than your average
Then
The moment we were waiting for
There was this Mad Dash of people swarming to the school bus yellow garbage
And the white recycling truck
Okay that's not passing it in
Swiftly tossing their separate recyclables in the bins tossing their blue bags and the garbage truck and running away
It was Madness
Like
Greenlee well-organized Madness
I was so chaotic
And this system for all its chaos has been working
Taipei City used to produce 3296 tons of trash a day
Today the city produces about 1000
What's a day that is according to Chadwick
When it's 65 official
Who supervised the garbage trucks
And the rocks
I met him at a garbage pickups
Where Jasmine Wong acted as interpreter
Eveready listen to mr. 10 and he's his supervisor
In his district 10 overseas 20 garbage truck routes
And all those trucks have to make sure that citizens are sorting properly
If it's a fly the garbage tree in the recycling bag
The people here will tell them that you cannot do that
One more Thai otherwise see you I get tickets
And how much is the ticket 200 US dollars
You might think
This is such a drag
There must be some people who Buck the system by tossing their trash into public trash can
Well there are hardly any public trash cans in Taipei
They're only in train stations or at bus stop
And those are little
Play come up just below your knees
So in Taipei for the most part
If you eat a candy or buy a coffee
You just take your empty coffee
Candy wrapper
Put in your pocket and bring it home
Your trash
That you put in your blue bag
I can bring out to the truck
Yourself
It's hard to imagine a system like this working here in the US
Every city here has a different method of trash pickup
But across-the-board
Uniting factor is that our American trash pickup system strive to be invisible
The trucks made great efforts to come when we're working or sleeping or trying to sleep
Keeping out of the way of traffic and not disturbing the flow of the city
We take our trash and recycling out to Benz or down the Chute or to a dumpster
And it's gone
We don't have to think about
According to the EPA
Americans recycle and compost about 34% of their trash
Which is less than most rich country
But some American cities
Do a lot better
San Francisco has
Probably the most forward
Recycling program in North America this is Robert Reed
Is the representative of Recology
The company that takes care of San Francisco's waste recycling and comp
Unlike type A which has a public trash pickup system
Mini waste pickup services in the US are private companies
And we are the customers
That's how it works with ecology which means
They got to keep their customers happy
Number one Focus
Provide Superior
Summer service
Our next Focus
Chris is stupid
Do as much recycling is
Is possible
And to make recycling easy and convenient
For customers
Recology has set up
Similar incentives to the system in Taipei
What trash pickup is way more expensive than recycling or compost
For example in San Francisco
Recycling and compost cost about $2 a month
Corbin
Trash is about $26 a month
Above all
Ecology system is meant to be
Simple
And stress
It has to
If you want people to keep
Paying for your service
People
I have a lot of demands in their lives we understand that you don't
Recycling might not be the very first thing they got the guy
Make the boss happy to go to pay their mortgage
Garbage and recycling and composting might not always be the top of the list
We understand that
Basically instead of putting the onus on the citizens to separate the different kinds of compost and recycling for themselves
Recology does the brunt of the work
Sorting so we don't have to
San Francisco like a lot of other American cities that collect recycling
Uses one catch-all recycling bin
So you tell your cans or bottles are cardboard all in the same place
And then all those different materials end up in a facility
Like recycle center
Recycle Central
Large
Recycling plant on pier 96
Where we sort all the materials from the blue bin to bottle
Cans with paper
Going to go inside now
The facility is massive
That's where ecology process is most of San Francisco's recycle
Scrapy
Pile of recycling
This is
From this morning
From one day
And we're going to get the
Started out
Because we got another big
Pyle coming in tomorrow so we do 600
Tons a day here
That 600 ton pile will wind its way up a huge
Surreal web of conveyor belt
Where some of the 173 people on staff will separate the recyclables into 16 categories
Materials
With the help of some Modern Recycling equip
So we've got a magnet's and we have fish ladders that separate bottles and cans
Sandpaper
They're on their on an angle and they temporarily
Suspend gravity
Make sure everything gets precisely sorted there's some real state-of-the-art technology
Like this apparatus that separates clear plastic from color plastic with
Optic sensor
Rainier
The scanners looking at the materials they come by and when it sees a
Clear plastic like a clear plastic water bottle
Hitler with a puff of air
And you can hear it
Expensive
$3000000 for this
Shein
And it came from the Netherlands
So this system with all this worrying twirling conveyors and magnets and machinery and 173 employees
Dazzling
Makes less trash by doing more cycling
And
Recycling
Creates ten times more jobs
Stan landfilling
Sonoran sunrise
Of course it also takes all the direct sorting out of the hands of people who actually create the waist
Charges them for the service instead
As a result recycling in the US
And I guess that's part of the problem like to be sent there's pushback in recycling
Which I've seen some of the United States now is often about the cost of a
Costly
And that's true if you're using me single-stream
Prophecies about China
And it was true
The household
That's Professor Mary Alice Haddad
Is your community wants to recycle
All that stuff needs to be separated and sort
Somehow
Whether you use a $3000000 machine from the Netherlands
Or compel an entire sweet potato shaped island of people to stand on the corner at night
The Taipei system is cheap and efficient because the city has conscripted their citizens
It's workers
And it's been successful
Taipei
The great example
A big major
Global
Metropolitan area
That did not have a good garbage collection
System not that long ago
And they have
Completely transformed
And it could be an example for us all
Which is not to say we should necessarily
Copy typing
What's work for them might not work
Work for the US
But consider the American garbage
Seeping around Dawn
Ordering work hours
Trying to be an inconspicuous
Trying to keep trash
Out of sight
Out of mind
You don't really pay attention to it
But
Everyone should
Pay a lot of a
Attention
We have to watch our garbage pile-up in our homes without taking it out to the van
And had to set aside time in our days
The catch the garbage and recycling trucks coming down the street
I bet we produce less drunk
But I also think if I had to hear this song twice a night 5 days a week
I would
Murder
Everybody
You like that story there like three hundred more episodes just like it in the archives even if you read the description of the title you think one
Download it and listen to it anyway because the show is about
Making everyday things interesting
Take the Wheel
Go for it
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman mix into production by Sharif Youssef music
Deshawn real
Katie mingle is a senior producer Kurt cholestatic is the digital Direct
Senior editor Delaney Hall
Ella Fitzgerald. Joel Rosenberg Vivien Leigh Sophia Carpenter and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Zoe Heller the policy director of calrecycle Noah Allman and Randy Hartman keep America beautiful
Greenpeace
Anti-hillary podcast for sounding the alarm about the problem we talked about in the first part of this episode
By sending us her dezeen
Atlas of foreign garbage guava link on the website
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On Radio Road
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most innovate
YouTube shows in all of podcasting
Bunnamour
And radiotopia
Don FM
You can find the show intro in discussions about the show on Facebook you can join me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi or
Instagram Tumblr invited to a great episode from 2016 me to think I really got to go back and listen to
The more the older shows
Well that's good thinking
We got you cover
All the episode of the Rat
MPI
Radio temperature
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com