99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1979
The Los Angeles Dodgers signed and unknown picture from Mexico
Named Fernando Valenzuela
A couple years later 1981
Valenzuela made his major league debut as a starting pitcher
That's producer and Angelina
Vivien Leigh
Valenzuela went on to have one of the most remarkable seasons in the history of baseball
This obscure player from Sonora Mexico
Became the first player ever to win both the Cy Young Award
Rookie of the Year in the same season
Valenzuela live the Dodgers all the way to the World Series
When he defeated the New York Yankees
Fernando Valenzuela 249 pitcher tonight
The season will always be remembered in Los Angeles as the year of Fernando Mania
The whole city fell in love with Valenzuela
Any particular always large Mexican-American community
We actually had someone
A real true Mexicana playing baseball
No major league team
This is Edward Sunday on La native and longtime Dodgers
And it was in Los Angeles and Eugene as you know
The LA is is
Is so big and it's full of Latinos were all struggling to Jamaican in this
This world end
He actually made it and he made everybody proud
Edward says it was nothing quite like watching a game at Dodger Stadium when Valenzuela with pitch
We would take younger kids that couldn't afford
To go to the Dodger game with me I'll get tickets and and take them and and
Haven't experienced the
The cheering and that you know fernandomania and Venezuela and cheering and training
Screaming for him so it was it was a good time it was fun
But not everybody in Edwards family wanted to go see Fernando's famous
Screwball and act
How many older folks especially were hesitant to make the Trek to Dodger Stadium
It was just
The younger generation that would would go with us
I don't know there was still a little bit of animosity towards the Dodgers for for what happened
What transpired up at Chavez Ravine
Chavez Ravine was a neighborhood where Edwards father Lewis grow up
I didn't used to sit exactly where Dodger stadium is
Today
Back in the 1950s
The community at Chavez Ravine with
It's placed in a contentious battle to reshape what the city would look like
Because back then
Los Angeles wasn't known as the
Sprawling World Center it is today
Here since the turn of the century
Has grown from a sleepy Pueblo
Seething Metropolitan City
It's an up-and-coming City
But it is not
Really
Sweetly there yet
This is Gerald poder author of the book
City of Dreams
Dodger Stadium and the birth of modern Los and
In the early 20th century
The population of Los Angeles with exploding
People are moving to California
Climate
The jobs in the cheap real estate
It was a city on the rise
Something was missing
When Americans were asked
Talk about the major cities of the
Look up the country
In the 19th
Obviously they would say New York
Are they would say
They might even say Detroit
But they might not say Los Angeles and they might even be amazed to know
How big is City
La didn't have the rose of towering skyscrapers that made New York and Chicago unmistakable
It was missing something else too
Something that was hard to put a finger on
Los Angeles felt more like a collection of neighborhoods than a cohesive City
If you ask me and do we know where they were from
What is insane
Los Angeles
They might say Boyle Heights
Highland Park
If they have any kind of
Civic identity
It's tied to their neighborhood and not know
Necessarily
Tudor City
So there are very very few pieces of what I call citic glue
In Los Angeles
In the 1950s
Very few Municipal Institute
Oceans
That's everyone in the city can identify with
And rally around
In a few city leaders thought if the people of Los Angeles needed something to Rally around
Let's give them
Baseball team
From its Inception
Professional baseball in the US
Play mostly on the East Coast
By 1953 only a couple of teams have ventured west of the Mississippi River
Cardinals
The Browns
But they only made it as far as St Louis which is actually on the Mississippi so barely count
But Los Angeles with a west coast city on the Rhine
And was looking for a way to boost its reputation
And how do you get the reputation will you get the reputation with big splashy acquisitions
Like a major league baseball team when there is no major
Elite baseball
On the West Coast
And so la city leaders began plotting to Laura baseball team out west
One woman named Rosalind Wyman
Even campaign for City Council on the promise to bring a major league team to Los Angeles
It worked
Choose electricity Council it just
22 years old
And as luck would have it for a Roz Wyman and other angelinos desperate for baseball
There's an East Coast team in desperate need of a new stadium
The Brooklyn Dodgers
They were a classic baseball team who have been playing at a classic ballpark
Call David's field
Any state is New Yorkers love to get nostalgic about Queen little Ebbets Field
Right in the heart of Brooklyn
But those who are nostalgic about seeing game at
Pittsfield probably never actually were there
Abbottsfield had a lot of problems
There were columns obstructing the view of the field
Steep climbs the upper deck barely any parking or freeway access and the building itself was falling apart
The team owner Walter O'Malley wanted to build his own modern well-designed stadium in Brooklyn
He even went so far as to hire Buckminster Fuller to Draft plans for a dome to go over the top of the field that would turn
On the stadium into an all-weather facility
You don't usually think of baseball team owners as being friends with that with futurist Architects but
In this case that was
Then that that was what was going on
O'Malley fought for years for his dream of a privately owned Stadium
But there was one very powerful bureaucrats standing in the way
New York Symphony
Master builder
Robert Moses
It just so happened that Robert Moses
Not only didn't like spectator
Sports he thought that spectator sports warraich
Total
Waste of time
And for what he called LaRue
And without Moses's
Support
A new Dodger Stadium in Brooklyn
Basically
Impossible
And O'Malley said well one I'm a brooklynite and I want the
The park to be in Brooklyn if it's in Queens it might as well be ten thousand miles away
O'Malley figured if he couldn't get his dream stadium in Brooklyn
He might as well move the daughter is all the way out
The California
Roz Wyman in the city council
Invited O'Malley out to Los Angeles
He had by my estimation and spent a total of
10 days
In his entire life
In Los Angeles
He doesn't really know where he wants to build a deal
Yet to come to Los Angeles but he's scouting it out
Decided to take a helicopter ride across the city to get a feel for the area
And he saw something that caught his eye
What look like an empty piece of land
Just a few miles from downtown
This hilly area was called Chavez Ravine
The thing that he sees is all the vacant land around Chavez Ravine
But it was surrounded by the freeways
This is Mark's Landing
The official historian for the LA Dodgers
He says that the freeways made the side of healing because it meant that fans would have
Easy access to the stadium
The train was really hilly
And we would need to do a huge amount of work
Flatten out the land
It was all worth it because of the highway Acts
He even estimated the amount of
Land that would have to be moved
That didn't bother him because it's easy to move that land but it's hard to build three or four different freeways
Broomelli probably didn't realize that the plot of land that he had his eye on
Wasn't completely empty
There were a few families living in Chavez Ravine
I've been there a long time and if the Dodgers were going to build a stadium there
They'd have to kick those people out
And it wouldn't be the first time
But the people of Chavez Ravine
Have been forced
To leave their home
O'Malley thought he saw a vast
Empty stretch of land from the helicopter
But what he was really saying we're the last legs of a community that had existed there since the early 1900s
In for a long time
It was a neighborhood full of life
It was very colorful
Because the ladies
Had
Colorful birds
Canaries were big I mean
Atwood wake us up canaries in the morning singing
And it was just a very colorful
Community
This is Carol Hawkins
Yes my name is Carol Hawkins
And it's spelled
Jacquees
Carol is 76 years old now and still lives in Los Angeles
And as a little girl she grew up in Chavez Ravine
I know you said you're pretty young when you left
I'm so as much as you can remember I'm out so I can remember a lot
Okay
Carol was only nine or ten years old when her family left Chavez Ravine
But our memories are crystal clear
I was very rude
So we could always see the trees
And at that time when I was growing up anyway
At this time of year there always be like
When you woke up
Chavez Ravine with like a small town within the city
It was home to mostly Mexican and Mexican-American families
Was made up of three different neighborhoods called
Palo Verde
Paloma in Bishop
Some roads were paved but most boring
Water pump at electricity but some didn't
In its own way though it was still a flourishing closely knit community
We're like any other neighborhood we had some people that we're doing very well
There was some families that were very
Or
There was some families that were not so nice
There was some families that were very religious
But they were all still
Friends and everybody knew each other
Chavez Ravine was located just a few miles
Bus from downtown Los Angeles
But it felt like
A world apart
It was this isolated pocket
Within the city
It has its own schools
Churches stores
Barber shop
The residents had everything they needed without ever having to leave the neighborhood
But a lot of the reason why they were so independent
Or because they had to be
60% of the
People
Mexican Mexican American people that were living in Chavez Ravine area
On their own home
And the reason is
Because that was the only place in the city we could live
Because of the Covenants
Covenants were racial restrictions
That limited where people of color could actually purchase property
From the 1910s through the 1940s
Chavez Ravine with one of the few places in Los Angeles
That non-white people could actually own a home
First threat to the community was not actually the baseball stadium
18 years before
In the form of a new housing project
The federal government passed the National Housing Act
Which allocated funds to cities all over the country in order to build new low income housing for
People in need
Los Angeles itself
We're going to be home to 10,000 of these new public housing units
This was part of an effort to alleviate a severe housing shortage that ensued during the early
Early 1940s during World War II
And public housing was seen as a solution to providing
Affordable
Sanitary living conditions for poor people who were not able to provide that for them
Sounds
This is Eric Avila
Professor of history and Chicano studies at UCLA
He says that the city selected Chavez Ravine to be the site for 3600 new units
It's because
City Housing Authority or chaa
Determined it was
Slum
Caj claim that it was infested with rats
Homes like electricity and toilets and it was actually in their best interest
At the community be replaced
With new modern house
From an urban planning perspective
Or from the perspective of City Hall
For Community like the Choppers are being
Fit their idea of what
Islam was
The time but if you talk to the people who remembered what it was like to live in the troposphere
They didn't think of their neighborhood as
Aslam
We have flushing toilet
Everywhere that I went
And I went to a lot of houses and when I had to go to the bathroom
We had flushing toilets
We had some lights not a lot
Because
We can still see all the stars at night
Without any problem whatsoever
We had a lot of things
That would not Marcus
As slums
But because Chavez Ravine was officially designated a slum
City Housing Authority was able to use eminent domain to clear the land for the housing project
Property-owning residents were offered payment for their homes
Which was Far Below market value
And it's debatable whether you could even call it an offer
Carol remembers when a man named Frank Wilkinson
Who was in charge of the housing project
Keep the house
I remember when the actual knock on the door came
Anda
He wasn't that congenial he wasn't really that nice
But
Who is it Italian
He was there to tell us
That we have no choice
That was made
Very clear
That there was no choice
But we all had to move
Almost everyone in Chavez Ravine ended up selling their homes and then moving to different parts of the city
By 1948 the restrictive covenants that prevented families of color from moving into other areas were ruled unconstitutional
Nutritional
A lot of these former residents became the first Mexican and Mexican-American families in these new neighborhood
We moved into what was it
Completely white community at the time
But what was going on for me when I move there there was a lot of white
Having people like me leaving because of people like me coming in
Some residents were told that they would be first in line to move into the new public housing community at Chavez Ravine
But those hopes
Short-lived
In 1953 a new Los Angeles mayor named North Pole Santa office
Ideological objection to the
Chi Brandon
Public housing as a communist plot
Or socialist conspiracy
Wholesome thought that subsidized housing for the poor it sounded like Tommy not sent
And he made sure that the housing project was dead in the water
The people of Chavez Ravine have been displaced
For no reason
Except for a small number of people who refused to leave their homes
The community of Chavez Ravine was basically gone
We would go there you know it's like oh look there's this house or this or that all they took all the flowers out of this year
We'll just go back and visit but it was a ghost
Discount
Except for a handful of people
All the stores were gone the church was gone they knocked down the school
The city ended up buying land from the federal Housing Authority
I left it undeveloped
For years while it figured out how to put the property to public use
And that's where the Dodgers come back into the
Walter O'Malley was convinced
Chavez Ravine was the perfect place
To build his perfect Stadium
The first it looks like it might be smooth sailing
The city council approved the deal to give the land
To the Dodgers
But as it turned out
A lot of people were opposed to the Dodger deal for reasons that had nothing to do with Chavez Ravine
I didn't want the city subsidizing a private business
Even if that business was baseball
Fact
The opposition was so intense
City decided to put the deal up for a referendum
This meant that the following year
Contract would be placed on the ballot
And the citizens of La would get the chance to vote on the new stadium
And in the end
Voters did come out in the Dodgers favor
Barely
But they were still the issue of the handful of remaining holdouts live in in Chavez Ravine
Even though the federal Housing Authority had tried to clear the land
There were a small number of families
Refuse to give up their home
Those who remain
Being so in protest
They're only about
20 families left after the federal Housing Authority tried to clear the land
And they needed to be evicted in order to start
Construction
These residents had watched their Community disappear around them
All the city referred to them as squatters
That was their land that was their property
I guess you could say that they were squatting
But from their perspective
They are on that land
For 4
Several Generations
That's not squatting
On May 9th
Time has run out
The city of Los Angeles
Send Sheriff's deputy used to Chavez Ravine to remove anyone who had refused to leave
What followed
Was a horrific scene of a family called the arteaga's
Being dragged out of their house
Their daughter a woman named Aurora Vargas
Was physically lifted and carried out of the doorway
Broen home
This was captured on camera by reporters
We couldn't find any audio recording
But it was broadcast all over the country
There are these scenes that are
Indelibly impressed
Into the living memory of Los Angeles
Of
You know a mother and her children being forcefully
Evicted from their homes
I'm a grandmother being
Got carried out in her rocking chair from
The home dogs barking chickens flying everywhere children crying it was a complete melee
When I saw
Aurora Vargas
Intellivision
Being
Forcibly taken out of her house
I saw the house
Being knocked down
That was
Really that was the point where I hated the Dodge
Because in my head
That's all I could see
Is is
This wonderful
Kind of Nirvana place that I grew up in
I was sad to have left that
Of course
But
I saw them
Knocking down
And doing what they did on
Live on TV
I think I was
Can a 15 psi under but it was pretty traumatic for
For me
Evictions dredged up memories not just of a failed housing project years earlier
What if an entire history of racial discrimination that
Latino and Chicano Americans have been experiencing in Los Angeles for decades
And if you know anything about Mexican American history
It is a history of Conquest
It is a history of displacement
And it is a history most of all
Loveland
Dispossession
So this team
Really hit a nerve with a community
That had a long
Suffered
The indignity the pain the inconvenience
Displacement and Landis
It just hit
What happened at Chavez Ravine will always be part of the team's Legacy
But it wouldn't be fair to blame all that
On the Dodgers
The Dodgers
God blamed for this
Although it wasn't the Dodgers
Koovs
Remove these families at
City Who removed
These families
I think it is unfair to say that
The Dodgers remove these
These families
The the chain of events is a little different
This history is complicated
It's hard to sum of all the forces and events that led to the destruction of job as ravine
But the stadium has become a monument
Physical reminder of the community that was the
Displaced from the land
On which it sits
Today Dodger stadium is the third oldest ballpark in baseball
And you have to admit
It's a beautiful Stadium
It's symmetrical with elegant lines amazing views of the city
And somehow
Even a bad seat
Still a pretty good seats
In some ways the ballpark did exactly what those politicians back in the 1950s wanted it to do
The Dodgers are a Civic Institution
Beloved by people throughout the city
The Dodgers are even known for having one of the most diverse fan bases in Baseball thanks in large part
To La's Latino community
I would have to say that that LA's Mexican-American Community is of two minds on this issue
I I think many mexican-americans see the Chavez Ravine as part of a larger story
Of discrimination
Displacement in Southern California
On the other hand Mexican Americans are among the Dodgers biggest
And that was especially true in the early 1980s with the arrival of Fernando Valenzuela
And Fernando Mania
Isn't the only reason why
The Dodgers have tried to appeal to the LA Latino Community from the very beginning with
Broadcasters like Jaime hurrying who's been calling games for the team in Spanish
Almost as long as the Dodgers have been in LA
Edward Satie on spotter Lewis
Was one of the many who refused to see games at Dodger Stadium
He didn't blame the team for what happened to his community
But the stadium would always be reminder of
The home he used to have
His claim to fame
Is that he was born where third base is at
And his umbilical cord back then
Would be buried wherever
You know you were born so he claims that their base
That every time somebody hits a triple or a homerun
He would get a pain in his stomach
Because that's where his umbilical cord is very that
On the 3rd Saturday of July
Former residents of Chavez Ravine get together for an annual reunions picnic in Elysian Park
Edward's father Louis
Started the tradition years ago and named the group
Los Desperados meaning be uprooted
And they don't get together out of anger
They're not there to protest the Dodgers
It's just a bunch of friends
Family
Want to tell stories
And celebrate the neighborhood
But they shared beneath the ballpark
What the hell is a Dodger anyway
Vivian will be back to tell us
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
So I'm back in the studio with Vivien Leigh
And we can talk a little bit more about the Dodgers
And mainly where the name the Dodgers
Comes from
So this is kinda embarrassing I am from Southern California
I moved here from La so the Dodgers
Have essentially been mighty
My entire life
And I didn't realize until I started working on this story
But I had no idea
What the hell is a Dodger
But you've never wondered or you've never been told I've never thought about it and I never realized it.
As an action and so I just
I guess I didn't really think of it either so what is a Dodger and what it what exactly are they dodging
The name actually comes
From where the team originally started out which is Brooklyn where they were known as the Brooklyn
Trolley Dodgers
Used to have a lot of
Trolleys that we're on the street and you had to.
Buy a few nicknames for this they officially started as the Atlantic
And then they were nicknamed The Brooklyn bridegrooms
For while and this was
This is so weird it's because
Six or seven of the team members happen to get married around the same time
And the nickname just stuck
Wow a lot of like major league teams in the early days
They went by nicknames instead of there
Official name so it kind of
It changed a lot
But back in the mid-1890s that's when they first started
Being referred to as the trolley Dodgers thanks to a man named General Henry
Slocum
It's lightning sounds
Vaguely Familiar
But please remind
So if you've ever heard of the PS General Slocum disaster
That ship was named after the sky
He was a Civil War General from Atlanta and then moved to New York after the war and served in Congress
And in 1891 General Slocum kind of made it his mission to modernize transportation and bring elect
Electric streetcars do Brooklyn and at first the city denied this
This sounds dangerous but in 1892 Brooklyn trolley ordinance passed which
Approved the conversion from horse-drawn to elect
Was it as dangerous as
People thought it might be
100% for the standard so
Charlie Rose where laid out all over the place like
In Brooklyn and Manhattan and Brooklyn Street for basically already
Neither of these trolley rails
At first it seemed like a good idea to
We could go faster and you can be
How much more efficient and
Clear
If you can pound that with
The fact that there's pedestrians all over the streets and you're suddenly changing this technology that
People have to with that tooth very quickly
It just becomes
It's funny cuz when I hear the name Charlie Dodgers it actually sounds kind of cute in it
But this is really like the streets were deadly
84 people all of a sudden
Is giant cards
We're going very very fast
Yeah yeah
So this is pre automobile culture
Are so people just weren't used to
Looking both ways before Crossing
The street and horse-drawn trolleys were not very dangerous cuz you
Probably
Briskly power wash Mexico
So the electric cars are going a lot faster and it was just catching people off guard and so it required
Color.
Yes
Astrologer going three times fast
And it was so dangerous that in
1892 the first year that they're introduced
There's five.
The next year there are 51 deaths
And by 1895 trolleys and already killed 107 people
And injured at least
400 other people
So people are literally having to jump out of the way of these
Basically like death machines
These political cartoons from around that time and they're just kind of horse
Okay so
Show me one near it
In the wake of a cable car
Andaz
Didn't mean to bodies on the street like have run over
Crying
Dark it really is
Oh my God
So what would
Possess you to name a baseball team after this
The weird thing is it was
I have a compliment
So you only found Electra
Search Ollie's in highly urbanized areas like New York
Or Chicago so having to act
Out of the way
It made you
It was the market like a modern
Cosmopolitan person and also a modern cosmopolitan
City so it was as good on the city was gone the purse
So at what point did the trolleys
Disappearing around the 1920s which is around the time that car culture
Sure start popping up so yo
But you know that the name stuff the trolley Dodgers stuck and eventually they got shortened to the Brooklyn Dodgers
And then eventually became the Los Angeles Dodgers
When they moved in
1950s
And when they moved in 1957
What's the red car still going on in Los Angeles for there any trolleys left in Los Angeles
Yes yes there were
For about
4 years
Dodge like
Probably
Cool alright thanks thank you
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Vivian Leigh
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real Katie mingle is our senior producer
That is the digital director
President is Avery trufelman Joe Rosenberg Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall
Darren mazet Sofia klatzker
And me Roman Mars
Special thanks to
The Carroll hakkasan Priscilla Leyva they've been working on an oral history and preservation project documenting the story
The former residents of Chavez Ravine it's called Chavez Ravine
An unfinished story
Find out more at Tavares Ravine la
Dot-com
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Acts of fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Baidu mall
Radiotopia. FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we do me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 bi or
On Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But if you want before and after pictures of Chavez Ravine
Look no further
99 pi
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com