99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
My fellow Americans
Memorial Day is a day of
Ceremonies and speeches
About America today we honor the dead of our Wars
Whatever you think about Ronald Reagan
They called him the great communicator for a reason
The Unknown Soldier
Who is returned to us today and whom we later rest is symbolic of all our missing son
This is him in 1984 during a military funeral at the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier at Arlington
10 National Cemetery
On that Memorial Day
Reagan was eulogizing the remains of an unidentified service member from the Vietnam War
The Remains would be entombed alongside three other unknown service members
From World War 1 & 2 and the Korean War
It was a big event
That's our own Joe Rosenberg
Horse-drawn carriage
Brought the casket to the two
Have 250000 on lockers
Putting hundreds of veterans who emerged out of the crowd to walk behind the remains on their way to Arlington
Most powerful part though
Reagan talks about through this unknown soldier might have been
Replay on some Street in a great American city
Titus father on a farm out in America's Heartland
Elementary
Expectantly to return
Cobra Kai
We'll never know the answers to these questions about his life
A Broken Spoke
Next on the side of the term itself with words known
What you got
It's already moving
You knowing what we know now
Bat
Are the person being buried that day might have been unknown to the public
A lot about his identity
The government like we even knew that he had a family who would like to have his body back
But they buried him anyway
How to honor
Unidentified remains always been one of the great conundrums of War
The Romans were fond of honoring them with an empty sarcophagus
After the Civil War
Union buried 2111 soldiers in a mass grave in Arlington that they purposely built on top of Robert
Chinese Rose Garden
It wasn't until the 20th century that it occurred to anyone to bury a single Unknown Soldier in a public setting
This sort of
Memorialization
Came about
From our world war
This is Robert
The former executive editor for National Geographic
What a book about Arlington
Called on Hallowed Ground
What does World War 1 era of
Total War
And Matt
Participation
What's the combatants on both sides were mostly ordinary City
Anonymous Everyman
Unrendered literally anonymous
It's the violence of the Western Front
Everything about the war not only the numbers but the nature of it was dehumanizing
Nobody who went through that war was ever the same again
And there was a British chaplain
Who was in the worst of the fighting on the front lines
Named David Ralston
Brokenwood spend his nights conducting funeral services over the remains of soldiers ripped apart by shell fire
Having them on the spot
In the giant craters the shells in Left Behind
And while
He was there he thought about how how terrible it was that they were these people who
Work essentially forgotten
Buried in their graves and nobody would ever
Remember
And that there should be something better than that
It was around this time the David Railton came across a temporary gray a few miles behind the front
Marked by a cross bearing the name of a regiment and the words
An unknown British soldier
And he realized
If you had a mass grave with
2000 people in it
Then it's a mass grave with two thousand people in it
It's not an individual
Who had a life
Something about having a particular person
Makes it more real
More human
After the war
Wilson advocated for a grave during the body of a single soldier
To bring the impossibly large tragedy
Down to a human scale
Soldiers anonymity without each person who came to the Grave to project whatever it was most important to them onto the mystery
It matter if you wanted to honor all those who served
Neely those who died
Those who volunteer doorbells overdraft
Reason why they were for the war or against it
Everyone was Freedom or in their own way
Sure enough when Britain dedicated the grave of an unknown warrior in Westminster Abbey in 1920
It was an overnight success
The dedication of loan attracted so many mourners
The line for viewing lasted 10 days
And Britain's unknown Warrior
Wasn't the only one
Britain France Romania Italy everybody at the same time
Jumped on this idea
Over 50 countries without a building similar Memorial
In part because the formula was so easy to follow
All you needed with the body of a single Unknown Soldier
The American Memorial is especially beautiful
It sits at the top of a hill that overlooks the rest of Arlington Cemetery
And starting in 1937
Has been watched over a day and night
Without a single interruption
Myloan guard
Forever marching back and forth
In front of the Tomb
No one knows which service The Remains are from
Soldier or sailor Marine they're simply referred to as the unknown
That anything that narrows the scope of who this person could be
Where exactly they were found
Is purposely withheld from the public
In order to make sure that they represent
Everyone
But you might become one of the Washington DC area's biggest
Tourist attractions
But in 1956
We made one small seemingly innocent changed the formula of the unknown
I would end up
Proving
Tricky
We began adding a new set of unidentified remains
For every subsequent War
World War II Korea
Eventually Vietnam
Each War
We get their own unknown
Which made sense
There were lots of unknowns to choose from
At least at first
In World War 1
There were something like a thousand 648
Unknowns
World War II
The unknowns were 8000
Korean War
And then the the last war in which we had an unknown
Vietnam
Things to improve Battlefield vacuolation tactics the Vietnam War produced or me
Four sets of unidentified remains that could potentially go into the two
As more information about those remains was discovered
Was down to three then down to two
The down to
Juan
One set of remains for
Paula Vietnam
Who was unknown
That single cell Remains the one Reagan eulogized in that moving ceremony in 1984
The public
Is the Unknown Soldier
What's referred to internally
As x26
His actual name
With Michael
There's not supposed to be favorites and families right
This is Patricia blasi
Has something about them
Michael blassie was Patricia's oldest brother
Is the oldest five actually in the Lassie family
So growing up in St Louis in 1960s and 70s
He was actually very good at anything that he did
Patricia says that Michael was
Constantly bouncing between activities mastering each one before moving on to the neck
Score music Sports
You know I think he could have
Done whatever he wanted to
But then he received an appointment to the Air Force
And he fell in love with flying at the Academy
Flight school Michael was assigned to fly a ground attack aircraft known as the a37
Dragonfly or sometimes the super tweet
Resign fly low over its Target
I would love it
Combat close to the ground the landscape rushing by the sense of flight
Speed of combat
Titan
To the uninitiated of course all these things may flying the a37 downright terrifying
But I don't remember Michael
Ever
Saying anything about being afraid of it
And so once he graduated
It was off
Pilot training that it from there it was off to survival training and from there it was off to be
Vietnam
And I remember
Seen him get on the aircraft
Is St Louis
And I remember him looking back and waving to us with that beautiful smile
And and and
I just remember thinking it all over him again
I think we all did
By 1972 and Michael blassie was
America's military presence in Southeast Asia with shrinking rapidly
There are fewer than 25000 US servicemen left in Vietnam
As opposed to over 500000 who have been deployed by the late 1960s
The war was in effect winding down but it was still dangerous and they were still out of combat going on
This is biltong
He's a reporter who wrote about Michael blassie for the Washington Post
He says that the American servicemen remain behind were stretched thin
How to do a lot with a little
That Michael was going to see a lot of combo
He arrived in Vietnam in January of 72
And by May of 1972
He had flown something like 130 missions
So he's been virtually almost every day
He had at least one combat sometimes to combat missions
G37 that Michael flu had a good record up to that point Vietnam
If you'd gotten hit
When they were hit
Things could get ugly fast
Because it could take all kinds of
Fire
I mean you're flying 408
In the air and you get hit
Deductible parachute out of the plane
So that made it very dangerous
Michael would always take off and land from a protected Airbase near Saigon
Ignition Saturn flying over a lot of dangerous places
In the most dangerous was arguably a town in South Vietnam
Called and lock
In 1972 hanlock was occupied by the South Vietnamese military
Along with a handful of American advisors
But it was under siege by an invading North Vietnamese Army
Very very long time it went on for months and I encountered of guy who it was in and lock
Chris Calhoun
And she described it was like a scene out of Apocalypse Now
The city of van laack was
Totally leveled it look like Hiroshima
This is Chris Calhoun
Eustachian to unlock an Army Ranger during the majority of the siege
Often resorted to analogies as a way of explaining just how awful it was there
One point he described with their meager medical support
As looking like something out of the Civil War
Unlock was completely cut off from the rest of the world
We got food and ammunition by
Parachute drop everyday
We were under constant shellfire
Chris's Beauty
List of all this chaos
Call in airstrike
It was Michael blassie Squadron that was providing the air support
They were flying bombing runs over and lock nearly every day
Michael and Chris never actually spoke one-on-one
The time there didn't quite overlap
Chris did get snow a lot of Michael Squadron mates really well
And we would talk on the radio they read me stars and stripes Stars and Stripes at the US military's
Finally run daily paper
Why would they redo Stars and Stripes
What was my only contact with the outside world
But in an loc they would
Be over is almost 24 hours a day
And they kept the North Vietnamese off our back so these were people who I owed my life to
And it was on one of these bombing runs keeping the North Vietnamese off their backs
That Michael blassie flew his 132nd
Final mission
We'll never know exactly what happened on May 11th 1972
Witnesses recalled that day's fighting as being particularly intense and chaotic so a lot of what we do know comes from
Flappy's commanding officer
Was flying in a plane alongside black most of all
Call was how bright everything was spelled with these planes and helicopters for Target
Also Tracer rounds being fired from multiple enemy aircraft
And they were taking ground fire the whole time but because they were flying into the sun they could
See where was coming from so this just added to the confusion of the battle
And somewhere in the midst of the blinding sun in the chaos and confusion
Michael's plane was hit by ground fire remember Michaels playing as designer flight love
I got hit
There's no more than 500 feet above the ground he has lost control of the plane
Buses playing bien streaming fuel inverted
And it disappeared into the jungle below
And there was no distress signal
Which indicates that the pilot had probably been killed instantly
I just playing the crash deep in North Vietnamese held territory
Helicopter team tried to get to the crash site
But did Heavy enemy fire
I don't leave after just a few minutes
Rather than think of me anyway
Get the side or find out exactly what happened
Michael blassie declared missing in action
Resume.
The blasi family was informed that Michaels Body would not be coming home
But with
I don't edit the strangest thing that when there is no
Body there is no Gathering
When Michael died it wasn't the first time Patricia it had to deal with the loss of a close family member
Other parents came from big families
Advance and uncle's lots of funerals
End Time song passed away
They processed it by gathering together at the funeral
Talking
A person's life
They were
Bedtime
Without a body to place beneath the tombstone
Family Optics
Not that material
I mean there was a memorial Gathering but it was
Did it still wasn't the same
We didn't talk about it we didn't
Everyone just was
They was at 3 I remember it's just like quiet
And then it was just like we will go on with our lives
And and try to be normal well it wasn't Norm
Patricia says that Michael's death
Or rather they're not talking about Michael's death
Ended up putting a strain on her parents marriage
A leader separated
Patricia join the Airforce eventually attained the rank of Colonel
Life in other words went on
Even at the topic of Michael sat undiscussed
Finished
It was just sort of the put on an over on a Shelf
This thing that we didn't
Get to deal with
And
It didn't resurrect itself until
26 years later after he
Was killed we
Realize where he was
In 1994 more than two decades after Michael have been killed
Patricia and her mother received a phone call
Complete stranger
And he said I'm Ted sampley
And I am a former Green Beret
Who served in Vietnam
Get that we have sent passed away but back then he was sort of this minor celebrity
Champion the cause of Vietnam pows Mia
Just convince the government everything is new
I was calling Patricia with outlandish theories about Michael death
I mean there wasn't anything in his voice that was like angry or you know he would just matter-of-fact
But he said I started
Researching who was shot down on May 11th 1972 and
And you know what was found with him and would that be on a fighter aircraft
Evidence was circumstantial and his logic was long-winded but he said
I believe your brothers and the Tomb of the Unknown
But the body from Vietnam that President Reagan in buried with Pomp and ceremony in 1984
Wasn't unknown at all
That wasn't fact
Michael
First Patricia didn't know what to make of any of
Garcinia
The body never even been recovered
Remember she herself was in the Air Force
Getting off the phone with sample
She caught the Air Force cattle the office
Could this be true
Could Michael be in the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier
And
They said by no means is there anything to substantiate that your brothers in the two
I said but you know what
Thank you very much because that is the craziest story
That I could ever imagine that a known Soldier was in the time of the end
I mean that's the crazy is it it's just
It just didn't make sense
I thought
This is the best example of Internet conspiracy garbage I've seen to date
This is Ben's Gonzales
Through the young reporter at CBS Denver when he accidentally came across a post and family made on the internet
Lattice theory that Michael blassie have been buried in the Tomb of the unknowns
It was a 1997
3 years after the phone call with Patricia
He says yeah of course the First Tee totally dismissed
And I thought I'm going to print it out I'm going to show it to college classes When I visit and say this is why we say don't believe everything you read on the internet
And I did that I printed out had it on my desk at CVS
And then one evening I sat down and started reading it and I thought
Maybe I should check this out
Direct evidence proving that Michael blassie was in the Tomb
But that didn't make them wrong
Whatever was known about the remains of the Vietnam unknown has never been repealed
Was all part of the effort to make sure that the unknown could represent everyone who ever fought in the War
But simply have come across some secondhand accounts suggesting that America's only set of unknown remains for
From Vietnam have been recovered from the aircraft that have been shot down in 1972
And you only been able to find one missing plane that fully matched the description
Michael blasius
Still made it hard to believe you
It was not supposed to bury any one of the two
The chance you could be identified like this
So it's called few sources in the military
Not asking any hard questions
Just wondering
Embarrassed
Current government
Possibly bury a known person in the Tomb of the unknowns
Not tell anyone
One conversation in particular
Told me there was an attitude with in some parts of the military that might allow something like this to happen I called up
Researching The Pentagon and I tried to talk really around the issue I didn't want to let them know what I was working on
I finally said what if you could figure out who this was
What if we could go in and identify this person and give them back to his family
And his response was
Thought I would never
And I said but that would be the truth
And he said well the truth doesn't matter
He's not a human being anymore
He's a symbol in America's most sacred military Shrine and we would never let the
The happen
So I wrote down the truth doesn't matter on a post
Stuck it to my computer console
And I thought if there's a chance
You can figure out who this is and give him back to his family you should do
It's began filing for Eric
Try to get his hands on any government documents
About Michael blassie
But there were things I wanted it only family member
We needed an affidavit
So that was when I reached out to the
In contact with Patricia
Laid out of case
Like that
How do I pattern
And Vince and I started talking and I called my mom and I said you know what
It's somebody
And if it's Michael
You know we need to pursue it
Eventually gave instantly way to file yet another foia request
Special
Get some documents related to Michael blassie
I'm an Air Force Base in Texas
Not mentioning it to him not mentioning the Unknown Soldier just asking for anything with Michael blasts his name is
And
I got back to really thick envelope padded envelope which is more than I think I've gotten back from any other requests
And I was actually back in Denver that point sitting in The Newsroom I opened it up and I was paging through it page after page and join
Oh my God
This is it
Cuz this wasn't just some small file continued Italy or a tantalizing clue
These were military documents showing
The entire Unknown Soldier selection process
When combined with his earlier research
Documents in Gonzales now held in his hands
Nearly complete
What the government do
Regarding the identity of the Unknown Soldier
Starting with something very important
Then known almost from the beginning
That Michael blasius remains had been recovered in Vietnam
And if they'd been recovered by Chris Calhoun
The Army ranger stations in the unlock
You know I don't really know exactly what went down
But I do I do know that everything pointed to me
Now remember telling didn't know Blackie personally
He was friends with a bunch of the other pilots in Michael Squadron
They were the guys reading the newspaper to Calhoun over the radio
It was on one of those Lonely Nights
Chatiw
They started telling them
Mount Michael
The only thing I know is they asked me that one of their Squadron mates have been shot down
They gave me the coordinates
And they wanted to know if we could get the body back
This was in October of 1972 over 5 months since blasts he's playing and disappeared into the jungle
They knew they were asking a lot
So I think if that Rapport wasn't there
Then the request would have never come and I would have never acted on
Christopher matter his regimental Commander
Who assembled a special South Vietnamese Patrol
Dressed up as the enemy
In North Vietnamese unit
Uniforms with
North Vietnamese weapons
And they went out
In no man's land
And they found the wreckage
And they brought back to me
What was left of the remains of Michael blassie
In a black
Plastic bag
It remains did not get this damn much
Just sixbones
But they also brought back other evidence
An inflated life raft with serial numbers
Parachute
Carmichael's flight suit
Critically
And that was a good shape
Pictures of him pictures of his family pictures of his sister
It was no question
The Remains were Michaels
Kristin Hannah the bag with everything in it
Awesome crew chief of the week's one outgoing helicopter
But he got the bag
The crew chief got the bag
And when you saw the remains I go in the chopper I mean
What was your girl we were we were sending him home to his fans
You know we were doing what was right
And of course those South Vietnamese rooster live stick
Get his body from the wreckage
Any deserve to go home
I just assumed that Michael's remains would be returning to his family
But according to Vince's documents that's not what happened
The Remains along with the survival gear
What eventually arrived at the Army Central identification laboratory in Hawaii
But not before the wallet
Continue the ID that could link the bones to blasi
Went missing
You know you knew about the missing wallet
Out of the lab using now outdated techniques
Determined that the remains did not match Michael blasius physical description
He's dead
Dedicated as
Btb
Believes to be
Michael blassie
Got a positive match to Army policy
Wacky family could not even be told that any remains have been found
Meanwhile pressure began to mount in the Pentagon to place a veteran from Vietnam in the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier
It was politics
There's also patriotism
Why there was a crass
Political angle to do this
To make nice with the Vietnam veterans
Are there was also a Feeling
Of we need to get someone in that tomb so the nation can feel around this
But by the 1980s
It was only one set of unidentified remains left
The ones labeled
Bleed to be Michael blassie
Labs ordered to strip their main their Formal Connection with blassie
I'm taking the anonymous designation x26
With the Reagan Administration eager to put someone on the tomb before election day
They were told to prepare
26 for burial
And I spoke with
Technicians at the Army lab later who said we gave them every answer
Possible to say don't do this the technology is coming
This is not an unknown set of remains
The lab technician stole the Pentagon that new dna-based technology was being developed
It would allow it remains to be conclusively identified
They also put into the artifact
Like the flight suit in the life raft
The record of missing wallet
All of which suggested that the remains were most likely blasius
But the push to put a Vietnam unknown in the Tomb
Overrode
And a general from the Army was sent to tell them
Everybody better get the hell out of the way
And that's when Michael blassie
1 into the 2
My fellow Americans
Memorial Day is a day of
Ceremonies and speeches
About America today we honor the dead of our Wars
And it's win President Reagan who may not have known that any of this it happened
Give a speech at a burial in Arlington invoking a powerful mystery
Did he marry
Expectantly to return
We'll never know the answers to these questions about his life
The file that means discover
13 years later in 1997
Showed that there never been
Any mystery at all
Armed with the documents
End up with veteran CBS correspondent Eric Anger
I talked to anyone they could find Who's involved in the unknown selection process
Monday felt they were ready
They presented their findings
And I asked my mom to
Call a family meeting
And I
We sat down and we looked at the documents together
And we discussed
You know
What should we do
Patricia wanted to go public with Vince and CBS
Her older sister Judy of anything
What's even more eager to blow the lid off the whole thing
George
Youngest brother
Michael's buried in a place of honor he pointed out
Make it stay there
And serves the unknown
Everyone else who's loved ones never come back
Tiebreaker was Michael's mother
She's a very it was a very patient Woman and
She would listen to
All of the opinions of you know her children are living children
And
Waited until we were done with our bantering or whatever
And and she just looked at us and she's
She said I want to bring my son home
Who sings the CBS Evening News
Tonight the results of an eye on America investigation lasting over half a year
Is it possible the government knows the identity of a Vietnam War casualty buried at the Tomb of the unknowns and
Arlington National Cemetery
Deliberately kept a secret from the public and even his own family
A seven-month CBS News investigation has found evidence of a long-running cover up
One story on Evening News he was more like a blizzard of stories
There are significant new developments tonight in the exclusive story that CBS News first broke on this broadcast in January
CBS is Vince Gonzalez uncovered new evidence an update tonight of our exclusive eye on America invested
Location
I think we did 15 or 18 pieces on this
It just was Non-Stop
And tonight is everything Burke tells us
There's more
The CVS in blasi family in just want the world to know that Michael as he was in the Tomb
I wanted the Pentagon to do something about it
Michael blassie sister Pat says the family wants the remains tested
Even if by some chance they aren't identified as my
Now Congress wants to investigate
If it's Michael we want bring them home
Edit certain point
They called us up
And they said
You're killing us
And
Day or two later they announced the team would be open to the remains were going to be
On May 14th 1998
The Department of Defense disinterred the remains of the Vietnam veteran from the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier
DNA samples were taken from Michael's mother jeans
Dexter Judy
Protected against the Romaine
They were match
And after the scientist were finished talking to my mother
We were wrapping things up cuz that my mother had to sign some papers and things like that and
And
Then all the sudden man walked up and said well
When we opened the tomb
To do the DNA test
Michael's artifacts were in the Tomb with him
And what would you like us to do with them
The life raft in other items have been found at the crash in 1972 I mean the only physical evidence
Aside from the missing wallet
That could have tied the remains to Michael blassie
But it was to preserve the artifacts or to hide them
Someone at the Army lab in Hawaii
I put them where no one would ever think to look
The casket with Michael
I've been sitting in the two underneath the guards in the crowds in the Arlington soil
14 years
They were in a box
And so after we buried Michael in St Louis
There was a reception and then once everyone laugh
We sit around the table and my brother George
Opened up the box and started
Pulling out the life raft
Portions of his
Parachute portions of his flight suit
And I have them with me today I I keep it with me
I was really glad I'm really glad to have them
Today there is nobody representing Vietnam at the Tomb of the unknowns
And thanks to improved forensics
It will likely never be an unknown from Iraq
Or Afghanistan
Or any future War
Military is now in the process of using the DNA from the families of missing veterans to identify / 604
He sets of unknown remains from the Korean War
It's conceivable that they could use the same techniques on the Korean unknown inside the tomb
Guns from World War 1 and World War II
Safe
Now
Premier of 23andMe
Well
What's your Say anything's possible
You go to Arlington today
The Tomb of the unknowns is still there
Minus the remains for Vietnam
Datura still take pictures on their phones and the guard still make their rounds in perfect silent precision
Day and night
Even when no one is watching
And it really is beautiful
You should go see it
The Heyday of this unique
Form of remembrance
Has come to an end
Avenue
Like the dad knew that there is no
I know for Vietnam anymore
I I can't say that it saddens me
I can't say that
That I
I respect the Tomb of the unknowns
But it
In order to
Have an unknown
They made one
They took Michael's name away from
To satisfy
Something that I understand it was very important to our nation
But the first thing that you and I did when we met one another over the phone hi I'm
I'm Patricia and Pat hi I'm Joe
A name is very very important
Patricia still visits Batu
She said she's not sure why she does it
It means that she's got to know some of the guards
One of them lights holder that their mission
Gardenias
It's never really over
Michael's case
Just once
Their mission was completed
They're just looking out for him
We could go home
Joe talks me through the very precise ceremony that has evolved at the Tomb of the Unknown
After this
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 99
Okay
When I was a little boy
My parents and
I think my grandparents
Live just outside of Washington DC
They took me to Arlington Cemetery to see the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier
And I've seen a reason I remember it so well
And the reason
I became interested in the Tomb again more recently
Is not the mysterious soldier in the Tomb projecting
Whatever you want on to his anonymity exactly the gar
And it's not so scaredy of the Guard keeping vigil like
Solemn Duty as much as it is what the guard is
Physically doing
And what they're doing most of the time it's just taking 21 steps to the left
Turning
Stopping for 21 seconds
And turning and stopping for another 21
Been taking 21 steps to the right
Stopping again turning again stopping again stepping again
Over and over and over
Until there's a guard change every 30 minutes to an hour
That's something very
Very precise
Yeah and actually that's me like
You say that but you have
Let me sell you on this by Lisa showing you a video of what this
Stripes on the legs
Zelda
Innovation
So is regimented as I was imagining it
Annies
Even more so he's like the innards of a Swiss clock the way that they move together and then they move in time
Stunning
Yeah I know and what is different kind of really appreciate it is just the way like
If you have liked
Taking away with
Precision it hasn't
This way of
Magnifying the silence
Around it is it kind of weird silence
To it
And apparently
To get this right they train and practice for months
Facility
Chinese it's almost meditative like you said like
Inside of the silence we hear the clicking of their shoes in there
Heels together
You do get this space that's created inside of it that's
Derry Medical
The word that just instantly came to mind is like Zen
You watch the market marching back and forth
And the guards
When you doing it they don't seem a lot
In the performance
Instead
At every step
They are totally present
They're completely aware of their surroundings
They're truly doing nothing
But this
Unless
You start laughing
It is requested at officers maintain an atmosphere of Silence
And respect
Adult time
Bert's out of nowhere and this is what happens if you get like kind of to rowdy
Are you laugh at the Tomb of the Unknown
Genre of YouTube videos
I'd like to guards yelling it
Visiting
Let's let's find it let's find another one
And like what they catch. Up thinking like very their tone they can switch up the words a little bit
Agar depends on there may be there that day
Oh I love it just let him have it at this is this is one where are they they reprimands some parent
Visitors must keep their children behind the grape trains and rail
Thank you
Billy Beane Yankees back real fast sneak in
What kind of behind the rails you can get a few of them and then they're yelled at and then they just like
They freeze like like like chipmunks have been like caught out in the open and then just like
Terrifying
My favorite, though is it from YouTube user who said and I quote
When I was 10 years old I made the mistake of sitting down during The Changing of the Guard
I almost shat
Does any other National Monument have something
In like this where there's this 24/7 ritual white why in particular is it happening right here
Question because
The thing
About the tomb
Is it like
The way it is now is not the way it always was it evolve into all of this kind of Pomp and ceremony and
When it was first married in 1921
The big moment
Question because
The Sting
About the tomb
Is it like
The way it is now is not the way it always was it evolve into all of this kind of
Pomp and ceremony at home
When it was first married in 1921
With a big moment I think it was the first like Nationwide radio dress that the president
Ever gave was from the commemoration the Tomb of the Unknown
But it was just kind of a slow stones
Slab
End
Between a second-rate monument for a while
But people would picnic fare
And photographers would like cuz it has a great view of
Yeah I love both of them to surrounding area cuz it's fun
Is hell and photographers would actually kind of set up shop there and people would like
Who's on the 2
And people but apparently like veterans caught on to this and started complaining about it cuz
They saw that kind of
Keyboard
Treating it yeah like
Cigarettes on it
And so they kind of complaint about the Congress and eventually
The government has money to it to post
Guard
And then starting the 1937 the guard was
24/7
And I think a painting
Records on this one some say night since 1937 other say since 1948
The guard has
Never left
State Fair
And then nothing happened during that time is that
They always intended for there to be like Amour
Updated fancy tune but it just took them forever to get around to getting the funding and spit events that they did
And so they built the kind of the giant sarcophagus
Annie 1931
And for that date they went to this query in Colorado actually
To ensure that they got the exact
Same marble as the Lincoln Memorial
And it wasn't designed by these guys it was sculpted like the actual physical problems by this light
Gorilla
Who were the Italian brothers
Who sculpted like everything is called the Lincoln Memorial and my favorite is a sculpted the two lions
In front of the
New York City
Wow
And then
In 1956 that's when we started
Adding is
Further
World War II
Excetera hangzhou just built and built and built
It has the image of
An almost Timeless tradition when you see it like this
But actually kind of
The fact
This is
Something that was
You know iterated upon and improved and
Given a little more weight over time
Aw appreciate it because I love when something iterative in the direction of honing towards austerity in LA
Internet
I'm feeling like clutter
Getting more casual
Or something
It's a fascinating
Place
Particularly because of the
Ceremony makes
All the more
Special
Have you ever had a chance to speak to one of the guards when you join the 40
I confess
Did not manage to Teresa guard in time for this coda
But
But I got the next best thing which is I found it one of the guards dude of course
Ireddit
And of course
What are things like when your reporter and you seen ask me anything thread you're like you go through it hoping someone's going to ask like
Question you would ask only question I want to ask
Just doing the long 30 minutes long hour
Marching back and forth
Meditative state right
And to finally something like that
That's right and the guard responded
I wish I could say that while we were doing this job we're just meditating I wanted means to guard the unknown
We are human and we are on duty for long
It's our minds do Wonder quite a bit
Was so disappointing to read
No but it's really human you know
I know but you were here to hear the irony was like I realized like when I was doing the story
Whatever they want on to the mystery of love
I like that's of course my
Repertorial and being really conceited and thinking like I'm above that
I don't fault
Symbolism
Like what do I want to see like I'm a reporter at 9 x invisible live in San Francisco
I see like the den meditation
Of course like in the ask me anything. He's just like no no no
Whatever
Dinner is right
And so you know I guess the the tomb is working smash
Thank you Joe
Alright thank you
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Joel Rosenberg mix into production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Katie mingle is our senior producer
Percocet is the digital director
Resetting is senior editor Delaney Hall Avery trufelman Vivien Leigh
Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn mazet Sophia
And me Roman Mars
Pennebaker in Andy Richards whose interviews were not featured
But without whose help this story could not have happened
We're especially indebted to Andy Richards biography of David Railton the clergyman who first came up with the idea of the Tomb of the
The unknown Warrior
The book is called the flag
And you should check it out will have more information on our website
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX
Fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
Find mall
And radiotopia
Thought I found
Define 99percentinvisible enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook you can treat me at Roman Mars and the show at 9:09 p.m.
I work on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But the real 99p ihq is that
99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com