99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The podcast twenty thousand Hertz tell stories about the world's most recognizable and interesting sounds
It is a great show
You should definitely subscribe to
Please represent one of their episodes here today
It's all about these sounds
Which almost need no introduction
Twenty thousand Hertz
Here is Dallas Taylor
If you watch cartoons as a kid you probably knew instantly that the sound you just heard was from Looney Tunes
You probably also know that sound Matt Wile E coyote failed to catch the roadrunner
Again
3 crazy how we can fill in the whole scene based solely on the sound effects
Even without a single meat meat from the roadrunner
Wylie Coyote started falling off cliffs in 1949
Yet we still hear that falling sound effect in modern cartoon
Shows Like Teen Titans
I wouldn't stand there about
Here it is in Justice League action
How do you do that
And here it is even in Family Guy
It's been almost 70 years since the first Wylie Coyote cartoon
And that sound along with many other cartoon sounds remains constant
The Beauty and the joy of cartoon animation is that the characters do not have to obey the laws
Isaac physics
They also don't have to obey the laws of logic
And therefore
Sound doesn't have to obey those laws either
That's Mark Mangini
An oscar-winning sound designer who works with the Formosa group
I don't very often get to talk about my early days and cartoons
Mark doesn't get a lot of questions about cartoons
Because he has an impressive resume designing sound for Hollywood blockbusters
I've worked on a hundred and forty-two live-action films
Most recently bladerunner2049
Mad Max
Fury Road Wiki
I want an Oscar for and I'm very proud of
Warrior
Kremlin
4 Star Trek
A die-hard Lethal Weapon
Green Mile
But before Market sound for films he worked for one of the most famous cartoon studios in the world
My first job in sound was at Hanna-Barbera studios in their Sound Apartments
I started as a track reader
Which is a subset of sound editing where
You're charged with
Transcribing
The recordings of the voices
So did the animators know when to open and close the mouth so the characters
That led to subsequent promotions to becoming a sound effects editor
In that department to Hanna Barbera
And an apprenticeship with a number of really amazingly gifted sound editors
Back then this was 1976
I didn't know anyone
Who is called a sound designer
But I would argue that everything that we were doing it Hanna-Barbera was every bit as
Designed
As Maybe
Something more profound that was being heard in a motion picture
Mark works on some of hanna-barbera's most famous cartoon
The Flintstones
Some Huckleberry Hound
A whole raft
Scooby-Doo's
Where are you
Super Friends
Their mission
To fight Injustice
To right that which is wrong and Reserve all mankind
And my personal favorite because it starred Mel Blanc
Captain Caveman
Long before Mark works for Hanna Barbera
And even before Wylie Coyote was falling off cliffs
Walt Disney made history with Steamboat Willie in 1928
This was the first cartoon with synchronized picture and sound
Walt
Android ndk Eyeworks themselves
Would be the sound effects guys in their live orchestral recording sessions for those early Steamboat Willies
In the early days before there was multi-track recording or mix
Thank you had to perform the sound effects live with your costura in one straight path
Saudi sound effect guys
How to assemble prop put them in front of microphones and
Perform anything that they put acoustically live and in sync with the orchestra
Music and sound effects had to be performed at the same time in the same space
Musical instruments were used to make the effects because they were easy to find
An easy to manipulate
Tom and Jerry clip the sound of a frying pan hitting X face and played by a simple crash
Falling whistle from the beginning of the episode
Displayed on a slide whistle
The percussionist would probably have it as part of their kit
And it was just a natural to convey
Going up
Or down
You could manipulate them in any one of a number of ways for quickly or very slowly
Sound effects
Play buy musical instruments became an iconic part of all cartoons
Then new technology in the 1930s allowed sound editors to add sound effects
After recording the orchestra
They could use any prop to make a sound
But often still shows musical instrument
Because sound effects and music were tightly linked
They work together to create unique soundscapes
Listen to this audio clip from the very first Bugs Bunny cartoon called Porky's Hare hunt
You can get an idea of how effects and music can come together
The sounds for Porky's Hare hunt were created by an editor named treg Brown
Treadworks on Looney Tunes for decades
Created many of the iconic cartoon sounds we still know today
Once we divorce ourselves from the need to record live to picture
Craighead the
Fundamental understanding of
How to decontextualized the sound how to take the sound
Your finger in a coke bottle
And make that the sound of the Roadrunner tongue flip
Why the sound of an inertia starter the sound
Of this motor that makes a biplane engine start
Why that's the sound of a spinning Tasmanian devil
He learned
A genius at
Taking sound out of one contest
Placing them in another
And that's what made him so amazing and when you listen to
Does
Looney Tunes shorts
There isn't a lot of
Cartoons
Is there is not a lot of
Comedic sound
It's all blood in his ability to
Take the sound from somewhere else
And put it where it didn't belong
Creating this bizarre juxtaposition that made it funny
Has anybody
Better than he was at that
Around the same time Shrek was working at Warner Brothers
William Hanna and Joseph Barbera we're creating the Tom and Jerry cartoons at MGM
Marc's mentor
Greg Watson
What's the sound editor on those early Tom and Jerry cartoons
When I met him is he was in a 6
Late in his career but immensely proud to be still working in cartoon and he still
So I deserve an art form
Something is very proud of
He would never take credit
For anything unless I asked him
Greg where did this come from and he said oh I remember back in
You know
51 1
Bill did this one funny scene with Jerry and we needed a funny sound and we thought it would be good to do
Do this
He was a man that was
Thrilled to be a part of the process
Bill Hanna and Joseph Barbera eventually created their own studio and during their 30 years of making cartoons they free
Created a massive library of
Totally classic
Sex sounds
I think they're unique
At least because
Of their own Merit
They're just
Silly
So many of them
Even out of the context of the cartoon
Just sound like that's just the silliest thing I've ever heard
But then within the context of the cartoons in the way that they were used in the life that they brought
To those cartoons
They just get better
Basking in the Limelight of the animation
The sound is pretty silly on its own
Now imagine Tom hanging from his whiskers in the unavoidable fall as each one is plucked from his cheeks
There were hundreds of familiar sounds like this created at Hanna-Barbera Studios
They had such a signature quality to themselves
It made them stand out as a unique piece of
Quality artwork
Sonic artwork
In the 1960
Hanna-Barbera started selling their Sound Library
Other production companies like Warner Brothers use these sounds to this day
The popularity of the Hanna-Barbera Sound Library has given cartoons and almost Universal sound language
But Mark feels some sounds are overused
I was on a one-man campaign to eradicate
Head take
It was this
Name noise that was again I think a recording accident
That you use whatever a character
Allison caught themselves in the midst of
Thinking or experiencing something bizarre
And it was way overused
And did you ever notice how it sounds when a cartoon character runs
Mark's not a fan of that one either
That running sound was called blob
Gallup
And again a sound that
Was I felt overusing I I tried to not use it
As often as I could it's a logical but I tried not to use it as often as possible
It's a testament to its effectiveness
Even in 1976 I was
Turning into an elitist I suppose
Embarrassing
Of course there are plenty of sounds that Mark loves
Like tiptoeing xylophone
Oh that's
Classic sound I have actually used
That sound
I did the two Flintstone live-action movies and I did use it in that because
That was a sound that Brian Levant the director and I just loved
We just couldn't avoid using that
My favorite was The Jetsons spaceship
And I never found out what those were made from a tried to deconstruct them
I asked around the studio if they know who made them and nobody knew
But that sound always brings a smile to my face
Some of these old techniques have been lost
But remember this was a busy Studio
And everyone was focused on getting the work done on time and getting cartoons on air
It was real machine it always started with track reading
This is ballpoint
Pun
Line 1
Good evening ladies and gentlemen
Which is to say
The voices would be assembled in a studio with a script and storyboard
The director of that show would walk
The talent through the recording session so that you captured all the voices
Speaking all the lines that you needed for that particular episode
Watch Supernanny
Okay
Then the animators would go off and then draw the characters doing these things
And a month later all the animation would come back and short rolls of completed theme
Then we in the editorial Department assemble them in their storyboard order
And then cut them down to sheol
Anomatic in between like we have in live action
Weed assemble a show
And then cuts down to it
When Mark was working with Hanna-Barbera they didn't have a department dedicated to creating new sounds
If you wanted an effect that wasn't in the library. To find himself
You would just
Kind of on your own
I was the most Adventures especially for
Super Friends I would go across the hall
Talk to the two composers of Paul to court and Hoyt Curtin
And ask them for musical sounds and especially synthesizer sound so they would give me
Long
Recording
Stretches are good
Weird noises they make with their synthesizers
And they would always be used as
Science fiction components if I had a
Beijing Opera
Flying Saucer in an episode
That's what I use the electronic sounds for because that felt
Futuristic
Efmark couldn't find the sound he wanted
Create it
Even if he had to use his own voice
If you can't find it you do it with your voice it's the easiest tool to manipulate you have total control over it
I use it for creatures and animals and funny noises
I did a lot of Gremlins voices for the Gremlins movies
It's just something where you feel the character inside of yourself and you think
I can do this better
And you just do it
Mark also went on to work on some of the most classic animated films
Baidu Beauty and the Beast
Aladdin
I can show you the world
And The Lion King
March experiences with animated films were different from the grind of televised cartoons
If nothing else
You get much better
Schedules
We usually get
The time to design
And create something that no one's ever heard before
Another sort of unique distinction is that
You have the option
To create sound
First
And then have animation be done to what you did
It's not that often that we get to actually drive the in
And on the
Disney animated films in the Pixar films in the DreamWorks films and others
They're smart enough to know the value of sound and how it can be the inspiration to the artist
To draw something they might not otherwise have drawn
For example in Beauty and the Beast
Belle's dad was this inventor Aeneid built that
Funny Acts
Chopping machine
That was a sound that we made before animation
The song
That's just pure design that's when you get to let your imagination run while you can see a picture
Storyboard and then
You just get to dream up what it might sound like and that's just gold for sound designer when you should've allowed to do
Design unfettered
With all the cable channels in streaming services available today there's more animation than ever before
How does sound design work
In modern cartoons in which iconic sounds are still used today we'll get to all of that when 20,000
Hertz on 99percentinvisible continues
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
If you haven't watched a cartoon in years
It might surprise you that sounds from decades ago are still being used today
I use the older side effects
Hanna-Barbera library of the Warner Brothers Library
That's Heather Olsen
Emmy-nominated sound designer for animation
She works at Advantage Audio
Emerging on Star vs. the forces of evil for Disney XD
Trolls The Beat Goes On
Spirit riding free for netty
Uki
Fairly Odd Parents
Bunsen is a beast
Pig goat banana Cricket for Nickelodeon
Also worked on the adventures of Puss in Boots from Netflix
Gravity Falls for Disney XD
Rest assured
There's a perfectly logical explanation
And The Boondocks for Sony
Heather is an expert in modern cartoon sound design
Cartoon sound effects are different from live-action sound effects because would live action you start with production sad you record
Burning a picture in the recording the audio at the same time
Street you have cars going by
Was it a cartoon if you were doing a street seeing all I get is dialog it's just the actors were recorded
Get to start with a blank slate I don't have to try to hide production backgrounds I get to get the dialogue and I get to create a word
Roll around it
Call the best thing and the worst thing at the same time to work in a cartoon because
You're not trying to hide anything but you have nothing to start with so in your head you have to think what was the sound like
Much like marks time at Hanna-Barbera Heather gets a fully animated show and often add sound effects from a ready-made Library
Sound
This includes many from the Hanna-Barbera and Warner Brothers Library
Dear are some of her favorites
Call the tooth sunk sound effects
Everybody knows how this sounds like it's called but is that
Get your head stuck in a jar
So clearly conveys my head is stuck in his jar it's not coming out again
Elsa
I'm using the phone all the time
I think I'm just persisted in everybody is because I said language that we've started to understand
Blake's you kind of expect to hear that
And of course Heather uses the falling whistle
I think in our side effects Library it's called bomb drop but it's the same thing
That's another piece of the language that everybody knows
And some of the show she works on or more realistic
Heather wants us to hear the sounds of the characters moving around interacting with their world
Kind of like a live-action movie
The Foley Department
Really brings the shuttle life they record
Things characters
Call props
They do more of the smaller sounds and it's great to have fully doing that still alive because then you're not hearing the same
Footsteps over and over they really make it sound more real
And just like in the past
If you can't find a sound you have to make it
Stranger things I've actually recorded it done myself for a sound effect is we had a bit in robot and monster with everyone
I was in a crowded restaurant so it's supposed to be this crowd of people gagging and grossed out by something
My library
So I grabbed a bunch of people around the office
And we recorded ourselves gagging and lots of different ways
Sometimes layering multiple sounds together is the best way to create something new
Combination that you might expect
Animals in engines is a really great one animal Roars under engines growls it really kind of brings
Vehicle to life
A lot of shows do it
Star Wars the Tie fighters are some growls under there as they go by
Actually love
It's fantastic
Inspiration
Another option Heather has is to take a classic Library sound and change its pitch to make a new effect
Take this cartoon boing sound effect
She can pitch that sound up
Or down
Other uses a lot
Classic non-literal sounds while working on car
Cartoons
But some Modern cartoons are more realistic than slapstick
Our choices really depend on the show
Should I get a new show the show the clients come in
Get together
Talk about the overall feel of the show I cuz it going to be kind of a realistic show
Fairly OddParents
Fairly Odd Parents taught me how to speak cartoon
Nothing without the appropriate protective gear
It's just nonstop cartoon cartoon cartoon
Where's the Bulldog Spirit it feels more like you're making a movie with horses
Outlook Fields with girls
What's my boy
Remember me from the Train
Because Spirit riding free has more natural sounds than a cartoon like Fairly Odd Parents
Heather needed some new sounds
We got a whole new horse library because in that show there's three characters who are horses
And each of the different personalities we had to find kind of different vocals for each of the horses
But even Spirit riding free still sometimes needs a dose of the vintage cartoon sounds
A lot of times people will come in with their show and say I don't want to use his old Hanna-Barbera sounds I want to do something completely different
But they kind of animated the traditional way so when you put new sounds today
Feels wrong and a lot of times go back to using the older sound effects
When it comes to cartoon sound design
Mark and Heather both agree that the medium pushes the boundaries
Creativity
Characters
Stretch a naturally
Out of their body shape
Those are just the simplest examples of visually what's happening with these characters so
In a way
It gives you
Permission
Break the laws of
What sound you should hear when you see something
Working for animation cuz I'd like to build the world with sound from the ground up
The best part is you're designing a world from the world that no one's ever heard before
Sound design for the process for animation cuz there's no
Talking so you get to do the backgrounds and
So now
There's so many tools that anyone can get their hands on
You're really free to design sound
In any way your imagination
Desire
Important for us to
Follow our hearts
When we follow our hearts
And then we make a career out of that we make a day-to-day avocation to something
That gives all of us purpose
And it allows us to make a contribution to the world
This episode of twenty thousand Hertz was written and produced by James introcaso in Dallas Taylor
With help from Sam schneebly
Out of the studios of de-facto sound
It was edited sound design and mix
Inex Spradlin
All the music in this episode was provided by music
You should subscribe to twenty thousand Hertz there great Indie podcast with big fan of totally dig it
Weather
On our website and in the show no
99percentinvisible is our product of kalw 91.7 in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all a pot
Tmall and radiotopia
Tok FM
Eve on the show enjoying scussion about the show on Facebook and tweet me at Roman Mars the show and 99 Peoria
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But are forever home on the web
Is 99 pi
Daughter
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I got a Thang
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com