We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
When the country's leading providers of Auto in
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Sometimes when I'm driving or walking around the Bay Area
Found it
Bite
Avery Park Ice Age
In a place where each
Parcel of land could be worth millions of dollars
There are these
Shared green spaces
Better at least
Theoretically
Mint
For everyone
I feel the same about libraries are like miracle
Sticky kid will library for the first time and you'll see it is a temple
Dedicated to the concept of sharing
Hill bookstore
But also
Just sharing space
Eric klinenberg is a sociologist in best-selling author who makes a convincing case that a healthy Community is not
To be held together by shared values
Goodbye shared space
Physical
Real World locations for people across all strata
Ages races and creeds
Bump into each other
Inform connect
He also makes a convincing case that we are neglecting
Spaces
What he calls
Are social infrastructure
And this is a shame because
Could help solve or at least mitigate
Some of our most pressing challenges like isolation
Correlation education crime
And even climate change
He lays out his Manifesto in a great book he wrote called palaces for the people
I think it's just brilliant
So I asked him to chat with me
My name is Eric
Kleinenberg
I'm a professor of Sociology at New York University and I'm also the author of
A book called palaces for the people
How social interest
Structure
Can help fight inequality
Polarization and the
Decline of Civic life
Where does the phrase palaces for the people come from
It comes from
Andrew Carnegie
And I have to tell you that
I was a little nervous about using that title because
Carnegie as you might know has a pretty mixed record when it
It comes to human decency
He was really a pretty ruthless
Capitalist
You know Titan of the Gilded Age among the wealthiest people in the world when he lived
Famous for
Breaking strikes in a pretty vicious way
And doing things that
Probably promoted inequality
The many parts of the world but
Carnegie was also an immigrant
Born in Scotland and came to United States
And
He believed that one of the amazing things about the US is that it
Created in
Tutions
Where people could
Get ahead in life
And achieve
Something greater than they could have achieved
In their home countries
And he wanted to help
Build a socialist
Tution
Doubt that would do that even better
And so
Over the course of his life
He helped
To fund
More than 2500 libraries
Around the world
About 1700
Of which were in the United States
And
He called the the the greatest of them
Palaces for the
How the library is carne guisada was a place where
A person who worked in a factory
Or lived in a tenement building
And experience life
Is crowded
Uncomfortable and rushed most of the time
I could go and an escape Oliver
Santa like that the great Carnegie libraries have
High ceilings
And big windows
And spacious rooms where person can go and
Andre Dan
Think and
Achieve something
Did they kill products
And and and I just thought there's a beautiful phrase when I hurt it
It send it
Can the title for the book
You talk about libraries as being the perfect example of what you call social and
What is social infrastructure more broadly
Yeah well it's a pretty New Concept especially
In the United States
But when I use socially
Structural
What I mean to say is that
There is a set of physical
Places
And institutions
That shape our social life
And
Social infrastructure is just as real as the infrastructure
Water
Power
Or for communication
But we haven't been able to see it
Because we don't have
Concept 4S
And
You know what I've learned over the course of of my work as a social scientist
Is that
When we live in places where
Invest
In socialism
Places like libraries
Parks
A school's athletic fields
We reap all kinds of benefits
We become far more likely to interact with people around us whether they are
Friends and family
Our neighbors
We haven't gotten to know
And when we don't invest in
Structure if we neglect it
If we let it fall
All parts
We tend to grow more isolated
You mentioned that social structure is more invisible than hard infrastructure
How is it that you
Were you able to see it for the first time
Yeah well
The first time I thought about social infrastructure was
When I was a graduate student
Doing a research project on a heatwave
In Chicago
The city I grew up in
And
I was
Puzzled by it
Something very strange in this heat wave it was a disaster in 1995
Killed more than 700 people
And
As a social scientist II was interested in understanding the patterns
The first pattern I observed was the most predictable thing that could happen in
Disaster
And that's
Stats the poor neighborhoods the segregated neighborhoods
On the Southside in the Westside
Chicago
I had the highest death rate
By far than and that's not interesting
Politically important because
Story about where resources go and where vulnerability is but
Scientifically it
It's what you would expect
But when I look
Even more closely at
The patterns
Something really puzzling did emerge
And that is that there were a bunch of neighborhood
That demographic
Look like they should have fared very badly in the
Disaster
But in fact proved to be strikingly resilia
They were safer even in the most affluent neighborhoods
On the Northside
And even more interesting Lee
There are these pairs of neighborhoods where
The demographics for identical
The same proportion of old pee
4 people
African American people
And
They were
Separated by just
Street to the literally neighbor is neighboring Abraham
And one neighborhood would have a
Astronomically High death rate
And the other
Would be one of the safest places in Chicago
And
The numbers alone
Tell
Story of what was going on so
And kind of classic
Keno ethnographer style I
Started traveling around and spend time in the neighborhood
What I observed is that
Places that had
Lodi three
I turned out to have
IRobot Surfline
Are they had
Sidewalks and streets that were
Well taken care of
They had
Neighborhood libraries they had Community organization
Grocery stores
Shops and cafes that Drew people out of their home
An into public life and what that meant
Is that on a daily basis people got to know each other pretty well
They use the social infrastructure to socialize
Until when
Chicago
They knew who was likely to be sick
Who should have been outside but wasn't
And that meant they knew who's Jordan knock-on and who to help
Meanwhile in the neighborhoods that had really high death rates
The silver lamp
Structure was the
Pleated
There were a lot of abandoned
Properties
Empty lots abandoned houses
Sidewalks were often cracked and broken very little commercial life not a lot of Institutions there and
And that meant that people were likely to
Stay home and if unfortunate during the Heatwave
This is a deadly thing to do
And I realize that the end of that project
Actually it's it was social infrastructure not the
Traditional hard infrastructures that we normally think of
That that explain who lived who died that we can Chicago
Chicago Heat Wave convince Eric that social infrastructure was vital to public health and safety in cities
Years later when superstorm Sandy hit the New York area he wanted to make sure people knew that was going to take
More than just seawalls to make New York safer
And more resilient in the face of climate change
You got involved in a competition sponsored by the federal government called
Rebuild by Design in again and again he emphasized the various design teams
The importance of building infrastructure
That brings people together
But one day
I was
Taking one team around the neighborhood and Brooke
And
They came up to me and they said you know Eric we've been listening to talk about social infrastructure and how important it is
And we realized that
Enid
The design that we're going to propose for this competition
I was going to be right in line with that
We have this idea for something we're calling a resilient set
I said wow that sounds amazing and who wouldn't want to resilience Center
Can you tell me about it
And they said
Okay so
Set this resilience Center is
Hyena going to be
A nice building
That will put in that in a vulnerable neighborhood in the town in Connecticut
And I we we we see is a prototype
That we could build
And in cities all over the country
And it will be open as much as as possible
It will be spacious it will have flexible uses
It will be staffed by
In a Personnel who are
Aggressively welcoming
The job is really to make everyone feel like they're welcome
I all the time
And
You know we know that that very young people and very old people are most at risk
And most need kind of resilience at home because they might not be as mobile as other parts of the population so
We're going to have all kinds of special programming for kids like
Things like storytime in the morning and since we know the kids come with caretakers in a parents or grandparents
Star sitters
Will do something for them to maybe we'll give that me no access to Wi-Fi and
Computers
And we really see this
This resilience Center as an amazing new Institution
That could strengthen people who live in every vulnerable part of
And I said to them
Wow you know that's an amazing idea
Cuz I'm a professor and I'm used to telling people first that their ideas are amazing
And then I said
Have you ever heard of a library
Speak because clearly they they had just redesign the wheel and at first I thought it was a little crazy
But then I realize that
It was
Completely predictable
And forgivable
Lie because
We live in a moment where
I so many people think of the library as
An obsolete insta
Right we
Wait we think it's a A Relic from another part of our history
And that it's
Not used much
Bye
By anyone
Even though it turns out that nothing could be further from the truth
And so I realized that I really needed to
Spend more time in libraries myself
And to write something
That reminded
People
Just all of the extraordinary things that libraries do
As social infrastructure
Banana because
They're such
Valuable institutions for us
And yet they are taking for granted and in many parts of the world in the country
On The Chopping
And so Eric started visiting libraries all over the country
He went to small town libraries
Suburban libraries
Big City libraries designed by famous architects
And small neighborhood libraries in little brick buildings
A nice time
He found lots of people using the library
And many of them
Using it in some pretty surprising ways
One of my favorite programs
I came from
The Brooklyn library where they created
The Library Lane
Virtual bowling league
Which meets weekly
In the basements and can kind of community centers inside Library
Common rooms
And the context for understanding why these things are so amazing is that about 20 years ago
A great social scientist and Robert Putnam
I read a book how bowling alone the complaint was like people
Used to do things
Together collectively
Informal groups and now everyone like in putnam's nightmare from 1999
Everybody was just watching television at home together in the living room
You know I think of now that I have kids who have like there on mobile devices that's like a socialist Utopia
Fantasy
Oh my God if only we could have a night together watching the same screen and it would be amazing
But
In it what what happened in Brooklyn is that the
Controlling people realize if there's all the older people
Who live alone in neighborhoods around New York City
And it did exactly the people who would have been most likely to die in the heat wave in Chicago
The writing
A tenant and they have to do special programming for them and
Some some older people are booked a session and
R1 duarte's things with some actually want to be physical and
And exercise
And be social that way and they need to be
So they created this program called Library Lanes
And when once a week
This group
Of older people
Come together and they put on
Actual bowling jerseys with their Library name on it
And a librarian connects an Xbox
2 television
And they compete against other Library teams who and I'll tell you like I'm a sports junkie I spend my weekend
Ken's following my son around his soccer games I like to go to professional and college games
I'm not lying Ramen when I tell you that
I haven't been to a sporting event is exciting and collectively effervescent the sociological
As this incredible match
In East New York where it where likely is this group of older bowlers
Came back and like encrusted in the final frames to win the match is amazing
Not so great
Wii bowling tournaments is not exactly what people think of when they think of a library and probably isn't who certainly wasn't what
Andrew Carnegie
What library is being used today outside of that the conventional like you get a library card you get
Yeah my goodness I was just thinking about Andrew Carnegie
You know being told about all the things that these palaces for the people have turned into it
I hope you would like that I mean let me tell you about some of the things that I saw I mean first of all
Libraries remain places where lots of early literacy
Development happens
And every morning often
Before the library would open
The librarian to open the doors for
Groups of preschoolers
Working a kids from Day Camp who would come in
I would teachers and get exposed to books
Spend and be told stories
And you know there's so many people who judge
Can't afford
I don't have books at home
Have parents who
Speak another language
And they and they come to the library
Learn to read and to learn to love books and that's amazing
Probably Carnegie anticipated that
He probably would not have seen that
You know libraries have now become the places where
People who
I used to be incarcerated, more than any other institution to
Search for job
To get help putting a resume together
He probably would not have anticipated
That libraries have become the
Places where there's more
Instruction for english-as-a-second-language
More citizenship classes
Are there any other public
Petition
He probably didn't
Anticipated
Libraries that do things like you know karaoke hours for
Immigrant communities that want a good place to sing together. You know I don't know that he would have seen all the team
Teenagers
Who comes to the library at the end of
The school day
Because it's the the safest
And warmest
Or if you're in a hot place
Coolest place where you can
You can study
Apply for college
Or just kind of mess around and play video games in a social way like
I'll tell you I said so so many kids come to libraries
Two-player games
And
Like when they play games together they did it in a way that was very Collective and very social it was not the
A stereotypical image of a kid
Die in a hole in their is knowing their own basement being on their own they were socializing this very new way
Libras is doing an enormous number of things
And I really think that we fail to recognize
How lucky we are to have inherited this
This institution I don't know if you saw this but about a year ago
There was a article that came out in
Forbes Magazine where an economist argued that
Libraries are in fact Obsolete and said you know if you don't show me the
Cost-benefit analysis that cashes out the value of the library
I think we should stop all the public contributions to them knock them down and replace them with Amazon stores
And I'm
Eunos animes like At first I thought my friends were just trying to troll Me by typing this article it for her.
If I was writing about the library
But then it turned out it was real
And it and it's amazing thing happened
The Librarians of the world United
God on Twitter
And wrote the most eloquent
Testimony to the
The ongoing power of libraries
To convene
People and
They wrote Such amazing things that
Forbes literally took the article down the next day
DIY that one of the few good things a Twitter has ever done so far
When I try to think of like what a great social interest
It's it. The libraries are the only social infrastructure
Hardly. But they're just about the most
Effective social life
The structure that I
I can imagine
And it is
It is it is a shame that we don't make more of them
By maintaining them or updating them
In the way that they deserve
Eric is there still radical and Innovative today
That's what's so amazing about
You bet they reinvented themselves
And and one of the things that so striking about libraries is that
The local staff has the
Capacity
An agency
Develop programming that works for the community that they're in
Are there stairs there's no strong hard rule that says a library has to do XYZ thing so
Library Canby
Okay can lend tools
It can land seeds
They can lend a close to people who
You need better clothes for a job interview
I can do programming all kinds of languages you know
I'm sure listeners can think of
50 things that happened
And their libraries that I don't even know about
Has the design if you space is shifted as they start to accommodate all these other activities besides
Some books and magazines and newspapers
Very much so
Although not as much as it
Could
If libraries had more resources
To to play with and
You know one of the things that I've seen is
A certain municipalities have
Recognize the value of libraries and have invested in
New facilities that can do other things like
Most libraries need to have a special room or set of rooms for teenagers now
Because so many of them come in in the afternoon
Did they can quite easily take over the
Maintenance make it difficult for other people
Also
So you see a lot of teen room
Unfortunately
Libraries have become these institutions of Last Resort for people who
Slip through the cracks in
Our safety net
And and so like you'll find homeless people
And people with mental illnesses
And and people were really struggling to get by oftentimes
What drug addiction
Coming to library
Sand
And I need
Special kind of
Protection or assist
And some libraries including in San Francisco
I have really been aggressively
Experimenting
I went with ways to provide more supportive environments
Like like that
Other countries have made massive new investment
In
National Library building
Things that
Extraordinary
The new library in Helsinki is amazed
There's a new library in Calgary that's
Amazing
And some American cities are beginning to invest in libraries as well
But but generally speaking when that happens
We invest in time to bright shiny Central Library
That you know that that patrons are likely to
I feel proud of rather than in the the branch libraries
Which I really the lifeblood
In the book you also talked about crime as an infrastructure issue which is
Which was a really
Subtle Nuance on the
Broken windows theory that I found really intriguing yeah
I don't know how much
People know about the broken windows theory of
Policing
I'm crying but
You know this kind of classic essay
This point from James Q Wilson
Enjoyed killing
That said that
When are broken windows in a neighborhood
People perceive the
Broken windows as a sign that no one is organizing the neighbor
No one has social
And
The notion is that criminals
Realized niche
Could get away with anything
In a place like
And so did
Intriguingly when
The original broken windows article came out
It was used as adjusted
Vacation
Green lot more police
Cin2
Poor neighborhood
Shred-it is broken windows
Theory got us
The stop-and-frisk policing and zero tolerance
Policing
Cuz the notion was
If you've got
Disorder
You need to make sure that there's a lot of extra help
How to keep criminals from doing that
And and that was a
Is a big reason that we have
System of mass incarceration that's really transformed
The United States
Sand
Especially poor neighborhood rain
And having spent a lot of time thinking about
The power of social infrastructure
And physical places
I found myself asking this question like
What would have happened if
We responded to its broken windows
Not by sending in so many police officers
But by fixing the damn Windows right. How did nobody ever think of that
And I went
And it's really weird like how I went back to the original article when I had that. End
And I found that if you really closely
That the chain of events
That leads to this idea that we should send in more police and do Zero Tolerance policing
Is
You know a neighborhood gets
Abandoned
Property property gets abandoned
God graffiti goes up a Windows broken
And then it thinks going to spiral out of
So hot why is it that
Siri wasn't called
You know the abandoned property Theory
This is a horrible title right broken windows is an awesome title
Ilia bowling alone and broken windows it was great like catchy phrases
Better not to justify
Really terrible social policies
And in the case of the broken windows thing it didn't even work. So we forgot all about the abandoned property part
So I started asking like what would happen
If we had fixed the windows if we did fix up their property
And when I asked it turns out that
Someone
Else
I would have thought about it much more than I had there's a
The team of
A scientist
At the University of Pennsylvania
That had been asking a similar question and they want of teaming up with
The city of Philadelphia
Which has tens of thousands
Of
Abandoned
Properties
An empty lot
And also the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society which like sounds like
Like an old person's gardening club but turned that kid is like
Powerhouse operation that
Helps to control all this vacant land
In Philadelphia
And they started like one of the most exciting social science
Experiments that I know of
Happening right now
And for more than a decade they been doing the same witches
Date they
Randomly select
Blocks
Where they will make simple intervention
So
If there is an abandoned house
They would
Board up the building and prevent
Squatters or being a potential drug dealers are criminals from from using
Property and if it's an empty lot
That would have
Weeds and
And debris
All kinds of garbage that would make it a
Public health hazard
They would clean it up
Motown
And put in a little pocket park maybe plant
Tree put in a bench
Put a wooden fence
And
Are they wanted to see what happened in the places where they made the interview
Pension and what happened in the places that they left alone
And the results were staggering
They achieved
Almost
40%
Decline
In
Gun violence
Around the
Abandoned properties that they treated
And that's it that's a staggeringly high number
Tic-tac-toe
To get that in
MMS has been durable
I over the course of
Decade
What's more they
Babe
Hooked up
Heart rate monitors
The people who live in those neighborhood
And they found that
Even for resident
When you walk by
An untreated Property 2
Just an abandoned places
Left to
Become a site of debris
Are people's heart rates really spiked
And of course we know that the
Stress-related
Diseases are especially High
A n
App for neighborhoods that have a lot of abandonment
IBooks but when people walk by a place it's been treated
And turned into a little Park
The heart rate hardly changes
And again looks like I'm amazing thing to achieve with a modest investment
In Social and
And did the crime just
Move
From one place to another or did it just reduce
In total
Yeah so that's what they thought was going to happen that
Fix up one block and crime just bounces to the next one
But the amazing thing here is
It didn't
It turns out that
Unless we think of crime is being about like
In a bad individuals doing bad things and
No. That's part of the story
But a lot of crime is just
Situational
I'd like if if you had if you create a city with lots of places
Where no one is
Is in control
And no one feels a sense of
Responsibility a 10 people have a hard time
Managing things
You create situations
Where crime is more likely
But if you
Take those situations away
The crime
Doesn't happen
And so the answer is no
I did not get
Are the crime bounce
Elsewhere
It's simply didn't have
Service bring your book and I think about myself in the in the city and how I interact with people
And how
My lived experience in my ideal Isaac
France is sometimes or not in
Complete concert so like a flower planter at Planters when I pay for it
Does a person floating through life
I don't always want to encounter people
When we live in New York City man I get that when we build social infrastructure
How do we make sure we're designing for our true selves and not our idealized self
Yeah well
It's my take hear that
There's no shortage of
Places where people can
Hunker down and get their own private space Tuesdays
We've created a whole society
I based on our idealization
Of privacy and autonomy
Right I mean like
It is
It used to be that
Family shared bedrooms together like family shared beds together
Now that I know so many people who moved out of their cities
Because they felt like their kids needed to have their own individual bedroom
Right I mean it's just
So so I feel like I'm with you that
We all need
Spacer privacy and in fact like a library is a really amazing social infrastructure and Park
Because
It combines you know shared tables and programs and activities
With little nooks where person can go and and anonymously
I'll be in the round head
Righto and Atalanta Park
Does the same thing
Write a park can be a place
For Collective life
And a parking be a place
Where we go to be like the rest
Anna and have our own time and space
I think you're right we always need to be mindful of those things you know we don't want to force people out into the public Realm
Hobbit but my sense right now
Is that the it's the publicly accessible
Public round that's really in shorts
I'm intrigued by this idea of them
Public ownership and how we
Convey that I mean I think one of the reasons why
The pocket Parks work and
Libraries work
It's because
We feel like we own them when they're done right
You know we feel like we belong
And that makes everyone
You know
Closer connected also just like
Tube8
They treat the world better
When it's ours
Private space
That we
Can just occupied as long as we
Are buying that
Cup of coffee
How do we make sure we make things so that everyone feels like
Like there really a
Oh man that is such a tough question
And I've been thinking about a lot you know especially in light of
The past year we've
You know we started
Seymour Public Li
Just how restrictive
An exclusive
Some of our
You know most
Value
Semi public spaces can be like
Remember that that video that circulated
About the
Two African American guys
Send Philadelphia who wanted to
To Starbucks now
And
Yeah that
They went there. Tell me if this ever happened to you like you go to meet somebody and they're late
Like all the time.
Right so you guys go and like
I know that I sat in Starbucks
Waiting for someone who doesn't show up for
10 20 30 minutes an hour and no one's ever said anything to like
You know why professional academic writing
Guy but but like
These two guys
Like the it
If they don't get asked to buy something
They don't
Get politely asked to leave they get arrested right then being in this in the shared space
Crazy thing
And until and that context
People who get in feel entitled and privileged
There's a whole bunch of people who laughed at all together
And that alerted me to the sent that like
To the extent that our public space and are our public realm are shared spaces
Are part of the commercial economy
They are really restrict
You have to be able to pay you have to be let in
Interlock places especially like in gentrifying neighborhood
Insidious
Where
Your people just know that they're not welcome
Because
It cost $7 for coffee or $9 for ice cream or they don't take cash at all
They're their only for people with credit cards right
And I have to say like one of the most amazing things I observed
In the public libraries where I spent time
Is that
There places where
This impossible community of people
Who are so different from one another
Come together
And all kinds
Who have real struggle
Come to because
There's just not space for them
Anywhere else
And in the year that I spent going to the library
Pretty much every day
I can count on one hand
The number of times that
The police had to be called in
And there was a real site
Security concern
People
We know where we're acting out
Towards one another
Most of the time when people going to libraries
They recognize that they are being respected
And dignify
And honored
And and I think
It brings out the best in US
So so I think it's a great question.
What kinds of public places
Can do that
Redken exalt are
Experience in the world in the way that the Libor
And and what can we do to make sure that the places that we built
Do that even better
Is there any momentum towards more social infrastructure are there
I mean do we require a modern-day
Carnegie
Do we require a government to do more to eat require us to just demand more what what is it going to take and
Evidence that
It's happening
Urgent
Question you know how we going to
To pay for this
And
It's true that Carnegie was a
The philanthropist
Austin philanthropic dollars went to build a bunch of libraries and
Am I close the book by noting how strange it is that
You know we live in a world with these kind of
Titans of the information age
Who have
Made
Billions of dollars
We have a things like social media
And computing
And who haven't made contributions to
Social infrastructure
In a way that
That I would like to see
In fact like
1A
Really off-putting things for me about
I like Mark Zuckerberg's use of the concept social infrastructure is
Is that
He's been promoting Facebook as
Social infrastructure he uses the language
The 21st century and says you know Facebook is where we'll go for Meaningful
Interactions and yet if you go to the Facebook campus
Menlo Park
Like no one on earth has spent more money on actual physical social infrastructure than marks
It's it's a workers Paradise there right in front of the bike paths in the yoga studios in the shared spaces for
Serendipitous encounters and
I know that
Massages for people while they're coding at their desks like it's amazing there
And
Emmett in fact people who work in those companies don't let their kids
Go on the devices cuz they know how dangerous a phone can be as social infrastructure
So on the one hand I kind of want to see
The big philanthropist of our time
Spend more on things like libraries
But I also know in my heart that
Enough
Philanthropic dollars
Are ultimately inadequate
And I kind of like randomly distributed to the places where the philanthropist 10 to spend time
And that if we're ever really going to make this work
It's going to have to be through a public commit
I got a major public works program
And
I think it's just a matter of time until we do that
Yeah but but clearly we're going to have to muster up the
The collective Will Ferrell
And we certainly can't eat a rally for it and call for it if we don't have a name for the thing that we want
And that's one reason why I hope that social infrastructure
This is sticky that it means something cuz you know what we have no problem paying for infrastructure
When it comes to
The things that we think of is critical
The infrastructures like one of the few things that both Trump and Clinton agree that we needed rent a few years ago
I just hope we can recognize the need for social and fish
Structure
And find some way
To persuade the people who are running our government
That without their support it will never have
It's Weenie like a social infrastructure week
I'm thinking more like a decade at least
A-10 look like if you look at any report that comes from you know the World Bank
Or even our own government
They recognize that
You know we will soon be spending
Tens of billions of dollars then hundreds of billions of dollars
And trillions of dollars internationally
To build new infrastructure
Because the the systems that we have
To keep us in the modern world simply don't work
And we know it's true in the case of the subway
And we know it's true in the case of the power grid
And it's my observation that it is
Also true maybe even more true
In the case of our social infrastructure
That they've just been absolutely
Neglected
At an end if we if we want to support the kind of social life that that we all need to know regardless of our Pilots
Text regardless of our income
And regardless of where we live
That we all need
LivWell
And any better connected
With each other
We're we're going to have to find a way
To invest in
Eric klinenberg book is called palaces for the people
You will enjoy reading it and
Nodding vigorously along with it
You can get it at a bookstore near you or
You don't forget it from the library
Next
Avery trufelman joins me in the studio for a little announcement
Stay with us
You you inspired Xfinity to create internet that puts you in charge
I brought your movie marathons are better when you can stream them all night
Video chats for Grandpa's birthday it should be possible from anywhere in your house
And when you can pause wifi before bedtime
Putting your kids to sleep
Gets a little bit easier
So Xfinity reimagined Wi-Fi in created Xfinity X5
Because for the best Wi-Fi experience you need speed
Coverage and control
This is beyond WiFi
This is X
Visit xfinity.com
To learn more
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
Open up man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24
Right here on the 99.
Make yourself and make it stand out with Squarespace
Create a beautiful website to promote your business public content sell products and much much more
I'm in Squarespace sites Roman mars.com to Showcase my work
His links to my TED Talk
Radiotopia
Steven has a sign-up
For the 99percentinvisible Weekly Newsletter
It was really easy to make a man of myself
Which is how I know that you'll have no problem making a Squarespace site
Christmas basic cam for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Easy offer code invisible
Oprah 10% off
The first purchase of a website or domain
Avery trufelman producer
At 99percentinvisible and Creator and host of Articles of interest and we have
An announcement
We do but this is the wind up to be announced
I recently went on a tour
The San Francisco Goodwill processing
Thinkcentre when you donate something to Goodwill and you're in the San Francisco area
It goes
This Warehouse
Sordid
Moved
To the place to the location where it will be sold
Huge
Hanger of a building in there so much activity
They are
Running out of space
The amount of stuff
They have increased by
30%
Because of Marie kondo because everyone else was the end of the year
Shenzhen taxes
But
Aegis
We're running out of space
Temporary
Racks on racks on racks on racks on racks
And it's pretty overwhelming
When you see it
All-in-one play
And it seems to me
In this world of ours
Has never been a better time
To talk about
What you wear
And really take a look at what you own and think about it
Your groundbreaking podcast within a podcast called articles of Interest
Which is now
Not just about gas within a podcast but it has its own feet
That's our announcement
So
You know you can go on Titan
Score
Apple podcasts or radio public or Google Play
And download all the episodes of Articles of Interest
We did this because
We know that many of you heard them if you're listening to 99ci right now means you already subscribe tonight NPI
But
We wanted them available
You almost look for archived
So you can just go listen to articles of interest and you can share that and I think that's
Really really
So we have a new feed available for that
And also on the feed is
The theme song which so many people have asked about
Advice to tell me a swear if she's amazing
And she has an album out now but this
Song the theme song of Articles of Interest
Just so beautiful has been stuck in my head for months now it's
So good you can only get that
Welcome fans of uploaded it to YouTube if you want to listen to it extremely conveniently
On your phone it's on the 5th
If you go subscribed articles interest right now or you can get
All six episodes and maybe you heard them that you should definitely them again I know if I heard them a bunch of times and they always reveal more and more
Barbie cancer
Intently
Constructed in
They speak to each other in cool ways and
You'll notice it more when you listen to it again
And you also on the TV show gets asami's theme song which we commissioned like an original commission for the
2 Series
And you'll have them all right they're all like full 7 episodes
Something delicious
Also I need your help because last night when Roman told me that the feed was up I went in and checked it out
Right away and you
You just go to the iTunes Store and you search articles of Interest
It'll come up
And it already had like at the moment it was born
Someone gave it a review and I just said yo this podcast is insufferable
Which of the Great welcome to the world of broadcasting
So here's the deal here's what you're in charge of now like you fare list
Go review articles of address to give it five stars anything is that
Cold out at the end of last year as
What's the best podcast of the Year from a lot of people
And if you're one of those people that admired as much as we did here and the people did largely out in the world besides this guy who's
I'm go give it five stars go download it again
Shirt with your friends this is an easy way to do it instead of going to I don't know and I don't even know what episodes it was like episode
310-230-6316 or something else
Find it on its own
Describe it let's run to the top of the charts and let people find it again I would really really enjoy that
So go out there and
Spread the word
Or they can be at second Viennese
Number of stars you want I just want more variety than one 1 star review
This guy does yoga
Cernit sky
Thank you. It's so quickly I don't know if he hates me or
Like love to me I like that you found this somehow
What is amazing Thailand
You said make me happy in the average get the average up
Insert with people and and go listen to the episodes again
Because it really really great so
So that's our little
Happy birthday articles of Interest
Happy Independence Day
And you mentioned going to Goodwill
And so that means you're probably
Doing stuff
Messing around
Listen listen listen to announce one's intentions
Is ultimately to broadcast one's failures so I don't want to I don't want to jinx anything
Anyway
You'll hear more about that
Great thanks every
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital director
The rest of Team includes senior editor Delaney Hall Sharif Youssef
Avery charm Intermezzo Joe Rosenberg Vivien Leigh Sophia klatzker and me Roman Mars
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most in a
Innovative shows in all a podcast
Fun Mall
Radiotopia
Tok FM
You find the Shogun join discussion about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you want links to Eric's book
And the articles of Interest feed
Look no further
The 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com