99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
My Roman Mars
Barbara Visser was 9 years old the first time she saw it
She was on the school field trip to the State art museum in the center of Amsterdam
I guess it's about
They were really at the Forefront of
Modern and contemporary art
The State Electric was built to impress
A huge
Stairway
Leading up to the light anyway a bit biblical stairway
Note to heaven but almost to Heaven 2
The whole of all nurse
Has displayed some of the Museum's finest paintings
In particular dominated the room
The tour guide LED Barbara and her class over
And this painting it struck me
Like lightning
And not in a positive way
What you saw was a massive canvas 18 ft wide and 8 feet tall
On the left side of a small strip of blue
On the right
A small strip of yellow
But the rest of the surface was painted entirely red
This Majestic
Fire truck red
It's kind of annoyed me
It's really
I didn't know
What to look at
Where to
What to do with it
And the only thing that the guides
Shared with us was the title
And the title is
Question
Who's afraid of red yellow and blue
Angry
Iran
I sat on the steps and
Was
Determined to go in
The full title of the painting Barbara saw that day is who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
By the American post-war artists
Barnett Newman producer John Cecile brings us this Tale
The galleries
Usually you walk into a museum is he a painting
You think about it for a moment maybe feel something
And walk away
Not this one
This was a painting that would produce such strong reactions in people
That they did more
Think about it
Denis and Barbara got off easy
She only struggle with the painting her entire life and made a feature-length documentary about it
It's called the end of fear and inspired the story
And
This story is about a reaction the painting received that was
So intense
So violent
It set off a chain of events
That Shook the art world to its core
Wasn't easy art
But first
Why this painting
The problem
Of the subject
Became
Very clear to me
As a crucial thing in painting
Barnett Newman was a late bloomer
A substitute art teacher turned art critic
Turned artist
He didn't have his first solo show until he was almost
She was as portly Jewish guy with a big friendly mustache who wore a lot of bow ties
And went by the nickname Barney
And he quickly became the de-facto spokesman for a new art movement called abstract expressionism
A painter is a kind of choreography of space
Create kind of a dance of elements
Abstract expressionism came out of New York after World War II
The movement please painters like Jackson Pollock
Mark rothko and Helen frankenthaler
Artist
Known for big canvases full of wild colors
Shapes and splashes of paint
Like many abstract expressionist artists Newman struggled with what to paint in the aftermath of the war
I thought the issue Emoji is was
Odoo
After all
What could you paint after the Holocaust
Hiroshima
Human answering this question required ignoring all of art history and starting from scratch
He began making large painting
Big
Even by abstract
Expressionist standards
Austin filling the entire wall of a gallery
Billions size doesn't come
It's scale accounts
Humanscale account
These paintings were
Physically big
NFL even bigger
They featured very few colors
Usually one solid Hue broken up by a few vertical stripe
Whatever you do don't call him stripes
I did not decide
The saying to myself
I'm going to paint stripers
Newman preferred to call them zip
I feel that my
Does not divide my painting
I feel it does the exact opposite
It creates a totality
In 1967
Newman finished what would prove to be one of his largest painting
Who's afraid of red yellow and blue
It was the third in a series
The title was a reference to who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf
A landmark play
Later a movie
Starring Elizabeth Taylor and Richard Burton
About a relationship full of miscommunication be careful not to pieces accuseal
Betrayal
Total
In a sense this big red painting with a slender zip of blue on the left
Play Slender zip of yellow on the right
Was Newman's way of saying
This is what a painting can do
But
What was the painting doing exactly
Barbara Visser says that when the state elect Museum acquired who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3 and 19 6
Why do people did not like it
Ashley let's go with the spice people despised
At the time
People would ride
Really long and elaborate letters
Touche how much they hated
Face painting
The painting evoked a common complaint about abstract art
Which is the throw your hands up and say why is this art
I paid to see art dammit not red paint on a canvas
Anybody can do that
There was one woman who Express that
It's really nauseated her and
Really literally made her sick
She felt it better be hung out of the CO2
Cochic
In 1986
The painting was the centerpiece of an exhibit called
The grand parade
La Grand Parada
Express CC Sabathia ejected
The purpose of which was to raise exactly this question
Of what a painting is or is it
Facebook
Depends
And that's when the negative opinions of who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
We're taking
To a whole new level
At the time Barbara was an art school
Somehow in the
Corridors of the school
People
Whispers
How did you hear it's something happened at the State Museum
You couldn't really verify it
I was on my way to the state museum for meeting
Patrick cincotta an artist and educator
Walked into the stator like that afternoon
Once there she headed to the gallery where who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
Was hanging
And then I
Came up on bedroom and there
I saw Jesus painting of Justice shorts
In attendance in the corner
Too petrified to move
The painting
Had just been attacked
And the man who did this
Set on the bench
The tall brown-haired man sitting quietly on the bench
Add stab the painting with a box cutter
Tracing a series of long slashes to the very center of the campus
Physicals in long long
Horizontal
The canvas had lost its tension
Sad
Turning the cuts
In a lopsided smile
And exposing the white wall behind
Patrick took it all in
And I saw this is a blink
Lands End
She went to find the Museum's curator
And I scream the painting is destroyed
It's murder
I remember I got a cold
Weekend
And I was at home
Ice Brown's Humulin is an art conservation expert in the Netherlands
And even though he didn't work at the
State Electric
He was called in that day
Along with the police
The director was there and
That lot of people wear
Around Italy
20 people are around in there
It was a lot of
Tension
The painting was laid out
In the middle of the gallery
They had it on the ground already
Face down
Could you see the slashes
Yes
The flashes when added up together
Measured nearly 50 ft long
Petra and Ice brand couldn't quite believe it
That's all I remember of the day
The show
Awful
The attackers name was here art Ian Van vlaanderen
Why did he do it
I did ask him
He was 31 unemployed living with his parents
He was a painter himself although not very
Barbara looked into his past
I haven't seen his is
Before he is sex offender
But I know that
Is
Action
What's regarded by him
Autistic
Gesture
Modern came from the school of thought that valued things like Landscapes and figures
He hated abstract art
Installed the painting is a kind of
Cultural provocation
One of the main arguments
His lawyer made in his defense
Was that
The provocation that the work inevitably
Cold for an action and
Goswami
Even as one blotter and was being sentenced
The five months
In prison
He stood by his action
As a defense of artistic value
Many people in the Netherlands agreed
They sent letters
Do the state elect
This so-called vandals should be made the director of modern museum
Red one
He did what hundreds of thousands of us would have liked
To do read another
Do you think that this painting was designed to upset people
That's an interesting question
I think
The provocation was not
The first intention of the work
But I do think that a title like that
Because it's a question
Dammam
An answer
The painting was meant to challenge you
Although by all accounts
Newman who died in 1970
Would have been
Horrified by what happened
Well then bladder and sat in prison the canvas of who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
Remained in tatters ice Browns and other experts wondered if it could be restored
Their initial prognosis was grim
Old paintings damage paintings can be treated
But you don't know what the results will be and in this case of course I
Realized it
This would be an enormous job
Or maybe an impossible job
These things look like anybody could do it that's not the case it's not
Carol mancusi ungaro from the Whitney Museum is one of the leading experts in the field of art conservation
The terminology in America is conservation
Not restoration
Okay good to know
Carol has Pioneer technique
Thanks for restoring work by modern and contemporary artists
She's worked on several paintings
By Barnett Newman
I've been in this business for a long time 40 years
Dali
She says
That there are set rules that conservators must follow
When repairing a painting
Irreversibility is a cardinal rule of conservation
We make every effort to not use any material that
That cannot be
Removed
Or reverse
In the future
For example if
Conservators add paint to a canvas
They want to make sure that
Paint can be dissolved
And removed later
They do this in case the artwork needs to be retouched again in the future
Conservators also try to preserve as much of the original material as possible
Touching only the areas that need treatment
And
They really study the yard
And look at their past work
In order to get a sense of what the artist was
Just trying to achieve
With these rules in mind
The state elect phoned up practically every conservator in Europe
As they tried to figure out how to repair who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
And it's 50 Ft worth
The slashes
Bee Health conferences with the best
People in the business
They couldn't really agree on what was the
Best way to do it
The biggest challenge perhaps counterintuitively was the very Simplicity of the painting
The busy texture and detail of a Picasso or Rembrandt
Often helps mask the repair work
But Newman's canvas was mostly just one big swath of uniform color
Any sign of repair however minor should be sure to stand out
Most conservators were too scared to try
Nobody wanted to burn their hands on it
As we say
But someone
Finally came to the rescue
Daniel goldbriar was conservator based in New York
Who had worked with Newman while he was still alive
They approached him Daniel Gaul Trier
And asked whether he was
Sheets to do it
He was very optimistic he said he could mend it
98%
This is 98% restorable
I'm Daniel goldwire
Gold Buyer promised that when he was done the slashes would be virtually invisible
The officials at the state elect breathed a sigh of relief
And
In 1987 who's afraid of red yellow and blue
3 was rolled up
Put in a narrow coffin like box
And carried solemnly down the steps
Beijing Museum
Then it was shipped off
The gold buyers studio in New York
From that time
The state liquor
Centier
Much about it
Ghost Rider this is not a small job so please
Piano please leave me leave me
To do the job
A year pass
Mentoo
Then three
Eventually the museum is like
What's up with our painting
You should post it
Funway
4 1/2 years later
Gold dryer
Unveil the painting
And when the museum director
A guy named Van Buren
Came to inspect his work
There was no sign of the flashes
The damage
Having a race
Who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
Was headed
Back to Amsterdam
Shortly after its exhibited again
The Press
Is invited
Debater speaks of the return of lost son
Did try to make it a very festive
Precious Moments
But
First day back
Visitors the museum
Began to notice
To keep people from getting too close to the painting
The museum had installed a low fence
One guy there
A conservator if you didn't work for the museum
Decided The Hobbit
He really wants to smell
Piano notes not just look at it from a distance
The he looks
And he said
What's ISO before
This is this is something else
Ice brand was there that day too
I immediately recognized it
It was like a wool
Milotic paintball
You know Dell
No tension
Yes the slashes had been repaired and yes the surface was still red
But before there had been depth
To the ride
Shimmering wall
That was all gone
How did you feel
Incredibly disappointed
End
About set
Fairies
Very sad
Did you feel like the painting had been ruined
Yahoo
At first
The museum tried to deny it
The director was like what are you talkin about it looks good as new
But everybody else was like
Dude come on
The city council of Amsterdam which on the museum in
Technically on the painting
Sent it to a forensic lab
How to figure out what goal dryer I done
In the lab
They
Made cross-sections
The layers
Because
Usually
A painting especially in oil painting
It's not one layer
Many different layers
Like the layers in the ground you know like archaeologists uses layers in the ground so you see all the paint layers and then
They took these tiny sample
From the red part of the painting
And compare them to earlier sample
Olsat icebrand and the other has had pulled off the gallery floor the day the painting was slashed
And then it was
Very
Very very clear
That
Four layers of
Paint on top of your original one
And the four layers of new flat dull paint didn't just cover the areas that have been slashed
Gold wire had painted over the entire red part of the Canada
Basically
The whole painting
And Gold dryer hadn't used oil pan
Which is what Newman have used
He'd use a type of acrylic paint known as Al-Qaeda
What you use for house pay
House paint
Destroys
Is house paint very hard in
In 10 years
It becomes very hard and very
Impossible actually 2
Takeoff
And that's not all
There were also splatters of red paint on the blue and yellow Zips at either side of the canvas
Which indicated
That gold Rider had used a paint roller
Gold dryer had rolled over the entire canvas
Of a 20th century masterpiece
With house paint
Who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
Have been murdered
Again
Theories abound as to what went wrong in that Long Island Studio
Maybe goldwire bluffed his way into the job
Realized it was a nearly impossible task
And panic
Not everyone felt he'd ruin the painting
Barnett Newman's Widow for instance. He did a good job although she hadn't seen it in good lighting
Publicly
Gold Rider insisted he hadn't painted over the camper
He said he had pinpointed the damaged area with 2 million tiny.
He said I did not owe her by this painting
That was
Really alive
We got we could prove it
Even though
They just proving all this
The state Alec was in a bind
Because the Museum's director had signed off on the restoration
Gold Rider suit for defamation
And the museum settled
The whole Affair cost over a million bucks and
To this day
They're stuck with a damaged painting
And I can't really talk about that damage that was part of the settlement
But for
In 1997
11 years after the flashing
Bun bladder in the slasher
Found out about the botched restoration of who's afraid of red yellow and blue
3 apparently he to believe that the painting had been robbed of its original Power
Even if you hated it
So we called the museum
He was put through to the new director
A man named Rudy Foo
Fuchs
Recorded the call
The attacker tells
Fuchs
That's
What he did in 1986
He would do that again
To restore
Should I cut it up again the slasher ass
Obviously not
But it's been totally.
The Flasher says
That's your opinion
Suspects
It's quiet
And he's
Apparently thinking about
About that
Then he says
Okay okay
I know now what to do
36 answers
Well I wouldn't do what you think you have to do
And then
Conversation
After this phone call from bladder and returns to the museum
He enters unrecognized
He looks around
Whos afraid of red yellow and blue 3
But the painting is not on display
Essence moments
We came to the museum with fairy
Clear intentions
It must be hard for him not to
Find
That work
So instead he goes and finds another painting by Barnett Newman
A large Blue painting
The white ZIP down the middle
Call Cathedral
That's another moment in my life I I will never forget
3D fix the Museum's director
Call Carol mancusi-ungaro
Right after it happened
You know it was a phone call for me to fix directress Kadlec that was a big deal so I immediately went to my office to take the phone call
And
He told me
That Cathedral been slashed and I swear the hair on my arms just to die
I could not believe
But it happened and it was the same person
For the second time
Here are Ian Van vlaanderen at attack
A Barnett Newman painting with a knife
When he was done he threw a packet of pamphlets on the
Floor that contained rambling incoherent writing
The others that aspect of it was
The slash marks where exactly the same
They were so
Similar to the earlier attack
That it became known as the artist signature
The flashers
Signature
At his second trial
Lateran was declared mentally unfit
And sent to a psychiatric Institution
Aaron's attacks may have been motivated by mental illness
But in the era of public art
They're part of a long sad history of vandalism
Picasso's Guernica was spray paint
It's in the 70s
Acid has been thrown at Rembrandt
2 Michelangelo sculptures have been attacked with hammer
Newman's work in particular
Has been vandalized multiple times
And these weren't artistic
Stick gestures
Remember Newman's a Jewish artist
Who's afraid of red yellow and blue for the sequel to who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
Was struck and spat upon in Germany
Because the attacker
Merced it bore a mocking resemblance to the German flag
A Newman sculpture at a museum in Houston with spray painted with swastikas in 1979
And just last year
Someone poured white paint into the reflecting pool
Surrounding the same sculpture
And left behind white supremacist leaflet
If you're keeping track
That's for Barnett Newman Works Too Faced a total of 5 times
6 if you include Daniel gold buyers botched restoration
And those are just the ones we know of
The Barnett Newman Foundation refused to
Speak to me for the story because
They have a really legitimate fear of CopyCat vandalism
Sure
I think that's right and it and you know maybe I shouldn't have agreed to talk to you for that reason
I am concerned now I hadn't thought about it
Myself Carol almost made a break for it during our interview
I have to ask you a question
How would you feel if after reading this Somebody went / 2 painting
I would feel terrible
And that would mean that we need me
I know
Because our paintings are so vulnerable
You're just out there and galleries
Come here at MoMA the Museum of Modern Art in New York
It's a Friday night it's really busy in here
When I was at MoMA recently
I saw this Barnett Newman painting titled vir heroicus sublimis
The title of the painting translates to man heroic and Sublime
It was the size of a billboard
It looks a lot like who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3 it's like red
With a couple of streaks of like is purplish color
In orange color
And has whitish color
But mostly read mostly
She usually read like this one solid wall of red
The painting didn't provoke me
To make me angry
Like it did so many others
And it didn't look simple either like something you could just
Roll over with a paint roller
It was towering
Impressive
Dance
You just get up close this thing you really get lost in it
For a moment
I think I felt this
Feeling
That I heard ice brand talk about
Something
That Newman tried to achieve in his work
Test do with the sublime
And a Subaru experience
When you are
Alone
In the desert
In the night and you
Co-lessee
Yunnan
Enormous
Describe
Are you feel
Very tiny
If you're overwhelmed by
This is a kind of
Feeling everybody knows I think
This is really overwhelming to be honest
The painting is more than just a painting
It's more than the material send the technique
It's the feeling
It evokes in you the viewer
And when you damage or destroy a piece of art
That's what you lose
That's the crime that's the real crime
Diminishing the paintings power
Yes
Experience
After cathedral was attacked
Both ice bronze and Carol advised on its restoration
Mmuseumm spared no expense
The canvas was stitched together with
Surgical steel
Teachers and orthodontic wire
On a specially-built table
For painstaking years later
It was unveiled
It's not perfect
If you know where to look and look closely you can see the scars
But the impression
Survives
The painting can still take your breath away
Cathedra is currently on display at the state elect
But not who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
It's a painting that
That is very close to everyone's heart at the Museum and in Amsterdam
Yet
We do all agree now
That it's not
What are used to be
The painting is sitting in a storage facility
At the edge of town
It's too big to fit
Into the normal
Places that are reserved
So it stands by itself
Kind of lonely
Against the wall
There
Hoping for a day when future conservators might be able to undo what was done to it
The layers of paint
And get to the original experience
The one the artist created
Still sleeping
Underneath
Delta CEO talks to me more about the coolest job in the world. After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
While he was working on this story a reporter jonatha seal
Really fell in love
With art conservation
There was a point in every conversation that I had with a conservator while working on the story
Where
I'd be like
This is the coolest job like there is no better job than this
In fact you can hear
One of those moments in my interview with
Icebrand I think you have
Maybe the best job in the world sounds like a fantastic profession
Daily I enjoy it
Why do you like it so much why were you so enthralled
Conservators are sort of this
Hybrid of an artist or they would probably say an artist
Assistant
And one of those
Forensic scientist
From CSI you really have to think like an artist
To try to preserve
What is Carol says the artist was
Trying to achieve
But their work and she actually spends a lot of her time interviewing living artist
When she's restoring their work
She's built an archive of these interviews you can access online
Call the artist documentation program
And if they're just audio recordings of her
Interviewing artists about their process
But in addition to getting inside the mind of the artist you have to know chemistry and all this hard science stuff
About the composition of materials that artists use
And there's some really far out
Technology that
That they employ
And they're able to work
Miracle
In what kind of Technology are we talking about
Let's start with imaging technique
Like Photography they have technology that allows them to see below the surface of the paint
Like the layers underneath the painting that is brown talked about in the story
Read reflect ography and I can get too technical on you they also
Bring
Painting
To hospitals to have them x-rayed and that's not the only way this field overlaps with medicine actually the cancer
Servitors who stitched cathedra together
In the Netherlands they were actually trained at the hospital
To do that I talk to another conservator who had been a pre-med
Student before going into this field
So that they're able to see below the surface of the painting using special types of Photography and end
Plano x-rays
They're also able to determine what
Elements
Are in the painting like in the paint layers
So they have this thing it's like it sort of looks like a grocery store scanner and they can
All over the painting and it'll identify the element
It's like choosing cures Cobalt
They can basically map
The the
Surface of
The painting
Down to the atom
Intrinsic
Of the elements that are there
They're also able to see
To how the painting
Will fade over time
They have these tools that can measure an artwork sensitivity to light
And project
How it will fade
They can only
See under the surface of the
Really inside the pain
Taking off to see into the future
That painting
Wow
That's so cool
How do you use that information when you're trying to conserve a painting
So you can determine how much light it can be
Supposed to like for instance
If you have a painting that is especially light-sensitive you wouldn't know not to
Play sit like maybe in
Like a bright lights of a main hall or maybe design special lighting
So that
It doesn't
Fade the painting fast
Oh so they're like
Trying to save a painting before it needs to be saved
Deception method right trying to save a painting before it needs
Mitsubishi
So in the case of this story
Whirlpool dryer
Applied a bunch of this red paint in effort
You fix the painting which allowed people ejected to
How would you go about removing
Paint
From a painting without removing all the pay
Chick-fil-A painting if you really wanted to to put it back to where it originally was
So very carefully
Bet there's a couple different ways they remove stuff from the surface of of
Of artworks
That's an added there that they don't
Like
They use emulsions and gels
That dissolve
Material added to the surface of the artwork but these are gels are like kind of discus you know it's not so it's not
Liquid it doesn't run
And they're able to keep it really contain
They also use the stuff
I don't think it's been used a lot but it's probably the coolest thing I've
Heard about wealth while researching the story
They use atomic
Oxygen what I'm about to say doesn't make sense but it's literally oxygen from space
It's it's an elemental form of oxygen that does not exist in the Earth's atmosphere.
You only find it in low earth orbit
This technology is actually developed by NASA because
Atomic oxygen is like they were sending corrosion on satellites in the international
Space Station
They basically either use like a an airbrush and like
Had it very close to paint where they put
The piece of art in a vacuum chamber and pump in the stuff
It's really good for removing
From fire damaged
Paintings that you can actually see
Some photos online
Obtaining save restored
That have been in fires
And it's pretty mind-blowing actual
Like a before-and-after like you have a picture
Black and ruined painting
And on the other you got a completely Lycra
Restored work
The atomic oxygen was always used to most famously to restore this painting
By Andy Warhol called bathtub
The painting of a
Bathtub
Somebody at a party at the Museum had a had kissed it so there was a lipstick mark on it
They were able to remove it using Atomic oxygen
In all these cases you know
Conservatives had basically given up hope
On this painting
They're like these are never going to
So with all this new technology
Is it possible
They could go back
Yeah really restore who's afraid of red yellow and blue
Number three
The way that
You would feel really want to do lyrics
Yeso
The answer is Maybe
Near the end of my reporting I talk to a journalist in the Netherlands
Hood written a book on the state of like his name was Ian lemures great
Resource
In a couple years ago he was able to get the full results
From the forensic lab
Analysis of who's afraid of red yellow and blue 3
The one that had
Determine that goal dryer
Had over painted it
So he was able to get the full thing released
And what the report showed according to him
Was that gold Rider had use several layers of varnish
Which is like this clear
Can I like a resin that he'd use several layers of varnish
Before painting over the canvas of theoretically
Because he did that
The layers of paint
Above the varnish
Could be removed
So it is possible
Yeah maybe not right now but it is possible I talked to Carol mancusi-ungaro from the Whitney about this and she kind
I never agreed
I don't know
I don't know I dunno
That
I've seen my profession grow
And our ability to do things that one time we couldn't do
I
Believe
That there may be
Procedures
That we can do in the future
That might be able to reverse
So one day maybe I really hope the state alike is doing everything they can to see whether the painting can be
Restored because
It'll be great to have it back
Absolutely
Cool thank you so much
Thank you
99percentinvisible was produced this week by John to seal and edited by Joe Rosenberg mix and Tech production by 3
Refusive music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is there a senior editor Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Russell team includes senior editor at Delaney Hall
Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman Mars
Additional reporting for this toys from bota bota is an audio producer in the Netherlands who also helped us out on our Siri
About the belmermere
Amsterdam
Thank you bota
Thanks also did you let Maury Hans and John Wakefield
And that's go back
We are product 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most innovative
Shows in all a podcast
Baidu mall
And radiotopia
Tok FM
You can buy the show into discussions about the show on Facebook you can do to meet at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi or Quan
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit too but if for some reason you're having a hard time picturing those Barnett Newman paintings
We got you covered
And I and i p i
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com