99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Tim Harford is a master at picking out the perfect little story
Explains some huge economic principle in his long-running financial times column called the under
Cover Economist and in his books in his radio shows he's been my go-to guy for learning about the economics and
Math behind World At Large for the BBC is called 50 things that made the modern economy
And with this project
Tim has made a podcast almost perfectly crafted to light up the pleasure centers of my nerd brain
Every produce 50 fascinating stories about 50 everyday objects you decided to come back
Another season that premiered last month
Another 50 mini-documentaries of inventions that are sold basic with so fundamental to how we live
We have three of the 50 things on her show today radar which I'm sure you know about that
You have no idea how fascinating its Origins actually are
Psband The crucial innovation in pipes
That made indoor plumbing possible
And Bricks
CEO Pixar
Circle
You're in for a treat
The first
The story of radar
In Kenya's Rift Valley Samsung cameras at home wondering when
Would be able to get back to work
He should have been in a greenhouse on the shores of Lake naivasha as usual talking roses for export
Europe
Put the outbound cargo flights for ground
Because the Icelandic volcano
Cattleya orchid
Add without sparing the slightest thought for Samsung
Spewed a cloud of dangerous Ash
Into Europe's airspace
Knowing you how long the disruption might not
Wicked like Samson
V a jobs
Business owners how to throw away tons of flowers at Nairobi Airport
As it happened
Flights with you within a few days
The interruption dramatically Illustrated
Just
Film the 10 million passengers who get on flight
Everyday
Reduced
I nearly 5 billion dollars
You could trace the extent of our alarm
The jet engine
The airplane itself
But sometimes it needs another
Unlock its full potential
The aviation industry that story starts
With the development
The death ray
It starts with an attempt
That's right
This was back in 1935
Officials in the British Air ministry will worried about falling behind Nazi Germany in the technological arms race
The death ray idea
Intrigued
Pepino freeing a thousand pound price for anyone who could zap a sheep at a hundred paces
So far
Nobody can find it
But should they fund more active research
Was at death ray even possible
I'm officially they sounded out Robert watson-watt
At the radio research station
And he post an abstract math question to his colleague
Skip Wilkins
Supposed
Just suppose
Said watts and Watts to Wilkins
Do you had eight points of water
One kilometer above the ground
And suppose that water was it 98 degrees Fahrenheit
And you wanted to heat it to 105 degrees
How much radio frequency power would you require
From a distance of 5 km
Skip Wilkins was no fool
Can you the 8 pints with the amount of blood in an adult human
98 Degrees with normal body temperature
105 degrees
With woman after
The kill you or at least make you pass out
Which if your behind the controls of an aeroplane
Amounts to much the same thing
So Wilkins and watson-watt understood each other
And they quickly agreed that the death ray was hope
It would take too much power
Level 6 or an opportunity
Chile the ministry had some cash to spend on Research
Perhaps Watson Watson Wilkins could propose some alternative way
Suspended
Wilkins pond
It might be possible
He suggested
To transmit radio waves into Tech
Pro Miyako's
The location of oncoming aircraft
Long before they could be seen
What's in Vault dash of a memo to the M Industries newly-formed committee for the scientific survey of Ed
Would they be interested in pursuing such an idea
They would indeed
Skip Wilkins with describing became known as radio detection and ranging
And then
Is radar the Germans the Japanese and the Americans independently started
My 1940 it was the Brits who made a spectacular breakthrough
The resonant cavity magnetron
A radar transmitter far more powerful than its predecessors
Pounded by German bombers Britain's factories would struggle to put the device into production
America's facts
British leaders plotted to use the magnetron as a bargaining chip for American Secrets in other fields
10 Winston Churchill took power and decided the desperate times call for desperate measures
Britain would simply tell the Americans what they had
Alaska help
Stomp the American
Davis search with years of the pace
President Roosevelt approved funds for new laboratory at MIT
Uniquely the American war effort
Administered
Dubai civilian agency
By any measure
Radlab was a resounding success
It spawned 10 Nobel laureates
The radar it developed
Detecting planes and submarines
Help to win the war
Urgency in times of War can quickly be lost in times of peace
Obvious if you thought about it that civilian Aviation needed radar
Given how quickly it was expanding
In 1945 of the war's end
Us domestic Airline
Convert 7 million passengers
My 1955
It was 38 million
And the busy of the sky's the more useful radar would be by preventing Collision
But rollout was slow and Pat
Some airports installed it
Many didn't
Inmost a space
Playing one track tool
Pilot submitted the flight plans in advance which
Should in theory and show that no two planes were going to be in the same place
Set the same time
But avoiding collisions ultimately came down to a forward protocol
CNBC
On June 30th
2 passenger flights departed Los Angeles app
3 minutes apart
When was bound for Kansas City
Bonefish Chicago
Zeppelin flight paths intersected about the Grand Canyon at different heights
10 thunder clouds develop
1 planes Captain radio to ask permission to fly about the storm
The air traffic controller cleared him to go a thousand on top a thousand feet above cloud cover
CNBC
Nobody knows for sure what happened
Planes band had no black boxes
No no Survivor
Adjust before 10:31
Air Traffic Control hooded garbled radio transmission
We are going in from the past
Captain of the wreckage
Stream four miles across the canyon floor
The plane seem to have approached each other at a 25 degree angle
Presumably
Sewer clown
Investigators speculated both Pilots were distracted by trying to find gaps in the clouds
So passengers could enjoy the scenery
Accidents happen
The question is what risks we are willing to run for the economic benefit
Got questions becoming president again with respect to crowded Skies
Many people have high hopes for unmanned aerial vehicle
Drones
I'm already being used for everything from moviemaking to crop spraying
Companies like Amazon expect the skies varsity's soon to be buzzing
Grocery delivery
Civil aviation Authority the grappling with what to approve
Drones have
Sense and avoid technology
It's pretty good
But is it good enough
The crash over the Grand Canyon be concentrated Minds
If technology existed to prevent things like this shouldn't we make more effort to use it
Within two years what's now known as the Federal Aviation Administration
Was born in the United States
And today American Skies
20 * busiest ill
The world's biggest airports now see planes taking off and Landing
An average of nearly two a minute
Collisions are absurd
That sucks too many things
But it's largely
Things to write
You're listening to my personally curated selection of stories from Tim Harford 50 things that made the modern economy
Come next
Lee Aspen
Gentility of speech is at an end Sundays in editorial in London
City Press
Stinks
The stink in question was partly metaphorical
Politicians with failing to tackle an obvious problem
Population London system for disposing of human waste became woefully inadequate
Do any pressure on cesspits
Which were prone to leaking
Overflowing and belching explosive methane
The authorities had instead started encouraging sewage into gullies
Different issue
The original intended
Directly into the River Thames
So that was the literal stink
The Thames became an open sewer
The distinguished scientist Michael Faraday
To write to the Times newspaper
He described the river water as an opaque
Pale brown suit
Near the pictures the feculence rolled up in clouds so dense that they were visible
Cholera with Rye
One outbreak killed 14
Styles in London
Steely one in every hundred
Civil engineer Joseph bazalgette
Drew up plans for new close to us
The pump the waist
Far from the city
It was this project the politicians came under pressure to approve
Michael Faraday ended his letter by pleading with those who exercise power responsibility
To stop neglecting the problem
Last offseason gives a sad proof of the Folly about carelessness
In three years later
That's exactly
What happened
The sweltering hot summer of 1858
Made London's malodorous River impossible to politely ignore
Want to discuss a Bleakley with gentility of speech
The Heatwave
Became popular
The great stink
If you live in a city with Martin Sanitation
It's hard to imagine daily life being permeated with a suffocating stench of human excrement
We have a number of people to thank
Perhaps none more so than the unlikely figure
Alexander
Coming
Watchmaker in London
Century before the great stink
Coming one Renown Titan Mastery of intricate mechanics
King George the third commissioned him to make an elaborate instrument for recording atmospheric pressure
I deposited a microtone
A device for cutting ultra-fine slivers of wood from microscopic analysis
Bart Cummings will changing invention
Oh nothing to Precision Engineering
Elizabeth pipe
With a caravan
In 1775
Coming Tyson Kidd
Aspen
This became the missing ingredient
Create a flushing toilet
And with it
Public Sanitation
We know it
Flushing toilets have previously founded
On the problem of smell
The pipe that connects the toilet to the Sewer
Alarm in urine and feces be flushed away
Will also let sewer odors walk back up
Unless you can create
Some kind of airtight seal
Coming solution was Simplicity itself
Bend
Water settles in the dip
Stopping smells coming up
Flushing the toilet
Replenishes the water
Well we've moved on alphabetically from the S Pen to the u-bend
Flushing toilets still deploy the same inside
Roll out
Came slowly
1851 a lifetime after cumming Peyton
Flushing toilets from a novel enough in London to cause Mass excitement
When introduced at the great exhibition in Crystal
Show Palace
Use of the facilities cost
One penny
Giving the English language one of its engineering euphemisms emptying one's bladder
To spend a penny
If the great exhibition gave London is a vision of how public sanitation could be
Clean and smell free
No doubt I did to the weight of popular discontent
Politicians drag their heels over finding the thumbs for Joseph bazalgette
Plan suicide
We still haven't reliably managed to solve
The problem of
Collective action
How to get those who exercise power or have responsibility
To organize themselves
It's been a great deal of progress
According to the World Health Organization
The proportion of the world's people who have access to what school
Improved Sanitation
Is increased from around a quarter in 1980
Two around tooth
Today
That's a big step forward
But still
Two and a half billion people remain without
Improved Sanitation
And improved sanitation itself
Is a lowball
It hygienically separates human excreta from Human contact
Who doesn't necessarily treat the sewage itself
Fewer than half the world's people have access to sanitation systems that do that
The economic cost of this ongoing failure to roll out proper sanitation a many and varied
From Health cafeteria real diseases
Two full-grown revenue from hygiene conscious tourists
It will Spanx economics of Sanitation initiative
Gastritis
About the price tag
Across various African countries for example
Attractions in adequate sanitation one or two percentage points
Of GDP
In India and Bangladesh
Over 6%
In Cambodia
7%
Hatsune jump
The challenges that public sanitation isn't something the market necessarily provide
Toilet cost money but defecating in the street
It's free
If I install a toilet iPad only costs
All the benefits of the cleaner Street
I felt by everyone
In economic parlance
That's a positive externality
I'm good switch have positive externalities tend to be bought at a slower Pace than society as a whole
Contrast say the mobile phone
But also cost money
But as long as there's somebody else I can phone its benefits the crew.
Tumi
Not one reason why the S Pen has been around for 10 times as long as the mobile phone
Many more people already own a mobile phone
Then a flushing toilet
If you want to buy a flushing toilet it also helps if there's a system of suicide
I creating that system is a major undertaking
Financially and logistically
Finally got the cash to build London sewage they took 10 years to complete the necessitated digging up
2.5 million cubic meters of Earth
Because of the externality problem
Such a project might not appeal to private investors
It tends to require determined politicians
Winning tax
And well-functioning Municipal governments
And those it seems
I'm in short supply
London's lawmakers prevaricator
They finally acted they didn't hang about
It took just
18 days to rush through the necessary legislation for Bible Jets plans
What explains the sudden impressive alacrity
Geography
London Parliament building
Is located right next to the River Thames
Officials trying to Shield lawmakers from the great stink
Soaking the curtains in chloride of lime
In a bid to mask the stench
But it was no use
Try as I might
Politicians couldn't ignore
The time described
With the notes of grim satisfaction
How members of parliament
Have been seen abandoning the buildings Library
Each gentleman with a handkerchief to his nose
If only concentrating politicians Minds
Purple wave
Doteasy
We have one more story from season 2 of 50 things that made the modern economy
What temperature
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
You're listening to Tim Harford 50 things that made the modern economy
99% invisible
I found Rome a city of bricks
And left it
A city of ma
Not supposed to have been the boast of Caesar Augustus
The first Roman Emperor
Just over 2000 years ago
If it was
He was exaggerated
Ancient Rome is a city of brick
No less glorious for that
Augustus was also joining a long tradition
Denigrating or overlooking
What are the most ancient and versatile
A building
The great Roman architectural rights
Vitruvius
Mentions them
Denis diderot is great French Encyclopedia of the Sciences arts and crafts
Published in 1751 and an inspiration for Adam Smith's famous description of the pin fact
Well
Diderot doesn't trouble himself to include any images of brick breaker
A tool
That's because a brick
It's such an intuitive thing
People open teaching themselves to build simple structures House of brick
The many thousands of years
And roundworms to
The Hanging Gardens of Babylon
So with the biblical Tower of Babel
Let's make bricks and bake them
Thoroughly
Genesis 11
Best three
They used brick
Instead of stone
Bacchus V the Lord is
And things aren't looking too good for the brick Loving Citizens of Babel
Has James Campbell and will Pryce
Point out in the magisterial history of bricks
The Humble cuboid is everywhere
The biggest man-made structure on the planet
The Ming Dynasty Great Wall of China
Is largely construct
Brick
The astonishing temples of Bagan in Myanmar
The Taj Mahal in India
Mytmobile
Castle in Poland
Siena's Palazzo
Florence Duomo
The bridges of Isfahan in Iran
Hampton Court
Palace in West London
Albrecht
So is the best Church in the world
Biosphere in Istanbul
The best Bridge
Clifton suspension bridge in Bristol
How's the best skyscraper
The Chrysler building in Manhattan
Rick
Brick
The architect
Frank Lloyd Wright
Once boasted that he could make a brick
Worth its weight in gold
Long time ago
Bricks seems I've been with us since the very dawn of civilization the oldest
Found in Jericho
In Jordan
Are the archaeologist Kathleen Kenyon in 19
There's something between 9600 and 10300
Years old
I just simply lobes of Nod
Baked dry in the sun then starts out and glued together
With Mormon
The next big step forward
What's the simple brick mold
Also originating from Mesopotamia
At least 7000 years old
And depicted with great
Priority auto painting in Thebes
Egypt
The brick mold is a wooden rectangle
Full sides but no top or bottom
In which clients draw could be packed to make bricks
Faster and more precise
He's bald, easy to make
They predate the use of metal itself
It was constructed much cheaper and better
Even in a dry climate
Sun-dried mud bricks do not usually last
V brakes are much more durable
Best stronger and waterproof
Making such Breaks by
Heating clay and sand.
The temperature of about 1000 degrees Centigrade
It's been possible for many thousands of years
.
At a price
Accounts from the third dynasty of
Dating back just over 4000 years
Notes that you can get
14400 mud bricks
For the price of a piece of silver
Ugly 504
Fired clay bricks
An exchange rate
Amelie 29 mud-brick
For a single Play 1
1500 Years Later by Babylonian times
Kiln Technologies how to improve
And the price of five clay bricks that fall into between 2 and 5 months
That's still too much for many people
Cheap and easy mud bricks
Still perhaps the most popular material in the world
The building houses
But as the economist Abhijit Banerjee and Esther duflo observe
5 bricks can be an effective way for a very poor household to save
If you have enough money
Buy a brick
Slowly slowly slowly
You'll have about the house
The brick is one of those old technology is like the wheel
Paper
That seems to be basically unimprovable the shapes and sizes
The breaks do not differ greatly
Edwin Thompson in the 14th Edition of his rudimentary Treatise on the manufacture
Bricks and tiles
There's a simple reason to psi
It has to fit in the human hand
As for the shape
Building is much more straightforward
If the width
Is half the length
That's why if you get your nose close up to some buildings
Culture
The minarets of Columbus
Uzbekistan
Decimals so costly in England
And the twin pagodas of Suzhou in China
You'll find the brick
Acceptable much the same
It's precisely the uniformity of the brick
It makes it so versatile
Many medieval buildings
Talk shows since Alban's cathedral in England
Simply reused
Roman bricks
Why not
Brick production still uses traditional methods in many parts of the world
Automation is gradually losing its way in
Hydraulic shovel dig the clay
Slow conveyor belts carry bricks to long tunnel Kilns
Forklift trucks
Shift Precision stock pallets of bricks
Oldest makes the brick itself
Building sites
I've resisted automation
The weather in the unique demands of each site require well trained workers
The bricklayer has long been celebrated as a symbol of the honest Dignity of skilled manual labor
Bricklaying tools have barely changed since the 17th century
But as in so many other profession
That all signs
Stop the robots
Maybe coming to Brookline
A human bricklayer
A300 600 bricks a day
The designers of Sam
Semi-automated Mason
Playmates can do 3000
What's the brick itself
Various designs of interlocking brick
Much like Lego the catching on across the developing world
The result tends to be less strong
You can find the show enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we did me at Roman Mars in the show at 19
MPI org
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to that are home for the Wayward beautiful nerds of the world
Is 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com