99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Once Upon a Time
It was a boy
Name Friedrich
Pro Bowl
Is early life reads like one of those dark old German fairy tales
His mother died in 1783
Right after he was born
It's a Friedrich froebel
Had a lonely childhood
He spent his days in the woods
Looking at trees and rocks
Sunflowers
Wandering the dense forests of thuringia
And what was then Prussia
It's a lush region
Sometimes referred to today as the screen hits.
The green heart of Germany
That's great cause that he produces story
I actually lived near thuringia when I was a kid
In the forest there are
Simply Magic
And I can really see how problem
He looked at Roxy study the trees he was rewarded with a Forester for a while he was in
Prentice Forrester
Best Norman brosterman
He's an author who studied Friedrich froebel for years
Braun strowman says that probably worked for a time as a land surveyor and even served in the military
Skilled at drafting in geometry
And at one point became convinced
He should be a narc
It did everything you need to become a narc
Taxi took all the right classes
But he didn't become a narc
Friend convinced him to become an educator and sad
And in changing course froebel arguably ended up having more influence in the world of architecture and Design
Than any single architect
And that's because
Friedrich froebel created
Kindergarten
I believe kindergarten had it
Tremendous influence on the twentieth century
It impacted all parts of society
Of course
Including
And architecture
If you ever looked at a piece of abstract art or modernist architecture and thought
My kindergartener could have made that
Well
That may be more true than you realize
The kindergarten was the product of frobbles Decades of experience in a wide range of fear
But the foundations are built on the principles of
Johanna
Pestalozzi
Pestalozzi is considered the father of modern education which basically means
They will learn better if you treat them well rather than hit them with sticks you know
In addition to the whole not hitting kids with sticks thing
Pestalozzi emphasized physical activity and active learning over rote memorization and repetition
And in particular
He felt that kids should draw
Pestalozzi was early childhood educator
Who had Incorporated
Pedagogical drawings
In the curriculum
That's author and Cooper Union professor
Tomorrow singer
And basically he is one of the first with all that rowing
Should be part of any school curriculum
And should be taught to the very very young
Trouble work for a time at a school based on these principles
Any building where you learn from pestalozzi
Incorporating his own ideas
Along the way about how children should be taught
Facility was
Especially busy with
Breaking down the two dimensional world
With what
Probably this break down the street image
National world
Purple realized he wanted kids to go beyond just drawing lines on pages
He wanted them to learn through the physical manipulation of objects
Froebel wanted to building blocks of reality
And this Alchemy
Crystals in
Teaching of pestalozzi and a childhood alone in the woods
Crystallized into a solid vision
In 1837
Previous 55 years old
Froebel founded the very first kindergarten
MBA glockenberg Germany
And his intention was to create an educational system for
Children who could not
Yet read or write
So he sought to use
Geometric forms
As a way to
Teach complex and simple lessons
All through play
If you can
Harness play you can teach kids a lot of things
The word kindergarten cleverly and Compass two different ideas
Kids would play in and learn from nature
But they would also themselves be nurtured and nourished
Like plants in a garden
And the key to it all
Was a set of deceptively simple looking
Toys
Lee's
We're froebel's gifts
The cold gift because they were to draw out the gift
Oh the children
German of course the phrase froebel's gifts
Is rolled together into a single word
Pro Bowl
Froebel's gifts were meant to be given in a particular order
The toys growing more complex overtime
Teaching different lessons about shapes
Structure and perception along the way
The first of froebel's gifts was a soft
The wool ball
Annie's basically
The first gift
Child could get
At the age of 6 weeks
Village hybrid graduate to another
Roughly the same size as the first
But this one is not soft it's hard
Wouldn't Maple wooden ball
Has
Surface
Smoothie can roll
And then they are given the
Cube
And the cube is an opposite
Pyside
Tusk
Edges
Sharp edges
Poems
The cube cannot
Kids are
Ask to enumerate the differences
Between the two
And then they get a cylinder which combines elements of both the ball and the cube
Blow their little Minds
Each do gift would get more and more interact
The more complex
Some were designed to be hung from a string
Spun in the air
And as the rotate
Some very interesting forms are created
That are not visible
When the form is stationary
Like a cube for instance looks like a cylinder when you spin it around 5
If you want the children to start to see that there's some invisible parts
Contained within the visible
Next up game object
It's made up of smaller
Like a cube that breaks down into a bunch of little
And then the toys would ship from being about perception to being about creation
They would become more versatile
Pliant and constructive
Locks gave way to paper string wire little sticks and peas that could be connected in Stockton just
Structures
Objects would get more abstract and creative
Leading to the finals
The last is really just working freely with clay
Play being the most malleable evolve
It's rigid and it's off
And there's a whole range of things a child could build with it
But even at this final stage
This wasn't the kind of creative free for all week
We tend to associate with childhood play
Pro Bowl head children sitting at desk
Workstations with grids lay down
So it's not free play
The fact that the table
Has an underlying grid
He's very much at the
Root of
The directive play
You follow instructions
And there's an underlying order
And so in this very structured very dramatic way
The gifts encourage students to think abstract
Interrelated ideas objects and symbol
A set of blocks could be used to teach
Counting
In the child could use those same blocks to build a house
And then tell stories of a family living in the house
So they were modeling the world different ways
All using the same
Set of objects
The children realize that they can create a new
Shapes in new forms that
The create on top of the grill table
These kindergarten smart just schools
They were art schools
Without the sex and drugs and clove cigarettes
They were places that taught about shape and form and color
And when kindergarten graduates went out into the world
The world
Changed
The kind of art that was being made in the 19 century is really different than
The kind of art that was made after kids went to kindergarten
Expressionist Cubist
Surrealist artists like Paul clay and possibly convince
Attended early
Others like Piet Mondrian
Encountered 4 billion methods as teacher
And when you look at a lot of their work
Alongside illustration
Things in kindergarten
Teacher guides
The resemblance
Is uncanny
It wasn't just artists
Kindergarten influenced designers to
Walter gropius started the Bauhaus in 1919
Gropius decided to hire a kindergarten teacher as the first
Higher
Apus famous School of Design
So the Bauhaus had its adult designs
Much like those found in kindergarten
The effects of froebel's work on design education
Rippled out Beyond Germany
And some of his most explicit and direct influences can be found
Among the world's most famous architects
Frank Lloyd Wright the American architect
Is the great child of the kindergarten
You can find the kindergarten everything right ever did
Frank Lloyd Wright was born in 1867
Around the time kindergarten for gaining Traction in the United States
And his mom took classes in kindergarten education
Neverwinter
School but he recalls that when he was young
His mother brought home a set
Afrobull
Right said that the moment he was given froebel's gifts
Key quotes
Began to be a narc
He went on to say
For several years I sat at that little kindergarten table
Mean by lines about
4in apart
But the smooth cardboard triangles and maple wood blocks would most important
All are in my fingers
To this day
And rate wasn't the only one
European modernist Le corbusier
Also never went to architecture
But he did attempt Rebellion schools
In Switzerland
The Grid geometries in repeated patterns of Lil Boosie a modernist houses and apartment blocks
Look like they were drawn on those credited kindergarten desks
Look up Lizzie and Frank Lloyd Wright
Considered
Price on the two most important architect of the 20th century
Had exactly the same childhood education
And then there's Buckminster Fuller
Famous for pioneering geodesic dome
Meetup of trying
Fuller discovery
Is greatest engineering inside
As a kindergarten
Connecting from belly and peas
Styx
You know Buckminster Fuller this is the thing he's most famous for
You know the domes made out of
Pizza sticks pasqualino's and rods
So he learned that in kindergarten
Obviously not everyone who attended kindergarten became a Frank Lloyd Wright or a little corbusier or a bucket
But the abstract lessons of kindergarten
Tilled and fertilized the ground
So the seeds of their ideas
Could find purchase in the world
Abstraction was accepted fairly quickly
In Paris
Time in Europe
Perhaps because children are doing a lot of the same kinds of things for many decades
That was one of the reasons that they were not so shocked when our turn in that direction
Do in terms of 20th century Art and Design
Kindergarten was an absolute Triumph
Friedrich froebel only got to witness the spread of his vision
For about a decade
Before it was cut short
In the 1850s the Prussian government was cracking down on the broth
An 1851
Are you shoot the kindergarten for
A national ban on kindergarten
And probably died the very next
And you know I wonder if he died of a broken heart 1952
Of course when I was
Even though the band slowed the expansion of kindergartens in Germany
It didn't stop the idea from spreading elsewhere
Far from it
A lot of free thinking liberals left Germany
And they brought froebel's kindergarten with
Who is disciples
We were so
Dedicated to the work that they immigrated many of them to the United States
And basically because of the band
That's
What's latooth foibles the series to be
Known around the world
In the most dedicated kindergarten evangelist
Or women
Has tomorrow singer points out in her book arcs
Section play
Froebel believe that women should play a leading role in educating children
To be clear
Froebel wasn't exactly a feminist
Cadbury traditional ideas about gender roles
And believe that it was the role of women to nurture children
As panties and kindergarten
But regardless of verbal reasoning
Teaching kindergarten was a rare opportunity
It was one of the only jobs you could get as a young woman
There weren't many jobs
And it was women
Who drew up in translated the lesson books that would be used
The future generation of young artists
Designers
By 1885 there were over 500 kindergartens in America
And they were taught primarily
By women
And you might be thinking
Hey I went to kindergarten why didn't I grow up with this incredibly dramatic immaculately plan sequence of toys
Play ironic leave the passion of some of kindergardens biggest proponents
Is part of the reason why you probably didn't grow up playing with froebel's gifts
The first kindergarten in the United States started in Watertown Wisconsin in 1856
But it was German language only
The educator Elizabeth Peabody was inspired by this kindergarten
And went on to found the first American English language kindergarten in Boston
In 1860
Peabody wanted to
To spread the teachings of frobe
Call to as many children as possible
And so she reached out
Milton Bradley
The Famous Board Game maker
She wanted Bradley to mass produce from
So they could be accessible to everyone
And Milton Bradley have encouraged her
Was convinced and since that moment
Attorneys entire attention to the manufacturer of Roblox
Send gift
Door Peabody saw an educational ideal
Bradley saw a business opportunity
Bradley began adding a bunch of new toys
And other manufacturers
Making all different kinds of stuff and just
Call me at all
Kindergarten
He just made up Stephanie said this is kindergarten this is kindergarten this is kindergarten it's not necessarily froboese
The simple abstractions of Robles gifts
Shandong commercial
It was in a few years Elizabeth Peabody
Went from promoting the manufacturer of kindergarten
Ryan toys to speaking out against
The interest of Manufacturers and of merchants of the Gibson
Materials is a snare
It has already corrupted this
Simplicity of froebel in Europe and America
His idea was Hughes Elementary forms
Exclusively
And simple material
Even the word kindergarten itself
Became of generic
A catch-all for early childhood education of all differ
These days most kindergartens are a lot different from anything froebel imagine
And few kids encounter those early gifts in any kind of sequence if at all
But kids still play with blocks
I mean I really think that
It's because of froebel or $40 however it's correctly pronounce
That
Children in the western world
Play with blocks
But I think also blocks are
Constant across a variety of educational
System
Because there's so much in them that they can teach
That's Alexandra Lange
An architecture critic and author of
The design of childhood
Material World shapes independent kids
The block is incredibly malleable toy that can be used in all of these different ways
Probably wasn't the only one to see educational value
Box
In the early nineteen hundreds
Carolyn Pratt debuted hurt you
Unit blocks
Switch are essentially those classic
Brick shaped
Pale wood blocks
That really I can't think of any
Early Childhood classroom I've been to that doesn't have those blocks
In some ways all modern toy blocks were influenced by Freud
Tinker Toys
Lego
Connects all about understanding
Inform Lincoln connection
They also represent a departure
Comfortable highly organized and linear
Approach
Roblox
You were supposed to proceed
1 to 20
Through his exercises
The unit block
Are much more open-ended there more like we tend in counter Blox today
These days we don't think that blocks need in a company gridded desk or a syllabus of objects
Mailbox are creative tools for children
That gives them a chance to use their imagination
As they build houses and cities and interact with each other
That's what I say when my boys play with Legos or
Build castles in Minecraft
There isn't this sense
Abstract progression
If it's Morrisons that
These blocks are too old for children to recreate their own world as best they can
And who knows how many Architects Builders designers and thinkers
All started with these literal building blocks
Pavilion or otherwise
Burning creativity
Through Construction
Froebel influence the design of educational toys
But his ideas also impacted help children play Outdoors that's coming up
After the break
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
Robles gifts impacted early childhood education inside the classroom but froebel also influence the way chill
Golden played Outdoors
That's because his kindergarten
Had little Gardens Little plots work
Kids kids
Get their hands dirty and learn to
Cultivate plants
Is her book
The design of childhood
Author Alexandra Lange traces the connection between froebel's kindergarten
And the very first playgrounds in Berlin Germany
The first playgrounds were actually piles of sand
Which are called sand Gardens
Which really popped up in Berlin in the the 1850s and 1860s
There wasn't much to them design-wise
They're basically just
Huge piles of sand dumped in public parks for kids to play around
And a group of
Charitable ladies from Boston
Saw this and Gardens in Berlin and thought Oh
You know the children in the settlement houses in Boss
Austin The Immigrant children don't have anything to do during the summer when school's out
So they decided to bring these tan Gardens to New England
The thinking in part was that
Dense urban areas didn't have a lot of places for kids to play especially kids whose parents couldn't afford a big private
So saying Gardens would be useful additions to cities
So they picked an empty lot and kind of the dentist part of Boston
And they just
Poured a pile of sand in it
And said okay it's the same Garden
Come play
And then the kids spent the summary no digging in the sand making mountains of the sand playing in the sand
And it was hugely successful and garden started popping up all over the country
Often in public parks
Sometimes they were staffed with play leaders who would teach organized games and
Marching exercises in calisthenics and songs
But also more traditional organized Sports
There is also this push to americanize the Immigrant children and so they teach them how to play baseball
Which was thought to be a very collaborative and Democratic sport
And so the same Garden actually starts to shrink and become a box
Rather than a gardener box rather than a whole lot
And they have
Paved areas in grassy areas
So sanh Gardens kicked off The Playground movement
Organized around ideas of American culture
Productive teamwork
And healthy exercise
And then there's a whole proliferation of amazing
Spinning wheels
Climbing structures giant slides all of this
Like the metal equipment that you can still sometimes find an older playgrounds in the twenties and thirties
Their catalogs of this
Send cities by it
Nearly every city bought into this idea of playground
Seesaws slides and swings
All became standard features
Actual sandboxes got smaller and smaller
Becoming just another thing the playground could have
In 2 weeks we going to bring you the story of the rise of the mass-produced playground
And the stubborn super famous artists who push back
But next week's episode
At work in the future the greatest
Podcast crossover event in history
Seriously
You don't wanna miss it
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Kurt Kolstad and Emmett Fitzgerald edited by Avery trufelman Mixon
Set production by Sharif Youssef
Music by genre
Recipe includes senior producer Katie Mingle
Senior editor Delaney Hall Vivien Leigh Sophia ClassDojo Rosenberg and me Roman Mars
This episode was supported by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
Advancing public understanding and engagement with science
We are product of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco is produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Lowe's in Halla podcasting
Fun Mall
Radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi org
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But we have side-by-side comparisons
Approbo kindergarten lessons
In famous pieces of modern architecture that will blow your mind
At Marina NPI
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com