99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance with Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their History season 2 Launches on May 15th between an episode
Really take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stock of love
Butters episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted of
Family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment in California and
On the globe Define transformational Solutions quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I want to be careful not to overstate what it means for a building to die
The building's worth is an infant a small fraction of the worth of a person's life
Even two buildings don't even move the needle comparison to real human laws
The building is still a living thing anyway
Breathe
And it moves
This movement makes a cent
The structural engineer who
Design the World Trade Center towers
Cuz of the people working inside
Couldn't feel this moment
The towers swaying in the breeze
But they could hear it
Dolphin building speak to you
What happens in a tall building is it
In the wind as the building moves
The floor above movies with respect to the floor below
My full name is Lester e Robertson I'm a structural engineer and I was responsible for
The design of the World Trade Center
The Shack is that tape was one of
Many that we took on during the construction and
Later occupation the building
For each cycle of oscillation the building here to creaking noise
And therefore with you have a tape that you can measure rather precisely the frequency of
The building itself
Text 10-second 4 World Trade Center 2
To go to one cycle of oscillation
This concludes the recording at the 67th floor
Rejection rate
I used to be extremely sound sleeper in the kind of put my head down the pillow and
And go to sleep and sleep for just a short while get up and go to go back to work or do whatever but
It's kind of not like that anymore I just
Bedtime
I don't I don't have images of the Trade Center in my dreams
Baidu
Wake up
With the thoughts in my head
But I do but
Instantaneous synonym
As you wipe your eyes you want this out of your mind
People keep saying well and you did everything you could have done the design was the best of could it could be and
You know all those all those thoughts
Which are
Nice butt
I guess I guess
Ultimately the responsibility for
The criteria for the Trade Center that was mine those were my decisions
And
The fact that they stood up as long as they did
Was because we had
Design the project for the impact of the
707 aircraft and and we had a great team working on the project in
And they did what they were supposed to do
They stood up under the impaction
And while it's true that the the plane that hit it was a bit heavier in a flying a whole lot faster and therefore
A lot more energy was put into the building
I think it's a tribute to the people worked on the project at that they did as well as they did
And yet I know as well as I'm here right this moment that
That the village could have been made more sour shrimp that could have been made stronger and it could have
They could have stood up longer
And
And that was my decision and I just
I thinking that since I can't be faulted
Is performed in many ways admirably
But there's always that nagging thought that maybe you should have done something else
American
Just push that out of my head
This episode of 99% invisible was produced by the kitchen sisters davia Nelson and Nikki Silva and me Roman Mars
It's comprised of extracts and outtakes from the Peabody award-winning Sonic Memorial project produced in 2002
A new 10th anniversary edition of the Sonic Memorial project which is narrated by my literary hero Paul auster is going
Will be playing on public radio stations around the country is very much worth your time to see
Seek out you can find out more I kitchen sisters. Org this program
But a person invisible is made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity it's a project of Ka
Kalw 91.7 local public radio in san francisco in san francisco
The center for architecture and design find out more at 99percentinvisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero and
A movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Two days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found
Found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had something
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Every takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast. Com