This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On the last episode I promise you
Greatest podcast crossover event in history
And here it is
Reply all Alex Goldman
And this week BJ we have a super text
Supercuts
Part is Saginaw show where listeners come to us with her
Weird unsolvable Tech problems and
What is usually you
Goes out interest solvent
And you have one
Baidu
Tell me about it
We got an email from getting been
He lives in Houston
And Ben is a hoe
Huge fan of pikas
He has his own podcast
He said he listened to over 100 podcasts which like
Possible
He said that the one complaint he has about his podcast app
Is that a lease how much time he spends listening to podcasts
Who tells me how many overall days of podcasts I've listened to
And it's just more and more depressing
You know you like to guess
Sure yes
40 days
And recently he started having this
Very strange podcast
So
Ben
Not too long ago got a new car it was a 2016 Mazda 6
And
The thing that he was most excited about in his new car
With that
He compared his phone using bluetooth so that he could listen to podcasts before he was like yes
For some reason
The radio in his new car
Refuses to play one podcast
And one podcast only
The radiotopia podcasts
99percentinvisible
Really
Yes and it's driving him absolutely insane
His car Bluetooth has rejected
Roman Mars and his stories
Yes I'm obviously like for people who don't know 90% visible host by Roman Mars
It's really great non-fiction podcast they tell
Like always art design like how things work in the world and why they're made
The way they're made like the stories behind those things
And apparently is the one I guess it doesn't work on his car
That's right
Turn fan to play 99% invisible
Through his car stereo while he was on the phone with me can you tell me exactly where you're sitting at the MoMA
I am sitting at my driver seat in my
2016 Mazda 6
And
Let me know when you press play
Press play right now
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
But
Like the display screen stops working at totally freezes
The buttons aren't working properly
He has no control it's just for playing on the phone
Record screen at all it still says whatever I played right before I presented
And then after about a minute
Passover
What you saw
And now it's cut off Andre
Restart it
And I'm not playing 90% invisible anymore because every time I've done that
It's still playing it will freeze
How can you have a type problem where the trigger was
Like content
You know it's weird right it's very weird
It's like it would make more sense to me if like
A broken a time you try to listen like
Podcasts at work
It didn't work for Car Talk
Okay maybe his car doesn't want to hear stories about sick cars maybe that's like upsetting or something like that
I really like that you've immediately got two cars a cheap sentience
You have any theories about what's going on
I don't know my best guess is that
Because I looked at the file sizes and I listen to things like hardcore history and
A blank check which have big file sizes
And it's not that my best guess is maybe he's using some sort of weird
Audio codec
Interac streams with my
System but I really couldn't tell you
So I don't know
Ben thinks that because Romans voice is so like warm and closing his podcasts
Maybe he's doing something specific and Technical
To the files to achieve that
That would be my actual gas is like it's like a
There's something about the actual kind of
File the way that Roman is putting you converting his bike as soon MP3
Does just like too complicated for Ben's
Car system
And I was thinking about it and I was like
These are the two constants in his problem one is the podcast it's always the same pot
Any other has been it's always the same radio
I was like maybe just act like a battery
But even if it's a bad radio silly Jersey just like why is this radio bad
Only
Not only that
But
We got another email
From another person
Experiencing
Exactly the same problem
With exactly the same podcast that is so weird
All right
Hello how you doing
I'm good
How you doing I'm good
It is a pleasure to hear your voice
Yeah man but me as well I was very delighted to get your email
Are you
Are you totally in the dark as to why I would reach out to you
Totally
So I told Roman why I was telling him and I told him about what was going on with in the car
There's one
That causes his car stereo
Jefferies
Shutdown and restart
And Roman had actually heard about this problem
From other listener
Yeah I don't know what it is
We got some details
Read a few times were few different people
But
I've never really figured it out
All Roman nose is that
In some cars
Bluetooth classic car radio
What's 99percentinvisible
Cousin everything to break
But he has no idea why
So
Iran Bentley
He's like what Roman obviously cares about the
Sort of texture of the sound maybe he's doing something very specific to his file
And I'm curious little
What is what is your setup like
You have a strange microphone of some kind
No I mean we have
A couple are you
Like a shotgun mic in the studio
But you're not using some kind of special encoding settings that are different from the rest of radiotopia
Roman said that he had a theory that he's actually pretty confident about which is
The thing that makes
His podcast unusual
Is that
It uses the percent sign
Percent sign
As into % 99percentinvisible
Oh
He was like it must just not play well with the stereo for some reason
So it's like
Because it's Derek also display the name of the podcast there's something about just there being a symbol where does inspector to be a symbol where it
Brakes and it really bums Roman out honestly he's been hearing about it for years
From other people who are not been
But
Like what can you do about it
He's not going to change the name of the podcast
You know like I would love it to be fixed and I really if someone is a fan of the show I really hate for them not to be able to hear it
I wish I could be better but I think I recognize the futility of me fighting and I think is that I feel
Like a primary fundamental tenet
Super tech support
Is a realizing that something is futile
And relever well outside of our capability
And
Putting on a football helmet and running headfirst into it anyway
I mean if you solve it I would be
Really grateful
It just said it just like when it just seemed like there's these those were those things were
All these Technologies are
Butting up against each other
And all I am
Is some little bit of grit
That
Gets caught between the gears
Youku
Companies
You know
Not knowing how to
Past things off and talk to each other
That's what I feel like I am
The irony of this was crazy make
99percentinvisible
Podcast dedicated to explaining the beauty of good design
That is the one podcast that breaks when you try and play it on Ben's Mazda
It just felt like an imbalance in the universe that I had to correct and
Romans theory about the percent sign
It felt really plausible to me
So I thought I'd start there
And I figured like
If a percent sign car trouble
Because it's a special character
Other special characters to break the car to
So I just wanted to test that theory
Visit your thing like classic tech support problem like you have to
Replicate the glitch
To understand it to solve it exact
So I started thinking about other special characters like you know what about like the carrot or the curly brackets or
Whatever
Curly brackets
Okay
So
We wanted to make a podcast that would break his stare
And to do that we divide the test
Who's we
Me
Most of the team to be honest
Okay with me Tim
Anna Sophia
Emmanuel shruthi
Damiano
I was about to make fun of you guys because like oh why is it take that many people to make a podcast but it's like
Also
We did make one podcasts
How many markers did you make
Well
Start at beginning
The first podcast
Carrot space carrot
You know the carrot which is at the top of the little pointy the pointy upwards Arrow
Whose job is it to make the Pie cast iron
I would mind
Okay
AO3 nights like a child's drawing of like a Bugs Bunny carrot and then in the background there's a planet how I get it it's like
Carrots and space I'm just for you
Coleman territory
Hello welcome to the carrot space character
I recorded this in my attic
ASMR that like printers
Has slimmers that travel forward through time
Atomic red carrot
Hot pretty sister.
Relaxed relaxed how do you feel
Hypnotize me to go to sleep so I can mug my data Queen Anne's Lace and dialects
Negative Queen Anne's Lace
We made it podcast
We uploaded podcast apps and to an RSS feed
I gave it to bed
And I asked him to try it in his car
Glamazon
And we'll see if it breaks your a car stereo
Let's do it
And but
Hello Karen speech
Can you look at your screen and see how this is affecting your
Syria
I have to tell you it's
It is functioning completely normally
Interesting
It also means it's not filtering for the quality of podcast
So then we wanted to make a podcast to test the less-than symbol the tilde which is the symbol that means uproxx
Ultimately and the greater than
I'm just going to play that
Most jaunty
Hi this is samin nosrat
Welcome to greater than less than
You got some
Samin wrote the book Salt Fat acid heat and she also has a Netflix show by the same name
Today I'm joined by a cooking new Alex
Goldman
Oh I'm so glad you could be here
You got her teach you cooking I've been trying to learn cooking for a book for like a year
A berry cough with tea is basically a pancake with berries in it but instead of being cooked on the stove it's
Cooked in the oven
Okay
Do you feel like this
I feel very well for a Mazda
What you have to understand about this is this isn't your average cooking show
Because the only way that you could give me instructions as by telling me the ingredients were less than approximately or greater than
We need a
I have my heart
Hbase
Less than approximately are greater than some other thing
So I let me find an example
The measurement for the sugar should be about do you have you ever had one of those toys that you eat
Stress balls
Yes
Okay you should put about a stress ball amount of
So you're saying like greater than one of those Super Bowl
This is
Greater than a Super Bowl
Okay okay
For the eggs can you add an amount of exits greater than the number of nipples you have
So you're saying like
Less than the sides of a
Square
Correct
Anyway
At the barre class 40 I made as you might imagine.
Was not edible
So did this break the Mazda
He popped it in the podcast player
Hi this is so mean
Go get the greater than less than
It seems to be working just fine
So at this point we have tried
The carrot
The tilde the less than sign the greater than sign we made another podcast where we tested the play
Plus sign equal sign
The curly brackets
None of them
Replicating is prop
Have you ever had that thing happened where you go to get like an object repaired and the people and repair chapter about the object differently than you care about it
Guarantee mean
What district is Harley needs like to be a double neck guitar in right now it doesn't
Then they're just like doing it and they're often doing it you're as I gave more of a relation to the work they want to do than to helping you
I don't know what you're talking about Tammy there okay
But of course at this point we were definitely going to test
Right right
Some would want to make a bunch of garbage podcast
How dare you call this garbage
So we made a podcast that was called
100% related
Hi my name is Alice Goldin and you're looking to 100% related
The price of it is
A couple days ago I was talking to our editor Tim Howard and he insisted
But I was only 50% related to my dad because I only have 50% of my dad's genes
Father answer your 50% relieve your dad your 50% related your mom I'm a hundred my opinion is I'm a hundred percent related to book
In hims worldview yes
And so what we did is we got my dad a former judge to adjudicate this argument
Thank you what should I call you should I call you judge Goldman or should I call you whatever
Now I'd like for you to lay out your case to him because what you're saying is insane
Well
I really just seems to me that if you were a hundred percent related
You
Wood
You would be mark
And you are not
You're 50% related
So okay
What I'm saying is like
I'm 100%
Related to anyone who's my relative
So you are as related
To your father as any other human being
That's what you're saying
And him are on the same page
Spoiler alert
So is my dad
Tell Tim your dad took Tim side yes
Good man
So why is this the podcast I cuz I like arguing with you is like for fans of arguing with you
I don't feel
So
The percent sign related to the thing
So clearly we were wrong about all the special characters breaking the radio witch
Surprise me
But
I just wanted to confirm
The one thing that we were actually confident was true
Which was that the percent sign
So I get back in the podcast
All right
Is it freezing your
Stereo
Allison really sorry to say no
It is totally normal
But how is that
How is that possible
So clearly this caught me off guard
Seromas whole Theory they found so obvious
It doesn't seem to
It has to be something
Within the file itself that they are uploading this bus
That it doesn't actually have anything to do
Interesting
But n Ben
Tell the something that
Again
Befuddled
Okay which is
Ben 10 a copy of a 99percentinvisible episode
On YouTube
And tried playing that
So he was like I'm going to see if pirated 990i works
And
It breaks the car
Brakes the car and your brakes
Which is weird because it just means like it's is not actually anything about the file itself because when someone's uploading a podcast
YouTube that's totally new file yes it's like the content
It's like the car is sentient and doesn't like Roman Mars
And so Ben would like the only option is that
There must be some
Some Sonic
Frequency that is breaking the car and I was like a note in Romans I said if you were just sitting in a Mazda and started talking too loud the cartridge
IFile
There's a rumor that there is
I'm very familiar
Is that the sound real
I don't think it's not real but I'm glad I've been thinking about it this whole time
I've been thinking about it since the story began and I could like
I'm in mixed company I can bring this up but you stop yourself from saying something one time
Everybody
I hope so
Okay
So
We're like okay
We have no idea we're like totally back and forth
You got to find them
Subway
Any other reason this doesn't make any sense is because
Roman has another podcast
About Trump
And constitutional law yeah it's called what Trump can teach us about con law fine
Romans voice doesn't break the radio on that podcast
Only when it's 99percentinvisible
So what happened
U-Haul John Mazda we call the company that makes the radio
We called Ben's Mazda dealer we are specifically dealing with a Mazda Tech problem
From a person who's in your service area and I was wondering if I could ask you
A question or two about it
They weren't familiar with
So we called Andrew quits
The CTO of PRX the public radio Exchange
Hello Steve Andrews
Oh hello how are you I'm good
He's in charge of how the show gets uploaded to podcast apps that RSS feeds
Cedar County everybody be like have you heard
Yeah
And Andrew said that he heard of it
And that he'd always figured like Roman that was the percent sign
But I told him about the test that we do
All of them work
Including 100% really
That's
He's like
So painful these kind of bugs
No one knew what was going on
And then
I saw this ahead of you
So did that
She actually got back in touch with us and said
Hey I've been running some tests on my own
I tried uploading a couple podcast
And
What I found is that it's not the % alone that is causing this issue
It is the percent sign followed by an uppercase i
That shuts down there
Lowercase i
It doesn't uppercase i
It shut down
That's all we know
We don't know why because I hate your car doesn't fly
Lowercase i
I got a guy
That's exactly right
So we're getting closer
And then you know arpel Kurt Melby who
Where to get my it works again when I play fortnite with most weekends
Who does coding at the at the office yet
He had an idea
Alex
Thank you for coming to the studio today thank you
The reason that we have you here is because you're the person who actually uploaded the
Podcasts that we made
Yeah you know this
But none of them work
I listen to them also and over
Surprised that didn't work
Alright smart guy
Kurt says I have a theory
The theory is
That
The programming language C
Oh I know it is I know it happen
Literally 99% mean something
Can you turn off your stereo
I would say you're close but not exactly
In a programming language C
Basically in some scenarios
The percent sign means hey
The character immediately following me the character immediately following the percent sign
Think about that like code rather than liked
End and start
Parsing bat as though it's asking you to run command
Being called Princess
NC that's like used very very common lean heavily
Another languages of copy this feature
Interpolate is the technical term
Interpolate the number into the string
And he said percent I
In
C & C
Is a command where a percent are which would be 100% related
?
Is not so like
What's the command what is percent I tell
Computer to Dell
So I have it up here it has to do with
Basically 2% in NC
Has to do with displaying integers
NC I know this is very confused
So
Percent and then a bunch of different letters tell it to display integers in a certain
In a certain way
But basically what's happening
It sounds like
Is the car
Stereo
Hey guess what
He thinks is it audio file
What is an audiophile
Okay this part of the information I have is just for the humor
This is like the title
Yeah 99 and then it there's some stuff for you the robots to understand
I can't get confused and a chest
Yes
So there's a bunch of different commands in C that would cause this to happen
Okay and so we were like okay
If curtright we should be able to test this with other commands
And those should also mess up the car stereo
And so
We made one more podcast
With another one of the
Another one of the recognized piece of syntax which is the letter which is the letter
Key
Which when it follows the % becomes the pointer at
Grass whatever that means
Okay but whatever as long as going to code it should shut down the stereo. That's what happen
So we made a podcast that's called 88% parents
This is Erica
Edelbrock
Let me tell you about this document I've been waiting for
This one piece of paper it was going to change everything I thought I understood it for now
It arrived on a Monday
Monday began like a normal day
I was walking to work
With my dog
His name is Bruno by the way
Come with that name my name to Bruno he's a rescue dog he came with a name like Bradley or something which I really didn't like
So I changed it to Bruno which by the way is the name I also wanted to name my son but my
I understand what you've done
Who is Bruno
And we get there it's a short walk like maybe 10 minutes which is
Crazy because people are always like what
Podcasts to listen to what podcast you listen to cuz you make podcast and I'm like not that many cuz I'm such a short walk to work anyway
The strong okay
I've heard enough
Okay
All seems like people are like I went the next season of Serial coming out like 20 minutes later than it would
So what happened
Well we send it Urban
And it didn't break the car stereo
I didn't break it
So that screwed up the whole Theory
Absolutely
I mean
We didn't just try
Percent P we tried a bunch of different things that should have broken the car stereo in the same way the percent Idol
And none of them cause a problem
So what that is Kirstie rebunk
Curtsy reappears
Not to work
The only combination that did anything what percent
Followed by an uppercase i
Okay but we don't know why
Noe.
And it is driving
Peanuts
And this is the point in the story where Andrew cuckoo it's comes to the rescue
Andrew Cuomo
Remember he's the CTO at public radio exchange the company that distributes 99%
He really dove
Like he
Really invested what is that mean
Well
You know we're trying to figure out a way to diagnose this properly without actually having access to the code
You made a bunch of nonsense podcast for no reason you talk to somebody worked at a Mazda dealership and one guy at work
We also called master
Andrew was God until like a Mazda owners message board and found the actual code
Code
For the Mazda connect infotainment system really and within the code from the name of one of your
Original authors of the original code
Which event gave to us
Author of the code for the Mazda car stereo program yes
His name is Brandon Guzman that you can look
Encode and see the codes author like I didn't know that
There's a way to write your authorship in your code
And it's been
Done forever as always like that like a signature on a painting
It's a little a lot of times it's harder to find you have access to the code to see the authorship
And my favorite story about this is early in
The development of Atari games Atari would not allow the author of The Game to put their name on it
Because there's being a company about it and so the author of the game Adventure
Create this incredibly arcane
Set up
Things that you had to do in the game so that you would find a secret room
They just flashed his name in the center of the screen
That's brilliant and sad
Because it said that they had to go to that much work.
I just feel like I made that anyway
Chicken tenders Brandon
Yes he works on exercise technology now
Work work
We develop connected strength products
As a person who's terrible at exercising
I'm not your toy
Yeah baby irony is the entire office of us working on this or not either
We're more like stay up late and Senator computer longer
So we told Brandon what was going on with Benz car
And he told us that he was pretty sure he knew what was going on
Which is
So
What he said was
One thing that caught my eye immediately is that there's a percent symbol in the name
And that has some special meetings and things like a URL
Right
Is a URL certain characters are allowed in certain characters are not
So our operating Theory with 8% I was breaking a radio
Because
The percent sign followed by the letter i
Meant something in the programming language C
But what Brandon told us was
Know that program wasn't even written in C
Is written in a totally different program
Okay
Into the radio
Super Sentai doesn't actually mean anything
Brennan think the problem is
Is that the code should tell the radio to ignore things that doesn't understand or that don't mean anything
But in this case for whatever reason it's not
So the radio Super Sentai
It just keeps
Desperately trying to figure out what it means
So it's like it's having a panic attack
Kind of
Is an eye
And so then
I was like okay
So why is the stereo restarting
And Brandon told me that when they designed the car
They made it to the radio
With regularly sending a little message to the rest of the car saying
I'm working I'm working I'm working Brandon call it a heart
And
The hardware layers listening for that
As long as it gets it
It's happy
If it doesn't get it
It will assume that the UI has frozen
And it will
Restart it to a known good state
It's it's saying it's not communicating with me
Something is wrong
And it just start start over
So if it freezes up
It's in the heartbeat
It is trained to automatically shut down and start back up by the computer is that swipes
Takes a nap
That wakes up and tries again
I really like how much effort we put into personifying these cars
I just understand that they're sentient
I do feel like this by original Theory
Like everybody else they freak out with it on the right answer
Threat
There is one other thing that was suggested to us
Several times along the way
Benz
Car stereo firmware
Is a few
So the theory is that it might fix this problem
According to myself
But been looked into getting a firmware updated and it was just too expensive
However
That doesn't mean that we don't have a more permanent solution for bed in Roma
Because
Andrew Collette from PRX
Had a very sweet idea
Maybe we got a publisher version of 99% invisible with some slightly different
Titles or something
I'd be willing to
Create the
The Mazda version of the feed be great
Love you super cool
There's just like a 99percentinvisible for bed and other Mazda owners feed
Why can't say that people in Nissans have also reported having this problem but yes for Mazda owners in Nissan owners who are having problems with this
Epic infotainment system
Asbury News podcast
So
I called been up one more time
Just let me know if
If I when you got it set up and ready to roll
Welding
This is 99% invisible
Tim Harford is a master at picking up
Perfect little story
And everything's working fine
Yep
So this is totally works
Set plane normally not freezing at all
Perfect
What a link to the Mazda safe 99p I feed on our website it's 99 Pi. Org
Have the break
Will feature 3 full episodes of the fake podcast from the story
I think they play the full episodes it would have disrupted their story too much but they are gems and I really want to play them for you
But the best
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
And now 80% parentheticals 100% related
And greater than less than approximately
In their entirety
This is Sarah came to 88% parentheticals
Let me tell you about this document I've been waiting for
This one piece of paper that was going to change
Everything I thought I understood up to now
It arrived on a Monday
Monday began like a normal day I was walking to work
With my dog
His name is Bruno by the way
He didn't come with that name I name to Bruno he's a rescue dog he came with a name like Bradley or something which I really didn't like
Which by the way is the name I also wanted to name my son but my husband Nix that
Anyway I'm walking to work with Bruno and we get there it's a short walk like maybe 10 minutes which is
Crazy because people are always like what podcast you listen to what podcast you listen to cuz you make podcast and I'm like not that many cuz I'm such a
Short walk to work anyway
Reach to unlock the door
And I notice it at the bottom of the door there is this envelope
With just my name on it
No return address
I hate that why
Do people not put Retin-A understand if you need to be anonymous but just generally I can always teach my kids
Put your return address on the envelope in case it gets lost
Anyway and one time I did get this
Crazy Anonymous letter which is a whole other story I can tell you about another time
Anyway so I open this envelope with just my name on it
And inside is a single document
Which I'll tell you about
Next time
This episode of 88% parentheticals was produced by Emmanuel Joshi or editor is Tim Howard music
Music is by the mysterious breakmaster cylinder
You can check us out online or so I've been told I've never checked myself on iTunes or wherever you get your podcast
Hi
Listen to 100% related a podcast about family
All right
Let's start the show
Hello
Father
Hello I am recording you right now in the interest of full disclosure
Alright you have my permission
Thank you
I'm in the studio with Tim Howard or editor
Hi how are you
Doing wonderful thank you what should I call you should I call you judge Goldman or should I call you mark
Mark all right that's me and Mark what should I call you
You should call me just
Got to love it
So we are actually calling upon you in your capacity as a judge me we are having a disagreement
And we would like you to hear both sides and adjudicated
All right because first is a plaintiff
That's it I'd say that to measure
T came to me yesterday with a bold proposition
I profoundly disagree
Yeah okay so I'll just tell you what it was
It just simply that
For some reason
Alex and I
I don't know how we got on the topic but I argue to Alex
That he
And you
Are 50% related
And I said that we are a hundred
I'd like for you to lay out your case to
Because what you're saying is insane
It really just seems to me that if you were a hundred percent related
You
Wood
You would be mark
And you are not
You're 50% related
So okay
What I'm saying is like
When you're related to someone
You're 100% related to them regardless of how many genes you share
Look
I have like a Mike I have like a second cousin twice removed
To get out who like
Act like my aunt's
Grandson
My cousin's kid 100% related to that
A person I'm a hundred percent
Related
To anyone whose relative
So you are as related
To your father as
Any other human being that's what you're saying
But you cannot be more related
Or less related
To anybody
Well this feels like a
Like more like a less like a math argument more like a semantics
I mean I don't know but yeah I'm just I'm just following your logic here
My logic is you can have a closer relation
In that Oso higher percentage
Judge objection
Is that all you got
What are you talkin about
Makes perfect sense what I'm saying we're not done with the idea that you just said that you can be club or closely related
But it's not a percentage what is it an on-off
Okay
Alright let me let me let me let me ask a question
So I might get a genetic testing
About 45 years ago
This doesn't sound good for me
In NFL once every 3 or 4 months
I get this notice from the company that says
We have found more relatives
And these relatives
Of my
Genetic
Makeup
Okay but this company which is 23andMe still consider these people to be relics
Although I've never heard their name I don't know what a access point
0.65% genetic
Identity
Alright
Is related to them as unrelated few out
F*** you
I'm get arrested at that point in court don't you
It's contempt of court attempt of court
All right
Thank thank you so much Mark
They said alright Tim Alex
Yeah same to you
I'll talk to you later
Thanks for listening to 100% related you heard today from me I was
Tim Howard
And my dad Mark Goldman
The show is produced by Emmanuel Church
I theme song by The Mysterious breakmaster cylinder
Hi this is
Welcome to greater than less than approximately
Today I'm joined by a cooking newbie Alex
Goldman thanks for having me oh I'm so glad you could be here
We're going to make a barre class
What is a berry clafouti is basically a pancake with berries
But instead of
Being cooked on the
Stove is
Cooked in the oven
Okay
Do you feel like you can do that with me today
I feel very excited to
Okay are you in your kitchen
I am in my kitchen
I've got that much down
Okay good that's the right room to be in
Alright alright let's make sure you have all of your ingredient
We need milk do you have milk
Got it okay
Do you have sugar
Yes
An Egg's
Vanilla we need some salt
I have salt
And then you need some flour
Got it
And some do you have any berries around
I have some blueberries perfect blueberries are great okay okay the first steps to making
Is that we need to turn on the oven
So you have her heat your oven to a temperature
That's
A little bit
Less than the number of days in a year
Okay so we're talking like the number of degrees in a circle roughly approximately maybe a little bit less than that
Okay alright okay
And then you have to imagine that you're going to bake this pancake in a dish it could be any shape
It could be round or rectangular or like ovular I guess would be a word
But it needs to be approximately the size of like a
Small
Pan pizza
Okay let me take a look old
Okay I think I got it
Okay great
So we're going to need to measure out some milk
Basically I want you to put the amount of milk
That is like approximately you know like
Like a small jar of mayonnaise
Amount
So like
Smaller than a full ketchup bottle definitely less than a full ketchup
Like a bottle of ketchup
That has been used
Generous
And then we're going to put some sugar the measurement for the sugar should be about
Do you have you ever had one of those toys that you know those stress balls
Yes
Okay you should put about a stress ball amount of shoe
Into the wall
So you're saying like greater than one of those Super Bowl
Yes greater greater than a Super Bowl
But less than a softball
Okay
For the egg
Can you add an amount of eggs
It's greater than the number of nipples you have
First of all it's very presumptuous of you to know how many nipples I have
Second of all
So you're saying like
Less than the sides of a
Square correct
All right
And I feel like I was born to bake
Really good I mean it looks really good
For vanilla
We're going to put
Less than the number of lights on a
Traffic light amount
Glug
Into the ball
You got it
I put it I put some plugs in there
Okay great I want you to put more than
Twice
The amount
Planets in the solar system of grains of
Salt into the bowl
You got it
Done
When it comes to the flower
How how big is your big child
Harvey
He is
I don't know I'll be
Is he bigger than like 3 basketball stacked up
Yes
Alright I basically I want to imagine the size of Harvey's foot
Okay could you do a little more flour than the size of Harvey's foot into the bowl
A little more flour than the size of Harvey's foot
Now what you're going to have to do is use your whisk
To blend everything until it's
Really smooth and frothy
All right it is looking pretty frothy
Okay great
Now you're going to pour enough batter
To create a layer that's a little bit thicker than a piece of
Cardboard into the bottom of the day
So like
You be like approximately like two pieces of matzah stack
On top of each other
That sounds
Approximately that
Oh my God I'm so
Does it smell good in vanilla
Yes it does
So I wanted I want you to turn one of the burners of your stove on until the flame is a little
Little bit greater than
A lighter
Like a Zippo lighter
Oh okay
And then
Set the dish on top of their
You're going to leave the dish on there for a little bit less than the time at
Takes to brush your teeth
And what you're looking for is that the batter
Begins to set
In the bottom of the day
You got it
You got it all right here we go
So when's it set
You could pull it off the burner
Aha and now you're going to add the bear
Okay now we're going to add another stress ball amount of sugar over the berry
Okay
And now you get to top it all off with
With the rest of the batter
Just sort of drizzling
Okay now you can just throw it into the oven
For how long
It's going to be in there
For about
Aztlan
As a movie
So approximately as long as
An episode of
Bones
Yes I would say it's
Greater than the length of an episode of Bones without the commercials and the length of an episode of Bones with
Somewhere in there
God I really miss Beau
Noted
All right it's it's in there
Alex are you going to
Who are you going to
Eat this classroom
I'm probably going to eat it with my wife and kids
Which which I'm super excited about cuz my son loves dessert
More than anything in the world
And your children approximately how old are they
Harvey is older than
A wheel of Parmesan
I don't know how old wheels of Parmesan are
Is about as old
It's a little bit
Find the length of a typical
American
He's he's he's greater than
A wheel of Parmesan
Has it been approximately the number of minutes in
In a Bones episode
I'm going to take the clafouti
I'm going to show you what it looks like it's literally just came out of the oven
Okay I can't wait to see it
Interstate now
I would say that it approximately looks like
Did your local skatepark
You know how there's like sort of
Hills and Valleys
That are sort of oddly placed in order to maximize like grinding into jumping and leaping
That's I think what it looks like right now
The rising in the following is a natural part of the process
So you've done that part right
I think you've done a great job
I'm really excited for what you've made it's not a booty
It's closer to like a souffle pancake or a Dutch baby pancake but unfortunately it does look like
It's less brown than the Villa golden deliciousness that I had hoped
4 but I still think it will be delicious and I think you should taste it
I wish I were there
Looks delicious
It's like eggie
Kind of yeah
I feel like it's a success
All right
Samin thank you so much for having me on your show
I'm so pleased that you were able to join me today Alex
Oh my God
I feel greater than I did on the day I graduated high school
Oh I feel greater than the day you graduated from high school to
The show is hosted by me some
I mean it's produced by Anna Foley and our music is my brake master cylinder thanks so much
Search for listening
These three podcast in all the other podcast the reply-all made to test the Roman Mars Mazda bug or
Available your favorite podcast app to search for them or on the reply-all website which is linked
Reply all is hosted by PJ Vogt and Alex Goldman I could not be a bigger fan of their show goes into
Disgrace
Blues by Shruti pinnamaneni via-vallen-yo-ayo marchetti manifold leak Jessica Jung and Emmanuel Jojo
Tim Howard is the editor mixing by Rick Quan and K bielinski
Fact-checking by Michelle Harris there intern is Christina Ayala dichosa
Special thanks to kalila Holt Jim Fisher Sydney vam Ellis Peter Olyphant Eli Manning and Kurt Melby
And from my and I like to give a special shout-out to Andrew cuckoo it's the CTO of PRX who created all those 99 PID
Dummy feeds for Alex and been to test
As evidenced here
Andrew always works above and beyond the Call of Duty
Reply all theme song is by the mysterious breakmaster cylinder
The closing song is Simplicity by macroform
Only met Matt Lieber once
He was very nice
I'm very very tall
99percentinvisible is a project of kalw
91.7 in San Francisco and produced
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are a member of radiotopia from PR except fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in
Paula podcasting findmall
And radiotopia
Don FM
You can find the show into a discussion about the show on Facebook you can treated me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi org
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But we have links to 99 pi and articles of Interest beads that do not break any car stereos
1099 Pi. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com