This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
You may have seen the noguchi table coffee table
Movies or TV shows when they want to show that a lawyer or an art dealer is really sophisticated they play
Put on a Gucci table in there waiting room
It is really a beautiful table
Too curvy wooden legs interlocked
And support this heavy slab of glass
It seems like it's almost floating above them last reporter Jackson Roach
Noguchi coffee table was introduced in 1948 it's become one of the emblems of mid-century Industrial
Design it has its own Wikipedia page and there's a thriving Instagram hashtag hashtag FYI
MCT which stands for your noguchi coffee table
Which basically means
Pure bougie cliche Interiors
Which is ironic because like all eventual cliches
New Gucci himself
Was quite
Avant-garde
Noguchi was a prodigy
The sculpting prodigy
Isamu noguchi was a Sculptor
And he was so much more than that
Choreographers
And fashion designers and art directors
SNL whole lot of different people across a really wide creative SWA
Look taniguchi as a point of inspiration
This is bacon heart
Senior curator of the isamu noguchi foundation and garden Museum
Noguchi himself built this studio in Queens
How's a lifetime of his abstract
Evocative experiments in stone and Metal
Princess noguchi was challenging himself
With every sculpture
Can I make something hard feel soft can I make something heavy feel like
Can I make something far away feel like it's right next to you
You know how to make rock
Feel fluid that way
Noguchi sculptures seem to twist and balance on themselves
Undulating with form and texture
But this is all his later work
Back in the 1930s
Before noguchi you had a signature Museum and a namesake coffee table
He was a struggling artist in New York City
We pay the bills by sculpting busts
Rich people
He called it head busting and he did it just to make money
Or he said he did it just to make money but in truth he used it brilliantly is a way to Social Network
And it was a way to romance the people who were his patrons
He was as great a networker as he was a Sculptor
Head busting wasn't exactly
The feeling
Do you want to think bigger
Here's noguchi in an interview from the 70s
The 1930s
Having done
Some more heads and being disgusted
Doing heads
Decide to get away you know
Another dimension
That was the same thing that makes us go to the Moon
Desire to get away
If you wanted to make art that would live in the world
I just in a rich person's home or on a gallery wall
You wanted to change the physical landscape that people moved
Gucci said that he wanted people
To feel like the first person on earth
The first person to explore
And so he's hard to think of a concept for a giant public sculpture
It looked like a massive
Massive
Pyramid
Imagine across
Between a Mayan temple
Gander Mountain
Pushing up out of the Earth
With a long slide slipping down it
Steps on two of its faces
It is it is a step pyramid essentially but on each side the steps are different heights
And they were regular very symmetrical
But it wasn't just a sculpture for a museum or a
Bank Plaza
Noguchi thought of it as a playground
He called it
Play Mountain
So he talked about play as the primer for a purposeful of pro
Approach to space
Trying to teach people to be more mindful of space and how we occupy it and how it works
This giant ziggurat wouldn't come with any Specific Instructions would have no rules no single
Obvious way to play with it she wanted play Mountain to be a strange new landscape
It would dare children to imagine other realities
So that perhaps they could grow up into creative open-minded adults
I think you do cheat hope that by making playgrounds he could impact people at that
Key stage in development
In fact the inspiration for play mountain when he was at those keys dates himself
When he was a little boy
Isamu noguchi was born in Los Angeles in 1904
His father yone was a famous Japanese poet
His mother was a white American writer named leonie Gilmour
They met when she answered an ad he placed in the paper for a translator and assistant
Pretty much as soon as a Simon was born
Unity abandoned
And went back to Japan
Noguchi and his mother eventually follow
But his father had already started another family by then
Gucci and his mother moved to a Countryside town
Where noguchi's bright blue eyes marked him as an outsider to the other kids at school
His childhood was pretty lonely
But from their little house
In a little town they lived in on the seaside
They did have a great view of Mount Fuji
Spec Fuji quite far away so like just a perfect little pyramid
So you can imagine that view that's a little boy has every day going down the stairs scene Mount Fuji
That idea of his own Mount Fuji stuck with noguchi
If I owe them money move to Indiana as a teenager
It followed him to Paris review Prentice with the Sculptor brancusi
I came with him to New York City
The place that he decided would become his home
The Gucci Road play Mountain was my response based on memory of my own unhappy childhood
The desolate playground on a cliff in Tokyo
Which I approached with Dread
It may be that this is how I tried to join the city
New York
HIPAA law
Knew she wanted to move the mountain from his lonely childhood
And reincarnated
Is a place for gathering in playing
As a kind of
Gift to the children of New York
And after years and years of carrying that Concept in his head
He got his big break
In 1934
One of the fancy people noguchi had made a bust of
Help them get a meeting with Robert Moses
The newly-appointed commissioner of the New York City Parks Department
Moses had said his number one priority was to build more playgrounds in the city
Which at the time and very few
Taguchi decided to bring him his idea
Noguchi brought Moses a model of play mount
2 feet square in white Plaster on a wooden frame
Designed to take up an entire New York city block
Noguchi carries this
Meter Mountain to Robert Moses office
Then sit down on Robert Moses desk
And says what if we know we built this for the children of the
The city this is Alexandra Lange
Architecture critic at curves and other of the design of childhood
Moses's
No way
The playgrounds Moses Envision were symbol
Asphalt or dirt surrounded by chain-link fence
With the four s's of playground equipment
Swings slide sandbox seesaw
All made out of steel
Moses was planning just the four s's in vacant Lots
All over the city by the hundreds
With this massive ambiguous otherworldly Urban Mountain
Which would have required the movement of huge amounts of Earth
And concrete
Probably would have cost a ton of money
No way dope
Play Kyrie 4S is I'm just going to order them
And like we're going to be out 400 playgrounds by tomorrow
Robert Moses dead end up erecting 658 playgrounds in New York as Parks commissioner
But from this moment on
Tienda Gucci
Became the lifelong enemies
He took his model and went home fuming and he fumed about it for the rest of his life really
The concept of play Mountain remained very close to noguchi's hard
Is a Gucci himself wrote
Play Mountain was the kernel out of which have grown all my ideas relating sculpture
To the Earth
Play Mountain represented this idea that noguchi had
The children didn't need instructions to play
With say
Swing Zara slide
Is only one way to use them
Kids just do the same prescribed activities over and over again
But if you give children an abstract
Surreal landscape
They can interpret it however they want
We can make up stories and have adventures and use their intuition
To play in a thousand different ways
This philosophy would later be called
Non-directive play
Noguchi
This was the way that
Sculpture could be out in the world
I'm really change the way people move
And think
He wasn't going to give up on it so easily
In 1939
Noguchi offered to design a playground for Honolulu Ala Moana Park
But that fell through
Bill not discouraged
Nicotine patches his Hawaii playground ideas
Back to the New York parks
Again
Again he gets rejected
Noguchi is relentless
Enso noguchi
Still excited by the challenge
When Austin design Contour playground
Contoured playground is really gentle
Basically a smooth abstracted landscape of sloping Hills and Dales and riverbeds
It's still a non-directive playground
But it's very subtle
This time
New York parks department actually seems
Open today
I even start talking about finding a spot in Central Park to build
But by then was 1941
And the Gucci's plants were about to change
Noguchi was in California
Visiting a friend
He was out shopping for some Onyx for a sculpture
That I was on my way to San Diego
And I can turn on the radio and that's where I heard
Am I really need a reaction was oh my God I'm a dumb in Japanese
Nisei are Americans born to Japanese parents
With the US entering World War I
Country playground was forgotten
By both the parks department and the Gucci
They were bigger Stakes now
I want to be able to help in some way
Noguchi started to link up with other nisei
Looking for ways to make it clear to the government
But they were firmly on the American side of the war
Intention was that we would contract the bad press
Stop.
But that hysteria was quickly coming to a head
Barely two months after Pearl Harbor
President Roosevelt signed executive order 99066
Executive Order 9066 gives the American Military the right to declare martial law
In any part of the country that it deems necessary
To protect the Homeland
And that's with the understanding that in the Western United States
David Roundup the Japanese American population
Evacuation orders with fast-approaching deadlines
Started landing on
People's doorsteps
My car in Los Angeles
Noguchi had always been good at finding exactly the right person for the movement
In This Moment
He needed someone to help him take action
So he found him
In Washington DC
So I went to Washington
You know what I can do
John Collier was the head of the Bureau of Indian Affairs
Because the government needed to build the internment camps in large
Open areas of federally controlled land
He decided to do two of them on Native American reservations
Which meant that the actual undertaking of building and running these camps
Woodfall to John Colliers Department
John Collier was relatively Progressive
He wanted to give tribal governments more autonomy and support Native American culture
And then
Suddenly
Have been given the task of Designing and building prison camps
On reservation land
Noguchi reach out to him
Noguchi and Collier started talking about what they could do with this assignment
Now that there was no way to prevent internment from happening
What do they cook time
And this is going to sound so crazy but in a way they cooked up what was a utopian scheme
Because
From their point of view if it's going to happen
Let's make it
As good as it can possibly be
Noguchi Drew up a suite of plans for the largest of the
Camps being built
The one at Poston Arizona
I make plans for the park
Noguchi Chuck the rigid grid of a military-style camp
With rows and rows of tarpaper barracks
And cutting Avenue right down the middle of
Lined with public services
Schools in gardens Hospital
Restaurants
Department store in a movie theater going to church in a cemetery
Zoo botanical gardens Sports fields and a mini golf course and
Playground
What you're looking at is what he thinks the key parts of
Civilization art
You have a huge population of people who have been removed from their lives and artificially plunked down in the
The middle of nowhere
Where do they are expected to live
Quote on quote what does that mean what is the light
What does life consist of
How would what does it need to be real to feel real
The playground is critical to it
The plans themselves are pretty unbelievable
But the really wild thing is that
Even though Japanese internment only affected people living on the West Coast
And maybe she was living on the East Coast
Noguchi and Collier decide
Noguchi should actually go to this concentration camp in Poston Arizona
Voluntarily
And leave it there while he carried out his plan
And that's how I happened
The camp was being constructed in the middle of the desert
The southwestern part of Arizona
On the Colorado River Indian Reservation
Who is hardly anything
For miles around
Scrubby brush and dust
Mountains in the far distance
Sanducci got to post in like a week before it opened
And I was hungry
Noguchi was giving his own room and thought he'd soon be getting to work on realizing his vision for utopian
This was a guy who plunged
Play Mountain down in front of Robert Moses
And said
Let's build this for kids
Estranged hopefulness knew no limits
Resume is the camp opened
It became painfully clear taniguchi
But the people weren't coming there for an idyllic new lifestyle
They were prisoners
Do the camp administrators from the war relocation Authority
Noguchi looked
Just like another one of the prisoners
I wouldn't give him the time of day
Because he had some special privileges
The other internees assumed he was the traitor
In Cahoots with the camp administrators
He immediately realized he was
He was sort of the worst of Both Worlds because he was just in an attorney from the administration's point of view
And he was a turncoat like a spy
From the other entries point of view
After about two months at Poston
Noguchi realize that the war relocation Authority had no interest in making it a nice place to live
They ran it like a prison
Because it was a prison camp
All of John Colliers and micucci's idealistic plans were ignored
See if there was no chance of doing what he'd come to do
Noguchi decided to move on
He figured he'd just
Go back to normal life
Mina famous artist in hanging out with his famous artist friend
And they wouldn't let him
Which was definitely
Not a part of the plan
You no idea that he wouldn't be able to leave
Noguchi with suddenly
Prisoner
Have you made enemies of attorneys and administrators alike
He spent most of his time alone
With nothing to do
Person with a bleak
Aaron place
Almost every day there was
Triple-digit Heat
Huge dust storms tearing through
Coming in through the thin walls of the barracks
Getting stuck in your bed and your mouth
In your eyes
Noguchi wrote to one of his famous friends
The artist Man Ray
Quote here time has stopped and nothing is of any
Nothing of any value
Neither our time
Or our skill
The world
Is nuts
After 7 months
And many many letters and phone calls
John Collier was able to get noguchi out
And he never
Went back
It's hard to know what to make of noguchi's failed mission to post in
And it kind of leads to this deeper question
Does it even make sense
To try to find Joy or beauty
Playfulness
In a system that's
Just fundamentally
Awful
You know
Trying to make a prison better when the prison shouldn't exist
Critic Alexander Lane
Like he thought he could
Make this internment camp more Humane but it's
Is it inhumane endeavour
The whole experience was painful for noguchi
His goals have been so compassionate going in
Racism in fear and bureaucracy
Kill those dreams
And then imprison him
When he tried to help
New York 1940
I've had about enough
After posting
The idea of Designing Public Works
And playgrounds
Must have seemed
Wrong somehow
How could you think about play
When there's so much
Cruelty in the world
In fact in 1943
The year after noguchi gets out of post in
It makes this sculpture called
This tortured Earth
Which is like the nightmare version of his model for
Contoured playground
Twisted landscape
It looks like it's been stabbed and torn with a knife
But once he was back in New York noguchi put Post in behind him
He threw himself into the art scene
He's designing Furniture he's making sculpture he's building a career New York City
Play Gucci steps back from his utopian ideas about art and sculpture
And this is the. When you design some of the things he's most famous for today
Including the iconic coffee table
The Gucci's career in sculpture really took off
And you also got to design other kinds of environments he designed and sets for Martha Graham
And sculpture Gardens for corporations like IBM Chase Bank
He was smoothing up a storm becoming a household name and a real star of mid-century Art and Design
Maybe she has that hunger in my soul
Something more meaningful than the New York art scene
He still wants to make something that can transcend a gallery space
And that is because again I have this feeling that
Culture was an important part of the living experience
Something for electives
After a decade of looking inward indulging in the Adoration of the art world and recovering from posting
Noguchi turns his sights back
The playground
Shake that realization that he had
The playgrounds were actually
The perfect way
Sculptor to make real change in the world
3 tried two more times to build playgrounds for New York
Once in 1950
At the new UN building
And another in the early sixties
Riverside Park
And again noguchi's playground plans were shot down by the city
But something was different
And those round 2 projections
Because noguchi was now
Mega famous
Everyone in the art world had heard
All about his rejected playground design
They've been written up and newspapers
And the model is worth
Displayed in museums
So other Architects artists and designers
Started copying
So there are fair number of people in the fifties and sixties making abstract concrete forms and saying that they
Care for children
It becomes
A movement
Whole strand of playground is
Taniguchi kind of founded
Alexander Wang calls this
The abstractionist
You can play with an abstract form
Anyway you want
Imagine it is anything you like
Face shapes
Can become anything in your mind
In the 60s and 70s
Designers artists and architects
Build abstract playgrounds all over the world
Climbing arches and stepping stones in Amsterdam
Blobby triple slides in Austria
Webs
Steel & Rope in Japan
And in the US
Modular octahedrons and pixelated wooden landscapes
All made by famous architects
Designing and building abstract
Non-directive playground
Even noguchi himself was able to build some
Abstract
Dish
Sculptural playground equipment in the 60s and 70s
She was one of the first to say that and make those things and kind of taking children seriously
Connoisseurs of 4
No one
It would seem like the perfect time for noguchi
To build the thing he wanted his whole life
True play Mountain vision
What's something that could turn Landscapes into massive abstract forms
But just as it seems to Gucci's ideas are gaining traction
It's cut short
Is the 60s turn to the 70s in the 70s draw to a close
The abstract playground movement goes Underground
Because in the 1980s
The entire world a playground design in the US
Change dramatically
After the break
What the obstructionist movement went underground
And why your neighborhood playground probably looks very similar to every other neighborhood playground
Atlas
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
2 year old boy named Frank Nelson was climbing a 12 ft tall slide in the Chicago Park
Because that's just how tall slides used to be
He spoke to the railing off the steps and hit his head on hard ass
And
Has permanent brain damage
Frank became paralyzed on his left side
Ear problems with vision and speech and had to wear a helmet
Protect his fractured skull
So there's this big lawsuit where the
Park system of Chicago has to pay out millions of dollars
9.5 million dollars
Be exact
The accident was in 1978
And it changed ever
The time
There were no laws
Or real industry standards even when it came to the safety of playground equipment
But Frank Nelson's fall was one of a number of lawsuits
Led the consumer product safety commission to publish
Handbook
For public playground safety
In 1981
Then another standards organization
The ASTM published its own guide
Pretty soon these Robux
We're in the hands of insurance companies and Parks Department
School boards
Across the United States
And now to this day almost all playground have to be approved
Buy certified playground safety inspector
ICraig Fatale with
Safe to play
With you just a few of the things that I used to make sure that your playground is safe
When I do a search YouTube video that a certified playground safety inspector uses to advertise his services
Is standing on your typical modern playground and he has a bunch of these weirdly shaped in the metal objects
Sun sticks
They're all different sizes each approximating different child size body
The handbook
Procure wish I could
Imitate head at 9 in so
Defeat would go in and then they had we get stuck so obviously we don't want that to happen
And safety inspectors basically tried jamming these probes into every space or gap on a playground
Looking for places where
Kids could fall or get
Pinch poke.
Trapped
Obviously no one wants kids getting hurt on playground
But as you might imagine
All these rules and regulations make the job of a playground designer
A lot harder
Don't get me wrong the job is
Fine as hell
Tom Keller designs playground
That look forward to coming in here every day
Because what a blast
But the more
Rules we have to wait here too
It just becomes
Noir Disco
Impossible
Definitely more difficult to think
Outside the box
Tom works at landscape structures
Playground Manufacturing Company in Minnesota
Annie's playground standards are so detailed
But they end up ruling out almost all variation
10 cases of common playground equipment
Swings
Slides
Spraying equipment and stuff like that
Truly
Create
Their own being because the rules
It's going to look like that
A slide is a slide
Your ability
Almost
Theoretically we've loved the idea of a special or unusual playground
Like even within Tom's company
They want to manufacture beautiful new forms for kids to play on
Are executives
You know they're like
We want to slide that nobody's ever thought
You got to be more creative than that and I'm like ice
You know what I hear you don't want to read the rule book
Cuz that's going to bore you
Baidu
Trust me it is what it is
So the playgrounds that you see everywhere
Neighborhood parks
School yards
They still all look
More or less the same
The majority of players
On the market today
Are what we refer to as post index system
Post index systems are also called
Post and platform playground
And with those you have Dax
And you have stairs
Bears and uibe pathways
The post and platform equipment
Essentially combines
Swing slide
And monkey bars into one piece of equipment is made of plastic parts in bright
Primary colors
Sometimes the parts are connected with Pathways cover
Grooves
Sometimes with Bridges
But there are steps
Find letters coming off the platforms at every turn
Blocking kids
It's from being able to just
Step off
The platform into space
That agglomeration is kind of in
Responsible safety standards
Post and platform playground
Definitely have more variety than the 4S is that
Robert Moses was into
On the music style playgrounds
Kids were just moving from one repetitive activity to the next
At least with posting platform structures
Kids can make some decisions about how to get onto the platform
And then how to get down from it again
But still posting platform playgrounds are all remixes of the same basic
Cat it's time for a change a little bit
This is Scott Roshe
Creative director at landscape structure
In addition to the standard playground kits
Landscape structures also designs custom playground
The clients that can afford them
Actually one of Scott's big inspiration
Is the work of isamu noguchi
Designs of today hours are echoing a lot of what what noguchi's concepts were
The kind of abstract playgrounds that new Gucci inspired
Are starting to re-emerge
We're starting to bring them back
In a lot of custom playground design
Pretty special projects Scott works with a lot of landscape
Moving Earth around and experimenting with new form
We've been to playgrounds that we've designed that are very abstract
And where parents literally say I don't know
How
This is supposed to work
That's the best
And this goes back to noguchi's concept of non-directive play
If adults are confused by a piece of play equipment
It often means that kids
Will be all over it
The kids are going to figure it out there
They're going to attack it they're going to
Go and have fun they're going to make it
Play
We don't have to tell them how to do that
We can make it safe and
Last a long time and look beautiful but man
Let them play
This Resurgence of abstract playgrounds is still developing
But special destination playground
I'm sorry experimenting with new materials and processes
They're able to make forms that would have been astronomically expensive to produce and noguchi's time
Contemporary designers
Are now starting to push back against convention and play with more abstract shapes
4 communities that can afford custom playground
So I feel like there are people that are pushing the envelope
And you know it's expensive to start out with but if more people adopt this
Equipment
The price group
Come down
Although there are no playgrounds in New York City with Nucci's name on them
Is ideas
About imagination in Freedom to play
I've left a deep mark
On playground designers
And are affecting the emerging playgrounds all around us
Noguchi could have never imagined the long shadow of his ideas
Is greatest Concepts
Had never been made
That's a recording from 1973
At that point
Noguchi had only ever seen one of his playground
Kind of built in Japan
A few years later he designed another one in Atlanta
But both of these were nothing close to his true
Play Mountain vision
His own City
New York
Have rejected him five times
Never found a way to break through a New York even after Moses was gone
For various reasons there's always a reason
But I am usually frustrating
This was his home
Noguchi's model for play Mountain remain on display in his studio in Long Island City
Unrealised dream
In miniature
That is until January of 1988
A man from Sapporo Japan comes and visits noguchi and is going around his Studio
In Long Island
City
And he says you know what like I I can get one of your playgrounds built in
In Sapporo
Japan
At this point in 1988
Noguchi is 84 years old
He goes out to visit this marshy site in Sapporo called moerenuma Park
It's just
Perfect
This is the spot
Foreplay Mountain would finally live
Noguchi started designing play structures and Earthworks for the park
With his longtime collaborator the architect shouji sit down
But in the winter of that year
I came down with a cold
How many came back to New York
They turned into pneumonia
And he died
Noguchi died on December 30th 1988
Having designed the vast majority of the park
Is collaborator Shoji sadao
Continue to work on it
From the cooties death at the end of 1988
More Newman Park took 17 years to build
They finally opened in 2005
It's enormous
454 Acres
Taking calls at noguchi Disneyland
5 times the size of Disneyland amalgamation the Great
Just Hits
Of all of these cheese unexecuted land and playground ideas
In one spot
Huge green swath of land tucked into a bend in the river there are forests of his candy like
Play equipment mounds and pyramids and swooping pads and enormous conical Hill to climb a huge
Fountain that Cycles through an hour-long water show
I mean you do feel like a tiny version of yourself
In this alien
City
The most satisfying of all
Rising High Above This alien landscape
Is play mount
Totally amazing
Alexander saw this mountain with her own eyes
Degrassi angular pyramid
Surreal and it's huge
At a hundred feet tall
Sorry I went to the support
October
I park my bike at the
The bottom of the sea
Flight of like 1000
It's really windy it's cold I'm all alone I mean
It's like I could be on the moon.
And I get to the top of the mountain and there's a memorial to noguchi
Says you know he made the
Isamu noguchi was never able to take in the view from the peak
What is creation
The sculpture he spent his
Whole life dreaming about
A mountain
Teleported from the wild alien planet is mine
The one place
Noguchi ever felt
He really belongs
Interesting to me people's place in the world
How we function in this
I think I have that kind of feeling about sculpture like wanting to be inside the sculpture
Not just looking at
Sculpture
Noguchi wanted us to see the world
What is if we were visiting
For the first time
To move our bodies through space
Is it the simple facts of gravity and Contour
Or brand new Delights
To look around with wide eyes
Feel with outstretched fingers
Imagine infinite possibilities
In other words
To live like kids
On a playground
99percentinvisible with produces week by Jackson roach and edited by Avery truffle
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kolstad is the digital
The wrestling team includes senior editor Delaney Hall
Joe Rosenberg Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza Vivien Leigh Sophia klatzker and me Roman Mars
Audio of noguchi comes from a 1973 oral history interview held by the Smithsonian archives of America
American art
Social things to Katie Swanson and everyone at landscape structures
Janine
Dana win Carlos Morales in Marfa Public Radio
Stefania Gomez Community Alliance and preservation project
And the staff of the Colorado River Indian tribes reservation Museum
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative show
Shows in all of podcasting
Fun Mall
Radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook and read me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But your Digital Playground for design stories is that
99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com