This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There's a common complaint that people don't read book
But the truth is
Print book sales are up dates.
Since 2013 sales of physical books have increased
Every year
The first people attributed to the rise of adult coloring books
But even as their popularity has dwindled
Book Sales have risen
I'm talking about
Physical old fashioned books
Paper Pages Boulevard
We love them
The great Argentinian writer Jorge Luis Borges once said
I cannot sleep unless I am surrounded by books
And I kind of agree
Best reporter Pierce County
Although he's not normal
Hoverboard
I'm a graduate student in creative writing
And for the past two years I taught fiction writing to undergrads at the University of Virginia
I assign a lot of reading but mostly it's in the form of photocopy pages
But don't worry The Print Shop pays for the rice
I don't want to force my students to buy too much but I always make sure I assign at least one physical book
I always try to pick something that's beautiful
When was the nice font a lovely page design a pleasing paper grain an intriguing cover
Don't get me wrong the words inside matter too
But I think it's important for my students to have an object that accentuates
The pleasure of the physical act of reading
It's something that would hold onto after the class attendance
I personally caused hundreds of pages of radio scripts and recycling bin every month
But I would have a really hard time throwing away
What's the pages have a spine
It's like they have
Seoul
It would feel wrong
Like you're spitting on knowledge itself
It's so hard
To get ready
Set up box
This is a story about books
And
Brace yourself
How to get rid of them
And in the words of REM
It starts with an earthquake
Just go in the background and we zoom into kilo stick
Fart
It was the most Bay Area sporting event imaginable
The Oakland A's were playing the San Francisco Giants
The 1989 World Series
Coming into the third game on October 17th 1989
The A's were in the lead
They won the first two games
And he fails to get Dave Parker
But just as the third game was about to kick-off
The TV broadcast cut out
When the signal came back
It was no longer a baseball
This is Cheryl Jennings on the channel 7 news room as you may have noticed our power was knocked out
Is the early minutes of the Loma Prieta earthquake
Race track near Santa Cruz
This was the first major earthquake ever to be broadcast live on national TV
An elevator in shelter
Part of the Bay Bridge has been destroyed their fires falling buildings widespread power outages
It all there were 63 deaths and almost 4000 injuries
But this is a story
About what happened to the San Francisco Public Library
After this earthquake
And because of this earthquake
The library suffered a lot of damage
Especially on the higher floors
So one of the things about an earthquake is
Daily effective it is intensified the higher up you go
On the upper levels of the library
Fluorescent cave
Jason Gibbs was a new library in there but he couldn't go to work
For two months after the quake
It was too dangerous
He says bookshelves would collapse sideways or falling on their faces
And books lie in piles everywhere
Like the books have been tossed around by
Some
Angry Forest
No one was injured at the San Francisco Public Library
But the earthquake
Dumped half a million books on the floor
Even after 2 months of repairs
The post earthquake situation in the San Francisco Public Library was still pretty bad
Library management determines the stacks weren't safe
And designated a new room for public browser
Librarians curated a selection of books that they thought the public would most likely
And those books went in that room
But they realized along the way that
Not every book was going to
To fit in other words
Even this window down selection of books was too large for the available space
They need to win it down even more
Earthquake just happen we don't have this shelving anymore
We need to make space
That's
A reasonable thing to do if you approach it in a thoughtful way
Biggest libraries do get rid of books
All the time
Earthquake or not
Put simply there are so many new books coming in every day and only a finite amount of libraries face
Practice of freeing up library space is called
Wieting if you think about it if it sounds ugly but it is a really good description
Mikkeller she supervises teen services at the Oakland Public Library
Avery Chapman went down the street to visitor and see how she weed
You have to weed your garden for like the flowers to grow
Reading is not just about holding the book in your hands and ask yourself if that book spark Joy
Specific guidelines
We're not just randomly grabbing books at the shelf and putting them in the trash
Tell her in many other Librarians at libraries all over the world with ourselves using the same set of guidelines
Excellent acronym
M u s t y
Is for misleading
Are factually inaccurate a little broken
So beat up
Indication it would love for sure so
New copy of it
If it hasn't been checked out in the last 3 years I would probably consider
Esper superseded
Buy a new edition or much better book
This is like an old manual for Windows 98 or an outdated travel guide
These are the kinds of books to get shredded
The last two letters rt for trivial and why
Your collection has no use for this book
Because I really want that musty acronym to work
Does last to the T in the Y
Trivial and your library has no need for this book
These are the tricky ones
They're not necessarily statements of fact
Their judgments of value
What's trivial to me might be very important to you and vice versa
But even hear these judgment calls are made by Librarians who specialize in the relevant section
Based on circulation
You just have to trust that you're Librarians are doing their best for the public
We want to be able to keep
Bringing you the most relevant
Most current
Information in the only way to do that is by having
To do it so the only way we can do that is by
Sometimes
Withdrawing the things that are not as though
Although some sections according to the library guidelines are
Generally self weeding
In other words
They disappear
How people feel
Certain sections of the library at 10 to disa
If you're more than other
Books about marijuana the Bible
They called are probably the biggest ones I can think of
But for the sections that do have to get weed
Weeding is generally a touchy subject
The reason why is probably already clear to you
People don't like the idea of books being thrown away
We like la
Perhaps no one loves books more
The librarian
There's a part of you that just winces every time you have to remove a book I need a legal books are dear to us
Hardy Weinberg sure has a librarian is
To get over that a little bit
Yes reading is normal and necessary
But after the 1989 earthquake the San Francisco Public Library started weeding and unusual
Amount of books
The Librarians were told to move quickly
And I didn't use musty
Or any sort of comprable system
The Librarians were ordered to go through each collection book by buck and insert a slip of paper into each
Green yellow and red
Green metal bucket been checked out that
Yellow metal bucket been checked out in the last 2 years
And red meant it had been over two years since somebody had checked out that
And the read books
We're the ones that were
In potential Danger
Danger because management had decided
At the Redbox
Had to go
Compared to the careful consideration of musty
The system of the green yellow and red card
Prices of rather blunt instruments
It's really not the only measure
Weather somebody is borrowed at
Within the last
Period of time
Felt rather arbitrary
And it wasn't really clear where the red card books were going to go or if they would ever be used again
And json gives us a
For example
The art and music collection
The discarded books got sent to an abandoned Hospital owned by the city
Because there was nowhere else to put them
Even battle-hardened Librarians like Gibbs
Stop the wedding was happening too fast
You had Librarians and different sections weeding furiously
And not really communicating with
Are the consequence
Lots and lots of books
Swirl remover
From the library
And no one quite knew how many
Because no one was
Keeping track
It was
Ultimately I think a weakness of management from the top
Jason Gibbs is a pretty even-keeled guy
But that's a diplomatic way of saying that
The problems began with the
The head librarian
A man named
Kenneth Dowling
We're going to hear it to you could be visiting the public
Library
Without leaving your home
Since this is the years leading up
The 1989 North
The San Francisco Public Library was starting to rethink its whole approach the books
The new little thing
Call the internet
Imagine plugging a computer like this one into any telephone in the world
And being able to search
Any library in the world
And a big part of this pivot was when in 1987
San Francisco hired Kenneth Dowling as its new city librarian
San Francisco city librarian
Kindling must make sure that two million people have access to 18 million books and other information on a limited
Stalin was all about the internet
Did recently published a book called the electronic library
In which he argued that technology was changing the way people use information
And therefore changing the role of librarian
This is a clip
Internet web world
Uwell
Collapses time
Classes distance
And is clamped
If it sounds unremarkable not to mention a bit quaint
Keep in mind that Dowling
Wisin all this stuff
As early as 1984
He certainly understood at an early stage
What the internet was going to do for communication
But there was a flip side to dowling's Visionary concept of digitally net
Worth library
Some people felt that Dowlen had a distressing lack of concern
Starbucks
There was a sense that
When it came to the
Physical collections he didn't
You just didn't have any interest
Dowling was also overseeing the design of a new main library for the city of Sanford
Francisco
Which would complete his vision of the library of the future
The city is building a new 100 million dollar library that is wired for computers as well as television
This new library would have
Twice as much space as the old one
But a big chunk of that face wasn't going to be for shelving books
Instead
Much of the library's interior was devoted to an atrium
In the middle of the building
We should rise 86ft to a conical glass roof
Lots of librarians worried that this big empty Atrium wouldn't leave a lot of space
4 books
The Atrium was evidence that books were not the sole priority of this building
And darling wasn't going to let a good crisis go to waste
Earthquake was a perfect excuse to do what he wanted to do anyway
Shrink the physical collection before the move to the new space
Gallons Administration started sending books to landfills
In the days after the quake
Books are being sent out by the truckload
Several times a week
This is not normal Library practice
27 librarian
Sign a petition
Asking Kenneth Dowling for the weeding to stop
But that didn't work
To Jason Gibbs and his colleagues
Decided to do something
In any institution you have a variety of
People there are some people who will just
Kind of
Do whatever they're told their other people
Who feel like they have a higher calling to the profession
Gibbs and Librarians from several other departments
Felt that Higher Calling
They banded together and call themselves
The gorilla Library
Gorillas like the
Freedom fighter
Fighting for the freedom to not put little slips of red paper on books
Against the orders of management
Let's just say that we did not withdraw books because they had circulated
We we we generally held onto the collection
Jason says that other Guerrilla librarians
Snuck into the stack
Replaced
Lips with green ones
Thereby designating the book
The circulating book
I'm keeping it in the collection
The gorilla Librarians wanted to determine exactly how many books have been weeded and how many have been dumped
But nobody had any idea how many books are being taken away
And there was a risk that they'd never be able to find out the magnitude
This massive clearing
Because Kenneth Dallas
Decided
Get rid
Of the physical card catalog
Those files full of index cards
Chronicling
Buck
Card catalog is an artifact
But I will not
Supportive use of the card catalog is a working technology to help people find books anymore
It's not
And most of the library in the world
Know that
And have moved on
He was right about the
Already at that point more than 90% of the nation's libraries
A computerized
Tarot card catalog
Earthquake itself allow the San Francisco Public Library to modernize their catalog
With the disaster relief money they were Gray
The library was able to get electronic catalog soft
So now logically
Delon wanted to get rid of the physical card catalog
Which the library has stopped
Stop dating in 1991
San Francisco's old card catalog was not moved
To the new library
It is locked up and in accessible to the public
But this move to get rid of the old card catalog
Cause of surprisingly intense out
Cry from the gorilla librarian
It wasn't just a matter of nostalgia or personal preference
Physical card catalog said exactly what was in the library before all the arbitrary weeding
If a book was red tagged and we did
It wouldn't be registered in the new digital system
It would be no record it ever existed
At all
Cancel the old card catalog was more than just
Card catalog
Card catalog is evidence
Evidence of a purge
To get to the card catalog
The Librarians pulled out their secret weapon
Nicholson Baker
I'm Nicholson Baker and I am a writer of
Books fiction nonfiction
And I became for a
Brief period of time
A library activist
Bigger is a writer of novels in essays
Celebrate the minutiae of daily life
Any 1994 Baker. National attention for a New Yorker article
Call about the disposal of physical card count
Has become increasingly common
How much upset Baker
A lot the San Francisco Public Library had a very ornate
Beautiful
Card catalog
That feeling that you have when your fingers would dance over the little cardboard
Pieces and and you could tell
A subject
That was popular because the tops
We're darker there's all sorts of
You know tricks to
We're just
The gorilla Librarians reached out to Baker for help
But now it was 1996
And the new library was nearing completion
The Lost Books
Evidence only by their locked away card catalog
We're teetering on the edge of disregard
In their email to Nicholson Baker the Librarians wrote
You are the only one
Can save it now
Part of me thought of goddesses
Just going to catch
Complicated
The time Baker was living just across the bay in Berkeley
So we made a formal request
To inspect
The card catalog
Can a felon deny that request
So Baker sued the library
For access
To the card catalog
Never Sue anything
If you can avoid it and don't Sue kleiber
This lawsuit took a while it was a bit of a mess
But it automatically classify the card catalog is a public document
Now the library had to keep
And then Baker and the gorilla librarian
Got to work
In secret
You know you can imagine this with
Kind of
Mission Impossible music on yes please
The gorilla librarian snuck into off-limits areas in the library
They took away books that were going to be destroyed
In other words
They stole them
The Gorillaz stockpiled hundreds and hundreds of library discards in their homes and their cars and their offices and
Lockers in boxes
All in the hope that they would someday be returned
Tool Library
Nicholson Baker stole books to
I was driving back and forth across the Bay Bridge
Car
Full of books that I had actually
Found in
This place that was the deselection room
Baker ignored the staff only sign
And walked right into the deselection room
The basement storage
All the places
It's where the sfpl restoring books
He picked up a bunch of books that had no match in the online catalog
Real treasure
They had stored all these you know
2017 Century very valuable books and stuff
Baker along with the historian
Begin comparing the online catalog to be physical
Car catalog
As a cross reference the two lists
It turned out
Got a lot of books
Books were missing
Way more than anyone had expect
Let me tell you what an opening-day celebration today
At last in April of 1996
The new main library opened its doors
With Panache
Nothing less than a parachute jump into Civic Center with the man holding the symbolic key to the new library
And weather in may of 1996
About a month after the library open
The gorilla Librarians organize an event
Anna Library Auditorium
Or Baker delivered a speech stating what he had found
Baker contended the Dowlen was responsible for a massive destruction of books
The systematic removal to a landfill that at least 200 thousand volumes
Set it right there in the library itself and
How to get really startled people
The phrase that got Baker the most attention was when he called this Mass disposal
A quote
Hate crime directed at the pass
This relate
Set Library management
Kind of minor dustup in san francisco
Where did began to spread that Baker was writing another story for the New Yorker
One specifically about this whole weeding to buy
So the president of the library commission road to the New Yorker zaditor at that
Attempted to kill the Peace by discrediting Baker
It didn't work
And Baker's article came out in October of 1996
It was called
The author versus the library
Current New Yorker article called it the Great Book Purge climbing more than 100,000 rare and one-of-a-kind book
Sprawled the job
And then things got a little out of hand
The library hit back
Condemning Baker
Accusing them of
Hate crime
I'm saying that he misunderstood the problem
They also tried to discredit him because of some bad Matthew have reported
It turns out
One of the Guerrilla Librarians had messed up the measurements
The old library shelves
In fact the new library
Had much more space for boy
Turn the old one
It was a very bad area was very embarrassing
Although it didn't change the fact of a library had taken so many books to the dump
Then both side started logging into
Tell tell each other
Has the local and national press piled on
One paper compared Baker to the Unabomber
It was basically an analog Twitter
I wasn't prepared to be part of it I didn't know that
I was
Getting into that
Times of battle
It was really ugly
And even from gorillas librarian Jason Gibbs a stamp
The whole Wheaton controversy got a little blown out of
Proportion
Probably was not as
Horrible is Nicholson Baker made it out but it was horrible enough
Meanwhile the new library itself had already been built
And it was judging from the influx of visitors
A success
The charges and counter-charges fly
Three times as many visitors stream for the doors of the new library
Indication that some book-lovers welcome the chain
Some of those books saved by the gorillas Librarians and boxes and lockers were transferred back into the collection
All the books and Jason Gibbs Department are in music made it back
He says that many of the other books did
They stayed gone
And many of them
Probably got the scar.
Nicholson Baker says he still has some of the Booksy stockpile
Given the painful experience of the controversy
The library wasn't really interested in resolving them
What is the end of the day
The controversy wasn't only about what to do with old books
It was a debate about what books are
Are they beautiful objects that week
Can smell and touch and collect
Or are they Eternal sources of knowledge accessible to everyone in The Ether
And it's both
In a given research Quest
You and I might want to
Find out what is in a book
In the fastest
Well nowadays it
It cements miraculous
Sometimes
You want
The words sometimes you want more than the words you want the words laid out on the page
Clearly Nicholson Baker can see dalian
Perspective
The baker maintains that we shouldn't give up on the printed page
His argument and the public battle around it in the 90s
Was a big reason why the San Francisco Public Library totally overhauled
Collections
They made it a policy
But if a library branch is considering weeding the last copy of some book
They must send a copy to a subject specialist
Who will decide if it can be weeded or not
And for the books to do have to go
The San Francisco Public Library develop the community redistribution program
To make sure the extra copies of popular book
Bugs can live on somewhere else
We
Distribute them to schools
City colleges in prisons
Strangely enough
One of the biggest changes to the modern practice of weeding
It's something that kind of down on himself
Help establish
Online communication
Between Library
Ideal World
You might want to have every book that we just
Don't have the Shelf space for every book so either you
Rely on somebody else's shelves to hold the book
Some Library spell musty with an i and an e at the end instead of a y
For misleading ugly superseded
Trivial irrelevant
Or elsewhere
Like if a copy of the book is at another Library nearby
Jason Gibbs at the sfpl and Sharon McKellar across the bay at the Oakland Public Library
Can now communicate with each other instantly
So they can share book space and make different volumes available to readers in both cities
And this has huge implications for what gets we did and why
In this respect
Kenneth Dallas
Was very right
He certainly
Failed in terms of managing the collection by the
Succeeded to the extent of
Bringing us
Set ceiling
Into the wider network of libraries online
And it's still because of Baker's 1996 lawsuit the San Francisco Public Library has kept the old card catalog
They're legally required to
The card catalog was a way of
Holding onto the memory
Of a quarter of a million books that they've gotten rid of
Those cabinets full of cards
Are still there in storage
Practically barricaded in by all kinds of other supplies but I'll go down and visit every now and then
Just to say hi
No just just to know it's there
After the Sweden debacle Nicholson Baker became even more vested in philosophies and practices of Arc
And went on to publish a book that touched on all this
Call double-fold
It looks at these event in the much broader context of the digitization of Libor
And this book is now commonly assigned in masters programs in library science
We read the Nicholson Baker book in library School
That Sharon McKellar again from the Oakland Public Library
She says that the debacle at the San Francisco Public Library
Has become a case study about weeding
Why we do we need and how we should we eat and
What could be done
How to do it well
What to avoid in all that kind of
And when it's done well with care and consideration
Waiting isn't so bad at all
For me reading is fun at the chance to really touch the books and
See how they're doing and see what people are interested in
That's what all this comes down to
It's what people are interested
Reading isn't just about what the cut
It's also about what to keep
It's about what the public wants to read
Your voice does matter and
We're maintaining a collection
For the public and for the people who use it
Until every time you check out a book from the library
Your Casanova
Your local librarian roving the stack
To keep this title in circulation
For everyone
To read
Coming up more radical librarian doing good in
This time
On horseback
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
The kitchen sisters are davia Nelson and nikki silva
2 audio documentary pioneers
Who are
Like the godmothers of the radiotopia collective
You can hear their stories regularly on NPR and we're lucky to have their podcast
The kitchen sisters present
On radiotopia
The current series are working on is called the keepers it's all about
The Guardians of history of The Eccentric individuals who take it upon themselves to protect the free flow of information and
Preserve some part of our cultural heritage
And when we were producing our story this week about the preservation of the sfpl book collections
I thought a lot about the kitchen Sister's Keeper
Brasseries in this story in particular I don't want to share it
This episode is called
The pack horse librarians
Of Eastern Kentucky
My name is Mary Ruth
Shooter theater
M97
Years old
Wait forever
Riding in the mountains
Kentucky
The children
Forest hybrid
It was one of them works
Roosevelt Roosevelt
That's Ruth
One of the last of the pack horse librarians
Today episode 2 in the Keepers series
Stories of activists archivists Rogue Librarians curators collectors and historians
The kitchen sisters present
Horse librarians
Eastern Kentucky
A problem is supposed to work 3 and 1/2 million and pliable
Men and women
Well now I'm really probe
In the depression that was horrible years after 1929
The Appalachians were
Chips so hard
Coal mines were being shut down lots of people in poverty
Eleanor Roosevelt
Decided to help create projects that would
Specifically benefit women and children
My name is Heather Hansen author of that book woman
Eleanor Roosevelt
Tell very strongly that the pack horse Library project
The pack horse Librarians mostly women Road circuits
Round 18 to 20
They followed animals have
I'm Kathy appell
The pack horse Librarians of Kentucky
Fake butt stuff their saddlebags for a pillowcase
With book
And strike out by horseback or mule
Library service for the remote areas of the Kentucky mountains
Going into the Appalachian Mountains of Kentucky with going back in time
No running water no electricity
Very few schools
Families with
The mountain
Creek bed
Greasy Creek
Change it to horses across
Web gear
Daenerys braids
You had to be
Hardy being able to clamber up the side of a mountain on a horse
You like to know the roads and Creek bed
My name is Eliza McGraw I wrote a story about the pack horse librarians
For the Smithsonian
One County would start a pack horse Library
Another County would hear about it
They would want one
Been that Community would ask the WPA2 let them hire carriers
Many of them were women between 25 and 35
There weren't people coming in from outside to
Take jobs from people who were in the community they were local women
Familiar with the people who wanted to read and what they might want to read
My grandmother she was a horseback librarian she was involved with the WPA because that was the word
Workforce of the time cuz Eastern Kentucky
I'm Rick Overby grandson of Grace
Call Lucas
She would ride that horse carriage Trails mud holes
I'm going back up into these flowers
She didn't own the horse she rented it for $0.50 a week
She will arrange the books and she would all around
Up200 not only books magazines of the time in the newspaper
Grace with a young mother with two small children
Her husband
Left
In the depression a lot of men that that
When I was two in the sister was about
Is Richard over
Chicago
Is she get up morning
At 4:30
So she got home last night
Caesars
Who is Shiva
Cereal lower next day
Dollar Days
She was glad that
Load groceries
Score
The only thing the federal government provided
Was the salary for the carriers
My name is Jean schmitzer
How often down cutshin Creek
Passports library of Eastern Kentucky
Lena Nasir one of the leaders in the Kentucky Library
Association
Really goes to bat
For this project
She started something called the penny fund
It asked for all of the state parent teacher Association
To donate a penny
Children donated pennies
One little school collected enough pennies to make a dollar and they sent the dollar in
Letting the depression it was hard for people to give up anything I mean even a penny Drive was taxing
As people from all over the United States learned about this they would donate
Cast off magazine used books
Swiss Family Robinson
Heidi
Better Homes and Gardens National Geographic Popular Mechanics
By 1937 they've gotten 60000 books
The librarian ragged magazine dilapidated books
Cannibalizing
Deconstructed remix scrapbooks
Jason Vance librarian Middle Tennessee State University
Library manual
WPA pack horse Library project
The following scrapbooks have been found useful recipes
Mountain ballads Kentucky history
Plaid names articles on a particular subject
Dog's teeth
Model airplanes
Carriers would collect
Recipes and patterns for quilts from people
Unwrapped put them together into a scrapbook and share County to County
E-40 2582 of the scrapbooks they were became part of the
The circulating collection
Dark Horse Librarians creating these cultural artifacts snapshots of life
Eastern Kentucky during Great Depression
They were so happy to get a book
We always say it under the belt
Chestnut tree
They didn't know how to read
Understanding
Kentucky in 1930 illiteracy in the Southeastern counties with anywhere from 19 to 31 per
Percent
Some people were originally little bit leery as a pack horse Librarians because reading was seen as part of a Leisure activity
When you're trying to get this load and work done on small farm
Somebody can't be sitting with their feet after eating
This is just
Frivolous there was a lot of illiteracy
The pack horse Librarians would sit in re2
People
At the houses
Mount back up and get going
They were really huffing at 2
Get done before dark
Grace without on a winter day and it started
To sleep
Ice falling out of the sky
Normally she might have stopped at one of the household along the way and spent the night that
The last house
Amherst circuit
Was a family that
She knew if she
Stay there
The time
Feed her and
Likely that would mean nothing for the kids
So she just pushed on
Before she could get home she had to cross a creek
The water was
High enough it covered her stirrups
Feet were encased in ice
Grace
Horse in English swim
Teresa Creech
Siri
Go to
The program ended in 1943
We're in the war or pulling out of this depression
The library program was no longer funded by the federal government the salaries for
Carriers but 1954 the state of Kentucky starts
A bookmobile
In Alaska there are bush
Librarians
In Africa there's camel
Librarians in Louisiana there were floating librarians
Polling flat boots in the Bios
Thailand
Horse-drawn in ermine rethink
Librarian says the quintessential Marian the librarian
Somebody who puts the books back on the Shelf Dustin
Make sure that everything's tidy
Librarian arfa determined Bunch they're far more subversive than that
The pack horse Librarians of Eastern Kentucky was produced by the kitchen sisters and mix
Bigeminy
You hear more from the Keepers series on their podcast
The kitchen sisters present
Zootopia
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Pierce Kelly and edited by Avery trufelman mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital thread
What's the team include senior editor at Delaney Hall
Joel Rosenberg Emmett Fitzgerald terremoto Vivien Leigh Sophia klatzker and me Roman Mars
Did not respond
You are various
Request for an interview on the Samsung
Public Library story
But a very special thanks to all the Librarians who help
On context
Good background especially
Shelly caulking & Mindy linetsky
Both from the same France
Stow Public Library thanks as well to Orrin Rogowski
We are protected 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
Radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member
Radiotopia
From PRI
The fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcast
Find a mall
And radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show in joints questions about the show on Facebook you can treated me at Roman Mars and the show at 9 p.m.
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But the full Archive of all things 99percentinvisible
99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com