This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
All over open right now people are wearing Warriors shirts
Find their Warriors flags on their cars
As much as we like our hometown team here at nine NPI we've been following these NBA finals
When you watch the games and Toronto the whole stadium is filled with people wearing red Raptors jerseys and t-shirts that say we did
North on them but every now and then
Easy little flashes of purple
Those bold fans
Wearing one of the most polarizing jerseys in sports history
The Jersey Messi did a whole episode about last year in honor of the Toronto Raptors and the beautifully ugly.
Jersey they gave the world
Booking rerun that episode for you today plus an update from our newest 99 PR team member Chris Berube
Who was raised and currently reside
Lights in the great North
He is very
Excited right now
Stay with us
On a March afternoon in 1996
Toronto Raptors a brand new team in the NBA at the time
Playing the Chicago Bulls
Jordan fadeaway jumper from the base
The Bulls were the best team in the league
And the Raptors
We're pretty terrible
36000 fan showed up that day
And the Raptors actually beat the Bulls
But it was a mostly meaningless game at the end of
Season this is reporter Whitney Jones
What's the weather is going to be about this game isn't who won or how the teams play
But the way they look
There's the Bulls were just classic NBA
I've had the same logo since 1966
They're wearing the red away jerseys that looks basically like every Chicago Bulls jersey ever
It's red with the word bull was written across the front and black and white lettering
It's simple
Classic
But then there's the Toronto Raptors the team is wearing their
White home uniforms which have Jagged silver and black Pinstripes as if they were cut by slashing
Raptor Claws and then across the whole front there's a giant red basketball playing Dinosaur
Who himself is wearing sneakers and a uniform a totally different uniform
And he dribbling a basketball
And that was just their home uniform
The real jerseys that you're even more fun
They were bright purple
All this including the Raptors name had been inspired by the Velociraptors in the wildly successful movie duress
Jurassic Park
But these jerseys got compared to a different
Much friendlier 90s dinosaur
That's now known as the Barney design because
Their Road uniforms purple
This is Paul Lucas
Uniform obsessive and writer of a column in ESPN called uni watch
It's it looks so cartoon Nations / 2
You look at it in
Like really that's a professional
Top-level
The Raptors jersey may have been particularly garish
But it wasn't the only Jersey of its kind
The 90s were this insane decade of NBA uniform design
Reduce some of the wildest jerseys that have ever graced a basketball court
Design the likes of which has never been seen before
And haven't been seen since
Like the Atlanta Hawks red and black Jersey with a fierce-looking hawk swooping in across the entire front of it
Holding a basketball and its little Talent
What are Milwaukee Bucks green uniform with a giant picture of a purple stag
Call Lucas called this one great
Hemingray in the sense that it was
So awful it was great
They had this you know this purple garish purple and green color patterns
Ridiculous butt
It definitely all these designs definitely
They push and extended
The idea of what a basketball uniform could be or should be
And many of these designs can be traced back to one man
I'm Tom O'Grady
I join the NBA 1990s League's first creative director
Tom group in Chicago
Sketching and rescheduling the logos of his hometown Chicago Blackhawks
Another classic Pro Hockey
Comes love for sports and eye-catching art
May this new NBA gig
Dream job
My first day at the NBA was just filled with excitement
I meant I'd always been a big sports fan
And I loved
Design and
I studied graphic design here Columbia College back in Chicago and so when I walked in the door and Junior 1990
I kind of had a pinch myself cuz I really didn't
Believe it was happening
Before Tom O'Grady join the League most NBA jerseys looks something like that classic Bulls jersey
It's simple two or three color schemes
With the team names across the front
There might have been strike here or there may be a cool font but that was about it
And they weren't designed by designers
The process of Designing team uniforms is mostly left up
The team equipment managers
Because they were responsible for getting
The players outfit
To play the games
Most of this consisted of the equipment manager
Flipping through a catalog
Choosing a design they like with the right color
It was not a sophisticated business let's say that
They were happy just to get Uniforms on the players back
But that was all about to change
Because in 1988
Charlotte Hornets introduce a radical new idea
The color teal
In this archival news footage from 1988
Hornets player Kelly tripucka stands on stage in front of flashing camera
Any rips off his teal tear-away warm-ups to reveal the Hornets new
Teal was not a traditional NBA jersey color
Not NBA red
It's not NBA blue it's not Celtics green it's not Lakers yellow
Tom O'Grady had nothing to do with a teal Hornets
But he took it as a sign that the league was ready for Boulder designs
It was I was at the kind of a leap of faith
Fiddly to say you know this is not really something we've seen before it but as an expansion team will probably let you have this one because
Maybe there's something that we can learn from
It turned out fans loved the teal Hornets Jersey
It look fresh
Indifferent
It was really very popular they
Soon became
Known as the men of teal and all sudden
The Charlotte Hornets have gained great recognition
Before they never played basketball game
When Tom O'Grady was hired as the NBA's first creative director two years later in 1990
He wanted to push Jersey design even further
Not just the colors
But the designs
On the uniforms
Until the early 90s there have been real limits to how Wild you could get with these design
Because all the details
The numbers the names and the logos
How to be sewn on
To do any kind of complicated graphics
Would have taken a massive amount of embroidery
And all that thread would have added additional weight
I made the Jersey hotter to wear
But soon after Tom O'Grady join the NBA he would get some new tools to work with
Computer programs like Photoshop and illustrator
Helped him dream up new logo design
And it was a new technique to get those drawings onto a Jersey
It was called dye sublimation
Sublimation changed every
Sublimation is a process of printing dye directly into the fabric
Now for the first time you could design something in Photoshop
You can make it big and you could add a bunch of different colors
Then with sublimation you can basically print that design straight onto the material
Without any embroidery or extra weight
So
It allowed us to start to take things
We would never normally even
Consider doing
On
A Jersey
And we started doing more
Outrageous uniforms and stuff because we could
We can so we will
Comes first big design was for the Phoenix Suns
We're celebrating our 25th year in the league
They were moving into a new Arena and they wanted a new look
Soto met with their team owner Jerry Colangelo
Jerry is great he was a fellow chicagoan so as soon as he heard my accent he's like
I think we're going to get along you know I think us your car guys kind of get this here's what I want to do
I want to have a logo that's going to last for the next 25 years I don't want to have to change it so I want something futuristic
The classic
So Tom and his team started on the Suns redesign
They come up with this big basketball that's
Also a son
Aziz long red to orange gradient sun rays coming off
And then they print this and a bright purple background under their New Jersey
It's not exactly what I would call Classic
But it is born
Definitely both
As luck would have it the Phoenix Suns made it to the NBA finals last year
And the whole country got to see that bright purple jersey
With its blazing basketball Sun
All over national TV
We got exposure that uniform that
Was
Priceless
That changed everything
For us we were able to do
Things with uniforms that we could not imagine even two years before that
Like a teal Detroit Pistons jersey with a flaming horse head logo or a Pinstripes Houston Rockets Jersey featuring
Cartoon rocket with an angry face on it
Over the course of the decade 2/3 of NBA teams got new uniforms
With new logos and new color scheme
There was a lot of teal and purple
3D lettering and oversized Graphics were everywhere
We look back on its a while to some of the stuff is pretty outlandish but
That's okay cuz that's what was happening at a time the technology let us go wild
Atoms boss NBA Commissioner David Stern
Gave him the freedom to keep pushing the designs further
He said you know if this is what selling any of your telling me this is what's going to
Work at retail
Count Me In
Before the 90s the NBA wasn't doing much with merchandise
If a fan wanted to buy a jersey they had to pay the full cost of a genuine stitched NBA game Jersey
Which was sometimes over $200
But with all these popular new design
Tom and others at the NBA got thinking
Why don't we
You know have a
A jersey that we can sell for about 45 to $50
That looks similar to the game Jersey
And we saw this business explode
Let me know when five years and went from a almost like
Baseline of nothing
A multi-million-dollar business largely in New Jersey
We were designing
The era of outlandish NBA uniforms Richards Apex in 1995
Wechat Jersey we talked about at the beginning
That one from Toronto
One that some people call the Barney design
We were told directly by the team owner at the time John bateau
I would like to Happy Meal box of uniform designs
We can't look at him pose like what did he mean by that
He said I'm not going to wear this uniform forever I don't you know kids don't eat out of Happy Meal box forever but if you going to get the kids
Insecure
Store
You're going to win him over
Happy Meal design isn't a term yet I'm making it one right now
The goal was to convince hockey loving kids in Toronto
That they should care about this new basketball
And so we created is purple uniform
What these Jagged Edge claw Pinstripes that look like a raptor, drip tip
And then I slapped a big dinosaur right in the middle of it
And they made it red
Because
Canada
You wanted red wraps up to represent Canada
Which made all the sense in the world
I don't know how much sense it made but that Jersey its soul
I think it was the top-selling expansion team logo we ever did even today
Sales were through the roof
Before they ever played a game
Before the team had even signed a single player
The Raptors were seventh in the league in merchandise
What is the nineties came to an end
Change was afoot
And stuff with about to get a lot more
Boring
By the early 2000 the NBA I become a booming Global in Des
And Wealthy business people were suddenly interested in team ownership
People like Howard Schultz who turns Starbucks into a multibillion-dollar business
In 2001 Schultz by the Seattle SuperSonics
And he came into the league with a whole laundry list of changes to make
He wanted to replace the hip-hop you'd here in the arena on Game Night
Jazz
He wanted his team to stick to the fundamentals
Best flashy dunks in showboating
The favored Team Bass
Basketball over individual Stars
Who's actually really bad for his team because it pissed off their actual Stars
Also Schultz
Hated the sonics 90s love
It had been designed by none other
Bernard Powelton
We were able to take this kind of basketball spinning around
Space Needle and kind of have the
Superman font
And then added for Sonics
In there and they change the colors from green and gold
The dark green red and a metallic bronze
Old Howard jazz instead of hip-hop Schultz
Was not a fan
So we hired Seattle design firm
Completely remake the sonics graphic identity
Jerzees warm ups
Logos
Everything
I was so damn excited
This is Andrew Wicklund
Who is the lead designer on the project
Hated
What
Sonic's look like at that time too and
A lot of other teams frankly that have been rebranded in the
90's show
Yeah it was it was
Can the candy store
The direction they were given was clear
Immediately go back to the old classic green and gold color scheme
And do something iconic
Howard's words
Where I want this to be something
That nobody would ever want to change I want it to be
The Chicago Cubs the New York Yankees the Green Bay Packers
Those are solid shapes simple shapes they are
Simple color palettes
Simplification
Is it strength
By the start of the 2001-2002 season
Everything was in place
Green and gold
No 3D anything
No giant logos across
The chest
Do uniforms look like an update or the ones that started wearing in the late 70
But if Howard Schultz was committed to making the sonics and iconic franchise with an iconic look
His commitment didn't last very long
In 2006 he sold the team
The new owners move the sonics
To Oklahoma City
But shelters aesthetic Vision Ripple throughout the league
Throughout the odds
One team after another
Slowly return to the old color scheme
And lost their big graphic
Jerseys
Even the Raptors look
Has completely changed
This year the two main jerseys were red and white
And they just say raptors on the front in the symbol font no crazy claw marks
No dinosaurs
And it's like I've seen better intramural jerseys
The college here is Tom O'Grady again
They're just there's nothing to them
Zero there lifeless
And I don't get it
Say what you will about Tom Brady's jersey
But they were not
Lifeless
Is designed are mostly gone from the NBA now
They live on blog posts listicles
A people's favorite jerseys from NBA history
Who are their least favorite
And their 2015 list of the ugliest basketball jerseys of all time
Sports Illustrated
Quote
The Toronto Raptors cartoon dinosaur logo is one of the worst in all of sports
Thankfully
It will soon be extinct
Baton doesn't mind when people call his designs garish
Or even ugly
He's proud of that Raptor
Jersey
It's meant to be provocative it was meant to be kind of eye-catching
We could have taken at start out with you know 72-point a vodka that says Toronto and a big number on the back and call it a
Add a butt
I think that would not have been a memorable Identity or no
A great way to introduce a new team
Athens for Newmarket
And if people are still talking about it
Then he did his job right
I'm fine with the criticism about people thinking it's the worst thing ever because
It certainly
Certainly says
We noticed that we have an opinion about it we have a strong opinion
We remember it and I think that's that's great
And the Raptors original plan to hook kids with the Happy Meal of NBA jersey
Love it or hate it
You could argue that it worked
Today Toronto has a loyal fanbase
Head over the past five years I've had some of the highest attendance numbers in the league
And as for those bold 90s jerseys
They haven't actually gone extinct
Turn out and tire companies that produce Retro Jerseys
And many of the designs, Grady and his team came up with
Are really popular
And one of the top sellers it's a bright purple jersey
For the jagged claw cut pinstripes
In a red dinosaur
Dribbling a basketball
The Toronto Raptors have won their way into the NBA finals and that Barney Jersey
Is more desirable than ever
Weather report from 99 VI editor and Canadian Chris Berube
After this
So I'm in the studio with Chris Berube
He's our resident Canadian of Special Projects editor and a long-suffering Raptors fan who's buried
Decided that the Raptors are in the finals
I genuinely can't believe this is happening. I have been a Raptors fan since I was 8 years old
And I'm in my early 30s so it has been
A great deal of sports-related suffering
What accounts for all that suffering to me why has it been so hard to be a fan of the Raptors
In the early days it was really tricky because
The team Camp Toronto nobody in Toronto
Cared about basketball over
Air hockey
In like the really early days actually played in a baseball stadium because
The basketball team wasn't ready yet so they set them up in this baseball stadium
And if you had like 15,000 fans like that's a good number of basketball fans
Baseball Stadium seats like 45000 people
So they just had these rows of empty seats with
Harps over the hump
When you go to the game it was
Is really hurting
Players just really did want
Play in Canada partly because of
You know stereotypes about
Too cold to know the taxes are high in Beeville Texas
Russell high in places like
California comparative Libra people didn't want to
Music Arabic
Very famously one player two
Just refused to come Alonzo Mourning was like traded
To the rafters
Keith head
Yeah you know what I've decided to do that somewhere else
Players kept having these like weird
Excuses for not being here like there is this guy Antonio Davis who played for the team
Said he was actually like worried
Is kids learning the metric system
There is this like
Fatalism to Raptor
It's like nobody wants to play here
It's
A place that
You know player is not seen is like a
Desirable location
4 player stand up
And then
You know we had
To wear this uniform in the really early days
With the Raptor on it and the bright purple and lots of players didn't like
Lots of players were saying like yeah this is
The only profession where like
You hit the very top of
Your field and then you have to
To wear a purple dinosaur
Unifour unless your field is being Barney the dinosaur that's the only other one
But it sounds like people kind of like that Jersey now right
It's true I think
People have really come around on it especially
With
Playoffs
Happening now so you know I've had all these friends who have been going up to
UPS out the door and all the dinosaurs stuff
For the most part is just completely sold out
And I went
To dispense it store actually
Fairly close to where I am called in vintage We Trust
It's run by this guy named Josh
Computer
Raptors merchandise forever Auntie is Toronto
Born and raised
Mission solar
Torontonians
We would say torontonians but you would say Toronto
Am I missing something what is the difference between
Yeah well torontonians if you hit that last t
That shows that you're not from here
People who are from your sake Toronto
OIC
I say
So it's the Toronto Raptors now the Toronto Raptors
Yeah if you want to sound credible the next two days you say that
So Josh and his partner Chantelle they run
Vintage store
And he says the last
She weeks he's been getting requests like every half hour
Some version of the purple dinosaur uniform from the early days
He's like everybody he knows
The dinosaur is a pretty ridiculous look
It almost makes no sense like
The actual logo
Is a
Dinosaur
Turn
Full dribbling a basketball one way
He's turning around the other way
And his toes are coming out of a pair of sneakers
Completely absurd and ridiculous
And not only is it like
A logo on hat as a fan
Players are wearing
Literally wearing this logo on their Jersey
It's insane
So everyone wants to bar New Jersey but also everyone
Terminologies that's a little bit silly so why do people like it now
Talking to Joshua came away with tooth
So the first is bad
The team is winning
And nobody wants to look like a bandwagon
So nobody wants to look like
They heard about the rules of basketball in the last two weeks
They just
Realized
This is something very fast with so everybody wants to make it seem like they've been there since
Beginning running
Look credible
A really obscure player like just told me he's been getting requests
People like Oliver Miller
To I had to look up I had no idea who that was shared about the feet forever so people are spending like all this money
To get these jerseys
Of players no Visa
The other thing is
Nostalgia
Brightness LG does not have to make sense it doesn't have to be something that is pretty or nice
And this is what Josh says vintage is all about it's about
What the logo Evoque
For people it's what time it sends you back to
When you look at that Raptors uniform when you look at that
A purple on the Jersey that is the diet
Reminds me of like Space Jam of like this gyro when there was so much
Billy Bass
Football stuff happening
Send you back to that time
The logo
Who is
Cartoonish and it
Very
Reminiscent of a specific
Era
And people love
Reliving
Parts of their lives
Tangible items
Things that they can touch you
Feel that's why
People are
Peeing out
To own it original
Because they're investing in their path
So obviously the Raptors are not wearing purple
Uniform for the night he's in the finals right now they're wearing their current uniform is
Pretty simple it's pretty clean it's like a white uniform
With the black
San serif fonts the word Raptors
Across the front
And then sometimes they wear
A red uniform with a white San serif
Raptors across the front and then room in this is where it gets
Very exciting
Davis third uniform
Which is black
With a white
San serif Raptors
It gets really exciting mix it up
But I have seen this one that's like it says North
Sonic
Describe that one for us
Yeah they call that the
City Jersey it's a red jersey it has like a white Chevron
So it's like this white arrow pointing up
And it says North on it I actually think that one's pretty stylish like I like that one
With all of them it's like
They're good design they're very clean
They're very simple and ultimately they're very safe
The current Raptors
Uniform
It doesn't
Have a lot of
It's kind of weird for me to look at a Raptors jersey with no purple
I didn't like you out of what you want to move away from the purple for a few years but like
Why isn't the dino Jersey
Being born as an alternate by
Like how crazy would a fan get
Food
Kawhi Leonard
Raptors
Dino Jersey
Would you imagine
Give the people what they want
At the timer recording this game five is just happened the series of still alive the Raptors have
12 chances
To make this happen so Kawhi Leonard I know you were an avid
Listener of of design podcast see if you can make this happen before the finals
Every so great if it showed up on the court
At Oracle
I mean oh my God
I would love it
Alright thank you Chris
Thank you Robin
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Whitney Jones and Emmett Fitzgerald with an assist from our new editor
Chris Berube
Mixing tea production by Sherif Youssef music by Sean real
Can you mingle is the senior producer of coal state is the digital director
The rest of Team includes senior editor Delaney Hall Avery trufelman
Turn Mazza Vivien Leigh Sofia klatzker Joe Rosenberg and me Roman Mars
We are projects 91.7 kalw in San Francisco is produced
Radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from TRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Lowe's in Avila podcasting
Fun mom. FM
You can buy the show into instructions about the show on Facebook you treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi or clone it
Instagram Tumblr and RedTube
You can tell us all about your favorite NBA jersey on our website is 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about your house
Another radiotopia show that you might like
Your hustle short stories about daily life inside San Quentin State Prison
From the perspective of those living it
Season 4 just launched after co-host earlonne Woods.
That's exciting news last fall this season will be a little different than the other three
Perception is replaced
Do everything
Filters through
The opening of the zoo
Summerlin Woods
I'm Nigel poor
And we are back
Season 4 of ear Hustle
MPR Exodus radio.
Owner Hustle
We bring you stories about what life is like inside San Quentin State Prison in Calif
Prisoners
Horrible
That will put the training
And forever and ever amen
And so all the white guys
Sing brother
How do I have a right
And this season we're doing something really different
We're also telling stories about life outside prison posting cost
So that people ask me what it was and how long after we're then why do I have it on in like damn
Seem like you locked up you still want to wear that how long ago to wear that outside stories inside stories
It all starts
Episode 1 of season 4 of ear hustle from PR X's radiotopia
Is back
You find your hustles 4th season on ear hustle SQ. Com
Or wherever you get your vodka