99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Trying to succinctly some of the character or purpose of any city in the world is probably a fruitless exercise
But for much of its history
Bonn Germany was
Particularly
The first word that comes to
And mine is
Wyatt
Unremarkable
A quiet town
Kind of hard to pin down Hills on one side the River on the other
Generally it's just a
Sleepy
Quiet
Quaint little
That's a ruse for of our
And he works for the German international broadcaster Deutsche welle
And he lives in pain
Bond has 300,000 people that's on the Rhine River so it was prodigiously important during World War II
It wasn't forgetting Beethoven was born there in 1770 but he took off in his early twenties for the burgeoning music
Capital of
Vienna
Not much happened in bond until the end of World War II
Bond was named as the provisional capital of West Germany
It became a city with a purpose
It was the government seat
And then
Half a century later
The country was reunified the Berlin Wall came down
Germany decided to move the capital away from Bond
And back
Tu Berlin
Now over a decade after its move
Bond
How to forge
Own identity
This is what cyruta street sounds like at 9 a.m. on a weekday
Yeah she lives in what was once the old diplomatic quarter of bond
Former home to many embassies and ambassador's residence
Pretty quiet it's
Be quiet
But it turns out that for newcomers like me
It's not immediately
Obvious where the embassies
Used to be
But according to Mikhail Dental
A local journalist who grew up in the neighborhood and wrote a book about bonds diplomatic history
There's one thing that you can look for in a clue you in as to where the embassies used to be
Flagstaff
With no flag
This house was a fraud example
English word
But today when you see a flag pole on my God
See a flagpole without flag that's 80% a sign for
Former m444 magazine
You have no other signs
Michelle explained to me that
Half a century before World War II
This part of bond was founded as a small summer Retreat for the wealthy
This specific
Part of bond is known as
Sadhguru
And this specific part of bad godesberg is
Call the feeling fear
The Village quarter
Don't closer to the Rhine Michelle pointed out the
Former British ambassador's residence
When the Union Jack was flying over this building you said there was a certain feeling about it
Union Jack Stars and Stripes feeling of
The end of World War II peace basically
Something important on the Ryan
American forces took bond in 1945 not long before the end of the war
After the war ended Germany was carved up into various the zones of occupation and bond was
Firmly in the British the zone
In 1949 who became the provisional capital of
Of West Germany
The choice was made mainly due to the advocacy of West Germany
Chancellor
Konrad Adenauer
He was a former mayor of cologne and a native of the area
But Bond was also an appealing choices the capital city because it was a small-town relatively intact
And it didn't really have a character
Choosing provision ality
Berlin was out of the question of course and Nazis had set up shop there
Before Frankford and homburg for the wrong choice because they were too big and would have felt too permanent
Bond
Was it clean
Slate
Little sweetie Bond was still the subject of some ridicule a 1986 Los Angeles Times article
Volleyball
Had a few good one line zingers about the city the minister of agriculture
The best thing about gone is the train to Munich former Chancellor Helmut Schmidt called Bond
A collection of crippled villages
He spend most weekends in his native homburg American correspondent based in bond said it was
Half the size of a Chicago Cemetery
Weiss's dad
But you shouldn't feel too bad for
It's crooked big is the cat
Tons of cash the City built
A Subway in International School
An opera house
All of this
In the city
Adjust around 300 thousand
Do people
But then
The Impossible
The Cold War ended
Germany reunified
The Berlin Wall came down
And
The German Parliament voted to move the capital
Back to Berlin
A June of 91 when the decision fails of to go to Berlin.
Call people
Beside each other
All the left All Things release to burn
Terrible
This moment
In other words everyone thought Bond would lose its Mojo at best
And at worst would become a ghost town
The parliament decided that by 90
Nearly all government minister
It would move back
Tu Berlin
And then of course included the embassy
Is all the action was now in Berlin
Today the former French Embassy in bought is the physical embodiment of all the fears that people had about what Bond would be
Do you like
Once the capital moved away
A ghost town
Is he this building in France
Frances old it looks terrible
Yeah it looks like there's graffiti there's broken glass there's there's a Vines growing everywhere
Image of this old French Embassy
See today they're like
30 foot high bushes in the front of the building there's broken glass in graffiti everywhere
You can see all this on Google Street View
And you might think that this would be the case
For all of the former Embassy
Susan Vaughn
But actually
What happened was
Somali embassy
She's got turned into
I'll just got sold internet
Private homes
Many actually still have empty
Flag poles out front
But the important thing
Is that Bond
Is not
A ghost town
It turns out that moving the capital to Berlin
I just be
The best thing
20 years later
CBC.
People's Choice in the newspapers Boomtown born this houses
The buildings were occupied by many countries about
E-40 50 years the countries left and the
Houses buildings offices became you owners on the first thing that the owners did was to
Renovate this house has its wonderful
Today what makes bonds
It for Lots
Two people including newly private
Major companies like Deutsche Post and Deutsche telekom
Is it all of that infrastructure that Bond looked into getting what it was the capital of West Germany the subway the international
That's what makes Bond such a nice place to live
And unlike the old and new capital of Berlin
Banhez
Had both
John and population growth over the last
And yours
Becoming the capital
For today Tacloban Zone Marathon article New York Times
Bond is no longer
A boring
It's now able to figure out what it wants to be
On its own
And maybe someday we'll even take down all those empty flagpole
Or how about this
Put up a flag
The city of bond has a nice flying to there's a strong lion and a cross
Tell her to call vexillologist
99% invisible was pretty sweet by ceruse farivar in Miramar
With support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
Sextant san francisco
Can the center of architecture and Design
But I'm or go to the website it's 99% invisible
. org
It's wonderful
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com