Hello beautiful nerds before we get started today I want to ask a favor of you 99percentinvisible is conducting our annual audience
Survey so we can learn a little bit more about you
Really love
Your feedback
Please take a few minutes to tell us a bit about yourself and share some things that you like about the show you can even share some things you don't like about the show
Just be gentle because
We do read all the comments
Goto survey nerds.com invisible
To take your survey today that serving art.com invisible
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Today Show is about something so tiny and unremarkable and ubiquitous
But I can't quite believe we're doing whole episode about it
It's sand
The tiny grains of eroded rock that we sculpt in the castles at the beach
Send my nuts like a topic worthy of our attention
Vince beiser wrote a whole book about sand is called
The world in a grain and I promise you it is fascinating
Is my conversation with Vince
All about sand
And how it transformed our civilization
You know when you were spending a few years on this I imagine you told someone you're working on a book about sand
What was the look on their face
And how did you explain to them to make them understand
How cool and important the subject is
So every single time I would get this looked at was just like
Like why my trap
You know why am I trapped in a conversation with this person who's about to you know who's so obsessed with the most boring
Thing on earth
And based my comeback was
Why would I write a book about what sounds like the most boring thing in the world
And the reason is because
Sand is actually the most important solid substance on Earth
It's the literal Foundation of modern civilization
Yeah
And so how do we use sand in our daily life
So basically
If you look around you
Right now I don't know where you are but chances are excellent no matter
What kind of building or office or room you're sitting in
Floor underneath you the walls around the ceiling overhead
The building you're sitting it is probably made at least partly out of
Concrete
Just like every shopping mall every apartment building every
Office tower everywhere in the world
From Beijing to Lagos is made out of
Concrete
And what is concrete
Concrete is nothing but Sand and Gravel
That's been stuck together
The roads that connect all those buildings
Also made out of sand there either
Concrete are there asphalt asphalt is also J
Sand that's been glued together
The windows in every one of those buildings are made of sand
Glass is nothing but sand that's been melted down
The Silicon chip
The power our computers or cell phones
Also made from Sand
Other words
Without sand
No modern
And here's the real kicker
We are starting to run
Possible if you feel like there is
So much sand in the world
There is a lot of sand in the world
It's actually the most abundant thing on the planet
But
We are also using
Way more of it than ever before in human history
We use more sand than any other natural resource in the world
Except for air and water
We're about 50 billion tons of the stuff every single year
Which is enough to cover the entire state of Calif
California
Why
Don't we just go to the Sahara and take all the saint there
Write great question
So there is a course
You know practically infinite amounts of sand in the desert
Problem is
That's and is pretty much useless to us
The reason is that desert sand
As a different shape that actual greens are shaped differently than the sand grains that you find at the bottom of rivers
Beaches
It's been eroded by wind rather than water over if you know thousands of millions of years
And as a result the greens are a lot
Rounder and smoother
And the crazy fun at the bottom of rivers
So the number one thing that we need sand
4 by far is concrete
And that desert sand just doesn't lock together
Format
Strong stable structure that you need for conch
If I could difference between
Trying to build something out of a stack of little marbles as opposed to a stack of little
It's all that desert sand pretty much
And so we have to get it
From
Water eroded sand that comes off of mountains and then accumulates in
Rivers and things like that that's that's the sound we need
Exactly
Exactly this is why I become such a problem because
You know when you're talking about extracting millions of tons of
Saint from
Bottom of a lake or the bottom up
River inevitably we are doing tremendous environmental damage
To get that sand
Ripping up riverbed stripping beaches bear stripping Lakebottom spare
Even picking it up out of the ocean
Cousin
Huge environmental damage all over the world
And in some places
Supplies have gotten so tight
Organized crime has actually moved into the industry that
Black Market in sand
So the demand for Sandi's Sewing Center
That is actually leading to
Global
Conflict it's true there is so much demand for sand that
In many places around the world people are being imprisoned
Tortured and murdered
By the hundreds
Oversand
And the violence is probably at its worst in India where they actually called in the sand Mafia
But it's
By no means the only place a lien keenyah in Indonesia and Gambia and many other places around the world
Same kind of thing people are are fighting and
Killing and dying over sand
Ma
And you've actually witnessed some of this
In India you witness
Some of the crime associated with
Cassandra
Yeah absolutely this is what got me started on it is I just
Stumbled across
An article about the murder of a farmer in India
And
What really caught my eye was that he had been killed over
Send
And you know that point I was like most people I never even
Thought about
Send my life and never given it a second thought Beyond like how am I going to get this sand out of my bathing suit
But then I do a little more research and found that special in Indian
Hundreds of people have been murdered over stand
In the last few years
And I just thought that was the
Craziest thing I've ever heard of like what what in the world would makes and so valuable so important
People jail for it
And what I discovered was
Did its sand is really the
Substance that we need to build cities out of
And in India as in most of the developing world right in China
Nigeria Indonesia you name it
We're building cities
At a rate and at a speed that has never happened before in human history
Means we need huge amount
Send
Weiser says that today massive amounts of sand are being moved around the world
The glass
Beer chips and asphalt
The years and has more
The little ground beneath us
Into a commodity that's mined and refined
And sold in a global Marketplace
And will Sanders the bases
I'm so many different products by far the biggest driver of a demand for sand
Is the production
Concrete
Yeah it's the story of concrete is complete
Completely fascinating to me I didn't know anything about it until I started the research for this book
You make concrete by taking sand and gravel and
Gluing them together with cement
And you can make cementing in a few different ways but basically
You take a substance like lime and you bake it down and it turns into a powder
And then when you mix that powder with water
I-84 misses paste
The clues together all that sand and aggregate but the real magic of it is
It does more than just hardened it actually forms a chemical bond between all those
The constituent parts
Like the grains of sand in the gravel in the cement
Which is why it's such a great Building Material rights
Really really strong it's really flexible
Anyway
There are at least a couple three ancient civilizations that
Somehow figured out how to do this the ancient Mayans
Use the form of concrete
Ancient Egyptians
Might have had a form of cement
But there was the Romans who really figured it out and they actually used concrete
And I really
Extensive way they build roads out of it they do
Aqueduct out of it
They build buildings out of there still standing today like the pantheon
In Rome
Has a concrete roof that's over 2000 years old and it
Still standing
So here's the really bizarre twist to the Romans
Figured out how to use concrete music
The great effect for centuries
But then when the Roman Empire collapse
The world should have
Forgot
How to make concrete like the secret of concrete making
Have disappeared with the Roman Empire
And nobody built
Anything with concrete for about 1500 years
Brookside now
I love the story because I feel like
It's the stroke that you seen a lot of Science Fiction and Fantasy that there's this ancient forgotten knowledge that holds the key to the Future
Is that a busy week never exist in the real world
Except
The story of concrete
Concrete is it amazing technology that gets completely forgotten for hundreds of years until the turn of the century
And then it re-emerges
In a big way
And what really made the big change
Was
An architect named Ernest Ransom
Was a British architect who had immigrated to the United States
Set up shop
In San Francisco
And he started tinkering around cement and with
Concrete
And
Figuring out different ways to
You're the perfect mix
And eventually
Literally threw tinkering in his backyard
He came up with the idea of reinforced concrete
Which is concrete with those steel bars
Running through it
And that is was
Ernest R and sounds great Innovation Paisley found the pie pudding
Steel bars
Inside the concrete to concrete woodbine's those bars
Edward
Massively increased
Tensile strength
Of the concrete
And you realized
Wow this is an incredible building material I can build the walls and the roofs of structures with this stuff
And it'll be cheap and it'll be strong and
Holy smokes this is the tale of the future
Darkness Ransom
So he ran around the country trying to sell people on this idea and basically people laughed at him
They're just like
Why the world
Would we even try this this crazy new building material
We build with stone we build with
Bricks we build with Timber
These things have been tried and trusted for centuries
Why on Earth would we
Take a chance on your wacky new idea
So he literally tries for years and years
Sell people on this idea and he gets a few commissions he manages to build a
You get a few buildings
Built out of concrete in a couple of different places
Two or three of them in San Francisco where he lives
So
Then comes 1906
The Sam great San Francisco earthquake
Massive earthquake demolishes most of the city followed by an enormous fire that basically Burns
San Francisco to the ground
But When the Smoke Clears
And the dust has settled
Some of the very few structures left standing in San Francisco are
Ernest Ransom
Reinforced
Concrete buildings
And that was a real Turning Point people all around the country and in fact all around the world
Look at that instead
Wow
That concrete stuff
I really works
You know it wouldn't make it withstood the fire
That stuff looks great
And in your book you talk about how
The new concrete industry that was developing really took advantage
Which of these images from the San Francisco fire in the concrete warehouses that survived his way to argue that
Like hey check out this
Amazing new
Fire safing
Earthquake proof material
Yeah absolutely
They push themselves you know to to builders to Engineers to the General Public
In a really big way advertising themselves really as you have the material of the future
And in fact
It is I mean concrete is an amazingly
Versatile and useful material
Very easy to work with
Cheap
And it's really strong as long as you build it correctly
But you can see it I mean I certify
Trawled through a lot of newspapers at the time
And he was almost like
Like their computers and digital technology in the 90s
It's the way that
Journalist writing about this
Amazing science has revolutionized our
Way of building Nevermore will we have to worry about fire like
You know as though concrete was going to solve every problem known to man it was really
People are just
Ecstatic over it and in fact
Thomas Edison
He was just in love with concrete
He thought concrete was going to be
You know it was not only going to be an important building material but they basically you could build anything out of concrete
He built several completely all concrete
Houses
At what she furnished with concrete furniture
Even though the concrete piano
50 Cent touring around the country
It doesn't allow architects
Quite inventive because if it
You know
Its ability to be shaped and all different kinds of way
Oh absolutely
Absolutely I mean you know
Look at things structures like
Like the guggenheimer
You know this the Sydney Opera House these incredibly fanciful
Annie's beautiful creations
You can make those things out of bricks
You know RR Stone
Yeah no concretas
Alien addition 2
To making it easy to to build really strong durable structures it makes
Is it possible
To build
Some of the most beautiful land and inventive
Structures in the world
Not to mention the most useful I mean
Things like
You know these enormous dams
That's really made possible the
The modern Southwest in a lot of ways
And we went through
In the Western World we went through our phase of a building a lot of concrete in the 20th century and now
There is a
Huge growth in cities in Asia and Africa
So is that where a lot of the Santa's going today
Yeah so we
I mean we're still building of course in the Western World we still use a lot of sand in a lot of concrete here
But it is absolutely dwarfed
The master we use in the western world is
Absolutely dwarfed by what's going on in the developing world
And the reason for that is number one there's more and more people in the world all the time right populations growing
And more and more than we're moving into cities all the time
Same thing to happen in this country a hundred years ago people left
Agricultural Countryside they left farming villages
And moved into cities
The same thing is happening in India and China
Oliver Africa but on a much bigger scale and how much
Faster rated a much more compressed
Time frame
So to give you an idea we're adding the equivalent to
Eight New York cities to the world
Every single
Here yeah
Here's another way to think about it
The amount of concrete that we use every single year
Is enough to build a wall
88 feet high is 88 feet wide right around the equator
Every year
And most of that is happening
In the developing world and more than anywhere else it's happening in China
China is
Far and Away the world's number one
Consumer of sand a concrete
Hundreds of Millions
The people in China
Have moved from the countryside into cities
In the last
Decade or two and remember of core cities are made of
Concrete
Into where is China sand coming from
Yasso
Famous Andy's you always want to get it from somewhere close to where you're going to actually use it because sand is very
Heavy
Cubic yard of sand weighs more than a ton
If you have to transport it more than a few miles the cost of it goes up very quickly
So basically
Builders in China and everywhere else are always looking for sand that's close by
So
Think about Shanghai for example Shanghai is one of these cities that is Jessica
Exploded
In the last 20 years
More skyscrapers have been built
In Shanghai
In the last 20 years
Then there are in all of New York City
So obviously they are using
Just a staggering amount of sand where's it all coming from
Well
Fur in the early
Part of this Century there getting most of it from the Yangtze River
They're just scooping it right off the bottom of the Yangtze River
And that caused a lot of problems number one it was causing Riverbanks to literally collapse
Apps right when you dig out the middle of the river
The sides of the river off and just collapsed taking with it
Agricultural land villages
You know it is snarls up shipping in a really terrible way
And also
Does serious damage to the river's ecosys
Emacs anything that was living on the bottom of the river
Obviously has gone their habitats just been destroyed
And also
That when you set up the water like that it blocks the sunlight from reaching plants that are growing underneath
The water
Huge damage
And the Chinese authorities realized this they were like well this is a serious problem for the Yangtze River which is
Probably important
Resource for China is the source of drinking water for hundreds of millions of people
Fish temperature
So
They had to ban
Buy sand mining on the Yangtze River
As a result
Sand miners just to push their operations
She doesn't miles Upstream
To the biggest freshwater lake in China
It's called Lake poyang
So lake poyang has now become the biggest
Sand mine
In the world
Spotify
230 odd million tons of sand are scooped out of the
Lake every year
And that now of course is starting to
Generate its own set of Environmental
Problem set Sun causing real damage
Two of the many many fish and and birds that live there including endangered species like freshwater porpoise
So basically where does China get its Ann from it gets it from wherever is Handy
And when you wrote that much pressure on whatever river or lake or whatever is Handy
It causes problems inevitable
I mean is this
A race to the bottom of weed
Going to run out of sand
So we're not going to
Completely run out of sand anytime in the foreseeable future we're not going to be fighting over the very last little
Pilot the last few grains on Earth
But what's happening with Sanders is much more like what's happening with oil and gas
Right there still a lot of it on the planet
But
The stuff that's easy to get at has been mostly Tapped Out
Stopped at stats
Close to the surface and chiba
And and easy to get our hands on
Is increasingly disappearing
And we're having to go further and further and do more and more damage
How to get the stuff
The same thing that you see happening with oil where we're having to do things like
Fracking
Offshore oil drilling
To get the oil that's left
Similar kind of thing is happening
Sad we're having to do
To dig deeper and deeper into more and more damage
To get at the dwindling
Supplies of sand
Beyond the damage that
You can inflict on the land by
Mining the sand
What is
The cost of concrete to the planet
Yashow concrete has some very significant costs number one
Is carbon emissions
So manufacturing cement
I is
Depending on how you measure either the second or the third biggest
Carbon dioxide is better greenhouse gas emitter
On the Platte
Did the energy that's required it takes up a lot of a lot of energy to
Incinerate all the
The line that you need to make cement number one and also the process
Self gives off a lot of gas
So it creates
Somewhere in the neighborhood of 10%
Of all greenhouse gases are created by
The cement industry
Course you need cement in Bangkok
So that's that's number one
Number two
Is that by covering so much ground
With concrete
You created a lot of places What's called the urban heat island effect
The sun's Heat
Gets soaked up and held by all that concrete
The temperature of cities can be raised by as much as
10 or 15 degrees
Just due to the fact that the concrete has is retaining all of that
And that's obviously a big problem in the world
It's getting harder all the time
Another fact
Impact it can have
Which is better can make
Flooding
Worse
Because
For the most part concrete is not
Poorest right at
Water flows over it
So
What princess what happened in
In the last
Set of floods in Houston
Is it made those floods worse because when those rivers rivers overflow their Banks all the water goes pouring into
Cities
And it has nowhere to go it just flows through the concrete streets of the Cities
So it can really exacerbate
Flooding I really
Serious way
Do we need to build with as much concrete as we do
No
Kitchen hutch Shelf
I mean listen we need concrete right this is not ring it's not analogous to oil
Right which is something that we can actually replace
What's something cleaner and more sustainable
What's solar and wind
Concrete is a great building at
It is created
Safe durable housing for
Billions of people the world over who didn't have it
20-30 years
That's pretty good
We need concrete we got to keep using it
But yeah we could use a lot less
How can we do that
Well
First of all by
Figuring out ways to restructure how we live
And said we don't need quite as much infrastructure cars being the most obvious
Also just by making things
Smaller I mean I just got back
I was just getting some talks about about my book
In the Netherlands
And
The size of the hotel rooms that I stayed in woodshock
Any hotels being American I mean they are
Tiny
There's room for a bed
A single bed
And a little desk
And a window
And a little sink
And that's it
Hi there I mean you can literally fit
Two or three of these rooms in the average Motel 6
You know it's kind of shocking when you first walk in or in that size but really like
Who cares I was in most of these towns for one night
I'd go in the ghetto
Do a little work on my computer go to sleep get up pack up and leave
I don't need more than
That's all I didn't need more than that amount of space
All the millions of hotel and motel rooms
In this country we could easily cut
Many of them in half
You know or
Houses I mean you know Americans famously we build
Cheyenne houses we love to have
Big huge sprawling
Tract houses in the size of the average American
Open Home by the way
Has nearly doubled
Justin the last
We don't need that much
You don't need
We can ease you know
Really
We can easily
Cut down
You know create a system of
Extra taxes or tax
Sentence for whatever
To encourage people to live
Smaller
And I
Cement we would be no less app
Are there other materials we could be using
Yes and that's the other thing
There is a lot of research going on around the world
To come up with other materials that we could use in concrete rather than
Since and so
There are people who are looking at using
Bamboo
Or shredded plastic
Or recycled tires shredded tires or hemp actually there's a thing
There's a product called hempcrete which
Actually buy right now
And all those things I think
Help I think they're all to the good I think they should all be
Encourage
But at the end of the day there's only so far we can go with with alternative
Materials because the like I said we use
50 billion tons
Sub sand and gravel every year
And even if we could replace
All that sand with you know
Bamboo
Where we going to come up with 50 billion tons of bamboo every year
Right that would create its own set of problems
Raid spray
I mean I think
The real way to think about
The sand
Crisis
Is too kind of referring to question the question isn't really
What's going to happen
When we run out of sand
And the question is
What's going to happen
When we run out of
Everything
We shouldn't just be thinking about like how can we
Solve the problem of sad because really
It sounds familiar right we know
That were using too much
Freshwater
We know that we're cutting down too many trees
We know we're harvesting too many fish out of the ocean
We know we're burning too much fossil fuel
Now come to find out where using too much sand
Welcome to My Mind these are not
Separate
Problems they're all
Symptoms of the same problem
Which is just that we're consuming
Too much
Write the way that we live
Here in the western world and that lifestyle that we have now
Exported to the rest of the world
It just consumed
Way too many natural resources
And the planets
Simplicam
Sustain it
Now
Where can I buy think we're going to hit that wall
With water
Sooner the word ahead with sand
But ultimately
It's the same problem which is just that
The way that we live our lives just isn't sustainable
We have got to find ways
To build our cities which is where most human beings now live
In ways that use
You are resource
That's the only way we're going to avoid total collapse
Vince Wiser's book is called the world in a grain
There's so much more to the story of Saint that we didn't even touch on here including
How glass change civilization
That's a big deal
So if you like this discussion
Joel of the book
There's a lot of sand locked up in all the concrete in the built world
But it's also a lot of embodied carbon
In concrete
How to quantify that
And concrete alternatives
After that
Concrete is the building Industries favorite material
But it's a problematic
Big save
And not only because of the global sand crisis
Has Vince beiser noted
Concrete is also extremely carbon-intensive
The production of cement
Which of the key ingredient in concrete
Is responsible for about 8% of the world CO2 emissions
In this section of program talking about the climate change impacts of the buildings we create
What is air made of concrete or wood or
Some novel material you've never even heard of
Did you do that I called Advocate synonym
I'm done and I'm an architect and structural engineer and faculty member at University of Washington
And my research has focused on the environmental impact of building the
When we think about the environmental impact of buildings most people really do think about the environmental impact of operating them
The energy cost of operating a building is stuff you probably know of energy that it takes the heat the building and cool the building and key
Keep the lights on
The Kate says that when we think about buildings and climate change that is not the full picture
There are also the emissions associated with the materials themselves
Emissions that were required to make all that concrete and steel and glass
The factories the steel mills the trucks that drive around all of those create emissions and those emissions are termed the embodied in
Emissions that are sort of embodied
In the materials although they're really the emissions that happened when making the
These emissions are known as embodied carbon the carbon emissions that were needed to create the built environment all
Around us
Kate heads up a carbon leadership Forum at the University of Washington
Is a group of Builders and designers and academics
Working to reduce embodied carbon
And she says that new materials and Greener manufacturing are important for the future
But the first thing we can do to reduce embodied carbon
It's just a
Keep using the buildings we've already built
If we can keep what we have
That's the first step to producing a body car
Wenzhou renovating buildings
Maintaining them
Isky
We've invested a lot in that concrete and
So
Let's make our choices
Is correctly when we
Choose to make new things and maintaining
But even so we know there's going to be a building boom in the coming decades we need to housing new green energy in purse
Construction new transportation and aldose structures are being made using traditional steel in concrete
Is going to be a problem for the climate
But Kate says there's a lot of potential low-carbon building materials out there these days including alternative conquer
And low carbon steel
Growing rocks
By capturing carbon from the atmosphere or at smokestacks
And turning it back into limestone
So that if we talk about carbon capture
Storage
Think about carbon capture and using
That carbon to build
Buildings with so we could take those rocks
Two buildings
That kind of carbon capture technology is a long way from becoming a reality
But when the most promising Green Building Materials that people are using right now is actually one of the oldest building materials on
On Earth
What
A wooden building stores carbon within it and so
If you can build with more wood instead of concrete you have the potential
To dramatically reduce the embodied carbon emissions
You could potentially even have a building that is a net carbon negative
And with that goal in mind
Architects and Engineers are developing large manufactured wood products that they call
Mass Timber
So Mass Timber is a term that defines
What buildings that are made out of large
Pieces of wood so massive
This is what
You make Master Timber products by layering sheets of wood on top of one another
And then compressing
Create extremely strong
Prefabricated wood panels that can be assembled into all kinds of structures
Architecture beginning to experiment with using mass Timber to build anything from skyscrapers to Bridges
And the advantage of mass Timber is that
The thick pieces of wood have an inherent fire resist
Characteristics
So it majan if you're trying to build a
Campfire
And you make it a little too small sticks they all burn up and you get a pile of Ash
But if you start with really big D
Pieces of wood
And then you fall asleep and Let the Fire Burn itself out you come back and you still have a log
In your fireplace
Buildings with a heavy Timber building at start of
Almost put
Itself out
I mean how
Skyscraper
Behaves
In fire is one thing
But it feels
I'm strange to think about skyscrapers made of wood at all
Not like in a modern age
Why is anything weird
Because we haven't heard of them if you went back a hundred fifty years nobody would have heard of a steel building
Wright cast iron so they were cast iron buildings in cast iron melted in
People were very concerned about it
So if you
If you look back
In time
There's been a massive Innovations about what we do
And if you look back in time there's been massively large tall wood buildings that have built-in last
To the long period of time
Sophie
We learn a trade
In a
That is handed down to us
I'm from other people so a lot of what we learn we've been told of work
So we have confidence two things
Because they've been done before
So
I don't think it's unreasonable to be
A little conservative
I mean we wouldn't want to build a high-rise building
And kills lots of
The people nor would we want to build a building that
Wasn't able to maintain over a long period of
My driver is climate change
My driver is
In order to
Have the building sector be part of
The climate solution we're going to have to take some
End
The risks will be trying novel materials new methods
Of using those
Materials
How to drive to a market where we have carbon-negative building
Cities full of carbon negative wooden skyscrapers is definitely
Attractive vision and Kate says that wooden buildings have the potential to be carbon negative
But it's not that straightforward
You to really analyze every aspect of the supply chain before you can make such a declaration
One of the most important things to consider is where that would is coming from
Because the forest
SBR NFA
To take wood out of the Forester change
Forest carbon balance
Turn order for would be a great building material for the climate
You have to make sure that it's being harvested sustainably
Incentivize wasting
Wood
And chopping down forests and not replanting
Kate simonin says that mass Timber isn't a perfect building material
There is no perfect building material
But building stuff always involve difficult choices and trade-offs
Skates goal to make sure that Architects and Builders are considering embodied carbon
When they make their decisions about what to build and how to build it
Because we're all going to be living
With the consequences
Body carbon is upfront
These are the emission
Is it happened when we build things
Now
We're going to be building a new New York every month
Until 2050
Across the world
Those emissions
Huge and if we don't figure out how to address them
We're not going to meet
Climate Target
The more and more people are recognizing that looking
Four strategies
To figure out how to
Reduce and drive the market
Low-carbon solution
99percentinvisible impact design coverage is funded in part by Autodesk
Autodesk supports the design and creation of innovative solutions to the world's most pressing social in it
Environmental challenges
Including Technologies to anticipate and respond to challenges facing the construction industry
Autodesk is a proud partner of EC3 the embodied carbon calculator for construction
EC3 is a free open-source tool to help design and construction professionals make climate-smart choices
About what materials to use in construction
Depending on how it was made
1 steel beam may have much lower and body carbon than another one that looks and performs the same
EC3 review embodied carbon of materials going into our buildings
Empowering Architects engineers and contractors to make informed choices
It's like in the materials that have the lowest environmental impact in providing transparency for more sustainable built environment
Tyler Moore and checkout dc34 yourself
You can visit building transparency.org
Go to Autodesk. Redshift.com to explore more
The future of making
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald
Music by genre
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Wrestle team include senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery trufelman Vivien Leigh Sophia ClassDojo Rosenberg and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in
Wallapop
Findmall
At radiotopia
You by the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can't wait to meet at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Instagram invited to
The concrete foundation 99 pi
Pi
. org
Radio timoun