This is 99% invisible
We are waist-deep in summer right now which is a great time of year
You're in the podcast business
Because
It's road trip season time to hop in the car
You of your favorite podcast
And hit
The road
That's pretty sure Vivian Lee and we recently sent her on a 1200 Mile Road Trip
Through the Midwest
They saw a lot of things along the way
Bob Dylan's childhood home a guitar made out of a bedpan the inside of about 400 boxes
The chicken McNuggets lots of horses
But we didn't send Vivian out to look for horses
Order check a few States offer bucket list
She was on a mission that require two equal parts science philosophy
And Dairy
In search of something that's been hotly contested four-decade
Gates
The world's largest
Ball of twine
I began my quest by following in the footsteps of the great Weird Al Yankovic
I heard about in Minnesota
About an hour away
Best of St Paul is a tiny little city called Darwin
It isn't the kind of place you'd expect to find a great Wonder of
The population is only about 3:50
I accidentally circled the entire downtown in about 2 minutes while looking for parking
The main street is only three blocks long
There's a bank
Water Tower and a 9-10 ball of twine entombed in a plexiglass gazebo
Hotels
World's largest ball of twine made by one man
It's very round
Very round and nicely shaped
It's hard to get a good look from the outside because of the reflection of the class
But once you press your face up against those windows
Will see this enormous
Perfectly round orb that's comprised of brown twine
The ball is the pride of Darwin
But before Courtney Johnson milk here
She had never even heard of
When I first
To the area I didn't know anything about the twine ball
Johnson's husband grew up in Darwin
So she asking
I was like what is this
And he's like
It's the twine ball and I kind of laughed at it be
Because
It is kind of silly if you think about it and he's like don't laugh because we're related to them
Courtney's husband is a distant nephew of France
Chris Johnson
The man who rolled the Darwin twine ball
Is she and her husband actually inherited the Johnson family farm
Which is where the story of great great uncle Francis and his giant ball of twine
Begins
I'd like to tell you that Francis Johnson had a vision of doing something Majestic
Rolling the largest ball of twine the country ever seen
But the truth is
He just had too much
Find lying around
Johnson was a farmer
And his farm like all Farms really
Lousy
Which wine
And one day in 1950
What cleaning up after his nephew Harlan
Johnson started rolling some of that extra 20
Into a ball
So he
Of course
Pick up the twine yelling at Harlan
That is just
Young and needs to start picking up after himself wall
Before you know it he had
You know it was 6 in twine ball
Well the 6-inch light bulb won't get into a foot
For reasons unknown even to himself
Johnson roll that ball of twine
The next
29 years
Between ball was easy enough to run its early stages
Johnson would work on it in the basement
But as it got bigger
She had to move the ball outside or it gets stuck down there for good
Here's an interview with Johnson from an early eighties TV show called real people
I had to roll it out of the basement
I can still get it through a 30 inch door and it's been Outdoors ever since
And it was Outdoors on his front lawn
They rolled it for 4 hours a day
Every single day
It became an addiction in on possession and it was something that he wanted
To do because it
Spark something inside of him
Princess Johnson was a perfect
And he was Adam
That is twine ball should be a perfectly round sphere
Has it got bigger he rolled it around the yard
To make sure he added 20 evenly
So it remained beautifully
Symmetry
Especially
The ball got so big that he couldn't roll it around his yard anymore with just his body weight
Johnson invented an ingenious method to rotate the volume using railroad Jack
A jack under the ball and use it to nudge the ball forward
And then the ball would roll
Intercourse on the other side of it he would have something to stop the ball from Rolling completely
He repeated this process over and over
Rolling a ball of twine rolling the ball
Adding more twine
Roll it around his yard change it to a tree so no one would steal twine ball at me who wouldst
Still trying Ball but that was the way he was
The ball attracted a lot of attention both in and out of Darwin it appeared on television that written about
Newspapers and Weird Al would eventually write a song about it
The ball had made Johnson's famous even if he wasn't willing to admit it
Well I don't know about that
About being famous
Alamar this little guy from Michigan
They got they got to take me to Cheyenne
Princesses toy ball was absolutely massive
It had to be the largest ball of twine in the world
So that's what he called it
Biggest ball of twine in the world
There's no one come forth with the bigger one
Until
Someone dead
I'm Linda clover
I live in cawker City Kansas
And I'm a caretaker of the world's largest ball of twine
Cawker city is about 500 miles south of Darwin
They too have a massive ball of twine
And it's Linda's job to look after it
The Wall Street Journal calls me the Bell
Of the wall
Bet a twosome
Local people I think I'm the crazy
Sweet wine lady
Cawker City population is a little larger than Darwin
But walking around you wouldn't guess it
It almost felt like an empty set of a western movie
And in some of the windows of the abandoned storefronts
There's twine ball inspired artwork
The Mona Lisa holding a twine ball
And what of Georgia o'keeffe's flowers with the twine ball at the center
We have things going on
But not match but that's okay
We have beautiful sunrises and sunsets
And
The wonderful Lake
They also have an absolutely gigantic toy ball sitting under an open-air gazebo right in the center of town
And unlike it
Counterpart in Darwin which is trapped behind glass
This one you can walk right up to InTouch
We want people to be able to smell it
Because twine has it
It sounds ragrets
It certainly does
Who's got a smell
Food smells moist
Linda Clover may be the caretaker of a Cocker City twine Ball but it was ruled by a man named Frank stauber
Stober started in 1953
Coincidentally right around the same time that Johnson was getting going up in Minnesota
Amazingly
Two men about the same time
One in Minnesota and one man from Kansas
Did twine balls
Sober was a farmer
That's like Francis Johnson and he got started rolling his ball of twine and basically the exact same way that Johnson.
He started it because he was cleaning up his
Barn and the man just was picking up
Which wine because it was on
Kiss Barn floor
Thinking he would roll it into a ball
Put it into a
Have to get it out of the way
Dover and Johnson were both raised with a depression-era reluctance to waste
Anything at all
Suppertime super may not have been the first person to try to roll the world's biggest twine ball
But he certainly had a talent for it
My 1956
6 to 3 years in
Stober's ball was already seven and a half feet tall
And weighed over 4000 pound
Nearly the size of the Darwin
Football
I think it starts with people
Maybe making fun of them because it's such a ludicrous thing but then
You quickly realize there's something about them that you know it's somebody who took
What should have been insignificant little pieces of
Twine or string or garbage
And they made something that's essentially made them immortal
This is Doug Kirby the co-founder of Roadside America
Which is a website dedicated to documenting the court
Cookies
Kitschy roadside attractions along our highways
The balls are pretty much a pilgrimage site for different groups now because you really can't go through
Minnesota Arkansas and not detour to see those walls
Herbie been tracking the status of the balls for a long time
And when I went to meet with him he even sketched out a little cartoon timeline for me
He says that for a stretch of time it looked like stober's ball in cawker City might have taken the lead
There's no record and we'd have our speculation on the website which was that pucker cities hit 11 feet and 8
By this point stober's ball have become
Popular attraction in Central Kansas
He would take it to local fairs and people would try to guess the weight
It was such a hit that town officials asked over
If you could bring the twine ball into the town to put it on permanent display
And then finally
After Decades of speculation
The world's largest ball of twine became official in
Pretty much the only way these sorts of things can
Yes it was in the Guinness Book of World Records
Officials from the Guinness Book of World Records
Kima cawker City Kansas in 1973
Declared stober's ball the official world's largest ball of twine at 11 ft
Diameter
Fortunately
Glory was short-lived
Because he died the following year and then
Meanwhile up in Darwin Minnesota
Johnson was still alive and kicking
And rolling
He kept going until he surpassed over his ball and Dethrone cawker City
For the Guinness World Record just a few years later
And without anyone left to challenge his place in history
Johnson retired
220 ball rolling
He died 10 years later
Promethazine
At the age of 85
It was a long disease
That didn't
Kill him and
We look at family history there's no history of it so a lot of people say is inhaling twine
In chemicals in all that throughout those years that probably was the reason of his death
It's family contends that Johnson's lifelong passion
Ultimately killed
Yeah but I don't think you change anything if someone were to tell him you know you're going to die from SUV looks old and you keep doing it
In the story could have ended there
With two dead twin men
Largest ball of twine in the world and the second largest ball of
Wine in the world
But
Cawker City wasn't finished yet
Stupid left the twine ball to the city after
He died
Infer few years it just sat there in the downtown gazebo
A tribute to the
The second greatest twine ball roller in history
But then the town decided
They didn't want to settle for second-best
We decided let's have some
Sean
And we started having
What we call our annual
Resident of cawker City decided to jump in and start adding more twine to the Stover ball to see if they could beat the
The record again
But this time it wouldn't be the product of one man
But an entire community
The town had what was a brilliant idea which was let's let the community keep rolling it
Here's Doug Kirby from Roadside America again
He says that cawker City started holding twine Athens once a year where everyone in town would gather to help grow the twine ball
And eventually
They started allowing visitors to wrap
The twine ball on a daily basis
Give me the ball
Became be reason to visit cawker City
What's the weather was townspeople
More visitors and let's just have it
The ball set up so that
All the schools ready you can add to the
The ball you'll see immediately that you're
Adding to this world records
So it's a
It's a different
If it's a different approach
When did Clover literally keep spools of twine on her at all times
On the off chance that she runs into someone
She wants to add to the ball
If you go to my car or my pickup
Either one has twine that I have ready to let
People add twine on to the ball
Anyone else in town
Carrie's twine with them
But Linda Clover does
So many people participating the cawker city ball continues to grow bigger and bigger
The latest estimate
How to get 20000
500 lb
Over 2500 lbs heavier than Johnson
And when you see it in person
It's unquestionably larger in circumference
But not everyone agrees that rolling 20 balls
Should be a group project
Especially in Darwin
Courtney says that Johnson's ball is particularly impressive not just because of its
Perfectly round shape
But because it was the soul accomplished
The one man
It needed to be done by him cuz it needed to be perfect and need to be solid
Needs to be done with only a certain type of twine
You know he was just so particular needed things done
By himself
And remember
Johnson had his own special technique for rolling a perfectly symmetrical sphere
People of cawker City
Don't have that
They have no way to wrap the top
In the bottom of the ball so it just keeps getting wider and wider
In fact
It's not really a ball anymore
Moreauville with a flat bottom
So
Cawker City Spa
Bigger
But the Darwin ball is definitely nicer to look at
Darwin
Is by far my favorite ball
This is Edward Meyer
And he's currently retired
But up until a year ago
He had probably
The coolest job I've ever heard of
My primary focus
What's the by Xzibit
Put in the museum
Ripley's calls Auditorium spelled o d d
Around the world
Where was vice president of exhibits in archives with Ripley's Believe It or Not
Wing it was literally his job to find the weirdest things in the world and put them on display
And back in the early 90s
Zion Darwin's giant twine ball
The Darwin ball
It's almost romantic as it's one man's dream and it takes him a long time
And he has certain Rules by and doesn't break
Getting silly I guess but now it's it's an accomplishment like climbing Everest
Meyer had been interested in the Darwin twine ball for years
And as luck would have it
Johnson's nephew
If you had inherited
His entire estate
Including
The twine ball
Johnson's nephew caldemeyer up one day to ask if you wanted to come to Darwin and possibly purchase the ball
He invited me and I said sure I'd love to come
Meyer was asked to pitch the town on the idea of putting Johnson's twine ball in a Ripley's Museum
Personally
He thought
What better way to honor Johnson's accomplishments
Going to put it on display or possibly thousands of
People of week would see it
I gave a presentation
But I wanted to buy
The reaction was all over our dead body
I was
Probably one of the most
Uncomfortable evenings in my entire life
I was literally in fear of my life
Not sure how this was going to end
Weather alert
He wasn't murdered by mob of angry townspeople
But they were pretty upset
For 1
The people of Darwin thought the
Twine ball
Could bring in Torres
Come to the area
The more important
The ball had become
Part of Darwin's identity
Slimeball is a good analogy with say it
The twine that binds represents
Do you know not only are we support that but
Support of each other
This is Josh Johnson
Send the mayor of Darwin
The town had adopted the ball is there around so much so
But they even started an annual tradition
Call Darwin twine ball day
Which includes a number of twine ball related activities like at Wind Cave which is
Kind of like a 5K
It starts out with
A 17400 400-foot run that's 70400 foot run to celebrate us
17400 pound twine ball
They pass out candy to kids
Roll miniature versions of the twine ball down the street and have a parade
He probably last round 35 minutes which is the right length for a parade these days in my opinion
Francis Johnson ball had become Central to life in Darwin
And that we made it clear that if Meijer wanted a giant twine ball for Ripley's
He would have to get it from some other town
And that's exactly
What Edward Meyer dad
Well I literally read it in an airplane magazine
At this guy in Texas
Had been inspired
As much by cawker city as he had been by a Darwin
As it turned out while Darwin and cawker city were battling it out in their public twine ball arms race
A third ball was rapidly growing in
Texas
The hands of a man named JC Payne
Paint was retired Brick Mason who was the type of guy
Who was always in search of a new project
And in the late 1980s
Hefei
Pain had read about the Battle of the balls in Darwin and cawker City
And have a clear favorite in the rain
From the beginning JCPenney did not want cawker City to beat Francis Johnson
Apparently pain was not a fan of the fact that the cawker City Community effort was about to beat Johnson solo Pro
Paine believed in the great man Theory
20 Barbara Lane
E-thot
You know that it was a shame the cawker city was going to be bigger than Darwin's cuz the whole town was involved in it
He thought that this was no I use the word cheating but that's my interpretation
And said y'all if Francis isn't going to be the world's biggest then I'm going to be
Can you start rolling his ball until 1987
Apple 37 years after
The by 1992 the Guinness Book of World Records declared it the largest ball in the world
In a few short years
He managed to create a ball that was 42 ft in circumference
13 ft tall and weighed six
Tons
Part of it is that he had a tool used
Technology to add the string to it he had a tractor he had a hook type
Implemented
Prevented him from getting his hands wrecked that he wasn't literally even touching it at some point
Part of it was the euro used whatever he could get in terms of string nylon specifically
Which bothered a lot of twine ball Pier is to like to think of
Twine anymore traditional
More natural scent
I seen the pile of
Is that plastic
You're Linda Clover from cawker City again
They're complaining were talking apples and oranges
You know complete
Something completely different
The main gripe about JC paintball
Was that he used artificial colored nylon twine
Well Johnson and Stover
Both used sisal twine
Sisal is an earthy color
Plant-based material
It has that classic
Whereas nylon just looks like City Slicker twice
Nylon also weighs less making paintball much lighter than both cawker City and Darwin
The end result was a multi colored artificial
Lighter weight
Monstrosity
And Edward Meyer from Ripley
Had to have a
My buying it was a backhanded
No I'll buy this because
You know I've missed out the one I really wanted but
I can still get one
So he flew to Valley View Texas to meet pain in person and see the ball for himself
Nice band salt of the earth
A little bit on the competitive side
But
Basic
Football when I first saw
Pretty darn good
But it didn't look good for long
Pretty soon they realize that they have to move this 6
Tongue ball Ripley's Museum being built
In Branson Missouri
Well we dragged it out of the barn and that messed it up a little bit and then we had to
Rain
Which messed it up more and then it was
Drop onto a flatbed tractor
Flattens
And then it was driven 3000 miles to Branson Missouri from Denton Texas
Build this misshapen monster of a ball was going to be the PS2 resistance
Of the new Ripley's Museum
And the ball was so huge that the building had to be constructed around it
If for any reason
They ever need to move it out of there
So either need to take the roof off
Or blast a hole in the wall
Oh wow
Yeah it's huge
I went to see pains twine ball for myself at the Ripley's in Branson
A person
It's a little Blobby looking
Like a ball of cookie dough that's been sitting out for
Too long
It's comprised of shiny nylon strands every color of the rainbow
Pretty impressive
But it's it's on display between an ornate miniature Palace carved out of camel bone
And a 6-foot ship made entirely of jade
Honestly
Those are so beautiful that
They make the ball look a little bit
Not to mention something else I noticed
So
I'm just noticing something right now which is that
On the sign it doesn't say the world's largest
20 wallet says world's largest string ball
So it's not even
Technically designated as twine
Here at Ripley's
In this
Might be why the Great American twine ball contest
Or string ball contest
Is never going to get a satisfying clear-cut winner
Because no one is ever going to agree on the rules of the contest
But at this point
All the contestants seem to be okay with the version of the story where everyone wins
Which town has the largest twine ball
Depending on what you mean by that
Darwin
Is the largest twine ball rolled by one man
Copper City
Is the largest ball of sisal twine
NGC pains is the largest nylon string ball
It's a three-way truce
Except
Hi
Is it okay if we come over
This is
Very impressive
Of course it is
Yep there's a fourth ball
And this one is in the Northwoods of Wisconsin
The man whose rolling it is named James Franco Terra
But he prefers to go by JF
I visited him at the end of my road trip
And
He doesn't talk a whole lot but he has handmade signs posted all over his property with the story of his ball
He writes that one night
And told him that he was going to stop drinking
Turn his life around
Become the world famous
Quiet Man
And that's more or less what he did
Is anybody help you with it at all
JFK's ball is a little different from the rest
Small segments of
Colorful twine and weaves and Tux the individual pieces into the ball
So the surface resemble the net
Don't do a lot harder for
Trying to reach the top
So the balls lot wider than
It almost looks like a modern art
Multicolored Funfetti but
Potato
Try to make it as loud as you can but it's hard
In JFK claims that his ball is the largest by using a
Different metric
Wait
23375 pounds
JFK thinks his ball is about 20 3375
Based on his calculations
Nearly 3000 pounds heavier than conquer City
He says he knows this because before adding twine to the ball
He puts it in the garbage bag
Waze it
And then adds the total to his overall measure by
If he's correct
Kiss is definitely
The heaviest
Of the 420 balls
But Gypsies not looking for official records
Doesn't need some Outsider to come in and tell him what he already believes
Have you heard of The Guinness Book of World Records
Are you interested in having them come to measure it at all
No no I do it myself
So you don't you don't really care about what they have to say
This is my this is just for you
So for now
A careful balance is intact
The four largest twine balls exist
Peacefully
Alongside with
Each content with their own version of superiority
Because there are so many ways to have the biggest ball of
Something
Like the largest ball of stamps in Boys Town Nebraska
Or the largest ball of VHF
Steven Kent
Where the world's largest disco ball in the UK
Let It Go video
What about the world's largest ball of paint
Indiana
It's time to come home
I talked to Vivian about other roadside attractions on her death-defying Midwestern tour
After this
So I'm back in the studio with Vivien Leigh and in addition to
Scene
Many many
Balls
When we were following a lot
We were deeply concerned about your
Your safety and well-being
I was actually very I was very concerned about my C
Taking over being at the same time
And it's not because it's wine it was
Because the weather
Apparently
If you're going to if you're going to plan a reporting trip
To a part of the country called Tornado Alley you should probably check
When tornado season is because I happen to be there during the peak of tornado season and there's the most
Tornado activity
11 or 12 or so
Yasso tornadoes where
We're Landing all around you
Don't open at all times and I was tracking the storm and being the exact opposite
Bill Paxton in the movie Twister
Track the storm and go as fast as I can the opposite direction
But it was a bummer because
I figured I've never been in this part of the
The country before so I can see I can make a list of all these
She said I wanted to
Cecile on the way
I'm so I really want to see the Frank Lloyd Wright
Gas station
In Minnesota
And
I want to see like the world's biggest banjo but I do
Cuz I was like rushing from place to place
But one of the places
That I really really wanted to say but just
Could not
Gets you in time
It was in Lucas Kansas and it's called the world's largest collection of the smallest versions
The worlds large
Sphinx
You said the worlds
Largest collection
Of the
Smallest versions of the world's largest chain
Understand everything you need is in the title has a lot of different types of roadside
Most popular in the biggest category is
World's largest
Things
Basically a collection of miniature eyes
Versions of all the world's larges
Just things
In the country so there's this probably about 400 in the
Fattest States
And
This woman named Erica Nelson has been basically traveling around
And making
Small versions of all the world's largest roadside attractions
And up she's an independent artist and educator in Lucas Kansas so I was so fascinated by this that I decide
Cited to call her and ask her a little bit about how it works
I go to a world's largest thing photographic Gatherings background story
Then I make a world smallest version
At world's largest thing and added to my collection
And since I've been doing this
For 15 years now
I now have the world's largest collection
Of those world's smallest versions of the world's largest
Goodness
Oh I like her
So why in the world did she start doing
So she would visit these roadside attractions
I'm in a lot of times they wouldn't
How to gift shop
Had to bring home a souvenir Sochi
She started
Making her own souvenirs
I'm in the form of these miniaturized version of these worlds
Just for herself and she just made her own thing
So now she has no over 200 miniatures
In her class
She still doing it so she still goes to world's largest things
And still makes me want to see
Awkward
But she has a process where she goes
All 400 like that's the that's the number of world's largest things inside of America
Fluctuates so there's always more popping up
And there's some that are just
Disappearing from lack of care or
Don't want to maintain them anymore
So Nelson Has
Like a special affinity for the world's largest things like these types of roses
But she's also fascinated with Roadside Attraction culture as a whole
And she was telling me that
You know if you look at it from a historical standpoint
You can see the ways in which infrastructure
And a push towards car culture have created this environment for roadside
Add fractions to really flourish
In that 1950s 1960s it was also not just our
Good roads policy
Des interconnectedness
That we suddenly felt
Witter automobiles
What's really salty
This is how you get your own personal freedom is by having this machine that can
Take you as far as you're willing to take it so all these little towns popped up in
In just the right distance to fuel up again or get water again
Use the bathroom again or asleep again
But then the interstate system kind of bypass everything and all these small towns.
Search become dependent on slow travel
We're being bypassed and I think those roadside attractions
Word that
Way to get people to
Stop again
The whiskey if you don't need to stop at town for gas
Or water or to use the bathroom
You have to create something
Gorditos the reason why. That's why you create
The world's largest Paul Bunyan statue cuz I just didn't pull people off the road
You normally just beat
Completely bypassed
I'm so it's just a way to take
Keep your economy
I'm kind of curious about this
World's largest phenomenon like is this just
An American thing that we like to make
The largest
Things are possible
Very distinctly
The world's largest ball of twine I don't think I could do anything
Go to Switzerland to get the worlds
Actually ask Nelson about this
And she says it's not
Specifically like an American thing but it's kind of like a new world
Country swing
I think part of that is that love of superlatives does seem not just an American
Something that is very young country kind of see
Because Australia and Canada also have that sort of need
To make a mark
Because we're kind of lacking in that old old old history of our built environment because everybody who
Here was much more in tune with nature and didn't make giant monuments
To themselves so once we
Started making our own history we realize we don't have much
So we started doing these
Superlative things
The kind of loudmouth show offi
Say hey we're here
This is
Look at our chicken
Look at it
Who is because we don't have something like that
The pantheon
We have
The world's largest frying pans or something like that
What I think I like most about
The world's largest
Question
Of the smallest versions
Of the world's largest things project isn't isn't just that it's
You know a catalog of the biggest things
It's
Also wait for Nelson to really explore the
Stories behind
You know The small-town Monuments that aren't traditionally valued from an
Academic standing
Right I mean I guess
There isn't the same sort of
Academic rigor applied to
Roadside attractions as there is other forms of vernacular architecture but there's no reason why
Yeah exactly
Nelson actually says that this
Attitude
Kind of ship
Lately
I think there's a growing number of people who are
Who are taking them seriously and I've had those
Debate since learning from Las Las Vegas
Just came out and ended up being such a tone for architects
They address that very thing is
When is when is Kitchen Bouquet
When is populous architecture okay
And so with that introduction into scholarly debate
People started
Looking at then again all of these things that they grown up around
The built environment and re-evaluating them in
The lenses that they were taught
To look at more serious
And we covered a lot of this stuff in it
Story Avery dad about Denise Scott Brown and Robert Venturi about
Gallery from Las Vegas
I mean this
Idea that
Yeah they became really advocates for the architecture of Las Vegas
That most people and even people like I performed in Las Vegas for the a conference and somebody wrote me
To say I can't believe we're doing it in Lost
Guess there is nothing of value
And I was like
It was a whole book about it
Around the stinking
You know in
In general
We should
Think about
What people go to
You know because
You know that's worth evaluating why they want to be in place
Lake Las Vegas I mean really does Tita
Yes exactly like that that demand is
There for a reason
Giant fiberglass pheasant
Or a twine ball might I mean yes it's silly and it comes off
It's too late but people are drawn to these stories
Stories behind them in the
People who made these objects
Because it tells you a lot about you know the region
And people live there
I mean since
They were a reaction
To the way that we travel
Embed we will be getting to bypass a lot of these towns
Kinecta came attractions for this reason
A Roadside Attraction continuing to evolve
As travel of all
It now and I I asked
I asked Nelson this question because you know we're not in like the rapid expansion
Face
Petoskey decades
We've been doing air travel and with climate change what kind of more aware of
Carbon footprints
And also this Wednesday
Okay
World
Largest
Ball of carbon
I asked her about this
Cuz I was kind of curious and
Still it's still a little bit of a question
I'm not sure yet I mean will there be a whole new set that surrounds Mass rail or
Artwork in airports has really exploded to artwork is happens in that controlled environment
Attractions don't really have an inlet there yet
Because they're
You're so control
Will there be a
A slow version in cities that
It's just Alleyway embellishments at the new roadside is the sidewalk
A little tiny thing
To the next Starbucks
I think that that's
Right on the money
I mean it just because like there's all these types of little artistic
Interventions in Urban Land
Landscapes and maybe they've always been there I don't know if 8
A function as attractions exactly but
They are about embedding art
In the world in that seems like that impulses there
Airport
Yeah I travel a lot these days
And Airport Rd
Exhibits at SFO and accept in the mural
At the Oakland Airport
R destiny
I love
And I look forward to seeing them
For a while there was like
Old board game
I'm just like a exhibit of old board game
Games in SFO
End
I would totally stopping at Museum
I would if it was like on the side of the road in Kansas I totally would
Go to the Old Port
That's great I'm glad you didn't I
I'm really glad I didn't die to thank you for saying
But one last thing
About the world's largest
Version
I don't think I could do this
Worlds
Largest collection
Of the Worlds
Smallest version
What's the world's largest things
Is that they have a theme song
I would love to
Don't let's do it will go out on this
Thank you so much babe
The world's largest
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Vivian Leigh
Edited by Emmett Fitzgerald
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Kitty mingle is our senior producer critical stage the digital
Director
The rest of the team is Avery truffle
Joe Rosenberg Delaney Hall Sofia klatzker and me Roman Mars
Very special thanks
To Josh Johnson
John Dixon from Ripley's Believe It or Not in Branson Missouri
Grace Lee
Pictures of Andrew zilch for tipping us off in that store
You can find out more about the world's largest collection of the world's smallest versions of the world's largest things on
Facebook or by going to world's largest things
.com
The world's largest things theme song is by bomb
Big one man band
Which of the project of artist Bruce Humphrey
We are project at 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
In
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
This was a member of radiotopia from PR except fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of
Podcasting fun Mall
At radiotopia. FM
Discussed about the show on Facebook and pretty meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi or Quan Instagram
Graham and read it to
But we got big pictures of giant balls at night IPI
. org
Can I do it
Required
Wake me up make me made it
I think we deserve it
We burn dead people we buy our debt
Radio 2