This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Today Show is about a design flaw that might be and I'm not exaggerating here
The single most common design flaw in human history
If potentially effects
Everything we have ever built
Its consequences are felt by more than half of people worldwide
Most people
Don't even notice it
But that's changing
Thanks in no small part
The work
Of one woman
My name is Caroline criado-perez
I am a writer and activist
Who is written an Incredible Book
Invisible women exposing de Tobias
No wait sorry that's the question
What is the Americans
The copy I have is called invisible women
Data bias in the world design for men
British people sweat
American people
Is this a non swery podcast
Well you can swear all you like we will probably bleep it
I'll try to I'll try to keep it to a minimum
And honestly Caroline criado-perez has a good reason to swear
Because this design flaw in addition to being everywhere
Is really
But like so many of the worst design flaws
It can be hard to notice
The first to demonstrate just how hard
Caroline start off by telling me a story
That begins
With a joke
About gender
Basically
In this
Town kukulska. In Sweden
They were doing a gender analysis
List of all the policies
No tearing when having a feast
Agenda
And it does sound on the face of it ridiculous how can snakes have anything to do with gender
After all the city of karlskoga plaudit streets the way you think all cities with Father's tree
Starting with the major arteries
Followed by local roads in Cypress
It seemed about as genderless as you could get
But actually it turned out
It's gender
Because
Male and female travel passes
Men are far more likely to travel in a fairly simple way using a car
For a twice daily commute in and out of the city center
You can see this in the way that most cities are laid out with major arteries going in and out of downtown and what's
An arterial cyst
Which makes a lot of sense if you are a man
It turns out
The weight many women
Is very
Women puppies more complicated travel packs
Say for example
Typical travel
Some groceries on the way home on an elderly relative
Public transport
DirecTV
Commercial air
When karlskoga snow plowing schedule was first designed all this trip chaining done by women
Simply wasn't factored in
Because it wasn't considered work
But actually this would contribute
Hugely
GDP
They discovered
That if you put all the unpaid carrot travel together at 10
Travel for those purposes
With almost as much as travel for paid work
Becomes a totally different proposition
What's the city planners started looking at the data through the lens of gender
Suddenly the idea
The city of karlskoga Sweden
Should plow its major arteries first
Didn't make intuitive sense
Because really really great for getting in and out of downtown
But it's not very good for traveling Between Difference
Some pups
Which is the kind of travel of the women are much more like to eat
To do
So the city council of karlskoga realizing that it's harder to push a buggy through 3 inches of snow than it is to drive a car
Decided to flip their snow clearing policy on its head
From now on it would be the miners
Streets and sidewalks
Rocks that were plowed first
Followed by the major artery
Expected it would actually save the money
Because it turned out that
Dramatic Kira Gees
The admissions into accident animations
Because they were right
Is much easier to drive a car
Events push a buggy
And pedestrians with massively dominating admission syntax
Accident and emergency
And women
With dominating
I'm sorry bites
The simple thing is
Changing the order in which they play at the
They had this traumatic
Effects
Healthcare bill
That was not an insignificant cost
Analysis
It was
3 *
The cost of the winter
What the point of the story isn't that karlskoga saved money
Or even that women suffer fewer injuries
It's that the snow cleaning policy
I've been poorly designed even though
City planners at started out
With the best of intentions
You know it's not like to travel, so I know you're let's make women full over in fracture that pelvis
That'll be really funny
Faith just
Proceed
Along the presumption that what would work for them
Would just wax it Society
And when the schedule with device
But they forgot
As happens so often in
I'm to remember that women exist
And this goes all the way back to
The fact that you know this isn't just
Transport
Infrastructure
This is pretty much everything
Today I'm talking with Caroline criado-perez about the largest and most persistent data Gap in history
The failure to collect data on in from women when designing
Almost
And the consequences of
Not just for women
But for everyone
So you talked about this a lot in your book
Which is that
At the root
I've almost
Aldi's design problems
Which don't seem to take women to
Is the fallacy of the default mail Daddy and that when we picture a kind of
Default human
When we design something
Whether we clicked it or not
We picture a cyst man
Were there times in your research
Were you discovered
That you yourself for me
Default mail or something
Absolutely
I mean that's kind of how I got into feminism in the first place
I was realizing that I had this male default in my head
But whenever I pictured
Anyone
And the gender versus pasta
Fidos picturing a man so you never Loya a doctor
Journalist
A scientist
Anyone
Show me picturing men and that was really shocking to me because no tiny
Capital to the fact that I hadn't noticed I was doing it
Because it is really shocking how would I know tonight if I'm a woman how would I know
How to say picture in the opposite sex
And so we really are so used to seeing men as
The default
That
Most people on to wear
That they are ignoring women
Bets for people who are developing
Text people who are developing Place policy
People are developing medical research
I wrote this book
Because
People collecting sex disaggregated
Really serious negative
Potentially fatal
Results for women
What you mention medical research how is the
Absence of women in data Gathering effects
Medicine
The vast majority
Of medical research and that's with vast majority of
Knowledge we have is based on the male body
So true so true
Diseases
The way we
Have her sets them the way we treat them
The way we diagnose them as being based on reception men
Women get misdiagnosed
Play free sample heart attack
Women more likely to die following a heart attack
The men
I'm not for a whole host of reasons faster which is that
Female heart attack symptoms
Not
The horse tack symptoms that we have always been to it
They sent me I had always been taught that I was having chest pain and pain down my left arm
I was having a heart attack
Actually
Those are not the typical heart attack symptoms for women
Experience
Nausea fatigue what feels like indigestion
Answer women realize having off
So then I go to the doctor
But even if the Jeep
Doctors don't realize that women having a hot shower
Female heart attack symptoms are seen as a tip
Even though they are very typical for women symptoms
Difficult women
Experience chest
But we just
Because of this way that we see men as the default
Male horse like symptoms STD
And female hashtags
Symptoms of CNS
This kind of Niche variant
I was just as stunning because if there was some kind of
Thing that affected
You'll 51% of the population
We wouldn't think that that is a nice problem
We do in all sorts of areas I mean another area that Springs to mind is call crashes
So
The car crash test dummy that is being used
Used for decades
EMT test cost
Itching based on a 50th percentile male
Perform male buddies in all sorts of ways I mean we have few neck muscles we have less upper body
Muscle mass
Spinal columns a different pelvises differ
NASA visa rules
Issues that need to
To be taken into account but
We got this 50th percentile male dummy
As of course the 50th percentile male is the 50th percentile human
What is quite
Enraging rainy is it
This was introduced in the 1950s
About having a female
But as happens so often, manufacturers Lovett against
On the basis that it would be to expense
And presumably it doesn't just affect
Bus safety
They are weak like it that affects the design of the car
Exactly
The result is that
Costas
So for example the seat belt
Hasn't been designed to accommodate women's breasts
We haven't developed a seatbelt that account
Pregnant
Similarly
Women need to sit much for the forge
Reach the pedals of a sequin impulse Apartments Drive
What's the standard seating position
In a frontal Collision
Alta Vista means that women are 47% more likely
Need to be seriously injured
I'm 17% more likely to die than a man
If I rent a car crash
Answer
That is negligence but I think it gets even worse because it'd have belatedly
Regulations of realize that women do exist
Bus realized women exist
2015 the EU realized women existed
You mean they finally introduce ya
Spider-Man
Because the car crash test dummy that they are using is not
Anthropometric plea correct
It's a scaled-down male dummy
Even worse
But not this
Is there any used in one out of the five regular
Journey in the passenger seat
You can say based on those tests is that we have Deja on whether it's safe or not to scale down men
And sit in the passenger seat
Malia Jones station on whether it's a factual
Undertaker tool
What it's like for someone who might be slightly similar to a woman to drive
Things like snow plowing and medical protocols and car safety are just a few instances where there is a crib
Medical data cap
Either because
There is no data on women or the date of that exists
Is not sex
Even something as innocuous as the width
A piano key
Has been designed only with male hand sizes in mind
The military's across the world marching regulations have been designed based solely on the average male stride
With Disaster
Results for female recruits
Construction tools safety equipment building codes smartphones voice recognition software all of it
It designed using a corpus of data
In which women largely do not exist
Back after the break
We'll look at another example that might just provide a blueprint
Try to do things better in the future
I've been talking to Caroline criado-perez about her book invisible women and
Of all the story is a poor design based on the gender data Gap that Caroline told me
Perhaps the most instructive was the case of the three stone stove
Three stone stove is a traditional form of cooking
That's used by 80%
People in the developing world
It is what it sounds like
Three Stones arranged in a circle on the ground
With a pot placed on top of
In a fire underneath
And the problem with
This type of stove is that
The fumes that are given off are incredibly tok
And it's not just that the fumes are really toxic it's how long women and children are exposed to
3 * 10 * 5 is
Not very efficient
So they will be
In a poorly ventilated room
Two I think one estimate with something
The equivalent of more than a hundred cigarettes
Today
And this seems like something like we've had
Stoves and ovens for quite a long time why wasn't this fixed
A long time ago did we even try
Yes sir
The happiness hack
Spy agencies to develop
Is clean start
To be cops
But we still have the big problem that is incredible
Simple it's that
The album design
And asking them
What they need
What they want
How are they liking
The Current Designs
The issues I mean that's hilariously basic
They keep developing stoves
That for example
Increase cooking time
Are women already cooking for
How to spend cooking
They often require
Atmore tending and again
When you having to spend so long cooking
You need to be able to multitask
This isn't something that is being
Xidan
Clean
Start with develop
They require
Accession amount
The design is just assumed I will the household will take care of that
But actually
Maintenance
With a mom's job
An amendment
He starves because they so well why do I need to know she can just cook them the old style.
I want to waste my time
Another one was similar issue
Stop
Start with cheese small to just put
Bits of wooden
You have to chop it up again
What is job
Didn't get to use fees
These all these really really simple things that should have been cool at the design stage if
What do you need and they would have said
But we need something.
Means that we don't have to spend more time cooking that weakened the cop truck hits while we're doing it
We don't need mental help Swiss because they bite
Programas de program so yeah I'll see ya his failed
So these really really face it
How many years are we talking about
An enzyme
Is that
Often reports that produce the basic he say that it's the woman's fault
The women unwilling to learn how to use the
The stove so the women are choosing to cook in these dangerous toxic fumes
Radius just insulting
Yeah I mean it in a 10 minutes remind me to buy call this language in the crash tests
You know that that women are the out-of-position drivers
And
You know it really does like there's a moment
Where
Designers in
People studying this
Finally see women in that is
Trying to find someone to blame
Yeah I mean
I student connect this
This position of will they must be something wrong with the women we go to fix the women
That is actually something that we
Apply to Mac
I think it becomes my
It's clear when you are looking at things
Place initiative
You know the ideas are what we need to build up women's comfort
Enough said that's why they
Getting from
Choosing a subject
And yet study after study has shown that she has pretty good at
Assassin
That Bass kill their intelligence
Estimate
Basculin
Intelligence
And so when you see that then you should have
Maybe it's not that the women write themselves
She likes the men raising themselves
I was too high
It just
We just never think of it like that
The mail is sativa
It's a symbol that must be the right level
So we got to fix
What's the weather
Did anyone bother to design a stove based primarily on the input
Of women and if so what what did they create
Have a happy ending
Say
Yeah a few years ago receptions in India
Instead of trying to create a holster
Fake creation
This device that you can put on any
And basically it comes
Woody's
And cuts
Smite
Too comfortable levels
Very very cheap
It's used with recycled
Metal material
And it's being picked up
Not just in India
You know they're being studies in Kenya and Ghana
With the same device
With similarly puzzle
Results
Menorah.
And basically
Went
Revolutionary
Say what these receptions did that was different was they started off in the basis of what do women actually need
What do you want
Provide that
And say the reception went awesome
What is the issue
Coming in from above and saying
You women
You're very silly of naughty
Doofus
I mean when I when I read your blog
Both
Satisfying and enraging about it is that
The solution is pretty simple
It's just
Talk to women gather data
And think of that while you're making things or include women in the process the whole time
Do you find yourself
Hopeful
Dispirited angry
Incredibly pissed off
Turn off
Is
And I'm particularly when it comes to areas that perception
But there was a problem
What's the most shocking thing you found
Because they're all so many shocking things
Because there are so many shocking things
Sensitive numb to it
Women of dying from heart attacks women of dying from unclean cookstoves
Oscar Wilde it's not the examples
It's the excuse
That make you really angry
To this day I have had
Notes
Entirely friendly exchanges on Twitter
Test on women because they have.
Complicate
Results
Yeah
I'm not switching raging because
They must know
But yes
.
De'aaron Fox
What you need to know
2019 and I have medical researches
You're trying Vol. Sandman and if we find anything in
Interesting them will include women
Which again
Is positioning malice
Default
And I suppose one of the things that
Makes me moist
Angry
Is
Think about how many drugs for women have we missed out on
Because they didn't recommend when we started testing
Deep do you see the
The end of excuses are like is this
I mean are we reaching an end where you can no longer
Have these excuses or is it still just as bad as ever
Not reaching an end
I am not trying to make you have a
Got a good view of this at all
Is ice crusher your I share your pessimism
I tell you what you mean you are sweet
How do I feel right in the back
I felt
Absolutely
Despondent
Since the biggest come out I have felt more
And that has been because the response has been actually quite incredible
Women
The main response
And reaction has just being one of relief
Wow the world suddenly makes sense
I've realized there isn't something wrong with me
I just
Have a body that
Hasn't been
Factored into the design of pretty much anything
Paternal side for men
I've had
So many men get in touch
Telling me about how they are changing the procedure and how they are changing the procedure and how
Designing
Incorporation what they have
Read in the book into the way that they
Projects that they are involved in
So if you were to
Describe a solution
You know to make this better
What are beans
Let's go for the winter
Sex disaggregated
And that she has an amazing thing that happens
Yesterday
And I think this is
Biggest win today
With the Scottish government
Have
Started a working group
On collecting
Sex and gender decipher dates
Fascia
As a result the book
And that was
I mean that's just amazing
I admit they are they are great and I'm going to have to move that time because when we brexit
Scotland Safe Haven
Caroline criado-perez book is called invisible women data bias in a world design firm and it's available
Wherever books are sold in a highly recommend you go out and buy a copy because it's filled with
Hundreds of other examples of dendur De Tobias
I will have you questioning the default system and design assumptions of the world around you
Illuminating and
Infuriating and inspiring all at the same time
99percentinvisible impact design coverage is supported by Autodesk
Autodesk supports the design and creation of innovative solutions to the world's most pressing social and environmental
Mental challenges
Autodesk Foundation is a proud partner of 60 decibels
60 decibels makes it easy to listen to the people who matter most
Their lean data approach turns customer voice into high-value insights that help businesses grow and Mex
They Leverage The Power of technology to communicate directly with marginalized communities
Collecting high quality impact data efficiently
A fraction of the time of traditional approaches
That means businesses providing everything from off-grid Energy Solutions to Family Health Services
Can better understand their customers
Adapt to their needs
And do more good
Claremore at 60 decibels, or go to autodesk.com
Redshift
To explore more on the future of making
99percentinvisible which produces sweet by Joel Rosenberg
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
The Russell team is Emmett Fitzgerald senior editor Delaney Hall
Treat yourself
Avery trufelman Vivian Lee Sofia klatzker and me Roman Mars
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia
CPR except the independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of podcasting
By the mall
Ed radiotopia. FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram and read it to
If you want to comment on your least favorite examples of gender bias in design
You can do that
At 9 RPM
. org
Radio 2