99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If I asked you to close your eyes
The mimic the action of using one of the Simplehuman interfaces in everyday life
You could probably do it
No problem
Without having a button to push
You can close your eyes
And pretend to push a button
And that action would accurately reflect the action of pushing a real button
Same with flipping switch
Start turning a doorknob
You close your eyes and fake the movement
It would sink up
With its real world use
Now if I asked you to do the same thing with a cars
Steering wheel
You think you'd be able to describe steering accurately and mine the correct movements with your hands in the air
But you'd be wrong
So wrong
You probably kill a bunch of imaginary people
But don't just take my word for
Even factors
His full name is Doctor Steve quote he just introduced themselves
Steve
He's a casual guy
And what was your research on
What's your mind
And that's Tristan cook and Thomas Nelson is also in the room they're asking
Steve Tristan and Tom run this awesome blog
Call humans and Design
My
Interests
Traffic behind
So here's the exercise
Put your hands up
And grip an imaginary steering wheel
Ellentube
Changing lanes
To the right
Have you tried it
All right if you like most
And according to Steve's research
We're talking the vast majority of people
You turned your imaginary wheel 45 degrees to the right or so
And then back to the center
And that's the action for changing lanes
But
That's not right
What you describe is actually the secrets of magnets that
Iroquois School
Do I actually change lanes you have to turn the steering wheel to the right then turn it back crossing the Centerline
Turning the wheel and equal amplitude to the left to correct your heading
And then back to the center
Knowing that this weird brain hiccup existed
Steve's team of the University of Queensland tested people in driving simulator
Turn off if you provided visual feedback
People could change lanes no problem
But as soon as you turned off the screen or blindfolded them and told them to change lanes
Even though they're only just moments ago successfully perform the correct action
They couldn't do it
Buy produced pretty
Catastrophic errors
Given no other feedback
You can't change lanes
Using a steering wheel without vision
Recent cars are designed to be dreaming with your eyes open
That's okay
And in fact this is a funky example that doesn't mean that a steering wheel
Is a bad interface design
You probably argue the opposite You could argue that a steering wheel is so well design
That anyone can use it with just a little bit of feedback in the real world
Even though they can't
Describe how they use it in the abstract
Data science
Expert
Facts about 45 minutes
Size of the Earth
But Stephens researchers decided to test this in a real car
So Steve got
I'm like 15 million dollars worth of insurance
It took people out in a real car and drove them down a test Road
And then took their Vision away
And ask them to change lanes
My friends Tristan to Tom where to the participants
It was absolutely terrifying
Little bit like when Obi-Wan Kenobi was teaching Luke Skywalker how to use a lightsaber without using his eyes
The blast shield down I can't even see in the first few runs people made the same mistake they did in the simile
Essentially they were told to change lanes
And they move the steering wheel in such a way that they turned a corner instead
Here's where things get really interesting
Straight Talk
People gradually started to improve and by the end of the real world blind trial
They were performing
Almost
Perfect
Laying chickens
In my experience there's no such thing as luck
When you driving
Open Shazam
Information
Is the vestibular system
Senses your balance or the somatosensory
Census
Pressure on your skin as your thigh presses into the seat as you turn the corner
Correct it
Using all those extra senses
People learn how to perform the lane change
In a real car
Blindfolded
But here's the crazy part
After it was over they asked the participants to
Mime a lane change with an imaginary steering wheel in their hands
And sure enough
They went right back to making the same mistake performing at corner turn in
Instead of a lane change
Just a ride bus this
Acerewards
Somebody
Steering wheel is
Pretty nice clean map
To our intuition but it still requires the
Why does spit up
Feedback to that our brain knows how to use it
Also I can't stress this enough people
Don't drop my phone
Really you just you're not going to go do it
99percentinvisible was produced by Tristan cook and Thomas Nelson of the blog humans and design fun at War humans and
Nine.com and me Roman Mars
It's made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a product of kalw 91.7 local public radio in Tampa
American Institute of Architects in San
I just got in the center for architecture and Design
To find out more go to the website it's 99% invisible
This Fire Burns
Here's an interesting side note if you want people to pretend to perform of perfect Lane change blindfolded years
You tell them you say
Not an obstacle in the road
And then return back
Boxer currently
That movement
Perfectly Jane
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing if you
Two days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast.,