99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Buchanan's Baxter and Bill Winston are doing their job right you probably don't notice that the
They're doing their job
But they are so good at doing their job you probably don't even know that her job exist at all
Are sound designers televised sporting events
Their job is to draw the audience into the action and make Sports sound as exciting as possible
And that doesn't mean that they throw a bunch of microphones on the field
This is Dennis Baxter
Sound designer of the Olympics
There's some sports that she just
Cannot
Capture the nag
Cross country skiing biathlon is another one
Because of the size of the core
And this has been further complicated because it's the camera lenses have gone up
110 Hunter 2000 3842 1
These cameras are able to see
A half a kilometer maybe McClung
And how do you reply
Placate that sound
Essentially if you got cameras that are
That far apart from each other you're putting 20 or 30 microphones
To feel
Why is the athletes are coming to you
Which is not
I am not a
Purest whatsoever in sound production
I truly believe
Then whatever the tool takes
To deliver a
High quality entertaining
Soundscape
It's all fair game
And
That has caused some issues because I use sampler
What a sampler is
It's a keyboard is attached
To essentially a digital recorder
When you hit the key on the keyboard
Triggers
The sound
At the playback
And with keyboard also triggers with sensitivity
Means it if I hit the
The key real hard
Don't have a little bit more of a heart attack
And you can vary the pitch
If I hit a C note that has a stamp
And then I hit a d note of the same sample
It will be apus
So for the sea and it gets
Rick Craven pension still hold the lead the French in third we could do without saying never a mother
In Atlanta one of my biggest problems
With Relic
Rowing is a 2 km
Course
They have
For Chase boats
Following the rowers
And I have a helicopter
That's what they need to deliver the visual
Okay but the helicopter in the chase boat
Just completely wash out
No matter how busy
You cannot capture you cannot reach
And isolate
Sound like you do visual
But people have EX
Expectations
If you see the rollers
They
Have a sound that they respect
So what do we do
That afternoon we went out on a canoe with a couple of rowers and recorded stereo samples of the different
Type of effects that would be somewhat typical of an event
And then we loaded those recordings into a sampler and play them back to cover the shots of the boats
Great Britain gold medals Steven Matthew Benson
Standby
Good evening
Let me do a horse racing you're looking to get somebody running around the pool softer
Snow White and occasionally you will come across pretty close up pic
Of the horses of the Pharcyde
Which is the most fun of all roofing companies
What you have
Engine oil
So that's why you wouldn't want to watch phone on that
Cuz when he retired
The car revving up when they come around cussing
Basically
The way you cover roll Lots
Stuff is to run a tape
Which has
Sound of horses galloping
Which is actually if I remember rightly
A slowed-down buffalo charge
That's pretty much a standard thing
Same recorded Live use for you
This episode of 99% invisible is produced by Peregrine Andrews for fallen tree Productions and features Dennis Baxter
Bill Winston
Is an extract from the much longer and really stunning audio documentary called the sound of sport
99% invisible is made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San
In the center of architecture and Design
The find out more go to the website of 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for a nap
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com