99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman
If you have the word courthouse and do a Google image search
You get the hundreds of results that look really similar to the US Supreme Court Building
Big steps
A granite Corinthian Colonnade
Top by Grand petomane if you could talk it would say respect
Serious s happens
That's Brett Myers he's reporting this way
Michelle he went to the New York County family court in lower Manhattan
It's a building that looks nothing like the classic Roman and Greek inspired architecture that most of us associate with
Courthouses
There's little to quite family with the building be on disk
Function family court could have talked before its 2006 renovation
It would have said
Built in 1975
Polish black Cooper's Hawk is about as welcoming as the Death Star in Patron reading from an article he wrote about
What is time is a paralegal in the building sums up the most common argue
About the original design
The New York County family court at 60 Lafayette Street
Is information architecture circles
Is an example of form giving not a damn about funk
And that's an easy argument to make
Absolutely it filled me with rage the first time I saw this building back in the late nineties the design just seems so
So wrong for family courthouse
It was like hiring Dick Cheney to be the nanny for your kids
It was brutal
Think repetitive angles and stick
Heavy forms
Lots of lots of concrete
It's a pretty polarizing Style
Actually kind of
And before the 2006 remodel it was possible to appreciate this building
From afar
Up-close was a different story
The shiny black granite panels
The cover the whole thing we're falling off and threatening to kill
People on the ground
It was a looming and menacing building
Even the entrance
There were these huge pylons offset at 45 degree angle
So that when you enter the building you can actually see what it was you were walking into
It was like stepping into a black hole
Definitely very Bleak and very
Oh my God what is this a black Bill do you know is this a courthouse
Miriam Hernandez works there as an interpreter translator
It didn't really have
The feeling of humanity or Humane you know it didn't really have that
What kind of stuff happens
Inside the question should be what doesn't happen
What does it have
I mean it's like
You could ride
Maybe You Forever book about
Takes place inside
And that Forever book wouldn't be a light read
Would have chapters about custody battles and divorces and abuse
Children going in the family court in their faith is being decided behind those doors
If anything
You would hope that the architecture wouldn't
Inspire Trust
Not
Fear
And maybe even can be a little bit of warmth
But instead
Goldenvoice refer to it as the Darth Vader building
Luke
Your mother and I are getting a divorce the question is
Was the form of the New York County family courthouse completely antithetical to its function
I met a guy who's got a really interesting theories
This guy goes by the name Loft room want my Clark Kent is a basic I do freelance research
By day he's a writer researcher
For a realist
But his secret identity is laughter one
It's the handle he uses when contributing to wired New York's this hugely popular website about
All Things New York City
The community section is basically a forum for Urban Design
After 1 is one of the biggest gigs on the side
How many posts have you posed is insecure
Furstenberg
About
Old couple thousand I'm not sure how I'd feel like 28,000 something like
28131 Plus
Excessive sweating
Texas morning video
You better if you today
I go out there almost everyday
In fact he averages almost 13 post per day
And most are related to architecture and urban planning
One of his first post was about the remodel of the building were talking about
The family courthouse
The building were standing in front of
Little place
I felt like I was
Kneeling down
And crawling
Through
Little
Bolin
Cave
And you know I didn't know what the hell there's a bear that
That's on the other side acting inside was not going to be good
They should have just put out you know
Abandon hope all ye who enter here
Because that's what the message
Who was sending
In laughter one argues that that message had a time set
That Old Black shiny death star of a building reflected the New York of the time
The New York back in the seventies when it was built
Watergate
Financial distress
Social
Divide
It all makes total sense
Total sense at this building looked the way it did
And this argument games even more weight when you consider a 1977 Story by Fame New York Times
Porter Lori Johnston
The article profiles users
The court in what is essentially a critique of the system
She interviews people who spend a Shuffling from one waiting room to another
And their critiques of the bureaucracy go hand-in-hand with critiques of the Arctic
Here's a quote from the 1977 article
It seems like a maze.
This place or worse
It seems like it's run like a prison
With uniforms all over
Maybe it's meant to discourage you
I'm going to head
Psycho you want
Form to meet function
This is how this
Cork function
This is what this court does
Sucks people in and spit some out
And there is no feeling
It doesn't solve the problem
Now of course the courthouse has been remodeled
And it's warmer and friendlier and it reflects a city that
It's friendlier and more function
The black facade is all gone it's
Edible light
Gradle
The entrance
Is all opened up
It even has come in on it
That doesn't look
Imposing or unfriendly tall and there's no more threat that those black granite panels
They're going to fall off the side of the building and kill
Oh yeah
It's also kind of
Boring
The remodel is definitely a little boring and it's not a building I want to talk to my friends about
But that original building
Angered me and it was something I talk to my friends about
It was dark and interest
And now Brett kind of misses the old boy
But I also know that I'm privileged because I don't have to interact
Because I don't have to work there and I'm not a kid who has to walk into family
For them this Milky Bland remodel is a definite improve
And probably
A sacrifice worth making
Kids math
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Brad Myers and me Roman Mars
With support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw local public radio 91.7 in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco in the center for architecture and design you can find out more at the website it's 9
99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com