99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the center of San Francisco there's a plaza with no benches
Central feature at the entrance of the plaza is it unique fountain that was designed by Lawrence Halprin in 19
The water shoots out at various angles from inside
Sunken pit
Filled with large
Granite slabs
It's a design that kind of
Hold you in and invites you to take the steps down to the water and climb in between the Hawking stones
And that's
Part of the problem
In 2004 radio producer been tension created a really fantastic documentary of UN Plaza
Call the biography of 100000 square feet at first aired
On the radio program mapreduce
Call the invisible ink in May of 2004
The dock Texas really hard look at UN Plaza when it was at its absolute worst
And ask
What I think is a really interesting question
Is there a
Point
We're good intentions and idealism of a certain design become so removed from reality
That it actually
Borders on negligence
Alright here's the show I listing My Pal been tension for him in the are premiering the piece back in 2004
And then letting me play it for you again more than 7 years later as part of 99% invisible
Things have changed a bit since the stock was produced so
Stay tuned and I'll give you a short update on UN Plaza
After the peace
Here's been temperature
This is the biography
Of 100000 square feet
At the heart of San Francisco there is a crossroad
Square Market
The Civic Center
It's called United Nations Plaza or less formally
Urination Plaza
And for most of the past three decades
It has been San Francisco's most public theater
Squalor
Misery
Sickness
That plays UN Plaza was with was a madhouse
You can go to any all the Desi needles
Liquor bottles
People fighting people urinating and defecating in that fountain that
That that's
Unsanitary
I see people shoot up at 1 and go to the other end and die
I saw that
Not easily
People don't scroll down streets and
You know I'm playing
Botchief it's not the mentality to use these big wide-open Plaza
It's never worked
I worked in UN Plaza for a summer
Walked across
The brick paving
Really wide u27
Cisco's imposing City Hall
Pastor Granite fountain
Protected by a yellow plastic
Chain
Through the thicket
Abdullah a crack smoker
Dealers who circled among the Bronze Star
All that's left of the benches
They cut them out with saws and remove them
I started spending time in United Nations on my days off
Talking to the people
Question I was after
Why does a public
Baseball
Derek Armstrong was there most days I was
Derek was enormous
Pounds and he sat on the planter bed walls everyday
Eating from bags of Cheetos
And listening to His Radio
I asked him
Why do you come down to UN Plaza
As you apply the centrally-located to a lot of homeless services that I used mainly Saint Anthony
UN Plaza is on the Glide path
Redo of San Francisco's poorest neighborhood
The tenderloin
And Soma
John delivery post office
Centrally located Nino netease
One Saturday I went down to watch some evangelist
Preach to the Lost
Sol's in United Nation
Plaza
When the preachers used to be homeless there himself
Had a. In my own ways
Off away from the main body of the audience I saw a man sitting against the black metal poles Circle
The fountain
He was behind the preachers and their loudspeakers
Watching
I asked them
Why are you sitting over here and not over there
Because I don't
Want to partake in anything right now
How many
I'm pretty much
Close myself away from everything
His name is Wendell Edwards
For sleeping on the sidewalk
And let out the same day
I lost a lot of love for the United States flag behind that
Because they made me feel like an enemy like I was part of the Taliban or something
And my father died fighting for this country
So when I was arrested that mentally really hurt me against the flag because I could
Breaking in somebody called I could have been hurting any of these people and taking their wallet at night
Catching them coming out of the storehouse or anyting
And I did none of that
It wasn't in my heart to do that
But it wasn't her heart to arrest me for sleeping merely sleeping on the sidewalk and I'll never forget that I still
Forgot to take it in my pocket it was just last week
And the devil keep telling me that
Since that happened
Don't you see what they trying to do to you
Go out and pay him back
Go Robert storm
Cuz you don't have no flag you don't have no country
You don't have nothing
They don't want you to be a part of it
That's just a nice way of saying
Niger get out of San Francisco
How did it get this bad
How did the space commemorating What are the great institutions in human history
At the heart of the richest city
And the richest
Country Inn
A place of so much
Promise
Turn out so wrong
My assignment was to develop Market Street over again
I said no Promenade
From the ferry building to the City Hall this is Lawrence helper
My idea and the whole idea for the city and our team and Design
What's the make a formal entrance to City Hall that people would admire and wood
Perceive as an important part of the formal quality of
Downtown area
Lake Perris
Have you ever been to Paris
In 1972
The city spent 24 million dollars beautifying markets
Richard been torn up for the installation of a Subway
The final section of the redesign was United Nation
Plaza
The city hired Halperin
To make the design
There is this quality of formality that we were at
An expressive the culture of a city
That was what we were thinking about
The importance of linear visual experiences
The blinking of one place to another instead of the kind of
Informality of neighborhoods where little streets go wandering around and you don't get any long
Longview
Lawrence Halprin is one of the most celebrated Landscape Architects alive today
He has been awarded the presidential medal of the Arts he designed the FDR Memorial in Washington DC
He designed the Promenade around Jerusalem
He has designed some of the most noted and famous public plazas
We wanted to make a statement
In the Greek sense
The visual qualities have to express what the politics of Summer
Not little daughter
Political this is a Nazi
Such a measure quality of
What's idiotic
Daylight
What it stands for
Wasn't
Called United
But hell no that wasn't anything like that
City planners designated the space UN Plaza after the decision
Close the intern
The intersection was closed
Because of the unique aspect of
The city's Urban Design
Peter bosselman chair of the Department of urban planning at the University of California
Plains lizard pecunia geometry about San Francisco
Market Street was lined up to connect the Waterfront with a set of hills
It's called Twin Peaks
But it is not aligned to the city grid Market runs at a 45 degree angle creating or kind
Signs of strange intersections where streets into Market Street never 90 degree angle
Always 45
But even for San franciscans is very confusing to find the connection between the south of Market in the north of Market
Very few streets lineup
The design helping came up with for United Nations
Was a stately Gateway
From arches to pass through
The Marchers would be funneled from the wide edge of the plaza that runs along Market Street
Between two lines of trees in raised planter bed
And then out through the space between the library and the Asian Art Museum
The vast green lawns
Civic Center Plaza
The centerpiece
Is the 165 ft long fountain
It contains 673 blocks of granite
Laying somewhere between three and four million tons
I took the idea of the High Sierra surrounding the bay itself and down in here you can see
See the bay
And I even developed a system
Of the Tide's coming in there was an hour long
Tidal action
Was Piper's out and then
Large.
Brew and Grow till it was up on these
Peeks
What you see in other words is a three-dimensional
Plaza
Which is unique has an idea
This title system no longer exists
Because maintenance was so terrible that's going to hell
Popsalot like
Relationships between people unless you take care of them
They go to hell
The fountain design was not immediately popular with
What city planners
In December 1970
The chairman of the Civic design committee said it was awful
Flamboyant
An example of a designer's egotism
Being passed on to the people is a
The piece of art
Ruth Asawa and acclaim San
Cisco sculptor said
As corny as this may sound
You have to design places in the city for people to sit on the grass
Sit under trees
ProFlowers
Birds
Even her obtain gun
When he called the Fountain of monstrosity
That must
B stock
But after five years
The planning in arguing
It was Bell anyway
Chris Adams has worked in the plaza
For more than 20 years
When that Fountain Blue Water it was supposed to work with the Wind
If the wind blew too far the water was supposed to go down
I've been here since app
Fountain was put in and I've never ever seen it work correctly
It's blowing 50 feet in the air in the winter and the water just pouring
And then the fact that it did start to stink the chemicals that were put in there killed all the trees that were around it
Children wanted to play in there and of course you don't want
Kids in that water many of the worries
Expressed by critics of
The design quickly came to
Pass
In June of 1979
Less than a year after the fountain was completed
A columnist for the San Francisco Examiner wrote an article about the Vandals
Derelict and social Miss
Who are turning the space
Into a garbage strewn graffiti two-faced mockery
Kevin Starr Road
What should have been the new Triumph and entering
H2r Civic Center
Is a resort
For Daryl
Thumbs Merchants all along Market Street
Great hope
The transformation of Mark
Whitaker
And it never happened if things went the other way
Bob Prentiss
Was the director of homeless Services Under mayor art agnos
From 1988 tonight
Ready to the merchants were
Extremely frustrated
Because of these you know these frustrated expectations that
Took the form of now
People actually hanging out in the plaza
It was just
A Tinderbox
That was the environment of the UN Plaza
Pretty much from the time that I started working in the mayor's off
Office in 1980
The Market Street associate
An organization of business owners
Property owned
Called for a farmers market
Be putting you in Plaza
Chris Adams runs the Farmers Market
I know it wasn't raining it was a nice sunny day 1980-81 when I believe it was
Springtime
12 farmers drove up with their trucks
And they did not sell out
But as they came weekly which is
What are Roots down there and
We're here to stay
It was some people in the neighborhood over
I'm trying to think of ways
To heal the Plaza
The end of the farmers market with
Poor people are
It's harder for them to go
It's not about
Driving them away it's about civilizing the places where they live
They can come out they can breathe out there it is part of the tenderloin
That's there
Front room
I've been told that
By almost all of the
Our place
Can see the refrigerators couches chairs
I don't want to
Push them out of there
I just
Shareit
Bob Prentiss again
It was a way to take over some use of that Plaza
With a purpose of supporting everybody
The idea that you would bring
Farmers markets in the Heart of the City where there was no Rito go
People who
Lived on the lowest incomes could not get decent
A decent prices
To me that's the spirit behind
Dealing with the seeming inevitability of poverty without being mean spirited
Chrisatm
The director of
The Farmers Market
I've been home
Good night
Teens
I lived in a car for two weeks with
Kids
It was no way I was going to stay
That's one reason I was hired
Not that I could do office work
But I got a long way
The people outside
I can get along with a few all the nationalities
I enjoy it
I think it's
Fine as a place that occurs every now and then
Good
Yes
On Wednesdays
Office workers in the
These neighborhoods skip microwave lunches gobbled at their desks
And head out instead to the Heart of the City Farmers
On Sundays it's a neighborhood crowd moving between the white tents
Wanda plaza
Folding tables covered with yellow squash
Blueberries
Salad greens all organic
The customers are from all over
The farmers
Are from all over
That's why I love being where we are I mean
Cambodia
Vietnam
Mexico
Italy
All over the world the heart of the city was a perfect name for
Fort because I thought that solution
Demonstrated
The kind of heart
It wasn't tension between the street people the ones that ran the other mark
I remember that
You think you know this is a civil way
To make due
With a situation
It's so far has been pretty lousy oh my gosh it's United Nations
But on days when the farmer's market and the newer less successful aunt
Flash flea market
Aren't in the plaza
United Nations reverts to what it used to be
At the East End of the Plaza
Between the glass windows of the fast-food franchise and stares down into the subway station
The Thieves Market moves
Black Market salesman fill the 20ft neatly laid-out close hand tools
Pornographic videos
Consumer electronics of
Questionable provenance
2 days before Thanksgiving I went down to the plaza to ask the salesman what have you got to sell today
I got the sweater purple sweater
And I got glasses again hat I got a new pair of under breast
Shoes Nike jacket
And I Got a Woman fly
My name is Zachary I was born in Ventura but I came down here about 15 15 years ago in
The general sense
My mother died in January in
Like
What's that March
Yeah I started it like
You don't go gambling
And I lost all my money so I'm out here now
I was just
Choosing everything to me you know and
I take that out my gambling
And somewhat
You know
Cursing God
While we were talking the drug addicts
Distinguishable from the merely homeless by their lack of luggage
Begin to line up
Against the windows
Carl's jr.
Hook everybody's all lined up
Why they are lined up
I don't know
He's bleeding
That guy with the dreadlocks
Taking blood off his nose
Another panaca in Hangouts
That's what makes them say okay there
Uncivilized
Yeah you guys must have punched a guy
So you going to clear up
Yeah I got to go down the way
Zachary packed up his meager merchandise
I went to find out what was going on
A Taurus
I bought food at the Carl's Junior to give away to the homeless
My name is Keisha Morris
My intention to be in California is two by two big buildings
Take the homeless off the street
It's hard to explain is a dream
I had
And
It's coming to pass
I've been driving around
This block twice
And this was the sign the people in front of Carl's jr.
So I know this was the place to rest
Play outside please
Manager tried to bring the food out
Seven police officers when he got outside the line collapse order
Broke down completely
He doesn't have to do this
I see how it is
This is Muhammad
The manager of the
Carl's jr. Serve the food to the hungry homeless people
Then I told him to wait outside on the line so I will pass soon as I get ready I will be outside
Fighting together I don't know why they start fighting
When I came outside
Start grabbing the food from the box
That's enough
In miniature this food Riot restate
The failure of UN Plaza itself
A dream that proved no match for its burden
Halpern to had a vision for something decent
The grace
The public spaces
But when this dream was overlaid on a real place
Just didn't work out
I'm not sure if
Now if I were going to be asked to design this is how much I would change
I mean why would I
You're talkin about my life's work for Christ sakes
I was the first person who ever designed a plaza and Fountain so that people could use it people
Should not be told you can't
Get inside of it and use it
All places should be usable by people in the city
Now having said that
Why would I design something to prevent homeless
I mean
Homelessness is a social problem
That cannot be designed for and in the sense of Aesthetics and culture
Of course they should be friends
That's a real question is what do you mean by friendly
Nobody is ever said to me I want you to design it unfriendly place
But you know it depends on who you talk to
When you say
You talk to people who say that to other
Sounds like a pretty stupid thing to say actually
I would absolutely challenge
I can't imagine that anybody
Say anything
In mm
The Department of Public Works applied for and was awarded Federal Grant
Need to clean up the 28th
Eight-year-old Plaza
Almost a million dollars
Enough to make real changes to
Did the design
This is Judy Mosqueda
A project manager
The Department of Public Works
I first got to know United Nations Plaza
Back in 1979
I used to take BART into the plaza with my sister I was about
12 years old
I was not a fast Walker and I remember so vividly my sister walking as fast as she could Up Leavenworth Street because
There were men harassing us along the way
And I would have to jog alongside her to keep up with her and that was embarrassing to me
Plan for the redesign had already been drawn up
Landscape Architects here at the Department of Public Works had made some recommendations for improvements to a
Things like replanting planter beds with flowers instead of the grass
It's there now something that would add color
A little bit of life to the plaza
As we went to the Board of Supervisors
The fencing around the Planters became a contentious issue
In December 2001 the plan drawn up by DPW was rejected by the boar
They didn't like the fences
A 15-member task force was created by the city
The taskforce ask Roma designed to make some recommendations
This is Boris drama
A principal at Roma
The mayor's office he was not too pleased with what was being proposed and I said
They're the standard kinds of things to prevent people from using space
The first step is you take out the benches then you put little fences around the green areas then you put barrier
Beers for people so they can sit down
And I said frankly I'm not interested in
The negative
Approaches 15 people with an interest
Sometimes competing in
We're appointed by the
Supervisors
To come up with a plan that would fix up the plaza without displacing anyone
The chair was Lynn Valente of the market
Street associate
Is it the same markets
Mission that had created the popular Farmers Market
20 years
Before people that are part of marketers Association
But have properties in
Who will live in work up there
Their number one request
Get that sound out of it
Because people were
Essentially living in a defecating and
Urinating in the fountain
And shooting up drugs the fountain
All that kind of stuff having sex and I mean they've seen everything
In the end
The task force left Halperin streamm4u en Plaza behind
Roma recommended they remove the fountain
But a street through the Thieves Market
Did any fact change United Nation
Shins from a formal play
A place for March
A Public Square in helper
French words representative
What are the ideals of a government
China City
And turned instead
Add to exactly what helper
Didn't want
Informality of neighborhoods where little streets go wandering around and you don't get any longer
Longview
This is Boris grandma
This is really a spray tan
That's been closed predominantly for traffic reasons
Fulton Street created a very awkward intersection with Market Street
And Traffic Engineers don't like triangular intersection so they tend to eliminate
Not because they thought it was the best place to create a gathering space
One has to question should be an open space of this size in this location
Why would you put it here
In Spring of 2003
The plaza hit bottom
The plan drawn up by the task force
Appointed by the Board of Supervisors
After a year-and-a-half and more than 20 meeting
Was rejected
By the board of
Supervisors
Around the same time
Channel 4 ran in extremely unflattering music out
Squalor in the plaza
Everywhere you turn people smoking crack
All day everyday
The mayor says he'll consider shutting down the fountain
Removing the benches and building gated playgrounds
Within hours mayor Willie Brown had made his decision about United Nation
Plaza
City workers cut through the bronze legs
24 bench
And by morning
Gone
I think people felt like they lost the battle of Yuan
That are vacating the premises now
They're taking the
The benches outfits contested terrain where they've given up hope they're going to win
Lynn Valenti of the Market Street associate
And would come up with now
After years and years and years
Community input
I wish I did
8 or 9
Caution tape around the fountain no it's not caution tape anymore it's a yellow plastic fence
I don't understand how that happened
I understand how it happened but it just
Sticks in my craw
Did the first plan that they came up with the fencing that were
Posing with no higher than 3 ft tall
Was not acceptable
Promethazine came in
I thought people drive down or bicycle down
And that's how it's been for almost a year
Flowers
No fences
No benches
The crack addicts have mostly been pushed out by the pervasive police presence and the street sweepers that Circle Khan
Do you like fish in an aquarium
The homeless people who used to sit on the planter beds are fewer in number but they're still there
Many of them have shifted 50ft toward City Hall
Where they sit inside a large sculpture
San Francisco's Pioneers in the middle of a traffic circle
It would be a stretch
To say this is an improved
Have you been
No I purposely don't go there usually
Have you seen the pictures of the chain-link fence around the fountain I know about
The city and the project manager for that
Project has been very
Careful about
Traffic keeping us advised about what's going on
He's trying to
Recapture some of the original quality to play sand
Also deal with some of the social issues
That are encroaching on them
I think some people want to turn that into something is never going to be
You know it's not going to be a renaissance that's not going to happen
I mean
This is part of the tenderloin and that
Influence is always going to be there I'm sorry but I think that's how it should read I really do
Why do you cut off the daily life of a city
In order to create a space for special events
The only occur
A few times a year
I would question whether
We should have an open space
Abyss size at this location
Rather than allowing
The traditional elements of City form
Like streets sidewalks
2xist
Judy Mosqueda is optimistic
But it is a resign.
The funds were to be expended
Buy I believe June 2003
Obviously I've missed that deadline I'm now shooting for June 2005 and I hope to be successful for that
And if
San franciscans can't come just concept
Consensus on what should happen in this Plaza
I may ask for another extension
Or we may decide that San Francisco doesn't know what
What to do with this Plaza
This point in time
Before San Francisco gives up on United Nations Plaza
We might want to consider some words of advice given by President Harry Truman
When the charter for the real United Nations
Was sind almost sixty years ago
A great day this can be in history
Out of all the arguments
Different points of view
My way was found to agree
Truman is speaking to the delegates who would sign the UN Charter in the War Memorial Opera House
Six blocks away from the present day
United Nations Plaza
It was the result
August Spirit of give-and-take of tolerance for the views and interests of others
Those problems and scores of others
Which winterize are all difficult they're complicated
They are controversial and dangerous
If we keep to our principles
And never forsake our objectives the problems we now face
And those to come will also be song
That was the biography of a hundred thousand square feet bruised by Ben tension in 2004
I'm recording this on November 17th 2011 and I was down at UN Plaza today recording the fountain
Pictures
Yard Market was being set up
And the water was flowing in the fountain that was
Marred by a bit of trash circling the Eddie's butt
Nothing too grotesque are expected
Yellow chain that cordoned off the fountain 2004 is gone
And this morning with the Art Market being set up I got
How much stronger feel for the intention of the Plaza
And was evident
It was at its worst
But the big issues were still plain to see
Landscape architect Lawrence Halprin who designed UN Plaza and is featured in the piece
Has since died
It is your first exposure to help and I really recommend you look them up and check out his other work
He is absolutely revered in matcha landscape architecture community
And the Very principles of interactivity and engagement
That works
To the detriment of UN Plaza
You'll did
Stunningly successful result
And other places so it's worth exploring more of his legacy
If you're into that sort of thing
Which I think you are
Because you just listen to a half-hour documentary about the failure of a public space
You're a big old nerd
Like me
God love you
This episode of 99% invisible
Who was produced by Ben Thompson
Any possible with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity it's a project of kalw local public radio 91.7 in
San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
The center for architecture and Design
To find out more go to the website it's 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com