99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
It's totally unfair
Hydrox cookies came out in 1908
Didn't show up until 4 years later
But it didn't matter
Hydrox could never shake the image
Sabina knockoff
An also-ran
Hydrox lovers with champion its 10-year cream filling
Vegetarian surprise them for being cruelty free
America's favorite cookie the Oreo
Contain animal lard into the mid-90s
As a consumer
Product
It's just not up to you
Sometimes you redeemed the mighty Transformer
And sometimes
You would love some Gobot
It's capricious you win
Swiss cake roll vs hoho
Twizzler vs. red vine
Maybe you were supposed to First Family on the Block Wiki technologically Sue
Superior betamax player
Only to be overwhelmed by the mediocre VHS
Sometimes it doesn't make
Any sense
At all
But sometimes it does
I'm John Wallin
John is a writer for New York Times magazine in a writer at large for pop-up magazine live magazine in San
Where this story first appeared
Greatest Hits 1902
And Theodore Roosevelt as president and he decides to vacation in a town called
Snead's in the Mississippi Woods
Rican and black
Is a big Outdoorsman
Hunter and his hunting trip became kind of a famous story
Basically it's been a few days hunting in
I don't think they even saw a single bear they definitely didn't get to
Shoot at any and then one morning
The dog is get the scent of a bear and they follow it down to this really weedy place where the
Presidents guide says you know what don't even bother going in there and then troubling yourself I'll go and I'll flush the beer out
You just stay here and I'll flush it right to you
So Roosevelt Waits and waits
But then he gets bored and decides to go off and eat lunch
Eventually the dog is to Corner the baron and the guide not really knowing what to do for scratched the bear over the head
With the butt of his rifle Knox
Unconscious or semi unconscious and tied it to a tree
And then starts blowing around reviewal trying to call Roosevelt facts that the president can be the one who has the honor of shooting
Roosevelt heaters Dubuque
And makes his way back to the hunting
Rdr2 female bear is about 235 lb
It's tied to a tree
It still semi-conscious
Injured it looks a little mangy
It's actually probably about half as heavy and big as it should be but there's been a real drought going on in the area
The bear look
Looks pathetic
Roosevelt
Expedia let me decide said it's it's unsportsmanlike
To shoot this thing you know he's not going to do it he doesn't want anyone else to do it either
And
In This Server merciful Momin
Is that your word of this spreads and a political cartoonist
Draw the cartoon of the of the moment of him
Showing the bear this Mercy
And the way the cartoonist draws the berries almost like a little Labrador puppy or a golden retriever
PizzaRev on it
On its butt and its hind legs
Kentucky's big round
Perked up ears almost like Mickey Mouse
Chinese big white eyes
Staring at the
The president waiting to see
What is fate
The cartoon was called
Drawing the Line in Mississippi
And from that basically spawn the teddy bear this adorable little
Bear in the cartoon was turned into a three-dimensional plush toy
The very first teddy bear was either made by a German company called Steve
Aura Brooklyn toys around are depending on who you ask and they named it after Theodore Roosevelt
They called teddy bear
It's a huge sensation
And it's actually more popular than baby dolls worth
Treats everyone out alone
That you know why should their children be playing with bears and and not dolls
Buffalo Savage
And within a few years I think Steve is producing close to a million teddy bears a year and shipping them to the US
It was considered so bizarre that kids would
Play with a stuffed bear that people just assumed it was a novelty and as soon as Roosevelt left office
No one would want them
This time the whole idea of mass-produced toys was also really new
So the toy industry wanted to come
Capitalized on its rally in
Keep it going
It was really looking for whatever was going to be the next
Cubby play things that American Kids
They're going to want though though it had no idea what that might be
The best forward in 1909
Roosevelt
Term is about up
In the president-elect
Is Roosevelt's hand-picked
Successor
William Howard Taft
And that January January 1909
Taft is in Atlanta he's trying to woo the South
I'll try to convince him that his administration is going to take them seriously as a
The constituency
Any suggestive on at this banquet
And the Chamber of Commerce in Atlanta decides it's going to serve him the truest
Most unpretentious Southern dish around
It's something that a writer of the time I found this little book about southern food from the
Calls it the Christmas goose
Epicurean nigra
The meal was possum and taters
And what it was was
An opossum
Would be roasted on a bed of sweet potatoes
And then presented hole on a platter
Who were the tat on
Tell on
And it often you'd get a smaller a little sweet potato Crown between the animals
By the way 52 has a parent leave the most teeth of any North American mammal
Which is faster
Indian the one that they brought to test table with 18
All the sudden orcas
Strikes up
Biggest person to song
Cenotaph is present
Surprised gif
Small
Stuffed
Possum toys
And this is a brand new invention that some local tap supporters are trying to position as William task presidencies
Answer to the teddy bear
They're calling it
Billy Paul
Already there was a company set up
Call the Georgia Billy possum
According to One account within 24 hours of that bank with their already deals being broke
Pixability Boston
Distributors
Across the country
In covering the banquet the LA Times
Announce that
The teddy bear has been relegated to a seat in the rear end for 4 years possibly 8
The children of the United States
It will play with Billy Paul
Superman on a bit of possum Mania started
They're Billy possum postcards Billy possum Billy possum pictures
Trader cream when you had coffee
There was a Ragtime tune called possum the latest craze
And
Does tap traveled around the South some people actually start giving him live opossums in cages when he would make public appearances
Handing them over like they were Floral
Soon baby possums were in toy stores from New York to San Francisco
Because real opossums when I see that comment and cities that and no one really knew what they were
A toy store in Brooklyn
Easter promotion with a live captive opossum
That they could show off the kids
Pacific kids
Familiarize themselves
What does new animals are going to be best friends with what
I found an advertisement for the story that read
Do not let it be said
Did any man woman or child in Brooklyn
Has not seen the cute little animal
Whose name is mentioned more in all parts of the world today
And any other
President on the newspapers
Hauser morning the passing of the dolls and and how sad it was at these teddy bears were coming into nurseries and Vanquish
And now the ra poems
In newspapers about Billy possums 2
Splicing teddy bears
But since you probably never heard of a billy possum
You can guess what comes next
It was a total flop
And the Billy possum was forgotten in almost
Entirely out of stores within a couple of months
What's another word for Billy possum never even made it
See Christmas time
Which is a special kind of tragedy
There are several possible explanations as to why the Billy possum never took off
Converse
Probably what you thinking right now is this
Opossums are ugly
And nobody likes them
But it was also the dawn of the mechanical toy
And even some teddy bears that evolved into wind-up animatronics
There is a French maid teddy bear
That quote wines up and is calculated to indulge in a number of ludicrous somersault
How could Olympics
Stuffed Billy possum compete with that
Pajama Willam argues that
At its heart
The acceptance of teddy bear and the rejection of Billy possum
Comes down to their origin story
In the story that was told about Roosevelt and his bear
It was a very kind of tender moment where
Rosella showing the bear Mercy
And when you looked at that cartoon the way the bear was drawn
It looked like something that you would want to just sweep up into your arms and
Take care of and that was vulnerable in that needed your help
It looks like a teddy bear as we know it
Although no one knew it at the time
The story with half we didn't give it anything else
Your top 8 is opossum for
I need a lot of it and he ate so much
The Doctor's first several helping is a doctor seated nearby apparently passed him a note
Suggesting that it might be a good idea if you slow down a little
Taft even bragged reporters the next day about how much opossum he consumed
Fly like a possum and I ate very heartily of it last night
And it did not disturb in the slightest
My digestion or my
I sleep the possum was vulnerable I guess
Splayed out on a bed of taters but
You're not exactly routing for it
I started feeling really bad for
How to use the more I read a little bit about him
He was just totally colorless
Politician
And he didn't actually even want to be
President buy some
How you assert
Strong-armed into it
Original Annie never really measured up to Roosevelt
Charisma and charm mean Roosevelt was the kind of guy who
You no matter what he did history seem too eager to
To glorify
Case in point
The messed up thing about the famous story of Teddy the bear on that hunting trip in Mississippi
Is it isn't even the whole truth
You have to remember that Roosevelt was
A hunter he was there to hunt bears he wasn't a Peta activist
Or something like this
Well he didn't show the bear
Mercy it was very particular
Kind of Mercy
After he refused to shoot it
He said put it out of its misery
And then one of his Hunting Buddies came in
And slip the bear's neck open
Man with a knife
They Carried the Bears body back
Camp over the back of a horse
And they basically ate off it
For the next several days
They finish it off they roasted its paws
And I could you not pay deposit with
Aside appassimento
So that's why you will never cuddle up
With a billy possum
Just like you will never watch a betamax tape
Travel to go betron with weeder one
And you will never again
Tonka hydraulic
Cookie
Management Hydrox cookies
Never really take
99% invisible with produced this week by Jon mooallem and me Roman Mars based off of
Puppies that John did it Papa magazine number 5 in San Francisco
This program is made possible with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
The American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
And the center for architecture and Design
This program is distributed by PRX
Public radio exchange making public radio more public
Find out more at PRX
. org
The new kid in town is Sam Greenspan
The first 99 percent invisible intern
And since he called me boss at the end of our first meeting
I'll be back next week
You find out more about this program or to say hi
99% invisible
. org
An island
Dad that are words
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com