99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The world of Philip K dick humans are often at the mercy of objects
Ataxia is coffee makers indoors
Here's a scene from his book ubik
The door refused to open
It said $0.05 please
Joe chip Services Paca
No more coins nothing
I'll pay you tomorrow
Hold the door
Again he tried the knob
Again it remains
Loctite
From the drawer beside the sink
Joe got a stainless steel knife
With it he began systematically
Unscrew the bolt assembly
I was money coping door
I'll sue you the door said
That's the first screw fell out
That's Benjamin Walker
He told me he's always subscribe to Dick's dystopian vision of man versus object
But then
He met up with Paola Antonelli
Daily potato
Dick's view of
Neutral objects was
Definitely dystopian and he needed
He did it for like
Drama reasons
But in truth we had
A report with objects throughout the century
Is always been affectionate motion
Heirloom ring or the bridge
Are you
Your first kiss means always been an attack
There's a whole universe and everything
Object
That
Becomes even bigger one
When putting relaxer
Paola Antonelli
Is a senior curator in the
Department of architecture and Design
At the Museum of Modern Art
Her most recent Blockbuster show talk to me
Examined
The future and the history
Of communication is
Furniture Design
Car design
Is just one fragment
Design world
And for many years there's been something called
Communication design
Which may be before used to
Call graphic
Which is the design of messages
Just Beat It
Advertising
I just sign it
So it's exist
That's design
Who subject
Is communa
But right now
The difference is that
Even Furniture Design
Nurse need to understand
That a Chad might need
To have some kind of conversation with
With people
There was a talking chair in
Michelle
We can talk you can sing
And talking
Toys
Talking Maps
But they were also ATMs and Subway kiosk
According to Paola Antonelli
Cutting-edge communication design
Is all about
The interface
When you say interface you can take out the face and
Section you can take out section and
Relation to me
One of these
Focal
Points
Of the way
Will look today
The wave
Paola Antonelli says designers under
Understand the interface
Between people and objects better than say science fiction writers
Because what they're really working on
Is the interface with
People and
One of the pieces she put in her show with almonds
Stration machine
Designed by
Nico
I need a particular case the interface is not Beach
Between man and machine is
Between man and woman
Alright so it's
Contraption that looks
Looks like a chest
Sticky belt
That
It's for men but also for menopausal women
At
It said it really gives you the
The feeling of menstruation it has electrodes
The stimulate your lower abdomen and they give you cramps and then it has a Reservoir in the back your
Supposed to draw your blood put it in there
And then you have your blood drip
Exactly where it should so
The whole shabang
And to me
It's the ultimate gesture of understand
And
That's what I really love
That is
Two-faced not
The human machine
Interface the human-machine into
The face you know what we are all doing engineer's designer scientist
We're all trying to make technology visit
That's the truth
Just like we go through
The toll booths in freeways using easy
He passed and we still have that box
Don't think about it
That's how
Life should be so that we can focus on real human habit
Human needs
99% invisible was produced this week by Benjamin Walker produces the radio program too much information
Confirm WFMU
He also Sports A Philip K dick inspired you big tattoo on his arm
This program is made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw local public radio 91.7 in San Francisco
The American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
And the center for architecture and Design
This program is distributed by PRX public radio Exchange
Making public radio more public more at PRX
. org
Are entering him Sam Greenspan
Define out more about this show and listen to past episodes
It's like 43 of them
It's on the website at 99percentinvisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com