99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment in California and
Around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm running more
Hello
We are Anonymous over the years
We have been watching you
First off we should describe what anonymous
It's not an organization it is a non organization
What sort of ever-changing Band of individual
Sometimes described as hackers or hacktivists
Store free expression zealots
So are just internet troublemakers you can't even call him a group I tend to call them
We are anonymous
And for someone who writes extensively about Brands and brand identity
Rob Walker became intrigued
Magazine and
Because this non group called anonymous
Somehow created its own
Visual identity it was so compelling and immediately recognizable which is a task that corporations are political camp
I think spend millions and millions of dollars
To achieve
And these people seem to have done something very effective
Without any organization or any budget for even any
There are two basic images used for anonymous
What is a logo headless figure in a suit
Juxtaposed against
Kind of world map
Very
Blatantly derive
From the United Nations
Globe
With a?
The other major visual image is a mess
Are there is a sort of stylized vicinage based on Guy Fawkes although no one real
Recognize
Guy Fawkes
Is the mask worn by the protagonist in The Graphic novel and then movie
V for Vendetta
The original mask design was by the artist David Lloyd
And it comes in handy when you're trying to stay Anonymous in the real world
And it is sort of bleached over into
Adjust Street protest
Street protests liking non-affiliated Occupy Wall Street movie
Anonymous has its roots in the anonymous postings on these / B / message board on 4chan.org
I would openly discourage your listeners from visiting the / B / message board
Yeah
Some things you just
Can't unsee
See it's really
Pretty harsh together as a kind of movement when they decide to take on the Church of Scientology
There was an embarrassing video of Tom Cruise
That people were posting and people representing the Church of Scientology were taking it down
Anonymous had a problem with that
Because of their kind of General free expression
Point of view and decided that they would band together and keep reposting that video and then
That sort of escalated into what else can we do
To basically cause problems for the Church of Scientology
It was an ominous YouTube video producer
Buy a small subset of a
We're more unified voice
Spaghetti for
I was absolutely blown away by this
It's directed to the Church of Scientology
It's not directed To The World At Large
Attention
Scientology
We are anonymous
And here's what we have
Say
And we're coming after you
And we recognize you as a formidable opponent
But we're going to take you down
And the visuals
It's just sort of rolling
Clouds over buildings
And this is kind of ominous
Music playing in the background and the voiceover
Is this
Robot voice
Which turned out to be an online AT&T tech
But it sounds really
There are a few notable moments
Send turns off
The phrase in the video but the first one to grab Rob's attention
We are Anonymous and we're going to do this
For the good of your own followers for the good of mankind and for our own amusement ind4
Enjoyment
It just sort of like
Really encapsulates this like we're righteous and we just sort of feel like doing this right now cuz we
We find it fun
Which is really kind of a scary combination
Of ideas
The video ends with what has become the anonymous tagline
And parts of this tagline I learned had been kind of floating around on 4chan at slash
Splash board
We are anonymous
We Are Legion
We do not forgive
We do not forget
Expect us
Expect this is so like
You know you just almost immediately want to serve freeze up with
Your keyboard and look over your shoulder
If they're there
Around the same time as this video the apprehension headless suit man in front of the UN flag logo was created
Again using elements that have been floating around these / B / board
For quite some time
Elsa created a website
And all this because
A media Savvy member of anonymous
Warn the others
But if they didn't brand themselves
Someone else
Would do it for the
You need some kind of a solid identity
Setopress
Because they're going to they're going to come up with their own
If you don't and you want to control that message
Rob Walker got the inside story of the early days of anonymous from Greg house
Who is part of the
Early planners
Various
Anonymous actions
You could say Direct
The action
But you know what
Anonymous everyone knows that you
You can only make suggestions that if they're good enough
Don't do it
Ignored in the process
Of being
Bombastic
They could tour
Scientology
They sort of accidentally created
Ominous
Self-image that is simultaneously scary but also very
So this video that they did took off
Currently it has over four and a half million views
And it decided the next logical
.
Was Street protein
We decided right then and there that that's what we're going to ask everyone to do we're going to send the internet
Outside
People are leaving their mother's basement
Sort of legal stuff
Church of Scientology
Is really going after 9
We're going to need to cover our faces
So we need to
What Mass do we use
He means the V for Vendetta mask
That's kind of
A Batman mask
Floating that night was old school masquerade masks
Where you would actually hold the little stick and hold it up
And then they got really pragmatic about their choice
We called around 2
Comic book shops and cost
Shoe shops in most of the major cities of the world from
Paris
To London
New York everywhere
And we ask
What do they cost
And it won't be found
Nearly every costume and comic book shop on the
Planet
Hadoop
The Guy Fawkes mask
For 6
The $10
Sitting on your local currency
I know it was you
It was okay
It
Every city in the world not only do we like it but it's the right choice
Basically up shot is
Enough people went along with the
The day after
Scientology
Photos
Videos
People wearing this
All over the
And
It just caught fire
A powerful thing
Sort of sot
Another quality of the V for Vendetta mask is that
Has its own
Twisted version of a Mona Lisa smile
That you can
And quite figure out if he's laughing
Or mean
Or laughing at you in a mean way having fun and Menace
You know it's not really that surprising that those two ideas
It is a statement of anonymity of personal privacy
But it's also a statement
Of
Wild freedom of expression
And
Absolutely
Through a combination of Mirth
I asked Rob Walker why he thinks he's too images
The Headless suit man and the V for Vendetta mask work
He gives two basic reasons
One is that they're just
Graphically
Pleasing
People up is like what is your empirical proof that this is
Is good
I don't really have any empirical
What I have is
I look at it and I say that's awesome
And the second reason is that the two symbols are easy to manipulate
Very
Simple graphics
Program
You can put
The Guy Fawkes mask
Over the Hedge
Why are you can manipulate these things in any number of ways
Which is
A strategy that
Traditional
Say corporate brand
Or political
Wouldn't
Maybe not be so into
But in this case there was no creative brief there was no set of brand
And standards
People just seem to intuitively know that you can
Play around with these things
Hand drawn the
Power of the
But make them your own
And in the making them your own
You're doing it in a way
That rebounds back to the original images
And that's just like the message board meme culture that
Anonymous to begin with
You can make the images your own and be one of them
Are use it for your own purposes and have nothing to do with Anonymous at all
No one will know the difference
Annies icons and anonymous
Will live on
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Rob Walker and me Roman Mars it's based off an article
That Rob wrote for slaves on how they link on the web
This program is made possible with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a product of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Can the center for architecture and Design
99% invisible is distributed by PRX
The public radio exchange making public radio more public find out more at PRX.
The program intern is named Sam Branson
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook and follow me on Twitter at Roman Mars
Or English join us at the website 99percentinvisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The bunny genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy's you know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
Actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast. Com