99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is the first joke I ever really noticed as a design joke
They can only become
Stairs
That's Mitch Hedberg
All right
Escalator temporarily out of
Only and
What's the weather
Release date
Sorry for the
Being designed elegantly deal with the extreme failure cases
Probably an under-appreciated design element
But it really is one of the things that makes an escalated rate
Worst case
There stairs
Feel for you getting a broken elevator
I bet everyone is escalators
Enjoying that design aspect to
Cambridge audio
That's 99percentinvisible Zone Sam Greenspan walking up an escalator in a metro station in DC
Ever since the Industrial Revolution when it became possible for products to be designed just one
And then mass-produced
Is Ben
Light
Failures and Imperfections
In the individual wear-and-tear introduced by human use
That transforms equality mass-produced products
Intuit thing we actually love your worn in blue jeans
Your grandmother's iron skillet the initial design determined its quality
Lusteric
Post manufacturing the imperfections that make them comfortable to make them lovable and make them yours
If you think a slightly broken escalator can't be lovable
Or maybe you have been paying attention
An escalator on a DC Metro platform is like a fine wine
It's better with age and without any industrial lubricant
Sam lives in Baltimore now we lived in DC for a few years he said that this sound
Came to embody the excitement he felt from living in a city
Yeah I mean I grew up in one of Florida's most
Depressing suburbs
Just miles and miles of highways in
Culs-de-sac
Very nice
Just want to move to DC I took public transit everywhere just because I could
The DC Metro System it's not the best in the world but it's pretty good
Although a lot of people do Lament
The poor condition of the Metro escalator
Broken and then there are some that work but make these crazy noise
Which you know I know a lot of people but for me
I found it a scrogging escalator was like this little Trumpeter announcing how awesome it was
To live in the city
It turns out that someone else loves this sound too so this is Chris Richards
I'm the pop music critic at the Washington Post
Chris is also in a band called q and not U hero. Kind of appreciation of the Metro escalators for the Post
For the Farragut North Metro Station
In Washington DC on the north side
Bell Street
Medical Avenue Chris told me that he'd never really noticed the sound of the escalators made until one day when he was on a bit of a
Having my ear trainer
For those sort of
Breath on brass kind of sound
I think maybe turning the corner to come down the escalators one day I thought there's a saxophone player
Playing at the bottom
Of the Metro
But it was not at all
There's kind of like
Walking in
Reaching away
Maybe I don't know if they're always has loud
On the escalator there's a plastic element on the side of each step that keeps it from rubbing against the metal siding
A lubricant keeps it all running smoothly
But when it rains or snows the lubrication wears off
So what you're hearing when you hear these kind of like
Morning squawk
Steel stairs
Rubbing up and Chase
Tap Plastic
Kind of like a beautiful
Serendipitous Aftershock
Of the wear and tear
It sounds like music
And like any good music critic
Chris started classifying the different styles of Metro escalator
So here at Farragut North the escalators might sound like whales mating or something like that
Whereas the escalator at U Street
Kind of sounded like Indian drum music
Columbia Heights
An Aviary of chrome part of ravens taunting you as you descend into your work day
We understand that we could be over-romanticizing escrow knocking and squeaking escalator
You can talk all day about
Appreciating the ambience soundscape around you and
Get really into aestheticized ways of listening Chris Richards was big on this by the way
But you could also just as easily say you don't hate this is all noise I think it's all really in the year of the beholder so
It is totally understandable that people wouldn't appreciate a screeching escalator
Chris actually told me
That when he called up Metro for his story their PR people didn't believe him
They thought he was running some big expose about escalator failure
Baby down
This is a wonderful little residual
Bonus
My point of view is if you're going to be subjected to some kind of sensory experience
Of which you have no control every single day then it's to your
Benefit
Why not
Try to enjoy it
Because there's no
Things in life
Play stressed out about
As much as people complain about what that all the sounds of cities making all the noise that the city's make
I think those noises to find it at
You really become our environment sound to be an irritation or can be information
Helping the escalators never get fixed
Except the ones that just straight-up don't work
The escalator stop
It is the longest escalator in the Western Hemisphere
It's 3 minutes to ride to the top when it's working
Let's hope that the Wheaton escalator doesn't conveniently become stairs
Anytime soon
99percentinvisible was produced this week by our intern Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars it was adapted from
Episode of Sam's podcast whisper cities
The show about overlooked places in the people who find them
Find out more at whisper cities. Org this program is made possible with support from the lunar making a
Prince with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
The American Institute of Architects in San Francisco and the center for architecture and Design
99% invisible is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more
Public find out more at PRX. Org
To find out more or keep in touch with us especially if you want to tell us about your favorite sound which you know
I know for a fact it's somebody else's noise
Go to our website it's 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com