99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
Enrollment
St Louis Housing Authority
This is a far cry from the crowded collapsing tournaments
Many of these people have known
Aaron Blake new buildings with spaces
Ground
Bacon live
Who would I go Miss begins here
This is Chad Fredricks
Public housing
Project that existed on the Northside of St Louis
Chad protects is the director and producer of the documentary The pruitt-igoe Myth
It was 3311 storey buildings
And it was part of a larger urban renewal campaign that the city was undergoing in the 19
It was touted as a solute
A cure for the disease it was viewed kind of as a replacement for
Low-rise
Tenement
Housing people who have been living where they literally never saw the
I was supposed to be everything different now
They would have more magnificent views than the richest people in St Louis
High-rise
The private Market housing
Was low-rise it was Federal and therefore you wouldn't have
The creeping influence of slumlords coming in and basically being derelict landowners
It was an opportunity to present where residents with light and air that was really the driving Factor behind food I goes to
Design tall modern buildings would give access to
Fresh breezes
Sun Life
The sensible remedy
Play to the unhealthy conditions in the inner-city slums
Google Play
Hotel Resort at stay with
Plenty of green grass trees Shrubbery and all the works
What happened
Well one day we woke up and was all gone in the Middle St Louis
Call Tyler
But instead a monster was
Create in the film The pruitt-igoe Myth it's made it very clear that the project wasn't just a monster
In the beginning especially it represented hope to thousands of people who never thought they live in a clean
New home
But things went downhill very fast
12033 building
Only 2500 people still linger in the remaining shell
Maintenance dropped off
Elevators in trash
Incinerators broke
Remain broken
Vandalism and crime rates Rose
The one thing you always ask yourself
Cuz why
Why is it like this
Why do I live here
What did I do wrong
I think it created a mindset for
The inhabited
Dead
They weren't. About
That manifested itself
Way to cause more harm to
The vandalism dead
Exist then pruitt-igoe
Environment
Things allowed to do
Deteriorate
People not really
Caring
It's easy to look at pruitt-igoe and think that almost every decision that was made was a
The vandalism that the housing authority to install a bunch of Unbreakable
Designs in the towers
Instead of trident has
Existing
We'll just
I think so they can't beat
Destroy
Everything had to be protected
Light fixtures
No light exposure
Scheels around with mesh metal protecting the bulb
The city made a big deal about
Estandar PR department actually came out and they had the installation of these
New unbreakable lights that were going out
You know they brought in all these people in the Press
The only human reaction to being presented with an Unbreakable
Object is
I am break
The fact that it was in destruct
Made you wanted
Try to destroy it
There was a
Screen
Around the light bulb
They kept you from breaking
But you know kids be kids
Broadway brake
You just put water in it
Throw it up
And the light would get high
Two decades after opening pruitt-igoe
The government gave up
Because they are so desperate
They are willing to try
The Housing Authority blew it up
The Press was invited
It started with three buildings in 1970
The rest follow
The image of the implosion with
St Louis Gateway Arch in the background
Became infamous
The pruitt-igoe myth
Begins here
It was viewed as symbolic
It was kind of viewed as an end of an era
So then several years later Charles jencks writes his book on
Postmodern architecture and he opens his book with
Implosion is the death of modern architecture
Which leads to this Quest
How will know when pruitt-igoe be
If you didn't have that floating in the
You know if it's not blown up and you don't have that image with the arch in the background and it's so point it
I will be discussing. I don't I don't think so
You know I mean if something becomes an icon because it's
Been visually recorded there's something about that building in free fall
That acts is better evidence than anything else for failure
That image was so powerful
So full of emotion
Connecticut usually bu
Step support Mini
Previously held belief
Register
It's about Federal housing
Or modernist architecture
Are you in the
The pores of cell
And tell people who use a constantly as such that's what people think when they think of public housing and
Anything Goes
Large-scale Federal probe Bandits
An architectural failure and here's a building that's being imploded because of his bad architecture
Bad architecture is one of the major cited reasons
4y pruitt-igoe failed
But that actually isn't
A factor that chat Frederick's puts a lot of stock in
Architecture was
La marginal influence if any on food I customize
Perhaps this is an overreaction that I tend to look as far away as I can from the design of the building simply because I see
So many other compelling factors
Infra Digos decline
I don't like to try to take
Should I go out of the city in which it resides and I think mud many of the discussions
Is that people have about pruitt-igoe
I tend to do that they tend to look at what I go as
Something that somehow divorce from the city of St Louis and what I went through in those years
What St Louis went through was it completely unpredictable
Did population decline
You have to remember food Iowa comes out of
The 1949 Housing Act in in 1949
The population of most major cities
Interurban Chlor was Rising
It was Rising relatively rapidly people coming into the cities for jobs from
Rural areas
And so St Louis was undergoing the same process where they just had the crowds and crowds of people coming into the city
And so the idea was well we need to find a place to put all of these new people
In a way that doesn't lead to the kinds of slums that you had
In earlier years going all the way back
The nineteenth-century factory City
The understanding among city planners and City officials was that the population would continue to rise
Show population of about a million
From 800000 from 1950 to 1970 and so over the course of those
20 years there was an expectation that the city would rise
How many 20%
Internship
Population what happened with the exact top
The bottom dropped out of
Population Naz
Population started to move
To Suburban areas
Out of the city
And this process was aided by the exact
Same 1949 Federal Housing Act that offered federally underwritten loans to buy houses
In Suburbia
I really started to see
A population's dip pruitt-igoe was undercut by the very law that created
The point where verify 1980 St Louis had half the population that it did in 1950
And that Trend continues to this day
What happens if you build this massive project to house all these people were coming into the city
And when those people don't come and the people who you attended to
Be letting their move out
All the sudden you have a vacancy
Crisis and that's really what
St Louis during these years
So given that the major architectural or design flaw that chat attributes
Am I the pruitt-igoe was
Sheer scale of the project
It was built so big
And they're just simply weren't enough people to populate it by the 1970
But it's something that is very difficult to predict as well
The scale Dune pruitt-igoe from
Start the high vacancy rate meant that the Housing Authority couldn't collect enough money to pay the main
The money for operating and maintaining the building supposed to come from the incomes of the rents from the
Things began to break
Conditions deteriorate
More people laugh last rent can be collected
Everything just got worse and worse
I mean often like to say that
Pruitt-igoe is
An easy scapegoat
It's high rise
Sending that something in
In are mostly low-rise Society
Is viewed negatively in some circles
It's public housing
Supposed to private Market
Can housing
And it's demographics are
Extraordinary
And almost 100% black
And so
What I like to do when discussing
Pruitt-igoe is to try to like think about a different scenario
And conveniently that scenario happened across the street
Euro to enter pruitt-igoe
In the late 1960
And you were too
Travel Due West
Outer prude
And so you would what you would do as you would cross Jefferson Ave
You cross the street into
The low-rise
Private Market
Housing
That exists across
What you would see would be
Similar levels of poverty
You would see the same
I kind of maintenance issues in those low rise
How did Market Building C with c
The same kinds of vandalism
And oftentimes you'd actually see higher crime rates in the surrounding neighborhoods and you saw pruitt-igoe
And no one really ever talks about those low-rise private Market houses that existed around crude I get with all
How is pruitt-igoe people focus on
The focus on pruitt-igoe is understandable when you see an aerial photograph
St Louis at
The time
The impact of pruitt-igoe
633 building
Footprint that they make in the city
Is Jaws
Enormous
Give me it had very little to do with the fact that pruitt-igoe was public housing very little to do with the fact that it was high-rise
It had almost everything to do with
The decline of the city in which it reside
99% invisible was produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in Sanford
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco and the center for architecture and Design
99percentinvisible is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public phone
Find out more at PRX. Org
The 99% invisible intern his name is Sam Greenspan
Funny more about the show see some pictures of pruitt-igoe and watch the trailer of the pruitt-igoe myth
Throw website it's 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com