99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
The boys and I
I have fixed up
We hope you like it
This is 99% invisible
Imerman
Constraints are good I think I mean
Constraints are healthy I'm not the only person to make this observation
Take 5 News
Two three
My name is Chad Clark
And I'm in the Band Beauty pill is a band I really like from Washington DC their last album the Unseen
Saleable lifestyle was released in 2000
Since then she has serious illness that nearly killed him
So usually it swells and you die
And I didn't I don't think it's entirely accurate to boil this down to cause and effect here
But at the same time
Is practice as a musician
Change dramatically as well
I just kind of became
Dismayed
About putting stuff out I don't think I was even aware that that was happen
If you talk to me like 2 years ago I wouldn't know all the
I know now
But clearly I was resisting
Actively resisting
And because he was sick and making music but not putting out music
People began to wonder
About Chad Clark being perfectionistic reclusive
Two words that have been repeated to me a few times the Brian Wilson fantasy that I like
He's going crazy in a sandbox somewhere and the whole point of what I want to do
Communication
So I will admit that it was a misguided path
Women look like the way things were going to be but
Then Beauty pill got an intriguing invitation
From Artisphere a new multimedia art space in the DC area
Just ask me to
Come down
To see the space
And talked about doing something
Creative
With music
Very open-ended very creative
Kind of
Idea the best kind of invitation
I came down and we walked around the space
Different things
We can do any obvious ideas spring up he could create
Ambient looping music developed
Space or some kind of audio installation
But as they're walking around they came to a room
Varied
Distinctive
Fenestration
And we looked into this black box theater and there's a window that looks down in
Did the theater this thing to detect
And the first will the black box theater look really cool to me
But mostly the window
Wasn't interesting
Because the window looks down and
Is the space and I'm a huge Beatles
And if you just Google Abbey Road Studios
And you will see this design
The famous Beatles Studio has a window that
Looks down a second-floor window it look
Looks down into the sea
It's angle almost exactly like the window at artist
And that
Excited me
Beauty pill record a new album
It's an album that no one that was going to happen
In the black box theater in front
If everyone letting people watch us
Work
All inspired by window
And there you have it
The closest one could ever hope to get
The dancing
Barakatak
They call the projects the immersive ideal
Immersive ideas
Will be accessible invisible
To everyone
And we would
Hopefully lose ourselves in
In the process which is where the title
The ideal weight
How to make music
Serve drop your
4.
They had two weeks there was a deadline
I think there's a way you could view the kids
Strain to the spa
This is a form of
Confinement
But to Chad Demers bidil was
Not about putting himself in a fishbowl and being forced
To perform a task with everyone watching
It was about
Opening up the wall
Inviting people
Into the process
In the studio
You can
Lose Yourself
Entirely and that can be a really narcotic
Can wonderful thing
But it can be easy to forget that the main purpose
This is what you're doing is
Make a piece of music that is
Heard by someone else
Excommunicate
And transmits an idea or a sensation
Ornamotion to someone else
It's easy to lose sight of that
When you're in the
Antiseptic
Closed wall
Environment of a studio
Working in the open air
You never lose sight of that as an object
Removing someone else
As an object
Case in point
The theater / recording studio was set up so people could only observe through the Abbey Road win
Now the reality
Is
We're nice p
And if we saw saw
Standing at the window for
Two or three hours
Watching a
That's work
I don't know it just seems right to invite them down so what I would do is I would wave them down
And I would wave
I'm at the window
And I would say
Come on down
And
We did this
Quite often
Sometimes the people invited into recording area would erupt into Applause
Can you gently one in the studio recording this was one of the manifestations where you could
Can tell people were
On our side or
Investigated wanting it to work
But the other factors.
The crowd begin to guide some of the creative
Process
On the song Steven Antoine gay Chad Clark came into the room without vision
For the song
My original
Demo was
Kind of slow
Disco
Kind of somewhat erotic
Somewhat dark
But
Kind of slow
Too slow to dance
And I thought this was provocative
But you can feel if there was a dance beat
But it was slow down to
The point where you really could
Dance to it
And the rest of the band
Was feeling that it should have
Agresco
Pace
And I was
Pretty ottoman on
Trying to pursue this vision of slow Disco
Who hasn't pursued slow Disco
But when they were recording this
Or something like 12 guests
Also in the room and
I could feel
And the band was trying to honor my vision
I could feel that it wasn't working
I could see the band wasn't on my side
And that I was outnumbered by the band
But I could also feel from
Behind me
I was like this is
I'm the only one in this
Sam's room
There's like 18 people in this room
And I'm the only one that thinks this song should be slow
I think I'm probably wrong
Like it was like this
I think I'm wrong
And
I probably let go of my
Concept
That it should be slow
Sooner I think
Then I would have
Had I not felt the
The presence of
Other people in the room
Cuda spell wasn't working on
And
If we've been working in a studio
I think I probably would have
Eventually acquiesced I do trust the band
But I certainly feel like the
The social presence of others
People
Helped me realize that
That my Approach wasn't
At all
But that's not to say that inviting the crowd in the room even the metaphorical
Cool crowd is the right way to create something
What's a paradox
Because
If Radiohead when they were making kid a
Had allowed
Crowding
While they were working
That crowd might have been
Fleetwood dismayed
But everything they were doing why are you doing this
Your guitar rock band
Why I liked your last record it was great why don't you just do another one of those
The crown doesn't always have the vision
So there are times when you have to knowingly
Push beyond what is socially desirable
That point to arrive at a fresh and worthwhile
Results
So it's complicated
It's not
Just one way or just the other
You can never design the perfect situation for creating radar
It doesn't work that way
But sometimes you have to make some rules
And sometimes you have to decide
The five notes are all it takes
But sometimes the circumstances dictate
That Disco
It's supposed to be fast
It's probably all the time
Actually now that I think about it
Sorry Jen
99% invisible woodspring Suites by me Roman Mars
The same dream
It may possible with support from router
Making a difference
Creativity
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco the American Institute of Architects
Ennis Center for architecture and Design
The program is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public
Ipra
Stop. Org
If I know more about this programme and beautiful you really want to find out more about
What are websites 99% invisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com