99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
You probably all heard that This American Life episode called when patents attack about Innovations
Stifling tech industry patents and patent trolls it's so good
So good together that you should just go listen to it right now
All right
We have to her the tal show but it gives an interesting backdrop to what you're about to
Because it's horrible and egregious as patent enforcement in lawsuits are today they rarely
Results
In Murder but things are different in 1879 that's
Hounded and pursued patent violator struck back
It made it possible
For average working people to afford quality dentures
It's a very historically significant murder I mean anyone who ever
Gets dentures
Indirectly affected by this crime
That's John Marr my name is John Marr I'm the editor and publisher of the fanzine murder can be fun
Before the 1850s Dentures were made at a very hard very painful and very expensive material like gold
Older ivory
They were a luxury item
But the invention of vulcanized
Hard rubber changed everything
It was moldable could be precisely fitted it was relatively cheap
Everyone began making dentures with vulcanite
And these Dentures have been
Overwhelmingly popular
But then in 1864 along disputed patent application originally filed a dozen years earlier and eight
Was awarded and then acquired
Weather Goodyear Dental vulcanite company
He was a company created to collect feezor
Very often Sue dentist
Who already used vulcanite
There are plenty of Dennis to go after
And the person that went after them was named Josiah bacon
The treasurer of the Goodyear Dental vulcanite company
And I'm the Vulcan and Company was trying to collect and cuz I bake it was trying personal
Royalties for their patent
The Goodyear vulcanite company now monopolize the market
Dentists required to buy the Rubber and other Contraptions used to make denture bases from them
And they were heavy taxes and fees associated with all of this
The price just kept going up and up
Josiah bacon
Crisscrossing the country drawing Dennis in jail
Extracting fees fine
Setting up sting operations he's a very busy man
Very enthusiastic about enforcing his Pad
It was reported and disputed that bacon Zeal for enforcing the patent
May have been more his personal mission than that of a good year vulcanite company rig the deal so
He actually personally got the money in
I don't know how much
The details but it sounds like a very unusual Financial arrangement
With the company
Enter Samuel chalfant
Adult
Who made that choice and who didn't pay the Goodyear vulcanite company
For the privilege
And Josiah bacon without to make
An example of him
Josiah bacon had chased Chalfont
AutoZone Delaware
Out of them St Louis
And finally in Tampa
And he was swearing who's going to
Samuel chalfant was completely beaten down by this Relentless Pursuit
And claimed that he went to Josiah bacon the San Francisco hotel room on Easter Sunday 1879
To make peace
Play whatever you could
And just go back to being a simple dentist
However Chalfont
I'm had a gun in his paw
And as he says he argued with bacon bacon
Threaten to send in prison
Man some respect
Chalfont
Pulled a gun and
Has guns that you wave in front of your enemies always do
It went off
Samuel chauffant murdered Josiah Bank
Chalfant was like
Extremely
Set aside in the hotel suite
Waiting for people
Come into caps
Everyone's down and breakfasts
So we slipped out of hotel
And he wondered why the
And took a room in a cheap
Rooming house
Could have laid in bed
A couple days you
Guilty feverish
Distraught
How many forms of energy
You made a statement to the police
He said that
He shot them
Bacon
Accidentally in the police believe he was sincere and thinking that he have to come up with some
Story better than that if it was truly premeditated
However when it came time for trial
The prosecution
Had this man marching in the hotel room of his
Bitterest enemy with a loaded gun in his
Pocket
The consensus was he was very lucky to get off with a 10-year sentence for second-degree murder
We actually had a very good gig in prison he was the the prison Dennis
Yatted office outside the walls
Or I should most importantly he didn't have to work in the jute Mill making burlap sacks
Like most of the other four guys
The only part of the prison uniform he had to wear wear striped trousers his patients who weren't on convict
You could collect fees from
Being in San Quentin he had it pretty good but
Nonetheless he
Just founded
Enormously
Oppressive
Was quoted as saying that he would um
Rihanna
Perdigon to The Gallows
They just be I've locked up
Going to sell for
15 hours
Chalfonte had a female admirer on the outside
Fighting press release by normal legal
But it was alleged
But she also try to get him out of prison
True less than legal
Someone slipped in
Some
Yunnan striped trousers
The railroad ticket some money and some pistols
Bag of laundry and he snuck out with
The crowded visitors I'm taking the boat back
City
And before they noticed
He was gone he was I'm safely ensconced on a Utah boundary
The only reason he
Hot
He disguised himself
The Whispers
But he was a meeting a
Peach water crossing Nevada and the juice
Loosen the gum holding
Reddit
Spotted
Auspicious
He was detained in Nevada he never made it past Winnemucca
Even though he got caught escaping and you later pardoned and only spent 6 years in prison
When you got out near attorney San Francisco and was a very I'm sick
Successful dentist
Until
Be retired shortly
Before the earthquake
But it must have felt kind of weird making vulcanite dentures
Enjoying my research
Guy found a directory professional men
San Francisco from the air
1890s
And there's a half-page in there on him and his talks about his
Location
Experience in serving the
Civil War
But it makes absolutely no mention of rubber dentures
Josiah bacon
Where did Vulcan
But this extreme case of anti patent troll vigilantism or cold-blooded murder of however you want to view it
Did have an effect
The Goodyear vulcanite Company stock
Apparently none of their employees was really young willing to
Take a chance of being shot by a dentist
And it's also the application that
Through this whole Venture Patton was going to
Josiah bacon
Project more than it was Major
Your policy the company
In the patent lapse
Most of the world forgot about Samuel chalfant
But the late 19th century Dental profession learn from their bitter experience and what they considered the vulcanite rubber pad
Reign of Terror
They collectively position themselves so that they could no longer be milked by any profit sharing patent holders
Many years later a similar scheme is put into motion to try to collect royalties for gold crowns
And the Dental Association killed it easily
Without firing a single shot
99% invisible was produces week by me Roman Mars it was based off a story by
Play John Mayer from his fanzine murder can be fun
The Great
Rate by changing fanzine murder can be fun
It's not a website
Paper
Ask your parents
Special thanks to Plastics historian Julie Robinson
Yes there is such thing as a plastic historian
And her name
Is Julia Roberts
This program is made possible with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity it's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in
San Francisco architects in San Francisco and the center for architecture and Design
Is Bruggeman distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public
Bunnamour at PRX. Org
This week and every week I've helped by Superstar intern Sam Greenspan if you see him in the hallway Time Warner back
I'm a cup of coffee I know you're listening to NPR be nice to know
Pretty soon
I think he's going to be our boss
You can find the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars or Venus catch up with us on the website
99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com