99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
Get this idea out of your head
A stamp is not a tiny painting
Somebody might be able to do a great painting
20 by 30 in
But you take that down to one in
By 1 and 1/2 in
And it's a challenge to make it
And Ethel Kessler is just one of a handful of people who take on that challenge
I'm Ethel Kessler responsible for turning out every single stamp issued by the United
It States Postal Service
Each year and I've been doing that
Does Banzai stance that just came out
With the tiny little
Beautiful meticulous detail drawings of trees
Those are hers
In a reporter there is postal service and stamp Enthusiast Julie Shapiro
Picture Flags or the Liberty Bell
Or the word love spelled in a cutesy font
But there are so many other stamps made every year what about those abstract expressionist stamps that were all sorts of awkward so
Are the Muppets that were on a white background and seemed to be bursting out of the envelope
And those new pioneers of industrial design stamps
Oh my goodness and I love the cloud stamps
If you looked at the sheet there laid out in the exact same layers they see
Just in the sky
Every year there are Artful samsara poetic stamps are stamps
Senses of humor
Even surprising stamps
Just that you don't really see those ones you just
See the flag
The bells in the love
Dems take on average a year to a year-and-a-half from conception to execution
I can just tell you that this process is never cease
Basically the art directors
Pull together the stamps once the subject matter has been
A dimension it's a long process
It starts with public suggestions for stamp subject in mail to the US
Yes stamp proposals must be submitted in writing
Visa stamp
The first thing is the subject and that is our other guests his name is Terry McCaffrey my name is
Jeffrey and I recently retired as the manager of stamp development
The US Postal Service
Stamp Services office
Where I was in charge of
My designing all the postage stamps
Grr
50000 suggestions
Is a year
That
Come in from the America
Public
Basically all of those
Subject
Suggestions
Have to be gone through and have to be reviewed
By a committee
The committee is called the citizens stamp advisory committee
For short csac
And that committee
Serves the Postmaster General
As you might imagine sesac has received some pretty
The far-out suggestions over the years
We've received requests for hate stamps
To combat the love stamps that we should
Every year
One for the devil one for the passing of
Great American outhouse
But luckily there are rules that help guide the committee and choosing the stamps up
About a dozen Rolls by primarily feature Americans anniversary significant contributions
Dead Presidents usually get a stamp 50th anniversary of historical events
Statehood
No repeats within 50 years accepting National symbols and holidays of University founding
No disasters commemorated
Keep away from religion of course
Christmas and there been a few people such as Mother Teresa but we're really honoring her for her humanitarian
Not for her religious orders of religion
And this one is interesting themes of widespread appeal that reflect the USA's inclusiveness in other words
Something everyone will love
To be bold and controversial is not what stamp makers are going for what you think you could do critically to
Although you know inclusive this itself could be viewed as a radical notion this on
But there's one more big roles
I'll get to that in a minute
The citizens stamp advisory committee follows the
Trolls pics the subject
Friends and by the Postmaster General you know the grand poobah of the u.s.
If he's not in favor of a stamp
It isn't going anywhere
But I think he
He usually defers to
And assigns them to the art director
And then the art directors follow their own rules
And the number one thing
Keep in mind around the stamp Services office courtesy one of the art directors Howard Payne was Tookie
Keep it simple and look at it
At stamp size
But the art directors also consider a few other
Keeping a bright and colorful and
Engaging and making the image
Something that people will want to put on their envelopes
What's the feeling you want to evoke what emotions do you want to evoke the social awareness stamps this week
Purdue them are the most difficult stamps
Reduce because you have to
Create an abstract concept and sell it to them
Public wildly successful in this
Both Terry and Ethel sided independently
The first stamp that I have to mention your card for many reasons
It also happened to be the first stamp that was issued that I
Are corrected
Was a breast cancer stamp
Not only is it a
Great graphic design and illustration
But it also is a fabulous message stamp
And that stamp was also the first time in the country
That the US did a stamp that raise money
For cause
In addition
The post
Because you pay an extra $0.08 on the
Average
To purchase
Which one of the stand
Zach stamp
Which went on sale in 1990
And it's still on sale
After all these years
And it's raised
About 70
3 million
For brest
Just looking at the stamp
From the lower left to the upper right
It goes from dark colors
Into bright colors
Layered with
A line drawing of
The Goddess Diana
Reaching over her shoulder
To reach
Or an arrow in your quiver
Which also has an ingenious resemblance to the line drawing cartoons from those doctors office pamphlets that
Explain how to give a self breast exam
Where are one beer
Breast would have been there
They have removed that and
Put in a slogan
Panda fight
Find a cure
It was a brilliant design
But not all social awareness stamps are wildly
I think one of the biggest examples of a stamp gone wrong as many years ago before I join the group there was a stamp
Stamp Out alcoholism
But unfortunately it was one of the biggest failures we ever had because
When the message
It was sent to
Another person that person received it and
Got the impression that the sender was saying you're an alcoholic
You need help
And I had a phone that a friend service
That's tempting
Not work
A technology pulls us deeper into electronic correspondence and away from snail mail
By the way the USPS
Has lost billions
The dollars
But it's trying to keep
Keep up and stay relevant
To that end in the fall of 2011 they changed one of the biggest rules governing stamp subject selection
It used to be that
First you have to be dead longer
To be honest app
And there were lots of reasons for that
In the beginning it was they have to be dead 10 years
They shifted that.
The five
And as most people know
They've just shifted that to even living people can be on
Stamps
Now you have to start looking and saying
Who's the first one
I had a feeling Terry knew the answer to that one
Yes I do
But I'm not at Liberty to say
It will not be Lady Gaga
Seat when the USPS change the deceased
Subject rule to allow living people on stamps
They asked the public to nominate someone for the first living Sam
Tragically nominations were accepted online
No stamps required
And besides Bob Dylan at the time living Steve Jobs
Lady Gaga was right there near the top of the list
Well you get what you ask for
Not that Lady Gaga's bad II
I love her music
Aprima chargepoint around
Miss open call for the first living person I see I can view it as kind of a gimmick to get people excited about
The post office in
Get Lady Gaga fans to buy stamps
It will not be Lady Gaga
For the people who design stamps
Sure they want you to buy it
But when you talk to them immediately you know
It's so much more to it to them in the
SFO puts it
Story of America
In pictures
You work on these things
So
Long
And put so much into
Heart and soul
That
Feel like in the end it has to be right
It's for the American public we vets
You know that's who we're doing this for
And
I just wanted to be right
It's something that touches every person in your
United States and its
Product
That I helped
Tamia
Wonderful
Undertow been part of
LPS
$0.45
The current rate for a first class stamp
Is an entirely reasonable amount
Tiny work of art that escorts your letter all the way across the country
I completely agree for $0.45
I wouldn't take your letter
Stairs
I'm going there anyway
Selection
Postal workers cancelling stamps
At the University of Ghana post
99% invisible with produce this week by Julie Shapiro
Artistic director of the Third Coast International audio Festival
Committee
Taken from this
Little radio Friday
And believe me I ask how to do it
I got some awards to win apparently it's not going to happen anytime soon but I'm working on it
Lunar making a difference with creativity it's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in Tampa
Sysco in the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Are distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public more at PRX. Org
This week and every week I'm aided and abetted by Sam Greenspan
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but you can always tell me what your favorite stamp is
And who you look to see on the first living person stamp
And 99percentinvisible
. org
Everyone I have one more message
If you're new here
Go ahead and download all the old episodes in trimount because it all short tall evergreen and I think you'll like
Also I want to thank everyone for
All the Twitter mentions
And Facebook sharing and ratings and reviews on iTunes there so amazing you are the entirety of
Give my marketing department so
I really need you no pressure
But I I just appreciate everything you've done so far so thanks so much
And dumb
All right I'm getting dangerously close down a thousand ratings on iTunes
Purdue does this independently at night in his bedroom I think that that is amazing
So that I really played this before thank you so much for being so kind
And I'll keep making episodes
Thanks
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast.,