99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
Have this habit
Walking into any
Door if it's unlocked
Actually
Does me well here in Macau
Capital because
You start poking around
Going into doors and you find the coolest
You have to appreciate the Moxy of someone who can wander around the Federal Building open up a random door and announce to whoever's on the other side
Hello
Hi I'm Andrea Seabrook with NPR you didn't catch that that's in VR Congressional correspondent Andrea Seabrook
Reporter
Poking around looking it
Secret
Things
I am so in love with Andrea Seabrook right now
Woman on the other side of the door tells Andrea that she needs to leave and that walking into random doors in the basement of the US Capitol building
Is not what she supposed to be doing
And that's 99percentinvisible Zone Sam Greenspan
He went with Andrea to the Capitol Building
I'm so jealous pain right now
That's not what we're supposed to be doing
I don't care what they think I'm supposed to be doing
I'm here
The governor of the United States
Frankly I see this is part of it
Even if you try to set aside its role as the Hub of Western democracy the Capitol building itself just the building
Is an overwhelming structure
6000 people who work in this complex
That's including the staffers though not including the politicians I mean it
A huge City and it has one
Function
Can call it a function
And that is running low
Legislative branch government
You know riding the bills and cleaning the toilet
As if we could tell the difference and my rights
The capital is known for its Grandeur of the Rotunda Statuary Hall the Crypt the marble staircases as places
Unbelievably ornamental
The walls upstairs kept gorgeous freezes you know with birds and squirrels and gorgeous
Gorgeous
Lilting beautiful paint work
And that's all the stuff we're supposed to say
But when you're an inveterate door knob Turner and Snoop like Andrea Seabrook
You also get to know the capital below the surface literally
The basement
Down here there's a whole bunch of Engineers Unilock HVAC engineers in
Blue uniforms it's a like you know Joe on them
The purpose of the building the business of government trickles down to these lower levels
The members of the House
Republican caucus and sometimes a Democrat meet in the basement
For there should have closed or secret strategy sessions and
It's a really good place to
Place to get
Tip from
Members that you know about what's going on
The main reason we're here is to see a little bit of the architectural Grandeur that is trickled down here to
PLS checking to be engineers
School is dumb
Andrea is leading me through the serpentine route of Ali's doorways and really in the oh my gosh
Here we are it's amazing and then there's these
Bathtub
It's amazing
Beautiful
Marble bathtubs with marble steps that lead up to them and Brass fitting
Bathtub
Just to describe it a little bit it's
It's sort of o
White Ivory marble that has this luster
It reminds me of the Venus de Milo or something
Trying to close a little bit and it's got very faint
Black beans in it and it's just
Gorgeous
The Curves in it are so
Gentle and continuous the tubs possess the room itself is the exact opposite
This place was supposed to cool off Senators now it cools
And he eats the entire Capitol building stairs
Big HVAC equipment in
Computer servers and large steel cabinets
Containing god-knows-what even though the bathtubs a little the sink and toilet were here first
They're the ones that seem out of place
The bathtubs were installed around 1860
During the expansion of the capital
DC is known for its swampy Somers and Legend has it that Senators could be banished from the chamber
If they were too smelly
It still reeks but yeah back that it was less figurative
And most people the time even politicians
Didn't have indoor plumbing come
So Congress needed a place where the politicians could go and wash up
Andrea reads from an informational card beside the tub
Okay here we go
Each bathtub and I am standing in one right now
Was carved in Italy
From a single block
Of carrara marble
3 bathtubs were shipped from Genoa Italy in July 1859
Unreached Baltimore in November of that year
July to November
The other three were shipped from Leghorn Italy
In September of 1859 and arrived in New York in January of 1860
The precise date for the bathtubs arrival and installation at the capitol or uncertain but the Senate bathing room is no
Don't have been in operation as of
February 23rd 1860
Each of the six tubs cost 90 bucks in eighteen
Which is around $2,500 up
Peace today
And that was justified
You got to figure out shipping from Italy
Receive them at the Port of Baltimore transport them to Capitol Hill and then you had a
Build a bathing facilities suitable to a senator
An oak wood paneling
Plaster
Cornices Minton tile egg and dart molding
Of the Six Original tubs
Only two are left
And what has a piece of
Plywood over at that props up some
Padlock
Steel mystery box
It was decommissioned years ago
This place is a total Collision of Heroes
Not just old vs new and I know that
Just a little bit ago
We were considering the Capitol Building as just a building
It's impossible to look at this room and not see a metaphorical debate right here in the basement
We are having this great debate in our country whether you're in the Tea Party or the Occupy Movement
Both share the same concern about who the government is
And
But I think the politicians
Have tried really hard
To make it look as if the government is for the people and not
The gorgeously appointed bathers of the world
For example when Newt Gingrich took over the house speakership in 1995 after
You know a giant sweep of the 94 elections
They found that
There were
Buckets of ice
Still being delivered to every
Single
Member of Congress has office even though they all had refrigerators with ice makers it was back from the top
Time when you had to buy I separately in
Today should have shut down all that stuff at the same time
They got rid of the house historian
Lady funded
All of these things they thought of as
Luxuries
And
They got rid of a lot of
The funding for saving things like this
Is Andrea puts at the spending versus austerity question is really just the modern form of the quintessential
American question of government
Which is
How much government should exist
What is it there to do
And
At one point about a hundred and forty some-odd years ago
There was this idea of
The government
Being an important institution one that would have
Gorgeously appointed baths
And now
We're sitting in a
Boiler room and
Beautiful Minton tile has been painted over with industrial gray paint
And
The walls are
Our kind of dirty and it's loud and
And
There's no way to pay homage to it anymore it's
Talked in a corner and dirty
And there's a roach trap on the floor
Sparkles a little bit if it's
A little bit clean master
Are bluegill persuasion they would advocate for the installation of luxurious $3,000 marble bathtubs for senators
As lovely as a baby bathtubs.
Ornate marble bathtubs are already there
What represents the people know
It's likely not going to be restored know unless we had some
Resurgence in respect for the government
Give it $500,000 to be crazy just to restore this area and maybe
A lot more than that actually come to think of how much you did
I don't know
Going to go open some doors
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan poem so jealous of any totally fine
I'm in my house
Trips around the Capitol building with Andrea Seabrook
You're dead to me
Envy rolling bars with support from lunar of making a difference with creativity it's a project of kalw
91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco by PRX the public radio exchange making public
Black radio more public
Fprx. Org
You can find the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
Or do you just catch up with us on the website 99% invisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden 2 playlist
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com