99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the US there called line
In Canada are called lineup
Sometimes and I was once
Interviews live on Canadian national
Radio and they started talking about whine up
We had a conversation about the police for 5 minutes until I realized what they were talking about
But pretty much everywhere else
It's known
As a q
That's Benjamin Walker
He's obsessed with Hughes
Keep sending me emails with links to YouTube videos
Of queues you have
Ecology students filming their surreptitious Q experiments
You have Asian road rage videos
You've got people filming fights that break out and accused
So understand that I'm not getting out of it
I'd like to call YouTube
Q hole
And when I found this lecture by dr. Q eye immediately
Made an appointment
To go and see you
And the reason I'm a professor at MIT
And I guess my nickname is Doctor Q
Dick Larson
Is aqi theorist
Just about every day we experience
Queuing
In some aspect of Our Lives
Dick Larson studies the mathematical and psychological models
Of cueing systems
Unfortunately
The dolphin times too many Q's
On a day-to-day basis
Dr. Q's able to put his Professional Knowledge to work
Everywhere he goes
I have my own ways
Supermarkets particular if you got to go to the deli counter and get a number
And then you start walking around and doing the regular shopping and you watch all the numbers
And then as soon as it gets close to yours then you go back
So that's a
Q that's been avoided because it's a queue within a q
Little ideas
Like this dr. Q
Hates waiting in line as much as
You and I do but he does respect
The well design
The Machiavellian
Spirits of cute design are people at Disney World in the Disney property
They have mastered the idea
That people can be happy waiting 40 minutes in line for a 4 minute ride I think
It's fantastic
Disney is very serious
About cutest
They employ about 18 or so operation
Researchers
Imagineers
These imagineers have mastered
The golden rules
Q design the first is to keep your customers entertained while I wait in line
Their guests
Think that the amusement has started before they actually sit in the ride
Don't have video screens along the Q route with
Games and if the lines are getting really ugly a park manager will
Saint Denis
Sweaty man
Full body
Yeah it so they're entertained and they're amused while they're waiting in line
The second rule
Manage expectation
Always manage your expectations such that you'll deliver
Butler performance
You say so
Prince and sip the wine says
You can anticipate 45-minute wait for
If the line is out
To this point
But really it might be only 35
So therefore if you
Look at your watch
In 35 minutes to get it on the line and then the dad and the mom and the
Go to kids at Hayward 10 minutes ahead of schedule
That's great you waited 35 minutes and you say we just save 10 minutes because we thought we're going to have to wait
For 45 minutes
Q series about a hundred years old now
But it wasn't until the 1950s.
Set the profession
Really came into its own after World War II they were saved
I burst of economic
Activity log
More high-rise
Buildings
High-rise hotels and offices and all of a sudden
Owners of these buildings are getting
Complaints about rush hour delays for elevators
In those days of course they didn't have microprocessors to
Go to optimized
The movement of the elevators been available babies actually had humans as operators
Pilots
The professor University of Pennsylvania sent one of his research age to New York City to check out these complaints about elevator delays
And indeed he found out that there were rush hours for elevator like 8 to 9 in the morning or 5 to 6 at night
Just like rush hour for cars
So is the traditional engineering approach
Dynamite this building it start over again with twice as many Elevator Shaft because you've got more demand than you have capacity
When is rush hours
Am I experienced Engineers are a lot more crafty than that but let's just go with it
But then in our stroke of Genius
He said maybe the
Problem is frame the wrong way maybe the problem isn't the 90 seconds of wait for the elevators
Maybe the problem is the complaints about the noise
If we can reduce the complaints substantially maybe we'll solve the problem and then another stroke of Genius
What if you give somebody a distraction and diversion
Let's try floor-to-ceiling mirror
Next to all the elevators in an experimental build
They got the money with the mirrors in
Watch for a month and guess what
The complaints drop to near-zero
Men who are wearing ties could have just their ties that women could make sure their hair was organized okay or vice versa
Sometimes
Men and women treatment center
The flirt occasionally through the reflection I guess it's less provocative the night I contact the complaints dropped in their zero problem solved
The statistical dwai
Unchanged
Ingenious
Mirrors won't work at McDonald's are Whole Foods though many fast food restaurants and most grocery stores use parallel
Accuse what does a bunch of open lanes and you're forced to pick one and stick with it
The one that's you could be going faster for any number of reasons and it's
Totally frustrating
Are you staying your line
And you play the hand you're dealt
But there's another way to do it
A single Serpentine line
That feeds all of the open Regice
It's first come first
Serve
It's a cute design for equality
Fairness
And when there's one line both blatant and inadvertent
Queue jumping
Is minimize
We call them slips and skips
An American company
They used to
Pride themselves
On designing these more egalitarian queues
Wendy's is very proud that they're the first ones
Fast food that had the single Serpentine line American Airlines
Is Ray proud they claimed that there was a
The first ones I've seen
Single serving wine in airport solo
British Air argues with them they say
Well they they've got
BCB Bank in New York
Chemical Bank
And they used to claim that they were the
Still have that
And their Bank lobbies
That's what is a certain Pride
To getting rid of
It is written line jumping by
Does skips do I have
But today
Cute design
Is changing
More and more we're encountering cues that are designed so that
Different levels of service can be provided to
Two different groups of people
Priority queues and given certain people priorities over others
You can see it in
Amusements like
Like Disney but more seriously
It occurs in some life-and-death situation
Like
Queuing for organ donation
My hypothesis
Is that this design change is connected to the
Cure
It's becoming more and more commonplace
And available to watch for free on YouTube
And I also believe that understanding this new Q Theory
Will better help us understand the enemy
Quality Inn disparity
It's on the rise in this
Why should somebody with a lot of frequent flyer miles
Automatically bumped up
The first class
Cuz I found out I recently was
Hudson flights
And therefore have to escape
The TSA q44 in airport
And I feel a little bit guilty about that
And it just yesterday I did this twice
And and I felt a little guilty because they're like 30 people in line and I went right to the front of it
Why is this fair just because I flywheel but want more than the others do
I think your question is is a deep one and requires some more
More thought in the sky
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Benjamin Walker and me Roman Mars got to tell you about Benjamin Walker again
Too much information from WFMU
Understand that will make your life better
This is a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco and the American hits
Do architects in San Francisco
This program is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public find out more
IPR x.org
This week and every week I'm aided and abetted by Sam Greenspan working all the way over in Baltimore Maryland Home of the
The third-best city flag in the country
Look it up
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
Going to catch up with us and tell us your cute stories
At 90% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
The movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech
Wait machine even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com