99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If you've ever seen an episode of the TV show The West Wing
You probably know what
Its trademark seeds
The walkie-talkie
You're going to this meeting
Ww168 near me
I don't even know where I am right now I'm working on this side
Filled with bees
Do staffers the White House walkthrough
The Halls
Talking about some government policy or
Plot point
The dialogue isn't Messi
Sara Lee exciting on its own
But at a little motion and you've got some compelling freaking television
From now on
Maybe our only hope
I don't know why they made the Oval Office a special shape
But if you want to view episodes you might notice some
The characters almost never look at each other
They mostly look straight ahead is a good reason for this location
We use our eyes to navigate
We use our ears to listen
But that doesn't work if your deaf
That's our reporter today Tom dries
He went to gallaudet University in Washington DC to talk to a researcher
And Robert service
Gallaudet is the only University in the world designed entirely for the Deaf
And hard-of-hearing
Robert is death himself and he's been looking into this question of how deaf people walk in
Inside
He told me about his latest pics
So I'm doing at the
Comparative study between people who are speaking walking along H Street
Yeah that's actually the voice of Carolyn wrestler
She's an interpreter I
Gary Oldman
So I'm doing it
Comparative study between people who are speaking walking along H Street
And walking together speaking to one another so to hearing dyads with the same kind of
Camera on their head
And then to death
Dietitian
Fancy term in sociology for a pair of people
So Robert put cameras on these two pairs of
People hearing and deaf
He had them walk down the street
And he did this
So we could put
Precisely monitor whooped
People look at when they walk
Can tok
Verses when they walk in sign
You sound very clear differences
Securing people look straight ahead the whole time they were walking
You might see just a few
It's very rare seconds when the person would look at the other
Person who they were walking beside and speaking
If they wouldn't ever make eye contact when we look at the
Pause what's up people there was a continuous maintained icon
So because American sign language is a visual language
It requires constant
Eye contact
But maintain eye contact also mean
You can't pay full attention
Zenni Optical
Close up ahead and that's a problem if your walk
I mean I guess if you can think about yourself as a person you can hear
If you weren't looking at the road as you were driving and looking at your passenger it was your driving down the road you can imagine how difficult
That might be the mediator
Your car down the road will the same kind of things happen
Deaf people but we watch out for one another
For walking and signing to work the people holding a conversation need to keep an eye out for optical
But it's not like deaf people make a deal at the beginning of a conversation
You talk I'll be the lookout
When deaf people look at one another there's an agreement and internal agreement unspoken agreement that's understood between the two
Conversing
That was like the people
When you're in a conversation you're in a kind of dance
We are not
Discussing what's happening between each other
But you just sort of know what the neck
Move should be
That's exactly it
When you're dancing you kind of work with your partner in the way they breathe the way they move their body and you respond accordingly the same thing
Conversation
When they're designing buildings post-hearing Architects are not thinking about providing a venue
For this dance
Robert says a lot of spaces are too narrow and confining for a good cover
There's this sense that
Buildings were not designed in such a way that they accommodate def
People so how does that feel I guess
The best way to say that is like weave
Feel like sardines
You know like we're all lined up one after the next
Converse in that way in
There's no he's in Arkham
Haitian actually also true of many buildings at gallaudet University
Even though it's dedicated to teaching the deaf and hard-of-hearing
It's a relatively old campus a lot of buildings were built in the mid-1800s
And it looks like a typical Northeastern liberal arts college
But there are signs
The school is different than your West
Senior Amherst
Mister whatever take for example the doorbells on campus
Nowadays people use lights you can flick a light switch and let somebody know that you're at the door but in the 1800
Dreads before electric light that use the vibration
The university has a display of an old doorbell it's about 4 feet high with a round metal handle attached to a chain
And at the other end of that chain is a lead weight
It arrived at the door
And you'd simply pull the chain
With that
Hit to the floor
When we're listening to the chain
But that hit to the floor
You'd meaning
Italy get it coming
The tunsel Bauman
He's now the director of design and planning at gallaudet Bauman is not dead
And in this case that is his
And this was one of the really cool but kind of anachronistic Innovations at gallaudet
Several years ago the university realize that some of its standards of architecture and innovation
At slipped
So the ass handle to help lead a group
Project that would rethink the campus design with deaf people in mind
They called the projects
Death space
Death space really
Started at the beginning of time whenever there
Are deaf people there is
This idea of death space
Deaf people have sensibilities of adapting their world tour their way of being
The campus took those ideas and poured them into the design of a new building
Call the Sorenson language and communication
But everyone calls it the SLCC
It was built in 2008
And also working on a new door
Hansel Bauman showed me around
And I saw that there are a lot of little innovation
Some that come to mind immediately like the type of doors
If you're walking and signing a normal door will stop your conversation cold
United sweet
Just passed through two sliding doors
The sliding doors are purposely designed to allow people to continue
A signed conversation as they enter the building so you don't stop
Open the door
Start the conversation again
And then there are more subtle changes
One of the big Ideas behind if space is avoiding eye strain
That's because when you communicate all day with your eyes it's
Easy to get tired
So if you have bad lighting
Conditions for example which is backlighting glare
High contrast between dark spaces
And white spaces
Air conditions in the environment which individually vibrate
Like if you have horizontal lines and
For the blind
You'll start getting vibration
All those annoyances in of themselves
May not be so bad but taken together over the time of a day
It's beginning of eye strain
And I strain really wears people out
Basically
I've actually noticed that myself like when I look at horizontal blinds and get that sort of eye vibration
And I thought I was just
Weird I don't think you're weird Tom
So the Sorenson building avoids those traps
It has enormous windows in a lot of diffuse light to reduce Shadows while you have some direct light coming on
It's still
Can filled with this diffuse quality of life
There's really not a lot of Shadows on the
Face
There's not a lot of distraction on surfaces behind us
And when we walked by a classroom Hanzo pointed inside at the color scheme
The color of the blue classroom that's a color we've been experimenting with his is a good
Contrast the range of skin tones
You can so clearly see
Sign language in there in that room better when you say you can the next door
Not all of the changes worked
In the building's design they decided to round off sharp corners
That's because if you can't hear footsteps from around the corner
A lot of times you won't know someone's coming at all
If people bump into each other
So they rounded off these
Again a lesson learned we didn't we realize
Two people now hug that
Curved corner like a race car
Can you still kind of have that problem
So our strategy now is to create glass corners
It allow you to kind of see through the corner but it still extend that.
Time
I think you have the
Before you get to
The building is definitely Pleasant to look at
The color scheme is nice the lightest pleasing
But as someone who can hear
Probably would not have noticed a lot of these little changes if
Hanzo hadn't pointed them out
But after walking around with Hanzo the most striking thing about the building was the level of
Thoughtfulness
Everything in the building seems to have a specific thought behind it
Chairs are on Wheels so you can constantly rearrange them in circles
And they made benches out of wood
Because you can feel vibrations more easily Through the Wood
And they try to
Strategically place air conditioning units
So they don't make as much noise
That's because it turns out that hearing aids can pick up that sound
A really jarring way
And for honzel working on deafspace Hazmat
Becoming sensitive
To arrange of issues that you never thought of before
I think
The
The window that
The death experience
First architect
Is to provide us with a new kind of awareness around
What's working and what's not working
In a row
That we might accept
Everyday is
Just kind of our condition
We're not aware of it
It's not
In front of us in a way that we can
Name
What's the aggravation in the room where the environment
Strasser
We don't have a way to recognize
I think it's part of everyday death
Experience
That's why everyone involved in the death Space Project says it is not just
For deaf people
Fundamentally this is about Universal
Designing to the widest range of people
Possible with a variety of a
Because
Not only is it more inclusive
The monster we better design
Regardless of
When oxo and smart design collaborated on make
Potato peeler for people with
Arthritis
They created a nuclear with an ergonomic
Bat
Black analysts turn out to be better for everyone
Now you see that application
Designing for the Deaf
Maybe more subtle but if we mitigate eye strain
Hearing aid interference
Air conditioners
There's no telling how much better everyone's
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Tom Dreisbach
Little
Alchemy Roman Mars
We are project of kalw 91.7
17 local public radio in Tampa
An American in
Q Market
The show is distributed by PRX
Public Radio
Change making
Public radio more public
Mourad PRX. Org
Sam Greenspan is our Charm City producer at Large
You can find a show and like
The show on face
Like tweet
@roman Mars
But you can always catch up
But that's on the website
99% invisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
A movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com