99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
Imerman
Here's here's the
The Baltimore city county line
Weapons in the Arsenal
Alphabetical
Armrest
Benches
Blood relative chords
Blockbuster
Bouncer
I think cities are great
Inactivity and diversity
Go to any City and it's pretty clear a place can be the first
Without really being injured
Cities exist to bring people together but cities can also keep people apart
What's Daniel do yoga
And I am an urban planner
I have a company in New York called interboro partners
Over the last few years Daniel and his two colleagues at interboro partners
Theodore and Tobias armbrust
And the three of us
I'm working on this project for number years called the Arsenal of exclusion and inclusion
This Arsenal is a catalog of stuff inside a city will be called weapons
Concierge
Expulsive zoning
Fire hydrant
Food truck horn
That architects-planners policymakers developers Etc used either bring people together or keep people apart
Open the city or closed
City or increase access to space to restrict people's access
Number waste
Stork preservation
Weapons ranging from
No loitering signs
Two big things like housing vouchers and it
Exclusionary zoning
And all that kind of
Today we're only going to focus on the Arsenal of Acts
The weapons that
People apart
Arsenal
In the city of Baltimore a place Daniel yoga truly loves
Maryland Institute College of Art
So I have a
A strong connection with
Baltimore
It's dog
A city that I
Love and admire very much
It's a wonderful place
But it's a city that has been honing its arsenal of exclusion
For decades
Baltimore was once to be invisible while building industry with Detroit was
To the automotive industry
Innovative Workshop
Creative minds work to think up and vent test out and ultimately export methods of it
Conclusion
Are producer and resin baltimorean Sam Greenspan went to look at some of charm cities exclusive offering
Before we go
Where we going to go and what we're doing
How to get there
Give me a second
Dandy yoga and I are driving north on Greenmount Avenue in East Baltimore
I can't think of Green Mountain North 33rd to Cold Spring
As a kind of Museum of of exclusion on Greenmount Avenue North of 30
It's clear that Greenmount Avenue is a dividing line but
Between rich and poor and black and white but what's not immediately obvious
Is why
Just to give you a sense
As we drive north on Greenmount to our right
Eastside is Waverly Waverly is lower-income and around 80%
16% of a bachelor's degree
Median income is $40,000 and on the other side
On the west side or left
What is oakenshaw and then Guildford
Well to the north of that
A really aswan area buffered by a middle-income
Only about seven percent
Can 75% have a bachelor's degree in the median income is $75,000
And then you'll be okay as view it's not the wide Greenmount Avenue that keeps these neighborhoods apart
Total and invisible
Get totally intentional
The teepees neighborhood sepehr
Demographically The Divide is very strict
And severe you can just see all these physical measures that
Deployed
To keep people from getting from one side
To the other Crossing Greenmount on foot is annoying
To crosswalks in that 1.25 Mile Stretch but what's more interesting is when we talk about the grid
Greenmount is where the grid end
The grid is there in Waverly on the east side
Notice that on the right
There's the grid is 37th Street 38th Street
We can make a right into Waverly no problem but on our left there's no grit right it stops to notice we're heading North now
If we try to make a left we're going to be confronted with
Dead End Street Ballard
If they're like these security poles that you can stick in the ground
Oh here's a wall right there's this long row of middle-income houses on the Westside
What kind of a buffer against the
Really wealthy Guildford stuff
Just behind
Almost all of the roads dead and the houses and the few street that do go through
Are mostly one-way streets coming the opposite direction
Outon
Greenmount is no way for us to
Baguette
Left into open shop or Guilford
There has to be some way to get into the neighborhood
Well there is but on Guilford Eastside you really have to go out of your way to find a street that will let you in
Tomorrow in Guilford finally
And then once you're inside you'll notice two things
The houses are super nice
And the roads are super weird
The roads are winding
And they feel disproportionately small
Next to these houses giant lawn and you need a permit to park
Another interesting
Residential parking permit
Residential parking
Case you're wondering you do not need a permit
Spark in the less affluent Waverly neighborhood
But back to Guilford the weirdest thing about these roads is that it's hard to know what direction
And could you tell if you snore
Westar South Philly how to tell right I would imagine we're actually going east
Greenmount Avenue
Super Outsiders and we don't know our way around Guilford we were shunted out of the neighborhood on a one-way Street
This is one of the one-way streets heading out of the neighborhood I got shall we really
Y'all got out back to remount and I thought we were going through it
These physical barriers in the Arsenal of exclusion grids and one-way streets are not that big a deal they're not that
Hard to overcome
But their placement has meaning because really matter that you can make a left turn into
Guilford wood would this be a more Equitable City
If we could make that left turn
Probably not right away
Is Morrison boxing
Right at this place where this demographic
Divided dish
Just rendered very
Physically in space
But it's worth noting that other weapons in the Arsenal of exclusion that once existed here in Guilford are now it illegal
Like restrictive housing Covenants
Restrictive housing Covenant
Tioga says that this neighborhood actually pioneered the use of segregation is covenant
Housing Deeds that restricted occupancy
Do only white
This wasn't illegal until 1968
You can point these Guerrilla street is being an emblem of the racial segregation that still exist in Baltimore
What is interesting to speculate what the neighborhood would be like if he's exclusionary measures warrant in place
Neighborhood been built on a grid
Upper middle class white people living here probably would have flooded the suburbs
In the seventies eighties right
Given that there are
Rich white people
Still living here within the city limits paying
City taxes
Is it worse than just having all the rich white people live in
Adams County
It's a really good question then the trick is to try to develop neighborhood
That's not a zero-sum game
Where one party loses in
Another party game
And that is interboro Partners next project
Green development solutions that are not zero-sum games
It all starts with labeling and categorizing the weapons in the Arsenal of exclusion
And inclusion
So we can figure out how to create cities that are more open
Everybody
Is linode
Most of the weapons in the Arsenal of exclusion create barriers
They're hard to see because they are subtle
Nondescript
Except when they're not
Here's here's the
The Baltimore City
Daniel cat exams the former side of Hollander Ridge it was a lower income housing project the way out on the city
County Line
It has since been torn down but one artifact of the project Remains The Rosedale Community up their Lobby to
8ft tall
Spiked
Wrought iron fence
Around the perimeter of Hollander Ridge
Are the separated from their Community with send was predominately white suburban community
It's like a gated community traded from the outside
The really strange and unfortunate
I think it's funny
The spikes are actually pointing
The other direction
So I guess you could you could go over but you couldn't
Right
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars with help from sky
Goldberg
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco in the American Institute of Architects in
99% invisible is distributed by PRX
The public radio exchange making public radio more public
A tiara
Support for 99% invisible and provided in part by tiny letter
Email for people with something to say
My boy Carver always has something to say
What you have to say Carver
Dog kennels
40w lava every year
Guardian lava
It's not that close to us so it doesn't
Tell us
It only kill the people
Chat live really close to it
Just tell the people who closed in it
Pei Wei
Bellevue houses
So did they don't get
Kid vitacup volcano
Now that's a reason to send a newsletter
Maybe even a phone a phone call
Tinyletter the simplest way to send an email newsletter
Tinyletter. Com
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
You can always catch up with us and look at more weapons in the Arsenal of exclusion
And 99% invisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast.,