99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The thing about being wrong is that before you know you're wrong
It feels exactly
Like being right finger that we were wrong
We wouldn't be wrong nobody's committing intentionally to a false belief
About the world
If they are they're not wrong they're deliberately lying
Even during the construction of the original Tacoma Narrows Bridge which was to become the third longest suspension bridge in the world
It seemed like something was wrong
Willy's in hindsight it seems like it should have felt that way
But that's not
Albion wrong work
If you grow up like I did watching the Warner Brothers
Cartoons this is Kathryn Schulz author of being wrong adventures in the margin of error
Moment
Where the roadrunners dashing off the cliff and the coyote is following him in the Roadrunner can fly
There's this great moment where he's run off the cliff but he does not yet realize that
You know he'd there's no Solid Ground Underneath Him and
The moment when we were wrong about something
But before we realized it is like that
We think
That
I believe
Is Rock Solid we think we have you know all of the facts in the world will stirring up
We feel like our God suspension
Bridge is not going to collapse
Down and realized
I know it sounds crazy but even during its construction the deck of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge
We go up and down by several feet
With the slightest Breeze
Construction workers on the Spanish food on Lemon wedges
The stop-motion
Book instruction continued
Because the bridge have been designed specifically to withstand winds up to 120 miles per hour
To everyone
Thought everything
Would be fine
Well almost everyone
The original Tacoma Narrows Bridge designed by Clark Eldridge was pretty conventional for suspension bridge
It was later Modified by Leon moiseff
To be Slimmer more elegant
The most notable change was the 25-foot
Lattice of stiffening trusses underneath the bridge on the original drawings
Replace
With an 8-foot solid steel plate girder
The new solid gutter along the side and wasn't design
Made for a much lighter
Slimmer and more flexible Bridge
It also got the wind like a sail
But they didn't know that
Moises design was also 2/3 the price of the original Eldridge design
And that fact
Ultimately won the day
Eldridge and other state Engineers were said to a protest in
But it didn't matter
The original Tacoma Narrows Bridge open to the public on July 1st 1940
They opened it was prone to having these oscillation
That's our Master of Disaster John Moore can I write on
Various murders and disasters mother rum Sunday topics
You supposed to Zine called Mercury can be fun about these sundry topics
He wrote about the Tacoma Narrows Bridge years ago workers on a bridge and nicknamed The Galloping Gertie in that game quickly
China became the bridges unofficial name even light winds caused the roadway to Ripple with longitudinal wave some 5 feet
The state of Washington was unconcerned about this but not like intensely so they're like looking at
Various things to reduce the motion to try some tie-down cables and installing a damper in
Very sad things
Again the roadbed seem like you can handle the waves just fine they're very confident in their structural integrity
The bridge was a solid as they are underneath Wylie Coyote
When you watch film of the waves traveling down the bridge
It is
Donnie the fact the bridge stayed open at all
Really illustrates how local governments have changed since 1940
That thing would never stay open today
If you were sitting in a car on the bridge when the waves were going the cars in front of you with Bob up
And then Disappear Completely from the you all look like it's Thrill Ride people actually dry specifically for the
The feeling of riding on this bouncing Bridge
The ride ended Just 4 months later
And the wind begins to speak with a roller
It was clear early on the morning of November 7th at the gale force winds were having a greater effect on the bridge
Previously these two source of waves on the bridge have been like a fairly transitory
Bounce out for a couple minutes but this was just going on and on so they
Got this could be problematical although they had seen actually
Deeper waves on the bridge
But then the movement changed things can't just got worse
The bridge begins twist violently along the Centerline and that became like extremely violent one end of the bridge.
45° angle
Little 40 mile-an-hour deals with feathers families like living in Queens with but you wouldn't believe
Palpable
Ohio River
Turning
Curly
By this time everyone had gotten off
The blunt solid edge of the bridge disrupted the flow of the strong wind
Causing one part to twist.
Well the other section twisted
Down
They continue this torsional back and forth for over an hour or so there was plenty of time
For spectators to come watch
Including the bridge is original designer Clark Eldridge
A local camera store owner named Barney Elliott arrived on the scene
And took the now-famous color film of the bridges Relentless Generations
Airplane
Giant table snap like you only friend
The disaster
Gunplay net worth
Others Dipper
But whatever the reason
Tacoma wheel rebuild
This timer bracelet will not provide a super thrill in the news
For the collapsed Bridge aerodynamics and structural failure due to torsion
It's scarcely been considered
Or maybe those lessons I've been lost in the rapid evolution of more and more slender and longer Bridges
But the failure caused the study of bridge aerodynamics to take off
In any bridges that were on the drawing board in 1940
Or redesigned with more conservative
Deep open truss deck structures
Believe designer Leanne Marshall
And his solid steel i-beams received most of the blame for the disaster
He never designed another Bridge again
Doing no small parts affected he died three years later
No one was killed on the bridge
A few people were very lucky to get away with
The lies because
I just imagine you're on this bridge and is twisting it at 45
3 angling trying to walk off in a fairly stiff wind
The only casualty was a dog
A local newspaper man named Leonard coatsworth drove his car just passed the East Tower when the twisting started
That bouncing so hard he couldn't control it
Car anymore until teen Bridge through his car into the side curve
And he had his daughters dog
Cocker spaniel named tubby
Coatsworth gets out of his wrecked vehicle and gets thrown face down on the curb
The dogs completely
Trick Daddy come get the dog out
Here's the concrete cracking beneath
Can he barely makes it
Safety
An engineering Professor studying the bridge named for cars
Ventured out to get to be right when the bridge was about to
Fall into the sound
But when he reached into the car
Cubby bedroom
The dog was just too freaked out to leave
Vehicle
There's amazing film on cars
Stumbling back as best you could
Sticking to that middle yellow line
As the bridge Rock
Wildly
So tell me what's the only casualty
Forecast
Coach with was quoted immediately after the collapse saying
With a real tragedy disaster in Black the dreams all around me
I believe that right at this minute
What appalls me most
Is that within a few hours I must tell my daughter
Better dog is dead
When I might have saved
This next bit is a completely unrelated addendum that will serve as a valuable life lesson to Annie 99
% invisible fan
Here's John Morgan
Several years ago I went to the Portland Zine Symposium to do a seminar
On research base scenes
Research-based seems like research-based blogs or podcasts
I have always been a bit in the minority
Anyway and was held in this building called the Michael Smith Memorial Student Union building
On the Portland State University campus
Very first thing I did like I can run the class and said okay this panel is being held in the Michael Smith amor
Memorial Student Union building
Does anyone know who Michael Smith was
Michael Smith was a captain of the Portland State University on College Bowl team
The college bowl with a televised trivia company
Matching teams from various University
Is the route the country and he led Portland State University to
The championship
Which is an incredible accomplishments are beating out schools like Harvard and Yale and uses Portland State is a state school
This is not the type of school the expected wind something like this I'm sure
Keyboard horribly embarrassed
And is quite a big deal the time
I'm also suffering from cystic fibrosis
And he would die 3 years after
So everyone agree this is a good story
Mass me how'd you find out about
There's a plaque in front of the building
My slogan is
Always read
The plaque
99% invisible with producer Suite by me Roman Mars in special thanks to John Moore of murder can be fun
And Alan Bellows of website damn interesting
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects
Support for 99% invisible is provided in part by tiny letter
Email for people with something to say my boy mouth always has something to say
What do you say Maslow
Talk about is
Boston Ironman
Stuff
Robots and Iron Man suits
Glitter
Free easy minimal powerful the simplest way to write an email newsletter
Online at tinyletter. Com
This program is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public find out more at
IPR x.org
And while I'm talking about PRX I have to tell you about another podcast they produced called
How sound
Buy the genius Rob Rosenthal
If you're a person who loves radio
Is also the type of person who listens to
Director's commentary on DVD
But how sound is the show for you check it out at the house now. Org
My man Sam Greenspan took off for a while to launch the TED Radio Hour at NPR
You'll be back Greenspan
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I would like it if you would like us
A tweet at Roman Mars
We can always catch up with us online at 99percentinvisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com