99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Julia Barnett been thinking about what happens when we build
Big
Maybe because she grew up in Dallas and the Go-Go eighties
Big football Arenas take freeways big houses
Texans love big
Dallas build a new city hall in 1978
Worldwide Plaza is kind of wedge shaped but upside down so the widest enlarges Flores on the top
Sometimes I go up to the top floor City Hall with my friends
That's where the vending machines were
They stalked my favorite candy bar
Caramello
Then we'd sit by the windows in chocolate and looking down over the plaza and I think
This is so cool
Bellator in high school Julia went to a protest Down Below in the plaza
And those same city hall windows were now
Hawking over us
We could see our tiny Reflections in the glass
Made me feel like a nobody
And that this whole event was a waste of time and
Environment seem to be saying the same thing
I'm important
You're Nobody
So Julia developed a mistrust of the big building the big project
In places where people seem to love the glory of the grandiose
I'm also fascinated by those kinds of
I can't stay away from them
Case in point
Russia
Biggest country in the world makes Texans look like amateurs
Totally
The Russians are real pros in the department of tall towering and humongous
And not just from the Soviet past
Europe's tallest skyscraper 93 story says going up right now in Moscow
So they had to stop for a while on the 67th floor after I caught fire
Russia's Southernmost city Sochi is the biggest construction site in Europe
That's because so she's hosting the Winter Olympics
I'm headed down there to check it out
I went on a two-hour bus ride from Sochi Center on the Black Sea up to the foothills of the caucuses
Weather building ski resorts
And maybe on that whole ride there were a couple of five minute stretches where I wasn't
Looking at a crane or a new hotel
Honey Chris Republic Chinese look for dessert
Conditional list
The Grease T
I also met this man named Alex a trivia
He went all his life in a cinder block house by the Black
I see the city wants to tear it down for new rail yard
They've already demolished the rest of his neighborhood
But trivia is appealed his eviction in court
He says construction workers
Just come up every day
Scrape is walls
Backhoe
We never asked the government for anything
Guess what trivia to say
And now the government wants to take everything away from us
He's painted slogans and red paint on his windows
Does things like
People live here and SOS
Sometimes construction workers throw rocks through the
They fall in shards of Cyrillic all over the
Big
Crushing small that's the way always seems to play itself out wherever there's a mess
Development but there's a theory
That big buildings don't just hurt little people they may in fact
Hurt the Builders of those buildings to
There is the well-known fact in real estate
That the great buildings tend to go up
At the end of
Recycle when everything
That's a Critic and philosopher Edward tenner
Well I was in Russia this last time I found an essay online that he wrote in 2001
Affect
Is
What I called
Appearance
The big building
The big structure
At
The time when things are starting
Counter site this idea known as the
Skyscraper pictures
Tall buildings correlate with bad times
The Princeton
The Empire State Building was conceived in the 1920s
But not finished until the Great Depression
When it was known as the empty State Building
The Sears Tower and the World Trade Center both opened in 19/7
33 on the verge of another egg
The people who run the NASDAQ
Change build the world's largest video display on Times Square in 1999 just a few months before the
Dot-com Bubble Burst and then nap.
Crashed
Xanadu effect
Is a symptom
People over reaching over
Planning
Thinking that everything is going to go on forever when
It's about to turn
I found Tanners Theory a little comfort
Plus I think Olivia Newton-John
Xanadu is one of the biggest songs ever written
I see what you're trying to do their Julia and it's not going to work
No Olivia Newton-John
Nicole Richie
I will allow
In Xanadu did Kubla Khan
A stately pleasure Dome decree was thinking of the movie Citizen Kane and Kane
Palace Xanadu
Okay then
Rosebud
Who's this ledge
So just as Citizen Kane build his Palace while his Empire crumbled
The big project can be a big bad distraction
Tender goes through several examples of the Xanadu affecting his original essay
There are plenty of instances of big projects that don't pre-stage any kind of crash
Enterocytes example of Cass Gilbert Woolworth Building
What up in a bun time of 1913
It certainly didn't hurt the Warwick
It's hard to say what these gigantic state-driven projects like the Olympics finit does Hannity
Plus
There are plenty of critics who argue that Building height much less bigness in general cannot accurately predict the downturn at all
Greatness is a strategy
That
Just about always spells
Unless it succeeds
Or you can say it's one that
That always succeeds except when it fails
And and there's really no
One way
That you can regard it
You have to see it as a
As a very
Powerful
Easy to
Misuse
But also
Tempting
Way to
Go about 4
Does energy affect might not provide that comeuppance
Julia desires
Design in any sort of downturn
A little person is still the one most likely to suffer
I guess the success or failure of bigness really does depend on where you stand in relation to it
Are you on top of City Hall
Or down below
Big places just amplifier reaction
Protest in Moscow
When we marched on one of the city's wide soviet-era Boulevard
Ordinarily I hate these boulevards
Because you can actually cross them
You have to find a pedestrian tunnel
Like
Sneak underneath
For a few hours Moscow suppressive bigness
ARS
The wide Road
Stalin-era skyscrapers
Block-long Institute
It all made us feel bigger to
That was freezing
Michael Cole
People
Smiling
Everybody is
That's my friend Vasily Sulkin
He grew up in Moscow but
He never experienced his grandiosity like this
As a grandiose stage for political
Expression
The way the crowds transform the National Mall in Washington DC or the Sean's Alizee in Paris
And even Edward tenner says
That's what can be wonderful about BigNik
It can Elevate people give them a sense of
Pride and
Purpose
I took a lot of the positive side
Or cities
Are the big buildings when they're done well
New York without
The Empire State Building New York without the Chrysler Building
New York without Rockefeller Center would really be a poor place
I keep thinking about Alex a cravat
Centos standoff
Developers in Sochi
Sometimes he goes out in films his confrontation
Construction work
I posted one of the film's up on 99percentinvisible. Org everyone speaking Russian but it's not hard to understand what
What is going on
Preview to put some of his things in a metal storage unit behind his house
The worker showed up with a huge
Crane haul it away
Career test do they work for in the supervisor this big Burly guy says
We are building the Olympic facilities
Then they hook up the crane while craviotto shelter
You can see a big building under construction behind millions of visitors.
During the Olympic Games
You can see the bones of what's going to be a soaring roof
A stately pleasure Dome
Dewey Barton travel most recently to Russia for PRI the world you can find more of our stories at
Toolbarn.com
99% invisible with prettiest this week by Julia Barton With a Little Help From Me Roman Mars
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Support for 99percentinvisible is provided in part by tiny letter email for people with something to say
Something to say what you have to say Carver
Daddy long legs utf8 legs to fix out of the darkness by
They are arachnids
But they're not spiders
The load off my mind
Free easy minimal powerful the simplest way to write an email newsletter
Online at tiny letter. Com
This program is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public
Radio more public
Borat PRX. Org
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars the only just catch up with us online
99percentinvisible
. org
Hello to Jason Isaacs
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com