99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
US Paper currency is so ubiquitous
That to really look at its graphic design with
Crash on
Requires deliberate and focused attention
The paleta Greenback from your wallet
Or look at a picture online if you're in
It's really take it in
All the fonts
Busy Philipps
A micropipette
Dreadful
Thermapure design of point of view
I thought I said that top because it is a little bit subjective but it's horrible
Topographically graphically symbolically if it never been designed before on someone was to submit that as a
The solution I think they were just going to throw it out and I don't want to get too critical at this point because
There are actually
Pretty compelling and understandable reasons for its particular brand of horribleness
Cracking the primary tension embodied in the design of the Greenback boils down to how my friend Tom Nelson at the
The blog humans and design for
When I handle American money it feels like an artifact
Because it's so ornate and it has an old look to it even though paper currency itself
The idea of money is a massive
World changing technology
The look and feel of us paper money
Is Barry stagner
It seems like a relic
When our country was founded would you buy a car
Food still look like the Model T Ford now you buy
The latest
Model all the things evolve
Two-time that's Richard Smith he run the contest called the dollar redesign fraud
It's become a classic like class
Suffix do
3 time
I'm sure usage and 3 familiarity sorry
Stole Christmas from a design point of view
Kind of been
Superseded by
Symbolic
So if you were to start from scratch when we design on US Paper Money
Smith says there are five major areas where we could improve
Number one is come
The idea of using one color doesn't really tell you much other than that we like the color green are largely monochromatic money
Apples
We've introduced a purple 5 and some PT use
But there are a lot of colors and most countries use at least some of them
Number to his size
Why the American currency old one-size-fits-all ways
Question mark in my head
Never really make sense practically
I'm philosophically having variable size coin certainly helps
The sort them and you could use the same principle for bills
Which leads us to point number three in Smith's manifest
Functionality
Some functionality button Abel's people if they count C2
Clearly
Distinguish
Waterbury to the fundamental level
Which note is which
The fact that there's no easy way for the blind to use our currency goes beyond bad design is actually immoral
Then the next fundamental thing I saw it was composition s number 4 meaning like what's it made from this is a
Is a little set of
Conceptual into like where this could go but be nice
Just seems that a product design I could come in and do the come out
Something really interesting recycled material with a smaller carbon footprint or more durable synthetics that last longer
And at the very heart of the dollar redesign project is number 5
Symbolism
Who should go on the bills in
Why
Why the founding fathers
The be-all-and-end-all of everything but is America
I think somebody that's the
One of the biggest issues if he went to change anything
I would say that was that would be where I would stop
It could be
Platform to celebrate everything that is
Unique special different
But you didn't know about America
And that's the suggestion that can get a British expat on his way to American citizenship like Richard Smith
Colorful hate mail
But it's an intriguing less than the last
Even if you just view the five suggestions as a philosophical exercise
To assess the current design for all of its strengths and faults
It's hard to imagine all those things being modified on US currency
But it's not hard to imagine each of them being implemented somewhere
In fact most of them are implemented everywhere
Case in point
Australia
On the other side of the world each and every one of these five issues
Coincidentally
Benadryl
Let me introduce
Is a Mastiff
Australian design
Australia's new
$5
I'm really proud about money
Absolutely no idea why I'm so proud of it but I really am
That's Tristan cook
You're about to hear why you so proud
Tristan and Tom Nelson NPR from the top the show
Are user centred designers the neighbor on the Block I'm a big fan of
Call humans and Design
Tristan is Australian Tom is American
What time went to school in Australia for a couple years
And the money they're made of
Big impression on
The money is plastic
And they're all different sizes and their colorful
At first these changes were disconcerting
I'll just look like toy money to me in this will shock you begin to appreciate all the different design characteristics
Australian currency
First
Is the color
$5 is sort of a lavender $10 is
Blue with little bit of a green stripe in it 20
You can tell the differences between things you generally is
Stock quote
And you code
Things like styes
Feel
And color
So in Australian money we have Al
Primarily by color
In some ways is a better index because it doesn't require knowledge of
Who's on the bill it only requires
Recognition of a color association with
The pineapple World Lobster
Very common just yet but we cool at night
SoundClick colors and my tooth personal favorite cycling a $20 night which is
Orange-colored killing a lobster
And cooling a $50 note
Which is
Green and yellow color and Cooling in a pint
Which is short for pineapple
It's all about the pineys number to size
Feel different in your hand sometimes I cash in my pocket I can tell the difference between a $5
Tonight tonight because Eli would say this about a centimeter difference between each denomination
Between a 5 and a 10 is in that big
But between a 5 and a 50 is
Very big
4 centimeters difference
Both number one and two relate to the third issue raised by Richard Smith
And that's functionality you can see whether you got
A5 A10
A 20 or 50 from the top of your wallet because of the color and size difference
Number for
Composition of plastic notes were developed primarily to combat counterfeiting
If you dropped a note on the floor Men's Room you don't really feel bad about
Picking it up and putting it under the faucet before you put it back in your pocket
But they last longer they tend to last four times longer than fibrous
Take a note
20 years old and I
Pretty much
Just looked at 9
What Australia chooses to put on its currency is more in keeping with what rich
Smith of the dollar redesign project would like to see
It's much more inclusive than
Founding fathers
Monuments
But it's hard to tell if these symbols are conveyed much a penny
Everyday
Australian
They don't put
Statesman on on money frequently there are artists
Poets
And
I think
Are there some Aboriginal leaders
If there's another thing till you couldn't awful prime minister's on
Oh no money
We don't have the reference to a promises in Australia
Couldn't name the people that
Are on their money
Except for one side of the $5 is the queen and it's just because I don't want her on there
Imagine if you ask any Australian if they know who is only noise
EBay would be less than 1% of people who did nine anybody other than Queen symbolism in Australian cash seems to be
Betide Morty
The innovation of the build themselves
Is a certain Pride
The Palmer bills were developed in Australia
And I've been exported to the rest of the world
Australia now manufactures the polymer notes of nearly 20 other country
The good design of the currency itself
Is the overriding brand
It's no ordinary night however
It's Australia Snoop on a $10
And was developed and printed right here I would like to
American currency
Redesign
Treated more like a live
Piece of technology
Rather than rocks
I think
Even the most jingoistic among us
Best could come
See that there are design innovation
Could be incorporated into US currency to make it better but there are some interesting reasons why we
Probably won't
You know someone once told me that
Getting rid of the Greenback would be like
Burning the flag
Steps of the Capitol is the end of mine
A lot of people are currently it's a physical touchdown of our national identity
Some of this is emotional
But there is this
Other concern that is
Simultaneously analyzing and scary
And that other concern is that when you redesign the money you are mine people what currency is
And what gives the currency value
And of course what gives the currency value
Is our belief
That it's value
In in a religious sense of
Nothing more than faith
Are TriStar worship whatever you want to call it
Makes a dollar
Warsaw dollar or worth whatever you're going to buy with it
So
That is upsetting to a lot of people and
To maintain the
Aura of strength and stability of the United States
Economy
It probably helps to maintain these leggings
Features in the design of our money
What is now
Three or four generations we had the same color I think since
War
Portrait
Steam crave styling the filigree
Legacy fit
Teachers convey stability
An hour currency the currency on which all other currencies are hedge
Has to be stable
So not only do we not redesign the stuff
But we don't
Pull older notes from circulation either
So we'll have
Reissues and redesign
AmeriCash
But you can still use
The last generation
Design
As legal tender
In other countries a complete redesign deprecates the old design
You're giving a Grace. To use or exchange it but after a certain date the old currency
Shredded by the central bank
And you can no longer
Spend any that you have left
This is never been the case in the US
You can even use it an 18 century coin
Stamped with just the value of $0.02 to go buy something you might want to be careful because I can be
So stupid
It could be worse
You know $3,000 to a collector out there
But if you want to go spend it as $0.02
You can
And again that this is part of
Creating is Aura of
Super stability and inherent value
Federal Reserve notes
David woman is quick to point out that even though these concerns events
Stability have
Incited when people bring up redesigning the money or eliminating the penny
He thinks it's
Pretty Arash
Hainan overly cautious
It seems to me a little bit patronizing to think that Americans couldn't handle a dollar redesign really who is going
Going to push it forward
You know if you're going to go to work in government
Don't you almost by definition have
Some of that sense of
Patriotism and nationalism that would make you a little bit more inclined to like
Greenback as is
And a little less inclined to
You let some
Really
Let's get after it
But still primarily driven by anti-counterfeiting measures
US currency has been pushed to change in recent years
And most of these new designs are why it looks worse than
Ever
Legacy features remain largely intact but a layer
Modern fonts
Swirlds
Text the bills look like they're busting at
Seems is the worst
Both world
It's absolute chaos there is very little Italian
About
Are money from a blind stamp on as far as I enter
When I told David woman about my new-found
Discovery Inn
Appreciation of the US
Australian dollar as evangelize by Tristan and Tom
He was less
I don't I don't think it's that remarkable congratulations to the Aziz and the scientist who came up with
Polymer banknotes
And I think they
Well because of that innovation
But I'm just not convinced
Very welcome
Pretty
Hey I personally think pretty counts
But from his point of view a better design banknote even a plastic one is
Still
Just a piece
Paper
I mean his book is called the end of money
That design efforts out there related to money that excite me more
Argue design
Are the user interface of apps for mobile money
Right how are we going to be transacting with money in PayPal mobile and Google Wallet and
What are designers bringing to bear on those interface
Paper or polymer money
I get it all right
Truly interesting Frontier of design is not going to be
The banknote
Art
But the Swiss come up with it
It's going to be
The interface
With
Mobile apps and what designers are doing
To make
Our interactions
With money
Fluid
More sophisticated and possibly God forbid even like wiser
Who's presenting the app
To make us a little more careful with our money
And how are they
Bringing to the Arizona principles of design to make that happen
And this is something that Tristan and Tom are totally on board with
Physical money is probably on its way out and polymer money as cool as it is
Is it technology
David Stein
They themselves have actually designed clever user interfaces so that the good aspects of physical money already
And transactions feel more tangible and morio
Even when it's
Just bits
Define Revere
Select Physical us
$20 bill will probably be gone from widespread use before it's a lovely shade of Orange erad
I'm okay with
This is long enough to see that wavy Six Flag amusement park font that says
20 USA in the back row
I mean seriously
What the hell were they thinking
That phone is even cruel to Andrew Jackson
Jerk
99% invisible was produced
Sweet By Me Roman Mars
A special thanks
Tristan cook and Tom Nelson of the blog humans in design
We'll have a link on the web
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects
Tax in San Francisco
Support for 99% invisible is provided in part by tiny letter
Email for people with something to say
My boy mad voice hasn't
What do you say Maslow
Talk about is
Boston iron
Robots in Iron Man 2
I would describe that newsletter
Free easy minimal powerful the simplest way to write an email newsletter
Online at tinyletter.
We are distributed by PRX
Public radio exchange making public radio more public more at PRX.
Is it just a reminder that every episode of 99% invisible is available to be downloaded for
Your listening pleasure
And each one
Is better than the last
Weather going backwards
Port Warwick
This is amazing and impossible but yet
It is still true
You can find the show and like
Show interact with me on Facebook I tweet and often Tweet back to people at Roman Mars
For this week you will find pretty pictures of
Plastic bills
99 percent invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com