99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into
High quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help
Target your customers with
Decision
Down to the job title company name
And Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get to board from UC Davis
Globally ranked universities
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe
Define transformational solution
No quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is Roman Mars I mean this is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
So I was out all last week at the Ted conference, give it talk it went rate
I'll let everyone know when the video was released I just had this amazing time
But I'm
Exhausted
And I need a week off to recuperate so
The episode I want a rebroadcast has an old one but it
And I remembered it
When was being interviewed on the Ted stage by Helen Walters here's the relevant section of the interview
Dramanice
The fact that you are really
Can come up with a really good rant about whatever
What's on your mind
What if you what is your other favorite
Set design rent
I can complain about us money
Prolong time
What is it about us money
So that's what this episode is about my problem
With American money
It dates back a few years till when the show was
Just a one-man operation so I hope you like it
Wella heavier the beginning the show I have a couple of business items
First is that we have a survey that I'd love for you to fill out
You let us know
Howard doing and demographic data about who you are and what podcast do like so it would really help us out
Goody survey nurse.com Nine-Nine
Balls have a link on a website it just takes a few minutes
I was going to give an extra shot out to some of the musicians who are regulars on 99 Pi Keegan DeWitt NY first discuss
Covered at the composer of the cold weather soundtrack we use it a lot he's brilliant
Okay akumi and all the artists on Hell audio are fantastic you cannot go wrong with them the folks in abandoned
Building records in particular I love the band set in sand and we use this song talking to her right now in the credits quite a bit
And everything I say sounds good on top of this song
And last but certainly not least our pal melodeon who makes music than spires meat on a weekly basis
There are so many more and I'll remind you of them regularly on the website
At the end of the show from time to time they all make great records they're all on bandcamp if you go support great artists like that
You will feel good in the world will be a better place
Thanks
Now on with the show
This is 99% invisible
I'm roaming
US Paper currency is so ubiquitous
That to really look at its graphic design with
Foshan
Requires deliberate and focused attention
The paleta Greenback from your wallet
Or look at a picture online if your internet
Just really take it in
All the fonts
The busy filigree
Micro pattern
Just
Dreadful
Thermapure design is point of view
I thought I said that top because it is a little bit subjective
Piper graphically
Graphically symbolically
If it never been designed before on someone was to submit that as a solution I think they were just going to throw it out
Critical at this point because
There are actually
Pretty compelling and understandable reasons for its particular brand of horribleness
Tracking the primary tension embodied in the design of the Greenback boils down to how my friend Tom Nelson at the blog humans
Then design
When I handle American money it feels like an artifact
Because it's so ornate and it has an old look to it even though paper currency itself just the idea of money as a
The massive
World
Changing technology
The look and feel of us paper money
Is Barry stagner
It seems like a relic from when I country was founded would you buy a car
Still look like the Model T Ford now you buy
Latest
Monologue
But things are evolving
Change your time that's Richard Smith contest called the dollar redesign project
It's become a classic like classic
3 time
I'm sure usage and three familiarity
Stole Christmas from a design point of view
Kind of been
Superseded by its
Symbolic
So if you were to start from scratch when we design us paper money
Smith says there are five major areas where we could improve
Number one is color
The idea of using one color doesn't really tell you much other than that we like the color green are largely monochromatic money
We've introduced a purple 5 and some PT Hughes
But there are a lot of colors and most countries use at least some of them
Number two is size why they matter
Casio one size
Question mark in my head
Never really made
Send price
Physically I'm philosophically having variable size coin certainly helps us sort them and you could use the same pen
Ansible for build
Which leads us to point number 3 and Smith Manifesto
Functionality
Some functionality button Ables
People if I come
C2
Clearly distinguish
Waterbury to the fundamental level
Which note is which
The fact that there's no easy way for the blind to use our currency goes beyond bad design is actually immoral
Then the next fundamental thing I saw it was composition s number 4 meaning like was it made from this is a
Who is a little
Conceptual into like where this could go but being a just seems that a product design
I could come in and soda come out
Something really interesting recycled material with a smaller carbon footprint or more durable synthetics that last longer
The very heart of the dollar redesign project is number 5
Symbolism
Who should go on the bills and why
Why the founding fathers
The be-all-and-end-all of everything but is America
I think somebody that's the
One of the biggest issues if he were to change anything
I would say that was that would be where I was
Stop
Could be a platform to celebrate
Thing that is unique special different
But you didn't know about America
And that's the suggestion that can get a British expat on his way to American citizenship like Richard Smith
Colorful hate mail
But it's an intriguing less than the last
Even if you just view the five suggestions as a philosophical exercise
To assess the current design for all of its strength
It's hard to imagine all those things being modified on US currency
But it's not hard to imagine each of them being implemented somewhere
In fact most of them are implemented everywhere
Case in point
Australia
On the other side of the world each and every one of these five issues
Have coincidentally
Ben address
Let me introduce
A masterpiece
Australian design
Australia's new
$5
Really proud about money
Absolutely no idea why I'm so proud of it but I really am
That's Tristan cook
You're about to hear why he's so proud
Tristan and Tom Nelson here from briefly at the top of the show
Are user-centered design your blog
Call humans in design
Tristan is Australian Tom is American
What time went to school in Australia for a couple years
And the money they're made a big impression on them
The money is plastic
And they're all different sizes and their colorful disconcerting
I'll just look like toy money to be a shock you begin to appreciate all the different design characteristics
Australian currency
First
Is the color
$5 is sort of a lavender $10 is
Blue with little bit of a green stripe in it
The ways you can tell the differences between things you generally it's
Simplehuman Pakistan for it
Can you code
Feel
And
So in Australian money we have Al
Primarily by color which in some ways is a better index because it doesn't require knowledge of who's on the bill and
It only requires
Recognition of a color
Or in association with a pineapple World Lobster
It's not
Very common just yet but we cool at night
SoundClick remains but I colors and what two personal favorite cycling a $20 night witches
Orange-colored killing a lobster
And cooling a $50
Which is a survey
A green and yellow color and Cooling in a plane
Which is short for pineapple
It's all about the pineys number to size
Feel different in your hand in my pocket I can tell the difference between a $5
Because they feel I would say that it's about a centimeter difference between each denomination which
Between a 5 and a 10 isn't that big
But between a 5 and a 50 is
Very big
4 centimeters difference
Both number one and two relate to the third issue raised by Richard Smith
And that's functionality you can see whether you got
A5
A 20 or a 50 from the top of your wallet because of the color and size difference
Number for composition 2 combat counter
Feel like plastic when you can fold and scrunch up
Actually put it through the washing machine and it'll be fine
If you drop the note on the
Florida Men's Room you don't really feel bad about
Picking it up and putting it under the faucet before you put it back in your car
Just more but they last longer fits in the last four times longer than fibrous paper
20 years old and I
Pretty much just look the same
What Australia chooses to put on its currency is more in keeping with literature
Smith of the dollar redesign project would like to see
It's much more inclusive and founding fathers and monuments
But it's hard to tell these symbols are conveyed much of anything
Everyday
Australian
They don't put
Statesman on on money frequently there are artists
And
I think
Are there some Aboriginal leaders
If there's another thing till you couldn't awful prime minister's on
On a money
We don't have the reference
No promises
The most Australian
Couldn't name
The people that
Are on their money
I've absolutely no idea who is on any
Except for one side of the V Illinois is the queen and I just because I don't want around there
Any Australian if they know who is on their nose
EBay would be less than 1% of people who did nine anybody other than Queen symbolism in Australian cash seems to be
Tidemore the innovation of the bills themselves
Is a certain Pride
Polymer bills were developed in Australia
And have been exported to the rest of the world
Australia now manufactures the polymer notes of nearly 20 other country
It's a good business for them
The good design of the currency itself is the overriding brand
It's no ordinary night
I'm supposed to Pelican printed right here I would like to
Steve's American currency
Redesign
Treated more like a living
Technology
Rather than rocks
I think
Even the most
Jingoistic Among Us
Yes could concede that there are design Innovations
That could be incorporated into US currency to make it better but there are some interesting reasons why we pray
Probably
You know someone once told me that
Getting rid of the Greenback would be like
Burning the flag
On the steps of the capitol
That David woman has David woman my book is the end of mine
A lot of people are currently it's a physical touchdown of our national identity
Some of this is emotional
But there is this
Other concern that is
Can you play 1011
Scary
And that other concern is that when you redesign the money you remind people what currency is
And what gives the currency value
Of course what gives the currency value
Is our belief
That it's valuable
In in the religious
Nothing more than faith
Are TriStar worship whatever you want to call it makes a dollar
Warsaw dollar or worth whatever you're going to buy with
So
That is upsetting to a lot of people and
To maintain the
Aura of strength and stability of the United States
Economy
It probably helps to maintain these Legacy
Key features in the design of our money
Through
What is now
Three or four generations we had the same color I think since I
War
Portraits engraved styling
Filigree
Legacy features convey
Stability
An hour currency the currency on which all other currencies are hitched
Has to be stable
So not only do we not redesign the stuff
But we don't
Pull older notes from circulation either
So we'll have
Reissues and redesign
AmeriCash
But you can still use
The last generation
Design
As legal tender
In other countries a complete redesign deprecates the old design
You giving a Grace. To use or exchange it but after a certain date the old currency is shredded by the central bank
And you can no longer
Spend any that you have left
This is never been the case in the US
You can even use it an 18th century coin stamped with
Is the value of $0.02 to go buy something you might want to be careful
Because I can be
So stupid
It could be worse
You know $3,000 to a collector out
But if you want to go spend it as $0.02
You can
And again that this is part of
Greetings Aura of
Super stability and
Inherent value
Of Federal Reserve notes
David woman is quick to point out that even though these concerns of instability have
Excited when people bring up redesign the money or eliminating the penny
He thinks it's
Pretty Arash
In an overly
Play cautious.
It seems to me a little bit patronizing
To think that Americans couldn't handle a dollar redesign really who is going to push it forward
You know if you're going to go to work in government
Don't you almost by definition have
Some of that sense of
Patriotism and nationalism that would make you a little bit more inclined to like
Greenback as is
And a little less inclined to
You let some
Really hot dogs get after it
But still primarily driven by anti-counterfeiting measures
US currency has been pushed to change in recent years
And most of these new designs are why it looks
Worse than
Ever
Legacy features remained largely intact for the lair
Modern
Fonts swirls mix
The bills look like they're busting at the
Seems it's the worst of Both Worlds
Absolute chaos
Is very little Italian
About
Are money from ads Einstein
As far as I
When I told David woman about my newfound.
Discovery and appreciation of the Australian dollar as evangelized by Tristan and Tom
He was less
I don't I don't think it's that remarkable
Congratulations to the Aziz and the scientists who came up with
Polymer banknotes
And I think
They profited well because of that innovation
But I'm just not convinced it's very world-changing
Pretty
Hey I personally think pretty count
But from his point of view a better design banknote even a plastic one is
Still
Just a piece
Paper
I mean his book is called the end of money
Dad design efforts
Out there related to money that excite me more
R-design
The user interface of apps for mobile money right how are we going to be transacting with money in PayPal mobile
Golang Google Wallet
What are designers bringing to bear on those interface
Because the interface with
Paper or polymer money
I get it already
Truly interesting Frontier of design
Is not going to be
The banknote
Art
But the Swiss come up with in 26
Phrase going to be
The interface
With mobile apps and what designers are doing
To make
Our interactions
With money
More fluid
More sophisticated
Possibly got forget even like wiser you know who's who's designing the app
To make a little more
Careful with our money
And how are they
Bringing today hours of the principles of design to make that happen
And this is something that Tristan and Tom are totally on board with
Physical money is probably on its way out and polymer money as cool as it is
Is it technology
David Stein
They themselves have actually designed clever user interfaces so that the good aspects of physical money already
And transactions feel more tangible and morio even when it's just bits
Define Revere
So that physical us $20 bill will probably be gone from widespread use before it's a lovely shade
Date of Orange erad
I'm okay with
Does it long enough to see that wavy Six Flag amusement park font
It says 20 USA in the background
I mean seriously
What the hell were they thinking
That phone is even cruel to Andrew Jackson
Black guy
Jerk
99percentinvisible is now Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project and then 1.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin and architecture in it
Interiors firm gives us a free home in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Support for 99percentinvisible comes from our fancy until agreed Kickstarter backers including storyworth the easiest way to
Record your family stories and preserve them for generations to come find out more at storyworth. Com
And from hover the best way to buy and manage domain name
Give me idea jump on it and make something out of it
The first step is buying a domain name
Hover makes it super easy and fun and if you're like me and you'll get
Even more ideas by registering those domains in the restroom more
I think I might actually have a problem
If you have several dozen ideas rattling around in your brain
Whisper them in the Harper Theatre
They will set you up
They are you're completely non-judgmental BFF for crazy ideas at 2 a.m. go to uber.com
Review your hopes and dreams
Dear secret Canadian confidant
I'll save you 10% off first purchase
Petharbor.com
Support is also provided by Squarespace the fast and easy way to create your own website blog or portfolio
Squarespace recently launched their latest version of their platform it's called Squarespace 7
Which has a completely redesigned interface Integrations with Getty Images and Google apps in beautiful beautiful new Temple
Try the new Squarespace at squarespace.com
Spray for 2 weeks no credit card required
You purchase
Into the office. Invisible at checkout
And I'll save you 10%
Squarespace
Start here
Go anywhere
And finally we are made possible by time letter
Email for people with something to say my boy Maslow I said something to say in three years ago on this very episode.
Robot in Iron Man
Iron Man suits and stuff
Cannot do much as change thank God
Weather.com It's free easy minimal and Powerful to simplest way to send an email newsletter
The great people behind Mountain
Thanks to MailChimp the Knight foundation and people just like you we were able to create radiotopia from PRX
Welcome to The Illusionist
This is Criminal
Welcome to the heart
The mortified
Theory of Everything
Love and radio
Fugitive waves
From the kitchen
Subscribe to the mall at radiotopia. FM
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter and Instagram Avery runs the Tumblr
I make the Spotify playlist of 99 Pi songs
Remember to go to that. Survey survey nerds. Com 99
But I encourage you to explore the entire world of 99% invisible
At 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about
The body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
West Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Cost of your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com