99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Navarre is on a mission
He's trying to get a case of beer called West flavor
I'm not a hundred percent sure but I think it's West Placer but apparently it's worth it
0 beernardo have a friend who's appearing
You probably heard a Belgian beer
Belgians take their beer very seriously
They're about 200 breweries in a country about twice the size of the Bay Area
Where I'm from
No amongst these Belgian breweries and Belgian ale
There's a very specific subtype
Trappist beer
Anyone who knows anything about beer
Will probably start to get glassy eyes
Didn't have a warm
Delicious feeling
Whenever they talk about them
Myself included
Sentences will be punctuated
Superlatives
Exclamation
Now I'm a person just like you but don't actually drink beer to off takes roses word for it
Or the word of one of the many beer reviewers on YouTube
Tuesday looks amazing
Titanic about it
So many flavors
Yes and I think we all know what you're going to get
That's something else
That sucks
My tongue is tingling
Yeah it's it's
If we need to know about Trappist beer
First they're amazing
Second
They're made by Trappist monks
These monks Trace their roots to a monastery in 17th century France
And have since spread out to
To all over the world
The main concept behind the Trap as lifestyle is at the Abbey should be economically self-sufficient
In other words
The monk should make
And sell it to the public as a way to fund the operations of the Abbey itself
So make cheese
So make spirits
There's even one in Germany
That makes lentil soup
But none of the Trap is products
Are nearly anywhere as famous as the beer
Only seven beer-making Trappist Abbey
Exist
Sixer in Belgium
And one is in the Netherlands Ben was widely available Trappist beer is Chimay
You can get it in a lot of us specialty grocery stores and some bars to
They make over 3 million gallons of the stuff a year
By comparison West waiter and makes less than 4% of that volume annually
But westvleteren with its plain brown bottle No Label in the only writing is on the cap at super cool
It's one of the rarest and many say
It's the best beer in the world
But here's the thing about Westway torrent you can't go there and have as much beer as you want you can't even have it shipped from the app
You want to buy beer to take a with you
You have to look up the beer reservation
Phone number on the apus website
Then you call the certain phone number During certain hours on certain days
As the most themselves worn on the site
Please take into a
But you may often get a busy signal
Call Tamika
Novation
Do the fact that are.
Overboard
You're not the only one
Just calling it that
Dudoir small-scale production
The number of
Phone calls is much greater
The number of available
Batman
A matter of Health
A lot of pace
As well as
And here's what you need to understand about me I have
Totally game for this I love being challenged as a food consumer
If there's a burger place in Connecticut that claims to have invented the hamburger in America
And you don't true to their century-old rules they refuse
To serve burgers
With ketchup or mustard
And the only serve it on toast
I love that
I mean if they told me that I had to do 50 Jumping Jacks and run around the block and then I could get a burger I would totally do
At 2
Back twist sweater
Who did that bonjour hello
Event sampling method vehicle from the suits
Sunday
Lucky enough to talk to a monk
And yes you do talk to him
To take your reservation
You have to give your license plate number and be available to come pick up your crate
During the appointed time that weekend
You're limited to one crate
Per person per car
Maximum
Supercar
And you can't buy more than one crate during a 60-day period
Oh and you agree not to resell the beer as well
For information PCC over website
You got that
There's a list of several seemingly arbitrary Hoops they have to jump through if you want to buy this beer
This sort of thing is not unheard of
Velvet ropes and random reward
Has long been imposed to create art of
Scarcity in the heightened demand
But the mainstream print today seems to be more geared towards greater access and accommodation for customer
The new ideal is that everything is available at all times no matter where you live
This is the digital age but clearly
This is not the case for the West waiter and Travis
They're trying to make it as difficult as boss
No no no no no no
They don't make a diff
You make it difficult
Tula
Too much people want
This beer
This is Jeff vondenstein
He's the author of a book called
Trappist
The seven Heavenly beers
He's even a brewer himself
Until 10 years ago
You could go to the NBA
Except on Sunday
Goes down they don't work
And accept on Friday because Friday they don't work
Because they don't eat
Friday
But Saturday with David open
You went there
Without problems
You could buy
Beer nuts
As much as you want
But normally
Three grades of two grades
Always pads
But then
The Americans
It's all your fault
I'm sorry I know is it the Americans
Set
What's playing today
The best beer of the world
That because English is World Language
No don't lie in in the in the US England
But also
Scandinavian countries
Go everywhere
Where they speak
Or understand English
Dickens read BeerAdvocate
Website
And suddenly
Did the moms of this beer was 10 times bigger
That's the problem
It's not their problem they Bruno
The same amount as they did before
Keep in mind this was basically the first thing that Jeff said to me when I sat down with him
I sort of felt
Guilty to be honest because
He was right
I heard about this beer for years
And now that I was living within Striking Distance just over the Border in Germany
There was no way I was going to pass it up
Just an older guy with a full
Bushy grey beard and he seems to know just about everything about beer
And having written about the Trappist monks
He was the closest that I was going to get to an actual Monk
But Jeff is sort of Trappist monk by proxy
Outline the main reason for putting up these obstacles to get in Westwood
They decided
Hebrew the same amount
As the Lost
The years
And they have enough for that
Why
Miss Deborah Moore
Cuz you won't
No
And I
They live between
The Wolves of
Rabbit
The problem
So with that in mind and after spending about 90 minutes at Jax Brewery deglazer Turin
And of course we bought some bottles
My three friends and I headed out
To visit the famed monks
Of Westlake
Now as we mentioned earlier you have to order ahead if you want to buy queso
Cerise didn't have any luck ordering crates
But he knew he could at least sample some when he got there
I realized as soon as my friends and I got to The Abbey
Is it
Jeff was totally right
The Abbey
Is in the middle of nowhere
Surrounded by
Small houses
And it's way out in the western edge
Belgium very close to the French border
Totally understandable why the monks
Decided to Institute
This new ordering system
Hundreds of cars descended on these
Tiny roads all of a sudden
It would be disaster
In other words
Designing this whole process to make access difficult
Calling the vehicle Reg
Restriction all of it
A lot of it comes down to Rhodes
Infrastructure
Is there ways to solve the problem one is bigger Road
They can also choose to
Skip the beer out to distributor and have no one visit The Abbey at all
There are solutions
But it's clearly not a problem the monks
Want to song
I did finally get to sit down and have a beer at the cafe across the
Until this year with the only place that was allowed to resell it although there's been a thriving
Blackish gray Market
Quite some time
I wish I could say that the experience was heavenly
Don't get me wrong this beer really is fantastic
It's not a complex flavor in an obviously crafted with a
How to pair thoughtfulness
The flipside of having a label
I'm having this mythology that brings people from around the world like me
To this Monastery is that the relationship but
Between customer
And Brewery
Feels almost anonymous
Generic
It's like my friends and I could have just bought this beer off eBay
And enjoyed it almost anywhere
It would have been basically the same experience
Just a lot more expensive
And this is a symptom of the exact same Credo that makes the beer rare and exclusive
Clearly the West waiter and Travis take pride in creating something great that people enjoy
But you the consumers of beer
Arnott
The real customer
God is
The head of the Abbey says on their website
We are not
Brewers
We are monks
We broke up here to be able to afford being monks
This beer is not about you and me
They're not creating a purist mystique and challenging us to come to the monastery and experience their beer in
I am totally ready to capitulate to the monks just like that Connecticut hamburger place
I will do
Whatever they want me to do
I want them to know that I am on board
Did I speak their language
But it turns out they're not even talking to me
As we mentioned earlier The Limited supply of us later and had created a pricey Black Market
As I'm recording I search
OfferUp KC
24 bottles of blood splatter in on eBay
The current bed
Is $550
Plus $50 shipping
23 minutes left
Original price paid at the Abbey was just under fifty bucks
To the Delight of beer aficionados worldwide and spring 2012 Escalade Ranbir was finally
Where did in limited edition packages of four bottles
Various countries including the US
They're called building boxes because the proceeds are slated to go towards the expansion and renovation of the 18th Ave
And if you're wondering if I didn't episode about rare beer and Trappist monks partially as an extended metaphor about bizarre
Customer Service Media piracy and why I can't legally download new episodes of Game of Thrones every Sunday night
Well you wouldn't exactly be wrong
Even the 17th century monks
Are sending their beer out in a little box
On demand
There isn't like
What's the little button I can collect and download something
I want to pay you
Please
A Lannister Always Pays his debts
99% invisible with producers week by Cyrus farivar and me Roman Mars with special thanks to Sean Seneca
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Fran
Cisco
Support for 99% invisible is provided in part by tiny letter
Email for people with something to say my boy Carver always has something to say
What you have to say Carver
They are arachnids but they are not Fighters the load of my mind
Free easy minimal powerful the simplest way to write an email newsletter online at tiny letters
This program is distributed by PR at the public radio exchange making public radio more public
Online furx. Org you can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman
But you can always find the Show online and even talked about beer if you want to
I'll just be over here in the corner
Minnesota alldrive don't worry
99percentinvisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com