99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Goethe said that architecture is Frozen music
That's lovely
Of course that was before audio recording so now for the most part
Music
Is frozen Muse
It's only very recently in the history of music that we've been able to freeze music into an object
In my life the form of the subject matter to lie
One spot vinyl albums and cassette tapes
And there were two first songs per album side a
Inside B
The energy of a first song
Made it stand apart from the other songs
At least my head
Then the CD came along and eliminated side B and there was only one first song
And the actual number of the track that you can see
Prominently displayed on the CD player URI
That became my index for sorting songs
An MP3 is jumbled my sense of track order in albums begin to feel more like
A loose grouping of individual pieces rather than a conceptual Hall
I can do this all day and you're welcome to try man let's just let's totally has the Sound website
But my point is this
When it comes to music the form of the thing
Matters
But no effect
Has-been is world-changing
As the original innovation
Freezing music in time onto a recording
Or a single version of a song a single performance of a song
Became
The song
This inherently mutable method of communication
Was fundamentally changed
Songs
Astonishing things and I also don't think most people really
Even know what they are
That's the songwriter composer and producer Jon Brion
No I didn't talk to John Bryan
But I know people who did
Jim derogatis and Greg caught are the hotel radio program I'm a huge fan of called sound opinions
It's a rock and roll talk show
And if certain
Nietzsche snarky corners of the internet
Have darkened or concept of Music journalism
Sound opinions
Is your beacon of light my friend
Anyway
John Brian came to WBEZ in Chicago to talk to sound opinions in 2006
And at the time
Brian Tedesco produced
Kanye West album late registration
He was also already well known as a film composer of a lot of really great movies
Mini by Paul Thomas Anderson
I heard the show broadcast on WBEZ while I was sitting in my car in a parking lot of a Taqueria in Logan Square
And I thought about this section of their interview about
Songs versus performances
At least
Once a month
Since then
For 6 years
But only recently did it on me that this is a perfect 99percentinvisible story
So here it is
John Brian sound opinions in 2006
I distinguish between
Look for lack of better terms I call songs and performance piece
And
What most people like are specific performance as we've grown up in an era of
Recording
Had you know the very thing
One of the very things I love
Recording has
Killed people's ability to hear songs purely as
Core change
Melody and
It's a very
Strange and beautiful art form cuz when it's right do you know it
But
What we have sort of Lost
Is
I don't know the best example I can give would be
Led Zeppelin
Those things are the ultimate performance pieces and I'm a big
I think they're just absolutely astonishing
And the sort of Dynamics they had
Sorely lacking in
Music today
Record making is
Great
The true band in the sense that you really could
Tell who the individuals
Remarkable thing
Consider most of those things
Songs
And the way I can sort of prove my point is
Have you ever listen to anybody else play Led Zeppelin song and got all that was a great satisfying experience
What people like is that
Specific guitar sound
Specific performance
In concert with that
Specific drum sound with that
Pacific drummer playing that song
Pacific Park
And it's beautiful it's a beautiful thing they're all different types of art and creative expression
However
If I were to sit and go here
And I can play
Ghetto 30 others that
That's the thing
You know I know it could sound like a snobbishness it's not
I love these records
They're great
However it is
There's a difference between
Is that
Anna song
Say a Gershwin song
You could actually play in the style of Led Zeppelin and have it completely
Satisfying experience all the time
But when you start playing Zeppelin songs in the style of
1920s music it suddenly it's laid bare that it's like
Oh no it was about those people in those people were in a room that it was
I was great and I love it
But I considered a performance
When I consider
A lot of rock the people listen to be
Performance
Necessarily song so you know I heard you had the time you work here recently and there's a songwriter
Comes into the band and goes
Here's the thing I've got and then they you know
Brock with holy hardness and and all the greatness they've got with them getting a room
I mean that's part of what makes a band like Radiohead
Stand out at second
Record came out we all collectively went
Oh my God
Actual songs in this guy's an amazing singer
Exactly what I mean
Okay here
Google Music
Just go
Cool was
Punk rock
Popular he had it factor for days
But
If
You take the average Punk rocks on it is that Same Led Zeppelin Melody
Thousand
Punk songs there's a big difference between that
I mean
Sit here on grand piano playing unaffected version and we can all go oh my God
Anytime
Play that Melody over those core change
Lithium is no
Different it's in the same realm is being able to go in
Where
You know
Most people I remember exactly where I was
First time I heard Lithia
Leopard back of the friend's car and it came on
And
I just
Freaked out I mean I was nearly in tears I'm like
Oh my God that guy
Better than everybody
It was so palpable
That's one of the best chord changes I've ever heard
It
Absolutely as good as
First one
Felonious Munk
Or any great thing that's a
Was John Bryant talk with Jim derogatis and Greg caught on sound opinions in 2006
Sound opinions is produced by WBEZ Chicago and distributed by PRX
Public radio exchange find out more at soundopinions.org
99% invisible with produce this week
Pretty much by sound opinions
Special thanks to Robin Lynn and Jason Saldana
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San
Support for 99% invisible is provided in part by the Facebook design team
Believe that design can bring positive change to the world
Is it time at facebook.com design
And my tiny letter
Email for people with something to say
My boy Carver always has something to say what you have to say Carver
I think that my dad is the best
Do you know like if I put that on everyone's going to say
O Ramen
You just made your son say that he's the best for you
What do you have to say about that
Can you take me to West about how to office phone
Newsletter tiny weather.com from the people behind MailChimp
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars and I'm serious let's talk about
Objects of Music change the way you both make and listen to music
I'm ready to throw down
At 99percentinvisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Arts on the truth podcast. Com