99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
My friend know where can advertising
Where is starlee Kine
And this is her friend all my name is
Noah Ritter
And I'm
Associate creative
What is a associate creative director do
Associate creative director
Guides
Helps
Alps
Oh my God
I don't know what I do
2003 Knowles working at an agency in Richmond Virginia
Everyone wants to work on flashy spots like Apple
Are Nike
Gatorade
You know it wasn't flashy
Insurance
Which is why when it company called Geico became a client
Everyone help desk
People would run the other way when the
Creative director
For Geico would come down the
Definitely some decking
What's happening
Is it a wrong water cooler at the wrong time or what
Altima got stuck with Geico
His job is to help him somehow figure out a clever
Explain how simple it was for people to sign up for their insurance online
So put this in the context for us because I've seen about a million of these at this point on all the time
Do you watch the Bravo Channel doll
If you didn't act like you're kind of Top Chef is still good and if you watch Bravo every single cover
Christopher Bravo
Is an insurance ad and there's any such as Geico anymore cuz now it's it's all these TV people selling insurance right
Does a president from 24
He selling insurance that loser boyfriend guy from 30 Rock who sells it to you
I love that you like them
Watch Miguel now that you're kicking that you have a favorite like back then
Before Geico there weren't any on so nobody could you you wouldn't nobody would be competing about witch hat with her
Favorite insurance commercial insurance commercials
I guess when Geico first cannon old office
Insurance is almost entirely marketed through Direct Mail
Noah's also in the midst of reading the short story collections Australia
George Saunders
The title story is about a theme park
Which has come to learn how other civilizations live
Attractions are
Russian peasant Farm
Pioneer encampment
And why is Mountain hermit
Focus of the story though
Is on the prehistoric exhibit
But you actors
I want in a man
Play the part of cave husband and cable life
No Love the Way contrast two very different elements that shouldn't have gone together
It was like taking
Unnatural
Cable
Stalactites
Stalagmites
And I'm showing what life was like
Back in caveman
Hiring these Lo Ren actor
I have to admit I'm not feeling my best
I'm doing so bad
That I really have anything to complain about
Thought that I would actually verbally complain if I did have
The story is both very funny
And very sad
The cavemen husband takes his work super seriously
Using body language to communicate
How to break in character even though weeks pass when no visitors come by to watch
I'm sitting back on my haunches
Waiting for people to poke in their heads
Hello it's been 13 days
Has anyone pooped in their head
The cable man on the other hand speaks English all the time
Janet speaker
Chicken, a job and tries to get him to loosen up
Is partly why I feel so
You know
Crummy
To the tedious routine
Pointless tasks
Elida language Echoes that of office life
Janet scratches under armpit
Makes it sound like
Time lights a cigarette
What about you
Why you insist I'll never know
Who's here
You see anyone here but us
At the end of each day they have to fill out daily partner evaluation forms
And the cave husband always says his cave wife is doing a good job
Even when she clearly not
A gesture to her. Put out the cigarette and make the fire
She gestures to me to kiss her butt
No idea walma Geico campaign
Gina's creative team
Whatever that is
Trying to come up with interesting analogies
Picture of baby
Can be potty trained
You could push the few buttons necessary to file a claim with Geico
Four puppets
Pulling fire alarms
None of their ideas felt right or special enough
We needed a break
And we
I had gone to lunch and we're sitting there eating your lunch
And then all the sudden I'm like
Wait a second please cavemen
From
The sondors bike like that
That's perfect
And
The whole slogan
Came to me for life
It's so easy a caveman can
Which of course became the ads that you are probably picture in your head right now
Michael George Saunders story bad they're funny
But also a little sad
Sarcastic cavemen who seem truly Pain by the label that Society has given them
Why did I bother you
Why does it bother me
So easy a caveman can do it
Geico.com so easy a therapist can do it
Therapist are what
Mark
No says when the caveman commercials first aired
His agency received several letters from Individual viewers
Hacking of a blurry caveman playing a piano in the background of one of the spots with the actor Val Kilmer
Commercial put Geico on the map
So that got started wondering if she could trace the trail inspiration back even further
So she called him George Saunders ask him
About some the influences in his life that made him the kind of writer he is
Only when you're a writer and you going towards people talk a lot inspiration you have a carnival
List
Piano
Will Shakespeare
Or at least it is coming from a different direction
And by different direction
What he's trying to say is Charlie Brown
Peanuts Christmas and Halloween
Embarrassingly
Big
In my
Childhood
I've never seen anything quite so totally
I know complicated or something that I felt a real direct line between
The way I was feeling about things in the way my neighborhood looking felt
I would do a lot of dreaming walking around the neighborhood
I really love that Lucy and Linus doing that
Etsy
Assure you
How that your experience is actually
Really sacred
That's really valuable your neighborhood is really
It's important as any other place in the world
Eating a part of the king of influences Inc
Say something in the world
That intrude on us
Change it
But the other way to see it is there something in US
Find
Mirror
And then I think when you go to do some work
Something in your eyes
Jordan also influenced early on by the jerk
Mighty Python and Jaws
Mew the teenager
Listen to his favorite Yes album over and over and over again
Fixated on the way they had ordered their songs
What did he mean what did they mean by putting this one lasted that later
Influence how you
Ordered your stories and treasure icon
Michael Jordan became engineer
We first started seriously writing to read only authors who are dead
Hemingway Carrick Mahler
He consciously tried to avoid all living Riders
One day
Just to get it out of the way
He went to the Chicago Public Library
And piled together a stacked literary journals
My goal was read about 15 literary magazine so I could pin
Totally abandon
Contemporary story
Go back to China me anyway
Open the magazine
Start reading a story and then push it aside thinking it was dumb
Many came across the short story called hot ice
Play Chicago author named Stuart dybek
A work of literature
That was set in a physical place in time that I knew
And Lily in 15 minutes
Lyrics for in the understood
Relationship
But I mean like your stories are these
Hyper realistic
You're free to invent 100%
You can just make up whatever you want
Knowing that your spiritual
Even if it's a theme park
Kaitlyn
Whatever it takes ring to get this
Shinobu fine-looking
Streetsboro
Poetry
Now that I didn't know what the hell
So crazy but at the end I was shaky at
Tears my eyes
Face was red
How to write like that then
Yep yep
Immediately lie like that night
Which got me thinking
What influenced Stuart dybek to write the way he did
I called him up at the place in Florida he runs every year
Boy catches fresh fish every morning
Enterprise I'm up for lunch
Stuart told me that when he first started writing it also fall in love with a great American realists
Saul Bellow and F Scott Fitzgerald and Nelson Aldrin
It never occurred to hand write any other way
He always wrote while listening to music
When he was 25
He became enchanted with two Hungarian composers
Zoltan kodaly and Bela Bartok
Play Traveller on Eastern Europe recording music on sonographic cylinders
He went to the Chicago Public Library
The same one that George Saunders would go two years later
And he discovered Stewart story
And checked out as many bar-top and kodali Records is he could find
Music on
Set down the right
Story about
Stuff we used to do as kids in the neighborhood tell Sam that I grew up in an inner-city neighborhood on the
Southwest sign
Corny to say you went into a trance
But I was
I was taken out of my
Can answer I turn the music off and looked at the three or four pages
That I had written
I realize that I was writing in a way I had never imagined I could write
In a voice I didn't know I had
The music it just opened something up in
Listening to that music was the central thing that would happen to him as a writer
Everything from that point on was due to putting those two Records On
Bad influence by the composer
Did you say
Inspired by the work of the poet baudelaire
Who have the work of Edgar Allan Poe
Baudelaire wrote that he loved Poe because he was like him
Quote
The first time I ever opened a book by Poe
I discovered
But the Rapture Nas
The only subject which I dreamt
The whole phrases I conceived written by Poe 20 years before
Destroy the Raven inspired by bird and Charles Dickens story Barnaby Rouge which poet actually panned in
Review he wrote In the book first came out
The burden that can story
Was inspired by his real-life pet
A raven named grip
Who died from eating paint chips
Which brings us back to the caveman
Shirley Drew
At least a drop of inspiration from the lovely bird song
Dennis Geico
Inspire a half-hour sitcom
99percentinvisible was produced this week by starlee Kine With a Little Help From Me Roman Mars
The product of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Support for 99% invisible is provided by the Facebook design team
Believe that design can bring positive change to the world
Visit them at facebook.com design
Support is also provided by tinyletter
Attorney wetter.com
Email for people with something to say
If you get an email from my son Maslow it would probably be comprised of pages and pages of images
Bruce Banner turning into the Hulk
Lava Hawk pictures
I swear he could stare at those all day
It's the simplest way to write an email newsletter
Taipei weather.com
From the people behind nails
99percentinvisible is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more pub
Find out more at PRX. Org
You can find a show and like the show on Facebook a lot of stuff happens on the Facebook page you should join us there
I tweet at Roman Mars
Oh you know what brand new
Playlist
Grooveshark and Spotify
Songs that I use
And I never sent available episodes so you can score your life
Vicodin episode
99percentinvisible it's all there at 99% invisible
Darling
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
What's on the truth podcast. Com