99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance with Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their History season 2 Launches on May 15th between an episode
Really take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stock of love
Butters episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted of
Family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment in California and
On the globe Define transformational Solutions quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
A very different Kickstarter message written and recorded yesterday
We launched the kickstarter campaign for season 3 of 99% invisible on July 11th
In about 24 hours later
We reached
The kickstarter goal
I can't thank you enough
It was one of those amazing things I've ever been a part of really stunning
I didn't even have time to release an episode announcing the kickstarter
But now
I have a new goal
Personal goal
Five
I want
Thousand
Kickstarter
Play did any level the minimum is a dollar
A dollar
At any level
There are meeting prices at all different kind of levels you can go up to $10,000
Awesome t-shirts and posters and notebooks
It's all stuff that I had someone design because I wanted these items myself
But I'm not even talking about those levels necessarily I'm just counting backers
People who pledge
On Kickstarter for the show
At any amount
This is my new
Crazily ambitious
Personal goal 5000 backers none like the original Kickstarter goal
This one will likely fail
But if you hit every goal easily
You're not setting them High Enough
Fortune favors the Bold my friend
Always remember that. Org to find the link to donate work go to Kickstarter and do a search
On the show 5000 doctors that came to me as a number because I want to send a message to the people who
Who control the money in public media that if my little show conceited it like little radio station of kalw in San Francisco
So can be this successful and get massive widespread support from people online
Then they will all learn to take risks and fun people who make things that are personal and authentic
I'm talking about thumbing my nose at the man I want to inspire everyone else to be bold and know that if they take
Delete and try something great that's maybe a little different like in a regular blank radio show about architecture
Well that there are people out there who will help at least 5000 people
That will be so bad
Any amount 5,000 people I'm going to break Kickstarter across the servers I want one of those
Crazy Kickstarter success stories to be about a little public radio show instead of the high-tech Gadget
Wouldn't that be cool
99percentinvisible. Org there just do a search on Kickstarter
Be one of the five
Here's the show
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The hotel on the very prominent corner of Touhy and Kilbourn Avenue in Lincolnwood Illinois used to be the
Towns most famous building
The first Hyatt Hotel in all of Chicagoland
Premier accommodation
Top Notch restaurant it was Swank
Roberta Flack stay there stay there Michael Jordan stay there
Find in Chicago every 13 year old boy in the area
Had his bar mitzvah there
Hotel was built in 1960
And it looks it
So if you're wondering how much potentially anachronistic Lounge music I'm going to cram into this episode
So it's going to be a
Then
Slowly over time
It became Lincoln Woods most infamous building
It changed hands
Got CD and rundown
It was the home of the Midwest fetish fair and Marketplace convention
There were drug-fueled sex parties attended by Shady Chicago politicians later convicted of things like
Torsion
And of course
There was the convicted mobster Allen Dorfman
Who was gunned down in the parking lot
That's not why everyone in the area knows the building
If you know nothing of its history it's still
Pretty hard to miss
Because
It's
Purple
Really really
Growing up nearby I always thought it was really
Really
Ugly
Lots of people dead
Lots of people didn't but everyone had an opinion about it
Brooklyn Max infl talking to you now by the way nobody SAS public radio host and Steven British sitcom one
She has a secret
About the purple Hotel
My father
Designed it
My name is John Max I am a retired architect and former professor
UIC
I designed a lot of
Just a building
I don't have time for the long by Odette okay I designed a lot of apartment build
Things in Chicago
We're here to talk about the purple Hotel
I need you say I design my name is Jonas. I'm an architect I designed the proposal
My name is John XII I'm an architect
And I was the designer of the purple
Finally
Now you have to understand that when I say the building is purple
I don't mean the kind of purple of saying Iris
Store a plum
It's purple as an lavender
Lavender purple glazed brick all over pretty much the entire thing
Which needless to say makes it stand out
Depending on how you look at it
Like a prized Jewel
Or sore thumb
What are the few buildings if you see it once you know it
You single forever you can't feel
It is so purple that after it changed hands the new owners renamed it
Purple
Hotel
WBEZ architecture critic
Wee Bey
I think that it's worth looking at
Absent the break the brick I like but I wish you could eat also prom glasses I can filter it out so you don't see
The Brick
At least in one trip
And really see how the building hold yourself together structure
I think it's really
The way the John was able to put those supports on the outside of the hotel
To get larger floor plates in the middle versus what you want what you want big function spaces
And then I get a little mix of green space in the way that I'm
So the building is going to stick together with a lot of good things going on there
Architecture
The thing that everybody notices first including architects
Would be the
I mean I think that if anybody saying that it's not the color that they're lying
Because you can't really look at the building
Stop noticing
Purple
So it's the only purple building around but then
You know after that initial wave of color hits you you notice really what a great modernist structure it has
Structure is expressed on the owl
Side which is also not something you see everyday anymore
I think it's a wonder
That was Jackie cool founding principle of the architectural firm coo and Associates
Will get back to her in a minute
The first the story of why and how the building got to be so
Purple
My dad
John Maxson
It was commissioned by the pritzkers
The Benedict family in Chicago
And it was
The first Hyatt Hotel
In the Midwest
It was called
Hiatus
Have nothing to do with it
The purple by the way the purple came
Because one of the pritzker say and the big man among them
Fiskars in the family
Ask me what
Color
Play style I want the news
And I wanted to use Gray
Adhesive install
I like something brighter
So I made a mistake of showing him
The samples
Books
Kevin Garnett
Color samples
It sure enough
You pick the purple
And you don't argue with a n pritzker
My father tells me the story but I suspect differently
He's always gravitated toward bold color choices
Our current argument is over bright orange balconies on a building that we always passed he loves them
And I hate
When I was growing up his favorite color was blue a color that to me uses
Suspiciously close
To purple
In fact every house we ever lived in
Brick bungalow summer house in the woods
Suburban Barn shaped house
Mustard colored siding all had bright
Blue front doors
That my father painted
My elementary school bus driver used to call me Blue Door
Upon interrogation
My father coughed up is strange Hungarian Lodge
In the near East
But ultimately I come from
The blue color on the doors blue and green
Is to keep the evil spirits away
So that's a reason
I always suspected
The
Entrance Door
Houses
Blue to keep the evil spirits
If it did
Do you think it works
Hotel
So you don't think the purple kept away the evil eye from the hotel
Not really
Because
And that was a murder in the hotel actually there were two
But I digress
The beauty of that building is the exposed
Concrete strain
How to tell him sorry
Pulled out of the stuff
Showing
It's like a human being
The skeleton will be on the exterior
Especially
That would be weird right now that's that's stick
The building is that column set
Pose.
The slap site
Slightly pulled out
It's a Building B
Reviews
It's structures
And that is architectural
The interesting thing about
Dudley lullaby
It could be green
Okay
It would be the same good or bad built
So as an architect I have to ask you
This is a perfect example of
What the
But the difference between what the public sees
And what the Arctic
Because the public sees purple brick
Ark
Protecta sitting here saying the purple is so
Unimportant
In the scheme of the building
It means nothing
It's just such a tiny thing but to the
Public that's all it is
That's right because the public is ignorant
Truly ignorant
Well you can't really argue with them there
But in our defense and account myself is
One of the public in the scenario
It's really really purple Smite how far the purple Hotel fell from its original Glory the
Dilapidation the murderer the drug-fueled sex parties and a demolition order
It was not torn down
Time passed
Economy fell to pieces
Mid-century architecture
Slowly came back into Vogue
Mad Men was on TV
Purple brick was kind of retro cool. However dim was starting to shine on the building and its future
Then the purple Hotel was nominated for landmark status a place on the historic registry
There was talk of finding a buyer talk of renovation
And then while I was searching and interviewing for this very story
Purple Hotel
Went up
For auction there was a lot of Pomp and Circumstance in the beginning of
You know the auctioneer yelling and saying
Are you ready
Booming voice and then and then
And then
Really
There was only one bidder so
And that bitter was Jake Weiss of Weiss properties in Skokie which happens to be right next to Lincolnwood
He bought the purple Hotel
And why why is a shrewd businessman with a Keen Eye and good instincts
This particular purchase
Was also
Labor of love when you have some of that really is just not realizing of the value and it's
Potential
That is such
Prime piece of property that bothers you you know it it's part of your neighbor as part of your community
And it's something that you really want to see be an asset to the community instead of a blight
Here comes the love part
Separately from that when my
And more importantly I think
We almost lived at the purple hotel for a period of time
Maya
When my grandfather passed away and my father was saying.
Traditional Cottage
That's the Jewish prayer for the Dead
There was no synagogue anywhere in close proximity to where he lived at the time
And because we're Orthodox when I drive on the Sabbath
That was a little bit prohibitive to
City college
There's a very
Convenient show right down the block so I'm
Every single job is for a year
How we would move into the purple Hotel
Had to accommodate my fathers
Responsibility to say the kaddish for his father
So we lived there for about a year every single weekend
And you know me my sister at the hotel was our playground
And the architect Weiss is chosen to redesign the purple hotel and bring it back to its original luster
Is Jackie COO of Jackie Cooper and Associates
Also
Former student of my father the original architect
John Maxon
One of the things that we're looking into is more of a historic
Restoration of the building
That would be wonderful I'm especially since we have some of the old drawings
The original drawings from the 60s 1961 when it was constructed
And there are a lot of pieces that are still left in the building such as this wonderful
Monumental Terrazzo stair with this wood wall behind it I mean you can really see it as a
Kind of
You know late 50s early 60s kind of Mad Men era
Pan Am sort of
Hotel
That really could
Be very current in today's Hospitality environment
Especially in the hospitality Market
For some reason purple is a predominant color not necessarily the color of the brick
But an older marketing I mean you'll look at the neon lights and the color of the
Bob card
IMDb
Brochures that get printed for some reason
Purple is popping and I'm not quite sure why
Have any of your buildings
Had
This kind of
History this kind of life cycle
But you know
None of them
The same way that a person they go through life and you might go through different Cycles yourself and
Everybody goes through different rebellious
Ups and downs
The same holds true for
A property like this that really was a character of itself the building was
Really a product of the environment around it at any given time and
Not too certain extent the fact that the building did change
With the
Decades and the environment around it
It really is in the building's character
And while it's true that this character this building
This structure of nine lives
Empty at the moment surrounded by board traffic and an empty parking lot
It may just be crouching
Gathering it's muster ready to spring back to life
Arresting that traffic
Feeling that parking lot
And spreading like a proud
A purple one
99% invisible was produced this week by Gwen Maxon host of ReSound
Third Coast International audio Festival With a Little Help From Me Roman Mars
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Support for 99percentinvisible is provided in part by the Facebook design team believes that design can bring positive
Change to the world
Is it them at facebook.com
Support is also provided by tinyletter
Email for people with something to say
My boy man's always has something to say
We have to say mad love
Where is Sangamon
What is that mean
Tony wetter.com the simplest way to write an email newsletter
From the people behind mansion
This program is distributed by PRX the public radio exchange making public radio more public
Online at PRX. Org
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook like tweet
At Roman Mars
This week we don't want to go to 99percentinvisible. Org
Look at pictures of the purple Hotel
And become one of the 5000
Come on don't think just go go to Kickstarter let's make this happen
Right now I'm optimistic
I might feel differently in Excel
Let's do it
Does the name
Mad Men mean anything to you
Madman
Mad
Men
No
No association with that word
Repeat it again
Mad
Men
Omad
Mad
Yes
But it's also
The name of a
The television show
No no I am fortunate
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked
Play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 lb
All of a sudden to play like a dad I'm Evan
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I
I had something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com