99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is not 99percentinvisible
But I am Roman Mars
This is a special presentation of the newest radiotopia podcast zigzag
Grandma Newsome Rohde & Jen poyant
Create a new woman run podcast company
Cold stable genius Productions
They're exploring funding through traditional Avenues but also through cryptocurrency
Inside of the reality show that follows their progress you're going to learn a lot about the digital economy and how decentralized crypto crew
Could change everything
Or not it's a huge experiment
That you don't want to miss
I'm in this episode that were featuring a whole lot
So I thought that 99 Pi fans would dig it
It's super fun
But unlike 99percentinvisible
There is swearing in zigzag even I swear in zigzag
So I just want to warn you
All right
Enjoy
I'm a new summer OD and this is chapter 4 of zigzag
Podcast about changing course
Of capitalism
Journalism and women in Tech
We're exploring these very big ideas
Through our own personal story
At this point it's late April
Gemini's don't have enough money coming in to
Parasol
Your mom's
Not having paychecks was giving a stomach aches and eye twitch
Is it time to nail down a plan B
The financial backup
Resistors how startups work you just got to knuckle down and wait out the uncertainty
We go looking for those answers in this episode
Chapter 4
Specifically we pitch
Sort of
A well-known angel investor
And then go see the co-founder of radiotopia Roman Mars
To find out how he build his
Podcasting app
This is me and my husband Josh not to be confused with Josh Benson
S&R blockchain Matchmaker
A little vacation from your family
Car on our way to the airport
He was going to Puerto Rico Governor Cuomo
Why are you speaking so slowly
Because it is 5:12 in the morning and it's taking me a little time to formulate my words
Politics for a local TV news station
We have two kids
But don't worry my mom was home with them as we scattered ourselves across the globe
I was going to San Francisco
What are you doing okay so I'm going out there will for a multitude of reasons we're going to pitch
A first for me
Going to hang out with Roman Roman Mars
For the day tomorrow in Oakland what do you think of my whole Endeavor so far are you
Aspects of it is too strong a term I'm happy for you for you
Serta following alarm
Like
Despite the fact
A block away
So instead
Everything conversation
514 on the way to the airport
It's our special time Josh
We should just get up every Sunday morning around 4
Take a ride to the airport and back
Yes
Josh has been super supportive of me doing this startup thing
I texted our little chat to Jen who was also headed to the airport to meet me for a flight
That's really cute you guys are just fascinating I assume that Josh
Schleich knew every detail for some reason of what's going on with you right now so that's pretty funny
End
That's badass
That
You guys both are like we're both going to
Do your thing so police report
Josh and I are really lucky to have families who lived
Nearby who helped out a lot
Jen doesn't have that
Most people don't
But that wasn't stopping both Jen and I from worrying how we're going to make this podcast and run a business
Steam
And that takes more than a cryptocurrency that doesn't exist yet
It takes cash
Just why
Jen and I decided to go on a wreck up
Mission
Trip to San Francisco
To see if we can find a back-up plan
A plan B
Because that's what responsible adults do these days
They'll put their savings on the line they get rich people to invest in their business
So far we've lost our first grant that was chapter one that we've been counting on
That was awful then we got in this other small grant that was having real money and having cryptocurrency that still didn't
This yet
Is like ziggety-zag Ade but like
Maybe it was trying to find some stability but having an investor
Or would that just create bigger problem
We weren't sure
Then I had done our fair share of reporting on tech companies that put their profits ahead of basic Humanity to a
Appease shareholders
But there's also the good side to Silicon Valley
Big Ideas can happen because people believe in them
And back then
Was big money
Okay we just landed here is our planet it's jam-packed we were meeting with an angel investor named Jesse
Torelli that afternoon
And I guess we're going to catch her
Our plans see if she gets it hopefully she will
And then say what are the next what's the next move
Flowers and shower later
Okay we are walking down 3rd Street
In the mission
To a coffee place to meet Jess Pirelli
Lucifer Ella
She was an early development strategist
@twitter
You've done your homework Jen poyant
Go to the copy shop we were going to meet Jess a little early
We just could not stop talking about what we had seen on our walk to the coffee shop
It's definitely the most extreme version of wealth disparity that I've ever seen
In America
Yeah look down and person after homeless person is lying in the streets
Look up and there are spiffy
Extremely wealthy people zipping by on motorized scooters and their athleisure wear
Jen and I had to abruptly end our conversation about the economics of San Francisco
Just arrived
We all agreed that the cafe was way too noisy
We grabbed some iced coffees to go
I went down the block to Jesse's apartment building
Thank you
She said we could talk in the conference room by the lobby
Is San Francisco show apartment buildings have conference
Yeah hi I'm Jessica Borelli
We were connected through a mutual friend
Crystal sacca
Who I've known for a long time
Founding partner of hashtag angels
Which is an investment Collective I co-founded with five other women
3 years ago
I spent my career working in Silicon Valley at
Twitter over eight and a half years
Start working for Venture Capital firm
We were frankly initially buried
Resistant resistant
We have reservations are skeptical about
Because we were a little worried about having to push for these returns
Define incentive
That is a smart question for you to ask and it doesn't work of us
You're really thoughtful founder which is
How do I make sure
Vision our expectations and hopes I have for my company
Aligned with the expectations of an investor
A lot of time because you get that right
Obsessed with it
Like we talked about it all the time
Venture capital
Is a great way to finance if you want hyper-growth
And so
Hyper-growth
It's not to be obtuse about this is is the rate of growth and the
I want to grow that's going to take
Anywhere from one to five years I would imagine
For us too
Launch 3 shows and then spend those off into those different multi-platform
But I guess the question
Is the
Maybe the exits
Strategy be expected to exit all those questions about what
What do the investors want back like what level of growth is expected in
Do we have to know all that at the beginning
Generally if you're raising venture capital
At investors are looking
Are looking for a business that they believe
Can transform an industry
Was this a pitch or more like a tutoring session
I guess my hope
And I want to be upfront about it is that we do have investors who care as deeply is
We do about the
You know that societal impact of the
Stuff that we make
That's really important
I mean I definitely want to be big so I think these ideas need to be big in their big ideas
But I also think like is there room for that to be
At this point Jen kicked me under the table
Conscientious
By accident she told me later
But at the time I thought you wanted me to shut up
I think so I think it's all about finding that right
Set with an investor
And given how important that is to you and given
Trump
Growth
I think being as exactly as you're being rather explicit about your goals are for their send what success looks like to you
Who is going to help you find an investor
That aligns
And I can do you know anyone like this is sound like farfetch.
Wait was this weird that we were kind of pitching someone to fund our work
Which would basically criticized the tech platforms that they had also funded
I think these people exist I think I want to send a little bit more time with you on
The ambition for what you want to build and what that business and scale might look like yeah
This face should be
All about building a product and get a few customers
If you need money right now then you got to think a little bit about like okay what is the right sourcing
Whether it's revenue or Grant or seed funding
But if you have a time for your back in a fundraising mode
I think we can
But they take
Tapastic the process is very often very bureaucratic
And we might have
But that takes time to come out
We're definitely going to have to go into debt unless we get some Defenders I think that's basically what
No that's correct
Yeah for sure
She haven't looked at her watch yet but the Justice we were wasting her time
AAA
You always take care of most of the rescuer and so it's about finding the right alignment with those that believe in you and believe what you're building
Show friends and family around maybe possible so far does seem like something word
The impact investors might be the better fit but I don't want to jump to that conclusion with edges like really like
Talk through that
It sounds like you have
An incredible background to do this you've been successful duena Senor prior roles
Can I take a look at some of that
How big of a business is this is this the next
Like massive
Like Global Media Company
Is this the seed of something that can be really big and is that what
They want to build
Do they believe there's a path to doing that
How quickly can we come back and do that
This week
Cool
Talk
Decide whether we want to do that
Okay I just wanted to make sure
Yeah
Absolutely
Thank you so much
Jen and I walked out of our meeting with
Jess
Kind of stumbled
Stunned
Into the waning light
Of a crisp
Spring evening in San Francisco
What a weird experience we had presented a united front
To Adventure capitalist
But meanwhile our brains had been talking to each other like ESP
Don't do this
Do this
Do I do this
Don't do that
Exactly 2 hours
She said she'd be with us for 2 hours and 2 hours
Since that meeting by the way just has been named the newest partner at the Google back venture capital firm GV
At least you knew what you was doing
Jen and I needed to debrief
Paint thinner
Isn't it just amazing words yeah
I feel like that was bad
You do
Why do you say that why you feel that way that's so interesting
Cuz it's not what I think in our guts she knew and we knew that it's not
Like you were like I definitely want to catch this and I was like
I felt pretty out of my comfort zone
We stayed in the media business like we both like it
We like the
People who are in it and we like the
Emphasis on ideas as opposed to valuation and
I just don't want to be thinking about money like to me the greatest luxury is not to be thinking about money
I can't wear business people now we have to
My golden is to get to where I don't have to think about money
My goal is not to like
Cap
Send
Tables and all that it's really not like I don't think like I really I really care very much about like make
Making stuff with you and feeling that creative
Wonder and like people feeling moved by the things that we make and like that matters a lot to me
Matters to me too I just don't know how we're going to do it
That leads me to okay just wasn't right like to even want to go back and actually try and picture
I mean it song
Like no
In the short-term
She kind of said like
Grants and family and friends
I think the bigger thing is what we're going to do like
We work our asses off until we watch this show and then we go back to Lake Amado are we to see where the fun
Comes in we grow it waste lower together
And there's no Lake
Is there shame in that I feel like we feel like there's a minnow but I just keeps telling us that that's not possible
Dan was a business consultant who is helping us project future budgets and Revenue
I mean seriously we need to have this entire conversation over again with Robin tomorrow
It's going to be it's going to be different I don't think there's any shame in that that's essentially going back to like they're real bootstrap
Remodel and then seeing where we go from there fine with that I'm fine with that which is awesome
I'm totally fine with it right then
It's weird how you eat I feel like you know there's still utilitarian in many ways there's not a ton of soul
Makes me so happy you said that
It really does
Yes dude you know I'm very much about
I mean not like in the not like Franklin
I think the other thing that's so strange is that we believe so wholeheartedly and Lee
We are women we could do this why don't we take that opportunity this is crazy not to
But it's not right for us
And that's
Hard that's why I feel like a disaster to me because I'm like
I feel like a disaster let me be clear
I'm realizing
It's like part of me was like guess we'll put you
Because I think I'm
So worried about letting you down money-wise
You taking a
Like
Are you at the same thing dude
Your aunt taking a big risk but your
You've invested a lot already into it
So I'm worried about the same thing
I mean it's not like we don't have
Some money coming in
Right right
Don't forget to forget that
Oh that looks yummy
Great and I want to eat one of your French fries thank you so much
Beautiful
We really wanted financial support to make our mission-based journalism possible and we really wanted honesty from Egypt
Weather
Right now we have the ladder
You're listening to a special presentation of zigzag
On 99percentinvisible coming up Jen in the news come to Oakland ride to spend some chill wisdom
We are featuring episode 4 of zigzag to follow along with the stable Geniuses as they formed A New Path
Women in media and Tech
Gota zigzag pod.com to subscribe
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You probably her to say that we are proud members of radiotopia at the end of the first three episodes
Some might say that we have rapper POs to thank
For our entree into that awesome podcasting Collective
Last year he put out a song called wearing a bear
He gave shout-outs to me
Radiotopia co-founder Roman Mars
Cup holder
But the passengers ice-cold pushing down the pressure when a guy I'll guess tags
Get better
Now Jen and I were the newest members of radiotopia
And that meant we owned all our work
I had hung out with Roman before but he and Jen had never met
And when he suggested that we come out
Spend the day with him
We were both sick
Ira Glass
Jad album Rod
Roman Mars
These are the great names and narrative audio storytelling
So it's kind of like going to Kiss the Ring
Accept all of them or public radio nerdy cool so
Enter code
Play Store
Same weight that morning
Jen and I were most
Definitely not
Just getting into the building seemed to be a struggle for us
Roman Mars to know which one he's on
So sorry
That conversation with jazz must have rattled us more than we knew
Start
Okay let's try no
Here we go
Wow that's nice
Hainan
Enchanted
It's so nice to meet you
Did we have like
24 hours
When did you arrive
Yesterday
And then we had like an epiphany last night
But we need your help cuz
Over already
Public radio producer making shows barely making any money
When podcasting started taking off about 5 or 6 years ago he went to PRX and they decided to Jess Conte
Concentrate on that form a collective where the podcasters owns their work
It's stop worrying about making radio shows
Make a business out of podcasting
Or at least a decent living
Still doing great Public Radio
Alcantara
Roman and radiotopia had done one of the most successful Kickstarter campaigns in the history of Kickstarter
I am Roman Mars I am the host of night
And I am the co-founder of radiotopia from PRX
And we're sitting in your office downtown Oakland California
Romina definitely taking some big Financial Risk
In his time
I mean it's just like it's a business like any other so you make enough money to
Pea salary odoo
And then you see
Can you make enough money to
Add another person that another person then you make enough money to have money left over to
You reap the benefits of ammonia
And it took me
Bi4
Almost 8 years
And
The way it operated in the beginning was that
I didn't
Pay myself
I mean were there moments where you were like
What is it
I just feel like you can always get a job
So what does failure mean in this case
Tele means you do with the thing that everyone else does
That's not really failure right right
It's true
It's like
I don't know I didn't
I feel more scared of it now
And I did then
Yeah because
Can employees
Opiate self like
A lot of the revenue that operates radiotopia is the percentage of my show because my show brings in a lot of AD Revenue
Until like
Now I feel like
Timeout
Keep hustling
It's like different
We've been struggling to decide how to fully fund the show
Did they decide I suppose we've been talking about whether we should seek out investment or get grants or
Yes make the thing and then get the sponsorship that way you should do all of it
Right away
Radiotopia fundraising
Because we have a model which supports shows that can support themselves completely as Advertising based
We
We really need donations to support
Asleep at the hole
Slate of shows
And then we then we have to do that to me is like
That's how we make art
Like rather than Chase Commerce
What you just said
Art rather than Commerce
Kind of
Thumbs up
The
Soul searching that you and I have been doing Jen
So the question that we keep getting is what do you want it depends what you want what do you want what do you want
I think we're getting closer to knowing what we were
Well I think it's because the news
We starting to succeed in these ways where she was being asked to speak she's doing the Ted talk so we could naturally see a model
That would work that was bigger than just a show
We are
About to document this experience both of making the show making this business
All the different choices that were just talking about right
And it feels very vulnerable to admit all this on tape
Yeah I can see that I'm glad I wasn't talking to you my friend
Publicly is to women to do it
But you also I get that
Can I get that that's a risk
We also you're going to get a lot of strength from that too
Again it's like this balance of risk and reward and you have a greater risk
Can we bake and also it's just like
I fully believe
That
Your uncle
In life is to live an extraordinary
Like live a weird life
I think that's true I think there's that there are a lot of women out there
That need to
To hear other women doing this
You don't
We've asked for a lot of advice from a lot of people and every
Bit of advice when it comes to business seems to be like well the way of business works like
You're not going to be able to do this like a lot of people kind of say like it's not going to work
It depends on what type of business you have or one
I totally I think
You know like
Videos of bad startup in a good business
Because it doesn't
Return money the way they wanted to and if you do you have to grow and make things that you don't care about
But
He just want to make a show and pay yourself
You can do that
That is not that Steep Hill to climb
You could do that
And then from there you begin to go
I think that you follow your gut when it comes to that.
And personally I think that there's no money without strings attached the only money I've ever
It has strings attached. I like
Is money from the audience
I guess I'm going to be very
Business and fraternal or something
How much you got saved
Do you have a year saved
Can you live without making any money
I definitely cannot
I like 2 months baby laugh
So
Is that asymmetry in your needs does that cause attention in your choices
I would say that at the beginning where I was like well if I'm going to invest in the company I want to own more of it and gents it now
I worried it like you're putting in different sacs
I mean if a company can never pay me back that's
Tell me something
That's what I kind of think I'm really
Money is freedom
That's what it's for
The hard part of ownership is that the
The runway
SB kind of long
Yes for you gets the points sustainable
And if the runway is short then
It actually
It f**** with the sustainability
I think we're trying to figure out
What's a minimum we can pull in through all these various funding
Sources if we're not going to do the BC thing and still
Sustain ourselves
Until that Runway gets long enough for it to become really sick
I mean it's something you have to be prepared
Recognizance.
Working
I just think things like what
Is it it's kind of easy if you don't have a lot of other pressures
To hold onto something that you maybe shouldn't be holding on to
What would make you sun set this whole thing
It's a really good question
But you know it's that is so hard to answer cuz if you had
Ask me that about note to self I wouldn't have
Shit happens and you have no idea
Set this whole
Is it a better opportunity
It's like no cuz this is
This is the best
But let me ask you this
Can you just make 99 Pi forever like
Well I wonder that too
I've given myself
A kind of a timeline
Of I need to make it as successful as possible
43 now
I don't know if the end of it's going to happen when I'm 50
I think I would probably go your route faster like right now
Weird
People are doing projects inside of
Rainbow
Which will be new things for the word
And I can't really talk about him but we could say this much
I could imagine
That my life
Is
Not
Hosting
Yashow
Running Shop
And also it's just like
I
Feel myself more tired
Can I ever have
I just can't
I can't work this hard
Forever
Roman thank you so much
You guys are taking action
I don't know but it's a good chance like it's like that's the thing it's like it's more you were that's why raise up your work
It's like
I don't own it
And we don't own it
It's your chance to take we just get to be part of it and we'd like to be a part of things that we're proud of
Our session with Roman kind of felt like a motivational pep talk
We don't have to stand on chairs and yell like a Tony Robbins event
Dyspeptic was way more chill
Thank you and welcome
My pleasure I'm so happy you're here
This conversation was just what we need
Jen and I were resolved
Investment money
For now
Was not for us
Another
Enemies Act
That we needed to focus on making the podcast
This podcast
Stick to the mission
And then if we made it that far
Weed reassess
So we went back to New York and even put a big red circle around one summer day on the calendar
We labeled it
Financial Reckoning day
But it felt good to know we have the support of not just one
But to Collective
Roman and radiotopia
Kauai Distributing this show
And selling sponsorship
Uncivil
Experiment using the blockchain
To create a new ecosystem for independent journalists
True the whole thing with Stacy
But they had given us just enough money to pay the bills
Maybe the token thing would actually work
Anyway
The Civil people
Felt like our people
You been listening to zigzag
Go subscribe to her now and maybe I can talk when you come down into having me on the show again
Find it at zigzag.com on Apple podcast Radio public
Or wherever you get your podcasts
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com