99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Tell quick announcement before we start
Earlier this year I went to the Ted conference in Vancouver and I gave it talk about flag design
It was an incredible experience
And even though
There's a little bit of skepticism when I started the talk
You know when everyone
Learned that it was really going to be about 5 design the talk totally won over the crowd and I got a standing ovation
It was a real highlight of my career
And last week the video was finally released
So I really hope everyone who listens the show
Go watch it
Insurance
You're going to dig out
The cool part is that let me perform the talk
Like a radio piece instead of the normal Ted talk I'm sitting down and playing audio clips and talking over music
If it wants to get there
See my face while I do it
If you've been listening to 99percentinvisible for a while and you know that one of the thorns in my side
Is the city flag of San Francisco
If you're not familiar with that flag
You'll see the video it's not
Anyway
99 P I had some fans at the company Autodesk maybe don't know Autodesk
All you need to know is this
If
The thing you're looking at exists in three dimensions in the real world that object was probably design
Find on Autodesk software
So Autodesk has this big office in San Francisco
And they saw the TED Talk
It suggested that we partner together and help plan a redesign
Of the San Francisco flag
I'm really excited we have a website
San Francisco flag.com you can watch the Ted Talk there
Sign up
Learn more get involved
That's San Francisco flag.com
Please visit watch the video share the link
I'm trying to get my TED talk to become the most watched TED Talk
In history so we just need
33 million more of you to get there
So if interview
Who download the show
Watch the video
Between 60 and 70 *
We can make it or you can just shared a lot and make it run watch it
All right
Thanks so much
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
The office of the chief medical examiner in Baltimore Maryland is a busy place
Anyone who dies unexpectedly in the state of Maryland will end up there for an autopsy
On an average day they might perform 12 autopsies
I have your day they might do more than 20
The building is 6 stories tall
Around 80 people are employed there
All day long please are coming in and out
People are calling about their deceased loved ones
The Press is calling with enquiries
But there's this one room on the fourth floor
That sits apart from the buzz of normal Act
Tivity in the bill
Producer Katie mingle was just there in Baltimore
This room feels a bit more like an art gallery
Because
Well it is kind of an art gallery
It houses the nutshell studies
Which of these miniature dollhouse like dioramas
And each one is a different
Scene
There's a kitchen Log Cabin a barn a bathroom
There are 18 different scenes
And each scene has different tiny features
I need furniture
I need Windows and Doors Atlanta
And they're also tiny people
Dolls
In each scene
And all of the tiny people in these scenes
Have one thing in common
They're all
Death
When you look at a nutshell diorama you're looking for clues about how the person or persons died
Was it a suicide
Homicide
An accidental death
The guns are you obviously going to get a lot of evidence off
Forgotten so why would
So when I came in and murdered
Why would they leave a gun
So I said a minute ago that the nutshell room is usually a quiet sanctuary in an otherwise busy off
Usually
But this week there are quite a few
People in here
They're mostly police a few FBI and they're here for a week-long seminar
A homicide
Is that you know maybe he
Attendees will hear speakers Delsea an autopsy
And will be broken into groups and assigned a nutshell diorama
At the end of the week I'll be asking for that their theories of what happened in their dioramas
This group is looking at one of the few multi-room. Tell studies
Point gets in the bed
And then fall asleep.
But he tries
Compare under him
He might have thrown it off before him just one room in about the size of a shoebox
This one is a little bigger and has three rooms
Plus a porch
It's in a glass case so you can look down and see the interior
House from above he doesn't
Inject around until it comes into the the baby's room
The scene is of a lovely well-kept Suburban home
There are lace doilies on the tables
Flower print linoleum in the kitchen
And blood
Everywhere
In the bedroom a husband and wife are dead from gunshot wounds
In another room a baby has been shot dead in her crib
Blood is splattered all over the pink wallpaper
It's a gruesome saying
It was supposed to be a murder-suicide with him and his wife
He wanted the neighbors
Casinos near me
The seminar that brought these folks
Have been happening every year for the last 70 years
And the person who started it
Is the same person who made the little death scene dioramas
Her name was Frances glessner Lee and her work in the field of forensics has shaped just about everything that
It happened inside the office of the chief medical examiner in Baltimore Maryland
To tell her story
I want to introduce you to
A couple of people
Medical examiner's office
Are you can call our investigations to
That's Bruce Goldfarb
And I'm the executive assistant to the chief
Medical examiner for the state of Maryland
And this is Karin I am Korean box
I'm an artist
And photographer and I'm the
Author of The nutshell studies of unexplained death
Prince spent seven years researching Frances glessner Lee
Frances glessner Lee would have loved the opportunity to study medicine and going to college but her parents were not to
What about that
This was around 1900 women weren't really going to medical school
Her brother got to go though of course
And he brought a friend home one
A guy by the name of George McCrae
Who is a pioneering medical examiner
And when you come to visit he tell her stories about cases he was
And she was just absolutely loved it came from a wealthy Chicago
Go family
She was supposed to be a proper Society lady with Lady Hobbies
Take me to work
Interest in death wasn't really
Courage to buy her
Family
Which meant for years
She quietly studied it
Pictures of operations reader
You're talking to experts
Getting first-hand experience
Bye
Going to
Crime scene
And then came to realize that people were getting away with murder literally
Police would routinely pot
Investigate
They would contaminate crime scenes move bodies do things that
Today will be obviously you don't don't do that
But at the time they didn't know any better
Beyond that the police just didn't know how to get information from the scenes
Another might not realize the significance of
You know a pile of cigarettes
Sore
The positioning of a firearm
And the other thing was
Autopsy
Either weren't being done at all or being done by doctors
With no specific training in forensic
Eventually Lee's parents and her brother passed away
She was in her 50s by then
And she finally had access to the family money and agency to do what she wanted
Money
To Harvard University to establish
The first program in legal medicine to train.
And make them medical examiners
Amanda in 1945 least arts and presides over these week-long training seminars for police
The ones that are still going on today
She wanted to displease some other things
How to gather Clues from a crime scene of course in terms of his
Legalities and time constraints and weren't actually able to visit
A crime scene during the seminars
We decided to build miniature death scenes for the police to study each one will be based on a real
The nutshell studies of unexplained death basically she would come up with
That Concept in the design and
Carpenter would drop
The blueprints
Scale of an inch to a foot
Lee's Carpenter belt the structural frame the room exactly as you would a real life size rim wheel studs
Real doors with real locks
Worked Lee handled all the figures and the textiles the rugs and drapes
Some tiny clothes on the tiny figures
Finally those Society lady skills
For being put to use
She wouldn't it the stockings with needles aside to straight pins using a magnifying glass and of course
She can only work for like a few seconds before her eyes which
Fatigue
The figures in the nachos also sometimes show rigor mortis which is a post-mortem stiffening of the body
And lividity which is the way the blood pools or settles in the body after death both provide clues
Set the how and when a person die
The detail in the nutshells is bordering on abs
Excessive
In one an ashtray overflows with tiny cigarettes
Made with real tobacco and rolled by Lee herself
Each one burn
And then stopped out
The coffee pot she has there's a stranger inside and coffee grounds in it
We were life is you know you going to somebody's home
They can have a bag of drugs
But a weapon over here and I have a heart attack it may or may not mean anything
Frances glessner Lee spared no expense on her dioramas
Lavished
Love
Aunt Annies
Brutal crime scenes
Each one took about six months
At around $6,000
That's about the same amount of time and money it would cost
To build a real house
The 1940
Lease out like if
The policeman looked at them
And so any fault in her
And take some seriously you know
They won't learn from them
So
That's why she felt like everything had to be
Be done
Perfectly
Of course Frances glessner Lee was always trying to be taken seriously and they all male world
She had entered
She was ultimately both respected and adored by the police that she worked with
The week-long seminar she led were thought to be the best
Training homicide detectives could receive
And they're still thought of that way actually even today
After Frances glessner Lee died in 1962 the program so you find it at Harvard including the week-long summer
Branded
In the nut shells were put in storage
Possibly headed for the trash
And then the medical examiner in Baltimore at the time a guy named Russell Fischer who was a former student of
Please programs at Harvard
Stepped in and said
Will do it will do somewhere and it will just pick it up here in Maryland
And they brought the Nationals down and so it's been the seminar and the Nationals been used here since 1969
Going up
The building that houses the medical examiner's office in Baltimore is fairly new it was built in 2010
Bruce is giving me a tour of the building
It has some pretty unique features including a full-size apartment that investigators can use to stage
Stuffing
Right behind us we got it all
Dining area
Bruce refers to it as a life-size nutshell study
And the most violent room in Baltimore
They also have a parking garage that in an emergency can quickly turn into a huge mark
And they have a biosafety
Facility to deal with death from highly contagious diseases
Holy solution Suites
And it has its own power generation is on ventilator
As we walk around the autopsy floor
Second floor
I'm on high alert
I'm basically terrified of running into something I'm not prepared to
To see
Or smell
If you go to the deep end. If you want to stop and turn around 6 will be fine with me.
What will hold it together mangle
Totally not being cool
But we go through and the
Fine I mean DS there are dead bodies
And I have many existential feelings about that that I won't
Cher here
But mainly this place feels like a really clean Hospital
Protect people
If you like yeah this is how it should be
Francis
Believe
And
Science
Based death
The
The whole institution top to bottom
I think it is
Probably
Fullest
Embodiment of
Her philosophy
And for approach
Bruce is talking of course about Frances glessner Lee
He says not only is this building and embodiment of her philosophies
But so is the whole Maryland system for dealing with death investigation
If you die unexpectedly in the state of Maryland your death is likely to undergo a thorough investigation in
Putting an autopsy by medical examiner with specific forensic training
But this is not what you get
Everywhere depending on where you die
You could end up in a facility like Maryland are you could literally end up on a makeshift table in someone's garage
From state-to-state and even county-to-county there can be huge variations in quality
And there are definitely no federal regulations
There's a lot of substandard work
Unfortunately being done in that
Field it's not like CSI it's not like what you see on TV very often
That's a c Thompson
He did a bunch of reporting on this for propublica a few years ago very often
It's
People working under
Dismal conditions
For very little money
With very little oversight
When someone dies in the US and Authority has to issue a death certificate with a cause of death
If you die from an illness in hospital this is something your doctor would do
If you die unexpectedly like if you murdered or a fall down some steps
A death certificate is issued by either a corner
Or a medical examiner
Maryland is on a medical examiner's
South Carolina Colorado and several other states are on corners
And then you have states that are weird mix
Both
Depending on what
County you're in
In Frances glessner Lee was actually really passionate about abolishing corners
In favor of medical examiners
Because
Well I don't know if she would have put it
Like this but basically Corner system is crazy
It's it's Bonkers and it's a scientific thing from another era
First of all you don't necessarily have to be a doctor to be a coroner
That is to be the person who issues a death certificate with a cause of death
Like I'm a high-school graduate in a lot of places I could just roll out and say I'm running for coroner
And be the County coroner now I would typically work with an MD who would do the autopsies
But I'd be the one
Who make the final decision
And that's the other thing
The coroner
Is an elected office
When you have
Medical professionals
Professionals who have to run for office
Based on what happens in the morgue
Satsop
Potential conflicts of interest
One of the situations where you might see conflicts-of-interest are cases where someone dies in police car
AC actually did some reporting on this very thing in New Orleans what you see in New Orleans
Over and over and over again
Is that when
People died in police custody
1 people died in Jail custody
That would be pretty good evidence that something
Untoward had happened
They've been neglected
They've been severely beaten
They've been attacked
And what was happening with the corner there
Was basically trying to pretend that these things didn't happen
He was ruling death
To be accidental that should have been ruled as
What's homicide
His name is Frank Minyard he actually was a doctor but he wasn't trained as a medical examiner
He was an OBGYN
And he seemed to have a bias
Toward protecting the police
Maybe because he constantly had to campaign to keep
Job who does he want to endorse while he wants the police to endorse him
And if he's got a big spat with the police
Is that going to look good for voters
In New Orleans BFDI finally stepped in and did some of their own investigations and some police did eventually go to jail
They offer some of those deaths
But Minyard was never fired by the voters or anyone else
He served as coroner for 40 years
Finally retired in 2014
So it's worth noting when you're talking about
Incidents involving a
Edith the police shoot somebody
The coroner medical examiner is going to say
It was a homicide can't really get around that
Then the question will be is it justify
But then there are cases that are less cotton dry
And there's the ones where an impartial scientific death investigation might matter the most
And actually while I was in Baltimore
One of these cases was playing out
You probably heard about it
Forsook
Contagion Baltimore a demand for answers into hell 25 year old Freddie Gray
Suffered a fatal spinal cord injury
311 police custody
Freddie gray sustained his fatal injury on April 12th
He died a week later on the 19th
And 4 days after his death people protest
Unweighted
Deceive the state's attorney Marilyn Mosby would bring charges
Against the police involved in the incident
Mosby was waiting to
She was waiting to see how the medical examiner would rule the death
As soon as she got their findings
She made her announcement
The findings of a comprehensive
Scarborough
An independent
What's the medical
Examiners determination
What's a homicide
Which we receive
Today
Athleta
Believe that we have probable cause to file criminal charges
We don't know if the officers charged in Freddie Gray's death will be conducted
But they were charged
And a lot of people this was an important first step
I have left Baltimore by the time the medical examiner's office released their findings on Freddie Gray
How to say that having just been there and seen the way they do things
I felt pretty confident in their process
It felt like their findings would be based in science
I'm not tied to politics
I don't think it's a stretch to say that Francis Pleasant early
Had something to do with that
You know if she were to walk around
See what we do
How we do things here
I think she'll be very pleased
And if she really is
I love her believe in guiding spirit so that sort of thing but she is very definitely a presence here
Everyday
At the end of the Frances glessner Lee seminar in homicide investigation
Attorneys present their theories about what happened in each of their nutshell studies
And then they get to find out the actual Solutions
Was it a homicide staged to look like a suicide
Or suicide staged to look like a homicide
Or something else entirely
This is the folder that contains
The solutions to the nutshell
They didn't then the guy that has the answers to these questions might be the most Baltimore guy
In Baltimore
Hi my name is Jerry judge you have a job also known as Jerry d
Sometimes the police will come up with their own
Solution then
Since they're all wearing guns I don't challenge him to say you're wrong I just say that's not how France's saw it
But I do have the
Yeah the answer
Gdb is not going to let me see the folder
Or record when he tells
Fruition
They guard the nutshell Secrets like the recipe for Coke
For the code for the Google search algorithm because they're still valuable secrets
As long as the solutions aren't easily searchable
The nutshells are still great tools for teaching homicide investigation
And that is something that the medical examiner's office in Baltimore Maryland
Pixelberry
Very seriously
Thanks to everyone at the office of the chief medical examiner in Baltimore Maryland especially Bruce Goldfarb
Green boxes but the nutshell studies of unexplained death is full of amazing photographs of the nutshell
So which you can see on our website is 99 pi
. org
Being that this is the
70th anniversary
In order to celebrate we've actually had a 70th
Anniversary challenge coin made with Francis Bismillah on the back and Associates on the friends
Yep Katie got a Frances glessner Lee challenge going when she was there and Avery is so jealous
Make sure you coincheck Katie when is here
99% invisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project to 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flask podcast
Joann
Pictures and links
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com