99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
3 years after moving to New York City
Maggie Wrigley found herself on the edge of homelessness
It was 1987
Cheater boyfriend at the time have been living in a warehouse in Brook
Their landlord was shady
And they didn't trust him
Weekly want going to stay and pay him all this money and you know you got kind of crazy and we didn't really know where we were going to go
Around that time they heard about an abandoned tenement building on the Lower East Side
Who is owned by the city
But it been left empty
And unmaintained
Friend told them a group of squatters had taken it over and started to fix it up
It was a place they could live without paying rent
And he said doesn't doesn't
If you want to come a prophet
Are you got to go through these meetings to get in they got to approve you it's pain in the ass we were like when we need a place to
So Wrigley and her boyfriend packed up their belongings
And drove their old car from Brooklyn
Into Manhattan
In fact the day that we drove
Here
To move in out
Axle broke
On the cob just fell apart literally right outside the front door
So is like okay
We moved in
The building with the four-story structure
With mostly boarded-up windows
Mets producer Delaney Hall
Maggie and her boyfriend discovered that when their friends that the building was
Rough
He wasn't kill
The building was
Full of rubble some of the walls were rotten and falling down
It wasn't any running water
You got to open a hydrant with a wrench and then fill up these water buckets
Carry them back into the house and
It wasn't fun
And it was also winter time
When Wrigley moved
My dog's bowl
Would freeze my shampoo would freeze my everything would freeze in the house a toilet would freeze
It was like living in a refrigerator
It wasn't just the building that was falling down the hole Lower East Side which today is filled with expensive boutiques
Senayan condos
Was struggling in the 1980s
It was pretty dire I mean it was it was it was a
Broken
Brutal neighborhoods
So forget how
Astonishingly derelict
It was
There were empty lots filled with trash and falling down buildings everywhere
In fact Wrigley's building wasn't the only property in the neighborhood
That have been taken over by squatters
By the late 1980s
Squatters would come to occupy more than a dozen old cinnamon
On the Lower East Side
All the Misfits on the outcasts in the
The people that didn't have any other place to go could come here and make a community
And these Misfits and outcasts would eventually managed to do something kind of incredible
They resist eviction by the city
For almost two decades
Holding onto many of the buildings at the neighborhood around them rapidly gentrify
And as the properties grew more and more valuable and it's the city
Try harder and harder
To kick them out
Understand why there were so many abandoned buildings in New York City in the 1980s
You need to understand how a usable building
Can become
Economical
Worthless
In the 1960s and 70s New York City began Halloween out
The city lost many of its manufacturing jobs
People with mean started moving to the
The suburbs
In many neighborhoods
Like the lower
Decide
Property values started to slide
When landlords
Couldn't make a profit anymore by renting out
Their buildings in low-income neighborhoods
What's the low income tenants
They would start what's called milking them
This is dr. Amy starceski
2 minute apologist in an oral historian
And she's conducted dozens of interviews with the Lower East Side squatters
What's your here in the story
Francesca says that when landlords quote-unquote milk
Stair building
They do all they could to extract maximum profit
So they were trying to continue to collect rents but increase their profits by not spending any money on the building
First they would stop
Providing services
Heat hot water stop making repairs
They would also stop paying taxes
The landlords would basically make a financial
Calculation
The money coming in from rents wasn't enough to cover the cost of a mortgage or property taxes
Some landlords would just walk away
They'd stop maintaining the building and stop paying the tax
Zayo
When that happen
The city could take possession of the Builder
So a property values in New York City tank
And as more and more landlords walked away from their buildings
The city ended up owning tens of thousands of
Properties
That were
In poor condition
Full of poor people and which had been taken care of properly for a long time
City government wasn't in a good position to take care of these buildings either
It was in the middle of an economic crisis
And the government had started cutting off services
The some parts of the city
It wasn't intentional strategy
They called it
Planned
Shrinkage
So what that meant in practice
Was
Closing fire stations
I'm in poor neighborhoods
Withdrawing services
Not making repairs on public infrastructure
Enso neighborhoods like the Lower East Side like the South Bronx
Ended up largely depopulated
And just full of
Abandoned
Stem and burned-out buildings and vacant Lots
All of which men
Terrible housing conditions for the people that remained and lots of opportunities for squatter
Freedom of squatting also meant that
Got
For sort of already
Rollin and Tumblin
To American Life
In some way or another
Peterson YOLO is a poet who moved into one of the Lower East Side squats in 1988
The building he lived in was filled with artists
Punks transients activist
In this place logo
There were also a fair number of squatters with mental health issues and addiction problem
People who weren't able to hold them regular jobs or make monthly rent
For one reason or another
Hard to tell the difference between
Person actually a psychotic on their own or or are they
A little eccentric
Pissing in a bucket for five years
Have no windows on the
January
New York the squatters said about fixing up their decrepit buildings
Clearing Rubble
Building stairs reinforcing walls and replacing windows
They illegally tapped into the city's electric bread and water cyst
Everybody works
Together Maggie Wrigley
I mean I built this house
I raised my floors in Ohio I wired electrical
People built out their spaces in highly personalized ways
One guy's apartment was furnished with cabinets Salvage from an old Pan Am airplane
One apartment was done all in shades of purple
Purple stained oak floors
Adult big open spaces for art galleries in puncture
For a lot of people it was thrilling
To live in a place that allowed for so much freedom
How many of the squatters saw themselves as a
For cheap or free housing
In the neighborhood that was plagued by homeless
You saw it everywhere you went and
Did every neighborhood
Especially true
On the Lower East Side
In the neighbor
Easter pocket square
Spagnola and some of his friends would make brochures and go hand them out to homeless people in Tompkins Square Park
And the pressure was basically like
You don't have to live like this
Within two or three blocks
To this park
AR
Dozens and dozens of abandoned building
Get together with your other
Folks were living like you are
And
Go take a building
From the early to mid eighties the squatters didn't face much active reserve
Distance from the sea
From time to time City officials would come by and brick
Their windows and doors
But the squatters would just
Smash through the brick
I frankly thought that
As long as the economy of New York remain
If you're dodging
We would be less than
Economic Cycles
Started to go back
Into a cycle of investment
Reinvestment
I figured we were proud
When the squatters took over the buildings on the Lower East
I'd they were tapping into a long American tradition
Of laying claim to land by occupying and develop
In 1862 the federal government was trying to encourage Westward Expansion and settlement
And so Congress passed the Homestead Act
It opened up millions of acres of land in the American West
The settlers
If the settlers farmed the land and improved it
Then after five years they could file for a deed from the government
And take legal ownership
At least
Legal in the eyes of the US government
Not necessarily the native peoples who lived on the land for thousands of years
By the 1960s and 70s the idea of urban homesteading had taken hold in cities
Local governments would offer cheap or free houses to low-income residents
Provided they worked on the buildings and brought them up to code
This was known as
Sweat Equity
And some of the squatters in New York basically saw themselves
Does providing
Even if it wasn't under any officially things
Program
Many squatters
May have lived outside the mainstream
But in some ways they were
Tapping into mainstream American values
They go way back
Values of self
Sufficiency entrepreneurialism pulling yourself up by your bootstraps
Individual responsibility and so squatting fits in with that Story 2
But the city government didn't necessarily see it that
And as time went on the squatters Renegade methods would draw more critical attention in a city that was run
Gentrify
By the late 1980s New York City
Turn the corner and was gradually starting to come out of a long a
Economic slump
People were moving back into the city real estate prices were once again starting to
The Climb
And the city was beginning to reinvest in neighborhoods
Dad long neglect
The issues of homelessness and housing on the lower
Seaside or becoming more and more
Squatters and homeless
Felt like they had to fight
To hang on to whatever space
Clean try to kick the homeless out
Because if you do you got a wart on your head a lot of attention focused on
Square Park
Lower East Side
The park was closed too many of the squats and was the place where spend YOLO have passed out his Pro squatting pamphlets
Homeless people
In the summer of 1988 the New York parks
Department implemented a 1 a.m.
Curfew at the park
They were helping to reduce the number of people living and sleeping there
The curfew sparked protests
Which turned into a riot
Many squatters were part of the altercation
Photographers being pushed by police
Tompkins Square Park riots were a turning point in the relationship between
Squatters and the City
That brought a lot of attentions around gentle
Application on displacement and
Class
In the neighborhood
To a head
More than ever the city wanted the squatters out of the neighborhood
Local politicians and even some other affordable housing act
Accused of squatters of not playing by the rules
Occupying buildings that were badly needed by other low-income residents
Who had deeper roots in the neighbor
Hundreds and hundreds of alpacas living doubled up tripled up and sometimes quadruple.
And substandard housing
Wally's
Yelp squatters
Art
Stealing from the poor
Alan Renton tax-free
This is an old interview from WNYC of a controversial city counselor named Antonio Pagan who represent
In the Lower East Side he was a housing developer turned politician
And he emerges a particularly Fierce critic of this Waters
Understanding The Way of the development of our community by the community
As criticism mounted
The city began working harder to evict
The squatters
Response the squatters began devising creative ways to resist
Sears weekly ad
We had we had barricades in the house man that was the mentality that we were living with you know we always had fun
But anyone in the house and white Speedy no fire and no content
That was one of things that came out of that. Was it
Realself
Statement
When the police did show up
The squatters have developed a plan for how to quickly mobilize
The eviction law
Eviction watch was a the organization of
Squatters throughout the neighbor
Here's Peter Espanol
And having your name on this telephone tree meant that in the event you were call you would come to a squat
Utica mm
Squatters would physically block police from entering the building they link arms and stand in front of the door
Sometimes the defend the building from the inside
Throwing paint in garbage down on the police
Or buckets of urine
Sometimes they hide inside
Does it cops couldn't clear the building
They would have little secret
Compartments and hiding places to go in
Physically occupying the building was always the best strategy the city was always very
Quick and eager to demolish a squad
But they couldn't imagine us a squad with people inside
At least four things down
Squatters weren't just fighting the city in the streets
They also began devising a legal strategy
We had developed among ourselves the idea of adverse possession
It's illegal Theory
It's something you can use
Squatters
Love adverse possession law
The details of the law vary state by state
New York it says that if you occupy a piece of property for 10 years
And the legal owner doesn't Force you out
You can claim the legal title
Address for the ocean is an interesting law
Because it's
Seems to
Destabilize some of the things that we
Say that we value about private property
And ownership namely that if you own a property you have a right to it
And it's yours
Forever
Adverse possession means owners have certain responsibilities
If you abandon your property and leave it unused for long periods
You risk losing it
To successfully claim adverse possession the squatters would need to meet a number of conditions
Like proving that lived in the building's continuous
For example
Some of the squatters were wary about getting tangled up with the legal system
But others saw it as their chance to gain ownership
They hired a lawyer and started putting together a case
The judge who had their claim found they were likely to make a successful case
Against the city
And he granted them an injunction against eviction
Until the case was decided
But before the case could be settled in court and in spite of the injunction
The city evicted the residents of two of the building
City inspectors said that they were in danger of collapse
Here's Mary Neville a spokeswoman for the housing
Xiamen archival interview
The occupants of the five city-owned buildings on East 13th Street are squatters and whether they've been there for
For 5 minutes 5 years or 15 years the fact of the matter is they broke into
Vacant city-owned buildings that were sealed
These evictions provoke the biggest Showdown yet between the city and the squatters
In May of 1995
Everybody was on the edge and everybody was on the look at
And I remember someone
Called me one night and they
I said okay this
Dislike
100 dry cough
Have arrived
And they're like four blocks away and then the number grew
They was sending in
Basically small Nami
The police have brought a tank repurposed from the Korean War
Officer took up positions on the roofs of neighboring buildings
Meanwhile
Squatters Patrol the neighborhood walkie talkies
Reporting on the growing numbers of police
They welded bicycle frames to their fire escape so it would be impossible for police or firefighters to climb them
Big factor staircases with rubble to make them impossible
Bayport are on the street so police would have to March through it on their way to the building
And you know again you know
Creative
Responses you know Chinese off to the building
Use your piss bucket and nobody's going to
Nobody's going to try and come get you know it's like
It was busy
Is vile but it's
What the hell you know
You got guns we got this bucket
The police presence one on for month
Seelbach the ends of the block
I'm required people to show ID before they let them through
Don't the squatters wouldn't leave
Expense and inconvenience and embarrassment to eventually decide that
That this wasn't the way to go and they're going to have to find some other way to deal with this
Squatters Everlasting
Rudy Giuliani was the mayor of the setting at the time
And he was a vocal critic of the squatters
But astonishingly in 1999 a secret negotiation between the city and the squatters started to unfold
They began to discuss
What it once seemed
Legalization
I remember being surprised
By the fact that we were going to have this
Discussion
And
Giuliani Administration which just made it weirder and weirder and it was it was
Just hard to fathom
A new plan started to develop
Separate from the adverse
Possession case
The city would sell the squatters buildings to 1/3
A nonprofit organization called do you have
The urban homesteading
Since the 1970s you haven't been helping low-income New Yorkers gain ownership
Distressed
You have would then turn the buildings over to the squatters and help them get loans so they could bring the buildings up
The code
After years of negotiation the deal went through
In 2002
The city sold 11 buildings to you have
For $1
And you have began working with the squatters to turn their buildings
From squats
Until we go cooperatively owned apartment
The process wasn't easy and it raised some hard questions in the squad
One thing
There was the issue of resale
Mini squatters were committed to keeping the building's affordable
They wanted to cap the resale price on each apartment
So that people couldn't flip their units for massive sums of money
But there were others who felt like they'd invested so much time and energy into the buildings that they wanted to be able to cash
There was a bunch of people
Basically the line was
Well if we're not going to be Atticus anymore we might as well be capitalized
Are the squatters rehabs the buildings and brought them up to code
Some of the more unique and handle elements of people's Apartments
Had to go
Some of the buildings became last Wild
More uniform
Pure handmade mosaic
More boring drywall
A few of the buildings haven't managed to get through the legalization process
Even 15 years later
There have been hard trade-off
Some squatters didn't want to take on debt for the building
And they've moved out
But for many like Maggie Wrigley
The legalization has been a victory for affordable housing
One of the most expensive cities in the country
And it's offered a kind of stability
At the end of nearly two decades of drama
Wework used by everything you don't speculation trying to steal these buildings
Racketeering
And that's the beautiful thing about where we are today
It will all these feelings will always be affordable
Maggie's building was the first to finish the legalization process in 2009
It's still full of artist and activist
Mini the people who live there have been there for years
In ears
People are starting to have kids
Start family
There's not that sense of constant threat
If you're there
Police might come by and break up
All their windows
Maggie's not a squatter anymore
She's something else
I am a homeowner
And it's incredible
And you know it's long as we keep our act together
Then nobody can put us out
You know and that's it we we got it you know we can tell it's help building his house to lose
This week's episode is part of a special radiotopia wide project welcoming a new radiotopia podcast to the family
Ear Hustle
Just coming soon shares true stories of life in San Quentin State Prison told directly by and from
The man living there
Show won radiotopia podcast contest last year but not 1536 other entries from around the world
In support of your hustle album Utopia shows are releasing episode in response to the theme
Doing time in our case we took it as doing time to place to make
Claim of ownership
Be sure to subscribe to all the radiotopia shows that they
Doing time I'm really excited to hear how all the other shows handle it and stay tuned through the credits of the show Heroes
Special extra-long sneak preview
Love your hustle
99percentinvisible was produces Weak by Delaney Hall mix into production by siracusa
Katie mingle is our senior producer of coal state is the digital director
The rest of the production staff includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman Mars
Turn messages the office manager and Sean real compose original music for this episode alongside music by Imodium and
Okay akumi
Thank you to Doctor Amy starceski Who provided us with oral history interviews with the Lower East Side squatters
This episode is based on her book
Called ours to lose
Squatters became homeowners in New York City
Thanks also to Alex vasudevan author of The autonomous City
Thanks to Paul dirienzo
For his tape of the Tompkins Square Park riots recorded for WBAI
And WNYC for additional archival tape
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
G10 entrance questions about the show on Facebook and Twitter me at Roman Mars in the show at 99.
I work run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But you're always welcome at our place
Emily 9 p.m.
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com