99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1999 a nature documentary about wolves
Call
Wolves
Came out in IMAX theater
Miss alpha female is searching for a damn sight
It isn't merely a personal choice
But her decision will be
Determine the disk
Film documents the reintroduction of wolves Across the Western United States
That's pretty Sir Edmund Fitzgerald
And it has everything you want in an eighth
Nature documentary
Sweeping landscapes
An aerator with a rugged yet soothing voice
Pray
And best of all
Wolf puppy
The film was designed to combat
The misinformation campaigns of the ranching and hunting love is
Which portray wolves typically is vicious
Killers
Fit only for elimination
That's Chris Palmer
One of the film's producer
Team to rehabilitate the Wolves image
By showcasing the relationships within a pack
Rather than just a bunch of scenes of wolves are ripping Caribou to shreds
They wanted to show the animals working together to raise a litter of
On gold
Was to show
Close-ups
All the Wolfpack
Interacting in complex
Subtle
Waze
Filming the intimate lines of wild wolves is
Virtually impossible
Because they do not
Tolerate the presence of people
Still they filmed inside a wolf
And in the Finish movie
Viewers are let into this private moment
As wolf pup
Cozy up
Against their mother's belly
Because newborn pops have no way to regulate their own temperature
Their mother's body
The only thing that keep
When the sun came out Palmer went to some screening
Where audience members could ask question
And often wonder screening
Someone in the audience asked me how do you film The Amazing shot
Of the mother wolf
And it's
Did
Palmer's heart sing
Because the truth about that intimate scene in The Wolf Pen
Wasn't pretty
Cover your ears
We rented
Captive wolves
We rented captive wolves
The shots of the puppies in the den were not filmed in the wild
Instead the film crew had gone to a game farm
Where the Wolves were more used to humans
And built an artificial Den with cameras inside
I was suddenly
Bearing
Stockley
As an ethical dilemma for myself did I tell
The truth and answer truthfully that for betraying our trade secrets in filmmaking
Did I continue to lie and pretend of the captive wolves
In fact what we want when they want
Homer decided to
To come clean
And when I did this I could
Feel the audience's disappointment
And this moment was a bit of a turning point for him
Up to that point I think I kind of assumed but why would they care
But they do cat people do cat when people watch documentaries especially science space documentaries
They are assuming they are seeing the truth they are seeing things that are authentic and Jen
Inuits and truthful
And when they find out that is not the case
They get very upset
Of course there's some level of allusion in all films
You're editing footage to form an area
We do this and Radio 2
But Illusions in Nature Documentaries exist on a spectrum
In some cases these allusions help tell the truth
About animals
But in others
Not so much
On the far end of that truth Spectrum you know
Over toward the straight-up false and
Is a film called White wilderness
I still remember watching
Willis as a child about 11 years old
It was a documentary produced by Disney in 1958 about the high Arctic
Land of many Mysteries
It's a strange fact that the largest Legends seem to collect around the smallest creatures
One of these is a nasty little rodent called the Lenox
In one scene of herd of tiny Lemmings approaches a rocky Cliff along the ocean
Reach the final precipice
This is the last chance to turn back
The little fur balls Pier over the edge
And then they go
Epsom salt
Show me Arctic sea is dotted with tiny bobbing.
It's dramatic stuff
Except
This entire sequence was staged
The producers
Went the Arctic
Bagged up a bunch of lemon
And flew them to this Cliff along a river in Alberta
And they put them on a turntable That You Don't See in the film
Elladan and they threw them off the cliff side into the water
And films it
And Lemmings don't actually hurl themselves off cliffs
Some lemon species do experienced dramatic fluctuations in population size bleeding to some creative 19th century
Three hypotheses about what might be going on
But the idea of a mass lemming suicide ritual
Is entirely apocryphal
White Wilderness didn't invent
The lemming suicide
But it certainly helped to spread it
The film was seen by millions of people
I even won the Oscar
4 best documentary
Everybody is learned that from that film and it be misled by Sophie
What we put in these films is important
And that means
So important they are
Made
Not only entertaining lie but made I'm accurately and an ethically because they do have an impact
The lemming scene is an especially egregious example of dishonest film
But smaller acts of deception happen all the time
And after his experience with the wolf documentary
Chris Palmer started looking into this stuff
He found filmmakers learning sharks
Closer to the camera by dumping bug
It's a fish guts into the ocean
And a producer using CGI to edit a sea otter into a shot
Homer is particularly bothered by filmmakers that harass animals to try to get them to do something exciting
He thinks all this happens because of a race 4 rating
And when you focus so so much on Resler that you inevitably
A move toward pregnant
That are highly sensational
And overly dramatic a lot of Palmer's criticisms have to do with the visual side
I feel making but any conversation about the accuracy of Nature Documentaries inevitably ends up on the topic of sound
That's because in most Wildlife films The Sounds you hear were not recorded while the cameras were rolling
Which makes sense if you think about how different the two technologies are
Most filmmakers use really long telephoto lenses
The phone animals from a safe distance
But there's no Sonic equivalent of a zoom lens
For good audio
You need to get a microphone really close to the source of the sound
Which can be difficult or dangerous to try and pull off all the cameras are rolling
You can't just walk up to a lion
Clip a lapel mic on its main
And so many of the subtle movement sounds a chimpanzee rustling through leaves or a hippos
Squelching in the Moc
They don't come from animals at all
They're made by Foley artist
30 Oz is job is to
Basically
Home
Lula
Movements
Queer film
Essentially
This is Richard Hinton windowless room
Watching television
Making
Weird Science Reynolds
Clinton performs in a studio with trap doors in the floor
And underneath the floor you have
6 pics
HBO with a different material
Foley artist spend so much time playing around in these pits
That they call each other pitmon
Is this one gravel once filled with sand ones.
I want kind of desk and grass
Elements of solid science lab
Which pet is mic'd up for high-quality sound
Hinton watches a silent version of the scene on an HD screen
And he tries to match the movement of the animal
Usually on on Sat On The Floor
Cross-legged
And I'm kind of blunt
So I can control my weight
I need my wife
I'm putting into the movement
He starts with the feet
As the animals move he tries to match their football
Boss with his hands
When you're feeling animals usually use your hands rubbing your feet
Because you have no control
If its Hooves out
You know use the tips of my fingers and I'll really driving into the surface so you getting a heart attack
If it's something like a lion then I'll use the flash my fingers
And you get a mole Patty
And I kind of stealthy kind of stoking kind of whites to it
Hinton has been doing Foley for years
And it's worked on many big nature
Including planet Earth 2
With all that practice he says he can often get it right in just a single take
I've been doing it long enough now to know
You know that point
Chase is about to go from a stool
Swiss print
Because of its shoulder move
Adjust the weight pins his back
You know the more of this stuff
But you do you stop picking up on these little visual Clues
The wild life gives you
In terms of what it's about to do with its Behavior
So many Wildlife films focus on the exact
Same cast of Marque species
Elephants
Leopards crocodiles
But hidden rarely comes across footage of an animal he's never fully before
When you first come across something you haven't done
You do spend a couple minutes just just watching the pussies three saying right okay well how is this thing moving
How
Yeah it wants its rhythm
Hazard shoulders working in relationship
Sweet Street
For more
It sounds as a giant storage area full of materials he's hoarded over the years
Sheets of metal pieces
Rubber
Different types
Rope
Wetsuits
He takes out a couple of items to
In front of me right now I have
Some hot wings
Which was actually just provoke gloves
Interesting if he's the fingertips
You get back wings
Detroit the movie
Reasonable
London
You got pigeon wings
To mimic the sound of an animal walking on snow
Continues has a bag of dried
Custard
When he squeezes the bag
You got that fresh snow
Crunch
Sometimes he brings in natural materials from the outdoors
The studio has a big Garden
And in the summer Peyton will harvest different plants
How to use
Set recordings
The Winter though can be more challenge
What will quite often do is we'll use small tape
Here I have a combination of Sunoco syringe type
Smok V8 chest tight
It's like it was kind of leaf canopy
Work
Something like a baboon or chimp
I'm a question about
Foley artists share techniques
And some tricks have become so ubiquitous
That they've actually changed our understanding of the way nature sounds
I mean this is the thing we've been thankful you're not restricted so long
People actually are used to listening to is how we fight Easter
Which is kind of weird some people expect what we do brazas and what nature money
Actually there in real life
For example
Elephant feet
We expect to hear a big booming sound when a massive elephant foot hits the ground
But that's not what elephants actually sound like
Have you told anybody that works around Dallas
They will tell you that elephants make pretty much no sound at all when they walk
Because the Departed
Sodalite section of that foot is just one big
Foxy plushie
So
They're incredibly efficient
Distributing the whites as they walk
But Hinton says that if you had no sound at all it would just
Fuel
Weird
It's very uncomfortable to see a foot
The song Enough
Telescreen in hit floor and O'Hara sign for
Hinton tries to find a middle ground
Between accuracy and giving people the sound they expect
But he says the main goal of Foley is just to provide a little bit of that movement sound need
The help the film
Slow movement sounds at one thing
But then there's the distinctive vocal sounds an animal makes you know a lion's roar a cuckoo birds
Cuckoo anything that you would
Termites vocalisation is a growler grunt
Scream a rule the bad Cole
It's okay to be as real as we can get it
But just because it's
Your it doesn't mean that you're hearing the exact same individual animal
But you're seeing on the screen
Unless you can see David Attenborough in kneeling next to an orangutan
Chances are the sounds that orangutan is making
Come from a different orangutan all together
Mini sound Studios have massive carefully catalog libraries of animal recordings that sound editors will use
To match the specific behaviors seen on screen and sometimes filmmakers will hire sound recordist to go out
Out and find sounds to fit their film
Recordists like Chris Watts
My name's Chris Watson and I'm a sound recordist
Watson usually gets a storyboard from the filmmaker
And it's his job to go and find sounds that match different scenes
He's working on a lion seeking
Watson will find a pride he wants to record
And carefully study their
And then realizing
You know when they're off hunting or when they're gone to another location
You lanco Radio Moscow
Two phones
Close by where you saw them
I usually very long cables
Anaheim
Conceal or disguise microphone
Near the source of the sound Ben Watson climbs into a hiding place
A safe distance away
And weights
He might take you two days but then it eventually
Stop Pride
3 for females in 9/10 it doesn't Cubs
Will come by today
Place
I'm just laying down watching TV microphone
Stop vocalizing
Watson takes big predators like these very seriously
He has all kinds of techniques for getting close up sound without getting too close
Do you want to use a really long boom
Take it as microphone near achita resting beneath
The tree and I
Over by an hour or very slowly
Lowered
The boom down
Choosing a bow
3 ft to this animals
Had
Havana recorded
Remarkable
Close up
Purring sound
Which wasn't even notable
But we were 1012 Yalta way
What's an ulcer record lots of ambient sounds and then he sends it all to the editors who carefully piece together an Acura
Soundscape
In the final product it looks like the vocalizations are coming from the animals on screen
When you can though Watson does try to record sound while the cameras are rolling
Synchronous sound is not impossible
Pieces
And I can bring a special kind of realism
The film
In the BBC documentary the life of bird
The director asked him to make up a bunch of
Trees and bushes
I swear he new song birds like the sing at dawn
And it worked
The bird showed up right on cue
And saying right into his tiny microphones as they film
Amelie morning like
I see the bugs
Brass is exhaled from the song
Recording synchronous sound is much easier with Bluebird than say
Polar bears
But Watson which has it happened more
He says that in general producers prioritize sites above say
I'll spend millions of dollars sending camera people all over the world
To get that special shot
And then just
Worry about finding the right sound later on
Sometimes though recording the sound separately can actually enhance the accuracy
Of the soundtrack
In the BBC documentary life in the undergrowth
The filmmakers wanted to Showcase this bizarre behavior of the Alcon blue butterfly
Wood ants mistake these caterpillars for their own larvae
And carry them underground to the end colony
Once inside the caterpillars do something remarkable
Next regulate an internal organ things about 300
I had to look up stridulate to
It means to make a shrill Sound by rubbing the legs wings or other parts of the body to
In this case it's the caterpillars attempt
Dominica hungry baby
This sound
Stimulates
Then
Feed the cats
Capella
So it's cross
Species communication
Which is actually
Something very special in the first
The filmmakers would destroy the antonym
That's if they tried to film this in the wild
So they established a colony inside a film set
And filled it with tiny Periscope cameras
And the capsule the sound
Chris Watson use what's called
A particle velocity micro
Screen record extremely quiet sound
About to go into a BBC Radio Studio very very very
Quiet place
Bahadis like somebody's cast
Phyllis
We shouldn't place
On
Particle velocity microphone
About the size of a
It might be like it P
Lots of diamonds have a butterfly
River sounds place on Sauk
And eventually produce this vibration which are recorded
One of the most astonishing
Sounds abysa Behavior
If a witness
It would have been impossible
To record it under
Wild conditions
Pausing videos impossible
Film The behavior
Idlewild condition
Was Chris Watts in the sound recordist and Richard Hinton the Foley artist
Work to give us accurate and satisfying sounds
Albeit in different ways
What Watson says there's something inherently artificial
In the process
Cast of making nature sounds
Nature Documentaries
Are are not reality
It's the creation of an illusion
Like any other
Pics of entertainment
But a lot of viewers get upset
When they find out that their favorite nature.
Isn't total
Real
Richard Hinton the Foley artist says he gets reactions like this all the time
And I when I tell people what I do
For living
Pizza Rizza fascinates you do they want to punch me in the face
Don't punch Richard hit in the face
I cannot stress this enough people
Discovering all the work that goes into the final product should not
Cornish it
Nature Documentaries are still movies
And they need a little movie Magic
Just like any other film
Chris Palmer the filmmaker from the beginning of the story says the most important thing is that the movie Magic
Is being used to tell the truth
He actually thinks that renting wolves like he did to show viewers how they behave in their dens
Was probably fine
Palmer says if he had to do it over he'd likely do it the same way
But make it clear to the audience somehow that the scene was not recorded in the wild
Homer thinks a lot of documentary filmmakers are doing their best to bring us accurate representation
Animals in the wild
But he does see one big problem
Even some of the best work out there
Fails to acknowledge human impact
Axon ecosystem
Which is giving the impression that we don't have any environmental challenges
Homer says that a lot of Nature Documentaries.
These days show animals as if they live in some magical fantasy world
Completely divorced from Human civilization
There's no shots
What's the nearby City
Where the coal mine that's encroaching on habitat
Either you watch the shows you think it was nothing wrong with the world nothing wrong
Which is its own form of deception
When you make a film about
About the natural world
To admit any mention of the environmental challenges faced by that natural world
Is misleading
But Palmer still believes in the power of good filmmaker
He thinks that if we want to sell big environmental challenges like species
Extinction and climate change
We need compelling true story
About nature
And to tell a true story
Sometimes you need
A little fakery
99percentinvisible was produced this week by init Fitzgerald with Sharif Youssef
Delaney Hall
Avery trufelman
And me Roman Mars
Katie mingle is our senior editor Kurt Kolstad is the digital director and Taryn Mazza
Is the baroness
All the music was composed by Sean real
We are product of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Percent
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Five podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars the show tweets at 99 pii
Instagram and Tumblr to but if you want to know what the word skarka textured mean
You have to go
39 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com