99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Hello friends
We have just 10 days before season 3
September 19th is the big day
The plan is a new episode every 9 days and Sam is here
Keeping us on task
And I really enjoy the new shows for working
In the meantime I literally have 10,000 tiny pocket size notebook samael staff to package and ship along with us.
Thousand t-shirts
Is all the result of a
Fantastic Kickstarter campaign that not complaining at all
Great that we're working day and night hear it
99p ihq
The resident reorder the feed with a repeater make you wait another week and a half
I have a story from radio show that I've only recently started listening to
Just
Great
It's called backstory with the American history
And it's the highly enjoyable show you don't even need a love history to enjoy it you just need to be
Curious about the
All around you
I like stories
About how it got that way which
What is the definition of history but the point is I think you're going to like
99percentinvisible is obsessed
With the things we build and what they say about us
Usually
In directory
Spruce Way
I'm drawn to Monument
Because
These are things we build that
Their Inception
Trying to tell you a story
Give a place
For a moment in time
Difficult
Meaning
But that meaning that's fused
Concrete
Stone
Can be slanted hurtful bigoted
May be misguided or even miss under
Stud
Anyway
This is a story about a monument
But I couldn't get out of my head the first time I heard it
One of the host of Acts
Destroy the 19th
Century history guy at air
Is going to take it from here
The 1890s the first decade of twentieth-century.
Veterans in both the union and the Confederacy were
Dying often
Their sons and daughters
Notice that
They better acknowledge their enormous sacrifices and
Begin a kind of mania putting up monuments in
Towns and cities and Villages all across the country
And
Even into the early 1930s people were still trying to nail down all the meeting
Except it's complicated Civil War
My Memorial
And one place of the memorialization of the Civil War
Was played out
Was it one of the places where the Civil War in some ways began
Harpers Ferry
West Virginia
Where John Brown lettuce famous raid
It 1859
A band of white and black abolitionists
Trying to
Inspire a slave rebellion
Today there are two monuments there
1 is a 6
Split tall obelisk
How looks like a miniature Washington Monument
And that Monument marks the original location of the old Federal Armory
That was so important in John Brown's raid
Today
Across the street
Maybe a hundred feet away
Up against the side of a large brick building is another Memorial
And that one looks like a big Tombstone frankly
About the size
A refrigerator
It's a large
Granite and
Ascribed
Monument
This is Todd Bolton
He works the National Park Service at Harvest
To buy producers Eric mental nailpassion Stein
Talk to him when they visited the town
And the mind that he's describing was dedicated 1931
In honor of the first person killed in John Brown's raid
A man by the name of Hayward Shepherd
There's no images on it no
No bronze it's it's it's
It's text
N64 Maybe
Space Halsey wear
That's in good shape
It's it really is
Rackaracka
Pretty good shape
The interesting thing about Heyward Shepherd
Is it just that he was the first
Person killed by Brown and his Raiders
Is a Hayward Shepherd was African-American
Free black
A fact that has made this Memorial more than a little problematic over the
Eric and Nell
Tell story
Hayward Sheppard work as a porter for the B&O Railroad in Harpers Ferry
He was on duty the night of October 9th
The night of John Brown's raid
Aware of a commotion outside
Shepherd took his Lantern and walk down to the train
Browning Company were on their way into town
It was dark
And Shepard was in their path
Either Brown himself or one of his men shot Shepherd
Leaving him badly injured
He died shortly after
No
Hayward Shepherds name might have been forgotten had it not been for the efforts
F2 group
United Daughters of the Confederacy
And the Sons of Confederate Veterans
The UTC and the SCV
They're run by the Descendants
Confederate soldiers and their job is to preserve Confederate heritage
Memorials Flags archives
That kind of
In 1931
The local chapters of the UDC and the SCV erected of Memorial Hayward Shepherd in Harpers Ferry
They placed it directly across the street from the John Brown obelisk
In one long sentence
The memorial reads
This folder is set up by the Sons of Confederate Veterans in the united Daughters of the Confederacy
As a memorial to Hayward Shepherd
Exemplifying the character and faithfulness
Thousands of negroes
Who
Under many Temptations throughout the subsequent years of war
So conducted themselves
The no stain was left upon a record
Which is the peculiar Heritage of the American people
And an everlasting tribute to the best
In bo3
Faces
Okay so to translate that from monuments p
We the SUV and the UTC would like to honor Heyward Shepherd
And all the other black people in the south
We're good and faithful to their white superiors never rebelling against them
Or the status quo
The group had a nickname for this Monument
The faithful slave Memorial
The faithful slave with an idea Confederate Heritage groups have been pushing for years
Logic was since most slaves didn't Rebelle
They must have been happy
And if they were happy
It's because their masters treated them well
Slaves were faithful because they knew slavery was better than any other situation available
Of course Hayward Shepherd wasn't a Slave
So even if there were such a thing as a faithful slave
Shepherd wouldn't fit the bill
But that was no matter
The monument was built in dedicated with
Plenty of fanfare and plenty of controversy
W e b Dubois called the dedication a quote
Pro-slavery celebration
For 40 years the monument stood undisturbed
During that time
National Park Service acquired a bunch of the land and artifacts in Harpers Ferry
Including the Heyward Shepherd Memorial and all the problems attached
Then in the 1970s
The Park Service began restoring some of the old buildings in
In order to keep the memorial from being damaged
They put it away in a maintenance yard or it stayed for 5 years
When they put it back in its original location they made one notable change
It was
All covered
With a wooden box
This is Elliot coming
Former commander of the Sons of Confederate Veterans in the nearby Maryland division
Remember the SUV is one of the two groups who originally funded the memorial
So needless to say
They were upset when they found out it had been covered
Todd Bolton
The Park Service employee
Says he wasn't at the top level of Memorial discussion
But he had to send a voice certain decisions were being made
My understanding was the
There had been
The Park at
Threats of violence or defacing of the monument
So it stayed in and storage for a
Some years
Guy in storage you mean covered or yours
The wooden box
With painted brown to make it blend in with
Trash can
Again Elliott coming
So
Concern me.
Illegitimate monuments
National Park Service
Covered up in
What kind of work from there
Annually 90s Cummings the Sons of Confederate Veterans member
Begin a letter writing campaign
To get the box removed
I worked with Bruce Babbitt who at the
Time was secretary
Bill Clinton
I wrote to Centerburg
Who was the senior senator from West
Virginia where harbin Springs located
In 1995 enough political pressure mounted to force the Park Service
To uncover the memorial
But they added a little something of Their Own
About 10 feet to the right of the memorial is a small interpretive plaque
Explaining who Hayward Shepherd was
And what's a 1931 controversy with all about
It also offers a quote from w e b Dubois
Quote
Hear John Brown aimed human history a blow that woke a guilty Nation
With him fought seven slaves and Sons of
The quokkas on about John Brown but mentions neither Heyward Shepherd
Nor the idea of the faithful slave
That the other marker
Should have been more you know expanse
Because it really doesn't say it
Anything it just talks
Survive
WV boy
That's all it does
This is Jim Tolbert
Former president of the West Virginia and AAC
CP
He said that he and other members of the n-double-acp or upset that
The plaque doesn't adequately debunk the faithful slave
Or as he put
That
Clearly a lie
I'll just keep on calling little eye
Sly
MLB nwacp thought the plaque said to little
The Sons of Confederate Veterans were unhappy it was there at all
We're
Not happy that they felt the need to put
Ian Halperin
Magnets
We feel the
Historical monument
Stand on their own
That is our job our job is not to tell you to
You come here
And this is what you
We want you to think about this particular
Part of History
We don't do that
RR jobs
2% the history
Yashow balanced perspective
And allow you as an individual
Debased on that
Unbiased information to walk away with your own
With your own conclusion
Today
The n-double-acp is still pretty upset about the whole situation
But there's only so much they can do
The Confederate Heritage groups would get rid of the plaque in a heartbeat
But they more or less moved on
The Park Service maintains that the memorial is in historical artifact
Entrusted to the US government
And the continued to maintain it as such
The Hayward Sheppard Memorial may have just been a monument to a particular vision of the
But it does point to something else
Over the past 150 years
There's been little effort to memorialize slavery in a way that reflects
The true scale of the experience
And it's reverberations
What's clear is that slavery can't be stored in the maintenance yard or covered up with a plywood box
And one has to wonder if there will ever be an interpretive plaque
Big enough to make sense of it all
They're little and now beschen Stein are producers for backs
Pictures of the Heyward Shepherd Memorial and more about its Origins
Visit backstory radio. Org
That's a story from The Monuments episode of back
Backstory with the American history guys
I'll have a link on our website to their show and you should say
Try because you're really
99% invisible is me Roman Mars and Sam Greenspan
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy, go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode
What about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
If you live in the Bay Area and enjoy Pizza
And repetitive tasks
Have no real need to get paid
Well then maybe you should get in touch
Roman at PRX
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of thing if you
Days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com