99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If you live in an American city and you walk outside to a major intersection and look into this
Streets
You know what you'll say you'll see cars and trucks and buses you might see a few bicycles trying to sneak
Either way through the traffic but you won't see our people not on the street anyway maybe on the sidewalk waiting for their turn to cross
And I'm crossing quickly
Hurrying to get out of the way so that the cars can get going again
In recent times
Some of us are coming to think the city streets shouldn't just be for cars
And trucks the cars take up too much space
Lewis too much carbon
Just to move a couple of people a short distance
But even those anti-car haters
And I am one
We know the streets belong to our enemy
We look both ways before Crossing
We don't let her children play in the streets
We might sometimes jaywalk
Across the street at the wrong place or time
But we know in our heart of hearts were in the wrong
Scofflaws
That's a reporter Jesse Dukes
This is a story about jaywalking where that word jaywalking came from
And how it was a weapon in a turf war between the people who Wanted cars in the streets
And everybody else
You can
Probably guess who won
All right there's a wonderful cartoon in the St Louis Post Dispatch from 1923
It's called the modern moloch
And moloch was
A daddy
Of the ammonites
A historian at the University of Virginia who studies cities
Moloch was a daddy too
To whom the ammonites
Sacrifice their own children
In return for prosperity
What an image for what the car was
Because the ideas that you were sacrificing our children in the name of modern technology
According to Peter Norton
There was a time in the 1920s when it look like
In this particular cartoon
You see a driver kneeling at an altar
Which is
The front grill of a
Car
With a huge
Full of
The corpses of children
Offering it up to the mouth of this
Machine Beast
As a sacrifice
It's it's a very striking cards
And it may seem a little
Bizarre to us today until you recognize that this thing was
Killing thousands of children every year
So that was 1923 90 years ago
But understand why cars were being compared to a child eating God
We've got to go back a few more years
And so she went back a hundred
110 years
I think you'd be amazed to see
People just
Strolling right into the street
Anyplace anytime
Sure they'll look
But not very carefully
At the turn of the century
There is nothing moving faster than about 5 or 10 miles an hour
Responsible parents would say their children go outside and play in the streets
All day
Even after the first cars appeared in the cities right around 1900
They had to conform to the customs of the day
Which meant that traffic
Slowly
There's wonderful video
Like 1905 people walking down mark
Street
And San Francisco before the earthquake
And people are just
Striding right in wherever they want to go
Children
People carrying
You know Boards of wood
Are people going about their business
It's not to say that the
The street
Off of the sidewalks
For everybody because people prefer the sidewalk
It's dryer it's cleaners got less horse manure
There weren't even really many rules about what you could do or not do
People are solving problems the way they solve problems
When you're walking in a crowded hallway like
You know I love in a car
High School building between classes and you have
Huge crowd of kids or something
Trying to find a way
And they start to figure stuff out like you know usually keep right while you're walking
It's not like the law
You know but there's no understanding you go that way I'll go this way I'll keep that right I'll get that guys are going to go to the right or to the left
Free from England and I think
The closest thing we have to that now is a city park
Or maybe a pedestrian Mall
You go to a city park
And you you're mostly Guided by
Understanding understanding psych you can use the park for whatever you want
Provided you don't endanger other people
You don't break the law
And you don't make a nuisance out of yourself
And then you pretty much okay and it's a lot like that in Street
Bubba 1922 things changed
For once
Cities in America where filling up with people
This is right in the midst of the Industrial Revolution when Americans were leaving Farms to move to cities to work in Factory
Or maybe
In the middle class if they're lucky
So the streets
We're starting to get more crowded
You probably heard of the other Big Chain
The Model T Ford
The first affordable automobile
Introduced in 1908
Mass produced in 1913
Price is just
Is falling every year
Buy 1920 a new model T without any extras
You could get for $300
And this is really now in the reach of the working-class the people who make the Ford Model T can afford to buy it at
Principal dear to the heart
Henry Ford
By the 1920s
Cities are crowding with
Any people are buying cars
Driving cars in the street
Drivers don't want to drive 5 or
18 miles an hour
Speedway Street traffic
For decades
They want to drive
Faster
And the pedestrians in children still linger in the street
Walking casually
Like it's 1906
And every year more people are killed in automobile a
Fatalities are rising and you can watch the Curve
You know it's like
Climbing a mountain you just
Going uphill the whole way
Buy 1920s
3 you've got about 17 18 thousand people a year being killed
Buy Motor Vehicles
Three-quarters of those people are possessed
Half of the pedestrians killed in the cities are chilled
Under the age of
As far as the public is concerned it's almost like they died in a war
Parades are held in dozens of cities to
Commemorate the dead children
Monuments are built
Mothers of children killed in the streets are giving us
Special White
Start
To honor their loss
And that's why in 1923
We see a cartoon comparing the automobile
Kamala
A God who demands the sacrifice of children for prosperity
And we get lots of newspaper article
Editorial saying this bloodbath has to end
And almost all of them blame the deaths
On the automobile
Like this from The New York Times
The horrors of
War
Les Paul
The horrors of
Peace
The automobile
Thumbs up
Far more destructive machina
The machine gun
The Reckless motorist
Deals Moore death
Artilleryman
The man in the streets
Seems less safe
The man in the trench
The greatest single leaf
The automobile
Elect shambles
Near X
In cities begin to think seriously about restricting the use of cars in the cities
City managers bukit outlawing curb parking
Are forcing cars to make right-angle turns
Around obstacles and intersections
So they have to slow to a crawl
Dubai 1923 a whole cottage industry has grown up around the automobile
There are the manufacturers
But also the dealers
You've been making a lot of money in the last few years
And there are motor
Switch word for curses to AAA and make a lot of money selling members
According to Peter Norton
There's a moment when all of these in
Start to worry
The city laws are going to make it so nobody in the city would want to buy a car
And have a collective
Crap moment
Oh that's really clear
It's really sharp
The oh crap moment
Is November 1923
Love that
So what happened then
Alright so
Cincinnati residents got a referendum on the ballot
To be voted on in November
For a speed Governor device built into the engine that would require cars to be equipped with one that would limit them just
25 miles an hour
And once the speed governor was there at had a police seal on it if you tampered with it you were in violation of the law
This
We had lots of popular support we know 40,000 signatures on petitions
Cats weird that they were all
Real people or so on but they were 40 thousand signatures on the petitions
They had newspaper advertisements saying vote Yes on this
This
Really woke up people who wanted
A future for
Carson City
They were worried that if cities have laws that restricted the use of
Cars
The people would stop buying them
Not for public transportation
Cars would be relegated to the countryside
Fewer and fewer people lived ever
This group of Interest got organized
And even give themselves a name
They call themselves motordom
Actually that sounds pretty behind my ears
Anyway
And they start to make distinctions between what they want and what the other safety Advocates wanted
So you start to see like in need Cincinnati Enquirer which was sort of a mouthpiece for the Auto industry and since
Cincinnati and they ran
Huge amount of their advertising was from auto dealers
The Cincinnati Enquirer at one point
Says
The cause of accident
Is men not machines
In other words
Cars don't kill people
People killed
Which is reminiscent of an NRA motto has been around
Quite some time
Guns don't kill people
People people kill
People the same basic idea
You can exonerate
The machine
If you blame the driver
It wasn't so much about blaming the driver
Who's about promoting a subtle but super important
Distinction
The cause of Acts
Recent deaths
Can children die
Wasn't cars
Speed
Reckless
Cars can be perfectly safe in the sea
They belong on this
And the beauty of recklessness is
That you could also be a reckless podesta
This is really important
What modem did
By suggesting that pedestrians could
Could be Reckless
Be the cause of action
What's start
Turf War
A street fight
The oh crap moment
A1923
Creates a clear sense in motordom
Did they have to change the problem
From
How do we control cars and drivers
Into
How do we make
Streets places for cars belong and where pedestrians don't belong
Notre Dame needed to market the idea that accidents could be the result
A reckless pedestrian
And even that there was such a thing as Reckless pedestrians which people were
Ready to accept you
One judge in particular angrily denounced the idea they could ever have such a thing as a reckless pedestrian
So did sell the idea of Reckless pedestrians
Motordome invented a new word
Jaywalking
Actually they didn't invent
Repurposed a word that have been kicking around for a couple of deck
They transformed it from a slang insult to a legal term
In the 19 teens Jay Jay
What's a word for country bumpkin
There for a jaywalker
Is somebody who walks around the city like a Jay from the stick
Was it the first actually clear
Illustration of what the word means I found is from Kansas City 1911
And there it's describing an x-ray of a cartoon that shows a jaywalker
They're describing the jaywalker there as exactly that the person from the countryside who's in the big city
And it's so dazzled by the show Windows the lights that tall buildings
The salesman and so on
That as they're walking on the sidewalk they're constantly stopping
To look
Thereby obstructing other pedestrians
So their jaywalker is really a nuisance to other pedestrians
Somebody took this word that had been a kind of annoying protest
Give it a new meaning
A pedestrian who breaks
The traffic rules
Who enters the streets in the wrong place or at the wrong
They did this by publishing editorials about jaywalking
Auto clubs in auto dealers got Boy Scouts in a number of cities
The handout little cards
That would say something like
Did you know you were jaywalking and
We know that people don't know what the word meant because it was carefully
Explain on the card with diagrams and an information
Hit it first
The efforts to get people to stop doing something they had done for decades
Just didn't work
There was even an incident where
According to a newspaper women's struck police officers with their parasols
For trying to control how they cross the street the lesson promoter dim was
You can't do this by law
But finally motordom hit upon a winning scratch
Device by EB Lefferts Ed left
Enemy of jaywalkers everywhere
He was the head of the Automobile Club of Southern California and I think he was ahead of his time a real
Public relations genius
A guy who realized before most others did that you can't just change Behavior by
Punishing people and putting laws in up you have to
You have to reach them through psychology
Lefferts created a PR campaign in Los Angeles
Explaining what jaywalking was
He helped get an anti jaywalking ordinance pass
But here's the really clever part
He told the police
Not to arrest
Jaywalkers
Lefferts
Wanted the police officer not
To arrest
The jaywalk
Which would only make the
Jaywalker indignant
But to attract ridicule
And he uses the word ridicule
That's a gap in the traffic. Just pop over to the drug is for some cannabis
Hey you out of the street don't you realize to jaywalking
What is a jaywalker
Lefferts wanted
The Pedestrian ridiculed
As a form of psychological control
Until efforts it was more important
That the onlookers see this person being ridiculed then that you actually sort of convert this individual to
Correct
Crossing Behavior
Date the onlookers are going to witness this ridicule and think
I don't want to
Get that kind of ridicule so I'm going to
Carefully
Yeah
The little hard to relate to now because Jay Walker is sort of a benign word
Like loitering
The 1920s America
It was a real term of abuse
And actually several judges in newspaper editors objected
You have such an insulting
Term for podesta
You carry the connotation of idiot
I think if you were trying to
Sort of
Have a
A public safety campaign that involves calling people idiots
You would find a similar kind of reaction today
Play-Doh people
Would really objected that
Or maybe something even more
Contemporary
Traffic
I just pop over to the drug is for some cannabis
Are you out of the street don't you realize your douchebag in
What me a douchebag
I think
The thing is
The ridicule work
Newspaper reports show that just after a few weeks pedestrians in La got the message
In the streets were cleared for cars
Peter Norton says motordom could declare victory
Find 1929
Coincidentally
Or maybe not so coincidentally
This is the year the first
Cloverleaf interchange was built in the United States
Cementing the country's future
With automobile
Incidentally that's around the time that you find it people stop objecting to the term jaywalker including jaywalkers them
Selves and
You know judges are no longer resisting that
A new city streets are built with cars in mind
The streets get wider to accommodate more cars
New businesses are required to provide parking lot
Crosswalk
Become compulsory
City start building Express ways to make it easier to get cars in and out of
It's worth taking a moment to reflect on how this story has been
Told
George Orwell explain that
History is written by the winners because in writing the history
You justify yourself
So
A history of the automobile has been written
Not by any single individual
But collectively overtime
That predominantly is a winners history of the automobile
And that's the history that says this was inevitable
And it has to do with America's love affair with the automobile
The automobile
In 1961 there was a TV program called the DuPont show of the week
Which
Represented itself as a documentary TV show at that time had a 1/3 interest
Just in General Motors are the two
Companies have a lot in common
And so they wrote
A episode
Called Merrily We Roll Along
Which was a history of the automobile in the United States
They got Groucho Marx
The Host
And in this show Groucho Marx introduced Americans
To the thesis we've all heard
Which is that there's an American love affair with the automobile
Together
Honeymoon with I know sweetheart
She had any form it was a
Like crankiness
So that's the love affair thesis and the genius of it is that
By saying we have a love affair with the car
We are saying that our relationship is irrational and not subject to logical
Judgement
Something like this
License plates
Merrily We Roll Along
And even critics
Including me
We bought into this idea of an American love affair
With the autumn
Because the critics of the automobile could say you know what this
This Love Affair this
This cultural attachment we have to be automobiles the problem
Which
Completely distracted them
From the fact
That
The actual story of the transformation of the 1920s was a lot more complicated
And in fact involve a lot of hate
Car
When you see real demonization of the car the twenties that's been totally forgotten
Nobody remembers the memorials to the car nobody remembers The Monuments
Nobody remembers the parades with
Satan driving a Model T nobody
Remembers the
Cartoons in editorial cartoons
Routinely compared cars to the Grim Reaper and moloch and Juggernaut and all that
And it's true that Americans love cars
The part of the reason we love cars so much as our cities have been rebuilt with cars in mind
We have parking
We have Expressway
We don't have a lot of pedestrian getting in our way and so it is down
And it may be changing
But for the moment
We still seem to like it that
99% invisible with princes Weak by Jesse Dukes
Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to the snap judgment radio players
Letter mad historical in
So historical
Reenacting skills
Pat mesiti Miller Nick Van der kolk
Amazon
Stephanie Foo Julia DeWitt
And will urbina
You guys listen to this all listen to snap judgement right
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects
Shenzhen
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
You can find 99% invisible on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but will have the modern mullet cartoon
A fascinating film of Market Street before the jaywalking taboo
And a link to the video of Groucho Shilling for the Auto industry
99% invisible
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
The movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech
Wait machine even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com