99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
And this is Eric molinsky
Thai America
Eric is an independent producer in New York City Brooklyn of course like
Most public radio producers here
But before Brooklyn Eric spent 10 years in Los Angeles
In the story
La had asked you know amazing transportation system called the red car
And it was a trolley that covered the entire city
And then after World War II either Ford or GM bought the red car
How to dismantle
And then built this Kino horrible freeway system that created the
Sprawling gridlock of today
What the hell
Shimmering cement running from here
Slow
Traffic jam
And
You're the first the story I thought well.
That sounds familiar it must be true I feel like
That's because it's the plot of Who Framed Roger rabbit
Human
Scheme that Christopher Lloyd reveals at the end of the movie
Nobody's going to try this lousy
I bought the red car so I couldn't
This isn't totally ridiculous remember the plot of Chinatown where I've Los Angeles mobile was stealing water from Northern California
That actually happened
Garrett Jacobs Chinatown
As I learned more about the history of LA
I learned that the red car was actually not the victim of a massive
Conspiracy
The red car actually was the conspiracy
The red car helped create the sprawl in the gridlock
Understand how this all came about
Where to go way back
The mid-nineteenth century
A boy named Henry Huntington was born into a middle-class family in Upstate New York
What's 3 as a very wealthy uncle
Name Carlos
Chuggington
Carlos has no key
Any sort of latches onto his nephew
And I mean I assume you must see something in Henry
Thanks is kicking me molded into a business panties right
Antecollis takes
Little Henry under his wing
Shazam everything about the family business which is
Railroads
Johnson 1900
Carlos.
Henry thinks he's going to inherit the company Southern Pacific doesn't want another Huntington in charge so
Henry's out
Consolation prize which is $50
Back then was up
You like $400 today
He takes his cash
Los Angeles
The city of Los Angeles really shouldn't exist
The LA River with a mess and it was so prone to flooding would actually change its location on the map
The only decent Harbor is Long Beach but San Diego has a center of Commerce
Disconnected flatland but where many people saw the desert
Robber barons of the late 19th century saw something else
A blank slate
So the modern city of Los Angeles
As we know it would created
A sort of like a counterweight to San Francisco which was liberal even back then it very strong union
Anelli wooden open shop
The businessman like Henry Huntington had free reign
And he starts by purchasing the biggest transportation system of the city which of the Los Angeles Railway
How do I sound
Larry
Incorporated into a new company called
Pacific Electric
I talked to a bunch of historians about this including a bill Friedrich
Text to grab him off and
I have this vague recollection of
Streetcar running up and down the main
Drag which is Brand Boulevard
And I think
I think I can remember the Bell
The bell ringing
Really would it sound like
Ding ding
Britax actually wrote a book about Henry Huntington
The key to Henry Huntington's operation was that this was before lot of regulation in the the area so
Henry
Pretty much decided where development Whitaker by Building A street car line out to the area
Just ahead of development
And most frequently he was building the streetcar lines
Out to
Where you own the land
Soda put this in modern terms
The red car with kind of like the Kindle Amazon loses money on the Kindle because they want you to use this
E-reader with a portal to buy lots of
You know bigger stuff on their website
Answer the red car was a portal
To get you to buy other bigger stuff from Henry Huntington
Like your entire life
He never really made money with
The Pacific
Took people out to
Who is subdivisions
Or he sold them land
Frequent seldom water he controlled some water companies
He also
Established
An electric operate
Ocean called the Pacific light and power come
It was essentially set up to
Provide electricity to his trolley cars but he ended up selling like
Electricity to the city of Los Angeles
Now even back then this was not the
This is usual there are lots of other streetcar developer
But they're much smaller
And the frequent went bankrupt
Other developers own land and they build a trolley out
To some land
But not the immense amount of land at Huntington
So
He deserve a complete package coming down
So from 1904 to 1913
Huntington opens 500 new subdivisions every year
He controls more than 900 red cars are more than 1100 miles
Track that's about 25% more track mileage than New York City has today
100 years later
No I mean historically American cities grow organically and Rings you know out of a downtown
In Huntington really forces Los Angeles to expand
Outward it twice the race
And I think that really weak in Downtown LA because he was creating these little downtown's along as trolley routes
So
I know you think he's crazy Empire
Trains he's got the electricity he's got the land
Water
Only need it now
Were people
Back then you know
There's a lot of reasons not to like cities and they were dirty they were crowded
Dangerous
In Los Angeles was going to be very different
Kind of city that was the dream
Huntington and Harry
Chandler and all these other side of LA powerbroker
When is media blitz
And during the winter that would blanket the Midwest with advertisement
Los Angeles is a paradise full of Orange
Trees the climate will
Cure your asthma
You can go surfing and it surfing was actually a relatively unknown sport until Henry Huntington hired a Hawaiian Surfer
George free
The surf along Huntington Beach
And it worked I mean for a while Long Beach was known as Iowa by the Sea cuz how many islands
But eventually the dream when bus
So now remember Pacific electric is designed to lose money at
Portal 2 Ending
Is Real Estate another company
Is it a border Pacific electric is not happy about this
In the meantime
The red car is becoming a threat to Southern Pacific Railroad which was you know the company that
Huntington thought he was going to inherit from his uncle
Southern Pacific wants to buy Pacific Electric
Honeyman says no
His own board overrules him
He's forced to make a deal and once again his power and his Ambitions are
Cut short
But Henry Huntington gets the last laugh
Hanna pretty weird way
Because his uncle's Fortune was
Split between him and his on Arabella
So Huntington marries his aunt
And consolidates the family fortune
Now it's actually not
Quite as icky as it sounds because they were not related by blood
She was his uncle second wife
Yeah
Huntington actually lived happily ever after
When is well that is on his aunt / wife
And he used to Los Angeles to create Huntington Gardens
The Huntington Library he dies in 1920s
And
I don't know if you knew yet
But it was clear already to historians
Looking back
Set the red car
Was doomed
Even though the overall track mileage rivaled New York
The red car wasn't comprehensive enough to go everywhere you needed to go by red car alone
Starting to come poorly-maintained I mean people started calling them
Slums on wheels
The big Turning Point comes in 1926 the year before Huntington died
Southern Pacific
Now owns Huntington Pacific Electric
Offers this master plan to build Subways and elevated trains
All around
Downtown LA
Mississippi pay for by the taxpayer so it's put up for a public referendum
Is a lot of money spent
A lot of advertising spend on both sides just like
Referendums today
And the voters reject the plan
People just didn't like feather Pacific they had meddled in California politics for so long
Did they called it
The octave
Okay so now remember the original sort of conspiracy
Theory that the car companies bought up a red car and
Tore them down in Belton
The freeways
So there was a subsidiary of General Motors
It's called National City
And they did by Charlie cars and they converted them into
Bus routes
And their people the time that.
It was a conspiracy this was in this conspiracy that suddenly you know people discovered 50 years later
But the fact is Pacific electric was doing the same thing to the wrong trolley
As freeways became the norm in the red car became a thing of the past
You can see how a conspiracy theory could become cemented into the public imagination
So when I first saw map of the red car lines
I actually thought it was an early map of
The freeways
Which makes sense because of the route that people are using to get around
And some cases like the Cahuenga pass
Trains were actually dismantle to make way for the Hollywood freeway
Santa Monica Boulevard
Paved over a trolley route and sometimes you know when I was heading to the 405 I actually
Drive over
Phantom tracks
Ellie's first freeway the Arroyo Seco Parkway which connects downtown to Pasadena opened in 1940
A few years later
City planners proposed another plan for elevated railroads
That was rejected by the city council
The last Red Car ran in 1961
And you have to think it was in a way a victim of its own success
Henry Huntington's goal was to connect his far-flung properties and create a decentralized city
That you need a mass transit solution
To get around
The problem was
He couldn't provide it
Overtime La was so spread out
Headed over Tok
What the red car
Was capable of servicing
I like to imagine you know if it's 1960 and I'm driving along the 10 freeway
I mean
Yeah I'm sure there's traffic but it must have been pretty smooth cuz I'm in the freeways that exist now we're the same freeways back
Then
But don't for a much smaller population
So they must have seemed like
A really impressive solution.
The time
And today angelinos can appreciate the great solution of their highway system
4 hours
Hours
Hour an hour an hour an hour and hour
In-N-Out hours
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Eric molinsky with help from Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
It's a project of 91 points
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Art
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook
We dat Roman Mars
We have pictures of red cars and red car maps and pictures of Henry Huntington and 99% invisible
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast.,