99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
So I think we're at
And this is Radio producer Sean Cole in New York City this is a reenactment
We're just going to lay this out the way it happen
I'm here with my friend Melissa
At the Hudson River on the piers where we were
Exactly a year ago
Walking along
You know casually
Pretty drunk
We were
Drunk talking about poetry
As you do when it's late and you're in a part of town you never been before
And it feels like anything could happen
Spontaneously Melissa asked Sean to read her a poem
By the late great Frank O'Hara
Is it dirty or before
Does it look
Dirty joke around with him everywhere that's what you think of in the city
Does it just seem
Dirty
That's what you think of in the city you don't refuse to breathe do you
Someone
Sean's a huge O'Hara fan which we can report in about 2 minutes anyway they kept walking
And walking again until finally they wind up in a little Plaza is it frame by 2
Decorative fences with an opening between them two fences
They hung out there for maybe 20 minutes not noticing anything
And then we kept walking to keep on going and I went Sears words
If I remembered me being those words
Words in one of the fences
I said like we not carved or inscribed into it
It says something but wrought
In the very middle of
The fence
It says
Contraband
Uwosh ins
Shear
City
Of
The sea
City movie of Wars reading
And stores were biwer city of tall
Facade
Of Marvel and iron
Rad
And
Passionate
City
Meddlesome mad
Extra
Again extravagant City Walt Whitman was a passage from another poem
And a big influence
On Frank O'Hara Walt Whitman
They run back to the beginning of the sentence starts over here in the fence
Fentons
City of the world for all races are here all the lands of the Earth make on
City of the sea city of wharves at stores
City of Tulsa sod
Marble and iron proud and passionate City
Meddlesome
Extravagant
City
Holy crap it's Fresno Fair
That's right the second fence
Is forged into a line by Frank O'Hara
Liquors like this
One need never leave the confines of New York
To get all the greenery one wishes I can't even enjoy a blade of grass and less I know there's a Subway handy
Play or record store
Some other sign that people do not totally Regret Life people do not
Totally Regret Life
It's from O'Hara's poem meditations in an emergency if you're a Madman fan you probably heard of it
Sean bent down and scooped his brains up off the concrete
You have to understand
I
That is why I write poems
And
You know poetry is just never
Treated
With this kind of
Reverence
And
Architectural permanents do you know what I mean it's like it's like you don't know
I mean like you see that little like poetry in motion placards on the subway and that's
Nice
This
Is like
The
The balusters of the fence that look that word up this the spokes of the fence come down
And bend around each letter and it sort of
Hug each letter each letter is painted gold
And then like
Oh wait
It's these two poets
With
Whom I have like an entire life of obsession I mean like I wrote I promise I'm
Uncle on 250 pages
Of
Academic
Gobbledygook about Whitman for part of my my college thesis
And O'Hara is like my poetry boyfriend like I'm just like
I like I thought he was my
I'll let you know what I mean like you have those like artists that you carry around with you in there like you've heard of him you know
And
So like to see him a
You know rotten metal you know she's one thing and be rotten metal
Next
The poet
Shio herisau is like
Is Gandhi called him like my great predecessors his big influence
It was the last
Thing I expected to encounter
That night
And I'm glad we went back because
It occurred to us
Sitting there
This time
You know I bet it's dated someone
And I bet there's a date on it
Yeah in fact
It says
The Plaza
Caesar
Kelly and it's pelli
Scott Burton
Sia
Parmigiani
And M Paul
Friedberg
We definitely did not see
I looked them up
Cesar pelli is one of the most influential architects in the world
Scott Burns an artist he died of AIDS in 1989 CRV Johnny is alive he's another artist living
Minnesota
And M Paul Friedberg
Impala Freebirds office is down the street from my apartment in Manhattan
Turns out he's really one of the forerunners of urban landscape design
We sat down for 15 or 20 minutes
Which quickly became almost an hour
In part because of this whole
Homeric
Feud behind the building of this fence
You ready yes no Marathon Iowa
Okay suit Cesar pelli was the main architect for the entire Plaza
And he tapped our guy Friedberg as his Consulting
And I was very pleased
Normally after the design was built
You would find places
For the art
To be located
And then you would go out
And select the artist that you wanted
Now that would that is deep traditional historically the traditional way
I hear a but
But this time someone else was calling the shots
Planning official basically
How to get members name I'm sorry anyway this official comes along and says we want you guys to work with an artist
And the architecture lecture course
But then the official goes
Now you don't quite understand
We want you to use an artist
As a co-equal member of the design team
The artist or going to have just as much control as the architect
That's too that was unheard of
It was really unheard of exactly
Architects in general or war on Happy
Will taking away
An assignment of Pisa
The Architects have always had
Richard
Car is the guys
Richard Conte
Former head of the Battery Park City Authority which control this project
You don't quite understand
That's the way it's going to be
Whether you work on or not
Okay
So the artist were chosen as usual through a competition
The fait accompli for you guys absolutely we were handed these two guys
Sia Army Johnny and Scott Burton the two other names on the plaque
So they're both artists
And Scott
Happened to be acquainted with Frank O'Hara
We met them for the first time I would like you to come up with a
I want to plant
Tori Kelly
Hostile environment
Buying each other suspiciously
Knew what the others were saying about each other and and how badly
And just you know each didn't want the other to be involved
And it wasn't going to get it was on principal
So
I just left him a lot of close the door left
Call me when you have something to show
We met once and they were
Replacement three times
And began to develop
Trusting each other
They fell in love with each other
And the rules are important
If any of us
Therefore
If any of
Anyone of us
Did not want
Peak design
Supposed
Of the other three
It had to be discarded
Time to do the
Defense
She is idea
Not Scotty
It was primarily see his idea that
Because it was part of his
Seeds from a Ron
More poetry is actually
Not mocked openly one need never leave the confines of New York to get all the greenery 1 wishes
Usually selected the quote not the rest of us I can't
Even enjoy a blade of grass unless I know there's a Subway handy
Read then took Sears idea or a record store and made it work physically or some other sign
In the fence
That's my job in this that people do not totally Regret Life
So I called see Army Johnny
And he didn't want to be interviewed for the radio
He did however want to go out for coffee sometime and talk about poetry
He said
Many people many Poets of what was known as the New York school of poetry
Call him after the fence was unveiled to thank him
You're such a wonderful tribute to their friend and colleague Frank O'Hara
O'Hara sister Maureen called theratears he said
To thank him
I just wanted
To be in touch with
This
Is Maureen O'Hara
Can I just say how electrocuting it is to talk with someone who shares the same genetic material as your personal massage
Your brother is my favorite
It's true
She said she loved the idea from when they first mailed her the design on paper
Sent me a 1980
And when she finally saw it in the Flash
Absolutely
Lighted
It was a baby
Blistering
Plus just aesthetically she said
Thing is brilliant and the letters are formed
Heading to the railing and how they shine and they
Really must have been
Quite a surprise
Steelers today
I feel the same way
Anne Frank
Loved it
So much Justice
If he loves collaborating
You know I mean it because really is in the spirit of it
Collabera
Collaborative
Do not get this
I know I was that's why I was so shocked I'm like not only is it
Poetry but it's Walt Whitman and Frank O'Hara I feel like that's a deep
Cut and like
I know you don't normally poetry so
Either maligned or ignored
And it was it's a wonderful for Walt Whitman I mean let's not forget
It would just be
Such a thrill
But to me I think poetry one I think I should be poetry should be in
Indoor gardens did I park
Michigan is M Paul Friedberg bikes
And this actually Taps into a major design principle of his I think information
Should be layered in the
In our environment
Information information
Should be late cultural information
It should be layered in the environment
Not a doctor
It should be an integral part
When I say layered
That if you are interest
You extract
A wall
Structural
Anthony
How do you express
That
It has
Force it has
Power
That's a very important part to the way you designed the wall
But then again the wall is also a billboard
Okay
So how do you then
Express what kind of probation
Do you express on a billboard
Can be decorative that can be color write him anything right
Like that
The idea that you looking at offense and yet you walk away
With the thought
As well
United defense is a barrier
So you really want me to have like a contradiction here
Break the barrier
Okay
Poetry breaks
The barrier
The idea that
Doesn't stop you
It begins some
Yeah
I'm making that up as I go as I go
So what are you end up with all this
Itsfunneh
Melissa nice to have the same thought about it
When we went back
Again for the second visit this time about like Whitman and O'Hara sort of looking down on the
Trump
Someplace
Cioppino
I mean I don't even know if I believe in
The afterlife but it would be cool if they knew
It wouldn't it really would be I think about that all the time
Really
Yeah it would especially be cool for
Troy O'Hara
And it really makes me want to
Go back in time
And say to Frank O'Hara
It's going to be okay
Cuz one day
Align
From a poem
That you wrote War in fact that you may have yet to write
Will be
Ensconced in bronze
In a
Fence
In New York City
Next to align by Walt Whitman
So don't worry
If somebody came and said that to me
I think I'd
I think I died you know
Feel a lot better
Then I usually do
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Shawn Cole Melissa O'Donnell and me Roman
Two gay poets to a minor it's a project of kalw
Local public radio in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
It's the punctuation parentheses
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 Pi feet
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
View of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Two unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode
About uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy, go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God. Info
Flask podcast
Can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us her on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more
A story including pool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
Go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio tupi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I
I had something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com