99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The night of December 8th
A huge crowd appeared on a tree line Boulevard in downtown Kiev
The capital of Ukraine
The crowd was there to watch as a statue in the boulevard was
Pulled down by a crane
That's producer Julia Barton
It's a pretty large statue
A little more than 11 ft
Talk
Odesza topples to the ground
The Crowd Goes Wild
The toppled statue was Vladimir Lenin
The communist leader who started the revolution that created the Soviet Union
Of which Ukraine was once apart
The sculpture had shown Lennon striding into a breezy future
One that just
Barely Ripple his marbles soup
But on the night of December 8th
This linen was no longer striding into a breezy future
He was lying on the cold concrete
As protesters
Continued to abuse him
They was just shouting that
You know what that's
This
Monument need to be ruined
And The Tease Aquila
And
It's not the place for sluggish it here anymore
I'm Thai
Ukrainians are owners of this land
Ukrainian photojournalist Alexander to Chin
Rush to the scene that
He and his colleagues kept a camera steady
Is the drama unfolded around
Their footage ended up in a documentary they later made called All Things Ablaze
It shows people taking sledgehammers the woman's torso
The camera lingers on one man in a shiny tracksuit
Spits on his hand
Crosses himself three times
And start to walking away with all his might
But at some point
Just an old guy in a black coat emerges from the crowd
Adjust wraps himself around linen
Chest
Yeah she was trying to protect him with his own body
And did he say anything
He was saying that it's it's not right it's not correct
Please don't do that
It's
Warszawa
Barbarism barbarism
Yeah another man
Hats the old communist on the back
A little threatening lie
He saved this old communist sympathizer
You're the last one in the whole city
The whole country understand
When you die things in this country will get better
Eventually some Volunteers in reflective vest
Leave the old man away by the arms
His hat is gone
He looks ready to fight
The protesters this old man in the Statue of Lenin represent old Ukraine
One that is associated with the Soviet Union and with Russia
The protesters saw themselves as New York
Independent
And allied with the European Union
The same protest that brought down that Lenin statue
Eventually brought about a new government
That new government
Has been trying to get rid of all kinds
Physical reminders of communism
And Russia
Lenin statue
Names of streets
In town
But it hasn't always been easy to get rid of these thing
Logistically or politically
Because it erases apart history
That is still important to some Ukrainian
People in a different parts of Ukraine conceived its history difference
That's Katarina trnava
She's a legal editor at
Vox Ukraine. Org
Website for Ukrainian news and policy in Dallas
Where someone it is a history of Oppression
It is the history of unity
Having your talent being developed under the Soviet rule in the process of industrialization
To understand all this we should zoom out a bit
Ukraine is a country about the size of Texas
Is bordered by Russia to the east
And the rest of Europe to the West
Between two superpowers the European Union and Russia
A lot of people in the US still refer to Ukraine as the Ukraine
Like the Midwest or the South
A region
Drives Ukrainian crazy
But there is a reason for the mistake
For centuries Ukraine was a region controlled by more powerful entities around it
And the word Ukraine literally means Borderland
In the 1920s much of the territory of Ukraine became part of the Soviet Union
Despite the efforts of a lot of people who wanted it to be an independent country
In the 1930s
Millions of ukrainians
Died in a famine
Installing engineered by
Forcibly taking food from peasants
Entrapping them into
Starvation
What's the policy of collectivization they would take away the
The possessions of the people that they they would collapse the grain from Farm some people worst
Starving many scholars believe stolen did this specifically to Cripple the movement for Ukrainian
A decade later during World War II
Hundreds of thousands of ukrainians especially people in the East near what is now Russia
What ended with the Soviet Red Army
The smaller number of people in the west who wanted an independent Ukraine
Allied themselves with the Nazis
And the Soviet Union and Germany
Both wanted control over Ukrainian territory
The trailer of Ukraine was the treasurer of clashes during the second World War
When was all over even more of Ukraine was part of the USSR
Soviet authorities one of the people of Ukraine to United around the narrative that they had
Defeated the Nazis in that communism
Would help the country rebuild
It was the story about winning the war and coming back
Victoriously and trading
To rebuild the country from scratch
The hard to find
Relounge the country again
And it was very hard to
Because they come
To empty house
Is that all
The territory of Ukraine was heavily ball
As part of a campaign team
Unite Ukraine under the banner of communism
The Soviets put statues of the ussr's founding father
Vladimir Lenin
Everywhere
Ukraine eventually had around 5500 statues of Lenin
In the whole territory of Russia which is 28 times the size of Ukraine
There were about
7000 Linens
Apart from covering Ukraine and linens
The Soviet Union did help develop
End rebuild Ukraine
In the years after World War II
Small villages
Became big industrial cities
But the Soviet regime also imprisoned by some estimates around 2 million ukrainians in ghoul
Because the Soviet Union was not a free Society with
The Free Press
Many people had no idea that kind of oppression was happening
This whole depression and building up labor camps and gulag
In the USSR and this information was not disclosed of people didn't have access to that information
The USSR said
Everything is fine
As they put up more and more Lenin statues all over Ukraine
Ukraine eventually became the most linen eyes territory
In the USSR
The chief State TV channel was halfway through its Evening News
When it got the first details of the agreement signed in means
Quoting from it the anchorwoman announced
The Soviet Union
No longer exist
In 1991 the Soviet Union collapsed
Ukraine became its own separate country and so did Russia
But Russia on onto its Soviet past
Russia after the collapse of the USSR officially announced that it is
Successor of the USSR
It's kind of the same they have the music in the national anthem
The famous just the words that have
Russia drop the tenets of Communism and embrace capitalism in many ways
But the leadership of the country especially current President Vladimir Putin
Never stop being proud of the Soviet Legacy
Ukraine meanwhile has struggled with its identity
Since gaining its independence in 1991
For a very long time Ukraine was very indecisive I would say in international politics
With the country Orient East
Patricia
Or west
What's Europe
It was hard for you created
Completely cut ties
Russia
One they relied on it
Charcoal and gas
But also many ukrainians have strong cultural
Connections to Russia
Ukrainians have a lot of
Relatives living in Russian
Call traits family and its business relationship to because
Boost Nation speak the same language it is very easy to
To carry out business
Activities
For years the country seem to vacillate
Some president of Ukraine lean West towards Europe
Others oriented e
Toward Russia
And all those Lenin statues and other communist symbols in the built environment
In Western Ukraine war
People felt less loyalty
Soviet-era
They got rid of most of them right after Independence
Then the rest of Ukraine they mostly stay put
The wheel to remove them just wasn't there
And then in 2013
The pro-russian president
Viktor Yanukovych
Tried to back out of a deal to bring Ukraine closer to joining the European Union
Huge protest broke out
The tide had turned
Ukrainians were in the street saying they didn't want to be beholden to Russia anymore
These are the same protests that led to the Lenin statue being torn down in Kiev
The one that you heard at the beginning of the story
But that's not the only statue that came down
People started spontaneously tearing down Lennon's all over Ukraine
So much so that they had a name for it
Lenin apod
The falling of the lens
In February of 2014
Following days of bloody protests in which more than a hundred protesters were killed
Viktor Yanukovych
Was forced out of the presidency and fled to Russia
The protesters in Ukraine established a new government
Athena Valentin shocking few days Ukraine
Ultimate
Victorious and arrange the top Rihanna curvage and install a new government
Russian President Vladimir Putin didn't like that Ukraine was turning away from Russia and toward the European Union and in March of
2014 hiexpress stop by taking control of a part of Ukraine called
Crimea
This morning more unidentified
Pro-russia armed militias patrolling the streets of Crimea capital
Meanwhile hundreds of miles to the east
Russian-backed separatists started fighting the Ukrainian military
Those battles continue today
At least 10000 people
I'm done
By the end of 2014 Ukraine's new government
Now definitively oriented towards West
Had inherited a country in crisis
You might think linen removal would be at the
The bottom of their list
But battles with the separatists
May the government want to rid its landscape
Once and for all of its Soviet
Which was
Centennial
Is it
Big furry
Shuffle symbol
One year after coming to power the new government led by Petro poroshenko
Decided to make the falling of the Lenin's into State policy
His allies in Ukraine parliament passed a package of bills
It's called decarbonization
Various post-soviet countries had already
In Ukraine these laws did a number of things outlawed communism
One of which was to ban communist
Symbols
Local authorities had a year
To get rid of their Linens tattoos
Is there town or streets had communist names
Those had to be changed to
Ukrainians in Hawkins have celebrated the toppling of the monument to former Soviet leader Vladimir Lenin
Statue of Soviet dictator Vladimir Lenin has been taken down in the Ukrainian city of another day another Lenin
Monuments pools in Ukraine's war-torn East
Some places in Ukraine Got really creative
It's about complying with the decolonization
A factory in Odessa hired a sculptor to refashion the figure of Lenin
As Darth Vader
Overseeing the removal of all these symbols is a government organization
Ukrainian is
Doot of national remembrance
National Park
Deputy head of Ukrainian Institute of national remembrance
Spark told me it's not easy to go from totalitarianism
To democracy
That's a very complicated person.
Coming from a totalitarian
Society Apso democratic
It's also not easy to raise communism from the built environment
The Soviets made things to last
Are long Bridges lined with wrought-iron Hammers and sickles
Their whole Forest planted in such a way that if you fly over
You see the Cyrillic initials for the USSR
And there are neighborhoods
That do this to
A set of building
Les Schwab do top in such a way Seresto construct
Letters of USS all letters
Wasn't
That's one, symbol that may have to stay for now
Truck says the process of decolonization isn't just about removal
It's also meant to help ukrainians
Learn their own history
Which is why in many cases
The Institute of national remembrance has suggested that Town's revert
To the names they had beef
Before the Soviets change them
This is actually what happened to Katrina donovitz home
Downtown Institute of national remembers made a proposition to restore
For the historical name of the town
In 2016
The name of her town was restored
To come and skia
Is routed back to 1750 when there were calls.
Settlements
The Soviet name of Katarina's town
That it had up and
Till 26
Was nip Road erosion
Can you put the bank and it's absolutely unpronounceable event for native
Enjoy of this town the majority of people just wanted to keep the old unpronounced
Soviet name
Cuz she says it was just a tiny village before the Soviets set up a metallurgical plant there
City owes its very existence
To the Soviet history
It has become a town and has become so big because of the
Soviet rule
So it does make sense that there was a big part of
Population that opposed to change
But in the end it didn't matter
People wanted
To keep the name
The town was named for a prominent Soviet figure
Felix dzerzhinsky
Who founded the Soviet Secret Police
And the new law mandated the town's name be changed
What local communities do not have is a choice to keep the Soviet
That's Tariq Serie Lamar
A historian of Ukraine and Eastern Europe at Columbia University in New York
This type of
As I would say
Trali Hampstead attempt
Dealing versus Orbit Legacy is actually producing
Some of the Soviet leaders
Some of the habits
What's up doing census always way
And this is a major criticism of the decolonization Ma
That Ukraine is being kind of authoritarian about separating from their authoritarian past
Not just because people don't get a say in whether they change the name of their town
But because the laws also make it illegal to join the Communist Party
Or display any kind of Soviet symbols
Or to deny the quote
Criminal nature
Of the Soviet regime
Criminal matrons a criminal nature is not defined so we're not even sure about what we're not
Allowed to deny requests
Scholars we spoke to for the story opposed these parts of the decolonization laws
The ones that seem to limit freedom of speech and freedom of expression
I never believed the laws too ambiguous
It's unclear if for example wearing a t-shirt with Karl Marx on it could make you criminally liable
Since the formal process of removing communist symbols began in 2014
More than 50000 objects have been renamed
This includes cities
Towns Villages streets
Squares and Parks
And more than 2,000 monuments and memorials have been taken down or modified
In general these changes have been hardest on Ukraine's older population
The people who lived under Soviet rule
Who didn't understand how bad it was for some people
Because there wasn't free press or freedom in Academia
Extent of the repression was hidden from the General Public
Some ukrainians are now just finding out
Add millions of people died because of Stalin
And that Millions more were put into goulash
These Notions of a
Prescience the facts
Statistics
Come to them as a
Big Revelation right now
Denial
There's been a lot of change in Ukraine in the past couple of decades
And it's still volatile
Over a million people have been displaced
And some Eastern parts of the country are locked in semi-permanent conflict with Russia
You you leaving this permanent condition of not knowing what's going to happen next and what day
That's why
It is easier for someone who has been
And I living under the Soviet troops feeling
Tell Jake about it
Donovan said that for now many ukrainians have shifted away from wanting to be allied with Russia and toward one
Wanting to be allied with the EU
But Russia still exerts a lot of political influence
And there were pro-russia forces within the country
Cause trouble for a long time
Despite feeling like some parts of the decolonization laws are too ambiguous
Joinable thinks that removing communist symbols in public spaces
Is an important step as Ukraine continues to develop as an independent nation
I think it is
I think it is because I think it should have been done earlier
It should be understood it's never easy
Suggest that there would always be a certain percent of the
The population would strongly oppose that change
It's Tricky for Ukraine
For any country really
To figure out how to leave behind symbols of Oppression without completely denying and erasing the past
In Lithuania which was also part of the USSR
They threw a lot of their Lenin Stalin and Karl Marx statues into one Park
Gruta Spa
Unofficially called
Stalin's world
And the Park is open for visitors
So those people who feel you know
Very sentimental about the whole Communist party and communist issues they will continue to come there to visit and enjoy
View of the big Landing statues
In the multiple variations arise
Ukraine doesn't have any such Park
But there have been some efforts to acknowledge the existence and loss of these monuments
For a week in 2016 a group called permission to put a temporary installation
Around the empty pedestal in Kiev that used to hold the same linen we heard being toppled at the beginning of this
Story
The installation consisted simply of metal stairs
That people could have send to stand on a platform placed over the pedestal
And then descend on the other side
In the process they could see the world from Lenin's perspective
And of course
Take a selfie
Ukrainian curator who helped organize the installation says
Quote
A way of asking what a monument is for
And everyone decides for themselves
That's because she says
Becoming ization starts first
In the mind
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Julia Barton and Katie mingle with Sharif Youssef
Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Coco said is digital director Taryn Mazza is the off
Music this week by okay akumi melodium in our own
Sean real
Special thanks to David marples Alix klineman off Misha Friedman and Katerina dronova
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Remember radiotopia is touring the West Coast from May 8th to the 12th of June Portland Seattle San Francisco or LA
You have to be there it's a requirement
Gucci radiotopia. FM live for ticket
If you want to see us in San Francisco this is
Pretty much your last chance for ticket
That's where nearly sold out already
Portland is on the brink 2 so act fast
We're in really big rims in Seattle in LA
So you nerds better step up
I fought for you
Call a couple of friends and make a note of it
Criminal one of the first and still the best
True Crime podcast
That you hurt
Criminal tells stories of people who have broken the law in
Caught some people that broke the law and got away with it
Victims
Cops and people caught somewhere in the middle
Every episode is completely
You never quite know what you're going to get some are really hilarious Omar tragic
But I simply adore
Every single episode
Don't change the way you look the world around you
You need to see him live if you're on the west coast but you can't be there for some dumb reason
Get to know criminal at this is Criminal. Com
Subscribe an iTunes Google Play
Whatever you get Podcast
In addition to the Torah I also have a one-off live show in LA on April 14th with Helen zaltzman of the illusion
It's a benefit show all proceeds go to
U arts for LA
Do you like art
And are a little nervous about hearts
And like dirty humor and obscure facts about seemingly boring things
This will be the night of your life
Will have full details
The 99% illusional art
Spore La benefit
On our website
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
Listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI feed
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find the show Android discussion about the show
On Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
We're on Instagram and Tumblr to
Do you want to read all about logo doppelgangers
I'm very popular post this week
You have to go
Tonight 9 p.m.
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com