99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
It's hard to imagine building a city from scratch
I just remember the difference between the first time I went there when it was just a
Little mud hole
Didn't look like it had very much potential at all
Turning a little mud hole into a full-service City
It takes an incredible amount of resources and people
And moxie
That's reporter Chloe prasino's
And the other voice you just heard is Milt Ritter
Okay my name is Milt Ritter
Ritter is a journalist he covered the story of rajneeshpuram which was a city that pops up in Oregon
In in the 1980s
Pajamas
Amazing
You know the service
Slightly breathtaking driving down into the canyon
After a few years compared to what it was
Rajneeshpuram wasn't trying to be any American city
They're trying to build a Utopia
Guided by New Age religious principles
A place where people of like mind could abandon the mainstream and live their own way
And almost as quickly as this place went from mudhole to City
It went from Utopia
2 dystopian
There's been a couple of big
Stories that I covered in my lifetime
The eruptions of Mount Saint Helens was one of them and the rajneeshpuram was was the other you know
Is that
Crazy
The story really begins with one man
An Indian Guru named bhagwan shree rajneesh
His name Loosely translates to serve God
Bhagwan shree rajneesh is a
Mystic
Xiaomi India
And he's what we would referred to as an enlightened being that's ma Ananda Sarita
When she was 17 she ran away from home and traveled the world
Looking for what she calls the essence
Thug Life
Sarita found it in India when she met bhagwan shree rajneesh
So of course you've heard of Jesus you've heard of
Buddha
Those would be considered as an enlightened being
Rajneesh was a philosophy Professor come Guru
He synthesized eastern and western spiritual thought
And Psychotherapy
And created his own brand of spirituality
He
Sad
You cannot make a Dogma out of my word
As far as I could tell his religion was
A non religion
Here's archival tape of bhagwan shree rajneesh from the Oregon Historical Society
Will be hearing tape from their archive throughout this episode
It is not available
This
It is a very of living
The guru's way of life basically trashed all the difficult stuff about religion all the Chastity and abs
Discipline and shame
And instead curated a spirituality of sex laughter and luxury
Which as you can imagine
Pretty appealing to a lot of paper
Rajneesh had a meditation center in India wear in the 70s
Lots of westerners paid good money for Spiritual instruction
Disciples dressed in red clothing and warlock hats with his photo inside
They called themselves sannyasins kind of spiritual Seeker
They even took new names given to them by the guru
The women were given the title Ma
The men were referred to as Swami disciples
They claim to be in love
Weather Guru
Iguanas my master and I love him
She was
Infinitely
Graceful
And in his eyes
When could
Experience
Universe
Passing there
Troubling alive
Rajneesh was known for a technique called Dynamic meditation
It was intended to quiet the mind
Practitioners close their eyes and concentrate on their breathing
Send
Explode
Scream jump
Kik
Dance
Rise
Then comes a mantra
And then
Silence
In 1981 rajneesh was basically kicked out of India
There were accusations that is ashram was a business not a religious Institution
Which would mean he owed several million dollars in back taxes
So the guru and his followers started looking for a new home base
And they found it in the United States
64000 acre ranch way out in the range country of North Central Oregon
Soon after they arrived Mill Twitter went out to investigate
When we first
Took that trip
It was almost like
Really is
Is this right you know are we
Headed in the right
Direction This is
Seems so out
And it was hard to understand
What a guru from India wood
What in a place like
The first time I met the garage Nisha was in
The about the second week of July of 1981
This is Dan dorough
He was the Wasco County planner at the
And the sannyasins new Ranch was located in his
Jurisdiction
When they first walked into the office there were just three of them at the time
And they were quite pleasant but they definitely word from around there
They were all dressed in red badge strange names
At one point in the conversation Doro asked if they were a religious organization
And the answer was so no absolutely not
We're not a religion we have members who are a ball face
And we just Celebrate life and laughter and
And happiness and we're just simple farmers
Well
That wasn't the case and that wasn't
1st and 10th
Duro didn't know it yet but the intent of his visitors was to build a mecca for the gurus followers from a
Across the globe
In order to build anything
Bassani assassins would have to get permits
For every single structure that went up
A mistake I think that
They made ultimately was to not look at the land use laws of Oregon
Versus other states
Listen to chose Amazon specifically for farming
And they weren't going to be able to get permits for buildings that weren't performing
But there was a workaround
According to state law if they became their own City they could have their own planning office and issue their own purse
Effectively skirting County oversight and
The land use laws
In Oregon at the time to incorporate a city all you needed was 150 people
Which was easy for the sannyasa
There really wasn't much to decide
Once I met the basic requirements for incorporation that did move forward
Johnson's name their new city after the guru
Bhagwan shree rajneesh
They called it
Rajneeshpuram
It seemed like it happened very quickly
That building started springing up
And
Garden started being planted houses
They scratched out a runway for
An Airfield
And they brought in
Planes
The city needed infrastructure to support not just the full-time residents
But visitors to
Every summer thousands of disciples came for rajneesh's Annual Festival
In the off-season
People came to take meditation courses and experience life
In the city
They built a strip mall and a hotel buildings for religious ceremonies
A crematorium
A discoteca post office
Many of the buildings were designed in a rustic
Alpine Style with wooden siding
Housing on the other hand was built quickly
With lots of prefab a frame structures littered across the valley
It was amazing at what they were doing and they were doing it very very quickly
But the rent is rapid expansion did not go unchecked
Immediately after rajneeshpuram became an official city in Oregon Environmental Group challenged in court
Operation
Basa
The
Attempt
To build a big city out in the desert
Which was
Agriculture
As a huge problem
For the land use laws
A judge ruled that the sannyasins could keep building there
Despite the pending lawsuit
But he won them
If the environmentalists won their case against rajneeshpuram
Almost everything they built
Would have to come down
Sonia Austin's were undaunted they work 16-hour day 6 days a week building up their City
Here's ma Anand Espirito again
And so we would work
All day and usually that would go until midnight
And then go to bed
Maybe have a lover and make love all night and then get up again
The morning and start over
Rajneesh taught his followers that meditation was the highest form of worship
And that work
Would be there meditation
A doctrine of Relentless work is
Pretty convenient when you're trying to erect
A city from scratch
Of course all that construction cost a lot of money
Luckily rajneesh had a Global Network of lucrative communes
That sent the revenue to rajneeshpuram
Plus the guru's followers surrendered everything
Sing from their former lives
They sold their jewelry their cars their homes
And give it to the city
The ranch was changing fast
Listen to ride in 1981 but by 1983
They build 140 small dams up and down the John Day River to slow the rate of a rodent
And it work
The dusty Golden Valley was Green
We had an amazing organic
Farm
I was
Very very nutritious vegetables
Within the first couple years the population jumped from a few hundred people to around 2,000
And their Farms produced almost everything they needed
They also accomplish some pretty impressive Feats of engineering
Rebuild a 45-acre reservoir held by a 400-foot Earthen Dam
Not to mention a mass transit system composed of 85 school buses that zigzag around Rodney Parham
But while the citizens got around in school buses
The guru
Preferred a Rolls-Royce
In fact
She owned 93 Rolls Royce
And everyday in a kind of ritual he drive around the city in one of them
Noon and then again like a
He would drive the roads and people the sannyasins would line up along the road
Hands clasped
In front of their faces
Sort of being blissed-out as he went by and tears streaming down their face
Writer of the time he moved to America the group began about silence
To be so cold drive-bys were one of the ways that rajneesh communicated with his followers
But it seems like he also just really like the feel of the open road and then he would hit the highway and he wouldn't
Drive a hundred miles an hour I don't know how many tickets he got
How many
Times he was
Threatened
Have his license taken away but
Evidently was a lot
While rajneesh was in silence he set up a government for the ranch
An elite Inner Circle of female senior
He wanted to come in to be a matriarchate because he believed that women were less dominated by their egos
At the center of the circle was a woman named ma Anand Sheela
Sheila was rajneesh's secretary and chief spokes
She was one of the only people he spoke to during his long silence
Here's archival tape of ma Anand Sheela
My purpose is
To live better living Master book launch. Mesh
Harmoniously
Because people around here
And he's a very beautiful rich life which we have here
Whenever Milt Ritter came to report on the ranch
She would try to convince him to join the sannyasins
What's the lose your everything is taken care of for you here all your food is made for your laundry is done you have
Housing why wouldn't you just do this
Whenever Milt Ritter came to report on the ranch
She would try to convince him to join the sannyasins
What's the lose everything is taken care of for you here all your food is made for your laundry is done you have
Housing
Why wouldn't you just do this
Sheila didn't convince mehltretter to move but she had a very persuasive way about her
And she was becoming more and more powerful
There was a kind of
We could call a power-elite so
Sheila was considered to be
The boss and especially when one was in silence
Then she took on more and more sporty
At first it seemed like she wanted to have a good relationship with this Roundy Oregon Community party out at the ranch
But it didn't last a lot of people think that it was Sheila that steered rajneeshpuram into a dark chapter
One that began with the neighboring town of anti
Antelope with a small community of about 40 people
Mostly retirees
Phenibut depressed
Little
Community
And had a grocery store and
Maybe a gas station
I think
And not a whole lot more
It's on yachts and saw an opportunity in Antelope
They knew the future of their coming with subject to the County's laws
If they had control of a
Town and establish town is incorporation wasn't hanging in the balance
They can influence County policy and carve out a permanent place for themselves in Oregon
Soda sannyasins purchase vacant houses in town
Move their people in and generally made life in Antelope miserable
They harass locals const
Partied in their driveways made fun of them on the street
And just to intimidate people
They took photos of license
It's and videotape City Council meetings
They were obviously given a mission
Take over the town of
Antelope
Over the course of a couple years the sannyasins Stacked the city council and elected their own mayor
They even took over Antelope School
Enforce ranchers to bust their children to another town an hour away
They ran the place
And eventually they changed the name of antelope to rajneesh
Now they were pissing people off
Anti rajneesh sentiments spread like wildfire
Across the state
You started seeing bumper stickers that said better dead than red
In reference to the sannyasins Red Clothing
And some of this anti rajneesh sentiment turned violent a hotel in Portland owned by the rajneeshees was bombed
Don't know when was killed
And both the guru and she will begin receiving death threats
Sheila felt they were under attack
Stop
Persecute
Once and for all
And if they want to come too
Can you persecuting us
Even though we are nonviolent
People
Rebuild Showdown
Kind of harassment
Rusty Spoons police force they called it peace Force
Started buying more and more weapons everywhere
Sheila carrying a sidearm
The city even had two helicopter reconnaissance teams
And then there were demonstrations that they would show to the media
If they're firing range
Tamales
Automatic and semi-automatic weapons
They had a lot of fun
The Takeover of antelope the brandishing of weapons it was all too much
State and County politicians got together and put the bureaucratic SmackDown on rajneeshpuram
First the Oregon land conservation and development commission amended their rules
Now counties would have to check with the state
Before allowing a new city to incorporate
The new rule was retroactive
2 right around the time rajneeshpuram was incorporated
And then a County Judge stalled all Construction in rajneesh
No more building until their status as a city with sorted out
Rajneeshpuram seem to be losing the battle to exist as a city
Pierce County planner dandaro again
And it wasn't long after that too I think that they'd then began to move in
The street people from around the country
And bussing the man and
Housing them there on the ranch 84
She went to the homeless
Their idea was that
If we can bring in enough people
A live here
And we can convince them to vote
Are the rajneesh candidates we could
Actually get a couple of people on that on the County Council
And maybe get some things
Going our way
She was denied that the new residents were there just to vote
She claimed she wanted to share the Bounty with
And name the initiative the share home Pro
Nobody else is taking care of them somebody has to do it
And I'm grateful that they are ready
Disheveled
The program got a lot
Of media at 10
Mention some 300 the new arrivals now meditate
70 of just become full-fledged sannyasins
As many as 4,000 homeless Americans were brought to rajneeshpuram during the share home
But behind the scenes the new residents weren't
Treated well
Rajneeshpuram leadership tried to keep them in line by drugging them with Haldol the powerful antipsychotic
Not surprisingly, many of the new residents ended up leaving
And then in a final desperate move the leadership of rajneeshpuram devised an insane plan
To prevent the rest of the county from voting
By making people to 6
To go to the polls
The way they did it evidently is
They would go to these restaurants
And
Buy a lunch
And when they went to the salad bar they would like
Pull out a little
Squirt bottle
That they had
Concocted in the lab at rajneeshpuram that had salmonella in it
And they would just
Spray this over the salad bar
And then slip it back in their pocket and nobody knew
There were no fatalities but 750 people are poison
The sannyasins power elite wouldn't be connected to the poisonings for another year
To this day it is the largest Act of bioterrorism
Honeywell Sol
My 1985 rajneeshpuram had entered its death row
It has become a kind of
Oppressive
Energy
You could say
The ranch
The guru finally emerged from his vow of silence
Sheila couldn't speak on his behalf anymore
And then I think she started getting more and more nervous as he
Out more
Then she started
Seething frog
Power was was winning
And suddenly
Sheila
What's going on
She left rajneeshpuram for West Germany
And then once she hits
Fled then all these things started
Light because then people started speaking
And
And putting the pieces of puzzle together
There was a long list of Dirty Deeds that Sheila and her the tenants had perpetrated over the past several years
Including but not limited to the Salmonella poisoning operation throughout Rogers from
A plot to murder The guru's Physician and Oregon's Attorney General
And the firebombing of Wasco County Planning Department
Dan DeRose office
There are also rumors of crimes Sheila and her Inner Circle perpetrated against sannyasins
Sedating people for days against their will
Telling troublemakers they are hiv-positive and quarantining them so their descent wouldn't catch
Some sannyasins were forcibly sterilized
Ninety-nine and forty-four 100% of the people
Who lived at rajneeshpuram
They were just good people trying to eke out a lie
You know in what they thought was the perfect Utopia
Antebellum
This was shocking
The complete shop
Disbelief
And then at the same time once it started coming tonight there was relief
Then she was gone
The girls started talking to reporters
He claimed innocence
And invited the authorities to investigate the ranch
Did you really not know what was going on in Antelope
But I was silent I was completely unaware
That's an archival recording of bhagwan shree rajneesh
Soon Sheila was extradited from West Germany on a slew of charges
She pled guilty but said rajneesh was The Mastermind
That she was only acting on behalf of
For Spiritual master
Her sentence
Three concurrent
20 year terms
To be served in Pleasanton California
The guru was also charged
Specs for Less
He got 5 years probation $400,000 in fines
And
He was deported
It was the whole Ranch
Just got a ground to a
A standstill
These people were
Grieving
And then
Rodney Strong
Everything was
Being auctioned off
Everything from
Rolls-royce's
Two police uniform
After the auction
It was a ghost
Sarita was one of the last sannyasins to leave
She admits things went terribly awry but she still feels good about what they built in Russian
Even though it didn't last
The fact is
Stood for a number of years
We were living in a
Very very beautiful
Harmony with each other
So
This was an amazing
Achievement
And I think
Can serve as a model
The fact that there was some
I'm kind of power games going on and there was these destructive elements
That you will find anywhere
Rajneesh return to India where you continue to be a spiritual leader under a different name
OSHA
He died of heart failure in 1990
What is teaching still command a global following
Sheela only served about two years of her 20-year sentence
She was released early for good behavior
Now she lives in Switzerland
Where she owns nursing homes for the elderly
And disabled
Today the city that the samuelson's Left Behind has been transformed into a different kind
Community
My co-producer Steven and I went out to where rajneeshpuram used to be
We drove down the long Gravel Road and descended down into the valley that
Is now home
It's one of the largest youth Christian camps in the
Country
Owned and operated by an organization called Young Life
The meditation Hall where sannyasins used to gather is now a massive Sports
Flex with a batting cage
For basketball courts ping pong tables you name it
The old hotel is now a dormitory
Occasionally they use the airstrip the sannyasins Left Behind The Flying International
Rajneeshpuram isn't acid anymore
It's now called the Washington family ranch and is under County jurisdiction
It's still a place for religious Seekers but not the kind that want to build a Utopia
Does thousands of Christian teens looking to have
The best week
There lies
99% invisible with producers week by Chloe prasino's and Stephen Jackson with Katie mingle Avery truffle
Greenspan Cuoco's dad and me Roman Mars
Special thanks the Oregon Historical Society for the use of their archive and this episode also features of a bunch of meat
Music from Amnesia his first album just came out it is going to be big
I like the album so much I decided to put the full vocal version of the first song on the album at the end of this episode so
Stay tuned
And you're going to have your new favorite song you heard it here first
We are brother to 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced by the offices of arcsin in architecture and interior
Sperm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made site
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a kid is another remember all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and like us on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify the pictures
Send supplementary material about rajneeshpuram are particularly fascinating so you don't want to miss though that 99 Pi. Org
And as a little train as promised
Here's for Love from the law from the debut self-titled album by animation
Do you like that song
Yeah
Do you think
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com