99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The Story Goes Like This
And keep in mind with all these words and stories when they sound a little too much like stories
They're probably not completely true but anyway
The Story Goes Like This
Theophilus van kannel hated chivalry
There's nothing you despise more than trying to walk in or out of a building
And locking horns with some other man in a game of horse
Ufirst
And more than that socially mandated deference to other men
Theophilus Van canal
Hated opening doors
For women
And Sophie opolis band Canal or po4 short took a German Innovation from 1881
The chew on a lute
Door without draft of air
He made some improvements to the design in an 1888 movie award an American patent for the improved revolving door
The first one was installed in Times Square in
That's our producer Sam Greenspan
Bent Nails improve revolving door at three compartments
And weather stripping to ensure an energy-efficient fit inside the door frame is eating 88
Patent states that quote
It is perfectly noiseless in its operation and effectually prevents the entrance of wind
No rain or dust
Either when it's closed
Or when persons are passing
And as a bonus and I liked any chance of social interaction that one might have
Well entering or exiting a building
The motto of Theo van canals revolving door company
Was always open
Always closed
And so for the past hundred plus years we have had the solution
Nikki dust and Noise
And rain and sleet and snow from entering our building
And yet
The likelihood that you'll actually use it
Is Barry
Very low
Problem is that people don't use revolving doors
Because they're happy or
They feel like they make it
Stuck in them
Compartments terrified
And this shouldn't be a big surprise when you're approaching a revolving door
It's always hard to tell
How are you going to have to push it to get it going and if it is already moving
It does right
And there's also the anxiety of getting a limb caught
Or maybe your bag and it's all mad
If you're walking with someone and talking to him is a little bit bigger of a revolving door
Usually get in there with him
Close
PU 2nd semester
Depress
And if you read Alan Moore's Watchmen
You may remember that detail about how some of the superheroes are wary of catesby
One time there Caped Crusader colleague dollar bill
Got his tape caught in a revolving door and was dust and mobilize a bank robber approached him
Man shot him in the head Point Blank
As long as you can tell if you need to
Bush
Pulled open the door
And that subjects
Could be up
Whole episode in of itself
Swinging Doors
Adjust easy
And most of us unlock van canal
Are well-adjusted human being to actually do try
To open the door for each other
Anytime you have a stream of
People walking together and
The first person that line open swing-door the rest tend to follow so this is Andrew
My name is Andrew Shea I'm a graphic designer Rider
Anderson station with revolving doors started when he was in grad
I was in my teeth
Tucson
Designing person
Change
And a good friend of mine was visiting
You found out what I was doing and he's going to revolving doors and he's like
If you want to design for social change
I wish you would get people to use
Use revolving doors
That was his challenge to
Andrew dobin to the literature on revolving doors
Which was shockingly
Quite slow
But he did come across
Study of
Study done by MIT
But you was focused on sustainability
It was the only resource like
I can find out there though
Authoritative
And their impact
I had a lot of math in it
I kind of avoided the math because
But you don't really need to see the math understand the logic
The basic idea of how a revolving door
Never open a can
Exchange of air from the outside
How do people move through the revolving door they don't open it then we are that week
Through is either the
Sakelaris
Transformer
People on the chambers
Of the revolving door
Or whatever leaks around weather stripping
That's Dan wasilowski
One of the authors on the revolving doors.
Back when he was a grad student at MIT
He works on a project studying people's behavior with respect to revolving doors and the Energy savings associated with
With using revolving doors
In large building
And in some ways it's a study that will not leave him alone
We were not the first people to contact
Packing for an
I don't understand it you know I've got like 20 review publication to Material Science and Engineering and I'll what do I have like
Constant Contact about
I turn paper I did
8 years ago
Anyway Dan did a bunch of signs that sounds like the Escalade key associated with all the water vapor that is
In that material
We didn't really give you enough contacts understand that little bit
But here's the result there's a time was more are exchanged when you use the
Swing door then when using revolving door air
Spencer
Death and Russia again the designer in New York
And this factoid really resonated with me
Which makes total sense because opening a swinging door is like tearing a hole in a building
All that heat or air condition
Leaks out
And the building has to kick into high gear to make up for that temperature and humidity fluctuation
Dan waslaski and his team observed by building on MIT campus that had both revolving doors and Swinging Doors
And found that the revolving-door usage
Sad and about
25%
The team realized that
In addition to conserving energy and helping the environment
They can also save MIT more than $7,500 annually if everyone just use the revolving door in this one building
And
They found the kid raised revolving-door usage at that building to 60 or 70%
What system simple signage
And even though the MIT study
What's on in Boston and Andrew was in New York
It seemed like a pretty transposal data set
To all this inspired Andrew Shea in New York City decide to take up his friends challenge back from when he was in grad school
And see what some simple observation and signage could do for one building in New York
That building was Columbia University
It was the applied sciences building at the brand new building
Three sets of Swinging Doors and three sets of revolving doors
At the one end
Entry point of this bill
Andrew started by just watching the building I spent probably altogether about
2 months
Once a week
Tuesday Mornings
Some of those weeks I was there for
For twice a week 2
I watch people
In the building and counted
And he counted
For about 20 hours in a 2 month period
I just never that only
28% of people reviews
Using the revolving
So my first invention was
Is chest tube
Create a bear
Took eight and a half
Depay 11-piece
The paper I wrote for Elise
Simply
Please use revolving doors
Yeah that factoid about revolving doors exchanging 8 times less air than Swinging Doors
Very
Curly taper
It cost 50% of
People
Two then go ahead and use revolve
So that's a 30-point and Grace
It was a thirty percent
And that of course
I wanted to know how it go
Get that number even higher
May 2nd
Can sign the shape of an arrow
And this era was smaller than the first time
But then revolving-door you said actually fell five points from his previous attack
To 53%
So Andrew treatment larger and he also made it mask Columbia University's visual ID
Columbia has like a light
Blue and dark blue
Color palette and their branding
So my Hope was that The Branding would help
People
Connect with it more and
And taken more seriously
And the fact that 71% of people
End up using the revolver
As result of that
71%
That's up 43 points and where he started
Twenty Eight percent
Here at 99 piht we were curious to find out if that could happen here in the Bay Area
Turn Avery truffelman to go stick out of building in Downtown Oakland
Text Evan
Mrs. Avery in sand in the observation stage
The residual scientist part of me has to remind you here
All the data sets were talking about today are very small so I understand that
But everyone's observations are aligned
Given the choice revolving doors just
Part that popular so far and how we doing
Forever swinging 04 revolving
Birthday
Nobody is using revolving doors
And when someone has a revolving door
It was notable
Market one
Revolving door
After a half-hour they tallied up the results
Crank It Up
Tell me to 259 people use swinging doors for people use revolving door
In a 30-minute.
Okay
These are the signs designed by Andrew Shay is an arrow that says please use revolving door
The Exchange 8 times less air
None of the people using revolving doors were watching
See what happens
Batman
And uses the revolving door
Another guy
Directions
They're already
Increasing the revolving-door traffic flow
It doubled in less than 5 minutes
And after another 30 minutes
Teen99 pile the results
Winter holiday
3 2
Alright how are you
Okay so these are people who use The Swinging Doors even though the sign was on them
5 10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45
I-55
And then people who use the revolving door this time or 5:10
1520 2065
There was no sign that building
Between the hours of
1230 + 1
On Monday
Originally it was 1.5
After
Define thirty and a half percent
The people went through the revolving doors
When there's a sign pointing to them
First 1.5
Percent without the time
Now we did not try testing all the variation
So people could have interpreted the signed as intended taking in the message that revolving doors were more energy efficient
And adjusted their behavior accordingly
Or they could have just thought the swinging door was out of order
Or they could have just noticed something was out of the ordinary and it none of them into using the revolving door
Whatever happened with this much is clear
Putting up an arrow on a door makes people do things
If you want to get people to use a revolving door
That's a good place to stay
And with that salmon Avery left the lobby of that building and took down the signs
Just like Andrew Shea took down his signs at Columbia then shared his results with the powers-that-be
But nothing ever came of it
Dan Wesolowski says that MIT did eventually incorporate some of the basic concepts of his study
When they created
Sustainability stickers to place on their outer doors
Although he thought his sons were better
Another really powerful way to increase the use of revolving doors is to address the issue in the architecture itself
It turns out they're actually much more effective revolving doors
Like at the Marriott Hotel in Oakland
It's much larger is the visual focus of the entrance and it has three dividers which are actually big enough for you to
To be inside one of them with stranger
If not feel too weird about him
And they were evolve automatically
Most importantly
The doorman won't open The Swinging Doors for you
Unless I see you're already going for the
So if you can't get institutional buy in
Or get a brand-new gigantic revolving door
Andrew Shea has a revolving door action kit that you can download for free
Take to your local office built
Scotch tape not included
BYU OST
FYI
Ymmv
Icymi
BRB
OMG
99% invisible with priests this week by Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in Tampa
American Institute
YouTube architects
San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
I can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com