99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
After the revolution in Cuba the young Fidel Castro hired an official photographer by the name of Alberto Cortez
Chronicle is New Life as a national leader
Cuda followed Castro and Che Guevara taking pictures of them as they met world leaders
Went fishing
Faced off in chess
He even took that iconic image of Che
The one that's on millions of t-shirt
That's comrade troubleman
My favourite images
That chord A captured
I have Che and Fidel playing golf
It was January 3rd 1961 two years after the revolution
When she suggested they go player
You know figure out what you know I don't play golf and Shay did play golf he's actually
Pretty good and he that keep it a caddy back in Chile
Helping us tell this story is
John Loomis
I'm John Lewis Simon architect and Architectural historian
To Che and Fidel drove out to what was the ritziest most elite Country Club in Havana
All of the members of the club they're practically have all left.
But still hear this amazing place the people who work here are still keeping everything clean and neat and taking care of it
And Che and Fidel romp around the bucolic Greenacres
In full military khaki in combat boots
Chase still wearing that beret
Golf club before putting around and grinning while Alberto Cortez snap publicity
And you know you look at the photographs and they're like Schoolboy just having fun and this was a lark and everybody
Buddy thought this was
You know a real a real hoot
And the photos are actually beautiful
Because Cortez an incredible photographer
Also because the lens
There's a river running through all these gently undulating perfectly manicured Hills
Where to buy this
Thick Lush Forest
Kind of magic
Che and Fidel were captivated by this place
And they looked around and wonder
What should we do with this I know to the wonderful resource
It wasn't going to say a golf course that was for sure
And some say it was Fidel's idea other say it was Chase
But one of them turn to the other end
Playing his vision
The property
There they would build
In art school
An International School
For the Arts
That would draw students from all over the third world and bring them in Cuba and give them a n
First class
Art education and all the artist
A free of charge and a beautiful vision for a beautiful landscape
Required
A beautiful building
Che and Fidel decided they wanted to build the most
Gorgeous art schools in the world
Something sitting with the newness
Statement of the
Restrepo
Castro was recommended the young Cuban architect Ricardo porro and he knew that Ricardo was
Very very much supported the revolution had risked his own life
Arrowhead never
Pick up a gun
And in addition to his commitment to the revolution
He was also really Talent
So he seemed like
The obvious person
Throw was told that if he wanted to design the schools he would have to do it almost immediately
Did you have to
In the projects
In 2 months to begin because
Structure message message
This is footage of Ricardo porro in 2004
Porto passed away in 2014
Or I was told that's it two months for the designs
You take it or you leave it
And I remember a sizable
Ricardo what do you send me sister
You're not going to take you know
You say I take it I take it
Naviance School wasn't just one school
It was imagined as an entire campus
Five separate schools for five distinct disciplines
Ballet modern dance
Visual Arts
Music
And theater
Ricardo Pereira was going to need some
He recruited to architect
Italian
Victoria Gotti and Roberto guitar
Oh and in addition to the time for lunch
There was the Embargo
Already with the Embargo importing concrete and rebar was
Very
They had to use what they had
The 3 Architects decided to build with
Locally-made brick
And terracotta tiles
And with these tiles they decided to make schools comprised of Catalan vault
McAllen bald is essentially a dome made of layer tile
And it's called the Catalan Vault because it's
Predominantly used in Catalonia
Especially Barcelona
It was adopted pratiksha
By Gaudi to do these very organic
Forms and so with the unifying element of brick and unified style of Catalan vault
The 3 Architects viento erected their separate designs around the edges of the golf course
Okay I'm going to throw journalistic impartiality to the wind here
These buildings are
So
Beautiful
Each uses the vault in a completely different way
And they all roll over the landscape of a golf course
And mixed with a
Plants in the palm trees
Winding Thunderman Furlan titties
Plazas and courtyards
And the curving rooftops with all those vaults make them look
Alive
Dancing
Every school has a clerestory to
What does very intentional symbolize
But poro School of Visual Art was the most literal imagine the School of Visual Arts or they called it
School of plastic Arts
As a building that would nurture art and artists and helped give rise to a uniquely post-revolution Cube
Ben aesthetic
The school was going to give birth
So I try to make the school
Plastic art
Has the image of a goddess of fertility
So I put a lot
Of breast
Indicated in the domes
No really the Volta Jones have these nipples on them
And there was a special fountain in the main Piazza
Linda Piazza I place a sculpture ideas
Just like a fruit called papaya
Chuba
Assist
Sexual feminine connotation
Some higher-ups found this pretty scandalous
I was told to turn the water in the fountain off
Yes you have. Brass and here you have the papaya which is a metaphor for
But everybody knows them
The Caribbean
But I think that it's wrong to overemphasize that
Because really
John Loomis says that the school is a commentary
Incubus past
And Future
As you're walking down those curved passageways
You can't see where you've been and you can't see where you're going
I'm in way that was a metaphor for this new chapter in Cuba you know this is a new
Adventure
This new Revolution
The Revolutionary Spirit was the driving force of the design and the canoe
Construction
Decathlon Vault required a lot of Labor
So there's this massive crew of young Cuban workers on the golf course
Making me structure
Goldwork is felt a real buying because they felt that they were building the school that their children could potentially go to
But previously they have no hope
Liquor children would go to University Art to an art school
And this endeavor was so exciting but the school is basically opened while they were still being built
At some point when construction began that they said well let's just use the space
The country club was already there with its meeting rooms and ballrooms
Of course they had those manicured grounds and the beautiful weather
Ballerinas pirouette on the putting green
Interceptor canvases in the shade
Practiced in the forest
And students brought water and drinks and food for the construction workers
And play drums to keep their spirits up
It was as beautiful joyous Undertaker
Except when it was
During that time
And still today it's difficult to talk about
The negative
Aspects of
The revolution
So people really focused on
The joyous part and the optimism
You know cuz that's what he hold on to
Weight when you're in this land of paradox
Alyssa nahmias co-produced
The documentary about the Cuban Arts
In Cuba
At the same time for example as artists were
Having drum parties to finish
The the buildings
Well the Masons were working and it was very beautiful and fun and joyous there were other students who were
Sent to labor camps
Because they were homosexual
Or religious
Or in other ways anti-revolutionary
Even before this agricultural labor camp
UPS opened in 1960
C5
The anti-revolutionary students were
Expelled from the art school
Ricardo porro continue to give them classes in his home
Broken feel that the values of the Revolution we're shifting as he says in the documentary
I used to tell
The other actor
Don't lose
Your time
Making small details
Try to do
Sings
Flask
Because perhaps one day it's going to be
After the Missile Crisis after the Bay of Pigs military defense was given a much higher priority than say
Creating the most beautiful art schools in the world
So there was the money issue
But also generally
Cuba was starting to imitate the Soviet Union in more and more ways
I made it very individual architecture and they wanted Soviet architecture
Blocky functional uniform one-size-fits-all
Completely the opposite
Of the sensuous organic malts and curves
Of the arts schools
There was an idea that
The designs for the Cuban national art schools were
Extravagant for
A socialist Revolution
That had to tighten its belt
And what are the earliest proponents of that argument was Roberto secretary
Roberto segret was the architecture critic
Like really he was the only one
He had tremendous influence
Cigarette was not a fan of the breasts and the papaya fountain
I segway himself says in the film
I like the connection
These days cigarette admits that he was a bit harsh
Now segree will say that
He really didn't want to write those things
But he was
Under constraints
My people higher up
Mostly Antonio King
Antonio Quintana was the last of a generation of established
Cuban architect
All his contemporaries had fled During the Revolution and this left Quintana at the top of his field by default
He wanted it to
Stay that way
Quintana clearly had a
Personal
Desire not to
See Ricardo plural
Drivers Market
Cuba architecture Quintana and the critic Roberto Sekirei helped
Turn favored against the schools
Workers were slowly reduce the amount of workers portals buildings were far enough finished so they were really
Able to be brought
To the finish line or very very very
Close but the schools designed by the other two architects were not so lucky
The theater school was only 30% complete
The music school was also in finished but had a few usable room
The most unfinished
Was the ballet school
Which didn't have floorboard
Glass in the windows
All the materials were there and it could have been finished in like 15 days and the lead of the Cuban ballet
Alicia Alonso is a very famous Cuban ballerina
She visited the site I don't like it no more
And that was that
The Cuban ballet opted for a much more centrally-located Studio
And in July of 1965
The schools were just
Declared finish
In all their varying states of completion
They had an opening
Declared them open and they were used in the state that they were
Even the unfinished ballet school was used very briefly as a Russian circus School
The Architects were scattered to different jobs within the ministry of construction
Ricardo porro
Started working directly under Antonio Quintana
That last of the Old Guard Arkansas
Corazon Amazon
Quintana
Gave him very demeaning jobs he gave him the job to design a cage
Pretty girl
In the zoo
Oh my God
I couldn't work anymore in my architectural I have got to do all four fingers they wear doing
And I decided to leave
In 1966 parole left Cuba and move to Paris
And as for the schools themselves
The crazy thing is that they never close
Even during some horrible spells in Cuba's history
When entire family is where
Squatting in the rundown parts of the school
And ransacking them for materials
Classes have always
Continued well except for the ballet school where the classes that require started
But the other four arts schools continue to be among the finest in the world
Although they are not as big as they were meant to be
And they're pretty run down and some parts
If Bloods like the first time I went there
There was a guy playing drums but I think there was like a foot of water
In the building
Today the schools are known as is
A
Isa you saw what it's called now
The
Instituto Superior de Arte
So now I'm going to come yell at us
Especially
On the dead rain nobody's going to come
The schools with students have guard course but Philippe Dells itis showed Avery the abandoned ballet school
How many times I haven't seen any security guard
WeChat
Now that is a graffiti and things happening
There.
Columbia
Sometimes you one day security
To be there
Felipe is a multimedia artist who once studied at the theaters
Back Down The Unfinished ballet school was a mysterious ruin
Graco swing is totally here
K&D 80s
The whole thing here with a jungle
Students would go there and party and stuff
It was a great play
Kaboom
He didn't know the story of the buildings
No one really dead
The story of this is Boudoir session how I get taboo
Spokane never discuss
What's the weather like
Secrecion
But then John Loomis
Who we've been talking to throughout this episode
Published his book about
The school's called revolution of form
Revolution of forms came out in
March of 1999
And through revolution of forms
Philippe finally learn the story of this
Place where he at
Studied for five years
This Israeli
Changsha
Taking care of weave
This is what something that was done with a lot of love
And with a lot of care
Something that only belongs with you while you're not alone 2
Human
Culture culture
I believe I wasn't the only person inspired by lumos
Eva funeral
Escuela Superior
That is Fidel Castro in 1999 saying
This school will get done
This National Art School that we imagined will get built
Okay we can't say that John Loomis single-handedly convinced Fidel Castro to take action on the art schools
But the Year Revolution of forms came out Fidel Castro publicly committed to restoring them
All 3 Architects reunited and Havana and met with high-level government officials to plan the restoration
But this project was abandoned in the wake of the financial crisis in 2000
For now the schools remain and various States
Completion
But even in the current disrepair
Architecture speaks
This View
Who is
Goosebumps
Telugu song
The schools of Isa don't look like any other buildings in the world
They are Cuban
They are the product victim and symbol
Of a revolution
To really understand the Majesty of these schools including some fascinating parts of the story that just don't translate to radio
Watch the beautiful documentary unfinished Spaces by Alyssa nahmias and Ben Murray it's rentable on iTunes
Find out all about it
An unfinished spaces.com you've also been listening to the film soundtrack throughout this episode which was composed by Giancarlo Valle
Gokano
Chords to John Loomis author of revolution of forms
Of being an employee of the CIA and writing this book to embarrass Cuba
I don't think it is
Scuba I hope not
Along with Jacob Reams Jill homburg Albert Lopez and Charles koppelman
I am the producer and librettist of cabanaconde
New Cuban Opera
The Opera about the given on schools just premiered at the Art School
As far as we know the last
For Cuban offer written in Cuba and performed in Cuba was over
2 years ago
It sounds like that
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
The East Bay's Premier architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife isn't another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Show the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and then we discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
And keep up with all the comings and goings of 99% invisible on Twitter or Facebook Tumblr Instagram and Spotify
And you can always catch up with us at our place. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com