99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
Hey
I'm Roman Mars
I'm going to graduate school in Athens Georgia which is a great place to be from the 80s
Have about
18 to 25
If you like going out to bars
And listening to live music
You know Athens is a fairly small college town
It's hot
Huge an important music scene for decades
In the most famous band to come out of the Athens scene
Undoubtably
Was REM
Be provocative right from the start I'm going to say that REM out of time
Is the most politically important album in the history of the United
Is reporter Whitney Jones
Do I have to say
I don't think at a time is even the most important album in the history of REM
Actually my argument here has nothing to do with the music
This isn't one of those oh it's a soundtrack to a generation or anything like that
Out of time made such a huge impact because of its
Packaging
The box out of time originally came in led to a bill being passed in Congress
An actual concrete law
Let's go back to 1985
The pop charts were full of Prince
Sheena Easton
And the Youth of America
Or being corrupted
Tipper Gore in a few other Elite women of Washington form of the parents music Resource Center
Where the pmrc for short
They put pressure on the creators and Distributors of quote on quote
Objectionable music
Musicians and labels called the censorship
There were Senate hearings about this
And eventually those little black and white Parental Advisory sticker started appearing on albums
This set off a wave of sensors
Step across the country
In 1990 a federal district judge in South Florida ruled that the rap group 2 Live Crew album
As nasty as they wanna be
Was so obscene that it couldn't be sold or performed within his jurisdiction
3 days after the ruling 2 Live Crew played a show in Broward County Florida
And after the show two members of the group got arrest
And it was a live performance
That they found obscene with you know girls doing what would be
Like what
Twerking I think it would be a very early version of the
Twerking
Jeff ayeroff wasn't there he saw it on TV and I just it was just
So offensive
Jeff was an executive at Virgin Records
And to be clear he wasn't offended by the raunchy lyrics or
The twerking
He was offended by the arrest
And a blatant censorship of the artist work
Just spend the next couple days mulling this over and then he had a revelation
One of the reasons why
Politicians get away with things
Because there isn't an anti constituent
There was never anything to lose by
Baiting
Rock and roll because there was this
Canard that young people didn't vote
And you know within the next two days the idea came to me like fully formed in some way
And I came up with the
This damn Rock the vote
Progesterone
The idea behind rock the boat was simple
Get young people to vote for politicians who wouldn't censor music
That was that simple it was the idea of you put
Kids in the game
The game becomes differ
Politicians can no longer scapegoat music they can't keep
Keep using us as a
Excuse
Jeffy Rap God about 60 people together in a Los Angeles hotel to talk about launching Rock the Boat
Frank Zappa was there
Past and present California Governor Jerry Brown was there
As we're a bunch of other record exec
So there we are
Part of this
Virtuous circle of record executives
Who have spent a lot of their career being criticized for destroying the Youth of America and it was sort of like an affair
Very altruistic way
I think we could do something positive we can get kids to vote we can
It's cool also in attendance was Jeff's friend
Also record label executive
Also named Jeff
Jeff gold
He was working for Warner Brothers
And one of his major project of the time
Was trying to figure out
How to package CDs
Compact disc packaging was the Hot Topic in the record world in the late eighties and early nineties
CDs have been around for a few years at this point
But record stores still didn't have a good way to display them
Here's Jeff gold
When
CDs first came out on the market
Record retailers
Were kind of angry about
Got them because their stores were formatted
To display
12 and 1/2 inch for 12 and 1/4 inch squares album
In other words they didn't have any stands or display cases for these new CDs
So somebody in the record industry said look
If you put a CD jewel case inside of a cardboard box that's as long as a vinyl album
And only half as wide
You can fit
Two of these longbox CDs side-by-side in an LP rack
Problem solved
Retailer set flying perfect
So millions of these things out of nowhere started getting made
Record people loved the long box
They thought it was the future
A head honcho at am I wrote this opinion piece in billboard magazine in 1989 entitled why we should
Keep the CD longbox
Your rights quote
I want to see the music industry continue to thrive and prosper as one of the cornerstones of entertainment
And I think making full use of the 6 by 12 CD carton is one way to help us do just that
But not everyone
Artist
I said wait a minute
We don't want you cutting down millions of
Trees
To put
Are CD's in
And then having people throw these things away it's
Incredibly wasteful
And bad things
Because the thing about the longbox
Is that it was never meant to be collected
Had the feel of a big Mike and Ike
When you bought a CD in a longbox
You open it up
It take out the
The jewel case which had the actual CD in the album art in it
And you toss a long
There's no reason to keep it around
So Re Mi record coming out
In 1990
And they're saying
To me and to Warner Brothers there's no way our record
Long box
We're sensitive to the environment
This is a ridiculous thing forget it
And where better sales Park
Singing absolutely
Ask about a long box
Or record retailers
And that's when Jeff gold got this idea
He could merge the two projects He was working on
They could use the CD longbox to advance The Rock the vote camp
But first he needed a concrete political, so connected
And Jeff are all fat found just the thing
We were sitting there looking for a raise on death row to get us
Send a political situation
I'm reading this week
The time and there's this column article
About the Motor Voter bill
We just said
We're going to help these people from the Motor Voter bill
This was going to be our first thing we're going to do but so there's this Motor Voter bill that's been bouncing around Congress since the 1970s
If past
It also allowed you to register by mail or when you apply for social services like welfare or unemployment
Basically making it easier for lots of people
Including Rock living young people
The register to vote
By 91 a few States had already adopted it
But Congress has never been able to get it passed nationally
Jeff gold went to a political event in Hollywood about the Motor Voter bill
And one of the speakers was Columbia sociologist and political activist
Richard cloward
He said that writing to elected officials could help sway them on the issue
After clouds talk Jeff gold went up and spoke with
What happened I started
What amount of letters would a senator of Congress
Richmond take note of
650 200
That would really have an empath
Really that
Few
You said yeah that people don't write so
Getting 150-200 letters
About an issue would would definitely make them sit up in
Take notice
That weekend Jeff gold was riding his bike around Santa Monica
Can I have this moment where
It rushed into my mind this fully formed idea that
We could
Take care of REM
By turning their long box into a positive
If we put a petition on the back of the long box
That would go to Rock the vote saying I support the Motor Voter bill
And we could distribute it to
Their respective senators
And I knew
We could generate an unbelievable amount of mail.
Jeff gold got on the phone with Jeff Tara
And they agreed that this would be the strategy
They would turn the album long box into a piece of political machinery
And they would flood congress with support for the Motor Voter bill
That Monday Jeff called Ariana's manager with the plan
It's alright Lily call the guys
I'll call you back
I probably heard back from him
Within an hour
Bernie said great idea they're totally into it let's do it
So out of time hit the record stores on March 12th 1991
And then the petition started rolling in
Can I remember vividly
Beef for 5 days
After the record come out
I mean a very short period of time
And they had bags
It was really incredible
Nobody can seem to put their hand on what the exact number of
That we got of these were but I remember thinking
Well after 3 weeks we buy 10,000 I mean that's that's
Already half of what Richard cloward said would make an impact
And he sings just kept coming in and drove their canvas bags full of them coming in
About a month after REM release the album Rock the vote political director plus two members of the hip hop group KMD
Will the shopping cart full of these first ten thousand petitions into a senate hearing
And they just left them there for senators window Ford
And a very young looking Mitch McConnell
It may have 1992 after thousands of petitions and
Senate testimony
The Motor Voter bill passed
Congress
But then president HW Bush vetoed
This was in July right in the middle of Bush's re-election campaign
Bush's opponent Bill Clinton took up Motor Voter as a talking point
Bashing Bush over here
Is Vito
And the rest is basically history
Clinton wins 92
The bill comes back before the house is actually the second bill that the house takes up in January of 93
Motor Voter passed the house and passes the Senate
And then Bill Clinton signed it into law
As the national voter registration Act
At the White House earlier today President Bill Clinton signed into law
The voter registration Act
Commonly referred to as the Motor Voter bill
Can we get invited to the White House
For the signing set
Totally surreal scene
His wife are there and I'm there
With my wife
All the people
Clinton at the signing talks about how Rock the vote really help to make the difference
To get this built
As I said I have
Long supported the idea of
Motor Voter
More than a year ago I promised
Does president
But I would sign hr2 and fight for its Passage
I'm pleased to be able to keep the promise today
That I made on this rock
The vote card would still has my signature
Back in New Hampshire
Shaking his hands after the bill-signing we are gonna fight ourselves Rockville you said you guys got this past
It was really one of the most surreal
Moments of my life
I want to stop a Minit in point out just how bizarre this scene is
Remember Rock the vote had formed an open protest against the censorship group that was started by the new Vice
President's wife
Tipper Gore
You know those little black and white parental advisory stickers those were nickname
Tipper Gore's husband was now praising Rock the vote
And it's a tribute to one group whose voice and organization was apps
Absolutely unprecedented
America's young people
They Rock the Boat
I got this time
Sew-in Jeff gold says
Was really one of the most
Surreal
Moments of my life
Yeah I think so real is probably the right word
What's interesting here is that this campaign
Really could have only happened during a very brief period of time
Because before Clinton that even signed the Motor Voter bill
Jeff gold at actually found a way to kill off the long box for good
He hatched a plan and he went to talk about it with the Chief Financial Officer at Warner Brothers
Murrieta
It's Mari how many of these things do we make a year
I don't know 90 million between the
Something like that
Niacin how much do they cost
$0.25
I said Okay so
You talking about
20 to 25 million dollars a year were music
Expense on lombok
He said yeah
I said so what if we stopped making long box
And we took that 25 million dollars and gave it in the form of rebates
Trek retailers
Just to pay for them to reconfigure
There been
And we did it as a one-time
Yo Discounters payment
And they got all the money we saved for the first year
And then
For the rest of time
We're saving 25 million dollars
A jackal tell that the other Warner Brothers Executives liked his idea
They took it to the distributor
Distributor went for it
And that was the end of the long box
Some stores got new racks to accommodate the long box for Jewel cases
Others held onto their 12 inch bins
Started putting CDs inside of these reusable plastic
The cartridges
And record companies have been profitable and solvent ever since
So long boxes
The Motor Voter bill
Which after it passed became the national voter registration Act of 1993
That's still very much a thing
Between 1995 when the law went into effect in 2012
The percentage of the voting age population that is registered to vote went up more than 10 points
From 69.5%
279.9
And in that same time span more than a hundred and fifty million voter registrations have been filled out at the DMV
That doesn't even include mailing registrations or registrations through Social Services
As for what's the law also
So I think that proves it know album is as important to politics in the US
As REM out of time
But we lie their most important album important of other things that actually really matter
Is murmur
Musically of course it's not their best album automatic for the people their best musical album
What how old are you
I'm 30
You're a child
You don't know anything
Murmur
We could go
It is 2 years after I recorded that it might stands has softened a little bit
I will also accept
Life's Rich pageant
Has the best REM
I swear counted as REM
Second
If you're fat
The reason I'm presenting the story again is that is nearly time to vote and I think that this election represents the most
Important we've ever had
Currently over 40% of the voting age population does not vote
And this is a
Tragedy
That 40% and set the entire agenda for the whole country
And they don't
Some are systematically disenfranchised
And that is disgusting
The mini just don't vote for reasons that are mystery
Voting should not be viewed as an obligation
It is a joy
It makes you feel good
It's an event you bring the kids to
Get information on how to register to vote
I going to vote
Usa.gov
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Whitney Jones was Sam Greenspan Katie minka-lavery trouble
Pirkle stats reviews
Turn master
Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall and me Roman Mars
Whitney Jones at the co-hosts of the show pitch
Which is an audible original program about music
Whitney is on Twitter at Whitney A Jones you can find out about
Pitch on the web
Package podcast. Org
We are project at 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced on radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
While we're on the subject of podcast and Civic
I'm very proud to announce that my new favorite podcast The West Wing weekly
Is now a member
Radiotopia
It's hosted by our own rishikesh her way from song Exploder and Joshua Molina from
Sports night
And what's wing and
Currently on
Scandal if you haven't heard it
Westwingweekly goes Way Beyond recapping episodes in talking about the West Wing they take issues covered in the television episodes like
Gun control for veteran's health
And explore them in our current political landscape
Discussions interview segments
What's it's really cool to hear Richie actually talk he has great chemistry
Tree with Josh
The show is already formed
Passionate and engaged community in a few short weeks really makes me happy
Aaron Sorkin himself the creator of The West Wing
Most recent
Fantastic
Find The West Wing weekly in all the shows in radiotopia
15 strong
Ed radiotopia
You find the show and join the discussion about the show on Facebook you can treated me at Roman Mar to the show at 99 p.m.
Ronnie Instagram
Tumblr 2
The Nexus of all things 99 Pi is at 99.
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com