99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Every game from rock-paper-scissors
I like to think of game design as a design discipline that is sort of shoulder-to-shoulder with other design
Find Fields like graphic design
Where architecture
Or industrial design
This is Eric Zimmerman
I work at the NYU Game Center
I'm actually a professor
Game design
If you can believe that
The raw materials that game designers work with
What game designers do
In essence is
Create the rules of the game
But when players enter into the system of the game
And decide to
Follow the rules what results is play
And play as the opposite of rules
Rules are fixed and rigid
And logical
Play is improvisational
And creative and spontaneous
And that's such an amazing
Weird little Paradox of games
The goal of good game design is what Eric calls
Meaningful play and it's sort of a shorthand for
Making sure that
You're taking care of your players
Ensuring that players stay engaged and their actions have consequences
Oh that makes sense
That's Blake asking
He makes the observatory podcast
Casper design Observer
But there's one game it's a really popular one and when I play it I don't feel taken care of as a player
I feel bored I feel trapped
I feel like it's never going to end
Mengapa
I've got the money you got the money I got the money you got some money
You are race car for a hat
Iron on Scottie dog
You're circling around and around the board
Passing go
Costing $200
Buying property
Having to pay when you land on someone else's property
Building houses
How's it go again
Circling
Again
No
That's usually the critique of an APA
That it's very very slow
And long
And
It ends up being this very gradual slog where one-player gradually survive
As the others as you know everyone is Bleed It Out for money from each other
Exact
Curious Louis CK
Talking about playing the game with his
The monopoly laws
Dark
Is heavy
I got to look at her little
Okay
All your property
Everything you have
The railroads
Your houses
All your money
That's mine
Monopoly can be slow
The losses
Best Louis CK
Can be dark
And yet
The game is incredibly popular
It breaks all of these
Classic
Rules
A good design
But in very interesting ways
When Monopoly was created
It wasn't supposed to teach children to be ruthless capitalist
In fact
It was just the
It became
The embodiment of everything
That it originally set out to critique
And I think that's
Maybe part of the fascination of Monopoly may be buried
Inside
This capitalist fantasy are somehow this seeds
Of its
Opposite
Hidden there somewhere
Within the design
The game we call Monopoly goes back to the Gilded Age
The time of great prosperity in America
At least for the carnegies in the rock
Rockefellers
The rest of the country
Was not doing so well
Income inequality was growing
An economist named Henry George
Thought he had a solution
Henry George proposed a single tax Theory which would completely up and the American capitalist system
Dumb as we know it land ownership would be abolished
Instead all land would be public property individual
Tax in this industry would create an economy where wealth is distributed more fairly
The theory is much more complicated than that but that's all you going to get from me
Planet Money yourself
The single tax Theory gain a lot of
Followers
Including one woman
Name Lizzie McGee
Lizzie McGuire
A woman
Who
I consider you very before
That's Mary Palin
Author of The monopolist
Obsession Fury
And the Scandal behind the world's favorite board game
The story that starts with Lizzie McGuire
Willie McGee decided to spread the word about single tax Theory
In 1904 she patented a board game that she called
The landlord's game
Landlords at the time are considered to be bad people
He took a white square board labeled one corner go to jail another one she labeled public park
The rest of it was rammed with rectangular spaces that players can rent
4 by
No colors no graphics
Just black rectangles and writing on a whiteboard
Players roll dice and circled the board buying up properties and railroads collecting money and paying rent
Players who ran out of money were sent
The Pour House
Players who trespass on land
Were sent to jail
And she created to rule
Monopolist
Real fat
And then
Botox ruleset if you played with a single tax rules when one player develops property everyone benefit
But in the monopolist rules the goal was to create monopolies and crushing
The Hope was you play with both sets of rules
See the differences
And come away totally sold on the single tax Theory
The morphe eye slay
Clearly has taken off IRA
Of course everyone preferred the monopolist ruleset
Because in a board game
Evil
Is fun
And the landlord's game at a greater capacity for evil than most board games at the time
If you look at games that are like late very end of 19th century early 20th century games
There's not a lot of depth
They're mostly games where you're just kind of moving characters along a track rolling a die
And
I think in that context
The landlord's game
Probably stuck out if something really interesting we're different and innovative
The landlord's game made its way around the Northeast
College campuses and activist circles
Folk variations organically popped up in different cities and properties on the board would be named after real streets in
Locations and around the time of the depression a man named Charles Darrow stumbled upon a version of the landlord's game it was
Made in a Quaker community in Atlantic City New Jersey
Future locations like Marvin Gardens and Vermont Avenue and the boardwalk
Daryl basically now the Quaker version not the landlord's game and started to tweak it into a board game that he would sell
Tell himself
He called it
Monopoly
Gyro
My reporting has yielded that he was in fact unemployed at the time
He was in fact living in
And this game made him enormously successful
Daryl made one game a day by hand he sold them out of his home for $4 a piece
Do use bright cheap paint
Any misspelled a few of the locations in Atlantic City
And yes
He totally stole
The concept
The look of Gerald's Game was pretty much the landlord's game but Darrow improve the graphics and added some color
Does it kind of graphic
Clarity to Monopoly that's really satisfying
And the game started selling like hot
Maybe because it was really fun to handle all of that fake money
Especially during the Depression
And then Monopoly attracts the attention of a family-owned company called
Parker brother
They buy the Darrow game
Amanda buys leftover stock
It seems affirm
On the brink of Destruction
But Parker Brothers wasn't pleased when they learned adero had not actually invented Monopoly
So they start to stamp out all the different versions of Lizzie maggie's game
And finally they buy her patently McGee as best as we know about $500
Recruiting
You know the landlord's game which is
I consider
Foundation of Monopoly
Monopoly then becomes the sole property of Parker Brothers and four years Parker Brothers perpetuates the myth that.
Cheryl just invented the game out of whole cloth
Monopoly made a lot of money for Parker Brothers
Eventually got acquired by Hasbro and of course today Monopoly is everywhere there are hundreds of variations on the
International competitions
That McDonald's promotion
And all kinds of shirts and mugs and neckties printed with Monopoly graphics
But just because people buy it
Doesn't mean
They play at
I think the people by Monopoly not necessarily to play to the Gris game of because
It's Monopoly
Something you have in your closet
Something you should have to me monopoli feels like
A cheesy
Christmas album like you know Bing Crosby or something where
It's not something that you would normally listen to but it's kind of something that you might drag out in an ironic way
Way or in a nostalgic way
Feeds itself
Then you have
Parents with kids
That are getting nostalgic about the games that they played
And they want to introduce those games to their children and play them again
In other words monopolies and popular because it's a great game
It's only popular now because it was popular then
And we don't even play by the real rules
Will nobody plays right
To begin with
How many people died
Really rad the ruleset that
For example the way most people play if you land on an available property that you don't want to buy or can't afford
Nothing to happen
Spend that is technically wrong
According the directions if you land on an available property that you don't want or can't afford
It gets auctioned off
This could make the game way more exciting
Though not necessarily fast
You can imagine every turn it's not like a quick decision do I buy this or not it's like
Let's start an option
What do you think
But let's auction this and who's going to be at higher in
So it drives out the game
But Eric is reluctant to accuse anyone of playing Monopoly wrong
The way we play Monopoly
Even all the cheating that happens Monopoly is notoriously people cheating and hiding money and
Taking money from the bank and
And things like that that I mean that is Monopoly right Monopoly is not just a set of
Monopoly is
All of the cultural meaning
And all the ways that we play it
And all of the ways that we that we use and misuse the game
And this is why some game designers defend Monopoly
The game designer Richard Garfield
He's a brilliant game designer he invented
Collectible card games with magic the Gathering
I've heard him defend Monopoly
And say
There's some things about monopolies
They're actually kind of interesting convention and
Came back
And my son told me that he has played Monopoly for the first time
That's the legend himself
Richard Garfield
That's great
How many times
You playing
You look amazing
You don't win monopoly you just playing
They're not as much about the rank of the end
If you're having fun
During the process of play
A lot of kids at the game
So for kids
Meaningful play in Monopoly comes when the game is treated less like playing chess and more like play
Clean house
Collecting properties a good thing getting money is a good thing being the Scottie dogs a good thing
And not going to jail is a good thing
But there's not necessarily
To it always trust
You're following rules making decisions and accumulating
Prometheus was a
Total revelation
I think there may be something to that but I have to say
I played Monopoly for the first time with my boys recently and they were
Totally in It to Win It
Carver Crush.
And when we went bankrupt
He would continue to give us a little bit some money
Just so we would stay in the game and he could crush us all over again
He was exactly the kind of capitalists that lives in Magee was trying to warn us about
And he loved it
My favorite part of Monopoly is
Taking money from my brother my name is
Staybridge Hotel
I really like annoying my brother
99% invisible with produced this week by Blake Askin and Avery trufelman as the Ironwood say
Greenspan as the Hat
When was Morgan Dewey as my favorite the race car
Eric Zimmerman co-wrote a handbook on game design called rules of play
In it he and Katie sale until you pretty much everything you need to design a good game and you can easily
You take those tools to design a good anything
Special thanks this week to Emily Kwong and Desi Fuchs met for back
Sophie Belkin sessler and everyone at the NYU Game Center
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced by the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and annuity
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Hawaii and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
Find the show and like to show
All of us
Instagram
Pictures at Lake
To all the episodes of
You must go
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com