99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
A few months before the end of the world
Paul Monaco posted this message on YouTube
Hello hello everyone
Call Monaco here
Buddha Paul
Know me as
Probably all heard the news
Online closing down
The world that was ending was called The Sims Online
It was online version of one of the most popular computer games ever met a wonderful
Help me through a hard time in my life when I first got online
But ironically the online version of the sentence with not very popular
Banded up losing tons of subscribers and changing the name to EA land
And then they finally
Pull the clock
Thank you and please try to stay in touch
SmackDown
Whatever you choose to do and move on to
As you can probably hear
Jalen is not a normal video game
There are no monsters no killing
And although it had some competitive element for many players competition wasn't the point at all
Unlike a lot of other games where you might be
Shooting people
Slaying dragons or something this is a game about socializing
That's Robert Ashley and Robert Ashley
Very long Hiatus and the creator of a life well wasted a life well wasted it's about
Video games in the people who love them
Any aliens a video game that a dedicated few absolutely love
The crowded attracted I think we're p
Where to get together
And searched at me
Meet strangers
It was a nice place
Over time it became
A kind of intimate
Almost bar like the cheers of video games where everyone knows your name and at the moment that Paul Mana
Maaco AKA Buddha Paul found ETA land it was exactly what I needed most
My wife's son
A long-term illness from a blood transfusion she had hepatitis C
3 years of silver life we're pretty
Yeah pretty much a challenge for a while for both of us
And after she passed away
I had absolutely no
Function of the new wake up go to work and go to sleep again
With with her illness I
Didn't get out and socialize much we know we weren't able to you know go out to the bars and meet up with friends
Have dinner
I totally be socialized myself
And this game was kind of a way for me to just can't get back into into living you
It was pretty amazing
And Paul began to live for Yale and 4 hours an hour
Really good but his friends were real friends and Virtual Worlds
Do have an upside your erase your call Eagle Imaging all that can be totally
Truly
Judged on who you really are and how you present yourself
There's no no prejudices no preconceived
Anythink
If you really taken at face value people could really like break loosen and be themselves and have some fun
But Paul is Utopia didn't last because he alien started hemorrhaging money
The writing was on the wall the server was about to go dark in this event this virtual apocalypse
My only exist in the memory of the players
Is it work
Dr. Henry lowood
I just stumbled across this and this
Project pie
Henry lowood who is this
Archival researcher at Stanford
Header project
Called how they got game which is on the history of digital games and simulations
Saving video games for
Generation
50 a hundred two hundred years from now are we going to say that history and I like
We got to save the video game
So doctor lowood his colleagues preserve what happens inside video games
Mount for a single player game like Pac-Man for example
This is easy
You effectively take out the Atari cartridge and put it on the Shelf
But saving multiplayer online games is not so simple saving the software alone is kind of a baronet
If you save the code for you and turn it on a hundred years from now
You enter a world and nothing would be there
All the things that Paul Monaco and his friends love
Would be impossible to find
You need to
Document what people are doing in these faces
That situation is much more like what a historian on archivist would do when faced with the problem of
Documenting the real world
Hello would caught wind of Yale and shutting down
He had the opportunity to record something I story in our calendar
With dye to witness firsthand in the real world
To see what it would be like
When an online world
Came to an end
What happens when a virtual world close at the end of a culture what is it like to be there at the last minute.
When it shuts down
To the tape is rolling in the last few hours the alien are being recorded
And the most dedicated DieHard users are there exchanging virtual hugs and reminiscing
The players are typing messages that appear like
Comic book word bubbles
You hear all these avatars crying
Can you also hear all the Coos and moans and then gibberish language of the game known as simlish
And you know they said they sound like they're going to be bombed and
And everything but it's not like a big pity party but then
Toward the end of the night
There's this radio station that you can listen to you in the game called Charmed radio
And they had
This DJ there
Names
Spike he is assertive
The only voice that you and appearing at the end of the world
And as soon as he starts talking
You understand what is being lost
Hey guys the last time you going to have me speak quote
The last time before TSI goes down
I just want to thank you it's been an amazing experience it ready has and
My WhatsApp account
Stress enough how much you guys have been to me over the past
How many years has been
3 has been awesome
Some people don't get attached to things
But not when you make fake friends
Rihanna
Subway
Can you play the last song is Sarah Brightman and Andrea Bocelli
Time to Say Goodbye
Hopefully you guys relax and got to my Yahoo ID
1 2 3 4 5
Py
You looking like everybody and
Best wishes
I love you all and that's been great knowing you
Play KGO 810.
Rich's Automotive
If you have another drink this proposed a toast to power that has been absolutely amazing
Cars that make you look like you
To get this feeling like
Like being on that
Deck of the Titanic
Anyone who actually stayed to the end
Very much invested in the game on an emotional level
When they pulled the plug on the server
Bits and pieces of the world started disappearing
Environment begin to the center brain
The texture on the trees flickered
All the people froze
In blank. Of existence
The actual ending was was
You're not with a bang but with a whimper and the last thing that they saw was basically just
Json error message
Server disconnect
And then
World ended
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Katie Mingle
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in
Architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
I produces story a long time ago for a radio show called snap judgment also from Oakland California
I was there first senior producer many many years ago and of all the people and places I've worked for in radio
It is the credit for which I am most proud
Scribus abdomen today and you'll be glad you did
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sand
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook we're on Twitter and Instagram Tumblr and Spotify but I encourage you to explore
For the entire world of 99% invisible
At 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com