99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Sam Greenspan
Infer Roman Mars
By now the story is well-known
A man sits in the backseat of a cab
Sketching on a notepad
As night falls over a crumbling City
He's proposal letter i
He draws a heart
And an n and a y
And right away he knows he's got something
This is it
This is the camp
The man was a designer named Milton Glaser
What city was New York the year 1977
A time and place commemorated by an entire genre of movies
Dedicated to making it look like a terrifying place to live
Enjoy a typical afternoon
Time in New York City
The most
Violent town in the world
I see the money man
The news today
The city needed a miracle
Any kind of got one
We letters and
I
Hyatt
And
Telling story with me is reporter muj
Sadie Glazier created the design pro bono
The Empire State development
Corporation
That's agency that handles tourism for the state of New York
Took the NY actually refers to all of New York State
Not just the city
So I Sylvania
Ms logo is literally ever
T-shirts
Hats towel test
The bags oven mitt
Prolong time
I didn't realize anyone had
Designed it
I didn't like it or dislike it
Is just part of New York
Of all the
Pronoun verb noun combinations that have ever been turned into a piece of visual design
I love New York is a pretty good one
I'll guess that there's not a single person out there and listen land
Who needs a description
I do not have to tell you
So you're talking about a 2 by 2 grid
The letters in a typeface with a friendly serif
Conjoined
A plump red heart
Both New York city and state have their own official flag
With a heart logo may as well be it
And like any good flag
The logo can inspire a sense of civic pride
I remember
The first time I bought and I heart New York shirt was actually a couple days after 9/11
I was living in Brooklyn and I was on my way to work and saw the towers you know exploding and
After
That experience
Your first your first thought is
How can I show the city that I love it
And of course the first thing that comes to your mind is this
Is beautiful
Piece of art
That says I heart New York and so I went down to Chinatown and I bought a shirt and I'm pretty sure it was probably not an official
Officially licensed product but it was $5 and I put it on I wore it until it smell bad and it helped me feel better
I Love NY campaign
Is that it was so successful that it became part of the built environment
So people started doing with I Love NY the same thing to humans
Have always done
When encountering something in nature
Distorted image
My name is Brian and I make plush internal organs
For my company I hergotz
Wendy runs I heart guts out of her home in Takoma Park Maryland
She makes is anatomically correct
Plush dolls
Internal organ
Kidneys please prostates your eyeball with faces full of joy
When he started I heart guts back in 2005
A t-shirt
The doll didn't come until later
And once you're within the style of I Love NY
Which Wendy knew was not totally groundbreaking material
UCI Orange New York on the Tropicana ads you see t-shirts that say I stomach
LA or
I spayed my cat like clubs diamonds Hearts Spades
Danny White UCF
You know rip offs of this iconic
Graphic design absolutely everywhere
Now Wendy is a huge
Is the guy who created I love him
He's a genius he's a brilliant graphic designer you go on SC there's about a billion different I heart New York Ripper
And nobody ever says that Milton Glaser the one who designed it
So I wanted to give the man credit
Where credit is due
So on her website
Keep it up a note right next to the teacher that called it a quote
Unmute eBay sammelan Glazer's iconic I heart NY.
Few months later actually on my birthday and July 8th 2008
Your birthday it was my birthday I got a cease-and-desist letter that said that I was infringing on
I heart New York
Trademark
With my design and could I please destroy all the shirts and take them down to the website
So I was completely freaked out
I heart New York
I really I love New York is intellectual property owned by New York State
You can't just rif on it with your own design and sell it without paying for it
Wendy made some alterations to the merchandise in question
Like cutting the design out of the shirt and sewing it back onto another shirt upside down and off center
The difference between an I heart guts shirt
And I are just New York Tropicana ad
Is that Tropicana paid for the rights to use it
Most likely
It's hard to get details on specific legal agreements but for the most part if you don't pay and you get caught
You get a cease-and-desist letter
Ignoring
You got a lawsuit on your
No as far as cease-and-desist letters go Wendy said this one was really sweet I'm looking at this you know
Scary season scattered all over the page
Ironically it may have been the shout-out to Milton Glaser
The. Wendy in trouble
Or at least she think so there's really no way to tell
I figured that they probably have legal spider robots that are
We searching for Search terms like Milton Glaser or I heart New York or I love New York
We do Google searches
And we receive Google Alerts I mean I don't think any of this information is very groundbreaking that's clear
My name is Claire Newman and I am an IP licensing executive and legal counsel for CMG worldwide
And we represent the New York State Department of Economic Development
Who is the proprietor and owner of the iHeart
NY train
Says iHeart not I love
It is actually I love I can't believe I messed up yeah it's I love New York
CMG handles intellectual property licensing
Sing for according to the website
Celebratory individuals from then now and forever
They represent the estate
Amelia Earhart Malcolm X
Frank Lloyd Wright
And a bunch of other famous dead people
And of course I love New York which Claire Newman represents from her office in Indianapolis
Claire says about half of her workload is related to licensing I love him
Adjust the number of colleagues who work on it too
Note to clear it wasn't clear who sent Wendy the cease-and-desist letter that happened before Claire was working with CMG
Her office works with interested vendors like
Blank t shirt manufacturers
Is the license the logo as is
Or a company can pay the remix the Loco by Tropicana did
With IRA
NY
Claire looks for infringement on sites like Etsy Polyvore and pint
She says people even report infringement
50 mg
I sometimes
She just stumbles into
Like today for example Cruise Line
Infringement inside the letter O is
Really coincidental but you know we found it
Said she couldn't talk
Her job at CMG is about protecting artists and their says it intellectual property
Is a protecting consumers to
Do you know if you buy McDonald's french fries
You know you're getting
McDonald's french fries you're not getting Burger King Spa
French fries
And so if you started
Putting different french fries in the McDonald's containers
That trademark that is the trademark on the container would stop indicating the source and origin of
Does french fries so
The reason people
Usually marks is so that
They can go back
Two trusted Brands and trusted
Labels
And I know they're getting the same standard in the same type of product each time
What is TMG is saying that and I heart guts t-shirt it's too close to the Glazer design
I got to wondering
How close is
Is 2 closed
I want to play a game
Basically I'm just going to give you
Potential logos
Like whether or not I would think that they would be an infringement
Okay
Let's say you saw my stomach
Stomach
I guess I would say yes
I bike Melbourne eye and then a bicycle and
I mean
I guess I guess
I would have to see it it's all about like the design and like what the visual is invoking
CMG is Vigilant about trademark protection because they have to be
The way the law works is that if you don't defend your trademark well enough
You can lose it
So you think someone is ripping off work that you've tried more
And you try to sue them
If they can prove that you've done a bad job enforcing that trademark in the past
I just want to study with them
So it's cmg's job to err on the side of thinking that something is an infringement
My position is that everything is a nymph
Wait why because it's my job to protect the mark
So just because Claire thinks something is infringement it doesn't always mean there's a cease-and-desist letter in the mail from CMG
They send out about 200 I Love NY related cease-and-desist for year
Ironically one of the people to receive such a letter with Milton Glaser
Who remember
Did the original I Love NY design for free
Right after 9/11 in an effort to raise money for local New York charities
Glazier created a new modified design that red
I Love NY more than ever
The state of New York land of apologizing to Glaser and chalked it up to a bureaucratic misunderstanding
Now we can go back and forth about whether or not this indicates something is broken and trademark law
Really the more interesting question is
Why does CMG eat a whole team of people working on I Love NY
I mean who would have thought that a government ad campaign from the 70s we need to be defended by a team of lawyers
I'm getting stolen and we mixed and modified in the countless permutations
I don't get it
I just
Totally don't understand that I have done a lot of things that are persistent
In the culture
It all started last
S560
Nothing like this
That doesn't make any sense at all
And you can probably guess who this
My name is William gleyzerman designer
And I spend my day pushing things around until they look good
That's what I do
It was clear from the beginning of our conversation
That Milton Glaser is
Really over talking about I love
And why
He's done a ton of other work
He didn't iconic Bob Dylan poster in Philip Roth book covers
He co-founded New York Magazine
And the 84 years old he's still working
Just recently he designed entire visual identity for Brooklyn Brewery
It for all his expertise as a designer
Even she doesn't understand the success of I Love NY
I would have thought it would have lost meaning a long time ago in fact I thought
Better would be a 6 month campaign
I felt that
In 77 it would probably less
6 watts should I be done with it
And then when I went through 77 and 78 I thought well
Maybe it has another six months ago and then went to the 78 and 79
Here we are
After
So many decades and it's still persist I can't believe it
I mean
There is no doubt that
I will go out into the street today
And I will see half a dozen versions of it
If you go down to Chinatown every building
Every street every
Side of a wall
Is covered
With I love New York
They are far more I love New York
Dumplings in Chinatown
Why
Why does it persist
I wish I could
Why isn't it tired
Everything is tired
Maybe I love New York is still around
Because people just love New York
But Milton Glaser thinks that its success that has less to do with what the designer
Represents
And more with what it is
You know I think it it really is has more to do with the
Trulia real brain function that has any kind of logic
It has something to do with the rigidity of that letter for
At the attempt of the grid to contain
The erotic nature of
The heart
The something that
Create an active
Closure and Pitbull
Mainz when they see it
That they want repeat it that doesn't
Board them
They can look at it at thousand
What's the time
A hundred thousand times and still nothing I've had enough
It's a trivial mystery
But baby. Baby it's a profound mystery
Why people are willing to look at certain things
Over and over and over and over
I mean
This is show a. Della Francesca
The frick
This week
I'm going to try to go up to
Today I don't think
Piero
I love you
Why am I willing
To look at the same
Pair of teeth
And the way they cling
To the ground
Depiero
Lower the feet
The painting
Can make me pay attention
Put that floor
For my whole life I've been looking at that same pair of
And I'll be looking at it till the day I die
With astonished
Why
Well maybe it'd be on the I Love New York at the phrase and they
Meaning to the city
They are simply the mystery of
Forum
Why does assert
Keurig
That is certain
Color in a circle
Countries
Hold our attention
Hawaii
Certain other
Forbes
Boris
I don't know
Economist
Happy Paws Wauwatosa
Something about all of this stuff
Olive
Graphics
Send all of language
Color is a fact
You never get
Maybe the I Love NY design continues to hold our attention
Because of its infinite capacity for remix
Then you can substitute literally any part of the equation
The eye the heart the NY
And the cultural reference still comes across
Exact even York state is doing good
You cannot find official spin-off logos like
Ipizza New York
I beach ball New York
It is now easier than ever before in human history
To take something
And change it just enough to make it your own
Imitating an altering Andre mixing has always been the way that humans engaged with the world
But there's a limit here
It will always be a baseline need for new ideas to break free of what's been done
And say something truly original
And should you ever fall short of the mark
Somewhere Out There
Is a cease-and-desist letter
Waiting to tell you precisely that
Hello
Here's a PostScript
Wendy Bryan from I heart guts
Says that there's a silver lining to getting that cease-and-desist letter from CMG
The language was obviously very frightening mean
Will not be tolerated immediate season 2 sister will be feet
So terrifying right and but later on I actually was able to use the language from the cease-and-desist to
Send out my own skis and assist two people were ripping off my stuff
I'm not the only person who put a happy face on an organ and I don't claim to be
Do you have to use different colors and different shapes and you have to come up with your own idea
So again thanks Melton
99% invisible was produced this week by muj zaidi Roman Mars and the sand green
We are a project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And the American Institute of Architects
In San
Special thanks to Debbie Millman for helping this episode come together if you like hearing designers talk to other designers about design
But you will love Debbie Millman design matters
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa is talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Five podcast
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this
Story including pool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an actor
The movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com