99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience
Your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network and
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make
Make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Visible linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Turning onto South Temple
Rose Place
It's just called South Temple
South Temple is in fact
Complete name of the street on which our producer Sam Greenspan is driving
Crossing
500 East
Exactly 660ft later Sam drives across the next major
Here's 400 East
And 660 feet after that
300 East
If you recognize the streets that Sam is calling off you already know exactly where he is
And what is about to say
200 East
And now here State Street
Which
Seems to work like a 100 East
Wow there it is oh my gosh
That is the Mormon Temple
The Salt Lake Temple of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
In Salt Lake City Utah
It's quite striking
It's beautiful
The urban grid of Salt Lake City Utah it's designed to tell you exactly where you are in relation to Temple Square
What are the holiest
Sites for Mormon
I first learned about this when I was writing a letter to a friend in Salt Lake
Whose address was like 300 something south
2100 East
Salt Lake City UT
Which to me sounded less like us
House number and more like a set of coordinates
That's pretty much of every address Works in Salt Lake City
And in Utah generally
300 South
2100 East
3 block
South and 21 blocks
East of
Temple Square with the most striking thing about Salt Lake's grid to us non utahans is the scale
Each block
Is 606
50 feet on each side
That means you're walking more than two football field
Dogs to get from one intersection to the next
Salt Lake's blocks of a biggest in the country
You can fit nine Portland Oregon blocks inside one of Salt Lake City
These giant blocks of created some challenges
For the city of song
But they were all part of the original plan for the city
One created by its Mormon Founders a century-and-a-half
Alphago
In an effort to create
Spiritual Utopia
In the desert
Every city plan begins as someone's Utopia
Urban planners imagine the way their City ought to be
Make some drawings and then watch as that Vision becomes reality
Throughout most of human civilization urban planners imagine their cities arising from a system
Streets joining at right angle
A grid
The idea of a grid goes back at least
To 2600 BC
In the Indus Valley
In what is now Pakistan and Northwest in
We know this from archaeological find
Ancient Egypt had grid
Ancient Babylonia head grid
The Greeks and the Romans had dreads
Any cities in Europe don't have a grid
But when European settlers came to North America they mostly build Gridiron City
When Joseph Smith founder of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints the religion of the Mormons
First conceived of a holy city for his new religion
He would not have had much experience
With large
Urban grid
Was born in New England and then when he was young his family live to Upstate New York he never would have saw a city that
Add more than a couple of thousand residents
This is dr. Benjamin Park
My name is Benjamin Park I'm an assistant professor of American religious history at Sam Houston State
Pace University dr. Park says that Joseph Smith's foray into urban planning began with a document called
The Platte
Zion Zion
Was a
Map
Details all the way down to how big the
Housing plots would be
How many Rosewood
Fit into the city where the courthouse would be where the temples will be how many people
Will live within these boundaries to plan which Mormons believe came to their profit
The Joseph Smith part and parcel with a series of Revelations that led him to found
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
A plan which would Inspire the Mormons eventually
Spiritual home
In the Salt Lake Valley
Have you been in the Temple Square before yesterday
Pepsi some of the sites
So we don't have to point out which is the Tabernacle which is the temple
Feel free to
Fix the radio
Showing Sam around Temple Square is Keith Erickson
Director of the LDS church history Library
The company name is Emily.
Historic sites curator for the LDS Church
I can go on for 3 weeks about Temple Square took Sam to the LDS Church History Museum
Reply to self
Is over here
This is it
Is it the original
This is
What they
Described and named the plat of Zion
The three of us are gathered around it
Display case in the museum that's actually pretty easy to just walk right past actually think the display case here under States
The significance of what's in it
It's just a rough-hewn
You know it's designed to look like a rough-hewn wood box
Inside
Thunderstick Museum glass
Is a large piece of parchment
Was Joseph Smith's Urban plan
American city of God
The temple blocks in the middle are kind of this
Ochre kind of red color
And the streets are labeled in a kind of light gray
The document were all looking
The plat of Zion
Is a city
A series of squares divided up by horizontal and vertical line
It is one of the
First documents
That the Mormon prophet Joseph
Smith and his scribes
It's a pretty simple system
Very large block
660 ft on each side
All forming right angles with one another
All of them the same
Except for these special blocks in the middle
Which he imagined would hold 24 Temple
The city's grid was designed so that you would always know exactly how far you were
Phoenix Spiritual Center
ICD definitely is divinely
As far as these are coming from
A man who
Had never seen a big city who would probably never heard of
Planning
And
Was really
Looking at this is the basis of Revelation
Understand how the kingdom of God looks
When it hits the Earth
This is ionic City that Joseph
Smith imagine
Would be as big as New York or Philadelphia or Boston worth
Eugene attempt to harness the best thing the city could offer
Infrastructure
Haitian community
But without the less Savory bit
Like bison
Crime Joseph Smith saw to achieve this by giving people
Lots of space
It would effectively be a rural City within the large blocks each
Church member would have a plot of land to have fruit trees in vegetable garden
And Joseph Smith imagine the essential piece of the urban fabric
Would be the home
Again
Dr. Benjamin Park
I think he would have rejected the
The general separation of a commercial and domestic level
You'd go to shop that's based out of someone's home
But Smith never got to experience his mixed-use
Walkable everything artistically crafted Utopian community
After leading his Converse to Ohio and then Missouri and then Illinois
Clashing violently with locals pretty much everywhere they went
Joseph Smith was
Killed by an angry anti-mormon mob
In 1840
The leadership of the LDS church fell to a member of Smith's Inner Circle
A man named Brigham Young
A large number of the church
Outwest to what was then Mexican territory
After a journey spanning years
The Mormons entered the Salt Lake Valley in 1847
And established Salt Lake
It would be the first place that they could build exactly as they want it
And when Brigham Young began devising a plan for what they would build
He returned to Joseph Smith
Bottoms on
Brigham Young's plan does look a bit like Joseph Smith's plat of Zion
But with more detail
And some changes
I see this utopian idea
Hitting some problems when you have to start dealing with actual landscape
That's Emily at again
With the LDS
Church Brigham Young realized quickly
Zion wouldn't work in the real world without some modification
Miss Plan called for
24 temples at
At the center of the city
Young decided to start with
Brigham Young also realized that the city couldn't survive on cottage industries alone
They would also need some commercial and Industrial.
There were limits to the rural City idea
In the mountainous terrain of the Salt Lake Valley didn't lend itself to a regular rigid grid
What is anyways Brigham Young's plan for Salt Lake City is faithful to the plot of Scion
The city is still after all built around a temple
And with streets
Name a way to tell you exactly how far you are from
At all time
And the orderliness of
The grid DuckTales with Mormon sensibilities
About the spiritual importance
Of maintaining
Heidi home
Brigham Young and his fellow Mormons did not stop with Salt Lake City
Over the next half-century they built about 700 lb
Based on a similar plan
All over Utah
Ended many of these town
They kept Joseph Smith prescription for large city block
660 ft on each side
With y Street
The joke is he could turn a wagon around
In the middle of the block actually one version of the joke I heard is that the streets are wide enough to be able to
Saturn wagon around
Without the drivers resorting to cursing
In Salt Lake City the wide streets in huge blocks have the effect of making you feel kind of small
And they say that everything is bigger in Texas
Just don't think those people have been to Utah
Before this is Molly O'Neill Robinson
Urban designer for the Salt Lake City
Government
We're walking around downtown Salt Lake
And she showing me just how hostile these wide streets
Can feel the best
We are crossing the street
Right now we're crossing 4th South also known as 400 South so we are given at 27 seconds
A 130
Right away the blinking pedestrian sign gives us less than half a minute to cross
Six Lanes of traffic
Normal pace
Many if not most
Send Salt Lake
Even Street
In the heart of downtown
Are four or six Lanes wide
All because the plot of Zion
Called for streets
With the Wind
Of 130
Back in the day
Things were plotted and measured using
The
Surveyor's chain
Also known as one furlong
The width of our street is
2 furlongs hours
32 ft
The streets are so menacing to cross the city tried making them safer by offering pedestrians
Bright orange
Flags visible lamp posts
There is a
Bucket of
To it
And I dislike once
4 5 6 7
Freepik
You're supposed to pick up a flag and carry the flag with you as you cross the street
For added visibility
We we should
And I'm going to make you do it
Embarrassed
No
I refuse to carry a flag
All right through Crossing now I'm waving this flag
I've seen these Crossing Flags in other places my neighborhood actually has them
At the intersection near the elementary school
But it doesn't kind of absurd to ask people
Ulta carry bright orange Flags in the downtown of a large American city
Veracross
So you refuse to carry these
So I refuse to carry the flag
And that I believe that our streets should be designed
To inherently make pedestrian Crossing
Safe
And
If you have to carry a flag
Across the street
To get someone to notice
Then we haven't designed
And difficulty crossing the street is not the only problem with lard
Roblox
Urban planners have long known that short block
Rocks are inherently more interesting
Because there's a greater density
What they call Network notes
Or sites of possible interaction between
Shorter blocks me more intersex
And more intersection
Show me more options for
What to do or where to go
Given the problems at large blocks and white streets are created in Salt Lake
You might get the idea that Salt Lake's Founders just started out with a bad plan
Not at all
Oh know what you're seeing there is a complete misunderstanding
Brigham Young's Concepcion
That's Andre stuani
A partner with the Architecture Firm
Dpz
He's also one of the founders of the New urbanist Movement
Which seeks to make cities and suburbs less car-oriented more walkable and more environmentally friendly
Andres duany says that in Brigham Young's original plan
The streets were never supposed to be paved from Curb to curb
The streets
We're basically a green space
With pavement only in the parts
We're settlers wanted the oxcart to
And Brigham Young never imagined that the huge block
Box originally meant for farming
Would remain intact
Is the city of all
You understood
Did the blocks would have to be subdivided from agricultural to Urban
Overtime
Ford Juanita Salt Lake City we have today represent the stagnation of Brigham Young's dream
He went from most beautiful
Most hostile in the West
And definition understanding of the intention
A Brigham Young
And the plot of Zion
Making the city less hostile to pedestrians is exactly what anti orange flag Molly O'Neill Robinson is
Is trying to do
She wants to take those huge blocks
Break them down into more walkable sections
And make them more interesting
You know that there's something kind of engaging and delighting
Your eyes room
Molly is hoping to do this block by Block in Salt Lake City
She took Sam to one current
Tekton regions
Where they're working on getting more pedestrian life into the middle of the block
So
Regent Street
Is really
The first
Christian first
Street
In Salt Lake
Pizza Street the street has always been here
Yes Regent Street used to just be an access road for some Downtown parking
Now it's a pedestrian walkway that opens up into a Plaza
The brand new theater
A new restaurant
The idea with the street is that we will be able to
How to close down pores
7th Street 4
Festivals
Events
Vic theater opening things like that
As of the time of this recording Regent Street is still under construction
But even so
People are already drawn to walk through it
The stakes for creating a denser more walkable Salt Lake or high
Even though the city
Feels wide open and nature is easily accessible
Salt Lake suffers from some of the worst air pollution index
Country the mountain ranges around the city trap in all the smog which largely comes
Cars with more Salt Lake is expected to double in population by 2050
And it can expand its city limits
Because of geographic boundaries
Like mountain
Great big salty lake
The city's ability to thrive will be determined by its
Its ability to make more efficient use of the space
It already has
There's a lot of optimism in the city
For finding better ways to
To use its large block
White streets
And there's been some progress
But several developers told me that the new city Administration has not been kind to bees
Approaches they seem to be more about keeping Salt Lake City
As it is
In the Church of Latter-day Saints
There's a principle called continuous revelation
The God is still speaking
And that Divine truths are still being revealed
So maybe with Salt Lake City needs
Maybe with all American cities name
Is it kind of continuous revelation
A way of honoring the principles on which the city was founded
But with the understanding that they must adapt
And respond
Hooda Math
The present
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan
Sharif Youssef Katie mingle court cost at Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall Taryn Meza and
Roman Mars
Special thanks to James alfandre Thomas Carter renewing Sam warlick Jason Brown Katherine daily and hurt back
All the songs and remixes on this episode were made by the great
Okay akumi on the Great
He'll audio label from the great state
Of Utah
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find this show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can tune me at Roman Mars in the show
99pi org
But you can find all things 99percentinvisible at 9 p.m.
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com