99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name in India
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 app
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars in 1898 China granted at 9
9 year lease to Great Britain for the areas across the harbor the british-controlled island of Hong Kong
But smack in the middle of that territory known as Kowloon was an enclave that wasn't included in the
A place that would at least officially still be controlled by the Chinese
It was a large fort
Built decades earlier to put a check on British expansion
But it evolved into something very
Very different
This was the first
Toto
That I saw that
But why don't you start describe an accident
Taking it in yet
The first analogy that the mind is it looks a little bit like the
The Borg
Cube from Star Trek
It's a city block
We're not looking at a neighborhood
That's nestled in
In the city
We're looking at
Borg Cube
But that is in the middle of nowhere
There skyscrapers behind it
Demarcation
Between
This neighborhood
Everything else
Staggering
That's my friend Nick vanderkolk from the program love and radio show me photos
He was the first person who told me about
Display
It became known
Is Kowloon walled City
And even of the walls eventually came down its name was still appropriate
There was no mistaking the boundaries between it and the rest of Hong Kong
I just became a waltz 13-story high-rises overlooking a comparatively sparse Waters
Buildings evolved
Drawing tendrils of bridges
Pipes and wires
Encroach on other building
Until the city turned into a single giant organized
Because it was an illegal no man's land
Not under British jurisdiction but pretty much ignored by the Chinese authorities
It became a magnet for the displaced in the marginal
Thousands of people move their after war with Japan broke out of
The 30s
And even more move there after the Republic of China went communist
Attractive gangsters drug addicts
Sex workers refugees
And also do a lot of average people from all over China who needed cheap rent
And so opportunity
Kowloon walled city was at its height
The dentist place
Anywhere
Ever
Had a population density of about 3.2 million people per square mile
Comparison Manhattan
Has a population density of about
70000 people
Per square mile
That means that Kowloon walled City
Was about
X is done
Has Manhattan
Only put that another way
If Manhattan want to get anywhere close to that kind of density
Every man woman and child living in Texas
Would have to move there
I came across it very much by accident
I came around one corner and
Saw this
Structure that looked
Really different than everything else
Around it that's red Gerard
Photographer
He live in Hong Kong in the 80s and 90s
And that
When I
Where is the walled City and
Started photographing there
Its density was immediately apparent
Buildings have been built
Up against each other without any space between
Each homeowner or each person who rented with
Build a different kind of caged
Balcony that would stick out
A meter or two from their apartment
It was a way of opening up the apartment and getting more space and and air and Light
I went for a first walk into one of the alleys and immediately struck by what's over here
Had enough just angle electrical wires
And wet garbage that have been thrown from the upper floors
TV antennas all over the place
Credible noises from the various manufacturing metalwork small kind of Foundry
Cotton Mills
Kitchen furnaces burning for barbecuing pork or doc or whatever
Sunsations underfoot as you go down from Ali's no into
Watery squishy stuff watery squishy stuff
You know stuff between buildings that you're walking on I mean I really don't even know what
All manner of
Greg took a lot of photographs of the walled City
There's one probably one of my favorites of his
Lama temple
It's much shorter than the 13-story high-rises around it
Over the temple is this huge metal grate
If it's there to keep trash off the roof
The lifestyle of living in the walled city was to dispose of garbage by throwing it out your window
And so did Temple do a big net above its roof
Beautiful Shadow through all this trash
Filter down through some of the bases in the garbage almost like a tropical kind of canopy except this one was moved
Refuse
The new voice you heard is Aaron tan
Aaron is an architect from Hong Kong
And wrote his master's thesis about the walled City
Any interviewed a lot of people
Up there
Diversity was at his prime times during the 60s and 70s
And it was also the same time where the
The great thinkers of architecture
Like the Aki grams
Body metabolize was talking about this kind of cell organizing structure
Intelligent building thinking
All these things are going on in the West
But not recognizing the existence of the word City actually is doing.
John Deere header
The one city in Hong Kong is growing myself out without any architect working on it
Existence of two one is very theoretical
What is something very real
And they do not know the existence of each other until
Much later when
Play 80s by Greg Giraldo
This to think
Giving the same time
Because the walled city was virtually autonomous from both China and Britain there wasn't a lot in the way of Interest
There weren't any building codes obviously and there wasn't any garbage collection either which is why people through the trash at the Wynn
DeWalt City gain reputation as a sort of den of iniquity there were high levels of prostitution gambling
Organized crime and for some reason there seems to be a lot of rampant unlicensed Dentistry but
Kind of order did emerge the Triads who are sort of like a Chinese version of the mafia
The power vacuum with film rule of law at hygiene
Jahnetics to clean up the streets
And residents organizations pops up and settle disputes between neighbors there's industry to do a fact
Factories fishball factories textiles were restaurants in because of Sanitation wasn't Ray it would kill you
Your meal in front of you to prove that they weren't serving you spoiled meat
A lot of electricity with pirated someone would tap a cable into the grid and run it over and across the
Building and then an official would shut it off then somebody would Tap & Grill again lay new cable on
On top of the dead shut off and so on so on eventually there were just so many cables
Running over and across all the buildings for the Alleyways below we're almost in total darkness
You cannot rely on what you see because you get lost right away and all but based on smell you could better
Maybe that's selling pork here and then actually doing Suga and Suites
Relying on your
Smell
You can actually navigate to the city Becca
It was said that if you knew your way around the cities of Labyrinth Maze of catwalk
You could walk from one side to the other
Without ever touching the ground
In the seventies and eighties when the end of the new territories lease was on the horizon
Britain and China begin to figure out what it meant for the future of Hong Kong
And part of that negotiation included the question of what to do
With the walled City
After three quarters of a century of ambiguity from both countries
They finally agreed on a long eviction process
Ana 1993
4 years before Britain handed over control of Hong Kong
China
Kowloon walled City
Was demolished
But the story of the walled city does not end with its destruction
Lularoe
I'm Brian Douglas and I designed the first draft of the Kowloon walled City level in
Call of Duty Black Ops
Call of Duty is a first-person shooter video game
Normally you get into like an army situation where it maybe you're in the middle of the street are you up on the second story or something
But it's not a very vertically Dynamic world most of the time except visually but we never usually get to get up to those Paul point
In other words
In most games like this
The scenery is just
Scenery
You can't interact with most the visual world that exists off the ground
They usually they're just there to make the world feel fleshed-out and real
So we can actually like will let's go up there
Call of Duty Black Ops is just one of many games to recreate the city
It lives on in a kind of virtual memorial
Picks up with them
Way more gunfire
This is kind of a level Builders dream because
It provides opportunities
So we don't normally get in our first sequence you can see sort of the Liberties that is allowed to take the kids if
If I needed to just
Make something really sort of crooked and
Awkward it was just all like carb lunch because it really fit into the nature of the city
The doorways weren't necessarily the right size
For the hallways were a little thinner and they Bend in the middle
Some of the feelings were a little taller where it wasn't really
Fully developing were wires coming off of it
You could just imagine what you will for it and it was probably suitable
I played the Vault City level
But actually that's a lie I watched a friend of a friend play because I probably would have died in the fridge
Anyways
It's clear that Brian and the other designers
A lot of thought into each location
Trencin
A particular room might have a half-eaten meal on the
There are the signs of a moment in someone's life
But even though the world is full of bad guys trying to shoot you
You come across almost no one who's actually living there
It's easy to lose sight of the fact that this was a real living
Breathing neighborhood
When you discovered that they were going to be tearing down I mean what did you think about
You should have knew it as a real neighborhood
Not just assertive
Fantastical
Den of iniquity
Yeah you know quite mixed feelings I mean the place was completely
Unbelievable and it was just a fantastic phenomena this is Greg Gerard again
At the same time. Civic-minded part of you knows that this can't and shouldn't continue it was
Fire hazard to health hazard
One of those things that it fell between the cracks
Andrew their into this beautiful monstrosity
Aaron the architect has a small ambivalence
I do for me as from architectural for him as very sad to see it go but when I enter
Movie with people 20 years later
At some point all this place is smelly is bad and glad he's gone so that now have you seen my new flex as much better
Some people
I have very good memory of the varsity
Dymista richness of the space inside the Mystic Community inside the Mystic convenience
Excited they can get things easily in the city
So you do get this two kind of opinion
But for Aaron there was a value in having a
Dismantled
As a graduate student he got to observe the city getting take
Can apart piece-by-piece
For him it was an autopsy
Way to see how the various pieces
The city all fit together
Is able to build an understanding about how
Dysfunctional most with their own well
As an architect
Aaron learn to allow for the
The sort of organic self-determination
Is projects
Incorporate some lessons of Kowloon walled City into his own work
Rather than planning
Everything to a T
He
He now looks for ways to allow the organic nature of a city
To organize
We're not saying that this is a wonderful place
We're trying to say that we want to duplicate this model because its existence is so unique
A position in history
You cannot recreate it
Indie on your head when you look at it it has a sudden of quality in his performance as an organism
In a very restricted constrain
Dad would like a water without electricity know how to organize themselves
The trash like I said on one hand you might see the Mount Rushmore
Even a postman
Inside know how to deliver the letters
I'm so it is a kind of good alternative model
Blood test to evaluate
Design strategy
99percentinvisible and snap judgement
With some help from Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
It's a product of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco in the American Institute of Architects
Tax in San Francisco
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Family ghosts
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you a long for the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black podcast
Can find the show and like to show off
Facebook all of us
Twitter Instagram
Open Spotify
Pictures and link
You must go
Radio
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com