99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The handle or name you adopt to be one-of-a-kind
Marshall 1973
Everything Is Beautiful
Radio radio meaning
You do not see the picture to hear the fun
Hear something called
Is a human boy
Ever did this is wjjk
Monday March 12th 1973 thank you and hear some morning music
29 people
On our way to Canaan land
Here We Go Again casting for lack of a better term
Has been good to me
But there's something about the transmission of radio signals
But I love
For billions of years the electromagnetic spectrum was populated only by radiation from natural objects
And then
All the sudden the air was filled with voices and codes and dots and dashes
And music
My Romance radio began decades ago but one of the key stories that captured my imagination at the very big
Beginning of my radio career
With the shortwave numbers mystery
Produced by David corn in the kitchen sisters lost and found sound Siri
It's one of my favorite stories about when my favorite subjects of all time
Coming to Fayetteville
Detroit numbers mystery was first broadcast in May of 2000
Here's David Gordon
Play-Doh
Bay City
The first time I heard a Spanish numbers lady
Lying in bed
Tuning around in my uncle's old shortwave radio
I was baffled by the solitary voice
She's still on the air
Even though I've heard her in one form or another since the early 70s
The sound of her voice continues to haunt me
Kabul
Gray
Fox 13
Number station
When I first heard them
Amber
And then what
Skip
At the end of the 70s they acquired a following
Buffalo hardcore group of listeners continue to obsessively tape and analyze the station
Think of them Kathy nicknames like
Birdman
Nigerian dead
Bedroom
You statement tracks the numbers for monitoring time
Eternal for hardcore radio listeners encrypted messages to somebody
I think it's despise being hope it's just a spies nothing more Sinister than that
The number station is defined as any of several hundred shortwave radio broadcasters
All of it you're using
Hightower big transmitters large antennas
Global coverage of the entire planet
Which do nothing
Sep broadcast
Meaningless strings of numbers
I never say why they're doing it they never say who they are
My take on the numbers Transmissions is the doctor the evil twin of a standard shortwave station
Stephen answers and programming of A Sort they even here to Advantage shortwave tradition
The interval signal this is a little ditty played a few minutes before the main broadcast to help the listener find and fine
Fine tune the signal next contact
Wicked meaning through the messages for it could mean there isn't any message has followed usually
Play something
Let's people know the header is over
The CIA likes to be other stations do other strange things
Then they usually go into the message
Which is a series of numbered group
Four or five numbers
I'm auditioning myself as a lonely agency in the basement
It's an urban area I have no friends I'm far from home for my family
Is my communication
This is my link back to my world
So I'm
Very carefully recording this message
I say again
I asked which Nia Ali arcademic photographer
Wine intelligence agency would communicate with an agent in the field in such an open way
Seems to be a relic of the Cold War
We always think of the radio is mass broadcast
You speak on the radio and everybody listen
This is an example of radio being used
One particular person
Decrypt a message
Which allows you to use this
Public broadcast medium to send a private message
That's really very pretty
The CIA does it Russia does a Cuba does it the British do it everybody does it Hue Stegman
Okay evidence that's a problem there's never anything that hard
I've always assumed these are using a one-time Pandora.
Which are
Theoretically unbreakable given the assumptions of only having ciphertext are only having what's broadcast on the station
A one-time pad is a page of random numbers
Which is the key used to encrypt and then decrypt the message
The sender and recipient each have a copy
Padgett's used once
Dentistry
What is pretty much untraceable
The operations have been compromised over and over again
People are captured people change sides people just get sloppy
Many many times they've seen the code pad they seen the receivers
The fact that the other side knows
But this is how they do it does not give them any more access to the information
It's a perfect system in that respect
Sub Station II Jam
Presumably by Rivals who pinpointed the transmitter site using sophisticated techniques
A number sentence got to rely on intensive listening to pick up any clues
What's up what you hear in the womb
Skates
Does come from Cuba
The Cuban stop started right after Castro got in
And start getting tensions in that area
It has gone on since
The engineering is sloppy tape stop in the middle of tapes are played backwards
Play radio Havana by mistake
Video Havana place them by mistake
Get the idea they're just barely on top of the situation but they keep that it
There's another Spanish numbers lady who is widely heard in North America
Some numbers monitors claim to trace the signal to a government transmitter site in Warrenton Virginia
They call her Cynthia
Evan starts with a C
Ends with IA
Havana Moon just came out of nowhere
He just started writing one day about the shortwave numbers
And the stuff was it
Extremely provocative
And it seemed to come from
Read inside
The only thing he would ever say about himself was that he was a retired intelligence type
Real trench coat Cloak and Dagger spook
Havana Moon was a gentleman named William godbey
He was a retired
Navel
Personnel and he was just a very nice gentleman
Havana Moon who died in 1996
Found a co-conspirator in John Sulphur
Ex police intelligence officer with an interest in radios Darkside
Turn the late 1980s
They runs around Florida with the radio director
He confided in me that he suspected there was one possibly two transmitter sites in South Florida
He had an idea where couple of them were we took some equipment out
I set the direction finder up
We took some bearings over
Couple weeks
With a very lines crossed was right around a military transmitter site
Located one of the airports in South Florida
We drove right to the airport when the transmitters came on the radio that we jumped out of our hands
Right there we have
During the day the Navy sent standard traffic over this transmitter
Located at West Palm Beach International Airport
Frequency
3 kilohertz away from the numbers transferred
Dantanna's were being down into the Caribbean
Who sent the traffic
What have no idea it is an unmanned site
Sent over a telephone line from Parts Unknown I would have no idea
Obviously one of the intelligence agency
My name is
John R Winston I'm the assistant bureau chief of the enforcement Bureau Federal
Medications Commission
We don't intend to discuss
Station
If any exist at all and I'm not saying there are
If you're trying to say there are those
That are transmitted
In this country
We know of innumerable ones outside of
Our only
Is if they are causing interference we then work with the
Country of transmission
To seek solution
We can hide a transmitter
Cryptographer Bruce schneier
Can't remember what number station is doing
Hiding location of the recipient
Location of a transmitter is not necessarily a secret
Person who is receiving it
Is somewhere
And we don't know where
Every night in the week in Europe you could hear these
Weird gong sound like some
Church bells
Chill
Bealls Palestine station
Simon Mason discovered the numbers in much the same way I do
Are the mid-eighties
She began to seriously document that European number scene
From his home in Kingston upon Hull in England
Does being a spy uncovered in bathroom City
And I know what he was listening to
When he was under the control of the Stars
East German secret police
The God knows what his wife and kids salt when Eddie's dogs cannot eat it
5 months after the Berlin Wall fell
Tom station went off the air forever
Biological of the big players in the Cold War theory of gone now
A lot of activity now in the Far East
The strangest one of the lot is got to be the one to Taiwan writer Hughes pregnant it's called new star
Start broadcasting and it has this lady who they tell me even in that culture is way way too enthusiastic
And she's been computerized comes out of the machine
He says things like good morning
Please decode your message
This is all the Mandarin of cars
She says things like
Thank you very much for decoding today's message
I hope you have a nice day
I mean
She's being nice to the spies you got to love it
Devastation is so over-the-top
It's take me to think that the purposes left for transmitting secret messages
Thanks for spreading disinformation
This is colossal diversion so that the mainland Chinese will think the Taiwan is put
Hundreds and hundreds of Agents into that country
She might or might not have done
I would say that's maybe why happens if you say you do it this way
It makes two guys in a government office and some crummy Building without water somewhere
Sounds like you know they're on the level with the CIA everybody sounds the same on shortwave
Bus monitor seemed sure that the number stations are part of international espionage
But some signals remain elusive
There are few strange stations almost at MIT
Like the buzz around 462 V pill High
Maybe he's just keeping his frequency open in case some solve well disaster happens and then they can take over that just December
Call Shockwave set up after all lights
Satellites of being blown out of the sky
Just like a notepad and paper left behind in case your computer faster
I think it's just not biggest conceptual art project unintentionally or otherwise
Anybody ever made it put Crystal in those guys to shame
Panatieri's
I listen to shortwave these days with a bit of a pan
It's fading out
Regarded as archaic by many International
Get the number stations persist
Sometimes when I hear one I write down some of the groups and wonder who the message is for and what it might say
Meet your contact
Blow up the bridge
Don't blow up the bridge
Maybe it's just
Keep list
Atencion seis siete Tracy at Estero the shortwave numbers mystery was produced by David goren
In mm
Special things to Hughes Stegman
Simon Mason
Chris malinski
Jonathan marks
Tom Savard
King Fernandez of the conet project
Anchor real wheeler
It was produced for the kitchen sisters lost and found sound project on NPR in the year 2000
I caught up with David gura in in 2013 and asked him about what was going on with the numbers stations today
They're still there
They're still on the air by still like to go out there and hunt around and unbearably
You can stumble across the station
What's changed
Is
The countries involved the action has moved
To the East China Russia North Korea Cuba keeps
Going onto and then away the sort of a mirror
What's happening on shortwave
In general with
Countries no longer using
Shortwave is a means of
Communicating their message are propaganda to other countries
So it's still being used and that's just kind of comforting and also kind of creepy she
Cuz when I tune across them you know it's like
The world tilts a little bit it was very odd thing to encounter
David Byrne current project is called shortwave ology which I highly recommend you can find it online at Short waveology. Net
And also put it on Facebook and SoundCloud
Together we were reminded us back in 2011
Episode number
This radio program
About one of my favorite websites
I thought I just practice on the in here for your enjoyment in case you missed it
Definitely
Here. Connection
You were listening to 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Wireless setting
My name is Erica Everhart and I'm the creator of the site you are listening to Lost
And you were listening to Chicago you were listening to New York you were listening to Montreal
And you are listening to San Francisco
Vehicle that has no bleeding or color the party last year after
The Giants won the World Series
I was out in the streets of San Francisco checking out all the different celebrations going on
And when I got home
I was looking on Twitter I saw a lot of people are posting links to
What's happening in their neighborhood people out
Lighting bonfires and one thing that kept coming up was
Hey check out the San Francisco police radio on
Soma FM
So I started listening to it
It was cool and got bored after a couple minutes and started putting on some of my music in the background
And something about that there was like a Synergy between
The police scanner and like the music I was playing
That really sounded cool I want to find a way to share that with
Oh that's right
And since it came online on March 6 2011
I've spent what might be considered an inordinate amount of time listening to
You are listening to
Some people think it's
Peaceful
Creepy I think it's mesmerizing
And its Elegance is in its simplicity
Show me load the page there's a little JavaScript file that pulls in an audio stream from radioreference.com they provide the
Police radio on
A playlist from SoundCloud which is music sharing site which has been screened by Everhart so that the play with only has these
Dreamy ambient soundscapes that complement the police scanner audio and also loads the background images
Coming from Flickr those are three main parts and they're all
Coming from site other than mayo and only possible because
Of the companies provide simple web API application programming interface
Kind of sharing and National
You can create something new that might not be what the Creator intended
The design toys being made by these sites.
Thing that you are listening to is exploiting
Is a relinquishing
A little bit of a control of their data in order of that data to spread across the web
In ways that they never could have imagined
In this way outside and independent developers like Everhart
Can act as a kind of
R&D Department
Radio reference and Flicker and SoundCloud and the artist
Is offering Creative Commons royalty free music on SoundCloud did not imagine this use of their content but they do
Do you have an API
They just created a shareable architecture that Taps into a remix and culture
Where new ideas can flourish
Synthesized launched and
It word gets around it's been very popular
I've been contacted by lots and lots of artists
And they all want to be part of it they all think it's cool
And they're asking me can I have my music included on your site
And now they're not getting anything out of it they're not getting paid there's no royalties there's nothing like that
But they are getting exposure I think these are people who
Posted their music out there because they wanted to share it with people
And now they're finding their sharing with lot more people
So
It's kind of like a virtuous
Cycle I got Square
I created something
I'm not looking for anything in return the artists are getting something out of it
SoundCloud and radio reference are getting something out of it because there are more people are becoming aware of their services
Cirilla
0-coast to me or to the artist
We're all building something
Together that's kind of enhance
Designing for openness allows others to answer the questions that you don't have the answers to
Did the greatest power maybe that it allows others to ask the questions that you haven't even thought to ask
This is Roman again in 2013
You are listening. To has grown into dozens of pages now including one that features the number stations
And probably the radio chatter of a city near you
These local radio Transmissions are passing through your body right now so he might as well TuneIn
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
We are now produced out of beautiful Downtown Oakland California
The home of radio
Thanks our friends at the architectural firm arcsin for giving us a place to call home a place to hang our hats
A place to hang out with real Architects they are really talented and kind group of people to get to know them at arcsin.
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast oh my God. Info
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars
We have all kinds of great stuff going on including links
To shortwave ology and you are listening to on our website it is nine 9 p i r
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com