99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
People all over the world
Flirting with an idea
Call Basic income
The idea behind the basic income
Is that each citizen
Receives a payment every month
As of right without conditions
I'm paid individually
Basic income
Also known as universal basic income or unconditional basic income
Or Ubi
That's producer Avery trufelman
Very very roughly defined Universal basic income
Is this idea
That a government would
Hey all their citizens
And everyone will get a flat sum of money every month to cover their basic needs
Whether or not they have a job
And this money would be no strings attached
With no conditions
And this would hopefully remove any stigma from receiving it
It's free money basically it's free money
The logic behind it is this
A lot of jobs don't pay enough money for people to even make rent or buy groceries
You can work full time and still be below the poverty line
Easy to understand why people on the left
Would advocate for a guaranteed income
Throw a version of this concept is popular and Libertarians
They see basic income as a way to shrink the welfare
For example you could take away food stamps Medicare and housing subsidies in
Replace all of it with one
Flatsome
People and Tech are also interested in the concept of basic income
And they feel a certain urgency
See about it
Robots are coming for our jobs
They saying and basic income is the best way for humans to maintain a decent lifestyle
When are Libra
What is increasingly obsolete
Our generation is going to have to deal with
Tens of Millions
Jobs replaced by automation like self-driving cars in
But we have the potential to do so much more than that
That's Mark Zuckerberg giving a commencement speech at Harvard and what he's getting at is in a world where jobs are scarce
Everyone will need a financial
Concussion
And then by his logic
If people don't have to worry about food and shelter
Maybe they feel free to innovate maybe they'd start a new company
Go back to school
We should explore ideas like Universal basic income to make sure that everyone has a cushion
To try new ideas
Listen to that Harbor crab that is eating it up
Elon Musk has also advocated for Ubi and the startup incubator y-combinator will soon begin his own politics
Right here in Oakland to say what happens when I give a group of people a basic income
It's actually an idea that's been around for a long time and there are many
Different variations on
But recently
They've been a number of experiments
Forms of basic income happening around the world
A non-profit is running an experiment with Ubi in Kenya and Ontario Canada just launched a test in three different
Twin Cities
But this recent excitement about basic income experimentation
Is largely focused
On
Finland
Experiment
With universal basic income
Financial
In the beginning of 2017 The Finnish government began an experiment with a basic income
And this news about the Finland experiment
Was really excited
Maybe we will learn what people will do if they can make money
Without work
They just hang out at home
What Society grind to a halt
How do people find meaning in their lives
And how will they evaluate
And that's a quart of dick
Question
It's the kind of the acid test
So basically
Will receiving basic
People more or less
Whatever deactivate
Whether it's
Just walking around or whether it's
Taking care of
Your neighborhood
Kids are
Applying for work this is Robin mocha
Founder of demos Helsinki we are helsinki-based anything
And here's what I learned
Talking to rope and other people in Finland
About this experiment with basic income
To talk about basic income
Fremont started before
The understanding off
What the outcomes of automation
B or the employment Market
The Finland experiment
Is not about robot
And it's not to see if people will
Stop working when they get
Free money experiment is to find out
If giving people basic income
Well actually help them
Start work
In this whole experiment is especially interesting to us here at 99 pi
Not just for what Finland is test
But how they are testing it
Finland is trying out a unique design-oriented way of thinking about government
Rather than just rolling Outlaws on a massive scale
They're trying to craft legislation in stages
With user feedback
Like a piece of design
Because every good design is made to fill a need or solve a problem
This
Is the problem
I hate it
Unemployed
Right now in 2017
The unemployment rate in Finland
8.8 /
Percent and that's about
Double the US unemployment rate
And that rate is worse than smaller finished cities like your insu
Is ephelides always being there
Poorest parts of the country
This is Donna leskinen
Resident of Yuan Su which is about an hour's drive away from the Russian border
She's 39 and she's been unemployed for a little over two years
Unemployment
Has been here
That's a in southern or Western Finland
Because we are far
From a bigger cities where are more much much much more
Job opportunity
Santa has a master's in history and she worked as a researcher
Docker project ran out of funding
And all over Finland has been a massive decline in manufacturing
Ever since Nokia was
Crushed by Apple and Android phones
Nokia's phone parts used to be made by contractors and companies all around the country
My mom actually work in that factory.
Kenny went down when Nokia started go down
I kind of know
Bottom part of a story
Pretty well in the US
Depending on the state
You can generally collect unemployment for about half a year after losing a job
In Finland you can collect unemployment for about
2 years
And then there different kinds of social assistance is an allowances
Apply for
If you still
Don't have a job
But here's the catch
If you're collecting unemployment assistant in Finland
You definitely cannot earn additional income
Or you risk losing those benefit
And then you have to reapply
Which is a massive drag
You cannot
Take
Like
Part time job
Because
Then you are gaining money even though
Very very little
Then is counted against you
As so you lose that little bit of support money you were already gaining
So unemployed Finn's don't want to risk that loss
They don't want to pick up temporary gig work or part-time jobs
Freelance work
So it's really really difficult situation
This actually happened with the person we hired to record sauna
We asked what is rate was
And he said he couldn't charge us
Because he's also unemployed and would lose part of his allowance if you took on money from freelance work
So he did it for free
Thanks
Basically the government of Finland realize that something had to be done about this cyst
That they were accidentally disincentivizing citizens from getting small jobs
Or maybe even starting businesses of Their Own
And these are citizens who want to work
Like Santa
Being unemployed
Makes me feel anyway so whatever
I don't know
Unimportant
Doing a job
Would make you feel like you're doing something for dinner
A purpose
Is something bad being unemployed
Hanging around and Chestnut
Being very important to anything anybody
So this welfare system clearly needs to be changed
This could be done in a few different ways
Like with an Earned Income Tax Credit
But first they wanted to try out something simpler
And go from there
And this is where we get
Tattoo design
They wanted to design and test policy in a process very similar to the way designers come up with new products
You would design policy
That you would think about policies ass
Kind of design objects
Our Design Services
And that means that you could do alteration
And tests
That's roping mocha again founder of the think-tank
Demos Helsinki and the prime minister's office
Turns to them
Soda prime minister's office
Stop roast ask and ask them how can I be employee
Design thinking
On
A national level
Now can we do like governments level design thinking
Design thinking
It goes like this
First there is a challenge or problem that must be song
Bend designers
Express
Test and cycle
That means designers come up with a few ideas and prototypes
Test
The try those ideas
Maybe with a model or sample
Get feedback to Understand what actually happens what are the outcomes
And
Cycle incorporate that feedback to make changes and revise the design
Then the process begins again
And again and again in different iterations
Couple years ago
This is how the Finnish prime minister decided he wanted to design legislation
Also the Prime Minister I mean he's not a radical
Ya te vi
Is the most dangerous
Fart story through frustration
They don't know
What a particular Lord
Hacks
Would cause
Will actually
Work
So demos helped establish and experimentation unit which is an actual office
Of the Finnish prime minister
At the prime minister's office is experimentation used
The first unit
Bus like
Design
Policies in the kind of design
Meaning of the word
There are other governments that are interested in experimentation
But here's what makes Finland different
They want
To create prototype
And then change and scale and update them dynamically
As a result of their experiments show what's effective
And what's not
And in order to run these experiments
Finland actually had to pass a law to ensure that they were not in violation of their constitution
Course
All the Constitutions of
The Democratic countries in the world they say that you have to
To treat people equally
And by definition if you're running experiments
You're not treating people equally
Cathay
People who are part of the experiment
I'm not
Treated equally
So they needed to be a special law
That's all fine. Okay how do
The experiment
Fit in the Constitution
That says
That people need
Will be treated equally
And one of the first experiments The Finnish government decided
Do was with basic income
Because the welfare office
Is extensive and complicated and rather than
Rejigger in one part of it and changing a bunch of stuff around and reworking their normal operation
The basic income experiment just kind of
Chugs Along on
We have automated and partly automated are processes so everything is run by computers
The money the basic income just gets deposited in participants bank account every month automatically
The program is currently overseen by Mario keturunan
Who works for government institution called Kellogg
Social insurance institution here in Finland
So I was in charge of implementing this basic income
Experiment
Project leader
Stigma about welfare in Finland
Everyone goes through this office every now and then in life
Because there are 40 different kinds of benefits that students can receive
Including student support maternal care maternal care pension subsidies
And of course
Unemployment
So in January of 2017
Kellogg 2000 unemployed fins at random from all over the country
In this experiment we have 2,000 people who are getting this a basic income $500
60 Euros per month
And so they have to be at between 25.
The eighth so they are not
Students or young people
And they are not those kind of people who will fill out their pension age during the sixth
Experiment so this is kind of like the profile
Participants didn't volunteer for the experiment
Kelly just told them that they would now be receiving 560 Euros a month
The news came in a letter
I got an
Fat fat
Mail
Andis
Says that's okay you are chosen to be one
It is basic income experiment and I was like out
What's that
Sauna the unemployed researcher and Yuan SU
I'm really thought about basic income until she read that big fat packet that came in the mail which outlines the experiment for her
And I was going to have the certain amount of money
Did my bank account every month
It's not big but it's stable money
560 Euros a month would be a little less than sauna would get on unemployment
But you'd also be able to work and not worry about losing
So I was happy about it because
Two years that experiments last
It's got to be that money every month
And I don't have to stress that much because I am a big
Dresser person
I stress a lot
Finding a job
Is very important
So now
Unable
If I find a job and work a part-time job
I could take it
And not lose the support of many that usually would if I wasn't part of this
Basic income
Experiment
Some of the participants have been talking about their basic income with a press
But China has kept it a sin
I feel embarrassed about it
Biggest it feels like I have this
Advantaged so I haven't been fairy
I'm excited about
Spreading that information and now us
Participating this
Your post this is like okay
I'm not very many people in Finland are probably here in your office.
I can see elephant devoted
Sorry to put it this way
I'll have you know we are
Huge in Finland sauna
Santa doesn't know anyone else involved in the study and most people in Finland don't
Her friends get kind of StarStruck when she tells them her Secret
I I get people out of court with that so
Oh
First one I've ever met
It's kind of funny really
When you collect unemployment in Finland have to go to these job training meetings and check-ins every couple of months
But these two thousand participants scattered around the country
Don't have to do anything at all to get this 502
60 Euros every month
Even though they're part of this experiment they also don't have
How to report how they spent it
And at the end of the experiment
Tell her we'll look and see if
This group of unemployed people who got basic income took on work
And compare it with their control group
Which is the rest of the unemployed people in Finland
175000 people who are in the same profile than these two thousand people
But they are not getting this basic
I'm so we are comparing these two groups of people
In this two years.
I see what is happening to these how are these people behaving when they get this basic income
And that how are these people
Behaving
And then when they compare the results
Basic income my
Just might get one step closer to becoming a reality
Play with the idea that these basic income would actually come a universal
I can compare in Finland
Which is kind of like the
The idea that I don't actually believe
Is going to happen
The people who
I'm not thinking this
A good idea
Guess the person currently overseeing the experiment for basic income
Believe that won't work
I think that it would be too dramatic
So we would wipe out the whole of this
Social security system that he would have been building up for decades
And then just replace it with one
Turn in imagines but not everyone would
Prefer a flat income
Some people do need more than one base some
Like what if you have children or parents
Special needs you have to take care of old
In that case
You don't have the capacity to start picking up gig work
The basic income wouldn't be enough for you
And of course
Forward pay for it
So who would Finance it
It's really hard to say how much basic income would actually cost
The average tax
Where it to be Institute
And we don't quite know how it would affect the economy or inflation rate
It's all dependent on a number of factors
And there's no exact math on this
If someone truly
Planes that they know how much
Morris
Basically
I think they're lying
Sasha
Systemic shift
Decide to start paying everyone a lump sum of money will change the economy in such way that the whole system chain
It's like once again something
Experiment
Ropa says yes basic income would save money by cutting back on bureaucracy
Blue probably still be expensive to fund
But that's almost
Technical
You know you know if you need money right money
It's like what politicians do they changed
By the way
Budgets are arranged
If basic income make citizens become more active and engaged
Girl that has faith that governments will
Find a way to pay for it
Because I'm excited and activated population is generally good for the economy
He says that's why they have to test before anything else
Basic income would really increase productivity and
Improve General well-being
At this point they're testing to see
If it be worth more in there
I really really
Really hope that this will continue. Just spread out that more people are involved
This experiment has
Integrated sauna
Even though she gets slightly less money than she would on unemployment
She's free to do whatever she wants
I am trying to find a job
I meant sending applications and take off
Play a part time job
She feels like she's about to start a new chapter
Ready for what snack
Tranquility of mind
It brought that to me
And if it sounds funny because I'm out of money is not that big
But
To give people hope
Give people a chance to
Take a moment
Away from the stress
As a
Panic
Do we survive
It's really important to keep in mind that son is just
One participant in a very small study
And basic income may have helped her search for part time work
But when I spoke with her she had yet to actually find employment
And also you probably noted that this form of basic income is not Universal basic income
Who are Universal
It would be money for every citizen employed or not
In this particular
Experiment
The basic income is only for unemployed people
Yeah I think what we're experimenting that would be cold partial basic income is 8
This is a limited experiment I don't know how relevant it is because
A lot of groups are missing
If we want to see what people do when they don't have to work anymore
Roper says they should next see what happens if basic income is given to people who are already employed
To see if they then quit their jobs
Critics of the experiment also argue that 2000 people is too small a sample size
To finish Economist published an op-ed in the New York Times called
Why finland's basic income experiment isn't working
And said it had the potential to incentivize people to
Accept low paying and low productivity jobs
It's an experiment that
Far from perfect
But it's not supposed to be a be-all end-all
Ideally
What's a first draft
Weekend which is considered
Give this amount to some thousands of people and then we'll know for sure
It's going to be
Ultra other experiments before we can find out how to
How to renew
Basically if this experiment is at all successful
Or even if it's not
It should lead to another
And then another
In Finland isn't Justice on the experiments with basic income
Dolby experiments for what languages to teach in schools
How to change child care
Everything
According to their website
Experimentation office is working on 26
Key projects National
And slowly
Hopefully
Finland will use the design process to figure out if it
It's possible
A worthwhile
To try radically new ideas
Express
Test and cycle
Will we ever get a basic income experiment right here in the US
It turns out we already had one
Decades ago
Avery explains after the break
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
People here in United States are talking about
Universal basic income in arguing about
Why is good and wet
That's bad but to me it just seems like
It's not on the table at all I just feel like there's something about the US
That makes it so it would never happen here the basic income is basically something
That can only be tested in Nordic
Welfare state
Yeah it's it's it's
It's the crazy thing about basic income is actually this very American
Idea
It was
First proposed right
He's kind of first mentioned by American Founding Father Thomas Paine
It's like as American as apple pie
And in terms of
Basic income experiment
We've actually been down this road before
For as a nation here in the United States
We did some studies
With basic income
Back in the seventies
I shall ask to change the framework of government itself
So we can make it again fully responsible for the needs and the wish
The American people wanted to see if you could guarantee a family of four
$1,600 a year
Like $10,000
Is today
Any hints at it in this State of the Union Address
Let us place the floor under the income of every family with
Children in America
Let us provide the means by which
More
Can't help himself
And so yeah and then he decided to really try and do it tens of millions of dollars
We're budgeted
So that more than 8500 American
Could be involved in experiments all around the country
And their bunch of different one
Different people running them and they tested like
Different variations of basic
Can come in different ideas around
When in Seattle in one in Denver
And one in Gary Indiana and one in North
Carolina just like
All kinds of places all over the country
And so why haven't
I heard of these at all
I have no I've known Elizabeth and what do they find out
Well the results were kindness
Screwy because
It wasn't like
In a perfect
Scientific
Bubble there all these variations
All at the same time
And some of them were like
Different marginal tax rates in like different benefit levels and all the different kinds of stuff which makes it really difficult
Identify the effects
Because you were texting so many different versions of it
And then
Actually
The really big pitbull like they did find some stuff for the reason
That
Has been pretty much discarded to the sands of time was because
People started analyzing the results
Or did it was a
And so they're like
These rumors
Swirling around
But people were dropping out of the workforce and just like enjoying this basic income
And it wasn't actually a statistically significant Trend it was
Kind of a Rumour which can sometimes
Be more powerful than a fact
And they're also all these reports
Increase separation and divorce rates
And that was considered really scandalous and set off a lot of opposition but then when the data was actually a
Analyzed
It wasn't as
Seems that many more
Is there a few but this wasn't necessarily A Bad Thing
Totally. The economic slavery
Akron public didn't have the patience for nuance and they're like this will be the end of the family unit
Cancel
Tolerate it and it's all just because like
They started chatting about it before they had before they had the numbers
It was kind disregarded before we really had a chance to
I think that's certainly a challenge
Keeping in mind
This is Elizabeth Rhodes
And she is a research director of a basic income study that is happening at y combinator research
Which of the nonprofit research lab
Can you buy a startup accelerator called y combinator
It works like right down the street from our office
And she's helping to launch a basic income experiment nearby
Colonel Glenn
We are
In the process of
Capri Pilots Mall
Protest sticks and work through
Questions around that and preparing for a larger randomized control trial that we hope to Launch
After that local time
They want to react
Expended actually looking
Do two US states
Embroidery
They have definitely learned from these early experiments
Start small
Expand slowly and to not
Promise to me
Because
You know they want to wait for this experiment to fully play out
I'm like Finland they're definitely doing this because of the robots
And because they're based here in the Bay Area which is
Home of the gig economy
Then just want to see if this will make people happy
In an era where robots take over all of our jobs
Or jobs are not like jobs that are today
Rare a big trout
And therefore
Having a basic income would ameliorate
A kind of economy that
A lot of the
Silicon Valley is helping to
To create exactly
Startup accelerator like to help businesses grow and they're like this is what it takes
If they need a basic income in order to innovate capital I like
Let's let's see if it'll work yeah and they just want to make sure that they don't set expectations
Too high
The funniest Urban UniFirst several years
And so I don't expect
Tootsie
No changes overnight
Anyway and so I think
We really need to give it time
Sew in
Doing this research about basic income
I come across a thousand polarizing thanks
Pieces that are either like
Ubi is a great idea and we should do this right now or like this is a terrible idea and we need to stop it
But realistically it's going to be years
Before we know what we can learn from this privatized American experiment
Or from The Finnish experiment for that matter
Because most of the arguments were having about
Basic income at this point in time
In all of basic incomes many different definitions and variations
It's all based on speculation
We're having a debate without
Data
And no one has solid answers yet about what basic income would mean for the national tax
Kotor inflation or unemployment rate for the economy or the robots are happiness and well-being
And
Right now all we know is that different experimenters all around the world are trying to figure out
Tum answer
We just don't know
So what is this is going to end like all radio stories end
What is a
Time will tell only time will tell
Time will tell
Savory
Thanks Roman
99percentinvisible with produces week by Avery trufelman
Mix antique production by Sharif Youssef
Music by genre
The rest of the staff is Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald
Aaron Meza and me Roman Mars
Special things this week to our fixer Ali Sudoku Easter
And Jana sabonim who recorded sauna for free
Thanks also to Tim Wong keroro the bombilla
Osmo super Anto
Uhaul Lebanon in believe Echo poker
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX collected for the best most Innovative shows in all of vodka
We are supported by the Knight foundation and coin carrying listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible in Torrance
About to show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
On Instagram Tumblr invited to
Give her wonder what it takes to get a business like
The gas station or fast food place
I want those blue highway signs
Turn down
There are rules
You can read about them
On our website
99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com