99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The Mind enter Barcelona's most famous Cathedral often stretches around the block
La Sagrada Familia
Designed by Antoni Gaudi draw so many people to see at the neighborhood is congested with tour buses and
Taxis in scooters
3 million people went inside the church in 2016 and another 7 million came just to stare at the outside
Estranged Behemoth structure
If you travel around Spain you'll see a lot
Old Gothic churches
Razor Katie mingle was in Spain
Earlier this year
But this one is different
First it doesn't look like a Gothic Cathedral
It looks like it was built out of Bones
Are saying
Or like it just
World out of the sea
Fractal
It looks organic somehow
But there's another thing that sets it apart from your average old Gothic
Cathedral
It isn't actually old
LD wasn't able to build very much of it before he died in 1926
Most of the church has been built in the last 40 years
And it still isn't finished
Which means that Architects have had to figure out and still are figuring out
How gow do you wanted the church to be built
We are all together in that room is
The special room
The most important part of the
Building we are building
That's heronema Boucher Rio one of the current architects of the building
He says the clues to understanding how to move forward on the construction of La Sagrada Familia
Are kept in the room were standing in right now
In the basement of the church
Photosynthesis radio can you describe
What's in this area
Now look up shelves
With
Fragments
Little pieces of
Plaster
Beeg
Small
Boy died geldi left elaborate plaster model of detailing his plans for finishing the church
But about 80 years ago
They're all basically destroyed
Nether in pieces
If it doesn't look like
Just from this and those little pieces that that would be enough
The lake
Figure out
The whole
Sing
I understand that it's difficult
To know what we have to do if the main architect is not
Cartier
Highest us what we try to do is to understand
How
He thought
And it's not easy
I know
It definitely hasn't been easy for the new architects
Recreate an understand the vision of Antoni Gaudi
And there are people who think
They shouldn't even have tried
But the building should have stopped
Took Audi's.
But it didn't
The building is currently the longest running construction project in the world
And The Architects are still trying to understand the mind
Gaudi
Antoni Gaudi grew up in a little town called where you
Which like Barcelona
Part of the reason Spain called Catalonia
And although he's become one of Spain's most famous
Yode would never have identified as Spanish
He was Catalonia
Through and through
Catalonia has been in the news recently because of its movement for independence from Spain
But in many ways this movement isn't new
Catalonians
Struggled against the rule of the Spanish for centuries
Castlevania has a separate language Castle
It is always felt very separate
That guy spends Bergen
This guy spent hens burden I'm the biographer of Antoni Gaudi
Pennsburg and says that as a child growing up in Catalonia Gowdy spent a lot of time outside
And was completely enthralled with the natural world around him
A lot of kids are curious about nature
Antoni Gaudi
It was different
It became a total obsession
He seemed to absorb essential lessons from the patterns and shapes
He saw in nature
Just looking at the way the insect
12 walking and flowers grew the way that A Tree Grows in
SquareTrade
Brooches
A dried-out snake skeleton
Honeycomb
These were Nature's perfect instructions
Pittsburgh Aldi a deeply religious Catholic
God was the master architect
Of these Wallace organic structures
Eventually God he left
A small town in the countryside and moved to Barcelona for University and then Arkansas
High School
When he graduated in 1878 the director of the school said
We are here today either in the presence of a genius
Or a Madman
Gaudi began his career at a difficult moment in Barcelona
Industrial Revolution and brought thousands of workers from the countryside into the city for factory jobs
They were toiling in terrible condition
Packed into filthy tenements drinking dirty water
Diseases like yellow fever in Colorado
We're ramping
In the midst of all of this suffering a Bookseller name shows up book of Isaiah begins selling a fundamentalist news
Paper
The kind of reminded everyone that their misery was punishment for their sins
Surprisingly a cool song
Pretty soon broke up with making quite a lot of money from his Catholic guilt seemed newspaper
Kept apparently on the hidden under the tiles of his book shop
With the piles of money he was accumulating decided to build a church
Women to inspire the common folk to lead a religious life
The church will be dedicated to Mary Joseph and Jesus
The sacred family La Sagrada Familia
The first architect at Build-A-Bear hired quit after a year
He went looking for a new one
Legend goes book of Isaiah had a dream one night blue eyes man would come to the rescue
The very next day book of Isaiah saw the person from his dream in real life
Drawing in the studio of another architect Inu
Ginger hair blue eyes
And he says what are you older man
The man he had seen was Antoni Gaudi
And immediately boccabella hired him to be the architect
Act of his church
The
Grace is Joven Spain
At that time
Was given to this completely
Lumos completely online 29 year olds nude
Done
Very little work
The basic floor plan for La Sagrada Familia
Had already been laid out by the former architect
And Goldie would stick with it
The church will be built in the Neo Gothic style Which is popular at the time in Europe
Miguel D also wanted to charge to be something completely unique
Inspired by Nature
And by God
What county wanted was a building which would actually have the kind of
Harmonies
All of the celestial spheres the idea of did everything
As a home mini in nature
And if you got that right in your building
The building itself with spirituality
That said Gowdy would never allow the building to outshine God's creations
So he set a limit on how tall the church would ever get
He felt that he didn't want to be taller than God's handiwork and God's handiwork
We're close to mountains
Only the side
La Sagrada Familia would be one or about 3 ft
Shorter than Mount montjuic in Barcelona
Majestic keep it humble
In 1883 when Gaudi started work on La Sagrada Familia is first matter of business was to finish the
The Crypt which has been started by the previous architect
The Crypt is essentially a small church under the bigger charge and a place where important
People are buried
In fact I was buried there when he died in 1892
9 years after he hired Gowdy
Sagrada Familia Crypt was big enough to hold services in
And this kept everyone happy while Gowdy took his time designing the rest of the building
The book of Isaiah died management of the construction passed through various hands
Purple Galaxy
It was only one client
That really mattered
God is the client and God is never in a hurry
After the Crypt was finished
Scoutee began to build the first big wall of the building
The Nativity Feast
He would work on it for the rest of his life
It was important to him that this facade get done first
Because it would be the Bible written in stone
Which
People if they couldn't even read or write they could look at the building and btools about
The values of the castle
Slick face
LD was a sculptor as much as an architect
In the wall would be full of stone sculptures depicting biblical seeds
The baptism of Christ
Christ in the workshop with his father flight to Egypt
With a life-size donkey
The stone sculpture of a donkey in that c was actually cast in plaster
I'm a real live donkey
It looked as if it had been through the desert for 40 days
One of these workers actually wandered the streets until he found the perfect starving donkey
Which he exactly hand it over to God
Each of the Donkey
And he Costco
Antoni Gaudi also tried making plaster molds from live human beings
One of his workers but they almost killed him and
I decided that maybe that wasn't the best way forward
This all took an incredibly long time but eventually the wall started to tell us a story in stone
And it featured hundreds of celestial and Earthly creatures
Little snails crawling all over ads and tortoises
The facade became crowded and cluttered and teeming with life
Lumos
Swamp fish
Tell the quality of the stain oozing out of organic
Shaping of the building it was very unusual
Varick Street
Antoni Gaudi was slowly building a Catholic Church
But not everyone was convinced the Catholicism have anything of value to offer the average working citizen
Leftists are the church is getting rich from the tithes of the poor
They sold them as being wealthy is being parasitic
As living off them
Communism socialism and anarchism we're taking hold in other parts of the world and in Spain
He left his parties thought they could offer the struggling worker a better life
Conflict between leftist in the state and left us and the church or a consonant
For the Lost
Decades of the nineteenth century
It's probably on the average something like two bones every week
In the center of the city
Brother years Gaudi worked on other architecture projects in Barcelona
His work is Peppers all over the city
Impalas is Pavilions and extracting homes
His sinuous in skeletal architecture was unmistakable
Everyone in Barcelona new hairstyle
But La Sagrada Familia
It's a project that consumed him
He realize the coast he could never finish it in would never see it finished in his lifetime
My 1926
73 year old Antoni Gaudi had never married and was living alone
He spent a lot of nights sleeping in his Studio at La Sagrada Familia
Too obsessed with his work
To care about his appearance
He was
Looking up it's like a tramp actually busy
Travis is what held up with safety pins in a bit of string
On June 7th of 1926
Gowdy is leaving work
And as he crosses the railroad tracks
He forgets to look
And the Tramp Runza maeva Antoni Gaudi was left nearly dead on the railroad
His body was found he was taken to the hospital where he died three days later
LD was buried in the Crypt
Under La Sagrada Familia
His last years have been consumed with building the church
The Barcelona have not forgotten Gaudi
Drawings of people came out to mourn population
Castlevania turned up in recession
Thousands of people that
When Gaudi died he left behind a largely unfinished Church
What stood was a massive war
The Nativity facade
One Tower
And the crap
His colleagues and apprentices
We have a lot to do to bring his full vision into being
Look out he had anticipated that other Architects would finish his work
And he left behind detailed drawings and models outlining exactly how he wanted his magnum opus
To be built
For 10 years work unless grata Familia continued very slowly
Much of Gabby's former team stayed on even though they could have gone and started their own projects
They were loyal
There was still work to be done
The jewel ring still existed
They continued working away
And then in 1936
The Spanish Civil War
Began
The decades-old conflict between leftist in the state and finally come to a head
The Republicans who were in Alliance of various leftist parties
Fought against the Nationalist
Which was the lines of fascists and other conservatives
Led by General Francisco Franco
The nationalists also have the support of most of Spain's Catholic clergy
On the 18th of July two days off
Start the Spanish Civil War a group of young anarchists
Breaking to the Stooges of Goldie and smash everything with hammers
All the multiples everything is smashed up into tiny little bit
When they're done smashing daylight the place Ablaze
Everything Burns including the architectural drawings
Absolutely everything in fact
The following day
Trying to come back and bum the Nativity facade
Which is the only one standing there with Gowdy's
Which
Miraculously they failed to do
Catholicism was under attack during the war
And by the end of it
40 churches in Barcelona had been destroyed
And 12 people associated with the Sagrada Familia project including some bits managing patrons and clergy
Have been killed
The war ended in 1939
Alexis Maas
The fastest 1 and general Francisco Franco took control of Spain
Should I use eco
What is all over
Few workers return to gaudi's Studio to salvage what they could
They very carefully
Picked up in boxes little
Sections and fragments of of the multiples
Unlike archaeologists do today they started piecing them together
For the next couple of decades the remaining Architects and other workers tried to figure out how to move forward on the
Suction without Gowdy's plans
But outside the church there was opposition to moving forward at all
In the 1960s an impressive group of intellectuals in Arkansas
Sex including Le corbusier and Alvaro Alto Road and open letter opposing the continuation of La Sagrada Familia
Amelia
LD wasn't only in Arkansas
Back they argued
He was an artist
And you shouldn't attempt to finish a work of art without the artist
They felt good
This was a total waste of time they should have left
Just the original Nativity facade
Almost like a Gothic ruins
That is a homage to Gaudi
And the Gaudi wasn't being well-served
But the patrons of the project would have none of it
The building was never supposed to be an homage to Gaudi they argued
It was always about something bigger
That said they would try to honor Gowdy's original Vision as Faithfully as possible but it would be easy
The models and drawings had been the roadmap for how to move forward on the construction and they were burned and smashed.
Pieces
And this wasn't just any Cathedral
All these years
Cody harbin designing something
So unique
So complex and so completely new
It would taste his successors
Years to fully get a handle on it
The church still had no interior
In the roof
It was just walls and Towers
Construction site
Open to the Rain
Fs20 fast learner 19
But I was 20
That's architect Mark burry
Mark actually been told an architecture school that Gowdy was not worth studying because his approach was to
Esoteric
That he was sad
Two extraordinary and that there was no school
Meaning that there was
Nothing to say you move alone this just got blurry more curious
So he went to have a look at the Sagrada Familia himself
Add by complete accident X not meeting the 290 year-old actex
Directions to project
And had died
They have been young Architects listing the guy with the expanding his latest discoveries
When they were students
The old Architects were ready to move on to the interior of the building
But they didn't exactly know how to do it
Facebook geometry
Play music system
Translation to
I kind of building methodology
In other words The Architects knew it was theoretically
Possible to figure out how to create the rest of the church
But it was a Monumental task
They pointed burrito couple of boxes
Immortals
Monster Paris models
Invitation to come and join the team and
Have a mistress
Puryear burry work with the model
Trying to extrapolate the geometry of the rest of the church
Based on the pieces he had
After a year
He managed to draw out architectural blueprints
For one window
It was a start
Mark Berry didn't stay long at the Sagrada Familia
He was only 20 and he had to go back to New Zealand finish school
He returned to work on the church
10 years later and found that when he was gone
A news thingamabob have been moved into the office
Computer
Thought these computers must have something to offer cuz I've never actually personally tax form
Winberry finally touch the computer he figured out that it had architectural software on it
But the software wasn't capable
Of dealing with Gaudi
Couldn't even go anywhere near what county was
Trying to do
The complexity of gaudi's designs with too much for architectural software of the early 90s
Marie wondered if there was anyone else who designed with similar geometric complexity
And finally you landed on it
People who design airplanes
He started using aeronautical software to figure out an architectural strategy for the interior of the church
And because I had to spray sophisticated software by accident undiscovered permit
Design
So we will baking powder mix
Play from 1991
Parametric design uses computer algorithms to allow you to plug in different variables
And see what the end result is each time you change something
Blackberry was one of the first Architects to use computers to design this way that we eventually figured out the
Frankie Ruiz team had also started using aeronautical software
To bring Gary strangely shaped curvaceous buildings into being
Every year I would go through LA and visit Frank's office and talk to the technical team and compare notes
Eventually Gary Technologies with help from work break
Went on to create their own parametric design software
Specifically for architects
By the early 2000 many of the most exciting new projects in architecture
We're being done this way
At the Forefront of this was a church designed over a century ago
By Antoni Gaudi
La Sagrada Familia
So from being the saloon Akron ISM in interesting but
Irrelevant it became actually live
Delete projects in the Hall of the digital Revolution affect
Parametric design allowed Mark Berry in the other Architects to move a lot
Faster on the interior of the church
Without this technology it's
Possible
Stilbene note inside the sea
It was only a few years ago in 2010
The Architects were able to put the finishing touches on the interior
Now people line up around the block
I got a glimpse inside
And it really is Brett
Taking partly because of these things
Edibly tall columns that Gaudi designed the branch out like trees at the
Top and are capable of carrying
A tremendous amount of weight
When people go into that building I'm not suggesting
But it's necessarily always a religious
Experience
But the
And surprise
Of walking in trailers doors
It felt like trees at the top and are capable of carrying
A tremendous amount of weight
When people go into that building I'm not
Suggesting
It is necessarily always a religious experience
The shock
And surprise
Of walking in trailers doors
Into this explosion of light
The light
Pours into giant stained glass windows
In the afternoon it's a red orange light
And in the morning it's a bluish-green light
And it filters through the huge
Tree like columns
You feel like you're in a forest
And you feel very tiny
If you're very small
You feel as if there's a hold of universe above you
But the building is still not finished
I'm in An Extremely Loud metal cage elevator that runs on the outside of the church with head on emo
Bruschetta
The architect volume at the very beginning of the story
And Anna Barbie who handles press for La Sagrada Familia
It's very safe on a says but it doesn't feel that safe
The elevator is shaking and we can see Barcelona getting smaller below us as we rattle ephylone beside the tower
Church
The elevator door opens to a spec
Spectacular View
I'm breathtaking
We are standing on the
Top
The Sagrada Familia
I have the parts
Barcelona city blocks stretch out all around us
To the east we can see the Mediterranean Sea
Until the South the mountain that Gowdy promise not to surpass
When the building is finished there will be 18 Towers
Including a new one right where I'm standing
This one will be the tallest of all
Reaching the 560 ft or 170 m
I don't email is working on designing it right now
And he's using the fragments
Gattis plaster models
To figure out how to do it
These will be Jesus Christ Our in the middle
One of Anjali
The architect of the building will be finished in 2026
The 100th anniversary of gaudi's death
But there is still a lot to be done
Meanwhile some of the neighbors seem set up with La Sagrada Familia and all of the congestion and Taurus
It brings to the neighborhood
Sometimes they're a little protest
Against the place
Like this one in 2011
Where locals chanted
No more tourist buses
The one their neighborhood back
The bigger the building gets
The more Taurus
Come
130 years ago is Joseph vocab and decided to Bill Foster about a Familia
Cleanse the people of Barcelona up their sins
Spire the common folk to live a religious life
He picked a piece of land on the outskirts of the city where cows and goats would sometimes wonder
We probably never imagined that it would become tourist attraction it is today
Architect head-on T-Mobile shadow
Does one of the perks of working at La Sagrada Familia is getting to be inside the church
When no one else is
Is there
Hermes
Is Israeli special
To be alone or to be
With not too many people
The church only holds one Mass a month right now and it can be hard as throngs of Taurus bump into you with their
Bear selfie stick
To feel connected
The building as a place of worship
Geronimo let me come into the church with him in the early morning before it was open to the public
So that I could try to get a sense of it
Are you going to feel that
Espiritual en.
Betty somebody somebody or something
More
Goddess symbol
Ansgear
To me and I'm not a religious person
La Sagrada Familia is not so much a testament
God as it is to humans and what they can create
The Gaudi would dispute that assessment
He once said
The creation continues incessantly through the media of man
The man does not create
He discovers
Coming up we discuss Kaldi's revolutionary models for La Sagrada Familia in a segment that was just
Too nerdy and dense for the piece itself
But it's new
It's too cool not to mention it at all
That's right after that
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
What are things you mentioned that piece are these models
Destroyed and
How important they were in realizing gaudi's vision for La Sagrada Familia
Bluetooth technical to get into in the piece
Kolstad
Noses
And I asked him to come to the studio and explain gaudi's modeling technique
And why it is so important
The creation
La Sagrada Familia
With a lot of Arkansas
Especially once
Do you like to use
Preferred to work in models rather than
Models helping experiment with really complex
Control structures
And Albany
Model out structural Arrangements test things out
Photograph as models in draw over the photo
The bottles were behind all of this
Yes they were driving the design
And one of the things that you tied with a lot and bottles were variations on what
What's called a cabinet
Okay so what is a catenary arch
Catenary is
The curved shape
That a hanging chain assumes
Under its own weight
Basically picture
Electric line suspended between Utah
Okay so you're driving on the highway
C2 utility
Electric line goes across them and there's that natural Boeing
Of the
Electrical wire
And that is
The Cat Mario
Exactly
And that term is actually
Drive from the Latin word for cheap
And it was already well-known by gaudi's time
That an optimal Arch shape could be made by mirroring
A catenary curve
Vertically
Basically you take that hanging curve
And you just flip it up
And that becomes the model of your
And that Arch
These building loads efficiently and a lot of God
Okay that makes sense you take this BO2 chain
Christy altomare
When you flip it over
And when Ukrainian churches in the gothic style this is a good way to create a good
Model
But
Gowdy took the idea further
Chi hung strings
Other strings
They added birdshot
To weight them down at structural intersections
Incredibles
Huge intricate
Wireframe model
End up looking about like Chandelier
And then God would use mirrors to flip
These vertically
And study the shapes they created
In order to shape his own elaborate building skeleton
And it sounds a lot like what
Leader Architects use
Software for
When they did 3D model
Yeah there are a lot of parallel
Innocence
Long before parametric
Design was a computer software problem
Gowdy changed
Parameters in his models by moving strings and weights around to see how
Who's individual modifications
3shape an entire structure
And then a century later people came along and finally made these digital
Technically
Handmade models have been doing
Allowing Architects to see how small changes would Ripple out to their entire designs
So you know you can imagine
It would take like
Call Amanda
Moving around a little bit
And that deforms like all the other shape
Types of Destruction
Right and then
Software you do this and nail the software
Cranks long and does its thing
But in gaudi's time
You would move a weight around
And you'd see how the
Connected set of chains with all kind of deform by adding a little bit of birdshot
That's amazing
And it looks stunning
Yeah the results are amazing
A lot of people you know they think Audi and they think of these beautiful sculptural scenes in these details here
Created but underneath all of that is this
Billie lovely
Structural logic
Instagram Familia that those details are beautiful but so is this internal frame
Columns and arches
Vault
Branches up and out and creates a kind of
Fractal Forest
Spell because
He didn't spend a lot of time
Teaching or explaining his methods or really writing about his designs
And because his work was so out of sync with
What modern is for trying to do with the time he didn't always get a lot of recognition from the architectural
Pizzerias like a starchitect but in hiding yeah pretty much
Spend all this time bragging about what
That's so cool
These models are
Wheelie stunt they're amazing to look at him we have some pictures on our web
Yes we have a ton of pictures of
These bottles
But he made as well as be
A really beautiful Church
Help create
Bagel thank you so much
99percentinvisible which produces Wheat by Katie Mingle
Mixing tank production by Sharif Youssef
Music by genre
Percocet is the digital director and the one Among Us who actually went architect
Staff includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall and me
Roman Mars
I think the folks at La Sagrada Familia for spending so much time showing us around
It was a true privilege
More detail on everything you are today check out guys van hens Bergen's new book
The Sagrada Familia
Kaldi's
Heaven on Earth
We are products 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99% of is what part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
And our listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoying discussion about the show on Facebook you can't win me at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
Michael work run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Do you want to read article about the oldest national monuments in the US or any of the other Design Story that we released
Every single week
You have to go to our website
MPI
Done working
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
5 part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com