99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
San franciscans have a healthy pride in their City
Maybe their pride is a little too healthy sometimes a little over-the-top
But they acknowledge this
It's the natural result
I'm living in the greatest City
In the history of the universe Belsay
But even the most die-hard San Franciscan has to admit
It could be better
Like if there was a funicular transport suspended from a bridge of a soaring Towers over the bag
Connecting downtown San Francisco
And this
Biscuit looks like a blimp that would be attached to the underside of a bay bridge that would apparently cross the bay in five
That's Allison area falcon
Designs in New York Times and is a Content strategist at
Remember organization dedicated to crafting smart solutions for cities
She and I are looking at an article
From the April 17th 1910 Edition
Of the San Francisco call
Fletcher Phelps Proposal with the most amazing
Headline
From the call building to Oakland City Hall in 5 minutes subtitle
16 million-dollar so that Fletcher Phelps can spend the day with his suspended auto motor Railway
Play which promises to revolutionize all kinds of traffic by rail
I'm going to use my old timey reporter voice here
Google Play Savannah ganondagan for you have scarcely made yourself comfortable in your seat when burned
You are flying across the bay in midair with the speed of a gun projectile
And almost before you can say
Jackie Robinson
You landed in the Athens of the Pacific
Now that's rather startling statement isn't it
Felts
Into the future
We are going to have such a railway
Oprah show you say contemptuously
It's only a dream
No
Some dreams
Come true
And they just don't write them like that anymore which would have been absolutely amazing if that have
Happens this is one that I really wish that happened
Quite sad that it
Happen
These are stories of the unbuilt structures
A subject which is really captured the imagination of the public recently
Funville San Francisco with a series of events and Exhibits explain the things that
Almost made it
Can the effects it would have had on the city
And there was also a huge exhibit called Never built in Los Angeles
In the classification of unbuilt structures I put Fletcher e feltz's suspended auto motor Railway
In a group icon
Jetsons
The Retro future pictures are super cool
Reminder
When we used to dream big
In the parallel universe of unbuilt structures in San Francisco
The big fish that Got Away the white whale that urban planning nerds
Was a city plan
From the Creator
Other White City
San Franciscan
The One That Got Away was the Daniel Burnham plan for San Francisco
That San Francisco Chronicle architecture critic John King
Daniel Burnham was a Chicago architect
Who oversaw Construction
Of the White City
At the 1893 Columbian Exposition in Chicago
That World's Fair
Brought about the city beautiful movement in
America
The city beautiful movement
With big Civic centers and Grand neoclassical structures that stir the soul
Burnham years later I did the Chicago plan he did a Washington plan which was implemented in a lot of ways
Burnham was hired by Big Time downtown business owners of San Francisco determinism raggedy rickety
Pretty well off City
Into something Majestic
Who better to charge
Of course the city Daniel Burnham
So Daniel Bernstein shows up and they set up shop
The cottage
On the highest point the summit of Twin Peaks
So they can survey the city
And craft the perfect plan
And here is this
On how to take San Francisco
The rich Queen City of the gold rush in the silver rush and so on and so forth
Andre make it with this
Imperial order
With diagonal boulevards connecting all the different neighborhoods of the city
The main Hills Telegraph Hill Bernal Heights
Twin Peaks one or two others
Turned into these open Civic markers so on and so forth
In a basically the city as a work of urban art
Supernova turns into plan to the citic fathers
In the fall of 1905
You might be able to tell where this is going
There's a big
Banquet everyone says that
Wonderful
The project is printed up in books
To distribute to begin making the case
And the legend goes that all the books were delivered to City Hall for distribution
On April 17th
Maybe that's a bit of an exaggeration but basically the whole plan was done
Turn it up ready for distribution in the 1906
On the very next day
April 18th
In the city level
Into this is the opportunity this is San Francisco's chance
To enact the Imperial Burnham plan
And the chronicle which was the big paper the time embraced it everybody said this is great
Let's bring out Burnham
This is the way to start
Everybody blessed it and endorsed it
But in some way
The plan unravel
It's something every city ravaged by disaster is seen
There is the way to do it and there's the way to rebuild quickly
Everyone who would Embrace did it first pretty sooner than symbol
The business of San Francisco is getting back to business and rebuild and showing people
We don't have time to do these crazy things
Burnham and his supporters kept trying to do these crazy things from near and far
But none of the real things he proposed
Stuck at all
Because they just
What had seemed to be an opportunity for them to be done
In fact
Created the pressure
Just to go back to the way things
It's Lower Manhattan after 9/11
What's New Orleans
After Katrina
Again and again and again
Those are two things
High-speed hanging Bullets Over The Bay
Analogical City
That we can hold in our imagination than curse our forebears for being so short-sighted
But quite honestly
A lot of things probably most of the things that we
Gold designer belt
Would have been just terrible
I mean here in the Bay Area alone
Plenty of near disasters that
Lowe's
To becoming a reality
Stuff so bad
He'll make you want to reach out and
Hug and NIMBY
And the culprit in the most terrible plans for the city
Was the automobile
They were proposed highway system that would carve up San Francisco in unimaginable ways
But here
They are certainly not alone
The invisible never built parallel universe bands Coast to Coast
And there are cartographers
Are these unbuilt world
Our producer Sam Greenspan spoke with one of them
A guy who calls himself
Been smoking Rockin I go under the name of vanshnookenraggen
It doesn't mean anything it's pure gibberish
My actual name is Andrew Lynch
AKA Andrew Lynch
He's a professional realtor and amateur cartographer
In New York City
Annies maps that he made
They first glance look like
Google Maps
New York City of the streets and everything
If you ever looked at a Google map
You know exactly what this looks like
Cray for the landmass blue for the water
Arterial roads there yellow if there side streets
White it's just like any other map
Except
Except that
The mattress looking at isn't
But really there
Andrew's map doesn't represent what is
It represents what almost was
What I've done is
To draw
What Google Maps would look like
If
Robert Moses
Had gotten his way in the
Mid-twentieth century
Okay so first we got to talk about Robert Mueller
The true power broker of New York
And we know that Robert Moses was the true power broker of New York because the title of Robert Caro's 1100 pay
Age biography of him
Is
The power broker
I've read it it's so good it's daunting but
Power through it
It really is worth it in public housing
He did a lot of the master planning of New York City and its surroundings
Stephen restructure the city government
But some of what he's most famous
I really Infamous for
Is what didn't get built
You see Robert Moses was a Man Who Loved highways
He wanted to build two highways through Manhattan 1 to downtown
Through
Soho and Tribeca
+ 1 through Midtown
Just south of 34th Street
And that's what Andrew Lynch has drawn into the Google Map
What does highways would look like
Today
Now if you're thinking
This is totally insane massive gnarled
Perpetual traffic jam through Manhattan
You have to understand what was going on at the time
Manhattan wasn't made for cars
And a lot of people really wanted them
So just like cities today
They were trying to solve the problem of a city that didn't function in the modern era
And also
Here's a fun fact
Robert Moses didn't drive
Can drivers
Cardizem around an indoor
The horrible New York traffic for him
Sit in the backseat
In gaze out the window at the scenery
But the rest will be in to have to drive ourselves
These highways probably would have inspired no small amount of terrible anxiety
This was a spaghetti network of
Wrapping themselves
Around building
Real talk
Probably would have been too much worse than any other giant Highway interchange
Anywhere else
I'm like everywhere else
These highways wouldn't have worked
We know now that traffic always expands to fill whatever the capacity
I mean maybe you could drive from Manhattan to Jersey like
5 minutes faster than you could today
But the real tragedy here wouldn't have been the failure of the highways Misha
It's a total catastrophe
It would have been left underneath
The Manhattan expressways would only feel like a slight nuisance if you are in a car
Put on the ground
Lower Manhattan in particular
Would be almost unrecognizable
It just so happened that when I was talking with Andrew we were in lower Manhattan
Right on barracks
And as he was telling me about all this unbuilt
Stop
I realize that a lot of these things were mere blocks from where we happen to be
I asked Andrew if he can give me a tour
What's not there
Going off
Right in front of us
Would have been
If we go down a couple blocks
We could like stand right under it
You can hear the street traffic
It would have been ten times worse than this
It would have been dark
It would have been like we were approaching
Monstrous creature in darkness right now
Lots of car noises
But wish you always get next to a highway there would be these ramps going along the side streets rapping
Brown building to get from 3/4 stores in the air you have to have ramps coming down
The highway itself
Running down to West over there good luck finding anyone deliver Winston everywhere
A dynamic
Hill's machinery
It's a really weird
Experience trying to
Take a tour of
It's
You have to have a very active imagination
Which I do
But if you want to try it
Stand under it and then come here and then try to remember what that feels
Back in the real world
Things are quite nice around lower Manhattan
Where were standing out
It's open
Was trees over there
Is big buildings right here none of this was
It's a little bit of a Plaza
Got shops
We're looking over there if there's
Townhouses
Tenements
Probably are asking way too much
What's for rents because
Cuz where we are
Nothing
None of this none of this would be
Which brings us back to Andrews map of Robert Moses unbuilt Manhattan
I think what's most striking about these documents
Is out on striking they are
With your Google standard Greys and blues and yellows
Andrew create a map to show how terrible these days
But in creating a map
He was actually able to see the project
From the Planters point
As I went through
Cutting across Manhattan
Before I drew in the highway I just looked at
The swap that I had
Erased
It was an interesting
Feeling
I could put myself in Robert MO
Shoes wear
I'm not looking at a city with him
China map
And because I don't think
Don't see the homes
The buildings
It's very tempting just be like okay
You just put it right there
You know not realizing
There's a disc
Building out
I know what that building me
The place of peace
People live that people go that I've been to
And now it's
It's off the map.
It's funny to hear you describe your own
I wanted
To put this
For the everyday for
To look at this
Inside wow
That would have been
I would have loved to be able to make
Review
I like put yourself right there so you could
Does Maps stand
And under the highway
See what it was
Was like
It does have the
Great Dark Mass above you
The story of how all this didn't come to be
Is a long
It often centers around the activist named Jane Jacobs
Who led a campaign to keep one of Moses highways
From destroying her beloved neighborhood
Greenwich Village
And there are other factors like the massive cost of those highways that were proposed
Fat captain from happening as well
But the interesting part.
Is how that threat the Lower Manhattan Expressway
Crystalline the story of Jacob's neighborhood
It's almost as if
The threat
From Moses
Made Greenwich Village into the place that now seems destined to become
And that brings us back
To the San Francisco Bay Area
Is John King and Alison area
The unbuilt can in fact
Start what does Happ
So if you drive north
On the Golden Gate Bridge
Immediately to your
Left as you start to reach the end of the bridge you see
Tremendously beautiful Hills overlooking
The ocean
I'm in the base the other side
And there's nothing built on those Hills it's
It's all natural Landscaping those people biking and walking and it's really help it go all the way out to the headlines
And when you see it for the first time it's kind of hard to believe that this much open beautiful landscape exist right next to one
One of the most expensive cities in the world
And just kind of remarkable because obviously it would be
Some of the most Prime real estate in the area and facts
In the sexiest
Someone attempted to do there and in the early sixties a developer thought
What a great place to build
20000 homes or so for people who are going to work in San Francisco
It was called
This was not seen as a rapacious idea at the time this was seen it how business is done
It was a massive mix of houses and hours
And
It was approved with very little controversy by The Marin County Board of Supervisors
Limoncello being approved with enough to alarm people and start people reacting to it
And it led to lawsuits it led to opposition it led to local city starting to fight it
When the dust settled the project did not get built currently the only thing that was built was the gate that was going to lead to the marketing
Center at the very start of the property
So the Golden Gate National Recreation Area was formed out of concern for all the various plans that were being proposed
Francello is blocked
The
Sutro Baths Lands End in San Francisco had a proposed kind of
Cancun type resorts
And if you are at all familiar with Lands End in San Francisco where the Sutro bath ruins are you no help
Silly that notion sounds
It is only Cancun as interpreted
By the North Pole
It is said there were various projects like that
What was proposed
Never got built
But it said
The events in motion that in fact
Tramadol landscape we have
What projects like that did in the early sixties
Is that they were a signal
Two people who cared about the topography the bay area in the proximity of open space to urbanized space
How to say
What are we going to do we can't fight every one of these battles occur
Is there a holistic way to go about it and you had some very smart people
Who came up with the idea of will what if there was a national park it could take in all this
And Marin cello maybe on Belt
But to say that there's nothing there in the headlands
Is not seeing the grand thing
San Francisco actually did build for itself and everyone else you visit
What they actually did build over there
Was the reason
We all love it here
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Julie Cain of klw audiograph for giving us some
San Francisco sound
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flat pocket
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
The world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along for the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99
You must go to 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com