99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There is a beauty
Do Universal standard
The idea that people across the world can agree that when they interact with one specific thing
Everyone will be on the same page
Regardless of language
Culture or Geographic locale
If I'm in Belgrade
Or Shanghai or Sao Paulo
I can look at a sign and know instantly without speaking a word of a local language
This floor is slippery
That the emergency exit is over there
And if that substance
Is poisonous
And I should not eat it
The group behind those internationally recognized logos
ISO
The International Organization for standardization best reporter Lauren over
And one of the most recognizable ISO symbols
Is the international symbol of access
What's the formal name of the blue and white logo with a
Stick figure in a wheelchair
Around the world you see the international symbol of access
Everywhere
Parking spaces on buttons that operate automatic doors
Bathrooms and on seats on the bus or at movie theaters
Anywhere where there's an indication of special accommodations made for people with disabilities
Prior to the late 1960s there is no universally agreed-upon accessibility icon
Everyone used a different symbol if they bothered to use one at all
But in the 1960s
The disability rights
Started picking up steam
In 19
68a group now called Rehabilitation
International announced today
Design contest
Create an international symbol of Acts
The logo would have to be readily identifiable from a reasonable distance self-descriptive
Simple unambiguous and practical
The winner was a Danish designer names to sonico fool
The modern stick figure in wheelchair logo that we know today is actually a slightly modified version from the original
That one didn't have a head
Within a decade the logo
The one with the head
Was endorsed by both the United Nations and ISO
Remember this is the group that sets iconographic standards across countries
It's overtime this logo
The international symbol of access
Begin to get embedded in the urban fabric of cities and towns across the world
People began to pay attention to the kinds of special building accommodations its basis needs to be inviting for p
People with varying degrees
Ability
And then in 1990
Congress passed the landmark Americans with Disabilities Act
Which President George HW Bush signed into law
Data was modeled on the Civil Rights Act of 90
The law
And I'm running this from the ATA website here
Quote
Prohibits discrimination and guarantees that people with disabilities have the same opportunities as everyone else
Participate in the mainstream of American Life
To enjoy employment opportunities
To purchase goods and services
Interpret dissipate
In state and local government programs and service
And quote
I think it's fair to say
Having a single attractive logo to signify a universal right for access
Helped create an Atmos
What's the built world
Could begin to adapt to new building parameters and regulations as specified
Pretty Ada
In many ways
Adoption of the international accessibility icon
Is a success story
In a simple design
Changing the world for the better
I think the current image
Always has to be lauded for its
Historic import
The form of waves
The form of easy navigation
You know it's historically
Profound I mean it's politically so important
But now you know you're guaranteed when you go out you're going to find one of these
Espaces that's
Reserved
You're able to count on
Accommodation
But this isn't the end of the story
Because it's the logo got absorbed into
The built environment
People with disabilities and their allies started finding it
Kind of like it
The shapes of the body in the body parts on that icon
Art squared off in geometric
And even though it
Does have a head
Had
Dangles from the neck
And the neck is in this kind of
Unnaturally erect
Posture there's not a sense of
Organic shapes of the body in space
That's her hedron by the way
My name is Sara hendren I'm an artist and design researcher in Cambridge Massachusetts
And I think a lot about
Prosthetics Adaptive Technologies
Disability studies and Disability Policy
Sara hendren is also a lecturer at RISD the Rhode Island School of Design
And most importantly for our purposes
Siri is the co-founder of the accessible icon project
This movement
Because that's what I think it has
Become a movement
Is made up of designers
Activist
Artist academic
And Disability Advocates
Old trying to change the conversation about
Disability in a community
Answer for starters the accessible icon project has
Take a name
At the standard blue and white
Wheelchair I
They've created a new icon that they hope will ultimately replace the iso standard
It's still a white
Figure in a wheelchair positioned in a blue field
But the head and body are tilted forward
The arm is angled back as if it's
Propelling you
And the wheel looks like it's in motion
The visible leg is also move forward and re angled so look more active
It doesn't just disappear into
The wheel
It looks modern
I'm asleep
You do a pretty good job picture in it if you imagine the new logo as the old logo
But italicized
Changing an ISO standard isn't easy
A proposal has two
To be submitted and reviewed by isos
Technical committee on graphical symbols
Then it has to be considered by symbols
Experts from around the world
And then finally approved
White Isis member
I talked with Barry Gray
The chairman of the two
Technical committee on graphical symbols
Oh my God I want very gray
He says he's seen the new logo and applauds the designers for the icon
Consignment
But he told me a lot of factors would have to
Taking into account
Before the current symbol could be replaced
Like whether this new icon might be confused with symbols used for wheelchair
So as much good as the current logo has done
300 among others
Text issue with how the logo
Portrays people
Disabilities
It has this a mobile
Talk to it
The figure in the image
Looks like it's waiting to
Pushed around
It's not that there's anything wrong with anyone who experience
What is mobility in that way
It's just that for hendren the implicit message the icons
Is it people with disabilities are helpful
In this new logo Grant a sense of autonomy to the figure in the wheelchair
And there's a clear delineation between where the person starts
And the chair begin
I think what the
Former icon lacked was
There just wasn't any definition of moving forward
You know it was just kind of
Stoic
Whereas this symbol
Shows that the malta Community is moving full-steam ahead
We are all moving
Full steam ahead
Gary Christenson is the mayor of Malden Mass in
The town of about 6
Mm
Diverse residence
Mary Christensen work with a disability advocacy organization
Call Triangle
Replace the old symbol all over Malden
And he is really enthusiastic about it
He wants
To have every
Conceivable
Spot
Here in Malden
Replaced with this
Accessible icon project
As soon as possible to talk to Jeff Gentry
From triangle he would tell you that I've emailed them called them
Texting him
Pigeon carrier
To find out when we can replace every symbol here in the city of Malta
That's how eager I am to
To try and fulfill
This wonderful initiative
At this point in our conversation
The mayor handed the phone over to Jeff Gentry from Triangle Eye Lauren how are you
Together triangle and the mayor's office
The new logo at the
Talbots Distribution Center in Malden
And exarch
Shoes which has a
US headquarters in Newton
Not too far away
People with disabilities
Are no longer accepting separate but equal
Work school life opportunities they're moving forward towards a
Are richer future
And hopefully the icon creates dialogue around that
And I believe that the accessible icon is creating a more inclusive world like we're building here
In Malden when I ask
Pro new signage advocate
It's about how they're expanding its use
They would point to Local 6
Both Jeff Gentry answer hendren from the
Accessible icon project
Referred me to a guy named my name is Brendan Brendan Hildreth
A disability rights
In North Carolina
Hello
My name is Brendan
I am not a machine or robot
Brendan has cerebral palsy and hearing loss and speaks through an augmentative communication device or a talking
We reproduce to hear using an interview transcript
This project is way more than just a picture and assemble to me
The project to me shows that people with disabilities can be active and participate
It makes people understand about the disabilities Rights Movement
Brendan has been working to bring the accessibility sign to his
Downtown New Bern
I did a lot of speaking with television and radio stations locally about the new icon
I have a letter from the state to allow me to use the icon here
I have painted the new icon in several businesses in New Bern
And still have many more to do
People at the North Carolina state level like the new icon
They thanked me for bringing the icon here
Jeff
Brian
And Sarah
As in Jeff Gentry of triangle
And Brian glenney and Sara hendren from the accessible icon proud
Realized how many businesses I am getting to use the new like on
Then they made me Regional director of North Carolina for the icon project
Because I am kicking their butts
In getting the icon out in the world
Sara hendren said she's not interested in what she calls sign washing
Or getting the logo change just to be politically correct
She says this project is a process of
Consciousness-raising quote-unquote
So that each time the sign is officially changed
There's intention around it
And dialogue about
Disability
But a symbol meant to start dialogue and
Spread through Grassroots action is very different than one created to be at Universal
An internationally recognized symbol
There's a lack of clarity as to
Even though the law states that reasonable changes can be made to the symbol as long as it
That clearly displays the wheelchair and indicate sex
Affability
There are still questions about what constitutes
A functional equivalent
New York City had planned to adopt the new logo in all five boroughs
What does legal ambiguity cause them to hold off implementing it
At least for now
I think a lot of people end up buying that old original image because they're nervous
About complying with Ada code and I think what we're trying to do is say look
Functional equivalence
It has a kind of legal set of definitions and Contours
Doesn't think they're going to probably need to be worked out at the state level but
It's not as though functional equivalence means
Willy-nilly personal interpretation it means
As long as it's
Perfectly clear that you're indicating
Access for wheelchair users
You can
Do a different kind of
Version of the icon
All comes back to the question of what we are trying to accomplish through our symbols
Having one unified icon can tell one clear story all over the world
But sometimes stories change
We said earlier that the group behind the original call for an international symbol of Acts
It's called
Rehabilitation International
Well in the 1940s
It was known by another name
The international Society
The welfare of cripples
The meanings and associations that words have
Shift overtime
And sometimes the symbols need to as well
Reno universality
It does have an upside
Especially if you're in Belgrade
And you're about to accidentally
Poison
99% invisible with produces week by Lauren Ober with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman
Special thanks to Pike melonowski
Who help with among other things
Pronouncing designer
Susanna
Kooples name
Whole Foods
I'd like to point out
It's spelled k o e f
Oecd
Whole Foods
I do not hear the D
Send it
I still don't know that doesn't make sense to me at all. That's why you say that
Again
Spanish for you
Cheers
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced out of the offices
Is of arcsin an Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show and likes on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars
Cool. Tumblr.com to really you'll really like
You should take a nap
Do you want to do it the real salad this week go to 99 pei.org search for your favorite episode of 99% invisible
Facebook. Sucker
Sharing is caring 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com