99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Wonder Bread
I'm Roman Mars
When I think about white bread
I usually think of Wonder Bread
And I can picture the Lowe's all lined up on the grocery store shelves in perfect
Cornrows
The red yellow and blue circles on the Wonder Bread label
We're supposed to conjure balloons
Floating away
Taking us somewhere
Somewhere one dress
Somewhere
Better
The first print advertisement for Wonder Bread which actually came out before the bread itself
Stated only that a Wonder was coming
That's Wonderboy Sam Greenspan
In The Runaways and it's time
Wonder Bread Billy was a Wonder
It was the perfect loaf
But now white bread and I just wonder bread but really any brand of industrially produced white bread
It started by food purists as part of the
Problem
The problem being that we don't know where our food comes from and we might be consuming in pure and unhealthy ingredients
The funny thing is
Industrial white bread that evenly sliced
Squishy moist perfectly white and wondrous loaf
Was once the highly design solution
Do that very same problem
You want to go bigger and stronger don't you
A sandwich Deli in 2 slices of Wonder Bread every meal give you eight elements you need
For much of human history has been
One of the most important foods
Our human ancestors 30000 years ago
Had a crude form of bread
Nearly every culture on Earth has some form of bread
Any importance of bread is shall we say
Baked into language
Take for instance the word companion if we take the word companion back to its Latin roots
We can't calm which is with and
Han
Which is bread
A companion is someone that you sit down and you you break bread with
He's the author of the book white bread a social history of the store-bought loaf
It is
Aaron also talks about the word Lord
It comes from a word in Old English
I'm not sure how to pronounce it exactly but I'm paper it looks like last word
HLA Ford
Holford
Flyboard and that men's
The keeper of bread or the person who gives bread
And that's
Striking because it
It tells us the very Act of political rule
Was rapped
Stop in the bread Supply
Plus think of all the ways that bread comes up culturally
Catholics believe that the communion bread transubstantiation into the body of Christ
There's Lord's Prayer Matthew 6:11 give us today our daily bread
The Jewish holiday Passover centers around the preparation of bread
And on and on
In the Middle Ages most people got something like 80% of their calories from Bratz
Fast forward on Millennium or so in the late 19th century
People are still getting about 30% of their calories from bread
That's so much bread that's breaded every meal and some meals that were only bread
For most of our long history with bread
Bb8 was made in our homes
Eventually we had small bakery is that
Buy bread for more people
But they weren't exactly a picture of artisanal
Purity and often Underground
Usually with terrible working conditions
You never knew when the baker would cut costs by cutting the dough with sawdust or some other horrible additives
During the time we're talking about the late eighteen hundreds early nineteen hundreds
There was a lot of foodborne illness
Colorado typhus
A lot of Americans were starting to fear their food
And for good reason
You were food
Could kill you
Middle and upper-class
White
Native-born Americans
Period go through this
Kind of freaked out
About
Safety
Beer bread
And you see newspaper headlines
During this time screaming
Things like that
And and people were really freaked out
Every city was holding major
Earrings on
On the bread question
The neighborhood Bakery
Pretty that we romanticize
Today
Was the Specter of
Fear and Terror
Until people started getting really interested in where their food came from
Kind of like people are doing right now
Knowing where their food came from mint actively avoiding
Locally baked bread
Factory bread the thinking went
Was born not of unclean hands in an underground furnace
Put in a modern light-filled
Palace of Industry
These palaces of Industry with
Supply bread to the masses
And it spread
Woody White
Bread is a delicious food
Its flavor blends perfectly with other food
White flour and white bread aren't recent technological innovations in and of themselves they've been around for millennia
Technically speaking white flour is whole wheat flour with the bran and The Germ from the wheat kernel sitting out
Industrial Bakers choice white bread as their Flagship bread
White was a marker of purity
And cleanliness
And if this sediment sounds vaguely racist you well the racism
More than that
Dr. Woods Hutch
Noted Health columnist
I'm in a new syndicated columnist in newspaper
Argued that
Only white bread
Which fortify
The white race
To do the things that had to do and go out in
Conquer other
And if that's not revolting enough food reformers of the day
I'm referring to the weight loss as a Chase
Loaf
And the dark Leviathan
Filed
A real Vector for a Contagion
That was mostly the meat and dairy Supply
Which is why Aaron bobrow strain argues that this fear over the safety of bread
Wasn't actually about bread
What I started to realize was
That is heavy
Become
Impossible in
And native-born middle and upper-class whites
Mine
Separate spheres about bread safety
From there
Fears about
Particularly The New Southern and
Eastern European immigrants
Who's supposedly dirty and
Diseased
Hands we're touching bread
In neighborhood Bakery basically Aaron believes that our attraction to white bread came from real fears about food contagious
They got mixed up unfairly with
Fears about immigrants
It was a shining White
Clean
Modern Marvels
Untouched by human hands
That was the antithesis of that scary supposed to be dirty and disease
Product of immigration
You knew it was free of dirt and other contaminants
Which you might fear from your local bakery
Whiteness was us in proof of purity
That logic is kind of flood because
Lots of the adulterants
Chalk
Alan the bleach white love just needed one more thing before I could fully and body are need for you
It needed
To be sliced
Which brings us to a summer day
In 1928
Let's say
July 7-9
On that day it was July 7th I checked
In the town of Chillicothe Missouri people have gathered at 1st and Elm Street
Treats and they were lined up around
On the Block I don't know if their lines down the block those weren't describe but but people were certainly eager to see this however they were
Gathered
People were there to witness the
The Advent of
Packaged
Pre sliced bread
When reporter in Chillicothe Missouri
Spoke of
Housewives who were visiting this Bakery to see the slice bread how they had
To relive enthusiasm
Awestruck by this perfectly sliced bread it was a small edible
Vision of progress
And the future
People like sliced bread so much I can't overstate how much they loved it and how quickly it caught on was the best thing
Another thing that was good
Industrial Baker's had the hype
They had the sense of moral mission
And they had the design parameters
White bread in streamline loves
With the uniform slices
But the science of industrializing and
Mass producing bread
Was still a little wacky
Bread after all
Is the product of microorganisms going through biological
Prophecies
When is a function of time and temperature and a lot of other variables
That was one of the last major Foods
How to get Industrial
Precisely
Because of how complex it is to make
Uniformly
The assembly process was
Really different than say
Making a car
Imagine if Henry Ford
Every time he wanted to make a
Car had to worry about the fact that
Is Parts might grow or Shrink the
Depending on the temperature and humidity that day
Bad a gust of air coming through the factory might cause his
Cardiff
These are the kind of biological
Questions that early industrial Baker
Had to figure out
And so from the 1920s and 30s on Word
Industrial baker's rack
Constantly tinkering
What the design of white bread
They cut the time it took
For the bread to rise by adding sugar
The temperature
The Anamosa fire
To allow those water in
Fatted mixed together better
Getting white bread its height
And more even grain
That also got rid of owls
Because wondersoft with Bread is made from bat or not go it has no holes under soft whip
Eventually vitamins were added and sold to the public as a means of making Hardy young men would be fit to fight in the
Do slices of Wonder Bread every meal give you as much phosphorus for cell metabolism
As much iron for red blood as free Lamb Chop
As much niacin for mental health at 6 sardines as much energy has two glasses of milk
Little by little
Terry's factories created their own recipe
Innovations for industrial white bread
And all of that came to a head in 1952
In Rockford Illinois
The USDA
In
Cooperation with
Key figures of the industrial baking world put together a a multi-year project
That I kind of
Jokingly referred to as the Manhattan Project of bread
The multi-year panoramic investigation of bread and bread eating habits
And the ultimate goal of the project
West you design the perfect loaf of white bread
Involves focus groups market research
Double blind taste test
The end product of the so-called Manhattan Project of bread
Was a white bread two and a half
Times as sweet as the average loaf available at the
The time
40% fluffy
Fear 2
The fluffier the manufacturers made the bread the more people wanted to buy it even though the Rockford research
Also showed that they didn't really like it
He just couldn't resist the fluff
Consumers are
Choosing the fluffier bread but not
Secretly liking its text
But yet they were eating it in large quantities
He's about a pound and a half per person per week
Not too long after the Rockford City closes shop
White bread goes through an identity crisis
Where was once a
Fielded symbol of progress
White bread began to get used as an epithet
Meaning of Stuffy conservative Square white Suburban in 1970 when Richard Pryor
Enough it storms off the stage of his popular show at the Aladdin Theater in Las Vegas saying
He's absolutely done
Which is white bread humor
From that point forward
Counterculture movement
Used white bread as an emblem of the established
The silent majority
Richard Nixon's America
The band by the 1980s
1990s
The meaning starts to bifurcate
It also starts to take on
The significance of white trash
I'm so white bread starts to
Stand in for
Poor white person
Who's making supposedly irresponsible decisions about diet
About their life
Travis fascinated by the way that white bread could mean
Essentially the opposite of it
South Suburban and rural
If there's one lesson from Aaron bobrow strains research
Debate over which
Kind of bread to eat
White or wheat
It's not new
Thousands of years
In Plato's Republic
Play-Doh sets up this kind of
Debate
About weather
The ideal Palace
The ideal Society or city state
Should
Function on a diet of
Soul drain gruel
Associated with Rural Life
Or
Citified White
Bread cake
But what's most interesting about these days in history
Isn't there often about everything
Except bread
Even back then it was really not about
The healthiness of bread so much as it was about
Anxieties about weather
The Athens was losing moral virtue because it was becoming less connected to the land
Receive that
Debates about white bread and brown bread get tied up into large questions about what do people think about
Progress what do people think about industrialization
Class
Hierarchy
About whether or not we keep white bread or brown bread
It's usually about much larger questions
We can learn
Something about her our own Society our own anxieties and aspirations by looking at first debates about what counts as
Is good bread
99% invisible with produces week by Sam Greenspan
With Katie mingle Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Benjamin Walker's Theory of Everything
Benjamin's most recent episode
We tell the story of how I Benjamin and I first met 14 years ago and it started immediately
Aspiring to make something like we've made and why do Topia today a place where the most creative video maker
Movies directly in the most curious and engage listeners
We are brothers 91.7 local public radio kalw
Arcsin in Architecture Firm in beautiful downtown Ray Cat Country Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
You follow along this show on Facebook Twitter and Tumblr and everything you ever need to know about the show you can find
Find out on 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com