99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network and LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And help you target your customers with precision
Counselor job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Alright,
About 10 miles south of San Francisco toward the airport
There's a town
Coldcalm
I have never been to, before but it's cool you can take the train right here
Mets producer Avery trufelman
Oh my God right behind the train station
Already
Is big
Rolling
Green Hills
Shepherd
With
Tombstone
73% of the land in coma
Is covered
With graveyard
Oh
Rose and Rose
Big gravestones
There are 17 full size cemeteries together in one town
18 if you include that simatai
This is
Huge
It is a city of the Dead
What's known as a necropsy
We claim to be the only necropolis
And the United States anyway the only city
That is
Primarily dedicated to
To cemetery
This is Maureen O'Connor
President of the Colma historical Association
It doesn't mean that there are a lot of cities that don't have cemeteries within their boundaries but nothing of the concentration
That we have
And, truly looks like a sprawling City
A landscape of mausoleums and monuments in
Towers and tombstones
The glint in the Sun
For as far as the eye can see
But it is eerily quiet
You're the dead outnumber the living thousand to one
We have 1600 living
Citizen
And we have about one and a half million
Residents who live underground
Or in Mazatlan
Maureen talks about her dead Neighbors
Everliving neighbors with
The same vocabulary
Like when she referred to John Daly
The long deceased Dairy mag
John Daly
For him Daly City is named one of our neighbors
She's a lot of famous neighbor
Like Joe DiMaggio
And Levi Strauss of Levi jeans
Tina Turner's dog is in the Pet Sematary
They're all around and Maureen's house is literally sandwich
Between two
Cemeteries
I live across from the Italian Cemetery
And the front of my house and then the back of my backyard borders with Japanese
And then I have to human Neighbors on east and west
The official Town motto of coma in
It's great to be alive
In, it's great to be alive
Coma had many lives
Before it became
The modern necropolis
Before it was even called coma
In the 1800's it was rich farmland
The cut all the moisture off the bay
And most of the vegetables
San Francisco work from there
Another point it was known mostly for hog farming and at another point it was known for cultivating flowers
Meanwhile a few miles north in San Francisco proper people were pouring in because of the gold rush
The population was booming
And so was the death ray
Well certainly there was an enormous amount of death at that time and just because
There were no antibiotics people died of stuff that
You wouldn't even think of dying of now
San Francisco Cemetery started
Develop
And starting in 1887
Religious groups and organizations began
One by one
To buy plots of land south of the city
To create new burial grounds
Which eventually covered over to square miles
In 1924 the cemetery Scott together they decided to incorporate
Is 2.2 square miles officially became a town
Pet Sematary town
Call Mondale
Which in 1941 would be renamed
Coma
And all of this was happening in the context of a much bigger change
American burial practices
For a long time the dead used to be buried in little squares are churchyards on Dusky plots in the middle
Motown
Graves were all around it was no big deal
Municipal burying-ground we're right downtown and they were relatively small crowded places
With
Really nothing much by way of
Landscape design they were just
Beyond the lands surrounding
A church
This is Keith Wagner
Professor of architectural history at the University of Oregon
And in his book cemeteries he talks about how these tiny plane graveyard where hubs of activity
You might find the
Plumber or a bricklayer or a carpenter
Seated at a cemetery waiting for someone to come along and
Poem
Farmers would graze their cows and cemeteries because many people believe that the grass grown in churchyards
Burial ground
Who's richer in made for sweeter milk
Prostitutes even would sometimes be found in
Burial ground so these were going to open public spaces
In towns and cities
Many of which didn't have much by way of alternative
In public spaces
But by the 1820s and 30s
Couple things happen that change
How barrels work
Firstly
Is a series outbreak
Disease and cities were hit with waves
Of typhoid
Cholera and yellow fever and it was just unsanitary
How to keep the deceased so close to the living
Also cities were growing in downtown real estate was becoming more volume
Graduate in the United States
Land of the living in the Land of the Dead begin
To separate
Gravesites ended up
Far away from the city
This model of a rural burial
Separate from the city
Took off in America in the 1830s
When Mount Auburn Cemetery
Open outside of Cambridge Massachusetts
Walmart Auburn was
What was called and what is still called a rural cemetery
What that meant was that it wasn't
Smack dab in the center of a town
Also it was one of the first cemeteries to
Actually be called a cemetery
At all
Previously they'd been called
You're burying grounds are burial grounds or churchyard
Cemetery was a Greek word meaning sleeping chamber
And just that word Cemetery
So romantic and euphemistic
Death had once been deeply enmeshed in everyday life
Americans had home funerals in their front parlor
Encounter modest tombstones daily and their Town squares
Mount Auburn Mayberry something removed from normal existence
Rural Cemetery
Stately
They look
Like they were a world apart
Mount Auburn was
Was and still is
Beautiful
With Emerald grassy Hills in manicured hedges
There are statues of weeping angels in Egyptian obelisk
All connected with winding walking path
So it was much more Artful
Landscape modeled on the English garden tradition of
Picturesque landscapes
As opposed to just simply a flat piece of ground with a bunch of stones
In a lined up with in it
This new style Mark the beginning of the rural cemetery movement in America
It would go on to influence the design of
Public spaces more broadly
Because this is at a time when a lot of cities didn't have
Public parks or botanical gardens or museums
These
Cemeteries none
Served as the model
For some of our nation's first public parks
Such as Central Park in New York which followed that
Picturesque Garden approach that
Was first seen in our cemeteries it was later picked up for
College campuses Suburban subdivisions
Many other applications
The cemeteries in Colma where directly inspired by the Mount Auburn model as well
They were places to go to have picnics and amble around and get away from the smog and soot of neighboring same
San Francisco
If the city of the living was designed for Speed and efficiency in business the City of the Dead was instead
Dead understood as a kind of quiet
Peaceful Arcadia
A kind of
Evocation of paradise or Heaven on Earth where one would take ones
Eternal reward
Oh and about that eternity thing
That's very
American
Americans
Have a
Rather distinct practice of holding to a burial in perpetuity
You don't find burial in perpetuity in that many other places
Buy burial in perpetuity means
Plot of land
That is yours forever and ever until the end of
Which is different than in say Argentina or France or Italy or any number of other countries around the world
We're families of the deceased typically lease
A burial plot
It could be for 5 or 10 years to a hundred years
And
If the family doesn't maintain that lease then
The Remains are
Jug up
And our disinterred and
What is left is often
Burned
The family is
Given the ashes in the plots are used for new burials
This almost never happens in the United
American cemeteries would rather double up on Berry
Or do above ground burials then
Dig up her man
That's just taboo
And that's why it was so strange in the early 20th century
When almost all of San Francisco's dad
Were dug up and evicted
To make room
For the living
Which brings us back
The graveyards of Colma
What happened in 1900
Was that the Board of Supervisors of the County of San Francisco decided that they did not want
Want any
Expansion of the cemeteries were already in San Fran
That's Maureen O'Connor again of the Kona Historical Society
So the legislation wasn't there would be no new burials and Sam
San Francisco
And that went into effect in
Sono new burial
Not meant the existing cemeteries didn't have a reliable source of Revenue
I'm so the cemeteries fell into disrepair and became these tiny wastelands for vagabond
Wells and Grave robbers
And also they were gross
So in 1914
Another ordinance kick them out
They passed legislation that said
Not only no new burials but these cemeteries just look off all they thought they were disease-ridden
So the city said
The bodies have to be disinterred and moved
From 1937 into the 1940s most of the bodies from San Francisco were dug up and moved Tacoma
Roughly 150000 bodies in total
To move a body with a headstone
Cost the family $10
If there was no money
Unknown X
The bodies were put into mask
Musgraves
In coma
But like respectful ones
Cuz when you think of mass grave you off
I think I'm a sex
Execution
And it was not that kind of
I was a much gentler
Respectful process
The deceased
In the mass Graves
We're blessed and memorialized and accounted for in Wrecker
And their headstones
Where we used as building material
Well
The mass grave headstones ended up along Ocean Beach
You'll see a lot of headstones out
No
Yes
They were used
To keep from erosion
If you find yourself in Buena Vista Park in the heart of San Francisco
Look at the pavestones letting the trails and the street gutters
And you'll see that a lot of them are Cemetery headstone
These headstones sometimes faded fragments of them
Sometimes completely intact
All over the city
Hiding in plain sight
And they are the closest contact most San franciscans have with Cemetery
There are only two graveyard left in the entire city
Death of the fact of life most Urban dwellers don't
See I don't think about
Where is Downing, Maureen confronts her mortality every time she looks at her window
I looked out on the cemeteries
And I think
You know these people are resting in peace and sometimes I feel overwhelmed by all the things that I have to do
But the day that I wake up that I don't have anything to do I'm probably going to be moving into
To a cemetery
Most people aren't sandwiched between two cemeteries and we don't really think about the question of what will happen
Our bodies after we die
I asked
The question and very often people are at like a little taken aback either they haven't
Thought about it are they
No I haven't made any plans
I certainly haven't made plans
Chances are you haven't either
I've no idea what will happen to my body after I die
What kind of unusual on the course of history
It was indeed the case that
Yes people
Largely knew where they were buried
Professor Keith egner says that
Prior to the Civil War Americans assumed they'd end up in their family plots
Counter-charge
And other parents and children would be buried there
To that is no longer the case
We move you know from job to job from town to town
We frequently encourage our children to and I'll go out and explore the world and we can. We don't really know where we're going to be
The ending up
Which is why today many people have opted not to be buried at all
Cremation has become increasingly popular
Again to our own time and this brought with it
A number of
New building types
Crematoria
But also
The public mausoleums
Where you have a small box containing an urn with ashes
But with cremation
You don't need a connection to one place
I should don't have to stay displayed in a columbarium or mausoleum
They can be scattered anywhere you've ever lived
Or wanted to live
If your family and friends live all over the world they can
Each have a part of you
And there are these services that you can order where ashes can be compressed into a diamond
And wander around someone's neck or turned into a hand blown glass paperweight
So there's
A kind of brake I think on going
Over the course of the last hundred years or more
In which
People were
Perhaps much more rooted to the land
Both in life and especially
Death
By virtue of
Burial and
Knowing where they were going to be buried
Then we are now
San Francisco's 19 century residents could never have guessed that they'd be evicted and relocated miles away
Away from their Hometown to a city of the Dead
Their headstones strewn about the
Parks and beaches
Of the city
Of the living
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman with Lani Hall Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman Mars
Technical production in mixed spice refusive with music by genre
Katie mingle is our senior editor Kurt Kolstad is the digital director and Taryn Mazza is moving to the Bay Area
Social things this week to Ashley Borman and Marcy Russell at the Chapel of the Chimes in Oakland
This episode was inspired in part by our friends at kuow in Seattle they have a new podcast called terrestrial where he
Each episode explores
A personal question to the lens of climate change in the environment
Ashley Ahearn the host of the show
The whole episode about what we should do with our bodies when we die
In light of our changing landscape
Miche features this
Katrina Spade
My name is Katrina spade and and the founder and director of the urban death project
Katrina's designed what she called a recomposition center
A facility where it would be possible to compost multiple human body
I realize this is pretty out there for a lot of
I know the Catholic side of my family would probably freak
Listen to the way she envisions one of these Center
Remember it doesn't exist yet
This is just how she imagined
Can you open the doors to the recomposition center the first thing you see
Is this three-story concrete
Form it ends you can see the top of it
And wrapping around that core
Is a series of ramps
That's what a commander
Rest of the concept of the recomposition center and some other ideas about the future of death
Check out the full episode when it comes out next Tuesday that's masic
16th but for right now
You can just go subscribe
Again that show is called terrestrial
Check it out
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On Radio Road
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa Alexa is talking to me and my wife
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad to take laxatives
Does routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars and the show at 99
NTI org
Run Instagram Tumblr and have a nice subreddit to
But we release at least two articles about design and architecture there just like the episodes but you know for reading
On our website
99 PI
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com