99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
About an hour east of Oakland the town of Livermore California
Hanging in the garage a fire station number 6
There's a small pear-shaped light bulb
The light is on
Right now it's glowing
And it's been blowing
Just a couple of momentary interruptions
For 113 years
Oh there it is
Looking at the longest burning
Longest continuously burning light bulb
In the world in the Guinness Book of World Records
And was installed in 1901
We send our producer Katie mingle out there to see the bulb which is a genuine heirloom from the dawn of electric illumination
Don't buy one of its pioneers
A guy named out of Chalet
Probably when you think about the beginning of electric light Hugo Amelia Thomas Edison
That's John welham he's a writer from San Francisco he wrote a piece about the Livermore Light Bulb for pop-up magazine earlier
What is here but the age of electric light didn't just switch on
All at once you had
Tinkers
Trying to come up with better designs trying to iterate and innovate something that would burn longer or maybe brighter
Where that would cost less
Socialite was one of these guys
It was a great time of invention and innovation
All Over America light bulbs were going off over people's heads
And some of those light bulbs were being turned into actual light bulbs
Take a big light bulb back the kind you'd see on a theater Marquee
And it would be one bulb of his own design in the rest of the bulbs from competing Brands then shall they would start slow
Slowly dialing up the power and one by one the competitors bulb all explode
Chalets would be the last one Shining
One of those tenacious light bulbs made it all the way to Livermore California
Its origin was in 1901 when a shop owner
Donated it
To the town's volunteer fire department they were called the fire boys
In those days
And with the ball hanging in their Firehouse this meant they could now
Gather up all their equipment
Place a call about a fire came in
In the middle of the night in the dark
In those Dark Ages there were no fire engines firefighters used hose carts pulled by horses
Here's Tom bramel former deputy fire chief in Livermore
This type of him is from a documentary about the bulb called Century of light
The volunteers Atwood
Got a ride to a twin incident they would come to the station there
Get there there
Postcard
Hitch up the horses
Look for all of the equipment that they were looking for but this light
Lit up the hose cart room so that I could have sent without getting injured falling over and
So the light bulb has very significant function
In 1906
The fire station boob just down the street the light bulb on at that point for 5 years
Bed no idea how long it will last
It was their only lightbulb so course they brought it along
It seems like people just
Stop thinking about the bulb after a while
There wasn't really an obvious way to shut it off
The way that had been wired
But it must have just been dim and unobtrusive enough that no one really
Try too hard
Eventually the old-fashioned hose guards were replaced with fire trucks
The bulb hung between the firehouses to garage doors
And the firefighters were like aware of it
I didn't think much about it
The bald hung down
Probably
Countdown app
A pretty good distance from the ceiling in a long cord that act
Massachusetts on today the same
The same chord
But it was
Pretty sure it was low enough that you could walk by
To reach open
Tabitha Bolton
Marcus wingback
As time went on
Would throw Nerf balls
In 1971 the first full-time chief of the Livermore fire department a guy named Jack Barrett got curious about the light bulb
Any as a local newspaper reporter to look into the bulbs history
The resulting article got resident of Livermore talking about the bulb
The Pride
Livermore to own little antiquity
The firefighters stop throwing Nerf balls at it
Five years later when the fire department
Was moving into a new building
They obviously knew that they they couldn't leave the bulb behind and if I cheat buried insisted that they take it with them
On March
XXXI
1970s
It was the day that we moved
The light bulb
From 2360
C5 first
Out here on East Avenue to this
Station
That's only the Omens he was the former division chief of the Livermore fire department this interview was recorded for the century
Reapply documentary released in 2011
March 3rd
31st of 70
Will always
Special date
The light bulb was escorted with red lights and siren
We had a special box
Built
Not only that
But the box was painted red
Which even made it more special
When they got the light bulb to the new station
The electrician set it up so that the light bulb could be screwed in immediately
Climbed up the ladder with the light bulb
Screwed up the wires together so that everything would go on
Anne Frank
And made the connection
The light bulb didn't come on
And we
Gas
Oh my gosh oh my goodness what did we do this world famous light bulb
And now it's
Gone
But then electrician jiggled somewheres around
The light came back on
Everybody made a big sigh
Meanwhile as a lightbulb is becoming more more thing as it was impossible for people not to start wondering about what it was made of and how it could
Still possibly be working
The obvious way to solve the mystery
Would be the crack of light bulb open and examine it but obviously no one wanted to do that it was just too precious
I am Deborah Katz
I'm a physics professor at the US Naval Academy in Annapolis Maryland
Dr. Katz did some tests on similar light bulbs
Light bulbs made by the same company in the same time.
She measured the thickness of the bulbs filament which is that tiny piece of wire in the bulb that can break really easily
And I did that using a laser so I didn't have to break the bulb
To get in there
She figured out that the filament
In the Livermore Bob was 8 times thicker than a regular bulb
And made from carbon instead of tungsten
What I figured out just
Don't tell me
Why the filament shouldn't have bro
Broken by now
That's Tuff
Pretty incredible I think it still is a mess
Stree what she does know is that in 1924 a bunch of light bulb companies got together and formed a cartel
Called Phoebus
The goal of the cartel was for all the light bulb companies that stop making bulbs that lasted so long
So that everyone can sell more light bulbs
Members of the cartel were actually charged fines if their bulb is burned for too many hours
And in two years the company
Light bulbs went from lasting 2500 hours
Delta 1500 hours
By the 1940s
They actually made their goal of
Bulbs that only last
2000 hours
The Shelby company which manufactured Chili's ball pad already gone out of business by the time the Phoebus cartel had been formed
But I'd like to think that they wouldn't have been involved with that nonsense
I think that I think they were trying to make a quality product rather than a product
With built-in obsolescence
And a quality product it was of course the Bold was just hanging there and continuing the glow
Turn away at story was taking on this air of magical realism
In 2001 a group of locals decided Livermore ought to have a hundredth birthday party for the light bulb
They formed the Centennial bulb committee and started planning what they thought would be a small get-together at
The firehouse that June Indian 600 people showed up
Ned cake and
The rock bands playing in
Kids dancing on the top of the fire truck
Committee members get live interviews to Katie Couric in CNN
By then responsibility for the party was the first fireman become interested in
To one of the firefighters who served under him Lynn Owens
You heard from them earlier
One of the younger guys in the checking their footballs at the light bulb
I'll be by this point by the time the Bold turn the hundred he was already a retired division chief he was grinning Asian guy with
These tiny glasses in it
Bruce Lee White mustache
Owens love the ball
Any love to Proclaim is love
Light bulb
That light bulb has
Has been doing the
Night
Teen
They was like he was talking about the lightbulb the way James Earl Jones with talk about baseball at the end of Field of Dreams
Reminders
More than once
I should not tell a lot of people end up talking about the lightbulb though
People write letters to the committee
And they say things like the light bulb gives them hope
Or they call it quote a reassuring reminder of faithfulness and service in a letter President George W bush
Bush called the lightbulb quote
An enduring symbol of the American Spirit of invention in quote
For a lot of people at all so ironically symbolizes another great American invention
Planned obsolescence
I like the label because
It's this little speck of continuity you know it's something that started more than a century ago
And it keeps going so it sort of connects us to that time
You can almost imagine it like these this little Amber of a campfire that was lit back then
How many still going
And it kind of in the same way
If you trace that history you see these waves of people coming together around that fire and then slowly leaving the picture and new ones coming in
The lightbulb outlive Jack bear the first fire chief who became curious about it and Lynn Owens it's most of
Go to the caretaker
Chalets lightbulb has seen generations of firefighters come and go through Livermore
10 mm one right around the time of the party
The Centennial bulb committee also set up a webcam
I'm in front of the light bulb
The camera takes a picture of the bulb every 30 seconds that people all over the world can make sure that it's still on
The guy who maintains the camera is named Steve Bunn
And he told me he's already had to replace
The supposedly high-tech webcam
2 times because the light bulb has outlasted both of those devices
The Bulb Has Its Own standby generator something in accurately named the uninterruptible power supply it's on
Doubt suddenly in the middle of the night in May of 2013
And when it did
The light bulb went dark
Steve told me that
When it happened
People around the world who happened to be watching the webcam at that point saw the bull blink out
And started calling or emailing him
Panic
You know we're just in disbelief
The bulb was out for 9 hours and 42 minutes before someone was finally able to get over to the firehouse and Rec
Make up an extension cord
What was turn back on Steve side
Everyone swore
It look brighter
99% invisible would produce this week by John Llewellyn and Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me
Roman Mars special thanks to Christopher lips who allowed us to use audio from his film Centre of light you can find a link to the phone
On our website
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw at San Francisco and produce out of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm located in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
But stay safe out there everyone
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Voice technology tok
To us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God. Info
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
It's a private family goes to wherever you get
Podcast and find out why they say
Every house is on
You can buy 99percentinvisible and like us on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars everyone's as killer
Tumblr for us for links and pictures and list of songs and all the back episodes go to 990i
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com