99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On the border of Virginia and North Carolina near the Eastern Shoreline
Stretches a Great Dismal Swamp
The Great Dismal Swamp actually
That's the name British colonists had given it by the early 1700s
The swamp covers about 190 square miles today
But at its peak before parts of it for drained and developed
It was around ten times bigger
Spanning roughly 2000 square miles of Virginia and North Carolina
That's our own should refuse
And it's understandable why people called The Swamp dismal
Temperatures can reach over a hundred degrees it's humid and Soggy filled with
Thorns and
Tickets
Oh yeah
Earthquake this morning
They named it
I think someone
Appropriately
That's Eric Shepherd
He leaves in Carrollton Virginia and he runs a company that leads tours to the great schism
Which is teeming with all sorts of dangerous and unpleasant wildlife
You still have black bear
And some of the
Poisonous snakes
Yellow flies and mosquitoes I mean
You still have the hazard
Bear in the swamp
And even if you go in with a compass and a map
It's easy to get lost
But hundreds of years ago
Before the Civil War
The dangers of the swamp and it's seeming impenetrability actually attracted a lot
Including one of shepherds ancestors
Who was enslaved in the
I've read information that
Approximately 50000
Escape
Africans with through and or lived
In the Dismal Swamp that's a lot of people to come through
Despite all its predators and bugs all its thorns and Vine
Alex dismalness and small penis
This land was home to generations of people
It was the site of one of the most remarkable and least told stories of resistance to slavery in the United States
African American
Set up community
And
They work
Protected there but they were also in in the state of
Empowerment that they were not going to let anybody come
They are and move them out of their community in that swamp
References to the Great Dismal Swamp
In the escaped slaves who settled there
Started appearing in newspapers and other sources in the 1700s
But archaeologists have found evidence that people were living in the swamp long before that
When you look at 1607 all the way to about 1660
I believe that the major
Group of people that were coming into that swamp
Interior indigenous Tamara
That's Professor Dan Sayre
And historical archaeologists and American University and a leading expert on the Great Dismal Swamp
Singer says that these indigenous Americans
We're seeking Refuge from European settlers
Who started building colonies
Down the eastern coast of America
Escallonia some sort of expanded intensified in the landscape development of the ranches in the farms at
The plantations and all the stuff to her Serta familiar with that swamp
It was a sort of the sun team
Place
Then around 1700 or so
The demographics of the swamp started to shift
By that time slavery was widespread in the American colonies
And why did enslaved people escaped
The swamp was an obvious place to hide out
News of the swamp probably spread quietly
Through word-of-mouth
Probably an underground city of Grapevine
That people learn this when they were trustworthy enough they learn the information about to go into the swamp and then fine
Resistance community
Escaped slaves who found refuge in the swamp
Came to be known as maroon
From the Spanish word Cimarron
Meaning wild or Untamed
Unlike some other runaways who headed to Northern cities
Maroons lived in the wilderness
And difficult to reach
Places
Herman to build their own communities
What the forces of nature and Landscape
Serving as a buffer between their new lives
And the society
That enslaved
Thousands of African-Americans who totally
Created their own world in successfully gave the bird
As it were
Right
Do that outside world
Had that capitalistic world that enslaving world
Sayers has been ears going into the swamp
And surveying
Quite a journey for participate
Project
The whole right there
This tape is from a short film about the Dismal Swamp
Cold landscape of power
By Nina Shapiro perl
Overtime
Sears has come to love this dismal Terrain
It's all just a wonderful thing that to walk around up there in the
In the thick of it
And out there in the thick of it
Emerging from the dark brown water
I'll send you come upon a little plot of dry ground
Islands
And the other pretty good size and medications like 20 30 40 acres and they just sort of sporadically pop-up
It was on these islands that maroon communities form
Likely a few dozen people on each one
Some mingling and trade happening between the islands that were close together
And based on archaeological evidence
Sayers has pieced together an idea of what their lives might have looked
The shelter themselves The Maroons build elevated cabin but they lifted above the moist ground using wooden post
Sayers knows this because the wood that they used to build the structures
Is change the color of the soil
So the post Robson Place and it looks much darker contrasting with that usually lighter soil around
And the Maroons grew food to support themselves
They probably almost certain
Cultivated for a community
Grain rice fields on the swamp
I think they did Community labor Camino labor like that you're Gathering Donnelly what they eat on a daily basis
Probably some of the Surplus
Storefront
Winter in hard times
But forming this picture of life in the swamp hasn't been easy
Because most evidence of The Maroons has long vanished all the organic stuff
The Creator
The other trees would plant materials whatever that's all along Route of the way so we enforce Lee lost with probably is about
90% or more would they used on a daily basis
Sarah says that normally at other sites from this. You'd find a bunch of mass-produced goods
Like glass containers and lead shot
Tobacco pipes
But there's not much of that stuff in the swamp
The dearth of these good speaks to how self-sufficient the Maroons were
There wasn't much from the outside world
Coming in
It's like okay our goal is to settle the swamp in this is our world
Instead of a bunch of intact artifact
Sears and his team have found
Tiny bit
Bits and pieces of Old Stone tools
Which Maroons found or inherited from previous Native American and habit
At one excavation site for example
They found
5000 such artifacts
And even though that's
Sounds like a lot
Say or says he can fit them all into a shoebox
Sayers research suggests that at its peak
Come around 1750
Day two right before the Civil War
The Dismal Swamp was home to thousands of self-sufficient maroons
And it also served
Weather stopping
Four other escaped slaves who were fleeing North
On the Underground Railroad
But like most maroon communities
It was under constant threat
Discovery
The Great Dismal Swamp is not the only example of a maroon settlement
Far from it
Wherever slavery exist
There were runaways who escaped
To live in the wilderness
That means there were Maroons in the British pound
In Spanish and Portuguese colonies and then
In the newly-independent countries and states that those colonies gave birth to
In some cases Maroons clashed with Colonial forces
Like in Jamaica
Where they fought Wars against the British
And negotiated treaties
To stay in their community
In fact there's a settlement in Jamaica where descendants of Maroons still there
A place called Mooretown
Tucked away high in the country's Eastern Mountain
Any us
Maroon communities existed
All across
The South and the North
And even in Western Sky
My Texas
Homestay in the world
Ingalls Homestead
This is from an interview with a former slave named Laura Smalley
It was recorded in 1941
Talks about what it was like growing up and working on a plantation in Belleville
The interviewer ask
What are the slaves of try to slip away.
And she replies
Now I hit mama said when she was a girl
Did they did Wonder Woman run off and every night she sleep home
Somebody have with something to eat
And she get that vittles
In going back in the woods
Going back stay in the woods
Did once this man stated which along
Can you use heroin and blowing like a dog
Jewish Dating Rules
Estate in the woods
You couldn't get him out
Stay in the world
All the Gold in me
Every maroon Community across the country was unique
Submarines lived in the woods
It's like a woman and man described by Smalley
Others lived in the mountains
Swamp
Some even lived in underground shelter
That they dug out in Wild areas near Plantation
Sow indoors
Little caves of dance as they sometimes
Call them as well you sometimes not a real house
Summit furniture
Some
Stove
This is Dr Sylvian do you
A historian of the African diaspora and author of slavery's Exile
The story of the American maroons
She says that these Subterranean maroon shelters
Brockton ingeniously constructed
Some Timber supported roof
Complete with trap doors that hit all traces of their presence
That trap
Which Bob turned on the outside at the camouflage to the point that it would be invisible but it would also be
Some shelters even had systems of wooden pipes that transported the stove smoke away from the maroons.
So it wouldn't go away their location
Prodigy youth is found that most Maroons tended to live in one of two types of places
Each with its own advantage
Some resided on the borders of Plantation
Where the family and friends
And so they would go back at night it'll just
To be able to get news and also.
Gather intelligence
Are the Bruins chose to live more removed from civilization
In the Hinterlands
The
Hinterland
The man
Future
Is that the West security they were just recalled
To access
But wherever they were
Maroons all had something in common
They wanted Freedom yes but
Even more
They wanted
Metronomy
A kind of control over their lives that wouldn't be possible even as free black
People in the North
The Maroons West self-ruled
Weather Argentina drawings of family resort community
They sell
Safe
In the woods
And the swamps even though it was a hard life
Food of danger
But they sell
Safer amount Educators data Mall
White people
In the late 1700s white people were rapidly becoming a greater threat than the reptiles of the Great Dismal Swamp
As more and more Europeans arrived in the area
Andrew scares
And more volume
Wealthy colonists all Economic Opportunity
In developing the swamp
In 1763
A young George Washington yeah that George Washington
And his brother John started a company with the goal of saving and proving and
Draining the land
George Washington
The Originals
Swamp drainer
Eventually their company and others would create a network of canals
So that boats could go into the swan
Of course they use slave labor for all of the
Dear Stan sayres again
We see suddenly a introduction of a whole new large group of people enslaved workers right
For brought in by these companies to help me get in transforming the swamp
By the early 1800s
Tract of land has been cleared of trees
And parts of the once impenetrable region have been opened up to new people
And Industry
But remember this one
Still huge
If Maroons didn't want to engage with that encroaching world
They can still find places removed from the industries presents
Even as that presents became more permanent
Timber Company set up encampments in the swamp for enslaved workers
Score sent in to cut down trees
They turning that Lumber into shingles
And ship them all over the region
Which brings us back to Eric Sheppard the tour guide we heard from at the beginning of the story
Whose ancestors spent time in the swamp
I believe he was
Migrate
Great-grandfather
Uncle
His name was Moses Grandy
And he was enslaved down in Camden County North Carolina born in 1786
Randy was a skilled boat captain
And his talents were highly sought-after in the canals of the Great Dismal Swamp
He was a
Waterman that delivered the shingles to the Norfolk
Area
So they can build houses
Call Grandy was working in the swamp it's likely that he got to know some of the Maroons who live there
Wall submarines remain isolated in their communities
Other saw opportunities with the new Timber into
Contact between enslaved workers in the Maroons who live near the new Timber camps became pretty comment sometime
X maroon
Help workers the shingle production in exchange for goods from the outside world
But one day during his time on the canal
Grandy foul a case of severe rheumatism
And when he needed a place to recover
He picked the swamp he ended up living in the swamp for a whole year
Shepherd things he must have had people
He could depend on their
I don't think you just do that and not know anybody in the
You knew some people there they watched out for you and
Over the course of years I'm sure
The Moses watched out for them
In a narrative later published about Moses Grandy's life
He described his time in the swamp
Read here by our friend Al letson
I built myself a little Hut
Provisions brought to me is opportunity
Deserved
He among the snakes bears and Panthers
Whenever my strength was
Efficient are cut down a juniper tree
I converted it into Cooper
Stimp
Will not
I was woke by large animal smelling my face
Sniffing strong
A filter School
Muscle
Asunder
Grossed out my arms and shut it with all my might
It was frightened and Madoff
I put my trust
The Lord
Can you don't spot
I was never attacked
Again
Eventually Grandy recovered and went back to work
In 1833 he managed to buy his freedom
You became part of the Abolitionist Movement
Travel to Europe
Murray spoke out against what he
CNN Xperia
And his narrative
Grandy reflected on what it meant to be free
After so many years of enslavement
I felt myself that almost thought I Can Fly
And in my sleep I was always dreaming of flying over Woods Rivers
My gate was so old to buy my gladness
What's the matter
Slavery will teach any man to be glad when he gets his freedom
What researchers can tell maroon communities in the states existed as long as they were necessary or as long
Long as they remained hidden from the outside world
Dancers thinks that the communities in the Great Dismal Swamp
Began to disperse around the time of the Civil War
My impression based on the evidence from one interior site right now
Is that somewhere more less coincident with the Emancipation Proclamation
These communities
Finally disband
Submarines left to join the union in battle
And after
War
Some may have gone looking for newly freed family in the south
Some man travels North some may have settled in neighboring towns
I want really knows for certain
Many enslaved people weren't allowed to read or write
So personal accounts from Maroons are rare
It's only in the past few decades that researchers have started to study most US Marine communities in any sort of death
For a long time it was barely a footnote in US history
And one reason for this omission
Is likely because these communities were intentionally secretive
But
Some academics
I think there's a bigger reason why the stories of Mehrunes aren't told
I think in this case you have a good amount of racism
That that sort of
Coach Serta people's understanding
Most Americans learn about the Underground Railroad way back in elementary school
A resistance to slavery that came about through white and black cooperation
The Dismal Swamp
And other Marine communities
Are all about Black autonomy
A complete rejection of White Society
Hair salon do you forgotten
I think that's the idea of
Black people taking their lives into their own hands
Not wanting to be any pop
The lobster Community not wanting to be
Quote unquote free blacks
Cinder North
Or
Pause for freeing the Sabbath being self-ruled
And leaving the oil
Kind of freedom
That was not part of the larger discourse
Obese country
I think we still have a ways to go in this country to be quite honest with you
In terms of
History uncut and raw
That's one of the reasons Eric Shepherd started his tour company
He wants more people to know the history
He left behind a good government job in Baltimore and he and his wife moved
Southern Virginia
Just to be closer
Bahat
Money
Dismal Swamp
I felt as though it was a calling there was an assignment
Was Annie
For me to be down in this
This area like
Unfinished business
Or whatever
In 2003
Several sites in the Great Dismal Swamp
We're added to the National Park Service Network to Freedom
Which recognizes 400 locations involved in the Underground Railroad
And a sign at the Great Dismal Swamp
Recognizes that this place wasn't just a stop for people on the Underground Railroad
There were entire communities
People
Who made this their permanent home
Today the largest remaining part of the Great Dismal Swamp is a national Refuge stewarded by the US Fish and Wildlife
Who aim to protect the wildlife that's made a home there
And to preserve its unique Lance
Keeping alive the memory of the people who found refuge in his dismal Terrain
It is strong and Rich history
Which should be acknowledged
And we are very proud of our ancestor
Is that a door
That he'll here on Earth
Among the blackbear
Bootcamp
The rattlesnakes and moccasins
Even the unrelenting mosquitoes
The very habitat who's dangers allowed
Thousands of people to live in relative peace
On their own terms
We'll share a little gem of an outtake from Sri SRI search of this piece
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
8th Street Pier
As I was making this story I read Until the End used book that the WPA the works progress
Resin ministration
Did this project called voices from the days of slavery
Oh that's where I found the tape of Laura Smalley who you heard from any episode
And I'm going through all those interviews
I found this song that's been stuck in my head
And I wanted to share it
On the Library of Congress website it says it's part of an interview with
Wallace quarterman
Recorded in Georgia in 1935
But there are several voices in it or not
Quite sure who they all are
But is it really good song
So I
Hope you like it
My garden
The lure
Dr Leslie schaffer
To the voices from the days of slavery project has a lot of really incredible tape
If you want to hear more it just Googled WPA voices of slavery
And you'll be able to find them
The hosted on the Library of Congress website
99percentinvisible was pretty sweet by Sharif Youssef with editing by Delaney Hall Katie mingle is RC Nerf
Freezer Kolstad is the digital director
Sean real composer music the rest of the staff includes
Avery trufelman Darren Masa and me Roman Mars
I just want music this week by a pal okay akumi
Well thanks to Sylvia and used book slavery is X-Files and answers book
Desolate place for a defiant people on our website
Thanks to Nina Shapiro Perl of American University for the use for short film
Landscape of power
You're interested in learning more about tours to the Great Dismal Swamp
Check out Eric Shepherds website diversity restoration.com
Special deterrence why can the Oakland African American Museum and Library
Lake Elsinore Outlets in the podcast reveal who voiced Moses Grandy
The archival audio of Loris male was from the WPA voices of slavery project
Hosted by the Library of Congress
This piece was inspired in part by an essay in the Smithsonian Magazine by Richard Grant
What makes all this and more on our website
We are project of radiotopia and kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are proud member of radiotopia from PRX supported foundation and listeners best like you
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook
You can sweeten me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi Oracle on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit too but you can find all the
Play old episodes and a brand new article about design every couple of days
On our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com