99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm running
My name is Melissa Lee
And originally I'm from Hastings-on-Hudson New York
A small town is
Projects to make your own fun
Everybody makes their own fun if you don't make
Get yourself it ain't fun at 10
Entertainment
I guess the big activity would be walking downtown
After school
And
You can hang out by the wall and watch people
But you knew go by
Not to square miles but it's right outside New York city so it's sort of like
You know there's a lot out there to do but there's not actually a lot to do
Right where I was
Besides people watching Melissa and her friends are also collected go
Sweden collect you break your own geodes
Brown and lumpy on the outside but when you smash my part would be some crystalline structure
And you've no idea
I'm outside what you're getting
It time to take a chance on it
The inside you
Got something great
Usually Melissa and her friend Liz would buy a few geodes at the store downtown and take him home and
Smash robot with a hammer
One day
When was Louis XIII
We are too impatient we just had to know what was inside
There's a parking lot nearby
It was an apartment building and we decided to start again
Side of a wall
It's hard as we could and hope that it would crack open that way
I think that was the first time that we had
Try to open them that way without a hammer
Just by throwing a
So I threw mine a few times
And
Finally did
Crack open
Against the wall
And Lucas doing hers and it wouldn't crack opens only one
Little window in the
Back of this apartment
My friend list
Tarzan
And Lucas wouldn't crack open
Sorry I threw mine and we saw it
Going towards the window and then
Kareem just went wild and
Then the geode went right through the window breaking with glass and shattering it
Everywhere you're this huge crashing sound
Glasses broken in
Is now lying all over the parking lot floor
Energy it was inside
My first reaction was to
Just pure full-on fear I hate doing things wrong
I hated getting in trouble
And I just got
Terrible singing
Feeling in my stomach
I just wanted to get out of there
We were such good kids I mean this is what we did
Find me
We broke up in geodes we never did anything wrong
And now you're committed this
Heinous act and it was sort of like the quintessential
Wrong thing that kids can do and you always I always saw
TV shows are read comic books where kids break a window
And then they have their face with a dilemma do they go back
And tell the guy
And they did it or not
We froze
For about 10 seconds
And then
My friend Liz ran forward
To reach into the broken glass
And grab the Geodon and we both ran
After initially running
Moral compass started
Nothing we realized we had to go back
Where to find this person and tell them what we did
Listen Liz went back to the apartment building
Figure out where the window
LED tube around to the front it was very confusing which door might lead to that window
And said that it wasn't their window
I did it for 10 minutes and I think we're like well
I think we did all that we can do and we're probably really
Glad have you tried
But we weren't able to find
Who's window it was in the end
Still feeling guilty Melissa avoided downtown and
The window
For a couple of months
Switch wasn't easy in a small town
I thought that we would just go about our business and somebody would fix the window and I would never
To think about it again
But when Melissa finally did go back to the window
It was still
Broken
Like a cartoon just like us
Jagged Edge
Keyshia Cole I was sitting there
Even though
Glass shards had fallen into the parking lot we're still lying there
It was pretty much
Like in pristine condition
From the day that we had broken it until
Months and months later
It stayed almost exactly the same
It was clear that the apartment was aqui
Actually we could see it TV on inside
Sometimes
So we knew somebody did live there
And sometimes the window would be
Raise up or lower down
The song was moving this window around but the whole was always still in it
We just could not even imagine
Who this person was
It wasn't doing anything to fix this window
They weren't even putting tape over it
Are we even go by in the winter and see that
The hole is still there
The window stay broke
Is Melissa finish Middle School
And those High School just hadn't gone away like I wanted it to
The one with the college and I was shocked to find that
Still broken
Even after I left town Melissa should go away do some growing up
When she came home she see that one don't feel exactly like the 13th kid she was when she broke the window
I think about 13 my most awkward horrible age the sight of this window would just bring me right back to feeling like a middle C
School Oregon
Melissa is 36 now
Think of all the Milestones you pass between 13 and 36/4 years and by the end of that
Pretty grown up
The world for 9 months so the window
Graduate school
Go to Washington DC
Saw the window
You get the idea
As much as I was changing is part of my past
Completely Frozen
As soon as I saw the windows just brought right back
To those middle school days when we broke
So in 2011
Years old 22 years after she and her friend broke the window
I decide to find out
Once and for all whose window it is
And apologize
And I guess
You know offer.
Now I'm recording stuff for real
So
I
Go downtown with my sister accompanying me
Courage
What the hole is still there
In the window
And
My heart is beating
So fast should I just say I'm tired of being upset you I just believe that
I know who
Pocket window
And I very very nervously blurt out
I'm sorry I'm sorry I'm not trying to bother you I'm just trying to actually make amends
Explorer
I think that years ago I'm not sure but I think my friend and I broke that window until I kind of
Make amends for it
I think so well I actually tried to find you at the time
And I couldn't find you and then
20 years later I
Came back to my tone how I left
And I'm going back since then and
Basically that's what happened
So I just wanted to kind of find out you know whose it was and
Good
Give me looking for me please just that you found me you believe it
Who I left town for a while
But you didn't want to talk to me
He thought it was amusing
But I was now
Fessing up
And when I offered to pay for it he said window
I'm surprised I know why it why did you just decide to leave it like that
You got a nice breeze in the back there
The landlord never fixed it
And when I offered to pay for it he said no
American used to it
He just left it
Cricket Lubbock
Anyway I'm sorry I did but I'm glad that you've come to like the broken wind
Thank you I would like to meet you after all these years I've wondered about it
That's kind of an understatement
Whatever it was I was keeping me
You know stuck in middle school there was sort of Cuba
I'm stuck with this broken window
Was content to live with it
The broken windows theory proposed in 1982 says that a seemingly small Act of vandalism if it goes on
Fixed
Precipitated further vandalism and even more serious crime
That really didn't happen here
Except for Melissa's life on the land for 20 years
But the broken window did way on Melissa
I'm guessing it affected the man in the apartment more than he's letting on
In a random passerby leso
And Hastings-on-Hudson New York soldiered on
Without missing a Beat
Architecture is personal
The strangest part of our interaction with the built environment
Is what can be so evocative and meaningful for you
Can mean absolutely nothing
Does someone else
This time when I was in town.
I just didn't really even
I think I was even in town for a few days before I even thought about the window I didn't really even wonder about it
Very much
And then in the end I didn't even
Go down in
Unlock
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars it's a brother to 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife
Wife is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
But this week you have to see the original art
Buy Emil Homewood of the Caravan illustrating this story that you just heard
It just makes me so happy
Check it out at 90% invisible
. org radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com