99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Visit 99 percent invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Begin there's someone our producer Sam Greenspan would like you to meet
Who You Are
How you know me
I'm your grandmother
My name is Gene green saying I'm Sam Greenspan's grandmother
Jean Greenspan is my father's mother I call her Grandma Jeanie
She grew up during the Great Depression and because her family got a lot of help from FDR and the New Deal
Grandma Jenny is a Democrat
Always has been always will be
Grandma have you ever voted for a Republican or anyone who wasn't a Democrat
Never never never do that
Always vote for Democrats
And so on the first Tuesday after the first Monday in November in the year 2000
Peddled over to community center in her retirement
And she did what she always does
Kubota straight Democratic ticket
At least she thought she did
Can you tell me where you live
Oh I'm now I live in Century Village West Palm Beach
In Florida
And what county do you live
Palm Beach County
An election in turmoil
A presidency in the Bala
Who will emerge the winner in the historic Florida recount
I believe the people of Palm Beach
Which county
Have entrusted us
To voice their right
Pate and their governor
Time moves
Disboards
Conduct a manual recount of all the ballots with
Presidential elect
The election was close
But tonight after account
And yet another manual recount secretary and I are honored and humbled
The one the state of Florida
Which gives us needed electoral votes
As a quick refresher the 2000 presidential race between Republican George W bush and Democrat Al Gore
14 down two contested
What's in Florida
And one of the four counties at the center of the controversy with Palm Beach County
Voters were using paper ballots where you indicate your choice by punching out holes with a metal stick
Palm Beach County's ballot known as the butterfly ballot had choices of candidates spread over two pages with the hoe
The punch out in between them
But some found a layout confusing
Voters who wanted to cast their vote for George W bush had no problem it was clear that the correct hole to punch
Was the very first
Right at the top
But there is some ambiguity about which was the right hole to punch to indicate a vote for Al Gore
Was it the second one down right after bush
Or was it the third one down
Gore was actually the third one
The way the ballot was set up some voters who believe they were voting for Al Gore actually cast a vote for Patrick bikini
Buchanan being extremely conservative Reform Party candidate
And there's also a problem with the physical balance themselves
Namely
The chat
When you punch a hole in something the Chad is the little piece of paper or cardboard of whatever it is that gets punched out
And in theory it should be completely punch out but sometimes it
This doesn't happen
Sometimes the Chad's hang on
In the case of the 2000 election
If the Chad was still hanging on
The ballot counting machine couldn't always read the ballot
And for the people who would eventually count them by hand in the recount
The auditors
Had to interpret
The intent of the voter
And the hanging Chads
Became
White Infamous as well because
INRI tabulating the vote
You had to make
Assumptions about whether a hanging chad
Was a vote for a particular candidate
Or
It was a mistake
That's Eric Heron Mine is Eric Heron and I'm the Everly family professor of political science at West Virginia University
Varsity
And I focus my research on elections electoral systems and so because of this faulty ballot in Palm Beach County
My grandma Jeannie
A dyed-in-the-wool new deal Democrat from the Jewish tenements of New York City
Might have accidentally endorsed a third-party candidate
Who Embraces all the things that
And then we were told
I was really
Embarrass
We felt cheated we felt guilty
I felt guilty
That I voted for the wrong person
Retirement community Century Village
Was actually called out by salon.com and other news Outlet
Has pulling unusually high for Pat Buchanan
There is extensive research to show that
The votes cast for Buchanan
In Palm Beach County
Extraordinarily High
They were anomalous in
The region
Engine
And the best explanation
The spike in support for Patrick Buchanan
Was the design of the ballot
Even Pat Buchanan himself admitted that his high numbers were probably due to an error
Now the butterfly ballot was only one small piece of the debacle that was the 2000 election in
Florida
Absentee ballot
Counted incorrectly there was a manual recount of a started and then stopped
And later it would come out of the state of Florida wrongfully denied the right to vote to at least
12000 people
A disproportionate number of whom or people of color
All of this in an election where the margin of victory was
Fewer than six
100 volt
There were a number of incidents
In Florida in
2000 election
That were
Politically charged
And
Potentially
Motivated bipartisan in
But the design of the butterfly ballot
Is much more likely
A case of malpractice
Zayn Malik
It was a classic design fail
It's a poorly designed
Valid it is a ballad
That does not take into account
The way that a voter
Would look at the balance
And
Use the particular technology
In place at the time punch card technology
Decoster
The ballot is a designed object that is critically important for democracy but in the United States it's almost
Never designed by an actual design professional
And as such
Are Liberty is being infringed upon by the tyranny of bad design
One of the oldest recorded instances of a vote is from the ancient Greek play the eumenides by aeschylus
In the story arrestees is on trial for the murder of his mother
12 jurors line up and take turns placing a stone in One
Signify not guilty
And there's no teeth of the stone as a marker of a vote
It's an image that stuck and the Greek word
Sephos which means small stone or pebble
Is the root
ABS apology
Or the study of election
And as Eric Heron tells it himself a psephologist
The whole Stone in the urn setup was not too different than how elections in the United States
So in the early us elections you will find voters
Casting a Voice vote they physically had to make their way to the polling place and announce their vote and one of the things
Things you do sacrifices the privacy of your vote individuals know who you are voting for
And what that can engender is pressure on voters to support
One candidate or another
In the polls were not calm places with orderly lines you could be battered and pressured into voting a certain way
Burley elections in the United States often featured
Liquor and violence
And fraud
Voters would have to
Push or shove or be physical to express
There
Right to vote
In fact an election could be so rock is it served as an argument for some against women's suffrage
Elections were deemed inappropriate for women
Then in the late 1800s
Election supervisors realize that having people by speaking their choices allowed was a terrible idea
The lack of privacy could lead to coercion
And had no way to verify that their vote
Is being recorded accurately
Called a ticket
But unlike a ballot we have today
These were printed not by the government but by political parties
Political parties would print
Their own ballot
That voters would take with them to the polling
Now these could be printed in newspapers that could be printed by the parties themselves and distributed
And
The voter would turn in that party ticket
The party tickets with generally only have the candidates
From that party on them so if say you wanted mostly Republicans
You go get a Republican party ticket and then you cross out the
The candidates that you don't want
And then either write in
Or literally cut and paste
Pieces of paper with your kids names
Onto that ticket
And this is the origin of the
Term
The cast of split ticket
Or a Straight Talk
But this system also had problems
1 parties could make tickets that look like those of their opponents
But actually had their own candidates listed
Duping voters into voting for the wrong party
Non-standard ballets also created other opportunities for shenanigans
Like racketeering scheme
Which facilitated a whole Black Market of buying and selling votes
Answer the party ticket system
Wasn't creating Fair elections either in the late 19th century there is
An innovation that is imported from abroad is called the Australian ballot
The Australian ballot
Is
Government printed ballot
That is distributed to voters who come to a polling place
And they
Cast their ballot
In
Private and this Australian ballot system was a game-changer
First of all we started treating ballots
More like currency
Administrator
How to store them securely
Store them safely they have to maintain a clear chain of custody over them to maintain the
Integrity
Of the election prop
They're often printed on special paper
To undermine counterfeiting
Or efforts to
Nick fraud
And with the Australian ballot as a Point of Departure polling places in the US began to see new machines the interface
With the official government printed ballot
They were machines where you pull levers
Or use a metal rod to punch holes out of an object
Will scan ballot like we saw with a butterfly ballot in Palm Beach County Florida in the two Thousand Eleven
There is tremendous variation
It how each County conducts
It's elections
If you move across the county line your polling place could use an entirely different balance
Because here's the really crazy thing about elections
The US
Unlike much of Western Europe
Haneda
Australia South Africa India
Most other industrialized democracies
Do u.s. runs elections at a hyper-local level because the US
Decentralized system
Process
You have
Patchwork
Of election procedures
All across the
And it can vary
At the county level or even within some count
How ballot
What are counted
And process
We do this because that's what the Constitution tells us to do
It says that states shall conduct elections
And the states generally delegate elections down to Municipal governments
Partly because voters have so many things to vote for that each municipal government
Why are zits on ballet
We vote
So many
Public officials
Everything from president
Drain commissioner
Can be on a ballot
Yeah michigan-michigan you can vote for County drain commissioner
And so given that each county is responsible for running its own elections every county is on their own naked
Hire a designer to make a balance
They could not hire designer to make the ballot it all depends on
What each elections official wants to do
And that more than malicious intent
Maybe how Grandma Jeannie and her elk voted for the wrong guy in mm
Exactly Pat Buchanan is
Religious Fundamentalist
Kind of guy
Not the sort of person that a bunch of Jewish grannies are going to be voting for
Guess you had tested out this ballot in the kind of pilot test or run what we call usability test even with just a
A few people that this
Issue would have surfaced pretty quickly
That's Dana chisnell she is a user experience design
And I do
Applied research
Design in folding Cadillac
Dana along with her colleague Whitney Quisenberry with the center for civic design have made it their mission
Design theory and practice
Two elections
In election Administration usability testing
Get done
Pilot testing on these kinds of designs
Doesn't get
Sodick co-authored a set of
Field guides to ensuring voter intent
Design manual for elections official
And the very first one in the series
Was how to design usable ballads
So whatever recommendations is use lowercase letters
Mixed case print is just easier to read
This is actually been proven in studies
We also say avoid Center type type is for wedding invitations in Wind Lake
It really doesn't belong
On a form
Especially when like this
Other recommendations include using
Type in New York
In 2012 I think
In about
It's not uncommon to find magnifying glasses
In New York voting booth
The center for civic design also recommends using one sans-serif font
If you look at some of these balance their kind of a they look like Ransom notes
There are lots of different type families that are used
The whole thing
Screaming at
We can, that down quite a bit by just going with one
San serif
The suggestion to the guide books for how to design a good ballot are akin to designing a good anything
When designers get ahold of these things are like
This is design 101
But election officials don't know this
And election officials unlike normal client
Often have to uphold legislation requiring them to use bad design
If you go look at election code
In practically every state
Thing
Design of the ballot is largest
What's a typeface is what size it should be what the grid is
Bad designs
Almost
Almost exclusively by Design officials have to apply better design principles to there
They also need to change laws
But one thing that might solve ballots for good is standardizing
It's actually a project with Dana chisnell and the center for civic design are also working on
They built a prototype called the anywhere about
It's a touch screen system where you can resize text
Adjust contrast navigate easily
Verify that you voted for human to vote for and it's open source so any elections official can use it
13 is quick to admit
Probably won't eliminate all forms of a
Will something always goes wrong I just hope that it
Will not
Geometric design
Master the election of officials prayer is May the margins by
May the margins be wide
Ever in your favor
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a
Cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Hollywood
We're looking the part
Mike
Cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get relief
Jaxblade superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to
Clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com