99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There is one word us radio producers can never seem to let go of
Tape
Our job used to be all about tape
My first Marantz recorder captured sound on cassette tapes
If you're a little bit older than me and you even produce your stories on tape you'd sit in front of a reel-to-reel and cut apart someone
Boys with a razor blade
And then splice the Magnetic Tape back together with clear adhesive tape
These days we use digital recorders in computer is but we still use the word tape
Did you get good tape
The raw material that we work with is tape it just is there is no alternative
Are tattoos also inextricably linked to tape cassette tapes in this case
Had it not been for obsessive fans collecting and copying and passing along his songs in the era of tapes we
We might never have come to know his music
Finnegan had he lived in a different era
Perhaps he would have gotten the recognition he deserved within his own lifetime
From Radio producer Charles Maines
Misses three records from Sundown
You know one of the things that
I've said a lot but I'm not sure how much people understand it
Really
I don't like singer-songwriters
It's not what I choose to listen to
Stop my first option
You know I grew up listening to Roots Music or to Jazz or to you no music
Bye
Exaggerated
Yeah music by real people
By people from the Earth
People who
You're not middle class
You know
And
I don't I know I don't think in history you look back I don't think there's that many examples of the middle class
Inventing anything
You know culturally
So
When I put on the tape
And I hear
You know
Well-educated White
Person
Strumming a guitar
Yeah I am looking at my watch and I'm saying okay I'll give this another 15 seconds
Unless the voice is
Really star
And
Nick Dre just
Grab me by the throat
It's one of the great sadness and frustration Supply
Life in the music business that I wasn't able to figure out a way to get it across to people
In his lifetime
Three records from
Producer Joe Boyd remembers Nick Drake
The early days
Joe Boyd
Young American
Drive to London hoping to make his Mark in the thriving music scene
This is the first Pink Floyd single
Any discoverist English folk rock Pioneers the Fairport convention
Arguably he makes his greatest find far from the Streets of London
Cambridge
Electronic drink
The English have such funny names for class I would call him an upper-middle-class boy
You know
The upper middle class always call themselves middle class
But you know
The lower-middle-class also call themselves middle class
Anyway he was definitely
Went to a boarding school and spoke with a very refined accent
He was
Part of a kind of
Gilded youth
Generation
Well off
Upper
Middle-class kids
The way the truth and you know he was
Very talented in music
He
Started playing the clarinet to switch the guitar his mother
Play the piano and wrote songs
And years later I discovered I heard tapes of his mother
And they're amazing
You know they have these wonderful
Chords on the piano
Any of the start of the song It's a bit
Very English free almost Music Hall
Upper class Music Hall Flanders and Swann Noel coward's kind of thing
End
He started playing guitar and he's just he was just I don't know where it came from but he
Beltway of reproducing the guitar the kind of cords that is Mother played on piano
I heard him first because one of the Fairport convention
Told me about hearing him at concert
The Roundhouse it was a Vietnam protest concert
And
Follow up the lead
Invited to come in and bring me a tape
He brought me a tape
And put it on
Immediately knew that this was something completely different a lot of retuning
String to the PE played in very unusual boy names
And his ejaculation of arpeggios on the guitar and the whole way he use
Guitar to underpin his songs is completely unique in my view men's suits
So strong and so Central and so devoid of solos and there's nothing about
Guitar solos in there it's just a way of orchestrating a song in a complexity that
Staggering
Openstack
I'm down to the
In search of America
40-minute designs neck trick to deal with his witch seasoning
Island records
Beers 1968
Drake is 20 years old
New Talent is beyond reticent
I would get used to make drinks way of answering the telephone
He was so shy as a performer
When the circumstances
Right
And the only certainty that I remember most clearly as being right was
Unscramble convention play the Festival Hall and his ride your Matic because they had a car accident the drummer been killed
Configuration of the group
So everybody was in their seats and respectful
Nick came out
Didn't say anything
Play the song to get Florida
3 minutes without speaking
Returnees guitar
Everybody stayed silent
Play It Again already gave a big ovation
Got an encore at the end
And I thought
He's going to work
Can you send him out on his own
You know Anna is a student union for kids bar the back
Doesn't say anything no jokes has no chance
Take me to Guitar Picks fights on time and he just has little intern
Between songs he lost everybody
And
Already stopped performing live
And there was no other way in England those days you really break an artist
The middle Zedd
Is Drake's career with Central recording studio
Boyd recruits engineer John would it sound technique studio in London for Drake's debut album
The record is called
Five leaves left
Beers 1969
Difficult to remember
There wasn't really a template for doing this kind of record
Record a singer with strings or with
Larger orchestral arrangement
But not in a pump way
It was a kind of dry Ash intimate
Sound on The Voice and
And doing it so tasteful way
Would not tell me they've been done much
And
We already tried one arranger the guy who worked on the James Taylor record
Retention record
And just
Just didn't work at all
And
And Nixon said well I have this friend in Cambridge
Robert Kirby
And I went up to Cambridge to meet Kirby you know and I was a bit freaked out because I thought Nick is world-class
So we want the best
You want world is top Ranger London whoever it is will spend the money will get the guy
And Nicholson will actually
Let's try my friend in Cambridge
It's 19 years old
And I think oh no no no I don't
But I would have met him and I just like the way they were together in the way my life Roberts and he seemed to
Really really love Nick and his music
I just felt okay let's just go with this
And so we did this procession in the first track they did was way too blue which I had never heard because you didn't
A way to play it to me
And
I suppose I could have gone down into the room
And just listen but I tended to
You know that John would be the guy running around moving microphones and messing around in the studio and I sat in the control room
Besides it was a climb you know the scrotum is upstairs
Anyway, we down all it back up again so I was just sitting up there reading my paper and listening to
There were strings rehearse and you'd hear them John would focus on
One microphone another microphone and another microphone try to get that thing go downstairs move the microphone will the
Chairs around active hearing these bits and pieces of this thing and send it to me
I couldn't figure out what it really did sound like
And then finally got everybody in position and John got his sound he water and every microphone every
Part of the six piece string string ensemble
And
And then he just pushed all the fighters
We listen to this whole thing
And I just oh my God
Don't you have a while to show
A way to find somebody tell me
Xiaomi
What you have to show
Cucumin
Have you seen the light I thought mommy made the record oh my God the critics going to love this is so awesome but we're
We're going to get headlines
Melody Maker said
It was an awkward mixture of folk and cocktail jazz
So
I don't know
It seems very sad
What you
Discouraged
Distraught
Strike back into the studio
What produces second record
Beers 1970
One of these events
When approached
Nick a lot
The first
Leonard Cohen album
Which I thought John Simon did a great job of producing
And
One of the songs I love it was so long Marianne
He has these girls mocking his line
Hircine behind him against him
Any kind of
Contrast in the air brassiness to his delicacy
And when he played me
Korbel originally when he played it to me
That Chorus Line old pool boy so sorry for himself
He sang
And I said I just had this idea right away I said Nick let's
Get some girl singer to sing that long when you answer at the end of them
He kind of looked at me funny like you sure
I said yes I'm sure okay
John Wooden I learned recording Nick very quickly that you just turn Nick off
In the markets
His next performance is always
Great
You know you when we would record Nick with
Strings or Rhythm Section or or whatever
Even if it was out of the room and when he recorded with strings he recorded in the room and it's different from the way people do things today
Trackside River man that's not an overdub string section and that's Nick singing and playing
Guitar in the room in the middle of the strings
Going to see the resume so you're listening very carefully to
Everybody else and you go for their performance
Get a gray tank from strings or the brass the Rhythm Section or whoever the
The weakest link is you don't even have to listen to me then you listen
Always
Guitar parts he never flubbed it just never did
Despite critical Acclaim brighter later sells poorly
London Tube
Parents
Behavior is increasingly erratic
At his family's urgent track seek psychiatric care
Around the same time California
Jobs in the film industry
What kind of reputation
Very solitary loan
Person you knew
Yeah I mean he was soft-spoken
Hesitant
But he was he nobody liked it
Behemoth
Very good idea
Can he work break laws
Robert Kirby
Incredible fun
Work in the city with me just because
Material you're working
And the fact that it's not
Self can
Group
You got to go out
Records
The end days
Directions to third and final album pink moon
Predecessors
Band
1974 Drake is found dead in his bedroom
26 years old
Nobody knows
The story
Boyd eventually sells his label steak in Island records
One of his parting conditions is a Drake's recordings never go out of print never
Second detail
Falcons draft picks recordings begin to find an audience
Fans make pilgrimages to the Drake family home in Tamworth in Arden
Text parents Rodney and Molly
The interest in our sun
Invitees visitors in the copy cassettes and home recordings of Drake's music
Overtime the Drake Legend spreads
Combination of word-of-mouth and
Tape to tape
To take to take the tape
Is it surprising to you how
Popular Netflix music has become kind of after his death and Call it spring
No I mean I always thought he should be that popular and my video is what took him ready
So long
The shame that people didn't recognize it in his lifetime
But you know there it is to music there
Are you know I don't know how to deal with questions like what was his ahead-of-its-time so
I think so is very much
You know what happened in that time and then set of influences that
You know
But I do think that
In a way it's failure at the time has been
Heart of its success now in the sense that
Very few people growing old growing up in the 80s
They didn't have parents who were playing Nick Drake to death
You know there's no films from the 60s with
Girls dancing around with flowers in their hair
What's Nick Drake at the soundtrack I mean it's not identified with that. It is
Culturally
Unanchored
So
It's free
To be
Adapted and embraced fine
People from other generations of people you know, for next to me
It doesn't serve said I am from the 60s you know
Nick Drake please give me
Please
I want to just sit on the ground
Come ride in my history
God by the bay for now
I'm just know how to find you are and your way
Three records from Sundown was produced by Charles Manson to
2009 he received a Third Coast Festival director's Choice Award in that same year
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are project
7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in Architecture Firm in
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how RC
Soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 Pi feet
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
You find a show in Lancaster on Facebook Tumblr Spotify we're all on Twitter about our true home online
Find is 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero and
Any movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com