99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name in India
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 app
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The Bellevue Stratford Hotel open in Philadelphia in 1904
And quickly became one of the most luxurious hotels of its time
It was 19 storytime at over a thousand guest rooms and what was said to be the most lavish and magnificent ball
United States
It also featured light fixtures designed by Thomas Edison and a grand marble staircase
The hotel came to be known as the Grand Dame of Broad Street
And for years the grand on with the center of high society culture in Philadelphia
Who's the presidents and queens and all kinds of other rich and famous guests
That's producer Elana Gordon from WHYY the pulse
In Philadelphia
The hotel went through some hard times during the Great Depression and then again in the fifties and 6
It was some of the prestige from its early days
But it was always considered one of the nicest places
Stay in Philadelphia
That is until the mid-70s when the Bellevue Stratford Hotel became the epicenter of a series of mysterious
Recent deaths
That terrified
The country
It all started in July of 1976
I'm more than 2,000 veterans descended on Philadelphia for the convention of the American Legion a support organ
Invitation for wartime vets
Statewide convention happens every year
The 1976
What's a really big deal
The time and place of the convention have been chosen to coincide with the 200th anniversary of the Declaration of Independence
Signed in Philadelphia in 1776
The convention would be held in
You guessed it
The Bellevue Stratford Hotel
The Gathering was going to be a big party for the members of the American Legion
Chants for the legionnaires
Celebrate and reminisce
So it's just a big get-together
And then there was a lot of wives and families there at the same time
That's Jasper Stout
I am a fast Department commander of the American Legion
Stafford drove to the convention from South Central Pennsylvania with his wife
And they wrote up with another couple of some really close friends of theirs
Charlie Chamberlain and his wife Henrietta
Here's Henrietta who is now 86
Recalling the trip
Or we were having a good time down there and everything was going great
The convention ran for days and the whole thing ended with a big parade of legionnaires through the center of Philadelphia led by
Brass Band
When the Saints Go Marching In
That was a real popular song
Henrietta's husband Charlie had just been elected commander of his local Legion Post
Toyota right up front
It was wonderful we had a wonderful time
After the parade Charlie and Henrietta began the drive back home with Jasper and his wife
Charlie
Fell asleep
Which was spring
He seldom ever
Slept in the car
Butterfly chair
Whenever we got on the turnpike at Brandywine he went to sleep
He came home and went to bed that night never got out of bed
I tried to get him better
But every day he got worse
Charlie's body eight
His temperature kept going up
104 degrees
106 degrees
Henrietta took him to the hospital
On Wednesday
Thursday they put in
Nice blanket
And then Friday he was dead
From a flu of unknown cause the doctor
Percent
Charlie Chamberlain was dead at the age of 48
I didn't know what to think nobody else knew what to think that was what it was
Think about it it was
Photoshop for everybody
Jasper sell for remembers
But it was during Charlie's
Funeral
He realized
His friend's death was
Part of something bigger
My one of the other members of the
Headquarters staff
Was there
And he said that
The headquarters are getting all kinds of calls
Some people letters
Got sick and passed away
Within a week of the convention region headquarters had started getting calls from around the state about members who
Fallen ill
But that following Monday
9 days after Charley Chamberlain fell asleep and South first car
News that this mysterious respiratory illness had spread across Pennsylvania
No one knew what it cost it
But the legionnaires were getting sick
I've been at the Bellevue Stratford for the convention
Health leaders back in Philadelphia soon caught wind that something was up
Dr. Robert Schuller was director of infectious diseases for the City's health department at the time
All of a sudden
I had four lines coming from Office off for lunch or let up at the same time
SMS said there's there's some sort of an outbreak going on
The death toll logged by the state kept growing
They called in federal investigators from the Center for Disease Control and prevention in Atlanta
The man charged with overseeing that investigation was David Fraser
He's originally from Philly and he was 32 at the time
He was the director of the CDC
Special pathogens unit
It's been a very intense
Plane ride trying to
Figure out how would I systematically
Begin to approach what
Look to be a very complicated problem
Within 48 Hours of his arrival
The death toll was near in 20 with dozens more sick
Some fear this mysterious pneumonia could be the start of a swine flu outbreak
Or worse
Flu pandemic like the one that had killed 50 million people in 1918
The authorities readied themselves for the worst
As many as 100 state and federal workers were called in
About 50 police detectives took part
This is the biggest investigation CDC undertook
We needed to define the illness
Gosip
Was potentially a new disease
News reporters were already giving it a name
Legionnaires
All might
Medical data is being flown in by helicopter
Everybody in the state of Pennsylvania know about it we had worldwide recognition weird phone calls from as far away as Australia
Asking his questions about
But scientists still had no idea what was causing the illness they was a bacteria a virus or some sort of
They had to tease out a pattern
Pennsylvania
Health investigators are talking to the more than 100 patients
What did they do at the American Legion convention where they all together at a single time
Or gathered in one location
Question after question
Brian fat commonly
Define answers
David Fraser and his investigative Squad cast
A wide net
Which means we had to send physician epidemiologist out to
Take histories from and examine
A large number of people
They monitor the people who have gotten sick and their families
But they also wanted to talk
People who'd been at the convention who hasn't gotten sick
And because there was no Central list of who had attended
They distributed questionnaires to hundreds of Legion Post
Throughout the state
And to have a comparison group
They telephoned random samples of people who weren't even at the convention
And through all this research it became clear early on that this was not the major flu pandemic that some had feared
The disease seemed confined to the legionnaires convention but still
Razor remembers public pressure mounting to figure this out
This was a time when
Infectious diseases were thought to have been largely worked out
And control
It challenges
And it increase the fear
Maybe it was something people ate
Or drag
Some people even thought it could have been an act
Bioterrorism by disgruntled batch
Investigators were stumped
But Roberts RR with Philadelphia's Health Department
Says they did have one General suspect in mine
It was called the Grand Old Lady of Broad Street
That's what I've always heard it referred
And she was the Grand
Survivor says the grand old lady
Sun save the ground down
But yes
He's referring to the Bellevue Stratford Hotel
Hotel
Perhaps this iconic landmark of the city was the Killer
Investigators flagged it in the reports and it didn't take long for this to become a media Frenzy
Stratford may still hold the key to solving the mystery of Legionnaires disease
Somewhere in this hotel there maybe
Being environment
And it was like Hysteria
Steve Hornsby
He was a doorman at the Bellevue at the time of the outbreak
Bright-eyed 21 year old looking to break into the hotel business
He remembers people started calling in to cancel reservation
Beer the place
An anything or anyone associated with it
I was dating young lady and I remember she
She told me her Mom 2
Didn't want me to come to the house and
Anymore because I work
Did the Bellevue
And the hotel was losing gas
We were going down for the
Account NH
Gay
Would get a little worse
They would have the engineer turn on
Lamps
The Broad Street room so that the lights are on
In the evening it wasn't all dark
That's how bad it got
Bedford David Fraser the director of the CDC special pathogens unit
There was only one way to get to the bottom of this
After spending the first week of the investigation in the state capital of Harrisburg
He and several others
Join the Philadelphia crew on the ground
Guess where they stayed
Because
There were rooms available
And we got a good price
Fraser brought his team to the Bellevue
He really wanted to solve this mystery
There was part of me that was hoping that somebody got sick
He's only half joking
This might give an important clue
They got to work trying to figure out the source of a disease
Maybe it was somehow traveling through the Elevator Shaft
And I thought perhaps
Validated
Permit
An agent
Walk into the air
As the elevator went up and down
But we found no evidence
Other theories blame the pigeons perched on the window ledge
Maybe the pigeons were thesaurus maybe the lady who
Feed the pigeons out on the sidewalk
What was the
In the end they came up with AIDS
First
The more time people spend in the lobby of the hotel
The more at risk they were for Contracting the disease
And second
The more time people spent just outside the hotel on the sidewalk
The greater the risk
Even some people who had nothing to do with a hotel or the convention had gotten sick
If they spent time on the sidewalk
None of David Fraser staff became ill while staying in the hotel but they also couldn't figure out what it was about the place
Forgotten everyone else sick
And so people's fear of the building persistence
And in November of 1976
The grand AMA Broad Street was forced to close
It already been in financial trouble but the outbreak was the final fatal blow
It was the end of an era for very elegant hotel with all kinds of memories in Philadelphia history
It was the final day today for the grand old Bellevue Stratford Hotel in Philadelphia battered
Finally done in by the fact that people died after attending the American Legion convention there
Vinyl party hornstein helps lock the place up
We had to put the chains on the door at the front door and
We put it around the
Grab handles
Couldn't open with a padlock
It was like a death sentence
I don't think they'll ever be out another hotel that big and bustling
Like that one was on Broad Street
Back in the CBC labs
Scientist continued reviewing samples and running more tests
Weeks went by
It was a very high pressure
Very frustrating
David Fraser and his colleagues were eventually called in to
To Congress
To account for why they
Still haven't solved the miss
We expected to be raked over the coals
For failing to solve
Not break and we were raped over the coals it was a very unpleasant couple of hours
Fraser worried about morale
Some of the CDC scientist had spent years trying to solve other outbreaks with no success
Which I was afraid was going to set in with legionnaire
Did you think maybe it would take years
Yes
I hope
It would only take years
5 and a half months have passed since the first death
Around 30 people had died
The grand Dom had closed
Things were not looking good
And then finally
The CDC caught a break
A scientist named Joseph McDade was coming through all the biological specimens they collected from victims lung
And re-examining them
Looking for something he might have missed
McDade said this process was like looking for a contact lens on the floor of a basketball court
But then
Finally on December 27
He found that contact lens
In his microscope it look like a red cluster of tiny rods
MacDade ran tests and found these tiny rods were part of the bacteria
One they hadn't seen before
Within a few weeks they confirm that this was indeed the bacteria that it cause the disease
On January 17th
CDC scientist
Announce their findings with great
Fanfare
I was so excited
This was such a spec Tidings of great weight off my
Shoulders
And a great discovery
Very very special discovery
They called the new bacteria
Legionella pneumophila
They had found the Fatal bacteria
David Fraser and his colleagues went from being humiliated
To congratulate it
But wait a minute
Where have the bacteria come from
This question wouldn't be answered until a couple years after the bacteria was to
Discovered
David Fraser retraces two steps around the outside of the Bellevue
Nearly 40 years after the outbreak
The Grand Hotel was restored and reopened in 1979
He points up to the very top of the building group
There are cooling towers
Which
Wood
Operate
To eject key
From from the hotel
Further explains that Legionella bacteria occurs naturally in the environment
Can make it hard to pin down a specific
Bookstores
But it really likes to grow in warm water
And one ideal environment is the warm water basins in air conditioning
Window systems convert warm water into
Cold air
A produce a mess
As a by-product
And that Miss
Can come across the
Edge of the roof
And layer down the side of a building
One of the curious things about airflow in cities
If that missed carries Legionella bacteria and is inhaled
I can make you sick
That's why people who are right outside the hotel and inside the front lobby where most likely to get infected
Fraser says contaminated mist from the Bellevue
Cooling tower
Would have likely
Drop down the side of the hotel
Exposing people on the sidewalk
And then I hear some of these
Utility
Vets here it also would have been stuck into event near the ground
But we've right into the front lobby
Frozen people there
The air conditioning system had always been a possible culprit as a breeding ground for the Legionella bacteria
The CBC couldn't say for sure right away because the bellevue-stratford is cooling system have been thoroughly cleaned follow
Outbreak
By the time the CDC got there to get samples
There was no Legionella bacteria present
But as the years passed
There were more outbreaks of legionnaires in other places
And in those instances
They were able to confirm that the bacteria
Had come from the cooling
Researchers retroactively link the bacteria to previously unsolved outbreak
Including a smaller one at the Bellevue a couple years before the 76
Legionnaires convention
In the Public Health Community the story of Legionnaires disease has turned into a sort of poster child
Power of epidemiology
That's true leather detective work that's used to map out patterns and understand how diseases move and strike
But unfortunately the discovery of the disease didn't lead to its demise
The government now has recommendations
For how to design and maintain cooling system
So they're not breeding grounds for Legionella
But even though the disease is treatable
There are still a lot of cases
In 2015 New York had an outbreak that was traced
National opera house in the Bronx
12 people died and more than 120 became sick
As for the bellevue-stratford
Cleaning the cooling tower is now a routine part of the building's maintenance
They also analyze water samples
Enduring a major Restoration in 80
The hotel got a completely new Heating and Cooling
These days business is good for the crime Tom a frost strain
The hotel now owned by Hyatt has been modernized
Play still has that classic
Rooms run upwards of $500 a night
And future king size beds
Views of downtown Philly
42-inch flat-screen TVs
And of course
In the summertime
Ice Cold Air Conditioning
99% invisible was produced this week by Elana Gordon Delaney Hall and Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan
Kolstad Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
A version of this story originally aired on the pulse from WHYY in Philadelphia at the poles cover stories
At the heart of Health
Science and innovation
We are project to 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin
Bhagwandas architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Percent
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
Family goes
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Pixelbook
The story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and a new week
Who discovered stock
Love letters
Eastern episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook and follow Saul on Twitter and Instagram but the best way to explore the 99%
Send invisible activity that shapes the design of our world if the click around the hundreds of stories that comprise
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
5 part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com