99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 2016 the Swedish tourist Association announced a new service called the Swedish number
Did you dial the telephone number
+ 46
77179 3
You will be connected
With a random Swede
You will soon be connected to a random Swede
Somewhere in Sweden
Hello hello
Ojai is this a random Swedish person
Cold calling this weeds is Will Coley
I have one question for you
What do you think of when I tell you the date 3rd of September 19th 6
Barbie change to write
We called about a dozen sweet
For the most part
If they are alive and in country
For any part of the 19th
The date September 3rd 1960
87 was a hugely important
And Harold
The day
Each day
Yeah Hal short for hoga traffic on Landing
Or something like that
Sorry
Meaning of right-hand traffic diversion
Each day was the day that 7.8 million swedes switch the side of the road they drive on
From the left side to the right
It would be the most massive overhaul in driving infrastructure that any country
Had ever seen
Historically if you're riding a horse
You want to keep the last so that you can use your right hand
Passers-by
Orino
Black man with a sword
But with the Advent of the horse-drawn carriage
There were some conditions in which it made sense
What's the stick to the right
In customs could vary by country
Ennis cars became more common
They follow the same laws that were established
4 horse drawing
Traffic
Up until 1967
Sweden drove on the left side of the road
Which set it apart from its neighboring countries
Finland Norway and Denmark
All of which drove on the right
And this presented problems
The biggest problem was
Accidents
Weather
Drivers
Uproar
The Visitor
Sweden
Also hadoop
Check out this
Wizard
Change from right hand driving
This accident
Increase
Continue
This is psychologist honors English
When he says left hand driving he means driving on the left hand side of the road
When under started working with a
The Swedish government in the 1960s
They were tired of seeing swedes getting into car accidents abroad
And have interest and truck drivers from other countries
Getting into car accidents
In Sweden
Level Solar Sun Sun motor vehicle
Swirl attempted to write and
I'm driving
Swedish car companies made vehicles that were meant to be driven on the right
So they could be exported more easily
But these cars also found their way onto roads
In Sweden
Redbox app Roku
Mainly having your steering wheel on the outside edge of the road
Overtake
Or call seeing as you say in your country
You don't see the oncoming cars
It was a big mess
Swedish government thought it could get a lot better if they just switched what side of the road they drove on if they can drive on the right like most of Europe
Legislative action to switch driving side have been attempted before you times
But it always fail
And then in the early 1960s
The Swedish government thought that this
Could be the time
They put it to a public vote
Asking the Swedish populist
Decide the answer from the people
Was a resounding
No
83%
Gosip
Voted for
Keeping
Left
So the government just went ahead and did it anyway
Sweden life
Looked upon as a democratic
Country
Despite sassa Govan
Decide
Change
Honors England served as part of the team that would help
Make that change
Iowa secretary in
The scientific
Street walking
As secretary under supervised three teams
1 assessing what methods they should
Deploy from
Educational
Campaign
One trying to forecast what problems they might encounter
I'm the third one
Media
One of unders is jobs is helping to come up with informational materials for the switch
Like a pamper
Never explain what would be different
What to watch out for
And what rules
Apollo and just take it
Second to think about what kind of a job this is
If you've ever been in a car
Driving on the opposite side of what you're used to
Everything feels wrong
Do you need to teach people to identify what is actually correct
Even though it feels wrong
And what exactly does
Wrong wrong
The pamphlet Anders and his team worked on shows where your car goes
When you make a right turn
For a left turn
How to pass
Pedestrian should be aware of
Hosea 7 Drive
The two most important things that
The pamphlet did was
One to familiarize Sweden with a new traffic sign
The six
Formed
Side
Wizard meaning
H
Hands of me
A hexagon sign with an H in it
Age for hugger or right
These signs will be visible on the road after the switch
And they're also little stickers with an H
You can put on the inside of your windshield to remind yourself while you're driving
And I might still spot NH sticker inside some of the older cars in Sweden
The second super important part of the public education campaign
What's the date
The switch
September 3rd
Nineteen
Dog and ho
HD
The pamphlet was a good start and getting people ready for a stay but soon the government realized they needed to bring out the big guns
They wanted to unleash their nation's most effective weapon for penetrating people's hearts and Minds
Pop
Wings television station had put out a competition to come up with the best
Song to teach people
About H day
The winner
The telstar's withholding still hug in Spanish
Translation
Keep to the right svensson
Svendsen being a stereotypically common Swedish last name like Smith
Or Jones
Tulsa bit of wordplay here
In Swedish
Keeping to the right as shorthand for being faithful
Your spouse
Going left
Means having an affair
The government had spent four years getting the country ready
Official HD pamphlet had gone out to every Swede
Dispensing song
Have logic
Self in people's brains
Psa's headset rated
McDonald
September has arrived
The evening of the 2nd
The came the morning
The 3rd
Everyone knew the drill
HD was here
All non-essential traffic was banned from the roads from late night to early morning
Most cars were kept off the road
The only people on the roadways were construction Crews
Taxi drivers who were given the okay from the government
And I hand-picked few
Like this guy
It was great fun
Chukar saltonstall, and I has
Black one of the very few
Go to permission to drive at night
What's for dinner
This is Bo holmstrom
Well I'm go home store Monmouth Swedish journalist I'll be working since 1960
In the television has a television reporter
A 19-6
27 I was working on
Switch to right hand drive traffic
And then
I'm doing a lot of stories
But was actually a pretty famous broadcast journalist
Kind of like a Swedish Tom Brokaw
At the time this was the big story oh yeah we were on there almost all night.
After two transmitting from different points in Sweden
Accessories
Work Crews were out putting up the hexagonal H signs
The ones remaining you drive on the right plus they had to flip around and move pretty much every street sign
Sign in the country
What I saw of a changing of signs
Turning them the other way
And then changing all the signs at bus stops
It's such a great feeling to biking around
10 years old and there was no traffic
A few of the random Suites that we reached on the phone we're also they are on each day
A song that will schooling repeatedly on the radio
Country codes
Benson
Something
Roundabouts were reconfigured for people to go counter-clockwise
Clockwise
Freeway off-ramps became on-ramps
Temporary bus stops were set up in the middle of the street to accommodate buses that now had doors on the wrong side
At 4:50 a.m.
Horn blared across Stockholm
Ana loudspeaker announced
Now is the time to change over
And then under the direction of thousands of traffic
Despatched around the country
All of the cars in Sweden
May the way to the right
For the most part
The HD transition team had accounted for
For everything
But it was disorienting
And not everyone was a happy camper
Some people said they got lost
They were in their own City
Then
I've been driving there for 4 years
Them you were used to take care of it one way street for example and it will say the one way but the other way
So go as I wanted
I remember
1 old lady or middle-aged
Hey you sitting in the passenger seat in one car when stopped
And she was mad
Mad as hell
Saying we didn't want this
We voted against
Everybody was against going over
Them politicians
Thousands of people killed in the traffic instead
Here's the really amazing thing about 8
Each day and the ship
What is a hole
The total number of traffic-related deaths
Ponhd
With zero
In fact the total number of accidents went down for a while
There were a lot of people thinking that they should be
Catastrophe
There should be thousands of dead people
Ananda traffic
It isn't
Likely because everyone was so freaked out about driving on what felt like the wrong side of the road.
Everyone drove
Really slowly and carefully
A year after Sweden switch sides of the road Iceland also switch
Driving on the right to be more like the rest of Europe
The United Kingdom and Ireland
1970s former British colonies including Ghana and Nigeria switch from left to right to be more like their neighbors
In West Africa and the rest of the world
Today
The vast majority of the world drives on the right and then places the do drive on the left
Like in the UK movements occasionally spring up trying to get the country
To switch to the right
But there is one notable exception
Rough Country
Went left
Office of the Prime Minister of someone how may I help you
Samoa
Hi this is Will Coley calling from New York
Hello mister
Sikuli is an island Republic in the South Pacific
Not to be confused with American Samoa which is
East
Of Samoa
In 2009 they did the opposite of
Sweden and nearly every other country who made the switch
They went from driving on the right
To driving
On the way
Will Coley called up the guy responsible for the change
Okay hold on for a minute I'll transfer the call
Okay thank you so much
Yes this is the actual Hole music the office
Hello
Hi prime minister
Prime minister of Samoa
Switching to the left offered one major obvious benefit
Aligning Samoa more closely with the biggest nearby Econo
Australia
New Zealand
And Japan
All of which drive on the left
Something that we have been nothing for a long time
Monica concert
We needed to import keepass
Samoa wanted to import cheap used cars from nearby Japan
Ashley
Cheapest
Call Marcus in the world the cars in Japan are made to be driven on the left so Samoa decided to make the switch
Two left side driving
HBO common sense
By all accounts the day of the switch
September 7th 2009
Was released
It probably helped that they're only a couple of major roads to modify
It began with the radio announcement from prime minister Malayalam Maui
Today we will launch
The great event
On the right hand side of the road
She was magnificent
Are gloves that was great but you said right hand I think you meant left
Right
Stick to the right svensson
Prime minister Malayalam Maui stick to the left
99% invisible would produce this week by Wilco Lee and Sam Greenspan Katie Mingle
Kirk Olmstead Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Peter kenkaid author of rules of the road also thanks to Diana Kincaid
You wanted person
Gustav Aldrin investor Victoria visaya or is linguist Kate Montague Rowena fatwa
Baba.
Anna Swedish radio archive
And thanks to a random Suites Kennett Johnson Lukas Nelson ponds bjorkman azami
Angela rummans
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin
In architecture and interior
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sign
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Message Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Ubuntu show in like a show on Facebook follow us all on Twitter and Instagram the best way to explore the 99% in
Invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
Click around the hundreds of stories
Is now both audio stories and prince stories
199p
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com