99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
What we've been doing
And this is friend of the show Sean Cole and yes he said Ikea Hack
Feel good about it
Feels
Subversive
And a little bit bourgeois
It's like being a
Hunk member of
Mainstream
Given that our audience is
You are audience
You probably heard like you had came
It's the practice of buying stuff from Ikea
And then re-engineering a packing it into customized
More functional than often just
Way better design stuff
John's case
That stuff is three
5 foot high shelves
Sean has decided upon the calyx variety
Plus two very heavy wooden doors from Home Depot
All of which he is drooling and screwing and folding together into one big beautiful queen
Size
Frankenstein storage bed
The Cure hits
Basement list New York City existence
We
Refinishing
Construction
3rd
Kallax Shelf
To become experts Hollis assemblers
The locus of the Ikea hacking movement is a website called Ikea hackers. Net it's a showcase for those who would trick
Work out there calyxes
They're arkelstorp
Nerf Bar bolts
Making both gather tips mother hackers and more importantly both pictures of their own acts and even messed up by
Guide to how they made them
Ikea hackers. Net has been in the news a lot lately
And not for happy reasons
You might have read the stories online
We're going to get into all that later
But first
I wanted to introduce you to my hacker partner-in-crime Jonathan Bean for bolts
He's an assistant professor at Bucknell University back in 2009 he co-wrote a serious academic paper
About Ikea hacking with Daniela rossner who now teaches design at the University of Washington
And I got interested in part because of how bendable the term Ikea hacking is
Here's Jonathan
There was so much fun
Nervous about what Ikea hacking
Could be it could be anything from
I bought the Shelf at Ikea and it was an inch
To long for
My closet
So I cut an inch off of it
Orbitz
Will you just take us a salad bowl and make it into a light
And this is Daniela right that's not even actually
Changing the object itself it's just changing it
And at the other end of the spectrum
An artist
Sandra Vaughn boots
Did a very provocative
Work of art
Is an Ikea chair
Reconfigure
To look like a
Stirrup
Oregon college
And both of these things
Fall under the rubric of
Ikea hacking
That's a really wide rubric
And now please put your hands over your children's ears for 20 seconds
I really like the Ikea love toy is another example where you take I love toy made of
Are the Orem song
Shoe trees and Ikea product the milk frothing device
So taking us together and making a little vibrator
This is a much racier interview than I was expecting it
And the hat karate aren't just diverse and turn to their sensibility their diverse in the most basic way pause
Possible UC hack posted from all over this country and from
Australia Russia Israel Dubai
Posted a hack
That's a French country house Library
Hunan actual French country house
60 billion Venom bookcases and he has these before and after pictures and
Explain know how he did it because everything's exactly the same at Ikea and no matter where you are
It makes it
Assertive lowers the barriers
To recreating something
Is this is the thing
Say I wanted to teach you Roman how to build a
Workbench
But you live in Germany
And I live in the US if you go in bio
Stud
I would start at Home Depot in the US
It's going to be an inch and 1/2 by 3 and 1/2 inch if you go and buy a wood stud at Bauhaus
German home improvement stores
It's going to be a
A different different size
Waited to tell me I'm not dreaming and he just said there's a German Home Improvement store called about yes but it's actually Swiss
That's so fantastic
I know
Ikea in spite of itself
Is the great leveler
And it's that very homogeneity that McDonald's like sameness from place to place to place
That's what allowing This Global community of hackers to thrive
So if I posted
And Ikea Hack in Boston
And someone in the Netherlands saw that they could probably reproduce it using this
You know the pieces at their local store much like a Lego kit
Make a mistake
The actual post themselves of showing your work
That's a huge part of this whole thing
I think that there is something to this
Feeling of recognition
You're not creative unless you're right
Nice is being creative
Yeah
If if
Ikea is hacked in the forest does it
Make a sound
8oz is Theodore here and I have officially done my first Ikea Hack
My first Ikea Hack an Ikea piece I will be modifying
And as you might expect there's a lot of this kind of
Hacking and showing and telling on YouTube to
By now the search term shouldn't be too mysterious
Transformation pieces which I like
To call them
You call them
I'll show you how to customize your hair measure how far my elbows are
Population of this desk
Dallas the only mammal contact
Paper onto the
Top of the table and there we have our
Installed
6 inch cabinet
Parts for my Kia why aren't they I mean if they're good enough to do some frankly pretty remarkable
Things
With these
Materials like why aren't they just
Going in
Lumber and screws and nails and
Hammering together something
Maybe more lasting and less pressboard
Well they're not just hacking and materials right there hacking Ikea
They're hacking the brand they're hacking
What that what that
Brand actually symbolises Beyond
Stores
Put another way to quote Danielle and Jonathan
They're mocking the modularity of Ikea
Sing this stuff is so tinkertoy I can mix and mashup the hell out of it
It also goes back to that
Homogeneity right that if
This is the McDonald's in furniture
I'm going to go against the grain and make a double
Triple extra pickle Big Mac with no middle bun in it right is part of your identity you're saying I'm a
Person who transforms things
But this is where it gets even more complicated
According to Jonathan
Within that group
People who wanted to
Completely transform something
Some of them really wanted to maintain the icky aesthetic
So they would say about this is something we want
That could have come from
I didn't
So there's a sort of
Sense of
Sure you want express yourself but you're also trying to see
Outdo the door to outwit Ikea right
Write out Ikea Ikea
All right now we're going to lay the
Is shelves down on there
Scythe
I did not intend
We now we're doing this Ikea Hack already in progress
Because everyone up
We have built
Alex show
WebMD
On their side
It's like my bed is a whale skeleton
Lying on its side
And you're going to be putting
Stuff in the
Rib cage
Door is really heavy doors on
Michelle's
You sound like an insane person doing
I know
You're like Aquaman standing on top of a wild Marine return this is but this is what it's like it's like
Taming you know the most plastic in the known universe and Ikea Shelf
Onyx side it's us that is usually the Plaza
This is the best part
We're about to drill unsanctioned holes
So why is this your favorite song
I mean I think that's it's just like for the longest time you know you're told that drilling holes where they're not supposed to go
Is destructive
And
Wrong
And we were doing that and it still transgressive in Deer Crossing a boundary but it's not the destruction anymore
Creation and you know it felt like for once
I wasn't just saying
What's out there you know which which one on the menu do I want I wish we were making what we want
Yeah but you were still shopping at Ikea
True well it's interesting ideas response to that's right it's not
The shutdown
Ikea hackers
Again this is Daniela rossner who co-wrote that Ikea hacking paper
There's a lot
More
Oma support for
For a hiking Within
The corporate world that never was
You're 5 or 6 years ago and I think
Part that is is
Corporation seeing that this adds to the
Buying in bulk
Products and yes this is the moment in the story what we do the ironic tape to tape a juxtaposition
Maestro
Earlier this week Swedish flat-pack furniture manufacturer Ikea Delta massive blow to the long-running fan
Ikeahackers.net
According to a blog post published by founder Jules Yap the site was issued a cease-and-desist order in March
This is the news that we alluded to at the beginning around the same time that Sean and Jonathan were hacking together his bed
Unbeknownst to them
A brand protection company wrote to the queen bee of Ikea Hack them
The woman who runs ikeahackers.net Jewels yeah
Jules isn't her real first name
The letter basically said that Ikea was not amused
And that if Jules didn't stop operating her website the way she was
She could be in big trouble
Hey Jules
Hi how are you
Jules agreed to talk to me
She was in Malaysia we talked by Skype
Before we get down to business I was just curious how she thought up the side
So I was checking out a few
Home decor websites and I found
IQ
They're scattered around on the internet
That was when I thought
How great it would be blow if I could see all these Heights in one place
No and that was when the light bulb
I knew I had to start it
So that was in 2006
And for some reason only this year
March 12th to be precise
Did Jules get an email with the subject line
Notification of violation of trademark rights
Wow
So I stopped my blood drain literally no I was
It was
Scary
Did they want her to do I'm Hanover the domain name
Stop using the Ikea trademark or anything trademarks by Ikea which I think means even pictures of the furniture
And she'd have to close down her Twitter and Facebook accounts to another social media staff
The thing that's ironic about this thing that I didn't understand right away
Wisdom
Jewels
Love's Ikea banshees just
Huge fan
I am I guess
Superfan
It strikes me that it's like meeting a celebrity that you've always really loved
And like that celebrity
Is really mean to you
Yeah yeah yeah that was fast close
Been given a restraining order celebrity
After Jules announced on her website that big changes might be coming to Ikea hackers
The story went viral
People are pretty pissed off
Cory doctorow who blogs on boing-boing famously called the cease-and-desist letter quote
Steaming Bull and quotes
But at this point Jules it was pretty much resigned
She thought the best thing you could do is just to comply and then
Transfer the tax over to another site which
Didn't have
Like his name on it
If nothing else she was just grateful that so many people reacted so strongly to the news
So it was on that Friday night to that I made the announcement at the following week
I received a call from
IQ
From whom at Ikea guy named Anders Westney
He's with the business side of things is
Supposed to be
Legal side
And she also took a look at the
The letter
The scientist
Letter and
She said that
She didn't recognize Ikea in it
Really he said that
Legend
You didn't have the
Spirit of the brat
Which is to make life better for everyone
And to that end
He told jewels that they wanted to find another way forward and try to figure out how they can resolve things
To come to some agreement
I seriously when you called me I was totally speechless I was like yeah
And inside me I was like
Screaming
Jumping you know if I could
Doing the Ikea dance
Was I crazy
And get this
As we're releasing this podcast
Jules is visiting Sweden and Holland
Meeting face-to-face with representatives of Ikea
Restoring the concept Center where their products are developed and then
Visiting the very Homeland Where it All Began
It's like she's
Charlie Bucket live in Willy Wonka's chocolate factory
Yes
I am
ET go home
I mean you get a sense that
Thank you would ever truly partner with jewels and make her some sort of minister of hacking in or whatever
We would have been saying is like
And I can't imagine Ikea could
Possibly endorse
Any individual hacker hacking on the whole it's just too risky you know I mean if something goes wrong I mean it it would basically be sanction
Channing what amounts to a misuse of their products
Even though I will say
That misuse
Feels wonderful I have to tell you Jules
The feeling of
Hacking together Maya
IKEA bed
Well I am
Jonathan Bean
It was really mostly hand but
We
Do you know
Reiterated
Something it in that thing that we
Create it is
Now something that I
Sleep on every
It's just such a
Powerful feeling
There is actually a theory that the
One of the reasons why I choose
It's so successful is because
You have
Make it yourself
If you are $0.07
Accomplishment
No I put together this
Billy bookcase
So I think I can use this
Picking it up
Level higher
Put the mattress
Onto my new
IKEA bed
Does it fit
That's good
It's a bad it's a real bad
I'm not just a
Loser Bachelor sleeping on the floor anymore I'm in an actual
I'm lying on my new bed it's so comfortable
He still sounds like a crazy person
When was a guy here
Realtor route to Andrews Wesley the Ikea rap who reached out to joules yap's and let's figure out a new way forward
He was very polite
But said that talking to us before talking to Jules
Would be putting the cart before the horse
So in short
No comment
What's the weight for an update
On ikeahackers.net
Right that's right it's still going to take place at 5 to 6 or so smart
You're hacking the hack you realize that you're hacking the Hat
What hacking is oh right
99% invisible West produced this week by Shawn Cole with Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman
Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
Batista the offices of arcsin
Home of some very handsome we hacked
Expedit shelves in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
The whole 99percentinvisible experience isn't Justice episode your hearing I post links to Google things and details
Office hours in live shows on Facebook LTD.
Jokes on Twitter at Roman Mars along with our team Sam listens Katie mingle and troubleman
Tumblr Instagram flicker SoundCloud and Spotify but you're always welcome at our place at 99.
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com