99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When were in for a tiny was going up in Los Angeles in the 1950s
He sometimes heard his parents refer to a place they once spent time
Place
They called
Camp
You know Camp reference for me what summer camp for the Y Camp
So what is this camping they keep talking about
The fact that it's brought up here and there but not elaborated on
You can't help but wonder if there must
Be much more to the story
Warren was right there was a lot more to the story
Producer Emmett Fitzgerald
During World War II the US government incarcerated Warren furutani parent
Along with over a hundred and ten thousand other Japanese Amer
Remote Detention Center
When they talked about
Camp
That's what they meant
In college in the 1960s Warren got involved in the civil rights movement and the Asian American movement
And as he got more politically active he started the research his people's history
He wanted to find out what happened to his parents and other Japanese Americans during the war
One day he was at a Vietnam war protest with his friend Victor shibata
And they started talking about how they wanted to organize a March for the Asian American community
But they didn't know where to go
And Victor and I support
This is Cam
But our parents were what what are these camps
We started talking to some people
About this place called Manson I what's the closest Camp to Los Angeles
It was a damn it we better just go up there
And just fine
It wasn't going to be easy to find
After World War II manzanar had been completely dismantled
By 1969 there were hardly any signs of it left
Warren injectors but with some people from their parents generation and learn at the camp had been located a few miles past the town
Town of Lone Pine
Off Route 395
And then a big green Auditorium building but still standing
Being used by the highway department store machinery
And sew on a clear fall day the two men hopped in Victor shibata old Triumph convertible and when
Looking for this place called manzanar
They drove North out of La about 4 hours
For the Sierra Nevada mountains
And ended up in a High Desert Valley
It was totally deaf
But a few miles outside of Lone Pine they found the Green Building
And they turned off the highway onto a small dirt road
Tumbleweeds
No trees
Lot of underbrush
In the background
What's the Sierra Nevada mountains
Covered in snow it was a traumatic
A landscape as you could imagine
The two men continued driving to the desert and then suddenly
They came across an old white pillar
With Japanese lettering on it
Just was funny
Like it was waiting there to be discovered
It was the original pillar marking the manzanar cemetery
And it was surrounded by faded gravestone
People who had died while in the can
As they explored the area further
Warren and Victor eventually came across a big pile of debris
And we found all of these broken dishes and on the back of the dish
Said Army
Dinnerware with dates
Indifferent things we found it was like an archaeological dig
And reveal
Historical reality kafka
The two young man that found the remains of a camp in only a few decades earlier had imprisoned over 10,000 Japanese
These Americans
And in the process they were helping uncover a dark chapter in US history that a lot of people at the time would have run
Rather forgotten
The incarceration of Japanese-Americans during World War II
Wasn't even mentioned in most high school history textbooks in the 60s
There was no books don't stories
No information can find it in the card catalog in the library
So we started writing our own history
And part of writing that history meant drawing attention to manzanar itself
When Warren and Victor found it
The place had no historical designation no sign and no plaque
But that was all about to change
Warren and Victor go back to Los Angeles but they knew they wanted to come back and bring more people with them next
And there's a thing in Japanese call hockemeyer
Will you have a pilgrimage back to important place
And sew on a December morning in 1969
Over a hundred and fifty people
Piled into cars and vans and buses
On a pilgrimage to manzanar
Going to that part of California
At that time of year was just stupid
Cole
It was so cold
But the Shivering pilgrims followed Warren and Victor's directions to the cemetery
So we cleaned up the cemetery and we brought paint and then wire brushes and
Scraped everything down and repainted The Monuments
We did a lot of work
In terms of refurbishing the area
We knew we were coming back
Most of the people on the pilgrimage were younger Japanese-American
We never spend time at camp
But there were a few people there that day
Do it actually lived at manzanar
One of them was Sue kunitomi Embrey
Los Angeles
The story of how she ended up in this desolate Valley begins in 1941
Fire was saw 18
I have finished high school in January
And I was helping my mother
Take care of a small grocery store with she had purchased the Delta Air before
Sue Embry died in 2006
This audio is from an interview she did with densho the Japanese American Legacy project
Back in 2002
And I noticed that came to our neighborhood was dated May 3rd and we have to move on May 9th
Which country had about five days
5 days to pack up all their belongings and report to manzanar
The camp was one of 10 set up by the US government to imprison Japanese-Americans during World War II
Following the bombing of Pearl Harbor
Anti-japanese racism reached a fever pitch in the United States
Military leaders repeatedly question the Loyalty of all people of Japanese descent without evidence and then
In 1942 President Roosevelt signed Executive Order 9066
Paving the way for the incarceration of thousands of Japanese-Americans on the West Coast
Here's a clip from the 40s propaganda film justifying the decision
When the Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor
Are West Coast became a potential combat zone
More than a hundred thousand persons of Japanese ancestry
Two-thirds of American citizens
One-third aliens
We know that some of potentially dangerous
Most families had to sell property quickly
Often at a fraction of its value
Some rented out their homes or left them with friends
But others abandon them all together
On May 9th Sue's family
Her widowed mother and her six brothers and sisters all went to the train station
They were told that they could only bring what they could carry with them
We all kept thinking we're American citizens and they're doing this to us and we have no rights nobody to
Speak up for us
They arrived at manzanar in the dark
And found their way to their assigned barracks
The camp was divided into 36 residential blocks each with 14 barracks
To which means
In a mess hall
Families were usually allowed to sleep together
All kind of cars
Known partitions of any kind we all slept in one big room
In total there were 800 buildings and over 10000 people packed into one square mile
One of the hardest parts of life at camp
Was the total lack of privacy
The latrines were completely open and exposed
With no stalls or dividers between the showers or toilets
Thunder beginning
People like my mother with stay up late
Hoping to take a shower
Well where our neighbors went to wrong but they all stayed up late Hotel wanted to take the shower and privacy
A 5 strand barbed wire fence encircled the entire camp
Petite guard Tower
Around the perimeter
Each guard Tower at a Searchlight
And a soldier with a machine gun
I remember
Going
All one day one night
Searchmont follow me all the way to the lake train
And I think everyone remembers those searchlights
Manzanar with undoubtedly a prison
With the people inside did everything they could to turn it into a livable City
They had schools
Churches in plugs
Baseball fields in basketball court
Courts people built Rock Garden
And planted flowers and vegetables
And I think it
Whittier Health the morale of the people
The camp also had its own newspaper
Ironically called The manzanar Free Press
Pursue Embry worked as a reporter and editor
Manzanar operated through the end of the war
During that time there were several legal challenge
Acoustic amps
But each time the courts upheld the constitutionality of Japanese American incarceration
On November 21st 1945 a few months after the US bombed Hiroshima and Nagasaki and nearly four
4 years after the camp at first opened
The government closed
Manzanar for good
And dismantled the camp
Families were forced to move once again
People who can afford to leave on their own
We're giving a bus ticket in $25
Often they didn't have a home to go back
When Sue embry's parents return to Los Angeles they found that their old grocery store and house had been
Demolished
After sukuna told me Embry left camp
She moved to the Midwest for a little while but ultimately ended up back in Los Angeles
But it bothered her how little people talked about what Japanese Americans had been through during the war
So when she heard about a bunch of young college students making a pilgrimage to manzanar
She decided to join them
Which brings us back to that winter day in 1969
Went around 150 people travelled to manzanar to draw attention
To what happened there
The media showed up
At this pilgrimage
In December
Wind howling very cold
That's Bruce Embry
Suisun
He says
His mom and another person who had also been imprisoned at manzanar
Began telling reporters what life had been like there during the war
And it caused an uproar
I mean people were just completely
A cast
That
Anyone would speak
To the broader public
Outside the confines of the Japanese American community
About what happened
The older generation they were mad
Again Warren furutani
Who helped organize the poker
Why are you bringing this up
It's better left forgotten you know it's
The hatchets been buried leave it buried
But these activists were just getting started
Especially Sue Embry
I think the pilgrimage
Made her understand
How important the site was
The community
And I think in particular how
The community itself
Had to come to grips with what happen
Following the 1969 pilgrimage Sue Embry Warren for a Tony and others formed the manzanar committee
With the specific goal of getting the site recognized as a Historic Landmark
We felt that we needed Society to acknowledge
This fact
Knott's let it be buried
In the back pages are in a simple paragraph in the history book
They lobbied hard for 3 years all the while continuing yearly pilgrimages to the side
In 1972 the state of California designated manzanar a state landmark
And agreed to install a bronze plaque
It was one of the first public acknowledgment of what happened there during the war
So the warden of the plaque
Became a huge issue
Particularly the question of what to call Mandarin
Was it a concentration camp
An internment camp
A relocation Center
Is it still contentious today
Some people don't like the term concentration camp because it's associated with a Nazi Genocide
Then again
Internment camp
Feels like a euphemism
Don't let my mother-in-law I hear someone call it internment camp
And Jesus
93 year old
White haired
Petite
Dynamo Shield
Kick your ass
In the end after a few fiery meetings the manzanar committee convinced the state
The plaque should read as follows
In the early part of World War II
110000 persons of Japanese ancestry were interned in relocation centers by executive
Order 9066
Manzanar the first attend such concentration camps was bounded by barbed wire and guard towers
Confining 10000 persons
The majority of which being American citizen
Maybe in justices and humiliation suffered here as a result of Hysteria of racism
And economic exploitation
Never emerge again
California registered historical landmark
Number 850
1500 people attended the 1973 pilgrim
To watch the plaque
Get installed
But it didn't go over too well with some folks who lived in nearby towns
Within weeks
They've shot it below
Shotgun pellets
Someone Took an Ax to it to try and
Chisel off
The word racism
You can still see the bullet holes on the black today
But Sue Embry in the manzanar committee or undeterred
The fact they were already thinking bigger
They wanted manzanar to be a National Historic Site
It's important to know that all this was a crying alongside a larger
Find for redress and reparations
Several Japanese American organizations had demanded an official apology from the US government and payments for the
Those who have been incarcerated during the war
And in 1988
President Reagan signed the civil liberties Act
Getting $20,000 in reparations to every living person who had been sent to a camp
Piano payment
Can make up for those Lost Years
So what is most important in this bill has less to do with property than With Honor
Or here we admit a wrong
Here we reaffirm our commitment as a nation to equal justice
Under the law
Sue embree was very involved in the redress movement and she wanted to keep the momentum going in the fight to get manzanar turned
Into a National Historic Site
But the manzanar committee face stiff opposition from the Los Angeles Department of Water and Power
The DWP actually own the land
And the rights to its water
So here comes the middle-aged woman
Saying know this land is really significant to us our community and to
The region is south
And we won
It to be a national park while the DWP didn't want to have any part of that
The manzanar committee ended up drafting legislation for Congress
And Sue Embraer flew to Washington DC to testify before the US Senate subcommittee on public lands National Park
In forest
She says democracy is a fragile concept
Only as good and strong as the people who practice it
Let us tell the world that we are a
People
Strong
And resolute
Acknowledging the errors of our past
In order not to
Repeat them in the future
And this is the Legacy which we believe the master instructs site
Can leave for future Generations
The legislation passed
And on March 3rd
Manzanar was declared a National Historic Site
But apart from the cemetery there was hardly anything there
The National Park Service had to decide how they wanted to memorialize this Injustice
They formed a committee that included people who have been incarcerated at manzanar
And the committee decided that they didn't just want to museum where visitors could read about what happened on placards
They wanted to rebuild portions of the camp
Exactly as it had been during the war
So that visitors could feel what life had been like
C-walk in it's a
Empty room although we have a cot in the stack of army blankets and a stack of mattress covers
The bunch of cots up against the wall
This is Alyssa Lynch of the manzanar National Historic Site
Showing me a rebuilt bearing
She says they tried hard to get it right
But it's still not as harsh as it would have been when people arrive to
You're back in 1942
Give me the should be dirt blowing up to the floor
The building should be creaking
The thing is we have the option of either
Don't make a mess they were
But not allowing people to walk in
Because they wouldn't be safe for people to come into
Or we could rebuild them
2 earthquake standards accessibility standards
And that's what we chose to do
Outside there's a dirt basketball court
With white metal hoops and a one-way Road tracing a long and winding circuit
Through what used to be the
The camp
Signposts along the way show where specific buildings once stood
In some places cracked concrete foundations and the remains of Rock Gardens are still visible or have been
Earth
In the distance you can see a rebuilt guardtower
Is 40 ft tall
With lattice wood sides and a giant Searchlight at the
The top it was very controversial
Because a lot of the locals especially
Did not want it to have a guard Tower because
People don't want it to reflect badly on the community
The park service continue to seek guidance from folks who would actually lived at the camp
Overtime people have said over and over the most important thing to show by the guard towers and the latrines
I've had people literally say you know
We're glad you have the visitor center
We really like to have the barracks
But no one will ever understand
Until they go in and see that row a toilet
Alyssa Lynch takes me to the site's newest edition
A replica of a woman's latrine
The building wasn't open to the public when I visited but she showed me inside
It's just an open room
Does a long trough sink
And a row of five toilet
With no dividers
Between them
You hear over and over about the humiliation
You know I've heard women talk about
Having your first period in public
You know which I think is a very personal thing to all people all women
And
There's no privacy here
Lynch has spoken with hundreds of people who lived at manzanar
And they all have different perspective
It's on their time at camp
Some people fondly remember the friendships they built here
Others say the experience tore their family apart
Yes it had baseball teams
It also had a hundred and twenty armed soldiers
You know yes it has beautiful gardens but it also had guard towers
She just wants the site to show the full Messi history of what happened here
I think the national parks represent America at its best
And Americans at their best
And I think it's also good that we look at the times and we haven't been our best and it's the lesson
For the future
This site existence national park exist because of the efforts
I'm Ordinary People to make sure this their story wasn't
Swept Away by the wind
Or buried by
Those that don't want to be
I reminded of
Of the weaknesses
Of some in our past
That's Bruce Emery again
Every Spring he's one of the hundreds if not thousands of people who come to manzanar for the annual pilgrimage
The one that started back in 1969
They hold religious ceremonies and drumming performances
And remember what happened here together
But it's not just for Japanese-American
The lately
Ever since 9/11
The pilgrimage has
Almost always had
A speaker from the Muslim Community
In recent years the activist who lead the pilgrimage have tried to connect the wartime discriminate
Nation against Japanese-Americans
With contemporary discrimination
Against Muslim Americans in the name of security
It's really important that the parallels to what's happening today get raised
And
This is story I think that needs to be Amplified and and
Shout it from the rooftops so that America doesn't embark on some of the same
Non productive
Dove racist Behavior
This year's pilgrimage will happen on April 29th
Andrew stinks
It'll be the biggest yet
99percentinvisible was produces week by Emmett Fitzgerald with Sharif Youssef Delaney Hall Avery trufelman and
And me Roman Mars
Katie mingle is our senior editor
Kolstad is the digital director
Intern Mazza is the office manager
Original music was composed this week by genre
Special thanks to densho
Japanese American Legacy project in the manzanar National Historic Site for the use of their interview with Sue Embry
Are tons of remarkable oral histories of Japanese American incarceration
You can check out
At 10 show. Org
Where's some really amazing images of manzanar that compliment is episode that you should really check out by Ansel Adams and Dorothea Lange
What's really stunning contemporary photos that
Emmett took while he was up there
They're on our website 99 pi
. org
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
Even show angel in discussions about the show on Facebook and Twitter me at Roman Mars in the show at 99
DIY org run Instagram and Tumblr to if you want to get really excited with Kurt about how people in Finland
Strider dishes you have to go to 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com