99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman
It was the night of March 30th 2005
And the Powerball jackpot was 25 million dollars
On TV the white ping pong balls rolled out one by one as the host
39 Powerball is
That's producer Avery trufelman
When are the winter in Tennessee
But the way the Powerball drawings work
They're usually some second-place win
Guess all of the numbers
Except for the very last
On average there are three or four of these play
But on March 30th 2005
There were 110
2nd place winner
Was there a computer glitch that played all the same number like someone compromise
This is journalist
Jennifer 8 Lee Lottery officials are planning to know because
Like something
Izzat
So the next day as the winners around the United States came to collect
The Powerball officials asked
So where'd you get
Your number from
And each of them have the same answer
They'd gotten their numbers
From
Fortune cookie
They were different cookies in different states
But they all had the same fortune
And the same lucky numbers
Very
F****** numbers
And so destructive
Made you realize like how
Much Portuguese and Chinese food
How to become an American
Chinese food along with
Pizza in the Frankfurter has been adopted in modified to become American Cuisine
Rooted in some good old-fashioned American xenophobia
The early waves of Chinese immigration in the 1850s
The new Chinese population work mostly As Miners and farmers and laborers
Americans as ever
We're concerned about these new immigrants
Taking away jobs
And it was actually only after huge anti-chinese backlash
That the Chinese actually moved into field
When was laundry is Handy one
Was
Restaurant Chili's for cleaning and cooking
They were saying
No longer
And as their livelihood depended on it
Chinese restaurant owners made up dishes to cater to American tastes
American basic like things that are sweet and their fry dinner chicken
And that's how dishes like Chop Suey were invented
Chop Suey the name actually means
Sordid peace
Like odds and ends
Chop Suey the biggest culinary joke that one culture is ever played on another
Chop Suey is not real Chinese dish
At all
It's as American as apple pie
And speaking of apple pie
Americans want to start because we are American and we waiting for
Are sweet and fatty
She needed a dessert and as Chinese desserts go there aren't that many options that the American pallet wood go for
The Chinese desserts like
There is a Mooncake which like taste and looks like a hockey puck but like there's there's not there's not a lot of stuff
And so rather 1920s the fortune cookie somehow enters the American Chinese restaurant culture
Where they came from originally is a bit of a mystery
But we'll get to that
First let's make this
Perfectly clear
The cookies
Arnott
From China I don't know why the Chinese
They don't need a fortune cookie
Steven Yang is founder of Yang's fortunes Incorporated
Chinese people in China don't eat fortune cookies
But Americans consume billions of them
Which means great business for season
Because he prints a lot of the paper fortunes that go inside fortune cookie
If a phone anyway I would have New York Boston
Houston anyway all you can see my fortune
Including all the fortunes for Panda Express
That's definitely Steven biggest client
Stevens tiny Warehouse in San Francisco's Dogpatch
Is filled with boxes
Also
Stuffed full
Of tiny strips
Fortune paper
Each box
Contains 300,000 paper
Portuguese
Alpena Lottery
Econo Lodge
See and Stephen Prince all these boxes and boxes with only five other employees and Lisa
Stevens daughter
Writes all the fortune
When I visited she was away on maternity leave
But she is written most of it companies 5000 unique fortunes
This is amazing because we think about it fortunes are deceptively difficult to ride
The messages have to be really really generic because they could be four
Anyone
You can't read messages like you will meet a tall dark stranger because an eight-year-old could read that and be like
I don't want that
Why would we
And fortunes also have to be careful not to offend
Famously there was once of Fortune that said lighten up
And a lot of customers were like
Is this cookie calling me fat
Intercourse no bad predictions
Americans like their fortunes
Sunny
So fortunes 10w Vape
Or just generally uplifting like tomorrow will be better
Or the fortunes are nab's from quotation books
Just whatever Lisa can find
Stephen doesn't really care
He doesn't read them
I don't know why the American people didn't like it
He said he would do when they got a 14
After eating dinner
Keeping the water
The keeper
Yeah that's true
Some people do keep the fortunes in their wallets
When I asked around it turns out a few of my friends do this or can recite their favorite for it since from memory
And it's crazy because a lot of these fortunes are Stevens
Written by his daughter
Lisa
But there are a few ways to tell we're abortions come from
If you get one with blue corners on it that was printed by a giant company in New York called wonton food
They make over 4 million cookies a day and we're responsible for the cookie that made all those Powerball
Winners in 2005
If your fortune has smiley faces on it
It was probably printed by a Chinese company
For the American Market
Of course
And if the fortune doesn't have blue corners or smiley faces chances are it was one of the many thousands that Steven
And all different
Colors and fonts
And send the factories all over the country
Including the Golden Gate Fortune Cookie Company in a tiny Alleyway in San Francisco's Chinatown
The Golden Gate fortune cookie
Company is pretty touristy
It charges visitors 50 Cent's of photo and doesn't actually have a very big cookie
Actually calling this place a factory is kind of an overstatement
It's just one narrow room
With most of the space taken up by three hulking Fortune Cookie Machine
Versions of machines that were invented
By Edward Lewis
My father used to call his submachine like this fourth child
He had three sons and then the 4th what's his
Baby
Memory one of Edward Three Sons
Met me at the Golden Gate fortune cookie
Company these fortune cookie machines are pretty simple
Fix bottom round absorb outer onto a conveyor belt
In a worker sits next to this Bell and fold the hot cookies around the paper fortune
One by one
My hand
And
We pick them up as you see them doing here
Hold it and put them on a conveyor named learned how to fold the cookies when he was around eight years old
The Lewis family used to have a fortune cookie company of Their Own
It was our whole life
Even during dinner
Which upshifts
Somebody eats the other one work
That's how we did it.
We used to call ourselves the prisoners
That was a famous saying
Help I'm a prisoner in this
Fortune cookie
Ming's father later developed the next generation of Fortune Cookie Machine
Fully automated version
Which also.
And because of this technology
Fortune cookies
Is are widely available
And cheap enough
At restaurants can give them out for free
No one in the movie Family really question where the cookies originated
But it was a mystery that other people try to solve
People like Sally Osaka
She knew they were not invented in China
What do you mean the Chinese fortune cookies
Japanese
Sally osaki is California born and raised
But her parents came from Japan in the early 1900s
When I was a child
Fortunes
Used to be in Japanese
Rather than the Chinese character
And the cookies weren't something you get
At the end of a meal at a restaurant
They come in a bag
And mostly I know who we got them when I was a child
Was we would go see Japanese movies
Sew-in Sally's California childhood
The cookies were a casual snack
But if you chase them all the way back
To their Origins
In Japan
You actually find them
At a shrine
There you will be able to find
Is Japanese Bakers grilling fortune cookies
Shrine in Kyoto specifically to dry them
But they're not like the fortune cookies we see in the United States are like
Bigger and Browner and they're actually kind of everything nutty Savory flavor so they're more cracker like
But still there that same iconic fortune cookie
U-shaped we all know
There's actually an old Japanese image of a baker folding a cracker
That dates back to 1878
Decades before the first reports of American fortune cookie
One of the bakers that I spoke to
Thought that
Fortune cookies they designed
She look like a bell in Part B
Because her Bells all along the path
Come to the shrine
But then why don't we eat it after sushi
Cuz I keep or not eating sushi in like 19
When Japanese immigrants were opening businesses in the 1920s there was no market for Japanese food again
Like a Chinese immigrants
Before then
They Pander to American taste
So a lot of the Japanese families
Ran a lot of Chinese restaurant
And these Japanese families ran American Chinese rest
Full of Chop Suey and other Pho Chinese cuisine
Annie's Japanese owners
Would throw in a fortune cookie
For dessert
When Sally was a kid fortune cookies were still made in Japanese bakeries in both LA and San Francisco
And the fortunes were still in Japanese
And then something happened that completely disrupted
Everything about Japanese American Life
Life in this country
And I don't know if you know that the Japanese-Americans hundred
20000 of us
During World War II were sent away
I was nine years old when we got sent to
Sally and her family were farmers
In Fresno
They were summoned to a train station
And sent off to a camp in Arizona
You had to carry whatever your day
That was a child I would carry that much
Pictures of small suitcase
And I remember my mother
Took me
To Us store
Our town
She heard that
Victorian era
Desert in Arizona
Do rattlesnakes and scorpions
Other word yeah oh yeah gila monsters and
Scorpions in
Rattlesnakes Young
In the camper parents were given jobs at her and hardly any money
Valerie lesbian
$16
Are $18
For 4 years
From 1942
California's Japanese
And Japanese American community
He was marooned in the desert
Out of sight
Attitude acacian
And out of business
Including a lot of Japanese Bakers & Japanese restaurant owner
My recollection was that
After we came out of the camps
What was the Chinese fortune cookie
The Chinese actually
Commercialized it
And
Did all the Chinese restaurants that are deserving
Thanks to Chinese business owners
And later
Edward Louie fortune cookie
Machines
The Chinese American fortune cookie
As we now know it
Flourished
It's nearly impossible to pen the Americanization of the cookie to one specific Japanese-American
Baker or Chinese American Restaurant
The transfer from Japanese cracker to American Chinese cookie was a larger phenomenon that occurred
Or less
Across California
And then swept the rest of the United States
And then the world
Except
For China
They still don't eat pork
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman with Katie mango Sam Greenspan Kurt Kolstad and Mero
This episode was largely inspired by Jennifer 8 Lee
The fortune cookie Chronicles which goes into even more depth about the origins of American Chinese
Cuisine and believe me now our way deeper depth
It's Gregory
Has Jennifer got a new passion project that needs your help designers
Weed is great project at the White House in your public library or inviting everyone to redesign covers for public domain books
Still need covers for titles like Peter Pan and The Secret Garden
You can learn more about it a recovery in the class
Sex.com
Special thanks to John Schmidt and needs to go crepe
Baton provided music for the show this weekend
Sally osaki highly recommend
By Richard Reeves
Invisibles project 91.7 kalw San Francisco
An architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California right next to Oakland Chinatown in
Future ever in Oakland Chinatown on 9th gatorfeet robbed will make your life better
Unpaid endorsement for getting your feet rubbed
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to see cow
Go to oh my God. Info
Podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and Lancaster on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but you can listen to everything
Single episode of 99% invisible
NC pictures at 99 pei.org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Steve your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth pot
Dot-com