99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Imagine for a moment the year 1800
The doctor is meeting the patient
Most likely in the patient's home
The patient is complaining about shortness of breath
Fever
The doctor listens to the patients complaints
Asks a ton of questions
Scribble some notes
Producer Emmett Fitzgerald
And the doctor might check the patient's pulse
But unlike today what's happening inside of the
Patient is
Basically unknowable
There's no MRI no x-rays
The living body is like a black box
It can't be open
The only way for a doctor to figure out what's wrong with a patient
Is to ask
You needed the patient to tell you what was wrong and what they were suffering
So doctors were
Very interested in the patient's history the story of what the symptom was how long it had been there how had it change
What made it better what made it worse
This is dr. Jacqueline Duffy
I am a hematologist
And a historian of medicine at Queen's University
Was all the doctor had to go on
The symptoms were often seen as in themselves
So for example today if you have a fever
You think of it as a symptom
Of some underlying disease
It's like the flu
But back at the turn of the 19th century
The fever is
Self was considered the disease
They're all different kinds of fevers
And fever itself was a broad category of diagnosis
Because doctors had no way of connecting symptoms
With what was actually going on inside the body
Until someone built a device that would help the doctor
Open the black box
And travel inside the human body
And suddenly the doctor could hear everything so much more clearly the heart
Salons the brat and everything
The inventor of the stethoscope was unsurprisingly a doctor
Rene laennec was born in Brittany in 1781
And she went to medical school in Paris
Where you learn to practice percussion
A technique in which the doctor Taps their fingers against a patient's chest
And listen to the sound
To determine things like if
Fluid is building up in the patient's lungs
Lennox uses the technique for years and in 1816 he's examining a patient and he produces her
Torso
She's a little bit plump and because she's plump he's not getting much sound back from for cussing
He thought about putting his ear right against the
The patient's breast but he decided that that would be inappropriate
So we took a notebook
That he had with them and he bolted up into a little cylinder and he put one end on the patient's chest and went in on his ear
Angie tells us
He was clearly he could hear her and her breath sounds
Satisfied to hear the beating of the heart in a manner that was clearer and more distinct than I had ever heard
Idirect application
The ear
She was so impressed by the quality of the sound that he said about trying to construct the
The perfect device
For listening to the internal sounds
The body
All based on that
Same cylinder
People said that he became a silandro maniac has cylinder Maniac because he
He was convinced
That the instrument
Mediating
Between
The two bodies of
The patient and the doctor improved but the doctor
Can use the lathe
Car cylinders out of wood
And at first he wanted to
Call his new device
The cylinder
But eventually he settled on the steps
Which means
To explore the chest
Line-X original stethoscope looks
Pretty different from the ones were used to
Do today it's a long tube-like cylinder it looks like a small handheld telescope
Line-X
Started using his new invention to listen to the heart sounds and the breathing sound
Sense of all of the patient
Summit Hospital
And he started to invent words to describe the sounds cuz nobody
Nobody had heard the sound before it
Lenoch and invented a way to hear the inner workings of the human body
But that wasn't enough by itself
He wanted to connect the sounds he was hearing in his patient
With what was actually happening anatomically inside their body
And how do you connect sounds to what's actually happening inside a body
You listen to people
Right before they died around the ward listening to all the patients documenting their
Listen to The Sounds they made and then connecting them to the discoveries he would make up their autopsy when they died
He thought that every abnormal sound heard with a stethoscope should correspond
Comical finding during autopsy found it equals
. anatomical finding later so that the stethoscope was a way of practicing the autopsy before the patient
I mean we're all this future cadaver is right but the stethoscope gave us a way of looking inside
Side of a body before it was dead to see what was causing a particular medical problem
In a relatively short period of time my neck made some discoveries using his stethoscope
For example he figured out that when a person has fluid beneath their lungs
They make a sound kind of like a goat
A sound he called egophony
He also discovered sounds that attract
With the different stages of tuberculosis
The number one killer in Europe
Set the time
Mainak publishes results linking different diagnosis with anatomical changes in the body that could be detected
Using his new stethoscope
Eye doctors
Who were his colleagues loved it did they felt that every disease would eventually
Be attached to an anatomical finding in and out of time
Chemical change
Some doctors began using Line-X new device themselves
Even put a diagram
I bet in his book so you could make your own quite easily
For you by any
Carpenter
And as these doctors use the stethoscope
To make more important discoveries about the body
New categories of disease were created
For example before the stethoscope
A lot of different ailments
Since we're all lumped
Into one disease
Call dibs
Which means
Shortness
Breath
But after Line-X
Shortness of breath
A various
Heart or lung problem
They could be diagnosed
Sing the stethoscope
Medical language completely changed
His doctors invented new anatomical words
Diseases
Bronchitis
Which means the inflammation of the bronchioles
The Airways that lead to the lungs
Little by little our entire understanding of disease shift
Became more objective
Diseases went from being constellations
Symptoms felt
Patience
Anatomical or chemical alterations inside the body detected by the doctor
This shift in how people thought about disease
Change the relationships between doctors and patients
With the doctors
Suddenly having a lot more power
Show before the stethoscope
Feel sick
The doctor had to find
But didn't matter what the patient
Line-X himself actually worried that many doctors were taking his ideas too far
He believed that listening to what patients had to say was still important to understanding disease
But the Quest for objective information about disease was underway
In the stethoscope
Was just the beginning
Then we got x-rays
Which do the same thing at the end of the 19th century and now we have CT scanners and MRIs and pet scans and all of these
Marvelous devices are basically trading upon the same Paradigm that the stethoscope brought along that we should be
Able somehow to image the pathological anatomical abnormalities inside the body
To reach the diagnosis
When is a patient has any symptoms at all or not
These new technologies have led to so many important discoveries about the human body and disease
Today we can
Spot tumors
Before they become life threatening
And diagnose problems like high blood pressure
Before it causes heart disease
But there are also patients today who struggle because they've got
Tons of symptoms
But the doctor can't find anything quote on quote wrong with
The Paradigm Shift brought on by the stethoscope has
Push doctors and patients further apart
The doctor is no longer visiting you in your bedroom
Interviewing
And you about every tiny detail of your
Experience
And sometimes patients end up feeling like just the collection of data point
Rather than a whole
Rene laennec died in 1826
Beta 45
Most likely from tuberculosis
Disease he and his stethoscope
Help us understand
It's been 200 years since he first rolled up his notebook and pressed
To that patient's chest
Medicine looks completely different than it did back
But somehow
The stethoscope
Has endured
There are certain tools of the trade that we have
Gotten rid of
So
You don't really see doctors carrying around this
Is big black bag
This is dr. Andrew Bomba
Is a nephrologist
A kidney doctor
And an assistant professor at the
Columbia University
College of Physicians and
Most doctors nowadays don't carry around reflex hammers unless their new neurologist
Most doctors
Don't wear that light on their head
But the stethoscope has
Never really falling out of practice
Of course doctors aren't walking around with wooden cylinders anymore
In the 1840s they began experimenting with flexible tubing
And soon after an Irish physician invented the binaural stethoscope design
With two earpieces that we still use
Today
There are a few kinds of specialized stethoscopes
Particular types of listening
And more recently
Companies have developed electronic stethoscope
With enhanced sound quality and the ability
Need to record
But to this day when you walk into a doctor's office
Is for a routine exam
You can expect
The field familiar stethoscope
Sliding along your back
But that
Could be changing
Almost 200 years that trustee stethoscope has been at the Forefront of the diagnostic procedure
CJ constantly hanging around the necks of doctors and often used
New technology is threatening to Exile this old friend
To The Archives of medical history
X-rays and ultrasound have given doctors at Clear Window into the body than ever before
And with new portable ultrasound machines
Doctors can see an image of a hole in a patient's heart
Right from the bedside
The rise of portable ultrasound has some doctors arguing that we don't need the stethoscope
They say that
If you have that technology why not
Use it right away
But ultrasound isn't available
In many developing
And even in the United States
It's
Expensive
Tell me if we eliminated the stethoscope and everybody got an ultrasound at every visit
We would bankrupt our Healthcare System
This is dr. Dan Burns
A cardiologist at Stanford
University
He says that when he hears something problematic during the stethoscope exam
He immediately orders in Ultra
But do I start
With every patient who comes in the emergency room
Taking out the ultrasound machine looking in the lungs
I think that's not a good
Sabbatical
Right now he says the stethoscope functions as a screening tool
So that patients don't need to go get an expensive ultrasound unless they need one
Still there's no denying that advanced imaging has
Change the
Instruments roll
Dr. Andrew bomback says that medical students today aren't as good list
The body as they want
And across-the-board doctors rely Less on the steps
How to make a diagnosis
It's become almost a ritual more then
A actual
Tool of the trade
In terms of helping us make diagnosis
Recently one of doctor bombax most
Respected colleague
Please ask to borrow a stethoscope
End
Bombeck was embarrassed
Because the only one he had within that day was this
Cheap plastic disposable
But he handed it over anyway
And he said he thinks that's perfect he was walking away he's like no patience
Expect you to have this
When you see that I'm not going to really
Need to use
And I thought that was such a funny story because
There's someone that I consider the consummate clinician
And
He was acknowledging that
The stethoscope
Was in many ways just sort of a prop
But it's an omnipresent prop
If you do a Google image search
4dr
Right away you'll notice a couple of things about what a physician is
Supposed to look like
Most of the doctors pictures on the first page of results are white men in white coats
Some of them are appearing inside a patient's ears
Others are writing something down
My clipboard
But all of them
Stethoscope
But what I find so intriguing about the Google Images search
Is 4dr
Is knowledge every doctor wearing a
Stethoscope
But they are almost all wearing the stethoscope in the exact same way
Which is
Like a shawl
Around the back of the neck
With the earpieces on one side and the Bell on the other
Baumbach says that this way of wearing a stethoscope
Draped over the shoulders
Is a relatively recent
Fashion trend
The first time I can remember ever seeing that
Was on the television show ER
And then on Scrubs
Which is another very popular medical TV show
Doctors used to wear their stethoscopes
Dangling down the front of the shirt like a tie
And this was
If you needed to use your stethoscope in a hurry you just
Pop the interior
It's almost like this new version of wearing it like a scarf or shawl is almost a concession that is more fattening
Accessory
Then actually a tool that were using
But even if the stethoscope exam has become something of a ritual
It doesn't mean that doctors are ready to give it up
And I would never give up my son
Because
I think in the very least
It's this conduit
2 connecting with the patient
Bombeck says babe
Physical contact between a doctor and a patient
Has become increasingly rare
Doctor's visits are short
And Physicians often spend half the time staring at a
Computer screen
The status quo
Provides an important opportunity
For intimacy
The stethoscope is still
A part of the exam that is still very much aligned with that idea of the laying on of hands that A Healer can do when we go to the physical
Omar desk we move away from the computer we stand right next to the patient
And it's a much more intimate conversation
And even with all these powerful
Tools for measuring what's going on inside a body
Intimate conversations are still really in
Important in medicine
Dr. bomback says he thinks that the
The stethoscope has come to symbolize
At the doctor is there too
And
Whether we're actually listening to their heart or their lungs is probably not that important but but they really want to know is that we're listening
Into what they say
200 years ago
Renee Line-X invention ushered in a new medical era
One with the patient's own understanding of their disease
Gateway to more objective observation of the body
This turn put a certain amount of distance
Doctor's patient
Today maybe the stethoscope lives on to keep Physicians and patients from drifting too far apart
Make sure doctors keep close to their page
And he pussy
99percentinvisible will be back in a heartbeat
Epididymis
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
Cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Hey it's Emmett
Okay so real quick
Before we go
Remember when I mentioned that there are these new electric
Tronix stethoscopes
Well one is made by this
Company echo which is based right here in Berkeley
And they're stethoscope can record a patient's heartbeat
Display the waveform
And they're even working on software that can help doctors identify irregularities
I stopped by their offices and ass
Record my heart
Depressed advice to my chest
And a little way Farm popped up
Stop here you see the heart start to fire
Yoshi City that's called a P wave right there
That's a co-founder Connor landgraf
And while he is not a doctor he says my heart looks healthy
Pretty normal-looking iPhone nothing really interesting looking
In their unfortunately
So just to send us off
Shear's myON
Fortunate
Well and you have a very disappointedly
Boring harpy
Sorry boss
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald with bugs and help from Delaney Hall answer effusive
I see you producer is Katie mingle Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
The music was by Sean real includes Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
Digital music this week bar friends okay akumi and melodeon
Special things to honor Prager
Who sparked this idea for us
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
I'm beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are proud founding member of radiotopia from PRX supported by the journalism defending Knight Foundation
And coin carrying listeners
Just like you
You find the show Angel discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
When Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But we have all the past episodes in at least two articles
Books about design published on our website every week
At 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com