99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There's this Photograph back on the wall here in the studio
The photo shows three men wearing bowler hats
Two of them and bowties
I'm looking dead on into the camera with this casual look
Of Conquest
Please raise
Hands on hips to spend admitere on the lifted arm of a giant dredging machine machine
Use the force the natural environment to bend to the will of humans
Even if you don't know this image in particular
Keep seeing images like it
Teams of people standing around probably looking good
As they shape the Earth
What fascinates me about the pictures from this time is that they speak to this moment
When was a real sense of awe and reverence
For the marvels of civil engineering
Now I don't mean to Oprah romanticize this stuff
A lot of things we did for the sake of progress or ethically dubious if not outright horrible
They were mountains tunnel Hills flatten
Swamp strain
But the environmental impact notwithstanding these Feats of engineering work. Amazing for their time there
Amazing for our time
The photo I'm talking about the three guys in bowler hats on the dredging machine
Is a scene from The Rubber Soul on the Chicago River
And the reason that photo is famous
Are these famous enough for me but I've seen it
Is because the reversal of the Chicago River
Was an enormous engineering project that was
Successful
But you got to figure there were countless other photographs depicting similarly awe-inspiring Feats of engineering prowess
That we have never seen
Because those feeds
Never got finished
They were you can say
Failures
Today with the story of one such failure which
4 people finally gave up on it
Probably also wants included a moment
A man
Posing
Machinery
So actually I do have a photo we can start from
Fated to 1890
Reporter Julia Barton grew up in Dallas Texas
Broadway takes place
These men
A few of them in bowler hats
Are standing on a wide flat boat
With a winch
A chain and hook dangle down from the winch and they're holding up a
Tree stump
Boats in a narrow muddy river and it's surrounded by
Huge piles of broken up trees and other debris floating in the water
The boat's name
Snagboat Dallas
Dallas man I love that name
Growing up in Dallas
I never saw a pic
Pictures of things like the snagboat Dallas of Dallas
I never heard of the failed project
Generations of Dallas people spent their lives pursuing
Even though it concerns an engineering project
So massive
But it was once compared to
Do both the Panama Canal
And the Great Pyramids of Giza
This is the story
Deport
Of Dallas
If you know anything about Texas geography
You probably at least know that Dallas is not
Close to the ocean
At all
It's more than 300 miles
To the Gulf of Mex
That's like trying to build a port to the Pacific Ocean in Reno Nevada report to the Atlantic and Eastern Tennessee
But unlike Reno or Eastern Tennessee Dallas is at least
Located on the river that flows to the ocean
The trinity
In Dallas though the Trinity is really low
And very narrow
So narrow that there are stories of Dallas's first ferry boat on the Trinity turning itself sideways to act as a bridge
From time to time
So the Trinity was not a great way to move
People are Farm crops to
But neither was the alternative
In the early days of Dallas in the 1840s and 1850s getting mood on a boat
They were in the back of a wagon getting pulled by a team of oxen
Railroad came to Dallas in 1872
The railroad companies could and did raise their rates whenever they felt like it
Dallas leaders wanted River navigation to keep access to the outside world
Affordable
But in addition to being low and narrow
The Trinity River is incredibly long and winding
Even though Dallas is about 300 miles to the ocean
Crow flies
With all the trinities Meandering
It's closer to 700 miles River
The few boats that made it to Dallas from the Gulf
Nearly a year doing it
One of them was the aforementioned
Snag boat Dallas
Dallas
Which clear debris called snags out of the water
To make a river navigable
Steamship
One of the first of those was the steamboat Har-Ber
When the AHA Harvey Jr finally made it to Dallas in 1893
The city went
Nuts
There was a massive
The parade the local paper printed it
It's front page
In red
It was a huge day and they declared
Dallas had become a Port City
Is resolved that leaving the city directories
Like a 19-1 city directory just got describes Dallas as a Port City
That's Dallas historian Darwin Payne
In the dynamic he's describing here in the city directory is very important
Dallas
There's the actual version of events
And then there's this
Grossly optimistic
Make version
And as I was researching the story
This kind of
Roostery salesman voice
Kept coming at me in different forms
Telling me that something that way
Absolutely
Untrue
Absolutely was true
We had Dallas Warren actor William Jackson Harper boy's various clippings from the written record of the 103
30 year old history of the Trinity project
Curious as the Dallas Times-Herald in 1893
Interesting
The navigation of the Trinity is not
A possibility it is an accomplished
Yeah BHA Harvey made it
But that's just one boat
For more books to follow
The river would have to become easier to
Remember this is the era of getting done
We got to move the River Vine let's move the river
Dallas convinced Congress to survey the river and figure out where locks and dams could help make it navigable
The Army Corps of Engineers finished the First Lock and Dam in the early nineteen hundreds at a site 13 miles below Dallas
But eventually Congress shelter
The locks and dams that had already been built
Mouldered
Locks
Damn
Along the river
Stood deserted
Moss-covered
And just as it had done before the white man came to text
Did an Empire
Wilderness
Trinity River
Muddy
Unclean
Turtle Inn
Festival
Wound sluggishly
23isBack
But then the port of Dallas caught a second wind
The Trinity may have been
Turtle infested
But it wasn't always plug
In 1908
The River flooded
And it made a mess
Dallas
It turned downtown Dallas into
Peninsula surrounded by raging flood
It devastated the city
And as result of that
Dallas
Are George Kester to created what was known as the tests were playing
Kessler was a famous urban planner
European trained but
Spent part of his youth in Dallas
He created a vision for the city that included Boulevard
Parks
But the part that really excited Dallas leaders
Is how Kessler reimagined
Mandarin
He envisioned it
Becoming a straight Channel about a half-mile West
Existing course through Dallas
Levies
Pain the new channel
And open up miles of flubbed
Development
Right neck
Downtown
Basically they moved the river out of downtown
Even if you do know the geography of Dallas it's hard to picture exactly what this means the project was even bigger than
Then you would think cuz it involved changes in the road roadways going over
The
Sewer systems in in utility connection
And a huge Earth moving project course
Supposed to say this was the kind of enormous project where there be pictures of giant machines Top by men in bowler hats
So fedoras would have been more in style
And so starting in 1928 The River moving project was a go the city of Dallas Doug Trinity I-20
6 Mile straight shot Channel
With tall Levi is on either side of an 1/2 Mile apart
Perfect for the commercial barges than Our Place Steamboat
And make no mistake
Historical record shows that even though this massive project was on its face
About flood control
Dallas leaders at the time
Saw this at the resurrection
The port of Dallas
So in 1930
You got another ceremony for the port of Dallas
A bottle containing the Sweet Sweet Waters of the Gulf of Mexico the final destination of the Trinity River
Smashed over a dredging machine
As people cheered on
A local Pastor gave the Benedict
Vision
See the coming Millions
When are virgin acres are up turn to the smiles of
Resources developed
Show people
They really like to lay it on thick I'm going to stay
And from there
The plan to build a port of Dallas
Was really
Underway
There was a general will for it there was political clout
Behind it
And it was eventually money to fund it
The Army Corps of Engineers came up
With a really big
Plan
To change the whole course of the trinity
Palau boat
Dallas
And even further Upstream to Fort Worth
President John F Kennedy just a month before he was assassinated in Dallas signed off on a huge 900
Billion dollar spending package for the trinity
And despite the
PR nightmare that
Rafael Dallas
JFK's death
The river play
Plan kept on moving forward
After all the new President Lyndon B Johnson
Was a Texan
And he was a favorite
The project
Give me is talking on the phone in 90s
68 with Fort Worth Congressman Jim Wright
Okay honey
I had a long hard week but a good run I think we got your things
I think we all know we're working on
I guess that'll be the major cronyism of the camp
The rest of us
Dallas was ready
In anticipation of the soon-to-be navigable Trinity River bridges constructed over the river
Extra tall throughout seagoing vessels clearance
Underneath
Most bridges are constructed 15 to 20 feet of existing Terrain
Wellies do high-rise Viaduct
Rise to well over 60 ft
One reason is so they may handle the hook for and sought-after Barge traffic
Xfinity performance claim will pour into the Dallas-Fort Worth area
It's been a hundred and thirty years
That's about 115 years longer than it took to build the Great Pyramid of Giza
Dallas is finally becoming a port city think of what this means
Riverboat gambling cruises
Heavy industry
Loading dock
Fisherman
Longshoreman
Stevedores
Romantic picnics on the Levee
But then the port of Dallas in his neck
So to speak
It went out not with a bang
But with the wine of a jet turbine engine
The great irony is that while all of this was taking place in the early 1970s Dallas and Fort Worth were bill
Burlington International Airport
Ramp transition is
Film producer
Who made a documentary about the trinity
For Dallas is public.
TV station
Kera
He says
The massive DFW Airport invigorated
The newest
Regrowing hair
Dallas was deindustrializing
The city of mood from its reliance
Agriculture
Trade
2 technology
Light manufacturer
Banking
Insurance
Companies like Ted
Texas Instruments
On the rise
They didn't need
Barges to reach the outside world
They had an airport
Am I considered judgment
The panel station to Riverwoods
Probably make Dallas feel the way of the other four cities with the flu to channel which Houston I asked
Increase crime and increase during a deterioration of the inner city
Alan Steelman who ran for congress in Dallas in 1970s
He ran against the
You're not locating in Dallas
And he won
Soon after that voters rejected a referendum to spend their tax dollars on the canal
So right when the dream of those men aboard the snagboat Dallas of Dallas was finally on the cuss
Reality
The dream was that
Dallas would not become a Port City
Which is really a shame
Navigate Dallas need to be Airport
But because they totally messed up the natural landscape of the city
Remember that the port of Dallas project
Eventually included The Kessler plan
But you literally move the river and channeled it into a man make now outside of town
The Trinity River used to meander through the center of Dallas
It's hard as I can guess the civil engineering needs of the time I mean
River did flood the city pretty regularly
But one can't help but think
Did this could have been a nice Riverfront for people to stroll along
A beloved piece of nature in the middle of the city
The board of Dallas not only failed
Stole the natural Riverfront
From the people of Dallas
Like a lot of people of my generation groin
Map of the 70s and 80s
I didn't really know there was a river in Dallas at all
You can
Kind of see the Trinity River in the
Title sequence of the
Tv show Dallas
Which launched in 1978
Put the camera mostly lingers on the
Skyscrapers
In real life you might catch a glimpse of the River Forest
Split Second
If you look down from one of those High freeway Bridges
More often
You'd smell them
A lot of Dallas
Does untreated sewage.
In the 70s
There were
After a hard rain in in Dallas
Thing that called the black rice
Wood Royal Downstream and
Kill everything in
The toxic sludge wasn't
The worst
In the river
I'm talking about
Dead body
The Trinity River Bottom wisdom
Place where you tie the Eva
Sketchy and unlit
It was so dark
Set If you flew into Dallas at night
You could pick up
The floodway B
It was completely invisible
This dark artery flow through the heart
You would never think of going
Never
But of course Julia now had to go there
She got in a canoe that's called the snack new Dallas or Dallas
Easy the snagit
12 are you going to go to the right or the left
Trinity River resumed its natural winding course South of downtown Dallas
It flows through a dense hardwood forest
This part of the river bottom was left alone for decades because the plan was to someday bulldoze all this into a big turning
Basin in loading area for barges
Now the Audubon Society has built a center at the edge of the forest and it leads canoe and kayak rides for
Urban River floors
Not
The suburbs
So you got 26 mile of river diverted
Into a walled-off artificial Channel plus another long stretch shielded by dense forest
Making that easily accessible for public use is the huge urban planning challenge the Dallas now has thickened
Done with
Good news is that the people now realize that this man made and man neglected landscape is the river they have
And that's better than pretending that they have no River at all
It's a strange place
Not exactly comfortable
But not the nightmare of my choice
Childhood imagination either
It's a landscape
Stuck in it
Patient of something
That never have
In the course of history there are plenty of undertakings just as unlikely that the board of Dallas
We just don't think of the reversal of the Chicago River or
To the Panama Canal
As polysorb forget about them entirely because Against All Odds
They succeeded
And they were crowned with much hat-wearing and machine posing
But when an engineering Endeavor fails
Sometimes all we get our scars in the landscape
If we're lucky
We get to try again
Make something good out of it
Like a park
Hopefully with a plaque
I'd like it if they put up a black
99% invisible was produced this week by Julia Barton
The same Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced out of the offices of Art
An Architecture Firm in the beautiful downtown Port of Oakland
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sand
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
X-Men episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
And keep up with all the comings and goings at 99 Pi on Twitter or Facebook Tumblr Instagram and Spotify I said hi to a
Every single person is indicted me on Twitter
You thought I was kidding
Was not getting
And you're always welcome at our place and then
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I got a Thang
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com