99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In July 1980 a group of Salvadoran immigrants cross the border from Mexico into Arizona
They walked over an isolated mountain range and halfway across a wide Desert Valley there were more than two
Two dozen of them
People who love behind lives and jobs
To come to the United States
They hired some guys to leave them on the journey
Reporting our story this week is Delaney Hall
And those guys had brought them to a largely uninhabited part of the Border
It was a bath
Empty and fatally hot stretch of the Sonoran Desert
The temperature the next day got up to around a hundred and 1215 degrees out there
Was deadly
This is John 5
Peter Presbyterian Minister from Tucson
Which is a couple of hours from where the migrants cross
They were in the middle of the most desolate
And and deadly area of the desert
And I think out of the group of
12 of them died
The first day out
The survivors were eventually found
Delirious and suffering from intense dehydration and Heat
Some of them had stripped off their clothes
Border patrol agents brought them to a hospital in Tucson
Which is where Reverend John Feit
And they are some of us who are
For pastors
To provide some pastoral care for the survivors who were
Traumatized behind
Understand
And they began to tell me
Why they fled El Salvador
At that point rev-5 had lived in Tucson for more than 10 years
We need a small congregation at a church called Southside Presbyterian
He didn't know much about Central America
Or what was going on in countries like Nicaragua Guatemala and
El Salvador
Around this time
Not only ignorant but I couldn't put El Salvador on a map
I knew it was somewhere between Mexico and Panama but that was the extent of my knowledge
So
So I had a lot to learn and a lot of catching up
People of El Salvador
El Salvador Civil War had been decades in the making
Since the early 1900s the country had been ruled by a series of oligarchs and corrupt military leaders
They maintain control over pressing large segments of the rural population
In the late 1970s and early 1980s
Number of left-wing Guerrilla groups
Begin to grow in power and info
The military responded by trying to
Crushed
Death squads targeted union leaders Community organizer
And other people they suspected of sympathizing with
The Gorillaz
That included priest
And nothing
Lots of civilians were caught in the middle of the
Violence
Thousands
People word
Disappeared murdered words
And El Salvador wasn't the only country where this was happening
Similar conflicts were unfolding in Nicaragua and Guatemala where authoritarian governments were facing pressure
Left-wing Rebels
This is the history Reverend John by started to learn about
What do you meant the Salvadoran migrants who nearly died in the desert near to
But basically they were telling me why they fled
El Salvador
About
Threats from Death Squad
Killings of members of their family or close friends that sort of thing
And and the reason why they they had
He didn't know it then
But rev-5 was witnessing the beginning of something big
Hundreds of thousands of central Americans were trying to get away from these dangerous and bloody Civil War
They were fleeing their countries
Making their way through Mexico
In Crossing into the United States
So a major
Migration of refugees occurred along this border during that 10-year period beginning in 90
Reverend 5church set less than 100 miles from the border
And it would be completely swept up
In this crisis
Eventually Fife in his congregants would give shelter to hundreds of central Americans
Baby joined by a network of churches across the country
All opening their doors and giving migrants
A safe place to stay
This would Mark the beginning of a new and controversial social movements
Based on the old religious concept of sanctuary
The idea that churches have a duty to shelter people fleeing purse
Persecution more than 6000 people have signed up to provide Sanctuary around the country
Down on so-called
Sanctuary City
There are
There's been a lot of
Talk about sanctuary in the news recently
And the modern movement in the US
Can trace its roots back
2 rev 5
We're going to spend the next two episodes looking at how the sanctuary movement started
And how it caused one of the biggest Showdown
Between church and state
In recent history
After that first encounter with the Salvadorans at the hospital
Reverend fight begin to see more and more Central Americans arriving in Tucson
Some of them would come to his church
And ask for help
At first his inclination was to work within the rules of the immigration
I was
Pretty naive its hit point
And I went to the immigration office here in Tucson
Met with the director
And said we're seeing refugees
Who are fleeing for their lives
What do we need to do to protect them
And he said
Well we have good political Asylum law
On the books
And if they're deserving of political Asylum
If they're refugees they'll get political Asylum
Asylum you apply for if you are
Within the United States
And have a well-founded fear of persecution
I'm talking law
This is Ruth and Meyer
I was District director of the immigration and naturalization service
For Arizona
Nineteen Eighty-Four in a couple years later they added Nevada
Since 1980 when Congress passed the refugee Act
The US has asked people to meet a number of requirements in order to be granted political Asylum they have to establish the
They fear persecution in their home country
Based on their race
Religion nationality political opinion
Her social group
They also have to convince immigration that their government is actually involved
In their persecution
Or if they can't control the group
Sitar
If someone shows up in the US
And they can meet those requirements
Supposed to be able to
Stay
But it's not always that simple
Myers used to interview people seeking Asylum if she says it could be tough to establish a person status
It relied heavily on a single individuals testimony about what they've been through
Depends on the individual
It depends on what they say and how they say it
And if they have any backing
So basically it was my decision
Based on my experience and
What the person said because
As you can understand
It was very little physical evidence
Despite the challenges of qualifying for a silent Reverend Fife in his church raise some money in organized legal assistance for the
The migrants I started visiting detention centers and helping people fill out Asylum application
Pay range for lawyer to represent them in court
But it began to seem like even the people who met their
Requirements for Asylum we're not getting
Like even in cases where there was four
Physical evidence
I can remember taking in a guy
Who had been tortured
In El Salvador
And
We flew in an Amnesty International Doctor Who testified that the address guys been tortured I'm an expert on
And the physical effects
Torture
And the immigration judge would order him
Deported the neck
Rev 5 begin to wonder what was behind these decisions
Central Americans hoping for Asylum face some significant
One thing just as they began turning up along the US Mexico border in 1980
Tens of thousands of refugees from other place
Buy Cuba in Tehran
We're also seeking refuge in the United States
The government was overwhelmed with application
Most Central Americans had also historically come to the US for jobs
Not because of political
Persecution
The government was more inclined to see them as economically
And on top of that
Where was the Cold War
Mr. speaker
Distinguished members of the Congress honored guests and
My fellow Americans
In 1983 President Ronald Reagan delivered a special televised speech before Congress
In it he outlined his concerns about the Civil Wars flaring up in Central America
2 minute photo Central America is just that place way down below Mexico that can possibly constituted
Red door will be
And that's why I've asked for this session
Central America's problems do directly affect the security
And the well-being of our own vehicle
And Central American Soul Central America is an important front in the Cold War
A region so close to the us that are National Security required us to stop communist movements from flourishing there
Nicaragua is Justice close to Miami San Antonio San Diego and Tucson
Have no cities are the Washington where we're gathered
Good night
Just a few years earlier in 1979
A socialist Revolution actually did happen
Nicaragua
The Saint Denis the National Liberation Front head elstad a us back to dictatorship
Which is ruled the country for deck
At the time of this speech
Reagan administration was sending Aid to contras fighting the new socialists and then he's the government
The US was also doing its best to suppress similar left-wing movements in El Salvador and Guatemala
Authoritarian governments that still had a grip on power in those countries
Information I say to you that tonight
There can be no question
The National Security of all the Americas
Is at stake
In Central America
Thank you
God bless you in German
So here's how this all connects back to Tucson and the deportations that Reverend fight with
Racine
Because the US government
Considered the governments of El Salvador and Guatemala
To be political allies
It's in the fight against communism
It denied these governments were person
Executing their own pee
The Reagan almost all Salvadoran and Guatemalan border crossers were classified not as political refugees
What is economic micro
That meant they didn't qualify for Asylum
They got sent back
Ruth Ann Meyers the former ins director in Arizona says immigration officers followed policy set by the
Which has broad discretion
When it comes to Asylum
The immigration officers
Weatherby enforcement or the Asylum officers or whatever
We're not making up their criteria are the wall
This all came from Congress
The result of this policy was
Stark when it came to Salvadorans in Guatemala
Between 1983 and 1986
You were than 3% of Salvadorans in Guatemalans who applied for Asylum or approve
Not same.
The approval rate for Irani ends with six
Bracken's fleeing the Soviet invasion it was close to
40%
Back in Tucson that put rev-5 in his congregants in a tough position
They didn't want to encourage migrants to report immigration when they knew it was almost certain they be deported
So they held a series of meetings to figure out what to do
And that's when Jim Corbett
Showing up
It's hard to describe him because he was
Unique
Figure
Jim Corbett died in 2001
The back in the 80s he lived on the edge of Tucson
Erase to goats
And he knew a lot
It's about philosophy
He was also a Quaker
And as the refugee crisis in Tucson continue to grow
Jim's religious Faith compelled him to take action
He started letting refugees stay at his house
And in some other ramshackled trailers scattered around his property
Jim starts coming to meetings at Southside Presbyterian Church where they're discussing the deportations
Another one of those meetings
Jim comes up to rev 5
And
His
Contention at that point
To me was
John I don't think we have any choice under the circumstances
Except
Begin to smuggle people safely across the border so that they're not captured and detained and deported
My response was how the hell do you figure that Jim
And he
Explain
Duke's Lane
The first was back in the 1800s when church people
A lot of them Quakers
Help to move runaway slaves across state lines and through the Underground Railroad to safety
And he basically said
We have to conclude from history that they got it right those were the folks who understood
Good and got it right
Dungeon pointed to the church and its failure to protect Jewish people fleeing the Holocaust in the 1930s
40s
Many Jews were detained and deported back to Germany where they were killed
Jim argued that Christians should have done more
And he said they
They failed
They failed,
As people of Faith as the church
And I said yeah you're right
And his punchline was
John
I don't think we can allow that to happen on our border
In our time
And after a couple of
Sleepless nights
I went back to him and said yeah you're right
I
Cannot be a pastor of a church
Beer on the border
And
Not
Do what you're asking
So
Sign me up
At this point Jim Corbett had already done some border runs on his own
Picking up migrants in Mexico and helping them cross the border into United States
But now Reverend Fife and a handful of others started helping him
At first they bring people across and put them up at Jim's house
Play quickly became clear they needed more space
So once again
Tim came to talk with Reverend V
He wanted the church to start hosting people
That was a question that the whole congregation had
How to deal with
And that's not an easy choice for
For people to me
They talked
And prayed and then voted to let Central American refugees stay
Soon On Any Given night
The church would have dozens of people sleeping in the main gather
Church members would provide food
Close English lessons Medical Care and access to legal advice
They help the refugees strategize about what to do
It wasn't as if the migrants were entirely safe
We're still undocumented
And face possible deportation
But they had access to resources guidance and a place
Stay
The congregation at Southside was drawing along religious tradition when they decided to take the refugees into their Church
It's actually
An ancient tradition of
Temples in
Churches and synagogues
And
And sacred sites
Of indigenous people
That goes back as far as any
History we know about
In Greek and Roman history people who are threatened with
Persecution could find protection in Temple
When the Roman Empire became Christian
Churches took on the same function
The concept of sanctuary can also be found in medieval canon law and British common law
Andaz nation-state evolved in Europe
Some of those Nations legally recognized
The rate of churches
Shelter
More recently
Churches sheltered conscientious objector
During the Vietnam war
But even though rev-5 was drawing on a long religious tradition
He is coming against we're still harboring undocumented immigrants who crossed into the country illegally
And as it turns out
Government was keeping an eye on their growing operation
Well what do we do under those circumstances
Dances in in the only conclusion we came to was
Well the only choice we have
Is
To go public
With what word
They thought maybe
By going public
The church could generate attention and Publix
They invited a couple of other churches to join them in a public announce
And in March of 1982
They hung two huge banners
On the front of the church
They said in Spanish
This is a sanctuary of God for the oppressed
Central America
And
Immigration
Do not profane sanctuary of
They held a service and publicly welcomed a new family from El Salvador
To join the other refugees who are staying at the church
And they stage press conference to explain exactly what the sanctuary movement was
And what their goals were
So yeah we we made some national news
The sanctuary movement has become a highly emotional issue supporters of that movement mainly church people
Refugees from Central America members of the so-called sanctuary
Illegal aliens from across the United States
Going to violate the laws of Nessa
Is the movement gain visibility it became more controversial
The federal government contends conscience is not a good excuse for violating the law
Our objection to any
Such move it
Is that
Text Louis Vuitton hats
Despite these government objections
The movement continue to grow
More and more churches and synagogues started to get in touch with rev 5
They call us and say
Can you send us a family we're going to declare sanctuary
A network started to develop
Richmond rev-5 in Jim Corbett
How to figure out how to safely transport refugees across the country to the churches that could support them
And so Jim and I basically sat
Down
Here
A map of the United States
And said okay who do you know in Albuquerque and who do you know in Denver and who do you know
Across the United States so we could move people
And we literally in one afternoon
Figured out an underground railroad in we modeled is on the old Underground Railroad
By the mid-1980s hundreds of churches and synagogues across the country had joined the sanctuary movement
Almost every mainstream church denomination and gotten involved
Including Lutheran's Methodist
In Baptist
Sanctuary volunteers came from a wide variety of political viewpoints including conservative
But everyone should have believed that churches needed to respond to the Central American crisis
These American churches were
We're connected to a network
Churches
Extended down into Mexico and Central America
So migrants could plug into
This network
And make their Way North
Some would find shelter in Mexico others would continue into the US
That's exactly what patricija Barcelo did
My name is Patricia Barcelo I am a refugee from Guatemala and I have lived in the United States since 1980
85 Patricia grew up in Guatemala City
Their parents were Union organizers during the Civil War
Which made them a Target
A big government
They live with my dad and my mom
Being involved in subversive Acts
In wanting to overthrow the government
And that was enough for them to kill you disappear you or
Another whatever they wanted to do to you
At one point patrizia's dad disappeared for many weeks
Ben 10
By the military are the
Police
Patrizia's family never learned exact
She came home
Being the shadow of a man that he was
Because he was so skinny in
Boney
Can a beard for long hair
My dad
But he's made it back
And
With him
Pita bread
Horrible story of torture
And things that had been done to him that
Humane
At that point patricios parents fled to Mexico City
Reading Patricia and her sister with their grandmother
The parents said they'd be in touch when they had a plan
For two years
Nothing
And then a letter from her mother
And the letter said
You know bring the girls to the Border
Bring him to this part in Chiapas
And I will be there waiting
Patricia and her sister across the border from Guatemala into Mexico and met their mom as a designated Park
They learn that she'd met some Quakers involved in the sanctuary movement
The Quakers told the family to head to Northern Mexico
But they were met by Catholic priest named father Ricardo elford
He worked closely
The drive-in 5
He wanted to know what happened in Guatemala
He wanted to know why we were
Wanting to come to the US
He said
You know just tell me
You know
What went on
Because you want to bring you
We just want to know what
We can do for you
And
My mom
Told him everything that happened
That the two and then he said
Everything is going to be okay
Father Alfred was wedding the fan
Just making sure they qualify
Is refugees
At the sanctuary Network had grown they've had to develop a more formalized
Process
This was partly to ensure their limited resources went towards helping p
People who were most
Stephanie
We wanted to try and ensure they weren't putting volunteers at risk
Bringing someone dangerous
Into US
What are the government's criticisms of the sanctuary movement was that they lack the expertise and resources to evaluate potential refugee
The government worried they might be helping criminals enter the country
Or communist
Who wanted to undermine the US government
Here's rev-5 again
I would just kind of smile and say
You don't understand the church
We have the best intelligence system in the world
As I understand what you say is you have 5c IAH
In El Salvador
Right now
I have thousands
They're called priests and pastors and all I have to do is pick up the phone and call them and they'll give me the whole fam
Family history
Once father Alfred was satisfied that Patricia and her family actually met the requirements for ref
ATT status
He arranged for them to be brought across the border from Tucson where they stayed at st. Michael's Episcopal
Another church in town that had declared sanctuary
You're living there for 6 months they moved into a house
And started the long process of applying to stay in the US
It took them more than six years of legal wrangling to receive Asylum
Patrizia still gets emotional thinking about what the sanctuary movement did for her and her family
I remember my parents
Talking about this and saying
You know
Who would do this
Who would risk their
Life
You know
The Good Life
Pier in the US
For people like us
But as the movement grew bigger and more visible
The whole Endeavor became risk
But quite frankly
I never thought we were going to get away with
The first time I went to the border to do a Crossing
1981 song
I had to get comfortable the fact
Fitbit
We weren't going to get away with
Did the government was going to come after
And it was only a matter of
John was right
It was only a matter of
Time
And the religious motivations of the sanctuary movement didn't get much sympathy
The from the government
They have the right to think what they want anybody.
That doesn't exclude them from obeying the walls of the United States
Somebody could say
I think it's my religious right to rob a liquor store
And I think most of us would say no it's not
Next week
Anthony 9% invisible
Undercover government informants Infiltrate The Sanctuary movement
Yeah couple of these guys I thought
They don't fit the usual Sanctuary violin
Profile
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Delaney Hall
What's refusive
Avery trufelman Ella Fitzgerald Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Our senior editor is Katie Mingle
Kurt Kolstad is our digital Direct
Turn Meza is the office
Sean real compose original music for this episode with a disco music by okay akumi and Melania
Special things to try
Party at the University of Arizona special collections
Injured party
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
Radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sign
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Message Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find 99percentinvisible and join discussions about the show on Facebook
Between a bi Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram and Tumblr to
You want to learn the subtle art of Wilderness Trail design that is the textbook definition
Of invisible design
You have to go
1099 TI
Dot org radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com