99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This sound is on mistake
Maybe you find it kind of like I do since it signifies the end of a trip to the grocery store
You found all the things on your list and now you get to just stand there and zone out for a second or flip through a gossip mag
Checkout person does the work that's our new producer Katie mingle I myself find that sound
A bit anxiety-inducing since it's also the sound of the total that I'm going to have to pay
Going up and up and up
And
When I go to the grocery store and check out
I'm utterly amazed at how well the stairs can read barcodes
No I don't tell the checkout people my wife always do
My husband here is the one that invented the barcode
I like those kind of look at yourself to say yeah I believe that
Course today
They would look at you in SF
To say you mean
There was a time they didn't have a barcode
It's hard to imagine now a world without barcode
A world
Without George lure
Hello hello
George J laurer
I'm the one
The UPC barcode
And symbol
In 1973
Found some of you might be saying to yourselves
I thought Joseph Woodland invented the barcode
Maybe you're saying that to yourself
You are a nerd
And I love you
And just hold your nerd horses because
We're getting to Woodland ride
Now
It started the way a lot of thing
People trying to make
More money
Video
Grocery business
Decided that they needed some way to reduce their overhead
One of the main places they felt they were losing money was the checkout line
They came up with the idea of having some kind of a scannable
Code
Which would move people more quickly through the line
One of the first people that started working on it with an engineer named Joseph
Woodland
After working on the Manhattan Project Woodland moved on to develop an Innovative way to produce
Elevator music
He was jamming on this project
Probably set to make a whole bunch of money until and this is according to Woodlands New York Times obituary
His father forbid him
Getting into the industry because it was
Controlled by the mob
So Woodland moved on from elevator music
2 barcodes
He was trying to come up with a symbol that when scanned would translate to a series of numbers that a computer could use
Identify a product
So one day he's sitting on the beach in Miami Florida
So the legend goes
And Woodlands thinking about his days in the Boy Scouts and more
As one tends to do on the beach
Any kind of absent-mindedly drawing in the sand with
His fingers
When suddenly he looks down
And he's got it
He's dragged his four fingers through the sand in the shape
A concentric circles
Instead of dot dot dot dash dash dash he thinks
Can you skinny and wide lines
Bullseye bullseye
The very first barcodes were in the shape of a bullseye
Actually they didn't call them barcodes yet
Woodlands convention was called a classifying apparatus and method
I'm really glad that we don't call him that anymore
That was 1948
About 20 years
The bullseye idea gathered.
The scanners and other equipment needed to put the system in place we're just too expensive for any of it to be feasible
Fast forward to 1970s
The technology is now a bit more affordable and a group of Supermarket executive led by a guy named Allen have
I like okay
Barcode or bust
Doing this
By that time there were a few other designs out there but none were purse
So they put together a list of qualities that their ideal barcode would have and ask 14 different companies to come up with
The Proposal
Could be no larger than one of those
1 1/2 square inches
How to have a good enough depth
Brookfield liquor to read
About a foot-and-a-half above the scanner had to be omnidirectional
That's George lower again
He was working at IBM at the
The time which was one of the companies competing to make the best
And most people thought
That a circular design like Woodlands
Would probably work best because of the way the scanners were
Those days
Just about every scanner
Was a single one
And you can just picture that if you had a single line and it was going in the direction of the bar it would not read
All the bars
Women's original circular design solved
Because it could be read from any direction
Batman the checkout person didn't have to take your bag of Cheetos and
Turn it in just the right wave
Before I could pass over the scanner
But George didn't think the bullseye symbol would work
I couldn't
Support
That is the solution to what the grocery industry wanted
Because
To me there was no way that it would fulfill their specifications
My Integrity just would not let me come up with a
Willow
Bunch of bull
So George went back to the drawing paper
My wife said life
Came back and I will work on it day and night
Come back at night
Again most of us was thinking arithmetic
Trying to prove that this would work
Also I have to admit how to disprove that some of the others wouldn't work
Ultimately came up with a rectangular barcode that fit more code into less space which was crucial since
Grocery manufacturers were already grumbling about having to make room for this new symbol on their packaging
But there was still the issue of the one line scanner
Somehow we got the idea that if we used an X
For the span powder
Which could be developed very easily with a pair of mirrors
The barcode can be read by the scanner and no matter which way it was oriented has it passed
Do even though Woodland came up with the original idea of using lines of various widths
George lure did more than dust
Teams that shape
From a circle to a rectangle
Improved on the symbol
The code behind the symbol
And the scanners that read the symbol
Even Joe Woodland thought so
Joe Woodland was
Very enthusiastic he worked with me
In fact he wrote the actual proposal
For the submission to the grocery industry
But it was
My
Invention of the particular symbol and barcode that we see today
The symbol selection
Committee unanimously voted
For George loros
Rectangular symbol in code
They called it the universal product
Kotor UPC
A year later in 1974
Pack of Wrigley's chewing gum
Became the first item to ever be scanned
With the UPC barcode
If barcodes engine invented
The entire layout of the architecture of Commerce would have been different
It impacts are very difficult to
Boris
My name is Sanjay Sharma and a professor of mechanical engineering at MIT
Sanjay Sarma has also worked with an organization called gs1
Afghans for Global standards one
And if you need a barcode on your product
You have to go
Do gs-12 get
Imagine
Delta telephone numbers 1 standardized
Bryce Canyon area codes
Two people can have the same phone number
When barcodes became the standard they didn't just make checkout lines faster
Payload stores to keep track of huge amounts of inventory and the collect data on what we were buying
Data they could use to keep us coming back for more
Without bar codes exist
But equally small store might need more employees
It's like degrees that
That makes a machine wrong that's one of the key you know elements of fun
Efficiency in our capitalistic system
When you put it like that you can see why for some people
The barcode has come to represent everything they hate about capitalism and consumerism
You can get wrapped candies every time bubble gum lollipop Fun Size candy bars
Just a dollar 89
Sellouts
Barcodes fall
But it's become the symbol or the glyph of
Technology we're afraid of don't understand or being
Cog in a wheel in a larger
Monolithic machine
The Matrix if you will owe why will my name is Jeri Whiting I'm the founder of Azealia soft we are here in
Seattle Washington
I've been
Writing software that prints barcodes
For 25 years now they aren't bad they aren't good they're just tools but most people look at them and don't even know where to
Start
So let's demystify for a minute and look at what's inside the barcode
Again what we're talking about here is the UPC barcode that George lure invented
Is the barcode that you and I and everyone in the world
Has had the most interaction with
The UPC barcode is divided into
2/2
It's actually two barcode sitting right neck
Each other
You can see this visually because there are these longer bars that
Come down in the middle and on each side
Those are called the guard bars
The guard bars tell the scanner that the code is starting and ending
The left half of the barcode tells you who the manufacturer is
And the right have tells you which
Particular product
And this was something I didn't realize the scanner is reading both the light and the dark light
Don't understand the standard just consider yourself
The darkroom
Where the wall behind you as far as painted on it
And you took a flashlight
And shined it over your head
Across the bars
You would see
The room got a little lighter when you were over the white bars
And it would get dark
When it was over the top
Black lines that don't reflect the laser light back to the scanner register as a 1 White Lines equal 0
They're actually 95 evenly spaced columns on a UPC barcode
I think black line is actually
A bunch of ones right next to each other
The computer add all that together and you get a string of 12 numbers
This number goes to the computer
The computer no looks up and it's table
To get the information
Such as
What is the product how much they're charging for it
But that is not in the barcode
The only thing that's in the barcode
Is where the computer should look
This number is also printed below the barcode just in case this
Scanner isn't working
Which for me really makes
The whole mystery a little
Anticlimactic
I mean
Right there
So when most people until recently thought of barcodes they thought of something that was
Is a combination of bars and Stripes
More recently two-dimensional barcodes which are
They look like crossword puzzles
Have emerged in most popular being QR barcodes quick response
That are scanned by cell phones
We've all seen these and maybe a few of us
I'm actually bothered to pull out our cell phones and download the app required to scan them
Yeah there's something about them that I find kind of
Lame or annoying
You know it's like
No Chili's I don't want more info on the Bloomin Onion
So anyway I Googled why are QR codes
Lame and I got a bunch of Articles basically saying they're actually really useful they're just
Being misused
Mostly by advertisers who just started slapping them on every single thing
But Jerry Whiting
He still believes in them
The nice thing about QR barcodes
Says they are not Justa
I'll look up number
To an external data
Yes it could be a chunk attack
It can be a URL
It can be a whole lot of different
But
There is no Central Authority
The tells you what or how to do anything
Meaning you don't have to go through gs1 to get a QR code
Which lets people do stuff like make a giant picture of Amy Goodman's face entirely out of QR codes
This is my QR code Amy Goodman portrait made with 2304 unique to Arco
Codes that link to nine years of democracy Now videos besides the QR
Barcode Lauren Woodland original barcode of bunch of other park has their use for all sorts of things
There's code 128 which is mostly used for packaging and shipping there's PostNet which is used by the post office
Their bar codes that use radio frequencies to send out there called RFID tags and they aren't really
Are coats at all
They just get put in the same category because like barcodes they're being used to keep track of inventory
With a grocery cart full of RFID tag items one could conceivably wheel their car through a big
I would read all the contents all at once
Basically eliminating the checkout line entirely and allowing more people to pass them stores even more
Quickly so that we can all buy more stuff
Track prescriptions library books luggage endangered animals
There are so many barcodes on so many things that
According to Jerry Whiting
When Future archaeologists come across remnants of our
Backward a civilization and they stumble across a barcode
They're going to sign it religious significance
But they don't understand this
Supply chain
We had no idea how far it was going to go
It we thought it would stay just within the grocery industry
Of course it didn't just stay in the grocery industry
It actually went way beyond that all the way
2 conspiracy
There is in fact a silly conspiracy theory that all barcodes have the number of the Beast
Six six six
Encoded into them
Yeah it has to do with those guard bars that come at the beginning middle and end of every Park
Barcode
And it's basically true that there is three sixes coded into the guard bars
The answer to why is a bit
Technically you can read about it on George lures
Personal website in the FAQ
Section if you
You want
But as exhibit B I submit
Gorge himself
Hello hello
George J laurer
After we were done with our interview he was talking a little bit more about him
Job at IBM
Hello my dad come home at night
My poor wife
And then he started talking about his wife
Kids
She had the hard job she gave up her career
Electrician career
In order to take care of it
Believe me we are so proud
Realtor
You just couldn't ask for better kids
So this is because my wife
Spread her career
Kids
I'm just home
Does that sound like a Satan worshipper
Can you guys
My daughter
Bachelor
99% invisible with produce this week by Katie mingle with
Roman Mars Turtle thanks to Jenny Morgan for production help
We are product of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the offices of
Of arcsin and Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
And engineering
Charlotte
Our youngest son
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook we all tweet you can find us we have a Tumblr it's fantastic but if you want to link
Two Georges lures self-publish autobiography called engineering was
!
Could have 99 pmi.org
Radio
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com