99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the late 1960s
Spell Italian
Scottish scientist
Started a club 2 address
What they considered to be humankind's greatest problem
Things like pollution
Resource scarcity
Andover population
And because this group met in Rome Italy it came to be known as the club of Rome
Over the next couple of years the club of Rome would grow to include politicians
Scientist
Economist and Business Leaders from around the world
It was a pretty Elite group I've always pictured a lot of leather furniture and cigar smoking
I don't know how much cigar-smoking there was
I mean it was certainly Clubby
That's Patrick McRae he's a professor of history at the University of California Santa Barbara
I think there's a tendency to
Imagine them as sort of this cigar-smoking cabal
Yessir pulling the strings behind the scenes but I think there is a genuine interest on their part
I'm address these
Problems of the world
The people who were a part of the club of Rome
Basically wanted to figure out if and when the world was going to hit maximum capacity
And one out of resource
And toward this end
They had a tool
A relatively new tool
What's the time
The computer
And so they plugged a bunch of data into their huge 1970s computers
And then looked at the results and switched up the variables
Ran the test again
No matter how they played with
The variables
Switch for a resource use
Pollution
Industrialization
Population
Gross things like that
All of the models
What they came up with
All of them should have led to the same conclusion
Sometime in the 21st century there would be
This massive collapse
Maps of globe
Will Society
In 1972 the club of Rome published a book outlining their findings
Called
The limits to growth
And it got a lot of media attention
They found the way things are going now the planet can support us for less than 100 years
It maybe never 50
The book became a surprise bestseller and was translated into more than
Two dozen languages
And yeah there were critics who disagreed with the findings
But overall the limits to growth was incredibly influential
You know there was a
Famous cover of Newsweek around 9
That your shows Uncle Sam on the cover looking into a cornucopia and there's nothing in it and the headline
On the cover of Newsweek says running out of everything
You can see the idea of limits
All over popular culture
New York City
In the year 2022
Nothing runs anymore
Nothing works
The famous or inFAMOUS movie with
Charlton Heston
Soylent Green
Give me the whole premise of the movie is
It's based on
A scenario where they
Overpopulation
And the Earth is
Xeos exceeded its carrying capacity
Pasadena
Hard to say and the people will do anything
To get what they need what they need most is Soylent Green
Exhaust
But I think there was a
Really Fierce debate
That the limits to growth report stimulated
About whether there was this need to curtail economic
Growth
Regulate populations
And perhaps even curtail individual freedoms
And out of this chorus of debate an alarm
Emerges a physicist and engineer named Gerard O'Neill
He was mostly known as Jerry
Andrea Neal says yeah we may live on a limited planet
But we live in a limitless
Universe
And the answer to a lot of our problems here on Earth may actually be out in space
In what O'Neal called The High Frontier
Here's Jerry O'Neil in an archival recording from the 70s
Opening the High Frontier
Means
Making possible and ensuring
The survival of the human race
Jerry O'Neill wanted to build settlements
In space
If you truly love this planet
The best thing you can do for it is to move as much industry and as many p
People as possible
From its surface out in the
The space O'Neal was motivated and really saw his ideas as a form of environmentalism
Jerry O'Neil wasn't the first person to imagine human habitats in
But unlike others who had come before him O'Neill was the first
Punjab and numbers and come up with technologically feasible design
Over the course of his work he would turn Skeptics into
The true believers
Fun support from NASA
And start a social movement toward the goal of building human colonies
In space
Before he started thinking about
Space colony
Jerry O'Neill was a professor in Princeton physics
But he wasn't content analyzing data
He like building things
O'Neill's contribution to physics
Was
Re-engineering the way in which particle accelerators work
Designed and built
And he was really really successful at this
He was very famous already as a physicist
Long before he got interested in space colonies
So he was very much respected among his equals
And a
So if a person of Great Character
I always got along very well with him
That's Freeman Dyson
Freeman Dyson I'm a retired professor at The Institute for advanced study in Princeton
My subject
What is mathematics and physics
I was just a pencil Pusher Distributing equations
Dyson is being modest
She was an is a
Polymath in a veritable genius
He's made huge contributions in quantum mechanics
But also in nuclear energy biology
Astrophysics
And he's got pop-culture cred to there's a video game character
You're named after him
There's even a Star Trek episode about one of his Concepts
Titan was also a friend and colleague to Jerry O'Neill
O'Neal died in 1992
How many students were always
Following him around
He actually
Russian students
Doing real projects
It wasn't just talk
In 1969 the same year the first astronauts walked on the moon
O'Neill posed a question to his introductory physics students at Princeton
What makes more sense
Building human settlements on the surface of another planet
Rebuilding free-floating settlement
In outer space
3 months of research and calculations O'Neal and his students came to the conclusion that building free floating habitat
Was the way to go
First of all you don't have to overcome gravity every time you go on and off of free-floating space settlement
But even more importantly in space you have access to the sun's energy 100% of the time
So no other sources
The fuel would be needed
But when the semester ended O'Neill didn't stop thinking about space colonization
In fact
He'd only just begun
Goodwill Sumter
Dreams of samurai the remote future
It was something O'Neal really salty should do
O'Neill decided he would build his settlements at a place in our solar system 250,000 miles from
Called
LaGrange LaGrange point
LaGrange points places in
Space
Will object
Stay put
They don't move around on August
And so these are the most
Convenient places if you want to have a fixed habitat
Object stay put because at LaGrange point five or L5
The gravity of the Sun and Earth are a special equilibrium
L5
What's his favorite
Electronics point
Play switches
Same distance from the Moon and the Earth
Oliver nails designs for habitats were variations on cylinders spheres or rings
And it designs have been copied
All
Uber science fiction
You can see O'Neal ask designs in the movie Elysium
Interstellar
The design that I find the easiest
Picture basically looks like
Giant bicycle wheel floating in space
The people would live inside the tire
Part of the wheel
Which itself would be enormous
There would be a huge windows
What's that let in sunlight
And allowed amazing views of outer space
The artist renderings of O'Neill settlements make them look really earth like
Unappealing
Water
Treason
Terraced housing
He imagined that thing would would be like
An Italian Hilltown we we knew that the first ones wouldn't look like
Anything like that
That's Tasha O'Neal
In 1969 Tasha had just moved to the US from Germany to work as an au pair
When she decided to attend a mixer the YMCA
In what Jerry O'Neill with his mop top haircut
Looking more like a member of the 60s rock band than a physicist
I looked at him and I thought that's the first interesting guy that I see around here
I wouldn't say it was love at first sight but it was definitely
Interest
At first sight words
Gulou into love very quickly
When he and Tasha met O'Neal have just started seriously thinking about space colonies
And he was eager to share his ideas
I thought it was really ironic
That I would
Meet and marry a physicist
My physics was non-existent
I fight
Flunked it
But he was
So good at explaining things to lay people
And Tasha also got good attic
Explaining his ideas
Explain to me for example that the wheel in which people with live with rotate
Very slowly on an access
And the centrifugal force of that rotation
Who created gravity like sensation for the people inside
To keep them from
Floating around
The rotating would have been very slow
And you would not have noticed it
But the closer you were to the Axis or the center of the wheel
The less gravity you experience
When when you went uphill
You got lighter
And lighter
And you started skipping like a mountain goat
It always say that
Jerry O'Neil imagine the first structure can house
10000 people and subsequent structures could house
3 million
I hope that eventually these settlements
Could unburden the Earth of a significant
Population
Anne O'Neill also thought his settlements
Could provide Earth with a source of energy by collecting the sun's energy in space
Where it's in abundance all the time and sending it back to Earth via radio waves
This was a technology that another scientist
I've been working on already
By doing this O'Neal believe
What has a solution to the energy problems of the world
At this point you may be wondering how O'Neill plan to get all of the materials needed to build these massive star
Structures
Into space
Imagine the first loads would be taken by the space shuttle
A new tool for which NASA havoc
Extremely optimistic plans
Historian Patrick McRae
In the 1970s people were predicting shuttle flights happening every week
And
Build at the time is basically a space truck
But even with the space shuttle taking trips once a week
O'Neill knew that it wouldn't be enough
He needs to get his building materials
From the Moon
The Moon is a source of
Minerals which we know about thanks to the Apollo project
All of the things in fact
That we need for many of the products of an industrial civilization
So his idea was to
Move that material from the lunar surface using a type of electromagnetic catapult
This catapult was called a mass driver and it would swing raw materials from the Moon through
Through space to LaGrange point five
O'Neil and some colleagues actually designed a working model of 1
The PBS program Nova recorded a demonstration of it
Free
All of the people who lived in the first Bay settlement would be working in space as well
The process the raw materials to build the next settlement
Also be jobs in other industry
I decided that I was going to be
Running the first
Restaurant up there
I thought about you know which spices I had to take along
That we couldn't grow up there right away
Capture the imagination
Not everyone was as enthusiastic about Jerry O'Neill's ideas as
Tasha
Aa1972 O'Neill hat
Turn his ideas into a paper and was looking to be published in a scientific journal
He got a lot
Rejection letters
But then in May of 1974 the New York Times ran a front-page article about O'Neill's ideas
Which changed our lives
Dramatically
We had to delist our telephone number
Shortly thereafter O'Neal's ideas also found Traction in the academic world
When his paper was published in the journal
Physics today
And the requests for interviews and lectures
Came rolling in
O'Neill was interviewed by the Smithsonian in the science-fiction magazine Omni
Even penthouse
But it was a very very good article
I mean I only read it
The articles
In addition to Penthouse or maybe
Because of Ben house
O'Neill even gained the address of NASA
Which funded the series of studies at the Ames Research
Explore all the different Avenues
To try to find weaknesses and what he was suggesting
+ 2
Really workout
Detailed
Design
The bills on his original ideas
In all of his interviews and lectures
Jerry O'Neill
What about space in this
Onew way
Space wasn't just a government program
For elite astronauts to take
Pardon
Bass was a place
Just another place
For you and I to get to Ana
Explorer
When we open up the High Frontier by building colonies in space there is going to be
Room for people who want to leave
We are to go out and to develop their own colonies
And to do their own thing
Did the play
This idea of
Space as a place
Appeal to a lot of different kinds of people
And soon enough a social movement started coalescing around O'Neal's ideas
By 1975 a group called the L5 Society
LaGrange point five
Headphone to spread the gospel
Of space colonization
They were
Very vocal they were politically active so they would
Oftentimes be lobbying Congress or NASA for
Expanded
Space exploration Pro
And get it published a monthly newsletter
El fibers were serious face Act
But it was the seventies and there was a strange convergence happening
Of scientist
Hippies
Beautiful nerds of every stripe
Beautiful nerds
Within
All right let's do
Who were the green
That's Bill Higgins
She's a physicist and former L fiber who went to a lot of Science Fiction conventions in the 70s
Where he says there was often a room full of people singing and playing instruments
Bilco wrote the lyrics to a song that became somewhat of an Anthem
Bl-5c
Society
Give me your
Where the graviton
Where the three body problem is songs
Where the microwave
Space debris
Scolex
We possess
Solar power
I'm just going to give you a second
Stop picturing zero-g sex
For awhile O'Neill seem to welcome and encourage the
Attention from group play
Like L5
With the L5 Society started to attract
More controversial character
How many of you
Would like to live in space and live forever
How about it
That's incredible
That's Timothy Leary promoting the idea of
Space colonization in the late 1970s
Leary became famous in the 60s for advocating the therapeutic use of LSD
And Leary had his own ideas about what
Space colonies could do for Humanity brother trippy ideas about how building space colonies
Help Usher in this new phase of conscious human evolution
Having Leary as a spokes
May not have been ideal as O'Neill tried to get the government
Take his ideas seriously
Yo Larry someone who President Nixon once called the most dangerous man in America
If you're successful in promoting and popularizing
Nuclear technology or particular technological future
You also risk
Losing control over the idea
He wanted to
I'm happy ideas out there
You know people talking about it is
Better than not talking
People were certainly talking about it and not all of it was
What's positive
According to Patrick McRae many environmentalists of the time vehement Lee rejected the idea that space colonization
Mission could be a possible cure for our planet
Problems
Play Sade nothing Environmental
How about if they saw this as a
Extension of the military-industrial complex
Into space
And there were none environmental critiques made as well
People said well okay who's actually going to go into space
It's not going to be
You know the urban poor it's going to be
You know basic
Creditease
White suburbs
It in space
Kritikos
Sullivan Eagles
Uniform
Going to literally whiteflies
A rat done bit my sister nell
With Whitey on the moon
Buffets in Alma Kansas
And Whitey's on the moon
I can't pay no doctor bills
Whitey's on the moon
10 years from now I'll be paying still while Whitey's on the moon
You know the man
Gil Scott-Heron was just one of the people that voice this criticism about any quality in the space race
But of all the
Take sour made of O'Neill's ideas
No one really said
This is technologically in pause
And in fact in the 1970s we had just put astronaut
On the moon
Anything seems pause
Patrick says to put this in perspective he likes to imagine
Hypothetical scenario
It's 1975 and you ask a random person on the street
Which is the more likely scenario
Scenario a
We are going to build a
Base on the moon
And then we're going to build colonies and outers
Space
Or scenario B
We're not going to go back to the moon for another half
Century
At least
No I'd argue that in 1975
Most people would have felt that scenario a
Was the much more likely
In 1977 all of O'Neill's research was published in a very readable book
Call The High Frontier
And he appeared on 60 Minutes with Dan Rather to talk.
About space colonization
Do you expect
Just had put on one of these space habitats
I sure hope so Dan or I wouldn't be working on it that's your hoe
But the question is what is your expectation
Putting my own professional time and end my effort
Into the scenario that says that these things will be realized within my working lifetime
But despite O'Neal's optimism
The 60 Minutes segment marked the peak
Mainstream interest in his ideas
And the goal of building settlements in space began to seem less and less attainable
NASA space shuttles did not become Reliant
Space trucks
The shuttles ended up making far fewer flights into
Space Center originally predicted
In general NASA became more cautious
Unless adventurous
It's not a lot of pee
People at Hope
Which is why in 1977 O'Neill founded the nonprofit space Studies Institute
Which raises its own money and does its own research
On Space colonization
Gerard O'Neill died in 1992 after a long battle with leukemia
And now 25 years after his death
Some people think that were on the brink of another is facing
When they could lead to the realization of
Some of O'Neill's dreams
There are a lot of
People
Working on it
He has so many young people working with him they're now calling themselves
Jerry's Kids
And they're in there
50s
But they did learn
Sitting
A Disney
Eric Tomlinson
Peter diamandis
My mission in life
Since I was a kid
Was
And is to take the rest of yuan
Space during our lifetime
They were going to take the people of Earth in transition off
Permanently
That is Peter diamandis giving a TED Talk
In 2005
We thought about the government always has the person taking us there
But the government is not going to get us there
The government is unable to take the risks required open up this precious Frontier
Like Jerry O'Neill diamandis believes that technology can solve Humanity's biggest problems
And that we don't have to live
In a world of limits
But unlike O'Neal
Diamandis has another primary motivation
Money
The universe is full of valuable things
To exploit for wealth
If you think about
Space everything we hold a value on this planet
Metals minerals real estate and energy
Is an infinite quantities in space impact the Earth
Is a crumb
In a supermarket
Resource
There are other entrepreneurs like Elon Musk and Jeff Bezos who would also like to make money in space
And build human settlement
However is
Happens both Freeman Dyson and Tasha O'Neal are sure humans will find their way in the settlements in
Eventually
Well I would say something it will happen
One day it's all a question of when
And I'm counting on it because
Jerry wanted his
Is a fascist
Scattered in a space colony
And I think by now you know his his grandchildren will
Or I hope not his great-grand
Children but somebody will have to do it
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle the same Greenspan's refuse South Delaney Hall
Cole said Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Robert Smith from the space Studies Institute for all of his help on this story
And thanks to Carolyn my now for talking to us about the L5 society and Bill Higgins
Home on the Range song
Learn more about Gerard O'Neill and his plans for colonizing space
Check out Patrick McRae Facebook
The visioneers
A group of elite scientists pursued space colonies nanotechnologies
And a limitless future
Also be sure to check out the artist renderings of the O'Neill settlements that NASA Commission in the seventies we have a few of those on our way
Website at 99 pi
This episode is part of your ex's stories in science project supported by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation to enhance
Public understanding of science technology and economic performance
Moritz loan.org
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin who is actually looking for a couple
New Architects with 5 to 15 years experience in your CV to design a TARC sign.com
You too can work
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Juventus show and like the show on Facebook and follow Saul on Twitter and Instagram the best way to explore the
99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world it's a clip around the hundreds of stories about the
Design that are reported in the way that only really do 1099 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com