99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
During this holiday season we have a special episode with two stories from one of my favorite writers John welham
He is a contributing writer to the New York Times magazine and also a writer at large for pop-up magazine
We're lucky to have him on the show a few times
The first stories about the origin of the teddy bear and it would be successor
And we also have this Encore presentation of Wild Ones live the song is Dory Extravaganza that probably
My favorite thing that we broadcast
And it deserves to be listened to numerous.
Here we go
It's totally unfair
Hydrox cookies came out in 1908
Warriors didn't show up until 4 years later
But it didn't matter
Hydrox could never shake the image of being a knock off
Also ran
Hydrox lovers with champion its 10-year cream filling
Vegetarian surprise them for being cruelty free
America's favorite cookie the Oreo
Contain animal lard into the mid-90s
As a consumer product it's just not up to you
Sometimes you redeemed the mighty Transformer
And sometimes
Give it to love someone kobot
It's capricious who wins
Swiss cake roll vs hoho
Twizzler vs. red vine
Maybe yours was the first family in the block with a technologically Superior betamax player
Only to be overwhelmed by the mediocre VHS tape
Sometimes it doesn't make any sense at all
But sometimes it does
I'm John Wallin
John is a writer for New York Times magazine in a writer at large for pop-up magazine live magazine in San Francisco
Story first appeared
Bright starts 1902 and Theodore Roosevelt as president and he decides to vacation in a town called
Needs in the Mississippi Woods
We can hunt black bear is a big Outdoorsman
Big hunter and his hunting trip became kind of a famous story basically it's been a few days hunting and I don't think they
Even saw a single bear they definitely didn't get to shoot it any and then one morning the dogs get the scent of a bear and they follow it down
To this really weedy place where the president's guide says you know what don't even bother going in there and then troubling yourself I'll go in and I'll flush
What's the beer out you just stay here and I'll flush it right to you
So Roosevelt Waits and waits but then he gets bored and decides to go out and eat lunch
Eventually the dog is to Corner the baron and the guy not really knowing what to do leaps off his horse cracks the bear over the head
With the butt of his rifle Knox
Unconscious or send me unconscious and tied it to a tree and then starts blowing away on his usual trying to call Rusev
Robots that the president can be the one with the owner shooting it
Roosevelt here's the buccal and makes his way back to the hunting party
Is this bear two female bear it weighs about 235 lb
And it's tied to a tree
It's still semi-conscious
Injured it looks a little mangy
It's actually probably about half as heavy and big as it should be but there's been a real drought going on in the area the bear looks
Pathetic
Roosevelt
Takes pity on it
He decides that it's it's unsportsmanlike
To shoot this thing you know he's not going to do it and doesn't want anyone else to do it either
Has gun
And in this sort of merciful moment
Is your word of this spreads and a political cartoonist
Draw the cartoon of the of the moment of him
Showing the bear this mercy and the way the cartoonist draws the berries almost like a
Little Labrador puppy or a golden retriever puppy survive on its
On its butt and its hind legs
Kentucky's big round perked up ears almost like Mickey Mouse
Nice big white eyes and it's tearing at the president waiting to see what its fate will be
The cartoon was called Drawing the Line in Mississippi
And from that basically spawned the teddy bear this adorable little
Bear in the cartoon was turned into a three-dimensional plush toy the very first teddy bear was either made by a
A German company called Steve
Aura Brooklyn toys around are depending on who you ask
And they named it after Theodore Roosevelt they called teddy bear
It's a huge
Sensation and it's actually more popular than baby dolls which freaks everyone out a little bit you know why should their children be playing with bear
Reason and not dolls
Hello Savage
And within a few years I think Steve is producing close to a million teddy bears a year and shipping them to the US
It was considered so bizarre that kids would play with a stuffed bear that people just assumed it was a novelty and as soon as Rose
Roosevelt left office
No one would want them anymore at this time the whole idea of mass-produced toys was also really new
So the toy industry wanted to kind of capitalized on its rally and keep it going
It was really looking for whatever was going to be the next
Cubby play things that American kids were going to want all though it had no idea what that might be
The best forward in 1909
Roosevelt's term is about up in the president-elect is Roosevelt's hand-picked
Sensor
William Howard Taft and that January January 1909 Taft is in the Atlanta he's trying to woo the South
I'll try to convince him that his administration is going to take them seriously as a constituency
And he's the guest of honor at this banquet
In the Chamber of Commerce in Atlanta decides it's going to serve him the truest
Most unpretentious Southern dish around
It's something that a writer of the time I found this little book about southern food from the time
Calls it the Christmas goose of the Epicurean negro
The meal was possum and taters and what it was was it an opossum
Would be roasted on a bed of sweet potatoes
And then presented hole on a platter
With its head on its tail on
And it often you'd get a smaller a little sweet potato Crown between the animals teeth
50 teeth has apparently the most teeth of any North American mammal
Indian the one that they brought the test table weight 18 lb
All the sudden Orchestra strikes up and they just burst into song suddenly Taft is presented with a surprise gift
The small stuff
Opossum toy in this is a brand new invention that some local tap supporters are trying to position as William Taft president
Answer to the teddy bear
They're calling it
The Billy possum
Already there was a company set up
Call the Georgia Billy possum company
According to One account within 24 hours of that bank with their already deals being brokered for Billy possums with distributors
Across the country
In covering the banquet the LA Times announced that
The teddy bear has been relegated to a seed in the rear end for 4 years possibly 8
The children of the United States will play with Billy possum
Government on a bit of opossum Mania started their Billy possum postcards Billy possum pins Billy possum pictures
Trader cream when you had coffee
There was a Ragtime tune called possum the latest craze
Does tap travel around the South some people actually start giving him live opossums in cages when he would make public appearances or
Handing them over like they were floral the kids
Soon baby possums were in toy stores from New York to San Francisco because real opossums weren't actually that, Nancy
Cities that and no one really knew what they were
A toy store in Brooklyn
Brandon in-store promotion with a live captive opossum that they could show off the kids so the kids could familiarize in
Animal are going to be best friends with was
I found an advertisement for the story that read do not let it be said
But any man woman or child in Brooklyn
Has not seen the cute little animal
Whose name is mentioned more in all parts of the world today
In any other
President on the newspapers
Hauser morning the passing of the dolls and and how sad it was at these teddy bears were coming into nurseries in vanquishing
And now the ra poems
In newspapers about Billy possums displacing teddy bears
But since you probably never heard of a billy possum
You can guess what comes next
Next it was a total flop and the Billy possum was forgotten and almost entirely out of stores within a couple of months
What's another word for Billy possum never even made it to see Christmas time
Which is a special kind of tragedy for toy
There are several possible explanations as to why the Billy possum never took off
The first
Probably thinking right now is this
Opossums are ugly and nobody likes them
It was also the dawn of the mechanical toy
And even some teddy bears that evolved into wind up animatronics
There is a French maid teddy bear
That quote wines up and is calculated to indulge in a number of ludicrous somersault
How could a limp
Stuffed Billy possum compete with that
Pajama Willam argues that
At its heart the acceptance of teddy bear and the rejection of Billy possum
Comes down to their origin story
In the story that was told about Roosevelt and his bear
It was a very kind of tender moment where
Rosella showing the bear Mercy
And when you look at that cartoon the way the bear was drawn
It looked like something that you would want to just sweep up into your arms and take care of and that was vulnerable and that needed your help
It looked like a teddy bear as we know it
Although no one knew it at the time the story with Taft it didn't give it anything else
You're tough
State is Boston for supper
I need a lot of it and he ate so much
The Doctor's first several helping is a doctor seated nearby apparently passed him a note suggesting that it might be a good idea if you slowed
Down a little
Taft even bragged reporters the next day about how much possum he consumed fly like a possum and I ate very hard on the other
But it last night
And it did not disturb in the slightest
My digestion or my sleep
The possum was vulnerable I guess
Splayed out on a bed of taters but
You're not exactly routing for it I started feeling really bad for tattoo and the more I read a little bit about him
He was this totally colorless
Politician
And you didn't actually been want to be president by some accounts
How you assert strong-armed into it
Original any never really measured up to Roosevelt's Charisma and charm I mean Roosevelt was the kind of guy who
No matter what he did history seemed eager to glorifying for it
Case in point the messed up thing about the famous story of Teddy the bear on that hunting trip in Mississippi
Is it isn't even the whole truth
You have to remember that Roosevelt was
A hunter he was there to hunt bears he wasn't a Peta activist or something like this
Well he did show the bear Mercy it was very particular
Kind of Mercy
After he refused to shoot it
He said put it out of its misery
And then one of his Hunting Buddies came in and slip the bear's neck open with a knife
They Carried the Bears body back to Camp over the back of a horse
And they basically ate off it for the next several days
And the last name of their trip
They finish it off they roasted its paws
And I kid you not date the paws with a side of possum and taters
So that's why you will never cuddle up
With a billy possum
Just like you will never watch a betamax tape
Or travel to go betron with weeder one
And you will never again
Tonka Hydrox cookie
Mandamus Hydrox cookies
They're really tasty
We have one cardinal rule on 99percentinvisible
No Cardinals
Meaning we don't deal with the natural world
Only the built world
So when I read John wellons brilliant book called Wild Ones a sometimes this main weirdly reassuring story
About looking at people looking at animals in America
I didn't think I'd ever do an episode of 99% invisible about it I just read it for fun
But then I saw John perform stories from the book live with musical accompaniment and I thought
I need to put this on the radio
Gaston College radio
Anyway what you need to know about Wild Ones is that it isn't a book about nature
It's a book about how we fit nature into our modern lives
Wild Ones is about the QT stuffed animals
Eco tours
In the Byzantine methods of conservation that involved
When our experience with Wildlife goes from something natural
Do something
Design
Human-animal interaction has become a designed experience
In the story of that transition
As the title of the book suggests
Is sometimes dismay
And also
Weirdly reassuring
John William is friends with the band black prairie and as he was writing the book
They can talk to this idea of the band creating a soundtrack to the book
And the result was an extended EP called Wild Ones
The musical score for the things you might see in your head
When you reflect on certain characters and incidents
That you read in the book
The writer and the band then went on a short tour with the song and story Extravaganza that I'm going to play for you today
When I saw them perform this live in San Francisco
I'm freaked out it was so good and I costed them in the dressing room and said
You have to let me share this with my audience
So here it is
Eureka
Happens every summer
Small turtles
Call diamondback terrapin skidder out of the water around JFK Airport New York
They start moving West
They're heading for a patch of sand
Where they like to lay their eggs
The crossover one of the airport's runways
Runway 4L
Sometimes
There's so many turtles on the move at 1
Control tower
Has to delay flights
Letterpress
Loves doing stories about how funny this
Hella Fleet a giant airplane
Can be held up
I just a few tiny turtle
The hold that picture in your mind and think about the Caribbean Sea in 1492
They were almost
A billion
Sea turtles living in a back then
Columbus has been anchored in the Caribbean
Rude about being kept awake at night
Butterfly king of so many turtle shells against the sides of their ship
Notice how that scene is the exact opposite of the scene at JFK
It's not a fleet of giant airplanes being held up by a few tiny turtle
It's a giant
Fleta Turtles
Bombarding
Just a few relatively tiny ships
So I wrote this book about people and wild animals in America and it only really started
Because I wanted to show my daughter endangered species in the wild before they disappeared
Like a lot of people I think I felt this pain
I knew that
All around us
Beautiful parts of the world are expiring
And I also knew that
People in the future
They might not even notice
Today I'm a world without whales or wilderness
Might feel normal
Wanted to counteract
Not forgetting
That's bound to take old overtime
This forgetting has a name
Scientist called shifting Baseline syndrome
It means that
All of us except
The version of the world we inherit
Is normal
Over the years we watch Forrest get louder animals disappear but
When the next generation
Comes along
Except
That depleted version of nature is there normal
Chart zoom out
Really feel the change
Stutter stacking up
Across the generations
I can't even imagine
What an ocean filled with a billion sea turtles must feel like
Last winter
I was in Hawaii
And I saw three seater
And I flipped
Felt like I was in
Eden
It wasn't so long ago that America was a kind of eating when people could be dwarfed and engulf by
Wild animals in a way that feels almost impossible now in the late 1800s trains with
Sometimes have to stop for four or five hours
Extremes of Buffalo moved across the tracks
Occasionally I Stampede with battery into the side of a train derailing it
The witness describes one of these scenes
1871 in Kansas
Each individual a buffalo went out in
What's the best ratio does paraplegic locomotive cars
Directed after having dreams thrown off the track twice in one week conductors learn to have a
Mother decided respect for the idiosyncrasies of the Buffalo this man's name
Was William Temple hornaday he was a bombastic mid Westerner with an elaborate Mustang
Hornaday was head taxidermist at the Smithsonian and he traveled the globe hunting a
Exotic animals and stuffing them for the museum in India after he took down an elephant climb.
Stop the carcass and popped open a bass ale
Once he trapped an orangutan named did little man gave it to Andrew Carnegie as a pet
It sounds weird but for hornaday
Killing these animals with a kind of
Conservation
He believed
By stuffing them
He was preserving endangered
For the future Generations that might not know them after they were gone
Do taxidermy
You can make them a more
In 1886
Hornaday looked West
Since all that America
So many buff
So rapidly
The Prairie was on
You figured
They were maybe
Less than 300 Buffalo left
And so we did
What he thought
Helpful and Lodge
He lit out for a month
Killed several dozen
They shot 25 buffalo in Montana and he built the best looking ones into an exhibit at the Museum
He gathered them around a pic Watering Hole looking for Lauren
But from there his thinking of all of you realize he was basically just a funeral director
Embalming the species that America was Exterminating it occurred to him
What if we actually tried to keep these animals alive
And so he became one of America's first real wildlife conservationists and activist the lobbyists to celebra
America was killing every conceivable kind of animal in their way and hornaday sit up for all of them
Micon's like the grizzly to lowly or less Majestic things like the squirrel
Alive squirrel two trees poetry in motion to save the silver tail
There was really only one animal on the continent that Hornet it wasn't worried about
It would seem to Mighty to be brought down by men with guns and it lived in a cold and brutal wilderness
Batman couldn't possibly take over
Polar bear
Is the king of the Frozen North
It's not very probable that the polar bear
Forever views
Terminated
That's hornaday writing a 1914
Back then
No one could have imagined the problem is abstract is climate change
But think about how quickly climate changes change the polar bears reputation in our minds
It's gone from bloodthirsty Man Killer
The delicate
Drowning victim
200 years ago Arctic explorers wrote about polar bears leaping into their boat
I'm trying to eat them
Even if they lit the bear on fire
I recently when I went to the tiny Northern Town that calls itself
The polar bear capital of the world
Martha Stewart had just arrived
The film The Animals
For her daytime show
The Hallmark
The town is called Churchill Manitoba it's on the edge of Hudson Bay and every fall right before the bay freezes
Silver Churchill gets overrun with about 900 polar bears and 10,000 polar bear tours
Prayers routinely wander into town they like hanging out at the elementary
Especially 675 Bear Paw Patrol officers will come
Chase the animals backgrounds of the tundra and their trucks bears that won't budge or tranquilizing
Shipped out to a quonset hut near the airport
Once this so-called polar bear gel fills up each animal is drugged again and airlifted one at a time
To an area north of town crowds of tourists come out to watch these bare lifts
And I went to one myself
There was
Something just a little ceremonial
About the bare lifts I went to
How do uniforms Wildlife officers arranged
Sleeping Bear
On a net
Epicenter of the
The crowd
How they talked
Pause
Carefully across it
Chess
Like some drunken Uncle after Thanksgiving dinner
It was so careful
Beautiful
You confusing
A couple of people cry
It was like the opposite
Of an animal sacrifice the ritual
To save the bear
To show how far out of our way we go not
I stood there and watched and as I did
Martha Stewart
Stood next to me
Her crew is there
Filming everything
Honestly it's a breathtaking thing to watch the polar
Bear flying away all of a sudden the helicopters started to turn the edges
Other than that lifted the furry shape inside contracted to you and
The entire package was off the ground
The helicopter client or the cloudbank
The bear twirling slightly underneath it like a tea bag and then finally
Polar bear was gone
Yeah I know
Airlifting polar bears
Strange no one could have imagined it would come
The way we help animals now has evolved into a surreal kind of performance art
We carry migrating salamanders across busy highway
We monitor pygmy rabbits with drone
At Cornell scientist breeding endangered peregrine falcon
Where is specially-made receptor
They called the copulation hat
Coach the bird named biercab to ejaculate on their heads
Several times
The day everyday
For much of
This is another Baseline that shifts
Overtime
The links were willing to go
Each generation does what would have look like
Fighting for a purpose
Just lost cause to the one before it
And then
Which generation
Comes along a new and does a little bit more than that
Nanako's Humanity
Strapping off the proverbial population hat
Again
And again
Consider the story
George
In the late 1970s there were only a handful of whooping cranes left in the wild
Also a small number at a government lab in Maryland
Scientist there were doing their best to ring as many new Offspring as they could from those capped
But the lab had one problem child a female crane name a text as a newborn Texas
Been raised in a cardboard box in the zookeeper's living room and having never seen another crane
She imprinted on the one animal she did see the Zookeeper basically she wound up
I'm sexually attracted to people but not other grains
The scientist kept trying to parietex off but text wasn't interested she wanted a man I specifically
William and it looks like her old zookeeper a dark-haired white man the medium build
Now there was a young crane conservationists named George Archibald
George happened to pee is dark haired white man of medium build he took text to rule Wisconsin put a mattress
Personal pan and moved in as Texas companion they'd Forge together build a nest
And they dance George doing deep knee bends and springing up with arms out like wings
Pitbull and holler come on text come on
Heather just like wild cranes do during courtship this would get text aroused and it just the
The right moment to assistance with Richard from a hiding place and artificially inseminate her with crane semen
George did all this for 3 years living with text for months at a
What time because the eggs she kept playing where infertile the man and crane would start out after Dawn
They go for a walk and they dance they dance and they dance send it down
George didn't enjoy any of this he was miserable actually miserable
Spring of 1983 text finally laid an egg that hatched and George was right there when it did
He was invited on The Tonight Show to celebrate
When headline Redman
Crane
Proud parents
George name the chick qiwiz
I know gee whiz as 44 grandchildren and great-grandchildren today there are more
Whooping cranes in the wild than there have been
In almost a hundred years
William Temple hornaday
The taxidermy
Just died at 9
His funeral
Bugler's
Listen to local Boy Scout
Surrounded the coffee
Played Home on the Range
20 years later
Hornet is Buffalo
The one he built
They found a rusty
Beatbox
Buried in
Inside was a
From hornaday
But I'm Dustin
I beg you to protect
Especially
Deterioration
Destruction
At last
The game butchers
My name is William
Please note
High-rises letters
To you
Real
Give the devil his
Is do
I am happy not to be
I have free food
Enjoy their beauty
Dubai
Trinity
I have protected them now to the
I have not stopped The Killing
You can move
Faster than one
Yocan
How to download
Of course
Hornet is written that pessimistic letter and 18
When he was still
Just a young tok
Turns out he was wrong
The Buffalo we're not all day
And the years
He actually played a big role in helping to save
Lots of others
But it was hard for him to focus on those
He lost so many more battle
By the end of his life
He turned bitter
Disillusion
I tried
To inject
The Croods
Into the hearts of men but today
I think that speaking generally
Civilized man is an unmitigated ass
Like all of us
His imagination was hope
Flea traps
And its own moment
It only see the world
Do the tiny
Keyhole
So where does that leave us
Maybe
Anyone of us
Can do is
Against the Baseline
You can be a tiny
Counterweight
We weigh almost nothing
Generation app
Regeneration
Sometimes
Fun places
The other day
The direction of more Beauty
But that happens
Terminal E to a
To be hard to know
So
Picture that seeing a JFK again all those Turtles
When hornaday was born
There are close to
Being hunted
They tasted so good in suit
We're like those Turtles
Erase of stubborn little things that barely notices is the Wilderness it migrates through fills up
With villages and lights
And swells into an Airport runway
Just keep migrating across that anyway talking in the eggs of the Next Generation into the saying
The world like the airplanes to
Cuz we have change we change into something that hornaday could never have imagined species that
10 least try to slow down try to stop
I like to think about those airplanes powering down the lines of them partying like a shining
Galaxy Sol this Tiny Tribe and turtles and pass-through I get it it look
Looks funny in the present but squint into the hazy Panorama of history and
Both airplanes idling in place that little moment of not moving forward
Looks unmistakably to me like progress
That was Wild Ones live text written by John Llewellyn music by black prairie Blackberry is Jenny Conlee
Injuries of some accordion and vocals
Chris Funk on Banjo dobro autoharp and vocals
Don Moen on drums and vocals
John neufeld on guitar and vocals
Need query on base
Annalisa tornfelt
I'm feeling knuckles
They're recording engineer is Rich Hill
Blackberry has a newest album called fortune that I know you'll like
In an Elisa from the band has an upcoming solo record called the number 8 that you can pre-order online and I'm going to have a link
Do that on our website 99 pmi.org
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
It's in a really spectacular year for us at the show
Thank you so much for your enthusiasm and support
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And produced of the offices of arcsin
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
IPic
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info slide podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
You can find the show and hang out with other people who like this show on Facebook
All of us at 99th PIR on Twitter please follow us there we were great Tumblr but you're always welcome at our place
99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com