99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Trophies are hard for people to throw away there's actually a service in Madison Wisconsin
Trophies and turn them into new ones
Boys & Girls Club for the Special Olympics
Some of the trophies they get come from people who have passed away
They're surviving relative Center
And sometimes they're from people who are just tired of their trophies taking up space and their homes
In both cases
People will actually pay the shipping to Madison to avoid putting their trophies in the trash
Donna Gregg who runs the service with her daughter Janet
Said that sometimes people request to be told where their old trophies and up
Almost like they're donating an organ
Most of the time the materials that make them are cheap
But that's not how you measure the value of a trophy
There's a little trophy shop down the street from our office in Oakland it's small but bust my windows are
Stuffed to the brim with the words made of all kind of material
And in any shape you can imagine
Chalices orbs golfers gavel
Apples
And plaques
Plenty of plaques
So of course producer Avery trufelman
Wrentham
We the membership of Mount Zion Lodge number for prevent this token of appreciation to Brother Willy adames we honor
And welcome you
Give me some
Are you allowed to reveal who that is Honor Roll Award of Excellence
Presented to Gavin Newsom mayor of San Francisco
Appreciation for your contributions to the Nigerian Community Club DJ of the year 1990
Does rifle
And there are plenty of touchingly heartfelt Engravings that you feel that maybe you shouldn't be reading
To my dear husband Gill on the occasion of our 35th wedding anniversary
Thank you sweetheart for 35 loving supportive challenging and exciting years together God has netted our hearts together
They're into a beautiful tapestry of love
Julia Riddell runs this job along with her husband
And she's always moved by what people want engraved on their trophies
People amaze me
With eloquence
And the sincerity and just the way that they can
Expressive
Cuz I am from the culture where people did not occur
Press the feeling
Julia is from Russia
And it was not always appreciated by the people would
Styx
Press sincerely
Their feelings
Let alone having
Engraved and be displayed public
Russians just don't give out Trophies the way that we
Americans freaking love trophies
And some of the fanciest trophies and Juliet shop actually in the fanciest trophies in the world come from RSO
Owens & Company in Chicago
My father built the company
Figure wizard
Guinea pig figure that he manufactured
Free guinea pig breeding competition during the Great Depression
Guinea pig trophy
Rsln
Companies that showed me around the factory
Like a real Bonafide Factory with big
Jones for the glass black
And wheeled carts full of castings and statuette
And rows and rows of industrial grade buffer
This is just
Song
What we
Did you hear they're massive showroom is full of
Crazy different kinds of trophies and Awards this
Westborough
This is the only time we made an award
With a built-in DVD player
Gimmicks aside RS Owens make some truly iconic
Tropheus
HDMI over
Yes an Emmy Award
But the enemy is outshined by its neighbor
Can't believe that's a real
A real Oscar
The Oscars real name is the Academy Award of Merit
It is now officially known by its nickname
There's lots of Mythology around where the name Oscar came from the official myth
Is that the academy librarian Margaret Herrick took a look at the Statue and whispered
Looks like my uncle Oscar
The number of different factories have manufactured the Oscars over the years
Since 1983
When I saw the Oscar
It was hard to believe that I was looking at the real deal
Because I've seen so many knock off
The design itself isn't hard to imitate
It's really simple
It mostly just that stylize gold man standing on a real film
Actually MGM our director Cedric Gibbons originally designed the statue as a knight gripping at Crusader sword
And the Oscar has been purposefully designed to be as desirable an object
Possible
There's more gold on the Oscars
The other award
By fire
Also it's really healthy is 8 and 1/2 pounds
Crazy shiny lot of Polish goes into a rabbit
Defect free
So that takes a lot of
Topology
Night over an hour
Oh man when I saw it I just wanted it
He was like
I'm almost
But somehow Scott Siegel resist the urge to make one for himself
A lot of people
Ask me about whether I have an Oscar at home in Hurst
I'm surprised that I don't know I've never even been interested
That's exactly what he would say if he had an Oscar at home
But some people do make a words for themselves
People do
Make a voice for themselves
Back in Oakland
Julie gets customers who don't look very athletic at all picking up trophies
Or elderly customers buying a trophy for being a young beauty queen
Or World Traveler
And this has happened multiple times
Yes
It's a Coleman thing
Julia is
So not judgmental about this
Giving yourself an award makes you feel better
She's all for it
It's a way of validating your own experience
And even more validating than making yourself in a war
Is making yourself
An entire awards ceremony
Welcome to MTV Music Television
Young MTV decided to establish a
With an award ceremony
Because that's a great way to quickly attract a lot of viewers get high ratings and bring in a lot of star power
And they wanted to further establish themselves
The really good trophy
Impact Gorman
The Moon
At you that's silver astronaut given out at the MTV Video Music Awards or VMAs
Pat Gorman was part of Manhattan design The Firm that created the MTV logo
The making this trophy
Fulfilled a longtime dream of hers
Open champion
Baton twirler with my sister
We have like a doubles routine and we have always a little war at home and I
I wanted to make a great
Trophy sometime in my life and then
The Manhattan design kicked around a few ideas
But eventually Pat realize it
The perfect trophy
Be a statue of a man on the moon
Rock and roll
For those of you who weren't around Avery
MTV played a little station ID clip at the top of the hour
It was vintage footage of the moon landing instead of planting an American flag
The astronaut had a flag
But said MTV
What's your status
Statue
And
I also wanted to make the statue
You look like it was
Loading
Serpadesign an astronaut figure in a wrinkly Apollo suit balancing on one leg holding a little flag that's
Said MTV
Seducing sketches
Santa gave them to a manufacturer
And then she comes back two weeks later
He says
Here's your statue
I look
Anything it was
There was a guy
Standing with feet
Firmly planted
Are you saluting
Saluting just upping their pets like this is totally unacceptable you've got to follow my schedule
And the manufacturer goes back to work
We come back in a week
Now I see something even more bizarre
I see a man in a leisure suit
He's got this whole thing Smooths out there's not a wrinkle in the suit also this leisure suit moon man was
Still not on one leg
And the manufacturer insisted nope
Can open it won't balance
William
One more
And that is like tomorrow
Who started building
Pat teamed up with a friend who is a Potter
And it balanced
There's a thing about balance where if you want to
Head
Center of the belly
You can balance in almost any pot
And so I just did that
For the manufacturer really didn't have a lot of time at this
The only got around to making five
Trophies
Right before the very first ever Video Music Awards
Any worse about 30 awards that we're going to be
What do we do
They decided that an usher could take each winter off the stage and sets the Moon Man each time and bring it back on stage during a
And this meant they could just keep recycling those same 5 trophies
Throughout the course of the night
Will never run out
Until
What could possibly go wrong disaster struck
Michael Jackson Thriller
Michael Jackson wasn't there sadly
First one but he won all these Awards
Diana Ross
Sitting in the front and she was accepting them
I talked to Michael
Today and he wants me
Firstier Bank
Diana Ross right in the front row
Would go up and down the stairs before the Usher could take her off the stage and get the moon info
And filler kept winning more and more Awards
Michael Jack
Acrylic
You weren't a lot in a row
She had all five statue
She's in her lap
So they sent an usher
Nick down to Diana Ross
The statues
And she starts fighting with him
Stand up as I remember
It was like a tug-of-war
And there's like a real disaster and the Moon Man tug-of-war got a little bit of air time
And it was embarrassing
But history is mostly forgotten it
Because much
Crazier things have since happened at the VMAs
Thank you so much for giving me a chance
I'm really happy for you imma let you finish but Beyonce had one of the best video
Controversy has become its yearly tradition
The whole network
You know and I knew that if it was successful then would go on to become like a yearly thing of tradition
Which is actually
And the Moon Man
Stayed which is kind of amazing
Honestly now that MTV is without music
And almost without traditional television
This award ceremony has become a big part of MTV's identity
And by now they figured out how to get all the winners their own personalized awards for the sexy let harder to plan than you think
Especially when you get into the high-stakes of War like the Oscars
Because
Back in Chicago
RS Owens doesn't know in advance who the Oscar winners are
So they've developed a smart solution
Because there's so few officers giving out and there so few nominees
We just grave
Play
And the academy can just quickly screw on the nameplate of the winter and destroy the other name
Effort but
Then the winners get to have awards that are already person
Because the most important thing about an award
Is that it has your name on it I think it was said that they did it the one word that's
Did the person
Would always prefer over all the other
Words in the vocabulary
Is kidney
Dale Carnegie's principle number 6
How to Win Friends and Influence People
Is
Remember that a person's name is
To that person
The sweetest and most
Important sound in any language
That goes a long way into the into the award business as well
That because people see their names not only hear it said but they actually see it engraved
Okay with that said
I'd like to present an award of recognition for producer of this episode 2
Avery trufelman
Oh so many people that thing
I'd like to thank
Frank olinsky
Who really helped me
I check and reach out
2Pac Gorman
I really also
Fred Seibert
Oh my God who else
Who's there
I really like the thing
Wingspan
Katie Mingle
You guys are the best
Roman Mars
Thank you for
Making this all happen this way
What happened without
And
Kalw the
Best public radio station
Arcsine architecture & Interiors
You make such beautiful buildings
And
Chocolate lying around
For us
Thank you
End
Okay thank you thank you all
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a new Wii
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You find the show and like the show on Facebook all the whole staff are all on Twitter and super fascinating there
Pictures and comments and every show we've ever made
And 99
Done working
Everyone in radio.
Just the whole radiotopia
You just make me
Want to be a better person
You know my mom
My dad
My sister
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com