99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The largest body of water in California was formed by mistake
In 1905 the California development company accidentally flooded a huge
Salty depression in the Sonoran Desert known as the Salton sink
Creating an enormous
Salty lake golf
The Salton Sea
Here we are at the edge of the Salton Sea
Credibly almost can't see across
And we're just at that
But it's pretty narrow here
Reporter Emmett Fitzgerald recently visited the Salton Sea on a hot summer day in the desert
That's just a mild 107 right now
The water is twice as salty as the Pacific Ocean
The only fish that can live there are tilapia
But even they struggle sometimes
It's just the line
Dead fish tattoo
Tilapia
Men
Broadcast fly everywhere the ground beneath the southern end of the sea is volcanic and boiling water
Bubble to the surface in muddy pools
It feels post-apocalyptic and prehistoric
All at the same time
But it's all so weirdly beautiful
In the sea isn't dead
The water is teeming with microbial life in the beaches are covered with sandpipers egrets and Pelicans
This C
Best gurgling sometimes stinky
Accident of a c
Is actually in danger of drawing up and disappearing
And you may be thinking
Good riddance it doesn't sound all that nice
And you wouldn't be alone
Over the years it's been hard to get people to care about saving the Salton Sea
Impark
Because it doesn't seem natural enough
In general we tend to think about places and objects is he there natural
Boronda
Forest
Natural
City
Unnatural
But that black-and-white distinction is sometimes greater than it seems
Today peregrine falcons are nesting on skyscrapers
Coral reefs
Are growing on oil Derricks
And some seemingly wild ecosystem
Are carefully managed by humans
The truth is a lot of places on Earth are the messy result of a combination of natural and unnatural
Natural events
Know where is messier than the Salton Sea
And it raises the question
Should we protect an ecosystem that's not purely natural
The Salton sink has not always been full of water
But it hasn't always been into either
Over centuries the Meandering Colorado River would periodically flow into the sink and fill it with water
And then over time the water would dry up
This cycle repeats itself every four or five hundred years or so
But when white settlers showed up in the desert in the late 1800s
There was no see there at all
Just a park space
At Ross
270 ft below sea level at a speed
And filled with natural salt.
Which companies Harvest
Giselle in cities like San Francisco
But Frontier developers soon realize that if you brought in water you can grow crops 12 months a year under
The Desert Sun
So they said about rebranding
This place as an agricultural Paradise
And they started by getting rid of the name
Salton sink
Well that's not a very appealing name if you're trying to sell Lots
So they thought of Imperial Valley it sounded great
That's not laughing
Suzhou local historian
Who's lived in the area for the last 60 years
They established a water company
Which would bring water by Canal from the Colorado River
They said if you start a farm here
Will bring you the water
This water came into Imperial Valley
And water the April
And
These real estate developers sold a lot of lots
In Europe
Two people who wanted to come to America and get a new start
And they had a wonderful agricultural industry going down there
For a few years anyway
In 1905 the water company cut a new canal
And before they had time to reinforce it
They had a very late
Flood of river in the Colorado and the water just
Came through and washed out that
Cut and flooded the valley
Water broke through the wall of the canal
Poured into the
The Salton sink
Destroying Farm
At home
It was a disaster
And it just kept pouring in
The federal government could not be bothered to help so the task of stopping the flow of water fell mostly to the southern
Pacific Railway which had lost train tracks in the flood and would lose more if they did nothing
Amazing tasks they built railroad tracks
Out to the break in the die and then they just took flat car loads of
Cement and old cars are any junk that they can throw in because there was just no solid
Bottom there to the river it was all sandy they did this for an entire year
Fill in the breach and get the river back into its Channel
But by that point the water had filled out the Salton sink created a massive Lake in the middle of a desert
The Salton Sea
And most people assumed it would just dry up
Puddle on a hot day
Which is what it usually did
Whenever the Colorado float in
The Salton sink
But the sea had a new water sources
Agriculture
Does irrigation float off the fields in the Imperial Valley
It ran downhill into the sink
And sustained this
Salton Sea
And for much of the twentieth century the runoff coming into the sea was about the same as the amount of water being
Evaporation
Creating a
Strange bounce
I need to see abs
Pierce table
And back then the sea was
Pretty different than it is now
It look like a peaceful Oasis in an otherwise hostile desert
Like somewhere you might want to go
On vacation
In the 1950s a new round of developers saw chance to turn the sea into a playground for loss and
Angela's weekenders
They called it
The California Riviera
Are is truly a miracle in the desert
All new outlet for the cloud
It's a big city
A Palm Springs with water
Here is where you can find the good life in
Today
Oil tycoon named Ken Phillips
Build a planned community on the west side of the lake
Called
Salton City he put in a yacht club over there and lay down
Bought
Sold lots and brought busloads of people down to
See the sea and purchase Lots
That's Pat Laughlin
She used to take her family
Like the Salton Sea on weekend
It was really a wonderful place to go for recreation when I
Came in nineteen
And I have memories of many
Hamburger fries on the beach and swimming
But the water was great and
There was water skiing and
They had a lot of boat races across
Send back
And then there were the fish
The California Department of Fish and Game
Decided to stock the sea with
With fish in order to encourage
More tourism
Scientists at UCLA work to design an ecosystem that can handle year-round Sportfishing
And they had to re-establish a hole
Food chain to get the larger game fish
To survive but they started with the little brine shrimp
And they brought them up from the Gulf of
Baja California and the brought in the brine fish and then whatever the
8 Bryan fish came and then the next thing up the chain
The water was salty but not too salty
And so they try to mix of freshwater and saltwater species
And a lot of his work was done by biologist
But some of it was just
Renegade fishing
I tried them all kinds of fish
Find harbor seals
And they survived I guess for a while back
That's why they didn't see any of many more
That Steve Harvey
A retired Ranger with
California state parks
Spent
10 years down at the Salton Sea living in the desert
Steve says that a few fish like tilapia siargao and Corvina
Thrived
By the 1960
The Salton Sea was one of the most popular fishing destinations
In the country
The marinas were
Full of Boulders the marinas were full of life
The Bars were falling
Was packed there were
A run of cars
Hannah coming from the LA area down to the Salton Sea every week
Stars like the Beach Boys and Frank Sinatra tooled around the lake and motorboat
And then gave
Concerts in programs on the shore of the Salton Sea
What's the place to go
There was a time when more people went to the Salton Sea then went to Yosemite
But the good life in the son didn't last all that long
In the 70s and 80s
Mugs knocked out a lot of the infrastructure along the shore
And most of the owners of the marinas on the yacht clubs decided not to rebuild
Anna by then people began thinking then
Maybe they were more issues than
And they were aware of it
The Salton Sea
And they were right
One of the biggest issues
This was salinity
The water entering the Salton Sea picks up salts from the soil
And those salts
I have nowhere to go
Salton Sea is
The clothes body of water the only way water leaves is it evaporate
Brazen as water evaporates
The material the solids
I saw the salt con
Centration continues to increase
Every year the sea gets saltier and saltier
Which is a natural process
That's four lakes with no Outlet
The tourist in like super salty water smelly fish die-offs in massive
Algae bloom
By the 1990s most of the marinas
Hotels
To close their doors
And a lot of people had left town
A rugged contingent stuck it out
In small Seaside towns
What the dream of the
California Riviera
Was over
And then in the mid-90s
The sea begin to dry up
Remember
Pretty much the only water going into the sea was from agricultural runoff
But over the years Farm to become more efficient
With water they install drip irrigation
Reduce the runoff draining into the sea
Then in 2003 as part of a complicated water deal
The water district in Imperial Valley sold off the rights to a lot of their water
Mostly to San Diego
Some farmers in the area had to stop watering their fields which meant less water draining into the Salton Sea
Steve horvitz and many other local
Fought hard against the water Tran
Which they say was done without a proper environmental review
They Lobby politicians in Sacramento and Washington
Demanding a plan for saving the Salton Sea
But few lawmakers wanted to prioritize a
Feeding Taurus
In the 90s celebrity Congressman Sonny Bono have been a champion
But he died
Ennis TX
Steve Harvey says that he even had trouble getting help from Environmental
Some environmentalists
I knew
They would discount the song Say Yes
Is the wasted body of water is just a man-made lake
Cancel why you so worried about
Resumes
How many people talk to us about why restore the Salton Sea it was an accident
Stem the assistant secretary for natural resources
Agency in charge of solvency policy and Broomsticks issue
People who call it an accidental
This latest version of the song she wasn't asking
Can I put three slots
Geologic history
It shows that the Imperial Valley was flooded periodically by the Colorado River
Either way
Wildlife doesn't really care whether or not the lake
Because an accident
Just look at all the birds
Ducks game
Still
And doscher's hair and brown pelican and white pelicans a large population
There are
About 425 different species have been cataloged
Are identified it's assault
Aside from the Texas Gulf
The Salton Sea has more bird species than any other place
In the US
Many of those birds migrate up and down North America
And the birds would stop at marshes in Southern California to refuel
But those marshes are there any
Most of the wetlands in Southern California are actually probably in all of Cal
Have disappeared because of development
End of one kind or another
The song season of the last stops
So if we lose that link if it dries up
I'm afraid we'll crash a lot of burping
And there's another reason not to let the sea evaporate
Probably the most compelling
When is human health
As the sea recedes
It exposes dry lake
Call Playa
And it's made up of tiny dust particles
Most I can get into your lungs
And cause respiratory diseases
Like asthma
To make matters worse heavy metals and other toxins from all that agricultural runoff
Have settled at the bottom of a lake
So there's a tremendous health risk and not just for people living near the sea
Toxic dust could get blown as far away as
Phoenix Arizona
The Pacific Institute of water think tank in Oakland
Weather report in 2014 saying that the
The cost of doing nothing at the Salton Sea
Could be as high as 70 billion dollars over the next 30 Years
As part of that 2003 water transfer
California agreed to send some water.
The Salton Sea for a few years
To keep the salinity in check
Well I figure out a solution
The Dust
In the birds that water will stop flowing after 2017
But there is a little glimmer of
This year California approved 80 million dollars for new Salton Sea task force with Bruce Wilcox heads
And they're using the funds to start designing ways to keep the dust down and the birds coming back
All using a lot less water
The plan is basically to build artificial wet
With water cycling between pond
The burying salinity
Each designed to support different birds be
NLB walkway
Boat launch
So people can enjoy the resource to
But there's no blueprint
For this kind of
Ecosystem
And planning an ecosystem runs counter to a pretty basic ecological principles
That nature Knows Best
A lot of environments the best approach is to keep humans as far away as possible
But it's too late
The Salton Sea
Humans have transformed this landscape
The entire Colorado River Basin in such
Profound ways
We dammed up the river
Irrigated the desert
We have dried up all the Wailing
We have made all these modifications for better or worse
And now we're in a position where
We have to step in and
Manage
That's Bruce Wilcox again
Assistant secretary for Salton Sea policy
And
I would be lying to you if I didn't say I was a little nervous about
Because
We don't know anywhere near as
As we sing
Just a little bit arrogant
I think we screwed it all up and then suddenly we decide which
Fix it I mean there's danger in that
But we're in a position where we don't have a choice
Building hundreds of Acres of artificial wetlands
Is going to require a lot of money
Much more than the 80 million they just got
And that means California is going to have to start valuing a lance
That's the furthest thing
It's easy to contrast the Salton Sea with California second largest body of water
Lake Tahoe
The Beautiful Blue Mountain Lake that Northern California Guppies and
Hippies and yuppies who used to be hippies
Flock to
Every weekend
I was sexy
And now there's no doubt but the song say it
Former park ranger
Prestige Portraits
The Salton Sea is ugly guy
Living down there and it does
Hot and sweaty guy
Anytime just repels people
And at Salton Sea
Will never be a late
But he'll have his own Beauty
Everywhere you go in Calif
Other bumper sticker
Keep Tahoe Blue
It's almost a badge of environment
The Salton Sea might not be as beautiful or natural is Lake Tahoe
But we need it all the same
But if the Salton Sea is going to get saved it'll need to get appreciated for
I need to see something bumper sticker
Just got to think of a slogan and it probably can't be
Save that
Hot sweaty guy in the desert
So
Buffet
See you at the Salton Sea
Make the Salton Sea great again
Redesign the Riviera
The Salton Sea is for the birds
We came we saw the Salton Sea don't add salt and keep God in your right shoulder and saw
Salton on your lap tilapia
I hardly know you
That's the one
99percentinvisible with produces week by Emmett Fitzgerald with Sharif Youssef Katie mingle Kolstad same Greenspan
Avery truffelman and V Roman Mars
Some of the music in this episode was provided by our friends at okay akumi from Hell audio
Okay can we have a new 4 song EP that I just bought yesterday
It's on bandcamp it's called
Selinsgrove
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
MPI feed
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find this show and like a show on Facebook follow all the people who work on this show on Twitter and Instagram at the best way to explore than
99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
Around the hundreds and hundreds of stories
Anthony 9 p.m.
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com