99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Back in the 1980s when Louise smuts was growing up in Johannesburg South Africa
His family couldn't go outside together without breaking the law
My father would never walk next to my mother
My mother would always walk behind them wherever they went
Louis was too young to understand why his parents couldn't be seen together in Johannesburg or as everyone calls
Joburg
Louis just saw a world that treated them differently
Your mother got sick and didn't have a medical Aid should go to a hospital out of the city
Where is
Meat that you can see what is the temperature
Just around the corner from where we started
Healthcare it like almost everything else in South Africa was decided by race
Louis father was white his mother was colored a local term for people of mixed race
They gotten married in neighboring Swaziland
But back home their marriage was against the law
When do we was a kid only white people can move freely in cities here
Live in the nicest neighborhood
Access the best hospitals
Schools in jobs
This is Dawson Woodley
He's a South African journalist
Black people on the other hand
Lived in the crowded outskirts
Which were far from just about everything you'd once in the city
The country's ruling white minority
Coldest system up at 8
Which literally translated
To separate
I want to see is one
And I say that is being misunderstood
Ice cream Justice Easley
That's much better be described
As a policy of good neighborliness
Apocalypse leaders like Hendrick forefoot
Claim that segregated cities were better for everyone
And apostates was strictly enforced
Policeman Patrol neighborhoods
To make sure that white people and black people weren't living together
If you lived in a house
But come knocking on your door
But the apartheid system was never airtight and people found creative ways to slip through the cracks
If you lived in a high-rise building with
5/600 flexible inner they weren't going to go through each and every
Flight to come and look
Xiaomi
Illegal person
You can easily disappear into flat
Over the years many families like Louise
Disappeared into one high-rise apartment building in particular
The tower called Ponte City in Johannesburg
Everybody knows party
Even looking at joburg Skyline now
Pontes Hudson MS
First of all it's
54 stories tall
That makes it the tallest apartment building on the entire African country
And it certainly makes a toilet than any of the other buildings around it
It's also completely secular
If you want to look at Ponte from above
You see that the center is Justice open hollow-core
Design to allow natural ventilation
N2 lesson daylight
The building looks
Kind of like a massive concrete toilet roll
It's also got this glowing red billboard for a cell phone company wrapping around the top
Like a crown
So wherever you are in the city
You can easily Spot It
Pontes larger-than-life architecture also comes with a larger-than-life reputation
So many the building symbolizes
Is Johannesburg
Because over the past four decades
Its fortunes have basically murdered the city
Because of its
Fail because of
It's chicken history
If toughness is restless
Cox Chesapeake traffic condition
That's Melinda Silverman
An architectural historian who studies inner-city Johannes
Hessberg chastity
Which guys very rapidly
Three cycles of
Declining
Prosperity and economy
Auntie has always been kind of a vertical waiting room for admission to South African society
But it's also been a laboratory
Place where the city seems to try out new versions of itself
Years before Ponte became a hideaway for interracial families like Louise
It attracted a much different clientele
I don't understand who first lived there and why
We have to go back to the 1960s
Before Ponte was even built
At the start of the 60s
The apartheid system had been firmly in place for more than 10 years
And South Africa's economy was a rising star in the world
It had just given birth to a new currency the Rand which was already stronger than the US dollar
The country's success was largely driven by its access to cheap black labour
And it's rich goldap
We were the major goal
Producers in the world
And the feeling was that if we could continue being the magical
What uses and keep and increasing erased
Black population
Under control
Futurist
Radiance
Unless of course
You were black
Over the next decade
Foreign investments in South Africa doubled
But skilled workers were in short supply
Because the government had denied the majority of the population at decent education
It had to fill the Gap by recruiting single white men from all of Europe
The country's white population increased by over 50% between 1963
A 1972
These new coming so a strong economy
And an idyllic life
White people
With a living of privilege
Did you probably couldn't have
Found it
Any other part of the world
If you were a middle-class person
Living in an apartment
In England
In America
You're probably have had to wash your own dishes and made your own bed
Where is if you were middle class
Json
Living
Is South Africa
Property head at least
And there was one square mile of in a city joburg the future sites of Ponte Tower
That was a regular Landing place for these European migrants in the 1960s and 70s
It was home to the city's most famous bars
And live music joints
A place where specialty stores sold French magazines Italian shoes and American rock and roll
Shiny Vibrava
That was a regular Landing place for these European migrants in the 1960s and 70s
It was home to the city's most
Famous bars
And live music joint
A place where specialty stores sold French magazines Italian shoes and American rock and roll
It had a shiny vibrant Bohemian Edge
The people compared to New York's Greenwich Village all blend in SoHo.
But it was also a place that felt almost like it wasn't in South Africa at all
Like most of joburg's nicest neighborhoods
This area was zoned exclusively for white people
Black South Africans could work there but unless they were live-in servants they had to be out by Nightfall each evening
Developers could hardly satisfy the demand for high-rise apartments in this part of the city
Buildings kept getting bigger and
Toilet
But that wasn't the only thing fueling the development of Joe Biggs new high-rises
The other
To drive I would say
With on your mark
And it's worthless
Hold me
Saints of what
Backless with a gray
Economy
These are good times
This was why people want
Make the mark on the lens
Skype
South Africa
Martin Progressive
Impressive
Place
Of course South Africa was neither truly modern no Progressive at this
This was the era of African Independence
Across the continent
Old colonies with falling like dominoes
And by the mid-1960s
Most African countries with black rule
This decade
Is it decade of African Independence
The people have got to see their freedom as more than a local trial
The only all African Dominion in the British Commonwealth
In the new Africa one more independent country
Tomatoes World South Africa's white government was starting to look pretty backward
And it didn't help that the country had recently thrown several of the anti-apartheid movement most powerful leaders in jail for
4life including a young lawyer named Nelson Mandela
Petrovic new buildings kept getting bigger and more audacious
Almost as if the government was trying to prove its wilikina
By the early 1970s huge skyscrapers with sprouting up across central jovic
Including plenty
Monkey starts of being
Tala
Around town
That's architect
Rodney kruska
It was one of the three architects who designed the bull
So now I'm watching the game
Tool trailer
Jewelry store
With a Halo down the middle
The whole outside of it
It is made out of
Ruel concrete
Unpainted
Unpolished
And then at its foot
3D anchor
So beautiful
People
Once Upon a Time City looks a bit like a wedding cake but not everyone agreed the building but beautiful
Some thought it look like an ugly brutalist
Wedding cake
Straight off the boat
It was voted as the second ugliest building in Japan
Not even the honor of being the first ugliest
The second ugliest
When can you reenlist chicken nuggets
Second ugliest or not
Tontitown AR was popular
President started moving in even before the building was finished
Lord bites furnished Flats in panoramic city views
All the units in Ponte Facebook Inward and outward
With entrances wrapping around the central core
From one side of the building you could see the entire downtown Skyline
From another you could catch entire rugby matches at the city's main stadium
By the time Ponte was completed in 1975
It's 470 Flats
Warren Heideman
Switzerland allergies about how I'll just going to use as much
Electricity is as every small town in
People in the every small town in South Africa
The developers thought that way to on pontes ground floor they built an elaborate shopping mall
And schemed about putting a miniature ski slope in the open core
So we had restaurants
Butcher Baker Candlestick maker
Desiindy next bison
As a little city
But even as pontes new residents were moving in the city around them with cracking apart
At this time Johannesburg center city was almost exclusively White
Black South Africans lived on the edges of the city
In communities called Township
And 12 Mile
Southwest Aponte
In a black Township called Soweto
A new revolt
Against apartheid had begun
Language they regarded
Is Nautica manifestation of urban black frustration
Protest escalated
And on June 16th 1976
Police killed at least 276 High School
During a peaceful protest
Images of the massacre quickly circled the globe inspiring renewed Kohl's
To end white rule
As Apollo smoke Rises over this black community
Minority
Calling or coming under greater pressure
The Soweto Uprising also sent joburg's urban planning dreams crashing
The June 16th Uprising and the international sanctions in boycotts that followed
How to destroy the country's economy
It became difficult to keep all the newly constructed high-rises
Fully occupied
And it wasn't just the crashing economy
Like many cities around the world Johannesburg had started to experience a wave of suburbanization
When white people moving out of the inner city and into new suburb
Meanwhile many black South Africans were fleeing from the poverty and violence of the townships
For them the inner city was an alluring option
Especially
Ponte
Physical effects they would have been more affordable
Really good location
The ability to be really near to
The wig places that still existed in the Inner City
In the 1980s
It was still illegal for black
Indian and coloured South Africans to live in these areas
But the scale and density of the inner city made the laws harder to enforce
Unlimited reading hot dance
Petit living offered which means that
People
Quit being less conspicuous
Ephedra legal in Italian
Gentleman
Black lady as wife
Is a French gentleman
Who old Santa colored
Why
That's Louis smuts again
Whose parents were in an illegal interracial marriage
He's talking about some of the other families who also lived in Ponte in the early 1980s
As the lines between Black and Whites began to
South Africans coined a new term for the phenomenon
Decoded Graham
For Louie gray areas were in Escape
Auntie was a place where his family could be together freely without fear of arrest or public scrutiny
I don't even remember seeing any building rides or anything like that you almost had protection being
In
The flashlight
Denial because so many places
Going to a flight yet going to reflect
You know they went thank you close down a whole block of flats at 1
But that doesn't mean that they weren't
Stresses associated with life in Ponte
Police regularly set up checkpoints to monitor who came in and out of black and white areas of
When Louise family went through these checkpoints
His mother would sit in the back seat
Posing as the families made
She have to sit in the back
Is plain and simple as that she sat in the back
Black and colored people who illegally settled in the Inner City
Also strike a hard bargain
Landlords who turn a blind eye to the color of the residents skin
And residents would have to turn a blind eye to Rising rents
Improvement
The stages of illegality
I think
With absolutely critical to the decline because
You are an illegal tenant you have no protection of the law
Sol ring
Canby rent
Any rain for rent
How do you fold the ring
You sublet
The rain stopped even further and then you sublet even more
Inside Ponte
Apartment started to get crowded in grimy
Plumbing broke down
Trash begin to fill the open core in the center of the building like an oversized concrete garbage can
There were giant piles of old mattress
Furniture in rubble
Eventually Legend spread that the trash and piled up so high it reads the 14th story of a building
Pretty soon Banks stopped issuing Home Loans in the area
And white people kept moving out
By the late 1980s
What you thought of Ponte and the surrounding neighborhood called hillbrow
Probably depends a lot on the color of your skin
1 Suburban
Would it be until 5
And he'll probably be the place
Who is acting for people in
That is mostly black and colored people
Beacon of opportunity
Your way into the sea
Your way of experiencing urban life
And all these changes in the inner city where fish are doing a much bigger change that was about to happen to all
On February 2nd 1990 then president FW de klerk
When some friendship Parliament to give his annual state of the nation
Three decades the apartheid government headband mini anti-apartheid political parties
They rested their members and sometimes forced them into exile
No one was expecting the president to announce the end of that attract
He shocked nearly everyone
Watching
The prohibition of the African National Congress the pan africanist Congress the South African Communist Party
He's being December
The government has taken a firm decision
To release mr Mandela unconditionally
This beats would change the course of South African history
A week later after 27 years in prison
For treason
Nelson Mandela was free
And after Decades of struggle
The end of Apartheid was suddenly internet
From all over the world exiled political activist began to return
They wanted to help shape a dramatically changing country
50 + 19
The year that we came back
That's lenswear most likely an anti-apartheid activist who fled South Africa in 1980
Like many other returning exiles
Lynchwood took advantage of the centrality and cheap rental Vienna City
And moved into a friends
24th floor apartment in Ponte Tower
Ponte and the surrounding neighborhood
Webb still run down
Butlins way was surprised to find the area felt a lot like the Westin City
What he'd spent the past decade
That's where the music was happy
54 hour
Food Outlets that we're Nazi
Send anywhere
Weather
So goodnight sweetheart
Throughout
Yeah it was like
Get big in jail
Some of the old European cafes from the 50s and 60s were still standing
Serving late night
Espressos and thick schnitzel
But alongside them were new shop
What's a nightclub
Including one run by the famous South African Trumpeter
Hugh Masekela with recently returned from his own Exxon
So if you wanted to find anybody
Who are around
Instead
McCartney says they stayed up all night
Talking about the future of danu country over beers and Brandy's
Thabo mbeki who would later become president of South Africa
Lived in the building next to Ponte
At the time of the first democratic election in 1994
One Observer counted 50 of the new members of parliament
Staying in Ponte and the surrounding area
But the end of Apartheid didn't represent the end of Ponte Towers evolution
The transition to Black rule in South Africa also meant the end of the countries tightly closed borders
Which four decades have cracked open only for white immigrants and a few laborers from the surrounding countries
Throughout the 1990s
Immigrants began arriving in Johannesburg by the
Tens of thousands
And many of them landed in panties
That's footage from a film called Africa shafted by Ingrid Mountain
She filmed entirely inside a panties elevator
That's why it sounds like the doors opening and shutting in the background world
Martin's found people from dozens of countries living in the building
Mostly in crowded Apartments shared by several families
Some had come for work
Others were fleeing political persecution
They shared one importance
Experience with past residents
For them Ponte was a place you could start over
I just wouldn't give
Malaysia boy the life that I never had
Over the years Ponte like South Africa itself continued to have its ups and downs
By the late 90s the building's physical decline made it a Haven for criminals
Who moved into the building and ran out like a vertical slum
Appunti Still Remains in place of Big Ideas
Nice and wild experimentation
Developments made a few attempts to gentrify the tower and turn it into luxury apartments again
But ultimately those plans
Didn't really work
Punchy today remains a lot like it was at the end of Apartheid
A home for recently arrived immigrants from all of Africa
On a recent Saturday morning at pair of kids are battling it out on a foosball table at the base of Punta
You can tell it's a close game
Just down the road people are crowding around a wall That's covered in hundreds of scribbled slips of paper
In several different languages
Summit on a stack of the older ones with WhatsApp bubble gum
It's a sort of analog Craigslist
A message board for newcomers searching for accommodation in Ponte
And around hillbrow
I'm looking for a lady
Balcony at 1801 Metropolitan
And the list goes on
Sifting through the messages that the Monfils Limitless
Lake South Africa itself
Ponte has gone from a symbol of white opulence to something far more complicated
It's hopeful
And it's a little rough around the edges
It's a microcosm of the country's history
That's also a place that moves on
And the stream concrete tube at the center of joburg skyline
Continues to play the same role for newcomers that it always has
The same
You know they might have been cheaper to vacuum Portuguese Italians of dance living in helper
Then what novel
Pomeranians and garlands Nigeria
Zimbabweans
It's voice has been your entry point into the city
So did Ponte Tower seem Vaguely Familiar but you can't quite put your finger on it
Cuz you probably saw it or at our inspired by it
IMovie
Epilogue about Pontius life on screen
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You know we only heard option Woodley's voice in this episode it was reported by two people actually
Second reporter is Ryan Braun and she was a resident
Ponte Tower
And it done a lot of reporting on the place
And what are things about Ponty
That is pretty interesting is that even though you might not know it's
Bible History or even know its name
You might
I feel like it's kind of familiar as a place and the reason is because
It has been two picked
In movies and dinner
And I asked Brian to talk to me about
The party is actually made
Quite a number of
Cameos in film and other popular culture
Most recently in the last Resident Evil
Some as a site of the zombie apocalypse
It was in District 9 a few years ago and the robots becoming human story
Chappie
A couple years ago to me on a number of other films too interesting Lee not always films
Comforter set in Johannesburg but always
Films that are set in places where
There's something either kind of apocalyptic or just
Gritty and Messi going on
Right it has that Vibe it's not necessarily
Johannesburg by bits the
It's the vibe of apocalypse
Apps that it gives off
Yeah totally but you know you have to sort of wonder where it where did
Filmmakers get the idea that Punta would be the scene for the apocalypse and I think it's rooted in the kind of stereotypes that people have about the
Intercity of
Johannesburg
Which are then intern you know rooted and I think the fear is that a lot of South Africans have about the city in
And what it's become
Since the end of Apartheid
And there's also a number of films where
It's not it's early
Ponte works on esterly Johannesburg but there's this
The idea of
Tower
That's a city in of itself
That is its own sort of
Dark place
Dread for example reminds me of the way that
About Ponte city as well
Yeah exactly I know an interesting thing about dread is that the movie itself was filmed in Johannesburg
And they didn't use Conte as assets but then
There's a sort of
Massive
Apartment Tower in in the in the Selma 200 story building
It has a hollow open course
So you have to wonder if you know where they got that idea
Right
Why do you think it's so evocative why do you think
Confused in this way
Are you
Troubled by
And anyway or is there no are you kind of
Please when you
And I think the way it's come to be as a combination of
Two things and the one is that
Ponte has become the sort of
Metaphor for
Johannesburg in for South Africa and this kind of outsize thing on the skyline on Twitch people can project their fears
Pisidian weather
Becoming and I think
Filmmakers have just picked up on that
And then the other thing is is
The aesthetic is to of the building is just
Pretty wild I mean it's just the sort of
50 stories of raw
Brutal concrete it's got these kind of
Exposed
Concrete ribs on the inside the chorus just this crazy
Rocky space
You stare up and there's like
50 stories of windows
Staring back down at you and this
Start of shaft of light
Almost otherworldly sword has this very cinematic
Quality to it
I do find the
Do you know the way it appears in popular culture troubling because I think it's sort of
Freezes in time this very negative
Vision of Johanna
Speargun this vision of Ponte in Ponte and Johannesburg both
Have changed and are changing you know
Assertive extraordinary quickly I thinking
Anybody know about any City but I think
Johannesburg is a
Tickly unsentimental kind of
City in sky
It was started as this sort of mining town was up it's always been a place where people just came to make money to get rich to go
Get ahead
You don't have this kind of sentimental attachment
Home in Johannesburg in into the city sort of moves on
And forgets very quickly but then
When you have
The Arbiters of popular culture when you have filmmakers come in and create this or you know start of reinforce this vision of
Joe Berger of 20 as these
Is really dangerous
Scritti crime-ridden spaces a kind of
Freezes that image in people's minds and that's
Setopati
I think the city is like
Whether or not
It still is
And you live there for a time right
I did I lived there for about a year coinciding with
Filming of the Resident Evil movie
I was treated to a number of days of the zombie apocalypse
And literally zombies wandering through my building
Screaming
Logical endpoint to this
Conte metaphor
If 20 * 2 represents
Sort of
Chaotic way that Johannes Berg has evolved since the end of
Apartheid in and thus the disarray of the city in that. I mean represents disarray more than a
Zombie apocalypse
99percentinvisible was pretty so sweet by Ryan Brown and Dawson Woodley with Delaney Hall mix into production by Sheree
Refusive music by Sean real with an additional song by Jenny Conlee drizos John neufeld and a query
Christina producer is Katie Mingle
Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
We all had in our two cents including Emmett Fitzgerald
Avery truffle
Darren Masa and me
Roman Mars
Special thanks to Ingrid Martin's without us to use audio from her film Africa shafted
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRI
Rockstar Collective of the best most Innovative shows in all of vodka
We are supported by the Knight foundation and coin carrying listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible into in discussions about the show on Facebook you can do to me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pio
Oracle on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Would you want to read a cool article by Kurt about fictional megacities in science fiction
You have to go to our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com