99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The ocean is not our place
We can't breathe under there I can't really see
We can learn to swim but it doesn't come naturally
Hips don't swear
They want nothing to do with putting their bodies in the water
It's only humankind's incessant need to explore that drives us into such an unwelcoming invite
And since our bodies aren't built for it we must design thing
But allow us to explore this
Warren Place
And we have
That's our own Katie Mingle
Alexander the Great is said to have descended into the ocean more than 2000 years ago in a glass Barrel
There are various paintings
This event
In one the great is being lowered into the ocean by a couple of men in a wooden boat
He's hunched inside his little Barrel
Still wearing his
Crown and robe
The guys in the boat looked to me like they're used to humoring his every whim
In some versions of the story Alexander the Great was not in a barrel but in a diving bell
Diving Bells have been around for a long time
Aristotle wrote about them around 300 BC
And they were often actual Bells
Like from churches
To understand how one uses such a thing to Aid in an ocean dive
Try this
Quick experiment
Fill up your sink with water
And push a cup open and down
Into the water
You notice that the cop doesn't
Fill up all the way
There'll be a pocket of breathable air on the inside
Amazingly this works using giant church bells and the ocean to
Diver's Cove lower about
Into the ocean and use it as a kind of home base
Swimming out and around searching for Sunken Treasure
And then popping back into the Bell
First few guys
But it wasn't a good solution
The air didn't last long
The bells were cumbersome
And the divers still couldn't go down very far
Because of the pressure
The main obstacle to exploring the depths of the ocean has always been the pressure
Bralette
200ft
Your lungs collapse and you die
That's Jim Gould telling it like it is
Professor biology
Princeton and he's married to Carol gold
Who will also be talking to you today I'm Carol Gould
I'm a science writer
Sheen Jimmy written 10 books together they've been married for 45 years
This is how Jim talks about the
The first time he met care
And
There she was
The person I've been looking for
All my life
I didn't take long from then
In the mid-1800s a naturalist named Edward Forbes
Hypothesize that below 300 fathoms
Or about 1800 ft
No life
Exist
In the ocean
And people pretty much believed him
Well the general thought was that
It was just common sense
Nothing could live down there
Because the deeper you get
Pressure
Increases
On the living tissues
And it gets darker and darker
And it just made sense to people
You know the way we are so
Anthropocentric
If people can't live down there well
Probably nothing else
But these anthropocentric naysayers would soon be proven wrong
Continents were about to be strung together with Telegraph wires
Starting an 1858 nations were connected with extremely long wires
Messages would travel great distances through cables that lay on the ocean floor
And in 1860 as the Mediterranean cable was raised for repair
I'm about 6000 feet
Lo and behold
Attached to the cable or Critters
Mostly dead Critters
The critters that were once
Alive
This discovery was much talked about in the Press
There was a life in the depths of the ocean and everyone wanted to know more about it
In 1872 the British royal Navy sent a modified warship called the HMS Challenger out on one of the
The first scientific expeditions
It was this big beautiful ship with sails it look like the kind of shape people hang paintings of and
Old rustic pubs
Or get tattooed on their bicep
The scientists and sailors spent 4 years on this ship
Studying the Earth's oceans trying especially understand the deepest
And they did things like put down Nets
Very deep into the water
And go along
Hoping
But the Nets would catch something
It was down there
But just like our bodies can't survive the pressure at Great depths
Fish that live at the bottom of the ocean aren't made to live at the top
So as they come up
They they basically crystallizing fracture
So every cell
MicroCell explosion what you have is a bag of
Listening to some Sailors were pulling up giant Netflix
Bloated
Fishkill
Still they managed to gather a bunch of specimen but they saved in jars full of pickling alcohol as they sale
Around the world
In the end they traveled almost 70000 nautical miles
Dredging in pickling
It was hard work
It was really an arduous
Trip because they started out with
How many sailors
Jump started with 214 and ended with 144
Two men went insane to drowned one committed suicide and several deserted
But the Challenger Expedition did catalog around 4000 new species and took depth measurement that hunger
Locations all over the ocean using a weighted string
On March 23rd 1875 at station number 225 located in the Southwest Pacific
Ocean between Guam and Palau
11 Caster weighted string over the side of the ship
And it just kept dropping
Dropping
10000 feet
They had dropped their weight is the Mariana Trench and discovered what is still the deepest known place
On the ocean floor
But despite the challenges many accomplishments
Still no one had
Actually been very deep in the ocean
Been among the living creatures to see them alive in their natural habitat
There were various attempts of diving suits over the years
The picture the aesthetic range of the suits
Start with guy in a barrel with arm holes and get to Giant ridiculous Spaceman robot suit
You look back at these old suits if you seen the movie Forbidden Planet
You've seen
Asserts Robby the Robot looks exactly
Like one of these
What's the Michelin Man looks a lot like these suits
They were incredibly heavy and cumbersome
You couldn't swim in them
He had to get dried up to the surface by boat
And they all had tubes that stretched up to the surface for oxygen
Using one of these suits the Navy had said the man 563 feet under the surface of a freshwater lake
When do the submarines have been as deep as 383 ft in the ocean
Brands of the 1920s
No one had gone further than that
And then came a scientist
Named William Beebe
William Beebe was a respected ornithologist and an exceedingly Charming character who got around by bicycle
Spend his time gazing into the skies and writing about birds
Titles of his books include
The bird its form and function
Two bird lovers in Mexico and a monograph of pheasants
He really love birds
And then in the 1920s
Working near the coast
William Beebe turn his attention
To the ocean
He would
Look down in the water
And just
10 hours wondering what was down there
And
So then he started trying to think
And plan
Awake
Could get him down there
What is BB parted ways to go deep he couldn't seem to think outside the cylinder
Which was the shape of pre-existing submarines
Buy babies time of submarines could go down about
He went down further
Collapsed
Crush the pressure outside
I flattened everything inside
The result is you had a metal pan cake
And then in 1928 a young engineer named Otis Barton got in touch with baby and told him
Pedego is deep as he wanted to go
Cylinder was never going to work
The design had to be in the shape
Of a sphere
Even though
The ocean
Brings on more and more pressure
The deeper you go
That pressure
If you're innosphere
Is present equally on every
Square inch of the spear
Who does Martin told BBC help him design and engineer this new submersible
As long as he was allowed to accompany Bebe on all of the trip
The sphere made into the sea
Which was a pretty crazy thing for Barton to want considering what eight tiny uncomfortable submersible he
He was about to make
The final design was about
4 1/2 ft in diameter
And there wasn't a bench or even a level floor inside the bathroom
I sat on this horrible cold
Wet concave
Floor
The kind of pushed back together
And they weren't really great friends
Either
The sphere was made of steel and had two windows
Fix you
Quartz
Provided
Extremely Clear View into the water
It also had a small hat
Enter through
They called it
The baathist
Bath is being the Greek word
Pradeep
William Beebe set up a science station on nonsuch island in Bermuda and they began doing Dives in the bathysphere
The submersible couldn't move on its own so I had to be lowered on a cable off of a boat and then plant drive to
In retrospect the whole thing seems
Extremely low Tech well it was 1930
And their high-tech is now our very very low-tech
Inside the sphere were some canisters of oxygen and some trays of chemicals that's soaked up the CO2 they were
Breathing out
It was cramped and humid in there
Condensation pooled on the floor and Otis Barton was often seasick
They circulated the air with
Onlyfans
Back and forth
And that was the height of comfort
They were literally just Fanning themselves
Yep
It wasn't comfortable but the sphere did completely Shield them from the outside pressure
They didn't have to worry about the bends or decompression sickness that divers can experience when it's ending too quickly
The thing that really scared them with the idea of a leek
Because if there were even a pinhole
Leak
A toastie
Pressures
A jet of water would come in
At such a high rate of
Pressure speed
That it would just be like being shot
The bullet if the two men can make it safely into the ocean's depths
They would be able to see out into the dark ocean using a spotlight
The Vessel also have a telephone they could use to talk to the people in the boat above them
Their first dive on May 27th 1930 was just 45 ft down
But overtime Bebe & Barton started doing deeper and deeper Dives in the bathroom
When they steal them in it was in
Ratably noisy
Because I have to hammer those
Big steel bolt in and
That just drove me crazy
Then you went to the surface and it was flashing around and then it just got very
Jerry
Quiet
And you hear the sound of
The oxygen
Coming in may be very quiet
Bush
And then you do the voice of Gloria who was on the other end of the telephone talking to BV
Glorietta bathysphere 285 ft
The Lusitania is resting at this level
Deepest point
You're now at 600 feet
1426 ft
We are still alive
And 1/4 of a mile down
As they descended deeper baby became obsessed with the changing light and color inside the bath
The sphere in his Memoir a half-mile down he dedicates Pages upon pages to this
Subject
The blueness of the blue
Outside and inside of sphere
Cheetah mask material
Definable
Translucent blue quite unlike anything I've ever seen in the world
As the bathysphere sunk lower and lower
They would have been floating in complete darkness
The BB & Barton both swore there was somehow still an aura of blueness to the blackness
It's as if the blue had seeped so thoroughly into their eyeballs that they still saw it
Even in the dark
And
Baby comments on this and many people
Spend down
Comment on this
When he wasn't having his mind blown by the varying shades of blue
BB was tripping out on the fish
After the sunlight disappeared
The only fish they be able to see without their Spotlight with the ones that provided their own light
What is
Fish with bioluminescence
So they spent a lot of time turning the spotlight on and off
Poseidus pentagramas
The five line constellations
Fish almost round
Longmont
The ocean was
Steaming with strange looking creatures
Call Dad
Evie would describe these creatures in great detail over the telephone line that went up to the boat above
On the sides of the body where five unbelievable
Equatorial
With two curved ones above
And then Elsa Boston
It was an amazing artist
With their onboard as well and she would make sketches
Island
Baby finally came up he would look them over and say yes that's right no that's wrong
Straighten it all out
Everyone was surrounded by a semicircle
A very small but intensely purple photophores bosselman sketches were published in National Geographic
My back and the creatures they portrayed were so strange so otherworldly that readers couldn't believe
If they were real
A lot of people actually accuse BB of making stuff up
And that hurt baby
4bb
Almost everything
But he described that so many people thought could not possibly exist
Has since been
Discovered
Only two or three
Still haven't been found
Over the course of four years Bebe & Barton made dozens of Dives and catalogs several new species of
They made it to 3028 ft deep
6 times deeper than anyone has ever been
On one of his final Dives in the bathysphere William Beebe saw something he'd never seen before
He saw this enormous
Sea snake
On the bottom of the ocean
It was long and black
The longest teacher he
Ever seen
Hand tractor
For a while before he realized it was the Atlantic Cable
It was one of the transatlantic Telegraph wires that I got in the whole world interested
And understanding the bottom of the ocean
By 1934 the bathysphere project had lost funding and BB was onto other Adventures
He really felt that he done
Everything he could do with the Baptist
The main problem peeing
It wasn't self-propelled
That you just
Hung there wherever
You know
You happen to drop
And you couldn't for instance move it to follow an interesting fish
Or turn it around at will
Eventually people would figure out how to make a submersible that could move on its own
Goodies Subs The Trieste in 1966 in the deepsea Challenger in 2012 actually made it all the way to the
The bottom of the Mariana Trench
The bathysphere is now on display in the New York Aquarium
Coney Island
You can peer inside of it and Marvel at the idea that two men want sets
Squeezed together on its concave steel floor
Fanning themselves with
Palm fronds
In all the shifting shades of blue
The creatures Beneath the Sea
And their place
All of it
I shall never experience
The feeling of complete isolation from the surface
The planet Earth
Is when it first dangled in a Halo
Tiana Swank
Quarter of a mile
Rolling Meadows
The bathysphere is just one chapter and William BB's lie
Carol Gould wrote a book about the rest of it it's called The remarkable life of William Beebe
Special thanks to Ron Allen who designed the deepsea Challenger and Captain Don Walsh who descended into the Mariana Trench
On The Trieste they both spent time talking to us about the story
Thank you to the 99 Pi players Dennis funk
Delaney Hall
I need to mail
99% invisible was produced this week by Katie mingle the same Greenspan Avery trufelman and Mero
Mars special thanks to Pat mesiti Miller for doing the sound design this week
If you want to hear his work on a weekend week-out basis I suggest you subscribe to the Fantastic radio program
Snap judgement
The newest member of 99% invisible is Kurt Kolstad he's our digital director so please say hi to him
But we are still looking for a reporter or producer to join us in Oakland so get your applications in
We are brother to 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sand
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
One of our favorite bands for scoring our stories is called lullatone I'm talking over there music right
They have something like 20 albums or a piece on bandcamp you should
Get at least one of them and I recommend all of them
Go to lullatone. Bandcamp.com
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify and you can listen to every single
Episode of 99% invisible
I-99 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com