99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance with Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their History season 2 Launches on May 15th between an episode
Really take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stock of love
Butters episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted of
Family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Have a couple announcements before we get started
We're currently
Reconfiguring all the different moving parts of the show so that we can start producing weekly episodes
Starting on February 4th 2014
Involves
Moving the office to downtown Oakland
Getting our new producer Katie mingle out here to the West Coast
An attending
All the various Kickstarter fulfillment details of which there are many
Thanks again for that Kickstarter that was pretty awesome
But even though we are up to our eyeballs in back office stuff I still want to play some grade radio for you in this week we have a story
My friend Nate dimeo of the Memory Palace
The subject is right in our wheelhouse
I thought you'd like it
Elevators are old
It would have to be
Because it is in our nature right
To rise
So history even ancient history is thick with things that lift other things
Ropes and platforms and weights and pulleys
With people to pull them
When the slaves of Rome were served up to the wild beasts at the Coliseum
Other slaves pushed the wheels that pulled the ropes that lifted the platforms
It sent them up from the darkness below ground
Up into the sun and the Roar of the crowd
End of the line
In China and Hungary and mohsen Michelle
Where can I find monks in Kings in Porta Sans and construction materials and meals fit Four Queens and sorted cons
Rising up
Well some slave or servant or caged animal somewhere
Pull down some rope or push some piece of wood around and around and around
One man in France spent the year 1743 inside a chimney
Waiting for a bell to ring
So he could pull a rope through a pulley
Invoice King Louie the 15th up in a flying chair
Turn the ground to his bedroom balcony
Rather than have him walk up a single flight of stairs
Elisha Otis was too sick for the family business
He was a good-looking kid and smart as a whip
But he was kind of weak link
Did when he was 19 he moved away from the Family Farm in Vermont to figure out something to do for a living
Something where he wouldn't have to exert himself
Sell anything bought or processed
Process anything sold
Bought or processed
Lift heavy things
In a Furniture Factory
Where he and his co-workers spent their days sanding crews in decorative knobs in the bedpost
And Otis spent his nights designing a better way to do it
He invented a machine that kind of lady that sped up the process
Increase app but it made the men's jobs a little easier
And it opened up the aesthetic possibilities of the bedpost in new thrilling ways
Knobs upon knobs on knobs Pine knobs
In his boss was so impressed that he took him off the floor
And made him head engineer of the Maze and burns bad Factory of Yonkers New York
Sotus got to work trying to solve one of the biggest problems in the place
The factory had a list
Madden elevator
A lot of factories were starting to have them that these were simple machines
Just picture a platform that could be pulled off the ground up to a second-story on a chain
Or set of cables or ropes
Sometimes the rosary pulled by steam power winch
But the one in the Maze and burns bed Factory Yonkers New York was pulled by a draft horse
The Monday that horse is pulling on the rope which is pulling the wooden platform loaded with Lumber and tools after the second floor
In the Rope snapped the platform plummeted dropping 15 feet
Slamming down onto the floor
And onto one of the men below
Sending its cargo careening smashing into the scattering worker
Just a few years later
In 1843
Elijah Otis stood on a wooden platform
30 feet off the ground
The elevator was loaded with Lumber and tools and barrels
Just like the one it been that day in Yonkers
In Down Below on the floor
Did hundreds of gentlemen and ladies
Who didn't want to spend the night out on the town being crushed by construction equipment
They had come to the Crystal Palace exhibition to see the gathered wonders of the world
A massive structure of Steel and glass had risen in Manhattan
Where Brian Park is today
It was America's first World's Fair
And New York website
In the gentlemen and ladies after walking through the sculpture Gardens in the art galleries
Found themselves in a great hall
Filled with industrial equipment
And while they stood on the floor of the main hall
Moonlight streaming through the glass roof
Craning their necks to see Otis and his elevator floating in air
They may not have known that they were looking at the future
Because they had seen elevators before
In scene one Adventure after another come up with some new way to get from one floor to another
So here was one more
Admittedly he was higher than 18 before
A three stories instead of two
But there's no way this thing was going to catch on
Because who in their right mind was going to ride a three-story elevator
Fall from the second floor break your leg
You break your neck
So they wants Donuts
And watched his son nearby
Raise a sword
And then bring it down like an executioner slicing the ropes that held up the platform
Naughty screen
And then they cheered
Elijah Otis didn't invent the elevator
He invented the break
The little metal piece that catches the car and stops it from plummeting if the cable that holds it up
Stop holding it up
Elisha Otis invent the elevator
But his son's kind of invented the modern world
The Otis Brothers convince the world to aim higher
The tallest building back in the 19th century the tallest buildings that weren't churches or lighthouses which were all show off
Aspires anyway
We just a few stories tall in part these buildings were held down by the lack of engineering know-how
But just as much as they were held down by stairs people could only climb so many
So the brothers Otis came up with a killer sales pitch
Higher was better
They targeted hotels 1st and convince them to turn the idea of luxury quite literally
Before the elevator the best rooms are on the bottom floor
You didn't have to walk
Stairs are for suckers
But the oldest Brothers convince hotels it should be the other way around
The first floor is in the one on the street
With the hoi polloi and their noise in their sweat
Inner fruit carts taking in the Sun
In worse the horses in the things horses do
What's in a King's throne supposed to be higher than his servants
Wasn't a lord supposed to Lord over
Why shouldn't the wealthy traveler be above it all
Hotels
Mayfield High
And Wealthy Travelers like The View
When it came time for them to build their next office building
They build hire Style
Nabozny Otis Elevator company
Building screw
Three stories to four
The sex
In the elevators group better and faster
To the Delight of passengers
Who love The Thrill Ride of hurtling 70 feet at speeds
600 ft per minute
Up to the penthouse on the 7th floor
But no the Otis safety elevator relieve them of the fear of falling to their Dooms it created a new concern
1G end up in the papers and in the esteem pages of the Scientific American
Which warned of the horrors of something called elevator sickness
Acute dizziness and nausea
Ode to the speeches fact that when an elevator comes to a stop
Not all of your organs stop at the same time
The best way to combat this it seems
What's the brace your head up against the ceiling of the elevator as it came to a stop so all of you
Stopped at the same time
The regional headquarters of the Otis Elevator company in my hometown is a one-story building
I just always thought that was kind of funny
Another World's Fair
In Chicago in 1870 the crowd gathered to watch a dramatic demonstration of the latest in elevator
Safety technology
Earlier that year a 7-story building in New York became the tallest in the world
And it had every architect in every illustrator in the Sunday circulars
Drawing up visions of the cities of the future
Gleaming Towers climbing soaring 11 and even 14 stories
I know people have grown to trust the Otis break at four and five stories
Would happen
If something happen
Anywhere after scraping the sky
So the fairgoers went out to a field
Where another inventor had constructed a temporary Elevator Shaft
This 109 ft tall
And they watched as passengers climb to the top
And step inside
Any watch that someone cut the rope to the elevator and it dropped plummeting for a few exhilarating
Seconds
Before it came to a slow stop
Cushioned by a pocket
Prestera
In the crowd politely applauded
The outcome never having really been endowed what were the Wonders American inventors were coming up with all the time
And really they had seen this trick of the World's Fair before
They may be more excited however
And they know that the same technique had been tested in secret in Boston
Not long before
And when the elevator car holding eight volunteers
Dropped on command
The air pressure in the shaft That was supposed to Christian its descent
Blew out the walls of the Elevator Shaft
Leaving nothing to stop the free-falling car but Massachusetts oil
Many bones were broken
Lions path
For eyes
All eight of them nearly died
Something the eight volunteers who climbed into the elevator in Chicago
And control
The Burj Khalifa Tower Rises 2722 feet above the desert in Dubai
It has history's tallest and fastest elevator
I notice
It travels
30 feet a second
Continue 124 floors in about a minute
Reviewers have called The Experience mildly exhilarating
Six stories first appeared on the Memory Palace podcast by Nate dimeo.
Another piece from The Memory Palace
I called it a bridge to the Skynet called it a stretch
So while we're here to talk about how great The Memory Palace is
I thought I play that one for you too
Bradford Gilbert Hispanic we're close to the ground
At 23 he took a job is the architect for the New York Lake Erie and Western Railroad
It was 1878
The Western was basically just Western New York and just left of Lake Erie
We're Gilbert walk bridges in Dallas
Mapped its Contours and calculated its slopes and Rises
Built Bridges and trestles anyways to go over the river and through the woods
New routes for coming around mountains
As an older man he would redesign Grand Central Station
But his early 20s I'm designing West Grand buildings
West Central locations
In Avon in hornellsville
Oyster Bay in Toms River in Essex Falls
The places you waited to get places where things actually happened
But buy a ticket there for Manhattan or St Louis and you could see other Architects building more impressive things
You can disembark and Marvel at 6 and 8 and 10 story structures
Mammoth buildings of stone and brick in wrought iron
Holding court on whole city blocks
Like medieval fortresses made for the kings of the modern American Insurance industry
The Emperors of imports and exports
One of these was looking to expand its Empire
John Noble Stearns had made a lot of money important still
He was looking to make a lot more in real estate
He bought some land in a prime location to 50 Broadway
It was the perfect place for new office building downtown near the ports
In the heart of the growing financial industry
But there was a problem
The lot was less than 22 ft wide
There are rules that dictate what you can build and how
Rules of physics and rules of men who sit on various bureaucratic boards and bodies
And those rules dictated that if Stearns wanted to build one of those 10-story office towers that were all the rage in 1888
He would need to build walls of stone and brick that were 5 feet thick
With anybody windows
Am I left room for an interior that was only 11 feet wide
Place off a few feet for a hallway a few for bathroom couple for a coat closet
Another for some filing cabinets in an umbrella stand
And he would be asking the quintessential modern Titan of American industry
To work in a dark cell
Better suited for a monk Illuminating a manuscript
Stearns asked all the best Architects for a solution
They had built medieval Bell Tower come Manhattan Bank headquarters
Dad made Midtown hotels that look like Mountain fortresses
But what's turns wide
Weather Flagstaff
What Stearns wanted was a blade of grass
And they weren't in the blade of grass building business
They told him it couldn't be done
Everyone except Bradford Gilbert
The in-house architect for the New York Lake Erie and Western Railroad
Had an idea
Even the simplest train trip between two of his Backwater stations often required stunning Feats of engineering
Hundreds of tons of cars in cargo hurdle over thin trestles and bridges everyday
What if he turned one of those bridges
What if he was one of the steel frame that so capably carry trains
And built it up
Instead of out
He told Stern that if he did this
The walls wouldn't have to be 5 feet 6
They could be 9 in
I'm in the 20-foot wide office spaces that that would create
The quintessential modern Titan of American industry would have room to stretch out of legs
While he made out his rent check to John Noble Stearns
They would call it the tower building
Stearns love the idea
For a while
Until people started telling him it was completely bananas
First he heard it from business associates
People looking out for his investment
Then it was the Press which called the project in the men behind it idiotic
Architects came in from all over the country to watch the tower building rise to pour over Gilbert's blueprints
And they all pretty much agreed
Gilbert and strength radiates
The walls were just too thin the foundation was too narrow
Sure it was quintessentially Modern Men could stretch out their legs
Boxers
But they could also be crushed to death when the first of wind came and blew the building down
Ask Gilbert to change the plans
Mira fused
He said he was so confident in his design
If you would move his offices to the top two floors of the building
The building
He would have the farthest to fall
In the longest time to consider his mistakes
Before he slammed into the pavement
The first if Winds of a hurricane blew into Manhattan on a Sunday morning in 1889
The tower building stood nearly complete
And people lined the streets to watch it tumble
By late morning the crowd numbered in the hundreds the Curious the morbid
The newspaperman who were professionally both
And as the wind roared
The man pushed through the crowd
He walked to the base of the tower to a construction ladder and began to climb
When Bradford Gilbert reach the top of this Tower
Doing whip through its skeleton frame it more than 80 miles an hour
It was too strong for him to stand in the burgers that crossed in the center of what he helped would Sunday be his Penthouse office
It was too strong to look down at the crab
Two were probably placing bets on whether he would die by being blown off the building
Or simply in the crushing force of its collapse
But he crawled out to the center of the building
Import from a bag rope with a red wave attached to one end
Beside the other end to a girder
Cintas the weight down for the empty cells below
When he got to the ground
He looked up
Saw the lead weight hanging in midair
Stockstill
Held up by a building that wasn't going anywhere
The next day the papers called Gilbert
An idiot
And it's time you probably deserved it
They admitted his idea was genius
And 4 years after
Gilbert gets hit in his Penthouse office in the tower building
And he can look out of his large window
Stretch out his legs
And watch a whole city
Stretching ever hire
As it took his idea
And built on it
The Memory Palace by Nate dimeo
99% invisible exam Greenspan Avery troubleman and me Roman Mars we are project 91.7 local pub
Book radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about
How are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
NPI feet
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God. Info
You find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars Sam tweets at Sam listens
Libra tweets at troubleman being fined every episode of his radio program and all kinds of other cool stuff at
At 99 Pi. Org
Radio tele
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really Jack
Play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 lb
And all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I
I had something to do with it now I need to clear my name somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com