99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Is a show about language and words
That's kind of like saying that this show is about architecture and design the description
Doesn't quite capture the way
We use those lenses to view the World At Large
My favorite
Words
Are eponyms
If you don't know what an eponym is you are about to find out
Because I love eponyms so much each year Helen produces an episode of The Illusionist
About evidence
Which feature me talking little bit
We put two of those episodes together for you to enjoy
One quick note
Helen is from the UK
For the often referred to ballpoint pens
As by Rose
You would have picked that up to contacts but I just wanted to eliminate that half-second of confusion that you might have if you're not from there
Alright without further Ado here is Helen zaltzman
The Illusionist
Molokai Raymond tweeted the following
I would totally listen to an ongoing Ray J series comprised solely of the stories behind eponyms
Firstly I thought
What's an eponym
F&M noun
A word or name derived from the name of a person
Or a pass enough to human Discovery invention Place Etc is named
Second day I wondered what it was about eponyms look up Romans so excited
An eponym does almost by definition
Has some gun store even if it isn't the origin story it has something
Where it
Got the F&M attached to it
Which is
A good enough story to be retold
And so for that reason I just I kind of love them and it's worth starts
A good conversation I think
That's what that's what I like
Silhouette because I think it's a little bit of a slur
If I have this right
The idea that like really elaborate
Painting portraiture was in
Was in fashion
Silhouette was the head of the
French Treasury
Was cutting back into Israel their version of austerity
And
And that's right at the time when
Outline drawings for becoming a fashion which are clearly not as elaborate didn't require
An artist inquire months of of time
And so
That type of a portrait was all a silhouette
Like a really like
Stripped-down simple
Didn't require
Real Steel
And
I love that cuz it
It's a bit of
A slight at the same time as being descriptive
Enzo I love those ones like
Like that but if you like silhouette Truman you probably going to love bowdlerization after the English editor Thomas Powell
Ua1919 released a version of Shakespeare's plays that Henry was
Make some more suitable for women and children
Hasn't he taken up Wilson naughty bits and foul language
The Lady Macbeth doesn't even say her famous line out out damn spot anymore but I don't Crimson sport
As if she's in the laundry detergent at Birth actually a huge success and brought Shake special much wider
But his name does now stand for cat handed expectation when it comes to word origins and eponym
Is the shortest that they are going to get a good story on
That's what I love
Taking me this long to realize what is the problem
I told you from the very beginning that she does being epidemic show
So you should start to do you want to do a regular one
Every 6 weeks
Olc
We'll see how this one goes
I'm going to start small with some eponymous items you probably old familiar with
You might be holding one right now.
On the Bayou
Attorneys fees for the first time in his attempt because I thought they were in the spirit of both Roman Chevy 99percentinvisible which
Under this one
Because this is a show about what and what is stationary without words
And words without station rate
Stationary
Basd
Physical infrastructure
Of what
Is James Ward
Author of Adventures in stationery a journey through your pencil case
So James knows a lot about ballpoint pens
Which we might casually refer to as by Rose obit
I guess what kind of interesting is
Stop
Jealous people
It just one thing
A people say a big fire
Controversial
I'm it's
Kind of
In the same way as you when you wouldn't say
I'm going to have a can of Pepsi Coke
I'm a space you might say I just bought a new Dyson Hoover
Yes this is what I guess it's when
When one brand name becomes too
Generic and the other one Remains the specific
How to take borrow
Generic
Alaska pipeline Road
He when he didn't invent the ballpoint
But he kind of
Text
Invention of the ballpoint going by patient filed in 1888 is credited to Johnjay loud
Had a great name for a product
But not a good pain
Which left room for Laszlo Biro to swoop in and claim both Point Victory
Food in Budapest in 1899 last light bar Arrowhead being very see a medical student a stage hypnotist
An insurance salesman a racecar driver
And eventually he became a journalist which was what she was working as in the early 1930s when he invented the pen
It would make his name
And indeed to take his name
One day he was in the front room
And the heat machinery
Kosice fountain pens leak
And so he wanted to develop
Little tentative wave
Creating pendant lights
Pressure
He saw the way that the
Allen screw
Compresses
Astrotheme
Onto the page
And
So he threw our funny could have like a miniature version of virus
But the problem AC cylinder Kearney Rowland
Forwards and backwards
Which one you writing it
Rolling Hills
And the story that is all my Sunday not true
Is frequently told
Is he was sitting in
In a caffe
Window
Trying to make sense of
How you make a cylinder rolling cooler
Directions
And it been raining outside
NSM kids
With marbles
Going to Sun Road Demopolis prep Hudl
And then he saw the
Salina full set at the marble made of
And then he suddenly realize how well
Apple roses
Edible Rose Hill directions
I hope will games
Based on that Prince
It took him
These children playing with marbles
Make the connection
And
But it's weird experience checking into a hotel
He signed in
Using his
I spy pen
And the guy next to him
I saw the pain
Icing
Tell me about your pain
The best pick-up line but that's passing penalties you turned out to be the former president of Argentina
Visiting Europe
To promote trade length
7 g equals labor I moved to Argentina to grow his pain Empire
Penn Power
Discuss two ways to be happy
Stipends
Annotate
Invest
And
Last night Pick 3 North
It's working
And
He's calling
Be unto the table hippie like some of the pens wet
And happy so I scraping on the bed paper
Static
Ben hektoen his a sample
Starbucks
Then he ignored
Unfortunately we don't have any price sex with
But
My next time
Become a rosebud
They had lots of problems they have to resolve
They have to find an ink
That was disgusting after it wouldn't leak out but then
No size 6
Coco Jam
They have to find a way that
You could keep in Minecraft
You poke it and it wouldn't
I hate
Make the Pain lyrics
Said Wednesday practice it then other people rifles
This is great Supply Road
Teams up with
With Henry Martin
Using voting IP
Evernote
Ninja stream
In the UK
And because he needs it
Bearings
Find bearings
Aviation industry
Makes the best ball bearings
And then released during the second World War
But they stopped manufacturing these
Depends night gave him to the RAF
Because
If your
Flying
Behind you need to write down at coordinates
Whatever
You want a pendants knucklehead Harley
Because of the air pressure
And these
Depends what
Hooray
But it wasn't all smooth rolling then schools
It was a lot of competition over my sleep
In the United States a Michael Milton Reynolds wanted to be the first to launch a bull point in that country
Yeah the Reynolds
International
Described as
Potomac age
Super pen
He didn't actually put in effort to make the soup of pain a super pain
He just wants to be the first to Market so everyone bought his pain
He was a kind of
Opportunist
She countries rushed out this this pain which
Cause lack of sensation
Time it went fast lunch
In New York
The richest
Crowds like thousands of people lining the streets is it
It was he was like that but
So it depends it was crappy
And it come with it came with a guarantee that if
Break within two years the net
Isotonic
Hatch replacement
Mm racing
In the US that created
The market flipacoin
Who said that
Nearly killed it off
Because people have this
Taobao experience
Back pain
But then another magical point that enter The Fray a manufacturer of fountain pens you kept getting inquiries for bull
Old Point pen parts
Mossel Bay
Spelled b i c h
But for his eponymous pain he dropped the age
So that you wouldn't think the big Crystal was pronounce big or b**** or any other ways and big
This is off the wall
Payment on
And
They licensed the technology from Biro
Everything is very complicated legal battle
Books where each party are suing the other one cuz I claim the infringement and
Smart Switch
Steve K company that virus
Golshifteh was suing bit
Nestle cookies
Haitians men
Subways
Average catches for mange
Comedy
Inevitability
Henry Martin who ran Wild Mountain
A company in his son
The daughter must help
Romeo and Juliet
It must have been tricky when they're treating which pants are in March
Yeah
Gru in Grand Prairie
Because
That that particular pen the big Crystal when they're born refers to as the big Pyro
With its
Nobody in it
Mediacom
Holding the end
Pain
Just blacks
Set meritocracy
Yeah it's actually something like
Think ha
Opal point
Pens sold in the world
Everyday armpit Chris
If you think how many of the
Millions of types
Poinsettia
United Supermarket
Iran
Fashion
Opus One
Hilton Hotel
Yeah the golden Hotel
The big Crystal just wax and
It's one in the collection of Museum
New York
Fitness studio lights on display but they put it in there
Connect collection somewhere
Pinkie Pie song
Yeah but it's a different experience
Let's take a little etymology break
Pen and pencil meisha a syllable but don't let that jeep you into thinking they have a common linguistic origin
Pain derives from the Latin Penna which meant feather
I think we'll plan is a tautology good tonight
Pencil meanwhile came from the Latin for a painter's brush penicillus
A diminutive appendicular switchman littletale
Intelligent Patel is also where we get to work penis
Anyway back to pens and how their development influence the development of rocking itself
The ability to make marks more precisely
Means that you are able to make more complex Ma
So
Fo you have is
Dipstick
Tablet
You can Arnie
She's quite
Script
Form is quite angular
But then if you stop using
Micah Reed Rush
Pirates
Office you more flexibility
And then if you start
Using
Pirates
Quite rough
Cheese pot
Snooze
Quillwork
Respectable
Ben
Arepas
Chase
Peaceful
My interest rates
Text
Eliminated
And so
With those
Development
The characters that you were able
Peace
Are we more easy
Distinguish that you're able
He's writing
My school with only lettuce use fountain
We would not allowed to write with both points
I'm missing shipping quote Tacoma not street with bullet points for a long time
Fountain pen companies thick lines thin lines flourishes and thoughts invest your handwriting with a lot of character
Fly for the pool in the pool point produces a line of uniform thickness
So a lot of people believe that the pens are detrimental to handwriting
Las Vegas
Daughter
She said
Her father would have to respond to these complaints
And he used to hit people say that the whole point was ruining writing skills
And he'd smile and say what writing comes from the heart
We can help
Hands before massage
It's nothing wrong with
I think it's interesting
Extreme excessive
Disposable
Yeah
San Jose
They
Disposable
In that you can owe a big
Is Noah pyro is
Peter Noone
I need to know who
Marcel
Is all here
Flashlight
Is
Say they could have made this disposable
Contributions a strain and in the same way they might themselves
So if you're eponymous product a successful your involvement in it and even your own identity is subsumed
Which one don't fit that well with the kind of people who put the names on things
Because calling something off yourself seems like quite an egomaniacal choice to me
I mean I may be wrong but my impression is a lot of eponyms are not
The person named in the map
Songs
It's more than a sign
By another person
Mark of respect
Yeah
Do you think boots
I believe
Disease a horrible medical condition named after
Quite a sad way to be remembered isn't it I don't know
You probably gotten past
The feeling of gross mess around disease and you probably just enjoy the fact that
You were instrumental in its Discovery or successful treatment
I have a feeling that I could I could even live with that horrible
Disease being in.
Yeah but I need help people who are you remembered you because you'll what killed their grandma
And you feel good about that
Just be remembered any of the most important thing
Couple serial killers banking on
Anel part two of The Illusionist eponyms Saga where we learn some bad news
About apus
There's a shift a gradual shift
Away from using up and down
Gyms in Madison
Who's this enemy of eponyms
My name is Isaac Siemens and I'm a resident physician in the department of family and Community medicine
I'm at the University of Toronto
There's two camps in medicine currently
People who
Want to use afternoons and people who want to move away from eponyms and there's
There's a few different reasons for that people that are more in touch with history perhaps and then people that are more
Moving towards kind of
Accuracy in language
In Broad Strokes that's the controversy
You can see the Practical case for this shift
Medical workers have to stay abreast of an awful lot of terminology
You try memorizing a load of surnames and which element each one represents
A list of
Diseases with
Somebody's last name as
The title gives you no information and
How to get bundled up where is
You can kind of fake your way through if you will if the name of the disease
It says something about the desert
To use an example that was all over the news when I was growing up
Cjd
Creutzfeldt-jakob disease
The name alone doesn't tell you much about what it is unless you were familiar with the early 20th century work of the Germany
Neurologist hands get hot
And alfons Maria
Do you have a name is also not easy to spell
At the far end of the scale tabloids called the condition
The human form of mad cow disease
Hey Brother cartoonish time for brutal and incurable illness
So the other option is the scientific term
Cjd is a form of transmissible spongiform encephalitis
Encephalitis from the medical Latin encephalon
From the ancient Greek and kephalos
Meaning brain
The itis
Suffix denotes inflammation
Spongiform encephalitis
To me that way
Be easier cuz that tells you something about
I mean although it's Latin
It gives you a bit of a
Information
So you could kind of peace
Is it together
If you had to
Spongy
Essentially it's all there
If anything
That's more literal than a lot of disease names would be
Think so perhaps when you're receiving a diagnosis this some psychological protection from the Grim reality of what's half
Play Nobody
Somewhat disguised by science be called the opaqueness of an eponym
On the other hand an overly academic or incomprehensible description of the condition can amplify a patient
Stress and fear
Thing that hopefully is changing in medicine that maybe tizen
OSU is
The sort of
Black boxing of knowledge and
Disorder protective
Nature
Different professions and I think it's similar to law or
Engineering maybe we're
You know in order to protect our jobs and
Seem like we have some sort of power over
The people we work with we kind of make
Things possibly
More difficult to understand than they need to be and we use a jargon and a lang
That needs to
To be taught
To be understood so
I don't know if there's some sort of like
Unconscious
Protectionism
Ivar
Practice
Involved with naming
Cuz even the non F&M
Names are very like complicated
Don't mean a lot
It's it's quite a common thing in language like the Bible using quite lovely sounding language so that
You maintain. Division of status
I just wonder whether that's a decent middle ground in medicine between
Wibbly wobbly heart disease a long complicated name
You don't want it so simple that you sound kind of
Stupider like you don't know what's going on
I guess but
It's also
In medicine as in everything communication
So important
And so
You want to strike that middle ground where you're making
To that person
So in some circumstances it's better to use the acronym because it might be more familiar
We learn about trisomy 21 which is a genetic disorder that
We're encouraged to speak about
Referring
The actual genetic issue
Where is
Down syndrome is the common
Eponym
I think the lay public as well are more familiar with
That language
Some concepts of really hard to describe without the eponym
And with an eponym
Much more memorable with a heimlich maneuver
Be something that people knew it wasn't attached to a name
Like Lime Lush
You know no I don't think so would it have made the news in May of this yet when 96 year olds
Henry heimlich himself
Save the woman from choking on a piece of hamburger meat
Are using the maneuver the best his name
Tell an interesting story
I totally get why then I'm not so tied to
My
Worldview or Nostalgia that I cannot accept
That it would be better another way
Well good because there was Stephanie some aspects to eponyms that I didn't think you'd like Raymond argument against
Eponyms is that it's sort of a simplification of complex
Stories where
Generally a white dead male will get
The
F&M
But if you look at
The process of discovering and categorizing
Diseases it's often
Over the course of more than a lifetime and it involves many many
Keep off
And it's sort of a false history to just
Use this
Its name
And then there are like
Ridiculous extremes where there's like
For it for 5 people
That all have
Similar form of the disease named after them and then later on they discovered that it was the same disease the whole time and then it gets off
All messed up like
I have one of them written down cuz I can never remember it but I think it's the longest it's the longest eponym that I've come across
And it's
At 4
Barros
Name if you will and it's
Mayer-rokitansky-kuster-hauser
Mayer rokitansky kuster Hauser syndrome is congenital abnormalities in or absence of the uterus.
Vagina it sounds like four people
All had some sort of a claim to the discovery of the disease in reality that were far more than four
People have been writing about the condition all the way back as far as the Greek physician Hippocrates
In the 5th Century BC
Rokitansky kuster and towels are all made significant contributions to the understanding of the disease
But they weren't even working together
Mad describe the syndrome in a paper in 1829
About 50 years before Custer was born
92 years before the birth of Hauser who went on to name the disease Mario cutkosky Costa syndrome
Someone else I did how's it to the end you don't hear that disease name a lot but I feel like every time I hear it the order is a little
Little different so I don't even know if there's
Like a standardized name order to it maybe they Shuffle it
5 everyone gets
Turn on the front
They take turns
The problem with quite a lot of acronyms is the person named therein
Reiter's syndrome
Is a
Condition where you get joint pain related to
And I kind of see
Systemic inflammation
And it's named after
Hans writer who was
A famous Nazi
War criminal
Gruden terrible experience
Buchenwald
Hans reuter discovered the eponymous syndrome in 1916 when he treated his soldiers during the first World War
Prior to his Nazi affiliation
The witch the American rheumatologist dr. Efraim Engelman was unaware when he coined the acronym in 1942
But he like to join The Campaign which began in 1977
To replace the Apple
With the name Anna somebody associated with war crimes and mass murder
If you don't want to avoid sounds right you can call this condition reactive arthritis
But while usage of the eponymous time has decreased
It is still being used in medical schools and in journals
The debate rages on do you pick and choose which parts of history of mock
Do you allow a person scientific achievements to be honored despite whatever horrible things they did
Controversial things eponyms
There's even more controversy about
F&M is where there's like a sub conflict if you will going on about whether to use the possessive or not in
I'm so
There's an even within people that use eponyms are down the people that use eponyms
Having debates about whether it should be Downs apostrophe s for possessive or down syndrome Enders research
Search about like
Which should be used
In medical journals
I'm to simplify searches so that you don't have to search
Turn
I think that's the one thing I would simplify I would get rid of
Apostrophe
Wow that seems like the right solution
Caesar salad Caesar salad
Seasoned ice
But yeah they possibly it messes up a little too much
And you shouldn't have nothing
You about it is already know something about about that horrible disease you got
And the great Rich story behind the name
It was enough
Samantha juggle in the waiting room isn't it
Nfnm
Just does have
So much
Story embedded in Fayetteville last night
I was eating dinner with my kids
And the wife
And
We were talking about childbirth
And mentioned
The cesarean section
The way
But these two babies
Pain in my butt when boys came into this world
And
It caused us to talk about
Caesar and
Was Caesar really the first person to have
Give me the results of a cesarean section in which case I have no actual knowledge
Probably not it's hard to imagine that the first person to be born through this procedure also became one of the most famous people
What all history of the most famous salad
Cfnm circus-like
They're endlessly fascinating so but it causes great conversation
At a dinner table with two 9 year olds and
And my wife and we had fun no talking about it and even the parts of it that are the
You're the caveats in
Dinnerly
The etymology with the tidiest story is the least true
You know it seems like that's the nature of it unfortunately there Shaggy are and messier than they
And in general the true ones are Shaggy or Messi
Give some gory dinner table conversation
Good grief
Believe Mrs produced by Helen zaltzman with music by Martin austwick
Find it at the illusionists. Org
Illusionist with an a not an eye
It was the first Show created specifically for radiotopia and I could not love it
Subscribe now
And then we can all talk about it on Twitter.
99percentinvisible is Delaney Hall
Sharif Youssef
Avery Chapman Emmett Fitzgerald Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Katie mingle is our senior editor Kolstad is our digital director and Taryn Mazza
Is the baroness
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sent Aaron Meza
Is the baroness
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Message Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Black podcast
Gun show in discussions about the show on
Facebook you can't order me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Pi org
Run Instagram and Tumblr to
Do you want to read about seed bullets for Guerrilla gardening or a rave review of The Atlas obscura book you have to go to
99 pi
Dot org radio temperature
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com