99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I fell in love with architecture
On the Chicago River
You can endlessly argue about which
City has the greatest architecture
One thing that puts Chicago near the top for me
Is that the Chicago River provides a beautiful vantage point
To take in all the Marvel is skyscraper
Rather than being crammed in on the sidewalk between looming Towers trying and probably failing to take it all in
The river
Pushes the buildings apart
And gives you the opportunity to post by on the roof of a fairy
Glass
Steel and concrete wonders
Presented in their full Glory
Everywhere you turn
The probably the city's biggest design a team and isn't a building at all
It's that River itself
Waterway disguised as a remnant of a natural landscape
But it really isn't
It's hard to tell when you see the river but it's going the wrong way
It should flow into Lake Michigan
Pennsaid
Fresh water from Lake Michigan flows backward
Into the city
The Chicago River is the large part A carefully-designed extension of the city sewer system
Even calling it a river may be off base
It's not really a river in Chicago it's really the Chicago canal
There's not an inch I don't think of the Chicago River that is natural inches
Death Richard cahan
He's a journalist and historian in Chicago
And in 2012 he co-wrote and published a book called The Lost panorama
When Chicago changed its River in the land Beyond
It's still with these gorgeous pictures from before and mostly after
One of the biggest Urban Design project
Ever
The reversal
And a complete transformation
Are the Chicago River
And that is Dan Weisman
The journalist
Moreau triangular buildings
A lifelong
Die Hard
Chicago
Reversing the river was actually the third in the series of Epic design project
Almost 50 years
Three projects that I melted to 19th century Engineers just
Taking it to the laws of nature with a kind of moxie but just seems to be folded into the DNA of 19th century
Engineers
And which is the first two
We're talking about two decades of massive ridiculous
Change people's ideas of how far you could go to make a city work
And those two have been so obscured by time
It was basically one guy who proposed and executed not one but two of these
Project
Unknown today
Ellis chesbrough
If you've never heard of Ellis chesbrough
You're not allowed to talk to his I record this he doesn't even have a Wikipedia entry
But you can bet
Richard Kane knows who he is
So he was a star and there is to his house is just North of downtown and there's a little plaque in for the house I was parked my car in front of it
And it says House of Alice chesbro and I'm sure I'm the only person that ever was very excited about seeing it
Stop back in the 1800s
Chesbro with the man
And no one has ever worked harder
To save Chicago from its own poop
Poop butt thing that has brought cities to their knees
For millennia
Now here's the setup
It 1854
City of Chicago has been growing like crazy for a couple of decades
Cute bun with a W population every few years
Call Rapids
Wiped out
6% of the city 6%
That summer
One account headcollar killing six
60 people a day in a town of 70000
One of the Republic this way
The death cart was constantly in the street
And not to be gross
The caller
It is a super nasty way to go
Sudden
Painful in love
Ropes
Vomiting diarrhea horrible cramps in your dead in less than a day
It is a really
Really unpleasant
The people were freaking out
Interchez bro
Amanda name with work he done in Boston
Will you people meet Old Chicago is a sewer
Which was actually a newish idea.
The time in the US
Northern City here at 1
Seward's yes
Systems not so much in Chicago didn't seem like the town you picked to go first
Not if you thought typography meant any
Chicago built on a swamp
Street-level
Water level
What's the same thing
You put Seward under the street there's no way for the material in them do you know run down peeling dead
Chicago was ready to try anything
Chesbro said okay
What's Jack street level up Tempe
It was a time when engineers' were really seen as the savior
It's so when he said first thought they were going to build a sewer system
And he said we're going to raise Chicago out 10 ft so that we can
Wooden sword
Everyone should let's do it
And there was a reason they went for it
People making tons of money
Chicago's location with perfect
Connecting the west to east through railroads in the Great Lakes and that's what the city was growing so fast that start with
Actually didn't jack up the street from cells they just pile dirt on top of the old streets to make them higher
And some of that dirt came from the river bottom which of the
Dredge to make room for
All of the stuff that they were about to dump in there
They did Jack up the building
Literally has a lot of Jack Spurs and start cranking
Bisquick picture for 1857 it shows a massive Hotel big is a city block
Dozens and dozens of guys crank
Perfect sink
You can also see Hotel guests in Top Hat standing on the balconies a couple flights up
They're looking out watching their view get better and better
Corduroy hats at a time
And this kind of thing happen over and staying open while they're getting cranked up Just for kicks
Another fancy hotel
1200 guys
Cranking away all at once
Foundation at top speed literally working around the guys with the jacks
Did another great picture of a huge downtown block of stores in Austin
All 35000 tons
Jacking up the street and Building Supply
20 years to finish
But by that time project number 2 with already done
Because it didn't take too long after the sewers went in for Chicago to realize that there was a big question that they hadn't given enough
Start 2 on the first go-round
We're did the sewers take all this out
Into the river
And where the river
And it'll wake and where was the drinking water coming
It's okay such as bro how about this
Who build water intake
2 miles out from Shore
Way past where the river
Don't turn Mac into the lake
And I don't mean digging the biggest deepest longest tunnel Everett
What do you think
They all said fine and they did it and it was amazing the city is growing people making money
And everybody agrees they'll do whatever it takes
Keep this thing rolling
So it's on round 2
Digging the tunnel
In 1864
Checkers guide
Start digging the tunnel out from the city
60 feet down from street level
After that
Install a giant structure
2 miles out in the lake they call them
Crabs and start digging a tunnel in from under that
Back towards Shore
The work went on around the clock from both sides
One true dug by hand for 16 hours a day
Tentacruel bricklayers
The graveyard shift showing up the area that had just been dug out
In November 1860
5 the two sets
Ted Cruz net in the middle
Center this is before GPS
You know this is just Ball by side
Everybody agreed with a
Genius and a half
Except they hadn't really solve the problem
And they were dumping more
Of their business into the river than ever
Which
Stank
And before the water for the new intakes even started flowing
The union Stockyards open on the River South Branch
Up the ante
320 Acres of slaughterhouses and meat packing plants
All of them
Dumping whatever they couldn't use and
Just imagine what that would be
Into the river
For the estimated the Stockyards were
The equivalent of a
A million people in the city
Yeah that's true
That bit of the South Fork still goes by the name and got then
Bubbly Creek
All the discarded animal stop wood rot at the bottom of the river
And eventually about methane which would double up to the surface and burst
Also
Sometimes a confiar
And sometimes the sewage
Got swept more than 2 miles out and found the water intakes
Later they dig these even further out there's one called The Four Mile Creek
And meanwhile the city kept growing by 1880 we're talking half a million people
End producing more X
The Stockyards group 2
A lot
When engineer would say
Chicago produces more filth per capita than any other City
And now typhoid was going to be a problem
Turn Chicago started pushing for a new state law to help undertake the biggest
Baddest
Craziest idea ever
They decided to dig a gigantic new Canal that would reverse the river entirely
Reversing the river would bring in fresh water from the leg
And keep Chicago's mug from polluting the drinking water pulled from that same leg
And
Flush all the sewage down to the Illinois River
Which would then take it out to the Mississippi
It took a few years to get the new law prude the town of Joliet so a river of crap coming its way and try to mix it
And then it took a few more years
To get plans laid out in contract issue
Red shovel day
September 3rd 1892
More than a thousand people came out to watch
An official took one cut with a nickel-plated shovel
And then an engineer detonated to massive loads of dynamite
Dynamite was there
Preferred weapon
Environment
And it was on round 3 in the Epic struggle against Chicago zonex Grita
Reversing the river
28 miles of canal
Price tag
31 million and change in today's money
Almost 20
3 billion dollars
8700 guys working at a time with work going on year round
And tons of dynamite
You can hear the blast downtown when the wind was
An enormous machine some invented special for the project including a 640 wide
Master conveyor
Broke after less than a year
During the 1893 World's Fair tourist
By the thousands
Day trip out to the construction zone
They would
Take boats and trains out to the site to see the work
If people are coming to Chicago and they were like
You got to see this
Yeah this town is
And they'll do anything to survive
Even after the theater closed train companies ran morning special so local sightseers could check out the big machine
And those ever-popular Dynamite blast
This was an amazing
New project
You know so many people know about the Panama Canal but it was
Really
In building this canal
I figured out everything
Pennywise in the
And a lot of the engineers
In the game
St.Louis got gas
We're talking 1899 all major digging has been done for years
And the fine-tuning stuff is getting wrapped up all the construction of bridges and extra digging in the river Downstream
Akira Chicago
Water for the Mississippi and whatnot
Is very very close to finish
And this is when st-louis figures out that all that water
Carrying who knows what
Is headed
Down the Mississippi
Upriver of St Louis
Depends on the river for drinking water
And for Brewing Budweiser beer
The city authorizes attorney
Prepare a lawsuit asking the US Supreme Court
Stop the Sanitary District of Chicago
From opening up the dance
And letting that water go
Thing is
It takes awhile to get a lawsuit ready
A few months
And Chicago start humping it to get the Dam's ready to open for St Louis can get an injunction
New Year's Day
Sanitary District trustees
Decide the major work is done
The next day
January to
They head out to a spot on the city's Southwest side
Religious one little temporary Dam holding back the river
British massive
28 mile Canal that's waiting for that water
The trustees arrived at dawn
One of them bring shovel
Most of these projects have these beautiful gold shovel
But one of the trustees
Just stopped at a hardware store and bought the
Timmy old
Rihanna work show is like stopping at Home Depot
Hey it's 5 in the morning
I had an awful time getting the shovel this time of day says any laid them out
Couple reported are taking notes
At least they try to
First off you should note that was in January in Chicago so
You know you don't shovel anything
That would said that the ground was absolutely Frozen and they were going to actually know where
So they bring in a dress
Which also goes nowhere
So they go get some Dynamite
Which is a dud
There was a lot of profanity
Number one
Trustees control it out and then the dynamites not working and then the shovels I work
Working in the end you know this was like
An insult to the kind of masculinity that I can't we can even you know open this thing up
A couple hours later
Pain in the morning
And maybe a hundred people have gathered
And the dredge
Get to work
Just get good Scoop
And it grabs it
Yeah baby
Dammit water starts dropping into the canal 24ft
Straight down
And where it goes
It is the Niagara of Chicago one of the trustees says
Almost there but there's still one last and open up and down the river which needed the governor's okay
It's a gate that's already been made
It's just a matter of turning the
We all set
And once the gate was
Open the water could not be
Meanwhile St Louis is still during a lawsuit
They're always worried about Saint Louis actually file a lawsuit that would stop
That was enjoying them
From actually opening it
This day I can't figure out why
Why they were so slow about it
Chicago still had to jam a few last pieces into place to get the governor's okay took 2 weeks
St Louis could have filed any day
And then
January 17th
Trustees took one more early morning track to lower the dam
They turn the crank
Pose for a picture in their fancy coats and top hat
Then put it back to Chicago for a big ones
Bother eating and got where the st. Louis had indeed file for an injunction that day
Too late
They brought a knife
To a gunfight they brought a little piece of paper into a torrent of fight
Late I might add
They waited till just after the flood gates were open
I can understand that
Legal philosophy
The story made the New York Times with the headline
The water in the Chicago River now resembles liquid
St.Louis push their case to the US Supreme
Chief justice Oliver Wendell Holmes noted that it is a question of the first magnitude
Weather the destiny of the Great Rivers is to be the sewers
Of the cities along their back
Which is an important philosophical question but
To paraphrase the waitresses on Spanish that opinion
Whatever man
Settling a question that big it wasn't really the courts job especially
Since Missouri allowed St Louis and other towns to dump sewage into the Mississippi and send it
Straight to Memphis
So in a very real sense there was no stopping it
The canal and River reversal was later called a civil engineering Monument of the millennium
It was a functional Monument to our dominion over the natural world
Or so we thought
Fast forward a hundred years right about now
And the forces of nature are looking for another go-round
There have been some big efforts to clean up the river itself in the last two decades
And by 2015 the treated sewage is actually supposed to get disinfectant
When Rich cahan liability bubbly Creek looking for bubbles
We may have seen Signs of Life there instead
I see bubbles
I think that's a fish
Is it
Write down there
It's some kind of living thing right there
Yes
Yeah
But now we're living in a time of the big 19th century interventions in nature
Seemed poised to Boomerang back at us
Water levels in Lake Michigan have fallen
Please for now to the point where gravity may stop
Pulling Lake water into the river
Potentially reversing
The river
If there were no
Engineering interventions
Chicago
There are other ways to keep the water and treated sewage flowing away towards the Mississippi
But Falling lake levels
This is most of the freshwater in North America
And a lot of people
Link discount falling lake levels
The climate change in the hole
Catalog of horror that comes with it
Payback
Exactly the kind of project that reversing the Chicago River stood for
We can just do whatever we want to plan and get away with it
And I think that's a completely valid lesson you could take from this
Hubris involved in reversing a river
Or manipulating the environment to suit our needs is exactly what is wrong with us as stewards of this planet
But taking another view
You could also see this as a lesson in the lengths we will go
To survive
If we harness that nineteenth-century moxie
Kind of moxie that makes you think
That you could and should
Reverse a river
And we added that the knowledge we gained since then
We could guide our best and brightest
To engineer The Impossible
No matter what it takes
And we would take day trips
Out to the far Edge
Cheer them on
As they save us
I'm getting buried
In our own
Or we can produce light
Maybe okay to
99% invisible was produces week by Dan Weitzman Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You find the show and like the snow on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars right now
Oh man
Pictures of the Chicago River being reversed
99% invisible
. org
Radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com