99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Ideas
PS4 magazine
Cover
Our God
You know the same
You can't judge a book
By its cover
Woodmagazine it's pretty much the opposite
He works here
You can and you should judge a magazine by its cover
Everyone is
They want you to
The cover of the magazine
Is the unified identity for a whole host of ideas and authors and designers who created The Eclectic array of
Stories and articles and materials within each issue
And some would argue this identity extends to the reader as well
Magazine covers
Third person
In the moment you'll seen with that
Either by yourself
Oh by your peers
And you are a bo3.
And this is different than being a Twilight reader or a DaVinci Code Reader
Moment In Time
Where's the magazine
Is a constant source of ever-changing
Content and that's why the design challenging
Magazine covers are a composition of text and visuals that are designed to express a specific identity
Hugo the phone girl
You got color
Secrets of magazine design
Reveals All This is Andy
Which is a block in Creative at Marie Claire
And a whole bunch of other magazines both in the United States and England
So we are two about covers starting from the top
Literally
Because that's where the name of the magazine always is
When you see a magazine
Best Central
If that doesn't happen everything else
And then you got to show them that this is the new issue the one they don't have yet
300 the last one
Is green
This one is blue
The photograph
Is the thing that creates really pound
Emotional
Connection
Weather radar
You see somebody you see the eye contact
Celebrity
On my level
But the photograph wasn't always part of the equation
The early magazine covers were recently illustrator
And so you looking at
Rockwell unisaw
Amazing Oliver
On the cover of Vogue
Andy had a few examples on hand
Like this one
Action
Which has
Redhatter
Women in short dresses
POTUS
To some sort of Indian totem pole
Illustrator
Like old movie posters
Pizza Hut Delivery
Paintings of the 60s
Men of the 60s were very imaginative
MB on the men's magazines a lot of major Publications actually had cartoon mascots on the cover
Some of them persist today
Like the Playboy Bunny Mad Magazine Alfred E Neuman
And the mascot of the New Yorker the monocle Eustace Tilley
Even UK Vogue an illustrated mask
Miss Exeter An Elegant 50-something woman who had an advice column about being a
Classy classy Dame
An Esquire
Had asked
A mustachioed skirt Chaser in a fedora
A lot of Esquire covers featured in
Until George Louis
George Lewis was the Pioneer in the industry
Who's the guy who made magazine covers sexy
He revolutionized the cover of Esquire
Using big
Pulled eye catching photographs
Probably seen some of these covers
Spratly store module
He didn't want to Richard Nixon getting makeup put on him one of Ed Sullivan wearing up Beatles wig
Is one of a beautiful woman shaving her face
In a man putting on lips
For the 60s
These were
Shocking
No more cartoon covers the crazy thing was that Louis didn't even work for us
My name is George Lois and I never had a role at Esquire he wasn't adman
He was behind a lot of the most famous ads of all time iconic 60s posters for American Airlines Xerox
And even political campaigns for candidates like Robert Kennedy and Ed Koch
Many people who dream about the covers
Call me do you want to make the best way I would never
I just did that covers
Harold Hayes head editor of Esquire magazine
Ask Lois to do a cover for it
And a Louis tell the story hey is needed to cover from him in 3 days
Description of the 20 things in the Magazine spread
Have a photograph
Floyd Patterson the photograph of the Sonny Liston Floyd Patterson vs Sonny Liston
This is the upcoming heavyweight fight
The issue was going to come out
For the fight
And everyone was predicting that Patterson
Woodwind
And Lewis
Did a really got a thing
Laying flat
Dead in the ring
Knock down
So there's a good chance that a square would be wrong
And this could make the magazine look really bad
So bad
Can you imagine a major publication that predicted the wrong outcome of a huge heavyweight fight
Oh my God so embarrassing
But Harold hey is the editor of Esquire
Went along with it
And Louis
Actually
Call Dad
And everybody in America went crazy over their shoulder
Newsstand
I think 800000 how to get it wrong
Create a catalog of 92 Esquire covers
Most of them just as eye-catching and controversial
Dispersed
Because
He was able to
Potential
Cui should in this age
Magazine covers
Apple presentation
No idea would just happen to be in the magazine
One big start image with little or no tax
They look almost like wall poster
And now many of them are in the permanent collection in the Museum of Modern Art in New York
Is radical an amazing world
Vietnam War
I'm probably finishes
He's is Muhammad Ali, is one of the greatest
Magazine capozzola Bowl time
Best
Cover
Ever
If you've seen any of Lois's covers or variation
Discover it probably this one
The cover is almost completely white with Muhammad Ali shirtless
Dearest all over his body with arrows
What's like a martyr
For refusing military service
Is a conscientious objector
Because of his new religion
He was sentenced to jail
Uneven strips
He was condemned
Is a draft Dodger
I need a new trait
Sunday idea
I'm just,
Was to suggest that he was in Malta
To his religion
Dementia
Is that the boss that I choose to muddle apocrypha
Is it Christian Moss
Specifically Saint Sebastian as portrayed in oil paintings by Andrea Del Castillo
Is also the patron saint of sports
Andy recounts the story as George Louis described it in his book
Muhammad Ali had to get on the phone
Woody's religious leader Elijah Muhammad
Muhammad Ali how to explain the painting
Excruciating detail
Because Muhammad Ali was concerned about
Abusing a Christian Souls
Is a non-practicing Greek Orthodox on the phone
After a lengthy theological discussion
Elijah Muhammad
Gay George Lois
His okay
Georgia cell
Schultz this portrait
Deicide man against the authority
That's a hell of a lot of symbolism
Change your cover
Change your life
And then
Game Cosmo
In 1965 Cosmopolitan ushered in the era of the coverline
Coverline
The words 26 sex positions we must try this weekend
Cosmopolitan wasn't the first to use text on the cover
Really provocative
Physicians Yuma
And they set the standard template for what a newsstand magazine looks like today
What is the traditional donut donut is not standard industry lingo or anyting
Is not a widely used term but
Is the Gulf in the middle
Looks like brains right on the other side the most had across the
Covers focus on words
After the 1960s
That's what
Stop making very explicit promises
Torito's
And
You type the reader's trust in your brand that you
Liberal
Promises
Like
Ansible save your marriage
847 style ideas 621 ways to get the most out of your
Easy ways to beat stress
Pokemon with the cover lines
Located very
Strategically
Tight
How to maximize the value
Cheap pieces
Real estate
The real estate vary depending on the kind of magazine
Celebrity weeklies always have their big cover lens
Splashed across the middle
And it's yellow
It's always just
It's yellow
And value
People
Lawson Style
InTouch
Lock installers
It's not just White
Is that trying to
Present himself
Fashion orientation
Celebrity news
And for the more lifestyle oriented
The location of the most captivating cover lines is the so-called hotspot
Immediately underneath the logout on the left hand side
Depends on which country you're in
How much of this has to do with the way in which magazines Iraq
Action stands jeans are very much designed around their rack
Hello magazine
I need the last OG review
Some England you get most of your headlines on the left side or the leading left Edge
British Invasion
Bros in the USA
Then there you have a wonderful presentation where you and you see the talk
Philly cigar best cover lines is high and close to the logo as we can on either side as Publications have
Many more cover lines from those in the UK
So magazines that don't rely on Newsstand sales look very different from magazines that do
And take Bloomberg time the New Yorker these mostly function on subscriber
User inside of magazines that use the hotspot
The same extent because they're not dependent on these stand soil
They are a little more Louis asked
Big photographs and pictures with not as much tax
New Yorker covers harken back to a pre-1960s illustration
Except when you encounter the New Yorker on the Newsstand
In which case was a little flat
On the leading left Edge
With a list of contents
Our guide to what
Take pictures by themselves just don't sell like they used
It's about volume of content
Magazines
Expensive
Understand this
Is a real job
Been reassuring readers that is plenty to read inside
Hence the illegible Cornucopia of cover lines on Esquire today
Yeah
Squad 2013
Very foxy picture of makeup
Bailey Reed
It just saying
Relax guys there's loads of stuff in
That design is the work of David Kerr career
Learn how this
Publication
My name is David currito and on the design director for Esquire magazine the guy behind today
Which look nothing like Lois
I'm responsible for the look of the magazine from cover to cover my job is to pick
Photographers
Take all the images
Typography
Pick the size of the Type R
The color of the tie
Typography
The key word here is
My choice in typography
Definitely
Sets the tone
Corrido style is loaded with words
Overloaded
Loads the donut
Chris Kyle Texas all over the cover
In front of the celebrity behind the celebrity
Handwritten
Scroll down the side
Much of it
Completely illegible a lot of texture in the sense that there's an overwhelming
Illustrate
We have a ton of material inside the magazine
So much material that we can't possibly
Show it all to you
Undercover even though we'll try
The text in the image weave in and out of each other in such a way
That the words almost
Become the image
What we've been doing is kind of overwhelming your senses
With both
The photography and
The typography
Combined together
It's been a radical kind of
Thing on the news
And this is Esquires way of standing out
From all the other magazines on the rack
But they don't stand out in the same way Louis is covers dead in the 60
We're a little more formulaic but
Yeah we don't have the ability to
Do exactly what he did back in
In the day if that's me
It's hard to replicate design from the 60s because the audience is not from the sea
I think people are less shot today it's been in the past
I think it's
I think we've become so desensitized
22 imagery
But you can still be done
I don't know what's shocking now
Kim Kardashian and Kanye West
So Kim Kardashian and Kanye West it is
Celebrities sell
Lionel celebrity 9 out of 10 times and we've been with that model for a really long time
Louis is not so certain that this is the way to get attention
Like showing a famous person
And that kind of work if you're only lonely magazine in the world
50 magazine
Try to choose to study your claim of the month each month
George Lois
Is not amused
What these buffoons have done before event sense
What everybody's done is let me look at you don't have to do anything about it
Magazine Newsstand
Can you take a glance at them
Network sucks
Infant George Lopez
The solution
Is George Lopez
I mean according to David there's a reason they don't
There are certain rules
Tip to putting magazine cover together
You know you want your logo at the top
A picture of a celebrity looking directly into the camera
You want to put your most important cover line
Your words on the upper left-hand side
And the upper right-hand side
And to be quite honest
You know
When everybody follows the same set of rules
Everybody looks the same
Cocorito is messed with the standard layout but he mostly stick to the formula formula
Word has been working for a long time
What time is right now
The people
Understand why they used to
They really aren't
Amazing towels
A new style of folding
And people doll no longer in The Hobbit
Even have committees
To wander into a newsagent or random basis
Cachapa magazine
Little click on a magazine
I know that one
He's been on your radio show
Be saying that the old
Dairy products
I really asked everybody around there in a great photograph
People and everything will be okay
That's pretty much exactly what he said
They won't surrounded with five or six or seven radio 910 blurbs
Unreadable blurb
Tell Bubba to magazine to magazine
Magazine
These days
Every place looks like a page from the internet
Hgm
What young people think
99% invisible with braces week by Avery trufelman Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
Can you produce out of the offices of Arts
A broken Architecture Firm that take special pride in their collaborative approach
Located in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinnerware
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
You run the show and like his on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars
But if you're interested in listening to the first 100 episodes of this program
Each one of them
Little gem of a radio story
Go to 99 pi
. org
Waiting on
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com