99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It is the most reviled form of contemporary architecture
There is
Mcmansion
Is an oversized house usually over 3000 square feet
That doesn't really interact with it
Environment weather that's the houses around it or if it's built in the middle of nowhere that environment as well
Kate Wagner creator of the blog mcmansion hell
She helps readers like me understand what is and isn't a mcmansion
And why we hate them
The main signs of a mcmansion or that they're built
Cheaply with very cheap materials new materials rarely ever traditional materials
As you can tell by the name of the blog and by her General demeanour Kate Wagner
Hates
The mcmansion
Their bills without any sort of consideration for the grammar of design
Since the creation of this show I've used the word architect
Any boost
Tenuous
And metaphorical of ways
According to Kate
The mcmansion may not even qualify
Fayez architect
At all
There's no real architecture
And it's too ostentatious
To be considered full
They have no architectural,
Commentary
All they do is
Represent
Should have been ideal
Well it's more an image of wealth rather than wealth itself
It's very much meant to convey that one
I have a lot of money in a lot of stuff
And I am
Putting it in this house that is
So tall and so Mass
That you feel intimidated by it just as you should
I feel intimidated by my apparent well
That's single-purpose
To convey well
Steamed rolls
Every other potential design principle
Symmetry or
Logic
History of beauty
Guess who cares if you have a big house
It's like so ugly I don't want to look at it
Kate believes the source of this ugliness
Stems from the combination of mass production
In customization
During the 90s and 2000's thanks
Easy access to a lot of money through Bad Mortgages pushed on the American people
The taste of the new homebuyer ran to the extreme
The standard model Elizabeth mass-produced homes reflected that
Blu Grand entrances and granite countertops and stainless steel appliances were nice enough
Many new home manufacturers allowed for customizations that brought the opulence
To the next level
So the combine the two done already design prototype with
Set up a custom home which can end up
In some pretty
While looking
Results
So they're designed and customized from the inside out
And it makes the outside
Big
And weird
And lumpy cuz somebody wanted cathedral ceilings in their bathroom wish
Is obviously in this us
The first victim in the design from the inside out process
Is the roof
Mcmansion roofs
RMS
The roof is sort of the number one way to tell
Mcmansion from a mansion
And that the roof kind of makes no sense
It's got various pitches which is held certif
Steep the Rufus and it's got
Many different shapes many different heights
Many different angles
Like a gabled roof with a hip roof the pyramidal roof you don't really need to know what these look like but just know
They're not usually all together
They're really just
There
To put a hat on a ridiculous
Crafted house
But the coup de Grasse of the mcmansion roof is a future that Kate has dubbed
The mcmansion nub
The mcmansion Novas
Where you'll see like a roofline that is relatively organized and I know just have like this
At the top because
Somebody had to have some fun
Feature and they just couldn't fit it in
Linearly usually it's like either storage space or like someone wanted
Some ridiculous
Feature so they just have this like
At the top
Just like a hat to a hat if
If you will
According to Kate another Hallmark of the mcmansion is the two-story entrance
You walk into a house and their son leave the house so much space
Wow look at our chandelier
Wow
So dramatic that was aware that
Dramatic
They being the real estate brokers in marketers and hoes
Civ house flipping TV shows
So to have a big entryway
You should probably have
Pretty big door
And then on top of that really big door there's a really big window sometimes there's like three foot of usual space and then the really big one
The window usually has a
Square bottom to match the top the door
And an artist
Top that kind of window shape didn't even exist really before the mcmansion did mcmansion invented that
Window it's not only the window on top of the door that makes
Caden the Avid readers that mcmansion hell cringe
It's all the windows
And I do mean
All of
The window
Is usually more than three different shapes
Windows
Of course
There are always thoughtful and interesting violations of any design guideline
Bratayley Kate thinks the house should limit the front facade to two or fewer window shapes
On keeping a single-window style across the entirety of a single story
Ridiculous houses in my inbox all the time
There's like six different types of Windows from 6 different architectural Styles it sort of
Garbled communication of source
You can't filter the signal from the noise design-wise
And last but not least you can't have a big ostentatious house
Without columns
So the columns usually either oversized or undersized sometimes the columns are not columns at all they're just called
Shaped
Protrusions from the exterior wall
Basically a column is
Is created to
Serve balance
Whatever it is that it's holding up
That's the point of college
I'm just that they hold things up
I know a lot of people seem to have not understood
Did that in the last
But they actually are supposed to hold things up and so if you have these really big columns and they're holding up the
Tiniest little pediment or Portico then it looks like
Pretty
But the point is is that you have the really big column so everyone knows that you're rich like a bank that also has
Alright so this kind of snarky criticism is fun at all
BP fun for me
But there's a larger point to be made about the design of the mcmansion
According to Kate
The age of the mcmansion
Saw the shift of the house
I'm a place that we live in potentially for the rest of our lives
To an asset
That we are decidedly not supposed to live in Forever
People started designing their houses with the notion of selling them in mine
Realtors would advise I wouldn't buy or do this because
The house isn't going to sell very well
So we sort of device this culture where we thought about selling our houses before we even
Spent one night in them
Kate lays the blame for this mindset at the feet of HGTV
And similar channels
The excess and Conformity of the mcmansion was reinforced over and over again
On Home Improvement and house flipping TV show
Because the house as object
Could always be improved
Atlas early to make it better
But to make it sell
Home Improvement channels
Wooden paint the house page and then you would see the sticker in the corner this is all we just
Add an $800 to the value of this house
Is there something like that
They would come up with these crazy ways to quantify
It'd be sort of improvement
Cause people to go into these frenzies and that's why it's so many houses look
The same is
Because
This is what was
Told would make our house worth more
Rather than
What actually does make a house worth more which is structural changes
Improving Energy Efficiency
Green upgrades things like that not like adding
Add certain color paint
Totally subjective
Older mcmansions built in the early 2000s are not proving to be a very good investment
Smaller houses are appreciating at a much
Faster rate than larger houses
But after a lull in the market following the housing crisis
Builders are finding buyers for huge brand new homes again
According to CBS News quote
Homes 4000 square feet or larger saw a sharp jump in sales last
Rising 30%
The year-earlier
And quote
It's safe to assume that all the bad design choice
First
Rounded McNay
Will continue on
In this new generation
Which is not good news if you enjoy the vibrancy
Variability
The built world
Houses of different style sets another thing that gives us
Sense of place
You can tell that you're somewhere else because all the houses are different
But
Sprawl aesthetic is that it's the same everywhere
And he'll houses in Styles didn't evolve
Through a planning committee
They evolved
The combination of popular taste and
Place like that's why you'll see like Pueblo style architecture in the west but you're not going to see it in
Cary North Carolina
It's just one of those things that gives you a context of where you are and that the built environment
Has everything to do with place as
Is the natural environment
Embedded in the pages of mcmansion hell are lessons in
Consumerism
Materialism
But fundamentally Kate Wagner
Pics of parties
These crimes against Arkansas
Hilarious and
Excruciating detail
To teach us the fundamentals of our cat
You're in a new way
Using humor to educate people about the world around them
Start of a great way to get people involved in
History of Greater design community
Most people with a learn about architecture in school as they learn like the Greek orders
Psycho this is the ionic columns yes this
Is the flying buttress everyone Snickers
And it's really dry
People like really don't care
I firmly believe that people do care
Even if we don't know why even if we don't know how to articulate it
We feel the effects
A bad design
Whether we consciously notice it or not
So now people can say
Now I know why
I hate that house
Thank you
Now it's like well actually none of these windows match I hate that
And it's empowering people to have opinions about the built environment
Which states have mostly been served through like
Marketing
Materialistic
The Glens
Rather than from a design standpoint
And as I've learned with pointing out the bad design of City Flags
Once you get people to notice bad design
Your annoyance
Spreads like a virus
I get a lot of emails like it a lot of messages that say like before I read this blog I didn't give two craps about architecture
And now I start to notice these things on all of
The building's I pass by and that makes me so happy because no other people have to suffer through what I have suffered for years
Years and years and years
And we will all suffer together
They're bad houses
Ugly Flags
Indoors that you don't know whether to push or pull
Are light switches you never remember which light they go to even though you've lived in the house for 20 freaking years
They're terrible currency ugly passports and I'm Comic Sans
Interpublic bench armrest
You're bogus expiration dates
Qunar confusing ballots
That one we really need to fix
Like soon
99percentinvisible is Katie Mingle
Refused
Sam Greenspan
Avery Chapman
Emmett Fitzgerald turn Mazza Delaney Hall and me Roman Mars
All the music this week was composed by Sean real we are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
So last week I presented at the Frontiers conference organized by the White House
President Obama was there and was a very cool event
I volunteered my time and I got myself out there
And is a thank you for my effort the White House organizers gave me
A presidential challenge coin
As you can imagine very big deal to me
The 99% invisible challenge coins are all gone
But for this year for the fundraiser we decided to design new radiotopia challenge coin
Likes to give to all the people who stayed with us as regular donors will last year
As a token of our appreciation
Enough of them to new back
Hackers who want to get on board
Nikki Barr show going strong
Having one of these coins means that you're committed to radiotopia being the home of independent producer driven podcast
When you challenge me with a coin
That means you're part of the family of people that makes us whole possum
What's the new coins box office
I can't wait to get one myself go to radiotopia. FM to become a coin carrying radiotopia
If we add 5000 donations to the rules
Press Box
To make Cloud accounting software particular design for independent creative people like me
Will donate $40,000
Do we need
YouTube make a channel
I mean you
Go to Radio Java.
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com