99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The best knockoffs in the world are in China
Sure designer handbags and roll up his butt
Also really large-scale imitations
Like fake Apple stores that are so dead on
Can employees of the store
Think they're working in a real Apple Store
But beyond just working and knockoffs many residents of Chinese suburbs live their lives in replica cities
Venice's with complete canals in replicas of the Doge's Palace
Paris with Eiffel Tower is an Arc de Triomphe
Chrysler Building
Sydney Opera House
Driving to the suburbs
A penny
City in China
You will find
A plethora
A fake Versace
British development
California
Dancehall bumping
App side-by-side
Just Shanghai itself has
Cities all built the ark
Profile of gif
European countries
It's possible to travel from Germany to Italy
To London
In the course of a few hours
Vitatress
Bianca bosker is the author of the book original copies
Architectural mimicry in contemporary China
And she coined a term for these buildings
Duplitech sure
Dipa texture refers to
Is Nationwide movement
Taking place
Whereby people are
Hopping in
Tired
Cities and towns from Europe and the United
Lifestyle
These are not theme parks do protector
Developments are actually living breathing Community is where Chinese families are raising their children
Living out their lives
The place that looks like orange
Dior Paris but a smack dab in the middle of the
These buildings are not just novelty is like that pyramid or the Eiffel Tower in Las Vegas
The biggest
Property developer
In China told me
2/3
Are there residential development
Are being built in
European style
Nor they like American Chinatown their German towns which were established by immigrants
An American or European style buildings
Which are often designed by Chinese architects
Visiting China
Copy of Paris on the outskirts
I found a place
In some ways was very emblematic
Paris with the Eiffel Tower
Square
But there was no new
Meaning the Chinese were interested in duplicating the newer buildings parents just the old classic looking ones that
That are iconic of the city
At the same time this is
Really easy
Most brand-new sparkling Paris I've ever
Even though these are intended to be copies it's pretty much impossible to pop a building onto a completely new environment without modifying
A little or a lot
Oven time for duplexer
Is
Larger
Or smaller than the real thing
Or different elements or features might be bloated bigger than others
Sometimes two protector get so twisted and warped until it's a freakish caricature of the original
One of the
Chris Sanders
Architectural
Has been the creation of
Mega high-rises
That are built in a baroque or near
Picture of Versailles stretched
20 floors
The air and you'll have some ID
Developers can take a lot of liberties with to protector construction like making the replicas work in accordance with Feng Shui
But nevertheless
A lot of these duplicate or compound
Have rules that actively discourage any type of modification that they think might subvert the simulacrum
They're very strict rules in place to ensure that
Chinese elements are formed elements
Don't crop in
And spoil the impression of other Paris
The European
CEO of this development
No hanging laundry outside
Installing air conditioner
Keeping
Chickens in the backyard
To further create the impression of Paris there might be a French bakery or a Bastille Day celebration
There might be a pub in an Irish town or real Canal Network in a knockoff Venice
Azan and uncanny as these building that communities can be
Do protector is pretty impressive
These buildings go up
Quickly on a massive scale and they show no signs of stopping
Baskets on new development popping up around China all the time
The Protector is not exactly a new trend
They have a lot of practice
In pre-modern China you had China's
Imperial ruler is he
Copycat
Buildings as a way of showing off
Their power and establishing their
Authority
The third Century BC
One of the rulers showed off
His Conquest
Kingdom by recreating their buildings
You also had Imperial hunting parks where would import Flora and Fauna of all kinds
Stone Landscapes within their own domain
Isn't real rulers would copy as a way of showing that they could literally move Heaven and Earth
They now possess
This foreign
Building
Or place
It was there
And even without tradition one of the most copied buildings in China is the very seat of Western power itself
The White House is generally credited
Demos
Copied
Building
An excuse for everything
From
Hotels to restaurants to
Courthouses
Just like the White House has a China collection
China
Has a White House Collection
The different Chinese white houses serve different purposes so they morphed into various permutations
But they all have those signature columns and square Portico built in the true blue Unique Style holy
Original to the US of a
I hate to break it to everyone
That's not
Original building
What's the white
Phases design
Huge
Building in Dublin
That is now the
Of
Parliament of Ireland
Arousing Dublin elements of classical Greek and Roman architecture
And it pretty much looks like the White House
Even though it's kind of Grey
Instagram
The founding fathers were really into
2 dupli textured as well
They were their own form of architectural plagiarize
And this is so obvious have you ever seen the buildings at Thomas Jefferson designed
They're also covered in columns eBay's the Virginia state capitol on this ancient Roman Temple and that design intern
Turn is going on to influence the design of many many state capitals around the country
American art
Architecture
Are copies
Is it the greatest hits
Ancient Roman art
Which are now all being copied by the
So we did it to
In North America was ruled by Europeans so it makes sense that we would have more European style architecture lying around
But we still continue to build these European homages today
Build
Mcmansions are building
Set drop
Some European elements
For being inspired
The Chinese they're ripping off
They're copying
There con artists
We should all recognize that what we're all doing
Copying some pretty old buildings
Because we still find them attractive and we still think that they have symbolic
It's easy to scoff at knockoffs of Venice
But these warped memories are the start of something new
I think it's all the time
Stealing
+ lack of talent
Equals creativity
I mean there is that any effort to copy something
Your skills or lack of skills
Are your different experience
It mutates the original so that very often you come up with something that's completely new and completely
Yours
Copying is totally underrated
And Munch alliteration It's All Good Things become great things
Successful at turning copies
N2 Innovation movement in China which is the name given for
Copies of the iPhone sneakers of social networks
Awesome X
The copies actually improve on the original in certain ways Chinese iPhone knockoff which
Cubs iPhone actually had some features that you couldn't find on Apple's phone
Head removable battery you have multiple SIM cards
Apple users
Actually really wanted and coveted
You could find it in this knockoff phone
I'm fascinated to see how China
Imitation and turns it into
Innovation
99% invisible West produced this week by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle same Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced at the offices of
Parkside a comprehensive architectural firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Speaking of our dearest by yours truly was named best local radio host in the best of the East Bay edition of these
East Bay Express
Totally made my day
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their hair
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
The 99 P experience isn't Justice episode that you're hearing we're all so fascinating on Twitter
Galant troubleman where else on Facebook Tumblr Instagram Flickr SoundCloud and Spotify to put RI
Home on the web is 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
Maven
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com