99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We live any post Billiards world
It was an age of Billiards and it has been over for so long most of us have no idea how huge bill
Billiards once was
100 years ago
Your 830 pool hall in my city of Chicago
Now if you add up all the gas station
All McDonald's and all the Starbucks in Chicago right now
Nowhere close to that
Maybe a little under 600
If you want to be exact and I know you do you beautiful nerds
Today
Chicago has fewer than 10 pool hall
That is Dan Weisman
Reporter
Chicago in
Dan originally reported the story for Marketplace so billion
Not what you say
But this is a post Billiards World any much more profound sense
Because the growth of Billiards led to the development of a material that
For Better or Worse
Came to define the modern world
I just want to say one word to you
Plastics
This story starts with a guy named Michael Phelan
Who's regarded by everybody else
But really the father of American Billiards
He's the author of The Illustrated Encyclopedia of building
Phelan was a brilliant player we also raised awareness of the sport
Promoted it
Arranging the biggest big money matches
Film was totally remarkable
Because he was everything
She was an all-around everything guy
He started huge Billiards on San Francisco
Deposited a new kind of billiard cushion and then
He took the money he'd won playing Billiards and writing books on Billiards
And use it to become the first
Big manufacturer of billiard tables and equipment
Feeling created the age of billiards in the US and he felt that you further popularized the game of Billiards
Sell more tickets
Send some more equipment
He would need a standardized
Cuz if tables and balls
Rent-A-Center
From one location to another
You were basically playing a different game every time you went somewhere new but standardizing the billiard ball was no easy task
It's a very very high standard to me
The billiard ball has to have certain physical properties it has to rebound properly it has to be the uniform density
And the time
It was really only one material that we do
Ivory
Which was not
Going to Africa shooting elephants that is
Dangerous and expensive
Not to mention horrible people for
Decades
Had been trying to find substitutes
For ivory
They tried a variety of materials including even metal balls iron balls
Which really don't
Perform well iron billiard balls just weren't the same Ivory balls had just the right way
The most evnroll
The best rebound off the cue stick
Each other off the side of the table
Laughing with this guy
Only the best
Great ivorywood do in fact
When you look at records in the ivory trade
The top grade of ivories actually called
Billiard ball ivory
And Billiard balls required a lot
Set of billiard ball grade ivory
Unlike the ivory on piano keys for a veneer over wood
Do your balls had to be made of 100% solid ivory
And therefore
The average number of billiard balls that could be obtained from a single tusk
What's 3
If you're the best
Lucky's billiard ball Turner
Maybe you could get five balls from One Touch
Even so
That mean one set of billiard balls is going to require chewing at least 2 L
Two billiard balls were very expensive
And when you're trying to build an industry that a problem
Her film company it was the problem
Sinclair trade
Depended on the forces of this one exotic material that's Robert fradella professor at the universe
First Tee of Maryland
He studied the history of technology and he wrote the book
I'm what happens next
Phelan and his colleagues were acutely aware that their dependency on Ivory was not ideal there really
That's what I don't think it proved wrong or what
Define chum kind of substitute material
Simply wasn't
Parent takes out an ad in the paper and here's a dramatization of what happened
When a guy named John Wesley Hyatt found at at
Look at this
Cries of
Dollars
For the discovery of a satisfactory substitute
Ivory and making billiard balls
That's my 1937 episode of a radio show called Cavalcade of America
Hey that's a lot of money
Certainly is
In terms of wages people earned at the time it was like 3 million dollars
Height was mcamis but he was a tinkerer
Any work for years to win fail and fries
By trade Hyatt was a printer and printers use nitrated cellulose to protect their hands
It still sold as liquid bandage
And that material turned out to have very interesting properties
And in particular
Dissolve
And it creates a very sure every liquid
In the radio dramatization I it gets his key inspiration when a bottle of the stuff overturns
Any watches that dry into a film that he finds
Interesting
Why is this
Giving me an idea
And the idea it might be worth $10,000
Giant idea might have been worth $10,000
But it was also dangerous
Nitrogen cellulose is highly
Highly flammable
But John Hiatt in his lab assistant Jim kept going
Baby heat up and I traded cotton put it in the press and
What's the weather
The Press
Look at it
All this time
A material that will take the place of ivory
A material that would take the place of ivory
Was plastic
Hyatt call Disney material
Celluloid
Celluloid did not win feelings $10,000 prize
Celluloid is a wonderful material
Thrift Shop
Beautiful plastic it can be colored an ostrich weight
Give me shape to deflate
It has a wonderful range of uses
Tell your boss is not one of them
Balls made of Celluloid just didn't bounce right but Hyatt tried to make a go of it anyway
Well Company
His balls are not made of cellulite
They have a
Thin veneer of cellulite on the outside
But I mainly plaster
On the inside
And there
Very inferior by your body
I didn't give up on cellular
You wanted a business with his brother Isaiah
Shut up
To try to exploit what they are convinced they're very
Nifty material
But they can't figure out what on Earth
The market trying to be
They tried dental plates you can color Celluloid to look just like real gums but
There's a problem
Turns out that
So you like it
Soft if you're drinking hot tea
Eventually they find the best use for celluloid
Is imitation ivory
Albeit
Not for billiard balls
But versions of popular Ivory luxury goods
Nike sandals
Combs
Hand mirrors
Even
Toys in boxes
A gigantic arranged
Many of which would never actually have been made it I write also
Piano keys
A Sears catalog from the 1890s
Offers pianos with a choice of key covering
Ivory
Cellulite
And of course the most famous use of Celluloid would eventually be to make film stock for movies
Meanwhile billiard balls kept getting made out of ivory
Ivory that came mostly from Africa which of course the Europeans have been busy colonizing and exploiting
In the ivory trade was pretty awful for the people of Africa
Joseph Conrad Heart of Darkness
Based largely on his own experience in the Belgian Congo
Where Ivory was a big Prada
Conrad called the whole Enterprise
Quote the vilest Scramble for loot that ever disfigured the history of human conscience
End
Current necessarily care about this part but
Obviously the ivory trade was also
Terrible for elephants
Why jumpstart a pretty common animal
In central Africa
In the middle of the 19th century
Becoming increasingly scarce
By the 20th
By the time of World War II the ivory Supply crunch the one that Michael Phelan had started worrying about
50 years before
Had arrived
And around this time the real significance of Hyatt
So you would have begun to show itself
However begin to inspire people
Think about
What artificial material might be
Available what what
People could make what people could invent
And I do a seven a chemist named Leo baekeland comes up with a new kind of plastic made from petroleum
He names it Bakelite
After himself
And one cool thing about Bakelite
You can melt
Mixing fillers
And it turns out that with that capability you can vary the density
You can bury the electricity
And you can make
A perfect day of fall
So they finally replaced Ivory balls with this new plastic
Bakelite
By the 1940s
Even top pool tournament being played with plastic balls
But by then
Kuhl pants
Peak
It crashed as the depression begin
Never gained its former prominence
The age of Billiards
Whatever
And this post Billiards age the age of plastic
And really got into gear
For example the handle of your toothbrush
What is probably at 5
So undoubtedly on the barrel of your fountain
Family instrument panel in your car
And yet these are just
A few of more than 25000
Modern uses
For Plastics
Static plastic
Plural
By that time you got a bunch on the market
PVC vinyl polyethylene of plexiglass
Nylon
Aunt in labs
You're discovering the stuff would end up becoming Teflon
And good old Celluloid the plastic that started it all had been retired even from the movies
It was indispensable to the beginning of motion picture
But it was highly dangerous
Flammable Celluloid film called several disastrous and fatal fires in movies
Vanagon 34 a new form
Cellulose acetate
I taken the place of Hyatt
Cellulose nitrate
Celluloid
Born out of Billiards
Was the first plastic
Ushered in a new age of modern products and but it never succeeded in revolutionising the game of Billiards
It did however
Revolutionize another tables board
Ping pong
Before Celluloid was invented ping pong was played with something more closely resembling a golf ball
Which as you can imagine doesn't didn't have that perfect balance
Celluloid ping pong balls that were used for years but finally got some from tournament play in 2013
The reason
A little too bouncy
Poor soil
It just can't win
Someday we'll find the perfect home for you my bouncy friend
99% invisible what produces week by Dan Weisman
Roman Mars
Special thanks to Dave on who runs the Chicago billiard Museum
Play the documents data and images will have a link on our website
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again
Again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Devon the show in Lancaster on Facebook or on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify
And you can see that Johnny Appleseed of Billiards Michael Phelan
Dreamleaf unsettling neckbeard
At 99 pi
. org
Just
Yes sir
Are you listening
Plastics
Turkey how do you mean
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com