99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
That's cool in Athens Georgia which is a great place to be from the 80s
Have about
18 to 25
If you like going out to bars
And listening to live music
You know Adams is a fairly small college town
It's hot
Huge and important music scene for decades
And the most famous band to come out of the oven scene
Undoubtably
Is REM
To be provocative right from the start I'm going to say that REM out of time
Is the most politically important album in the history of the United
Provocateur is reporter Whitney Jones do I have to say
I don't think out of time is even the most important album in the history of REM
Actually my argument here is nothing to do with the music
This isn't one of those oh it's a soundtrack to a generation or anything like that
Out of time made such a huge impact
Because of its
Packaging
The box out of time originally came in led to a bill being passed in Congress
An actual concrete law
Let's go back to 1985
The pop charts were full of
Prince and Sheena Easton
And the Youth of America
For being corrupted
Tipper Gore in a few other Elite women of Washington form of the parents music Resource Center
Or the pmrc for short
They put pressure on the creators and Distributors of quote on quote
Objectionable music
Musicians and labels called the censorship
There were Senate hearings about this
And eventually those little black and white Parental Advisory sticker started appearing on albums
This set off a wave of censorship across the country
In 1990 a federal district judge in South Florida ruled that the rap group 2 Live Crew album
As nasty as they wanna be
Was so obscene that it couldn't be sold or performed within his jurisdiction
3 days after the ruling 2 Live Crew played a show in Broward County Florida
And after the show two members of the group got arrest
And it was a live performance I believe
That they found obscene with you know girls doing what would be
Like what might working I think it would be a very early version of the twerking
Jeff ayeroff wasn't there he saw it on TV and I just it was just so offencive to me
Jeff was an executive at Virgin Records
And to be clear he wasn't offended by the raunchy lyrics
Ixora the twerking
He was offended by the arrest
Send the blatant censorship of the artist work
Jeff spent the next couple days mulling this over and then he had a revelation
One of the reasons why
Politicians get away with things because there isn't an anti constituency
There was never anything to lose by
Baiting
Rock and roll because there was this
Qunar that young people didn't vote
And you know within the next two days the idea came to me like fully formed in some way
And I came up with this damn Rock the vote
Progesterone
The idea behind rock the boat with simple
Get young people to vote for politicians who wouldn't censor music
Yeah it was that simple it was the idea of you put
Kids in the game
The game becomes different
Politicians can no longer scapegoat music they can't keep using us as Annex
Excuse
Sogefi Rob got about 60 people together in a Los Angeles hotel the talk about launching Rock the Boat
Frank Zappa was there
Past and present California Governor Jerry Brown was there
As we're a bunch of other record exec
So there we are
Part of this
Virtuous circle of record executives
Who have spent a lot of their career being criticized for destroying the Youth of America and it was sort of like an affair
Very altruistic way
I think we could do something positive we can get kids to vote we can
You know that's cool
Also in attendance was Jeff Sprint
Jeff gold
He was working for Warner Brothers
And one of his major project of the time
Trying to figure out
How to package CDs
Compact disc packaging was the Hot Topic in the record world in the late eighties and early nineties
CDs have been around for a few years at this point
But record stores still didn't have a good way to display them
Here's Jeff gold
When
CDs first came out on the market
Record retailers
Were angry about them because their stores were formatted
To display
12 and 1/2 inch for 12 and 1/4 inch square
Talbots
In other words they didn't have any stands or display cases for these new CDs
So somebody the record industry said look
If you put a CD jewel case inside of a cardboard box that's as long as a vinyl album
And only half as wide
You can fit
Two of these longbox CD side-by-side in an LP rack
Problem solved
Retailer said fine perfect
It's so millions of these things out of nowhere started getting made
Record people loved the long box
They thought it was the future
A head honcho AEM I wrote this opinion piece in billboard magazine in 1989 entitled
Why we should keep the CD longbox
He writes quote
I want to see the music industry continue to thrive and prosper as one of the cornerstones of entertainment
And I think making full use of the 6 by 12 CD carton
Is one way to help us do just
That but not everyone loved along box
Artist said wait a minute
We don't want you cutting down millions of trees
To put
Are CD's in
And then having people throw these things away it's a
Incredibly wasteful
In bed thing to do for
Because the thing about the longbox
Is that it was never meant to be collected
And the feel of a big Mike and Ike Carter
You when you bought a CD in a longbox
You open it up
It take out the jewel case
Switch out the actual CD in the album art in it
I need to toss a long box
There's no reason to keep it around
Auriemma record coming out
In 1990
And they're saying
To me and to Warner Brothers there's no way our record is coming at a long box
We're sensitive to the environment
This is a ridiculous thing forget it
And one of their sales department is saying it absolutely has to come out in a long box
Or record retailers
Going to penalize
And that's when Jeff gold got this idea
He could merge the two projects He was working
They could use the CD longbox to advance The Rock the vote camp
But first he needed a concrete political cause to connect it to
And Jeff are all fat found just the thing
We were sitting there looking for a reason. Try to get us
Send
A political situation
I'm reading Newsweek or time and there's this column article
About the Motor Voter bill
We just said
We're going to help these people from the Motor Voter bill
This was going to be our first thing we were going to do but so there's this Motor Voter bill that's been bouncing around Congress since the 1970s
If passed Motor Voter would allow people to register to vote at the DMV when you got a driver's license
It also allowed you to register by mail or when you apply for social services like welfare or unemployment
Basically making it easier for a lot of people
Including Rock loving young people
The register to vote
By 91 a few states that already adopt
But Congress has never been able to get it passed naturally
Jeff gold went to a political event in Hollywood about the Motor Voter bill
And one of the speakers was
Columbia sociologist in political activist
Richard cloward
He said that writing to elected officials could help sway them on the issue
After clouds talk Jeff gold went up and spoke with
Then when the Panic started talk
What amount of letters would a senator a congressman
And take note of
Particular
350 200
That would really have an empath
Can I should really that
Few
People don't write so
Getting 150-200 letters
About an issue would would definitely make them sit up and take notice
That weekend Jeff gold was riding his bike around Santa Monica
And I had this moment where
It rushed into my mind this fully formed idea that
That we could
Take care of REM
By turning their long box into a positive
If we put a petition on the back of the long box
That would go to rock the boat saying I support the Motor Voter bill
And we could distribute it to
Their respective senator
And I knew
We can generate
Unbelievable amount of mail
Jeff gold got on the phone with Jeff era
And they agreed that this would be the strategy
They would turn the album long box into a piece of political machinery
And they would flood congress with support for the Motor Voter bill
That Monday Jeff called REM manager with the plan
It's alright let me call the guys
I'll call you back
I probably heard back from him within an hour
Bernie said great idea they're totally into it let's do
So out of time hit the record stores on March 12th 1991
And then the petition started rolling in
And I remember vividly
Maybe four or five days after the record come out
I mean a very short period of time
They had bags
It was really incredible
Nobody can seem to put their hand on what the exact number of
That we got of these were but I remember thinking
Well after 3 weeks we got ten thousand I mean that's
100%
That's already half of what Richard cloward said would make an impact
And he sings just kept coming in and drove their canvas bags full of them coming in
About a month after REM release the album Rock the books political director plus two members of the hip hop group KMD
Wheeled a shopping cart full of these first ten thousand petition
Into a senator
And they just left them there for senators window Ford
And a very young looking Mitch McConnell
It may have 1992 after thousands of petitions
Senate testimony
The Motor Voter bill passed
Congress
But then president HW Bush vetoed
This was in July right in the middle of Bush's re-election campaign
Bush's opponent Bill Clinton took up Motor Voter as a talking point
Bashing Bush over
What is veto
And the rest is basically history
Clinton wins 92
The bill comes back before the house is actually the second bill that the house takes up in January of 93
Motor Voter passofallpasses the Senate
And then Bill Clinton signed it into law
As the national voter registration Act of 1993
At the White House earlier
Today prison
Bill Clinton signed
The voter registration Act
Commonly
Referred to as the Motor Voter bill
Can we get invited to the White House
The signings
And it's this
Totally surreal scene
His wife were there and I'm there with my wife and
All the people
And
Clinton at the signing talks about how Rock the vote really helped make the difference
How to get this built
As I said I have
Long supported the idea of
Motor Voter
More than a year ago I promised
Does president
But I would sign HR 2 and 5
Rich Passage
I'm pleased to be able to keep
The promise today
That I made on this rock
The boat card
Still has my signature
Back in New Hampshire
Shaking his hands after the bill-signing we identified ourselves as rock the boat and said you guys got this past
That was really one of the most
Surreal
Moments of my life
I want to stop a Minit in point out just how bizarre this scene is
Remember Rock the Boat had formed in open protest against censorship group
That was started by the new vice president wife
Tipper Gore
You know those little black and white parental advisory stickers those were nicknamed Tipper stickers
Tipper Gore's husband was now praising Rock the vote
And it's a tribute to one group
Is voice an organ
Malaysian was apps
Impressive
America's young people
They Rock
The vault
They got this
So when Jeff gold says
Was really one of the most
Surreal
Moments Abaya
My wife
Yeah
I think the real is probably the right word
What's interesting here is that this campaign
Really could have only happened during a very brief period of time
Because before Clinton had even signed the Motor Voter bill
Jeff gold at actually found a way to kill off the long box for good
He hatched a plan and he went to talk about it with the Chief Financial Officer at Warner Brothers
Murray
Lisa Marie how many of these things do we make a year and he said okay
I don't know 90 million between the
Something like that
Niacin how much do they cost you said
$0.25
I said Okay so
You talking about
20 to 25 million dollars a year were music
Expense on lombok
And he said yeah
I said so what if we stopped making long box
And we took that 25 million dollars and gave it in the form of rebates
Trek retailers
Just to pay for them to reconfigure
There been
And we did it as a one-time
You know discount or payment
And they got all the money we saved for the first year
And then
For the rest of time
We're saving 25 million dollars a year
El jacal tell that the other Warner Brothers Executives liked his idea
They took it to the distributor
The distributor went for it
And that was the end of the long box
Some stores got new racks to accommodate the long box Free Jewel cases
Others held on to their 12-inch bin
But started putting CDs inside of these reusable plastic
Stick cartridges
And record companies have been profitable and solvent ever since
So long boxes or not
The Motor Voter bill
Which after apus became the national voter registration Act of 1993
That's still very much a thing
Between 1995 when the law went into effect
In 2012
The percentage of the voting age population that is registered to vote went up more than 10 points
From 69.5%
279.9
And in that same time span more than a hundred and fifty million voter registrations have been filled out at the DMV
That doesn't even include mailing registrations or registrations through Social Services
As for what's the law also brought
So I think that proves it know album is as important to politics in the US
As REM out of time
But we lie their most important album important about the things that actually really matter
Is murmur
Musically of course it's not their best album automatic for the people their best musical album
What how old are you I'm 30
You're a child
You don't know anything
Murmur
99% invisible was produced this week by Whitney Jones was Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and Mero
Whitney Jones and Alex Kalman are the creators of pitch
A documentary radio show about music on which this story originally appeared
Their second season start in August
So you might as well subscribe their podcast now and meet up first in line when the new episodes start flooding in
Find out more at here pitch.com
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced at the offices of ox
Design and Architecture Firm in Near Wild Heaven Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinner
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Info podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
99percentinvisible
Episodes that you hear the 99 Pi crew are graded Twitter you can follow us at Broad and Morris and listens Katie mingle and
Troubleman were on Facebook Tumblr Instagram Flickr Spotify to
But I invite you to tell us which REM album makes you the happiest
The judgement free zone
And 99 pi
. org
Radio temperature
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com