99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We begin with an unsolved murder mystery
Actually a series of unsolved murders
Perhaps the work of the United States
Worst serial killer
Before Jack the Ripper terrorize London
Before HH Holmes stock the Chicago World's Fair
Austin Texas
Was haunted by the servant girl annihilator
Producer Avery trufelman would like to reiterate that these murders are unsolved
So it's possible that these were individual murders rather than the work of one man
The hard fast
Fact is this
In 1885
8 Women
Mostly black servants
Brutally murdered
In the dark of night
And the night was very dark
In Austin in 1885
There was essentially no Street
The darkness
Just life
After sundown
In the 19th century it's something that modern
People are just completely
This is Bruce hunt
He's an associate professor of the history of physics and Technology at the University of Texas Austin
Basically there was no outdoor lighting there was moonlight
When the moon was out that was about
And in 1894 the City of Austin decided to buy more moonlight
In the form of towers
They're called Moonlight Towers
Because we were supposed to
Full moon
Austin adopted Moonlight Towers
Was really work Powers there 15 stories high
Very industrial-looking made of metal scaffolding and each was crowned with a circle of six lights
Soaring way way high above the city
Austin wasn't the first to implement Tower lighting
In the eighteen-hundreds a lot of major cities had them
ArcLight hours illuminated streets in New York Baltimore La San Jose and Detroit
Detroit had a very huge
Much larger than Austin
And that's actually where Austin got their moonlight
Towers
In 1894 the city purchase
Just 31 of them
From the city of Detroit
And despite their romantic name
Be absurdly tall Moonlight Towers were actually a very practical design
And their height was meant to accommodate the lighting they use
There are clients there initially were ArcLight
Carbon Arc lights
The precursor to the incandescent bulb
Park lights are basically a continued Spark
Between two carbon
They're extremely bright
Lot of glitter
And if you put Arc lights at street-level that's blinding will the solution that was to put it up High Enough
Food spread the light up
But even on their Hightower
Dark lights were still so bright
I mean they be bright by today's standards but then imagine what that would look like to you if you were an austinite in the 1890s
Accustomed to pitch black streets
And gas lamps
The Gaslamp has the power of about 15 kennel
An arc light has the power of a couple thousand
It was a very intense light almost two months flight
People would go out and enjoy the life that they would bring umbrellas in order to Shield themselves from the glare
This is Ernest freeberg
Head of the history department at the University of Tennessee Knoxville
He's also the author of the book the age of Edison
Electric light and the invention of modern America
In the glare was just one of the problems with our clients there were a few other downsides sounded like a
A swarm of angry
With Buzz
And they would
Child abuse azby's carbons burned
They were dropped
Shreds of Ash burning Ash down on people down below
There's a girl back
Even with their blinding glare and nefarious hum and deposits of molten ash
Carbon Arc lights were still so exciting
They created a whole new world for people accustomed to dim and Dark City
Because bright electric light can highlight certain things that you might not even notice in the full light of day
There's a lot of great discussion about
Seeing the grass in a totally different way
People love to look at their hands under the ArcLight in
In the dark
They were seeing
The details of their hands and
In new ways
They heard
It was really up for a change in perception
What's up
The thrilling feeling of being out at night and feeling safe
Because disability equal safety
Some cities that these newfangled streetlights are going to cut back on the need for police
Or even eliminate law enforcement entirely
If you could set up a
An arc light in the middle of a
Town Square you charge for be returning the square to the public and take it away from criminals and
Mary Wells were hanging around in the shadows by driving out the shadow
People called The Arc lights policemen on a pole and they allow for a whole new kind of life
Many people were very excited to go out and
Attend a fancy ball under the arcway
Once they got there they realized
Set this
Spark blue light
Highlighted every one of their
Imperfections so every gray hair and wrinkles
Many people felt that they would never again go near
Electric light
Vanity aside everyone was kind of nervous about the general idea of light at night
It was unnatural they decreed the towers could cause sleeplessness cast Erie Shadows crops would overproduce
Hinswood overlay
There were stories at the ArcLight slurred Restless alligators to the shore
And attracting biblical proportions of crickets
According to the Austin Statesman in 1921
Bruce hunt suspects of these reports were overblown
Journalism was so much fun back then
But the biggest problem with the towers was that their height made them a drag to maintain the arcs
Burn down the carbon electrodes very rapidly
So you had to go up and change them about once a day and I cannot emphasize enough how
Super-tall these things are
How tall is a 15-story building
If you look at one of Austin's Moonlight Towers
There's a rickety little pulley type thing in the center of it
Like a dumbwaiter apparatus
Supposedly there
Guy would stand on Madden
Pulling self up
To go up and change the carbon electrodes everyday
That's a nuisance
Panda Express
And so
As soon as
They could really by the 1920s the city replaced it
Arclights the carbon Arc
With
Big incandescent bulbs
Which were not as bright
But we're a lot
But while Austin was fussing around with different bulbs
Most other cities had already removed their tower lights completely
Every place else abandoned
Please put Austin kept them
Awesome had fallen on Hard Times in the city couldn't afford to tear down the towers
And so they just stayed
And to this day 17 of the original 31 survive
The last
Of the Moonlight hours
Although today without the arc lights the Moonlight Towers have a kind of weak and distant low
They're easy to ignore
That you might know them from a little movie called Dazed and Confused
Dazed and Confused is set in Austin in 1976
In the movie A bunch of kids party and drive around until they all gather at the end
By my tower
There's a new fiesta in the making as we speak
Santa Moon Town in the movie Dazed and Confused Richard linklater movie
Matthew McConaughey
Party at the Moontower but there Moonlight Towers
In real life people don't actually go there to party
Most of them are
Justin sort of like parking lots or something
I went to a Moonlight tower on the side of a busy road on the corner of 9th and Guadalupe
Guadalupe clearly I need a local to help my name is Wiley Wiggins I'm 38 years old I was born
Torn racing
Austin Texas
And in the early 90s I was in a movie by Richard linklater called Daisy
He played the Freshman Mitch Kramer who wanders about the moon Towers
What's it called the Moontower anyway
I guess they decided to
Put up out here whenever they were building the power plant
Actually it's a good idea I mean you got a full moon out here every day of the year you know and then they all climb up the moon tower
Places to be off-limits man
Some drunk freshman
Fell off
You went right down the middle smacking his head on every
Beamer
I hear it doesn't hurt after
The first couple though
In real life these Moonlight hours would be really hard to climb which is my for this scene
Richard linklater made of fake Moonlight hour
The one in the movie had a ladder not the pulley thing
And it was nowhere near as tall as a real Moonlight Tower
And I'm terrified of heights
Wiley would have never tried this stunt
No one he knew actually did when I was a kid there was always somebody who knew somebody who knew
New somebody who would climb that it's unclear how many times this was ever attempted but in any case
Stories about
And it was a point when Austin considered finally taking these old lights down
Just like all the other cities have done fifties and sixties beatitude was Willy's are out of date
Can I pull those down
In fact I've got a video that I found online that was a sort of
Little
Historical vignettes of Austin that was made by one of those
What TV station
Tonight
Progress report Austin
The legends of Austin
And is it
Here's the Moonlight Towers in Here Today Show
Romance of these Moonlight Towers
Disappeared
Ears
29 of these towers left
50 feet high
Mercury vapor lamps of 9000 Campbell
No power now they're out of date now and no doubt will soon disappear
Modern times
New improvements in life
How many days
Inefficient for
Providing light
And it's a shame
For anyone who has walked
They're going to party
Watching the Shadows
Lowe's Dubuque
And there's a sort of tone that that's well as little remnant of our past that we will lose soon
What people just said why should we
Keep them up
Two Towers were inducted into the National Registry of historic places
Some of the towers even have plaques
And Austin power provider Austin Energy
What has a lot of resources into maintaining the towers
Take it from Austin Energy spokesman Carlos Cordova
Right now it's really in
Christine about the moon
Mike Towers is there going to be going through a renovation
In this renovation is a total drag
Because these towers are in the National Registry of historic places
They have to be restored
To the original form so we can go to Home Depot or Lowe's and buy bolts and
The contractor has to
Cast bolts
Parts that look
Exactly I did
So you can keep it
That's what I love about these Moonlight Towers man
I get older
They stay the same age
Have an expensive project it's very specialized word that of course affect the price
But notice there wasn't any uproar for the citizens about spending this money on the Moonlight hours
Austinites
Are willing to put up the funds
Towers artist point of civic pride
Every year during the holidays Austin Energy strings Christmas lights from the Moonlight Tower and Zilker Park
And austinites lovingly refer to that Tower as the Zilker Park
Tree
Austin also host the Moontower Comedy Festival and there's a local band called Moonlight powers and at a restaurant I ordered
Drink called a Moonlight Tower
The towers have become part of the character in folklore of Austin I mean there's all sorts of
Some stuff about them
Like when I was a kid. Of course there was always a legend that somebody had climbed up on acid and falling off
Which is definitely not true
But then of course
The other Legend is that they were built
Because of there was a
Serial killer
Like a in the
For like the 1800s
And that one I think is supposed to be true right have we have we verified
The servant-girl annihilator story is not a myth that all that is absolutely true
It has nothing to do with the Moon
At least not directly
That was all over with
Welder
Before the cock
But I've never seen any
I need four
Still the servant-girl annihilator became that awesome expel about these lines
And the story of the servant-girl annihilator does truly illustrate the limitations of nineteenth-century
Nighttime
Is carbon Arc Street lamps were chasing away Darkness
Sphere
And I think it's something we
So easily take for granted
Liberating
This is how much the darkness
Was a permanent
Form of limitation on
Freewheel one human activity
EBenefits
It's of course said that that we sometimes Miss
Because we have too much right now
Moonlight Towers were strange offshoot
Sort of Neanderthal in the evolution of the street light
And in Austin where Keep Austin Weird is an unofficial slogan of the city
Printed on bumper stickers and sprawled on bathroom walls
You can't help it feel like the moon towers are doing their part
After every other city has torn their towers down
Boston holds on to theirs
And preserves them
A reminder of the time when the Texas Capitol was Dustin Oddball little town
That bought the Moon
Those who have
Look closely
The day of the artificial Moon
Yes I will one day this
The last and Foundation
The Moonlight glow
Dutchtown
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman Katie mingle Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars we are
Project of kalw
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Special thanks to Josephine Hill and Mark Oppenheimer for help on this episode
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars that he bought me in either one of those two places you could be aware of all
All the things in toxin events we have coming up
Including a free public talk
I'm giving in a middle school gym about 2 miles from my house so excited about that one
Spotify playlist on Instagram but I encourage you to explore the entire world of 99% invisible
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com