99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I'm going to
Tell you a story first about
Powerbuilding got design
A very unusual building in New York
Citicorp Tower
What it was built in 1977 was the 7th tallest building in the world
You know I can still remember the first time I saw the citicorp center
If you exit the Local 6 subway station at Lexington and 53rd in Midtown Manhattan
Confronted by a sheer
Shooting up right from your feet that's reporter Joel Werner
Gleaming kassadin Blossom feeling
Striking 45 degree angle crown
Citicorp Center is truly one of the most
Spectacular skyscrapers on a Skyline known for spectacular skyscrapers
Really it's the base of the building that takes your breath away
Matthew 59 story skyscraper levitates meet hovering
115 space above the street corner
At first glance the building seems to violate the basic laws of physics
The underside of the building corner
Even the ground Instead This nothing
Of course the building isn't really levitating it's propped up on stilts which join the building at the midpoint of each side
It does not exert a
It's got to be starting Scott to be safe they wouldn't have built it this way
Gerald f
Secret about this building
It was literally a secret for nearly two decades after it was built
The citicorp center
Could very well have blown over in the Wind
What I want to know
Which one was this building waterfalls
The architect of the Citigroup Center was Hugh stubbins
The most of the credit for this building is given to the chief structural engineer William lemessurier
Who laugh at me but I did conceive it on a napkin
Greek restaurant in Cambridge
La mision passed away in 2007
This is him giving a talk at MIT in 1995
The whole problem was to build a building
On a site that has
A church in one quarter St Peter's Lutheran Church
Crummy old building
It was the lowest point in Victorian architecture
It was that bad
Set at the corner of the lots and when the church sold Atlantic City called it was on the condition that they built
Build a new church
Inexact
Same location
Beyond that the company was free to build a skyscraper around the church
And in the airspace above it
So a plan was hatched
Flute the building over the church
Hence the stilts
And because the church was in the corner of the lot
The measure put the stilts in
Kind of weird place
You couldn't have columns in the corners where they ought to be
Unconventional building so they were moved to the middle
Placing the Cullens at the midpoint of each side rather than in the corners made the building lifts table
Additional support
Lamesha designed a Chevron bracing struct
Essentially rows and rows of these
8/8 stories high pointing down the middle of h building face
Twitter supporting columns if they move
Actually I can take one and to keep the building simple it is
Skin because there was so much drama going on at the bottom and at the top anyway
Should know if you're going to have any diagonals I don't ever want to say them
Set the Chevron bracing structure was slipped under the skin of the building
I found the city court sentence
The skeleton
One of the amazing things about the Chevron bracelet
Is it so light White
The wind the wind blows
It is more dynamically excitable than the building that weighed twice as much
In other words
It movie
With the Wind
Which most people find really unsettling
Understandably right
Lamesha added something cold a tuned Mass damper
The tuned Mass damper is a massive concrete which is 29 ft
Square
In about 8 feet second wave
400 tons
It is flooded on
Pressurized oil bearing
Sits at the very top of the building
An axe to steady the oscillation
It offsets the Wind Gap
So to recap we have a 59 Story Tower floating on 115 foot still
Still switching not in the corner where you'd expect them but Rob it in the middle of a side of a
Face with a skeleton of beans shaped like these which make it super light for a skyscraper
And to stop it from swaying in the wind there's a 400-ton block
The concrete on the roof
Totally ingenious
Really cutting edge design
Limitations of pro so in accordance with the New York City building code
Medical model
To make sure the building is going to hold up
And everything seemed just fine
Until as
He got a phone call
June
I'm in my office
I got a call from a
Student
I do not know the school I wish you would call me
For the past you never had one and it was a real student
From New Jersey
I think it was an architect
Student English teacher
Giving him this buildings
Study
And report on
Because it's unusual
ASLA midget elf
Closest college senior
Hold him up to ask how he's building structure is going to cope with quartering winds
An undergraduate student calling out the head of a world-renowned engineering firm on one of the most Innovative skyscraper
Designs of a today
Quartering winds the winds
Caught the students attention
Adults that hit the building on the corner
Exerting pressure on two faces at once
Emissions calculations on the perpendicular Twins win to hit the face of the building Square on
Seem to be fine
But as The Story Goes
The student raise the alarm about citicorp Center being particularly vulnerable
Cornice
It turns out the measure had never run the numbers on what cornering winds would do to the building because normally
Buildings are strongest at their corners
But this is no normal building
Remember what's going on team
Supporting column shift
Did the midpoint of each building phase
The Chevron bracing skeleton
And the unusually light mass of the build
Taking a loan no one of these design quotes should have presented a problem
But as a
Student told lamesha taken together
Payless citicorp Center
Tequila vulnerable to wind striking the structure corners
And when the measure started to investigate the students claims
You realize that the root of the problem had to do with a change that have been made to the original plans
It has to do with how the Chevron bracing structure was fastened together
What measures plan originally called to the joints to be welded with full penetration weld with the contractor had
Just said using bolts instead
Bethlehem Steel axe
Design beautiful Bolton connect
For the forces
Did my people gave them
It was a cost-saving measure
The measure says that this change would have happened without his knowledge
Given the wind load calculations lamesha tame Hadsell
Applied
Welding these days together with Overkill
Run the math and it looks like both would do just fine
And bolts would have done just fine I'm pretty much any other building except citicorp Center had an Achilles heel
Each of its Four Corners with no one else had
No one except for that pesky student
From New Jersey
And Islam Asia started looking into the students
Claims about these quartering winds
You realize this
Situation wasn't just bad
It was a disaster
Waiting to happen
The return. To failure
What's 16 years
It's about that
Cancel that meme
Limited calculated the quartering wind velocity
Required
Coppell citicorp Center
He didn't match these velocities to weathertap
To see how freaky
On average
Winds strong enough to blow the building
Occurred
La mejor found that storm strong enough to knock over the building is New York City on average
Once every 55 years
But that's only if the tuned Mass damper is working
The tuned Mass damper needs
How it's run
If you getting shoot Stone The Measure be alive
It's not unlikely that the city could suffer a blackout
La mejor random numbers again this time Imagining the damper without power
Without the damper a storm is strong enough
Topple citicorp Center hits New York on average once every 16 years
To put this another way
The entry of the building was standing there was about a 1 in 16 chance of a stone potent enough
To take out the citicorp center
This building is 915 feet high if it's fail they would topple sideways in the Wind
Crashing into other Manhattan skyscrapers
A whole slew of buildings from Midtown to Central Park
Would fall like dominoes
Thing is in real
This brand new skyscraper was on the verge of catastrophic failure
But the imminent disaster wasn't the result of
One glaring oversight
Robert it was a sequence of minor issue
Let's remember how we got here
This building was on stilts
Because they had to build over the church
Instills place at the corners would have been just fine except the church was at the corner of the lot
So the stilts had to be in the middle of each face
And that could have been a okay
Except the offset stilts led lamesha to use an ultra-light Chevron bracing
Which would have been perfectly adequate except in the end
Those Chevron V's were bolted not welded together
And even that could have been fine
Except
No one thought about how vulnerable this crazy design was
Wind blowing at its corners
No one except
An anonymous college student
La measurement
Citicorp chairman Walter wriston and told him
That would need to open up the building
And weld it back together
That is how much is going to cost
I don't think it's going to cost an awful lot
Billionaire 2
That's nothing
Rebuilding the cost 275 minute and if it falls down from he'll make sure when he's team worked with the city code
Bigwigs to coordinate emergency repairs on the bill
With the help of the NYPD
They worked out an evacuation plan spanning a 10-block radius
They had
2500 Red Cross volunteers on standby and
Three different Weather Services
Is implied 24/7
To keep an eye on potential windstorms
They welded through the night and quit they break
Just at the building occupants
Pretend to work
But all this happened in secret over three months without telling anyone who works there
Which is the part of the story I kind of have a problem with
I mean isn't the situation serious enough to Warrant informing the building's tenants
My wife works in a skyscraper in Midtown Manhattan
It's about informed consent
I want her to be able to make the judgment
Quote about whether or not to go work in a faulty building
But The Hobbit made for her
Their thinking was
A contingency plan was in place and ready to invoke as soon as a storm strong enough to blow the building down was in
Striking Distance of New York
Except
It was a giant storm Racing update
Hurricane Ella
The message says the palace at Baywood just hours away from calling in the evacuation
Spit the hurricane in the Atlantic
Of course
And in the end
The public was never notified
And I know what you're thinking
If only there was some kind of independent organization that serves the Public's right-to-know
That might wonder why citicorp Center was aglow with blowtorches all night every night
You know something like a newspaper
Except
The New York Times quiz on strike
Saturday did the New York Times go on strike but all the newspapers in the ward went on strike
Until October
So we had a
Chris blackout
And that was the greatest thing that ever happened
So weird never got out
And construction was finished
And citicorp Center has remained standing ever since
Long enough to be renamed Citigroup Center and lighter
Nothing remains a secret
Almost
20 years
In the early nineties
He interview limiter and broke the story in the New Yorker in 1995
La Mesa weather
To tell the story public
Like you did a mighty which is how we having talking
About this
End
Written up as a textbook
Case of good ethics
In Structural Engineering
New York was spared a tremendous loss of life
Pantheon Elation of it
Skyline
Old Pecos Bill a measure with humble enough
Give time
The inquiry of an undergraduate
Thank goodness this uppity college senior and his thesis and kudos to build a measure who threw his humility
And heroism
Save the Day
Panda
That's sweet of you
Except
Nobody but the couple more things
Let's take a step back
And remember how this story start
I got a call from a spoon they was a real student from New Jersey
Giving him this building to study I do not know the school I wish you would call me
College students
Yum story
With love
History
Play wait for it wait for this moment it's a good one
Here it comes
It would have been sometime in the early 90s
Being upstairs in my bedroom
And had one of my sons
I was sort of hanging off me as I was trying to
Put him down to go to bed
And
Suddenly my husband who have been downstairs
Started
Yelling a little bit
Diane Diane quick quick
Turn on the TV
Your thesis building is on TV
This
Is Diane Hart
As far as we can tell she
Was the student
In the mattress store
And so I holding the baby with one arm I fumbled for the remote and got to the channel
Just in time to hear
This building
Could have killed
Tens of thousands
The extraordinary chain of events began with a phone call out of the Blues from a student in New Jersey
Professor who told him to write a paper on the city
William lamarche
Explain to the student that a telephone call
Professor
I was
A gas
I nearly dropped my baby
This was the first time Diana never heard of the emergency retrofit
Weather monitoring
Evacuation plans
In the involvement of a student
So when she heard lamesha reference
Students
A male student
I of course assumed you know
Gosh
There was some guy
Studying the building as well
And wow you know how could I miss this
Wow
So it was pretty remarkable but I have course assumed at the time that
There was another fellow who
Been a better researcher than I had
In fact I never even considered that she might be
Student in the story
That is
Until she went to Princeton event
Honoring her thesis advisor
David Billington
When I
Showed up at event
David said
Well have you ever heard
Of the problems with the citicorp center
And I said yes
Isn't that pretty remarkable I wonder who it was
That discovered this problem
And you said you know there are very few engineering schools in New Jersey
And
Quite frankly
I know all of them
And I know the heads of the program
Of all of them and I've talked to all of them
There was no other student from New Jersey
That was studying the building
Except for you
So it must have been You by I don't know about any other student
This is David Billington
The thesis advisor
That's my name is David Billington that's correct and I'm an engineer
Respect
53 years at Princeton
Faculty member
I was dying Hartley ceases advisor she wrote the most
Outstanding pieces
Two big volume
NetSpend
To hear Diane Hartley and David Billington
Diane wasn't some in-your-face nodal
Here's her version of the events
So I was 21 years old
And there was a senior
At Princeton University where I was studying
Architecture and urban planning
My thesis
I had
Selected the topic of the
Citicorp Center
In New York
Which had only recently been completed and knocked
She reached out to limit his son to get the calculation
Diagram
And then she tried to replicate the math
Hisself
To do the work again from the start and see if she got the same answer
Tesla motors engineers
David Billington her adviser asked her to ask him about the quartering
The quartering wind I thought that was a problem
And that it should be looked at so I
Obtain calculations from the design engineer
I'm from the measurers off
And I concluded the governing
Loading condition
Was the wind hitting
The corner of the building
The math just wasn't coming out right
I was struggling with the calculations
I assumed
Of course
That the engineer had done the right thing
And any
Inconsistency that I might find
Would be mayor
Back in the building was standing
After all
She was just a college senior
Elementary established
Internationally-renowned
Professional
Structural engineer
Diane got back in touch with the measures firm although she never talked with the measure herself I never called
I never said these things that
That were documented in the in the various reports that have been published today
Diane Tito to Junior engineer the measured New York office named Joel Weinstein
Calculations but at the end of the day no I didn't I didn't feel that I
I had put my finger on a major problem
I assumed I was wrong
And wasn't understanding things
Play it didn't think there was any imminent threat I mean I don't think either of us
Really were in a position to say it
The time
You got to do something bill right away
We didn't have that
Feeling I have the feeling that
She should talk to the designers
And find out
Weather this quartering wind has been considered and
So what is it
What was the outcome
But somehow dianthus cover ain't got silently passed out the totem pole within the measures firm
I said well I better check with Bill
That would have been the logical thing to do and he probably did that
I never heard that you never heard it I guess
Yes we are still one staying the engineer about meeting Diane and what happened afterwards
He says he has no memory of this either way
Diane remember
Speaking to him
Send it
Probably happened
And in such a sick
He would have talked him message
On television
So it could be that's why the measure remember speaking to a male student he was complaining Diane Hartley the student with Joline
Weinstein his own staffer
Now of course it is possible that there was a male
The third man is somehow
The same data
Is Diane and actually did
Hoksila measure on the phone
But I find it really hard to believe that such a person didn't come forward and claim the spotlight after the story broke
Gendercide Diane definitely doesn't fit
Poches student
Chatted about a problem without even recognizing
Significance
What she done
Decades
It's not that I did some
It's that perhaps
What's my questions help
Someone
Figure something
Perhaps my questions were meant to be
I think if I had
Really realized
If there was a problem
Put my finger on it
And raise it up the flagpole
I could Pat myself on the back
Having done
Pretty remarkable
But at the end of the day
I feel like I was a bit
Player
Play
That had a happy ending
So yes she deserves
More credits
You can tell her that
True that I think that that's right
Code up for this
99% invisible was produces sweet by Joel Werner and Sam Greenspan with Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me
Roman Mars
Special thanks to Michael Vergara who wrote the area trust white paper about citicorp Center
Samuel rogovin at the National Academy of engineering problem is trackdown archival audio of William lemessurier
And Alan Bellows of the website damn interesting for talking to me about this.
Who years
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And produced by the offices of arcsin
Beautiful Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If
I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinnerware
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Surprised the family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can keep up with this show and all the people who make this show on Facebook Twitter and Tumblr
I want to see some pictures of citicorp center cut a 99 Pi. Org
Make sure you say that
Play starset
I say this is not architecture
Destructor
Engineering structure
I'm very sensitive about the
I don't want to mix up
These things
So I think that in this case
The measures design
Was a brilliant structural design but it was all covered over typical of Arkansas
The cupboard I wish I could never see it
Most people make that
Decision about
Call Bill
They wanted to be architect
And that's why most of them
So bad but anyway
Prejudice
But what we're talking about is structure.
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com