99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Welcome to the first episode of the kickstarter-funded season 4 of 99% invisible now weekly
From here on out
And I'm excited to announce
The launch of radiotopia
From Bri
A collective of the best story-driven audio shows on the planet
What more information about radiotopia at the end of the show
So thank you all for your generosity and support
We're going to make it
Here We Go Radio.
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The greatness of New York is perhaps most spectacularly seen and its buildings
New York has been forced to build upward
Like the best of these stories
The two bitter Rivals started out
As best friends
William Van alen alen was
It kind of the archetypes of
Architect is artist
He looked at buildings
As art
Anyone to do
And Craig Zimmer
Craig Severance is very much architectus businessman
He looked at buildings as way to make the land pay
They were business partners and as partners
They were
Incredible together
Because you had vanallen as the
Architect
Does artist
And you have
Severance as the business
Making everything run on time making
Work efficient
And together they were able to do quite a bit but they were not just business partners
They stood up at each other's wedding
Van Allen was The Godfather
Stillwater
But years of working together had taken its toll sadly we don't know exactly what this word
Potato Factor was other than the fact that
There were some
Records that I do
Discovered just
What about been on one
Change plans
Continuously
Running over budget
And to someone like severance
That wasn't going to stand and
Relate on plan
Delivering
And
I think the severance at a certain
Sad
I can do this better on my
Telling our story today is Neal Bascomb
My name is Neal Bascomb you wrote a great book about this called
Higher
Historic race to the sky
In the making
Of a city on the author of fire and a number of other
At the time of the Van Allen and severance break up
New York City was undergoing a boom like nothing ever seen before
Massive wealth concentrated on this tiny Island
Turn Manhattan into the most valuable property in human has
Women property gets valuable
We build up
The Roaring Twenties
Stock market
Is going crazy
Real estate prices are going through the roof
A skyscraper is a machine designed to turn land into money
At least
That's out severance
Skyscraper
There were talks of skyscrapers of 12
I mean off the chart
It was a symbol both of the economics
And also
The times made
Culture-wise we want everything
Faster
Higher
Satyr
And so it sort of all came together
Into the sky sky
At this point in 1928 late 1928
Van Allen's career is best
Get out in the basement
I mean he's not getting many commissions
Meanwhile Severance is
Going crazy
He's getting commission after Commission on
Building after big building
1828 Walter Chrysler
Founder of the Chrysler car account
Came to New York City and bought a plot of land and wanted to build with
He referred to as
A monument
Tumi
Allen had already been working on plans for the previous owner of that
In Chrysler decide to hire him to develop that plan
It what would become
The Chrysler
Chrysler I thinking
Was
In his own way revolutionary
Very committed to Art and
Design
And I think saw
A very real way I kindred spirit
Meanwhile downtown at 41
Ben Allen ex-partner Craig server
Was building the Manhattan company building
Ei and Severance
Building was very different
Kida exactly to his personality
The Manhattan company building
Was downtown the Chrysler Building was
Uptown
Severance was an investor in this
This building
It was being funded primarily by
Amanda George ohrstrom Who was
Is considered the Boy Wonder Wall Street
Incredibly rich
Incredibly quickly
And they're building was
In a very real way I was
How to make money
While the Chrysler Building was
Sort of make a monument to what Chrysler had achieved but also
New ground in Ark
At the time Cass Gilbert Woolworth Building
Towered over everything
792 ft tall
What's the tallest building in New York and in true Monument to me fashion
Chrysler set his sights
On his building being taller
And the Woolworth Building
The tallest
In the city
And even though the Manhattan company building didn't quite have the same motivation to be the tallest
To celebrate
One man's greatness
The team decided that they wanted to take
And be the tallest
I think the motivation initially for the Wall Street Building for the Manhattan company building
Is
One because of the cost of land downtown in Worcester
You have to build High
You know got their spreadsheets out and decided
Exactly how high that would be
And then they decided to go a little bit higher to have the in-form otter of the world's tallest building which
When your
Selling office space is something that is real estate agent
You consider hand out a car and says do you want to work
In the world's tallest building
So it was a
Sales tax
As well as an economic
And so the race was on
2x partners
Van Allen with the Chrysler Building
In severance
With Manhattan company building
We're going to battle it out
Supremacy
On the skyline
Initially the Chrysler Building was the first to announce that side
Chrysler and then I'll wait a little bit further along
And so they announcing early 1929 that they're going to
Roughly 822
Star than the
Woolworth 792 a couple months after that
Greg Severance comes out and says we're building
To 840
And then you have this over the course of
Of that year
Tickly that summer even as the buildings are going up
Setting the foundation even as their War during Steel
Then Island and Severance are both changing their plans
Both not knowing what the other person is doing but sure
That
Their respective bosses
Want to go higher
And I think at this point they very much want to beat each other
But it wasn't just a high price
It was also a speed race
At the point in the in the summer of 1929 when both of these buildings are going up very fast
It's it's very much who can
Did the Woolworth Building first hookah
Get out release that first statement saying
World's tallest building
In the public was into it
It was a race
Almost weekly
There were
Newspaper articles
About
This buildings going higher Christ was going to be 900 ft man Company Billings going to be 950 ft
Severn twins premature statements and it was very much covered in the press and in all
Call the New York newspapers of that time which were many
Front page photographs
It was pretty incredible
Pitbulls Chrysler and vanilla we're not content just being the fastest on the toilet
Remember that I'm going into Chrysler's office
Chrysler's on the floor
You know with plans spread out on the carpet
Looking at how the lobbies going
Shut up
Walter Chrysler was very interested in Arden arcade
And so he wanted a beautiful building
A building like none other in the world
Meanwhile at the Manhattan company building they see what's happening on the Manhattan company building is there just adding floors
Thirsty well the foundation will be able to do this if we had four floors if we had 10 floors
We are at the top we can go higher so it was almost incremental movements
Honda Manhattan
On the Chrysler Building they were achieving the last-minute height advantages in two ways
Originally the Dome of the Chrysler Building at Arch Dome was
What's much more
Compact as you see it now it's almost like it's stretched out
And that happened because of the height race
I wanted to find more floors it wanted to get
Tim Moore height
And so that elegant elongated Dome that we love on the Chrysler Building
Was the result of this silly I Rise
But the sneaky masterstroke that ultimately led the Chrysler Building to
It surpassed the Manhattan company building for good
Was the gleaming Spires
Called
The vertex
And that was 185 foot triangular Spire that was built
Inside the stairwell basically the fire
Stairwell
Inside the building at the top of the building
Manhattan company building had no idea what we
What's going on if brought up each
Peace separately up
The side of the building by Derek's
Instructed it inside the fire tower in one day at the Manhattan company building
Finished top.
No chance to add any more floors
Suddenly
Best concealed vertec
From inside the building
And it's better now I'm sad sort of like a butterfly emerging from its cocoon
They put this thing on top of the building
It was 185 ft
Tall and made the Chrysler Building
46 ft
Hi in the tallest structure in the world
Now surpassing the Eiffel Tower
And if you're thinking
This is stunt of secretly riveting a giant metal
Expired 900 feet in the air sounds ridiculously dangerous
You are
Is extremely dangerous I I can't imagine today it not getting approval everyone basically
Thinking from
Chrysler the Van Allen is this thing
The fall
And if it does you going to impale half a street
Armoire
And you can imagine the damage that would have
Now you probably know and can clearly picture the now-classic
Art Deco style of the
The steel-clad arches
Sunburst
Triangular windows
Not to mention the hood ornament
Eagles
And the hubcap freezes
It was made for a car guy
But it's doubtful
That you
Even heard of them and Company
First
Because now it's called 40 walls
Building
But also
Cuz it just never took hold in the public hunting
You know
Curiously the Manhattan company building 40 Wall Street got all the accolades
It won awards
The design was mostly by this Japanese architect
Yasuo Matsui
So we did in a wonderful and in the trade
And it was just basically a fairly Bland look
And then you have the Chrysler Building with this
New Dominus nuvertex something
Really new yorker the world has never seen
It was pretty remarkable stuff
And it was almost Universal
Sleep and it was considered a stunt design
Some people called it a monstrosity know it was
Largely reviled by architectural critics and it was only overtime at the Chrysler Building
Became the sort of
Hazard landmark
That it is and if the story stop there you might think Van Allen the artistic Maverick won the day
The Chrysler Building
What's the tallest structure in the world and even though
Design with Pandora Jewelry we all know that
Eventually got it
Do
But the story
Does not in there
After all this hubbub
Partner against partner fighting for who would be the tallest
Amir 11 months later
The great Empire State Building was completed
And it became the tallest building in the world
For nearly 40 years
Brinkley
I don't care about that so much
What happened next
Was the real trash
The lack of business acumen
That probably contributed to the Van Allen and Severance parting ways
Really came back to buy
William Van alen
He never actually had a contract
With Walter Chrysler to design the Chrysler.
Chrysler
At the end of the the day so I'm not going to pay you your feet
Sweden have a signed contract
It was widely sort of
Considered normal at the time for the architect to be paid
Roughly 6% of
The cost of the building
That sum of money is is what van all expected
What Chrysler was willing to pay
Van Allen ended up soon Chrysler
The newspapers
And
At the end of the day
Cass Gilbert
Woolworths
Came inside you
Yes
Percentages
Typical rate
That's what man on ship
And I wanted that
But then Allen was never given a major Commission
Again
Both because the Great Depression in head
And also because he had now sued his Patron
And that was something
Things that I think
Others
Shied away from
Ben Allen spent most of the rest of his life teaching sculpture
The bozarts Institute of Design
But Severance on the other hand
Continue to succeed
The Manhattan company building
Did terribly like every other office building
In New York at the time but Severance you know when into
The depression and
Got a bunch of government work actually built a bunch
Hangers for
Her balloons and such
And so he did quite well and
Live nicely in
Died in luxury
So that's at least 1/2
But we do have a happy ending the fact that
The Chrysler Building is so sore
Howard Stark
And then Alan we did get the commision of a lifetime
There was no expense spared by
Chrysler
If you ever go into
The Chrysler Building
From the lobby all the way to the
The top I mean
Just
Expense
Inexpensive
Expanse images
Beautiful Art Deco interior work
Wood paneling
Art Deco murals
Just an incredible building
Top
The bottom inside and out
And very rarely do you have
Commission where money is no object
In Savannah on was given one shot and I think he can
Greg Severance was standing in front of me
Think I'd say
I wish you worked it out with Van Allen
You did well
You deserved
I think
You would have been greater
Together
And if I could talk to Van Allen
I'd say
I'm sorry you didn't get the Biltmore great structure
But no
That you created the building
I can stop the most architectural e blind and generally disinterested person dead in their tracks
And they will Marvel
At your accomplice
No
And to Walter Chrysler
I'd say
You
Pay your bills
Deadbeat
I could we could have had another Chrysler Building or something is good
You ruined Van Halen live
Probably not because the Great Depression and all but we'll never know will we
I'm going to need a minute
99% in
Exam Greenspan Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And produced are the offices of parks
Brilliant Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
When we get a little out of hand they sometimes ask us to use our inside voices
What did I say
You should try working next
Snapdeal
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 Pi feet
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
You can find a show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars
Sam tweets at Sam listens every tweets at troubleman
But right now it is the first episode of Season 4 we are going weekly from here on out so now is a gray
Right time to tell everyone you know and love to start listening to 99percentinvisible and everything you need
Baby, 99% invisible fan is available at 99pi.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really Jack
Play superhero in a movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad I'm Evan
Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for a nap
Action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech
Check weight machine even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com