99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Look at that it's like a
Three houses on
Set of stairs
I love those moments when you're walking in your neighborhood and suddenly nothing is familiar
Staircase for a giant I don't want to meet
Giant not that you don't know where you are but
Where you are where you've always been
Seems foreign somehow
Jim before beautiful little streetlow boxing houses
It happened to Sean call friend of the show
Back in the spring he lives in Brooklyn up in the northern part near Queens
Gallagher the comedian
Talks about when you have a kid and you start seeing the world with new eyes
What kind of seeing the World by neighborhood with new eyes
It was
Due to this artist that I was going to meet that's why I was
Walking through the neighborhood and what's his name his name is James Gulliver Hancock
Here we are you told me to meet him at this Cafe not far from where they called Cookie Road
Right on time videos
The old cookie road though not the new one on Manhattan Avenue
And I'm thinking
What do you know about the new one you live in Australia
James
A microphone in hand how are you
But the thing about James Gulliver Hancock is that
Just knows this city
So intimately he did used to live here
From about
2010 to 2012
And back when he lived here in this is why I was going to meet him back when he lived here
He started this
Pretty obsessive little project
That ultimately culminated
Yes so I have the book I'll gret and the name
Of the book
How to say I love
The title is
So earnest
Is
All the buildings in New York all the buildings in New York
That I've drawn so far
It's like what I said
6 year old what is that what it was
It implies that you're going to
Drumore
Sure
I like the first part of the title of mice
So
He's saying he wants to
Show all the buildings in New York
I think he would like to
How many buildings are there in New York
Hunter 2000 building
It would you would probably need to spend a lot more time here
Sure I actually look this up later in the New York City Property Tax annual report of 2011
It said there were 1030202
Parcels but I think Parcels also includes separate condominium and rental units
And then I found myself on the website of something called emporis
Which bills itself as a global provider of building information
And the number it said
Was closer to
720 8452
They're closer to that closed in the book there are only about a hundred
Most of them in Manhattan
But you'd also dry around here in Brooklyn and
Everyone
Bronson
Linda Burrows
Try to mix it up a bit
He's hit every Borough except Staten Island so he did
Draw the fairy
And despite the title these are not all the buildings in New York that he's drawn so far the book is just a sampling of his
Blog of the same name as blogs is called
All the buildings in New York
Lizards map
500 drawings on it something like that
Some of them are just black and white and Wiggly sketches others of these really loving
Color treatment with all kinds of intricate details
Just one per page mostly
A little kid draw superheroes
Empire State Plaza
All the classics but also all these anonymous
Down-at-the-heels ones robbing houses
Synagogue rigorously labeled with the address
53 Pitt Street to 22 West 23rd Street
Monolith
But even the intricate drawings are still kind of
Cartoony
Little squiggles and dots hovering above the rules
Is that the building you're saying
Lookout
Maybe
I mean
Exactly right yes okay so
What's on this project
In different fashions in different cities
I've done all the rain in London in
All the cars in Los Angeles
And all the bicycles in Berlin but
He was just passing through the city's so we didn't dig in like with the building
Looks like it would parachute into a place
And immediately trying to find its noun
The thing that the city was
About in
I'm in Berlin mine I'll be about box Forever on that when I was there ever run out of by Candlebox all over the place
Just focusing on one thing
I'm getting to know that one thing about that place
Trying to record it as obsessively as opposed to
New York was definitely the building
And that's
When I'm going to go when I'm here
I just thought of doing it
James and his wife move home when she got pregnant so they could raise their kid in a place with more than one blade of grass sprouting
I can't even enjoy a blade of grass unless I know there's a Subway Andy book and the blog
Buzz
A big newspaper write-ups and a lot of mentions on the blogosphere including one that due to a glorious type
I said James is on a mission to draw the buildings in New York
A lot of coverage really frames James is a kind of Don Quixote
With a pen okay so how's it going so far
Whittier dream of painting all the buildings in New York
It's going pretty well this is from a segment on Good Day Sacramento
I talked to James by Skype
No it what it what is it this is New York
It's a tough City
There's some people yell at your like why you paid my building what's going on
I know it's
It is New York's that people let you do whatever you want really you know it's a guy drawing on the street is probably one of them
Normal things to say
Go back to my retirement
Does plenty more where things are not around
Is a building just on the corner that I've drawn a couple of times
And what I wanted to do with James
Was go to some of the buildings he drawn and hold up the drawing next to the building
How to see what he sees
I'm only realizing this now but you don't ever get to do that to sit with the artist in front of the thing
That they made into a picture
There are a lot of Brooklyn buildings in the book but I have my smartphone with me so I figured we just call up his blog
The first drawing on his blog is in Greenpoint actually a little apartment complex at 587 Manhattan Avenue
One of a loose Chamblee charcoal sketches
Looks more like an idea for a building
James uploaded that picture on May 20th 2010 you still brand new to the city at that point and this was sort of
In his way of keeping a diary of his time here
It also has a very real pragmatic function
Helping him get around town
That was what I did for the
The project to Mathis
Spice that I did not very well
To myself drawing what's the differ
I mean was it in F
To sort of
Contain I mean like I
Netflix error
I've only lived here two years but
Ain't no I can't stop ya
You can take it all in
Yeah I said it what you trying to like bring the city down to 8 by 11 size so yeah
Turtle
You get a
Much deeper understanding of the plasma. Just
Sit in front of the Cross building in the end by side which I've done but you sit in front of
Roblox assassin
Pfister 811 is it on
And
Danny Way those buildings been become as
Kind of special as the Chrysler
Can I think
I got a drone that before that grocery store with the
The tree
Stories about nothing just that.
He's planning to 97 Franklin Street we walk
Passed it to Greenpoint Ave
Plop down on the bed
James take my phone and Scrolls back on the blog
To another Bodega across the street from where we're sitting
What is this one just
The deli down the bottom it's a similar one to the one we were talking about before
Oh
You really captured it I mean I have to say it's like it's like that's what I like about drawing
Like it's not exactly
Like I might have missed a few things and
This isn't actually that that's a bit further I ever the V down the middle
The windows down the middle
Organic
And it's almost like you've made it more
What it is
Yeah if you bring out its character of it
I can pull up
Oh yeah yeah yeah
Is 144 Franklin Street
An older 3 level apartment building
That's
Lavished with all kinds of intricate design frills
It's one of those places that makes you think
Tuesday
Who decided that this building out of all of the buildings on this block should be so crazily ornate
+ 2
You know they just don't build places like that anymore
Do you do you know ARCA
Architectural terms what do
Call like
That
Filigree
Another
Flowers that
Keep going across
Freeze up top
Cornice
But that's the funny thing because I'm doing this
Largely architectural projects icon
I get off
About architecture and I haven't trained in architecture and I done
Know the times
Outside of
The Standard-Times
So yeah it's hard to
I just appreciate that man
Chatham throttles
I mean I'd never
They have noticed them if he hadn't drawn them
Door if I wasn't sitting there with him
Sitting with James it's like the whole city is a museum
Usually
You know buildings are
Too big
Horseshoe cookie cutter to notice
But because he's drawing every window
Every
Fire escape railing he's eventually going to hit the funny little decisions
Or awkwardness is
That make that building that building
That nobody would notice otherwise
Dentists have a studio in the old Pencil Factory does half a block down
Funny actually the top of it all the way around
Is appointed with
These
Pencils that are vertical it's like an incomplete
Crown going across around the top story just in case you forgot what they were making in there
I mean it's like a 15 B * 15 foot long pencil
I like pencils for a giant
That's the second time you mentioned Giants
Thank you for keeping track
I've done a few on the roof of the building we can get up there
We duck around the corner into this Warehouse he looking Lobby and go right up to the top floor
I love these old elevators
Jog around to the stairwell
GameStop's at a window for a second point something out to me the weirdest thing just under the roofs on the Builder
Wings across the street
Are stenciled
The address numbers of those buildings
See the numbers up until
What's above Earth
Oh yeah
Oh how about that
You would never know it's what it's like who is that for a giant
Just walking down the street
What's up with you in Chinese
Oh man
Oh wow
Amazing app
Brooklyn and Queens
Just like a helipad
A huge roof
Ando and one of the iconic water towers
So yeah the Empire State the Croswell all the classics over there
You know it's crazy like now that I'm looking at the skyline from up here I mean if it feels like because I spent some
How much time looking at your drawings that feels like a drawing as opposed to reality vibrations
The wiggly line
I see someone's perspective that's what I say
I see someone else's perspective
I painted your eyes
Damn you got to say everything is quiet
Explain everything is pastel
Exactly
That's the thing about writing someone's story which kind of what this is I guess it's
Have a different view of the world off the woods get inside someone's head
See that post office affected
Just doesn't happen the band was this time it's in pictures
Yeah I picked up the book again the other day
Just leaving through it for a minute and then walking outside to the
Street
And looking up at the buildings I look up
At all the time and kind of
Hate
Now
I don't know how to say this is like that they seem to fund all of a sudden
What kind of carefully like now they were these carefully made objects
I mean you know that
When you see the care that
Someone put into something and
The Genius of everyday decisions
I think it makes you
Almost packed
Logically
Optimistic
Somebody put care into this
The world is
Better because of it
And I think that
That kind of optimism feeds James I mean it's funny that you say that because like I've been wondering like my see such a happy
Person but I think that's
Do I will say that
Pessimistic little moment they're on the roof
Cuz of course he's not just looking at the city he's looking at the impossible job he's carved out for himself
Makes me anxious that icon
Through it all
Now you look here at this
Amazing view and that's like
That one
I got us a planet
I'm by that one over there
Rosemary's Baby Ghostbusters
Install
Under under the brown with the
The creamy brickwork up with help decorative grain copper roofing
I don't know what that is
Makes me anxious that I'm on I'll get that I want to do it I want to know that one
Makes you anxious why
Cuz I want to
Spend time during all of the different buildings
When you're specially when I'm crossing the bridge it's you say that the law of the land
Do you remember the name of the project
You want to you want to do it then I hear the nine-year-old and they wants to just
Let's do this
But what would it mean if you don't get to all of them are dumb get to the ones that you want to do
Diane unhappy death
Force my son to start drawing
Generations
He's probably going to be
Why do you say that
He's one
Are you already doing Matt's performer in his dad's a drawer
Adele
I can do it every once
That's a good dad thought about it I've only
Yeah something too hot
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Shawn Cole
Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
And we have a new intern her name is Avery droppleman
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa is talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
What about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Five podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but right now
You going to 99 piaa.org and you can look at amazing pictures of all the buildings in New York I've drawn so far
Read my building what's going on that's 99% invisible
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden 2 playlist
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com