99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There Comes A Time in the life of a modern city
Where it begins to grow up
Literally
Ever since Bridge frames were upended into soaring Towers
And elevators were equipped with reliable safety brakes
If there a lot of people in one place it just makes sense
Nebraska Stockyards
On top of each other
Santiago the capital of Chile
Has been going through a tremendous growth spurts and economic boom of the mid-1990s
It happened fast
In just a few years single family homes all over the city will replace with high-rises
It's Daniel Alarcon he's an award-winning author and host of a radio ambulante
I have a friend in Santiago named Rodrigo her office
Well hello my name is Rodrigo
A small part in Santiago's upward Mobility
Which wouldn't be that remarkable he wear an engineer or real estate developer or an architect
Actor something like that
But he isn't
Rodrigo Rojas
Is a poet
Literature professor
How to write poetry
Everyone is a poet
I love your red bologna but it's like poets are chili superheroes
30 writing poetry
No I'm an unimproved
This is the story about rojas's poetry altered the physical shape
Santiago's
Rapidly
Changing Skyline
This is how it work
A developer bought an old house
Had an architect plans for high-rise and then stepped in
And my job consisted on very simple thing
Had to give a name
He worked early in the mornings and
How to get into people's heads
I have to
Walk around a lot
Know the different neighborhoods
And see what color
Patristics
That neighborhood had
And what characteristics
It would
People who
Vine
You looking for
So
People aspired
To be something else
They wanted
So they had a dream
And I had to walk around the neighborhood
Thinking
Kind of dream
That person was
Looking for and a happy device
A name
Phylactery
Rodrigo works for a public relations firm it's one of 10 or so in Santiago that we're doing this kind of thing
As far as I know no other firm had a poet on staff
Little was in school at the time working three jobs to support himself and his family
In the course of a little over a year he named more than 40 buildings all over the capitol
Basically doesn't the little poems he wrote are now embedded into the design of his City
Well to be honest that
I wouldn't confess this in Spanish
ECI
I don't feel quite proud although you might consider as you suggest
My first publication
Baby short poems
But I think it mount
I'm listening to myself as I speak
I think it is it is a story that should be told
Because it's a story of a
Dreams of people
Proud or not he wrote hundreds of building name poems
He conjured the names from myths from history from literature
And even did some field research
What time he had the name a few buildings going up near Santiago's Polo Club
But there was a catch
He couldn't use the words
Polo or Club
So it's not going to a party there to look
Looking for just the right name
The first thing that I learned is that you don't dress
Because he be dressed happier
You just trying too hard
Turquoise coming up with names was just half the job
The other half was negotiating with developer
Yeah I would choose the best 10
Given
A speech
What characteristic
What kind of dreams were behind each of these
10 Main
And they were
I know that what you own until he said their own name
Well and it can also be called
Don Jorge
So yeah not poetry to win Awards necessarily
But like all good poetry some of his work to be transformative
There's just one neighborhood tell yeah I know that's particularly cold and humid
Thanks Rodrigo at now has buildings that make it seem almost trapped
Imagine that to forget the weather
Residents might sit on their balconies
Staring at the slate gray sky
And dream beaches
Surfer names
Cancun
Cancun.
Cancun weather
And the developers was so excited about they said they they bought palm trees
And planted them in front of the
I take it there aren't huge Groves of palm trees and Santiago know there are not
It's not a natural thing to have palm trees in Santiago way have a Mediterranean climate
Granada Caribe
Cancun's were some of the first buildings in the area and they sold really well
So the other developers followed suit so there's a whole neighborhood with names of islands in
And beaches
It looks like
Hawaii
He learned to read the taste of his clients
The meeting
We're usually in the office
Of that development which gave me a lot of
What
What he wanted to be seen
Nssi
One time he went to a developer's office that was just a lousy
Weekly column
Lots of imitation of marble
And everything
Colin even like
Greek columns in order to get to the bathroom and
When they sat down to talk names relieved abandoned all the research it done going in
And he said
How would you like to
That the building gold
Dennis Bethenny
Oh yes
Sparta
Even there's a building called
Olympia Alice
How do you come up with you
I've been working on this fabricated whole story
Services building an identity
Scaffold one story about a ship called the son seba Zanzibar
See you at was a s*** build
Longwood
Most likely small
But the Scentsy bar never sank
Never had it
Survive 2
And it was always known as a
Discrete
And they really like
Sounds
So
It works so well he used it again and again and again
He actually can't even remember how many times you use the same trick
Yeah I can't remember at this time I think I am made up
To see what I made up Normandy
French name
Well this was
What's the competition
It's always the same story
It's a shame
Build to survive
And
When you mix a lottery with
Survival of
Tragedies that's very important for chili
Cuz that's a search of status and the survival of
Earthquake
Edible developer rubbed him the wrong way he's sneaking a joke
There's a building in Santiago name in fantastic Ariane which sounds nice even Noble
Investment children of Kings in Spanish
And Korean
I said oo
Gibson
Prestige sure does
And let you know that the infant has a carry on
One of the most famous epic poems in the Spanish language
And you're not just any villains
There was a real bastard
They raped
A girl in the books
It does is not really something that you would be proud up at the developer he really liked it and and
He wasn't accepting any
Single name
And I was angry and I said okay you might as well call it looking fantastic.
Yes
So there is a building
A name dr. Aziz
Literary rape
But when he wasn't tricking his client
Rodrigo was
Interpreting dreams
That's important because he was naming buildings that hadn't been built yet
Do nothing but drawings on a piece of paper
The name of the last step
Before the brochures to be printed up
And those brochures wear with the buyers took the bank
When they ask for a loan
Open up Apartments were sold the building went up
If not
Project was abandoned
And the entire city was remade this way families taking a chance on imaginary buildings with made-up names
The same process repeated thousands of times in hundreds of neighborhoods
Husbands and wives
Looking at a picture
Reading a poem
I'm taking a chance
And Rodrigo did the same thing
He lives in one of these buildings now
Unfortunately
The name of his building was a decidedly lacking
An imagination
Apartment on Skyline Chili Espana in the district of New York
A building called
Chile Espana
Redundant building
So what if it's redundant
Names or how the anonymity of a places.
Amy building
The name Xavier
Usually in
Timberlands
It has a concierge
The Shining
B-day
Says I live in that rectangular concrete over there
I live in Cancun
The Titanic know you've never heard of it because it never sank
99% invisible whisper
Ambulante
With Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
It's a product of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in Sanford
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinner
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars the right now
We have links to radio ambulante
Which bills itself
As This American Life
In Spanish
Is a couple stories in English would mainly if in Spanish
So if you speak Spanish
You are in luck my friend
And if you don't speak Spanish
I bet this is not the first time
That you are
Filled with regret
About the choices you've made in your life
But I'm more at 99percentinvisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an actor
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com