99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I am walking down hundreds
Towards Manhattan Avenue
I can see the building and
That's producer Jessica Miller
Wandering around her old neighborhood
Oh yeah
So you can see on the back of the tower there's like a smokestack
Or at least the remnant of the smokestack
Just used to live near Central Park and she's been walking by this building and wondering about it for a long time
So she met up with Jim ratzenberger who's done some writing about the building for the New York Times
The address of the building is 455 Central Park West
And it looks like
The castle
Huge it takes up the whole East End of the block
It's made up of red brick
What does intricate Stone trim and it's got
Five or so large cylindrical
Cool turrets
Silver cones on
Gigantic gigantic
I was going to say ginormous
Building looks like something out of a fairy tale
Until like Rapunzel could let down her hair through one of the windows for some knight in shining armor
Bro just wandered over from Central Park
What I found out is that this building's past is not very fairytale like
At all
You want to let just take a walk around the building and see what we see
I saw it coming up around the side there are these things that look like
Smokestack
Kind of off of this Factor
Maine Smoke Stack has been torn down
And it was
Part of the crematorium where they used to burn bodies
Well that took a dark turn
So the building has been renovated but when it was built in 1887 it was the country's first hospital
Devoted solely to the
The treatment of cancer
And they weren't very good at treating cancer yet
So
The crematorium Smoke Stack
It was smoking pretty often
The old castle-like building
At 4:55 Central
Carquest can actually tell us a lot about
The history of cancer and the
History of Hospital
WhatsApp Casino
It's the late 1800s and people seem to know that cancer starts as a tumor and that sometimes the tumor
Mercante be removed
A lot of hospitals in the US don't even want to treat cancer patients
Some people fear the disease they thought it was contagious
Some doctors thought it was contagious
And also
There's a lot of stigma by having the
That's william shatner
She's a clinical associate professor of medicine at Weill Cornell Medical College
And she's writing a book about cancer awareness
On top of misconceptions about cancer being contagious there was another reason that hospitals might have hesitated
Today cancer patients
At the time
They had to publish their death rates
So they turn away patients who are likely to skew the numbers
This is why you had tuberculosis hospitals and other specialty hospitals for diseases that were particularly deadly
In the late 1800s Europe was a bit ahead of the US
In terms of cancer
During and after the Civil War
Patients in the United States who had money or could afford to go to Europe
What do so for care
And
Doctors from the United
States who then in it for the most part had minimal education would go to Europe
Study science and pathology and surgery
One such man was J Marion Sims
Sims went to Europe and learned a few surgical techniques for removing cancer
He wanted to bring this knowledge back to the US where he had worked previously
New York Women's Hospital
And then in 1874 the hospital decided
They wouldn't let women with
For all the reasons we
You just talked about
It was two deadly they thought it might be
Contagious
So in 1884
Simple interest including Elizabeth Cullum who lost her son to cancer and later died from the disease or so
Broke ground on what would become
The first hospital exclusively devoted to Cancer Care
It opened in 1887 and was designed by architect of Charles hate
Earlier I talked about the hospital looking like a castle
From a fairytale
And it turns out that was a
Pretty common style for hospitals
They look like like castles they look like aristocratic mansions
And we see in the architecture that they
They have
Deck the walls they have gate houses they have elaborate entry sometimes
Tourette's
They have
All the trappings
A very very wealthy neighborhood they're very domestic
In their
That's Anne-Marie Adam
I'm sorry I'm Ann-Marie Adams
I'm director of the School of Architecture at McGill University
She's also written about hospitals from the time. And she says that in the late 1800s hospitals were chair
Charitable institutions run by wealthy philanthropist
Where poor people went for care
Rich people still mostly receive Care at home
But Hospital administrators wanted to change that
Architecture
The tool of persuasion
Convince wealthier
People
To come to the hospital
1887 the first cancer hospital opened its doors to both paying and non-paying patients with can
And it tried hard to be an inviting place for paying customers
Even the food was good
So they had great chefs
Part of being
Competitive
Really good food
People went
The hospital dining
To celebrate
Special occasion
Like we might today
Go to a hotel.
Even out for
I saw that
Changed a lot
The cancer hospital for palliative care
In other words just making people comfortable in relieving pain
So
They had champagne parties
They took people on carriage rides in
Park again that's Jim rosson
Play met up with at the beginning
Was a beautiful building and meant to be beautiful
So the people didn't feel like they were going off
A terrible place to die but rather going off to the French Countryside
And the big round turrets with lots of Windows that make the building look like a castle were actually wards
That has page
But the patients were in beds around
The perimeter
And there would be
10 or 11.
And so the doctor would come in and make his rounds from bed to bed to bed
Just make sure you can really picture this the rooms were perfectly circular in about 40 feet in diameter
And an aerial view of the rooms looked a bit like the face of a clock with beds around the perimeter
But the roundworms weren't just about Aesthetics
By having these rounded rooms
Fewer corners
I was thought that you could
Keep the hospital cleaner
You know dirt accumulates and Corners so
Just get rid of the corners
Kind of brilliant
Another distinguishing
Feature of this hospital and of others at the time
Tons of
Any idea was it the open window
What allow
Fresh air
How to flush the
The space between
Patience
And this
Of course played into the idea that
It's sicknesses traveled in
Bad air
This idea that sickness was spread by polluted smelly are was called the Mae eisma Theory
But the weird thing is
By the time the cancer hospital
Was built the miasma Theory had been debunked by The Germ Theory
Which rightly held that.
Diseases spread through germs or micro
The architecture just
Haven't caught up yet
The architectural design of a hospital does
Doesn't always correspond
Exactly
To the medical
All theories of that
I'm almost like
Society is
Hesitating
To fully endorse
Light Airy room champagne parties
Carriage rides
Do the park
It all sounds
Kind of charming
Until we get to the part about how nobody had any idea what they were doing medically speaking
Beyond palliative care the main treatment for cancer at the
The time with surgery
But surgery for cancer was still incredibly
Massive cutting of people with tumors
With the idea of removing every lymph node in their body and as much as possible it could be done won't keeping them alive
Surgery was also hugely risky
This was before the type of antibiotic soap a lot of people die from infections after surgery
But desperate patients
Play Desperate Measures
You know what the doctor said I can take this out of you and it's causing pain
Bleeding you know
People would often agree
The surgery is at the Cancer Hospital in New York as in other hospitals at that time were happening in an Amphitheater so that
That students could watch and learn
There's a show on Cinemax I watch called the Nick but graphically dramatizes he's Amphitheater surgery
Come around that same time.
I want the students to take know the doctor Christensen is answering on the medial line just above the pubis
As you can see there is significant blood in the cavity vacuum
Surgeon from this time we're doing pioneering work and patients were pioneering guinea pigs
We had to start somewhere
But that show makes me so so happy that I live in 21st century
Agreed things were bad
And they stayed bad for cancer patients for
Quite a while
As late as 1920
Only
15% or so of patience
Survived
Cancer diagnosis
For more than two years
Almost everyone died so the numbers were bleak
And
In 1900 the numbers were even worse
Which must be why they felt they needed a crematorium
Decide if you were there and you can look out your window
And see the smokestack imagine looking up there and seeing smoke come out of that Smoke Stack
I would have been pretty awful
Under that billowing smoke the New York cancer hospital soon earned a nickname
The Bastille
It was trying to look like a French Chateau but
It ended up feeling like a French prison
Which is why despite a huge demand for cancer treatment
The hospital couldn't get people in the door
That is the very few people wanted to go to the New York answer
Hospital and what's amazing is that
Good place
Struggled financially Cancer Care
Before 1904 a long time after was not lucrative
The hospital also tried to attract
Send funds by
Procuring a controversial new form of
Radium
For awhile around 1920 the New York cancer hospital boasted the
Country single largest repository of radium
Lori in 1921 in therapy
Understood
It was administered by people who didn't know how to administer it be
Didn't really understand it
A lot of the radiation workers doctors in nursing
Themself develop cancer
It wasn't until the 1930s or so that things started to improve surgery became better the radiation
Woodworking
I think of the 1960s and 1970s then you have
Chemotherapy and
Much more how much more organized approach to cancer
Care and one that ultimately became very lucrative
In 1939 the cancer hospital left Forks
$0.55
Carquest for the operator
Decide
Where became Memorial Sloan-Kettering
Which is now known as one of the best hospitals
For cancer treatment in the US
And of course
Hospitals don't look like castles anymore
After World War 1
Hospital start to look like
Small Civic and
Institutions more like City Halls or
Or schools
They're very square that is called
The block plan
We also see the end of big open Words
With lots of bed
Paying patients could expect
Single room
Or
Typical page
Could being a double room or a room
And we said goodbye
The good food Champaign
And carriage ride
The money was channeled in things like surgical Suite
And in mechanical equipment
And rather than
Decoration
And we see like things like wooden beds and dresser
Pierre everything
Is metal
It has a kind of look at
After World War II the office building / skyscraper
It all changes again and then I
1980s
With the onset of
What we call Payson
Tendercare
For the atrium
These are hospitals that look like shopping malls
Just one or two floors
Big Open Spaces
We not to bury
Kind of capsule
We've done away with completely round rooms now
But the general idea of round rooms being easier to keep clean as actually persisted
So where the wall meets
The floor
If you
Visit Hospital
Today you'll see it probably
Curved
So that nothing could get
Stock in
In the right angle
In the wall in the floor
As for the castle-like building that housed the first cancer hospital.
In the mid-1950s who becomes Tower nursing home
That becomes one of the most notorious nursing home
New York
Is this a place
Terrible things happen
Roaches crawling around walls
Patients being abused
The nursing home was shut down in the
And the building sat vacant and in a state of disrepair for along
Jim ratzenberger used to walk by at in the 80s
Thought it was a
Cookie place
But it was even better than that
The castle
It just seemed to be
Inevitable fall
It was really
Didn't seem to be any escape from that
Because it has gotten so bad
Try to make some
Building
That was New York in the 1980s
In 21st century Manhattan even haunted castles can return to the Luxury Condominiums
In the year 2000 the building was bought by a developer
Now it's
17 condo units
The parking garage a spa a pool and a fitness
The hospital Castle on the park finally became on the inside but it always pretended to be on the outside
A nice place
Rich people
Still got it coming
Hospital food
99% invisible with produce this week by Jessica Miller and Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery truffle
M&M me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced out of the off
Offices of arcsin in open-hearted collaboratively minded Architecture Firm that generously gives us our home
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Show the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and then we discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can keep up with all the comings and goings of 99 Pi on Twitter Facebook Tumblr Instagram and Spotify do you say hi
I guarantee if you just write hi I will write hi back to you on Twitter
I guarantee it
And you're always welcome at our place and 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com