99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the 1980's the United States experienced a refugee crisis
Thousands of central Americans were fleeing brutal civil wars in El Salvador and Guatemala
They were traveling north through Mexico and crossing the border into the US
We covered this history in the show last week if you haven't heard that episode yet go within now
This is part
In response to this Mass migration
A network of churches across the country declared themselves sanctuary
That's producer Delaney Hall
In defiance of federal policy
Some of these churches help smuggle Central Americans across the border
And offered shelter to people who were threatened with deportation
And most of the churches did this publicly
Without trying to hide what they were doing
By the mid-1980s the sanctuary movement had become very visible
And also very controversial
Here's a report that aired on NBC around that
Size of the congregation at St Mary's Church they are hero
In the eyes of the federal government they are criminals who smuggle aliens into this country illegally
The government didn't like the churches were openly Define immigration law and harboring undocumented immigrants
The immigration and naturalization service now known as Immigration and Customs Enforcement or ice
Contended that many of these people didn't have legitimate Asylum claims
The agency's Stance was that many of these migrants had come to the u.s. to find jobs
Not because they feared political persecution
A refugee from El Salvador
Administration contends he and others like him have come here for economic reasons
The young man listed other reasons for fleeing his homeland
Kelly
Misery
And hunger
The US government found itself in a tub
Situation
They could allow the churches to continue openly disregarding the law
Or they could launch an investigation into the movement
And risk public disapproval by targeting sympathetic Church
In 1984 the government launched an investigation into the sanctuary movie
They called it operation Sojourner
A biblical
Call term for Traveler
Oar Wanderer
The goal was to collect enough evidence to indict the leaders of the movement into stop churches from Sheltering migraine
The investigation would eventually raise big question
It's about the freedom of religion and the right of churches to declare themselves
Protected spaces
Free from government intrusion
This is an issue that's playing out in the news again today as churches and other institutions anticipate large-scale.
Deportations under President Donald Trump
On day one I'm going to begin swiftly removing
Criminal illegal immigrants from this country down, demonstrators outside the end
Immigration office in Colorado
Supporting a mother-of-four from neck
Currently
In 2017
Many churches are starting to shelter undocumented immigrants once again
In this episode
We're going to look back at what happened in the 1980s
The last time a big confrontation happened between the federal government
And Sanctuary Church
In 1984 shortly after the government launched its investigation
A couple of new volunteers approached members of The Sanctuary movement
Ask him if they could get involved
Their names were Jesus Cruz
Install a monogram
I thought
They don't fit
The usual Sanctuary volunteer
Profile
They look a little tough
A little
Experienced On the Border
For the average
Volunteer work
This is Reverend John Fife
Back in the 1980s he was the pastor at Southside Presbyterian Church
In Tucson Arizona
He helped found the sanctuary moved
And five said that even though cruising Graham seemed a little different somehow
Wicked policy to Welcome All who said they wanted
Are crucifixes around their necks
And they presented themselves as folks who'd heard about the sanctuary movement wanted to
Be a part of it
Sew weave
Welcome to me
Included them in
Kruse & Graham began attending meetings
And helping transport Central American migrants through the sanctuary Network
They would drive
Folks from
Tucson to feed
Or from
Phoenix to Albuquerque
Phoenix to LA
So they would drive like sun
But is it would turn out Cruz and Graham we're not ordinary volunteers
They were undercover informants
Government had hired them to infiltrate the movement and gather evidence
Cruz and Graham were both former Smuggler
They worked on the border is guide
It's bringing people into the country illegally
Then they been caught by immigration
And they reached an agreement that if they would
Infiltrate us
And inform
The government about what we were doing that that they would not only pay them but
But drop the charges
Against them
The Inez had decided to investigate the sanctuary movement using the same tactics they might use against any criminal smugly
Wing Enterprise
Agency wasn't swayed by the religious motivations of people like rev-5
Here's Allen Nelson then Commissioner of ins speaking with ABC in 1985
If you and I are meeting at a church building to plan to rob a bank and open with a prayer and close with a prayer
I don't think many people would say this as a church service that should be protected
That doesn't exclude them from obeying the walls of the United States
This is Ruth Ann Meyers
She became the ins District director for Arizona in 1984
She didn't oversee the investigation into the sanctuary movie
I meant but she was briefed on it when she arrived at the Phoenix
Yeah I was totally surprised
In my experience I had no knowledge before of a church
Breaking the law and harboring illegal aliens
Smuggling and harboring
Myers says the case was pretty straightforward
These people were breaking the law
The wall of the United States
I'm in favor of skews me where you go by migration but not illegal immigration
I think we have the right
To have our laws and to enforce them
And decide who comes into this country and who doesn't
Cruising Graham along with a couple of other government agent spent 10 months Undercover
Gathering evidence against the sanctuary workers
Their methods would eventually come under public scrutiny
Because they hadn't just
Infiltrated
Sanctuary movement
They were also secretly recording meetings conversations and in some cases church service
When they cry for help these undercover methods truck some people as offensive in over-reaching
Here's Anthony Lewis then a professor at Harvard Law School speaking to ABC News in 1985
What's the message that bother me
I think
Most of us Americans would believe that in America you
Are entitled to a sense of
Privacy when you go into a church maybe privacy of a particular kind you and your God
The state was infiltrating in secretly surveilling churches
In a country where the separation of church and state is a deeply held idea
We reached out to two agents who were involved with the case
Both declined to speak
The people overseeing the investigation at ins. These methods were Justified
I saw the movement as more political than religious
Yes there are many that thought it was
Under the guise of the church
Meaning the sanctuary workers were using religion
As a cover to push a political agenda
And undermine immigration law
And it's true that some Sanctuary volunteers were vocally critical of the American policy in Central America
Some expressed support for the left-wing movements developing their
In fact there was divided within the movement itself about whether their work should be motivated primarily by humanitarian concerns
Or political
Let the beat got to the point where we decided to have a gathering
And
And try to resolve it
But two weeks before that meeting was supposed to happen
The government indicted 16 of the sanctuary workers in Tucson
Including
Rev 5
On January 14th 1985 federal agents swept down
Arresting 63 Guatemalan and Salvadoran refugees across the United States
I'm handing out indictments just 16 of the sanctuary movement
That morning Reverend Fife was sleeping
When he heard someone banging on his front door
And so I got up and I
Went to the door and there were two border patrol age
Is immediate concern was for the refugees that we're staying at Southside Presbyterian Church
Right across the street from his
The only thought that occurred
To me was
I got all these vulnerable people over in the church I need the key
Keep these guys occupied
So I invited him in
Made coffee
Stalled
Every way I could
He read through the entire indictment
The officers have handed him
Trying to buy some time
My
Charges were
Pretty clear in and they were pretty typical
If everyone
They were a number of counts of conspiracy to
Violate federal law
Harboring illegal aliens transporting illegal aliens in 1800
Illegal aliens in everyone head
Different counts under each of those categories
Eventually the border patrol agents went on their way and Reverend Fife and the other leaders of the sanctuary movement world
The situation
They faced an impending high-profile trial
In which they be facing off with the federal government
In the charges against them were serious
If convicted they could spend years in prison
They got to work assembling a team of lawyers to defend them
So is this true basis as I see it for sanctuary
It's very simple really
This is James Brosnahan
One of the defense
The first is religion
And
Many churches many religion
Have as a distinct
Imperative
That you are to assist people who are on the road
And who are fleeing some form of violence oppression
It's the teaching of Jesus
The defense that there was an argument to be made that the sanctuary workers were just acting in accordance with their face
Not only that the lawyers believed the religious rights of the sanctuary workers had been violated by the gov
German agents who infiltrated their churches
Android secret recorder
And that's intimidation of people who are pursuing
Their Bible studies
Eric Church
The second part of the defense's argument had to do with Asylum law
The law provides that when a person shows up at
The Border
And they are fleeing certain
Specific kinds of Oppression or violence they have a right to come in
And one that is true and that can be established in an immigration
Court that person
Is entitled to
The stay in the United
States
That's Asylum
As a defense team research the laws they started to believe that their clients hadn't really violated the law at all
They thought the US government have
I did research
How the United States government was handling
Asylum applications from people from Central America and I also researched international law this is
Ebates Butler the Third
Another lawyer for the sanctuary Valen
And I was appalled by
What I discovered about how the United States government
Was systematically it seem denying
Asylum applications from Central America
This was all happening in the context of a major shift in US Refugee policy
Before 1980 the US approach to taking in refugees had been expressly political
It gave preference to refugees fleeing communist countries and countries in the Middle East
In 1980 President Carter signed the refugee act into law
Why was supposed to create a fairer system
By adopting a more humanitarian non-ideological definition
The Refuge
It use the criteria developed by the United Nation
Which identified a refugee as anyone with a well-founded fear of persecution
Based on race religion nationality social group
What political opinion
Even though these new criteria were in place when Reagan came into office
The lawyers for the sanctuary workers believe the government was not following its own law
They thought ins was turning away large numbers of el Salvadorans and Guatemalans
Who should have qualified as political refugees
Butler had been skeptical of the sanctuary movement when he first learned about it
But his research had changed his mind
And so I moved from
A position of well this is all fine and dandy in this is the religious thing to do
But it's illegal
I moved from that position to its
Lawful to help these people in the United States government that is
Violating the law
Dependents and their supporters March to the Federal Building in Phoenix for the first round of Arrangements this morning
Charges transporting aliens illegally harboring them and conspiracy
Play the not guilty they were released without bail their trials were set for April 2nd
The sanctuary people say those trials will be a major test of religious freedoms in this country
This afternoon in
After months of preparation the defense team was feeling confident
They thought they had sympathetic clients a good amount of public support
A compelling legal argument
Here's a rev-5
Our position
Oh we welcome
The opportunity to make that casing
And we think we're going to
When
In a slam dunk
But then very early on
The defense team faced a major step
Lead prosecutor for the government was a lawyer named Arnold Reno Junior
And one of his first moves was to file a series of motion
Asking the federal judge who is hearing the case
To limit the arguments the defense could make
And then the federal judge who was hearing our case ruled that we couldn't say anything in our defense
During our trial
About 5 subject
United States refugee
International Refuge
Conditions in El Salvador
Conditions in Guatemala
Or religious faith
So
That wiped out
Our entire legal
Position
What
Nothing was
And
The way my attorney explained it was
Well federal judges in
Criminal
Prosecution
Have enormous
Power
To exclude
Evidence
Did they
Believe
Is not relevant
To the
Charges
Better Bean
Filed against the defendant
The judge and effectively reduce the case to its most basic level
Had the sanctuary worker
Engage The Conspiracy to smuggle in Harvey
Undocumented people
Yes or no
There was no discussion about contacts
History or motivation
One of the defendants was a man named Jim Corbett
Along with rev 5 he'd helped to found the sanctuary move
Corbett died in 2001
But in an archival interview
Describe the situation that the defense team found itself
He said it was as if a man was driving late at night
In freezing weather
Is car breaks down so he goes to a nearby house
And breaks in
And then is discovered
And rocks
Trial
And the judge
Rules out any evidence that would indicate that
It was 40 below
His car had
Gone bad he had stop
Went to the only house in the area
And edit it
Without understanding the context
Jim thought there was no way the jury could understand why the sanctuary workers had decided to shelter Central America
In terms of the necessity defense were talking about something very similar with people fleeing torture in the murder in a very
Contacts
About to rule out the ability to refer
To that
Necessity
Simply makes a mockery of the law
The judge named Earl Carroll
Died in early February of 2017
We requested an interview with prosecutor Donald Reno Jr but he still a trooper
That
Necessity
Simply makes a mockery of the law
The judge named Earl Carroll died in early February of 2017
We requested an interview with prosecutor Donald Reno Jr but he still an active litigator
For what's now known as Immigration and Customs Enforcement
The agency declined our request
But he was featured in the news report from 1985
And he describes the sanctuary movement as
Quote an alien smuggling conspiracy
Induced
Anchorage
Smuggle
Transport and Harbor illegal aliens
The government says that's not much different from drug smuggling
Together over the next several months the prosecution laid out its case against the sanctuary worker
Relied heavily on testimony from their undercover informants
Reno characterize the sanctuary movement as a smuggling operation
Pure and simple
The defense team tried to undermine those accounts in cross-examination
Sneaking details about context and motivation when they could
But in most ways
Their hands were tied
And when it came time for the defense to present their case
They declined to put anyone on this day
Today the defense rested without questioning or single Witness
Jury deliberations could begin next week
It is alleged
The sanctuary jury deliberated for more than 48 hours
Spread over 9 days
On May 1st 1986
16 months after the indictments in more than six months since the start of the trial
Jury filed into the courtroom to read the verdict
Of the eleven Sanctuary workers who went to trial
Read work with it of all charges
8 more found guilty
Including rev-5
Which head Bates Butler
The lawyer
Really hard
After the jury came in I was so disgusted
Whistle system
Now that I have worked in for so long I didn't know part of it
Then we were so upset
Better government
In our court system
Had
Cast aside our clients
With her moral positions and then we felt like the government
And of course were bankrupt
The system was bankrupt
But the other defense lawyer James Brosnahan
Had known there were significant hurdle
They needed to over
You know juries are very good but they come in to the box with their own attitude and the attitude is
People just can't come over the Border
You got to do that you got to pay the price
Ruth Ann Myers of the ins
Thought the verdict was fair
The people that worked in the sanctuary movement did not present those people to
Immigration officer
They smuggle them into the US
They gave them
Quote sanctuary in their churches
They did not follow the law
Next
Can the sentencing by the judge
We really were worried that the judge was going to put them in
Prison my attorney told me
Take a toothbrush in your hip pocket
When you go to sentencing
Because they want you bad
So I had made arrangements
With the congregation and with my family in
And everything
Expecting to go to prison
And much to our astonishment
He sentenced all of us who
You were convicted
Two five years probation
The judge gave them relatively lenient sentences
Considering they've been convicted of
Some cases
Felonies so we were relieved at that point
I think
I don't know what he said but I thought that if he
Gave these nice people to jail term
It would be awful
Publicopiniononline
And I think he had some some senses that might be true
Many of the sanctuary
Workers including rev-5
Went back to their communities and continue their work in the same shoe
Churches continued Sheltering
Volunteers continued helping p
People across the border
Many of the sanctuary volunteers had made
Clear in their closing arguments in the trial
But they wouldn't stop doing the work
The government may have sent
John 5 and 7 other Sanctuary activist
But it is hardly silence them nor stop
7 from a cross-country Crusade
At that point of the government just back off I mean they must have known that you were continuing to do exactly
Play what they just tried you for
They backed off us here in Tucson
But they tried one more trial
In New Mexico the government charged a man and a woman who were part of the sanctuary movement for transporting undocumented immigrants
And the jury in that case
Found them not guilty
And if that point
We knew
That the movement had
Grown
To the point where juries would no longer
Sanctuary
Not long after the criminal trial attended a group of churches and Refugee Rights organizations filed a class action law
Lawsuit against the government
They alleged among other things that the government had engaged in discriminatory treatment of Asylum claims made by Guatemalans
Salvadorans
In 1990
The government settle the lawsuit
They agreed to
Give everyone it was here without documents from those countries
Temporary protect
Did status work permit
And agreed to a whole series of reforms of the paleta
Nicolas Island
So we essentially
Began to wind down the sanctuary
But even though the churches were slowing there were
The whole idea of sanctuary was spreading
College campuses cities counties even holes
States began to declare themselves anxious
And not just for refugees fleeing
Persecution
But for undocumented people more Broad
This accelerated through the 1980s
Has continued up
2 today
But what exactly Sanctuary means
Varies from place to place
Anything you want
That's part of the problem
Dad eats
He said he is probably a little bit different
Once again lawyer James Brosnahan
Usually
The local
Authorities police
Sheriff
Will not assist you in the deportation of undocumented people
In some places police aren't allowed to inquire about a person's immigration status
Or to give that information to the federal government
In other places all residents are promised access to city services regardless of their immigration status
These policies can be son-in-law or they can just happen in Broncos
President Donald Trump talked a lot about Sanctuary cities during his campaign
And he's pointed to murders committed by undocumented immigrants as evidence that Sanctuary cities should not exist
He's threatened to pull Federal funding from cities that identify as sanctuaries
And he's also promised to accelerate deportation
In response
Churches are once again shelter in PA
I think a lot of congregations Across the Nation are struggling with what will it mean to be faithful to the mandates of our faith
Face underneath the
Administration
She's the current pastor of Southside Presbyterian in Tucson the church where the sanctuary movement began in the 1980
Cheater congregation provided Sanctuary to a couple of people were threatened with deportation during the Obama Administration
They're now having conversations about whether that work will expand in the next few years
I mean I can't ignore the fact that my predecessor John 5 was indicted
For doing the work that I'm doing right now
And that he was looking at 10 years in prison
I try not to think about
But you can't ignore that
Since 2011
Churches have had some protected status
Sanctuary
And that year Immigration and Customs Enforcement
Under President Obama
Issued a memo
It said that some sensitive locations
What's require special consideration
My immigration
The government has said we won't
Enter into those sensitive locations
Dream situation or we have higher levels
Approval
Hello sensitive locations are houses of worship
Hospitals in
School
But that practice isn't codified into law and could easily change
Recently there have been reports of immigration agents targeting undocumented people in hospitals and schools
Churches
Might also be vulnerable
That's going to have to be worked out
Through a number of
Of institutional decisions as well as Court decisions
Well well into the future
What's going to be the result
5 years
Will see no one knows
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Delaney Hall
Wish reviews
Avery trufelman
Edmund Fitzgerald same Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Katie mingle is our senior editor
Cole said is the digital director intern Mazza is our office manager
Sean real compose original music for this episode with additional music by okay akumi and melodia
Thank you to Miriam Davidson the author of convictions of the heart for letting us use tape of her interview with Jim Corbett
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 99
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but the
Doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can meet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 p.m.
We're on Instagram and Tumblr to put the Nexus of all things 99 PMI is at
99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com