99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When people ask us where we get our stories from
The answer is usually hard to pin down
It could be something one of us noticed walking around
Or something a friend mention
Some forwarded link on Twitter
It's nearly impossible to say where inspiration comes from
Nner
It's a long way from the seed of an idea to its execution
The brilliant architect Alvar aalto put it very well in an extended metaphor about a fish in a stream
He wrote
Architecture and its details are in some way all part of biology
Perhaps they are Princeton like some big salmon or trout
They're not born fully-grown
They're not even born in the city or water where they normally live
They are born hundreds of miles away from their home grounds
Where the rivers narrow to Tiny streams
Justice it takes time for us back a fishpond to mature into a fully grown fish
So we need time for everything that develops and crystallizes
In our world of ideas
This is a story about one idea born hundreds of miles away
Cinnabar off stream
An idea that would travel
From northern Europe
To Southern California
Or it would take on a whole new life
Before making its way back again
It's a story in three parts
By producer Avery Shuffle
Part 1
California
Two skaters in a plaza are confronted by a guard
Can't skate here
Oh man it looks so good
Just one broken leg please
It's kind of a Pity that skateboarding is banned in so many places
Because skateboarders appreciate the small details of architecture more than anyone
They recognize the quality of concrete
The Greenwood
The incline of a stroke
They recognized the way of landscape
Flo's
Start biking
My name is Jake Phelps I'm the editor at Thrasher magazine from San Francisco California born and raised
What are you got
Thrasher is a skateboarding magazine that skaters called the Bible visiting its headquarters is kind of surreal
It's like if you went to a skatepark and yelled at to all the pugs hey you guys want to go hang out in an office
They're all there
Sneakers and beanie caps
Lunch behind monitors like caged animals
You can tell they rather be skating costumes of my life
I don't wear Louis Vuitton clothes and fitted them and I wear sneakers
And this is the way it is we were utilitarian we skate
It's the greatest thing in the world
Jake Phelps is 55 years old
Tattoos all over his arms
Big stick glasses over his face and close-cropped gray hair
He blatantly hits on me in the interview and invites me to his punk band show over the weekend
I don't think he'd mind that I told you that
Skateboarding never says no
Girlfriends
Jobs life people always say no can't do that
I've been doing this for 40 years you can't tell me a joke
State of Kuwait
KFOR News
You know it's like
Extension of me
It's like the dark
It's something you have to understand
So what is
Where does the artist
It's your whole
You want to see how you how you
You hold yourself
And that is why I love you
That sort of
Badass devil-may-care attitude that skaters have perfected
That's kind of funny because skateboarding
Was pretty dorky back when it was just getting started
The very first skateboard was called the skateboard scooter
And it was a scooter
This is Stacy Peralta
Skateboarding Pioneer and director of the excellent documentary Dogtown and Z-Boys
Which is all about the birth of modern skateboarding
CC says at some point no one really knows when but someone knocked the handlebars off the scooter
I just rode the board
And probably emulated surfing
And so what happened was
Skateboarding had a very very brief
Appearance in 1960
4 + 65
Skateboards were sold in toy stores
And skateboarding briefly became a fad
But then as quickly as it started
Died out again
It was like a hula hoop
It has come and gone
As a skateboard fad was receding into the distance
Stacy was growing up in Venice Beach California
Was the early 70s and Stacy was a little surf rat with long blond hair
I'm on the waves were bad in the middle of the day
Guinness friends wanted something to do what we really wanted to do was emulate surfing
They wanted to surf
On land
And they discovered old skateboards
One of my friends his older brothers at skateboarding in the very early 60s
And they had two skateboards left in their garage that they never touched
So we started riding those boards
Early skateboards
Hard clunky wheels made out of clay or Steel
Eat dirt if you ran over a pebble or a penny on the ground
Indictment Rick Saturday very simple like
I can stand up straight or I can balance on the tip of the board
Maybe a wheelie
You could just kind of scoop back and forth
On a flat smooth surface
Flatland tricks
That's basically what you could do
DC was really young like maybe 7 years old
You can remember skating for the first time
Even with those big clunky clay wheel
Little Stacy found
A blissful Stillness
It was so profound that
From that point forward
I needed to get back on that board and find that Stillness because
I'm more relaxed when I stand on a skateboard that I'm when I walk
What season is friends were discovering skateboards while the rest of the country was forgetting them
Stacy had that old board heat on Earth then his friend the garage after I wore that out there was no more boards
Casino that I can buy in stores
You couldn't buy a skateboard back then so instead
Cece and his friends
Thrift store
And buy a pair of roller skates
Which had clay or metal or hard place
Classic Wheels
And maybe
Stacy would take the left skate and his friend would
Pick the right skate
And then cut the bases out the wheels and put them
Are plank of wood
And then ride that back and forth and back and forth and back and forth and back and forth for hours
And the hours that we spent doing it would be equivalent to a kid today you know jumping up and down for 8 hours in a pogo
You know every single day 7 days a week and
You probably goat cheese
Maybe we should tell this kid that there's no future in this
Then in the early 70s invention comes along that would revolutionize skateboarding
The urethane wheel
This soft plastic will have more give to it and held the ground
Unlike those clunky dangerous claywheels leprosy today
These soft Wheels were intended for roller skaters at the dawn of the roller disco era
But a small company called creative urethane begin producing urethane Wheels
Pacifically
4 skateboard
Surf shops
Hunter Werner skate shop and they were advertised in Surfer magazine
Anime summer of 1974 sales of urethane Wheels went
Gangbusters
Suddenly we had a wheel that could grip
And I could roll over bumps in Little Rock's
A little louder us to attack terrain that previously were not we were not able to attack
Now they could skate all surfaces
Greater Los Angeles was theirs
Claim it so that means School yards that meant in garages City buildings it was any place
Anything was rideable
But none of this was designed for us
None of it
These young kids were jumping fences and trespassing breaking things
On search of new surfaces to ride
They were reinterpreting the city around them
Finding the beauty in the pavement and the concrete
And then
In the mid-70s
There's a drought
In California
In Southern California
Brush fires
Some of them big
And expensive
Aurora fires with
California
Favorite
Right now
Worcester State
The drop was so bad in the 70
That the water company ran billboard ads
Did encouraged
Couples to shower together
To save water
And the further save water
People didn't fill up their swimming pool
And in Los Angeles
There a lot of swimming pool
And they're very
Thinktiv
What we had in Los Angeles if we had the big
Beautiful voluptuous shapes
That you did not see anywhere else in the world that you find in less
Except in very very very very small quantities
The pools of Los Angeles are shaped like peanuts
Like Keyhole
White kidney beans
They have
Curved
Undulating edges
There paved even smooth concrete with gently varying rounded depth
Look back up to the lip
And
During the drought in the 70s
They were all
Auntie
They were
They just
We're so beautifully conceived and designed and
We fell in love with the shape
Stacy and his friends with a hunt for pool
They find a house under construction or Patrol the fancy part of town where they knew they'd find the most sumptuous
Luxurious pool
Tony
They have the fence they break in
There's a little bit of old dirty water in the pool they drain it out themselves
Buckets they brought or trash cans a pound or eventually
They bring an industrial vacuum along with them
And then
Up and down the pool
They go so fast they could go up
The wall
Escape like they were surfing a wave
When we finally got to write swimming pools
And feel weightless
Like going up a vertical wall
Weightlessness is pretty extraordinary
Skateboarding became a form of choreography
We're trying to do as much as possible in The Limited space of the
I'm a graceful while doing it
Here we were a bunch of Scruffy kids
And here we are riding in Backyard Pools and we know what we're doing is beautiful and we get to feel beautiful
And this beauty attracted attention
Back in the first wave of skateboarding in the early 60s
There'd been a magazine called simply
Skateboarder
It went out of business from skateboarding fad died out
But in the mid-70s
The magazine came back
And it featured
Stacy and his friends
Riding in backyard
Deadpool's
At that point every kid in America and all over the world wanted to get inside a swim
That was that was the Holy Grail
Instilled the drought
Really acted as a wonderful midwife
To the skateboarding
Eventually Stacy and the other skateboarders got so good at pool skating
They were able to
The up
Over the edge of the pool
Do you kind of jump up up in the air and maybe do a spin or something before dropping back into the pool
Annie's aerial tricks
Let's do another genre of skateboarding
So style became less important
An extreme Maneuvers became more important
Aerial tricks pave the way for the X game
Half pipes in Tony Hawk
This whole chapter of the sport where skaters were trying to vote themselves really really high up in the air
And that can all be traced back
To the rounded
Biomorphic pools
Los Angeles
The ones shaped like peanuts
And keyholes
And kidney bean
La was
The backyard pool Mecca
But not just
The backyard pool Mecca the properly beautifully-designed backyard
And I don't know of any place in the world
That has that proliferation
Of that kind of voluptuous sensuous design
Pools of Southern California
And their proliferation
Led to the proliferation of skating
More people are skateboarding now than ever
List the 7 billion dollar industry God damn
That's Jake Phelps Thrasher again everyday people skating right now people just saw somebody just broke their arm in a
Pool right now
Trust me
In the pools of California bring us to our next
Do you know the story about like where the bean-shaped will comes from
Being shape has to be in shape but I don't deserve the right any kidney
Well yeah
No colored bean-shaped obviously would be
Some esoteric designs of someone's backyard
Well Jake Phelps
Doesn't have to be all like that about it but he's right it starts with one esoteric design in someone's back
But it might be the most famous private backyard in 20th century American history
Part 2
Sonoma
On top of a remote Hill in Sonoma County in Northern California
The end of a long curvy dirt road
Car
Pulls into a driveway
Three small dogs rush hour to me
Original
Got a little lost
Sorry we overshot it a little bit
Justin fazioli and Sandy Donnell are the owners and caretakers of this property
Which is known as the Donnell Garden
It really famous in the world is landscape
But if you want to visit it it's kind of challenge
You can't find it on Google Maps
That address is wrong
And there aren't any public listing for sites with contact information for it
Because it's just a private home
Amara size retro modern looking house on a hill
It was Sandy's parents place
Minecraft on The Dental Ranch property
Born in 1951 the youngest of three children
The Donnell Garden was planted in 1948
He was revolutionary
At the time
Traditional Gardens of the early 20th century
I've been more or less symmetrical Rose a different kinds of flowers
They're kind of like plant museums
Maybe accented with a geometric heads or a fruit
The Donnell Garden is nothing like
It's mostly lawn
The lawn is
A unifying feature
Help me understand who everything
It becomes the river the Green River
That goes from space to
Space Garden looks like a
Sea of clean cut grass
The floating islands
The tropical plant clusters
Groups of rocks
In a few ancient oak trees
And there are a large swaths of concrete
A big wooden deck
From above the garden is almost like a
Cheese collage
Arrangement of
Abstract shapes
On a green grass
The most distinctive shape
Of course
Is the pool
Oh my God there's the
Picked up your search
A kidney pool
From what we know
Was the first kidney-shaped pool in California
If every bit as beautiful as
I thought actually
It is bright pristine electric blue
And in the center of the pool is an abstract
Sculpture by adaline Kent
Which has two holes through
One above water
1 below
And you can swim through the holes in the sculpture like a dolphin and it's insanely fun
I know
Because I tried it
Pool Overlook Acres of Dusty Ranch and property
You can hear the hum of cars on a racetrack off in the distance
And you can see the hot tub skyline of San Francisco
Grooming hazel-e Beyond
I can help but think that is skater wood
Kill to drain the pool
Beautiful
Wow
It's hard to overstate the importance of the Donnell Garden
Formal landscape architecture and everyday American backyard
Sandy Donnell told me that a picture of the garden was in the Encyclopedia Britannica under landscape architecture
The property also helped create what we think of as the modern Suburban backyard
The lawn
Deadpool
I would guess with the exception possibly of Versailles
The
The Danelle Garden is probably the most published
Garden released in the 20th century
Architectural historian Mark Tribe
The garden was designed by Thomas Church
A landscape architect who wanted to create outdoor spaces that people would use and love
The title of Thomas churches book was actually
Gardens are for people
In Garden Surfer people he asked hypothetical clients how much do you really like to guard
If you don't want a garden that you didn't get another Paving makes a lot of sense
Church said that Gardens didn't necessarily have to be those traditional rows and rows of
Flowers
And this was a revelation for modern families like the Donald
They wanted a place for parties and relaxing lounging
They wanted their yard to be a piece of
Functional art
But their kids and dogs
Clamber on
The Donnell Garden became the epitome of outdoor California life
Throughout the 1950s lifestyle
Sunset
House beautiful
Feature the Donnell Garden on there
In many ways it it became the icon
Certainly of American modern landscape
A lot of it being of
Of course
That's why we're here for the swimming pool
Images of the Danelle Garden began to spread
Newly-minted suburbanite
Lacrosse Southern California
Begin to imitate it
And West Coast landscape architect
Text for inspired by its creative use of
The paving
And Lawn
And it's beautiful
Biomorphic
Kirby pool
The pool inspired thousands of imitators and eventually thousands of young skaters in Southern California
Now we can't know for sure exactly where Thomas Church came up with the idea of using the original kidney shape
Retro Boomerang shapes were appearing in everything from fine art
To mass produce textiles and formica Tables by 1947 the shapes we are everywhere
Another one
Everything and every
So it's really hard to say
But
There's a really interesting and widespread Terry about where Church got his inspiration for the kidney pool
Skateboarding came to my neighborhood like
Night at the end of
1980s
We got little bit of flak magazines and videos coming from from the California and seeing
Part 3
Finland
Avery Joplin actually went to Finland
Videos
The skaters in
The first ones came like when some
Shameless dad went to
$60 business trip sisters and then they April
Brought back some videos
Jonas REO grew up in Finland
Watching videos of California skaters
He caught the bug
A big way
He started skateboarding
And then became sponsored and started skating in cities all over the world
True skateboarding I fell in love with architecture and Design
Young and went to University and studied architecture
I have more control over the space is he skating
I'll just like
Sneak into that business on
I won't tell anyone that I'm scared and just make sure that the handrail is scared of the stairs
Have a good give good material
And Ferb
In architecture school Yana distinctly remembers a lecture he heard
About the origins of the kidney pool
There was a professor coming from California
She was having lecture and talkin about the Donnell Garden
I think she was saying that it's the
Mother of all
Kidney pools
You know about another kidney
It's actually a grandmother of whirlpools
Finland in middle of Finland
It was designed by an architect and designer
Name all of our Alto
Alan Alda
Where can his life was
Exceptional in that sense that he was a Pioneer in
Cross-disciplinary
Thinking on that
Design this is Auntie Oliver
An architect and Vice President of aalto University
Which is named after Alvar aalto
He designed the model
Furniture
And also he had a flourishing business
Alvar aalto is the man in Finland
Bust of him everywhere
He designed a lot of the public and government buildings in meeting halls in Helsinki
Ann Oliver Altos Furniture is in I kid you not
Almost
Every
Single
Building
Almost every home has
Samsung design
Also is beloved and venerated Beyond Finland to
Frank Lloyd Wright loved Alto and he hated other architects
Frank gehry also cites also is one of the only other Architects that he admires
Alvar aalto Was An Architect architect
At his work helped create a unique finish
Aesthetic
Which was an important part of developing a unique
Finnish identity
Because Finland is a relatively young country
Test for about 500 years part of Sweden and then for one
Yes part of Russia
There are two movie theaters in California that are older than Finland
It was only in 1917 that Finland became independent
Before that it was Russian
It looks like it
The architecture in downtown Helsinki is unexpectedly Regal intimidating
The buildings line the streets like towering pastel cakes
With white ornate
Trim
Helsinki has stood in for Moscow and Leningrad in a number of films
And I at the end of 19th century became very important to create our own national identity and try to
Get independent
Finland wanted to step away from Soviet romanticism
Especially because the rest of Europe was experimenting with a new
Approach called functionalism
Functionalism was a reaction to the dirty nasty polluted cities of the 19th century
Which were loaded down with extra trim and ornaments
Statues
Functionalism
Was like an architectural cleanse
Functionalist wanted to be a healthy dose of sunlight
Are between buildings in phosphorus
Think of the sharp lines and
Steel and metal of the German Bauhaus
Are the pristine concrete of Le corbusier
Functionalism
Is clean
DMX
Stock
Spacious
Modern
And a little sterile
So
Ulta was influenced by functionalist ideas
Who wanted to humanize them
Adopting
Discount of international influences
I'm making his own version
That
Aldo's architecture was
Was crisp and functional
A little more natural
Raw and organic
And
He did this in part by using a lot of wood
Midwood behave in ways
Bending and blowing
And you wake this is jonas malmberg
Architect an art historian with the alto Foundation
Where are we you describe where we are
Show Business
Honda
Also the
Office
Jonas showed me the legs of some chairs and stools out there had made
And talked about Altos patented method for bending and curving wood
This method allowed also to make
Curvy molds
Make these wavy glass vases
He became famous
Blown in.
Timber Mall
Earthquake at a bit different than any new shapes for a curved made their way into Auto stairways
And walls and he made
Curtain partitions to break up space
And he used rounded tiles and undulating countertops
Is it fair to say a lot of the curves he just made cuz he
Could like you figured out how to do it and he was just getting with it
And then he would have wanted
Toshiba he wanted to buildings
To be kind of
Something that you can't really predict
So when an art collector and lumbreras nimri gullikson asked alter to design her country home
Villa mairea
Also wanted to keep it very start and clean
Loss of a friendly in natural
And we don't have their like any expensive material
Justin Bieber in the floor
Frederick on the wall we don't have any any
Material that would be posh
But of course in Finland
If you're going to have a Country Villa
You're going to have a sauna
Autoflower finish
Bending two-timing
Peru Countryside
China culture and if you're going to have a sauna
You need a pool to cool off in
Ann Oliver Alto
Made a pool
The very curious shape
Preformance
Maybe a sock
With curly ends
The Story Goes that Thomas Church
The California landscape architect who designed the Danelle Garden
Went on a trip to Finland
With his wife Betsy
In 1937
Somehow they found out the address
Alvar aalto is home and studio and got themselves
And they just knocked on the door architectural historian Mark try it again when The Story Goes also came out in his bathrobe in it
Invited them in and Sir Thomas Church and his wife Betsy and Xarelto and its first wife I know all really hit it off
And they got to be good friends
Quite possibly the case
The Altos design for the villa mairea
And it's Akshay
Pool were displayed in his Studio
When Thomas Church
Visiting
Miter was finished in 39
But they were there in 37
Maybe it was on the drawing boards and maybe there was no pool at the time I mean we just just don't know
There's no way to verify
But that's the
Story Architects tell
There's a book about the Donnell Garden
Probably going to have a mention
The Villa Maria
Yeah The Story Goes that Summers Church went back home then it was
1948 when the Donnell Garden
Was made
Almost Ten Years After and then the Danelle Garden Pool becomes famous
Appearing on magazine covers and inspiring hundreds of imitators across Southern California
And he's hundreds of curvy biomorphic pools get emptied out in the drought in the 1970s
And inspire a whole new skate culture
And that culture-inspired kids around the world like Jana to take up skateboarding
And skateboarding inspired Jana
To become
An architect
And now
He has a specialty
Yeah I'm going to the skatepark Tucson already feeling
He designs curvaceous pools
All over Europe
Pools
Exclusively for skating
That's one big pool coming to the Eastside of Helsinki
It it's it's not really nice figurine
That's something to be proud of
I think when Jana says he's proud
Jeneane's at Publix
Skateparks in skate pools
Should be a source of civic pride
Especially in Finland
Where
Ian Alexa
Modern skateboarding
Began I kind of use it as a joke when when we are out
Which skatepark builders that usually from States or Canada and try to claim skateboarding for
Having its roots in Finland
Some say that Oliver Altos pool at the Villa mairea
Was inspired by the soft bends in a Finnish Lake
Or maybe also was just excited about his ability to make wavy forms
Since that kind of became his signature in his furniture and homewares
Who knows maybe he was inspired by a some other curvy pool somewhere else in the world that we don't know about
Although didn't like to talk about his inspiration
She didn't write too much about it either
Although only talked about the birth of his ideas
Anunnaki
Ended metaphor
Betta fish
Manestream
Architecture and its details are in some way all part of biology
Perhaps they are for instance
Like some big salmon or trout
They're not born fully-grown
They're not even born in the city or water where they normally live
They're born hundreds of miles away from their home grounds
Where the river is narrow to Tiny streams
Just as it takes time for a speck of fishpond mature into a fully grown fish
So we need time for everything that develops and crystallizes
You know world of ideas
Go farther up
Q
99percentinvisible was produces week by Avery Trucking
Edited by Delaney Hall
Mix by Sharif Youssef in music by Shawn real and Malone
Orsini producer is Katie Mingle
Tripp Halstead is the digital
The rest of the staff includes Emmett Fitzgerald
Tyrann Mathieu
And me Roman Mars
Sincere gratitude this week to Michael Burnett Mark Rodriguez
Jason Reitman
Chris Funk and adamle
Charles Birnbaum in the cultural landscape
San Francisco Garden designer Gabrielle camera
David Lewis & Alto University
Central route to Andrew Norton
Bridge Park in this idea
The archival sound was
Vanderbilt University archives
In the 1978 movie skateboard Kings
If you haven't seen Stacy's documentary Dogtown and Z-Boys yet I'm actually kind of jealous of
Really glad you're going to
We are project 91.7 KAAL
LW in San Francisco and produced
Radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
You can find the show and when discussions about the show on Facebook
You tweeted me I Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
When Instagram Tumblr and Reddit too
But you're not really getting the full 99percentinvisible
Experience
If you don't go to our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com