99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If you hear these footsteps
Can get some idea about who is walking towards you
Probably woman that does not to be
She can be a supermodel a CEO a drag queen
Bridesmaid
Destiny
As a fashion object and symbol the high heel is weighted with meaning
It is also weighted
With the where's entire body weight
The high-heeled shoe
Might be one of the only designs
That is physically painful
And yet somehow purses
Avery truffelman doesn't tend to wear heels I really like the way he look
And I've tried wearing them
But I just
Cannot do it
So I talked to someone who actually wears them
Every
Day and I have a standing desk
So I'm even a bigger dumb
Wright Lake
I am in these heels all day and standing when all these other job you can't even tell she's doing it in
This is all things
From NPR
Believe it or not we radio folk actually bothered to get dressed
Trolley corners
Like a lot of professionals
High heels are strictly for the office commuting to work it's flat
After work
Back and forth because it is impossible I feel like to find a shoe that is
High heel.
Really gorgeous
And fundamentally comfortable
She's tried high heels that claim to use Comfort technology and it's like a three and a half inch for inch pump like
It's only going to be so comfortable there shoes that are wearable I can wear them front doors
Comfortable as possible and she does not like to complain you do
Yourself right so it's
Dumb to walk around heels hurt
I failed
At this look
But people have been failing at this look for a very long time
I can't
Couch
When the heel was actually invent
I think that history is long buried
And
Dates back centuries and centuries and centuries in the near East
Elizabeth semmelhack
Sure it's a very specialized Museum in Toronto
I'm Elizabeth semmelhack and I'm the senior curator at the battle sheet music
I've got to ask
Why isn't it the shoezeum
I don't know you are the first to ask me that question
The collection of the baddest shoe Museum or shoezeum
Includes a lot of different kinds of Footwear
But high heels of the focus of Elizabeth
And the subject of her book
Heights of fashion
The history of the elevated shoe
And that his
As it turns out
Started
With men
Many horseback riding cultures wore heels
On their boots and on their shoes for riding
He'll help you stay in the stirrups
What does my cowboy boots have heels
As early as the 10th century
The Persian Cavalry was wearing inch high heel
In Bruges I had a really big
Really talented mounted military
So the spread the
Continental European men
Field added to the riding boots
It's associated with
Upper class practice cuz having horses
Keeping horses yunnan
Lycoming sports car
And so it seems that from their men word first and within short order upper-class women
Added heels to their own outfits
And then
Heels become
A form of Upper and middle-class stressed out the 70
But it really wasn't yet a strong signifier of gender
In all those paintings of Louis XIV little kitten heels
He's dressing like
A pillar of normative aristocratic masculinity years
Nothing effeminate about him
Bath time
But then he'll started to get gendered in their designs
Men's Health Group Broad and sturdy and women's became tapered and decorative
Finally mending them impractical agent Century the high heel strictly a lady shoe
And something really interesting happens at the end of the
18th century which is the French
I'm in the French Revolution happens
High heels
Although they were very much associated with femininity they were also very much associated with aristocratic femininity
Post French Revolution aristocracy and frivolity or out of the
And then he'll stay out of
Style for a really really long time
Until
And this is Salma Hayek
Siri
The invention of the camera
Because
With photography
Came pornography
And with the rise of pornography
Came the rise
Of the Hill
Pornography embraced - Hills before Vashon dead
Because he owes work great when you don't have to move and you're just
Posing for a few minutes
It's around this time when heels be
Come sex
The pin-ups that are in the barracks during World War II
Almost always have high heels on
When the war is over in the Men return home
That is when the Stiletto was invented
Cuz the Stiletto brings fashion
Into a lineman
With meserole
As heels made their way out of photography
And onto the street
Into the office
There arose the engineering challenge
I'm trying to make
It's fundamentally uncomfortable thing
Comfortable putting the physics of putting the weight of a woman's body base
Stickley on the balls of her feet
Is
You know that's a lot of pressure to try to Medicaid
So people try to find ways around the design
There are foldable flat shoes that you can take with you and you just can't take
The pain of a high heel anymore
But if you want to go to Whole Nine Yards
Or nine hours in pumps
YouTube is full of hat
Tips and tricks
Flopping off
MacGyver type sixes for the shoe
Scissors
Do not burn yourself
MacGyver type fixes for the foot
Skip work classes and tutorials for learning how to walk in heels
Practice practice practice
And I don't want you girls to be afraid about going up and down the stairs in heels it's actually fairly easy
In the most extreme cases people have gotten surgeries to shorten their pinky toes dead and their nerves
Botox into their feet
All to circumvent
The pain of a high heel
Start to feel at the very bottom of your
Your foot the ball your foot
And then I'll start to rub on your heels and rub on the sides
And then suddenly stepped down and it's going to be a shooting
Stabbing pain
And after that pain you go numb
Meet the twins
Animal alien
I'm three minutes older I'm Jessica
We have a vintage inspired modern Comfort wedding shoe line
So that people who are getting married don't have numb feet or aching legs
Crooked posture
Or nerve damage
Because it's not just your foot pain
It's your
Ankle pain is it shortens your calves
It ruins your posture not to mention bunions and hammertoe and haglund's deformity
Google these if you want to but do not click image search
Some things you just can't unsee young twins designed hack into the shoe
And borrowed elements from other kinds of Footwear
When we actually first started we
Frankenstein the most comfortable athletic
Of different shoes they started with the toe box
Which is basically the very front of the shoe
Where the toes are
The triple toe box from a salsa dancers high heel which tends to be roomier
Just to give you a foot enough room
To be able to
Well as you're standing every foot will swell throughout the day the whole shoes really padded and cushion
And like running shoe
They have Arts
Don't write in
They're not stilettos
For balance purposes the Leon's made that you'll stick where it meets the foot
But for aesthetic
The sturdy healed tapers
To a finer point
Where it meets the floor
You don't want to look at this shoe and think it's a cup
Although Comfort shoe is relative
We guarantee our shoes are going to be at least an hour more
Comfortable than all your other shoe
For the Leung twins even the most comfortable high heels still have a time limit
But Martha Davis
This begs to differ
So I wear these shoes
12 hours a day everyday and I know
Quite a few women who do the same and I
I've never had any problems
About Martha Davis is talking about shoes that she made
My name is Mark
Davis
And I'm an industrial designer
And I've been working in the Footwear industry for the last eight
You may be familiar with her industrial design work
Martha Davis design the compact case for the pill
Like aliens win
Davis was wearing high heels before she started designing them
And she couldn't find a high-heeled shoe that look good
And didn't cause pain
Davis went to Milan to study a process of shoemaking called balloon
Which emphasizes measurement and proportionality
And her takeaway
Is this
Successful as long as
It's not a question of the
And there's one critical point
Weather fit
Really matter
And it's called the calzada
How's that
I called the fitting point
That's the number one critical
If you look down at your feet it's kind of right before your foot becomes your toes
Some terms of girth it's the widest part of your
But you have to secure that
Spot and make sure it's not too loose
Talk to tight though calzada is not the only significant spot
The toolbox could be too shallow and the pitch of the heel to be too steep or not sleep enough
There are number of factors
But it's most important to keep the calzada in proportion to the other numbers for comfort and security
Method allows Martha to play around with sculptural forms and hard materials
Steal a gnarled wood
With hardly
Annie Potts
No she keeps her shoes relatively low
Put a quote on quote
Low heel is nothing to scoff at
I wore round 3 inch heels
This week just to
To try it and my feet are killing me
Why bother
Mosto
I asked Audie Cornish.
Into
Same twins that makes me feel awkward about discussing high heels
What is the same thing that makes me think like
Why do I shave my legs
Feminism
Collegiate self
Deck railing at me from
Being like you sold out it every way possible.
There is something to be
Sad for
A well-made
That
Kind of
Makes your calves look amazing and puts that like
Inappropriate probably sexy arch in your back
I like that feeling
The heel is so tied up in web
Gender
Sex and
Power
Look
I can't speak for everyone
But when it comes to the appeal of the heel
It's actually not very complex
Psychology
Kiehl's
Affect the way you move through the world
They change your walk
They make you
Push your shoulders back
Hold your head up
Swing your hips
They make you taller
But it's not really about that
I mean I'm already pretty
Actually in general height is not as big a factor as you would say
People will often say to me while women wear high heels today
He doesn't want to be as tall as men understand
That reasoning but
There are many many many men
Who would
Equally benefit
Increase height
Until why are they ignoring
The potential power of the high heel
But it wasn't too long ago when heels for guys were kind of cool
Think of the opening scene in Saturday Night Fever
John Travolta is walking through the streets of New York
Annie's strutting around in high heel boots
The camera is focused
It puts an undeniable Swagger
In his steps
Men try high heels in the seventies and why didn't it stick
The Condemned Elizabeth similax research
Men's heels in the 70s were too tied up in subbed
The exoticizing elements
Captain
On The Fringe
Until the men's chunky platform went out of style when power dressing of the 1980s came along
Men wearing suits and ties
Women wearing suits and heels
And they still are
But high heel could come
Timmy mean
Simply professional power
Or it could come to be that
Female professionals are the new
Power Brokers
But then I would not be surprised if that happens that men will be as eager to wear high heels as when
Okay
But only if they can design comfortable
99% invisible whisper
Troubleman the same Greenspan angle and me Roman Mars we are project 91.7 local public radio
AOW in San Francisco and produce of the offices of arcsin
Do walk around with paint cans strutting
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinnerware
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Surprised the family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black Box
Keep up with this show and all the people make this show on Facebook Twitter and Tumblr but your calzada will always
Please be comfortable
At 99 bi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com