99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This week if it isn't obvious I'm what you'd call
Infrastructure
Of course some infrastructure is vital and necessary and some infrastructure isn't
But it all has to be made right
It's hard work it's dangerous work
And it's often Union work
This story is about New York City sandhogs local 147 and they are the urban miners who build every
Free tunnel in New York City and many of the bridge foundations
Without them
Filipino stores no Subways no tunnels for car no water basically no New York City
Quote the local 147 website without the tunnels built by the 10 Hawks
New York would have ceased to exist around the time of the American Civil War
Zoe
Little number 3 interview scene the third Die Hard movie Die Hard with a Vengeance
It's pretty amazing to see in the voices of the sandhogs responsible for building that tunnel
Amazing to hear
Seriously I can listen to them talk all day but on this episode will just listen for a 22 minutes
Visit Saint Talks by long-haul Productions produced in 1994
My Dan Collison
Through the heart of a great Metropolis
Lowe's on Mighty Hudson River
A natural barrier between two states
A challenge to man's Ingenuity skill and courage
60 years ago the challenge was to build another tunnel under the Hudson River
The Holland Tunnel in the George Washington Bridge could no longer handle the mounting traffic between New Jersey and Manhattan
I'm so the Lincoln Tunnel is starting
It was 1934
The Great Depression
And jobs were scarce
A my day
When you were hungry is beyond easy
And to be a Santa
My gym Bethesda
You had to work almost
Exclusively in compressed air
Are that was pumped into small cramped underground Chambers
Caissons
To hold back the water and silk during tunnel
Under Pressure work is a strain on heart and lungs
There is danger also up infecting an illness called the pain
My early life I had trouble with a bunch of my niece
You had a way of curing it at home you get into a hot cup of water
And it would disappear and then you'll fall asleep the water would get call it come right back and hit you like a toothache a very very bad
Bad toothache
It's the same problem deep sea divers
When they come up to the surface too fast
Severe cramps
And in some cases paralysis
They can even lead to death
Around the turn of the century
During construction of the Pennsylvania Railroad town
The bands took the lives of at least 50 sandhawk
Initially the men were declared dead of natural causes
Later it was revealed that the death certificates had been falsified to cover up unsafe working conditions
Public hearings led to public outrage
Eventually
A sandhogs union was born
I wouldn't have the union would have nothing
Believe me when I tell you absolutely nothing
You would think that would be any kind of wages or any kind of conditions
It looked the contractor was going to give you
Rich man got rich because he was holding onto his money is going to give it away to a bunch of slobs
30 unit Canon
I'm going to read the title of a local but you must remember that we came from an international Union of compressed air
That's why the title is compressed air free at tunnels
Foundations case on subway sewer cofferdam construction workers union of New York
New Jersey state and vicinity
Edward McGinnis
Is a former president of the sandhogs Union
Local 147
For sure
McGinnis is father was a sand hog
A foreman
As a kid growing up across the street from the bar where his father recruited his work
Young Eddie decided he wanted nothing to do with a business
The banging on the bar
And the fights that went on there I was petrified I never thought I would go near
Anybody that was a sad hug never mind waiting for them
But despite his vow to stay away
Eddie McGinnis
Like a lot of sandhawk
Ended up following his father down into the tunnel
Economics the size of a lot of Our Lives
And it decided mine I know the first time I went into a tunnel in
And they set off a blast of about 206 Zapata
I said what in the name of God brought me to this place
That was my reaction I'm going home and never coming back
But when I went home I had
Young Sheldon
And I had to come back
Adam jahns everything else is good
Are you feeling buddy
You doing all right
10 years ago there were twenty-three hundred members of local 147
Ecuador here in a small office in the Bronx
Today there are only about 700 member
And almost half of those are pensioners
All our men
Richard Fitzsimmons is the business manager for local 147
We had women they did go down there was a thing
Pretty Woman
And they worked alongside they done the best they could but they didn't come back after lunch it was just the door battuta
I'm a firm believer that a woman should
Do whatever she can in life to support herself
But I don't think that's a noggin
Hey is is a place for a woman like to put it this way I would want to see my wife and my daughter's hand
His son is another matter
Richie Fitzsimmons started working as a sandhog 6 days after he graduated from high school
Today he's the president
Local 147
Spacely a father-son union
Just about everybody has either had their father or their brother is the saying haga that cousin and
It's a small but it a tight-knit union
And the union is running in in such a way that the
It's almost like an extended family
And local 147 is a union that has long prided itself
When it's racial and ethnic diversity
Yeah tell me she was my name
Yeah come here from Ireland 1971
I joined / 147
A 1972
And I'm here ever since
My name is Ed
Johnny Moore IL from Brooklyn
Urgent born raised in Brooklyn and I lived on the Jersey Shore right now
Honda
The sanhok 30 is
How's boarding by a fellow named Charlie Doherty
Naughty Boy
Iwata Dyna-Glo poisonous
Local same as we do have West Indian Jamaicans
Polish
Have a good contagiousm polish colors
My name is Lincoln Richard
I am
From Saint Vincent West Indies and I've been assigned hug for 23 years
Lincoln Richard speaks almost reverential
About the unity of local 147
That no matter how they might feel about each other
Above ground
Down below
Santa
Dogs are like family
Very close you can just finish fighting with a man
Interchange house
You got on the elevator and you go down to work on
It's your brother
Each as last meal with you share anything with you
You look out for you you know anything you do for you
That's how beautiful a relation
Kinship we have
Wechat integration so to speak before any of this ever came out about integration
Will be home even know about integration
Kiwi bar work as a sand hog for 35 years
Before retiring in 1987
Yeah you could work with Polacks I was Irish Irish American Dad work
Fallout games and what
Black angels
That was the method of operation
Was all work rules
It was all work
It's always been that way since I've sent
In New York one of the most important work rules
If not the most important
Is that you have to have a union card to work as a Santa
The being in the union doesn't guarantee a job
Tunnel work is scarce.
Several hundred members of local 147 or out of work
Most of those who do have job
So working on City Tunnel number 3
A massive Construction
Edwin finished
Will get much of New York City a brand new water system
City Tunnel number 3 is badly needed
New York's existing water
Some of which dates back to the
The turn of the century
Is so antiquated
City officials are reluctant to
Turn off the valve
Apps to inspect the tunnels
Because they're afraid the valves are so corroded they won't be able to turn them back on again
A small part of City Tunnel number 3 is shaft 21p beneath the heart
Part of Brooklyn
Monday morning
Approve sandhogs
He's about to go to work inside shaft 21
Five hundred feet below street level
Are we getting ready to go down the drain
I'm going to be driving for maybe three or four hours
And then we get the dynamite donated would be a blast
Music
The 300 pounds of dynamite
Everlast
The crew is off to a slow start this morning
There's an electrical problem
So it's Pitch Black
At the bottom of the shaft
Don't like status
The problem is quickly fixed
Then the first group
Cops and Hawks Reston hard hats and bright yellow rain slicker
Step inside a metal cage
And a sin
Give me one kiss and I'll be
Next sound you about to hear is Mendon cage going down
Men in motion
Foremost sandhawk the first trip into a shaft or tunnel was the moment of truth
Point at which they knew whether or not they had what it takes to be in the business and you can tell the minute you step on a cage
You start going down what do you do when you don't have it any Mike gimenez grew up not too far from his sight words
Long as he can remember gimenez says he wanted to be a Sandra what did you do
We told we boldly go where no man has ever gone before
We come across virgin Rock This Rock has been here since the beginning of time
Nobody's ever done that
Not every sandhog shares this romantic view of the work
Charlie Cannon is a 2nd generation stand
It's more economic than it is anything else
For the glory of being the first one to be with nobody else has walked
It says basic economic you got to feed your family pay your bills and try to get ahead in this life
That's the whole picture
Where do they work for the glory or the paycheck
Sandhogs work together and extremely close quarters
You're at the bottom of shaft
Tencent
In a battery of heavy equipment
Are packed into a space about the size of a large hot tub
The walls are Jagged Rock
Granite quartz limestone
Illuminated by a panel of flood light
As you can tell it's cramped sardine but this is what it's like to be a life of a sardine
Close to it yeah baby you don't get any better than this stuff
It's like working at the bottom of an empty missile site in a rainforest
Groundwater
Pours Down from the rock walls above
Collecting in knee deep pools below
The sandhogs
We're getting ready to drill
They pull out big pneumatic Jack
Attach long drill bit
Start boring holes for the dynamite
The opening at the top of the shaft
65 stories up
Looks like a pinhole
If something were to fall from above
Even a small rock
Heart
Could be deadly
It's like being in a funnel
Is No Escape
Is there a skate for Medicaid at 4
It was into a shaft similar to this one
Jeff 19 in Queens
Did something did fall
Something big
Last November the day before Thanksgiving
16 ton winch
Broke loose from its Mooring
At the top of the shaft
Tom Flanagan and Mike Boyd
R2 of 8 Santa
We're working 450 feet below on a catwalk
About 50 feet from the bottom
When the huge win
Plummeted downward
You know all of a sudden notice of cable that's like real fast and
They looked up and always seems his big snake coming out of the cable coming in
Couldn't see the surface due to the fog so
Cable Fitness up real bad knocking everybody all about
And at that big
Big ones come through and
All hell broke loose everything flying all over and
Had no warning at all
Hatteras I seen flashes out of the corner of my right eye
Sound like an explosion
Did that broke loose and I was
Have my foot caught in a cable
Put my fingers on a great and hanging upside down
I was going to drop in the water or take a break my fall cuz I was slipping in like with all the other guys I thought of my two kids and
Turn my hand around in the great and stuck in it again and just let my
Fort Lewis from the Gable
Manage my way up to
A good cable to pull myself up onto the form
I managed to get up to
Flat piece of that condition
Hang on a PC
Post on the guardrail
Just hoped and prayed until the dust settled until the tell everything stop calling
We're all very lucky that
That made out of there
I just wish
Anthony could have been as lucky as the rest of us
Anthony oddo was the 20th sandhawk to be killed during construction of the water tunnel
That averages out to almost one fatality the year
You come here today
Pray for the heroic men and women
Mesa tremendous sacrifices
The people that
The city of New York
We have water
Life-giving water
All the days of their lives
The generations yet
To come
St Barnabas Church in the north Bronx
Monsignor considine
Hold a special mass
Each year in memory of the sandhogs
Killed working on the water
So now
List the names of those
Stanza
Switzerland
Who has suffered and sacrificed
The work of art son
Charles
Spectrum
A minor
Joseph
Boston
The operating engineer
Stuart Birdsall
First guy got killed on water Tunnel construction that killed about 20 feet away from you on a wolf deck
To hear that man moon
It was something
I mean you're not enough
Gilbert J Horton
Minor
Frank's one accident on Battery Tunnel happened on Easter Saturday
Portugalia on a motor
That's going to really have a bad sloping
The great wonder by 4 degrees
They were shutting the inside a lot
He came down with the more we couldn't stop at the brakeman jump Rockets like
He hit the door
The battery jump to a column in half
They come in and they got Auntie Ann and Andy took me with him and we went over and put them in a sack and brought them out and I wanted it the whole night
All right
Had enough
That's it
Lord
Have mercy
Christ have mercy
Lord
Have mercy
For every sandhawk who is killed on the job
There are hundreds maybe thousands
Close call
The most legendary took place in 1960
As The Story Goes
Marshall Maybe
It was working in compressed air
Are in a tunnel below the East River
It was a blowout
Maybe into other sandhogs
4 shot out through a hole
Enough to the riverbed
On a geyser 25ft high they were Mining and they don't have the equipment or not enough to stop at blow
And he tried to stop and he went up to the river with two other guys
And he survived
Yellow to red.
The stories
Seem to catch attention cuz Marshal maybe went back he was in a Long Island College Hospital
I think he only spent a couple of days in the hospital
And he was backbiting
Quick as you could
Okay
Sakamoto sanitizing and they're going to tell you
Are your time's up your time's up
Buddy walking down the street or working Underground
It's going to go you're going to go
When a man says it's time you're gone that's all
Simple Jack
Just One Last Time
Stewart Williams
Thought it was his time a while back
He was working on a subway
When suddenly
The tunnel caved in
Stewart
He's only five foot three and weighs less than
130 lb
Was nearly crushed to death
Damn this feeling ever had
I saw those beautiful lights on my wife my kids
Just declared a
And I passed out
I woke up in hospital
A broken leg my back
Head cut open broken collarbone
Shoulder
A week later I'm back work
8 weeks
These days Stewart Works above ground
As a supervisor
Tonight he's directing a 650
The pound Dynamite
The chap 22
Part of the water tunnel project
Brooklyn
Chapter 22 is wedged between the brooklyn-queens
Expressway
And a row of low-income apartment
It looked down on the site
It's surrounded by Loops of razor wire and bathed in high intensity flood light
Do it blows a whistle once to warn people living in the apartments that an explosion is 5 minutes away
Dynamite Blaster an almost daily occurrence
Still Stewart is anxious
He's pacing back and forth smoking a cigarette
Nervously pushing the plunger on the empty Detonator in and out and greeting men as they come out of the shower
I'm responsible for these men and thank God. That would never hurt
Turn my life or had one get hurt working with me and I don't want I don't want to start now
The one minute warning
Fire officials
On hand to monitor the black
Moving closer in
Put their earplugs in place
After 35 years of Drilling and Blasting
Stuart wears hearing aids in both ears
Can I pair a rag up or something stick it in your ear the countdown is finally over Stewart hands the Detonator
The blast man
Shout out the final warning
Sounds good sounds good when we get down
Funny things about shooting you never know till you get back down there what you got
Returns on the fan
Clear the smoke out of the tunnel
And head for the sandhogs locker room
The hog house
Located in a nearby trailer
For some barbecued ribs
The game of gin rummy
I love it
Weather
I'm riding with Amanda people that I've met I've met some of the greatest people in the world
And
Beginning I guess your blood after a while
It's really all you want to do
There is a price sandhogs pay for this love of the tunnels
You age
You wage
And a whole
Sodus Bay
Many retired sand
Kiwi bar is one of them
Suffer from silicosis
From years of Reading Rock
Down in the tunnel
And caissons
Deterioration of the bone from working in
Compressed air
That puts a hurting on your body so
You can ask any of the old-timers that joints hurt
You know
El Ricon Del Rey
I don't think there's anyone who works as hard as a rock
Two men would gloat about a yard of sand in about
The two-and-a-half to three minutes
And this because I continuously for 6 hours
What are the stop
I don't think there's anybody
Stand up with that kind of work
But I never go to coming in and I'm I'm never ashamed of being what I am
And this is what I am
When the ribbon-cutting ceremony is finally held for City Tunnel number 3
Scheduled for completion in the year 2025
Most of the sandhogs working on the project
Livia retired or have died
61 year old Lincoln Richard may not be around
But he says there's satisfaction and just knowing he was part of it
Every time you know I go down and I
Come out after 8 hours
I see what I've made my contribution
I don't know what you doing
It's that people would be able to
Enjoy it in future years this is something that I thought I'd died and gone it would be still there
Because we're doing something that
New York City would always have
Federation
Any mechanics that look at another way
Eliminate all the tunnels the sandhogs have built over the years
The Lincoln the Holland
The Brooklyn Battery the Long Island and Pennsylvania Railroads
The subways
And you get an idea
Of the extent to which sandhogs
Help build New York
What picture of picture New York City if you will
What barge is going across bringing people across some fairies
And the best ferry system in the world can carry about 80,000 people in a rush hour
That's like from 6 a.m. to 10:11
I am
A tunnel can do that in
20 minutes
Without that
Progressive people coming back and forth
Manhattan would be a Dead Island
Manhattan would have been nothing you wouldn't why would you build anything for if you couldn't get people in and out
3 years and 7 months it took to complete run to by the Lincoln Tunnel
It open to traffic December 22nd 1937
Through the Lincoln Tunnel
Traffic moves with the speed I'm safety a hundred people over the river
A new link
Joint Base of New Jersey and New York a great engineering Z
Upgrade highway on new Converse
Sandhogs was produced by
Dan Collison for long-haul Productions Long Haul Productions is Dan Collison and Elizabeth Miser
You wasn't all their stories and they got tan the gray one Skyrim overhaul bro. Org
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
Seven kalw San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin and architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
You find the show and like the show on Facebook or on Twitter and Instagram too and we have a new episode from
Maybe next week and you'll find it first and 99 pmi.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden 2 playlist
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com