99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
View of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their History season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
We build the cities for us
The concrete the metal in the glass were formed into countless austere structures designed to give comfort
Too squishy
Hairless
Bipeds
We made the cities we were largely unconcerned with the feathered as finalists for the photosynthetic
Put the quote our greatest scientist
Dr. Ian Malcolm
Jurassic Park
Life finds a way
But the life that found a way to thrive within our city limits isn't celebrated for its Ingenuity or lauded for it
Fortitude the plants and animals that have made at the life that found away is revile
Familiarity has bred contempt at worst or indifference at best
We kick pigeons
We poison snails
WeMo down even the most useful weeds
But in the tangle Johnson's new book unseen City
He implores us to slow down and notice the beauty
And resilience of the life that thrives within our Urban landscape
You can covers weeds that are tastier than you've imagined
Squirrels are smarter than you suspected
Pigeons that exemplified their aristocratic Origins
There no grosser than us humans but let's just say
But every time you admire the queen iridescent Shimmer of the neck feathers on a pigeon you will all
Also be reminded a thing called pigeon milk
And it will haunt
You are nightmares
A few weeks ago I interviewed Nathaniel Johnson in front of an audience at nightlife the adults only night time weekly event
Did the California Academy of Sciences I had such a good time there and I enjoyed hunting City so much that we thought we'd
Shared as a special episode
I start out by asking if angelwood ascendant rope was
And why he decided to write a whole book about them
Synth ropes are the creatures
Beds
Thrive
Together with humans
So send
Is together in the Greek and and throws humans synth ropes
And these are the
All the creatures that are living right alongside us the weed spring up to the cracks the
Starlings that are growing generation after generation your attic
And I've always been kind of a wannabe naturalist is interested in these types of things but
For some reason
These particular
Creatures
Always seems like they weren't Worthy
A real study
And so I kind of ignored them
Until I had
Baby girl
And she didn't ignore them she was
Incredibly interested in these creatures
And
So I started looking at them too
And when I started looking at them in the way that she did through these fresh eyes I started seeing things
But I've never seen before
And that was really cool because you know you can go out into the woods and find something new that you've never seen before and it's like
That's amazing
But it's
Even more magical
When it's been there right in front of you
Day after day right underneath your nose and then you
Are able to look at it in new way
And see something that's
Just pops out
And is it
Do you remember the first thing that she
Pointed out that you
Felt like you had
Define answer for
Yeah there's this thing that would happen
Pretty much every day
As we were going to
Her daycare
I have her in the front pack
And
She would point at basically everything that we pass
What's that
I'd say that's a tree
Stay.
That's still that's actually the same tree even
That and so I had this terrible choice between like
Same tree tree tree over and over again or
Listening to a screen for the entire time
Until I decide to complicate the game a little bit by making a new rule which was that I could only say
The same thing one time so I can say tree but then I would have to say
Branch
Twig
Leafs
Stemen and by doing that this one time I
I saw it
These tiny little flowers
On this tree that I've never seen before and we've just got close to it and they're these beautiful little
Yellow flowers
And so then I had to go find what
The three wise
Send
And it was it was just this wonderful moment and then you know
Came back later and saw the same flowers and we saw they were developing into
Peapod
And she remembered in
That's cool inside so that was the first real MoMA
Where is like
There's stuff out here then I could be noticing that I'm not
Right
You can be kind of a toolkit for noticing things that in one of my favorite so like
My show 99percentinvisible we have a saying it's always read the plaque
It is not because
All plaxer fantastic
Many of them are really boring
And
Factually incorrect
But
But at least
If you're the type of person that
Read the black your person who notices
The story in place
And you have this corollary that I love that store the
Equivalent in the the natural wonders of the cityscape always eat the weed
So how does that through worked into to how you cultivate awareness in the natural world
So if if you always eat the weed
You you walk through the world in a very different way and I should say that
We're talking about edible weed
There's a surprising number of them that are edible
And all these things that
Grow in these
Ready situations a lot of them
I happened to be
Pretty tasty
If you catch them in the right situation
We just interact with nature generally through our eyes
I seen a we look at stuff
Sometimes maybe we'd like
Listen to Birdsong or smell
The roses are the skunk or whatever but
We rarely interact with nature by putting it in her mouth
And when you do that
All of the senses snap into Focus
Because you got the feel in the mouth
Centos at the back of your nose
There's a crunch
And the taste of course
And you also start seeing things differently because as soon as
The brain registers that that's
Food
This mishmash of
Weeds
That you can really distinguish before it
Comes right into focusing
I'm terrible at remembering different species names
If it's something that I can eat
I'm for some reason there's this like evolutionary thing that like that
I remember the nasturtiums in the
You know that the dandelions when they're just coming in and
Mallow and
So
Let's talk about pigeons
I kind of view them as disgusting lice ridden lizards
You don't do them that way obviously in by the end of the chapter I didn't feel that way so why do we hate them
University people don't really like them
And what are we getting wrong about pigeons
I think the
What happened with pigeons
This is
I mean they are legitimately
Revolting let's let's just put that on the table noted
But all the things that we find
Really loathsome about them are really caused
Biots
But humans because
We bred them to be
Massively productive
And then we put them in the situation where we
We fed them all
Food and we created this massive amount of food waste that they could eat and they reproduce like crazy
And so then they're overpopulated and they're all squished together and they get
Parasites
Diseases and
A lot of the things that we
Find
Disgusting about
Mr result
Of that Cesaro thinks those are things he didn't start
He said Nobel Origins expansion
Right so
Pigeons
Are really bird of the aristocracy
Late
Were first domesticated probably in the Middle East and then they spread around Europe
With the Romans
And
With Roman
Upper class really they were built into the
Architecture
Of Roman houses one of the
Classic elements
The Tuscan Villa
Is this
Belvedere
Stop like structure that
But you can go out and see the beauty
Mapleview
And that was a pigeon house
Open
Rooftop
Structural
At the top of the
Building an out
Common
Picture of
A beautiful stately
Upper class
House
And then they came to the US with
The upper crust as well
Samuel Champlain
Governor of
Quebec
Person to bring them to the new world and
They spread across the us because
Governors and dignitaries
This would give them to each other and
You had to have you know a pigeon
Roost in your house
Gym nearby
And so they spread with Upper Crust
But then they became really successful
End
As America became more and more successful and we started producing more and more food and started building these
Plaza
Statues in the middle of the
Kitchen
Started
Taking to those places
You taking them over
And you can't really maintain
If your status as a symbol of aristocracy
If you're incredible
Common
Think
And so they they fell from grace and you can see this happening in the language
One of the interesting things about pigeons
The words
Pigeon and Dove
For a long time they were just
Mixed together there's no scientific
Distinction
Is two things
Cenote all kind of the same family often
The common name of something we'll both be a pigeon and a dove
But at some point
Everything good
Wizard of everything bad was occasion and and you can see it today I mean if you try and change it
Around there's this huge cultural
Antipathy toward
Pigeons rights of you
If you think of
Like kitchen
Soap
Work
Kitchen chocolate bars
It just it just doesn't work or you could use you to think about it in like
Busa's in in the Bible like
The Holy Spirit
Sending from heaven
In the form of a pigeon
And so they say
Undergone this radical transformation
And I sort of feel for them if you look at them closely there these beautiful birds
If they're not
Disease didn't
We're coming is Cold War maybe even a hot war with pigeons all the time and it doesn't really work all that
What are the ways that we do with pigeon trailers
So there's the pigeon control industry is
Massive
Industry and you can do a lot of things you can put
Bikes
Out
To stop the pigeons you can
But netting that blocks them
They even have like miniature electric fences
Keep pigeons away
And none of it worked
I mean it all works to certain degree in that you can push pigeons off of one building
But they can just go to the next building
And that's what they do
And as long as the food sources they are the
The pigeons
Will be there
Okay so let's
Let's go
Pigeon milk
Please
I read this
And it was really upsetting to me so I want you to upset all these people here in this room
What is Pigeon milk
Normally we think of mammals
Giving milk
But it's a really useful
Delivery device of
Have nutrients and
Birds have figured it out too or at least
Pigeons have figured it out to
And it's it's completely on convergent evolution it's not like
This is something that has
Spread up the evolutionary tree
It's very similar in structure but it's
Completely
Independently derived
And essentially what
What happens is
The birds secrete
Some nutrients through the inside of their
Throats and there's a little pouch that birds have
Inside the throat
Stop the crop
And it collects
In the crop
And it's the sort of yellowish cheesy
And then that the squabs the little birds
Stick their heads down the parents throats
And thrusts
To get the
Pigeon
Both the males and the females produce that sits
It's a beautiful
Wonder of nature
When you were researching pigeons
You noticed
That a bunch of them
Have messed up legs
And there's a mystery to why so many pigeons have messed up legs
Yeah so I don't know if you've seen this but
I started seeing this as soon as I started looking closely a pigeons that
They
Often would be missing a toe or they'd be missing their foot
Entirely and it was just
And it was like this huge percentage every time I would look I would see you again either be like 10 pigeons out there and one or two
Two of them would have something wrong
With their feet
And when I started
Looking for the answers about
I found all of these ideas and people were pretty sure that
Predators
Attacking their feet
Why would they just attacked
Or they were getting staph infections
And it took me a really long time to figure this out it was sort of throughout
The entire course
The research I was
Cruising down the
Different threads
And eventually what I found the United Premier pigeon researchers said oh yes all of this is nonsense
What happens is that they
Pick up little bits of
Red
4share
Incredibly common
Insidious
And it gets Tangled around their feet and they don't have any
Anyway to get
Get it off and it just
Tighter and Tighter
The causes these lesions
And
Normally birds don't get this because most Birds hop
And pigeons kind of Shuffle
And so
Really well adapted to cities in many ways except
Parable
Protest law
Some reason their beaks to
They're not capable of tear not capable of
What's that okay feel bad for pigeons now
In the book most of the Flora and Fauna
Are species that thrive in the concrete landscape purposely make it easy for them to survive
That's not the case for the ginkgo biloba which is the tree that
I probably wouldn't exist anymore
If it weren't for people
Planting them in cities
Why are
Kinkos unsuitable for nature and what do they do so well
The Golden Age of ginkgos
Was
The Cretaceous
Kinko's
Rule the world as we all know
That's all we think of that you're on it just scared of dinosaurs
Really they were in charge
At that time
Kinkos had some evolutionary partner
They had some kind of creature that would help them distribute their seeds
And today we have no idea what this
Mystery
The people are still
Still trying to figure out
And it's a double mystery because their seeds
Smell
Like
Like a microwave death
Terrible
There's male and female ginkgos in the
The females produce the seeds in a few
Around and around September
November
You'll notice
Stop that's one thing you can
Open your eyes to the
And stop and find the seeds and notice just how terrible they smell
But there was something that must have liked
The smell
And must have eaten it in
Cherry did two different places
And at some point the seed distributor probably died out
And
It simply meant that the ginkgos
Couldn't outrun the glaciers
At the climate change
Until you see them
All lacrosse
The world they have these really tough leathery leaves
Great boss
Find them all over the place
And then they
Retreat
And they retreat
And they Retreat until they're just
Apple Valley's in China
Were there left
And their entire
Family gets wiped out
They're the only remaining species
This whole
Division
A plant life
That Remains
And then people come along
And people fall in love with
Kinko's and it turns out the ginkgos kind of love us too
They can
Drive-In
Polluted air that do well in concrete they do well in partial eye twitch
Which is perfect for cities
They're famously
Good at taking abuse in Albion
Backed into by a delivery truck for
Or
Close to atom bomb there's one just a kilometer away from the
Hiroshima bomb site that survived and regrew
It was kind of amazing story where they just
Barely hung on for millions and millions of years and then they happened to
Find themselves in this
Crazy
Point in the Earth's history
Where they could thrive
Human cities
Because the the fruits that the seeds are so stinky
We tend to plant only the male
The species right that's right people try to just plant the males and sometimes they get it wrong
And it's heart you know it's like 30 years
Before they become sexually mature so then it's like
Oops I guess that was a female but even the males have their downsides because been
You know they pretty
Tons and tons of Allah
So
One way or the other
So you discovered that Ginkgo seeds
Edible
Once you get rid of that really stinky flesh that's are around them in this quote
I want to be
Which I really liked a lot says
Ginkgo toxin is similar in structure to vitamin B6
And eating too much of it interferes with our ability to synthesize the vitamin
That can provoke a biochemical Cascade that especially in children
May lead to seizures and even death
This sounds alarming
But it wasn't enough to deter me
What does deter you
From eating things
And a little too paranoid about poisonous nature
Yeah I think we're a little too paranoid
About poisonous nature and just poisons in general
For the previous book that I did I
I ended up researching a whole bunch about
Relationship
Plants and
When you look at that relationship
Deku evolutionary Exchange
Between animals
Implants
It's a history of chemical warfare
You know plants produce
Crazier and crazier chemicals
Try and protect themselves from animals
And you would think that they would just win right because they have these amazing Laboratories where they can just synthesize
Stuff that would make
Ghetto people
At the NSA just salivating
Crazy stuff
But they don't because
Animals are
Really really tough and basically animals are like
Pretty good poison their plant
Guess I'll eat a little bit less of you
Interweave evolve
The ability to deal with it and you really if you spend enough time with this history are you really taken the
Lesson that the dose makes the poison
And with Ginkgo seeds especially
Yes there is this possibility of poisoning but
Also there is this history of
Millions of people
Eating this
Thousands of years
So I feel pretty
Okay well it's safe with it
How did they end up taste
So
First of all I tried to
Do it myself
And I was a little bit paranoid about
The poison it's white like
I cooked and cooked and cooked and I cracked up in the ginkgo nut and
It was like this shriveled little
Brown thing I was like I wonder if that's how it's supposed to look
Like it's really hard and kind of
Carmel tasting
And then I went to someone shoes
Chinese cooking enthusiast
Knows how to
Prepare this
Correctly
And she made it
It was it was a little bit of a letdown because it was so mild
Justice
It's kind of a tacky
Very mild
Slightly bitter
But not
Especially flavorful
Not it's kind of like
Overcooked gnocchi
Just a little bit
And it's really valued more for its texture in Chinese
Jeans in for
Taste
And it's it's supposed medic
Eagle properties
Yeah what's the deal with medical properties
I don't know I mean I mean the medical properties that we generally talk about
How to do with
Compounds
Unthinkable obeid has been shown to
Help facilitate
Blood flow
And so
And I can help with things like
Sodium blood flow
Low in the brain
So maybe yes there might be some
Waiting Richard
Makes you
Smarter bed
It's kind of a stretch and it does
Facilitate the blood flow by kind of thinning the blood to sew
You can have some dangerous complications
If you're already on blood thinners
Such
I wouldn't either one more species before you wrap it up
But there's a bunch of them in the book and you
I want to talk about crows a little bit
Cruise
Are the species in the book that seems the most knowingly take advantage
Of human cityscape samin shockingly bright
Things that
Are probably not good for us as humans like streetlights people think that upsets are circadian rhythms like crows are all about Street line
YouTube
Tell us a little bit about that and how they've particularly
Work their way into our lives
There's this mystery because there's this
This boom in Crows
And
It doesn't seem like there's really a booming crows
But actually just the concentration of crows in cities
So then the question is why are crows coming into cities
Season 1
Explanation for that
Is
Street lights
Because if your Crow
The scariest thing in the world
Is
A great horned owl
Because they just
Lying around in the dark
And there's huge
And there's silence
And they just swoop down
And totally e
You
And if you have street lights
You can see them coming
And so. Maybe why Pros are moving in
Well we're protecting them
Were there acting like they're awful lights on all the time
Fundamentally rosarian is always like
Really all about
Soliloquy you stories about
Through Monday and ugly things all the time and I can be seduced
Like the ugliest building it has a good story I'm like all about
We to the story about
Inflatable
Two men you know
Those are dumb as hell
But you have this guy talking about him and he's
Trinidad Migos that dancing up a storm like that it's like the greatest thing ever and I love those things
And that's really what this is about you like you find the story of these things and all the sudden this nature which is
Kind of setup to be a nuisance or like in our heads like a nuisance
Is it then you can fall in love with
Everytime I pass one of those two men
Story
And it makes my life a little bit richer because I hear that guy's voice and I think of that hole
Story and the same is true with all these
This creature is that I've started
To get to know
Because on my way to
Work ayuna
Stop at the bus stop in the morning
Instead of just being kind of
Annoyed
In the back of my head that there's a crow cawing all alike look up and see if it's having a
Squabble with
Squirrel in
Like wonder what that's about
Or
I'll stop to look closely at the flowers that are coming out in the tree and be like
Oh that's telling you something
Thing about that part
Dollar Tree
All of these things are telling
Stories
And
I just would like
To be able to read those stories
Fully
Follow the narrative
You know these creatures are passing out
Newspaper
Where is the way the guys do in the city
At the top of the subway
And I'd like to really be able to read those news
Have that
Rich understand
So if
If people hear it leave here
I want to go out and do what you do
Assignment for them to soar like begin to notice something something
There's a bunch of things that
One thing that's right in front of you I mean there's pigeons everywhere we
We talked a lot about
Can anybody tell me
What color are pigeons eyes are
Adesh screen flu
I heard I heard I heard a correct answer
The one we just leave it and take a close look like
Next time you see then it's really crazy
So it like when you do it find it but on Twitter tag it with unseen City and we'll watch for
So if you're like me and you read in bed next to your spouse
And you like to go hey you know what about the snails
They have two antennas so they can find calcium this is the book for you my friends
Every five minutes you're going to be saying something like that
Thank you so much for being here
Unicorn wallpaper
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall Kolstad Kitty lingle Avery Kaufman Sharif Youssef and Mero me
Mars
Things to do nightlife at the California Academy of Sciences in San Francisco is Golden Gate Park you can explore music creature
Pictures and Cocktails with other curious mind if adults every Thursday Night at the Museum is a cool that you should definitely go
We are project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors burn in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flash podcast
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook and follow Saul on Twitter and Instagram the best way to
Floor the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world is to become friends with our website
Side to get to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy
Do you know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to
Huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com