99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
By all accounts if you've ever taken a bus
Tour from Tel Aviv new Central bus station you've never forgotten the experience
It's one of the most bizarre and magical and disgusting and enchanting places you can imagine
This is Missy Harmon of the radio show and podcast Israel story talking about the unforgettable ramshackle
Massive bus station known as the city under a roof
It's dirty and smelly and feels depressing
Dessert
But at the same time it's colorful and full of life
The Station House is vendors
P*** workers and refugees from all over the world
Filipino Cupid
Brazilian
On the 4th floor
And what's called Manila Avenue you can stuff yourself with homemade pan fried lumpia that Filipino caregiver
Sell on their day off
If you turn the corner
An old-timer my drag you into The Mists of David synagogue
After what you can Meander pass tattoo parlors churches the free STD clinic AirTrain brides getting their hair
Hair braided the Israeli Filipino matchmaking agency Fringe theater spaces
And end up at a giant Yiddish book Library
We're about twenty years until the year 2010 Tel Aviv new Central bus station was the largest in the world
This isn't a city whose population just barely reached 400,000 people during this time
The bus station is busy
In fact it's almost impossible not to get lost there
All attempts at designing proper wayfinding have failed miserably
But what's probably most interesting about the new Central bus station in Tel Aviv
Is that it's sort of a layered fossil of the history of Israel
If archaeologists were to excavate through the layers they'd find remnants of every phase in the short story of this day
From Independence through post-war Euphoria to recession and westernization
They be able to trace the waves of immigration to Israel
From Europe and North Africa
Africa so in many ways
The story of Tel Aviv new Central bus station is
The story of Israel
And this story of Israel As Told through this bus station
It's going to be told to us
Mile High middle
From the brilliant radio program
Is real story
Silverado Chevy single thing I like about this station
Everything here is worthless
Believe me I'm here cuz I have no other choice before then
That salon
He bought a store in Tel Aviv new Central bus.
Fiction in the early 90s
Even before it opened
He dreamt of eventually passing it on to his
Cathy bought it is an investment 20 years ago
Now I'm stuck
No matter what happens I'm stuck
Taxes utility bills office fees will suck me. His place ruin me
Ellen store has been closed for years
Because no one hangs out anymore at the far end of the fourth
Where are you supermarket
And Ellen is just one of hundreds of vendors
To pay good money to purchase the store here and
Who are today
Stuck with a property that's worth
Absolutely not
I Met You London
Section of the station called that I'm load Market
On the thirty
He was Moonlighting
Selling baby clothes
Do Eritrean refugees
Friends doll
Trying to make up for the Lost income
Chrome is out of business shop
Which of the Stalls around him are abandoned
Old newspapers are glued to the display window
Nearby sports bar
If you can close you can make out headlines about the 2003 Columbia space shuttle disaster or
The disengagement from Gaza in 2005
The ceilings are covered with black soot
Board paddlers
Anxiously smoke cigarettes
It's right underneath an old sign that says no smoking
And the smell of nicotine Blends into the stench of urine swak
Diesel
What can I say
It's depressing to hang out with the vendors of the Dominican Republic
I love you
New Central bus station
The structure itself is terribly confusing and that's no coincidence
It was designed to make people get lice
The Labyrinth
It was coined by the station's Chief Architect
Lamb County
Indiana Labyrinth you get lost
You know how you get in
But you have no idea how he'll get out
So even if you get out that liquor County I'm an architect
And I'm the Widow of Salem call me
Let me always say
Did the good city is a city you get lost
Andy mentioned the central bus station is a city and the Wolf
So if it is a city and a wolf
Why shouldn't we get a little bit lost inside
So in order to help me get lost in in
I don't know
Slightly more organized fashion
I teamed up with an energetic architectural Duo
I'm an architect from Israel and I'm currently at Masters today
Bent at the architectural Association in London I just graduated from Master School design in Harvard
And I've been investigating researching the central bus station in Tel Aviv with Talia
For many years now
Research
Of the Central bus station started
When we had to reorganize the time carmie's archive and while going through loads of
Dusty documents and plans we found amazing materials
David from the sixties and seventies
About the central bus station
When you're the station pretty well even before
And when you what everybody thinks about the station how complicated the building is
But then we saw these
These drawings and they were like
Really beautiful actually the drawings are indeed
Beautiful
They're sweeping lines and huge glass skylight
But
Few people see much Beauty in the building as it stands today
Dalian
And I accept
It's really hard to do
Describe it without getting lost
In this weird dark
Ollie's
Where you really don't have anybody around you
Almost half of it is underneath the
Street-level
So it is dark really dark
Ender list
In a way it's like a dark amusement park
You're actually of Spades
On one hand
And on the other hand having like
The most
Exciting environment around you with people from all around the world
Super colorful
I would say to Movie Central place
It's a lousy
Almost
Anything or everything to happen in its is what went wrong
So we go there and try to find
The answer for that
They took me around this magical multi Central dark amusement park
There's
At some point they let me down to the abandoned first
Store then up a narrow ramp
Creaky side door
I looked around and realized
We are in the lobby of a deserted movie theater
So we're actually 15 meters below ground level here in what was the Grand Cinema
And there was Six movie theaters here with
Amazing names like John Wayne Everest Gandhi
Even though it's been more than 15 years since the credits roll on the last movie played here
The theaters are still in great shape
The walls are covered with posters
Films like Pulp Fiction
Titanic
The Acoustics remain excellent
And the cushions of the red velvet seats are
Still pretty comfy
Miss forgotten glamour is testimony to the big hoax
The station invited in
It's early days
What time does the original idea was that passengers would pop in and catch a movie as they waited for the bus
That never had
And the cinema closed down just a few years after dope
Today as you can see is completely abandoned still here
The new Central bus station open its doors to the public in the summer of 1993
After nearly three decades of planning it was shiny and new
Exciting
But then in just a few short years
Became the grimiest place in town
How does a place go from such splendor
If such neglect
So short a period
Sean what about xiamen architect writer
Publisher and
Who lives right near the sea
300-meter
Thinks that in order to answer this question we need to go all the way back
The days before the establishment of is
In 1948
We should talk about the land Central bus station was built on
I just don't do Arabs
From Jaffa used to be in Orange Grove
Play Sublime of grew up on the outside
He remembers it well
Jamaya party
It was called Abbotts Grove
We used to sneak in underneath the fence steal some oranges and then run away
Following the war of independence
Most of the Citrus Groves in the area between GFI in Tel Aviv
Where abandoned
Deserted / confiscated
Depending on your political
In any event the state took over the land
Jews started moving in
Princesses Homestead exactly where the new Central bus take
Situated today
I buy chili II by my house was a special house
Right on the corner of levinsky Street
Second house from the corner
On the second floor there was this big wall
How to mural
Of the Sea of Galilee
For the fisherman fishing
Llama llama
Really something to favor
Beautiful houses in Bryans mother
Initially the government wanted to expand a nearby neighborhood by the name of Novation
But is always the plans were delayed
Installed
So they were forgotten altogether
So instead of a brand new residential neighbor
Fayetteville Observer
Started to develop
Islamic tents
Sheds
Warehouses meanwhile
In a better part of town
Leave the man called alyafeets
He was an immigrant coming from pollen and studies
And he open up
Cafe Pele
Switch was a really famous
Coffee shop on the seaside of Tel Aviv Cafe Fields was the
Swankiest joint in town
Senior British officers
Came to relax over a dry martini
Elegant waiters in long tails and a boat I would walk around serving cocovan steak bearnaise
In an orchestra played the latest hits in the back
And as he spent his days sitting in his Cafe smoking his cigars
Pete's couldn't help notice the construction friends
Going on all around it
Imma be this person with life right now
This is a promotional permit Tel Aviv from the late 50s
Over here
New York
Well, the same
Apart from the fact that we haven't got the skyscrapers
Tel Aviv was humming
And feels the tireless entrepreneur spotted real estate opportunities everywhere
So we purchased the old Orange Grove turn slime from the Jewish National Fund
But then there was the problem of the squatters
Like
DLC gear
Bill showed up
And wanted to see what them
Gradually he bought them all out
Brought in tractors and raise the shed to create one giant product line
The location wasn't ideal
Across the street was New Vision on
Densely populated low-income neighborhood
And in the middle of Nevaeh Shannon's to Tel Aviv
Mean buster
The Olsen
Everyday dozens and dozens of buses zigzag through the neighborhoods Narrow Street
And as often happens
This contributed to the areas
Decline into a hub of crime
Poverty
It was clear to the municipal planners that
Something wasn't working
They wanted to move the station to another place while they renovate and open up the old one
So cute
Who was a really clever guy just
Came out to dance party and told them
Wait a minute
Why
Would you move the bus station and then
Bring it back just keep it
Where do you
Well I will build you a new one
And pills had Big Dreams
He was going to finance the building of the new bus station
By making it part of a huge Mall
It was
Meant to be the largest bus station in the world when it was
I conceived
Israel is still a small country
With a population of just over 2 million
So as you might imagine lots of people thought the idea was
Absolutely insane
But this is charismatic
And even more importantly he knew all the right people
So you managed to persuade the folks at City Hall and with their approval
He approached a 33 year old architect
Langkawi
Enfield said to him
Build me a central bus station
Promise first proposal was relatively simple day there was the decisions that will ever would be similar to
Train station in the sense that the buses would pass right through it
On top of that they would build
Apartments hotels offices in in the center that would be a big Park
Which would actually sit on the stations
From there on it only went down
Pretty quickly issues a rose with
Counties plan
Bigger than than the two rival bus companies
Could become stakeholders in a project
Where is furious when they realized they would have to sheriff
Not a problem
The developer
We'll put the bus companies on separate
Carly had a brilliant idea
Dividing the transportation between the 1st and the 6th floor
The dance city buses
Svn stop on the first floor
And it gets Intercity buses would leave from a platform all the way up on the 6th
So passengers transferring from one to the other would have to go through the entire building
And what's been good money in The Malt Shop
Yeah it seem logical at this time
Was very trendy at the time and I'm coming forward this idea to Israel
Built in the meantime understood that the project was going to be much more expensive than he originally expected
He said
Cuz I mean we need more spaces which we can sell
And so in every subsequent design, submitted
The station grew bigger
Bigger
By the six draft handed in in November 1967
The blueprint that started to resemble that behemoth
Reno today
In fact I remember I'm talking about the central bus station
And saying that they wanted
To build the largest
Bus station in the world
And they kept wondering why would anyone wants to build a largest
Central bus station in such a small country
But this is exactly what I
In the end the new Central bus station was designed to include 8th floor
For a total of 230 square meter
Parasaur 57 Acres
Which is more less
Empire State Building
By the time Prince Carlos building permits in order
Architectural Styles around the world had begun to change
New wisdom had it that a few small scale public transportation hubs
We're more efficient than one gigantic station
And besides
There were enough examples to conclude that megastructures
Rarely function the way they were originally intended to
On top of all that has had other problems
He had bought out all the squatters
But the residents in the adjacent streets were living
Even though their neighborhood had never been particularly nicer
Upscale
They were concerned that the new station
And all the increased bus traffic
Would depreciate the value of their
Apartments even more
The day would end up living in a cloud of smoke and
Fumes
And
As it turns out
They were right
This is Sheila Kesha
A resident of the neighbor
Can you imagine what it feels like to wake up
Z82 this terrifying rattling noise
And I wake up and this news doesn't stop
You seated home you want to watch TV and you can't hear it
You want to talk with the family
You can talk
Deafening noise
Beside that we have to
We have to shut the balconies
Because the people who go by in the buses
Chimney practically see what's going on inside our houses
Give me a call.
Someone knocks on the door I can't hear it
It's awful what can I tell you
My niggaa.
Terrible noise
All the time
That's in Canarsie
Who still lives directly across from one of the bus sex
He was one of the residents who complained
And well you can judge for yourself
This is a recording from his living room window
10 p.m.
Inline sander Central bus station should never been built in the first place
Absolutely not
But pills was determined
End on December 14th 1967
Six months after Israel tripled its size in the Six-Day War
The minister of Transportation
The mayor of Tel Aviv and many other dignitaries
Gathered at the edge of the old Orange Grove
And lay down the Cornerstone
Perricone's create
It went now felt like a huge country
Huge station scene
The hubris of building the world's largest by state
Was in line with the general sense
Post-war euphoria
In the months that followed
Hundreds of workers dug Foundation
Splayed rebar poured in concrete
Drilled and hammered
And all the while residents demonstrated outs
Hilton the meantime was ready to move on to the second stage
He needed to sell the vast commercial space he was building
Who invited Jews from all over the world
Time to come on and see the place
And get a free tour in Israel
On him
Sort of like breath right before birth
And of course the grand finale of the
The trip would be a visit to the new Central bus station filters new project
With expectations that the visitors
Would buy a shop in the station
Teens hope to tap into the overflowing Zionist sentiment
Follow the Six-Day War
And amazingly he succeeded
Hundreds of people bike shops
Some of them took out loan
And others like Macklemore from France
Solder houses
Natalia
Sunday will promise the Magnificent shop in a shopping center that the
Whole world with
Others like
Whose house with the painting of the Sea of Galilee was
Demolished
To make way for the station
We're giving shops has some sort of compensation I got 42 at the central bus
It's at the shop will be
Be something
Something great it's important to bear in mind that peels didn't lease those shops as a
The mall developer
Weather today
He sold
Property
The owners register the asset under their own name
Just like buying an apartment
Over the next 6 years
It's sold more and more of his stories on paper
The massive building started taking shower
People were excited
Every few months that would be a headline in the paper
Saying something like
A city under a roof is
Is coming to life or the world's most high-tech bus station due to open but then in 1973
Became the Yom Kippur War
And with it a general Nationwide recession
Chicago levinsky Contracting Company field setup to build
Bankroll the
Started fault
It was a shortage of concrete
Problems with the Worker's Unions
Growing debt
Finally in 1976 filed for bankruptcy
The construction stopped.
By that time the structure was already moved
A huge concrete
In the middle of the city
Tell your grandma and grandpa's all remember this place is the series
Big white out
Now a saga of who should take responsibility for the Fiasco erupted
Public commissions were established
But the blame game went on and
On
And so
For 12 years
That miserable station
Spit some self called it
Remain empty
Or
Almost there
A huge colony of bats
It's made the building their home
Gradually started to host those sort of national Park of society
By the early 80s the station had already gained its notorious reputation
It served as an underground meeting
Huge Raves Rock and Metal
Replacement
In 1983 after a decade of neglect
Inhabited only by bats
Punks
It finally seems like the station was going to be redeemed
Contractor motivacion about the crotch
From its creditors
For a bargain price of $5000000
Once again you could hear the hustle and bustle
Construction work in the empty concrete show
You're not like his predecessor peels knew the right people
Like the then minister of Transportation
Shaketha
When cats have visited the site just
A few months before it was supposed to open to the public
He said that I'm certainly pleasantly surprised
And we of course will be happy to help you in any way to overcome bureaucratic Oster
What guitar was happy about
Was that Jana was delivered
The station was set to open more or less on schedule
Most of the real estate had already been sold
Back in the day
So in order to make this financially viable you don't know how to build more
And more
The huge station like The Very Hungry Caterpillar just
Gru and Gru
Toto Build-A-Bear ranger station is more than double the area that was authorized
That's the issue
Lawyer who represents many of the original shop owners
Long-standing class action suit against
The station
He's actually continuing a fight is
His father also a like started
LaFollette
Thousands of square meters
Equability legally without building permits or even organize plans
And they were also sold to people
Tennessee impossible Fallout.
And there's really nothing
Things to do about
So what you're saying is that the new Central bus station is
The largest construction violation in the city
Bollocks in the country
Casa however promise to remove bureaucratic Ops
And he kept his
Advertising brochures in radio campaigns to the public to buy a shop
The country's biggest commercial centers
Is on its way
Don't let it start without you
And again people who seem to have forgotten the heartache of the station
First incarnation
Lined up to buy a store from you on
In the summer of 1993
29 years after the ambitious architect that I'm counting put pencils
The paper
All the usual dignitaries reconvened at the station
Prime minister Yitzhak Rabin was there as was the transportation minister
Finance minister
The mayor of Tel Aviv
And even, himself
And what was the only time he ever visited the building
While it was working
In a rare moment of self-deprecating humor
The opening ceremony was kicked off by releasing a giant helium balloon in the shape of
All white outfit
But not everyone was amused
Here again is Chula Kesha
One of the station's unhappy Neighbors
At the time they were celebrating inside
We were standing outside in a big demonstration of thousands of people
Thousands of
People
And we were standing in demonstrating
At the foot of the Central bus station
This terrible monster that is destroying lives until today
But the neighborhood residents protest was largely ignored
While all of Israel heard about the grand opening that evening
National TV
Sahana milk
More than 30 years after Creekside first set his eyes on
The new Central bus station in Tel Aviv was now up and run
It's been open ever since
But it's far from the Posh shopping
What was meant
Does a certain temptation to view
Do those first years as the years when things were still working
But honestly
Things never really worked here
You'll never manage to sell all the new stores had built
So many of them stood Baker
And many of the ones that were open
Specialized stores located in
Far Corners of
Last Labyrinth
Where
Barely getting any footage
You can understand why the vendors
Don't have many good words to say about
This Saturday in Tarzana
Not good
Working
Play mice but nothing more wife in a cemetery
The wedding was not enabled
Nothing it stinks
Can you look at my cash register
No money
Then. You can't make a living here no work
No nothing
I'm just sitting here passing the time
I prefer to work in another place than inside here in Tel Aviv
Central bus station
And we can go on like
Believe me
We're not short on this kind
In 2002 the ground floor was closed for Good
The reason excessive Airport
That man that done the municipal bus company moved up to the 6th
Right next to egg
The national bus
So now what
All the platforms located on the top floors
The entire concept of the station
People will trickle down through the shops on their way from one bus
To the other was
Gone
The lower floors of the station became ghost
Before long just like his predecessor.
Mordecai and I filed for bankruptcy
Since then the station is falling deep in debt
They're real estate billionaires and Banks
Passing the hot potatoes from one to the other
Store owners suing in court
And in the middle of all of this is me Kizi the station's general manager
Who's doing his best to run the play
He's tried all kinds of creative solution
Cheap rates for artist Studios
Cultural events conferences
But it seems as if the station is
Is just getting emptier and emptier
We have here
1500 pesos
But only say 600 open
Because the building is so huge
Download necessary
At first the planners thought that up to a million people a date with
Pass through the station
Nowadays
Eva rage
50000 people are coming
It's going down
50000 people
That's just 5% of the original estimate
Maybe this is the root of the problem
The developers agreed LED them to sell more and more commercial space
Which in turn
Do the station size out of
Proportion
Or maybe it's all just a location location location and putting the station in the poor neighborhoods
Southern Tel Aviv
Sealed his fate
Or perhaps it was simple short-sightedness
In the 1960s there were only 24000 private vehicle
Wilson all of Israel
And everybody use public
Capitation
Who knew then that this number would increase more than a hundred fold
And reached a 2.5 million cars
Crowder roads today
When Pete's and call me dreamt up the project
The imagine the city under a roof
When all said and done
Does kind of have that vibe
Here's Talia the ark
Anyway the fact that it
It's called a city under a roof
Kind of says it all
In the city of got everything you've got the dark spaces you've got the lease spaces you've got the interesting bits you have the scary bit
To have the exciting bits
And all of it just
Coexister coexister
In a way
Despite the gloomy this all around
Sometimes you get the feeling you can spend your whole life
Does that post office
Grocery shop
Travel agencies Clinic lawyers
Churches Market
Close
Artist
Studios
Kindergarten does atomic bomb shelter
In synagogue says the whole world in here right on the television news
It's just a shame that nobody bothers to pick up the stone and take a look beneath it
More than 50 years have passed since the idea for the central bus station was
Born in the creative mind of Alia.
And started to take shape on rom-com is drawing for
Ever since people have been trying to figure out what to do with it
Here's schonwald
About the architect
I can search and see how and about 10-15 years do use of the station's decreasing shops are closing
Trade is deteriorating and gradually
Causing deterioration in older neighborhoods around here
In this case there is no deal winner
Everybody's loser the architect of the
Office building lamb call me asking to be despised for this
Project
Stand the fact
Severus video
O the OJ residents of the neighborhoods around
You know they say in Hebrew 11 said fish.
Hummingbird floor theater
Between a food May throw into a whetstone which 100 wise men cannot pull out
Widow
Is a bit more Optimus
I believe the story of the Central bus station is not over yet
Pinterest for his part
Is desperate Let It Go to Benjamin employees
I'm over 80 years old today
Spell mighty say it has to be on
I have the wheel
To deal with them
Nowadays
I have no energy
Amelia Earhart
There are many parallels
Between the story of the Central bus station and
The entire science project
Entrepreneurship creating facts on the ground
The patchwork system
Gradual move towards privatization
Capitalism
In the state's case it worked pretty well
But not so with essential bus
At least
Not soap
But who knows
Maybe the station's good days still lie ahead
The grandchildren of Elon campus market
Many more
Will end up inheriting a shop in the Soho of Tel Aviv
For now
Well Street debates whether the new Central bus station is
Stone thrown by a fool
Brass spectacular human Monument
Many people that we would rather forget
Turn the strange
Confusing place
Into their home
That's reporter you'll find me tall
Prince real story
Reproduction help from Katie pulverman
It was edited and produced by your hymen.
Missy harbin
Angeli Supra
Israel story is a great new podcast from PRX and tablet magazine toasted bye mishy Harman stop the show
A lot of people including Ira Glass call it
The Israeli This American Life they specialize in telling human stories and Arabs
Secular and religious people
From 1 Most Fascinating places on Earth
You can find all their episodes every place that you get podcasts and on their website
Israel story. Org
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan
Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars on kalw San Francisco
Offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
Family Guy
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled into weed
Who discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You find the show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Instagram Tumblr and Spotify the best play
Place to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world is on our website it's 19
NPI
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com