99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Met last time I went out there was 2005 us
Early stages dating this lady
I went over to ask the guys had this crazy dream
Where you and I we're like walking through a field and and camp on a spaceship
You want to go there
You like what you talking about
I know that's a place we can go we can go it's not far
I finally saw this place she was just like overtaken with
How magical it was too to see this thing that just doesn't seem real
Why are you guys taking us out to the middle of nowhere
Don't know where we're going to go it's a secret
I was really lucky to grow up in Ann Arbor we had a great record stores in Ann Arbor
Palace movie theater
And of course Ann Arbor is the home of the University of Michigan
So there was a lot going on for small town
But it was a small town
And I
Was a misfit
And like a lot of young Misfits in small towns
I was bored and disaffected and angry
That Misfit is Alex Goldman
He's a producer at the radio show on the media may now lives in New York City
I hated High School I was a bad student and most of my friends went to different schools
In fact
Although I come by Alex my entire life
That's actually my middle name
My first name is Michael
And for at least half of my high school career
My teachers and peers all called me Mike
It was like I walked around pretending to be a completely different person for most of my way
I felt like I didn't belong anywhere
I desperately wanted to escape this oppressively small town that felt completely devoid of wonder
And then I found her
Okay where are we
I hope someone brought a flashlight
It's take my body
The only way you found out about Hayden was if someone took you there
It was like there was the secret Club of kids who knew about it
I got initiated when I was 15
You drive out in the middle of nowhere
Deep in the country
Impark alongside this dirt road
We've got to get over that fence
There's this fence that you had to climb over
The sign on a guy's I don't know about that the sign read turn back on back
This is private private property
You're not welcome here for any reason
Please
Now
Turn back and leave in peace turn back and leave in peace
It almost felt like a dare
This is going to change your life
Once you are over the fence
You pass along side a white farmhouse
The guy that owns that house
That he shot a kid full of rocks off reading near his house
In the kid alive
A path behind the house led to this thin line of trees but once you made it through the trees you're in this huge field
And there was something else there in the field
Something man-made something really big
Forgot to do when we get up to that clearing
Fast as you can until you see it
Whoa
Welcome to Hae Eun
It's beautiful
The structure is made mostly of wood
With a canopy of Teflon and nylon stretched over a metal frame
From the base there were stairs leading up to a platform about 10 feet off the ground
Suspended over a boulder up about the size of a Volkswagen bug
At the top of the stairs there were these two pieces of glass in the floor
And one night a friend stood underneath with the letter while I look down from on top
There was an etching on one of those pieces
It said
The Hayden Pavilion
Hey
There was other signage to
One sign that Turtle welcome to there
This Pavilion
Is a work of art
Designed and carefully put together for more than 2 years
How many workmen artisans
If you buy some happenstance are now here in this place please take pleasure and serenity
But please do not disturb it
Nordic face it's Beauty in anyway
It's beauty alone is your reward for Meandering here
For your respect
The spirit of a designer artist will leave you in peace
But then right next to that
There was this other side
It said and I'm quoting
If you are here you shouldn't be
Is it privately owned Farm off-limits to Outsiders
You have crossed clearly marked keep out and no trespassing signs on fence lines and Gates
Please
Now
Respect the owner's privacy by leaving this place in peace
Thank you
Some of the no trespassing signs may have backfired a little bit
Because there was like this I feel like there's a sort of contrariness two teenagers where it's like
Well if there's that many no trespassing signs
Be awesome
I rounded up a few of my high school friends and talk to them about hey you
It seems like it's still as entrenched in their mind
As it has been in mine
It was a blue my mind first time I saw it
I'd best describe a union
Who's never seen it
Biggest
That's maybe the size of a small house or Hut and it looks like a hot air balloon with a jellyfish mushroom mushroom
Assertive
Telescope
Observatory spaceship a rocket ship
Or something that looks
Very alien
Foreign sitting in the middle of that Big Field
The place definitely has a Stonehenge
There were a number of myths about why he was there
That was built to commemorate the owners dead daughter
There was built along Ley lines
That was created for a wedding ceremony that it was designed for paganistic rituals are for stargazing
The place was such an enigma there's no way you could have known it was out there someone didn't take you to it
The first person who founded has been lost to history
By the time I was taking there
It was an oral tradition handed down from one group of teens to the next
Part of its power was that in being Secret
I created a community
Bound people together
Appealing for an angry 15 year olds it was
A secret
Sneaky
Teenagers only like
Kids versus adults secret time
Hyun was was mysterious beautiful and peaceful and it just kind of reassured
About all of your inner turmoil your of your deeper questions I guess it's almost like it was designed to
Inspire teenagers in the local area to come out there and hang out and drink beer and smoke pot and
You know kind of capture their imagination
I probably went out there once every couple of months for the next 4-5 years
We go out there and drink do drugs sometimes just talk
And of course it was always thrilling to bring new people out there
Indoctrinate our secret Club
Plenty of romantic relationship started out there
The first time I made out with someone who became my girlfriend happened while we were sitting on Hayden during a rainstorm
It was otherworldly and magical it fell out of time
And it felt like it was ours
Going to visit a unit was the perfect mixture
Danger
And secrecy and
To capture fifty-year-old Alex's imagination
For the next decade-and-a-half
Even after I moved away in 2001
I was fixated on trying to find out why it was there
7 mm and 9 I wrote a letter to the white farmhouse we always snuck past on our way to hey you
Asking them if they were the owners
Alexander letter back they didn't own a yoon their neighbors did
Rita and Peter Hayden
That's when I realized that what we've been calling the Hayden Pavilion 4 years
Was actually the Hayden Pavilion
That Gaelic font made the D look kind of like a second o
And we'd only ever seen it in the middle of the night
If the names Rita and Peter heydon sound familiar
It's probably because they're nonprofit the Mosaic Foundation has been underwriting public radio for decades
By the Mosaic Foundation of Rita and Peter Hayden based in Ann Arbor
Honoring the literary arts and the universe of great ideas
Do good work
And keep in touch
I sent the Hayden's a letter
Apologizing for my youthful indiscretions
And asking them if I could interview them about hey you
Peter Hayden Road back
So you're one of the little too invaded our privacy by visiting our Pavilion when you were told at many places along the way now
Not to be there
This was in 2009 before I was a public radio for
I was just a guy New Yorker fix computers
And a guy who used to trespass on the Hayden property
The rest of his letter was friendly but he wasn't too keen on talking to me
I couldn't let it go that I communicated with the creator of Hae Eun
And that the mystery could be solved
It drove me bonkers
So in 2012
After working in public radio for a couple years
Now I had a better excuse to try to talk to Hayden
And I decided to try again
Peter Hayden can be a hard man to read
He doesn't use email he doesn't always answer the phone
He was reluctant to give an interview for fear of attracting even more people 2 a.m.
But after a couple phone calls in a few facts messages
He agreed to meet me for an interview about Hae Yoon
Hey you
It was like meeting the wizard
Yes I am hi nice to meet you
Let's go back up there
Okay which fits you want to go to the first gate just south of that white residents
Yeah and during the day
Certainly has
Computer
Alex nice to meet you nice to meet you Alex
Thank you so much for agreeing to do this yeah
I have mixed feelings about as you can imagine the at-bat in my effort to try and respect the Hayden's privacy
I offered to refer to the Pavilion only as hey you
And not use his name
But he told me from the beginning that he wasn't interested in an annuity
He was interested in privacy
I don't think that I want this to be anonymous
I wanted to be with my name is
Attached to it
But that doesn't mean to say that we have to violate our privacy we don't have to tell where it is we don't have to
To say whatever I mean if you said Ann Arbor that's good enough note most people would not know
I was actually going to be even less specific I was going to say Southeastern Michigan
To give people less of a so my name from our credit in PR
Eden Peter Hayden
Based in Ann Arbor
Honoring the passion of NPR journalists all around the world whose stories take us there everyday
Harbor that's what it says
Always
Peter Hayden told me that Hayden was designed by a friend of his
An artist and designer named Joseph kinnebrew
When a massive blizzard came through in snow the men
We were trapped in our house down at the bottom of the hill for 5 days
Just the four of us
We got to know each other quite well during that period
I think Joe is nuts and I like being around him I find him
Can a person I'm not
Close
That's brain
McKenna Breeze came back for a visit
And I we went to a downtown restaurant we got absolutely suddenly drunk
We had planned and he said I'm going to build you a pavilion I said okay will do this invite by dusk
But we decided we come out here and look at this field
Send
Position where the pavane was going to be have a flashlight
Watch these two stumbling drunk walking across the field and Joe said I can't see you nice
He said
Place an order for me to see you I've got to have a light and I said what's I going to be
Isabel
Here's a piece of the New York Times when you do a florist we'd let the stand are we could set the whole field of light we've eaten
And so
That was exactly the spot where I was standing with his burning newspaper
It was funny stuff to
Watches working at night
And running around with a burning newspaper
Decided to build hey you
Peter paid for the parts and labor design for free
I found that the creation of helium came out of the same sort of drunken Antics my friends and I would get into
2 almost two decades later the same spot
That you could trace its origin story back to a sleepover
Peter couldn't give me any particular reason for its existence
It just there because it is
Because it's beautiful
Because it's art
Do I was a professor of English at the University of Michigan for 20
For five years
Sorry in the 1960s and up
So I do not have a kind of anesthetic
View of what
Or is
It teaches you
Steps
By which wisdom is gained
In that sense art is useless
It doesn't have any Pratt
Golang pack and sew for me
This Pavilion was always sort of that
It was
Something that
Was
Place for contemplation in place for
Pleasure
For enjoyment for conviviality with people that I chose to be here
Peter's relationship with Hayden feels like an echo of the possessiveness
The secretiveness
The ownership that me and my friends all feel for
The only difference is that Peter actually owns it
Like us he feels protective of it
Unlike us
He's actually responsible
Over the years
He said to clean up the mess left by drunk teens and even some damage left by Vandals
Unlike you I'll explore some heads that came out here and actually did some damage
So we had to repair that is ax
The cut the
Covering
We know there were parties out here we had
Candles and things like that sometimes it looks like there maybe it have been
Religious things going on here that may have been
Poetry readings and it was
You don't think of him as a sex
You know I don't think you were orgies out here I think a couple would come out here and
Weather Berea
Compelling to be part of nature out here
Ynobe
When was the nature especially in full moons and stuff that was always a very
Seem to be the tractor times
People be out here
I'm sure you know
Was talking to my friends about the signage that's out front and the
The first sign the sign that says you know
Prospectus and leave this in peace congratulations this is your reward for finding this
But anyway please continue
Well I have the reason I say that is because one of my friends said to me
I kind of believe that they wanted us to go out there
They wanted us to find it and
And that's why there are so many signs daring us to
To visit it
No that's absolute fabricated that's that's wishful thinking on your part nothing like that of the sort we wanted
If I Choose You Liza that's my business that's my religious
Experience
It's not a
Kumon Temple for everyone to utilize
It's funny you should put it that way
Because that's exactly how my friends and I all felt about it then
I still do now
Even though we ourselves
For trespassers
One of my friends I talk to you for the story Jason vanmatre
Put it this way
They were like certain kids who would I would talk to her
Oh yeah that
That Pavilion out there I
I took a six pack
Wasted out there
I feel
A little bit hurt by that
You just going out there
Drink
He's talking about
Your 30 pack of
People riding zebras
Dalian like
Sacrilege
It's like my shirt
It's like
Sacrilege
My church
When we found trash at Hayden left over from other people
My friends and I would clean it up
Or at least try to minimize our impact on the
Buffer Peter that doesn't matter
We are all just a bunch of
Interlopers
Did you go to Pioneer High School
Actually went to all three I went to Pioneer community and
And here on in the course of my troubled High School
The English language you were able to read things especially something it's
Subtle like that like that
But I would challenge you to say that was an invitation it was not an invitation was really meant to say look
Here's the fact you're here
You come to this place
I don't want you to do any damage and I don't want to piss you off so here's what I'm telling you
You know leave
Admire its beauty but leave
Don't stay here leave
And I think that was the message that I wanted to I wouldn't want them so I didn't because you know spending
20 minutes in your sock drawer as opposed to 5 if it's for 2 minutes in your sock drawer
It's just
It's okay if you can kind of
Fluted to me in some ways when people
Didn't know didn't invite had nothing to you had no knowledge of and who
Whose values and whose
The sense of Aesthetics are not the same as mine I felt that he has a personal violation
Talking with Peter I can see how much he values privacy
And having control over the stuff he owns
He hired a former cop to drive a decommissioned police car around his property
Scott lights and sirens and a logo that says rph security
As in Rita and Peter Hayden
He says it's mostly to keep out Hunter
What I say is like we don't allow
Hunter's we allow
A hunter
Who hunts this property
He's entitled to take one Buck a year
His many doses he wants and when he did catch kids that we're out there to sneak into Hayden
He make them give their names and addresses and make them write letters of apology
He still has a lot of those letters
Gift for all Peters possessiveness of Hae Eun
He doesn't actually do a lot with
You know the place itself
Is not meant to be used
For me anyway
Another words it's it's
Perfectly
Good being by itself not having any Auto
Kittens
Peter has private wine tastings winter twice a year and he Yuan and maybe he'll Wander over to it from his house from time to time
But that's pretty much it
And it doesn't really matter
Peter's the actual owner of
He can do anything he wants with it
He can use it
You cannot use it
Even talk to me about how he thought of tearing it down
And you can it's his prerogative
The way he can get to it doesn't get you
Is under total control of the Hayden
But when you think about design intent
What humans actually designed to do
Then one other person for whom it might be fair game to weigh in
This guy so happy
In spite of Peters unhappiness about Interlopers
That
Young people
Amen to sneak a peek
This of course
Is Joseph kinnebrew
The designer taehyung
The guy who got drunk and set newspapers on fire with Peter Hayden back in the day
He left Michigan decades ago and never had any idea that a unit become such an underground attraction
He's taken
Somewhat different than Peter
I'm delighted I'm absolutely delighted
How could I not
Feel
Good about what you did even though you weren't supposed to you're all quite naughty
That's quite alright
It's one of those things that life should include
Granted
Joseph kinnebrew
On my Peter Hayden
Doesn't have to deal with
Interloper
Coming on his property doing god-knows-what under the cloak of Darkness
But Canterbury says that it's bigger than a question of property
Is the impact that the Pavilion has a maslansky
On the psyche of the people who come into contact
Through means legitimate or not
For kenebrew
Hanging about in the world
Pasadena tomato paste you have this wonderful thing that used to say you know once they're peeled are packed
Referring of course to the tomatoes tonight
I'm gone I'm out of the picture doesn't even belong to me anymore
I'm not even sure that thing belongs to the Head
Is he
Possessing it has nothing to do with it
Actually nothing
I remember as a youngster sneaking off to look at something called Peabody's to which is left
Is a mausoleum
Tibetan monastery
Visited on occasion
6 bus to Chicago
Where I grew up
Legislative
Peabody was in this glass coffin with
Years old for God's sake
You're still holding on to it
Even though I'm sure it pisses peterhead enough to say this
I can't help but feel like part of a unit belongs
I think that other people I know have a similar feeling
There were a couple of people who refuse to talk to me
Because to them to share Hayden with the world
Is the ruin
We found a photographer quit taking some pictures of hey you
But when we asked him if we could post them to our website
He replied with an emphatic
No
He did not want the secret getting out on his watch
And I have to admit I understand where they're coming from
When I put out a call to friends on Facebook to see you would talk to me about
Summer
What say you
And they gave me the same sense of exclusivity
Hopalong
That I had when I was a teenager
And now
Over the course of producing the story
I've actually gained a kind of buy-in from the grand Arbiter of hating himself
I no longer just a little
Peter hate Alex look you're a different person
So then you were then
Secondly
As you know
The radio guy
I like voices
And I like
The word pictures that people can
Weave on the radio you you you came credentialed because
I hear your voice I hear your name
Alexson at this morning I heard your name on on the media again
You know so what are you what you associate producer
Yo I'm proud of you for doing that
I'm grateful that I ever got to see her
But I live in a world where
But I'm also grateful that I live in a world where their magnificent structures that are made without me and mine
With nobody in
And while I'm out of it
And attempted to protect it by only gifting at the certain people
They are just trying to do the same thing
So even though this feels a little hypocritical
I have to say it
If you ever find yourself out in the middle of nowhere in Southeastern Michigan
You happen to come across some foreboding sign the side of the road
As a favor to the Haydens
And me and my friends
Please
Now
Turn back
Leaf
Don't stay here
99% invisible with producers week by Alex Goldman and Sam Greenspan with me Roman Mars
The people I was interviewed about break into human with him when he was a kid or Rob Logan terekhova
Ben Tidwell and Ryan Fred Thomas Jason vanmatre and Alex Berg
Hopefully the statute of limitations on trespassing is up by now special things
Cast of radio players including Cameron lock Ashley and krichbaum
Pat mesiti Miller they did not break into a eunuch they did on my backyard
So please don't
Write us and asked us how to find a union
We do not know
Alex did not tell us
Flashlight
September 14th
No flask
No flex
Disney characters
No flashlight should I start over
Does concludes he Yuan reenactment
June 7th 2013
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects
Tax in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but as I said we couldn't post
Photos of Han so we have the incredibly talented graphic artist Emil Homewood of the Caravan make us a real
Great illustrations to go with this episode so the story continues and 99% invisible
Dot org radio Japan
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com