99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When you send a letter to the president it first passes to the office of presidential correspondence
The office was started under President McKinley in 1897
Twitter receiving about a hundred letters per day
By the time Herbert Hoover was president that number had gone up to about 800 letter
Verde
Today the president of the United States gets tens of thousands of letters Parcels in emails everyday
Matt president
Mapreduce this story is still
Barack Obama
Dear mr. president dear mr. president mr. President we met 1
You came to my hometown to Tuscaloosa Alabama
With Canada
And if you are one of those letter-writers
You must
Imagine
The odds of the president
Actually reading your letter
A pretty slim
Beth Jacob Brogan
A writer for slate.com and host of working
Asleep
And you be right
Those chances are pretty
People often begin with a reflection on
I know no one will read this
I mean that as a really common open
But someone does read your letter or email
And sometimes that person is Fiona Reeves
Director of presidential correspondence at the White House
We are the office that handles all the incoming correspondence from regular p
Ball to the president in the White House
So where at
A group of small offices made up of
45 Stafford
35 interns
In about 300 volunteer
Everyday Fiona and the small army of people read through thousands upon thousands of letters addressed
Address to the president
President Obama has requested that 10 letters be
He passed on to him to read every night
And it's filled his job to decide
Which town
It will be
The president have asked since day one to read 10 letters
From regular people that
What's coming in
These letters
I think do more to keep me in touch with
What's happening around the country than just about any
That's a clip from a 2009 video put out by the White House
Some of them are funny some of the merengue
A lot of them
Saturn
Frustrated
About
Their current situation
Sometimes people reach out about being fired
When they're down to their last breath
Types of savings
Are there concerns about gun violence
Climate change
So a lot of
The stories
A heartbreak
People who work hard
A lot of times I'll say I've never written to a president before
I'm not looking for a handout
All I want
Is just a fair Shake
And
It ends up being a powerful motivator for me
You know it is it is crazy to
That you are holding my pee
Paper that
What's in a person's hand when they were
Which apps are government is crazy
The president holds those pieces of paper
Of course these days letters don't always arrive on paper
Fiona and her staff also have to sort through all the emails that come in
Through the White House's Web format whitehouse.gov contact
Truthettes
Where in email office for the most part but we have a room at that really looks
Like what you think of a snail it's white
Nail in shelves
Topics in a list of what kind of agency is
Dental Works in the executive office building located just west of the White House
We are scattered throughout this building in whichever rooms happens he available
I can tell you we are tightly packed here we sit very close together
In the staff sitting side-by-side in the office of presidential correspondence
Securities on an old tradition
I'm opening reading and sorting letters for the present
I would say our paper processing
Cannot be very different than it was a hundred years ago through a screening process
So when the office of presidential correspondence receives them
They've already been opened by Secret Service
You know checking for anthrax
Explosives
Paper letters are clipped to the envelopes they arrived in
But then it's up to the staff
Can interns and volunteers
To dig through the letters and emails
And figure out
Which ones to pass up the chain
Fiona
How many do you have to be today
It varies depending on a day but I would say on General de the number that gets rid
Past me
Melton Motors
And you read
Can you read that many emails and letters
Everyday
Roughly
Everyday the presidents in town
He only
When he's in Washington
Fiona and her team are looking for a range of opinions and styles Express what Americans are thinking about
Want to give him
Now that is representative of geographically we also
But for different writing styles and different levels of writing in Waze
Communicating the office also put some thought into where the president is heading in the coming weeks and what issues he'll be just
To try to maybe make him better equipped to a Time in Mexico
To discuss an issue that maybe he doesn't have a personal perspective on sort of a way of
Giving him more advisors
And the letters don't just inform and influence the president
Fiona make sure the entire White House get the chance to see what people are rioting in about
Each day our team does something without the volunteers called a random daily sample
So we'll look at all the email that just came in and put
Together
A list of topics and for imposed and we circulate that list
Throughout the White House trip reprod distribution group
I guess folks
What the American people are saying that day
They also put together a word cloud that shows the most commonly used terms across all forms of communication
The biggest word as hell
Because generally when you're reaching out to your government you are looking for help with
Must you
There are times though
Like you can see right now the biggest word is gone
Where there's
Conversation topic
So in that case
Fiona will make sure the president gets a letter about guns
When we do that we make sure he sees
Both sides
And we think a lot about the order in which things are given to him you know
How you write something
I think affects the way it has
And after Fiona chooses the 10-letter she hands them off to someone who scans them
And then hand them to the person who puts together the
Husbands briefing book
I reach my heat
Text Mom homework binder and
It has information on what he'll be doing the next day
Every night include
I'm like almost everything else that reaches the president these letters have not been fact-checked her committee reviewed
They're some of the most direct communication he receive
When people are writing a memo to the president
Enough air
I Ching on a policy topic
And everyone who has hand in that or who may have information to Advocate add value
I take a look at it and ask her
And so by the time the president
See that
It has gone through so many eyes
Our correspondence
Is really like someone sits down at their kitchen table
Anime
And Anna kissing their mind and then
That's basically two sets of eyes in the White House
Volunteer if I hate
Fast and then it's me
Yeah I agree with that
And because these letters are so Direct
An unfiltered
A lot of them are pretty intense
Empty plate
Personal
Our office
Deals a lot and emotion and empathy because
We are absorbing so much of what people
Hope
Next year and what they're expressing to
Who's the president of the United States but also
Barack Obama in the way they see themselves and Barack Obama and that
That I think makes our work play
Quite an emotional one
A lot of people write about where their writing from
For what time the writing
Now I'm staying up late at night because I can't stop thinking about this
Open that transports you immediately what are they going to say or
From my kitchen window I can see these mountains that we call and I nearly
Kitchen with them
We also recently have seen more and more letters
The begin with something like
I've been meaning to write this for 7 years
I think
Yeah as the days dwindle down we're getting a lot of
Under The Wire
Here's what I've been meaning to tell you
There was one letter
The President yesterday from a man who wrote
.
He
Feels like pee
Because
Present sir
Pervasive nature of
Violence in the US
Despite
Being a gay man in the United
I like you would rather live somewhere that
Didn't recognize same-sex marriage on a place where
He could be discriminated against
His ankle Darren
If we just gave out
I don't last night so I don't know how that hit him when he read it but when it hit me hit me hard
Are there any are there any that were there
Bunnies that are that are the kind of the other side
We got some funny letters one
Have with me
Is
From a young woman who was
Running for class president of her
Junior class
And she
Rodan that
She wanted some
Speech writing advice
President Obama actually responded to that letter
Is advice
Keep
Speeches
Short and some of them he responds to my hand
Some of them he writes
Something like
Neil can you look into this that ass would have to ask someone out on his
Team to take a look at it
And on others he writes reply
But then he right sort of
Crafting items
The White House at the team of writers who elaborate on the president's notes
And turn them into letters
Which they then hand back
For the president
Design
And because he's responded personally to so many letters of the year
The writers often have a really good sense of his voice
And often his margin notes are so expensive he's practically responding to the letter himself
Fun Riders
When the president does engage with the letter whether by replying or by extending it
Invitation to a White House Event
Orta highlight
Specific letter in a public way
The White House
Usually gets in touch with the author
Sometimes Fiona gets to be the one to make that phone call and the truth is we don't always need to make those phone calls
We make them because they're really energizing it's just
So exciting when someone has taken this crazy long shot of
You're writing something to Barack Obama and putting it in the mailbox when you call them
Sometimes people flip out
I generally make those phone calls
And I sound
More serious than I feel when I make them you know I found your address one in my heart
Can you believe me
Fiona's excitement is palpable
She's been a part of this Administration a long time and it's played a huge role in her life
She met her husband while they were sorting Obama's mail
And the job is that a real impact on the White House and the people who work there
I think its shape
Houses built the White House
Mercedes I think also
Its shape
Egg-shaped the humans who work here you know you can't help but think about it when I think about that
Water bar office
1 is
We
Pretty big team
How young people who will go on to do other things and we'll go on
Broader perspective
And then some
Personal perspective on
What people who they haven't
I feel and expect
And Fiona is about to be one of those many people who have passed through the office
Because her job is ending with the administration
And what's next for you
I don't know
I have no idea
I think it's a funny place to work
Has
Institution
For so long
Begin again before 8 years
I'm so
And when you are getting ready to leave
I figured it out or nailing it
The White House is keeping their contact us form open to the last day of the administration
January 19th
Even if you write a letter on January 19th
It can reach Obama
He'll be receiving 10 letters on his last night
A version of this piece originally aired on slates working
Broadcast as part of a series on jobs at the White House
Sounds produced by Jacob Rogan
And Vicky Capper
He 99percentinvisible teamwork on this episode includes Avery troubleman
Sharif Youssef MKT Mingle
With her Cole stats and Greenspan Emmett Fitzgerald Karen Meza Delaney Hall and me Roman Ma
We are Brotherhood 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce
On radio row
MP4
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
To find the show in joints Cushing's about the show on Facebook tweeted me at Roman Mars and the show at 99
NPI org
Run Instagram and Tumblr to but every day I read 10 messages
I sent it through the contact page
GI
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com