99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1883 Samuel Clemens Alias Mark Twain published his memoir
Life on the Mississippi
Init
Queen describes his love for the Great River
And Howard captured his imagination from Boyhood
In fact
The pen name Mark Twain
Probably a reference to what a deckhand on a Mississippi riverboat
Call out
To indicate a depth of two fathoms
These are recordings Murio Steamboat worker from 1939
Twain would have heard this call many times
As a young man he worked as a steamboat pilot
On the Mississippi
This was a job that required him to learn everything there is to know about the red
That's a Ryan Kyle
He's a reporter at New Orleans Public Radio
Working on steamboats
When would come to memorize every Scholl
Bend Rock
Island Bluff Reef wind Reef Eddie snag sandbar
And he would learn how all those things change
When the river was high or when it was
Is low
Incomm breezes
High win
Nighttime
Date
Wayne Road
The face of the water became a wonderful
Mark Twain loved working on the river but he found it came with a price
Has he gained knowledge about the workings of the Mississippi he began to lose something to
A sense of wonder
About the Great River
Twain writes about this in his memoir
I had lost something which could never be restored to me while I live
All the grace
Beauty
Had gone out
But not everyone had such a complicated relationship with the river
For many people who live near the Mississippi it was simple
The river was a force
To be reckoned
When you talk about the Mississippi River
To me it's not something saying
This
Great force
I'm enormous power
This is John Berry an expert on the river's history
He served on the Levee Board of New Orleans
And has written extensively about the Mist
And the thing to know about the river
Especially back then
Was that it
Flooded
All the time
A river flight or at least I know flood like the Mississippi
You can see coming for weeks
Fight it
4 weeks in in 1927 people knew the river
Was coming for them nine straight months the middle of the country have been getting hit nearly
Non-stop with rain and the previous winter there been tremendous snow fall river in Minnesota
Who's now washing Downstream the levees were strained and in February of 1927
They started giving out y75 was probably worse than Katrina
Roughly a million Americans
Almost 1% of the entire population of the country at the time
Flooded out of their homes
That's spring 145 levees along the Lower River
Fail
27000 square miles
Penn State
Or put under water
It's unclear how many people died because for One Thing official counts didn't include black people
But the death toll was likely upwards of a thousand
On April 30th 1927 then Secretary of Commerce
Herbert Hoover
Discuss the play
On a national radio broadcast
Everything humanly possible is being done by men of magnificent
Courage and skill
Oncoming Rush
Metal
The engineers are directing
You got to remember
This was enormous news
Dominated
The front page
Lindbergh
Flew across
The Atlantic in the middle
Flood that's the only thing that
Knocked it off the top
And after the flight
Looks like Meats back on
In the wake of the flood Congress essentially declared war on the Mississippi River
I passed a law called The Flood Control Act of 1928
Apart of
28 Act
Involves studying basically every major
River basin
A River Basin is all the land that water flows through on its way to a river
Sabrina sample if it rains in South Dakota
Anywhere in the whole state
That rain will eventually make its way to the Mississippi
Which means that South Dakota is part of the Mississippi River basin
Even though it's actually pretty far from the Mississippi River
In 1928 Congress decided to study rivers and their basin
Especially the Mississippi and it's enormous basin
Which includes more than 30 States
And not just study them but
Also changed
The Flood Control Act charged the US Army Corps of Engineers
With designing and executing
Plan to Corral and maneuver them
To better manage
Abs
Lowe's
So that future disasters could be a bird
With the Army Corps of Engineers face a dilemma
The river control system that they had been tasked with creating needed to be
Huge much bigger than anything they never built before
And I didn't want to just jump into building something until they knew it would work
They started constructing scale model
Different parts of the Mississippi River basin
In order to understand them
Hammocks at the river
The earliest ones were ditches cut into the dirt with water running through
The models help forecast flooding in St Louis the impact of a dam Construction in Ohio the working
Kings of spillways in New Orleans and Florida
But the Army Corps of Engineers wanted a way to test the entire river system all at once
So in 1941 they started building a model to represent all 1.25 million square
Square miles of the Mississippi River basin
When you think of a scale model you might be thinking of something you can peer into a museum
Not so with this one
This would be bigger than
Anything they could ever fit into a display case
Is a jungle out there
The Mississippi Basin model located just outside of Jackson Mississippi
Is a scale replica of the entire Basin region
An area that spans from Appalachia to the Rocky Mountains
Nearly half of the continental United States
We'll have to crawl through here
Check I hope we don't get your equipment
I went out to see the model with a woman named Jamie Vaughn
Cheese to work at the model as a
The technician
Before it was decommissioned in the early 90s
Jenny showed me how to sneak in
Right through a wall of poison ivy
I just always ask
Did any snakes
Will
You know kind of runoff
We're also there with former project engineer Wayne O'Neill
I'm waiting on you
Amici
Now that we've made it through the IV
We make our way to this
Enormous
And this
Is the beautiful Mississippi River
Macy Mississippi Basin model
Wow in all its Glory
Wow
Ryan is looking down in a three-dimensional map a completely man-made landscape
Hills and ridges
Big winding River bat
Every foot of the model represents 2000 feet in a real-world if you take a good step
You stepped off a mile
It's hard to overstate how enormous this model is
Is about 2 1/2 times the size of Disneyland
125 city blocks
I saw some pictures online but
This does not prepare you to Caesars thing
It's awesome isn't it
Just also
You just can't take it all in at once
Damian Wayne tell me that you can really only see all the edges of it
If you climb up this for story observations
There's also a water tower
Looming about them
Turn the pipe shooting off in every direction
In the pump houses
Spigots
These big hulking machines
Strange looking instruments
Dottling
What they had
Envisioned when they
Built this
It's just
Fantastic
Back when the model was operational
There were little sign
For pretty much every town in
That would be one for Vicksburg and Rolling Fork
And all along
The signs are gone now but Jamie still knows the geography of this place
Buy Hardware around Baton Rouge
So you can go from Baton Rouge up to St Louis in about
10 minutes
The Army Corps of Engineers started work on the Mississippi Basin model in 1941
And it first
They faced a massive labor shortage
Start of the model came about during World War II
No labor
What's available
Everybody was off at War there wasn't troops are people here to do it
So they built a bill to be Camp here to supply the labor German prisoners-of-war help with every fast
Of the construction
And they did the groundwork and the
Typography layout and the drainage system
For the model
By 1949 the model was ready
Staff of 600 engineers and technicians with calibrate the model by recreating past floods in the region
Then they'd forecast new flow
They would run thousands of gallons of water through the model
Recording the waters height
After it was all done
Did change a few variables
More sandbags over here open this
Spillway over there they played around with the motto
Gathering data on how each piece of the river system
Affected the whole
Then they could use that data to come up with better plans for
The future
Like they did in 1950
When Council Bluffs in Sioux City Iowa were threatened with a
The model predicted
Where the ladies were going over top
Overtop as in where the water would spill over the Levee
And so they ran the model night and day as they were fighting the flood what they were doing here it'll overtop here
Your put your sandbags but you working this area
And of a predicted stages with into tenths of a foot
Meaning the model mimics the actual behavior of them
Mississippi to Within
Inches
It was credited to saving over 50 million dollars in damage in 52
That's about half a billion dollars in today's money
The Mississippi Basin model was amazingly Act
Dealing with these incredibly complex
Hyper-specific
Problems
The model save the government millions and millions of dollars while it was in operation
Inspired people from the kinds of disastrous flooding that had happen
Back in 1927
But two hundred acres of pipes pumps and machinery and Earth movers and a staff of hundreds were expensive
To maintain
Because got even harder to justify after the Advent of the computer
Late sixties early seventies there was a big push to go into numerical models
Math model
The numerical model playful and
Core looked at the mall us as well
We don't need it anymore
Expensive
Gradually the Mississippi Basin model
Lost its funding he saw the handwriting on the wall and it
The closing is down
The computer models weren't is good but they were good enough
And the Army Corps could not or would not
Pay for the gigantic River Basin model anymore
The muscle is used in a diminished capacity
Until 1990
When it was closed for Good
Today it's
Completely Darrell
Damn this place is depressing
Rap
Everytime I come out here at work
A lot of Labor there's a lot of
Lovin
And when did this thing and it is just
Abandon
I feel like if I was a teenager this would be my number one
Come get high and
Get in trouble spot exactly
Exactly
The pipes in the pump house is rotting and rusting away
And in the model
The Earth and mud and water of all dried up
Now it's just a disheveled mess
Concrete and
Wire mesh I've seen the original design drawings this place
Those engineers
I would be doing good to sharpen your pencil
You know the mind that came up
With all those pieces of
Equipment with the knowledge they had in the 40s
And they're coming up with
Ways to protect people and make the stuff work
You just don't see
Engineering feats
Like that everyday
Now in a normal public radio story this would be the part where we would bemoan the death of craftsmanship in Rome
Mark on all the things we've lost by choosing virtual things over physical ones
But before you get to Misty eye
You have to see where Jenny Wang work now
How's it going pretty good
Hey did you get any
Poison Ivy the other day I didn't I didn't
About two weeks after going to the Basin model Ryan that Janie at the US army engineer research and development center
Verdict
In Vicksburg Mississippi
I keep forgetting that you actually work for the Army and like badge in the real deal
Mama jokes
Yeah walking around Arctic feels like being on the back lot of Hollywood
Studio
There's no after row a big hangar
Full of miniature landscape
Is hangers over there and
Hangers over there
Hangers with model and model and model and model just lined up
Engineer zip around and trucks
Golf cart
They test all kinds of things
Including a few things that and have nothing to do with what
One hanger I saw Engineers developing a temporary airplane
They were driving over it with the modified dump truck on 14ft tires
To simulate the weight of
Mostly Ehrlich build scale models of rivers and dams and water
Albeit smaller more manageable ones than the Mississippi motto
So we're looking at
Bluestone Dam
In Hinton
West Virginia
It's on the
New River
A place that actually did Flood recently
And the Army quarters models help to manage that flood
The Army Corps also uses the models as a public relations tool
Decor and bites people from local communities over to artic
So they can see how new projects
Like building new navigation channels or removing old dams will affect the area
Engineers at Artic say they take Community feedback and incorporate that into their designs
But here's the most surprising thing I learned about these physical model
The reason that engineer's continue to rely on them is because
Today
In 2016
We still do not have the computers or the science
To do all the things
The physical model
Girls can do this actually this
Realm of human knowledge
Physical
Behavior and how the Earth Works
That we don't understand
This is Stanford Gibson
Senior hydraulic engineer for the Army Corps
This is a guy with a PhD and three Masters
Even the math
He can do isn't sufficient to fully describe what happens in a river
I think that there
Needs to be a little bit of scientific humility to say
Well
Maybe some of these processes are outside of our reach at least outside of the reach of Our Generation
Are we going to get there we'll get closer
Believe It or Not Hydraulic Engineering it's in the some of the most complicated math there is
Allegedly when Albert Einstein son Hans that he wanted to
Study how sediment moves underwater
Einstein I asked him why he wanted to work on something so complicated
The physics involved happen on such a small scale that we still haven't built equations complex enough
The capture
Stanford Gibson
A world-class numerical model
Is actually one of the most Ardent supporter
A physical map
Because a physical model
Doesn't require equations at all
Physical model
Will stimulate the processes
On its own
And even if Stanford Gibson develops new numerical model
The process is inherently tied to the natural world
When I start a new project
I go and I rent a kayak
I float the river
Because there are too many processes that you don't understand that
You can't represent in the equation
Stanford the more time you spend on the river the more you learn it
Secrets
Kind of like Mark Twain
And all those years he spent working on Steamboat
Learning to read the Mississippi
Like a book
You know it did you ever read Mark Twain life on the Mississippi by did
So you remember that whole like maybe a hundred Pages near the beginning
What are you talkin about the Mississippi for him was
Like this
Magical
Mystic
Golang imbued with
Mystery and that once he learned the river
That was lost to him forever
I remember that moment exactly
Because that is exactly not my account
The idea that science demystifies the world
I just don't understand that
I feel like the kind of deeper down the scientific Rabbit Hole I go the bigger and grander and more Magical Door
World famous
And the same goes for going down the rabbit holes of history and engineering and Mathematics and Design
If there's one thing I believe more than anything
Is that knowledge
Creates Wonder
99percentinvisible was pretty so sweet by Ryan Kyla same Greenspan and Delaney Hall with Sharif Youssef Katie Mingle
Kolstad Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Mark Twain was played by Ken toys and Herbert Hoover was refused
I love the music in this episode came from some of our favorite favorite musicians including lullatone melodium and
Okay,
Give me the full list at 99 Pi. Org
This episode is part of pure X's stories in science project supported by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation to enhance
Public understanding of science technology and economic performance
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa is talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find the
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com