99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Spell this out I'll leave it on the door
So that the owner is aware of the fact that we made a visit
And that
They need to take care of
The lawn
They may not even be aware of the fact
City Gainesville has Norman
Prohibits
Jessica Graf
In communities across America
Moms that are brown or overgrown are considered especially heinous
Elite squads of dedicated individuals have been deputized by their local governments or homeowners association
To take action against those whose Lawns failed to meet Community standards
Call them lawn enforcement agency
Producer Sam Greenspan
This
Is his story
In 2008 a lawn enforcement agent stop buy a home in Hudson Florida
Outside of town
Maybe the agent snap some photos maybe there was some boxes ticked off a checklist
Whatever the agents field method
He or she went back to lawn enforcement HQ
And sent out a letter
They send out letters stating that you know
European your Lawns not up to par
You have a lot of bare spots
In a lot of weeds
My sprinkler system was busting I didn't have the money at
Demri Parrott
That's Joe prudente who with his wife Pat
Owns the home in question
Lawn enforcement thoughts of the prudente is long with two brown chewy d
I'm not well maintained this was not the first such letter that the prudente is had received
But Joe prudente says he is no deadbeat over the course of a few years he had tried to keep a clean
Mean Green Lawn as best I could
He watered it
He put down grass seeds and grass plugs
He even dug up and completely replanted the grass in his front yard three times over
3 *
The first time I had a company do it
They charged me like $1,200
And I said I'm not doing this you know every time it dies Joe met with his homeowners association
But they were not cutting him any slack
So then finally they
Did some ruling that that if I didn't put sod down the whole place
Dale a law firm was sending it
To the judge to the court
See what would happen
Are they going to lock me up then I got to put me in jail
Banana pudding
Brasstown listen to fetch crazy
Shortly thereafter Joe got another letter
I don't want everybody to see police coming to the house
Caught me a wafer
Rob the bank and you know how neighbors are
So I did it to them the choir way I turn myself in
At 66 years old Joe prudente
And otherwise law-abiding retiree from Long Island
Presented himself to the Pasco County Jail wearing a grandpa gone wild t-shirt
He was apprehended on allegations of failing to properly maintain his lawn
To community standards
There was no bail
No bail until the side was done
Now fortunately for Joe the local paper had written about the arrest and detainment of a senior citizen for having a
Brown mod
Word got around and dozens of people came to help dig up Andre saw the prudente is lon
Joe was released from jail the next day
Most cases of homeowners brushing up against the lawn enforcement
Do not end in jail time
The only person to have ended up behind bars because of a landscaping issue
Frankie Rose of Grand Prairie Texas did two days in jail for having an overgrown lawn
And Gary settle a seventy-five-year-old former city council member of Riesel Texas had a warrant if
Issued for her arrest until some neighborhood kids came by and
On our own
There's a paradox for the lawn
On the one hand it is the pedestal on which sits the greatest symbol of the American dream
The home
And homeowners are independent and free
Have dominion over their own little corner of the world and yet
And yet
The lawn is the least
Freewheel control
Landscape
Insofar
Constantly pressure
Nearby formal or informal
In the management just like their neighbors
That's Paul Robbins director of The Nelson Institute for Environmental Studies at the University of Wisconsin-Madison
And I'm the author of the book lawn people
How grasses weeds
And chemicals make us who we are
Grass maybe a plant
But a lawn
Is a designed object
Elan is an entirely design.
Imaginary nice
Clean Green Lawn
That's entirely engineered
Landscape
And the reason we maintain this landscape says Paul Robbins
Is about everything except the grass
It's about every
It's about Community it's about
Proper moral Behavior
It's about participating in the life of a community
Even in the beginning Lawns were always about
The lawn or really the idea of law
Began with art
The Italians for a while we're painting these
The Pastoral
Scenes scenes full of grasslands and had to
Grasslands in hedges
That didn't actually
Exist
No I mean these are pastoral images out of somebody's imagination of what the landscape
Should look like
Chinese paintings got popular among Great Britain's landed Elite
They like the painting so much but they wanted to live in them
What
The British were doing
Designing their landscape to look like what was
Trending in Italian
Paint
So life definitely followed art
In this case
A style of English garden developed where a prominent feature is a green lawn
And by the way everyone recognized that is soft
Verdant grasses were more than just a nice place to walk around barefoot outside
Elan
Was about
Power
Elan was away for these English Elites to show off
They were so wealthy
They didn't need this land to grow food
They can afford to let their fields go fallow
And could afford to keep raising animals inside wielding peasants to keep it short
When European colonists set sail for the new world they took grasses with them
But morons were still mostly for rich people and eventually public parks
It wasn't until the turn of the 20th century with the first suburbs
That lawn started appearing around the homes of the middle class
And here is where the launch
It's from being about the flagrant display of wealth
To a moral Force for the good of civilization
Andrew Jackson Downing considered by some to be the father of American landscape architecture
Who is slightly older than the other guy considered to be the father of American landscape architecture Frederick Law
I know you're thinking it nerds
Downing Road in 1850 quote
When smiling Lawns and tasteful Cottages begin to embellish a country we know
That order and culture
Re-establish
There's kind of a social message which is that if you make it
Look like this we will make
Better City
As opposed to write having
I'm living in squalor
And the urban areas are considered evil
Unproblematic will maintain lawn in other words is the opposite of a broken window
It's precisely
People think whatever is going on outside
If it's civilized manicure.
Reflects something is going on good inside the house
With the start of the Great American suburbanization in the 1950s
Suddenly middle-class people were owning a larger and larger swaths of land
So covering it with grass was
Partly utilitarian you know you have this big piece of land they got to do something with it
But this connection between Lawn & Order
Only grow stronger
E&R lawn
Got bigger we did an air photography study and you
Tax assessor
Stayed up for Franklin County
Columbus Ohio
Typical
American city and we found that about
Percent
The entire County
Was turf grass lawn
That doesn't include
Football field
Golf courses
A quarter of the entire city of Columbus
Islam
Grass living a completely unnatural life cycle
We don't let grass grow tall enough to go to seed
But we also water and fertilize it to keep it from going dormant
We don't want to die
Reproduce
The author Michael Pollan wrote that
Lawns are nature purged of Sex and Death
Feed
Weed
Cut
Repeat
Paul Robbins interviewed dozens of people about their lawns for his book
People told him that if their grass got too long
Neighbors would come by and ask if their lawn mower was broken and need to borrow one
People who wouldn't blow their lawn might find an aggressive neighbor had done it for them in the middle of the night or while
How they were out of town
Uomo because everybody else does
The free-market American
Free
Neoliberal subject
It does that
He or she pleases would just say to hell with my
Let my lawn grow
But instead they do the Communists
Which is collective management
Of what is essentially
Commons
It's not your lawn
It's the whole communities
Your response
Deviate from acceptable Community norms
And your community goes to war with you
What does how you get cases like Joe prudente being thrown in jail
For failing to keep his lawn up to quote on quote
Community
One of the guys in my city
I said the Griffis of smoking it or selling it
But as much as the lawn seem to be rooted to the American landscape
We may be seeing a transition
At least here out west
Where in historic drought
And that demands
Unprecedented Act
Trump treason
I miss you
Executive order
Men dating
Substantial water reduction
Across our state
California Governor Jerry Brown declared in 2015 that our state would need to cut water use by 25%
Read a new era
The idea of you
Nicely green grass
Lots of water everyday
Skimpy thing of the past
Here in California the lawn is perhaps the most visible symbol of the drought
Water restrictions allow people to water only two or three times a week
Down from four or five or even more
In California and Arizona and Nevada
You're actually paying people to rip out their grass
Prices range from a dollar to as much as $4 per square foot of turf removed
Which homeowners continues to buy artificial turf or use it for xeriscaping
Which is Landscaping with things that don't need water like
Rocks
Some people are also choosing to put native plants new yards which theoretically should grow with rain water only
And would help restore the ecosystem that have been there before
Or you can just let your lawn go Brown
California has a bunch of public service announcements that are all like
Look at through this truck just
Movement that help fight the drought
Get down with brown
Brown
The new Green
Do your part
To help Cal
Nobody bought a home in this country to have a brown lawn this is America
We have green grass for a reason here that's the American dream is to
Have a green lawn so
And last a little bit
And our service and you can have a
Green Lawn during the drought season
Is David Bartlett of extreme brain brass
He is decidedly
Not down with brown
I'm David Bartlett with extreme Green Grass and we are
Turning her brown grass green
And he doing this by literally painting a customer's laundry we are spraying on and on
Natural Earth friendly
Product that we manufacture called Extreme green grass
Last 3 to 6 months was golden brown
It had been watered in 6 months
David uses a spray wand attached to a tank full of liquid which he swears is non-toxic and as he's spraying
It's like magic like he's transforming a Wheatfield into a soccer pitch
I cut the grass is still crunchy
Unfortunately
Target changes out process I'd be rich
You do anything besides green
Yeah we do white. Christmas
Precision
Megan looks like you got a
Snow your kind of looks like you went up and got some
Snow from the mountains
I like pink or purple Orange
I'll do that for you bro
David got in his line of work after a friend got him a similar service for his lawn as a gift
David has been working in landscaping and
Thought he could do a better job than the other company is he insane
Mom painting is actually not new
But if you've never heard of it it's because it's generally only been used on golf courses and pro sports
It's only since this most recent drought that lawn painting has come home
I first heard that long painting I had assumed that we stopped at by the lawn obsessive kind of people who had
But a lot of extreme green grasses clients
Are homeowners association
1 painting
Is becoming accepted by even the strictest lawn enforcement agency
It kind of makes you wonder if we as a society are beginning to
The question the supremacy of the
Perfectly kept lawn
Maybe
We can finally quit lawn shaming each other
This is America we can always find ways to shame each other
I think it's very very
First thing to see what's happening
In California
With
People getting on each other's case
We're having
After all these decades
Getting on each other's case
For not having
That's Paul Robbins again now we have a case where the drought has inspired peep
Really wack 100
On the Internet or whatever else
Shame people
For putting water on their lawn
See Twitter hashtag
Drought shaming
Paul says it's good that people are looking to conserve water
But the moral architecture of drought shaming is a little too familiar
It's just the newest trend on how people beliefs each other's lawns
It's just another version of the same thing
Like moral outrage that people are not doing their share
Is soda bad
A natural response
Two people's Land Management
Just like it was for keeping a lawn green
And so if David Bartlett does his job too well makes Lawns look too much like they get tons of water
His customers Micah drought shamed by people who have gotten a little too down with brown
As they say
The Grass Is Always Greener
Even when it's brown
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan
Katie mingle Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Thank you to Issac Brown and Eric Flagg directors of the film gimme green
That's where the tape of a lawn enforcement agents
Have you heard the beginning
Originally appeared
Will have a link to the film on our website
Things also did Devin Brown
Robert Fogelson Brent Green Sharon Hall
Kelly Lawrence
Molly Peterson Taryn Smith and Kelly Turner
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced are the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If
I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get
Podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about some
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find this show and likes on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but you can listen to every single app
Episode of 99% invisible pictures and lots of other stuff there too
At 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really
We jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com