99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In September 1958 Bank of America decided to try and except
One that would have far-reaching effects on our lives and on the account
They decided after careful consideration to conduct this experiment in Fresno California
The thinking was
No one was paying much attention to Fresno
The plan failed
It wouldn't get a lot of media attention
Dangerous low back down here
Fresno was not the big metropolitan area is today
That's Joseph Russo
My name is Joseph Russo
I work with Bank of America since 1956
Henry tires 1985
Started off as a teller and worked our way up
As most of us
Young
Fellas did
Joseph was there when all this went down
And so in September of 1958
Bank of America sent out 60000 pieces of mail to people in Fresno
Inside with a little plastic
Checked has become an equal parts emblematic of opportunity
Convenience
And that
He's talking about the credit card that's reporter Nate Berg here to tell you when I'm talking
Bank of America had recruited about 300 merchants in Fresno to accept this new payment
And they asked employees like Joseph two-hand credit cards out
The people they knew
We did we pass around our friends and you know the neighbors that's about it
But that's for Joseph
He was skeptical about using a credit card himself
Be honest with you I don't remember if I took your car drive better in order
If I waited a couple years
But dog
As a bank riding reap leaving credit myself
Minot
Well you have to pay back interest and I don't like giving money away
Joseph wasn't alone
The whole town of Fresno was a bit nervous about this new credit
Card system
The concept of credit wasn't new
But it never been done
Quite like that
Going back in to say the 1800s early 1900s you had
Credit with a store or some kind of a business
It was just kind of a ledger book type of thing
This is Ken hallenbeck
He's a numismatist
A numismatist
That is someone who studies or collects currency
Not just coins but it's paper money medals tokens
Anything that some money or money substitute can is retired now
Who used to work
The American numismatic Association
New Miss Matic
So back in the late 1800s
Every place from the Corner Bar to the local pharmacy
The allowed patrons to keep open tab
Big record everything in a ledger book and allow their customers to charge of a bill that they typically pay back
At the end of the month
For businesses this was an accounting nightmare
Stores could have hundreds of accounts billing tabs for a dollar here and
Dollar there
And with each
Chart a shopkeeper would have to haul out a ledger book
And look up a customers records just to complete a transaction
Eventually store owners cut down on some of the paperwork by assigning customers account numbers
Which state would inscribe on little token
Most of them are round or oval a hole in them and they had a number on him and that was your account number
Kim has a collection of a few dozen of these old credit
Many dating back to the early 20th century
I have one here at
Pocahontas
Pioneer
Garage
But it has a head of an Indian on it
And in the back it has a number 839
After credit tokens came something called charge of
They look like little dog tags for the Army
They were metal and had your name and information imprinted on
Shopkeepers could make an impression of your personal information directly onto the bill
Instead of having to write it all down
The more accounts you had the more charger plates and tokens you had to carry around with you
It still wasn't a great system for the retailer or the customer
So in 1949 a New York businessman named Frank X McNamara
Came up with an idea for a single charge
Card that could be accepted at multiple established
He called it
The diners
Club card and with it you can make charges at a number of New York restaurants and hotels
But unlike the credit card of today
You could only use your Diners Club card in certain places
The idea caught on someone
About 20000 people signed up mostly businessman
It wasn't a smash success but still the bank started to see an opportunity
So you have this
Giant change taking place
Right around and especially in the aftermath of World War II in the American economy was the basically
The only economy in the world that was
Still Standing that's Joe nocera
Columnist for the New York Times and author of a piece of the action
How the middle class joint the money
Keepall
I haven't gotten to the war
Settling down
You know getting married raising kids wanting to live in the suburbs
There was suddenly things they wanted to buy
Refrigerator for example
Or as
Cayman divoga television
Do you have a Sears account
You could buy things there and pay your bill at the end of the month
We didn't have an account with a store you'd have to go to a bank and get a traditional loan for any relatively large
Large purchase
What it was
Car whether it was a sofa
Weather refrigerator you'd go to the bank
Every single time every single time you know you have to
You know have collateral to pay for it
Every single time
The bank it would have to figure out what you were good credit risk it was it was a pretty cumbersome process both for the
Consumer and for the bank
Bank of America wanted to find an easier way to make
Make these small loan
Bank of America
Was
In the 1950s.
Premier
Consumer-oriented
The bank and then I
Bank of America really believed in the idea that
Would grow
By helping consume
So it was Bank of America that decided that they would basically give clients a car
Did they can put in their pockets
That would give them roughly a $500 line of credit
Unlike the Diners Club Bank of America one of their customers to be able to use their card anywhere
Not Justa restaurant
And where the Diner's Club had to be paid off within 60 days Bank of America would allow its customers to pay them back whenever they
They wanted
They called her new credit card the BankAmericard
You could spend it all down you can pay part of it back youku
Call back
You didn't have to get a bank or to approve your purchase
And you didn't have to pay the bank back by any specific time
They called this revolving credit
The card was essentially an instant loan
Of course it was a loan with an interest rate attached
This was one of the
Profound shift
And the way people handle money
Instead of it the banker being
In control
Your money
Upsetting the terms
For how you dealt with your money
With a credit card
You were the one setting the
And you were the one making the decisions about what to do with your money
Now all Bank of America had to do was convince retailers to
Accept credit cards as payment
It convinced people
The user
Now because they were a new invention
And because people didn't really know what they were
And because there were no laws
Surrounding
Credit cards
The way they tested the car
Was they simply sent a mailing
To basically every Bank of America customer
In Fresno California which brings us back
To Fresno
They called it
The Fresno drop
Bank of America mailed out 60000 credit cards all over the
Fresno had become a laboratory
For the future of personal finance
The Fresno drop was supposed to be a controlled experiment with a bank could test the concept in work out any kinks
But within just a few months of the Fresno credit card drop
Bank of America's Got word that one of its competitors in California was planning a similar program
So Bank of America quickly expand
Mass Millions went out in the Central Valley Cities of Modesto and Bakersfield
The bigger cities of Sacramento San Francisco and Los Angeles
Within 10 months of the Fresno drop
More than a million BankAmericard have been mailed out across California
Once the cards have begun saturating the bigger cities
People would go around to mailboxes in the suburbs and steal cars out of on days when the new
The car tripping dropped
The system was being abused
But the system was also randomly mailing out pre-approved
Credit card
Is that allowed anyone to buy it to $500 of whatever they wanted
No dead people get in car dogs will get in cards
It was just very very willy-nilly
Despite these Mass mailings the cards didn't catch on right away
It was hard to convince stores to accept
They had to pay a percentage of the sale to the bank
It was hard to get custom
First used
And when people did start using the cards they didn't always pay the money back
Which was a bit of a surprise to Bank of a
People that mostly been pretty good about paying back traditional loans
And what they forgot was in those days when you made a loan
The customer look the banker in the eye in the bank or look the customer in the eye and they both had this kind of relationship
And the customer would not want to let the bank or down
Whereas with the credit card it was an anonymous thing
And this one in four people weren't paying their credit card debt
In 1959
About a year after Bank of America did their first mass mailing in front
They mailed out more than 2 million Bank of America
But they hadn't made a single Cent lyrics pyramid
The fact
They lost about 20 million dollars
Until the bank
Started making a few changes
They really start to think about it differently
Bank of America setup
The collections department
People who weren't paying their bills Heather cards revoked
The government also started to regulate the credit card act
In 1968 the truth in Lending Act made it illegal to mail out credit cards to people who've never asked
From that point onward
Instead of getting a card
In the mail you got instead of solicitation to apply for a card
Which
It's in one form or another existed
The stack it wasn't until 1961
3 years after the Fresno drop
The Bank of America actually turned a profit
On their crazy credit
They were making about 13 million dollars a year
The Bank of America system which became a nationwide system
Eventually became known as Visa
And the other card
That had competed with Bank of America they also Consolidated and they became Massacre
The major credit card companies now make lots and lots
Lots of money
Every year
Which is great
For that
Maybe not so great
The rest of us
Today over 70% of American adults have at least one credit card
And the us as a whole has about 900 billion dollars in credit card debt
In 2009 more credit card reform was passed
It prevents arbitrary interest hikes
Stop credit card companies from specifically marketing to college kids
Prohibit certain types of abusive fees
But a lot of people think more reform is needed
The experiment in Fresno created a tool that made buying things much much easier
You no longer had to put on a suit and a tie and go to the bank for a loan every time you wanted to get yourself something nice
The credit card facilitated an unprecedented amount of economic freedom for the middle class
Aspect was intentional
And maybe even Noble
What is important to keep in mind that the credit card
Who designed to make money for bags
And everything about their design betrays that primary objective
Credit cards don't have to be complicated
They don't have to trick you
What they do
Because they were designed that way
I got a gal.
Play
A big snack
99% invisible West producer Suite by Nate Berg with Katie mingle Avery trufelman same Greenspan crew Kolstad and me
Roman Mars
Are Delaney Hall
Sharif Youssef
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Five podcast
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify and B are fascinating
On every but for the easiest way to get more information on every single episode of 99% invisible is at 99
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com