99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
Just a quick note
This episode is a little on the crude side
Nothing too terrible but
It gives more kids you might want to listen to this one first before you let them listen to
Cut the check it out
Thanks
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
There was a rubber shortage in the US during World War because we were fighting Japan in many of the country
Raise that supplied are rubber
So the government funding Research into synthetic rubber to make up the shortfall
What are the products of This research was a new material made by mixing boric acid and silicone oil
Bounce said he could stretch it was rubbery
Sadly it could not be used to make tires or rafts or gas masks
It had no practical use at all
But a marketing consultant discovered that it was pretty fun to play with
So we put it in tiny plastic eggs and sold it
And silly putty
Hey hey it's silly putty time yesterday
Hours of hours of fun in the little egg that silly putty comes in
We're surrounded by products that were designed for one purpose but found their true calling in another line of work
That is Amy standing co-host and co-creator of the new KQED podcast the leap
Play-Doh was invented
Clean Coal set off
Walls with Viagra and Rogaine
Are designed to lower blood pressure
Before they found their real purpose
Making boners and growing hair
In all these cases the original designs Were Meant to solve big important problems but they had to settle for less
Less meaningful get no maybe slightly more delightful rolls in the world
But in rare cases The Story Goes the other way and something designed to be a trifle
A gag
Joke
Stumbles upon its true destiny as something heroic
An honorable
Ladies and gentlemen may I introduce you to the heroic and honorable product
Known as liquid ass
Liquid ass is a bottled smell and you can probably guess
It does not smell good
That's an understatement
It's important that you get how bad the smell
Kind of Lynch
This whole story
So while I was reporting this I made a bunch of people in my life smell like
White throat constricting
It's super
Real
Do you feel like there's a sense of Shame associated with that smell
Yeah like
If you feel like you should
It smells like exactly
That you did
This terrible smell it was invented by a guy named Alan Whitman
A teenager Allen's main interest was pranks
Smell related
There's one with Limburger cheese
Something else he called the
The ketchup situation
But it wasn't until he began experimenting with a chemistry set his parents gave him that he created his master
When asked what exactly the ingredients were but he is a very comfortable describing
How it smells
It smells like ass
It's like it's a butt crack
Kind of sewer smell with a little head of
Some dead animal in there
But crack with a hint of dead animal
15 years liquid ass languished in smell obscurity Ellenwood use it to pull the occasional prank but it never
Ever found a larger audience
And then when he and his friend Andrew Masters lost their jobs at a trucking company they decided to turn this terrible
Herbal smell
Into an income
Enter now and didn't even have to advertise
Liquid ass radio talk shows did it for them
Have you ever seen that does a bottle
You don't liquid ass liquid assholes
Hitman the liquid ass
Howard Stern
The opium
The orders poured in you can probably imagine the
Clientele teenage boys playing
Extremely stupid
But then it 23 years after its invention liquid as found a higher calling
Pinterest
See who produced a bunch of television shows in the 90's
Including the shows Hunter Renegade
He was a cop
I'm good at his job
He committed the ultimate sin
And testified against other
The cops gone bad
And Silk Stockings
Silk Stockings with one of those shows you might have watched on the USA Network on the people you were babysitting for didn't have HBO
Stu's business was thriving until right about September 11th 2001
My business changed after 9/11 because
The networks want to get away from violence
You want to get away from shooting things and blowing stuff up and
What is dramatic change
Flatline my business for
Quite a while
One day we were
In
Sick of making television
And the next day we weren't
Set seat belt we're just sitting there
Gathering dust
Vacation idea for only business
Maybe cops who needed training could get some use out of those old sets
We did quite a bit of training
How best to respond to a school shooting
Or had to carry out a drug busts
Where to position the officers
Break down a door
This was good business and then in 2003 the US invaded Iraq
Reservist for being called up to go overseas
And a lot of them stew already knew because he's for the same people cops me like they've been training on his set one day
He got a phone call
Call me open today
I got a hundred
50 guys sitting here on the tarmac we're going to a place called The Rack
We got about a week
Don't you help us out
So that's how it started
Stew's big idea was that he could use not just the stats but the whole lineup of Hollywood effects
To create effect
Assimilative
Combat show soldiers
Exactly what they were
He says no one else was doing this
18 and 19 year olds were being sent to a rod with almost no sense and how the place would look what the culture was like
How to communicate with people
Always training was pretty much sterile
Are make believe this is a dork
They would take the Marines and turn your shirts Inside Out say okay
Those are the bad guys
It's not raining it's not realistic training
She says the military has gotten a lot better at training
But in the beginning
KissAnime
Mission was to try and make trainees forget that they were on a TV set in Southern California
His SATs should look and feel as much as possible like the kind of place a group of Marines might go out and Patrol
Anorak
We're in a simulated Iraqi Village
Upon this Tower here will have two huge speakers
Playing card prayer
In a simulation this whole place would be full of actors
Actual araki's who live in San Diego and now get hired as extras to
Like a rocket
The Village has a complete fake araki Marketplace
Benzoplast
The cucumbers and yams stand selling Dusty old Sony Discman Zayn
Clock radios
Can others hear work very hard to make this place look
Realistic
Android can do this because he did two tours in Iraq as a medic in 2007 and in 2008
And he remembers exactly what it felt like to walk into a village like this
How unwelcome he's out there
And how much the Iraqis wanted him to go away they feel they're just trying to live their lives
And now we set up the space right outside their Village
7 a simulation the whole place
Supposed to feel on edge
Like Anything Could Happen
And then
He well sometimes well pipe in the sound of a scene from Saving Private Ryan
Just to pant
Things up a bit
You can talk about it
Intellectually beforehand
But once the gunfire goes and people are screaming and yelling
All the things that happen
Israel
Except
I know he bleeds out
We can do it again
Stu says kissing recruits wet their pants even throw up in a simulation
That's normal reactions
The screaming the smoke
Explosions the disorientation
Have it all teenagers some of them are going to have to make decisions in the midst of all that
Life-or-death decision
Some of them the Medics will have to deal with horrible injuries
Amputations severed arteries
For this they use a cut suit that was invented here at strategic Ops
Kept in a locked storage shed
So
The main thing we do here
Yaz with this
Wow
Tattooed as in a suit that you cut Works kind of like a fat suit
Arms go through here
So the bass goes on
Skin goes up
Over top
You step into the legs
The front side goes over the top of the best
Zips up in the back
It's a realistic-looking body that you wear over your own body and then with the help of makeup artist
Inflict
Horrible
Very realistic injuries on to
Bullet holes
Shrapnel wounds even disembowelment
Chinese can learn how to perform or assist surgery on a cut suit where the intestines are literally hanging outside the
And for that scenario there is something very important
They need to learn and it is in the context of these very realistic combat scenario
That we will be reunited with the true star of the story
Liquid ass
As A Firefighter knows the smell of smoke as a barista can sniff sour milk
Surgeons know this smell
They fear it
Because this smell is a signal
But something has gone
That there's a tear in the end
Then and feces is leaking into the air
Abdominal cab
No pun intended ocean
This is a huge infection risk
People died this
Whatever surgery you were just doing or attempting to do
You just complicated it by 10
Strategic Ops
Prides itself on areolas
Hypertrophy
So they needed to recreate that oh s*** moment
Show young soldiers what it would be like today
Encounter this in the midst
There was only one smell
For the job
We found a bottle of liquid ass in the
Take It Outside
Will Smith
In his hand
Greg holds
Auction that Alan Whitman in
Oh it's so
It's it's like
It's so bad so many ads
Years
Yeah fecal
Dried
Nasty
If liquid asked for a person
I don't think it would be totally farfetched to call this
Because to strategic Ops this ridiculous disgusting prank product is also indispensable there one
Liquid ass is most loyal customers
Stu says 750
3000 people have trained
Strategic
Liquid ass
Some of them might be better prepared
To save the life of a
A fellow Marine
He or she screams in pain
Mystic
Exploding RPG
Machine gun
Surrounded by a miasma cloud
Of the worst smell
In the world
99% invisible with springs this week by Amy standen she's the co-hosting co-creator along with Judy Campbell of the new
New KQED podcast delete
Storytelling podcast about people making traumatic risky changes will have a link on a website
99% invisible is Katie mingle same Greenspan Avery Kauffman Kurt Kolstad and me Roman Mars
Recording from Autodesk University in Las Vegas Nevada
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
The finest architecture and Interiors firm
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and likes on Facebook each member of his team is on Twitter and Instagram I recommend you follow them
I'm all and you can find out more about this episode and listen to every single episode
99percentinvisible
At 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com