99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
Our motto is always read the plaque
It's always worth stopping to see what person or event is being commemorated in stone and Metal
Person being depicted is not always worthy the story being told
If not always true
Lights off until you more about the person who commissioned them than historical figure that they are honoring
It's still worth always read the plaque
But it's not enough
To just meet the black
If I did nominate one person to write all the flags in the world my choice would be Nate dimeo of the Memory Palace
He produced an episode about a statue and an imagined plaque in 2015
Adjust destroys meat so good
I've been thinking about it a lot recently
And I want you here
Notes on an imagined plaque
To be added to the Statue of General Nathan Bedford Forrest
On hearing the Memphis city council has voted to move it
An exhume remains of General Forrest and his wife
Mary Ann Montgomery Forrest
From their current location in a park downtown
The nearby Elmwood Cemetery
First it should be big but black
But necessarily because there's so much to say
So there is so much to say
But big enough to be noticed on the side of this rather Grand Monument after they move it and the bodies beneath it
Across town to the cemetery
And that's as big for the sake of bigness
He needs to stick out
Is something off
Something that disrupts the admirable balance of the statue
Currently so tasteful
Regal even
Is bronze man on this bronze horse
Goatee
Square jaw
You got it
You seen it before
Even if you haven't seen it before
The statue faces North
This culture wanted for us to face South
You better catch the Light
But people complained
Implied that the general was retreating
And he wasn't a man who retreated
He surrendered once
But if this culture face North
Maybe people would forget that part
I guess
She has to be big enough to catch your eye
When you're checking your cell phone or walking your dog eating a chicken Caesar salad from a plastic box and a bench
Whatever people are doing there in the cemetery and whatever they might do there in the future
Because that's why we make these things right
Plaques
Bronze man on bronze horses
You want people in the future to remember
But first we want them to notice
So let's think about material for this imagine black
Because the flag should be garish
Not intentionally ugly not necessarily but like titanium Maybe
A patch of Frank gehry futurism on the stage state legal thing
Catch the lion
The catch the eye
In contrast to the northward facing brown green man
On his brown green horse
Or a great pigeon
Elite on his brown green at Gillette
I like that the Geary of it all the futurism
Is not at all futuristic it's millennial
A decade from now it'll be dated literally dated
Do Bauer Disney Hall or wherever will seem so late 90s
So 2000s
Window scarf
They want that
I want this pain to be fixed in time
Let people know when it went up
Let people know what was up at the time
Because Dad at the point here
The point of this plaque is to make sure that these future people realize
That this lovely old statue
Wasn't always old
He wasn't always here in the cemetery
And moreover I want the reader
Standing there in the shadow cast by the late
Somehow still demented
Nathan Bedford Forrest
Once and future summer Sunday
To know why it wound up in a park and the other side of town in the first place
Because memorials aren't memories
They don't just appear upon death
Letter of surrender
Signing some Farmhouse at the edge of some Battlefield
Doesn't come complete with a historic marker it fixed the door
The monument to Nathan Bedford Forrest
Was put in that park downtown for a reason
At a specific Moment In Time
And at that time General Forest in mrs. forest
We're already buried in Elmwood Cemetery
The same place the city council recently voted to put them
His body
In her body
Were originally dug up from the ground
Because a group of prominent memphians
Thought they were better off somewhere else
That was 1905
40 years after the war
30 years after Forest death
They felt the city needed Nathan Bedford Forrest right then
Because they had seen that City fall from Great Heights
Memphis have been left relatively unscathed by the war
But not by its outcome
Not by the end of the slave trade
That had been one of the economic and cultural pillars of the city
Without the slave market selling men and women and children
Without the river boats and Crews and suppliers and dockworkers
Sending them up and down the river
Memphis was Harley Memphis anymore
And then there was the yellow fever
And it swept through the city some years before in killed so many
I drove many more away
People who never returned after a mandatory evacuation
And now it was the turn of the next century
In the city was increasingly
What you said
Which has stopped not saying things
Increasingly black
Increasingly tense
What businesses did not like competing with black businesses
Black people do not like being lynched
This move to move Forest started not long after Ida B Wells a memphian to get started writing
Rabble-rousing
Boldly bravely
Against lynching
After her friend Thomas Moss was improperly imprisoned
After a fight between children over a game of marbles
Escalated into adults were threatening to burn down a store
And after Moss wound up being pulled from that prison
Inspiron from a tree
In Wells with threaten so much so often
But she moved away
In the paper should written for burn to the ground
So wealthy white Memphis
The beginning of the 1900s
Found all this unpleasant
So they raise money
$33,000
Not to rebuild that newspaper office
Or build a police force that would properly protect all of its citizens
But to make a monument to a man they thought best represented a Memphis they lost
A man who had risen from nothing
A blacksmith's boy
Who became a millionaire
Men believe so strongly in the Confederate cause
Enlisted as a private
Then went on to prove himself perhaps the most brilliant military man
Born on American soil
Even if you didn't fight for America
Those are facts
It's a true story
And they like what this story said about the American dream
Even if it wasn't technically American
Even if Forest million was made by buying and selling human beings
In selling cotton raised and picked
And cleaned and packed
Enslaved human beings
Even if the cause for which employee that military genius
Was to ensure that men like him
Can Rise Up from nothing
And make $1000000
Buying and selling human beings
And stealing their lives in their labor
In 1905 they held a parade at the unveiling of the new Statue
Inmate speeches to honor the northward facing General
They said nothing of slavery
They said much about heritage
And honor
Chivalry
They said nothing of how Nathan Bedford Forrest
I've been the first Grand wizard of the Ku Klux Klan
Nothing of the terror it had wrought
Nothing of the assassinations
For the lynchings
Nothing of how it sought to undermine and overthrow the nation's political order
The nation that they celebrated their in Memphis in 1905
When they play The Star-Spangled Banner
Yankee Doodle Dandy
Right alongside Dixie
They might not have mentioned any of it
But they knew it
New about forest in the clan
They certainly read the Clansman
Was flying off the shelves that year
A novel about heroic man
Hidden beneath bed sheets
How to save white virtue from black barbarians
It was a historical romance
The top billed itself
It look back longingly to a time not long before
When people were still chivalrous
Would stand up against barbarism
In miscegenation
Instability
And stand up for order
Private property
Who better to represent what they had lost in Nathan Bedford Forrest
They talked about his heroism in battle
Don't they didn't talk about the Battle of Fort Pillow
Rainforest ordered the massacre of hundreds of American troops
Attempting to surrender
Most of them former slaves
We talked about his faith instead
Is strapping build
About their own homes
The Future memphians Would gaze upon Nathan Bedford Forrest
And be inspired
They even raise some extra cash for skating rink
So that the white children of Memphis
Play nearby in the shadow of this great man
And learn from his shining example
Do the bronze wouldn't Shine for long
With brown and green is the symbol of all that was good
Disposable light of the Sun
Washed by the rain
There is debate
There is always debate
About what the client meant when Forest was its wizard
Bad as intentions at Fort Pillow
They say forest repented his sins in his crimes in his Deathbed
Should that be in the black
She didn't notice his regret
Missingno
May it have ruined him
May it have corroded him like rain on bronze
Made him choked him
Like smoke from the crosses in homes and churches
Sprint by man who revered him decades and decades later
Revered him at least in part
Because some influential memphians
Decided they needed to Revere him in this way
And that Park
To the blacks to be big
But it can't be big enough to say all that
Maybe it's you just say
Maybe they should all say
Many many thousands of Confederate memorials and monuments and markers
Did the men who fought and died for the CSA
Whatever their personal reasons
Whatever was in their hearts
Did so on behalf of the government
Form for the express purpose
Of ensuring that men and women and children
Can be bought and sold
Destroyed it will
Maybe that should be enough
But I want people to know about those memphians 1905
Wanted people to remember for us
And why
Wanted a symbol to hold up in Revere
To stand for what they valued most
I want people to know that that statue stood in Downtown Memphis
For a hundred and ten years
It's remember that memorials aren't memories
They have motives
There are historical
They are not history itself
I want them to know why it was moved
That in 2015
After clementa Pinckney
Sharonda coleman Singleton
Tywanza Sanders
An apple Lance
And Susie Jackson
And Cynthia heard
And Myra Thompson
And Daniel Simmons senior independent Middleton doctor were murdered in a church in Charleston South Carolina
There were people in Memphis who are done with symbols
And ready to bury Nathan Bedford Forrest for good
In 2016 the Tennessee historical commission ended up denying the Memphis city council's plan
To move the Nathan Bedford Forrest statue from the park
It's still there as of August 2017
The events in Charlottesville Virginia have resulted in protest at the site of the statue
And renewed calls by the public and City officials
To have the monument removed
The Memory Palace is produced by Nate dimeo
You should subscribe to it and get all the old episodes are short their beautifully written and produced
They're wet podcasting was invented for as far as I'm concerned
The staff of our show include Katie mingle Avery trufelman Sharif Youssef Sean real estate Delaney Hall and it did
Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are protected 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio Row in beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Sea kelp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
Even show endurance test about the show on Facebook even tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show and 99
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to our lovely home on the internet with more design story than we can
Ever tell you here is our website it's 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Two days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Every takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast.,