99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We are a culture
Fascinated with style
It always seems to be some award ceremony or gala where people are talking about but everyone is wearing
But it seems like it's always Fashion Week somewhere am I right
Living every week
Like it's fashion
And there are street style blogs and
Festival fashion Roundup
And then out of the sidewalks and the catwalk
Dial emerges
Then it comes time for the mass Market
To get the look
Which might mean
Graphic t-shirt
Are hot right now
Are cobalt blue or minimalism
Are platform sneakers
And you might be saying to yourself
Trends Arbor trendy people I follow nerd stuff
Catholic podcast I don't follow trends
They might say that but they do
Professor Sarah Pettit
Calling everyone's Bluff
Kind of outright lying
They just don't realize what they're doing
Professor Pettit is
Coordinator of
Fabric styling Pro
At the Fashion Institute of Technology in New York
You might not realize it
But subconsciously
You can kind of tell when styles are shift
You may not think
That what you have on is Jaden
But this other thing suddenly male
Look new to you
And it's all over all the windows
It's all over all the racks
And you probably would get influence
By that
Don't you think so
Whether or not you consciously notice it
The trend cycle is circling
All around you
That's moving fast
It's not like we just have a spring fashion season and
Fall fashion season
There's now a steady turnover
Style
If you go to certain stores like
H&M
Change the wine Maybe
Every two weeks
Because
Avery how many
Close to any of us really need
They have to get US Destroyer close out so that we buy new things
This creates
Manufacturing this
Create sales
And it makes the monetary
Retail world go round
And it's not just clothes it's our home where
Are linens
Sarkar whatever
Our tastes are constantly made to change
Coloring
Is that kind of
Shane
Like Charlotte Russe
May come in every 5 years or so
Purple can be big
One year and that it takes
Facts about
5 years to
Come around again
Moose
Friends are
Question
Is about timing
That wedding
And pretend to come back around again
I got their timing right
A lot of designers and retailers and fashion students
Turn to one
Major
People use wgsn
Yes as a school we have access to
To wgsn
Wgs
End
Which sounds more like the name of radio
From wgsn
90.7
Your 24-hour
Christian companion
It is indeed a radio station in Tennessee but that is not the wgsn we're talking about
Wgsn
Is the company that might have determined what you are wearing right now
And I never heard
A lot of people haven't actually it's a little bit of an industry Secret in Iowa
This is Sarah Owen
A forecaster at wgsn
Which is a global trend for
Casting agency
Their other Trend forecasters and Trend forecasting companies but wgsn is the most
Influential
We have been around for 18 years
We're in over 94 countries in terms of clients
In around 6000 companies subscribe to us
And dumb
What does wjsn
This is why I'm not sure where that cuz it used to be
Worth
Global Style Network
Worth as in Market
Who founded the company in 1997
But after he sold wgsn it was called world
But mostly it's
Call wgs
So I think it's
Become an acronym that doesn't really have
A meaning
Wjsn is part publishing platform parts fashionhaus Part research company
And what they provide is a comprehensive website behind Annex
Tremont
Epayroll
Like tens of thousands of dollars depending on the size of the company in the subscription level
But pretty much every major manufacturer design studio and marketing company
Subscribe to it
And we have clients across ol
Industries not just retail in the fashion space
Do a few about clients range from fashion companies such as
Nike and Cochin HM2 food and beverage companies like Starbucks to TV network
Looks like MPC Nickelodeon toes quite varied
Wgsn reports on all kind of Trance
Including Behavior patterns
Consumption patterns and advertising prediction
The majority of their users are coming at it from the design.
So if you are a designer colorist or merchandiser for a major company or brand
You consult wgsn to figure out what colors will the
In what styles are ahead
And other designers heed this advice or not it's considered essential to at least know what wgsn is saying
Because they're commenting on Trends they notice in a really in-depth
Way
To that level analysis that you just
Can't find people actually just don't have the time
To do themselves
And to keep ahead of the trends
Wgsn predicts
Two years in advance
That's as long as we can really look look ahead without College a different quantity
Seed of analysis further out than that and it's really quiet
It's speculating guesstimation is you want to say but honestly I had a really hard time wrapping my head
Around wgsn and what they offer
Until Sarah let me take a peek at the site it is a website behind a paywall a really beautiful
Sleek website it almost looks like an upscale online store but then when you click a category
It looks more like a Pinterest page
Loaded with pictures
Catwalks images high resolution
Original image 84th Street style for trade shows fit denim in addition to all the photography of models
Festival-goers and beautiful stylish people there are articles and reports organized by category
Google fashion categories from accessories to be
Footwear kids way on women do I use
Denim get its own category
It's a huge Market
Did the den insinuated addendum director to I think denim associate editors
The editors are working on articles but not only find the trend
But explain them
Because we do work so far in advance
I did
Do a report
Close to two years ago I was cold and young contemporary contemporary
Next Generation
Consumers
Genze ujenzi is your teenager
She's about to go back to school she's back to school shopping
She still going to festivals
How she lives at home
She's always weighed digital-native
Multiscreen
Personality and Sarah's report found that genzie's Idols are
Fashion model
Not movie at
So these models are on Instagram and magazines wearing Couture on the runways
And this makes the members of gen Z want access
High fashion
Is consumer base is really being Prime to be the next luxury consumer
Enter that we we come to them
Fruition now it seems super Alabama two years ago was kind of
Stila testing idea with some retailers
And other researchers at wgsn are already preparing for the next wave of cancer
After
Gen Z generation Alpha
The newest that the ones under gen Z
Welcome to relevancy millennials
In addition to the reports in the images wjsn has this really fascinating component that makes it very
Very different
Journalism side or a fashion blog
They have a database
Full of colors
Patterns and 71000 original design template
For design teams to use
However they want
So there really is a lot that you can take as a designer
Open in illustrator Photoshop and rework it however works
XPO customer will get embellishments entrance and you have prints and Graphics as well
Do you want to make
Shirt
You could choose a template may be out of
Pocket or something
It's like a color swatch a pattern that wgsn says will be popular two years into the future and why
There's your design
Oh my God it's so these are these are jeans
For 2018 oh my God
What do genes of 2018 look like
I kind of can't tell you because wgsn is very protective of this information
And rightly so people pay a lot of money for it this precious until makes it fast and easy for design teams
To come up with new styles
Somewhere are you
Too easy
Mark worth himself the founder of wgsn sold the company in 2005
According to the independent
Wurth called his creation a monster
Same quote Shoppers complain that everything on the High Street looks the same but is it any Wonder
Instead of looking for inspiration brands or line on templates
Because everyone uses the same template
There's no competitive patch
Whether it was an adherence to an ideology of creativity and competition or just
An opportunity to build another business and sell it off again for tons of money
Mark worth
Started a rival forecasting company called stylist
The much smaller company
With two offices about
400 Club
And it doesn't have all the templates and ready-made designs
We don't tend to have like downloadable
Prints and patterns and things like that because
Fashion is just kind of one element of what we do that's Shannon
Forecaster at stylist
And their New York office
Stylus is also a website behind a paywall
And they do a lot of custom Trend report
Tailored to specific clients need
So basically are
Clients get a
Login
And they can
View all of the content they have a client services person
Send help them so if
America says
I'm doing a piece of research on
The future of bracks
Our client service person goes in
And says here's a really interesting piece
Piece of work that we did about fluid lifestyles in about people multitasking and this could affect the
Picture of breakfast
Future
Breakfast
No but really there are trends for breakfast
And stylist will say to the client here is what we saw something interesting from our packaging teen about you on the go Packaging
Which seems silly but that is really the kind of stuff that often like
Dino client
Have to think about wrap their heads around
Trend forecasting is not just about taste
Store aesthetic
Trends also take changes in life
So wgsn and stylus also work
What stats and projector
Like this one
40% of Americans work from home by 2024 some questions around my head am I okay so if ever
Everyone's working from home a sweatpants back in stock
That's Sarah Owen again from wgsn
Translate yes
Sweatpants are back in the trend cycle
But like cool looking sweatpants
But you could also wear to a bar
Both wjsn and stylist say that arrived in what they call the athleisure style of clothing
Which looks good at home on the couch
In the office or out at night
To me it's connecting the dogs
Pattern recognition
It's taking those cues that and pairing that would that Jada and that will kind of inform the future
Oh created that sound
Tagline
Create
Tomorrow
Is actually written in huge neon letters
Wgsn New York office
Which is
I don't know it's kind of strange to see
It made me wonder if wgsn was catering to my
Or actually
Creating them
For me they have such a strong influence in the industry
I can't tell if they're reporting trend
Dictating them
Yeah that's always a hungry like I said we do have some of the most
Time influential and recognizable brands in the world using us so it's like did we create it or was it actually
About to come to fruition
Shannon at stylist told me that even paint companies and textile manufacturers were using their Trend forecasting sir
Services to decide what fabrics and colors to make
Which then inform the transit stylist puts out
At some point you just lose track of who is influencing whom
But ultimately the buck stops with us
The consumer
What's the
The thing you can lead a horse to water or something
Drink Professor Sarah Pettit again you can show them
Things that are very
Far out things
You think they should buy
But if it's something that's not going to work
They're not going to do
For example Professor Pettit says there was a movement recently to bring back the mini skirt
They sorta okay that's been
Around while
And four units the new generation of
Kids with tray
Reintroduce
A flop
Totally
So if people
Really don't
It's going to
Slot
The consumer has a voice in this
And it's a very
Active
And lately it seems there's been
Great refusal of swords
A massive backlash
Against fast fashion
And transformed cells
It's interesting we've come off this kind of
Phase in fashion of trends
Changing really fast
A lot of design today is
Simplicity
Minimalism and quality
Even with with fashion
Which for a long time was super super Trend driven
That people are starting
Anything more about bass
Some more of having you know that
Great pair of jeans that they can wear
With everything
But Shannon seemed remarkably, she told me about this change in the tithe
She does not think the trend industry is doomed
So you know it's not like Simplicity means that people are just
Sweet Leaf
Not shopping and
Do you know everybody
Becoming
No anti
Consumerism
God forbid
Just that the things that made people buy before or
I'm going to say the trend of their future Trend but maybe that is also a trend
Sing shift
But it's not to say that it's not going to ship
It's hard to say
But what's the check back here
2 years
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery Trump
Katie mingle Sam Greenspan
Kurt koester
Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza
And me Roman
Special thanks to Cara Rose defabio of fusion
Without the article she wrote about wgsn we would not have known this company exist
What a link to that article on our web
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce
On Radio Road
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing.
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Family ghosts
Play the podcast the Explorers all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled a new Wii
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and join the discussion about the
The show on Facebook
Meet me at Roman Mars or the
Show Atlanta.
We're on Instagram and Tumblr to
But the Nexus of all things 99 Pi is at 99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com