99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The term hijacking
Goes back to Prohibition days
When
Gangsters would
Stop
Trucks carrying moonshine
And they come up to the guy in the cab with their pistol and pointed their face and say Hold Your Hand hijack
And they take all the liquor and then drive off at the truck
But in the early days of commercial air travel the thought that someone would hijack a plane was scarcely
Even considered
When they created government oversight of aviation in 1858
The Congressional
I did that did not
Nick hijacking a crime
Because no one had foreseen
Did anyone
And in a country like America
Where are theoretically if you wanted to go somewhere I could just buy it
To go there no one
Assume that any American ever do
And Brenda Nike Runner author of the Skies belong to us love and Terror in the Golden Age of hijacking says
Feather design of airport terminals
Reflected that
It's hard to Fathom now
You could literally get out of a taxi at the curb in
Walk to the terminal
Walk onto the tarmac.
The top of the boarding stairs
Turning onto the plane itself
Without a ticket
Without showing anyone your identification
Sooner than anyone searching your personal or your luggage
In any way shape or
So it was a very much similar to getting on a train and that was by design by the airline
Then starting in 1961 an epidemic of hijackings began
It really wasn't epidemic
And I mean that in saying that the devirus the behavioral virus mutated over time
What kind of basic features of
Did hijacking change
The first phase of skyjackers
May 1st
61 was the first American hijacking
Perpetrated by antulio Ramirez ortiz
He was kind of a
Someone mentally Disturbed electrician in Miami
Got on 80 westbound
White
Announce
With a holding a knife to the pilots throat that he had been hired to assassinate Castro
Fidel Castro and wanted to go there to warn Castro about this
In the second phase
The skyjackers broaden their Horizons
Two more distant lands
My favorite example is Amanda and Raffaele minichiello
Italian American Marine
Who actually went from Los Angeles to Rome
Howard Hewett
Hell of a hero upon landing and Ashley and up only doing 18 months in prison
Extradite him while she charged him with hijack
And after that
Signing a contract to start a spaghetti western film
Very good-looking guy then skyjackers more than the classic kidnappers demanding Ransom
Tamanna started this was a
Mini Mart agates Barkley unemployed truck driver had a
Whiskey with the IRS
And he actually hijacked
Plane from
Phoenix to Washington DC where he demanded
100 million dollars
In cash to be given to him by the Supreme Court
Enraged and taken attacks
So that kind of setup is last phase of the
People started asking
Confirm
Tons of money and gold bars
Creative liquor and cigarettes
Anything your heart desires
100000 in cash
Getaway car
I want the letter m
Stricken from
English slang
And all the while
Hijacking was never considered that serious a threat by the airlines
Or the passengers really
He was more of an inconvenience in any
Assumption of part of passengers was that well we know the airlines will fly is down to Havana
The hijack will be taken off a plane will maybe have to spend the night in Havana will
Capital hotel
Maybe buy some cigars and rum from relative and go to the 6 show with Fredo and Daniel
We'll have a good story to tell the next cocktail party back in the US
It was taken lightly because the notion that this could really be something destructive and turn into mass murder
Was not sending people to mind at that
And because this guy jackings weren't especially violent and the passengers weren't yet demanding extra security they are
Fought to keep things exactly as they were
The airlines were scared
They thought that if they treated all their customers kind of like criminal suspect
Because they were merely flying
People wouldn't fly anymore
People with drive-thru destinations
Instead
Do the airlines put a lot of roadblocks whenever someone especially in government
Mention the
Concept of having
Physical screening of all passenger
They would shoot that down
He's all their older lobbyist muscle
Shut that down
They really Force the FAS hand
To come up with the weakest
That must have been security
Improvements
BFA the Federal Aviation Administration is the US government body that is responsible for the safety and regulation
Up civil aviation
This is all in the name of well we can put up with some hijack
Does Costas however 2030 grand for hijacking
Convenience and whatnot
Or they could pay millions and millions on x-ray machine screenings and security personnel
For the airlines
Smart Financial choices
Is clear
I put up with the tree out of hijack
Reply totally
And keep the customer experience in the ground the same
But clearly something had to be done
If the airlines were unwilling to consider a mandatory screening and checkpoints inside the terminal
Some less intrusive and somewhat Xenia Solutions
Had to be considered
So in 1968 the FAA created a special anti-hijacking
Task force to come up with some solution of each
Palatable to the airlines actually open it up for public comment
Invited to the public to submit suggestions about how this could be done
The most common suggestion was complete capitulation
Quote
Provide free transportation to Cuba for those persons leaving the United States
Another tactic that was seriously considered by the Federal Aviation Administration
What's the build a phony Havana Airport
In South Florida
Phidias this time all the skyjackers want to go to Havana
So you kind of just fly them out over the water and then turn back and
Atlanta Pacific airport in arrested when they got off the plane was
The big idea
Try not to be too expensive that it would have cost prohibitive so they couldn't do that solution
But there were also a lot of delightful Technical Solutions whose patents
Are so much fun to read
There's a hijacker ejection seat
There was also one patent for an injector seat
Which would have a quote
Hypodermic injection apparatus arrange for driving the needle of a hypodermic syringe
Ruben seat cushion
Into the passenger to instantly kill the passenger
The more you act like Wile E coyote tomorrow
There was a trap door that was patented that would go right outside of cockpit and lock
The hijacker in cutting plexiglass chamber
Make Me Brave
Brought to Justice when a plane landed
The public proposed that Pilots depressurize the aircraft or expel sleeping gas throughout the cabin so that
Everyone falls asleep
Country would go out with oxygen tanks and disarm the hijacker
One that I loved actually was giving all the passengers boxing gloves and making them wear boxing gloves the duration of the
Siri being that you can't hold a gun
If you have boxing gloves on your hands
Of course then there would be an epidemic of extremely ill-advised boxing matches at 30,000 ft
But the real thing at the end up going with
Was this
Behavioral
Profile now sure the one thing about
Cathay Airline terminal there was one
Place you had to halt
General in that was a ticket age
She get a boarding pass or to purchase
Is a ticket
There are many more tickets
Purchase on site
So this is the one choke point
In the terminal experience
TFA solution was to train a ticket agent
In this
25 Behavioral
Cues that might indicate
It's someone it is
Is a temple Skyjack
These were things like not maintaining appropriate eye contact
Not caring about your luggage
Wearing Military Surplus Gear
And if you saw any of the
Traits
Behavioral traits
A customer
Through to get a ticket or boarding pass
You would Dre discreetly are asked if they go to a room on the side and be searched
This was not a good solution
And the real problem is that ticket agent or not security personnel
They're dealing with
Hundred
Hundreds of
Often very harried customers
Per day
And so they're not the people truly identify
Even if you assume these behavioral Q-tip off
Work and it turned out to be a bad assumption because plenty of skyjackers pass-through without notice
He was meant to be very low impact solution at the one show point that already existed in Arabic
Was really a failure
But the solution that we all know that eventually came up with screaming everybody and their luggage with x-ray machines
Requiring ID all the things that make
The airport the horrible place it is
Wasn't seriously considered
Until one hijacking changed ever
This is a really forgotten
Really pivotal moment
An American
Security history this is on November 1972
Kind of tail end of this
Really crazy hijackings went after the neck
People asking for
Huge amounts of money
Then you have these Three Fugitives
From the law who hijacked Southern Airways
As flight 49
Detroit
They had a grievance of the Detroit police
And they wanted
10 million dollars
And they said they didn't get it
They were going to crash.
Plane
Into the Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Senior Knoxville Tennessee
At the heart of that Laboratories actually a uranium-235 react
All the sudden everyone realized an airplane could be a weapon of mass destruction in this case threatening to turn East
Eastern Tennessee into a nuclear Wasteland
And that's really when the light goes on
For the Airlines and the government
That the current situation is no longer tenable
Fortunately they escaped
Cataclysm there what happened to the the airline doesn't have 10 million dogs have 2 million
Has landed in Chattanooga Tennessee to pick up the money
Andy hijacking by that time and actually drunk all the liquor on the planes were completely
Be bombed
And they bring on a 50 pound of cash
A lot of money in there
I think it's $10 and so they actually didn't bother to count it
Who is taking forever to count that much money anyway who never takes them into consideration
Hijackers eventually landed airplane in Havana or Cuban authorities captured
Crisis averted but
Shortly after that you have the
Executive order mandating
Universal physical screen to start on January 5th 97
3 in the airlines put up
The airline's really wanted the government
Provide airport security for the government reviews
And the airlines hired contractors to do airport screenings and run the metal detectors at the airlines desk
Really trying to avoid
And they put them in Jericho 1973 and there's literally not
Single hijack
In American airspace.
159 Skyjack in the US from 1961 to 1972
And they really change the nature of air travel
Even though most of this history is completely forgotten along with the
Image of the deranged
Desperate Loan hijacker in Military Surplus clothing
Teepublic
Conception of hijack
Actor change dramatically
Any ATM response to specifically the
TWA hijacking
In Lebanon in
5A hijacking associated
With
Islamic terrorism
A real kind of
Scary Prospect
You know something
People didn't understand
Name of the real boogeyman
I think once we kind of have that image
Famous image of the
The pilot of.
Play Na Na
CarMax
Beirut with
Capture with a gun to his head
Weeding out of the cockpit
We completely forgot about the
It's kind of more
Quaint hijackers
You want to go to Havana
Get a bad experience in Vietnam
That's what I think about more
It's really
Scarier crime
Crime of kind of a
An enemy we don't really understand or know very much about
Answer that earlier I was forgotten papered over
He will buy the buy the snoo
Image of
The hijacker was
And that image remains today
Reinforce the course by the terror attack
9-11-2001
A date which was preceded by an entire decade free of any commercial airlines carjackings in US airspace
After 9/11 the airlines finally got with a lot before back when mandatory screenings were introduced in nineteen
The government took over security of our nation's Airport
Who created the Transportation Security Administration
The TSA
Now calls the shot
99% invisible exam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are project of 91
7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce of the offices of arcsin
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Fox podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and likes on Facebook the staff tweets at Roman Mars Katie mingle Sam listen to troubleman we've a great Tumblr
That Avery curates
Right now if you
For our website you will find five dispatches from our image correspondent Kate Joyce who takes
Amazing photographs based on themes from our favorite episodes
Please do check them out
At 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that car
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com