99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
The chair is a difficult object
Skyscraper is almost easier
Those the words of mise van der rohe architecture of also design chairs
Eaves
Geary
Adid
Liva skin
Kombucha
Royer
If they've designed a big building chances are they've designed a thing on which to set
And this makes sense the chairs will be signature design pieces for Ark
Because chairs are almost like teeny tiny buildings for one person
Producer Avery trufelman
And of course it's not just Architects designers of all Stripes have this love affair with
Chairs
Well I think every designer
Really would love to design a chair
I mean there's so many interesting things about yours
This is designer Bruce Hannah I'm a teacher
Pratt Institute
In Brooklyn New York
And
Design things for know for years
Including plenty of chairs
Free office for everything
Cheers
Exist
They kind of look like placeholders for human beings
Are you going to a restaurant that's empty and there's a little place hole
Yet when the people sit in the chair
It disappears
The person replaced
And so there's this distinct challenge for chair designers
To make this thing look fantastic when empty
And remain comfortably invisible when in use
And Hannah's pursuit of seating Innovation actually led to something else
When he was experimenting with foam cushioning
Hannah accidentally invented
Dinner
Well actually it's called the phone
Still really cool if it did it come out of Designing
Are you a much more interested in the chair yes those designer sure do love chair
Love them
They keep turning out new ones all the time
Which brings me to one of my favorite headlines from The Onion
Quote
Report confirms no need to make new tears for the time being
Because yeah
There are already a lot
I think you could say that about anything don't have enough cards
Personally
I wouldn't be against it
But new chairs are out
Who is coming out
The fit our ever-changing needs
Because chairs determine how we use
The space
Anna brought up this great example of
Seating in cafes
Cafes used to be places for
Another places
Is 4 working
So people are sitting
Interacting different
And so the furniture
The vault
Space
In the action
Throughout our lives
We have been told
Sit down
In school in the office and the Plate Company of a dinner party
In a car or plane or bus or movie theater sitting is the default
We spend a lot of time in chair
But I'm sure you heard all the talk lately about how unhealthy tears are especially if he was in public radio which I bet
You do you feel
First we'll talk about chronic
Sitting
Are you sitting down well you might want to stand up
You can be bad for your health and those who were sitting more worse
Substantially more likely
Play today
I think I sound like five articles with the headline
Sitting is the new smoking
The absolute number of hours that you sit is directly correlated
With mortality from all causes
Cancer heart attack
And it doesn't matter how many hours you
You spend in the gym as compensation
This is Professor Galen cranz
You come in in the secretary says have a seat
She doesn't know she's
Wishing you
Death Note the death wish
This research along with those scary headlines has led to a new market for medicine ball chair
Adjustable
Standing desks
Treadmill.
The chair back
Is upon us
And Berkeley architecture Professor Galen cranz totally nailed it
Way before anyone else it is nice to that people are
Yeah saying that I was prescient
I wasn't present
Everybody else
In 1998
Can't publish the book called The Chair
Rethinking culture body and Design
In the argument of the chair is that we should stop sitting in chair
At least we should stop sitting in them for so long after 3 hours
Doesn't seem to have much concert
But Professor Kranz takes Innovative chair-sitting to another level
I try to eliminate
All conventional tears in my own life
Which presented a challenge when I went to go interview her
I wonder if it's
See how should we say
Professor Kansas house was full of floor cushions tatami mats and lots and lots of unconventional
Hybrid chairs
Like a medicine ball on an office chair chassis
And one that looks like a sleep
Pared-down horse saddle
And when she's not in her home feeding Oasis and out in public
Versatrans does a lot of standing
Instead of sitting when she gets tired
Cheops Tennille
Or Squad
Or lie down
I laid down in a bank and somebody came up and asked me if I was having a heart attack
I just kind of them you know I understand
But I said no I'm fine I'm just resting cuz the line is so long
Got2b
Gutsy to actually avoid the chairs everywhere
So how the rest of us gets suckered into the seated position
Well it all started when we got off the farm
In the twentieth century we moved from being an agricultural economy or most people worked on farms
Then we move into
A manufacturing economy were a lot of people worked in factories
And some sad
Some stood
To work the machines
In the longest conveyor belt
Not to over romanticize life on the farm
They were still doing back-breaking work
They just probably had better posture and less carpal tunnel syndrome and then we moved into a service economy
And that seems to be where the chair really took off
And became the dominant
Redis
Our Lives
And then when we settled into the service economy
Sitting became the way to type in file and fill out paperwork
You could do that standing but
For reasons I don't
Fully understand
We did it sitting until office chairs become V chairs the chairs that people spend most of their dad
And until very recent history
They were not made
Fit your body
They were made
To fit your job
So you had a managerial one you had a
Bruce Hannah had to design a few of these kinds of office
The status oriented chair design meant then some cases
You had
320 lb
Executive sitting in a gigantic
Because it really was about his presence when he was
For her price
And then you had
The
The pound
Assistant secretary sitting
Tiny little chair
The most part status Trump organize emacs
And then Along Comes now
The Aeron chair
Where it's
The same chair
Precise
Everybody
All of you just
Wii guitar
They get everything they need
Need to work
Because everyone
Equally
Hard
The Herman Miller Aeron chair
You've seen an Aeron chair
It got this mess looking back
And you probably heard it mentioned on public radio
You Beautiful nerd
Support for NPR comes from set for life in Herman Miller
Featuring The Aeron chair
Including the true black color
They're usually black
For True black
There's one of them everywhere I was surprise when I woke
The studio today
Because you're everywhere
Do you think
Did the ubiquitous
An Aeron chair brought on the sage of ergonomic office chairs that look like little robots
They display their Technologies of selling point
And they show off their swivels and their adjustments and there are ergonomic technology
The Aeron chair
Define what an office chair ought to look like
Right now I think it's what society says
That will make me
The piece of machinery
And no one guessed that these are
Expensive
Pieces of machinery would sell like hotcakes
No one except guilin cramps first came out people said well
You know nobody's going to pay for
An ordinary Clerk
To have
An adjustable chair with all the bells and whistles
Oh that's way too expensive that Will never happen
Well then there were repetitive strain injury in a whole lot of lawsuits
Spend
Insurance companies suddenly thought it was a lot cheaper to buy those
Fancy adjustable chairs
Then to pay for medical bills
Cranes is a fan of what she calls body-conscious design
And considers any chair that takes the human figure into account
Is a vast improvement over
Bean bag chair
But Krantz argues that some of those bells and whistles on office chairs actually don't help that much
Specifically those ergonomic chair backs
Because in all likelihood
You are probably sitting in this chair
While working at a desk
And the desk
It turns out
Is the chairs devious accomplice
The True Villain is the table
Flat surfaces
Force you to lean over
So you never really take advantage of the chair back
The chair in particular
Asks us to sit at this right angle position
Most of our work is forward oriented
Clerical work reading writing checks and eating even drinking tea and coffee and all the
Everything's
Forward
Or more likely slump
Even if you have
Excellent posture
It's hard to avoid leaning over your keyboard or your dinner or your book
So the hand
Gets seduced into coming forward
And then the spine turns into a
Big C shape
And Galen Krantz says that when you curve your spine into the sea shape
It's bad for the spine of course but it also compresses your organs
What does really bad
Especially for hours on end throughout the day in an office
And because of this
Horrible chair desk Dynamic chair designers
Solve much by adding economic elements
Put the chair back
Actually Professor Kranz thinks we should do away with back support entirely
I think back support is a
Big mistake and it's it's weekend are back
If you support something you usually weaken it
So if you're in a situation
Where you must must
Sit in the chair
Karin says it's best to ignore the chair back
Back and sit yourself right at the edge of your seat
Write out to the edge
That way you don't get seduced to using the chair back
If you're on torso strength
Keep you upright
With the strategy of getting your sit bones out to the edge of the chair
You turning it into a stool
Tools princess
Are good alternative to jerez
Because they don't have
Back support can they get your body out of the sea shape
It positions the body halfway between sitting and standing
And if you take
That body position and lean it backwards what do you get
A lounge chair
And that's how I'm
Position right now
Yeah
Dylan Krantz was reclining in a lounge chair for this interview I'll be in the lounge
And I'll have you in the rocking
And she put me in a rocking chair because unlike a normal chair it allows for more fluidity and movement
This all sounds great and healthy and fun
But in practice I was sitting
All the Way Forward rocking right to the very front
Retching my microphone out to Kranz
She was lying back in her lounge chair
And it hurt
I just wanted to chairs in a flat desk to rest my arm on
But I don't know maybe I just wasn't used to this alternative world yet
Maybe I need to get acclimated I don't know
I mean Professor Kranz looks pretty comfortable in her lounge chair
4 people got so into standing desks and treadmill desk
Professor Krantz was sure that lounge chairs and lounge chair.
Who replaced Harrison
Of all the solutions to the seating problem the lounge chair is the solution that requires the least physical effort
Will still supporting the human body in a healthy way
But it's not like there's one single piece of furniture that will correct all the problems of chair-sitting no
Lounge chair is not the answer
There's no the answer
What we need
Is variety
The best posture
Is the next
Bruce Hannah agrees the more variation in your day
Better off
But he's not chair avoidant
Sitting is the new smoking
Really
We should be up and running everyday I run run run run run run run run
Set mean that all restaurants will be will be running in place at restaurant
Toby treadmills
Will do nothing be safe
I like to see it
I want to sit down
And ideal space to live or to work
Could be full of unconventional mismatched chairs for you to try out and cycle through
Lichen Galen Kansas dining room
People say
Wow you have a lot of chairs I say yeah to cheer Museum and I say old truck be sure to try them all and people do they like
I said in that one can I go try that one if we threw the dinner you know
The middle-class thing is you want everything to match
And
It's fun that these don't match everybody loves it trying outfit all the different attitudes
Towards
Seating reform
But the solution isn't just alike only in Berkeley kind of thing
So maybe in this one case this one exception
The onion is wrong
We don't need fewer things to sit on
It turns out
We need more
In all different kinds
Stool purchase
Lounge chairs
Throwing some desk redesigns while you're at it
Ones that rise up to meet us like drafting table
Design more
Much much more
All That Jazz
I can make the most
Before I leave
99percentinvisible was produced this week by
We are project 91.7 local public radio
W in San Francisco a produced of the offices of arcsin in beautiful Downtown Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
Got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but if I find out more about this story
Including full pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Radio tupi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com