99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It's New York City 1882
At night the city is mostly dark
But it won't be for long
Thomas Edison has already invented the phonograph
The automatic Telegraph
In the first commercially viable light bulb
He really could have stopped right there
He was still young
Only 35 years old
And then he had the brilliant idea of doing something even more ambitious
He wanted to construct
The design
The electrical system that would Supply electricity for those bulbs
Pets4luv Shoei
He wrote The Grid
History of how Society uses and loses electricity
The Edison Illuminating Company build a power station in lower Manhattan right in the shadow of the newly constructed broke
Enbridge
Small about one square mile
They work so well but soon all across the country
These little self-contained electrical systems started popping up
In the coming 10 and 20 30 years
The grid got larger and larger
Is the grid gruit made Modern Life possible it powered electric lights running water and sewage pumps elevator
Pearson air conditioning
The bigger the great God
The more complicated icon
The more the possibility of failure crept in
Whenever we talk about
Large
Designed
Human made
Complicated electrified
Sings it sometimes takes four or five things together going wrong but
If the system is complicated enough
The chances of something bad happening go up
Which brings us to New York City's blackout of 1970
Wasn't the first blackout or even the biggest
But it might have been the most infamous
That's producer Delaney Hall and oh yeah this story it's not about Thomas Edison so it begins with the electrical grid
He started building back in 1882 agreed they got so big it's been called the most massive engineering project
20th century
This story is about what happens when you disc
Connect people from that grid
For one hot night
In New York City
It was just time
It's time for a new interpretation
That's hip hop Pioneer Grandmaster cat
And he says on that night
When the Lights Went Out
A movement
Have I was a kid in the 50s out of Ben Chuck Berry
You know what I'm saying if I was in
3240 Audubon New Nola jazz artists
The same
Amana G that every generation
You know exercise
And it just comes out in different forms
This is Grandmaster Caz and yes I was there
During the night of the 1977 New York City blackout
And survived
Thunderstorm swept over the New York City area on a hot night in July what happened
First of all you have what in in this might even be the technical word for 10
Act of God
A lightning bolt came down and struck
Overhead transmission line
When lightning adds a bunch of extra electricity to a transmission line the line shuts itself off at the circuit
When one mind shuts off the electricity start squeezing a
Smaller and smaller channels
Like how cars on the freeway crowded
Single-lane when the other lanes are blocked
This is all fairly normal so far
But then
Flash of lightning
And this knocked out a couple of
Lions
So now you got even more electricity with
Fewer lines
To distribute it
And it was hot outside
Really hot
Which meant that lots of New Yorkers were running lots of air conditioners putting an extra burden on the system
And now
They started to have trouble there wasn't enough
Room for all the electricity to flow
And so Con Edison that same power company that Thomas Edison started way back when he was laying the lines for the first
First electrical grid
Started doing the debris last thing they like to do which is
Turn off
Whole neighborhood
By one by one
Okay so the year of the blackout
Hip Hop was starting to spread
But
It was still pretty much a
A bronx kind of thing
It didn't have a name you know people referred to
Oh y'all still doing that hippity hoppity
Hip hop hippity hop hip to the hop
Hip hop the hippity Hip Hop
Okay Hip Hop
Hit on me
I do remember what New York was like in that hero
And I remember how chaotic it was
That's Joe Schloss
I'm a professor at City University of New York
And I research and practice hip hop culture
New York City experienced a major blackout in 1965 in which the city had stayed mostly calm
During the blackout of 1965 residence treated the situation with good humor and, Roderick
But things feel different
It was like a powder keg like something like that was on the verge of happening all the time all it took was something to
To push it over the edge
A couple years before in 1975 New York City was in such a dire financial situation that it had turned
The federal government for a bailout
President Gerald Ford's response was a resounding no prompting the New York daily news to running now famous headline
For the city
Drop dead
In 1977 things were still bad for New York
And in the Bronx they were even worse
You had neighborhoods that had lost something like 46% of the population my name is Lloyd
The Bronx Borough historian
And they were blocks at the Block at the Block
Rubble
And the ombatse what was on the horizon where buildings that were empty and boarded up
Really it look like
Berlin right after
The bombings in World War II
The municipal government had forgotten about the Bronx and then the youth
In the Bronx have been forgotten about
By the older people in the Bronx
We didn't have those music programs all those were cut out when we were kids you know we had them but those intermediate years
This is like we don't have none of that anymore
So they work like a forgotten minority of a forgotten minority of the Forgotten minority
So I mean you can
You can really see how people
Enfield today
I mean is it's hard to describe you know what I mean cuz that we older
I can look back and say wow we got through some pretty rough times
Do you know if you were born into rough times then it's just time
And once again my friend the funky beat has no end we bout to take it on down to the
Would you and your friends
Put the sound to hear it's got a tough on your ear coming at you so loud
But you have no fear
On the evening of July 13th 1977
The same day as the blackout
Grandmaster Caz and his partner disco Wiz
I've been challenged to a DJ battle
Buy another
DJ
So we decided to take our equipment out into the park
We used to hang out play basketball in everyday so that's where the battle was going to take place they said up all their stuff so
Side by side
I just remember them having a very very
Good professional sound system
Pandas have an hour
Thrown together it all in pieces set
The two groups of DJ started the battle
I was doing this dude combo that I used to do
And one song was a song by DC LaRue
And I was cut it up
With this other break fee
Repentance
Love
And I was chilling
Now remember that the hype
Of everybody you know being really excited
And then the record just started slowing down
You know what I mean just you know
Do not turntable cuts off and then just that kind of situation
So quite naturally we thought
It was us
We thought we had drain too much power and we shorted out you know the electricity
So we're frantically looking around with checking buttons with checking switches with seeing what's up cuz this is death in a battle if your
System comes out on you
But after a while
Everything around us started getting dark I mean windows
The apartment buildings around us we're all dark
Kind of came over everybody at the same time like oh
Generators all over the city had been turning themselves off one by one
And then the biggest generator in the city
A machine called Big Alice
Turned itself off
Just about everything left that was still lit up in the air
Turned off
Boroughs of New York City went dark
Turn All the Lights Off
That go all that
Diffuse light goes away and you can look up
How there is the Milky Way
If people took a minute to gaze up at the newly visible in the night sky they didn't stargaze for long
Because pretty soon
Things started to
Field 10
The stores
Started to close
Like the local bodegas on each Corner we would hit a gate slamming Down Show
Like they knew what was happening they know what was going on at like week
Be closing out now
New Yorkers reactions were very
Some through party
SummerWinds Waukee
And many same from you
Thelma stayed up in the bars and clubs
Send someone out to help
But many took it better
Age of a sudden chaos
The park was right around the corner from the Grand Concourse
And the Bronx which is like
Shopping area all the way up and down stores electronics stores toy stores
Furniture stores
Pet stores I mean everything
Here in corner of 135th Street and Broadway
I'm amazed to find a right before my eyes a Singer sewing machine stores
I saw people taking stuff that people had stolen you know what I mean like
He couldn't get in the store so they wait for people to come out the store with something they just grab it from them it was
Chaos
And it was exciting
But while it was going on
It was scary
In the Bronx liquor smashed a steel door open auto showroom and drove off
$50,000
Every other Block in the Hi-Fi store a liquor store a sporting good store
Can people still all kinds of stuff including
DJ equipment
Turntables
They want to become DJs they want to begin on at me
And
Equipment
Crossed
SSI you could count the amount of DJ's at their work
I even like I said I even got a new mixer I went right to the place where I bought my first set of these yet
Rossmont money in here
And I went by Anna and I
Got me a mix of holiday
The blackout lasted 24 hours
And some p
Including Grandmaster Caz
And get catalyzed the growing hair
Hip hop movement
After the Blackout all this
This new wealth
That I like to call it you know what I mean was founded by people and and they just
You know
Opportunity spring format
Can you can see the differences before
The blackout
And after
So
The question is
Did they go and seal turntables
The things like that so they think it actually becomes
Those disc jockey
I think it's true
I cannot rule out the possibility
But I think it's also important to 2
To keep in mind that
Basically hip hop history is an oral history at the
This point
But I cannot say definitively that that act
It did happen and that it's all my fault
In some sense
The true story is as well as the fall stories
We have the key
I music
Alive we ever keep you know
Exercising this
This this need this this enemy for my soul 2 2 2
You know
Experience music
The same as a state
99% invisible was produced this week by Delaney Hall and Katie mingle the same Greenspan Avery trufelman and
Me Roman Mars
This episode was based off of a piece that Delaney did for the in the dark radio series based in London
We are project at 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcs
Beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another room in Brawl hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299 pi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com