99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stuck
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
20 years ago
Back in 1996
A crowd of reporters and politicians gathered in the White House Rose.
Vice president
President Bill Clinton stepped up to the podium and announced that he was signing a landmark bill
They would dramatically redesign welfare
The 16 billion-dollar government program
That millions of poor Americans relied on for basic support
Today we are
Ending welfare
We know in this as well as another Prescott
Clinton made it clear that a central tenet to his readers
Was the idea of welfare to work
First and foremost
It should be about moving people from welfare to work this new reform said that in order to collect welfare
Recipients would need to work
Better job
Transform a broken system
The traps too many people in a cycle of depend
The one that emphasizes work
And Independence
Give people on welfare a chance to draw a paycheck
Are welfare
This whole idea of a paycheck
Not a welfare check
Work not welfare
It's relatively familiar to us now
But there's a complicated backstory behind how it came to be at the center of the reforms that President Clinton pass that day
Day in 1996
Reforms that still affect many people today
Over the last 20 years the number of families living in deep
Poverty
Unless than $2 a day
Is rising
And most of them don't receive welfare
Miss Chrissy Clark
Senior correspondent for marketplaces wealth and poverty desk
She has been researching the history of welfare reform for podcast series called
The uncertain hour
And today we're presenting an adaptation of the first
Set from that Siri
It's about a guy who basically
Pioneer
The work not welfare reform
A guy who came to be known as
The magic
Bureaucrat
My name is Lawrence
Townsend
Larry for short
Larry is 79 retired he's got close-cropped white hair
Broad shoulders and a serious face with one of those Army General Smiles that never quite turns up at the edges
Today Larry lives in a beached
Town in California
Where he drives around in a green Cadillac Seville that has a brass frame around the lights
Play Undead
Into the brass
It says
Life works if you work
Larry
Love's
Work
Just the idea of it
He has a binder full of work ethic slogans that he's collected over the years
These are from famous quotes
From all over the world
Alphabetically
Spectre
There's something that way
Just show you
He starts with a Aristotle suggested that happiness results from meaningful activity
Goes all the way down
Quantity Tolstoy
Des Peres a duty of each man to earn his living by the sweat of his brow and calloused hands
Makes independent
A virtuous man
Oh that was a little sexist but
That the point is very valid
And just as much as Larry Townsend loves the idea of hard work
He hates
Welfare program
I've seen so much of damage
Two people that are on welfare they have no hope for a better future
They are setting a good example for their children once when Larry was working in County government he noticed two children
Run in the welfare office waiting room
Waiting for their mom
And they were
Tending
Play welfare
What are the children
Was playing the welfare recipient
The other one was Steve playing the eligibility
Now you tell me they aren't learning how to get on welfare
Like they were like he's like kids wood Playhouse
Playing House in the waiting room while their mother was
In the
Office with the
Eligibility
Now they're catching on
About the concept
Getting
Now that one
And then there's the story about the two women he says he overheard an elevator one
And that's why I said that the other one is my oldest child's going to become 18th and I won't get welfare benefits
You know I need to get pregnant
These are the kind of anecdotes that got told and retold among critics of welfare
Individual moments
That may not be typical of welfare recipients in general
But for critics B stories represent all the failings
But in the late 1980s
Larry suddenly found himself in a position to
To change welfare in a big way
Because he became the head of a welfare
Apartment in a big
Suburban County east of LA called
Riverside
The way he saw it
His role in the welfare office
Was to invade
Concur
That was my attitude
Quick history lesson here
Since the Great Depression when the program was first signed into law
Welfare had worked pretty simply
At least in theory
If you are a single parent
If your family was poor enough
And if you met a few other technical requirements
You qualified
For welfare check
End of story
There was little expectation that
Mother's woodwork
This is James riccio a sociologist who's been studying welfare programs for most of his career
And she's talking about this
Crazy flip-flop that happened over the years
Around who we thought deserved welfare
When the program began the whole point was to help single mothers
Mostly widows at the time
Make ends meet so they could stay out of the workforce
Focus on raising their kids into productive citizens
Attitudes begin to change
But you really in the 1970s
In early 80s
Part of it had to do with the fact that more middle-class mothers were entering the workforce
So somewhere asking the question what about mothers on welfare
Shouldn't they have jobs
Joe Hudson's a labor Economist at Duke and he says
Well most welfare moms did have jobs
At least on and off
There was this persistent group of
Largely single mothers
Who stayed on welfare for long periods of time and it didn't work
NL
Are arguably had a life of
Dependence on welfare
And that
Small but persistent group of completely dependent welfare recipients
Started to get all this Focus
Lot of
Academic attention to this certainly a lot of attention in policy circles to
This problem of welfare dependency
The View was that you know what's key to changing this was to make
Changes in the welfare system which encourage people to work
But then the question was
How
Out in the suburbs of Riverside California
Larry Townsend had some ideas
And his County got a special waiver from state and federal authorities
To try some of those ideas
I was absolutely stunned that I was forgiven
Freedom to design a program
To implement a program
Higher the staff that are needed
I felt like it was
Honor
Oceanographer
Tunity
And it's got a chance to
Change
The concept of welfare
Larry's changes happened under a California pilot program
How to gain
Short for greater Avenues
For Independence
See what the time in the 80s there was the standard welfare approach
Which is like you make less than x amount
And you get welfare check every month
And there were two basic Avenues counties could take to get more of their welfare families closer to Financial
Independence
One was the Education and Training route
The idea here was to help for single moms who dolphin dropped out of high school
To get more skills
Maybe a GED
To fare better on the job market
But down in Riverside
Larry did not have much patience for that approach
His approach
Much simpler
Get people into a job
Immediately
Don't worry about are you trained enough for do you have enough education just get that
We're not going to train you for years we're not going to send you the school for years
We're going to show you how to find
A job
No vocational training or GED to get in the workforce
ASAP
Anyway you can you can still hear the conviction and Larry's voice talking about this program almost
30 years later
Listen to it
To find a job
And the point wasn't to find a perfect job or even a well-paying job
But at least your foot is in the door and how will you succeed
From there is up to you
With
Unimportant cat
If you do not cooperate
With us
We will take you off of welfare
Your children will still get money from us
But you won't
The carry out his Jobs first plan Larry restructured his welfare office to run job search
Classes
And job clubs
For welfare
James riccio and Joe Hut
The sociologist in The Economist we heard from a minute ago both sat in on some of Riverside's job clubs
And they left an impression imagine people sitting
In the circle chairs in a circle
There be a job
Club leader
Who would
Talk about what it means to work
How to find a job
How do you approach potential employers how do you dress
Dealing with testy supervisors
Eventually the people on welfare would be handed a list of job leads
And the telephone
I'm told to start calling around and asking for job
Is Joe Hudson again
And there's a whiteboard right
So somebody would get us if you know an interview and it would go up on the board and everybody you know
Pause Gracepoint in cheer
This is like going to these Weight Watcher meetings where you know I lost 15 pounds right I got a job offer
And that sense of this is exciting we're doing something that's really important and novel
You could see had an impact on the the recipient or
Involved in these jobs
But those job clubs
The cheers and the white boards and a Weight Watchers vibe
They were just the beginning
Of Larry's plans for the welfare recipients of Riverside
Larry says his vision was much
Bigger in
Fact welfare recipients with a positive attitude
With
That the beauty and Glory of work
And so I became sort of like
The preacher for work
This was a campaign to change hearts and minds and get people excited about getting a job
Cymbalta alarm marketing
Booklets posters billboards
Full of welfare-to-work slogan
Success depends on your backbone not your Wishbone action turns dreams into reality
Get into gear start a career
The messages were printed on bumper stickers to catch the eye of a welfare recipient walking through the welfare office
Parking lot
Unbuttons that the welfare intake workers with pin to their love
Powell's personally answered nothing as a Target he can't miss out of honestly don't wait for your ship to come in
Men swim out to it
But even if you somehow missed these messages on the bumper stickers and
Posters
Pins and outside of envelope
It was especially hard
Kumasi death
I thought music is a
Very inspiration
Go formative
Acacia
And soleri made this CD
Called work makes the
Use $2,000 of taxpayer money no authorization
To record it
I figured I might get fired over
But he didn't
This is the first track
The title
William
The Next Generation
Play
The music was made to be played in welfare waiting rooms over the PA system
To be the hold music when people called up the welfare offices
It would play during voicemail greetings
I have to say since I first heard me songs
Cannot get them out of my head
There are 10 songs in all
Different genres to appeal to different demographic
There's a song that features a whole rap
Section
And there's a song with the kind of
Slow reggae Jam
Get back home
Evan there's a jazzy Andrews Sisters 40s style thing
It's very hard not to snap your fingers to
But we're not done yet
There are also three different versions of a song called
Feels so good to have a job
Country
Urban contemporary
And for the Spanish-speaking audience
And all these songs were written
Compose
Produced and recorded
By the staff of the department of public social service
Or SPSS
Which was the welfare department at Larry Townsend Ranch
What happened was he sent out a memo
Paper memo memo
Keith Rogers was working in the Mailroom of DPSS back then
His job was to
To send out the welfare check
That's according to one of the songs he would later write
Welfare recipients should be envisioning in their path
The Memo from Larry said he was looking for volunteers to take some of the work ethic slogans he'd collected
And put them to music
Turn them into songs
Keith was a musician The Mailroom thing was just as day job
So when he saw this all set memo he was like
Oh I got a chance to do
My thing
Let me just go up and whip something up
And then submitted
Tulare Townsend
So after work
Keith sketched out of Melody
He still remembers it will first temporary
9 way of life
And he sent a demo over to Larry
I love it
Next and I'm up in his office
He's as naughty
Your
You're not doing well right now you're you're going to be a
Producer you're going to produce my CD
Wow
Six months in the studio later with
$2,000 of taxpayer money and musical contributions
From The Mailroom on up through County social workers
And they had their CD
It's worth pointing out that before he worked in the Mailroom
Keith had actually been on government assistance himself
Back when he was struggling to make it as a musician and in between gigs
Yeah
I don't mean I receive Food Stamps
You know but that was just something that I needed until I became gainfully employed that was not anything that I wanted
Depend upon
It was temporary not a way of life
Oh I knew it wasn't well I try to live off food stamps
Keith was already on board with the message
Getting a job was important
And he was game to spread the word
You know you hearing that beer in a beer
Bumps all over in the system
And then
You might call at some of the welfare office
Dezeen
You know they put you on hold year welfare the temporary way of life
And I'm thinking you know you play certain things over and over again
It does have a
Subliminal
Guess what
I want to find a job
And whether it was the songs themselves
What's or the buttons
The Billboards
The bumper stickers the job Club
Or the jobs first strategy altogether
Somehow
Larry's plan in Riverside
Seemed to work
Three results in Riverside
Where
The most impressive we had ever seen in a welfare-to-work
Program
Up to that time
This is sociologist James riccio again hired by the government to study Riverside
Jobs first program
His team followed the families who participated
Cracked what happened to them
First five years
And compared to that
To what happened to families who stayed on the plain old welfare program
Or they just got checked
No job clubs are job kept
Turns out the ones who participated in the jobs first program
Five years later they were doing way better on average earnings that were 42%
Entire
In those
Who
That were assigned to the control group
They were making 42% more money than the families who hadn't gotten any of the jobs first
James also compared the people who went through the jobs first program in Riverside
Two people who lived in other parts of the state that emphasized Education First
And the Riverside Jobs first group
Came out on top
In that comparison
Listen to
Five years later they were employed more and had higher wages
Funny education first group
And because of all of this
Larry Townsend the director became
I kind of star in this narrow world of welfare reform
But this narrow world of welfare reform was about to widen
And play a very big role on the national stage
And Larry's get a job any job approach for welfare recipients
Became known as Riverside miracle
The Riverside miracle
The Riverside Department of Social Services received an award from the Harvard Kennedy School of government
Riverside miracle
Got a lot of attention from the national news and I'll just read a few quotes here from The New York Times no Pro
Program has done as much to raise the earnings of people on welfare
As one here in Riverside County
And from the LA Times
Riverside is pursuing a notion so obvious as to be stupefying
If you want to get people off welfare
Stay on their backs
Until they get a job
They call me the
Magic bureaucrat or something in it it was an editorial page
But I picture
Special over the top
Larry has a framed copy of the editorial hanging in his house
But in all the news coverage Larry's thoughts about the welfare system
Sometimes revealed
A more aggressive
Then the one you hear in those song
In one article
Call from 1993
He says that every time he sees a bag lady on the street
He wonders if it's a mother on welfare
Shoe quotes
Hit the menopause wall
Who can no longer reproduce and get money to
To support herself
I asked him about
Please don't go
Well it is out in the
The public record I just wanted to give you an opportunity to
Chicago
I don't know about the need to clarify it
Well since we're going into history you know we
Part part this whole story is about the history of them
Regard
Soleri clearly did not want to talk about this
But I still wanted to know
Whether he ever worried some of his welfare-to-work rhetoric
Might be hurtful to people
There is this tricky territory it seems like in discussions around this where
There can be
Stereotypes that come up
Or feelings of judgement examples at that
Toxic
About
I'm it was
Concept where I was concerned about ladies getting into a nun
Unfortunate situation and nobody ever helped them to discover how good they are
And that's all he wanted to say
Regardless of what you think about Larry's opinion of work and work ethic
And how that applies to who's on welfare and why
The fact is these opinions were widely embraced
Eventually Larry story
His Riverside miracle
Started getting noticed in political Arena
The results in Riverside influence thinking among Republicans and out
Many will come to order is one of the continuing
Series
And in the Years leading up to welfare reform
Larry flute Washington DC
Five different times
To testify before Congress
As they debated how to restructure
The Summit
16 billion dollar program
If we have heard anything
From the witnesses
The date it is work work
Work
But that will work better
And anything else we might consider
The attempt to
You're the
What we would regard as a
Baby River
Welfare United States that's Republican senator Bob Packwood from Oregon in 1990
Just a year before welfare reform legislation would be signed into law
Impact what dies the Riverside miracle
Would be the key to
To fixing welfare
Lauren Townsend who's the director of the Department of Public Social Services in
Riverside Middle
Upstanding succession examples
And
Their Larry was in a dark
Suit with a big blue button pin to his
Lapel that read self-sufficiency is supporting
Thank your honorable chairman
Backwood
Larry told the senators all about his welfare to work
Programming
All the ways he had enlisted his
Staff to promote it
If you call Riverside County and nobody answers the phone will get a work ethic message
We have posters in the
Waiting room we have produced a compact disc
With work ethic music
Benefiber
Epic music
Now what we found commercial reproduce
Compact disc
And then we started
The new
Hi ho hi ho it's off to work we go
Eventually the laughter would die down
And the Senators would come to take Larry's methods and philosophy
That's seriously
As he did
Where is the dismissal of educating welfare recipients as a waste of money and time
Is emphasis on getting a job any job
Both those ideas show up
In various ways in the welfare reform bill that Congress passed and President Clinton signed
In 1996
It had a name that Larry would approve of
The personal responsibility and work opportunity reconciliation
But just a few years after this change was made
It came to light that thing that all of this reform was based on
The Riverside miracle
It turned out it wasn't a miracle after
He just get a job approach
Was it the magic thing
Text that everyone wanted it
Unfortunately
It wasn't that
In the early 2000s Joe Hut
The Duke economist
Can two other researchers
Check the back in on what it happened
To the welfare
Pantsuit gone through the Riverside
Job first
And they compared their circumstances
The folks who gone through other Pro
Sand counties like LA and Alameda
But it's focused on Education and Training
What we found was that yes indeed work for
Work better in the first few years out of
Treatment but by years 7 and 8 and 9
Actually the effect reversed
Meaning the people who gotten more education
More skills
Rather than being told with buttons and songs and slogans
To just get a job any job
They were doing better
They were more likely to be still in work they were making slightly more money and less likely to return to welfare
The effects
Of the Riverside miracle
Had all but this
Appeared
Joe says the Riverside Miracle had less to do with Larry's work first
The tactics and more to do with the fact that
In Riverside back then
It was a booming job market for low-skilled workers
This plan doesn't work in places where there aren't a lot of low-skilled jobs
When there are jobs out there
You can have all the job clubs you want right you can have him calling this many employers is
Is it one
It's not going to change the fact
There are no job and by the late nineties there was a very very little of his kind of Labor
Even in Riverside
It turned out a better name for the Riverside Miracle might have been
It's not as catchy but maybe it's something like
The Riverside short-term
Spike in the labor market
Was a fluke and
That's probably not going to get a sound bite the Riverside Miracle did not look like a miracle
9 years later
It didn't
Put people on a trajectory that was going to last a lifetime but this discovery
That may be climbing out of poverty and an unpredictable economy
Takes more than job clubs and songs that
Did not get the same kind of media play
As the Riverside of Miracle have gotten
Because in the meantime
The ship had already left the dock
The Riverside miracle
Have inspired a whole raft of federal welfare reform legislation
Based on the get a job any job work first mantra
And collectively changed how we think about welfare
Today we are
Ending welfare as
As we know it
And the thought of revisiting and restructuring welfare
Again
Just wasn't something that the federal government
Or the states that ran welfare-to-work programs had the political will to deal with
Cuz their view was how we took care of the
25 and we don't need
It wouldn't be till later but the weaknesses
Is out of the get a job any job welfare-to-work approach
Revealed themselves on a big
Painful
In the Great Recession
Started in 2008
When job markets crash
All over the
Especially for low-wage
Joe says the Riverside Miracle had been such a
A tantalizing low-cost
Quick fix
The poverty
Get people off welfare and in the self-sufficiency just Inspire them
Tell them to get jobs
It was a hard approach to let go of
Unfortunately
After a while we realized
These problems are age-old
It's
If it were that simple we would have saw that much earlier
Unfortunately
In the people who went through the Riverside Merrick
Are still dealing with the Bittersweet aftermath
Okay so we got paid.
A Carl
After going through the Riverside jobs program more than 20 years ago
Sophia Elsman has been off welfare Everest
For the last decade she's worked
In this plus size dress shop
She's a store manager
In charge of a small staff and figuring out where to put
The pink sweaters so they don't
Clash with the coral one
But this Coral here with this that looks good
The fact that Sophia has a job
Is evidence that the Riverside Jobs first program
Did have it sick
Excessive
In fact she was featured in a newspaper article in the early 90s
As an example of the Riverside miracle
But for a woman in her fifties she has
Physically taxing job
She's on her feet all day dragging racks
The clothes from here to there
My hands are
Screwed up now
I bet crap
And for all this she makes less than $15 an hour
Sophia lived up to the Riverside program's name
Game
She found greater Avenue
For Independence
But I asked
Do you consider yourself
A games
Success story
She thought for a long time
Yes
Endnote
She said
And then she correct
Their self
You know what to tell you
The truth
You know I've been working for it like
Since I was 14 years old
The work requirements
The job Club
They were actually a bit of a distraction she says
She'd already had low-wage jobs and she knew how to get them
I felt like it was more a hindrance
Tumi
Yes because I
I had to go there
But
I did what I had to do because they said I had to do it
So I did it
Sophia has moved out of
Poverty and off of government assistance
But she says she would have done that anyway
Welfare was just a temporary bit of help she needed when she had her husband
But two decades later she hasn't moved that far out of poverty
Things are still tight
And rather than getting pep talks
Find a job any job
She wishes
She'd had encouragement to get the training to do
What she really want
I want to be a nurse
Probably if I got offered
The opportunity to go back
Score
Right now I could be in a hospital be
RN
Make it a lot more than $15 an hour
A longer version of his story was recently heard on the uncertain hour a new podcast from Marketplace has wealth
In poverty.
Really good
The uncertain hour is Chrissy Clark
Caitlin Ash
Gina delvac and Nancy Fargo
Bend holidays the engineer and Mark Miller is the managing editor
99percentinvisible Ashraf Youssef
Avery trufelman Delaney Hall Katie mingle Kolstad same Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are buttock 91
What seven kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa Model X
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about some
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
If you are anything like a people work in our office you still have the welfare-to-work jingle stuck in your head
But luckily
I have the Cure
Last week one of my favorite artists
POS of the Unstoppable Doomtree Collective dropped a new track
Rename checks me Roman Mars at about the 2-minute mark
Coolest thing that ever happened to me so I'm going to play for
I'm leaving the song unbleeped
So this is your warning
This is wearing a bear
My minneapolis's own
POF
Telomere
Everything's cool.
Tiny professor
Looking like a fist fight
The way back
Or IP
POS
Wearing a bear by
POF
You buy it right now on i-22 2012 album we don't even live here is one of my favorites of all time
To get it
We'll have a link on our website
It's 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to
Clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com