99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Okay this is
Secret Stairs
East Bay walking
If there is ever a place that's higher up than where you are standing
Is a reasonable chance
You're going to want to go out
And wherever there is sufficient demand to move between two points of different elevation
There are stairs
Turn left
Walking between the opposing Gates
Hunter Rock Ridge Boulevard
Note the line
A very tall very old palm trees ahead of you
Check
California has a lot of hills
Enter neighborhoods in our great state
You can find outdoor stairs
Just passed the house at 6:09
Honey almost hidden staircase
It is your first climb
Publix Deli
609-6107
If you know how to look
Holy moly I totally missed
Wow I walked right by these steps
And then
That's our producer Sam Greenspan and as you may remember
He just moved to the Bay Area
I think I knew California had Hills I just didn't realize how much of a thing it is
Large number of often hidden public staircases
Why do Bay Area is so great
The Tourist
Crippling filbert steps to Coit Tower
Are not to be missed
The monument way staircase that leads you to my favorite place in the city
The pedestal of what used to be sutro's Triumph of light and liberty statue
And I go out of my way every single day
The walk the two blocks worth of stairs
By my new place in the Berkeley Hills
We have public staircases
And they Rock
And the guy who wrote the book on East Bay public stairs
Is Charles Plumbing
But he's not from here these base their book is actually a spin-off
Of his previous work
Secret Stairs of Los Angeles
Which is where Charles lives
That's where Sam tracked him down
My name is Charles Fleming I'm the author of Secret Stairs a walking Guide to the historic staircases of Los Angeles
Is more than 30 people assembled here
Because one Sunday a month
For the past few years
Charles has been leading Public tours
Through the Rosen acequia
Stairs book and we're we're here and we're Sunset Boulevard meets the Pacific Coast Highway in Pacific Palisades
About to embark on a stair walk it's actually scare walk number 41
From the book secret stairs and we will set forth here
Walk up the Coast Highway a little bit and then enter the historic castellum are a area of the Pacific Palisades which features
The number of
Striking public staircases
And we're off back before the tour is before the book
Before you really cared about public staircases at all
Charles
Just needed to walk
Now I got started with the stairs because I was trying to walk my way out of a surge
Surgery I had had two hip replacements and two spinal surgeries
Space of about 6 years and I was up for a third spinal surgery and I
Simply couldn't trace it and I knew what the surgery was going to be like and I knew what the rehab was going to be like
So I told the surgeon I'm not coming
Because I had found it a little bit of walking relieve the pain I was in so I started
Walking flat streets maybe two blocks at a time it was that hard to walk
Oh it was literally would have to have my wife put me in the car and drive me to a
Platt Street and help me out of the car and watch me walk two blocks pick me up and take me home that was
What's the first day and you know within a week I was walking three blocks and
Within a month I was walking a half a mile and because it was working I kept going and when I got
Boardwalk in the flat I started walking the hills when I get bored walking the hills I started
Taking out the staircases
So
First point of his
Dora Kent
Charles knew a little about the
The staircases
15mm around Silver Lake where he lives
The staircases are generally either from the 1920s boom years
Or from the days of the works progress administration
They were built because developers in hilly areas needed to find a way for
Prospective homebuyers
To get down from their houses
School work
Church for a streetcar line
But the depression
And then World War
Halted staircase Construction
And after that in the car really became the dominant feature of the Los Angeles landscape
So staircases were necessary because they weren't trying to serve a pedestrian
Population anymore they were trying to serve a car population
So they stop building the staircases
Charles looks for an inventory of all the public staircases in the city
I can find one
So I decided I would map I think they were probably 15 of them and I would make that my my little Quest
Neighborhood
Silver Lake
And but I felt so much out there when I was done with that and I decided I would do Echo Park 2
I figured they were probably 10 or 12 of them over there will turn out there about 60 and Echo Park
But I felt so healthy when I finish that continue
Sir Charles kept extending his reach
Different parts of Los Angeles
Pacific Palisades where we are now in Santa Monica Hollywood and walking
Franklin Hill Washington Highland Park Happy Valley and Pasadena
By the end of it he recorded routes that use
400 public staircase
400 and change over 500 that I actually map but in terms of ones that I was able to turn
Turn into practical walks 400 and something in the stairs and making all the routes to connect them
Charles Morgan 3 years
At first he just wander aimlessly through the neighborhood
Overtime
His approach began to get a little more sophisticated
Call Cindy was just looking for hilly areas where street cars used to run
And then I gradually figured out that if you found a curvy street a Lamppost
And a sewer line and a fire hydrant in the middle of a curve there was probably going to be published
Because if a city is going to retain ownership of a little
Slice of land
It's probably don't want to pack it with as many public utilities as possible
These little slices of land often snake
Greenhouses in yards
And that's one of the
Great things about the
Its 6
Exploring getting really close to someone's yard and house
Without actually trespass
But not everyone loves that these stairs are public
One set of stairs we came across
Buzz fence.
I'm not sure who put the gate up there it's another public staircase that was open to the public until quite recently
Is it at night sometimes the staircases can get used by people looking for a hidden place to do Shady business
I suppose it possible that could happen up here in the Pacific
Palisades
But but seems more likely at least in this case
Is it someone fenced off The Stairway to keep out the riff
The staircase is all go through residential districts and because they go quite narrowly between homes
There are a number of staircases
Around the city that have been closed by the residents
Against other residence without any permission from the city can they do that well they can't do it legally
Has managed to get some of these fences taken down
I'm meeting on congressman and City officials
Throw some use less
Bureaucratic
I know one fellow who just goes around with a bolt cutter and liberates the stairs
We couldn't confirm this but
I just love the thought of a guy going around in the dead of night
With a pair of bolt cutters
Liberating staircases
This is my kind of vigilante
Play idea of public access to the small spaces in between private property is in an oven
Self-compassion
As is the Allure of hidden.
Connecting neighborhoods
Art across the city
The part of the magic
Republic Airways
Is that you
Don't see Public Instruction devoted solely
Pedestrians all that much
They feel like going back in time
On your feet
Connectedu
To everything around
La is kind of a hard City to own I don't think people feel an intimate
Personal connection to it the way that they might if they grew up in Boston or London
And I think part of that is that you're in a car going past it so fast
Most of the city is just
The name of an off-ramp it's not you don't have any sense of who lives there or why they live there or
What would you like and when you slow down and move at pedestrian Pace it gives you the opportunity to get a little more connect
I think anybody would want that I make us human beings that's part of what is it
Why we live in cities
Why we live in community
If the streets are arteries
And the public walkway
Cesar the occasional
I can get so narrow
But only one red blood cell
Set a time
And when you encounter someone on the path
Air Force in Iraq
The step to the side
Maybe smile or not
Also it really feels like your trespass
I can't stress enough how fun that is
99% invisible with produces week by Sam green
Expand and Mero
Link to Alana Goldstein
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in taipei
It says go in the American Inn
Institute of Architects
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find a show and like the show on face
Guy tweet at Roman Mars
Web links to secrets are walks and you can always tell us about your favorite hidden stairs
Or the flatlander equivalent of hidden stairs
99% invisible
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com