99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I stepped off a plane from Hong Kong to San Francisco International Airport
It was his first time on American soil
At 22 years old he had left his homeland of China and traveled across the ocean to build a new life for me
Self and his young wife in this land of opportunity
When
Immigrants first come to the u.s. census in this is such an old Trope in an old story that you expect
Yeah the streets are paved with gold
This is Bonnie toy
Jorge's daughter
She's also the author of a book about American Chinatown
Even today a Chinese people still call San Francisco comes on gold Mountain
This is why you find your fortune in
George toys and very first stop in San Francisco he's very first stop in America like generation
Upon generation of Chinese immigrants before him
What's San Francisco's
Chinatown
And he was not impressed
The Gorge
San Francisco Chinatown
Out-of-date
All the things he saw in Chinatown these Pagoda roofs these Dragon Gates
These flourishes that
You know to a signal
China
And Tiny's notice there were things that he actually hadn't seen in back in China fur
Years and years and years and they were not used in that
Architectural vernacular back there and so
He wondered how Chinatown in this
In a relay supposedly modern America was
Why did it feel older than oldest parts
14 krona
Because it was designed that way
That's producer Chelsea Davis
For George soy and many other Chinese immigrants
San Francisco's Chinatown and the chinatown's in a lot of American cities
They don't look much like the China they know it actually
It's a lot of contacts to anything else
Next to it on either side
That's filmmaker Felicia Lowe
She made a documentary about San Francisco's Chinatown
Walking around Chinatown together
Epass Bank of America ATM
Guarded by gold dragon
Shops with neon lit names like
Heart of Shanghai selling paper fans in pots
And towering four-story bazaars
Crowned with little pagodas
But Chinatown hasn't always looked this way
In fact before the massive earthquake that leveled San Francisco in 1906
Chinatown look like most of the other neighborhoods in San Francisco rows of brick homes done up with Victorian
Italianate facades do you want anything you recognizes Chinatown other people in it
And Chinese signs
Instead of
American
Signs
That's Phil Choi a retired architect and historian of Chinese America
He grew up in San
Cisco's China
And still live there today
He says
It's not like Chinese immigrants in SF had strong opinions either way
About their neighborhoods
Victorian flourish
The columns
The porches
Beijing
Didn't have much
Choice when it came to where they live
After arriving in America they moved into the old homes that white people had abandoned for greener pasture
And after that basically the Chinese didn't have
Time
To really pay attention to
The architecture or creating
Chinese architecture
The basic
Desire was to make a living
And making a living with easier said than done
If you were Chinese in early 20th
Since the 1860
Chinese immigrants have been a convenience
Scapegoat for Nationwide job short
The result
Was Federal legislation like the 1882 Chinese
Exclusion Act
Which bar the vast majority of Chinese people from entering the
Estate
And made it impossible for Chinese already in the US
Become New American
And citizens
In San Francisco racist housing policies made it almost impossible for people of Chinese Heritage to live
Outside of Chinatown
And when they did set foot outside the 15 square blocks of the Chinese Enclave
It was at the risk of physical violence
So the self-contained world of Chinatown serves as a desperately needed Refuge
4 Chinese stamp
But in 1906
That Refuge would be eviscerated
Buy a double whammy
I'm a disaster
Early in the morning of April 18th of that year San Francisco magnitude earthquake
It was the biggest quake in the cities recorded history
But those violent Tremors were just the beginning
Shattered the cities gas means
And the gas that leaked out somewhere it connected
With a spark
The massive fire that resulted lasted for three days and destroyed about 500 city blocks
Chinatown was one of the first neighborhoods to go up in smoke
The safe space
For Chinese release at 15 block radius of the neighborhood and without it
Give me something very dangerous
Situation
Andrea Davies
This is a historian at the Stanford Humanities Center
But before her career in Academia she was in a slightly different line of work
I was a San Francisco firefighter
For about 5 years
And so my first assignment was trying to tell
Fighting fires in that neighborhood later LED Davies to write a Social history of the 1906 cutkosky
She says that in the wake of the disaster
Newspapers pedal this
You'll goodies story
But the SF quake and fire where social equalizers
That the shared experience of suffering
United San franciscans of all colors and creeds
Man helping man and so on
But while white man may have helped
White man
No one was open the Chinese
And the racism against them only intensified
I called Heiden post-disaster race
You could see this heightened racism happening on at least
Two level
First with individual White Sands
The built environment
Everyone in there
Your place
And that's what gets erase
So
If you're an elite White San Francisco and you don't have
The residence of China Town unless you go there
As
The Chinese are leaving their homes in desperation they're being yelled at to get out
And don't turn back
And according to Davies it wasn't just private citizens who were guilty of that heightened racism
Because the second place that the fire spur to flare up and racism
Wasn't how the recovery efforts were managed
The fire department
Did very little to
Stop it in China
And in fact made it worse
MN water main depth
Broken so there
Not wet enough water
Is if you look at
Chinatown
Which is nestled right against
Nob Hill
We're all the elite manga
All the water goes
Bridge by the mayor to save nod
And all the dynamite
Goes into
At the time fire departments would Dynamite buildings
To keep fire from spreading
But the fire department use the wrong kind of dynamite
In Chinatown burned all the faster
In the following days
At the Embers of Chinatown
The Chinese found themselves
Homeless
A new Leaf vulnerable
And hostel Street
But things
We're about to get worse
So many of the city's political and Business Leaders
Or actually excited about
The social
Equalizing disaster
Because of the Limited in Chinatown and they thought will never be
Before the quake
Many whites it's in the Chinese Navy
At the Camorra of opium dens
Prostitution and disease
In 1885
City Hall had prepared a municipal report on China
And in that report
Hate yourself
Of documentation listing all the houses of
Prostitution and the number of gambling houses and opium dens throughout China
This reputation for Vice
Had actually created a minor industry of Slum tourism
In Chinatown
Thrill-seeking white people could hire a guide to lead them through scenes of alleged
Depravity
It would be taken through dimly-lit building then shown opium smokers
Person prostitute
Sam gambling
Evidence suggests that some of these scenes may have actually been staged
By the gods themselves
And one thing that was definitely fake was a widespread rumor
That San Francisco's Chinese resident
Lived in underground tunnels this is what they really believe
That the Chinese lived underground and even today
People wants to see
Chinatown Underground
On top of all this
Chinatown was right in the middle of choice downtown rio
Real Estates at San Franciscan Elite
Had long wanted
For white business
In fact
2 years
Before the fire
Then-mayor James Phelan had hired an architect
Back to drive sketch
Free nude
The architect they hire
You may have heard of it
Daniel
Burnham
And in his plan there is no
Burnham was a proponent of the city beautiful movement and urban planning philosophy popular in the late 19th and early
20th century
And this idea of City beautiful
Biracial
Review
And the idea is
A more beautiful Urban environment create
My beautiful citizen
Like we want a beautiful city of well-educated
Citizens
Everyone is
White and productive and with China Town burn to the ground
City leaders seize the chance
Make that white dream a reality
Within a week of the fire
City Hall created a committee dedicated
Solely
To relocating
Chinatown
The group included former mayor James Phelan
The one you would hired Burnham to drive those revised draft
Cisco
And so the minute the city Goes Up in Flames
I'm not kidding I don't think so
Burning
And James feeling is
Telegraph
Daniel Burnham
Send more reports
Immediately get them at the hands of the
The city leaders and Business Leaders
Here's our plan we can rebuild
Here's the perfect
The plan for that perfect City
Who did the Chinese all the way to Hunters Point
A region on the edge of town
It's where the city slaughterhouse
But it wasn't long before the Chinese residents found out about
And they fought back
And I think they fought back very intelligently
They got china's empress
Dowager Sochi involve
She sent her consul-general from Washington
To meet with San Francisco officials
But the coup de gras
Was Financial
For decades
San Francisco had been a key hub for trade
What's China
So a group of the Cities
Chinese business owners wrote to the current mayor in a language San Francisco officials could ease
Totally understand
And so the on the business level of the negotiation was
Okay you don't want us to
Come back we're not going to Hunters
WinCo Tacoma
Weather Portland
What is a panic of a loss of Revenue
And that was a loss that city leaders
Couldn't take
Less than a month after the quake
The mayor dissolve
What is committee to relocate chine
For Chinese Americans at this time this was an unprecedented political victory
But they didn't stop there
The fire had left Chinatown
Blank slate
And for the first time
The Chinese were holding the
They were sick of Chinatown getting this bad rap for Vice
Sick of City Hall harassing them
Sick of visitors asking them if they lived in tunnels
The Chinese wanted makeover
For their neighborhood
And an American Born Chinese businessman named looked in Eli
You just had to go about it
The word was build me a pagoda
That's Felicia low again
She says that look Tennille I figured
Hey if Taurus
Are always going to come to Chinatown
Seeking a taste
If some imaginary is
Let's give them what they want and so he was able to hire white architect
To create a Chinatown that looked
The way
White people imagine Chinatown to look
Even though he knew
In his own mind that
The buildings in China didn't all look like this
That looks plan might seem a bit counterintuitive at first
For decades the Chinese of San Francisco had been harassed precisely because they look
And dress differently from mainstream White America
And he was the guy saying
Let's rebuild our neighborhood in a way that
Emphasizes are foreigners
The cars are different from the rest of the city into the very face of our buildings
The bunny soy
Whose father had been
Flummoxed by the look
Chinatown when he arrived in San Francisco
She says that the Chinese community of 1907
Saw a positive side to that
Foreignness
And they also were pretty Savvy with the fact that
People were interested in them and they were interested in this exotic
Element and if they could
Bill that in a way that was attractive
Instead of repellent
But that would be
Protective
For them
Look hired an architect
Text name t Patterson Ross
And an engineer named aw Burger
These two men
Had never been to China
At the time
The architect
Or not
Train did the tradition or anything about
Oriental architecture
Because
Also at the time the Orion was consider way behind the West
So
Culturally everything
Was look down upon that say
There's nothing to study about
Rothenburg runs knowledge of China was limited to a few images they seen of ancient palaces from the
The Song Dynasty
An architectural style that was already hundreds of years old
By the early 20th century
But that didn't stop Ross and brogren from using their imagination
I know how they use their imagination
They created the sort of Disneyland effect
Prince the sing Chong building was topped with a small structure that
Sort of look like a pagoda
The choice has that in China you typically wouldn't see a pagoda on top of another building
Pagodas there are free-standing structures
Not a decorative flourish
And secondly
In China these were The Monuments for religious purposes of the religion of Buddhism
Here and it's San Franciscan for him the Pagoda Inn
Stead houses in Monument 2
Consumers
Sing cheong became a bustling department store Hocking Asian art
Which it still is
To this day
But nonetheless the designers that looked in Eli hired created a striking building
Another Merchants rebuilding in Chinatown
Couldn't help but notice
Soon sing Chong's bombastic chinoiserie look had become dstyle Foremost New structures
Is going up in China
The Architects were trying to reproduce Beijing in San Francisco may have gotten a lot of the details wrong
But for the Taurus
They were wrong in all the right
Waves
Taurus
Loved the new trident
This was exactly the Westerner friendly version of China they want
Vaguely exotic
But safe enough for middle class
White America
Visitors began to flow into China
And so did their cash
Antenna towns Pleasant new appearance was beginning to change popular sentiment towards the Chinese people
American newspapers made it explicit that the neighborhood makeover was causing them to rethink their contempt for the time
And one newspaper the bulletin put it in 1909
Quote
Chinatown is one of the most noted places on the American continent
We have held up to the public gaze for
Too long the racial grief that separates the yellow and white people
The Earth
And quote
Looked in Eli's plan
Have work
In Chinese communities elsewhere in the US
We're taking notes
All of the success of Chinatown
That have come
In America
Take a cue from this take a page from this
Play book
New York San Francisco LA Honolulu
San Francisco
That's funny story again
She says visual style and tourist-friendly attitude that San Francisco's Chinatown
Affected
Soon began to spread
In fact a new Chinatown brand was so successful that it's still influencing chinatown's being built in our own time
Princess
Take the Chinatown in Las Vegas which was created in the 90s
It also had the same
Pagoda roof lines and dragon Gates like the same language architectural language at same architectural vernacular
I was being used
To create
The newest Chinatown that was used
To create the oldest Chinatown you know you outsmarted the devil you know who basically there is a phrase you know that they call
Call white people
Parkway which is
The white devil
I think that it was a victory absolutely
Of course
This architectural Revenge
Didn't instantly fix everything
For the Chinese in Sanford
They still face
Plenty of legal and popular discrimination
For example they were still required by real estate laws to live in Chinatown
And on a federal level
The Chinese Exclusion Act itself wouldn't even be repealed until 1943
More than 30 years later
And even if the rebranding of Chinatown help to ease negative sentiment towards the Chinese
Philips Hue believes it may also have helped promote certain stereotypes
It continues to promote
Al forniss
And my I remember my daughter coming home
One day very annoyed
And
These people look look look it's like they never seen a Chinese person before
By contrast
Look at the other traditionally ethnic neighborhoods in San Francisco
Japantown or the Italian neighborhood of North
Choices those neighborhoods
In South exoticize in the 1900s
The nearly the same extent the Chinatown did
They deliberately not embellish and embrace the ethnicity
Other immigrant groups at that time didn't face the same antagonism that the Chinese did
So only the Chinese were forced to cater to white people
Fantasies
As a survival knife
That's the irony
At that time we have to promote our forniss
To be accepted
But even if chinatown's architecture is a somewhat
Authentic representation of the real thing
But a lot of tourists don't realize is the fact that real people live there and that it is a place
Actually that is for poor people
You know I mean it is
@its
Essence a place where people
Come to live
When they first get here because they can't afford to live anywhere else
Because they need the services that are provided
There
Bunny soy says this is true of all the Chinatown she studied they're all portals of entry for
New immigrants of a particular class in a working-class immigrants who
Don't speak English
In fact
Thanks to factors like rent control zoning restrictions and really active tenants rights groups in the community
San Francisco's Chinatown has managed to remain a relatively affordable neighborhood
For low income in Agra
Ebony says yes
Chinatown has been disneyfied and rebranded to cater to American tastes
But there still an authentic and important history there
There's something about it that if you can reserve wreaths
Skyline you can read the story of
That's how this place came to be and also in that is Chinese American history and in that there's like there's a power in that
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Chelsea Davis and Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery Joplin Kurt Kolstad
Anne Meara
Version of the story was originally broadcast in the public radio history program backstory
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
The beautiful architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing.
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
It's a private family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You find the show and lecture on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify and you can listen to every single episode of
99percentinvisible
At 99 p.m.
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com