99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name in India
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
Terdema
A free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible
Linkedin.com
Invisible fear free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The story we're about to tell is pretty much the worst
A parent can imagine
We were awakened by the phone ringing
That's Noreen Gosch
It was early on a Sunday morning in 1982
In Des Moines Iowa
Marine son Johnny had left for his regular paper route
It was a neighbor saying they did not receive their newspapers
This wasn't like Johnny
Even a paper boy for years
He never missed a delivery
His dad got up and said I'll go help him finish the route he's probably just running late
He went
The street and that's where he saw Johnny's wagon sitting
Johnny's Red Wagon was sitting at the corner
It was still full of newspapers he rushed back and told me
Johnny was gone
Call the police
Johnny Gosch was 13 when he disappeared
He had blue eyes and dirty blonde hair
The small gap between his front teeth
And his would be the first face of a missing child ever printed on a milk carton
It's been 30 years since these milk cartons came and went
I wasn't alive to see them but I still know about the faces on the milk carton
That's reporter Annie Brown
The image of a missing child on a milk carton became iconic
A kind of cultural shorthand for missing children
And even though this image has stuck around for three decades
The actual milk carton campaign only lasted 2 years
It was largely unsuccessful at locating the kids on the carton
Good morning that Johnny disappeared Doreen said it took 45 minutes for the police to arrive
So he called around the other boys who deliver papers that morning
She found five witnesses that saw her son talking to a man in a Blue Van
She relate this to the police
The cop looked at me and said will has your son ever run away before
And I said well now he's never run away ever
Nor did he run away today
But the police were skeptical
This was Iowa
This kind of thing wasn't supposed to happen to kids like Johnny
In places like Iowa
Would never had a crime like this
This was before Amber Alert
Before those text messages that you get when a kid goes missing
It wasn't even a category for missing children
Kids were put in the same group as missing adults
In an adult have to be gone for three days before they were considered missing
Without the police's help Johnny's parents tried everything they could on their own
They hired private investigators in coordinated search parties
Meanwhile as a search
They also wrote Iowa State legislation that would differentiate missing children from missing adult
I wrote the Johnny Gosch law
Camping kitchen table
But after all of this
Noreen Gosch is sun was still gone
And then two years later in 1984 another little boy disappeared while delivering newspapers
He lived in a neighborhood not far from Johnny's
Morning
The second Paperboy had a relative who works at a local Dairy the Anderson and Erickson Dairy
The relative in the dairies owner has an idea to help by Newsboys
Anderson Erickson Dairy contacted each family
And they wanted to do something
Helpful in the investigation
The families of the missing boy the greed
And within a few short weeks thousands of milk cartons were rolls out of truck
An inter grocery stores
As clerk stock their shelves
The faces of Johnny Gosch and Eugene Martin smiled back
The campaign started out at 1 local Dairy
But over the next few weeks it spread to other Midwestern towns
In Illinois there I saw it and said hey
Why don't we try that
And from there
It went National
Nearly everybody drinks milk Mill turns over quickly so we could put a lot of different kids photos on
Run and pull children's off that needed to come off at a moment's notice
That's Barbara huggett
She was working as an artist
At the national Child Safety Council in Michigan
When the national milk carton campaign took off
Our founder apparently he'd seen
Johnny Gosch and Eugene Martin on the Anderson Erickson dairy milk cartons
But he felt that the program should be Nationwide
A nationwide milk carton campaign Willard families in California to look for a child who went missing in Iowa
The national campaign brought together local groups looking for missing children and together they came up with a list of
77kids
From all over the country
We used cases that were believed to be
What they termed in those days dangerous stranger abductions
In other words kids that weren't taken by someone they knew
Farbstein didn't have computers
So they cut and arranged all 77 layout
By hand design to lay out there was just doing a rather simple
Did across the top of each waxy paper panel
Photos of two children were laid side-by-side in black and white
Height weight
They also printed the pictures on school milk cartons but only one child could fit on those
Barbri started Ares all over the country asking if they'd be a part of the campaign
Within months 700 independent dairies had signed on boys I wish I knew how many cartons
Had circulated
Imagine its way into the billions 700-750 Dairies
Printing in and day out for years some sources of estimated that as many as five
Five billion milk cartons for printed with the faces of missing children
200 missing children were featured on milk cartons as part of the campaign led by the national Child Safety Council
Two were found alive
One with a kid named Bobby Smith Jr
Barb still remembers when she got the call about Bobby
After we gotten the word
That the child had been found
It was just a sense of
Of elation and you wanted to let everyone in the building that
Had mailed it box
Good chip dip
You know you just wanted to tell everyone who had
That
Did that was worthwhile
You could hear the cheer throughout the whole building
Yes we found a child that was wonderful you know
But Bobby Smith wasn't found because of the milk
Bobby was found by coincidence
His kidnappers car had been involved in an accident
And when the police came looking for the owner of the car
They found Bobby
The other child found alive with a girl named Cheryl Lynn Kramer but most of the kids featured in the national campaign
And and in the smaller local ones
We're never found
Unfortunately the leads from the milk cartons did not reveal or Johnny's look
Location was
That's Noreen Gosch again
Her son Johnny was never found but Barbara huggett and Noreen Gosch are both adamant
The campaign had a positive impact
What it did was promote more awareness
So the people were looking
They saw a child that look like they were into
Stress
Maybe you could
Whether or not
Those were the parents
During the milk carton campaign
The missing children assistance Act was passed
It established a Federal program to find missing kids
Changing the rules for
Children when they're missing not having to wait
The hours and in days
And mostly the milk cartons just got people thinking about kidnapping
That this could happen to your kid
I have talked
To quite a number of adult
And they could remember their mom putting the milk
Carlton on the guitar
Table
I'm saying
Now
We're going to go over the rules in
And they would use the example of the boys on the milk
And make the correlation between that child and their child's life
In other words the faces on the milk cartons scared the hell out of everyone
Which ultimately led to the campaign's downfall
Almost as quickly as it began the milk carton campaign started by the national Child Safety Council ended
Just two years after the first milk cartons were printed
Dairies began to pull the missing kids pictures from their side panels
One reason of course with the carton says that the industry shifted to plastic
But there is also started to get tired of the depressing message
Took it away because there were people that were
Complaining that they thought it might scare children at the breakfast
The famous pediatrician
Dr. Benjamin Spock
Rope columns
Condemning the milk carton campaign
Is traumatizing he said
Kids shouldn't have to face that over there Lucky Charms
They see these missing kids kind of staring at them
That milk carton almost demands them
To have that conversation
What to do if you see a stranger
Worst Ranger cost you
Let's Palmer Ziggy Renfro he's a historian at the University of Iowa
On the Milk Carton Kids
And their effect on us
He believes the milk carton campaign reflected a larger fear that was gripping Society at the time
Stranger danger
Paul studies the way that child safety was talked about at this time
In the news on the radio by politician
He says that the sphere
Stranger danger was exploding
Folks are taking around these numbers that are just astronomical
Picture saying there 1.8 million missing children in the United States
Missing becomes very closely attached to abducted by strangers
But that just wasn't true
Every year
800000 kids are reported missing to the authorities
That's around 2000 every day
But a report from the Department of Justice
Found that the number of kids taken by strangers every year
Is only about a hundred and fifteen
The milk carton campaign led by the national Child Safety Council focused on kids who were kidnapped by
Strangers
And they were criticized for this
But they were also smaller more localized campaigns going on that were Bound by this rule
It was one of these smaller campaigns that ended up featuring the face of a missing girl named Bonnie Lohman
Cannot my strangers I was kidnapped by people that loves me
Bonnie Lohman was kidnapped by her mother when she was three
After her parents got divorced
Even though she wasn't kidnapped by a stranger Bonnie that had managed to get her on a milk carton
Funny had no idea that she had been kidnapped
But her childhood was pretty strange
After taking Bonnie
Her mom and stepdad went to Saipan
A tiny Island near Guam
After year in Saipan next was Hawaii
But they were still lying very well
We stayed inside all the time and
I recall Maybe
One or two times being outside
Finally they ended up in Colorado
Her mom and stepdad started to relax a bit
The next-door neighbors had a bunch of kids and
Bonnie played at their house all the time
Will you play Barbies and I had my little
Barbie case and I would bring that over
Aside from going to her neighbors Bonnie was hardly ever allowed to leave the house
But on an unusual occasion her stepdad took her to the supermarket
They needed milk
Just remember like looking and
Seeing how many
Part of the milk there were
Like nowadays it's like whatever brand it is would be facing
He knew where I was at that
Pictures were
He grabbed the milk
Irritating after that is
Hey arthena
And I saw myself and I was like
That means like
Yes
Bonnie actually saw her own face
On a milk carton
Though she had no idea what it meant at the time
Funny step dad bought the milk carton
And when they finished it
He asked her do you want it
You you want to keep it
Until I remember cutting it out and being like Willow and staring at the picture
My hair was leaking a little
Ponytail on the side and I was wearing this little
Dressy like now you got to keep it in a safe place and I must have tossed
Barbie case
Looking Back Now
Bonnie sees her step dad's actions as arrogance
He was so confident in himself
Could show me that because nothing's going to happen
But the next time Bonnie was at the neighbors house she left her Barbie case
Is there
With the picture she cut out
Her own face on a milk
Carton
I remember there
A lot of police showing up
A police
Within hours of the neighbor of finding the picture
Police had sworn Bonnie's home
She was whisked away and returned to her father
She was having at the time
But their Union wasn't easy at first
I remember
Being scared because I didn't know my dad
And I'll be with her
Bonnie is very clear that her mother loved her
What you didn't know then was that she'd been denied some pretty basic
Pieces of her childhood
In the three and a half years he was missing money didn't go to school
Jen learn to read
I know I didn't read and then because I would have realized that I was missing because on the picture Attack
Actually said
Missing child
And then my name and the date
After returning to her dad
Bonnie's had a pretty normal life
She started school went on to college and eventually became a nurse
Just two kids now
She's really happy
She's one of the milk carton campaigns
Fue success
I believe that I am who I am
Because I was on a milk carton and II was found and
I had opportunities that with my dad growing up that I might not have had with my mom
I was able to live a great life and I'm grateful for it
2 years the milk carton campaign had ended but the faces of missing children were still being printed on all
Kinds of other things
Pizza boxes
Plastic grocery bags
Utility bills
Actually the utility bill campaign
Went on for 10 years
Much longer than a milk carton
But most of us haven't even heard of it
It didn't stick
The weight of the milk carton did
Again here is Palmer's Vicki Renfro
The historian
It's one of those troops with which role familiar and it's appeared in the novel's film
Now there's a band called the Milk Carton Kids
There was something different about seeing a face on the side of a milk carton that really struck a nerve
There is a sense of familial
Unity
But I think milk
Helps
The author maternal nurturance
Also being this kind of
Item around which people gather
Around The Breakfast Table
Putting missing kids faces
Horn
That item
What's white deliver in
Perhaps
The reason why that lives on
99% invisible West produced this week by Annie brown with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman Kurt Kolstad
Andy Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
Open up man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting
Special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you go
Podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
But it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find this show and like to show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Instagram Spotify
Tumblr
If you name that we're probably limit but you're always welcome at our place
99 Pi. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Do your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth pot
Dot-com