99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
There is this moment in my life when I needed to interview the rapper Busta Rhymes for the radio and this is friend of the show
Shawn Cole and sorry I tried calling his people which got me pretty much net worth
Then tried Googling Busta Rhymes and Boston which is where I was living at the time cuz I figured
Babies coming on tour in a good Ambush and backstage and one of the first results I got
It was a map like on Google Map
Of a little pond in Shrewsbury Massachusetts which is this little
Town outside of Austin and in the pond was this tiny Speck of land
And labeled Busta Rhymes Island
What
Needless to say I was a little confused
Shrewsbury is like the least likely benefit of all the for there to be a bus
Catherines Island anywhere is pretty unlikely but but Shrewsbury is like his bedroom community for
Worcester it's not even
Is like the most exciting thing to do there on a Saturday night is going to Chili's
After like
Shopping at Lumber Liquidators and I was like is this for real and then underneath
Meet the link for the map
With another link
To this short little
Blurb in the Boston Globe
With a headline
Busta Rhymes Island Is For Real
Send
And they interviewed
Kevin O'Brien who lives in house overlooking the pond
Millpond is the name of it
And who this is still true
List his phone number as the number to call if you want to contact the island
So he's a guy who named the alley the one named Ian
And this is a quote from the the Boston Globe
This guy Kevin says
It's a very small little island with rope swinging blueberries
And
Stuff Buster would enjoy
Adorable
So
So just to give you a sense of the differences
Between Busta Rhymes
And Busta Rhymes Island
Is like an internationally known
Really fast rapper with 10 albums has got at the other one
Being me and I went right yes no man is an island
After all
But also just sonically
Busta Rhymes sounds like this
Busta Rhymes Island
Sounds like this
So what about this island
Would you say bespeaks
Busta Rhymes
Just pretty much the kind of feel of it
This is Kevin O'Brien I drove out to Shrewsbury to spend some time with him on the island
It was cold
February
We walked across the ice to get there
Little more about Kevin he's in his early 30s
Works in tech support and DJ's wedding on the weekend
You know if you come out here in the summertime it's
A really nice relaxing place to be
It's it's
Dead Silence
It's really really Loki in
Who wouldn't let us aren't aspects of Busta Rhymes dead silent emoji
He meditates
Kevin started canoeing out to the island about 10 years ago now when he and his wife first moved here
The pain is practically in their front yard it's a teeny tiny Speck of land you mean
40 feet
And that the end there is a rope swing
Hanging from one of the trees
And blueberry bushes which Kevin planted just visit the island a bunch he takes
Caribbean island
Cleaned up after the teenagers who have beer cans laying around
Drinks beer himself on the island with his wife and their friends
And when you love a place
The way Kevin love this place
You don't want to refer to a generic lady that just doesn't feel respectful
So
One day
I was sitting around with my friend Brandon
And we just
Started talking about
How we are always coming over the island and he asked what his name was
Who started saying we'll have a Busta Rhymes Island restaurant everybody was Busta Rhymes
Tell me the directions to my house I know you know just look up Busta Rhymes Island on Google Maps and follow your way there
I think it sounds a lot better than saying Millpond so
We went we want Busta Rhymes and
We have a lot of respect for him
So how did you get it on Google Maps
We just stopped just apply Tajima tag to it it's that easy it's that easy and really the whole thing with seem like a big
Big joke
If it weren't for all the effort Kevin went through to try to make the name stick
Around the time I contacted him he submitted a formal proposal
To the US board on Geographic names
Besides with the federal government is going to call a piece of land
He showed me the proposal
Feature class
Island
Meaning or significance
Busta Rhymes is a gravel voice rapper we all have an incredible amount of respect for
Supporting materials
No
They turned him down
But not for the reasons you might think
The only way you can name the island or a body of land
After
Celebrity
Is in a commemorative patch
Cancel that person has to be deceased
For five years so
Fortunately
Really can't be official until
Basta Pasta
That could be a long time I'm willing to wait
So someone has to be dead for 5 years before the board will consider naming a place after that person that's right
What my five-year-old I wanted the same thing so I called a blue Yost
Who's the executive secretary at the US board on Geographic names
Regarding domestic
Names in the United States
Forenames is another
Anyway when someone passes away
Soon after person's death
Emotional time
Close
Relatives
Friends
Feel they want to do something
To honor this person
It's like you're waiting
What's it settle
Do are people disappointed when you tell them about the five
After explain the reasoning they
Weather disappointed they they agree
I really say they agree
That it that it has to be still want to name an island after that person half a decade later
Type of sentimentality
Right
Lou Yost says the board actually discourages naming places after people at all
ID rather than a bee
Future Bass
That is having something to do with the way an island or mountain or a river
Looks or sounds
How big it is
Rather than who homesteaded
But with the exploration of the West and Alaska
It was bound to happen
These guys have been around a long time
6 days after JFK was shot
Soap 1963
Lyndon Johnson announced the Cape Canaveral would be renamed Cape Kennedy
To commemorate the president
Jackie Kennedy's idea
Well
People in Florida did not like that at all
Why not have been called Cape Canaveral for like 400 years
And I didn't know this can a parole
Is a Spanish word
It roughly means a plantation of canes or reeds
10 years later the Florida legislature voted to change the name back from
And the board went along with it
And it was this event
That led to the one-year waiting period
But it was a five-year waiting. It was one year then
New Year's in in 19
95.7
And there has never
Never
Been an exception to the rule since then
No naming places after people who have been dead less than 5 years and certainly no naming a
Place after someone who's still alive
It's a board starts naming features for
Living people
And then
They going
Heinous
It's not going to look
Look good
Busta Rhymes is being accused of using gay slurs at a fast-food restaurant in Miami this was at
Cheeseburger Baby
In Miami Beach and he was apparently therefore some promotional purposes and
Then I'm looking fell There It Is by
As I was learning about all of this I remember this one place that have been named after someone
Not while he was living but not that long after you died either and here we are
Central Square in Cambridge Cambridge Massachusetts
Where I was born
Black sign in the sidewalk
Says Mark Sandman Square
Corner of Brookline Street and
Mass Ave
Martin is another musician who was the lead singer of the band morphine
He died in 1999
Collapsed on stage during a concert in Italy
And then just one year later this sign went up on this corner
Right outside the Middle East
The Middle East nightclub Merced menu
Forum
Or just hang out
The sign was Joseph satyrs idea
He's one of the owners of The Middle
Do you remember the dead of the dedication ceremony
I think it just Public Work Wallace and they said the sign is it ready
Do you know
So wonderful to sign up
What flowers in March
Branson national Park
You know in his memory and nothing of the good time
So how was Joseph able to dedicate the corner to Mark Sandman only one year after he died
When the regulation says that he has to wait at least five years
The way you're explaining any would have been relegated to
City of Cambridge this is Lou Yost again at the u.s. board on Geographic names
Building
Would be what we
Considerate
Administrative features
The board has relegated that it's already named
Best features to the local
Administrative
Would be up to the city
Explain the five-year rule to Joseph at the Middle East
And how
Especially in that first year of course everybody wants to name something after their loved one who died
Everybody want out
Stop on the wagon
You want to name every if they wanted him everything everything after
Understand. It wasn't like this was my you know I mean definitely will missed him he moved on
Who got cheated by not having him around.
It was an emotional itsuno admits
You know friend around
Venom
They did a lot of this community every time you call on him for
Fundraising auto show you know he's there to play for free or barely any money cell
Definitely you did due diligence social you know
What would he think of the signs you think
If the square
He wouldn't he would laugh
Funeral but doesn't matter
I also got in touch with the mayor's office in Cambridge
To ask what the
The criteria are for naming a corner of
The city after someone
They sent me the application you fill out when you want one of those signs hammered into the sidewalk
Mark Sandman would fit under the category
Distinguished careers by present or former residents who have achieved state or national Fame
And then I asked them if the person in question had to be deceased
And they didn't respond
But on the application it says
Deceased it's in it with a?
And then a box of checks that makes it sound like you can memorialize people who are still alive
Or it's just like a test
Because I remove all the ones that are still alive
But then I started noticing
Those black commemorative signs
Everywhere all around Cambridge
John tijani Collins Square
Commander Francis X buddy Foster Square
Robert E Goodman Road
It's
Been very loose
This is Charley Sullivan with the Cambridge historical Commission
Anyone
Who is interested in having a square named after a family member like
The stairs one of those signs right on the corner Helen and John black Square
Could just ask a city councillor
And they would put in a council order
The city would do it
So we have intersection
In some parts of town that have one of those
Signs on each other
The four corners
Really
Yeah
Preponderance
Dedication
Proliferation of dedication
You seem you seem
Not so pleased
Well it gets to be a little
Instead of a clutter after a while
And they begin to lose their meaning
So I think the
City council is a little more resistant
Used to be they're running out of places to put these
So I just to be clear these places they're not recognized by the US Board of geographic names
Maps are used by the federal government in any way but
That said
Local usage is something the board takes into account when it's evaluating a proposal
And not just the local Authority recognizing the name
But the locals
Those Folks up there
In that house
Getting that Over Yonder this is Kevin O'Brien again
That Busta Rhymes Island we would have to go to them and say hey do you know the name of that Island if they were psycho that's
Busta Rhymes island or whatever else we're going to name it
Then that would be considered local usage so if
If local folks know what to call it
Everybody calls it that
Then you have a lot more a lot more weight going to the government and saying I'd like to name this island
But as far as Heaven Knows
Nobody except for him and his wife and their friends call this island anything
We spent about an hour on the island together
I like
Is very cold
And just as we're about to leave these two kids have been skating out in the middle of the pond came wandering over
Two boys
Maybe 10 years old
Morning
Doing a radio story about The Silence
Do you know anything about this island
I just moved here how did you
Well if you if you look up this island on Google Maps
Christina what it's called
It's called Busta Rhymes Island
Do you know who that is
Nope he's a rapper
Firewood
She named after
G named after him
Cuz he's a big fan
Would you name this island
You can name it something
I don't know
Wait wait all the shoes very Island
Shrewsbury
Do you have a favourite
Musician or anything like that
No
Busta Rhymes Island
Great to meet you guys
Local usage Ram
Give us right we just witnessed Busta Rhymes Island being used
I did call them into it exactly into it
Say I did try contacting Busta Rhymes again
Those managers all about the islands that I wanted to interview on
Again they never responded
Also a few days after I first emailed them
Google Maps
And the geotag was gone
I contacted Kevin right away
First I've heard of it
And he said
Well I know what I have to do
At it again and see how long it takes to be taken down again
Sure enough
Couple weeks later
Busta Rhymes Island
Was back on the map
Like Mount Rainier appearing and disappearing with the weather and not long after that
Friend of mine randomly met Buster in a bar in New York she was dating a guy who knew him
And when she asked him about the Island bus to said this is quote
Not that I heard about that
99% invisible with produce this week by Shawn Cole
Put Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
The offices of arcsin the brilliant architecture from the wheel of rubbing elbows with every single day and beautiful.
Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is another word for all hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars at Sam's with the same listens
Set droppleman
Katie mingle sometimes tweets at Katie Mingle
Is the law because she's the youngest but if you would do as a kindness until everyone you know to subscribe to the show
99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast
Dot-com