99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
I think if you ask somebody on the street
What is camouflage I believe most
Common answer would be so well
It is a figure
And it's being blended with its background
The scientist today call that background matching by similarity camouflage
Let's Roy Baron Barons and I teach in the department of art at the University of Northern Iowa I teach graphic
Design and the history of design is also one of the foremost
Camouflage expert
Swell
I wouldn't go that far. What I do
Item molarity or blending is just one type of camouflage
Kind of boring one
But another type of camouflage that you can find both in nature and in military use
It's disruptive camo
Figure disruption
Raptor options
Breaks up the figure
It's the opposite of high similar to camouflage it's high differ
So you're making it
Very difficult
For us to look at the figure and to see it as
Only a single
Continuous thing ruption drops
Zebra stripes have long been thought to be a form of disruptive
Stripes
Make it hard for a predator to distinguish one zebra from another
When the zebras are in a large herd
Botrytis might also makes me Breathless
Attractive to bloodsucker
Horsefly
But when it comes to humans
The greatest
Most jaw-droppingly
Angular application of disruptive camouflage by the military
Is Razzle Dazzle
Camouflage
Strictly applies to ship camouflage and even more strictly it applies to World War 1
And it came about because it was discovered
It's
Almost impossible to make a ship
Invisible
On the ocean
The Horizon is changing in color it's changing
Amount of light
So they're all kinds of conditions that make its way constantly moving ship can't blend into the background
Odyssey
And even if you could make a ship invisible you still have smoke coming out of smokestack so it's not as if your
Hiding ship it all
To the less heavily armored ships were sitting ducks
The crisis came about at the time that the US had not yet entered the war remember this is World War 1
It was the British ships
That were being sunk and
The German submarines were sinking as many as
50 ships
A week
Naval ships were Merchant ships
And they were
Bringing supplies
Which is an island of course send
It really depended on those and then also there was
Armaments and other things that were being secretly taken there
Where to
So the design solution was not about invisibility
It was about disruption
A number of artists decided that the best way to avoid getting torpedoed
Was not to make the ship invisible
But to make it
Hard to hit
That's why
These kind of erratic
Crazy quilt patterns came about and that's why they were used in that war
It's going to be hard at pictures
Best but I'm waiting to try
There was a time when military ships
Steven us ships by this
Pour painting
With an i
Quote
This is from an anonymous article in New York Times from 1980
Any New Yorker will see a tanker or coming in or going out
Numerous ships
Who's painted signs reveal such Wild extravagances
A form and color
And make the landsman open his eyes
With amazement
And mystification
Black and white was very common they consist of
Stripes and Swirls and kind of Arabesque almost Art Nouveau shapes
Blue
Was
Use predominantly especially in the British versions
But I think you'd be surprised
The range of colors there were Reds that were Sometimes using greens and really quite intense oranges
Another on identified you as journalist Road
You should see our Fleet
It's camouflage so it looks like a flock
Seagoing Easter eggs
During World War 1
Dazzle ship camouflage with absolutely
Fascinating to the public
You have to remember that this is happening
Just a few years after the
What's called The Armory show in New York it's the first
International show of Modern Art
In this country
And it was the introductory show up
Cubism futurism
All of those things that
People make fun of and they thought
Good universities are really crazy directions for artists to be going in
When this happened
People looked at those ships and they said
Succubus nightmare
Futuristic
As you can probably guess they were plenty of people
Who hated Dazzle camouflage
Traditional Navy men most
So they compared it to the clothing it up prostitute would wear and they make fun of it
Here's how it work
The steps
At the time Torpedoes fired from U-boats were quite slow maybe taking a couple minutes
To reach their target so the person firing the torpedo
Had to lead the target
He had to anticipate
Where the target ship was going to be
When the torpedo arrive
So we had to calculate how to do that in that
During which depended on knowing
The exact angle it's it's headed toward
That's terribly terribly bored
And the other thing is that you have to figure out
The speed
Of the ship
Because then you'll know
How far to go by the time the torpedo
The Dazzle camouflage certainly made the ship
Stand out
But they're bulging shapes and Vivid hues
Also made it difficult to determine the
Speed and direction of the moving ship
It's praying on our assumptions about
Things
Looking smaller as they are more distant
So you could paint perspective patterns on a ship
That would make it look like it was
Turning
Is a different direction when in fact that you're actually seeing them frontally and they're absolutely flat
Bedazzled patterns
Broke up to figure
So that I can look shorter than it really was
Or I can make it hard to tell if there is one shift for multiple ships
But even painted
Fake ball waves on them
And they would paint the
Fake bow wave
Either on the front
To make it look like the ship was going fast
What's actually going
Cuz that was one way of calculating
Or fish would
Paint the bow wave
On the back
And so you would glance at it
Why you looking through this Periscope you might conclude that
Going in that direction
Not in the other two
New Surface again
Tula calculate where you going to shoot in
The thing is
Gone it's an entirely different direction and location than you imagined
These patterns were just slapped on the side of giant ships hoping that they'd be confusing enough to be effective
Tama florist
But they were called
Pajama floors
Tested toy model
By inviting an experience submarine captains
To peer through periscope
And Report what angle they thought
The model
Square pointed
They determined that
Sometimes on really effectively
Camouflage ships
The calculation of a ship captain
Could the office much as
Degrees
Dazzle only had to screw up the torpedo counters estimate by 8 degrees
For the Target ship to effectively avoid
A torpedo
The theater of war has changed
So camouflage has changed with
But there is still dazzled to be found
Actually if you look at military crafts
Today
There is still dazzled in Pratt
But of course the conditions of change
Just as a World War
This came out of those particular set of conditions we have to say
Well those are the conditions that we have now so what would be most effective
If you look at their craft
Broken up very often
If you look at ships
Two of them are broken up
Eliza geometric
Patterns
If you look at some camouflage uniforms
Infantry uniforms around the world you'll find all kinds of bow
Break up with jazz on so forth or tanks or
Truck service
But I'm sad to report that there are no longer phlox
Pepsi going Easter egg
99% invisible is produced by me Roman Mars and Sam Greenspan
We are product of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a kid is another remedy for all hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
But it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
But this week you absolutely must
Go the 99% invisible. Org it look at pictures of Dazzle
They are just that amazing
You will not believe it
All you will do
This week
Batak Bedazzled
That's why I almost guarantee it
10% invisible
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
It's something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com