99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
One of the most exciting things in sports is to see a truly great player shatter all previous attempt
About what is possible to achieve Ligety
Millwall fans applaud
Announcers lose their minds
Opposing team scramble Define strategies.
In basketball they tried to stop Shaquille O'Neal by immediately following him when he got the ball
So that he'd have to shoot from the free throw line
Which he wasn't very good
Best strategy became known as the hack-a-shaq
Cuz he really have a hackashack call
I don't believe it 5 seconds in soccer opposing teams continuously file the great Argentina
Player Leo Messi to keep him from dribbling to their defense
Absolutely
These tactics
Stop the great players
Can be aggressive
And they often stretch the limits of the rulebook
That's neupane bringing us up
Story today
He's from 538 data journalism site owned by ESPN
But in baseball they did it differ
In baseball the solution to
Stopping the greatest hitter of all time
What's the actually redesign the game
Itself
It all started in the 1940s
With the Great
Ted Williams
Famously he would say that when he grew up he wanted to be the greatest hitter who ever lived
Ben bradlee Jr wrote that
Definitive biography of
Before a game in the clubhouse she would put up a mirror
And strip down to was
Skivvies
And swing a bat
Say
Ted Williams
I'm the best hitter who ever lived
Pardon my French
Not a humble man
Doug Williams but also not wrong
In 1941 the Young Red Sox Superstar finish the year with a batting average
Meaning of he got a head in over 40% of his at-bats
Which is incredibly good
No one has batted above 400 since Ted Williams
Ted Williams
The greatest hitter of them all
And Williams kept it up
Even left to fight in World War I
Came back
And was still the best
Best hitter in baseball
But in 1946 just as Ted Williams was on track for another record-breaking year
He came face-to-face with someone hell-bent on ending history
A guy with the Cleveland baseball team named Lou Boudreau
Boudreaux was a shortstop for the Indy
But he was also the manager of the
Because back then you could actually be both a player and a manager at the
The same time
He was an incredibly ambitious person
And a great player
But despite Boudreaux's success
There was this other player that got
All the attention
Ted Williams
The greatest
Hitter who ever lived
Williams-goss
Most of the headlines
Praise
Freshwater being such a great hitter
That's Russell Schneider
He covered the Indians for the Cleveland Plain Dealer
And became close with
Knowing Boudreaux's
Think I did
There's no doubt but this was a Clash
Eagles
Between William
Boudreaux
But Boudreaux had a plan
He knew that Williams almost always hit the ball to the right side of the field
Between first and second base
As the Indians manager
He could actually set up his team strategy
Specifically to beat Williams
Voice whisper.
Cleveland manager
Burning the midnight oil perfecting a new type of DP
Blue said the Hound is I'm tired of having Williams
The Beatles
And it is
This is what I want to do
Lou Boudreau decided that he would shift three players from the left side of the field
To the right
He put a wall up
3 infielders between first and second base with a trio of outfielders backed up behind them
Now 6
Of the seven Defenders were standing on the right side of the field
Only one lonely outfielder remains on the left
The Familiar symmetry of the baseball diamond
Adventist Rock
And with it
The Ted Williams shift
Was born
I called the Boudreau shift
Some people call it the defensive shift or just
The chef
First time boudreaux use the shift on williamswood july 14th 1946
Fenway Park
When William stepped into
The place and saw the shift for the first time
He said that the Umpire what the hell is going on out there
They can't do that
But they could
Totally legal
And so Williams had a choice
Swing just like he always swan
Any might hit a homerun
But he might also hit the ball into the crowded offender shifted to his right
Or
He could go outside his comfort zone
Try to hit the ball to the left
Boudreaux knew they would be difficult for Ted to alter his swing
The song I'm selfish
The Slugger
Home run hitter
And that therefore he would
Continue doing it his way
Who wrote the Ted Williams biography
He was appealing to the williamses pride
And it worked
The first time Williams came up to bat he hit
Straight into the teeth of the shaft
In fact he hit the baseball right to Boudreaux himself
Standing directly between first and second base
Boudreaux kept using the shift on Williams and pretty soon other teams were using it against him to
Wasn't long at all maybe within a week or two that the rest of the American League
Was adopting it
The Williams argued that
No he wasn't going to alter his natural swing
But the fans were showing up at
The park to see him hit
In interviews William said he thought the ship shaved about 15 points
Off of his lifetime batting a
Back
Probably the only tactic that ever actually had an effect on head while you
Eventually Ted Williams retire
And the chef
It more or less disappeared from baseball
A lot of managers were hesitant
To use it because it didn't always work
When it goes bad you look
This is John Dewan the author of The
Fielding Bible
And the guy you'd be safe calling The Godfather
Shift date
And he says for a long time
Teams didn't have the kind of data that would back up the idea that risk would pay off overtime
You know they weren't real strong Analytics
Back in the seventies and eighties that could tell you
I just kind of think
Would work but then sabermetrics came along
Sabermetrics is a movement in baseball that started in the 90s to collect data and study it to find advantages
Suddenly GM's in front office is across the major leagues were focused on this idea that to win without spending much
How much money
All you had to do was look at the numbers
Enter the Tampa Bay Rays
Formerly known as The Devil Rays
It was regarded as
You know maybe the worst franchise in all the bass
That's Jonah Keri
A journalist who wrote a book about the rain
They just didn't really understand what it took to win
This is bad baseball defensive miscues have cost a Devil Rays
Dearly in the 8th
But things started changing for the rights in the mid 2000
Stuart Sternberg former partner Goldman Sachs
Decided he was going to buy the tea
And with him he brought a bunch of other Wall Street
You know number guys
Quad
Guys who are good at using data to find hidden
Advantages
Is Siri was
Let's just succeed and be 2% better than the competition
The Rays numbercruncher study the data and they discovered a really efficient tactic that can help their fielding and defense
Atactic
Dredged up from baseball distant past
You guessed it
The defensive she
The shift really is a perfect example of an extra toe
2% Advantage because this doesn't work all the time Infected fails quite a bit
But the Rays didn't have much to lose so they decided to take a risk and bring back the chef
And they hire manager
The team who's on board with their plan
A guy by the name of Joe Maddon
And right away
Madden starts using the show
Death on all kinds of
Different headers
Joe Maddon he's kind of the doctor and the master of the defensive shift
Against Hardy
The Joe Maddon has come up with all kinds of interesting shifts this year She'll follow me you don't really ride
See this type of shoe
Just all that often
And all the sudden
Just a disaster of a team
Airtight in the
You can score runs off their pictures
From nowhere they transform themselves from a
Petrol doormat to a championship contender
And the shift was right at the center of their resurgence
The shift caught on
All the sudden every team the league started shifting
In fact other teams began shifting against the Rays on best hitters
Including this guy my name is Carlos Pena net play Major League Baseball 414ce
Carlos Pena grew up playing baseball and a kid in the Dominican Republic
And being a power hitter I believe
Was his ticket to the US
We swing our way you know off the island we have two other stuff that's the way we but we were taught you know we want to make some
You better
Swinging
Empower
And swing for power heat
Dead
Carlos Pena height
Home runs in
In 2007 while playing for the Rays
Right around the same time Joe Maddon was reintroducing
In the shift to the Major League
And there's a high fly ball back into right field number 46
Bad to shift on
And the shift is absolutely a killer
Ground ball right into the teeth of a shift and Lopez
I'm short right field throws out Pedro
Let me know if this is going to be
You know for the rest of my career and sure enough and that's exactly what happened
Anna Johnson
Newhattan plate between first and second in the ship
Even the greats like pain yet can't hit home runs all the time
When Penny was shifted on
He had to make a decision
Do I swing my natural swing and maybe get a homerun or maybe hit straight into the shaft
Where do I change my
Eventually
Unlike Williams whose ego led him to try to power through this shift
Pena started to adopt another tax
He did something Ted Williams it only tried a handful of times during his whole career
Shifters on Prytania
Carlos Pena
Budget
Be humble but
There's nothing pretty about this move
You just kind of bummed about with your bad and it dribbles out onto the field
Bunting with something that players traditionally did just to move their teammates from one base to another
For Carlos Pena turn the butt into his own
Secret weapon
Using the bundt pan you could tap the ball toward third base
Where no one was around to pick it up
And it worked a lot of the time
Even if you didn't always feel good about using it
It felt like I was giving in
You know like I was saying okay
You guys got me I'm just going to buy
That's kind of silly but
In reality sometimes says prideful athletes we think that
No man
Play the game
Daniel knew he had to swallow his pride
But it went against everything he had learned growing up
I grew up watching
Comanche
Home run
That's what was celebrated
You know no one said
Grapevine Sun
Painless bumps though they were
Really great at one point in his career he was 15 for 25 on bunts against
The ship
Carlos Pena become the most prolific bunters
In the majors against the ship
Fastball inside
How about that great white
Front by Pina
Pena says his success at combating the chef has actually changed the way the game is played
But he's not happy about
Man that shift is just a
Images of shift is something that
I wish they could get rid of
New baseball commissioner Rob Manfred actually agrees with
Siri is talking to ESPN about how he wants to improve
Things like eliminating shifts
I would be open to those
Mannford thinks the shift makes the game less
Exciting because it makes it harder for teams to score run
He also thinks it's just happening
Too much now
Shift is on as the shift is on there it is
Ship design
The shift is on for the Rockies defensive
In many ways the fight about the chef has become a fight over the nature of the game
Ever since sabermetrics came along
Baseball fans
Pundits
Players
Have bristled at the idea that on-field decisions
Are basically a product of data analysis
That could be maddening that too many players just like weight
This kid
From Harvard
Who has never
You know throwing a baseball
It's deciding the future that angers
Like you wouldn't believe
But unless there's a rule change the field will keep shift
Pause it
Works
It's huge
It is really here
According to John Dewan the author of The Fielding
It can help win about three extra games a year
Which is
3 wins
I think every single year has separated
I'm getting into the playoffs
Tinder not going to give up that competitive advantage
So now it's a fight between the number guys
In the traditional
Between the Nerds and the jocks
Decide the design
Have the game
In the meantime if my boys ever decide to take a baseball
I'm going to make sure and tell him
Bright Bugz
99percentinvisible with collaboration this week with 538 the data journalism site owned by ESP
Who is produced by Joe sites with editing from Jody avirgan and adapted for 99p I by Katie Mingle
Sports reporter Neil pain
Neil is a painless on 538 Sports podcast hot take down and they're doing a whole series of documentaries called
Ahead of their time about players and coaches were doing something radical but weren't appreciated in their era
You can find them all at fivethirtyeight.com podcast store by searching hot takedown
Favorite podcast app
99percentinvisible is the a prevention Katie mingle Plus
Kolstad Sharif Youssef same Greenspan Avery Chapman Emmett Fitzgerald turn Meza Delaney Hall and Mero
We are product 91.7 kalw San Francisco introduced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
To all the beautiful earrings out there who donated during a fundraiser thank you so much
Index depositor magazine in freshbooks
For putting up generous challenge grants that motivated us they hit our goals in the wee hours of the morning
Are listener support makes us strong and helps us try new things
It wouldn't be radiotopia
Without you
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sign
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Talking to me and my wife is in another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flat pocket
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at 9
99pi org run Instagram and Tumblr to
But the Nexus of all things 99 pi
Is that 99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com