99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman
When basketball was invented
As an indoor sport that can be played during long New England winter
The basket
Was literally a peach basket
And that basket was quickly replaced
Buy a metal hoop
The Rope net
But it was so close at the bottom
Every time a player scored a basket
The game had to stop
Pull data Lottery
Retrieve the ball
You can also sometimes you knock it out of the hammock with a long stick
But it took
Over a decade
For someone to come up with the brilliant idea
Of cutting a hole in the bottom of the net
And it finally put an end to the practice of manually retrieving basketballs every time ago
Discord
That took
Decade
Maybe it's a testament to have fun bad boy the play that the game going to work 10 years of such bad game design
Regardless
It someone not invented open-ended Nets
Basketball with Schwarz suck to watch on TV
What is a moor
Subtle development
Taking decades later
That made basketball
Sports juggernaut
But it is today
Okay I appreciate that not everyone listening as a sports fan
But what's your feelings about basketball aside for just a few minutes
And listen to The Raw
Human emotion
In this
This in basketball is called
A butterbeer
The game-winning shot made just as time expires it's exhilarating it's
Heartbreaking
It's a moment of pure anxiety that millions of people can share
As one
And the fact that a 48-minute game of basketball can still be won at
That's final macro
Thereby keeping you on the edge of your seat chewing your fingernails
The best until the final buzzer
That my friends
Is what we call good.
It is good design
But it's not the way basketball was originally designed
In fact
The drama the game clock
Really became relevant after the Advent of another clock
The 24-second shot-clock
This is the story of how the smaller less visible clock
24-second violation created the reaction
Outside for pain lets it go
For the uninitiated a shot clock is the smaller clock that you sometimes see counting down in the bottom corner of the TV screen
In the NBA
When a team gets the ball they have 24 seconds to make a shot
With the violation
They lose the ball
But this
Hasn't always been the case
In the early 1950s during pro basketball infancy
There was no shot
Nothing force a player to actually shoot the ball
NFL team was winning
They wanted to keep their lead
They could literally hold onto the ball for
10 minutes
That means you could turn off the game and listen to this entire pod gas and go back to the game in
Not miss it
I mean the game stock it was
Boring it was
Stupid
This is Dolph schayes
He's in the NBA Hall of Fame player and Coach whose career spanned two eras of basketball
Before the Inception of a shot clock
And after
He says this problem of players running time off the clock by just dribbling the ball around
Can really be summed up in a 1950 game
Between the Fort Wayne Pistons
In the Minneapolis Lakers
Good game near the end of it
Season
The Lakers they had like a dynasty at that time
And so the Pistons were ahead
Decided
Have a Slowdown
Meaning run time off the clock
So the game ended up
As the final score
The final score
What was something like that was in the teens
Actually was 19 to 18
Go Pista
And of course
The crowd was booing I mean that the became a real Forest
It was such a joke that in 1953 NBC decided to forgo coverage of the NBA Championship
Take out the game would be too boring
Finally it became a
A crisis
Sol basketball
Lizard a rule change
1954 enter Danny by Zone
Owner of the Syracuse Nationals
The team Dolph schayes play for
Crunch some numbers and he believed that some simple arithmetic could save
Basketball
And anybody song
It looks like I have this
Is formula
Why don't we try it out
Bizon figured that the best games of basketball the ideal games at Team scoring 80 or more points each
A store that buys on figured with high enough
To retain the audience's interest
Right so by Zone started tracking how many shots a team needed to make
Tuscora requisite 80-something points
Each team averages
60 shots
Hurricane
And there's two teams that means 120 shots
And the game was still 48 minutes long
48 minutes
Equates
To 2800
Is 82nd
So you divide the number of seconds in a game
2880 by the number of shots
24 sec
Spur shot
And hold a player to that standard you need a 24-second shot-clock
Myzone invited a bunch of League officials to Syracuse to watch a practice game using the shot clock
I mean dulces played in that game
Everybody felt
24 seconds remind me it was just very short. Of time
So when we got the bus
Everybody say oh my God
The entire team sense of time had become compressed
The old him didn't seem slow to the players
But with this new clock everything felt rushed
And the owners
Loved
I thought wow this is going to be great
Even if he's practice games there was a new sense of suspense
The owner sells it
And the players learn to love at 2
The clock became official in the 1954-55 season
Other changes in the Pro game is limiting the offense of possession what's the basketball
If that offense
Space of time
Another ball
Immediately
The scoring went up
Hayes passed away
This is audio from the 1955 NBA finals
Snowman as basketballs World Series
It's the first year the Clock Was instituted
Change the team the Syracuse Nationals made it to the finals last season
Play an important part in Our Winning
Because with the old rules the
Christian
Probably would have held the ball
Most of the second half
Because of the shot clock will be able to call way back and finally went in the last couple seconds
The next year the NBA finals are broadcast on television for the first time
Team scored almost 30 points more game
The next few seasons
And shortly after that attendance jump
By 40%
That's 24 seconds
Hawk the little idea
Started in 1955
Revolutionize and save the game of basketball
So let me just live for you
The reasons I actually like watching basketball
You can turn on a game of basketball in between commercial breaks of something else and still feel like satisfied that you saw something happen
It is the fastest
Toothpaste
Back in the baseball game you're not guaranteed to have that and I love baseball Talkin Baseball
But there's a lot of sitting around in baseball almost certain that something is going to be happening is so fast
That's wonderful right and I love how athletic basketball players have become I mean the things you see LeBron James do
Are Blake
Out of this world is mind-blowing
What he can do with a ball and even the worst guy on the court now is like
A crazy athlete in ways that I never thought like human beings could be
The players have to be stronger and faster
Because they have this set. Of time they have 24 seconds
To get the job done
I never would have thought that
That really made me love the game that made the game worth watching was some guy in Syracuse
60 years ago with a pen and paper and some long division he's the reason that this game is thrilling this one little
Innovation
Donnelly made this game so much better but make the players better themselves
Like a created better athletes it pushed human potential to a totally different limit
I never would have been possible before
He was all things to the shot clock
I got to tell your mom
But according to Eric
There is yet one more thing that basketball does
Is a pretty good job
I also really love halftime shows
99% invisible was produced this week by Eric mental
Based on his original story from the Great
Great radio show
Backstory with the American history guys
Get some help from Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And the American Institute of Architects
Tax in San Fran
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast.,