99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
And I'm sitting in that tiny little room this microphone right up to my mouth
So the sound of my voice is transmitted directly
From me to you
There's no sense of the room that I'm in
When I stop speaking
The sound stop
There is no reverberation
No Reaper
Roman and I are both talking in rooms outfitted special 8 for recording
Rooms that sound
Good
Mass producer Avery trufelman
Because if I step outside this tiny
Completely padded Studio
Okay it's so quiet
Because I'm inside
But I'm going to walk around a little bit so you can secure the architecture around me
You can tell now that I'm in a bathroom
Or you can tell if I enter the stairwell at better office
If you're not listening in headphones my voice is bouncing around your car
Or whatever room you're in
Whatever you're hearing
Sound is affected
By The Arc
There are two main ways to control the sound in a building
Active acoustics
Impassive
Passive acoustics
Are the materials in a space
Like a padding in the studio room
Carpeting and drapes are also absorptive material
Soak up sound
Glass and Porcelain on the other hand
Create more Reverb
Essentially if it's shiny it's going to be reflective isn't easy way to interpret that
This is Ashley Hansen
My name is Ashley Jansen I'm the design services manager at Myerstown
Meyer sound is a company that mostly makes
Active acoustic
Which is this a speakers
Amplifiers and other electric sound equipment
People probably have run into our products
They just don't know that it's
Meyer sound
Meyer sound makes a lot of the Big Show
Speakers hanging off of the ceilings at concerts and Broadway shows
But their products are also in a lot of unexpected places
Cruise ships
Restaurants
We are in some corporate headquarters at
Educational facilities
Airport
Over 600 Meyer sound speakers were used when the Pope
Spoke in Mexico
One of the things I tell people in general is
If we're doing our job right
You might never notice that were even there
And that's part of Ashley's job at Myerstown
To make sure the sound equipment is effortlessly integrated into a building
Using both passive and active
Materials and electronics
But often in architecture what looks the best is at odds with what sounds the best
Of course you don't necessarily want to always see the big black speaker somewhere and so we have to get creative
We like our speakers out of sight
And we also like high ceilings and long glass windows which makes
Spaces sound
Wheatley
River
So architecture is a puzzle for Ashley and her team to solve
Whenever we see rooms that have curveballs we kind of cringe
Especially if they're out of glass
Oh that's pretty
When we approach spaces there are things that although they're beautiful
We know are going to definitely
Put pressure on us
To come up with creative and unique ways
A Pista
Visual
And Sonic needs a
Set the room
So it depends on what you're trying to do and that's
Space
If it's a venue for the symphony or the Opera you want the sound to be big
And resonance
An echoing
Or cafe or place with
Acoustic performances
A little Reverb is nice
But you're trying to hear a lecture or reading
Per se
Have a meeting
You probably don't want much Reverb at all
But we haven't always been able to precisely control the acoustics
Sever building
Sound until fairly recently
Was a somewhat mysterious element in architecture
In the late 18th century there are all sorts of different theories about how to get good sound but
Half of them contradict the other half
And no one really knew what
To do this is Emily Thompson
She's a history professor at Princeton and a scholar of sound technology
She says at the turn of the 20th century
Architectural Acoustics are pretty much a roll of the dice
Architects
Begin to fret
But they don't really know what they're doing with this aspect
Of their designs and it was all kind of left to chance and if you were lucky
Aurora Theater would sound good
And if you were unlucky
It wouldn't
And in 1895
Harvard University
Was very unlucky
The university had just completed building
Fogg Art Museum and it had a lecture hall
Where there was so much reverberation that they simply
Could not hold classes in that room
You couldn't understand the speaker
Harvard had just wasted a lot of money on a completely useless room
Sound
Henry Linda
And in an attempt to save the space
They listed the help of a rookie physics Professor who had some time on his hands
So the president of Harvard
Ask this young physics professor
To figure out how to fix that Auditorium and make it use
Visible teaching
Hbase
This professor's name
Was Wallace Sabine
And through this task
Sabein would eventually
Become the father of architectural acoustics
Lissette Wallace sabein onto an investigative path that actually took several years
Collecting data basically making sounds in rooms and timing the Reverb
He would take
Measurements of the different reverberation times in different rooms all over campus
And in order to do this under the quietus
Possible circumstances he tended to run his experiments in the middle of the night
And he would change the reverberation
In time within a given room by bringing into it.
Sound absorbing material
Sabein was a perfection
Keep throughout over 3000 measurement
After determining that his own clothes
Had a small effect
Upon the sound of the room
He started all over again
Taking measurements in the dead of night
But now
Wearing the exact
Same outfit
Every time
Meanwhile the president of Harvard is is waiting and waiting for this lecture hall to be made useful again
One point you finally
Does to the young Professor it's
It's time for you to tell us what to do here
Enough is enough
Night night
Feeling nervous under pressure
Saybein pours over his notebook
I had a breakthrough
Looking at all his measurements he starts to notice a trend a mathematical relationship
Between the size and materials of a room and it's reverberation time
Relationship so steady
That you can make a formula out of it
He discovers a mathematical formula
Bitconnect
The architectural materials of the room and the behavior of sound within it and this is a formula
Sa Vines formula now that really
A enables
People to be able to predict
The reverberation time of a room
Based on its design
Design savings equation allowed for
Planning
Something you can manipulate the Reverb of a
Space by changing the materials the room was made of
So that then you can take any sort of Arkansas
Textural plan
You know the dimensions you know
How many square feet of
Plaster or wood or glass
Soar upholstered seats
Fill this room
And you can just kind of plug and chug and if the formula will turn out a predicted number for the reverberation
The room
Stabilized formula helped Architects design for as little or as much Reverb as they want
Architect
Could now control
Sound of a
They could make
Big rooms
With very little Reverb
Until they begin to do Jess
Stat
And the most remarkable early example of this
Was Saint Thomas
St. Thomas Church
Which is
In New York City not far from the Museum of Modern Art
The architect of this church wanted to build it in a neo-gothic style
Basically to make it look like a European cathedral made of stone with
High ceilings and stained glass windows
But while they wanted
This building to look Gothic
They realized that a Gothic
Sound would not work for modern
Temp service
They wanted to hold a much more sermon Focus
Service
Not Justa medieval math
I needed less Reverb
I'm so prisoners could understand the words
So the Architects turn to Wallace Avon
How to make a Sacred Space that would be
Clear
Calming
Reverb
Free
Shure wireless Avon could add felt and padding to the building
But he thought that didn't fit the feeling of a church
He work with a tile maker
To come up with special sound absorptive ceramic tile
Dogs with porous surfaces
He called them run for tile
Rumford tile
Named it after
Physicist
2hat kind of been interested in solving practical problems
And
Play the substantial architectural material it's not a matter of just hanging drapes or tack
Felt onto a surface it's a
It's much more integral
So with St Thomas Church
By using the sound absorbing tiles way up and all the ceiling vault
They have the gothic look
But without the gothic sound
St. Thomas Church was completed in 1930
It's definitely not modern look
But it was a landmark modern
Sounding building
Completely engineered of formulated for environmental control
Thanks to the Rumford tile
Say mine works in public and private spaces all along the east coast
And came out with more Broad
To accompany the Rumford tile
And he passed away in 1919
Rate really at a moment when a much
More pervasive interest in
Controlling environmental song
The Roaring Twenties
It got that name for a reason
It may very well be the case that it was louder in the twenties then now
This was an ERA when cars and trucks did not uniformly come with Mufflers there were
For these new unfamiliar unprecedentedly loud sound
A car the trains of industrial machinery
Construction of skyscrapers Rising everywhere
In the crowded City
An escape
Was hard to find
Sound Christmas and Clarity could provide calm and control
It meant a complete Mastery of the
And so the desire
To control sound within interior spaces isn't parked
A kind of a drive to create Refuge
From the noisy tumult of the world outside
Rumford tile launched in industry
By the 1930s
Dozens of different corporations were manufacturing and selling vast quantities of acoustic build
Building materials
With names like acoustic
Acousti celotex
And saving it
For those who could afford it
You know whether you could buy it at a soundproof
Apartments or just enjoy
Quiet offices or or theaters
Quiet
Became a luxury commodity
Acoustic materials were so advanced
It's a Barnes formula couldn't apply anymore
By 1930
You're really able to
Create spaces that simply didn't exist
The 19th
Century
State lines equation doesn't work
It was a product
Of the world
In which he did his invest
Castigation which was still that 19th set
Country World filled with
Glass and wood and
I'm class
After all this new acoustic technology was able to create a level of Silence
Unprecedented in say Vines
Time
Finally
It was quiet
Too quiet
What is the 20th century went on
Who became disenchanted with the idea of completely closed off spaces with dampened acoustics
They wanted to let in air or light
And sound
Interesting lay by the 1970s
Some of the cultural
Factors in the aesthetic
Preferences of
People with respect
To sound design
Headchange
Since the early 20th
Rhiannon some of these spaces including st. Thomas Church
They actually decided they wanted
More reverberation
And this material
Engendered
So
In some cases
Porous surface
Of the rump
For tile
Has been painted over
Peel off those
Pores and then to make it more reflective
Of sound
And these days we want our architecture to have a range of
No one single room or venue can accommodate a lot of
Kind of sounds
And that's possible using not just passive
Acoustic materials like the ones they bind pioneered
But also
Active
Using microphones and loudspeakers
And digital signal processor
That's Melody Parker and acoustic engineer at Meyer sound
Cannabis product
Called constellation
And so what constellation allows
You to do
Is to create multiple environments in one space
It basically allows you to manipulate the sound of the room completely digital
Do a system of many Chinese speakers and microphone
Where the microphone
Throughout the ceiling
They're really smart
Melody showed Avery the test room for consolation
Inside Meyer sound headquarters in Berkeley
It looks like a very small theater
It's a room with a low Reaver
Time thanks too much acoustic padding
But it's outfitted with a variable active acoustics
We're tiny microphones capture the sound
And the speakers playback no sound
Monster mimic the reverberation in different size rooms
Okay so I'll grab Melody took out an iPad and activate a different settings
Which completely changed
The Sonic shape of the room
Midol do
I'm dramatic
Demonstration
This is what
It sounds like
With a very long
Melody play the clave to demonstrate the Reverb time
This setting was called Sacred Space I gave this tiny room the sound of a cathedral
And it's one thing to hear a Reverb effect
In a song or podcast
It's another thing entirely
To experience a Reverb effect
In a room
In real life
In real time
The echo completely changed my perception of the
Then Melody took the Reverb completely out of the room
Entirely
And suddenly it felt
Stifling
Like I'd been muzzled or something
It's hard to breathe
And those are some of the most dramatic setting
There are lots of subtle change
Is that a client can make to a room
They have the ability to change the length of the reverberation change the strength
The loudness
Set the reverberation
And 2 even
Change the perceived height
Of the room in the perceived width
The room
Constellation and its competitor sound systems are expensive so they're not
, exactly
But they're in a lot more places than you'd think like a number of big venues all over the world and classrooms and offices
Restaurants use so-called variable active acoustics
So they can adjust the noise level
How to keep it a pleasant home
Regardless of how many people are in the space
An architectural implications of this
Are fascinating
Of course Architects and acoustician still have to pay attention to the path of acoustics
Building materials
But there's a lot more design flexibility now
Yeah we actually have an interesting one that we're working on
Attack business where they took over an old
Factory
Does Ashley Henson at Meyer sound again
And so the challenges in that space
It's the factories all brick and exposed and beautiful
And
Have these high ceilings and she says
Combination of active and passive acoustic systems
Help architects
Repurpose old buildings
Were able to
Text faces that would never be used for certain applications and make them
Great for
All sorts of
Different events
And that wouldn't happen before this office
Space in this old factory would just be a reverberant nightmare no one could
Focus and
They probably wouldn't have
I purchased it
For that
Buildings like Saint Thomas Church Mark the beginning of our quest to control sound in the built environment through Pass
Passive Acoustics no hundred years later with Advanced active acoustics
We can separate sound from space warehouses can be made to sound like Opera Houses and Opera House
Siskin sound like small clubs it's just a matter of how much Reverb we want
In this episode we featured some actual sounds from New York City from the 1920s and 1930s you can find them on the
Portable interactive website that Professor Thompson made in collaboration with the University of Southern California, map of
New York and you can click around it to see what it look like and what sounded like in the twenties
And the easiest way to find it is to go to shut out the noise. Com
Shutoutthenoise.com
Special things have been strange Alex toll and everyone at Meyer sound 99percentinvisible was produced
Sweet by Avery trufelman with Sharif Youssef Katie mingle court cost at Sam Greenspan Emmett Fitzgerald
Delaney Hall and me Roman Mars we are product of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in April
Reduced on radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
MPI fade
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to see cow
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can tweeted me at Roman Mars and the show at 9
99 pi
I org we're on Instagram and Tumblr to
But the Nexus of all things 99 Pi is that
I mean IPI. Org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com