99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We went to the Portland airport recently when I got off the plane
Picture of my feet
In keeping with the local custom
A foot selfie
That's producer Julissa Bhatia host of the podcast render formerly known as destination DIY
She lives in Portland
And I almost always take a foot selfie when I'm at PDX
Portland Airport
I think I do it most often when I come home like
Here I am I'm back in Portland
The feet are actually not the most important thing about a portland-airport foot selfie
It's actually what's under your feet
The famous PDX airport carpet
It's allowed decidedly 80s teal color with a repeating geometric pattern
Like any carpet you might see in an airport or hotel lobby or an office building it
Probably not what you choose for your living room
The design I'm told is based on the way the runways and lights look from the air traffic control tower and also on
On the radar screen that the air traffic controller sees with that sweeping line going around and around and the dots
Are the little blips representing airplane
It's hard to say if it's the pattern people are responding to what the bright teal background color but one thing
Is for sure the carpet is very very beloved there even sign the airport
Right now it's saying your feet with the hashtag
PDX carpet
And it goes deeper than that
Meet Emma
She actually has
A PDX carpet inspired tattoo
It hurt a lot
21 year old Portland native which means a lot of the carpet in the airport is actually old
Older than she is
She got a tattoo of the carpet pattern on her back
The side so yes my last
Emma travelled a lot as a kid
Her parents are divorced and her dad lives in LA
I think the first
Time I ever took
Flight as an unaccompanied minor
Mama's probably 11
And freaking out
But the carpet had this kind of calming effect on her
On my way that was kind of like my send off the carpet was there and that you knew that
That would probably be there when I got home
Several years later when Emma decided to take the plunge and get a tattoo of the Portland carpet design
She realized
She was not the carpets only admirer
Not by a long shot
When I got the tattoo
I
Posted a picture of it on Insta
And one of my followers
Tagged at PDX carpet
Upon further inspection I was like
Oh my goodness
The carpet has an Instagram
The carpet has a Twitter and a
Facebook page
And that's kind of when I knew it
That it was
This kind of notorious Portland
Entity
It's important to note that the airport Communications Department says they are not running any of the social media accounts.
Devoted the PDX carpet
Emma says that occasionally people on social media make fun of her tattoo
Sitting back and
Letting people say what they want about it
I'm in love
I used to live in Boston
I cannot imagine telling boss tonight's like
I'm obsessed with the airport carpet
Logan
And having someone go yeah me too
Jeremy Dunn is a designer in Portland
And he's another fan of the carpet
A couple of years ago he decided to have some socks made with the carpet pattern on them
He said about $500 on the minimum order
Which would 72 pair
So he was hoping some people would want to buy them
Posted them on our Instagram account
Think it was
An hour maybe two hours and they were all sold out
The carpet socks were so popular that Jeremy quit his day job and opened up a retail space
Jeremy socks are actually told in the airport now
Alongside many other items emblazoned with the carpet pattern
T-shirts coffee mugs throw pillows tote bag stickers keychains bike helmets water bottles
PDX carpet IPA from a local Brewery called Rogue
That's what's so interesting to me about this whole carpet phenomenon
It's great for Pediatrics it's basically free marketing for them
But if the airport had tried to create this kind of fervor for the carpet
There's no way it would have caught on
At least not like this
I love this carpet
Like a big thing ever by socks
It just kind of represents for tonight if we're kind of known for this at our airport this carpet makes traveling a little bit more enjoyable
I guess what I'm in the airport selfie
The foot
But maybe there's something they should secretly magical about it
People having
Stream unprecedented inordinate amounts of affection for the carpet at PDX
When you ask people why they love the carpet so much
They pretty much all say the same thing
When they see it
It reminds them that their home
And that's sweet
But like so many great love stories
I'm afraid this one
Is coming to a tragic end
That is the sound of Portland heart being ripped
Out of its chest
Speaking of PDX workers are replacing the airports
Famous carpet you know that
Teal with the red
And purple and blue accents it's hard to say goodbye especially for travelers with an emotional attachment
A person came up to me and said oh I love your tattoo
Did you know that they've already started
Tearing it up and I just kind of
Felt my heart sank
Free carpet it's actually had a pretty long life the oldest sections of carpet have been in the airport since the late 1980s
Are things that
You just can't reach
Pair can't dispatch your way out of it
It really just looks
Tired
That's Robin McCaffrey
She's an engineering project manager at the Port of Portland
The agency that controls the airport
She's in charge of the carpet removal project
Starting late January
Can you describe what you're doing
To the carpet so the machine can pull it up
Mike mackley works for
4M Floor Covering
Actually he helped install the carpet here at the end of the C Concourse in the mid-1990s
I laid all of this
1995 for rubenstein's contract carpet
So do you have any kind of attachment to it
You're not sorry to see it go
Just carpet that's my opinion
The machine are using to remove the carpet looks like a cross between a motorized wheelchair and a Zamboni
It's called a panther
You attach the carpet to the machine and drive it forward to pull up the
Huge sections of carpet all at once
Most of this work will be done at night so it can have minimal impact on Travelers
It's going to take a long time
13 acres of Corvette does not get Panther. Away overnight
If all goes well
Perfectly it will be earlier than November
But
We're giving it a healthy
A window on Word
For
When the carpet is all removed most of it will be sent back to the manufacturer and recycle
But not
All of it
They're giving away for 1000 square yard pieces
Businesses will have to submit proposal to get one
Outlining what they plan to do with the carpet
In the meantime
And how they will eventually make it available
To the General Public
Whatever happens to the old PDX carpet
One thing is for sure
Its replacement has some big shoes
FFL people are going to hate it
Well hopefully not
It might be a perfectly great tonight but people will still hate it though
Why didn't you replace all the carpet and use the same beloved design
If they had decided to
Just recarpet
With the same design that would have been cool
Yeah it does seem like the most obvious solution
But the decision to replace the carpet was made back in 2008
Before all the foot selfies and hashtag PDX
Carpet I don't
At that time
There was an awareness
So that Grace
Ready for the carpet
That we became
I'm aware of Maurice
Somali
Did you ever consider
Replacing carpet with the same design
I think that we
Had
Thoughts about
People asking that question
Once we were well into it
I had already come
Come up with
A conceptual design
Now when you walk through the airport you can actually see a sizable Swatch at the new carpet
It's a darker green with a repeating geometric motifs it's reminiscent of the old carpet
But busier the busyness of the new design actually helps hide dirt and other wear-and-tear in fact there's a cup
Different versions of a new design
One that's extra busy that they'll lay in higher traffic areas
It looks like a
Tropical Jimmy Buffett version of the
Of the airport carpet and not in a good way
Jeremy Dunn the stock maker
Is not a fan
Seems very swoopy and like
You know what has more curves to it and
It's a little bit different green
And it's a little has some yellow in there and I think those are all
To me those are all things
Are not as
Appealing
Are you going to make socks with a new design
Yeah probably not
Yeah I think it's tough
People don't have it
Love everybody
Wishes that there
Design work was
Michelle Bo is a partner at hennebery Eddy
The Firm that took on the unenviable challenge of Designing the
Home carpet design work
There's a lot of thought and consideration that went into it
The inspiration for this
Had a lot to do with what you see from the air as your
Coming in
Green color that
It's the main background
Is much like
Static Spray
We have a unique situation here
Coming into Portland The Greenery of
Our surroundings
Come right up to the doorstep of our city
And those soupy lines
Also we're looking at
Flight path that pattern event
Curvatures
Flying in
If you were to look at
Kind of the way that aircraft
Curve around
Did you ever think about how people's feet with
On the new carpet
I didn't
Even with all this thought in care designer Michelle vo is fully aware that this new carpet is going to be a
Hard Sell
But she hopes it will grow on people over time
Can you carpet going down as something that will
Become enduring night
I hope that it will and maybe it won't reach cult status until
20 years out when it's time to
Replace it by
You know that's okay
You can't manufacture a cult following for an airport carpet
It has to happen on its own
You don't say but I do think that part of the reason that people fell in love with the carpet is because
People have a lot of love for the airport itself
Which is kind of become a microcosm of Portland
Good local restaurants and food carts in the terminal
There's even a mini farmers market in the C Concourse
And so maybe the new carpet will eventually become a part of the airport the same way the old carpet did
Crucial to the experience
I'm coming home to Portland
Then again
Maybe not
It's a lot like
Just having anything in your childhood replaced
With something your kind of resentful towards the new whatever it maybe
And you could potentially grow to like it but it'll never be the same as the original
Things that you loved
Someday MMA
With its Jar Jar Binks
Americorps in microbes that control the force
And
No there's no way I'll ever like it
You hear me George Lucas I'll never liked it you ruined it you ruined
Everything
99% invisible was produces week by Julie sabatier and Katie mingle with same green fan Avery truffle
Ben and me Roman Mars special thanks to Brian Kramer
Dewey's body age Red Dirt is an independent show from the public radio world carefully-crafted for Nani
Makers and doers and curious minds it's fantastic it's a new member of the maximum fun Network along with anavar
Favorite that Bullseye mybrothermybrotherandme in the flophouse
Bind it and subscribe at rendered radio. Org
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced of the offices of arcsin and architecture and
Interiors firm who is lay down some memorable carpet and it's time in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Pocket dude
What was the value
Yeah man it really tied the room together
Shrug
Story County
Were you listening to the dude's story
I was balling
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing.
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you a long for the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Pause podcast
You buy the show and likes on Facebook real on Twitter and Instagram Avery run
Spotify playlist of 99 Pi songs by encourage you to explore the entire world of 99% invisible at 9
99 Pi. Org
That rug really tied the room to go
Did it not radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com