99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that
Audience when your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network
Can LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to
To make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships off
Open turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools to
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust redeem a free $100
Burlington at credit and want your first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible with LinkedIn.
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It started with a place called The Stonewall Inn
Gay bars have been raided by police for decades
Gay lesbian bisexual and transgender people
Had been routinely arrested and subjected to harassment and beatings by the people who are meant to protect
But one night in this place called The Stonewall Inn
The police stormed into continue their abuse
The clientele
Fought back
The uprising that night light by drag queens
Turn into a protest over the next few days
An evolved into a movement that is still making the world better for everyone
Today
And it started with a place
On June 28th 1969 the patrons at the Stonewall Inn made history
Which is why gay pride celebrations all over the country take place in June
End on June 27th 2016 President Obama in the National Park Service designated The Stonewall Inn
Christopher Park in the surrounding streets
The First National Monument
The lgbtq rights
In 1989 twenty years after the Stonewall Uprising and now nearly 30 years ago
Radio producer Dave Isaiah created the first documentary of Stonewall ever
In any medium
Is also days first radio story if you can believe it he later went on to found the much-beloved and hugely
Popular storycorps broadcast
With the anniversary and National commemoration of the Stonewall Inn and the tragic massacre in Orlando
I thought it would be good to revisit this place
Which like so many other gay bars around the world is much more than just a place
This is remembering Stonewall by Dave I say with Michael Schenker
Originally broadcast in 1989
I Am Legend Hardwood
And my age is 80
I'm
Bruce Merrill
I I don't I don't
I don't know if it's really true but now people do refer to us as the two oldest gay men in America
We do hair I think
Have maybe a record relationship
Of almost 60 years together
Being gay before Stonewall was was
A very difficult proposition because
We felt that in order to survive
We had to
Try to
Look and act
And as rugged and manly as possible to get by in the in the in the society that was
I really very much against us
My name is Randy wicker I was the first openly gay person to appear on radio in 1962 and
On television in 1964 is a self-identified homosexual
And they are before Stonewall people thought of
Need to hide
Because of the
Precarious legal position they were in they would lose their jobs
There was a great hostility socially speaking in the sense of people found out you were gay they assumed you were a communist or a child
Leicester
Any of another dozen stereotyped to a ramp in the public media at the time I'm very fair and I'm 80 years old
I started a gay lifestyle in 1948
When I was around 39
At that time
If there was even a suspicion
But you were a lesbian
You were fired from your job
And you weren't such a position of disgrace
Baidu
Slunk out without saying goodbye even to the people that like doing your life
Never even bother to clean your desk
You just disappeared
You just disappeared your window
Quietly
Because you were afraid that
The recommendations at the tongue if you even still there protested would be worse than just
Leaving
My name is Sylvia Rivera
My name before that was spray Rivera until I started dressing and dragon 1961
Dara before Stonewall
Azahara
It was always the gay bashing
On the drag
Science
Bye
Heterosexual man
Women
Anna party
Wheeler
Flip with it
Because it was part of the lifestyle at that time I guess
But none of us were very happy about it
My name is Seymour Pine
In 1968 I was assigned as Deputy inspector in charge of public morals
In the first division
In the police department which
Cupboard
The Greenwich Village area
It was a duty of public morals
To enforce all laws concerning Vice and gambling
Including prostitution
Narcotics
And laws
And regulations concerning homosexuality
The part of the penal code which applied to drag queens
Was section 2 for 0.35
Section 4
Being masked or in any manner disguise by unusual or unnatural a tire
Or facial alteration
Lawyers
Remains or congregates
In a public place
That time we lived at the Arista Hotel
Is Scott around
Try to figure out when
When does
Harassment the come to an end
And
We would always dream that one day
It would come to an end
And we pray and we look
Ford
Wanted to be human beings
My name is red Mahoney
Ivan
Hanging out
Drinking partying and working
And the gay boys for the last 30 years
In the era before Stonewall
All of the bars
90% the boys
Word mafia control
There wasn't that many
Gay bars
It had me B12 uptown
And the Upper East Side
They would get close down and if you wanted to in the Westside they get closed down in
Midtown tb12
Read maybe open
As they would get close down they'd move around
And they would dumps
I'm Joan Nestle
Co-founder of what is now the largest collection of lesbian culture
China world
The police raided lesbian bars regularly
They did it
They both did it in the most obvious way which was holding women away and paddy wagons but they did there was regular
Weekend harassment
What consists
Are the police coming in regularly to get their payoffs and then the Sea Colony we had a back room with a red light and when that red light went on
It meant the police would be arriving
In the round
10 minutes
And so we all had to sit down at our table
And we would be sitting there almost like school children
And the cops would come in now depending on who is on which cop was on
If it was something that really resented the butch women
A little bit many times very beautiful women
We knew we were in for it because what would happen is
They would start harassing one of these women and saying how you think your man come outside will show you in
The woman would be dragged away
They throw up against the wall
And they say so you think you're a man let's see what you got in your pants and they would
But their hands
Docker pants
Stonewall
That was
Just to get into the Stonewall
Get woke up and you knock on the front
Kid knocking the door opening
Ameristep Megatron and girls
The Stonewall
Like all gay bars at that time
Painted black
Charcoal black
And what was the funny part
The place would be so dimly lit
But as soon as the cops are going to come in
The collected percentage of whatever they were coming in for
Tried being a nice
Dimly
Lip dump
The place was lit up like Luna Park
You felt like two guys and that's very often or we sent in would be two men
Could handle 200 people
When you tell him to leave
And they leave
And you say show me your identification and they all take out their identification
And file out and and that's it and you say okay
You're not a man or woman
OU or vice versa
You wait over there
I mean this is a
Kind of
How is it you have
And you never gave it a second thought
The drag queen took a lot of Oppression and we had to
We were at a point
Where
I guess
Nothing would have stopped us
As I stay or should I go
Esl
Do the ladies-in-waiting
Just waiting for the thing to happen
And when it did happen
We were there
On Friday evening June 27th 1969 at about 11:45
8 officers from New York City's public morals Squad loaded into for unmarked police cars and headed to the store
Stonewall Inn here at 7th Avenue and Christopher Street
The local Precinct just received a new commanding officer
Who kicked off his tenure by initiating a series of raids on gay bars
The Stonewall was an inviting Target
Operated by the gambino crime family without a liquor license
Dance bar drew a crowd of drag queens Hustler's in minors
The number of the bar patrons had spent the early part of the day outside the Frank Campbell funeral home where Judy Garland funeral was how
She died the Sunday before
It was almost precisely at midnight
Immortal Squad pulled up to the Stonewall Inn
Led by Deputy inspector Seymour Pine
It was never any reason to feel that
Anyting
Of any unusual situation would occur that night
You could actually feel it in the air
You really cry
I guess Judy Garland's death just
Really helped us Bailey head
Fan
For some reason things with different this night
As we were bringing the prisoners out they were resisting
People started gathering in front of the
Saturn Square Park right across the street from
Stonewall
People were upset
Now we're not going to
People started
Screaming and hollering
1 drag queen
As we put her in the car
Open the door on the other side and jumped out
At which time we had to chase that person
And
He was caught but back into the car
Made another attempt to get out the same door the other door
And at that point we had to handcuff the
The person
From this point on things really began to get crazy
My name is Robert Rivera
My nickname is birdie and I've been crossdressing all of my life
I remember the night of the riots
The police were escorting
Queens
Out of the barn into the Patty wagon
And there was this one particularly outrageously beautiful queen with Stacks and stacks of Liberty style for the
Bella style hair
And up she was asking them not to push her
They pretended for sure and she turn around and she matched the top with a high heel
She knocked him down and then she proceeded to first come for her have the keys to the handcuffs I wanna
She got them understand it herself and pass them to another coin that was behind all hell broke loose
Then we were we have to get back into the song my name is Howard Smith
On the night of the Stonewall Riot I was reported for the Village Voice
Locked inside with the police covering up
For my call
It really did appear
But that crowd
Looks a little peepholes
In the plywood windows
Lookout
We could see that the crowd
Well my guess was within 5-10 minutes is probably several thousand people
Mm music family yelling chola
Police brutality let's get them we're not going to take this anymore let me out as a group of
Persons attempting to uproot
One of the
Parking meters a witch that in which they did succeed and they then
Use that parking meter to
As a battering ram to break down the door and they did in fact open the door
They crashed it in and at that point was when they began with throwing Molotov
Cocktails into the place it was a situation that we didn't know how we were going to get with me
Remember someone selling a Molotov cocktail out of every other person was but I mean I saw that and I just touch my
Myself in Spanish I sit on my card to record wash it is finally here and I'm since I started screaming three
We're free at last dude I would have
I felt really good there a couple of cop station amoeba side of the door with a pistol bucking combat stance
Midoriya
Couple others with stations in other places behind like a whole another one behind the bar all of them
Guns ready I don't think up to that point I other at ever seen
Cops that scared remedies were Pros
But everybody's frightened is no question about that I Know I Was Pregnant
And I've been in combat situations and there was no
Never any time that I felt more scared than I felt that night
When did you know there's no place to run
Once the Tactical police force
Salvador
I think that really excited us a little bit more
My name is Martin Boyd in 1969 I was a drag queen known as Miss Mart
I remember on that night
All the strikers begin John's like about cats
And sing the song
We Are The Village girls
Beware I have a girl
We wear our dungarees
Above all Nelly
And at least went crazy hearing that necklace and mediately rush though
Gave one kicking today
My name is Rudy
Andrea the night of the storm while I was 18
And to tell you the truth
That night I was doing more running than fighting
I remember looking
Back
From 10th Street
And they're on Waverly Street
It was a police I believe on it
A cop
And it's on his stomach in his tactical
Uniform and
Is helmet and everything else
With a drag queen straddling him
It was beating the hell out of him with her shoe
What it was a high heel not I don't know
She was beating the hell out of him
Christmas Carol
My name is Mama Jean's
I'm a lesbian
I remember on that night I was in the gay bar I will make bark or cookies
Lila coming at the gay bar going toward
8th Street
And that's when we saw everything happen blasting away people getting beat up
Please come from every direction
I hadn't
Women
As well as men with their nightsticks
Gay men running down the street with blood all over their face
We decided right then and there we scared or not we didn't think about it we just jumped in
Here is Queen is going completely bananas you know jumping on hitting the windshield
Alexa you know taxi cab lesbians hard dog roll the cars with the entire dopest things
Windows with shattering all over the place fires burning around
It was a beaut it was beautiful it really was it was really beautiful
I remember when kept coming at me
Hitting me with the nightstick in the back of my legs
I broke loose and I went after him
I grabbed his nightstick my girlfriend went behind him
Choose a strong 7 again
I wanted to feel the same pain I felt
And I kept on saying to him I'd like the pain
Do you like it do you like it I kept on hitting him and hitting
I was angry
I want to kill him
At that particular minute I want to kill him I wanted
Every destructive thing that I could think of at that
Time
Check hurt anyone
That hurt us
The year
Is that just when you see a man protecting his own life
They weren't the queens that people call them
They were men fighting for their lives
Can I find a website in any day no matter how old I was
Ellada has Sebastian
But it didn't hurt
True feelings they all came back from the war
Nothing
That's when you can tell that nothing could stop us but that time
But any time in the future
Every time
The riots were well covered in the media
The New York daily news featured that on the front page
There were reports on all of the local television and radio stations
By the next day graffiti calling for gay power had started to show up all over the West Village
Next night thousands of men and women came back to the Stonewall to see what would happen next
Wella couple of trash cans were set on fire and some Stones were thrown
The 400 riot police Milling around outside the bar
Ensure that the previous evening's violence would not be repeated
But on this night gay couples could be spotted walking hand-in-hand
Kissing in the streets
Just by being at the Stonewall surrounded by reporters photographers and onlookers
Thousands of men and women were
Proclaiming that they were gay
The crowds grew and came back the next night and for one more night the following week
What happened at the Stonewall on those nights
Help to usher in a new era for gay men and lesbians in Stonewall happened Bruce and I were
Still in the closet
Where where we at Ben
For nearly 40 years
But we realize that this was this was a
A tremendous thing to have happened
At Stonewall and
It gave us a feeling that
We were not going to be
Remaining closeted
For very much longer
And soon thereafter
We did come out of the closet
My name is Junie puso
In 1969 I was in the convent
And when Stonewall
Hit the Press
It
Hit me with a bolt of lightning it was as if I had to
Incredible release
Of my own outrage at having to
Sequester so much of my life
I made weight my way down I seem to recall
In subsequent nights
Being
I'm down on the unit kind of just in the periphery looking Observer
Clearly in observer
Clearly longing to have that
Courage
To come out and
Was a matter of record was only a matter of weeks
Before I left
The convent end
Start a new life
I'm Henry beard
In 1969 I was in the US Army specialist 3 station to Long Binh post
Near Saigon in Vietnam
I remember I was having lunch in the Army mess
Reading the Armed Forces news summary of the day
And it was a short paragraph describing a riot
Led by homosexuals in Greenwich Village against the police
Am I heartless
Filled with joy
I thought about what I had read
Frequently but I had no one to discuss it with
And secretly Within Myself I decided
That's when I came back stateside
If I should survive to come back stateside I would come out of scape
And I did
For those of us in public morals
After the Stonewall incident
Things were completely changed from what they had previously been
They they
Suddenly were not submissive anymore they now suddenly had gained a
A new type of
Courage
And it seemed as if they didn't care anymore about
Whether their identities were were made known we would now dealing with human beings
Today I live in the senior citizen apartment building
What's different now
Is that I can be free
I have a daughter who's a senior citizen in my son is 58
They know
About
My homosexuality
My three grandchildren in the thirties
Know about that grandmother
I have a great-granddaughter who at the age of 10
Learned that grandma Jerry was a lesbian
And she thought that was most interesting
Jack by still don't have the personal courage
Black hair
Beijing to Summit Building
Know that Jerry is a lesbian
Well I retired from the police department in 1976
20 is a Pastime I'm going to be 70 in a few months
I still don't know the answers I would still like to know the answer
I would like to know whether I was wrong with her I was right
In NFL thinking that there was a dick
And it was thinking that maybe
You shouldn't trust a homosexual because
Something is missing in his personality
The Archives of lesbian culture
Which surrounds us now and was created for years after Stonewall
Hose at least from my part it's creation to that night in the courage
That
Found his voice in the streets
That night
In some very deep way
We finally found our place in history
Not as a dirty joke
Not as a doctor's case study
Not as
Freak
But as a people
Today I'm a 38 year old drag queen
I can keep my long hair I can pluck my eyebrows and I can work wherever the hell I want
And I'm not going to change for anybody
If I change that I feel that I've
But I'm losing
What 1969 brought into my life
And that was to be totally free
How can I
Avocado
And the same
Its June
Love
Remembering Stonewall was produced by Dave I say with Michael shirker
In 1989
This documentary was a production of sound portraits which went on to spawn Story 4
Which is dedicated to collecting sharing and preserving people stories from around the world
You might have heard storycorps on the radio but they're podcast which is hosted by their producers offers longer stories that go
The more in-depth and offer more backstory
It's even better than it is on the radio you can get it and get more information about storycorps
At storycorps.org
99percentinvisible of Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall Kolstad Katie mingle Avery trufelman Sharif Youssef and mirror
Mars we are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced of the offices of arcsin
An architecture and Interiors firm and beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here and then
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy, go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flash podcast
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode
What about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastland episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and likes show on Facebook and follow Saul on Twitter and Instagram for the best way to explore the 99
10% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world look like around the hundreds and hundreds of stories
On 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero and
Any movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy's you know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast.,