99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1889
Kodi Android
He was 33 years old and he was working as an assistant to another psychiatrist
He hadn't had any of his big Ideas yet
But he was about
That's producer and hepperman Freud was mostly practicing hypnosis at the time
Still kind of a controversial treatment
Monday-friday gets a new patient
President of Wesleyan University historian
Fred's new patient was struggling from all kinds of ailments
Asteria sleeplessness
Pain and odd text
Fannie Moser has lots of doctors
Tiffany Moser would come in and Freud would have her lay down on the couch just like he did with his other patients
Eyelids getting heavy
Fred wasn't the only person using a couch during hypnosis but
He particularly needed it to get people into a more relaxed
8 heavier and heavier
You're breathing deeper and deeper
But he wasn't very good hypnotist
She was kind of a clumsy hypnotize
Moser was on the couch. You're getting sleepy you're getting sleepy
No I'm not
She talk
Interrupt her with his theories but Fanny just wasn't having it
She wanted to talk
First let me tell you my stories
And then the light goes on
Revelation
If you just let patients talk and don't say anything
They will let down their defences
And the unconscious
Will be revealed this is the moment when the pre Freudian Freud becomes a free ride
Freudian Freud's new techniques and theories for therapy
Would come to be called
Psychonaut
Most new theories in the world to not get assigned their own piece of furniture
But
This one ultimately inexorably dead
The couch
If psychoanalysis had a flag
Oh you know
It would have a picture
Macau China
You can actually go visit price couch
It's in his last home in London
Freud had the couch ship from Vienna after
Fleeing the Nazis in 1938
Good call Sigmund
It's all patients on his couch right up to his death a year later
We sent our de facto London correspondent the allusionist Helen zaltzman
To check it out
This is Helen zaltzman reporting count signed from Freud's old study
But the one we now associate with him with a gift from a page
I'm a dime
She told Freud that if she was going to have her head examined
She might as well be comfortable
Apparently she found the couch Freud had at the time sorely lacking
So she got him a Cozier one
It's really a very cozy looking couches mechanical looking into it it looks like a great place to take a nap
Print studies full of rugs and books and artifacts from other culture
It has sort of an Indiana Jones vibe to it
This couch is in keeping with that
It's a Devon style so
Some people might call it a swimming cap
It's covered in exotic red Persian carpets and piled
Velvet pillows
So you can actually tell what the couch beneath it is ready like whether it's
Stain remover
Human Experience
What's underneath is a surprisingly Plain Jane beige sofa
All clean lines in rectangular form
It's almost boring
A very popular style back when Fred got it in 1891
Domestic
Piece of furniture designed for relaxing and dream
But the more patients Freud saw on the couch
Couch became thought of as an essential instrument
In Freudian psychoanalysis
Look at that the couch was Central to the idea of getting to the unconscious
That's Dr Arnold rich
A psychoanalyst
Two practices on New York's Upper East Side
In traditional analysis Richard says the couch is a tool a patient lies down on his or her back
Looking up at the ceiling
To staring up your steering
Into yourself
You looking inside
Rabbit outside
Traditional psychoanalysts believe the
Couch
House of patient relax and open up
And understand their unconscious conflicts and inhibitions like why you can't do no finish your paper while
Why you can't work
What are your symptoms and what are your inhibitions and you want to understand
And that's what cycle analysis of cycling
Therapy is a
And some of these therapist believe that even the placement of the couch
Like where it is in a room
Makes a
I know there was one analyst
Who would put the couch in the middle of the room
Because he felt it
The patient shouldn't be close to a wall
That the war would make them secure
And he wanted the patient to be insecure
He wanted to promote the regression
The endless typically sits in a chair out of sight from the patient on the couch
I know some analysts believe this positioning helps the patient feel Freer to open up Droid may have had more selfie
Which reasons he wants were marked I cannot put up with being stared at by other people for 8 hours a day
In any case
When an object play such a
Central role to the work that you do
Choosing the right one becomes a big deal
It's like a Rite of Passage
Just like you made it
Which means good business for the guys making those couches
We had to have a separate
Factory just to make the couches cuz we also made sofas and club chairs
Fred branfman used to run Imperial leather furniture company in Queens New York
And selling psychoanalytic couches since the 1940s
Actually patented a version of a psychoanalytic couch he designed with his bed
Business partner
Alicia brafman says her father was it
Extremely proud of it
Every time anybody walked into the store
Kids saucer up to them and say you know he would say
We make Freud's couches
Which of course they didn't
The couch say sold wasn't exotic
Cozy pile of cushions
Their psychoanalytic couches work
Like the one you're probably thinking of
Low to the ground
Sleek Rahman soldi psychoanalytic couches all over the country and around the world
For decades
And the psychoanalyst
Finance
Add some particular aesthetic
Most of them were being made in leather
Patience
They would pick at it because they were edgy nervous and
It would present the maintenance problem basically
Constructing the perfect
Psychoanalytic couch
Is like building a sofa
For Goldilocks
It can't be too sore
And it can't be too hard
So will you
Special spring and special
Cotton and Hozier Hagia combination
To make it as they said just right
Fred's business boomed in the 40s 50s and early 60s what some have called the Golden Age of psycho
Who is very good very good business
But then in the late 60s
Things changed
People started to experiment with alternative Therapies
And the first generation of antidepressants offered faster relief
Traditional psychoanalysis
Fell out of favor
And you might be able to guess what happened to analytic couch sale
Now couches aren't being used all that much
Please
Play sit up in
Club chairs with lounge chairs and
They took the league
Psychoanalyze
Even within psychoanalytic circles
People became less certain that the
Couch was a good tool
Different schools of thought started cropping up
Whether or not you use the
The couch
You know
Can determine you know what you're doing and why you're doing it while you theory is
You can say that two camps formed in psychoanalysis
Team couch
Antino couch
Some would say it's easier to have a conversation you know sitting face-to-face
And some people some analysts
Psychobabble insist on not using the couch
They said they preferred sitting up
Richard's hasn't really chosen it
In his office there is a couch and a chair
I do whatever seems to
What works
Best for the patient
There may be a team couch in the team no couch but even Floyd wasn't that dogmatic about it
Patience heat-treated on the couch and Sami didn't like the famous composer Gustav Mahler
Employee treated while strolling around the park
But here's the thing
Well Freud wasn't dogmatic about using the cow
And while use of the psychoanalytic couches
Does declined
You wouldn't know it from popular culture
The analytic couch has become shorthand for therapy
Particularly in one place
Hi I'm Batman car from cartoon editor
Bob mankoff is surprisingly qualified to
To talk about this
Well I have a background in experimental psychology he wasn't a psychoanalyst exactly
I was an animal behaviorist so to put the little rats and pigeons on couches
Extraordinary
Manta says the couch is Fanta
Thick as a symbol
It is just what a joke needs
I think the couch immediately established
Power relations
The psychiatrist is in control
You are so helpful
Childlike
Lying on the couch
Even though real therapist aren't using the couch all that much
Cartoonists
Still need it when we look at
The cartoons now
We do see that they're all on the couch
Of course it's not just the New Yorker we've seen the couch all over popular culture like it's hard to imagine Woody Allen
Without the couch
You've been seeing a psychiatrist for 15 years
You should smoke some of this uke off the captain no time
And then there's The Sopranos
Tony Soprano spends a lot of time with her
Even though he's always sitting in a chair
When the camera pans out there is a very typical Brown analytic couch in the back
As if the set designer wanted to reassure our subconscious about what he was doing there
Not imagine
Having to make New Yorker therapy jokes
Altec how does a device
How don't make me cry
I've made by mangkok Rio just like to win
The couch
Back there I mean
Thousands of people have made pilgrimages
It's a relic to how Freud revolutionize how we understand the human mind
The couch especially Freud couch
It came to symbolize an invitation to open your mind
Have to let someone
That's fine scholar Michael Ross
Reminder that
We have the ability
To reveal our sin
And that's
It's irresistible
Take a Magic Carpet I can get on the couch and suddenly I'll say things that
Reveal white what I really love
I put my whole life
Pretending to love other things
How to get on the couch and suddenly
I say
My mother she ruined my life
Michael Roth loves his mother
But if you didn't and he does
It might be revealed on the couch
Whole number of complexes
Abby on creating a vocabulary of the mind he gave us a place to rest
Ephelides
The share our desires are in Ambitions are dreams
A place just to lie down
Can't talk
99% invisible was produced this week by ann heppermann
Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are project 91.7 Ka
LW San Francisco and produced are the offices of arcsin in architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful down
Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you a long for the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Pause podcast
You can find the show in Lancaster on Facebook or on Twitter Instagram Tumblr and Spotify to
50 Floyds couch to our Freud is 99.
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast