99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 2012 by Design Group in New York City called pilot project
Rolled out a strip of red carpet in Union Square
Public park in the middle of Manhattan
They hired a flautist
And a waiter in a tuxedo who wore white gloves
I have a small towel draped over his forearm
And one by one
They serve people drinks
Drinks of water
In the public drinking fountain
That's our own Katie Mingle
This Design Group pilot projects how does event to promote their plan to install a hundred new drinking
Fountains in New York City
But not just run-of-the-mill drinking fountains
We're talking about drinking
Fountains that
Kobe designed by artists and
Designers and architects
That's Scott Francisco from pilot projects
We really want to drink time to be something that
People love to use and
Share with each other and
There's a sense of pride in the fountains 2
Pilot projects was hoping to put some Prestige back on the drinking fountain
Make it cool again
I know you're thinking
Drinking fountains have never been cool
No one has ever been like
Yo
See you at the drinking fountain later
But you're wrong
There was a time when everyone was like yo see what the drinking fountain later
All the 21st of April 1859 the Streets of London
What's wrong with crowds of people who came to witness the opening of the first
Free
Fresh drinking fountain
That's Philip Davies heat wrote a book about historic drinking fountains in London
And he's talking about the day that the public drinking fountain was the coolest thing in town
The scene was recorded in the London Illustrated news so we actually have a pretty good idea of what it was like
Woman's hand out in that that's finery the men have their top hats on
Children with clambering over the ratings everyone was so pumped
I like
Water is the
Bats
People
Lawson couldn't believe that they were blessed with something that was
So important to them
And if you look at the picture in the London Illustrated news you can see above the fountain engraved in the Stonewall
The first
Drinking fountain
It probably wasn't the first drinking fountain in the history of the world
But it was the first one in London people a day
And understand its Mass Appeal you have to understand some things about London before this Fountain was installed
City Life in the 19th century in London
The poorer classes
Part of that nightmare was the drinking water
Most people did not have access to water in their homes
Instead many got water from the nasty Cesspool known as the River Thames
Great sewer
It was full of feces and chemicals
It was not uncommon to see dead animals floating down the river
The Thames was so nasty that London has the distinction of having a. In their history called
The great stink when the smell from the
Thames was so bad
They had to evacuate the House of Commons in Westminster father though
So some people in London got their water directly from the stinky tens
And other people got it from Wells that were also dirty and contaminated with disease
Cholera was rampant
Outbreaks of the disease in 1847 and 1854 kills 58,000 people in
An accepted Theory at the time was diseases including cholera
We're spread through bad-smelling air
But some people were skeptical of this including a scientist named Jon Snow
Jon Snow thought that disease might be spread
2 water
And everyone was on like
You Know Nothing Jon Snow
I'm he was like actually I know that the water is killing you
And I'm going to prove it
He went to work
Are you sick or members of your family sick and he actually marked down on a map
Everyone who was sick
That Peter Glick and expert on water related issues at the Pacific Institute
He identified
In the center of this
Outbreak
Particular water well
He went he removed the pump handle
So that nobody could pump water from that water well
And the cholera epidemic in this neighborhood ended
No one had ever really mouth disease patterns like this before which is why Jon Snow is known as the father of modern
Epidemiology
Jon Snow made the discovery that Colorado was a link to water in 1854
Shortly after that group was formed called The Metropolitan free drinking fountain Association they'll
Change their name to the Metropolitan free drinking fountain & Cattle trough Association
Because it was just catchier
No
And providing clean water for Animals also became a central tenet of their mission
Baby drinking fountains all over London
Very soon off to it's within
Five or six years / AC Fountain Seminole Towne Center erected across London
By 1879 the Metropolitan
Free drinking fountain & Cattle trough Association
I built almost
800 drinking fountains in London
The association was made up of wealthy mostly Christian philanthropist
And they had a couple different agendas and building me fountains
One was clean Safe Drinking Water for poor people
And the other was temperance
The temperance movement a social movement that opposed the consumption of alcohol
Was an early supporter of this new beverage called water
There was a terrible epidemic of alcoholism in London at the time but not just inland
And a lot of other places too
Including the United States where the temperance movement was also taking hold
And really the reason that temperance
Is invented is because alcohol is what people drink that's historian an architect Marta Gutman
Water is dirty water is
Not understood to be a suitable beverage milk is unheard of
Except for babies and coffee and tea are expensive
So that's it
Men women and even children were drinking alcohol all day long
Alcoholism is destroying families
Life in order to fight against alcohol
And one of the Alternatives that at this time
Once we figured out how to provide Safe Water was water
Temperance fountains were built in public parks at churches
An option right outside the local bar
Hoping to snag those few people that weren't going in because they wanted to get drunk
But just because
They were thirsty
The architectural style of these fountains vary greatly depending on who commissioned them
But they weren't like the drinking fountains you grew up with
They were generally made of stone for granite
That first fountain in London was fairly simple
But they became quite rapidly much more elaborate
Racine nice opposes
Symbols
Philanthropy
Somewhere ornate Victorian Gothic structures
Clay Coleman
Architectural detail here with us Alliance headed spouse
I came out of the mouth
Lionshead the ones built by Christian organizations often included a Biblical inscription like
Fear of the Lord is a Fountain of Life
You can still find Temperance fountains all over Europe in the US
There's one in New York City's Tompkins Square Park
In Oregon a lumber Tycoon / Tito learning Simon Benson built fountains all over Portland
They came to be known as Benson bubblers in Portland OR is love them
Prefer to drinking from them as
Having a Benson highball
There's a fountain in Petaluma California with the inscription
Total abstinence is the way to handle the alcohol problem
Ultimately drinking fountains in
Handle our problems with alcohol
But they quickly became part of the public landscape what comes out of it
Is an idea that there should be drinking fountains in cities
That sounds should not be ornamental that there should be water available in public for people to drink
Developed people started to require
A certain number of water fountains
In
For example Stadium Sports Stadium
Poor in Music Hall
I think that became an important part of our Municipal design
But it took awhile to refine certain aspects
At the design
Four years drinking fountains were sort of like a public faucet
You'd set your cup under a spigot and turn off the water
And this cop it was a common cop that hung from a chain and was meant to be used by all
Gonadal sinuses please
Please replace the cop
It was actually a pretty big battle to get rid of the common cup
Public Health officials knew it was spreading disease but people weren't in the habit of carrying their own cup around
In 1912 the very first
Federal Regulation on our drinking water with past
To abolish the common cup
A drinking fountain
Meanwhile a drinking fountain was designed that did not require a cup
It was similar to the drinking fountains we use now the difference being that the water came out in a vertical jet
Got that shot straight up
Which is exactly like a bidet
But for your mouth
And all of your backwash would just
Ripped straight down onto the spouse
Or
People just put their lips on to the spout
This vertical jet style drinking fountain was called
Ironically
A sanitary drinking fountain
And in 1920 the American Water Works Association issued a sternly worded report
That begins
The war against the common drinking cup has been won
This Victory however
Must not be allowed to Blind us to
The dangers lurking
In the sanitary drain
The report goes on to detail a study of one of these so-called sanitary drinking fountain
Of the 47 people who
Use the fountains
In almost every instance
Ellipse replaced
Sweetly around a metal ball from which the water spurted
And One Small boy acted as though he were trying to swallow the
Machinery
It goes on
Of the 47 people 3 looked as though they were unmistakably victims of tuberculosis and
Three had eruptions
On their faces
They advised putting cages around the spouts
So that we couldn't wrap our mouths around them
And finally they advised switching to a slanted or Arctic
Jet of water
This along with the guard around the spout
Proved to be the design that's.
Finally a drinking fountain we could all get behind
Sort of
And I say segregation now
For a lot of Americans
The public drinking fountain conjures and image that has nothing to do with the slanted jet
Are the common cup or with temperance
It's an image of segregation the segregated drinking fountain during the Jim Crow era in the South End is one of us
Images of Sprite
Sharing water made racist America uncomfortable
Whether it was drinking fountains for swimming pools
There is
Acute anxiety about the contact
Black and white bodies
The Civil Rights Act of 1964 ended segregated public facilities including drinking fountain
Although a handful hung on in the South for a few more years
Even with that darkest
Period the drinking fountains
History over
It's never really been as beloved as it was when they open that first one in London and 18th
Recently public drinking fountains have met their most formidable opponent
So in the United States
We consume 9 or 10 billion gallons a year
Expensive bottled water
And it's growing
5 to 10%
A year
That's Peter Glick again of the Pacific Institute he also wrote a book called bottled and sold
The story behind our obsession with bottled water
The consequence of that is
Billions and billions of plastic bottles
What's that
Have to be
Thrown away or recycled
Another consequence
Drinking fountains are starting to disappear from the public landscape
Despite the fact that many people believe public war is sort of a standard
Part of any Urban Design
We have seen
Movement away from water fountain
The University of Central Florida
In 2007 opened
A brand new football stadium they had built the stadium with no public water fountain
And on opening day 45,000 people showed up to watch the UCF Knights
Play the Texas Longhorns
It was an incredibly hot day almost a hundred degrees so everyone was thirsty
House for sale Force but it cost $3
And then the bottled water sold out
18 people were taken to hospitals and 60 more were treated by local campus Personnel for heat-related
Illnesses
At first the University was Unapologetic
And then some angry students organized into a group called
Knights for free water
They demanded drinking fountains be installed in the stadium
We're going out for blood we just want water they said
The local press came up with a name for this candle
Yes it was Watergate
And finally the University was forced to concede
They installed 50 drinking fountains in their Stadium
The nights for free water probably didn't know anything about there for mothers and fathers in the metropolitan
Free drinking fountain & Cattle trough
Association
But it's because of them and their teetotaling brethren in the United States
That we've come to expect access
Clean
Free water
In public places
If Watergate proved anything
You know besides Nixon was a liar and a cheat
It's a drinking fountain still matter
And when they're gone
We notice
Because even though we as a society have mostly rejected the idea of temperance
And embrace the idea that we love booze forever
Sometimes water
Is still the best
Special things to Marta Gutman. She gave on her book City for children women architecture and the charitable
Landscapes of Oakland inspired the story
Bonus Pack
The Metropolitan free drinking fountain and cattle trough Association still exists
But they change their name again now their jaws
The drinking fountain Association
They still maintain Linden's historic fountains
And build new ones
In developing countries
The Design Group we mentioned at the beginning of the piece pilot projects is trying to build 100 new drinking fountains in New York
They're still trying to make it happen but they need the city to partner with them
If you really into this
Write a note to the mayor's office and
Ask for better Drake
Fountains and mention 100000
Project as part of the solution
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery Troutman Kolstad and the
Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of Arkansas
In architecture and Interiors firm
Beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Wall Katie was working on the space we collectively couldn't get the Tune-Yards song water fountain out of our heads and
Which is what happens at richy at song Exploder Dead episode about that song which
One of our absolute favorite
So we thought we'd out of here
Enjoy
I want my music to be a product of the world that I am growing up
And growing old
So if this song is going to exist as a two-year-old song
It has to have
Some dirty nasty
52 it
My name is Merrill Garbus and I make music
Sick under the name Tune-Yards
Nate Brenner is a co-writer on most of the songs now
Skreets
It was January 2013 and I was like
Okay it's the new year and I'm going to start to make a new album
What kind of force myself in
Into this routine where I go into my little
Studio which was a shipping container that had been made into a little rehearsal studios I was there in this like
Super hot metal box
Sitting at a computer and trying to make
All these damn
Stipend
Taking a lot of walks around Oakland and I was walking
Around
Lake Merritt
Which is
Down the street from where we live
And I'll just walk around that like a whole lot and
Passing water fountain
Some of them working some of them now and
You know at that time I was hearing stuff about conservatives not wanting to pay taxes and I just kind of let my green Wonder
They're like we know what if no one ever pay tax
Doesn't what if no one ever
Decided that it was worth it
To put money into our greater
Good seeing that three of my imagination that
In on the roads no sidewalks
Snow
No one
I don't know there's something about the rhythm of my walking
And the rhythm of that
Prays that no other than water fountain that just like
I came out of that
The lyric and the melody and
Sing song Inus of it and the
Topic of it
I think I'll came
Bundled up
When tuners begin I was really interested
In-rhythm being
Abuse
Part of that
I just super obsessed with the
The interplay between rhythms and this creation of a greater rhythmic
Call when you have these multiple
Rhythmic voice is going on at the same time
X to the 3/2
And the other
Two three
And that was me and you know in the hot box
Just Larry loves over one over another and just saying okay that's a start to something and then
I kind of would just
Hear what was missing
Like we're can
Can I fill an even more gaps
Between those two clapping
And when it came up with was this cut.... Bye. Bye.
So it's really those three rhythms
Slate over each other
I love when things are human and not machine like obviously as anyone listening stupid music would know
It is not perfect by any means
But
There's a tipping point at which I go nope I was a little bit too op the beat there
For using a song that I really wanted to be a dance
The story of the song is basically that I almost threw it away because I thought it was
Dumb
It just sounded like really simple I mean think about me spending hours trying to workout Lane
Mike laps over one another and then
Coming up with the words like no wood in the Woodstock
What the hell does that mean
And I was like this is so annoying
And I'm annoying and everything
Pink sucks
And neat had a hot dogs across from mine
And he would walk over every opportunity
Ruby Lake
A sanity check and I be like this sucks
And he like no no it's cool and he
She came in and he played the first base line.
And I thought rhythmically is Baseline was awesome
But I thought no it sounds to rights like if you play in that kind of major key then it's going to sound too
Rate
A little bit more wrong
We kind of thought about it a little bit
In our peaceful way
And then he came up with if he's playing in minor
And all the sudden the color of the song
Completely changes and that was really important
To me that the things that the song was
Talking about to me or really heavy and so it didn't make sense to just keep the whole sun in major it was like
This is
Disturbing
That's kind of weird
Do you like
How about this and I was like how did that in the world like okay both
I saved up for my pants
Then I gave them to the special guy
In the store
Pretty simple major Melody but then you just make
The bassline minor
And all the sudden it's like
Stomach-churning
Part of the song where all is on you know that
Something's going to go down
You know now there a lot of people involved into yards the record label in our manager and they're like
Men's the single this the catchy one
Can you please just make it less dissonant and I was like
No
I really can't
I mean tuner it started when I was listening to us
Ton of dancehall reggae
And there's something about the tradition
Reggae that
For so many reasons
Stairs
Dissonance
And
Kind of dub sensibility where there things that feel wrong or don't link up exactly but there's so much
Much implied in that
Disagreement between Ellen
There's some Reggae albums where you feel like
Singer came in and saying and couldn't
Hear the track
And then the check that they end up putting underneath the singer is like
I totally different
Song with a different key
So I love
That sensitive
Wrong parts put together but then when it comes back together as a whole it has is holding
Conversation
Wrongness
Bino no water in the water fountain is
It's like a horrible concept
Even more so now in California but in 2013 to we were talking about the drought and it was
Terrifying to me to allow my imagination to go that far and think
Of life without water coming out of your toe
You know even just talking about these things now it's like this
Really uncomfortable
Tension in my
Stomach and I think that's
That feeling that I love to evoke in songs where I'm not writing pretty songs
For people to fall in love to Nessa
Literally I'm writing songs that sound more
Like the truth of the world to me and that has to mean that
That's literally built into the song that's literally built
Come to the harmonies or the friction or that
Reading sense of the song
And that's kind of why
I don't know what's listen to that drum machine stem and that first got the cute little cow bell sound
And then throughout the song as he gets the end of the song it's like this
Crazy distorted meth of a drum machine
I found this awesome water bottle of the thrift store and
It's just like these things like
Fit into the world of the
Spare parts
Like a water bottle
Evokes water somehow even if you're not saying though the water bottle
There's just something about it that
Buffets in
So this is where
The brilliant
John Hill comes in
Because
He introduced the lasers
Now we were so nervous working with other producers and I'm very possessive of the
Turn producer because I feel like
You know I am
My own producer
But
WeChat
The song in
Of some of our label people
And played it for
John Hill who's
Worked on a lot of
Rihanna and
Am I a an
And so he had those lasers
For us and I
Played those lasers
On honest
Add with a stick
So we all agree that that was
Again another
Dancehall Elliman
Amps up the song
When it's like another losers come in
You know what it is
Oh my God
Me and my voice
Tongue making fun
Crazy roll in there
But then
Sample
Implead
Keyboard that we did with Dunhill as well as we
Resembled my voice and then
I was able to
How to play it on a
MIDI triggering
Keyboard
And I can play
Play chords with my own voice
It's doing that
Crazy gurgling noise
I am so captivated by music
The ability
Speak without words
The sound itself
Telling the story and
Kind of like a big
Puzzle that even I am
Figure out
So fun the recording is amazing
Now here's waterfowl
Okay it still works in the store
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting to special episode
What's from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flat pocket
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com