99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When designing a commercial structure
The architect must make the hallways wide enough for wheelchair the materials must be compatible with its surrounding climate
The beams must be able to support the building and withstand the wind
The building should be
Interesting
Comfortable
And to be completely abandoned
There are a number of considerations for how a building should respond to emergency
Horns
Strobes
Speakers
The
Pulsating
Frequency of the light the intensity of the light
Smoked dampening
There's a sprinkler stepanek bars
Spring loaded horizontal bar that you push to unlock emergency exit
Does smoke detectors
What kind do you use and the distances between them
You know a lot of people
Harley Vin lookup
And see these things in and they just need to be there
When an emergency happens
Now Adam line again Daniel Scoville or Architects we work with them that arcsin in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Most of the time when they're working on fire safety they'll consult experts about where to place what kinds of architectural
Call emergency devices
But there's one safety device
I spent a month design
Right into the building from the get-go
It's impossible
To ignore
Torrid store locations that's pretty important right from the start because it changes the whole dynamic of
Typically buildings required to fire stairs
But it all depends on the size and purpose of the structure
In architecture and building codes do you always need a certain number of exits or means of egress
What's the ways out of a building
And
This fire escape
Precariously
Bolted to the side of the building is
Is one of our means of egress out of the space
This is how 99percentinvisible is going to escape a burning building
This is how I work sign and 99percentinvisible
In case of fire Architects Daniel Scoville and Adam Wayne a game producer Avery compliment would put their Steely resolve
Athletic prowess to The Test Escape right outside of our window
And I thought it was defense
It's all rusty and stuff
But then I bothered to read the sign with the evacuation plan for our building
Fire escapes are not allowed in Newquay
Construction
But because we are at a beautiful old brick building
The fire escape is actually one of our means of egress we just speak of
Means of egress thinking of the whole route
The Carter
And the stairs
And you think of an exit as being essentially
The door Professor Sara wermiel
Independent scholar and researcher
MIT
One of my
Books is called the fireproof building
I can't remember the subtitle
It's the fireproof building
Technology and Public Safety in the 19th century American city
The single most dangerous thing for architecture
Historically
Is fire
And in the 1700s
The fire did break out
There wasn't a whole lot you could do about it
But that time there were firefighters loudly
And they would come and it would bring you
The fire stick
It was a cart with a ladder on it
That was actually what
The earliest fire escapes were
So fire escape method started to get Incorporated in the architecture
Starting with the scuttle
It look like a skylight it would have some kind of cover would like a trapdoor
On the roof
And then there'd be a ladder
To to get up
And out and sew in a fire
You would climb through the Scuttle out onto the rooftop to your neighbor's cattle and crawl into their building
Which presumably hadn't also caught fire
That was the beginning this idea that a city could require something
For the sake of fire safety
Around 1860 New York begin to record
Choir means of egress
In tenement building
Turn that buildings were tall
Flammable densely-packed tinderboxes just
Pull up families of course landlord went with the least expensive option
The popular cheap fix
Was rope
Ropes with baskets
That you're supposed to somehow you know the building's on fire
You have your kid you're terrified and you calmly it'll open this this
Little
Nightstand
Pull out the basket with the ropes
You know set up the apparatus strap yourself in
And somehow you know lower yourself calmly to the ground you know what's it's just preposterous
30 hilarious old advertisements for fake cabinets
Holler frigerators an empty washing machines
So that you can store your ropes and basket apparatus because no one would notice that extra washing machine
One engineer actually thought that instead of dispatching ropes from inside archers could shoot the ropes up
To the higher floors
You know people aren't
That athletic necessarily to begin with but
Second of all
It's a fire
You know this isn't the best time to eat a like figure out
How to lower yourself on a rope
Another patent proposed individual parachute
That's with a company in rubber shoes to break the fall
They're also these
Big slide fire escapes
That were largely marketed to schools as both emergency devices
And playground equipment
They're actually used to be a giant spiral slide to Escape The Claremont Hotel right here in Oakland
Which
Would have made that place a whole lot better lots of ideas
But by the 1870s
Fire escapes begin becoming
Something iron something fixed
Out of the building
Although by that point they still weren't anything great
They were
Like a iron platform outside of a window
With straight ladders attached
Or it might just be a straight ladder clamp to the wall
In some cities the external ladders
Angled and widen to become more like stairs
This was an improvement
But ultimately fire escapes just didn't suffice a terrible tragedy to show this
So the asch building
In New York
Was built as a locked building
And its owners
Representative as being
You know maybe for warehousing
Not necessarily for manufacturing
Based on its Dimensions the asch building was required to have three means of egress
But the developer insisted that the property would just be used as warehousing
Two rather than three stairs
He was allowed to put into stairs
And a thin fire escape
Then the owner rents the top three floors of the asch building
The Triangle Shirtwaist company
In March
There's a fire in the building
It's not know exactly how it begins
And it is
It spreads
Quickly
The 10th floor has an exit to the roof
So many of the 10th floor workers are able to survive by taking the stairs up and
The workers on
The 8th floor
AR
By-and-large able to get out or we're trapped
The door to the stairs opened in word and became block with bodies
And the stairs
We're backed up with workers exiting from the floors below
The workers on the 94 couldn't even get down
Only a few workers on this floor new about the 10th floor exit and so they didn't even try to go upstairs
There was charged that one of the doors was locked
And this was approved at the trial
But
I believe even if it had been
With all the people exiting from the 8th floor
And the staircases were very narrow and winding there just wasn't the capacity
Some workers tried to use the outside fire escape
And it collapsed under the weight
It was from the windows of the ninth floor that many workers desperate to escape the flames and smoke
Fell or jumped to their deaths
146 people lost their lives
Right in the middle of Greenwich Village
There were a lot of witnesses
It was horrible
But the building
Was fine
The asch building was a fireproof building
And of course it's it's still standing
And it's now part of
New York University
The asch building now called The Brown building was well-made
Which is why at the time
No one really thought it needed an egress
Exit and egress were a problem people fought for the tenement
And the poor quality build
The logic was if a building was first class it was in and of itself say for the occupants
And then the people could just be safely locked inside of these non-combustible building
The triangle fire proves that architecture couldn't protect
We had to protect ourselves
From Ark
This is when
An organization called the National Fire Protection Association
Does a lot of
Studies in thinking
You know about
Egress
And goody Grace meant getting rid of fire escapes
For so many reasons
They weren't commonly used
So they were often out of order and states of disrepair
In Northern climates they were covered with snow or eroded by rain
And not everyone could access them like people with disabilities
And the very young and the elderly
And women who are hamstrung by the fashion of the time
Women in these long skirts
Might not have the presence of mind to take off their skirt could actually get out
Also fire escapes are scary using some narrow rickety staircases on really tall building
That make you feel like you should
Strap on rubber shoes in a parachute
And if people weren't used to using fire escapes they often didn't know where they were
People
Try to leave the way they came in you know that's
That's what they think
And that's where Modern fire escapes come in
They're not bolted to the side of the building
They are the logical place
Where you go in an emergency
They are the stairs
Well they look like normal stairs but
Really
They're pieces of Emergency Equipment
Enclosed in fireproof walls and sealed with a self-closing door
I'm covered with sprinklers and alarms
And because
They
Work perfectly well as stairways
They're often
The stairway
In a building
So if the
The building won't have
The grand stairway any longer
It'll have
Lots of elevators
And
The fire stick
Goodbye opulent lobbies with sweeping grandstand
If you like to take the stairs you probably already bemoaned the fact that they are always shoved off into a tower
And are very cold and Industrial no matter what the building looks like from the outside
If we want we can make them look good but most clients
Alexa spending money on things that people are going to see me
Officemate an architect Adam line again
The stairways need to be what's called
Raided meaning that they need to be enclosed
Any type of construction that won't melt
Or a lot of Fire
To penetrate as quickly
As a non rated wall
These rated Towers can be like buildings within buildings
The prime example of a souped-up
Fire stairway
Isn't Freedom Tower
The Freedom Tower which has this emergency Corps
Which is on its own separate electrical and plumbing system
It has its own elevators and stairs
That's a logic huge he's a professor at Wesleyan University
And I'm also a practicing architect
Can I run a small firm called periphery project
And part of that periphery involves doing research on architecture
He's particularly fascinated by these core structures around the fire stairs
And these emergency
The cores are modeled with software
End simulation
Dedicated
Egress
This program Exodus 4.0 I think there's nice
Is 5.0
Can simulate
How quickly
A floor of a building can be cleared
Based on the maximum number of bodies that
Would be allowed in the space
How quickly could those bodies
Exit this
So the architect
Or actually more likely the consultant
Will plug in the measurements of a building
All the information about its Emergency Equipment
The maximum number of occupy
And basically
Play
And watch the digital people
Escape the pics
A lot of agent-based modeling programs with humans
Don't work terribly well cuz he was doing necessarily behave predictably
But in emergencies they do
Given adequate signage
People will behave in predictable ways in the event of an emergency
So this makes sense
We've already established that in an emergency
People don't want to go places they haven't gone to before
Or use devices I've never seen
You know figure out if they can catch a rope shot at them with a bow and arrow
The way egress works now is in keeping with the way that we use buildings normally
Even though rated Towers take up a lot of space and money
And make for an unpleasant shopping experience
It's hard to argue with this solution
Is paid off let's say
Sarah again
In nonresidential structures
There were 65 deaths
In the whole year
You don't probably more people struck by lightning
Usually 28 people were struck by lightning in 2012
But still
Even though each one is a tragedy 65 gas doesn't strike me as all that money
This number is already down from 2003
Where they work 220 des and on his eventual Bill Dance
So these are the buildings with heavy regulations in core structure
Modern Emergency Equipment in egress procedures are really helping to minimize the effects
The fire accident
But from an aesthetic standpoint it
Almost a pity
Because fire escapes are beautiful
And although I'm not really thrilled at the prospect of clamoring down the fire escape outside my window
I do like to look at it
Is there a fire escapes even the ones that are no longer in use
What is physical reminder
That we evolved past being a culture that says
Here's a rope
Good luck buddy
I just like seeing them
And hope that
They'll be preserved
Because
It just makes me realize how we
Kind of have to work together as a society
You have to rely on other people to put in the stairs to follow the rules for the rules to be there
And that's what makes us safe
Climbing up a fire
I am summer in the city
Save my baby
World
99% invisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman with Sam Greenspan Katie mingle and me Roman law
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of our
Arcsin in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting to special episode
What's from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how our soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets
Scrolled in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
If you like this program you get more and more and more stories and correspond with all the people who make this show on Facebook
Twitter and Tumblr you can shake a stick at
99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com