99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Metaphorical anecdote coming in three
Years ago we were asked to do resign for a school
A school that will remain anonymous
It was further sports bra the new mask
That's Christopher Simmons my name is Christopher Simmons I am the principal and creative director of the design firm mine in San Francisco
He also teaches Identity Design at the California College of the Arts
We've created some alternatives for a few new mascot
Steering committee
They had their favor but they were unsure they wanted by in
From the student body and alums
Seem reasonable but also treacherous Terror
So they got like six hundred something responses and overwhelmingly by write-in vote
The original logo was the favor
Not surprised
Change is often the hardest of all possible options and people would argue well you know
But it was a real problem with the old mascot
The problem was
They were using their original logo illegally
It was actually University of Notre Dame's
Logo and the reason 8th and Gage. The change it was because they would know they realize they did not have the right to do that
Of course the constituency of the school all the people who love
The original logo
Didn't know anything about that they didn't know the reason
Why there needed to be a new logo
But the public dialogue continued
Santa Portugal
It's a Well the reason we don't like the new and you had to pick up the new one why is it a white
Person right where
A diverse
School so it should be any more ethnically ambiguous
Why is it a male wear coed
So maybe I could be more androgynous
He's so aggressive I know it's a sports program but you know
We are a Catholic school could you
Make it less violent
And so they wanted a
Ethnically ambiguous
Androgynous
Nonviolent
Mascot
And are the Fighting Irish
There are factors at play that guy that design of which not everyone
Is aware
But that doesn't stop everyone from having an opinion and I like people having opinions about the time I think I'd design awareness is that a no
All-time high
And this has by Lord help designers of all kinds
People have cottoned on to the idea
That their interaction with the built world and they're hidden communication with the people who designed it
Really matters
It's really important
And like I said
This usually works out
Pretty well
But sometimes
It's a
In Trainwreck
This is the biography of a logo
Debrief
And tumultuous life
The new logo
The University of California
So if you're not from California or miss this bit of news the University of California
Kinda
Or rather had a new logo
What is the kind of entirely accurate but completely wonky description
Think it's Matt with sarcastic eye rolls from anyone who isn't a designer
But there it is
But they don't have a new logo anymore
Because of a massive public backlash
Do UC system actually suspended the new monogram logo
While we were reporting this story
And the creative director of the UC office of
The president is not happy
About how it turned out I would say that it was use of the rhetoric of democracy
The tyranny of the minority
That's Vanessa Curry I will hear more from her in a minute and the fill you heard before
Having reported about Bonn Germany
And amazing Belgian beer
But now he's back home here in the Golden State
California
Alright so before we get to why people hated this new logo
We need to tell you what it look like
It looks a little like a shield with a mostly flat top and a rounded bottom
Superimpose on The Shield is the letter c it was first presented in the
Was in Gold these are the historic colors of the University system
Stream reversal and almost any color
So just to be clear this was the new symbol for the entire UC system as a whole
UC San Diego open campus
What are the reasons the public backlash surprise the in-house team color scheme
Associate icons
Is that it's all been around for nearly a year it was part of a massive
Onward California public marketing campaign to build awareness of the University system as
Part of what makes California great
In fact that they took it on tour to Alton camp
Where they drove around a huge truck with the logo and all the new colors and everything
Around 2
Show it to the faculty and students
No one said a word
The design team at the UC Office of the President probably thought they done a good job and they were ready to move forward
Then in early December these Shield like you see monogram hit the block
And two things happened that set the stage
Three burning torch reaction that I got from the pub
Beyond the aesthetic
I do recognize that there
Completely valid criticism that can be made about the design itself but this first error on the part of the press
Really doomed it out of the gate
There were lots of articles in the media nearly all of them actually
That put the classic University seal
Side by side with the new UC logo
It's so strongly implied I think to the most people in reasonably so
That the seal was the before
And the monogram was yeah
That's Christopher Simmons again are you heard from at the very top the show
He had nothing to do with this UC logo redesign but he waded Into The Fray with a blog post on his own website
Called why the ussuri brand is better than you think
And that therefore the Demonic and will be replacing the
And of course that wasn't the case it to frame the conversation
Completely wrong
The second missed up
And this one actually got to me as a UC Berkeley graduate
Was that the UC Office of the President released a video online that show the graphical Evolution from the old seal
Deal to the new logo which is produced by the University of California
Kind of show
Some of the thinking behind the Genesis of the new
Monogram
And how it related
To the c a Heisman took some of it
Excuse women in the video hands pulled design elements from the seal to create the new design
I literally sweep aside the old seal
Brushing away and tossing it out
The video reinforced
Everyone's greatest fear about the new brand
From the get-go
And change is understandably very hard
NSU University logo
It was really
Standing out all on its own it's really easy to criticise
The UC alumni in the California public-at-large saw it
In the reaction
Was Rome really negative
Roman that is actually an understatement a lot of people felt that this new logo with two modern
Too cheap
I'm really denigrated the gravitas and that was the word that was used
The gravitas of the University
In fact lieutenant governor Gavin Newsom
The former mayor of San Francisco sent an angry letter
On December 11th
WC president
Quotes
The overwhelmingly negative response to the recent change to the University of California logo
Demands immediate attention
Yunnan
Perhaps now it is time to return to the use of the old logo
It allow the university community a cooling-off period to concentrate on the long-term health
The universe
Instead of being creative with the University of California logo
We should be searching for Creative Solutions
For funding the University of California
He's wrong because the logo there is no logo to restore
There was no old logo and again it's a classic case of the misinformation
Reaching the very very top
That's Vanessa Correa the creative director of the UC Office of the President
Vanessa led the team that came up with this logo in the new visual brand
She says that a lot of the negative reaction was because the media imply that the classic CEO was being replaced
But there were no such plans
Paseo which UC has reassured everyone will stay on diploma
Is more of a classic
Collegiate icon
It's circular with the words
Seal of the University of California around the edge
An image of an open book
In the motto let there be light
At the bottom
An earlier version of a sealed dates back to when the University was founded in the 19th century
In its current form
That seal has been unchanged
Since 1910
So UC Berkeley my alma mater
Has the UCC law on its official communication
It's what's on my diploma
It was on my aunt's my grandparents
And yes
And it's earlier form it was on my great-grandparents diplomas
I'm the fourth generation in line of UC Berkeley graduates
Like the cows crip logo that's on the UC Berkeley football helmet and every tenth person sweatshirt in downtown Berkeley
Or the Sea Bear Claw logo that's on a baseball cap
SoCal UCLA and lots of other universe
Please have this distinctiveness
Between a more official seal
Animal casual logo
What do you see
System as a whole
Did not
Bastille
For all the good things that it does represent
Can't carry all of that symbolic
Wait
Why not
Because it's already
Interacting in a sort of rhetorical space
That is
Much more
It's institutional
Too stuffy
You can say that if you want but how you feel about it like a zit
Is Santa
Because when we need to have the weight
Weight and gravitas
City University
Behind a budget book
Or behind
Proclamation by the president or whatever that is that still gives us that gravity
But we don't always want that gravitas tok gravitas
It has a place
In communication
It's like
Having a tick
Tuxedo and be forced to wear it every single day
In other words with a team of designers at UC intended to do
Was to create an icon that could be used as part of a broader campaign to more dynamically and more casual
Explain the university system to people
Kree explained that the logo would never stand on its own as it was depicted in media reports would almost always be presented with the words
University of California next to it
Or the motto let there be light
He would have all these other visual cues that would help you see sell itself
You talked about
You know expressing dynamism and light and you start to think
Do you feel like that the that the logo should be able to
Stand on its own I mean I think that
Again for me
I feel like when I look at this and you say well you know what is part of a larger thing there's text that goes with it there's other contextual information that would help me to
Understand what it is
Because when I just see it
This does not scream
Scream to me you see
Like I don't
What time today it doesn't but it will
Okay
So you know you need the ecosystem
To build the meaning in
Into the object
You need people to begin to identify it with
The good works of the University
For them to you build them
A logo on itself is nothing
It's a thing
You know you a logo doesn't come
Fully formed with the meaning baked in
The meaning is
Accrued overtime
The Nike Swoosh
Looks like a giant check mark
I mean if
People had social media inside into a date today
Only one
Why is it so plain
By the looks like a check
You know what that supposed to be a wing I don't get it I don't see it
The meaning has accrued
Through years of
Quality products
Thorne on quality products
An athlete's associating with it and
And the interaction
Can you have with the brand
Writ large
The same thing for Apple can you imagine I mean
It's an apple
The computer company while you have an apple is this a grocery store I don't understand you know it's
It's the same kind of thing the meeting is not baked in
You build mean
That's what the
Brand is
People's emotional resonance
With something develops over
The only reason why
So many other using moms
Have such a strong bond with the seal
Just because
It's been around for over a century
And that bond is further strengthened
Buy every other seal in the world
Really
Not all that distinct
Feels now kind of naturally communicate a history and tradition and indeed
Vanessa says she gets all that
And while she herself may have attended another UC
That would be the universe
Cincinnati
She thinks that
Part of why there's been so much negative attention for the logo is because it's become a lightning rod for other issues
I think that
There are other things going on here
And the outcry
Part of what's going on
Become a very simple
Way
Express a lot of other fresh
I mean I receive that
I'm a lot of different
They are frustrated because they feel like the mystery
Inaccessible
Frustrated
Is there tuition score
They're frustrated for all these things
They're frustrated about the privatization of University
Rightly so
I'm frustrated too
That's part of the reason why I'm sitting here trying to get people
Bolt actually care about it
Because I want them to go and vote for it
Describe the purpose of the logo and the uphill climb and had head of it
How do you spell to talk about the actual graphic design that a lot of people both
The lay public in several designers
Had huge
Problems with
One common complaint was the back of the sea part of the design
Wasn't totally solid it was a gradient
The bottom part of the sea was lighter than
And while the intention was to convey movement to luminosity
That's not what a lot of people saw in it
The first time I saw the logo I immediately thought of
Computer icon of something loading
I spent a lot of time in front of my computer maybe you do too
This sea looks exactly like a circle indicating a loading browser tab or Skype opening or any other
Number of loading scenarios on a computer
Vanessa told me this was
Pure coincidence
Expressed a little bit of regret over
This particular color combination
Is
One that really
Pops out that
Lodebar
Reference
In a way that is again I mean
Nuc website where the identity was introduced you could actually see other versions of the logo with differ
True colors
They were black and white and blue and white versions The monogram that didn't have a great-aunt at all I personally prefer those but I don't
I think those were very widely
Vanessa also told me that what's gotten drowned out in all the noise a journalist like me wanting to talk to
Is the fact that people in the design world
Do you like it
There was an op-ed written in the San Francisco Chronicle by Rob Duncan
Formerly pentagram
He's now an art director at Apple
He also runs his own Design shop in San Francisco
He called the new UC logo quote
One of the freshest
Sandra's Creative Education identity schemes in a country
Full of boring
Institutional logos
But the much more common and widely publicized response was very
Very nice
An online petition called stop the new UC logo
Received over 54000 signatures
Earlier
On December 14th a few days into the extremely vociferous public reaction to the logo
Puc director of marketing Communications release a statement
Saying that the new UC monogram
In the past week it has become clear that the University of California system wide monogram recently created
Is a source for great debate
Dialogue and Division
Insured
It's too much of a distraction from our broader effort
Communicate uses value in vital contribution
California
Intent to suspend use of the demonic
You will begin to take steps required to do so
I certainly had an initial negative reaction to the monogram when I first saw it too
I still think the gradient is just not quite right
But overall after talking to Vanessa
Even a skeptic like me is
A little bit more convinced of its usefulness and of its quality
You don't have to
Like
Designed to recognize that
It's good design I don't like Led Zeppelin
Sing about it I don't
I have no opinion on Led Zeppelin one way then understand
What they've done and wiped
People think they're good and why they are good and where they fit into rock and roll history
It's fine not to like it
Do you need understand what it's trying to do
And
And go from there
You know I would say I hate the IDM logo but doesn't matter
Doesn't matter
It does what it needs to do and
So from that perspective I would say you know I would
I would hope that people think about design and in the way that one should be thinking
How to sign rather than a
Purely subjective
Response to one thing
Badly
Post it on the internet plot
Is enough to the basement
I talked to my 91 year old grandfather about the new UC logo to
He graduated from Cal in the 1940s
And he said he didn't like it either
For many of the same reasons that we talked about earlier
It wasn't clear what it was supposed to represent
Leprosy
And you see look weird
And when I explained what Vanessa had told me
He chewed on that for a while
But ultimately I think came away on convince
Taqueria and mini designers have spoken out in support of her and her team's efforts
They continued to say that their work was bold
Daring and does represent modern California
Paragon is Christopher Sim
I think the role of
An expert
An expert to me is to someone who is
Trained in
Particular
Field and has
Some perhaps
Hopefully deep experience
Skin the practice
Is
To see the world through a different
Flatso
For example
When
We had our
Kitchen renovator
I don't know anything about
Architectural nothing about engineering I don't know anything
Not really about
Interior design
I have my opinions
And so
When a designer tells me why I think this
Would work best
I defer to that app
When a mechanic tells me that
The thing is
My car
I trust
That pure she is
That when I go to my doctor
They're telling me
How to understand my own body
And
I don't know how to interpret what's happening to my body so
Allow them to do that
When it comes to design
We don't seem culturally to have that same
Trust
And so
Perhaps saying that people are
Are ignorant of design or
Not knowledgeable to process
Or short-sighted
What is contentious
It's probably strictly speaking true
But it's not always wise to say the true thing in exactly the way
We live in a time when everyone feels that their opinion matters
And the reality is
Does that not all opinions
That's not popular
Because you like to think that your voice is
The same as someone else's but when it comes to for example
Physics
My voice is not the same as Stephen Hawk
Nor should it be
Aesthetic
Is a very easy
Target
Because everyone no one understands how Aesthetics works
And they feel that
Subjective opinion is
The role of the day
I don't like it therefore it must not
So I guess that
No one wants to be told how to do their job by rank amateurs
You don't understand what they're trying to do
I don't go to restaurants and tell chefs that their Pizza could use more basil in the tomato sauce
What's the difference between designers like Vanessa
And the physics world
Is that we the public
Are not invited to sit in Stephen Hawking's physics Lab in Cambridge
We're not part of that world
.
But design in general and this design in particular is about communication and interaction with a public
Who are completely unaware of the motivations behind a certain design
The logo isn't meant to sit in someone's SketchBook
It's meant to be out there in the world
Telling the story of the University of California
And right or wrong
The people connected to the university
Still feel like they have a say in the matter
It's hard to say what the ultimate effect of this whole Fiasco will be
I think institutions like University of California which tend to be
What are you change averse anyway
Will be more gun-shy about pushing new designs and new ideas for work
There will be a chilling effect
If that comes to pass
That will be a real shame
I hope the people who really dislike the logo at least
Would also not want to see that happen
I also don't want
Designers to circle the wagons and claimed that no design can be criticized and less
The person with an opinion knows the fullback
Story of the design process
That just
Seems false
And incongruous with reality
I didn't see people making the same defense of the new Gap logo with the little
Please square that appeared briefly in 2010
It was divided by
Everyone
Everywhere
Even Christopher Simmons who has very thoughtfully considered and spoken out against the overreaction to the UC logo
Took some swings at the Gap logo backpack
Someone made some meow
Jerky website where you can
Turn anything into the Gap logo
Besides have generic
My Facebook
Profiling
My name
Squaring the top
Panda in retrospect
That was probably mean and
Laughing take it back
I what
I think it speaks well of his character that Christopher regrets
But I don't know if he's
He cared
Any comment
Fundamental
Because of these things matter to him
On one level is great that the public is
Engaged
Compassion about
It's a little dispiriting that
Every time it happens it's
Typical UC logo
Recall the Gap logo
Call the Tropic
And
We don't see the office
That we don't see people galvanized around you know a great new identity that
It's very easy
Me to certify
Pylon
And not offer you a meaningful
Alternatives
Dad said
Yeah the fact that design is even being discussed
Signals attitude
But it's important to people that sing
Culture that it's in
The business and
That's a win
For everyone
99% invisible with produces week by Cyrus farivar with help from Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Is a project of 91 Point
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Art
Christopher Simmons the principle of mine who is featured in this episode was also interviewed by my hero Debbie Millman
Not a recent episode of her design matters podcast
I was also featured last season if you want to check that out you can find design matters in iTunes or at design Observer
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
Slash podcast
You can find a show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but right now you can look at the UC logo
And all kinds of links to all the controversy
And 99% invisible
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech
Wait machine even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com