99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1956 General Motors hosted a car Expo called Motorama
As with all car Expo
Motorama with a chance to show off concept cars and other kinds of Longshot projects that they hope would revolutionize
The Auto industry
One of the most forward-looking things on display was in a car
The movie
That's forward-looking producer Sam Greenspan
The film was called e to the Future
In it we see a family of four cruising along a desert highway in a beautiful futuristic GM Firebird
It's got aerodynamic fins gas turbine engines and All Glass passenger cabin it looks like a car
The Jetsons only it's not flying its driving
On a highway
But his car is actually just the set dress
What GM really want
Show us
Their vision for a self-driving
Firebird tattoo
We're heading for Chicago
Please route us through
Over
Rodger Firebird
You're now under automatic
Hands off
After being put on automatic control the dad who's driving the car
Pushes the steering wheel
Out of the way
Faith School
Comfortable
Mind if I smoke a cigar
No longer Tethered to the steering wheel
Dad uses both hands to light his cigar
The car zooms along
For nearly as long as there's been an auto industry there have been dreams of a car that drives on its own
The car where people can enjoy all the freedom that cars offer but without the annoyances or the dangerous I'm driving
I can't speak to What specifically inspired GM to dream up that self-driving car we
Seeing this film
But it's very possible that it had to do with safety
The film is only 9 minutes long
But I can't stop commenting on her
Oh darn safe
It's automatic driving
Safe
Easy way to make
Peter this film was shown at Motorama 1956
That you're alone there are nearly
1000 vehicle related deaths
In the United States
Ever since the 1950s
There has never been a year with
Fewer than 30000 people killed in car
Vehicle related accidents are the number one cause of death in the United States for people between the ages of
5 + 34
And
More than 90% of all automobile
Students are attributable to one thing
Human error
So for some industry people
A fully automated car
Is a kind of Holy Grail
The thing about automation though is that as it solves problems
It inevitably
Create new one
As automation makes our lives easier and safer
It also creates more complex systems and fewer humans who understand those
Which means
What problems do arise
People can be left ill equipped to deal with
Human factors engineer is called as
The automation parody
Last week in our story about Automation in aviation we heard about various ways people are trying to deal with the
Paradox in that industry
One Pilots are being encouraged to practice manually find their plane to keep their skills polished
And Engineers are also trying to make smarter more collaborative automation that doesn't strip
Skills from Pilot but instead works with them to complete tasks
The position I would have dropped is one that has been termed a human centered automation
Where we see what you need to do in Disney animation
The team player
That's an alien starter a human factors engineer who believes
Human Pilots still have a crucial role to play in flight
Let's just get rid of the human
And it's fully automated vehicle
You know I I do feel
Comforted by the fact that
Is a pilot up there
And that
Is Chris
I'm Christmas and I lead the self-driving car project here Google
Chris may be glad there are pilots and planes
But he's got a very different vision for cars
He believes the way to solve the automation Paradox for cars
Is to take humans out of the operation
Entirely
If you have a steering wheel there there's kind of a name
Explicit
Expectation
That you're going to do something with it
We're needing starter thinks that allowing for human intervention is best
Yes you still think me to driver who is
In the vehicle and who has the opportunity at least to intervene when necessary
Chris is to make a car that is safe
Because no human is driving
You get to sidestep
All of these kind of control confusion confidential challenges
By taking that out of the way
You get to to remove a part of the system that you can't
Designed
No human drivers
Just human path
We are about to enter Uncharted Territory
Automation has been appearing in cars almost since they hit the market anti-lock brakes automatic transmission powers
Steering cruise control DPS
Cars that can parallel park themselves
The fully autonomous self-driving car
It's been a long time coming
There's been a few players developing self-driving car technology
The most visible among them
Being Google
In 2009
Google began retrofitting Toyota and Lexus cars with new technologies
Allowing the car to drive on its own
The cars can accelerate stop at traffic signals make turns merge onto freeways and avoid pedestrians cyclists another
All with little or no intervention from anyone inside the car
And then in 2014
Google started Manufacturing
Their own
Cute little two-seaters
With no Gas Pedal brake or
Steering wheel
They're designed for the user to input a destination and just sit back and laugh
Car do every
Google has videos that show blind people and children sitting in what we normally think of as the driver seat
As the car scoots
Around a test track
Pulling Santa's sleigh
You shouldn't have to have any training
You should be able to get in them tell them where you want to go
Tell them you changed your mind do you want to go somewhere else and then get out
Google wouldn't show me the
But Chris
Did show them to Planet money's
Steve head
So I you want to open it up and show me the inside
So this is one of our early prototypes will actually start our 5th generation prototype
This vehicle is one of the ones that will start to be testing on the roads in Mountain View in the next over the summer
We talked to Steve about what it was like after
When you get inside
There's no dashboard there's no
Steering column so I'm about to
Tall and
The seat is all the way again
What's the back window
Of the car and I can
Take my legs
Straight out in front of me
Because there's nothing there
Well almost nothing what you can see in the center here so this is
The steering wheel brake and gas pedals and lessor for our test drivers
But their removable California law allows autonomous cars on the roadways but
Only if they
Can be driven by a human
But the design of this car is to have none of them
Right into their very very few
User controls in
Inside
There are buttons to lower the windows
There's a button
To pull over to the side of the road and stop
You know if you suddenly see a yard sale if you want to check out our friend do you want to pull over and talk to
But is also an emergency stop button a button that halts the car and its track
Skellige on an elevator you know how they say it the big red button while they're still you know I really need to get out now there's some
Something very wrong here
I've never press the red button elevator but it's kind of comforting notes there
The cars look kind of endearing
Goofy the small and round Steve versus them as bubble cars
Not that they would let him ride in one
Yeah so they didn't
Let me ride around in the bubble car and in fact the bubble car hadn't hit
The streets of man
But he was able to get inside one of their older mod
With a retrofitted
Lexus SC
TV okay
Should I jump in the front or the back
You should yeah probably this back
Corner right here
I think the most remarkable thing for me
Was how quickly the
Experience
Became
Just kind of boring it came to a full and complete stop at the
Stop sign definitely soda car follows the law very closely
Passenger the car is driving with more or less indistinguishable from a human driver
Well a human driver that always follows the rules of the road we were driving
True residential
In Mountain View
Including through streets that were under
Construction so it was navigating
Streetscapes that were changing
You know lanes were blocked off Lanes
Foreclosed
And at one point on their drive a construction worker was directing traffic
And Steve was chatting with the other person in the car
We were both sort of
Distracted
And suddenly all on its own wow
Car slammed on the brakes it was startling
Steven the Google employees hadn't seen it
But the construction worker had flipped his handheld sign from slow to stop
The machine had noticed that handheld stops
When all of a sudden
That actually kind of
Scared
Because we didn't see it
Even the Google employees hadn't seen that before
The autonomous car was working better than they had expected
Maybe these things can react faster than
But sensors will fail navigation will get screwy onboard computers
Will break
Car owners barely know how to fix their own Vehicles as it is now so
Will people be able to fix the kinds of complicated problems that come with a self-driving car
Payday really depends on
How they end up being using a mark
Right
Chris imagines that if a self-driving car breaks while it's on the road
It'll pull over
Another car will come fetch the passengers
Leaving the broken one for technicians.
Which means
Google doesn't want to just change how we relate to our cars
Google wants to change how cars
Relate to society
If you look at the car that you own today
You know it's
South Park Somewhere 95% of the time and that's kind of poorly using
Now both your kind of financial resources that went into it
But also the environmental resources that the material and energy we put into making that vehicle so we can use that more efficiently by sharing at that sounds
Fantastic
Maybe
Eventually
Instead of owning these cars you would hail them from off the street
I'm going to get out the car would drive off and pick up someone else
In other words it's possible that these cars could enable a world in which no one owns a car and all of us just
Get Around by robot Taxi
Well
What's the great thing about predict
Always wrong
My name is
Professor
In a civil Environmental
Carnegie Mellon
Kostas Samaras has thought a lot about how self-driving cars will change society
He is the co-author of a report called autonomous vehicle technology a guide for policy
Jocasta like Chris urmson and pretty much everyone else I meant working on autonomous vehicles
He thinks that these things hold a lot of Promise so reducing crashes
The first wave that automation
Help Society
But that's really only the starting point
After all the vast majority of American cities are built around cars
And so transforming the car means transforming the city
Starting with parking lot
We can
Get rid of a lot of the parking garage space and put in housing or commercial development because if all or most cars are
Taxis
We don't need to clear out spaces and congested downtown's just so cars can have a place to sit idle
Get out of the robot taxi and it's off to give a ride to someone else
Urban core downtown
All the things we learned in driver's ed staying a certain amount of seconds behind a speeding car
Those things will now be taking over
I'm by self-driving vehicle
They will make the
Determination of how far its
Be from the car in front of us
And 10 order for everybody to be safe
This would allow cars to get closer together
And not just bumper to bumper
Side to side
The Department of Transportation requires that Highway Lanes be at least
12 feet wide
That's about twice as wide as the average
Car so suddenly a 3-lane highway can accommodate 6 Lanes
Without any new
Less space between cars means more cars can get where they're going faster
But these cars could also we organize cities for the worse
Right now I have a cost
I'm driving and that cost is
Running my vehicle
And also the time that I'm in it
Anyone could read or sleep or write emails in a robot car people might feel just fine about living far
Or outside the city and commuting a long way in
And that type of scenario we would see lots more vehicle-miles-traveled lots more
Sprawl into the deep excerpts and into
And of course the inside of the car could become another place for advertising
Your route data could be for sale
Maybe it knows I hadn't had coffee
Because it's connected to my refrigerator and my coffee maker at home in
He hasn't had coffee yet let's make the slow route next to the coffee place
Or the route data could even become a matter of National Security
Take control of your car or
Fleet of cars
Stop every car that's on the Bay Bridge at one time
For malicious
Intent
Clearly there are still a lot of details to work out
But I wonder once the science is done and the policy is carefully considered
Will people even want these things
Is America ready to give up the steering wheel
I mean will people still go on road trips and tailgate in the stadium parking lot
Will you still be able to get in your car and go on a nameless contemplative Drive
I guess we hadn't really thought about that that's Chris urmson from Google
Assumption is he would give it a destination and say where you want to go but you'll always be able to change it
Right so
I don't do a whole lot of
Contemplative driving but when I do you know you start heading somewhere and then you like out maybe I'll go
Afterwards
But you know
Sometimes you're really just need to get in your car and go
Like say if you're getting chased by gun-toting corporate goons trying to stop you from eating Martian colonists Rebel
Arnold Schwarzenegger did
In Total Recall
Hello
I'm Johnny Cash
Where can I take
Would you please
At which point Arnold rips the robot driver out of the car
And Pilots it himself
It's funny because as Fantastical as the Sci-Fi world is
We can recognize the same kind of user annoyances
As we have here in the presence
And we can see Arnold as heroic because he can do the things the machines can
I think about Star Wars when Luke Skywalker is on his way to blow up the Death Star
The one his robot co-pilot that supplied
And he turns off his onboard automation
Because automation is not as good as what Luke can do on his own
Used
As much as we love building things that make our lives easier
It seems like we never get tired of seeing someone cast the robots of side
We love seeing people do things by
Anxiety about
If we lose the ability to do something ourselves
Are we losing a piece of ourselves
Or something
We are going to have to answer these existential questions
Battle cars
Kind of salmon
Chris urmson has said that his personal goal is to get the Google self-driving car done by 2020
What is Tucson
The oldest of whom is 11
Will never need
To get a driver's license
Definitely think that when is sunrise
Sakura 17
You would have to get a driver's license
Raj Rajkumar is friends with Chris
They used to work together at Carnegie Mellon University
Before Chris went over to Google
Raj is co-director of cmu's autonomous driving collaborative research lab
The university has been working on automatic
The Cars Since the 1980s about six months back we lived three celebrated
The 30th birthday
Actually working on
Raj is also the CEO of a company called automatica which has a prototype vehicle that is already driven itself
From San Francisco to New York
Mirage doesn't plan on taking the steering wheel out just yet
In fact his car actually monitors the person in the driver seat and beeps at him or her if the driver's eyes Wonder
From the road hey you guys on the road Rogers not in a rush to have us 100%
Dependent on his autonomous technology
The way he sees it unfolding is with incremental advances over time
Just like right now pretty much all cars have cruise control and some cars have adaptive cruise control
Calibrate speed the next generation of this technology against
Would be you do not have to control the steering wheel either
You get onto the highway
Pickling
And then engage this so super cruise control
An unlikely Str8 self
Brachycephalic
Also imagines and automatic mode for when you're stuck in a traffic jam
And in the number of scenarios dekhtyar automatable will increase over time
And one fine day
Reckless able to control itself completely but it lasted literally minor
Nicki Minaj stab and one would badly noticed at 8
Sowell Raj does see humans as having an important role to play as we transition toward fully automated vehicles
Is go like Chris urmson
Is to eventually get human drivers out of the process entirely
But even when that day finally comes
We don't need steering wheels and don't even notice that they're gone
There will still be active
Stelvio lease be submerged cases
Google
Beyond beyond anybody's control
This is going to be nightmare scenario for all of us researchers
If our somebody deploys something prematurely
And then it turns out that they didn't stop.
Hacking a child of God for bed
If and when people do get hurt in autonomous cars
There may be circumstances in which the passengers wouldn't have been injured have there been a human at the wheel
These cases will be hard to reckon with
But we'll have to keep in mind that there were 30000 Americans dying every year
Inhuman driven cars
If autonomous vehicles lead to fewer Car Act
Then
As with planes
We're going to need to accept edge cases and periodic failures is the cost of living in this safer world
But
I don't want to be an edge
Case I don't want to give up total control of something when being in control might save my life
And yet while I was reporting the story
I almost caused a terrible car accident
It was early the sun was in my eyes and I wasn't really paying attention as I made a left through a crosswalk
And I nearly struck a pedestrian
I got so close that the guy could have reached out and slammed his fist
Imma go to my car
Which he didn't do
So I wouldn't have blamed him if he had
Ennis terrifies me
I want automation to save me and everyone else
From myself
And I want automations protect me from everyone else
And so when the time finally comes
I will probably roll the dice on autonomous cars
I think we all will eventually
Maybe one day I will be in old man bouncing grandkids on my knees saying
You know when I was a young man
We drove cars ourselves
You move them around with foot pedals
And I think all the steering wheel
And they'll say
What sounds amazing
And I'll say
It was all right
99% invisible what produces week by Sam Greenspan with Katie mingle Avery troubleman and me Roman Mars
Reporting
Brunswick
Extra special thanks to Steve Hand and Planet Money the great grade Planet Money
Tristan cook Bob's Red Chris nozzle Joe Brown Katelin jabbari Jackie Miller and Sherry Stokes
This story started life as another story about automatic doors in trains in Argentina but the folks who helped us out
Tomas Momo Sada
The ceremony theorita Catalano Mariano peshala Annie Murphy Jim greller Anna eberstein
And Ernesto and Ricardo Barrera at the association of Tramway friends in Argentina
We are project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce
Are the offices of arcsin a beautiful Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
Cluttered world of man-made sound
If
Listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
But it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter
Funny Instagram Tumblr
Even have a Spotify playlist but you can find the information you need about this show and every other episode we've ever done
A99 pill
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com