99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
A man walks down a dark alley
He's dressed all in black
Black beanie hat black gloves
He approaches a door
Drop the money
Produces from his pocket
A small metal tool
Answers the tool into the keyhole
He definitely slimes the tool around inside the keyhole
Until
He's at
Security
Has been breached
But only in the movies
It's because
Prospective lockpickers take note
You definitely can't do that with just a pic
We're hair pin or Paperclip
There are two tools you need to pick a lock
And one of them is usually left out
When you see people picking locks in movies
This is the part that
Don't forget the tension wrench
This is a tension wrench
The L-shaped piece of metal with the
An L-shaped piece of metal that with one hand you insert at the bottom of the keyhole while the other hand uses the pick 2
Work the pins in the lock
And hold
The walk with a little bit of
Rotational tension
That but away is Leigh Honeywell showing our producer Sam Greenspan
How to pick a lock
Lee is a digital security expert and amateur lock-picking instruct
I taught a bunch of
People how to pick locks
At a feminist science
Fiction convention one year
I met Lee at her office in Sanford
We sat in the conference room among piles of tension wrenches and lock pick
And special practice law
Built for the picking
You have to push each pin up far enough
That
You can't see that bottom part 2
There's two piece
So when you pick a lock you're using the pick and tension wrench
To do the work of the key you need them both
Into
The keyhole
The pursuit of lockpicking is as old as the law
Which is itself as old as civilization
Fire history of the world there was only one brief moments
About 70 years
Were you could put something under lock and key
A chance to save your home
And have complete
Unwavering certainty
That no Intruder could get
A feeling that Security Experts call
Perfect security
And since we lost perfect
Security in the 18th
It has remained elusive
Despite tremendously
Security technology
We have never been able to get
Fox go back at least as far as ancient Egypt
But in March I'm dropping a big paper
Theorizing that the Mesopotamians racks
Ashley the creators
Of the original walk in the beach
The Egyptians then learn it
This is Skyler Town Schuyler town
Security anthropologist
Research scholar
Kimberly Justin
Independent academic of all things related
For the Middle Ages on for hundreds of years
Locks were not very good
If you were poor you can have a terrible lock
And if you had some money you could have a terrible lock with some added features that night at best
Confuse a trespasser
They're just one false keyholes there padlocks even with false keyholes
False keyholes which they hoped would draw the FIFA way from the true Keyhole
Some locks had Falls Keyhole that even had a lock like components of fix to them
So it felt like they were attached to the latch mechanism
But actually weren't
Seriously the best you could do is try to confuse an intruder into picking a fake lock but as soon as the wheel key hole
Was known
The security was pretty much nil
There was no law that could keep
Everyone out
And then in the 1770s
An English guy named Joseph bramah entered the locks
Like a wizard from the future I had to come back in time and invented the most amazing lock in the world
If the name Joseph sounds familiar to you Bello engineering history
Is the same Joseph bramah who invented the flush toilet and the first water pumping fire engine and pneumatic
Tree murdering machine that they would literally just rip a full grown tree out of the ground by its roots
That one wasn't as popular but
Pretty cool
And so Joseph bramah inventor
Time wizard
Tree murderer
He was really interested in locks
You need something called
Appellate
The Brahma Safety Lock
Brahma disconnect
The chi
From the bull
So with the keys doing
An inner chamber of this lock
Take my word for it
Explaining how this thing works does not make
Compelling radio
But the main thing about this lock is it added levels of complexity in between
Key and the vault
It's like a whole Rube Goldberg scenario plays out inside the lock
Akita
And, was so confident in his lock the Republic
Detailing exactly how it works
No more hiding the keyhole or shrouding the locks operation in secrecy
Rama revealed everything about the lock and still claim that it could not be opened without the key
And he also had another idea that would revolutionize locksmith
He also contributes the idea of turning this whole thing into a contest
Showmanship so as soon as he has a padlock version of this lock that he is very confident in
He puts it in the window of his store Piccadilly and he paints on it a message
A challenge
In Gold lettering
Quote
The artist who can make an instrument
They will pick
Or open this lock shall receive 200 guineas the moment it is pretty
200 guineas in 1777 is something north of 20000 British pounds today
Try people actually take a real honest shot
But no one
Not even with their own tools
Could hack it it remained in that window for
70 + years challenging all comers and everybody
Promise new unbeatable lock and the hoopla surrounding it
Caught the attention of the British crown
And they wanted up the game
They wanted a lock
It wouldn't just be Unbreakable
I would also alert the owner if someone tried to get into it
The government-sponsored a contest with a hundred British pounds as reward Jeremiah chubs
Detector lock
And we did this work does that when you lifted one of the Tumblers up too high and see what actually trip
A latching mechanism that would hold that Tumblr up in the air too high
And a wooden drop back down again
A man that happened the Lockwood completely freeze up
Even a kid would know
Until you put a different key and rotated in the opposite direction and reset all of the Tumblers
Interview went to unlock a Chester of alter
Your front door
And the key to your Chubb detector lock didn't work
You would know
Did someone had tried to get into it
And
Did they had fail
Advertisements for the detector lock ran In The Bleak House cereal
Which red
Quote
My name is Chubby
That makes the patent locks
Look upon my works
EBay burglars
Despair
And as these newer and better locks were getting invented
The public spectacle around them
Rose to a fever pitch
At one point they offered a guy in prison parole if he could break the chop block
Breaker heat open many locks and his wife
And he tried and tried and tried and literally who's
Potential Freedom was genuinely on the line
And he had to turn the thing back in so you couldn't do it and you couldn't imagine that anyone could do it
And going forward
The names Brahma and Chubb are basically interchangeable for
Perfect security
But only until
The great La Concha
Of 1850
Travel to London for the first intern
National exhibition of manufactured products
Back in the States Hops and made a name for himself as a sort of white hats
Security consult
Heat over the banks in st. Pete
If I can break the lock on your safe you want to buy one of mine
Give it a shot when he was selling locks like
Crazy
Hobbes was a natural
Naturally
On day one of the exhibition
He publicly announced that he would pick
The chub detect
The one that seizes up if you pick it incorrectly
Hobbs successfully pick the Chubb detector lock-in
The inventor Jeremiah Chubb
Wasn't convinced
He wanted to see Hobbes
Do it again
So another trial
This time in front of auditors
And reporters
Mac Hobbs open the lock again
Take that job
A witness wrote that it's
25 minute
In the way Hobbs did it was to actually use the locker
Against itself
You pick it until he tripped the detector mechanic
Causing a lock to seize up
That would give us information about what was going on inside
And then he would pick the lock any
Opposite to right
Action to reset the detect
He go back and forth firing and resetting the detector
Until the walk told him everything he needed to know about how to get it open
Miss time in 7 minutes
He had complete control over the Chubb lock
It has absolutely been open
But the Chubb detector lock was really just a warm-up
The main event
Was a Brahma Safety Lock
The one that
Talon painted on it in Gold lettering
What you been sitting in Joseph brahmas
Storefront window
70 years
Unbeaten
Taunting lockpickers everywhere
AC Hobbs
Threw down the gauntlet
So trial is conducted against the Brahma lock they give him 30 days to conduct himself against it Joseph
Mama had died by the
And his sons were running a shop
Do you have the room above the store
And Hobbes got to work
Just want to set the lock up in a way that was easy to work on
And he could use all his own tools
Monitors would come check in on him periodically
If you want to bring them this thing for about 52 hours over the course of
214 days
And finally gets it over
And the way that he gets it open is much more like
Serta brute-forcing any kind of designed a method of building a key for it
It wasn't super elegant it couldn't be really easily repeated against the brand new one and some of his methods could have been
Prevented with some slight alterations
But still
Abramowicz
Had been open
When Hobbs open that lock
I
Swear to you the world
Overnight
The feeling of power
Security hat evaporate
And we have never gotten it
Boxmas weren't able to convince the public that perfect
Security could be restored
But they did keep inventing new locks
One such locksmith was Linus Yale Jr
You've probably seen present-day locks with the name Gail on them
That's because he has company was able to mass-produce their locks
Descale that no one ever had
Turlock
In the most common in the world
Nails design patented in 1851 the same year as the Great Law controversy
What's called the pin and Tumbler lock
Is the kind of lock you see everywhere
If you live in an apartment building is almost certainly the same style of lock do you have on your front door of your
Apartment building it's a kind of lock that Lee Honeywell taught me how to
How to pick this is a design it's been
Really commercial
Successful because it's super
Pretty well
The pin tumbler locks be up today or not too different from the pin Tumbler lock
Manufactured
In the common pin Tumbler lock is nowhere near as secure as the Beast that was the Brahma Safety Lock
Which took one of the greatest minds and locksmithing more than 50 hours to defeat
What about 2 hours of instruction in some practice anyone even you
Can pick a simple door lock in a few minutes
And if you're feeling confident in your abilities
You can square off against other lock Pickers
And that's our man Skyler Town competing there that a match in New York City
He's also competed in arguably the World Cup of locks for the Dutch open
Competitive locksport these days isn't so much about
Weather lockscreen
Good morning. How fast
And the locks use for competitions
More complicated than your average door
The lock on your door is so
Easily subvert
Just
Casual
Really I'm almost
People stores
With some skill and patience with a tension wrench and lock pick set
You can get it to almost anyone's house
But you don't even need that much just a few seconds with a crowbar or a brick through a window will do the job nicely
In our homes are
Incredibly
The locks in place now at Banks
Other high-security venues
Are light years beyond what they had them
The average consumer dreadlocks
Give me a call from nearly as much
It's not that we don't need lock
Badoo
We just don't need them to be impenetrable
For actually trusting
Is not
The walk
Wooper trusting
Is our community
We're trusting the sort of social order
In what the lock is now
The walk
Is a social con
As much as it is a mechanic
And soaking a post perfect security world
Most of the lock that we interact with everyday don't in
Inspire us
To trust them
They Inspire us
To trust
Each other
And that's why I $15 log from your local hardware store
Will probably survive
99percentinvisible was pretty so sweet by Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flat pocket
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter or Tumblr Instagram and Spotify
Are you can unpick the lock that is 99% invisible
99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com