99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Off the Southeastern coast of China is a small sweet potato shaped island of Taiwan
Yes I assure you
It is
Sweet Potato Shack
Not regular potatoes
Taiwan is not recognized by the UN as a Sovereign Nation so many people who live there would like it to be
Depending on who you dare ask
Taiwan can be considered a part of China
Orlando Park
Before I travel to Taiwan
I'm embarrassed to admit I wasn't entirely sure where it was
Producer Avery trufelman just back from Taipei
The capital of Taiwan
And a lot of people in Taiwan know this
Fat people like me
Aren't really sure where exactly they are or if they're a country and this is part of why in 19
City of Taipei set out to do something they hoped would
Put them on the map
They set out to build a very
Very
Tall building
Taiwan really need to let the world see it
You know Taiwan has seen such a beautiful Island
This is Michael Lu
He's a representative of taiwan's tallest building
Taipei 101
He says the City of Tempe started with a plan for a 66
Story office
With a high-class Mall food court
M-66 stories was enough to make it among the tallest in the country
The den the city government said all we know we should
Gladys the world's theater we should have a
Big guy Morgan says plan decided to change the plans
Eton building 288 stories
Which would make it the same height as the Petronas Towers in Malaysia
Which were then the tallest buildings in the world
And it was not satisfied
So then
One of the Developers
We should go for her birthday
And so they decided to make it 101 stories
Anthony
Taipei 101
In Chinese philosophy
100 is a Zipcar facts
We're not satisfied with the perfection
Taipei 101
67 feet
Up in the air which is about 508m
It is Bonkers High
It's stick
So far above the rest of Taipei
It looks
It's surreal
You can see it from almost anywhere in the city
Even from neighboring towns
Like a benevolent eye of Sauron
Building something of this size is never easy but I pay an extra optic
In a city prone to earthquakes and typhoons
They had to design a building that could withstand these conditions
And they had to convince the public that this freakishly tall new building was safe
And for a while at least
Taipei 101
But hold the coveted title
Of tallest building in the world
I think
It's fair to say that a large part of the story and history
Pole buildings
Is really wrapped up
With ego
Competition
Optimal so than any other building type
This is Anthony Wood
Executive director of the
The Council on tall buildings and urban habitat
They are the organization that gives out that official title of
Tallest building in the world
Yeah we have a very big ruler
And we send someone on socket
No it's it is all based on
On drawings on submit
Drawings
And it's important to have a fair an official measurement process because a tall tall building always represent
Something larger than itself
Historically a tall building was the embodiment of
Corporate power and you could see that in the titles of the pro jet
Pence Chrysler Building
Chicago Tribune Tower or Sears Tower
But in the last couple of decades the agenda has shifted
The motivation is the same in terms of getting attention I'm getting Brandon but it's now Moline clay
To befall a city
People and economy
Country
Which is why projects are now more likely to be named for places
Like Shanghai Tower
Doha Convention Center
Dubai One
Signature Tower Jakarta
Mecca Royal Clock Tower
And Taipei 101
How tall tower is a way to show the world
We have arrived
The question I typically get asked
Space
How high can we go
Most people think that the limits on high off technology
Nicole
And I can tell you that that no
Really the height of a tower is
The product of its base
And as long as you've got a big enough area at the base of the
The tower
It's just down to Structural Engineering that you can go as high as you
Necessary
Which means the only real limits
AR resources
And will
The main limit
Is financial
That's the only limit on tall buildings really is who the hell is going to pay for it
And then should it be done in the first place
In Taipei securing funding for their new building with a huge endeavor
Is Taipei 101 representative Michael lucak
This was a public-private partnership
R a handful of local financial institutions signed on as shareholders
Including Taiwan stock exchange
And a lot of local bangs and some telephone company but local and getting the rest of the city on board with this
Plan meant taking a lot of different considerations into account
Light commercial flight pattern
When we proposed it is a big big challenge renovation Department
Type is airport is right in the middle of a city
So we went to a very very difficult time you need to talk to them
And
You know knowledge of the city but also the the country
Recognize that we need this
To really go for
The tallest in the world and then saw the end
The fly detour
Because if
The land was sad
The air was cleared
The city of Taipei was ready to create a building that would be the tallest in the world
Now they had to make it look good
The important thing is that you have to design building to be really iconic
Otherwise you cannot become a landmark
That is C Wiley
He's a bona fide Stark attack
Kid already designed big buildings and other cities in Taiwan and all-around China when he started planning this project
Back in the late 90s
He wanted this new building to be
Look different from skyscrapers in the West
Imitate like mod a Chinese Pagoda
So some more like a high-rise Pagoda
Super elongated
Multi-tiered Pagoda
Covered in
Sea Green Glass
Olympic a little bit light green mucus looks of record in this Pagoda is divided into 8 segments because
Eight in Chinese sounds like the word for wealth
Because that building is a financial building and for even more luck and wealth are a giant gold coins on all fours
Four sides of the base of the building
And for extra extra good luck the corners of the tower are accented with representations of
Clouds
And Dragons
The Cornell I have so many kind of a small thing that's expressed a dragon
Protectors of the building
In Taipei 101 needs
All the protection it can get
It is in what I like to call a tough neighborhood
That's Leonard Joseph
Thornton Tomasetti
They provided the Structural Engineering Services
Does on Taipei 101
You have both
Typhoons that are
Significantly more severe than
The Hurricanes we see you in the eastern US
And it is an active seismic
Until thing about having both harsh winds and seismically-active ground is that in an earthquake you want a flexible belt
So you would
Really would like a nice cool Timber structure
An earthquake zone kind of roll with the flow
When the wind blows that limber structure
Sways too much and people get seasick
One of the ways to lessen that sway
Is with a tuned Mass damper
A wind damper or a tuned Mass damper is basically a counterweight to wins
Tuned Mass dampers appear in many forms
These can be weights on rollers
Blocks of concrete suspended in pools of water or oil
Or
In the case of Taipei 101
A gigantic pendulum
By having a 2 Mass damper having this big pendulum
Has the building sways
And this business pendulum is designed to sway at about the same rate
The pendulum will handle a behind the building moves a pendulum follow
Slows the sway of a building
Tower would still stand without a
But the people inside might feel seasick or they might just be unnerved by the fact that they're building is Wayne
The damper
Is typically intended
Just to improve occupy
Comfort having a temper is not unique there are lots of buildings that have one
What's unique about Taipei 101
Is the way they've turned it into an ass
Usually the Denver gets treated like another piece of machinery
Velvet looks at it says
Well if I have to I'll put it in
I don't want to but if I got it all right
It takes up space
It cost me money I got to maintain it I got to buy it you know it's a thing
That they have to pay for
And so if there's a damper at all it's usually hidden away
You're the top of the building in some sort of machine room or attic space
Put in Taipei 101 the wind damper isn't just visible
It's the main attraction
So of course
Avery went to see it
This is like the 90
First
Oh my God my ears are
Okay now we are walking into the tunnel where it says
Giant Windber with her friends bike
Come here
This is
This is the pig camper
It is a massive
Massive pendulum
An orb made of 41 stacks of solid steel
Wayne 728 tons
According to an informational video elephants
It's suspended by 4 bundles of thick cables
And all of it
Has been painted
Goal
Really surreal again
Just kind of
Dystopian
If you're coming today
Gigantic
Golden orb
Paris
And the damper is on display because the engineering at work
Make people feel safe
Even in today's volatile climate you don't need to worry about the title
Even the Wave A Lot in Taiwan in December but
You don't need to worry
And to promote their awesome damper
Taipei 101
When even a step further
We hire the San Diego company Hello Kitty
So they created Denver babies
Powerball
The Denver babies are little cartoon figures that have a body like the orb of the damper
The big head and little arms and legs
Becoming black red
Yellow
Silver and green
Can you get to this corner
Next to the damper itself you can watch a little video with a damper babies
Explain how the damper works
Are the Denver like that so terrible
Sway in a strong wind
By the way the damper babies are in speaking Chinese
Where Taiwanese
Or Japanese
They speak their own made-up cutesy language
But the video is subtitled
With all the information about the damper
And the Denver babies decorate the hallways leading to and from the damper itself
It's a whole wall of glowing damper babies
Music kind of rules
In all different forms of taipei101 gift shops sell all kinds of damper baby souvenirs and Webster
A lot of different kind of Prada
That's we have bugs we have
Cops
Sweetheart
Amox
So we have you know hats
I totally bought some damper baby stuff
A lot of other tourist
Just so funny to me that this huge crowd was geeking out about a tuned Mass damper
The factory
Been taking a stage further and used as a
Tourist object
Does just smile really
Anthony Wood of the Council on tall buildings and urban habitat says the damper help keep taipei101 on the glow
Global stage
Long after it lost its title as the world's tallest building
What position is held from 2004
And I'm yes the world has largely move. We now have an 828 me to building
In the bridge Khalifa Dubai
The Burj Khalifa in Dubai took the title of tallest building in the world in 2010
As we record this it is still the tallest building in the world
It's over
Thousand feet
Taller than Taipei 101
163 stories it is
Staggeringly
The US may have once led the race for the tallest buildings but now most of the contenders are in East Asia and the men
At least according to the Council on tall buildings and urban habitat taipei101 is currently the fifth tallest build
World
But at the rate that super-tall buildings are being erected that ranking won't last very long
The council to find buildings that are taller than 300M
Or 984 feet
As super tall building
Right now there are a hundred supertall buildings in the world
In fact if we go back 5 years
There were only 50 super-tall buildings complete in the will
ATL to use to come to fruition
And the next 50 super tall buildings were completed in 5 years which shows
The absolute massive boom that tall buildings have been going through in the last decade or so
Supertall buildings can't just depend on their height anymore for notoriety
And this is why I taipei101 try to rack up all the superlatives you could
Including the biggest wind damper in the world
Fastest elevators in the world
And tallest leed-certified green building in the world
Which is a little bit of a a marketing thing but
Which shows the commitment you know what shows this commitment to progressing not building
Beyond just hate we're going to build the world's tallest
After all the title of world's tallest building is earned slowly and lost
Quickly
A lot of things
Pull together for beauty
Tallest building in the world
It's a contest that Architects C Wiley isn't planning on throwing his hat into again
Do you think you'd ever do it again would you dissolve
No that was quick why
I think the one is enough
99% Invisible Boy produce this week by Avery Trucking
We can't even Goldstein Greenspan Delaney Hall Sharif Youssef Kolstad and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Carol Willis and the Skyscraper Museum in New York
Mantis bite or tea
We are production of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco introduced of the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Percent
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again
Again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
You can find this show and like to show on Facebook you can follow each member of the production team on Twitter and Instagram but the best
Best way to explore the 99% invisible activity that
Shapes the design of our world
To spend as much time as possible and 99 pi
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com