99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
So tell me why this isn't a repeat
Goatman
In the first story we talk to Doctor Keith
Okay
In the first story we talk to doctor Q at MIT and he told me how America you
Used to be all about the
Serpentine line the first
Come first serve
This is where one line serves all the available register is like the way the airline ticket counter used to be
Or Wendy's
Changing the American Experience of waiting in line
He said that I was onto something
Priority line is where you pay to get to the front of the line
Exclusive
Shorter
Faster-moving one
All right I think that's good
That is Benjamin Walker
I hear all about cute earring design check out episode number 49 of 99% invisible
Benjamin Walker is Q obsessed
He also did a half hour radio documentary on priority queues
For the BBC
I took a trip a
Across the country
Tree and I visited
Highways
Amusement park
Community colleges
Who was using these priority queues and how they work
But the other thing I found out is that
Can actually help us understand
All the fighting that's going on
Over the internet
You mean like on a message board
Talking about the internet internet
The wires and the pipes
Where do we start
We start with Netflix
Chief product officer at Netflix and I've been here for about 10 minutes
And
Built a lot of the technology that we refuse to fill both the DVD service and now the streaming service
News accent has faded a bit
You can hear he's a Brit
Back 13 years ago I was incorrectly more
British
Speaking that I am today and
Tilda comes naturally to a bread this
Does it worth to you
In addition it's it's a computer science technology watusi
Motivations for that happening
When I
Drafted the original specification for the thing that you was going to The Logical what to use and it kind of slipped into
Product usage
Americans generally don't use the word cue and referring to an ordered list or line until
Netflix
Is very clear to me at least
Within in a month to
Refusing a lot that it would probably was the wrong way
For the US market
People see this word q u e u e
And they have no idea how to pronounce it
Way too many weird pronunciations of that word
From quetta que yo to
All kinds of weird and wonderful things that it's him
Quite bizarre
And so I have been lobbying for about a decade to change the word Q2
A list
Something different
Unfortunately
The marketing department was very attached to the ownable
Qy because it's such an unusual had it since it's honorable from a brand perspective
And so are
With that we've been that you think you ever sent to a Netflix US somewhat inextricably linked together I think
In the consumers mind here in the US
Oatmeal it seems that you might
Single-handedly
Responsible
For how many Americans
Know this word today
I would say that you could make a case
Because of Netflix
That this word even has a
Understanding
Recognition
That's out there today
It seems like a really comes out of you
Well I guess that's possible indeed I have to say this probably thinks that I'm more proud of introducing
Does the US consume early American public
That's possible that that's one of them
No Coast
Most of our business is streaming
The
The Q is a much less
Relevant and much less important piece of
How we do business
Netflix's future is not in DVDs
But the queue is still Central to Netflix's existence
Because
Of Comcast
85% of Americans who want a high-speed wired connection to their home in the next
5 years or so
Their only choice will be there local
And in 22 of America's 25 largest
That local incumbent
Comcast
So they're the information
Not just
Internet access
Ryder Rochester
Entertainment provider not just
Sports
There every
Susan Crawford is a law in public
Public policy professor
And writer
And her upcoming book
Captive audience
She warns that Comcast is using its
Power and Market domination
What companies like Netflix
Let's say I'm sick one day and I watch
A whole bunch of episodes
Mad Men
Over my neck
And then I wake up in Exmore
And my Broadband bill is
Higher
Because I watched
That's what Comcast
Is trying to put in
Place
This idea that
Any video from anybody other than them
Will is going to do nothing but make your Broadband Bill higher
It's actually
Brutal
Because what it does is train consumers
Not to want to watch now
Netflix
And this practice of treating Comcast
Streaming video differently than
HBOGo Hulu and Netflix
Has been criticized publicly by the CEO of net
Netflix Reed Hastings in particular
And net neutrality advocates in general
The idea of net neutrality
At least all the data of a given type
Sol video should arrive
Your computer or
Or TV
Without any prioritization or discrimination based on
Where that video is coming from
Susan Crawford may be able to watch Mad Men all day long but
Her concern about the cable companies in net neutrality goes Way Beyond
Focusing on Netflix in some ways is a little misleading because it's just an application like another
Imagine instead
Backup of all your files on your computer
Really good connection to do that
What is the standing in the middle
Who could charge whatever he wanted to for your ability to run your business
Any high bandwidth Apple
Is actually
Subject to this kind of highway robbery
Comcast cable
What Susan Crawford wants us to understand is that if companies like Comcast succeed and cable eyes and be in
Internet Denzel routinely use their power to single out a type of service or a type of data
And prioritize some and discriminate against others
Was not how the internet was originally designed the funk
Totally
Different
Model
We have these two models that are clashing
Like planet
And1 model
Definitely
The other planet is the basic idea telecommunications in
Where everybody gets the same service
At a reasonable price and that allows all kinds of interesting things to happen
It was called
Common carriage
Which war
Universal service
Basic ideas that everybody is a
Society gets access
Common carrier is this is really what's at the heart of a net neutrality
The debate is the idea that
Access to telecommunication
Be transparent
Affordable Fair
And predictable
Sort of like a good old-fashioned
Q
Q-Zar the essence of democracy
In that they're predictable you can see when you're going to get to the front of the line no one gets special treatment
But you're all standing in line and take your policing
Each other someone cuts in line people get prettier at 8
The opposite of that innocence is a system that's only driven by money
Where people buy preference
To get to their place in line or decide what
Services they get ax
What happened in communication
Is that what we used to think of as a
Basic affordances everybody got at a reasonable price
Has become more and more
Within the sphere of
Markets
The problem with attaching
A market
Communications
Is that is ideal
Predictability
Knowing what you're going to get it being treated just
The same as everybody else
Goes out the window
Net neutrality Advocates like Susan Crawford argue that cable companies like Comcast
Need to be policed and regulated
Because they don't consider their networks parts
Of America's information infrastructure
This is why we never had a telephone nutria
Because the telephone
Was considered a vital component of
America's Telecommunications
It used to be that all Americans had itself
And they could call anybody they wanted to that was our basic Communications
We subsidize the very poorest Americans
Be sure to have a telephone line
And the telephone company had no say over what business
To transact
Using that
As time went by
Cable actor
Garden
Providing
Telephone
Tazewell
Now internet
They
Don't see themselves
What's as providing Democratic public service
And they
Really held onto the right to
Just charge whatever they want
For access
That wire and raise prices
If you like it
The cable companies argue
The net neutrality regulations will be burdensome and unnecessary
Market competition they say Protect
The American Consumer
But Susan Crawford who was part of Obama's 2009 FCC transition team
Says competition
Disappeared a long time ago
We used to think that competition
Between the telephone
Cableguys
Would protect
And on that basis back
Wheatie regulator the entire sector
No more Federal oversight go ahead charge whatever you want
Because competition will be the cop on the beat
If you remember back over a decade ago there used to be
Internet service
And it never really occurred to me why
All those options went away and
Cable company became the only option for a lot of people when it come
High speed internet
It all boils down to something
Fundamental
The internet
The wires
The telephone companies
Old copper wiring
That couldn't handle internet
Network traffic
And they just kind of gave up
Telephone companies realized it was just too expensive
The dig up
Can old copper wires and replace them
By contrast
All the cable companies have to do to upgrade the service they are
Copper is to update the electronics
Don't have to dig up the wire just
What new gear on the back of your wires
Which is really cheap
Comparison of cost advantage on the cable side has been so great
The telephone companies have simply dropped out
And the cable companies won by default
Leaving us with
Actually no cop in the beat we've got the worst of Both Worlds
Neither competition nor oversight
In the end it's more like the worst of three world
Because
When we turn over the future of the internet to a cable company
Susan Crawford says
We don't
Even get a few
What is all amounts to
Is nothing more than just
Entertainment
Rather than something that produces new forms of
Making living new jobs
New ways of
Venting
Valuable things
The world we won't have that sandbar
Other country
But we won't
In America may have to get used to being at the back of the line
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Benjamin Walker from the radio program too much in
Information from WFMU
With a Little Help From Me Roman Mars and Sam Greenspan
We are project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco in the American is due to
What's in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world
Man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
Can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us her on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more of
About this story including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero and
In the movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast. Com