99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It's hard to overstate the vest
Of the skid row neighborhood in LA
It spans roughly 50 blocks which is about 1/5
The entire downtown area of Los Angeles
In some ways the streets
Skid Row are built like other parts of LA
That's reporter Carla Greene
There corner stores in Street vendors selling everything from jewelry to loose cigarettes
The Old Brick
Townhouses filled with low income housing
Their parts were grown-ups gather to talk
Children gather to play
But it's also very clear When you entered Skid Row
The one thing there's the smell
Streets of skid row off Instinct of urine and other excrement
Baking under the hot Los Angeles Sun
The gutters are lined with
The trash
The sidewalks are mostly and on some blocks entirely
Occupied by
People's make sure
Shift homes
A dizzying array of tarps and Tents
Stretch out for blocks and blocks
One structured reading up against the next
Nginx
And there are lots of people on the street
Many of them pushing special red shopping carts
The carts are handed out by a local advocacy group because the police used to arrest people for having what they believed worst
Stolen shopping cart
It's all a person got to do is just be homeless and come here
You're standing at a register give you a shopping cart
People
Using music to put their property around and stuff like that in
Panda Pop Statham
That's General dogon walking around skid row with me
Is a community organizer and lifelong resident of the neighborhood
Has lived in both low-income housing and on the street
So this year so I'm born and raised on Skid Row my parents met
Joe Kenda 50
They both got a job at Bullock's department store
7th and Broadway
When I went to lunch
Fell in love I was born nine months later in general hosp
And I've been down ever since
Walking through skid row it's not hard to see when you reach the edge
The line that divides Skid Row from the rest of downtown
And if you stand right there you'll notice that you're at the intersection of two radically different neighborhood
So Main Street is a divider line
Mainstreeters / between 1/2 and 1/2.
Because you got homeless people
Does sleeping on one side of street in The Loft buildings on the other side of street
And some of the homeless people lay down and they can look up
End in Los Angeles
That dividing line between Haves and Have Nots
Skid Row in the rest of downtown
It wasn't drawn by Axel
Result of a very specific plan
Homeless people on one side
And development
On the other
Explain that someone surprisingly
Was written and fought for by advocates
Skid Row's resident population
Back in the early 20th century
The railroad went through downtown Los Angeles
Right around where Skid Row is now
And like many other cities around the country
A neighborhood formed around the train tracks
What what what do we have in front of us
The first thing Ryan Atkins a Los Angeles CA
A beautiful yeah it's enough for 1909
And the reason I
About the sound is
Pictorial hair 19 + 9 actually predate
Back on the area now known as Skid Row started to develop
There weren't any zoning laws in LA to say what types of developments were allowed in different areas
And so what about the time you can have the Confluence of
The real
And the Los Angeles
Produce in agricultural markets at the same point
Which brought a large transient population
The railroad workers
And agricultural workers
I've gone through the archives of the LA Times
Dimensions of skid row back
100 years ago
Around the turn of the century
Blasey of the UCLA emeritus
Professor was a housing and homeless advocate in and around Skid Row back in the 70s and 80s
So it grew up around the Rail Yards around downtown
And the people that were referred to in the LA times as for example bums
All the way up into the 70s
Most people in Skid Row live in cheap apartments
Single room occupancy hotels or
Sros
They're homeless people but
Fewer than there are now
Was
Homelessness was just
Again General dogon who's living in Skid Row in the south
So you had a
You had occasional rhinos inventory on with white males
Indominus you drink white board and all that kind of stuff
Skid-row was not yet the sprawling tent city that it would go on to become
But it was still considered a rough neighborhood where people went to seek out drugs
Or drink all day and sleep on benches
And homeless population was growing
A skid row grew the greater downtown area of La was also growing
Developing
Developers
Didn't like what was happening in Skid Row
Stop for example the Union Rescue Mission
I was on Main Street
And there were lots of people there and it was full all the time there were people lined up outside a lot of activity there
There was simply an open-air drug Market
Around the corner of 5th and Main Street
And so a plan emerged in 1972
A plan drafted by group of businesspeople and endorsed by many City officials
Remove Skid Row population out
Enveloped the area for new more money resume
It was known as the Silver Bullet
That was essentially
To raise Skid Row
Take everyone out
Bulldoze buildings
Start fresh
Of course residents of skid row and their Advocates didn't like this new plan
And they began thinking about how to fight it
One of those people was Charles elsasser
A young lawyer at the
Who remembers coming across some research
It showed that when you bulldoze a neighborhood like Skid Row
It just means more Skid Row like neighborhood pop-up Elsa
What I did when we weren't quite sure whether it was true and such
True or not
The theory
Was useful
But it was it was it was a very can
Useful
Theory
For purposes of saying this is a mistake
Did that whole idea was a mistake
The theory that Skid Row will just pop up somewhere else in Fresno
Smoove
Scared people who didn't want skedros residents to end up in their neighborhood
Some of these scared people join the skid row activist cause
And the activist
We're happy to have them
It really did
You know come up with this
Idea that
IDE samskara Lee
Support
But also really really help
The Advocate
And so
Armed with their one study
Elsasser and other activists came up with an idea to replace the silver book plan
Which would bulldoze Skid Row
With another one
Here's Jeff Dietrich who helped write the new plan
We develop was called the Blue Book
Jeff Dietrich and his wife
Kathryn Morris
I've been longtime advocates for
The homeless
They run a well-known Soup Kitchen in Skid Row called the hippie
The Bluebook plan was this
To contain the spread
Skid Row
It's basically what's it called the containment plan
This new plan will call it the containment plan from here on out
Propose some pretty radical ideas
Including getting all the missions
Going to Charities and other homeless services
To physically move their offices
So they be within the newly drawn borders of
Skid Row
Again
Gary blasi
The deal was
All the services that tend to attract
Homeless people will be concentrated
To the east of Spring Street
And
Here in exchange for that
The Redevelopment agency will not only not bulldoze all of the sros but it will
Also find a separate nonprofit called the SRO housing
The SRO Housing Trust would be charged with protecting and maintaining a whole slew of low income housing in Skid Row
The actor who spent several months
Writing and developing the containment plan
Any work every angle trying to get the city to take it serious
So
Someone knew someone
In the city council
That's Kathryn Morris
Explaining that they got someone to distribute a draft of the plan to everyone on City Council
And so
They agreed
That while there was a lunch break
That they would bring these and put them at every
So the people came back in the council
Came back in
Shut down
Picked up first thing on there
Paging through this where this come from I don't know where it came from
The containment plan was enough of a compromise that somehow
Amazingly
It went out
It wasn't a legally binding agreement but
I want you to find the city's approach to
Skid Row
For decades
And it was a totally unique approach
Who said no one else was doing what they were doing
Nobody really seems to have done it sent
Elsasser says he's worked on lots of campaign
To save skid-row like neighborhoods
Housing projects in the 70s
But Skid Row was the only time he's used containment
Ed Estrada
The containment plan Mayberry suggestions on how to keep
Skid Row types within the new borders of the neighborhood
There's a section of the plan called inducements
That reads
Toilet public restrooms benches
Pleasant Open Spaces within the contained area of Skid Row
The residents might be inclined to confine their activities to
The immediate area
That section would serve as a magnet
Ahold undesirable population Alamo
In Skid Row
Not against their will
But of their own accord
And the plant talks about a buffer zone
Which would create a border between skid row and the rest of downtown
Strong Edge
Will act as buffers
Skid row and the rest
Central City
When the skid row resident enters the buffer
The psychological comfort
Familiar skid-row environment
Will be lost
You will feel for it
And will not be inclined to travel far from the area of containment
Payment policy was officially adopted in 1976
City started to implement it
Including many of the meticulous and uncomfortable suggestions of how exactly to contain Skid Row's population
Like the buffer zone
And I don't remember how I know this but I do remember learning app is bad
Graduate students from
USC you were hired basically to shadow people living in Skid Row
Answer keep track on a map of where they went
Answer the question was how
Bronner buffer zone did you need
How far do people Wander from Skid Row
And I think the determination was made that you need a buffer about 2 blocks
The city also began using unpleasant design like annoying bright lights on Skid Row's bordering Street
To keep homeless people from wanting to expand their territory
A Main Street always had the regular Fantasy Life
Directions to old metal
What's the best down
And that was it
General dogon
It's all when they start
Building The Lofts on Main
They came pacifically and they put these big ass
Prison life
I know they found no prison lights when I see you
All right about this big and a brown can go over there and look at it
Targeting
People who like me who come outside the SRO and smoke cigarettes hang out front of the building or
And then there was a more aggressive measures
If you stayed within the borders of skid row very lazy says
The cops might not bother you
But
Yeah if you crossed over
That border then if you
Looks like you might belong on skid-row the cops were going to stop
The containment Zone made some
Practical sense both for the city and the resident
Skid Row
But it's also an uncomfortable dehumanizing idea
Is Warehouse
Warehouse
Is what
Is where you store
Great
If so
You're the idea was to push all of the city of Los Angeles
Is unfavorable citizen
Right in one general area
Elsasser the lawyer who helped write the plan says
If the way it's written sound unempathetic or even
Defensive
That's because
They weren't trying to run a PR campaign
They weren't trying to change politicians Minds about Skid Row's residence
They were desperately frantically trying to save Skid Row from being paved over
And containment was better than doing nothing
He always spoken of it rather derisively maybe we could have thought of a better name
What is better than the Federation
Yeah I guess you didn't catch that would be better than in obliteration plan
For better or worse over the course of just a few years La Skid Row became the place to go
So if you are homeless in Los Angeles
Some hospitals would even discharge patients there if they didn't have a fixed address
God in south-central you know
Roundabout
You know there's very few service providers
They give 24-hour access
There's no place
You know out of South Central Community
Well home people can go to in everyday get three meals be able to go take a shower baby
Bathroom stuff like that
Car trade in one area
So
Out in South Central if you homeless
If it draws you to Skid Row
La was fumbling all of its homeless people to Skid Row
And in the 1980s the homeless population of
Los Angeles begin
Explode
Crack was decimating black communities across the city
And many of these newly addicted people
We're going to Skid Row
Today there's a new epidemic
Smokable cocaine
Otherwise known as
Super addictive and deadly cocaine concentrate the crack problem has become a crack crisis and it's spreading Nationwide
What is an explosively destructive and often lethal substance
Which is crushing its users
In the midst of the crack epidemic
Back in the escalating War on Drugs
Reagan aggressively cut back the welfare state
Which drastically shrink the space
Between poverty
Skid Row I wasn't mostly white male alcoholic
One thing I became overwhelmingly black
You started seeing families in the street
People might have otherwise taken a room in single-occupancy hotels
Just enough for the money
3 days in a motel
In LA with three with with 200 dollars
Tell people like hell I'm not going to keep my $200 and get it
And save my money to eat on
Gary blasi was young Advocate at the legal aid Foundation
He remembers us
Skid-row was so crowded
I felt unsafe
I want from
You would see you know a few people in a block to you would see a hundred people
Autoblog
Meaning of basically
People wear shoulder to shoulder
And so the density was just
I mean it was like it was a completely insane
Price
Blasey remembers that
For Christmas of 1984 in an effort to get folk some shelter he and some other Advocate set up two big tents with a bunch of
Cots on an empty patch of land just opposite City Hall
Pretty soon there were
800 people sleeping on cots in those shots
The last couple of decades conditions on Skid Row have changed a bit there are fewer homeless people
They are no longer sleeping shoulder-to-shoulder on the street
But skid row has endured as a place for homeless people to live and find services
Even as other skid-row style neighborhoods around the country
We're eating up by gentrification and their residents were scattered around their respective cities
Over the years
The sense of community and skid row has only gotten stronger
Has become not just a hub for social services
But for activism
From poverty and homelessness
And we always seen it afternoon
Right
I get more a how you doing brother what's up how you doing
Skid Row
Then I do when I walk on the
The Java file
This is a community
Dalian
We work
To make this a community
Apart from the containment plan there's another major reason why skid row has not been taken over by new apartment buildings
And that's
Zoning
Aside from the single room occupancy hotels in a bit of other low-income housing that was grandfathered in
Most of skid row is zoned industrial other than commercial
Or residential
Again city planner Brian
In the eastern half of skid row where it is zoned Industrial
That has
Precluded the expansion or the ability to create a new housing
But all of that could soon change
Los Angeles is currently undertaking a Total Recall of its zoning code
Starting with downtown
And a lot of skid row that was formerly zoned Industrial
Will probably be rezoned as mixed use
There are a lot of vacant buildings in Skid Row
And the city would like to make some of that real estate available for housing
Many residents of skid row would love to have new housing
They've been asking for it for years
Having more housing has been been something that they have
Expresses is something that
Critical for the neighborhood
Having grocery stores with Vino healthy and accessible and cheap food
The city is basically saying in order to give you housing
We have to rezone
Let's get real residents want new housing in the neighborhood to be affordable
And that isn't something that can be dealt with through zoning
Zoning can say whether an area is industrial or residential or mix
I can't say if housing will be affordable
That would have to be done legislatively
Some residents believe
Political leaders could find a way to build affordable housing in the neighborhood
But instead
No use the rezoning process as an excuse
Open up the real estate market and get them out
Like Craig r
Do you want to give me his last name but
He's a longtime resident of Skid Row
And he says zoning is just a tool
The tool they want to use
Get rid of homeless people
And create this new
Location program uses only
They've they're planning on making billions of dollars
By pushing us out squeezing us out or kicking us out
Meaning of support People to disadvantaged People
Butler homeless and n+
The residents of the neighborhood
Even without zoning change
Skid Row is getting smaller
Containment was never a legally binding agreement in the city seems to be increasingly less Guided by
Is a whole neighborhood
Actually that juts up again skid row that used to essentially be a part of it
The new hip neighborhood filled with art galleries in sheet Cafe
It's called
The artist
Tennessee areas around Skid Row have continued to identify
Taking bites out of the edges
The neighborhood
Skid Row itself has changed
Including General.
Police car
In 2006
Citylife they call us a precisionist
Which brought a Huntington extra police Skid Row
But I containment zone is being broken up
Busted up by the police
The police come in
Swinging billy club people
To spread out
And so that's why you got the chance all by the freeway all over here
Because people say
You'll be over here on 43rd Street in my tent
Play chill out on San Julian Street
Against the wall being jacked up three or four times
Back in 1976
Swen elsasser and Morris and other activists came up with the containment plan they included a map
That laid out exactly what the borders of skid row would be
They were trying to make a deal. Kind of compromise
We'll stay over here
Just don't try to push us out with new development
Animals that contain
Just a couple weeks ago is Skipper residence and activist we're out on the street fighting for those same borders
The ones from the 1970s
Containment plan
But with a different attitude
But I'm trying to contain Skid Row
They're trying to contain
Develop
Or at least
The luxury housing development that
Currently being considered
Right at the edge of the sky
It's a 33-story high-rise apartment building
Just need approval from the local councilman
Move forward
About two dozen people at the protest
Including General dogon
This is ours
Don't build here
They're saying
Or else
La Skid Row was not the first
Skid Row Avery Chapman has a story of what is rumored to be the first use
Of the phrase
After this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Some of this video with a rich Hoffman and Quintanilla you were doing a story in Seattle
Where
You ended up on another Skid Row
And not just
Any skid row it was maybe where the name Skid Row comes from
And if you go to Seattle
And you go downtown
Yuan counter place called Pioneer Square
Should actually a triangle and it is the tourist area and
Seattle
Used to be a really big logging town
And the mill used to be right downtown so
Loggers will go up into the hills and chop down these massive huge
Trees and they lubricate them with fish oil
And hook the logs up to
The teams of oxen and mules
And then would run the logs down this road over the mountain that would be called dragon or skidding
The Lox
Skating the logs
Makes this road the skid
Wrote it was called skid Road
With a D
According to my guide Dina Jerian
And that street is now called yesler way because Henry yesler was the owner of the mill at the end of the street where the logs are being
Get it down to
And the smell
Is also very close to the seaport
And so here in this part of town
You got
The sailors
Who are taking their Shore leave and then these loggers or like
A lot of guys around
And they got these hard jobs
With long periods of downtime
They are looking for action and fun luckily
Seattle in this area in the skid row was here provide
Before there was Vegas
Sin City was right here
M bars lot of brothels
So this is the original Skid Row
Maybe maybe
Term of the logging industry in other parts of the world
I don't know if those other skid roads also developed like bars and red light districts in Reno
Rough attitudes but
That's definitely what happened in Seattle
More about that in the future story
Thanks for stopping in thank you
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Carla Green Mix and Tech production by Sharif
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer cholestatic is the digital director
Avery trufelman play
Play The Voice
The rest of the team is Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall
Aaron Massey
And me
Special thanks to John malpiede and Henriette Brouwer's
Los Angeles poverty
They have a number of really interesting exhibitions on Skid Row's history and present at their space in downtown Los
Thanks also to Linus shentu and everyone at the Los Angeles Community Action Network
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco in produce
Sun radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX that Collective with the best most Innovative best-looking show
Shows and all the podcast
We are supported by the Knight foundation and coin carrying donors
Just like you
You find the show into a discussion about the show on Facebook even tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
What are true home on the web
Is 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com