99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
So many classic movies have been made in downtown Los Angeles
Even if they didn't take place in downtown Los Angeles
It's always fun when you watching a movie that take place in New York and you spot a palm tree
Palm trees are just one of the factors that a location scout has to worry about
Most films they really have to avoid them
It's at a cost
Lori Bolton is a location scout in LA
She's worked on Inception heat A River Runs Through It
Whole Lotta movie
She was the first ever location professional ever asked to join the academy
You're not the only one I am the only one the first and the only yeah
On location with Lori is producer Avery trufelman
Lawry's job is to find interesting
Plot conducive locations
Lots of them are frequently will show someone over a hundred different options for one location you know before they get a sense of what they
But Scouts also have to make sure that the locations they find are actually usable
So big part of Lawry's job is convincing Property Owners to say yes
Part would she is really really good at
I just want to show her
She's from Oak
Lori sweet-talked our way up to the top floor
City Hall
Up to a panoramic view of Los Angeles
Surf Great River
So you know Emily has its problems but I think any location person you talk to
Really proud of the city and the variety of locations and how much fun it is to dino drive around and discover
Everything
From the top floor balcony
We could see the massive City unfurling around us
Emily pointed out all of her favorite location
There's so much variety here it's amazing
But even with all the architectural variety of Los Angeles
Some buildings just keep coming back on screen
Again and again
Those architectural gems are very
Particular and very kind of
Binding
It's someone's watching it for like pina 10 minutes going like this feels so familiar what is this location
I know I know it and then I'll just
Oh my God that's the Bradbury Building
The Bradbury Building
Arguably the biggest architectural movie star of Los Angeles
It's one of Lori's favorite locations
It can be modern that can be.
It's kind of
Upscale steampunk
The iron work
Open balconies
Just beautiful building
The Bradbury made his first on-screen appearance in 1943
In the movie China Girl
When it played at Burmese Hotel
It played a London military hospital and white
The Dover
It was the background of the Fillmore style Thriller DOA in 1950
Model
In the 1969 movie Marlowe
Bruce Lee steps into an office of the Bradbury
And kicks all the furniture apart
Who played in office again in the final scene of 500 Days of Summer
Next to me
It was a movie studio in the artist
It was a chocolate factory in a recent commercial for Twix
But the Bradbury's most famous role of all was as the toymaker's house
In the 1982 movie
Blade Runner
In Blade Runner the Bradbury is a dark Moody ruin
Which seems like some real Hollywood magic when you see what the building actually looks like
From the outside the Bradbury just looks like a brick office
This building at the corner of 3rd and Broadway downtown
Kind of unremarkable
But then you step inside and it's like
Is this great
Biblical shaft of light shining through it
It's basically a tall narrow Courtyard Walden with terracotta covered with a glass ceiling and flanked by two
Do iron clanking hydraulic powered elevators
The kind that are still run by human operators
Avery Road in one
Cheap is it at the building
Thank you
There's a reason the Bradbury is in so many films
For 1
It's really beautiful
For the tile
Steps are marble
Annies
Floor in the atrium with a layer of ornate
Wrought iron balcony
But it's not just Aesthetics
You have the balcony isn't all of the different levels and you can shoot across and down and
Catty-corner the balconies allow the crew to shoot at many different angles
And create a whole range of different moods
For various genres
The romantic comedy would probably be straight on the horror movie would be more shooting up shooting damage in that sense
Vertigo and the Bradbury can accommodate all the film gear
I just have to get in so many toys you know the lights in the boom arm and this and that
But look at the ceiling height this is great
Hosts of the Bradbury is near a parking lot
Which is surprisingly crucial
Because it don't shoot involves Vans and trailers and tons of people and tons of equipment
And the parking lot is the place to put it all
It's also nice that the Bradbury is close to downtown and the crew can just go grab lunch
It is
There's like nothing like it in Los Angeles them
So that's Kim Cooper architectural historian
She brought me back to the Bradbury along with her husband Richard shaver
We are founders of Essex
Twerk
Is a
Bus tour company
That gives tours of Los Angeles focusing on architecture True Crime and literature
Free element switch
All come to a head
The Bradbury
The Bradbury opened in 1893 way before the movies ever came to LA
And for the record it's not named after the Sci-Fi novelist Ray Bradbury
Name for Louis
A gold mining millionaire
In the mid-1890s Ribery
Decided he was going to build building
With his name on it because he was an important man that built up the city so in 1892 Bradbury
Brake emissions this big deal famous architect Sumner hunt to design his building
The Bradbury didn't like any of the plans at Hunt Showdown
Bradbury disappointed
Turns to leave Hunt's office
But
As he goes out
For some reason
His eyes caught
Buy one of Hunt's draftsman
This young guy name
George Wyman
He has no
Professional training yet
As an architect and no one knows why
Takes women
Pulse asleep
I have an offer to make tea
Well that offer is completely impossible and inappropriate he wants
The higher the skit was an alarm
To build this very important
And this young guy George Wyman
Is a bit weirded out
Understand
Because he is
Totally unqualified for this job
And he didn't want it to seem like he was taking business away from his boss
But on the other hand
This opportunity was incredible
It's
An irresistible offer
But George Wyman is an ethical man
And he's also scared to death and so he does what any good Angelina will do
In the very late 19th century which is he will consult dead relatives
Spiritualism with huge at this
And George Wyman thought that his deceased brother Mark might have some wisdom to offer from the afterlife
So why man sits down with a planchette a precursor to a Ouija board which
Rode out sentences with a pencil when you rested your hands on it
Planchette's would typically be consulted when someone had an issue that they wanted some guidance on
So he and his wife were sitting together saying what on Earth should I do about mr. Bradbury's wonderful terrifying off
The planchette
Overcome with the spirit of Wyman's Dead Brother
Began
And it wrote
Take Bradbury in in a very childish script and
You will be
Blah blah blah
Justice
Nonsense script
And women and his wife were like one and it was when one of the two of them walked around the other side of the of the
People in read it upside down this Palmer typescript actually said successful
Cakebread
You will be
That was a clear enough message for women
He says yes to Bradbury
The design of the Bradbury was directly inspired by a novel
Looking backwards by Edward Bellamy
Which was written in 1887
But in it
There's a description of a building in the year 2000
The future
Women with
Trying to do with this balloon I think I think we can answer just simply by reading the passage
A vast Hall full of light
Received not alone from the windows on all sides but from the Dome
So that's
What this building does
And that's why even though the Bradbury is quite old by California Sanders it field current
It was designed for the year 2000
It's this blend of styles that makes it an architectural gem
But aside from the occasional film shoot the building spent a lot of its life totally ignored
Late 40s early 50s is once described as a chicken
And in that just refers to the dustiness and the sword of untidiness
By 74
This this place is really falling apart
So when Ridley Scott shot Blade Runner and it's Central Atrium it wasn't actually that hard to make it look so shabby
Blade Runner
That was just
Amazing that was before we'd actually
Fix it up and you can tell that
From the movie
This is Adele yellin
But my husband bought the building
In the late 80s
And he retrofit
Adele's late husband
IRA yellin
Spearheaded LA's downtown Revival
If I restore an old historic building
And turning them into housing
Businesses
But the Bradbury was just
Virtual and he wanted to work on it then he felt if you build it they will come
So
I don't know
They ultimately came but he he did have to use
I have the city to help him
Arielle and asked
If the city of Los Angeles could find a steady
Lieutenant for the Bradbury
He ended up getting the
Police Department
Most of the office space in the Bradbury Building belongs to the internal affairs division of the LAPD
Yeah they're they're there all the time and
They don't mind the filming generally Bender
Hino handled all the filming requests
For the Bradbury
What we do a
The police
Drama will you take extra
Precaution to make sure they know that
We're filming and the person running around with a gun type of thing is not
Very
But filming isn't the priority for the property anymore
Send it to Innovation the tenants needs come first
Try not to bother the tenants too much so we try to
Do the filming or not do more than one or two filming project
4 month
And generally this is the case throughout buildings downtown
Now that people live and work there they don't want production Crews periodically taking over
These days film Crews can't blow up cars in the street or have 300 zombies Stampy down Broadway in the middle
Full of the workday
The downtown Revival is a part of why
Filming is leaving Los
It laugh
I mean there's no feature films shooting here I've
It's scary
Because I said I love living here and I would like to continue sleeping in my bed if possible
Location scout Lori Balton just spent almost a year
Scouting and shooting in Atlanta Georgia
Which might just be
Become the new Hollywood
Because I've spent so much time in Atlanta it's like I'll look at a moving go oh yeah that's Aslan that you can't fool me
Atlanta like a lot of other cities in the South Midwest and Canada
It's offering major incentives to encourage filming
These tax breaks can say producers millions of dollars
Going broke giving the incentives that they are
Cities like Atlanta are also developing state-of-the-art Studios
And attracting good production town
We're
Really need to do everything we can to keep filming in LA
Which would mean making the public more open to the disruptor
Custom chutes
Bookkeeping the cost of
Permits down and adding new tax incentives
And to stop developing so rapidly
What's happening in La as we're losing a lot of our parking lots that will tear them down and putting buildings up
It's so funny to hear people bemoaned the loss of parking lot
People location people there's a difference
We're kind of a weird breed
But however state-of-the-art studios in Atlanta Toronto or Chicago are becoming
There are elements of Los Angeles that cannot be replicated
Even on the finest soundstage
Like experience of entering the Bradbury Building
The place so unique
So remarkable
But after it was built
The draftsman George Wyman decided
Take some classes
And actually become
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery troubleman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Special things this week to Linda Dishman head of the LA Conservancy
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw San Francisco and produce of the offices
Cos of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights.
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Info podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com