99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the late 1800s as more and more people began to have electric lights in their homes utility
Companies began looking for a good way to measure how much electricity each customer was using
Actually way back when Thomas Edison built
The first electric power stations
There were no electric meters in people
So he build a monthly fee based on how many lightbulbs they have
Sam evans-brown
New Hampshire Public Radio
That billing / light bulb system
Wasn't great so people came up with a meter that did the job well enough
It's the same basic meter that most of us in the US have in our home
Holmes today
And the way it works is when the electricity comes into your house a little dial turns forward and shows how much you've used
And even though the original designers in never really intended for this to happen
If you send electricity back into the grid
Dial turns backwards
Yashow electricity leaving your house
If you like me there's no electricity leaving your house
It's only coming in
If you're like Sam who has solar panels on his roof
Electricity is leaving the house
I'm going back
Into the grid
Yeah
That's because my solar panels
Create more energy than I can use
That excess energy goes back in
The grid and
Out to my neighbors
In my state New Hampshire
I get credited for that extra energy I create
It's practice called netty
Metering
And for a while it was totally
Not controversial
But now it is
There are huge political battle
Being fought over this
Sam his colleagues at New Hampshire Public Radio actually did a whole episode of their podcast outside in about net mean
Because
They are even earlier than we are
And I'm actually just going to hand it off to them now
So here's Sam in a little bit you'll hear the voices of his colleague
Maureen McMurray
Ann Taylor Quimby
So before we get into the controversy over net metering
I want to go back and introduce you to the guy who accidentally started it all
His name
Steven Strong
Sun energy lights
Despite
Appropriately
Anime cat plugin
To like me
Steven is in energy nerd
He's a guy who went Toyota came out with a Prius he got his engineers
Hack the thing
What are sub gives driver looking at here
Battery pack
The shoehorned into the spare tire
So he and his engineers
Made a plug-in Prius
Hundred years before the car company
And also Toyota WinCo Nana's when we told him we were doing this
The way back before he started messing around with Priuses
Steven founded the company called solar Design Associates
This was at a time when solar power
Besides being something on satellites in outer space
Wasn't really
Vignette
When was this again is the 70s
It was a heck of a hard way to make an easy living in the 70s and the 80s and the 90s
So Steven Strong is this
Hard-charging ready to drop everything and get his hands dirty kind of guy
And he kicked off would eventually became
Kind of a revolution in the way a lot of
People are getting their energy
He did it by putting solar panels
On an apartment building
For people with modest income
Barely acceptable
Oh wow it's huge
Pretty wife looks kind of like a big college dorm
It's brick
And pretty unremarkable
Supposed to drive this way
Well
That's The Story of My Life
Boone was built
How much proof that was this massive array of solar panels
When the first-of-its-kind
This was one of the largest
Source for most systems in New England
Candid
Met something like 80% of the annual hot water required
But this was this was like the early days of sources is solar thermal is just like heating hot water didn't make electricity solar
Thermal
All uses solar panels but all it does is heat up hot water
And
That was
It was cool like the simplest technology
It's so simple
Big Boss
And on the inside you got some tubes
That are colored black
And you put water in it or some sort of coolant refrigerant in there
And The Sun Shines on the black tubes
And heat it up and then you can circulate that back into a tank and that's all it was as I feel like I could come
I think that's that's like on the level technology-wise of like using a magnifying glass
Digital access
Pizza Patron
Wait
The solar panels at Carter put on the White House
Where does the solar thermal once
Stupid water at the White House
Yeah
In any case it was mostly
Solar thermal panels
Steven Strong convinced the developer to let him install a couple
A solar photovoltaic panels to
Photovoltaic panels are the ones that actually make electricity
And that time they were brand-new technology
Not as soon as the technology was available we were employing it
But there was this question
How should I do the wiring
Wait what do you mean so whenever the sun is shining obviously the electricity will go towards running all the stuff in the bill
Building you know water pumps hot water heaters whatever
Or what happens if
The sun is shining and there's nothing going on in the building
So what are you decided to do
We should configure
No son the building would work just like any other building
It would buy electricity from utility company
I'm a little dials on the electric meter would roll forward
5 kilowatt hours
10 kilowatt hours
20 30 40 50
I don't I don't know what a watt
Money
He don't have to know what I want
What a kilowatt hour is
You don't have to know all you need to know is that it's the measurement for electricity
Just getting back to Steven solar panels
What he did that no one had ever done before was too wired up
So that it's
The Sun
Was shining
In the building wasn't using any energy
The unused electricity would flow out into the grid
A little dial on the meter which is
Roll in the other direction
Backwards
At the end of the month when a person comes to check the meter the owners of the building would pay for whatever the dial set
So like if they use 60 kilowatt-hours but they put in 40
The guy with a 20
And it would only pay
Who was just
It was intuitive it was almost like
That's just the way it should be
Looks like we're producing electrons that are just as valuable as the ones provided by the coal plant or the heavy residual
Fuel oil drum
Implant
Why shouldn't they
Receive the same value
And enjoyed it just made sense
Did you talk to the utility at all what did you show them your design and say this is what we're going to do
No
The Developers
You should don't you don't worry about that you just got the technical side of this done and
And get it get it working
And we'll take care of it
We're going to be interfacing with utility
I turned out that
Did they didn't say anything about the system to the utility purposefully
I am
And told me if
The time
There's one thing in your career that you should learn early in that is it's easier to ask for
Forgiveness than it is to ask permission
And that
Ladies and gentlemen is how we got a little policy
Call Net metering
It's electric so why wouldn't he tell them
Well
Uncharted waters
I would say
He don't want to be told no
The net metering
It's the net of
When a meter goes forward and goes backwards
What's in between
Yeah net as in net
Versus gross
I mean the only reason it was designed that way
Is because that is what the meteor could do you know that little
Spinning disc
Electric meter all I can do is Bend forward and backwards
That's what I use
But it was well and truly the first one
That was connected to the utility grid
Outside the fence
The government Laboratory
Okay so puts in the solar panels on the roof of this building what would happens
So the utility company they were actually fine with the whole thing in fact
They praised Stevens innovation
But the solar panels didn't last very long
Baxley blue off the building in the first year
I didn't like
Kumon or whatever
Is it gets windy
So not a terribly auspicious start
What it did was kick off some intense interest in this idea
That solar could serve the needs of a home but also produce electricity for the grid like a tiny
Part-time power plant
And this concept of homeowner as power plants is actually important in thinking about how people with solar panels
On their homes will be
Hade
For the power they're producing
Because big established power plant sell power to the utility companies
At a cheaper wholesale cost
And then the utility companies can
Sell their customers at powered higher
Retail row
So they can make
Profit and
Pay for their cause
Send the question becomes
Do people with solar panels
They become like the mini power plant should they be paid the lower wholesale rate or the higher
Retail row
Are they like Costco or are they like mom-and-pop
Is that what is that it
Elegy
I think that's pretty good
In any case
States eventually started passing laws about
Dairy question
And that was all through the 80s and the 90s
And for the most part these laws that the utility company should pay people
The higher
Retail rate because
Inexpensive solar panels
Your house and this would incentivize solar
And eventually
41 States passed laws allowing people to get the tire retail rate for net metering and utility companies
Have the time
They didn't put up much of a fight about it
Jibbitz utility companies at this point they're like dancing with the devil and they don't even realize it
Yeah and nobody nobody had any reason to say
Oh this might not be a good idea because solar was just like this
Weird thing
Probably would never going to be cost of a
And that's how it was for a bunch of years
Until
Suddenly
Solar star
Where to get cheap
For decades or power was so expensive and unwieldy if you can afford it
And that is changing in a mind-bendingly rapid pace
Solar related stocks rally.
Wednesday on the news that Congress planes food
Extend a solar investment tax credit
During the mid 2000
A bunch of really ambitious Well Finance Company start saying
Hey we can make some money doing
And so from 2009-2010 amount of solar in US doubled
It doubled again from 2010 to 2011 doubled again from 2011 to 2013 and from 20
2013 to today
It soundtrack
Triple A game
Okay so so what is
What are these companies doing that's different like how are they
Making money what's their motto
What they're doing
Is there offering people solar for no money down
They pay for the cost of the panels and exchange they take
A chunk of the money that you would earn by producing power
So if you had someone come and knock on your door and say hey want to be part of the next renewable energy are
And you can have solar panels on your roof right now is not going to cost you any money and we're going to give you a discount on your power bill
That yeah
And that business model
Is made possible by net-metering
By getting this higher retail rate
But our people are producing with solar
And I think it's fair to say that the utility company
Basically did not see this coming
And so now
They're starting to push back
They don't want to be paying the retail rate
They think people generating electricity with solar should get
The wholesale rate
Just like a power play
So where where are the fights happening now
Where were the really high-profile fight over
Well so the obviously Arizona is the number one
So that's Christy shallenberger who works for this industry new psychology
Utility I've attract all the
She points out that we've seen a net metering battles
In California
And of course you have Nevada which has basically become
The byword for what
You don't want to see
Nevada's fight got really
Huge huge blow back from
All walks of life basically up celebrities your presidential candidates
I do not often get involved
State or local issues other than my own state
But I find it rather in
Incredible
Seattle public utilities
Commission Nevada
Has made a decision
Which makes it hot
What people
Play who's that Bernie Sanders
Really that's crazy obscure policy that's getting tons of attention
Hillary Clinton talk about it when she went to Nevada and talk to local newspapers there
They're fighting
Iowa Texas Maine Vermont New York Utah Hawaii
Of course right here in New Hampshire
Isabel what's happening
All over the country
Dubai state
The local electric company
Is pushing back and all the solar installers fighting against
Utilities
Local
Flavor to this argument but I still don't understand a little bit about this fight like why would me having solar panel
What's on my roof
Why would it make the utility company like
So
Angry is it just money
Of course it's about money
With whose money
Do utility companies want to reframe this argument
Slipknot
Just about there in
But it's about the interest
The people who
Don't have
Here I talked to Michael herring
Who
Cure New Hampshire he used to be one of the guys who regulates
It's a
Taking from the not so
People that have not so much and giving his
People have more
Say I was retired school teacher Manchester living in an apartment is no way I'm going
Roof
And get any benefit from that meeting but I'm going to have to pay for it
Because
Some guy in Bedford
She's bedford's example
Nothing to do
Bedford if you're not from New Hampshire is a wealthy suburb of Manchester
Which is our biggest city 4000 square foot house
And he said if I do this net metering thing in five or six years I'll be getting basically free electricity
It's a reverse distribution of wealth when the way we normally do
United States
And I don't think that
Right
I get it so it's like someone ultimately has to pay and all of these people who are people of means we're homeowners have
Solar panels than the cost of the other utility will go up
And that means that people who are renting
Or anything like that they get screwed because I want
Solar panels on my house
This is how rate structures work
Write a utility is
A big
Company that invest
What's a ton of money in
Poles and wires
Is in energy to send across those poles and wires
And then they take
All of the customer
And they divided the cost of that up between all of them
Spread it around
And under that business
If they 50% of the people in the US went solar and started at me during
A big chunk of the money that their saving is money that's not going towards
Paying for the poles and wires
So this is the argument against net metering witches
You
Or anything
USA me because I actually do have solar panels on my roof right because I don't screw and you yeah me putting solar panels on my roof
Cost you money
What the hell Sam
Except
The problem is
We're not 100% sure
I got to look something up cuz
This is another former regulator Cliff below
He's the one here in New Hampshire who wrote
The first initial net metering law here in New Hampshire
Even then
There was this intuition like this feeling
That maybe they were actually benefit
So the feeling was solar Mike
Higher-than-average in in value
And I think the evidence is
Is proven that out over the years that solar tends to produce at higher than ever
Average price hours
Toe clip below is literally saying the exact
Opposite thing from Michael Harrington he's saying that me 20 solar panels on my roof actually
Saves you guys
Okay but this is a pickle I don't know if I believe
I don't think I don't think it's going to save enough money
Alright so
So let's first maybe dig into why it might be
Even though we pay the same amount for every unit of energy on our electric bills
All electrons are not
Created equal
In reality every 5 minutes there's a new option for energy so every 5 minutes
We got a new
Price for Energy
When demand is low
Prices are low and they can actually go negative
Like power plants
Us
They don't have to shut down
Usually that's at night
And when demand is high prices can be in
Saying like a hundred times higher than normal
And again do utilities take all of those costs
The average them all out and they divide them by their customer
The thing is
Solar panel
Those are producing at times of day that
Really high value
Sunny hot
Desert usually times where where electricity is expensive and that's when you're producing solar power
And so by feeding back into the grid
We're cutting usage
So much that
That it lowers the price during the
Exact
And so Cliff below's arguing
These people are actually
You don't even though they're getting paid
More than a regular power plant
They're actually getting paid less than the energy
And that means that there's
Saving
Things for every solar panel
Can you put on the grid
I would read but that's only true up until a certain point right I mean if you suddenly tip it and it's
Goes from 20% of the population on solar panel to 5270 then
I'm sorry clip your math doesn't work out
That is exactly right
You should go work for MIT
People do have ideas about how to solve office
Which we can talk about
Or we could not
The most interesting to me
Is from a guy
Call Don Creech
Do you think of the way
That we pay for electricity
Is it dumb
Deleting question yes
It is clearly inappropriate
In today's technological age
To continue to charge people the same price for electricity 24/7
When the cost of providing people electricity varies
Sometimes by orders of magnitude depending on the time of day and the time
Year
And the great condition
Randstad apply
So is it not then by extension also kind of dumb
To not very the
Price that were paying
Customer toward generating solar power from the roof
I agree with that as well
Don is Stacy
Consumer Advocate his job is to watch out
For people who pay electric bills
So basically he's supposed
We keeping costs down and looking out
A little guy
It simply isn't
Fair
To take a you know
Tired school teacher living on a fixed income in
Manchester and force that customer
To pay subsidies to a
Wealthy hedge fund manager living in Bedford
Who has a mcmansion discovered in solar panel
Is there is there some actual retired school teacher in Manchester and some actual hedge fund manager in Bedford because my
Michael Harrington gave me p
Exact same as how could she
At not not that I'm aware of
There totally is
Where are those
But anyway I mean Don Kris
Also thinks that this cost
Shifting thing
Is a problem
And so this
Is what Don Chris wants
Called
Time-of-use rate
Isn't you get paid more if your solar is going during those high-priced times like later in the afternoon
But
You also
Hey more if you're using more energy
The afternoon
SO2 make
Is really simple everyday there be a different price
Higher price
Between 2 p.m.
At 8 p.m.
What's the weather like for cities prices
And this
Is cracking open the door
Tor radically different weight
To pay for energy
Instead of abiding by the
Crazy illusion that every electron is worth
Same amount
Is acknowledging that when demand is high
Expensive
And maybe we should let people know that
I think that we can
Provide that Morad frequently updated information to Consumers
So this is Jessica Transit
She's a professor of energy studies at MIT I think that that should be possible yeah
But she wants to take it even a step
Farther
Remember there is
Constantly a new price for electricity every 5 minutes
And she thinks we should have a display in our houses
Is it says
Here's the price of energy
Right now
Play something literally follows like the 5 minutes every 5 minutes to Market clears you get a new price
Well maybe hourly you know I think 5 minutes 5 minutes might be a bit too much but but hourly
So if if you ever find a utility that wants to
To do that I'm I'm ready to sign up
I'll be in the pilot
I think I'll be fine
Okay great I'll let you know I'll let
Messi I actually find that really interesting because I had no idea that it buried at all and it
Varies wildly and you know I don't think twice about turning the light switch on if there was a flashing
Red high price alert or something
Yes right
Now there are some really important caveats
This pouch
41 rolling out new meters everywhere would be
Expensive
And this would be a very big maybe very difficult change in the way utilities operate
But for two
The market
Can be brutal
Dip their prices that can go up like a hundred times the average which is
Crazy
And that's why even Jessika trancik thinks that they should have
Have a cap
And why Don Chris wants this
Sort of
Declawed version of that
Which is
Look like a slightly more expensive. From 2 to 8
P.m.
Verses really following the mark
But they both
I think it's time we looked at
Redesigning the way our electricity is metered
Because solar
Has made everything
More,
Houston Kris
Metering started
There Was An Architect guy and yeah
Actually talk to him
Really so you know that like he just did it without asking anybody
Run backwards
Just why are my building up
Encino and attach it to the boss
But the fact is that it
You know it it was like a commission on uniform state laws got together and said
What's design a net metering statue that will promote the development of distributed generation
You know when it's really large go rigorous way
Accident
And now it's everywhere and so it is high time for everybody to take a look at it
See what a rational well-designed and public policy would be
Is it will promote the development of distributed generation
Logical rigorous
Accident
And now it's everywhere and so it is high time for everybody to take
Take a look at
See what a rational well-designed bit of public policy
Or maybe we'll just go back to Feeling by the life
I'm going to reduce my number of lightbulbs
I can I can handle that
Revert
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam evans-brown and Logan Shannon
With help from Maureen McMurray
Taylor Gourmet
Jimmy Gutierrez and Molly Donahue
A longer version of the story aired on the podcast outside in from New Hampshire Public Radio
Go listen to some of their other episodes they're great big nerd stuff just like we do and they make it really fun you're going to like it
Special things this week to Bob Johnstone who wrote the book switching to solar
Haskell world
You can see pictures of that Infamous First grid-tied Solar apartment building at our website
Linode API
. org
Music this week was from jahzare Jason Leonard Blue Dot sessions
Paddington Bear okay akumi and Sean real
Be outside in theme music is my brake master cylinder
99percentinvisible is Delaney Hall and it Fitzgerald Kurt Kolstad
Turn master Katie mingle Sean real every child Ministry fusive and me Roman Mars
This piece was edited for our use by
Katie and mixed by Sharif
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI feet
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Does routine
I think about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Docinfo podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Five podcast
You can find a show in joints question about the show on Facebook and Twitter me at Roman Mars and the show at 99.
War
We're on Instagram Tumblr and have a nice subreddit to
But we released at least two articles about design and architecture every week on our website
What's 99 Pi. Org
Radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
Kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com