99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On a Friday evening in the summer of 2011
Los Angeles resident Brighton rain was driving home from work
He was coming from a job site and took a route he doesn't usually take to get to his neighborhood
And I might not have come this way I mean I'm glad I did because
I saw this I knew that it was a problem and I got out of my car
What did you say
That's a producer Sam Greenspan he met with Brant in Los Angeles
I saw
About 25 to 30 guys with
Heavy equipment all wearing orange jumpsuits they had
Backhoes they had
Transfer printing machines any like large tractor material like stuff that you can't just like ignore you and I
I might not think there's anything weird about a bunch of guys doing work on a freeway burn
But Brent took one look and thought
Well this all seems
Fishing charters it seem laid for a city work crew to be doing landscaping
Domo 77
What are you doing
Look up be up to something
The crew was manicuring some trees and a fenced-off piece of land next to a freeway
Inwood long being a low-income neighborhood
It's a patch of land that never gets landscape
The only reason the trees were there was because about 40 years ago
The bird flew over and pooped out fertilized
And no one ever touch
It's not like
They're just putting the tree up to make it look better on the freeway look at all the rest of them they look like crap
And that's when Brent put it together
A work crew doing an after-hours landscaping job in an area where they never do any work
DeBrands this meant one thing
I know
With all my
Being that there's 30 seconds free
Stealing trees
Now the reason that Brent Green was able to deduce all of this
Is because he is by
Grade a landscape
And so he knew the worth of the trees
Did the work Rueda messing with
How much to purchase these trees for projects and then like 20 grand
$20,000 a tree
Rent in front of the workers and ask them what they were doing
Some of them took off running
Later a woman who lives in mats
Street came down from her apartment
Inverness
If you knew what was going on
Didn't just take that one and I think they took like six other ones
They took two over there for when they are living here all week
You know that I called
This is not the first case of poem theft bomb wrestling has been reported in Texas and San Diego it even get to
Mentioned in Susan Orlean's book The Orchid Thief
And understand why someone would want to steal a pump
We need to really understand their value
Which has a lot to do with it
Space they occupy in our Collective
And for that
We need to talk.
My name is Jared farmer
I am the author of
Trees in
It is book
Beard farmer traces the history of the Golden State
Four kinds of trees
One of them
The Palms
The others are the Redwood the Citrus and the eucalyptus
That we should get sent away first
A palm tree isn't really a
It's actually not a tree
What kind of grass is like a super grass is like hundreds or thousands
Long Blades of grass in extensions like fused together don't make bark
Or branches
If you cut them down you won't find any rings in the trunk
All the roots grow on a compact making them easier to steal that say like an oak tree which has next
Vantiv underground root Network
And as far as trees go we don't plant palms for any of the normal reasons we want other tree
It's not for the shade is not for
Climbing you can't really climb a palm tree very well It cast
Precious little shave
Palm trees it seems
Do something else
Darrell vocativ
They're transported it
They Inspire us
To dream big
Image of beauty
In fashion
And Design
Architect
Palms
Especially Urban Palms in places like Los Angeles are planted less
For what they do
Then what they mean or rather what they mean
Is
What they do
If you trace the history of what palm trees have
Have symbolized in the western imagination
Ask Jared farmer has
You start to get the idea that palm trees have always been about evoking a spirit of Elsewhere
Even 200 years ago palm trees were planted in California by the Spanish
As a way of signifying on the Holy Land
Orthodox Christianity in Rome
Catholicism
Dolphin demands actually happen
Franzen at the wrist reason the Spanish in California Groupon
Pounds for
On Sunday so palm trees were around by the time that California be
Estate in 80
And around that same time
There was a trend in art and literature of what we now call orientalism
A kind of fascination
So that fantasy of like Arabs and Bedouin sand
Oasis in Sahara Zod back on
The palm trees dovetailed quite nicely
Put those kinds of fascination
Palm trees were also used to make people think of the tropics
MLB Street ropes are unfolding
Palm tree symbolizing the Holy Land the Orient
The tropics
They also kind of do this thing where they all congeal and collapse
Sent you a bigger nose
That we can still recognize
Today
Palm trees in the symbol
For luxury
And Leisure survive if you went to San Francisco.
Two Union Square
Corky went
To Manhattan or to Paris or The Londoner
Uniworld City in
In the West
You would find a Palm Court
In the hotel
Even the RMS Titanic had a Palm Court
Even though Palms were already going International by the dawn of the 20th century
It was in California
Around Los Angeles especially
Their place in the global imagination really
Took root
So good
A trend emerged among homeowners
Price of planting palm trees on either side of their front door
At first this was only thing that wealthy people did but at some point
You're not rich you just have a little starter Bungalow in LA but like you got palm trees
Ways to that really did sort of signify you have achieved
Not just
The American Dream by the California version of the American dream which was
Everything in the American dream
Offer but also
Great weather
Gorgeous setting
Trees that flower smell good and look good every month
Am I taking off
Something happens in the rich suburbs outside of LA
In towns like Redlands in Riverside
Which were then Super affluent
People there started planting Palms
Not just on private property
But also along city streets
Almost as if to say we will be reminded of luxury
Everywhere we go
It's about
Really what I would call the Municipal Park
The Palms At
Symbolizes the city of Sailfin symbolizes good life in the city
Eventually Los Angeles proper got hip to this idea of Municipal trees
And during the Great Depression the works progress administration put a lot of unemployment work
Planting trees
Throughout the cell
There are more than 2500 species of palm tree
What is Palm Trees florist in California there's one particular species that still down
The Canary Island date palm
Or
Phoenix canariensis
Yeah it is probably the most spectacular Palm in the world.
In terms of the number of Franz
What's the width of the France
And it has a kind of bumpy
Crosshatch
Truck front window
Franz detach
The Phoenix canariensis is so stately and Majestic
It was used as a v symbol of California boosterism a pattern of descent
When Phoenix was even dug up
Put on a railcar
And freighted
All the way to Chicago
For the 1893 Columbian
And everyday
On the trunk
California boosters would put up a piece of paper that listed
The temperature
At Coronado Beach
It San Diego
And at Lake Michigan just for comparison always Bendix about our weather
Exposition
The palm tree was sent back to
California
Obviously it wasn't going to be left to suffer in The Frigid City of Chicago can you imagine
This is me being a dick about our weather
For a long time the Phoenix canariensis was mostly a symbol of Southern California
But eventually
Especially for the 1990s they were also in hot demand up north in the Bay Area
And since of Phoenix canariensis takes 52
60 years to mature
Tree nurseries
Couldn't keep up with the demand
You just can't manufacture more 50 year old palm tree
So broke
They go to older residential neighborhoods
What people have liked a little bungalow
They're like a 3rd generation
Uncle are they now have this
84 Palms
They might have some sentimental attachment to a profession not doing much for them
If someone offers them
A few hundred dollars
Take it off there
Many people
Will take that opportunity
Recession
Canary Island date palm trees has
Has died down a little
But they are still in high demand
Between the demand the time it takes for a tree to mature
And this year have to move in these things
Phoenix canariensis is the most expensive palm tree to buy
The going price
Including a truck to move it
A crane to lift it
Fruta planta
A lot of money
Twenty Grand apple tree Des again $20,000 a tree
And that is why to bring it back to work earlier
Angeleno Brent Green was so outraged when he saw that work Brew in his neighborhood that summer night into
They were there
Rental lease
To steal more than $100,000 worth of palm trees
Reported what he sought the police
Also got the local NBC affiliate on the trail
And our investigation is found this could be
An inside job
We found at least one Caltrans official
Could be involved in these staff
Long story short
Employee of the California Department of Transportation had signed off on a work order allowing the third party to go
Go in and remove the tree
A lawsuit followed
One result of which
Was six Canary Island date palms getting put back on the freeway burn
Inbreds neighbor
At any rate it might not matter too much in the grand scheme of things because the treescape of Los Angeles is about to have
A lot fewer palm trees to co
Fungus called fusarium wilt
Has been randomly killing off certain species of palm trees
Including the Phoenix canariensis
Several different landscape designers told me that they avoid using the Phoenix canariensis Palms right now
Because of their susceptibility to the wilt
And on top of that as of 2006 the city of Los Angeles has greatly kuerbitz replant
Dana fan Palms
Those are the really tall
Spindly guys with the skinny trunks
The motion approved by the city council stated that fan Palms don't provide adequate recover they don't release novox
Oxygen into the atmosphere
And they said so many fronts that they are considered hazard
All the palm trees that got planted in the teens twenties and thirties
Are all going to be dying of old age in the next
Few decades
I'm helping getting replanted
Pompa largely disappear from the law
No course Palm Trees will still get replanted in the iconic spots where people expect palm trees to be
Designated tour sounds like Hollywood and Sunset Boulevard
That's where they will always be
But Jared farmer is actually not too sad
I see the palms of Southern Calif
When you go this is a guy who writes about trees for a living and it's a self-proclaimed lover of pain
The time of
Up less water more
People
I think we have to make
Wiser choices about the country
California was still have an incredibly diverse
A treescape
But Los Angeles without palm trees
Not unfriend greens watch anyway
He told me that when he was a kid he used to draw house
Houses with palm trees next to them
And now that he's a grown-up he's fulfilled his own California American Dream
Though his house is a modest bungalow
It's made so much more stately by the 10 or so Palms in front of his home
And even knowing
Everything I know about palms that they were basically marketing tools and how they play this
Sony sense of exoticism
I have to say
It all still kind of works on
I found myself in awe
And a little jealous of Brent's California Dream
Palm of Gumball bumpers now
The number problem hello my phone
99% invisible with Bruce this week by Sam Greenspan with Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Cindy Gilliland Jason DeWees Darren Sears and Tom Dreisbach
We are project to 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in architecture
Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a new Wii
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Does routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Docinfo podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook we're all on Twitter and Instagram Tumblr and Spotify but I encourage you to explore the entire
Tire World of 99% invisible
At 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com