99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We have one cardinal rule on 99percentinvisible
No Cardinals
Meaning we don't deal with the natural world only the built world
So when I read John wellons brilliant book
Call The Wild Ones a sometimes this Mane weirdly reassuring story
About looking at people looking at animals in America
I didn't think I'd ever do an episode of 99% invisible about it I just read it for fun
But then I saw John perform stories from the book live with musical accompaniment and I thought
I need to put this on the radio
Phil Collins radio
Anyway what you need to know about Wild Ones is that it isn't a book about nature
It's a book about how we fit nature into our modern lives
Wild Ones is about the QT stuffed animals
BP Go tours
In the Byzantine methods of conservation that involved
When our experience with Wildlife goes from something natural
Do something
Design
Human-animal interaction has become a designed experience
In the story of that transition as the title of book suggest
Is sometimes this may
And also
Weirdly reassuring
John William is friends with the band black prairie and as he was writing the book
They can talk to this idea of the band creating a soundtrack to the book
And the result was an extended EP called Wild Ones the music in your head
When you reflect on certain characters and incidents
That you read in the book
The writer and the band then went on a short tour with the song and story Extravaganza that I'm going to play for you today
When I saw them perform this live in San Francisco
I freaked out it was so good and I costed them in the dressing room
And said
You have to let me share this with my audience
So here it is
And here we go
It happens every summer
Small turtles
Call diamondback terrapin skidder out of the water
Around JFK Airport New York
They start moving West
They're heading for a patch of sand
Where they like to lay their eggs
NAFTA crossover one of the airport's Runway is to
Runway
4L
Sometimes
There's so many turtles on the move at 1
The control tower
Has to delay
The Press loves doing stories about how funny this is
Fleet a giant airplane
Can be held up
I just a few tiny turtle
The hold that picture in your mind and think about the Caribbean Sea in 1492
They were almost
Billion
Sea turtles living in the back then
Columbus has been anchored in the Caribbean
Rude about being kept awake at night by the flagging of so many turtle shells against the sides of their ship
Notice how that scene
Is the exact opposite
Of the scene at JFK
It's not a fleet of giant airplanes being held up by a few tiny turtle
It's a giant Fleet of turtles
Bombarding just a few
Relatively tiny ships
So I wrote this book about people and wild animals in America and it only really started because
I wanted to show my daughter endangered species in the wild before they did
Disappeared
Like a lot of people I think I felt this Pang
I knew that all around us
Beautiful parts of the world are expiring
And I also knew that
People in the future they might not even notice
Shut down a world without whales or Wilderness might feel normal
Wanted to counteract
That forgetting
That's bound
To take hold over time
This forgetting
Has a name
Scientist called shifting Baseline syndrome
It means that
All of us except
The version of the world we inherit
Is normal
Over the years we watch
Forest get louder animals disappear but
When the next Generation comes along fix
That depleted version of nature is there normal
Chart zoom out
Really feel the changes
Better stacking up
Across the generation
I can't even imagine
What an ocean filled with a billion sea turtles must feel like
Last winter
I was in Hawaii
And I saw three sea turtles
And I flipped
I felt like I was in
Eden
It wasn't so long ago that America was a kind of eating when people could be dwarfed and engulf by wow
Wild animals in a way that feels almost impossible now in the late 1800s
Trains would sometimes have to stop for four or five hours
Extremes of Buffalo moved across the tracks
Occasionally I Stampede would batter into the side of a train derailing it
The witness describes one of these scenes
1871 in Kansas
Each individual a buffalo without it
What the desperation does paraplegic mean green locomotive cars just as blind Madness Chester directed
After having dreams thrown off the track twice in one week conductors learn to have a very decided respect for the idiosyncrasies
The Buffalo this man's name was William Temple hornaday
He was at bombastic mid Westerner with an elaborate mustache
Taxidermist at the Smithsonian and he traveled the globe hunting exotic animals and stuffing them for the museum
In India after he took down an elephant climb to top the carcass and popped open a bass ale
Once he trapped an orangutan named did little man gave it to Andrew Carnegie as a pet
It sounds weird but for hornaday
Killing these animals with
The kind of cons
Motivation
He believed
By stuffing them
He was preserving endangered
Speciesism
For the future Generations that might not know them out
After they were gone
Do taxidermy
You can make them immortal
In 1886
Hornaday looks wet
Saw that American
So many buffer
So rapidly
The Prairie was almost
You figured
They were maybe
Less than 300
Buffalo left in
And so we did
What he thought
Was the motel
Helpful and logic
He lit out for Montana
And several dozen
They shot 25 buffalo in Montana and they built the best looking ones into an exhibit at the Museum
Gather them around a pic Watering Hole looking for Lauren
But from there his thinking of all of you realize he was basically just a funeral director
Embalming the species that America was Exterminating it occurred to him
What if we actually tried to keep these animals alive
And so he became one of America's first real wildlife conservationists and activist the lobbyist ASL
Liberty America was killing every conceivable kind of animal in their way and hornaday sit up
For all of them from icons like the grizzly to lowly or less Majestic things like the squirrel
A live squirrel in a tree is poetry in motion we have Perry American to lend a hand to save
Silvertail there was really only one animal on the continent that Hornet it wasn't worried about
It would seem to Mighty to be brought down by men with guns and it lived in a cold and brutal wilderness
Batman couldn't possibly take over
Polar bear is the king of the Frozen North
It's not very probable that the polar bear
Attributes
Terminated
That's hornaday writing a 1914
Back then
No one could have imagined the problem is abstract is climate change
But think about how quickly climate changes change the polar bears reputation in our minds
Scan from bloodthirsty mankiller
The delicate drowning victim
200 years ago Arctic explorers wrote about polar bears
Leaping into their boat
I'm trying to eat them
Even if they lit the bear on
Bonfire
I recently when I went to the tiny Northern Town that calls
Itself the polar bear capital of the world
Martha Stewart had just arrived
Film The Animals
For her daytime show
The Hallmark show
The town is called Churchill Manitoba it's on the edge of Hudson Bay and every fall right before the bay freezes over
Silver Churchill gets overrun with about 900 polar bears and 10,000 polar bear tours
Bears routinely wander into town they like hanging out at the elementary school
Especially
Chase the animals back run to the tundra and their trucks bears that won't budge or tranquilizing
Shipped out to a quonset hut near the airport once this so-called polar bear gel fills up each animals
Drugs again and airlifted one at a time to an area north of town crowds of Taurus
Come out to watch these bare lifts
And I went to one myself
There was
Something just a little ceremony
About the bare lifts I went to
How the uniformed Wildlife officers arranged
Sleeping Bear
On a net
Epicenter of the crowd
But I checked its paws
Carefully across
Chess
Like some drunk and Uncle after Thanksgiving dinner
It was so careful
Beautiful
Confusing
A couple of people tried
It was like the opposite
Of an animal sacrifice ritual
To save the bear
To show how far out of our way we'd go
Not to kill it
I stood there and watched
Geneza did
Martha Stewart's the next
Tumi
Her crew is there filming everything
Honestly it's a breathtaking thing to watch
Polar bear flying away all of a sudden the helicopters started to turn the edge
Images of the net lifted the furry shape inside contracted it to you
You and then the entire package was off the ground
The helicopter client or the cloudbank
The bear twirling slightly underneath it like a tea bag and then finally
Polar bear was gone
Yeah I know
Airlifting polar bears
Strange no one could have imagined it would come to this
The way we help animals now has evolved into a surreal kind of performance art
We carry migrating salamanders across busy highways
We monitored pygmy rabbits with drone
Is Cornell a scientist breeding endangered peregrine falcons were specially made receptacle
They called the copulation hats Coates the bird named beer-can to ejaculate on their head
Several times a day every day
For much of the
This is another Baseline that shifts
Overtime
The links were willing to go
Each generation
Does what would have looked like
Fighting for a purpose
Just lost cause to the one before it and then
Generation
Comes along a new and does a little bit more than that
Nanako's Humanity
Strapping on the proverbial population hat again
And again
Consider the story
George
In the late 1970s there were only a handful of whooping cranes left in the wild
No sew a small number at a government lab in Maryland
Scientist there were doing their best to ring as many new Offspring as they could from those Captain for
But the lab had one problem child a female crane named text has a newborn text have been
Raised in a cardboard box in the zookeeper's living room and having never seen another Train sheet
Imprinted on the one animal she did see the Zookeeper basically she wound up sex
Attracted to people but not other grains
The scientist kept trying to parietex off but text wasn't interested she wanted a man has specifically
Amanda looks like her old zookeeper a dark-haired white man the medium build
Now there was a young trained conservationist named George Archibald and
George happened to be a dark-haired white man of medium build he took text to rule Wisconsin putting mattress
Senator pan and moved in has Texas companion Forge together build a nest
And they dance George doing deep knee bends and springing up with arms out like wings
Kid Wolf Pen holler come on text come on
Just like wild cranes do during courtship this would get text aroused and it just the
Right moment to assistance with Richard from a hiding place and artificially inseminate her with green semen
George did all this for 3 years living with text for months at a time
Time because the eggs she kept playing where infertile the man and crane would start out after Dawn
They go for a walk and they dance they dance and they dance send it down
George didn't enjoy any of this he was miserable actually miserable
But in the spring of 1983 text finally laid an egg that hatched and George was right there when I did
He was invited on The Tonight Show.
Celebrate
When headline Redman
Crane godparents of chick
George name the chick she whizzed by now g-wiz as 44 grandchildren and great-grandchildren
Today there are more whooping cranes in the wild than there have been
In almost a hundred years
William Temple hornaday
The taxidermist died in 90
At his funeral
Fuglers
The local Boise
Surrounded the coffin
Played Home on the Range
20 years later
Estonian words
Killing Hornet is Buffalo a
The one he built.
They found a rusty box
Buried
Inside was a letter
It was from Hornady
Written
At the Museum
Dear sir
But I'm just an ass
I beg you
Protective specialist
Deterioration of Destruction
At last
The game butcher
My name is
Please
I write this letter to
To you
Google
Do
I am happy not to be
Enjoy their beauty
Trinity
I have protected them now to the
I have no Stop The Killing
Youku
You can move faster
How to download
Of course
Hornet is written that pessimistic letter in 1887
When he was still just a young tax
Dermis
Turns out he
What's wrong
The Buffalo we're not all day
And in the years to come
He actually played a big role in helping to save them
Lots of other
But it was hard for him to focus on those two
He lost so many more battles anyone
By the end of his life
Bitter
Disillusion
I tried
To inject
The Croods
Into the hearts of men but today
I think that speaking generally
Civilized man is an unmitigated ass
Like all of us
His imagination was hopelessly trapped
And its own moment
It only see the world
The tiny keyhole on
Present
So
Where does that leave us
Maybe
All anyone of us can
Can do is
Push against the Baseline
We can be a tiny counterweight
We weigh almost nothing
Generation after
Regeneration
Sometimes it
In some places the bass
The other girl
The direction of mortgage
But that happens in
Incrementally tuvan
Can be hard to notice
So
Picture that
Seen at JFK again all those Turtles
When hornaday was born
They were close to
Extinction
Being hunted
They tasted so good in soup
We're like those Turtles
The race of stubborn little things that barely notices is the Wilderness it migrates through filza
Sup with villages and lights
And swells into an Airport runway just keep migrating across that anyway talking into
Legs of the Next Generation into the sand
We're like the airplanes to cuz we have changed we change into something that
Hornaday could never have imagined species that can at least try to slow down try to stop
I like to think about those airplanes powering down the lines of them partying like a
Shiny metallic see so this Tiny Tribe of turtles can pass through I get it
It looks funny in the present the Squints into the hazy Panorama of history and
Who's airplanes idling in place that little moment of not moving forward
Looks unmistakably to me like progress
That was Wild Ones live text written by John Llewellyn music by black prairie
Blackberry is Jenny Conlee Drees house on accordion and vocals
Chris Funk on Banjo dobro autoharp and vocals Don Moen on drums and vocals
John neufeld on guitar and vocals
Make query on base
Annalisa tornfelt on fiddle and vocals
They're recording engineer is Rich hip
That's 99% invisible for this week the show is Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco in the American Institute of Architects
Tax in San Francisco
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info slide podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
We have links to all things Wild Ones at our website it's 99 pi
. org
Radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com