99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1960 a new wonder drug hit the US market
And while a lot of new drugs promise dramatic results
This one would actually transform millions of lives and radically shift
American culture
It was called an oven
It was the first
Oral contraceptive
Drugs for many
Cindy answer to all the problems agency approves the first birth control pill and 19th
It helped set in motion forces that will soon change the social mores of the world
In just two years 1.2 million American women were taking the birth control pill
That's reporter Leila Turner
Within 5 years
Is the poet become the most popular form of birth control in the country
It let women choose if
And when they wanted to have children
I give them more freedom
SuperSU careers
And it helps us learn the free love era of the late 1960
It was a big deal
And even if you never taken the pill
You can probably picture its Packaging
There's the round plastic package that opens like a shell and looks
Kind of like a makeup compact
There's also the more low-key rectangular pillow sheets
What do you spell arranged in for neat rows for every day of the month
It's hard to think of other prescription drug packages that are as widely recognizable as those of the birth control
But the pill didn't always have special package
The first birth control pill to hit the market came in a simple glass bottle of loose tablets
Like any other prescription drug
They come in big bottles or a year's supply smaller bottles for a month
Apply on hair
Is the pill went from nondescript bottles
What's to the iconic pill package
It came to represent larger Trends in American Medicine
Women were beginning to take more control of their own body
And their demands for a new standard of patient autonomy
Would go on to affect
Description packaging of all kind
It all started with a family in Illinois
In 1961 David and Doris Wagner
We're a middle-aged couple with four kids
They didn't want any more of them
And so they were thrilled to learn about the pill
Doris got a prescription
The pills came in a big bottle
Instructions said to begin the pill on the
5th day of her period
To take one pill every day
20 days
Followed by a 5-day break
For menstruation
Is Doris lost track of recycle or if she forgot whether or not she had taken a pill that day
She was instructed to pour all the pills out of the bottle
Count how many pills were left
Subtract that from the original number of pills
And consult the calendar
Not as super user-friendly design
And if she missed a pill
She risk getting pregnant again
David Wagner
Noticed that his wife Doris was often
Should have concerned about taking her pills and he was also concerned about whether or not she was
Taking her pills
The Wagner Simpsons passed away
But this is Carolyn Hiser
A women's health expert whose research the Wagners
And their role in the history of birth
Control package
So he thought I'd do something
About this
David Wagner was an engineer for a tool company in Illinois
And he was used to solve any mechanical problems
He figured he could create a packaging system that would make the pill taking process easier for his wife
First he tried something really simple
He took a piece of paper
And he wrote out the days of the week and put the pills
On the piece of paper along with the days of the week
Turn it make it into a bit of a calendar and that works pretty well
At least for a few weeks
Then I guess the story goes something
Fell on the dresser and the pills
Got scattered and fell on the floor
And that was that that made him think
Maybe I can make a package
Say you could
Throwing your purse throwing your bag take with you and
Keep everything in order
So what he came up with
Is today very familiar to anyone who's probably use the birth can
Control pill
Is a curator of the extensive birth control archive
Smithsonian Museum of America
Can history
And we actually have some of the
The prototypes over
Here
Widener's original prototype was made out of two discs
Clear plastic
In a snap Fastener that he borrowed from the child's toy
The bottom disc held 20 pills
Which could be rotated each day to expose
The correct pill along with the corresponding day of the week
Having this system that made pill taking more intuitive Health Dorset David
This is David
Wagner writing in
January 16th 1995
This is a letter Wagner sent the Smithsonian Museum
For their birth control archive
Both Doris and Ike
Katella the glance weather appeal had been taken on a given day
Listed wonders for our
Kinship
Wagner successfully received a patent
For his design
But he had trouble convincing Pharmaceutical
It's to get on board
He actually took it around to some of the big companies and most of them said
Sort of things like what we don't need that that's kind of gimmicky and everything
At the time drug companies were known for the boring sameness of their first
Action Packaging
Wagner was told that a special package just for birth control
Sounded kind of commercial
Flashy
A design was turned down by every company he approached
But then just a few months later
One of the companies he met with
Cold Ortho Pharmaceutical
Release their first broken
And these pills came in a circular plastic container
With a dial
The movie today
Trivial the neck
Pal
It was called the dial
To David Wagner
The dial pad
Look very
Familiar
Maybe a little too familiar
Wagner and threaten a lawsuit
In December of 1964
He signed an agreement with ortho Pharmaceuticals
$10,000 in a promise not to sue
Another company called Cyril soon began pain Wagner royalties with rice
Similar pill container
Pretty soon all birth control manufacturer
We're coming out with a version of this circular design
Cheers Diane went again
Reading from the letter Wagner Road to
Smithsonian
He said some people have wondered how I made out financially
I spent about $30 on the six models I made in my basement and the rest of my cost for legal fees
Over the life of the patent
He says he netted about
London royalty
Eventually David Wagner got tired of chasing royalty application
From Pharmaceutical
Coal companies and he sold the patent rights to Ortho Pharmaceutical
You returned to his quiet life in Illinois
What is design
Camping National
Sensation
As pharmaceutical companies began marketing these new birth control pills they faced a couple Lobster
Obstacles that the packaging design would help overcome
First of all the pill marked a big turning point in the pharmaceutical industry
Before birth control only sick people took pharmaceutical drugs
The birth control pill was one of the first prescriptions intended to be
My healthy America
And so
Pharmaceutical companies design the packaging to look and not like medicine
But instead like an ordinary everyday objects
The begin packaging the pills and circular plastic cases that looked a lot like makeup
They were decorated with bright colors and graph
I would say
Flowers and butterflies are probably the most common on them
I was kind of wonder about that why
They didn't get a little more edgy at Lisa time
Pharmaceutical companies also experimented with Packaging
Make daily pill taking normal
One pill company went so far as to bundle up
Toothbrush and a bar of soap with h
Description
You know what is brush your teeth wash your face take your pill
It's kind of
You know another part of a daily routine
The other challenge that pharmaceutical companies face as they rolled out this groundbreaking new medication
Was the conservative Outlook of some doctors
In the 1960
Doctors were overwhelmingly male and some were worried about the Revolutionary in
The birth control pill would have on sex and gender roles
The subject for this afternoon
Continuing discussion
Of the pill
Is the power
Prescribed
In 1967 a group of doctors gathered in San Francisco at a symposium called the pill and the
The Puritan
The Explorer the moral in
Applications
Stop the birth control pill
Dr Donald mink
A leader in Women's Health and Family Planning
Describing the challenges
The pen presented
Preposition
Who might be uncomfortable with changing attitudes
Towards premarital sex
How can you maintain his emotional
Neutrality
In the face of rapidly changing values among his younger patient
Who's code of conduct
Often will different mark
The ethical dilemmas posed by the demand in the oven
Contraceptive advice Among The Young and unmarried has generated a good deal of anxiety and
Discomfort
In the minds of
Not only were Physicians grappling with stuff that was actually none of their business
They also thought that some of their young female patients
Might not even be responsible enough to manage their daily pill-taking regimen
Here's another doctor at the
Dr. Albert law
The girl who can't remember to take a pill every morning
This is this is one of the problems with the pill
We have to have
A patient who will understand how it is you
Correctly
Pharmaceutical companies needed to market the pill to skeptical doctors who might not be totally comfortable with the idea
Kia of women taking control of their reproductive health
Once again
I use the pills packaging to help them do that
Pharmaceutical companies produce dozens of ads that targeted Physicians
They marketed the new pill pack
As a way to help female patients
Take the pills correctly
Advertise the device as
The package that remembers for her
Or the Fool Proof
Each company insisted they are pill package design would help the female patients
Stay on schedule
Which was true the packaging did help women stay on schedule
What the marketing
Of these so-called
Compliance
Played into some doctor struggles
Birth control at a time when their cultural Authority was weakening
Here's medical historian Dominique Toby
Prior to the introduction of
Oral contraceptives the image of the physician-patient relationship is really
One in which
Patients with a male or female would really kind of just
Do what the physician said it was like this. Of medical paternalism
That
Physician Knows Best
With the introduction of the
Pill
The idea that a woman would go to the doctor's office and Demond of particular prescription that was
Something that was quite new
As the 60s progressed more and more women begin to
Taking the pill
The series of Supreme Court cases also helped establish that women
Unmarried and married
Heading legal right
Two contraceptive medication
The invention of the pill and Lisa
Subsequent legal victory
Were hailed as feminist mosto
But there was a darker
Car sign to the
In the store
Would be to one more major Revolution
Pharmaceutical package
Pill of the 1960s is not the same time we have today
The old Tale
7 times more s
And this
High dose of estrogen cause some negative side effects
Slight dizziness and nausea
As well as more serious problems like
Blood clots
High risk of cancer
Some of these problems have been apparent in early birth control trials
The trials have been conducted in the 1950s in Puerto Rico
The pill was primarily tested on low-income women
Many of them were not even aware they were participating in a medical term
Researchers mostly ignored their complaints
As the pill moved into the mainstream most women do not hear about this house
Are there doctors
I know it's hard to Fathom that the
Pill that Kim and pink paws
Compaq
The pill that millions of women carried around in their purses
The doz pills
Could be dangerous
Then in 1969
A book was
Barbara Seaman who is a journalist
At the time wrote the doctor's case against the pill which
Which documented
What she and others believe was really kind of
Play the greatest treatment by drug companies and positions on the FDA the failure to
Knowledge these serious risks around the pill as women learned about these risks
They got angry
Most didn't want the pill to be taken off the market
But they did want more transparency about the
Side effects
In 1970
Barbara Seaman's book inspired Congress to hold hearings to investigate the safety of the birth control
But no women
To testify at these hearing
It was a panel of men
Whiteman
And this not surprisingly was really al-amin to semen and other feminists
About time
And so
They protested that those hearings and demanded that their voice be heard about the pill
Each morning of the hearings a group of women from the activist group
DC women's Liberation convened up
Capital
With prepared questions and bail money
Tucked into their socks
Truman strategically place themselves in the middle of audience rows
And repeatedly interrupted the hearings
Demanding marching
Parents
Because they can justify why don't you get top priority
Was really remarkable show of activism and can
Showcasing
Capitalism of medicine at that time
Inconvenience
This way
You ladies with the
These hearings reveal that some doctors had long been aware of the negative side effects of the pill
And many had failed to adequately alert there female patient
The situation left many women feeling torn
They were grateful for the freedom and
Economy the pill
Forgive them
But they also felt betrayed by the doctors and pharmaceutical companies that had failed to warn them about the
The possible risks
At this point
The pill I've been on the market for nearly a decade
We will no longer tolerate
Intimidation by white-coated gods
Antiseptic redirecting alive
This really had a different kind of
Transformative impact on the physician-patient relationship because
The health risks around
Birth control pill.
Really
Raise the issue of like does the physician know best
Do they know best
And do they act in the best
Interested
Patient
Over the years the hormonal dosage of the pill with gradually lower
And it became much safer for women
Although there are still some negative side effects
You know the longer longer-term Legacy is that
You know now we have
A healthcare environment in which
Patients pharmaceutical consumers
I'm really much more willing
Raise questions and raise concerns
The Scandal also led to one more enduring Innovation and fill Packaging
Feminist Health activist successfully changed FDA policy
Require a typed warning of side effects to be included in every birth control package
This laid the groundwork for the side effects warnings that come in all prescription packages today
So today when you pick up a prescription
Any prescription that little type sheet you got that list every side effect from the mild to the Tower
Terrifying
You have birth control the things
Of course these interns percent their own design
If you ever tried to read one you're familiar with a tiny font the medical jargon
The completely
Overwhelming amount of information
Libido
Let's hope there's a good designer out there to make sense of all that information
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Lila turn if with Delaney Hall
Mix into production by Sharif
Music by Sean real melodium
Okay akumi
Senior producer is Katie Mingle
Kolstad is the digital Terrain
The rest of the staff includes Avery trufelman
Edmund Fitzgerald
Aaron melzer and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook and tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
We have new articles by Kate Wagner mcmansion hell
And our own Kirk posted on our website
That's 99 pi
. org
Radio tupi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com