99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Custom record
Okay
And that is producer Mark bramhill recording himself
It is Monday
November 7th
So
What's happening here where are you what is going on in the state
So I was getting ready to go to IBM's headquarters in San Jose Calif
I was going to this presentation to about
20 people
I am
Way more nervous than I thought I would be
But
It's happening
I'm just going to practice
Running through a
Little
Planned script I have
So tell us what this presentation is about
So I was getting ready to make a presentation
For something that
Approved
Would be used by millions of people all around the world he would change
Every last cell phone tablet and laptop all around
Alright I'm sold
What is it
Okay so it was a proposal for a brand new
Emoji
You know those little pictograms we used to text
Each other
Thumbs up the woman dancing for the little yellow faces that
Smile
Winker
It works sunglasses
Okay I know what an emoji is Mark Z's I'm not battle
You sound so nervous I know it's
Really really embarrassing
I'll let you know how it goes
Okay so before you tell us what your emoji was and what they got approved
I feel like
We should start with something like
Why why am I doing this whole thing
Exactly why are you doing this all day
Right so
Create Emoji it was not too because I actually planned on
But you do cover this stuff you have a podcast called Welcome to Macintosh you cover things like the intersection of Tech & Co
Culture and service seems to be part of your be
Exactly and you know I think emoji
They're kind of right at that intersect
They've become this
Really interesting part of the way that we communicate
There's kind of
Universally spoken language of pictures
But going into all this
I didn't really know that much about emoji
So I reached out to Jeremy Burger
He's the creator of emojipedia
My job is
Keeping on top of any new emojis and serve documenting how they change over time so it's her a real
Set of History lesson. Emoji they started in Japan in the 90
The first set of emojis was designed for a Japanese cell phone company by this guy named chica Taco Cody.
In 1998
When texting was still really new
There's only a hundred seventy six of them and they were 12 by 12 pixels
So that's really low rats for an emoji that's super Lopez
But these were like the first images that can be sent by a text message
Before photos or anything like that
You see the Japanese Wednesday
Very basic abstract pixel art
So these super low res emojis
Became really popular in Japan
And quickly
Almost all Japanese text messages became
Dotted with these cute little pictures
But they were still only available on Japanese cell phone
Depending on which carrier people in Japan were using
These emojis could be different from phone to phone
That's that's a problem
It seems like in our modern world of computers
This should not be happening
But the reason that this was happening was that when different cell carriers in Japan added these images for their customers
The encoded them
So when are you taking just a minute to explain what character encoding is this is Mark Davis
Every time you see a character on the screen on your
Mobile or laptop
It's always represent internally by a number
So there's some number associated with the letter A
So the problem in Japan was that
The companies weren't coordinating about
What emojis were assigned to what number
So one company might have the hamburger in coded as
Well another carrier would have the Pooh raincoat it is 44790
So when American cell phone companies decided that
They wanted to enter the Japanese Market
They do that thing he did the coating for these emojis to become standardized and they turn to Mark and his organization
A group called the Unicode
I'm the president of chicken care Consortium
People behind the curtains
Making sure that everything works
Can like plumbers you know you don't notice them as long as the water keeps flowing
They're doing the 99% invisible work
The internet
If you will
I guess all that was
So the Unicode Consortium had already been working on standardization for a while
Emoji with text
The Consortium was founded back in the early days of the internet
When there is no Universal standard for encoding texter
Anything else you saw online
People at the time we're really used to getting emails or looking at websites and they would see.
Jumbled up garbage on the screen because it was the wrong encoding
The internet used to be so ugly like when you were baby you don't even know the internet
Yeah I have I have heard stories
Unicode they were founded to help with that
Most of the work has to do with length
You're making sure
But even little known languages are legible across
Websites and Platt
That seems totally fair that make the World Wide Web worldwide make sure everyone can be represented
And ultimately
Unicode became the be-all end-all text encoding
So since people were already relying on your coat
Standardized testing coding
I thought why don't we get these guys to do Emojis for us to
Though
When Unicode was first approached about emojis in the early 2000s
They weren't interested
They thought that these cute little pictures
They're probably a passing fad
I think we were all kind of hoping and praying for that emojis are here to stay
And Fighters later around 2006
Unicode realized emojis were not going any
So they decided to take on the project of standardizing
So they looked at
All the different emoji that have been created by the Japanese carriers
Sorting through them to establish
An initial core Library
So what was in that original set of emojis
It was
Kind of a hodgepodge
2 camels
That for mailboxes 5 train
It's really important and so once they had that core Library
Unicode decided that all additional emojis
Should be considered very careful
And voted on and approved by Davis and the rest of the
No more
Two camels
Slipping through the cracks
Each emoji that we encode we really have to think does this sort of break new ground
Does it isn't going any direction is it going to be
Extremely popular because we know the faces for exam
You know the parts are very popular and so
So we try to wail these factors when we pick us up
Guys really do pick all the emojis that are on my phone that they they are the ones who decide
Yeah yeah exactly
4 times a year
Unicode meets to consider all the proposal they have for new emoji
And they are the final say in which ones are free
And once an emoji is approved
It never goes away
Emoji can only be added
Once an emoji always an emoji
Get out
And who comes up with these new ideas for emojis like who gets to submit proposals
So I had this question 2
And I asked Jeremy the guy from emojipedia
And this is what turned this story from idle curiosity
Into a year-long
The Proposal
Like who is actually
Responsible for
Bringing these
Emoji into the world
Richly anybody anyone on the planet
Can send a proposal in right now
Unicorn would look at it and there's a chance that it could become an actual emoji
So so like
I could do
Like I could send
I could send it
Yes
So of course
When Jeremy told me that
I knew that I had to submit a proposal for an emoji
What better way to understand the process been to go through it myself
But
I didn't really have an idea for
What I wanted
Propose
So Jeremy gave me a few basic guidelines
You should be trying to prove this old ready to man before you got involved don't start a petition and generate demand
He said that Unicode wants people writing proposals
To cite evidence of demand like
#usage on Twitter Instagram
Or Google search
He also said that my proposed Emoji it should be visually distinct
If it looks the same as something else it doesn't matter if it means something different emojis about what they look like
But
Two specific
But it can't be for this one really specific kind of dinosaur whatever
And at the opposite end of the spectrum
It can't be too big
Know if your emoji with just dinosaur
You might need more specificity
Like T-Rex
What's a pretty fine line but I think I can
Okay
Another thing
They don't want to add an emoji that
Potentially just
A fad right I get that
That so you don't want an emoji of like a
I don't like a fidget spinner or something like that
Yeah yeah exactly
Fidget spinners
Who knows how long those will be
You also can submit logos
Brands
Pacific people deities
Etcetera Superman and Batman
Starbucks and those are just not going to be included they have to be generic
They're already like
Do you thousand emojis right there's 2666 as of hasn't recorded
If you're not going to do Batman and Superman what doesn't exist yet that you could actually propose
So I actually asked Jeremy this
What do people really really want
And this is what he
Sorry
There is a yoga
Because what's up popular activity little lot of people around the world do if somebody decided to submit yoga and all meditating
I think that would
Eclectic
So
I'll be honest
I've never done you
I never meditated strong feelings about either one
But
I wanted to pitch in emoji
And this had good odds of being approved so namaste
I went I went full Namaste on
All kinds of research about yoga and meditation
Did you know for example Roman that there are 35 million Instagram post with hashtag yoga compared to
#running
Paltry 31 million
There have to be an emoji for yoga SF
What would you use to represent that
So I actually decided to go with an image that I felt represented both meditation and yoga
A person in Lotus
I'm at the one where you said cross-legged and you have your hands
Face up on each near and yeah
Famous
Cross-legged sitting
Yeah and so
I found some clipart on the internet to illustrate
What the Emoji might look like
And in the end I put together this eight page proposal
To submit to you
I don't pretty good about it but
I wanted to run it by someone would actually gone through the process
My name is Jenna Fraley and Isaac's actually proposed a ðŸ¥Ÿ
Her middle name is actually the number 8 which is so cool and she was actually in an episode that we did about
Fortune cookie
Yeah and she actually successfully made of
A ðŸ¥  as well
Anyway
Back in 2015
When we was working on getting the ðŸ¥Ÿ added into
She learns that Unicode is this nonprofit
But it is controlled by a small handful of
Yeah that one hit 11 full voting members of $18,000 a year to vote so
11/8 of them were us multinational company
Does oracle IBM Google Apple Facebook Yahoo
Microsoft and Adobe
Of the other three
They were the German software company sap
The Chinese Telecom company Huawei and the government of Oman
Did she say the government of Oman
Yeah because
Remember most of what Unico does has nothing to do with emoji and mostly to do with in coding language on the
So the government is there to advocate for greater Arabic language support on computer
Oh that makes
Yeah
And now we is a part of the Emoji subbed
You can't vote on which Emoji get approved but she is able to help novices like
Myself
Navigate the difficult path
Two emojis
So I showed her my proposal
It looks
Pretty solid yes
But I think your emoji characters are little bit ugly
No
Well
You did use clipart
Fair
Fair probably not the standard of emoji characters I don't know where you got them but you might do them
In more like either the APA style or more of the Google style she was right
My design
Was not great
So
I ditched these clipart images
And hired a professional
A woman named Abby Messer
Just to let my case would be stronger
And unicode would have a better idea of what this Emoji could look like
I polished my proposal
Person meditating
And submitted it
Wright Avenue
And then a few weeks later
So I'm just coming into the studio now I just got an email
From unicode
She let me load it up
Says
The Emoji subcommittee has decided to forward your proposal to the UTC
Docket number will BL2 / 16 -
Regards
All right
All right that's it
So that sounds like good news but what does that actually mean basically means that I got through the first round
That Unicode was going to hold
Unofficial vote on my emoji
And at this point you know you can sit back and see what happens
Or if you are extra excited
Like I was
You can actually show up to a quarterly meeting of the Unicode technical committee
And present your proposal in real
Is it that brings us back to you being
Super nervous before your presentation
Back in November
Okay
It is Monday
November 7th
Today is the day that I'm presenting to the Unicode
Technical committee
But before we get to that
I want to talk about someone I met while I was there in the Bay Area
She was also there to make a presentation to you
Her name is Rio Alameda
My name is Rafael from Brady I'm 15 years old
She's 15 years old like in high school and she wrote up one of these proposals like you did
Yeah this is
No small task
I've never written any
Proposals whatsoever the closest thing I've done we're lab report
Inside slots
But for real
This whole thing just had a totally different level of importance
You mean that some people do this not just to make up cool radio psoriatic
Folkyeah
Because emojis represent culture
And just like it matters to see a representation of your culture in
Television in the movies
Turn yourself in an emoji can feel important in the same way
I mean
Humans all over the world Shenzhen like
6 billion of these little things to each other everyday totally there everywhere
Yeah
And so in The Last 5 Years
Unicode has tried to represent more people
By adding
Characters with a range of different skin tone
They batted some gay characters and gender-neutral androgynous ones as well
But there was still no one that looks like Ray you
Because
She wears a hijab
Aikido be nice for me to
On the keyboards
That I could use
Felt like her Emoji would help other women who wear hijabs feel more represented in mainstream
Even though it is something small I think it will you notice normalize the hijab you'll definitely be
That might be the coolest like
Coolest kids
I like it because it does
Pause I just told her friends were going to have to sell cupcakes
Even for the teachers
It be something so amazing
Hopefully desk
Well now I'm totally rooting for you
Choose more than one rabbit you can root for us both if it's between you and her
It's definitely her
Okay that's that's fair that's
So are you tonight we're both presenting to Unicode on the same day
11:30
When it was my turn they made me turn off my microphone
So I don't have tape of what I say
But basically I gave a little spiel about
Why the world was in dire need of a yoga emoji
I got a few laughs heads
It lasted about 5 minutes
Then I took a few question
After it was over I stood there
Waiting for some indication of
Weather in the committee liked it
And if they like it
They wouldn't say
Finally someone told me basically you need to leave so we can vote
I left
I just figured that they'd be in touch soon
Okay yeah
So if your emoji is approved
Then what happens next
So even though I submitted this really beautiful visual for my person meditating emoji
It's really more just to demonstrate what it could look like
Ultimately
If emojis approved
Google Facebook and apple and all other platforms
Will get to decide what exactly person meditating looks like in their own platform Style
So I talk to someone from Google
My name is Rachel being I'm a creative director at Google
On the material design team
Butts
She has another title
Oh yes
I am also
Funnily enough
The creative director of emoji
Google
Once Rachel bean and her team get the list of new emojis and their codes from unicode
Those are the images to be used on all of Google's Android phone
And what kind of guidance do they get from Unicode about
How to draw them how to make them look
Right so they don't actually give them
All that much they give them the name of the emoji and a few key words of things that might represent
Occasionally they might give
A little bit of guidance of
You know
The Bagel Emoji it should be drawn slice
So that people won't confuse it with the donor
To it
So that makes it so that Google emojis
I'm different from Apple emojis and they look
Twitter emojis are all different
Exactly
Characters might be facing in a
Different direction
A different outfits on or maybe dancing another Style
But it's all illustrate the same basic con
And recently
Rachel be in entertainment Google have redesigned the entire Library
Of Android
Broly emojis that weren't
Disembodied faces
The team had to deeply consider
All the clothing and accessories that they were
Because
Designing for a global audience
Take for example the farmer
Originally we had designed the farmer Emoji very American Gothic style
So
Pitchfork
And wearing overalls
But
A lot of farmers all around the world
They don't actually use
Pitchforks
It's kind of an old and very American characterization
And also the overalls to some degree
Weren't necessarily the outfit the most Farmers globally where
So you change the actual profit the farmer was holding into a grain
So to really put more emphasis on what
Grown University versus tools that may not be universally used
And this kind of global inclusivity
Is the same stuff they'll have to consider with the Emoji that I propose
You know other person meditate
What will it wear
Like what's the color of the clothing
Is
He or she or they going to be wearing
Games
Leotard tshirt
You know it's good that they're thinking about this but
The Google designers and never going to really be able to fairly represent all culture
Right
And unicode is this governing body with
A bunch of Representatives
But they're all mostly from these
Big Tex
And so this whole system it
Kind of works.
Is not a good system you shouldn't have to ask these people's permission
This is Keith winstein I'm Keith winstein I'm an assistant professor of computer science here Stanford
And he says if there is not an emoji that represents you order
Your culture
Unicode process for getting one is not exactly
But having to wait until two or three years for it to end up in the standard and that's a long time
It doesn't take
Quite that long anymore it's closer to 1 or 2 years
But still
Winston points out that are already platforms like
Swac that let you take an image and make an emoji size
You don't need to go through Unicode yeah totally because a critical stat on our staff he does this any makes a
Mod for every episode of we shared when the episode comes out
And is this a little picture it's not really an emoji
Exactly
And so there is no special encoding process
Required to make
This is a much simpler way of doing it rather than trying to cram everything into
Unicode
And even though I think Winston gets at some really important criticisms
If we went to a system where we really just sent
Tiny pictures
Then the things that I really love about emojis
What kind of bee loss
Which is that they turned into this store
Universal standardized language of pictures
Like the idea that some stranger in Argentina and I are both sending a ðŸ˜ to express love
Think there's something really cool about that
That is a nice quality to another Universal
So so what happened with your meditating person you must know by now
So for a few days after my presentation
I still haven't heard anything
No email thanking me for my proposal 1
Letting me know when I hear back or
Anything you like
It was just total radios
And then I was just scrolling on Twitter
I'm so I just saw
That emojipedia has a
Tweeted about some of the new emoji
Paige
Person with a beard
Star eyes
Zebra giraffe that's really cool
Sea mine
Serious face with symbols covering mouth
Face with open mouth vomiting
Person in steamy room
Person climbing
Person in Lotus position for yoga and meditation.
There we go
So that's it you're is fast and more importantly reuse past that's so great
Yeah both of ours were accepted and I am super excited
Probably tell
So they they change the name of mine from person meditating to
Person in Lotus position
Unicode really likes the specificity of these things
And as of now we're recording in August of
It's on your phone just yet
But person in Lotus position
The hijab emoji and always new ones
Should be on your phone by the end of the year
So when you get the ðŸ§˜ on your phone
You can think of Mark
And how he doesn't even like yoga
No but that's that's the same
I actually have started doing yoga and meditation it's one of the many things that came out of doing the story
Assurance to appreciation of yoga and meditate
That's remarkable well then Namaste for real then
Namaste Roman
You know that just means hello right
More mod talk after these fine people pay for our listening experience
Praise dance
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad to take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Are female dancing bunnies
Is vs. are male dancing bunnies we made the decision that they're wearing the exact same outfit
Men get the skimpy leotard just like the ladies
Really gender a lot of it is
Social cross
Attract advertising to be more Universal
It's it's sometimes good to eliminate some of the social constructs so doesn't
Co-Sleeper bassinet for one
Another
Yeah also I just have to say that that men in
Dancing men with bunny ears
What is my favorite emoji
Me too
I love that we kept
The man
Wearing little a little leotard instead of
But I'm short.
That was one of the the best moments of my career
Iconic
But I but I do think
I do think the Great
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Mark bramhill with Katie mingle in Avery truffelman
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
Music by brake master cylinder melodium lullatone and Sean real our digital director is Kirk olsat
Sedin includes Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald Aaron Mazza
And me Roman Mars
The story was adapted from Martha podcast welcome to Macintosh where is currently airing a multi-part series on emoji
Goes a lot deeper than we could fit into these 25 minutes so if there are things are still wondering about
Emoji related
They're probably answered in this series
The first episode is out now you can find it at McIntosh. FM or wherever you listen to
And so has lots of other episodes about design and technology that you beautiful nurse
Are bound to enjoy
We commissioned original Emoji art from Cara rose difabio that tells the complete
Story of this episode entirely in emoji you have to see it is at 99 Pi. Org
And finally thanks to rishikesh her way for explain to us on The Illusionist podcast
What Namaste actually means
I heard it
It's a joke
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX I collected the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
And coin carrying listeners just like you
You can find show intro in discussions about the show on Facebook and Twitter me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 Peoria
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
What are fabulous home on the internet with more design story than we can ever tell you in audio form use our website
And 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com