99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
On May 8th 1945 the Allied Powers declared victory in Europe
Putting it into the Nazi regime
President Truman address the nation
General Eisenhower in farms
The forces of Germany have surrendered
For the United Nation
Much remains
There was a lot to be done
Rebuilding Europe
Setting up a provisional government
And getting Germany to be Wes
Well nausea
Our producer Sam Greenspan is just back from Deutschland
And to that end
There was one thing the Americans and the British and the French and the Russians
All wanted out of Germany
It was a book
Mine comp or my struggle was Adolf Hitler's fictionalized autobiography outlines his political
Audiology in plans for Germany's future
It's a synthesis of his hatred for Jews and other groups
It was everywhere
Whole number
Excel copies
Of mine come only in Germany
At the end of World War II was 12 points
5 million
Ants around 1 billion
Copies in
Many many different
Editions and translations
In other languages
This is Sven felix kellerhoff
A journalist and author of a book about 9
He says that according to one survey after the war every V
Xiamen
105 1/2
Mind Kampf
Mein kampf was given out to people when they join the Nazi party
And in some cities
The government would even give it as a wedding gift
If I copy to a fresh married
As we do to a close a lot of Germans threw away or burn their copies of mine comp
No one wanted to look like a Nazi to the occupying Army
Still
The Allies felt the need to ban the book
Especially the Americans
Military government
Maiden law in 445
Which Nazi party itself and
And also
This law Bans
A mine comp no mine comp was only banned outright for a few years after all the Third Reich had been infamous
For censorship and banning books
In the last thing the new German Republic wanted was to look like Nazis
Hitler's intellectual property
Including mine
Was ultimately given to the government
The state in southern Germany where Hitler Rose to power
And the Bavarian government decided that as the copyright owners
They would not publish any new German editions of Mein Kampf
And it would seek to limit and control who had access to the book
That way they could make sure it was used only for scholarship
And Nas in an attempt
To revive
Fascism
And it just so happened that Germany had the perfect tool for the job
Something to help them deal with sensitive information that's neither censorship nor
Open access
The gift shop
Gary was
Once Upon a
What time
YouTube
All this is the release of the room
We are in the gifts trunk
Gift shop
Gift meaning poison
Shrug meaning Kaiser cupboard or cabinet
Poison cabinet
Or in this case
A room in the basement of the Bavarian State Library
The word gif
Can actually mean
The few different
In a pharmacy it's a place for keeping controlled substance
But one of the oldest usages
Going back
Hundreds of years
Is a gift wrong
Of a library
A boxer place to Lockaway material
Deemed unfit for the public
These materials were set aside not so much to protect them from people
Protect people from them
Little biohazard sounds for information
Over the course of centuries
Steve poison cabinet
German libraries
Have emptied and filled up
Emptied again and filled up again
They're content speaking volumes about what German Society considers dangerous
At any given moment
You can read the gift shine as a
Cultural history of
Morality of behavior
A staff Astorian at the Bavarian State library and author of a book about its gift shrunk
The name of my Bukis
Deactivate trunk
Are otic sexual Christmas Chef political literature
BBQ spare ribs in Boucher dividers in Stroudsburg
The gift shrunk erotic sexuality politics and literature
Hidden book
Of the Bavarian State Library
This Story begins
In this library at shortly after the foundation in 16th century
At this time in the 1580s
Vario was a kingdom inside of the Holy Roman Empire
Which didn't want the public reading works
They considered heretical
They put aside authors like Martin Luther and Galileo even some Catholic office which will not
Okay for the
Catholic Church
Well these anti-clerical writings may have been prohibited
The powers-that-be didn't just round up all the copies they can
Find Burnham
They thought it would be good to hold on to them
You have better arguments if you know what the other side sings
At the order of the Duke of Bavaria the library took all the Forbidden literature
Put it in a lockbox and called it
Deactivate trunk the poison cabinet
The Box contained about 500 works
Opposed by the
The Catholic Church
Which around only as a means of reference
It's for those working to oppose the people
Who opposed the church
They
May not be used without permission of the
The Juke
Overtime
The Catholic Church's grip over Europe got weaker
What is 18 hundreds to give shrunks of German libraries were less concerned with protecting us from the Protestant writings of
Martin Luther
And more concerned with protecting us from sex
And this came to the fore when the king of Bavaria acquired a private collection of books
That had belonged to a guy named fun
Printer France Fontana library to house Franz von printers collection
Which was an assortment of books
For adults
Books
Concerning love in all that prospectus
Marquis De Sade of course
Something about weeping and so on which was
Repeating
People who like to be whipped and okay
Unwilling to throw these controversial books out and unwilling to make them readily available
Librarians found a home for Bond cleaners erotica collection in the gift Ron
And they were very serious about keeping its contents secure
There were two keys
And only if
They virtual care that they could open that
The gift wrap
It's like it like a nuclear launch
Yeah and some people believe that the books inside the gift wrong
We're so dangerous
They could literally make you sick
There was one librarian at the time who got crazy
Yusuf She-Ra
And he put mentally ill
And after he was in the hospital his friend
When trees room
Open the caplets so many of trainers books inside and said
I think that must have
Being the reason for his illness
Time pass
Germany fought and Lost World War
And from the rubble of that to feed brew a liberal counterculture
Donna is Proclaim that art was dead expressionist films afford the darkness of the Soul Berliner is past lay down
Hours at cabarets nudists challenged traditional modesty Burlington in 1920s
It was sent off
All forms of
Different m
Life experiments
And at the center of all this
Was a physician named Magnus hirschfeld
And he founded the institute for
All those people which had another
Sexual orientation than usual
Hirschfeld also promoted acceptance of transgenderism
STD prevention contraception and women's emancipation
He wrote that
The woman who needs to be liberated most
Woman in every man
Handsome men
Liberated moose
What does liberal Renaissance in Berlin
Would not last for long
As a Nazi party Rose to power hirschfeld Institute for sexual Sciences had become a Target
Magnus hirschfeld
Was very famous at the
Time he was
Gay he was a Jew and he was left it
The German Student Union
Rated Magnus hirschfeld Institute
They threw many of his books onto the street and burn them
This is 4 days before Nazis all across Germany
Started burning books by Jewish authors in public rallies
But even so the new regime didn't get rid of every
The rain start Library they said we have to keep
Keep them because
Have to know what the enemy rides and two
5%
Magnus hirschfeld books went into the gifts Ron
12 years later in 1945
The Nazis had lost the war
And now their own literature including of course mine,
Was thrown into the gift Ron
The Hope was to Dina to find Germany and build a new Society
Germany did not
Become a noose
He became to new Society
Are the Communist barrier between East and West Berlin Rose higher
Stronger
The more determined Grosso Villalobos
On the Border
East berliners are forced to evacuate their home
Has the Communist police moved
To prevent their escape
The two germanys would eventually each have their own government
Their own culture and of course their own Library
And the contents of each side's gifts Ron
Became a mirror for what was deemed dangerous
In east and west
So the Nazi stuff
Mine comp
And the writings of Joseph Goebbels and
Alfred Rosenberg
This could be found in gift shrunks in both west
Andy's
West Germany actually thinned out there GIF trunk overtime allowing more access to
So-called pernicious information
In East Germany it was the opposite
East Germany was dictatorship so they were
I like a very obvious and straight censorship
Western Print material wasn't normally accessible this is Elena Demco
While she was a student at University
She was looking to read some band check poetry
And with the help of an idealistic professor
She was able to get access to the room where the University Library kept
Gets banned material
What's the nickname Ross gift home
Poison room
Nervous and excited when I went there
It's a very
Representative
19th century building
So you have to go to the major staircase and go up to Majors Steakhouse
And keep going up
Smallest smallest staircase
Spiral staircase
Houston in front of pantry door
It was made of iron and had
Big circular
Glass window made of Barista class
Henna tattoos at the same time in order to open the door
Past the bunker door was a dark room
Western looking lady check to see if your name was on the list
Then she got your book
And let you go through another door
And then you went into the like small reading room
Ritual synonym
Station of glass
Very very pleasant sunny
Place
In East Germany to get strong had become a place you can visit
And in this library at the University of Leipzig
The gift shrunk was actually a pretty lovely place to be
Define assuage
Elena have been hoping to meet other counter
Who were also there to read politically
Literature I was disappointed realizing that the other
People we're not reading politically
Relevant literature
And when I saw
You're pretty students
Reading fish literature I thought OKC Jedi prophecy
Get access to this room to read
Fashion magazines from the West
Within about a year of Elena visiting the poison room
The East German government had collapsed
The Border was opened
In Germany
Was reunified
All across the former East
Gift trunks
Frank
Literature critical of the East German government magazines that showed life in a capitalist Society
They were taken out from behind iron bunker doors
And returned to normal circulation
Today the physical rooms and cabinets that once served as gift trunks all across Germany are mostly empty
Their contents return to the regular stacks
But on everything
Today mine comp is kept in what step on counter cause
Assault
Virtual gift wrap
A virtual gift song meaning there's no physical box or even a particular room cordoning off the books from the
Rather the library relies on the infrastructure of their catalog and checkout system to create a series of checkpoints between
When the user
In books at the library wants to keep an eye on
When you search for mine comp in the database
You can't just order it
You have to go see Susie
Susie coolback was the librarian on the desk.
And she said the first thing to do
Go to our
The permission
And as long as you don't seem like a Nazi you can get a copy of Minecon
No problem
The process of accessing Minecon from the Bavarian State Library should feel
Pretty familiar to anyone who's ever got material from an academic Library
If your underage
From the parents
Speed runs like a god
Peasants
Go seek
Well
Good luck getting through Susie
If someone says I want to get this book because I want to learn how to be a Nazi
Then comes in
Though if you do go to the trouble of checking out mine comp
Just don't go in expecting too much
I read it
These days of course you don't need a library to read mine Kampf in Germany
It's not hard to find a copy at an antiquarian bookstore
And a text has been on the internet for at least a decade
Cuz you can get Nazi literature
In the internet and so on but even if the book is readily available on the internet
Stephan calendar says the library still has responsibility
To try to control who leads their copies
And for what purpose
Even if it's
Anachronistically have to be a little careful
Not a little bit have to be careful with
Part of
Law Library
And now for the first time since Hitler was in power
New copies of Mein Kampf are on sale in Germany
On January 1st
2016 the copyright of mine comp expire
Which means
This book is now in the public domain
The Institute for contemporary history in Munich has just published a new critical edition of mine comp
This Edition is Big it's heavy it's expensive it's two volumes with 1,500 pages of footing
Notes and commentary meant to disprove and contextualize all of Hitler's claims
There's no way you can mistake it as anything other than serious
Scholarship
It makes you work through layers and layers of critique in order to get to Hitler's writing
It's almost as if the Publishers wrap a gift shrunk
Around the new edition of mein kampf
To let the world would be inoculated
From its poison
99% invisible with produces with by Sam Greenspan the Katie mingle Clemente Delaney Hall
Profuse f&me Roman Mars we have so many people to think this week many of them have names that I cannot pronounce so I asked
Send thank-you to Tobias Colt vilhelm hilpert and Peter stitzlein at the Bavarian State Library
Agnes breast in and Simone Paul Michael at the center for contemporary history in Munich
Sarah
Rummikub
Louisa back in the city Miller
Daniel vessel
Zigfried locutus burned Florida
Michelle krasowski and Jeremy
Thank you one and all
Thanks also to okay akumi and melodium for providing some of the music this week we'll have a full list on website
We are production of 99% invisible ink project kalw 91.7 in San Francisco
Introduced of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors for
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Can find this show and join the fine community of people who would like to show on Facebook
I love seeing all the night IPI coins showing up on Twitter and Instagram but if you want to explore the 99% invisible
Activity that shapes the design of our world
I recommend you spend some time
With 99 pi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com