99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If you know anything about central European cities
When you hear Warsaw he think
Gray
Ugly
Communist but there is a part of Warsaw that is anything but those things
The Old Town historic district
It just like any other quite European city
Tourist shops horse carriage rides Church fires
The buildings are beautiful
But actually
It's all fake
It just a replica of what once was
Like so many European cities during the second world war Warsaw was destroyed it had to be rebuilt
Now when you walk around the reconstructed historic part of Warsaw
You'll find these big glass mounted plaques on his way on the sidewalk
In the emerald painting so they start buildings in front of you
The first time I noticed one of these displays anniversary out street and I was completely drawn in
I study the painting and then I studied the building above
And just like I was set up to I thought
Wow they did an amazing job rebuilding it
But then later our reporter Amy just us Cafe found out
It's not quite like that
You're entering something which is effectively
A stage set
Intended to recreate
And I miss fear of a sudden.
But you're on your way over there
That's me how modovsky he was born in Warsaw
Now he's a social anthropologist
The Cambridge University
He told me about the incredible process of putting the city back together again
It's a challenge a lot of European cities were facing after the war
Warsaw's massive rebuilding of its entire medieval Old Town
Was lauded as one of the most impressive rebuilding post-war projects on the continent
They made it look to everyone
Like they reclaimed what was lost
But here's the thing Warsaw historic old town is not a replica of the real thing
And historic City
It never really was
So it's back up for the mystery
Sure Warsaw was damaged during the war as what other cities
That really worse off occupied by Nazi forces
Got hit particularly hard
One of the worst cases in the whole War
Practically the whole city was destroyed
People quibble about the exact statistics but most agree it was something like over 80
Percent of the core part of Warsaw
Really most of the city
Especially the part supposed considered important
Dupatta surviving pools for an 11th Hour attempt
Steak after capital
Hitler gave an order
Ossify Warsaw
Raise it
To the ground
Luma goes to high buildings
Disable using civilians. Doesn't work has pearls and Jewellers
They bite for today
2 days
Hi
The destruction was focused on the most important buildings in the nose
Significant
Historical buildings
Because day weather
Identify the past and national identity in that that was exactly what was identified as most important to get rid of
Warsaw burns the Soviets ready to take over after the retreating German forces
Stood on the other side of the river
Starling forces did nothing to help the polls in the Warsaw Uprising or save their City
It's not anyone in the instruction to fail because destroyed Warsaw
Would be that much easier to take over
Once the Germans were defeated
After the war
Warsaw is in ruin
Was liberated in January.
And this is when the inhabitants. Coming back
Tool saw and the Zodiac descriptions info people
Can you show me the bags in the Han just wandering around
Dazed
Unable to find their old homes and then unable to recognize anything
This wants muscle
Maybe again after a year
The true meaning of that battle will be assessed by soldiers and historian
Maybe a bigger and more beautiful city will be built on the road
DaVita Capital revenue and better problems
This one
Dinosaur jokes dead
Common chords
Andrew died in Bethel
Is to live forever
The first there was talk of giving up
Moving the capital to another city
But instead pulsus I didn't start over
Scratch
Much of the city was rebuilt according to communist
Cheap and big
Apartment blocks wide Avenues heavy gray buildings
Communist ideology in architectural form
But when it came to the historic district of Warsaw the old town and a long connecting section called The Royal route
They decided to restore not just rebuild
Anne Hathaway planners were going about it
Historians archaeologists
All the specialist involved
It really seemed like they're going to bring Old Warsaw
To life
There was this incredible focus on authenticity
In rebuilding the old town so
That was ready to give an emphasis for the Old Town
To be built from the same
Physical matter
Has the old
So
That was a special kilums
What built on the outskirts of Louisville
Weather rubble from the old town
Was taken
I made into bricks from was the old time was to be rebuilt
I'm the bricks that were reusable that would just sort of lying
Around in the rubble
They were collected and they will clean the neighbors 2
Polished copper and a Wii used
Building these new old building
You took several years
But they did it
The new old town was first opened
People are happy
Static have a back
Even in the last it was seen as a major accomplishment
A kind of Victory after all the destruction of the war
Triumph of the human spirit
The pictures from the time she was sort of Carnival as it was unveiled
You can see it from old photographs people are kind of joyfully wandering around this miraculous be recreated
Play Switchfoot have disappeared forever
This is something that made
Millions of people very happy
Thousands of people of Ordinary People participated
It was really a very successful kind of social solidarity exit
So the old city was brought back to life
How people started to notice something kind of strange
It seems like Old Warsaw
What's a little bit off
There are these descriptions.
David Crowley houston
Unemotional talks about
Of people who knew the old town before the war wandering around in density feeding this this kind of uncanny
Disjunction between
This is Heath. V remember them in the city.
They wandering around now
It was almost the same it felt incredibly
The first one is very closely to what they knew before but then something wasn't quite right
Remember what I said earlier about warsaw's Old Town not being a re-creation
But instead a reimagining
It turns out that despite all that effort to use exact same bricks from the rubble
That show of authenticity was just that
The show
Like morosky said before
Disorder stage set
And this is
Highlights even more about the fact that United the passage that the couples
Everything seemed absolutely
Fine and then you wonder through the doorway
And you wonder into hectometers
Imagine
Staircase
I'm heading to imagine flat
With this kind of
Historical experience hitting that there was this to very uncanny sense
It's not just the builders concentrated on the exteriors of the buildings and didn't bother creating what was by
Warsaw historic district
Was incredibly odd
By Design
Cuz actually it was different
It was never supposed to be exactly the same as it was
So
Visit this weird disjunction between this incredible and fishes and with intensity old bricks being reused and
Special K was being built for this purpose this
Big focus on on continuity
Physical continuity
But at the same time there was a very clearly stated
Idea that the Old Town shouldn't be the same old town
492 touchdown should be better than
So it should be a more perfect
Old Town
It existed before the war
Before the war ironically
Warsaw historic Old Town the slowly fading away on a
Before the word was basically
It was a slum it was more or less
It didn't have proper storage facilities I didn't have proper draining
It was basically lived in by very poor and Appleton
With a few kind of judges in and none of another see the cathedral was in
And the Royal costume
The beyond the castle Square the Old Town Square was the location first
Haphazard Market
I'm looking into the table
Is the prestigious
Had been
Ruined every time
But after the war reeling from loss piled upon loss
Historic Warsaw took on a new meaning
Now that it was missing completely
It had more power in Polish people's memory
And if it was around
No matter what
Set of the Communist way of thinking
The Old Town needed to be rebuilt
So that it could be
Forgotten
The cynical argument is that the old town was rebuilt as assertive ideological camouflage so
In order to master
The fact that protein was being taken over by a certain
Alien power
This alien power decided to rebuild the old town to make it seem
Like they had some surgery
Extra Comfy Couch
Republic history wise in reality they was undermining everything undermining the old
The social structure
Everything that came before them
It's like this
If warsaw's historic Capital just got leveled over and replaced by grey ugly apartment blocks
People with long for what they were missing
They remember their significant
Today
The seat
Of the nation
Cast
And not only longed for it
They make a martyr of it
The Terrace passed
Killed by communism
Are the Soviets
The same Soviets by the way you stood on the other side of the river and watched for saltburn
And the Communist whenever whenever the polls
In The Old City back
The Communists made it
Hopefully their partner
Destruction
Forgettable
Pass
Stop being such a distraction
And they can go about their business of overhauling the cut
So that's why they decided to rebuild the Old Town
But they didn't touch a way to keep their core ideals intact
And this is where it gets really weird
When city planners were looking for inspiration and had a better rebuild Warsaw
They went back further
And just before the war when the old town was far from its heyday
1930s
They look to the 1830s
Take one of the most famous streets in the old part of town
Devesh Fiat New World Street
For decades before the war nervous Fiat Street was one of the liveliest places in Warsaw
Hello shop
Cafes in hotels
Overtime
Who wants uniform buildings there started to take on differ
Heights
A different owners with extra levels
Expand and improve
And then when it was rebuilt it was decided that this too too bustling capitalists in that got a Therrien
Atmosphere of no shots
It was improper
And so it was rebuilt effectively in the image of how it would have looked
In the early 19th century
In the city
Classicist
Lowe's Patio stair
Simple
Style
I'm needle to buildings but where would you stay
Dua to three stories
Answer this is suitable to this is an attempt to make it into an egalitarian kind of enlightened Ministry
Rather than usage of nasty
Capital
Cutthroat lese fast
Street that I have been in the in the 90s
And here's where it gets even weirder still
For other parts of Old Warsaw
Those for city planners went back further still
To the 7th
Toy City
The never really existed
A city imagined by an Italian painter
Remember this sidewalk
Display as I mentioned earlier the ones that show pictures of Warsaw before the war
It turns out that the paintings are by an Italian named Bernardo bellotto
He was what's called a venutis
Beanie specialize in the Venetian Art of realistically painting cityscape
And precisely documenting their details
He was invited to Warsaw in the late Seventeen hundreds by the king of Poland
To become court painter and make pictures of
The capital
Help his work below to use a camera obscura
The predecessor of the photographic
And he had an incredible eye for detail
So the 20-plus paintings he created what a pretty remarkable document of what Warsaw look like then
Except for one thing
The lotto had a tendency to make
Fu
Improve
And one level
The paintings were incredibly precise
But on another level below day was
He was very prone to making stuff up
So she didn't sit
Stairway from indulging his autistic lights
So you have
In several examples uprichard fight
The building she was painting
Like adding a story to a building here adding some decoration there
Maybe changing the number of windows in a building
All sorts of little things
The met the paintings
More pleasing to
The king of Poland loved
And so it turned out later did the Communists
They like the Lopez paintings because they showed a full range of society
Not just the elite
They also liked
His paintings because they were out of the city
For the Heyday of capitalism
When Warsaw
They sought
Still pure
In fact
There was plenty of other documentation of Warsaw historic section
A group of Architects and students
Painstaking work
During the war before the destruction
Creating blueprints
Taking photographs
And a lot of those blueprints were used in the war song reconstruction
But when it came to rebuilding the Old Town
Balotas paintings became the primary source
Now you can see the evidence
Busy building codes Young's house
Which is attitude 18 century
Townhouse
He basically said these kinds of freezes into
Coughing
Facade
I think the number of floors was changed as well
Some of the roof detailing was changed
If you look at it first if you compare a photograph
Of this building from
99 NFL draft
Publix today and the painting
You can see that basically the stuff that bill to
I did to the building
Because it's now in reality
So he's such a
Two flights of fantasy
Materialized in in the weight of the building look soft
The city's historic Warsaw buildings like John's house
They never exist
Dead at least not like they do now
In the city continues to recreate itself in the form of these paintings
Recently they finished a huge remodeling of the royal roots
Winding sidewalks renovating a church
Sade looks exactly like it doesn't below toes painting
But never like they actually looked before
It's like making an imaginary City come to life
In the end Warsaw has at Old Town
Groups of children on School field trip strip dutifully through it
Taurus conspicuously absent for the rest of the
The city block there
And varsovians themselves
Largely avoided
It's a place for your kind of begrudgingly obligated to bring out-of-town visitors
You are Fisherman's Wharf your Navy Pier I'm sure you know and hate the one in your town
Sunday or holiday with your family
But you don't think of it as the real Warsaw
I feels more like Disney Zapped
There's a certain young hipster contingent in Warsaw
The troubles instead and
Ugliest parts of the city
Failed communist experiment
They scoff at the old town because it's so fake
Such tourist trash
But moroski says they're wrong
It's the old town that really represents
What the city and the nation itself
Has been through
It's equal parts truth
Then falsehood
Ideology in art
It's trauma
And the anti D recovery
It comes after
99% invisible was written and produced this week by Amy dress.
And Dave McGuire with help from Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
It's a project to 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy, go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black podcast
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled into weed
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
Talking about and pictures of Italian painting brought to life in Warsaw
And 99% invisible
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com