99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
All over New York City there are semi clothes or nude women
And they are so baked in architecture that we don't even see them
For example when you enter the New York Public Library on the left hand side
Is a sculpture of a young woman leaning against the horse
On 59th and 5th
Little statue of a woman holding a basket
107th Street and Broadway there's a woman
Reclining on a bed
That's former New Yorker Avery troubleman
100th and Riverside Drive
Stone woman sits
In a chair
The child
And on a very
Top of the New York Venus
Support building
There's a golden woman
Holding a
Crown
And these women
Or actually
The same woman
Audrey Munson
Was the most famous artist model
In the United
Midstates statues at the Met are made in her likeness in the memorial
Regal buildings all over New York City
She basically was the equivalent of a supermodel at the time this is Andre Agassi
An artist herself and author of Queen of the artist
The story of Audrey month
Everybody knew who she was her picture was in the papers
And if one trust Legends I call every boy had a crush on her
She was a very desired
A young woman
In her lifetime
She would go on to decorate buildings and Memorial
Is all over the United
It states
Before becoming a movie star
And eventually getting embroiled in a sensational murder scandal
And although Audrey Munson's body has been immortalized in iron and marble
Her name is mostly forgotten
But she was a prolific writer and pandas series of Articles telling her life in her own words
Sometimes and the third person
Where is she now
This model who was so beautiful
What has been horrible
Is she happy and prosperous
Arshi sad and forlorn
Her beauty God
Leaving only memories in the way
Like so many supermodels that would come after her
Audrey Marie Munson with scouted
On the streets of New York City
Audrey's mother and father were divorced which was very unusual at the time
And her mother decided to get a fresh start in the big city
Audrey was 15 enrolled in music school
And one day
She was picked up on the street by a photographer
When she walked around with her mother this photographer gave Audrey his card and asked if she would pose for some portrait
Her mom was invited to so intentions were good
These photos were fully clothed
Audrey
By chance was picked up as a model and then in the studio
Proof that she was somebody
Who was very good with the camera
Very good in creating and generating poses
This photographer recommended that Audrey me to front of hits the famous sculptor Isadora Conte
At first, he thought he didn't really need Audrey
But as Audrey herself later recall
Suddenly he rose from the table
What about me asked me to stand and walk
And then said that he thought he could use me
But significant
You will have to pose in the altogether
Posing in the altogether mint posing naked
Audrey's mother consent
If they would have been wealthy people
I don't think her mother would have let her pose in the nude
From that encounter the resulting sculpture was
The three muses
Three nude women with their arms around each eye
All three
Model.
For decades the sculpture was in the lobby of the hotel
Audrey called this statue quote
A souvenir of my mother's consent
And this was the first of many sculptures that you would model for his Door County
Audrey began to work from many other famous artists in New York
As a reputation grew she's recommended from Studio to studio and slowly
Her likeness appeared
Mostly naked or half-naked
All over the city
1913 the New York Sun dubbed her Miss Manhattan
But Audrey is not always recognizable in sculpture her figure is different in different artist dies
Sometimes she's lying
Sometimes she's Fuller
In sculpture the sculpture there are no obvious giveaway is that you're looking at Audrey's body
The clues are interface
It's the expressions
Of the eyes
Is in the mouth into nose
Like once you know how she looks you can see her everywhere
It's really fascinating I would like to look at sculptures in the map and be like
That looks like her and then research and be
Yeah be right that was her
Before it was easy for artists
The snapper reference
Audrey could pose in a way
I could have booked a mood
She must have been a very empathetic person she could really
Translate emotion
Fully into her body
Battery can hold the same pose for hours sometimes for an entire day
And she worked closely with the artist
Learning their temperaments
She thought of herself as a collaborator
That she told the New York Herald in 1915
Study yes indeed I do
Every model who is a real success must study the work of the persons
She is with
Audrey's unique set of skills aren't her a decent salary
About $35 a week
Which today would be like $800 a week
She made enough to give a day's salary to the suffragists
Which is in full swing around
Audrey with an independent
Confident Woman
Had a good time to be
Because the architecture that was in Vogue in the United States from the end of the 19th century through World War I was the
Bozart Style
And this style required a lot of sculptures and detailed ornamentation
It was
A great time in many ways
To be an artist this is architectural historian Karen McNeil
Whether you an architect
Skelter
Painter
Across person making lamps
Using Bozart style architecture virtually all state capitals are in this style
That image of an authoritative building with
Columns and statues all around maybe a big dome
That's Bozarth
The style is a cross between like
Italy Greece
Parthenon and Flowery French Versailles
So opposed our building
It's a greek temple but then you do have the sculptures on it you do have the freeze work you do have all of this
Ornamental detail that is integral to the building
An architecture and sculpture
Are we bound together in this movie
When you take the decorative elements off of a bozar building
It started looking weird the dimensions don't
White work anymore but also the sculptures are signs of a building
The very overly representational
Like in a private home the statues are of domestic scenes or on a market there of harvest and eating
Free government building say San Francisco City Hall it's all going to tell us about this is the seat of government
In California so great and fabulous and
But it's all going to be allegorical
In a government building
Might find a statue of a woman holding an olive branch
Or the scales of Justice
Representing the state liberty
You name it
Just women placed on this
Pedestal
Virtue
Morality
Motherhood nurturing
Strength
Women decorated the seat of power
They didn't set in it
Why's it gotta be a lady because women are pure
You know a woman with a spear
She would only use that Spirit to really defend her kids
Right
And for several years as pure uncorrupt symbol of virtue in the US was Audrey Munson
She was everywhere
The World's Fair in 1915 held in San Francisco
Audrey posed for 3/4 the statues on the premises
Her face and body appeared
Everywhere throughout the grounds
But Aaron Garcia of the California Historical Society
She curated an exhibit about the 1915 Panama Pacific Exposition
In San Francisco
Where Audrey Munson was dubbed the exposition girl
In the court of Four Seasons she was the seasons of the Fountain of energy
She was
The Priestess of culture at the Palace of Fine Arts she posed for 91 figures meant to represent the Stars
She was all over the
What about 24 years old Miss Manhattan had won the West
And there was a new form of RN during the scene
Cinema
The obvious next stop for Audrey Munson was Hollywood
And Hollywood was
Unfortunately
The beginning of the end
Friday night
Cheers cast in a few films after the exposition
But in every case she has cast
As a nude model
As an artist model and she appears nude
Audrey was acting the first leading woman in Hollywood to appear naked on film
Audrey may have been a good model
But she honestly wasn't much of an actor
If you heard films
She actually had an
I cleaned up
To basically do everything except the naked posing
And the movies that end up really being worth it for her financially
She's paid very little
And none of them seem to have been critical C
Excessive
That might have been okay for her her career might have
Survived
Scott
But then unfortunately she was involved in a murder
Scandal
Audrey and her mother had an apartment in New York
And the landlord
Dr. Wilkins
Fell in love with Audrey her landlord apparently became obsessed with her
And
Killed his wife so that he could be with Audrey
Murder or any kind of romance with dr. Wilkins actually moved out of the
Before this happened
But they were questioned they had to testify in court
And they were should have dragged through the mud in the Press
The so-called Wilkins case
Became a phenomenal media scandal
As Audrey told the daily variety
In 1920
The Wilkins case ruined my career
I'll never count for anything again
From loving and admiring me the public seems to have grown to hate
Badri couldn't find any work
In Fillmore in artist Studios of Audrey's career wasn't just because of the Wilkins can
She was after all
Totally innocent
They're just a lot of factors changing in the culture around here
I want the Bozart style wasn't
Very popular anymore
The Bozart style came out of Europe
And there is this thing called World War 1
Where Western Europe kind of fell apart
And so there was a questioning
About whether or not
We want to be using
That kind of symbolism
Both European and American Architects were trending towards modernism
Away from the old world bosarts presidents
Also the economics of Bozart style wearing possible
It became increasingly expensive to
Construct these buildings and pay for all of the artists and artisans
To design all of the elements of the building and install it
The architectural world didn't need Audrey like it used to
And also at 30 she was aging out of the business
Audrey's 15-year career as an artist model had come to an end and her money started to run out
She moved Upstate with her mother
You clean homes that support them both
As they tried to carve out a place for themselves
In the small rural town
Of Mexico New York
It's not an
Kind of open easy going
Andrea Geyer went up there to talk to people about Audrey nobody was unfriendly to me but
There's something
About these close-knit Community Square as a stranger you don't
Feel welcome
Audrey could not get used
Small town life
Her whole adulthood she been traveling around the country
Studying art
Working with artist engaging in intellectual discussion
And wearing fine clothes
Information lost
Well she still had the clothes
People told me that she was
Very flamboyant
She like to dress up and colorful garmin's I mean I'm sure she had a pretty
Impressive wardrobe that
Was very outlandish
For a small community but it wasn't just Audrey's style that set her apart
She would dress up on that and then part of her
Workout routine in the city was
Roller skating so you know you can imagine a beautiful woman with long hair and a turban on her head
You know trying to roller skate on a country
Unpaved country road that was quite a scene
The town new Audrey as that crazy woman who used to get naked for money
Parents would close their Windows whenever she came roller skating by
The kids of course we're totally fascinated with her
But
There was a general consensus that she was
Crazy
Just because she was different
So it's not hard to imagine why she
Would have
Falling into a depression
In a May 27th 1922 Audrey Munson attempted suicide by swallowing poison
I don't know how
Committed her suicide attempt
Was
Maybe it was just an expression of being some her at the end of her line
After her failed suicide attempt
Several years went by
And Audrey's mother was
Struggling to provide for her depressed daughter
Just
Couldn't do it anymore
But Audrey Munson 40th birthday
June 8th
Her mother checked her into the state mental institution
At that time it was extremely common for families
To put
Relatives into these in
Tutions
In moments of
A financial hardship where they felt
They couldn't care for a person
Body remained in the
Institution into her nineties
Then she was put in a nursing home
About 30 miles up the road
But this home for the elderly
Well situated on this little four-lane Highway
Which handlebar
And she was known
Sneak out of the home for the elderly and
Sneak across the four-lane highway
To spend her evenings at the bar
Ordering drinks
And telling stories
4 * as a model and isn't a
They could not stop this 90 something elegant older woman from running across four lanes of traffic
To go to the bar
It sadly meant that they put her back into the Mentalist
Situation where she
You know spent the rest of her life
Audrey Munson live just short of her 105th birthday
She died in 1996
Miss public body that once represented truth
Civic Fame memory the universe and the Stars
But anyway
For nearly two-thirds of our life
But that 1/3
That glorious day
Immortalize her
And place her all over American cities
Perched High
Quietly
Out of sight
I'm wondering if many of my readers have not stood before a master
A remarkable painting of a young girl
And ask themselves a question
Where is she now
This model who was so beautiful
What has been hoverboard
Is she happy and prosperous
Arshi sad and forlorn
Her beauty gone
Leaving only memories in the way
99% invisible was produces week by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan stat Delaney
F&me Roman Mars
Call Audrey Monson quotes unless otherwise noted were taken from a tell-all series called Queen of the artist Studios That Mountain Road
Food for the New York American in 1921
Audrey Munson was voice by Cara Rose de Fabio
This story was score with original music by Shawn real of the band Little Teeth his website is Sean real.
We are production of 99% invisible ink a project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco in
Produced by the offices of arcsin in architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of sun
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights.
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black Box
Find a show and like the show on Facebook I still want to be tagged at Roman Mars or at 99 Pi Oregon
Twitter when your challenge coins arrive
You can also keep tabs on us on Tumblr Instagram and Spotify
Best way to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Steve your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth pot
Dot-com