99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
He wondered at Machu Picchu or Stonehenge or the Colosseum or even snuck into that abandoned house on the edge of town
Sound you know the power in a piece of decrepit architecture
Even if you haven't been to these places
They've been photographed in film for you
Abandoned Soviet bus stops
Deserted old movie theaters
Ducane residential street
They're fascinating in this life
Planet of the Apes
So of course
There's a German word for it
Ruin and Lewis
The long-standing aesthetic obsession with decay
Resident germanophile and producer Avery trufelman
It might actually be one of those made up German words
It probably is
For the concept itself is totally a real thing
Ruins Inspire Wonder
They give the mines this task of reconciling what's there and what's not
What once was
And what now is
People flock to remainders of ancient civilizations
Romans the Mayans the Egyptians
But people also flock to things that just look like they're ancient to
That combination of decomposition and romance makes a perfect cocktail of repulsion and Allure
And for San franciscans this place
Is Sutro Baths
My friend Austin brought me there one night
How do you get into the trail just bleed right to it
Head to the rocks at Land's End
I'm a very northwest corner of San Francisco
Walk down the flight of stairs
Into a grassy slope
That hugs the sea
Off to the right is the gaping maw of
The cave
To your left
Is the crumbled Foundation
Have a concrete structure
It looks like a giant Belgian waffle
About 7 feet tall and 50
2 feet wide
On the longest side
Beside the waffle
R2 pools
Stillwater
For the concrete jetty
Between them that dares you to walk in
Make it to the end
And you are at a seawall for the Pacific Ocean crashes into the Rock
There's no fan
No guard
Only a warning sign
That says
Danger
Cliffs at Surf area X
Extremely dangerous
People have been swept from a rock
Ground where you can sit down here are the ruins of the bathhouse
Have you heard any rumors as to what was what year
Strangely no I mean other than a bath house in San Francisco
But all that might indicate San Francisco bath house
If you thinking of what I think
He's thinking of
But we'll get back to that in a minute
At last time you were here is like
People wondering about the history of it at all
No it's like three hundred bucks in a cave
Austin and seen a band playing in the cave
The plug their amps into a generator that they brought themselves
He told me things like that were happening at Sutro Baths
All the time
And it's easy to see why
This place has a draw
Like that I was there
The group of photographers with snapping shots of the Moon
This is like a known photo definition
3 years have been more common so I think people finding out about it
I just know they're going to like 2:30 is it was some sort of bad for people to sit in and just soak
I don't know Who's hotter colder
Ruins of drawing people to them for centuries
End of memes to go visit sites of antiquity Paris Venice Rome and learn about the roots of Western Civilization
Did a lot of people visit what's left
Of the old world
People like ruins
It gives us a sense of time passing
Baby sense of place
Why do people go to ancient Egypt why to go to the Acropolis
Sense of time gone by
A sense of timelessness
And I think also like that
Try to explain but
What people are looking at
Anytime you got to
Crawling all over the room
But the thing about these ruins
At the edge of the continent
They may look ancient
But they really aren't
At all
Utah
I'll try to figure the place out
These tunnels doing
This thing is it curiosity to it they know their ruins
Nathan fake if anything
Future Bass
And that's about it
This is historian John martini
Martini wrote a book about this place
Cold sutro's glass Palace
So named because this pool of water
Used to be underneath an enormous
Flask
Structure
It was the pet project about off Sutra
The name Sutro might sound familiar to you especially if you live in San Francisco
There's Sutro Tower Sutro Heights there's a Sutro library at the San Francisco State University
All named after this one German immigrants
He struck it rich by engineering tunnel during the Nevada Silver Strike
And he turned his money into San Francisco real estate
A lot of Real Estate
Some historians estimate that one point out of Sutro owned 1/12 of the city
Adolph Sutro was to San Francisco with John D Rockefeller was to New York
And what Henry Huntington was to LA
Do travel Public Gardens presented free concerts
And build a structure that would eventually become Sutro Baths
Sutras original idea
Was that he wanted to build a giant outdoor Aquarium
That would be filled by the tides and it would empty it low tide so in 1884 he created a catch Basin that refill
Build naturally as the waves broken
And then Sutro kept making more and more plan
Adding on an aquarium
Built
The network of swimming pools
Connecting canals Even build up our house is a freestanding building to keep the water then when all that was done Vinnie Hunters Market
Assembly would be like if
Some crazy self-improvement guy built the foundation for an elaborate house
But didn't know what house was going to look like he just built foundation and he plumbed it
And then you hire an arch
Give me to make a building sit on top of what was already there
Toilet bathroom design
From the outside
Sutro Baths look like an ornate
Palatial Greenhouse
Underneath its Majestic
Three tiered glass canopy
For several different swimming
Hot water and cold
Saltwater and fresh
And there were more than 500
Individual changing rooms beneath the sweeping arena-style bleach
And attached to the bath
Was a museum
Full of sutras crazy collection of
Stuff from around the world
Miniature boats
Model building
Taxidermied animals
Gems
Mechanical figures
A real Egyptian mummy
All inside of a glass Palace facing the ocean at the edge of San Francisco
Up the hill
When's the road was a street called Merry way
There was a first wheel
Basically a ferris wheel
Along with a roller coaster and a Hall of Mirrors
And games of chance
And keep in mind Sutro with a building at the edge of nowhere
On the rocks by the sea
And public transit didn't go there and this was a challenge for both construction workers and for customers
The lost money from the day it opened
It was huge white
Medcost Adolph Sutro
About a million dollars
When it opened in 1890
And you've you put that today that's
3740 million dollars
It could make money from the church
People are $0.10 to get in and $0.15 to go swing it would have had to be packed
Almost everyday
And in an attempt to pack the house
Sutro poured even more money into electric Rail lines that let out to the bat
This was a huge Boon for the city's mass transit at the same time he owned all the land
Surrounding at the people going to be traveling through
And there were always advertisements for did the sutralam company were they trying to sell and so he's doing things for the public
At the same trying trying to make some money
But Sutro Baths
Just
Never
Ever
Made money
By the time out of suture was elected mayor in 1890 for his beloved bass we're still not turning a profit
When he died four years later in 1898 his family started looking to get rid of a property
The Sutro family tried for years to sell Sutro Baths
Well also trying valiantly to make it turn a profit
In 1934 my father was hired by Adolph Sutro who is the grandson of the pioneer eight
Adolph Sutro
Just about that time at all suture wanted to do something to
Get more people out here
If you go to Sutro Baths you may run into Tom Bratton
Parks in the come out here
Once a week in for a few hours in the talk to people in
Let him know just exactly what are these ruins were it out
Tom's father was an engineer and he helped Sutro Baths undergo it's really Wiggy midlife
Crisis cut off the bottom
Cool cut that off
From the regular pool
Drain that scatter sand around on it put in some
Tables
Ping pong tables in
Picnic tables
And they called that the traffic be
The Tropic Beach was supposed to be a warm Sandy place in Doris's to hang out
Even though the real Bates
Right outside
That it really didn't work out too well
Which it really is a shame because right outside the beach is
Freezing and usually foggy eye drop conversion isn't that crazy
And so they said well
How about this
Take that traffic Beach away
And we'll put a platform there
And we'll make that into an ice rink
And when Tom was in high school his father got him a job working at this very ice rink
Yes Tom work at this place while it was still standing which seems impossible
Given the how ancient the ruins look
People will really come up to me and say
Were these really ruins from Rome
Not really not at all
Tom just being nice
By the time Tom was employed there the name of the place had changed
From Sutro Baths
Suggest Sutro
Bozzuto family had finally gotten rid of this place in 1952 when entertainment Tycoon
George Whitney bought it Whitney was the boss when Tom braaten started as a locker attendant
And even more than the Sutro family
George Whitney was really trying to do everything he could to get people to come out
So we tacked on more amusements including a ride
High above the sea that shuttle between the two cliffs
On either side of sutro's
He called it
The sky tram
This thing that hold about 20 people
It took about 20 minutes to get across
Took didn't eliminate make a lot of money on it
Whitney also thought an Aviary might bring in the big money
So he ordered some exotic birds
Phantom cages
What happened was all the birds came in at once
Before the cages
So they had that we need to go out to all the employees and said okay
Everybody here
Take it home take home a bird
Until Dark Ages come in and then we'll bring the birds back
But even after the ice ring
Mava
And the sky tram
People still weren't coming to sutro's
The whitneys
After struggling for 14 years
Decided we're going to sell the property historian John Martini again
It was sold to a land developer
Who began to
Demolish it
Amanda
Engine 66 that's when the very convenient fire broke out
In 1966 a mysterious fire broke out to a pile of rubble an arsonist was suspected
But no one was arrested
And then sutro's
Never rebuilt
Eventually the last owner sold the land for National Park Service in 1980 so it's part of a
National Park area
Sutro Baths is right inside Golden Gate National Recreation Area
Included into this big National Park area
It's not a national park
And it doesn't look like it belongs within the Golden Gate national parks Conservancy at all
It just looks like a bunch of ruin
Sometimes ruins are more evocative than its
The site is restored
Cuz this is the real deal even though these are only 45 years old
They have the same attraction
The Purge try to explain
But
What people are looking at
So unlike other ruins remains of Sutro Baths for less than 50 years old
They're part of the National Park
Since 2012 they do have their own tiny Museum and Gift Shop on side
Ride along the Midway used to be
The street sign is still there
The roads are still pretty dangerous and too many people
Still mysterious
So this point you may be wondering how to get out to the bath
Or about parking availability
Or maybe if you can go hold your photoshoot there
Joe can help
People write me with
Can I have my wedding there how can I get there can I fill my movie there
I answer all their questions
New Corral run Sutro Baths. Com random chicken Seattle from Seattle
You know I just respond to their question
Like yes is your wedding party smaller than 30 people sure you can have it there
Jill snag Sutro Baths, 2000
When it was Sutro Baths on Facebook or Twitter those accounts are also run by gel
In Seattle people ask me like how much does it cost can I get in
It's just like
Just go
It's never close
And unlike
Tom braaten or John Martini who actually both experience
Sutro Baths when it was a functioning building
Jill first encounter the place as a ruin
Phone out to San Fran
Just go for a job interview 1997
My main mission was to touch
Pacific Ocean that Davis
For my interview
I went down there and I stumbled
On this
Just
Insane
Playground
Concrete metal
Sticking out of the ground I don't know what the hell it was it was just
Pretty much
The closest to a magical place I found as an adult
And if I fell in love
I think I will
Toss my assets after I die
Jill actually did bury her to pet lizards there
They're in the cave
The story of Sutro Baths didn't exactly shape history
Does it help expand Sanford
Transit
Yes you can see the ruins
Briefly in a scene in the movie Harold and Maude
But ultimately it was a strange glass complex at the edge of the ocean that was destined to fail
And Amusements
Attractions
Constantly added and removed throughout its life
But in a city as rapidly gentrifying is San Francisco
In a country as young as the United
States
These ruins
Are an anomaly
I respect people's desire
For it to be like this
Mysterious unknown thing
But
Whack your
Twist talking into sitting there wondering like I
I have been known to walk out today
And tell them like they're used
To be there
Giant
Before magical thing here
Know about it
Always read the plaque right
You got it
In addition to researching what the battles were
Joe keeps tabs on how they're changing
Ruins seen status
What affects the ending
But of course they're not
I have watched it continue to fall apart
There used to be a deck
That you could go and Redan by the cave and then it just
Crumbled into the sea
Sometime around
Still
Living in
Dying
In slow-mo
Which is a process the parks are actually trying to stop
According to Tom Brown
As far as the national parks
So that is not going to deteriorate anymore that already has
If it deteriorates anymore you're not going to really be able to tell what a really what has
Tom speculates they might do this by adding more signed by destabilizing some of the decaying structures but not
Too much more
Both parks
Really don't want to do it
They don't want to make it look like a box
Can I go inside and look at the ruins and it comes out again
But recently the young ruins have become something else entirely
Nature's reclaiming the site
The ruins
Continue to evolve
The old swimming pools themselves
Have become partly silted in
It's become a wetland
Migrating birds website
And recently an otter appeared
Swimming in Sutro Baths
The public dubbed him Sutro Sam
Sutro Baths continues to be a machine
Regenerating new San Francisco Folk
Today Sutro Baths
Is pretty much back to where it started
All That Remains is the foundation
Including the original catch basin
Adolph Sutro built
Before ever imagining
A swimming pool
Tropic Beach
A carnival Midway
An ice skating rink
So after all the years of building the Palace of Wonder after adding games and rides and Oddities
Trying and failing to draw the public out to this strange place by the ocean
All out of Sutro or George Whitney had to do was let it burn down
In crumble
Into ruin
9% invisible with Bruce's sweet by Avery trufelman with Sam Greenspan Katie mangle and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced in downtown Oakland
California out of the offices of arcsin
Values collaboration so much
They could have even work without on Sutro
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa Model X
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
Would you like more cool tidbits about design or random jokes in the middle of the night
Try finding us on Facebook Tumblr and Twitter but if you're one of the hundreds of thousands of people who are kicking themselves me
Because they missed the kickstarter I would love a 99percentinvisible t-shirt
Meet the black
Go to 99 piaa.org and click the link that says shop
You can show off your great taste and radio programs
Associated merchandise
Bedazzled shaped Eastern is guaranteed to start at least one conversation
Guaranteed
Click shop
At 99 pa.org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com