99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Welcome to the
Interaction design
Our producer Sam Greenspan has seen the color of the future
I have seen it
You have seen
We all know
The color of the future
Is blue
Lesson 1
Are mostly
Science fiction becomes science fact
The team colors have already been chosen pretty much science fiction is
Denim blue
Inhuman
Future looking
Kind of mystical
That's Chris nozzle
Sci-fi aficionado
There's not a lot of blue in nature
Right there's not a lot of blue food
So I think there is something
Fundamentally
Inhuman about that color or unnatural that really fits the Technologies
Of the future world
As contract
Yeah
The other guy is Nathan shedroff
Also into sci-fi
And like many sci-fi guys there love the art form that takes on an obsessive quality
And here's the thing
Chris are also designers
Chris is with a firm called Cooper
And Nathan is on fact
California College of the Arts
Sci-fi Obsession Matt design of session in the resulting glorious nerdfest
Was a book where the author of the book make it so
Interaction design lessons from science
Make it so is a comprehensive compendium of real-world lessons that designers can and should end do take
From science
So to give you an idea of how exhausted their line of inquiry
That lesson about future screens being mostly blue
Lesson 1 future screen
Bethany Kris actually figured this out in
Accurately
They build the database
More than 10000 image
Sci-fi movie
Out
The keys
Streams of interfaces
I'm stuck into Photoshop for a given year
Shrunken down to a single Pixel
Ion pump saturation
They can determine the average color of all interfaces
From every sci-fi movie that
Came out in a given year
And when you lay those average colors next to each other
You can see 1968 to 2011
Pretty much science fiction
There are some exceptions
Very red Terminator 2
But for the most part
You just blur your eyes and glanced at it
Always blue
Queens of the future may or may not actually
But syfy's about letting our imaginations run wild and great imagine world
And someone has to design the experience of characters moving through that imagined world
And even if your sci-fi world is a thousand years in the future
Those choices are in constant dialogue
With the present
When Chris and Nathan started this project
It went back to the very first sight
Levi Austin Ally
A trip to the moon
By George menu
Is that you in the first film
.
And the thing that I noticed when I saw that movie was wait a minute
With where the hell are the interface
Because there aren't any
In this future as seen from 1902
You sent people to the Moon
Putting them inside a giant canister
Latinx
Canister into an enormous Cannon
How do you get to the moon
The audience and even the filmmaker still had an
Industrial Age paradigm
In their lives they only ever encountered lovers
Buttons
Maybe
Technology in electricity we're kind of a strange and off-putting things
To audience did not require any type of UI for a lunar space
Which tells you something
About living in 1902
Chris Nathan say sci-fi doesn't just reflect reality
Reality sometimes reflects
Syfy
Components of Science Fiction saturate the public imagination
It can affect
How we design things
Casein
What a Motorola first cell phone
The Microtel
It was not a particularly successful phone now the microtac was a flip phone
The open
Downward you have the device in your hand in the mouthpiece
Flipped down so you can talk into
And the microtac
Wasn't selling
So the Motorola engineers in Illinois
Took it down the road to the Argonne National Lab
And the Argan Engineers immediately said oh you made it wrong
Islamorada folk survival
What do you mean no one's no one's ever made one of these how do you know it's wrong
You know like on Star Trek
And they said it has to open up like this
The Argonne Engineers just
Expected the phone to open up work
My Captain Kirk's communicator
Downwards just felt weird
And they went back in
And made it open the right way and then and then the next
Generation
Phone went gangbusters
It was called
The startac
Motorola accidentally happened into a system where
Their customers had been trained for 30 years of reruns on the right way to do mobile communication
Is actually a whole host of design lesson
Lesson to establish a comprehensive
Visual Center
Star Trek the Next Generation Excel
Creating a holistic visual syntax
It was probably thanks to extreme budget
They didn't have the production budget just require tons of
Surfaces with dummy buttons and have them lit individually so that they could control them
And as a cost-saving move they should have
Develop this idea of what we can just print out film
And backlight it under surfaces and that can serve as visceral wow factor of man is a lot of control
For this it must be a Starship
Working
If you've seen one episode you know what
A flat screen with a black backdrop
And a bunch of brightly colored buttons
Underneath a glass
They're everywhere on the ship
The bridge
The Sick Bay
Engineering
Turn on the tablet
Computers essentially all of the controls show up that way
They all have this uniformity.
Did not only looks
It also tells you from a very quick glance that it's related to
But even give the interfacing name
Elkhart
Steven Library
Computer data
Provide full access
The operator
I do have the definition
For those curious
It stands for library computer access
Slash retrieval system
The archetype of the image under glass Paradigm that governs our virtual live
And people
Really latched onto it to this day
There are still people modding their computers and tablet devices to make them look like
Anel cars device from the 24th century
By way of
Late 1980s and early 90s
But here is a really brilliant
Every single species
Has their own equivalent of Alcott
What's the Klingon racetrack
It's already trying
The bajorans have the sort of bluish purple oval thing
And the Borg have an array of green circle
Green lighting everywhere
If it's amniotic lesson for storytelling right green equals
Borg
And wherever green creeps you know the Beauregard
Assertive essentially a visual Macro for an entire class
The story is fix their own brand and the really good brand manager
The Chris and Nathan are
Quick to point out
Did not everything we see in sci-fi is Nessa
Really good
Feasible
The minute we started our interview they could not wait to go off
How much of a waste of time they think
Gestural inter
Think minority
You're when you move your arms in space that's called cardio
Aerobic exercise and it's tiring
Lesson 3
Avoid gestational age
Supposedly Tom Cruise had to keep taking breaks
Set because
Tire demount
That future flow
Exhausting
Even if conducting your computer like an orchestra turned out to be
A dead end
That bad in her face
Of that imagined future
Actual user interfaces of the present and that's how we can get into apologetic
Lesson 4
Employ apologetics
Wherever Papa
Apologetics is a term borrowed from religion primarily is the practice of coming up with
Rational explanations to reconcile the apparent contradictions inside of a face
Basically making sense of the plot hole that surface when
Various religious stories
Are stacked on top of
Each other this can become applicable
If you just assume for the sake of arguing
Everything in sci-fi is there for a reason
You can find some really interesting less
Design
So let's consider Star Wars
Name of that part when Luke and Han Solo or in the Millennium Falcon blowing up
If you really in space watching this ship
Glow up
Wouldn't hear anything
I mean really takes that that moment where you have to describe it you realise wait a minute they are fighting in the vacuum of space
Where exactly is the sound propagated
Because sound is how our brain interprets the vibration of air molecules
Of which there aren't any
In space
So why do we hear these ships
Exploding in the film
The easy answer would be oh that's just Lucas
Trying to make something that feels right
People who were used to
World War II films
But in fact
If you imagine that scene without the audio
It's a lot more miserable of attack
To Nowhere In
3D space of these Tie fighters around me
How would I find them
Sure you could give me a screen but that requires me that I take my eyes off of the action
You can give me a heads up to
Display which might work but
Audio is
360° much more than my what is 120 degrees of vision
So that if that audio wasn't there
Then you would expect somebody to put
Sensors on the outside of the Millennium Falcon and provide
3D sound inside the gun ownership that would
Put that audio there
So the so the sound is an interface
The sound is
But the main part of interphase
Right at yes
Luke can look at this TIE fighter but he's also aware that
Coming over his right shoulder is another one
But as soon as he this one explode he's got to turn his gun into
That's
That's vital to that interface of working
Are you going to get there by
Trying to reconceive
Why does that thing
Seems broken
Would really work
Okay so here's another one 2001 A Space Odyssey
Directed by Stanley Cup
2001 Dr Floyd is on a satellite and making a video call to his daughter back on Earth
Bad
Hello
Are you a square
What you doing
Where is Bombay
Country shopping
And then you see his daughter
Start button mashing
Controls on the video
But strangely you don't hear any of the button
Now you can sing
Hey that's wrong what was the sound designers
Sleeping on the job
But with our apologetics hat on
But in fact
That's the way it is
Thoughts to work
If you had a
System that was context aware and that would include awareness of
The identity of a
What's user
It would say I've looked at this conversation
No one has asked at this little girl to push a button she's a little girl of about 5 or 6 years old
And it's indiscriminate mashing
I can safely disregard this is input
It's not a crisis
It's not a select
So if you were designing a system that was truly context-aware that's exactly the way you would
And anyone with a
We had to have a telephone call with a kid would know this
Is actually the way it should be built
Into the inputs to the interface
Or just not getting relay
The interface
Is actively
Russian five
Interfaces should not just interpret
But but also report
That's
Only broken if you presume that the
Interface is a dumb capturing device
Television
If instead you re conceive of it as sort of a real time
Scanner
Interpreter and
Presenter
You got an opportunity there to actually interpret the information
Let's do one more
This one's kind of tricky but stick with it
Lesson 6
Find the human factor
And technological shorts
For this lesson we go to a movie called Logan's
Where there's this interface
It's called the circle
Which people of this post-apocalyptic World used
Define
Ex-partner skits Craigslist it's
Even weirder than crack it is so hot
Energy audit sayings
So Logan is hanging out
Department of the future
Insurance on this thing called the circuit
Which basically lets him tune in different
People who are
Ostensibly available for
Couple anyway the thing about the circuit is that it's a really clumsy piece of
Technology
We can see that takes
Kind of a long time to turn someone in
Events at the Logan
Decide quick yes or no as to whether he wants
Pull that person
Into his apartment
Or send them back out
Either as an interface
It's
Unbelievably bad
For lots of rain
Like the male gaze problem alone in this case
Morally reprobate
Isabel
But if you can get past that for second
I just noticed that the circuit only lets you tune in one person that
Do you have to give a quick yes no answer
As to whether you want that person
Coming into your apartment
If he's going along and he sort of suzhou
Number one's not good number two is not good number three is not good number for okay maybe it was a two or one that was better
Maybe I can go back but
You don't see a mechanism to go back
And to make things worse
There seems to be no ability to adjust the settings of
What
Who you might want
Like the first person that Logan Tunes in is a guy and you can see right away that our hero
Triple him or any other dude
Hinduism
Pardon my
Gender or sexuality binary here but one of the most fundamental things you would name is what's the gender of
My
Possible partners
And that he didn't have a single preference setting on this interface
So it just seems horrible
But
There is evidence
If this design has some Merit
If you can think of an apologetic for it
I used to play this game with
Friends of mine
I called the 11th Man game
An 11th Man game
Or XI woman game depending on how you're playing with
I works as follows when
You're sitting in a public place you pick a doorway and you challenge that friend who say Okay want you
2Pac
One of the neck
10 people to walk through that doorway to
Date work
If you have that sort of friendship have sex with
And or you will be forced
To do that same thing with XI
Okay so you're with me is he person
Yes or no you say
I know you can
Yes or no
I know you
Three you can't go back and pick a previous person no going back
And if you say no all the way up through the 10th person
You have to take the 11th
So according to Chris when you start off playing again
Can you begin to play this
People are looking at negatives
Oh well let's
Pretending playing with a heterosexual man he be like I don't know she's
Shih Tzu short or I don't like her hair color whatever I'm eventually would get to 11 and I didn't expect that I deal with a gram
And then he
Freak out
But after playing for a while
There's the shift in strategy
I'm looking for reasons to reject someone
Looking for reasons to
To accept
Over time the strategy shifts from that
Negative view Twitter positive language
What is wrong with this
But what is right
And then being satisfied with
Choice
I'm in over time people begin to
Adopt that
Positive
Search mode
If the designer of the circuit
Computer
Wants Logan to find a mate that he's going to be happy about
And the limits of the technology
Are such that Logan can we specify yes or no and can't go back to
The previous choice
More likely to find an acceptable Choice sooner
Because
He's immediately Prime to look
For the positive attributes
In the candidates that follow
I'm at Super subtle in fact I think when I first started talking about this
I kept talking about how bad it was
Ottoman stumbled across this goodness which is as good a way to get to apologetics is any
I love this game of design apologetic
Because greater knowledge and awareness usually leads us down a path
Of miserable nitpicking
And I'm over good criticism but if you can apply a design solution
Two account for a bad design
Decision
In a Sci-Fi movie
It uses the same
Critical muscle
But in a different way and the Apologetics
Are endless
Like for example let's take lesson number three about bad gestural interface
Maybe in The Minority Report world
People work
Wheelie sedentary
And these types of interfaces where the way to get people
Get some freaking exercise
Gestural interfaces might be okay
And it leads us to our final
Lesson 7
Find your own design
In science
Who's talking sci-fi apologetics
Chris and Nathan
I can't help it look for them everywhere now
I even found one.
We had gone off on some tangent about the Star Wars
Queen Amidala has an interface for which we cannot
Apologized which is ironic because I believe I deserve an apology for every aspect
Of the Star Wars prequel
On her giant silvery spaceship
I'm and I'm sure it has a name somewhere in the Star Wars Canon but I can't remember
A shirt that serve big panel of controls
But when you review it the three times that she uses
Uses an interface aboard the ship
Are they are for routing a hologram or volumetric
Projection across the Galaxy
Second time she uses it is
For summoning a star chart of a
Distant planet
And the third
Is to land her spacecraft on corset
But when you look at those interface
The actual interaction she has it
Did you press the exact same button
On the panel
On the ship
To do all three things and nothing else
Is that you see her using the same single button
Burberry different tasks
Right
But I actually came up
With my very own app
Apologetic
You know if she's the queen she probably has love underlings
Probably someone
Somewhere offscreen who does everything for her
And this is the make it sew button that I like that computer management
Communications management room somewhere on the ship and they're just like oh she wants to do something but why I like that be hilarious as you press the button
Annabelle ring in another room literally a little. LOL
Right
Do that thing we were discussing vague
99% invisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan
We are project of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco
An American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Family ghosts in the podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and annuity
Rediscovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find a show and likes on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars Sam tweeted Sam listen to Avery tweets at troubleman right
Right now the good the bad the ugly of sci-fi interfaces are all at nine 9 p.m. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com