99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is our special Halloween episode so I'm going to turn up a little bit of this
Little of this
Just to get us in the mood
I want to hear hear some buns
Winter creepy
All right
A couple of weekends ago the whole 99 Pi team got together to do something none of us had done since we were 13
Matt slumber parties
And it basically sounds exactly like it did when we were 13 at slumber parties
Who's there
That night at my house we turned out all the lights
Unlit candles
An attempted to
Summon the spirit world
With the Ouija board
That's producer Katie mingle she was our host that evening
Fingers on it
We were using a homemade board that Avery designed in the style of a store-bought Ouija board
2R throes of letters the top row a through m
The second row in druzy
Enable of the letters
A straight row
Of all the single digit numbers
And then of course yes and no in the upper left and right Corners respectively
And goodbye at the bottom of the board
The way we just supposed to work
Is participants usually to those sometimes more
Ask a question to the
The spirits
And then they the participants lightly rest their fingers on a planchette
Which is the pointer that
Slides around the board
And you're not supposed
Push the play
Planchette
Supposed to allow the spirit
Guided around the board indicating what letters or words
There's something
Communicate
Equ
The Ouija board is so simple and iconic and it looks
Look at comes from another time
Like it has a real history would it turns out
Is more than just good design
People have been gathering around a board like this one
For about 130 years
Hi my name is Robert murch
Most people call me merch
And I'm considered the world's foremost expert on WeChat and talking board
Merch also collects boards and all sorts of other Ouija related artifacts
So the stuff is everywhere
You know I I befriend things that the arrangement I have with my husband
When is that
I can only put things on the wall
That can be friend
Now what you need that agreement
She didn't realize that I
Frame anything
Yeah that was unfortunate for him
Merge cells to understand we're talking boards
Came from
Degenerate
Keyboards
If you go back to the middle of the 1800
The three sisters
In New York
The fox sisters
Dr Ringwood
Starts at 6
Explosion
Mediumship in spiritualism in America and Beyond
The fox sisters claim to be mediums to the spirit world
Public demonstrations they would ask questions of the spirits and receive audible Knox back on the wall
Knox that they translated into letters of the alphabet
The fox
Sisters worth it
It was a most visible faces of
A growing movement known as spiritualism
Which Hobbit spirits of the Dead
Maybe contact
By the living
And that they had secret knowledge to impart
When tales of the fox sisters swept through American newspapers more and more
Started to believe
During and after the Civil War spiritualism became even more important to people
Everyone had you know where there was a father a son grandfather and uncle
They all lost somebody people just one way
And you didn't come back
Show
What else you going to do
You know you turn to
Trying a contact with these people who are gone
An 1886
The fledgling associated
Press read an article in papers
All over the country
About these new talking board
It's coming out of the spiritualist movement
In Ohio
It's unclear whether he read the article but a few years later and 1890 a businessman named Charles Kennard
Baltimore Maryland
Realize this talking board could make him lots
And lots of money
Cunard pull together a small group of investors
Inform the Kennard Novelty Company to exclusively make and Market talking boards
Contrary to popular belief
The name weija is not a combination of the French and German words for yes
We India
Which says that according to document
It's belonging to the original founders of the company
They sat down and asked the board itself what it wanted to
And letter-by-letter it spells out o u i j a
And when they ask the board
What that means
The board spells out
Good luck
They called the board Ouija
The Egyptian Blackboard
They added Egyptian just for a little
Exotics lair
The patented Ouija board looked a lot like
The talking boards that came out of the spiritualist movement
The only real substantial change was that the Ouija board
The letters of the alphabet in a double art
Instead of two straight lines
Ross
There have been a few small design changes since the early boards for example there was once a full moon and a crescent
The moon in the top left and right hand corner
Eventually the full moon became a sun which is what you see now
But through the years
The brand has always been very identifiable
Anyone who looked at it with no okay that's it
Buy 1893 Charles Kennard have left the company
And it was taken over by William fault
Who has come to be known as
Father
A WeChat
Folds New York Times obituary actually credited him with inventing the board
He did not do
But he was incredibly good at selling it
Instead of being a straight-up evangelist for the boards
Keep report to be one of the Skeptics
He would say I don't believe in the Ouija board jarno spiritualist
I'm a presbyterian
At the same time
Same interview he would say
But we lost the ship and a Ouija boards
On the train tracks and we asked the board where
They were and it told us and then they went down that track in
And sure enough they found
The train has derailed
And we found all our boards
Whether the board works and how it works
Whether it was just a game or more serious spiritual tool
Was something fold kept
Intentionally mysterious
And this marketing strategy
Was extremely
Did everyone have one
People played at home with their families
Ladies played at tea parties
In fact one of the boards and Merchants
Collection doubles as a tea tray
People even play with their little kids
Which might seem kind of weird now
Fast forward a couple of decades around 1920 and we just still good clean family fun
And
It turned out
It was also a great thing to do on a date
So you're coming out of Victorian times when men and women are not supposed to be alone together
Are there supposed to be in the dark together they're not supposed
Touching
The original Ouija board would be placed on
Go out
Your name should be touching
Your fingers will be touching on the plane chat
You know you want it
By candlelight
You can see really quickly
That's the directions
Add in
You know
Two people a man and a woman prefer
And if you need proof of what a normal part of Americana the Ouija board was
Look no further than the king of Americana himself
Norman Rockwell
In 1920 he made a painting of a man and a woman in the position merch just described
Knees touching he looking flirtatiously at her
A Ouija board
Resting in their laps
Of course we just always had a few naysayers
It's some of the first and loudest were actually the people whose jobs these talking boards had just stolen
We see mediums actually saying
These things are dangerous
You don't know what kind of doors are opening
You need someone like me who's it
Experience to guide you through this Unseen World
Now why would they say that
Well because it's
Cutting into their profession their money on The Fringe through the years
Oh sure they'd be the occasional the Ouija board told me to do it murder that would make it into the news
But they were few and far between
Throughout the decades we do mostly held onto it's wholesome reputation
The Exorcist
Released in 1973 I had to sleep in my
Trans bedroom
For a week
After I saw this
The kid
At the beginning of the movie the main character's mother.
Discovers she's been playing with
A Ouija board
The Exorcist is really the first
Big
Medium
That
Infers that playing on keyboard by yourself
Could lead to demonic possession
The following year saw the Ouija board denounced by religious groups
As Satan's preferred method of communication
Ouija boards are harmless
Seances are harmless
Don't be playing games on Halloween don't call on demons because they'll come and live with you
The Bible says he who seeks evil evil will come to him
Pat Robertson is pretty extreme
But still the image of the board changed a lot since that Norman Rockwell painting in 1920
Parker Brothers and later Hasbro which acquired Park
Brothers in 1991
Still sells a lot of boards
But the reason people buy them has changed
It's not good clean family fun anymore
Now people buy them
Because they want to get
Scared
There's another Ouija movie just released called weijia which will do nothing to change the board sensor reputation
Funny faces doing
Spell Hi friend
This is freaking me out I'm done
But it's Sinister reputation is
Fine with Hasbro in fact they put up a lot of the money for that new Ouija movie
They've also released a new version of the game
Unchanged the tagline
Which used to be
It's just a game
Isn't it the new tagline
Do not play the Ouija board
The design is different to very long time the Ouija board
Got a makeover
Baby I did a couple of modern features like a purple lights in the planchette but overall they've tried to make the board look
Older than the classic board it's brown and kind of weather and it looks like something you might find on a pirate ship
He will be gone for
The older look just need because people assume these boards have been around for
Thousands of years which
I know isn't true
But
Belief is important
Belief is
Very important to the Ouija board especially subconsciously
Which brings us finally to
How these things work
Basically when it comes to the
Ouija board
The reason
That
It seems to work at
Feels as if it works
Is down to something called the ideomotor effect
I'm what that is essentially
Is non-conscious muscular moving
That's Professor Chris French
I am head of the anomalistic psychology Research Unit at goldsmiths University of London
Before you ask psychology
Is the psychology of
Weird stuff
The term ideomotor effect was first coined by an English physician and researcher named William Benjamin carpet
Back in 1852 right when spiritualism was starting to become popular both in Europe and the US
The ideomotor effect
Applies in the case of WeChat
In that our bodies are making small subconscious movements that are Guided by a suggestion or some subconscious
Knowledge of so particularly once the
So is lateral to husband has been made apparent and you kind of
Is going to come next so if it was
Spelling out a name
And it spells out the letter b and then I will be no trouble
And the ideomotor effect becomes magnified as more people play
I want very interesting things that happened
People who have played around with weave
Ouija board
Level very often
Claim
That they've got answers from the Ouija
Nobody around
Borat
Chile news out so that proves it was some
What kind of external agency
Professor French says that what's happening
Here is that our subconscious mind does actually know the
Answer our conscious mind just can't access the information
Researchers are so convinced of this
They've even used Ouija boards
To study
Subconscious
Super example in one of these studies
Participants were asked simple fact based questions like
Is Buenos Aires the capital of Brazil
Percent of the time
But when they used a Ouija board to help them answer the same
Ohio schools then
I got the answers right about
55%
I'm so in other words I didn't know them so you can if they couldn't come to the access it
There's been all kinds of studies
Hainan paranormal
Experiences
And Professor friend says they never reveal an external or spiritual Force
At work they always reveal an internal
Horse at work
Even if
Subconscious
I don't have any doubts in my mind.
We can explain the vast majority
Call
Ostensibly paranormal experience by
Into psychology
Whether or not we can explain every single one
Is the
64000 dollar question
Was there an R
When we played weijia at my house
The planchette seemed less to be governed by the ideomotor effect
And more by the law of
Inertia
What's going on
Another experience wasn't terribly strange or creepy
It was mostly just
Slow
But merch has played enough times to
Just had some weird experiences
Xiaomi
I think are just
The person pushing and they don't know it
It's clearly ideomotor response
Other times it's answered things that just seems so bizarre that I wouldn't know
You know if you can talk
To the spirit world why wouldn't the Ouija board work
The real question is
Shunyi
Make contact with the
Spirit world
And that's a question that has been tugging Humanity since the beginning of time
The first time someone realized when they died
Don't come back
After everyone left my house that night I was sitting on my couch by myself
It was really quiet
I hadn't blown out all the candles yet
Mood
And then
One of my spring loaded blinds slammed up and scared the s*** out of me
And I have to admit
I looked at the Ouija board
I wondered
For a second
Just a game
Would you work for
99% invisible with Bruce's sweet by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
It was reported by Linda Rodriguez been robbing and adapted for a piece she wrote for the Smithsonian Magazine
We are product of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of
Architecture and interior design firm located in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made site
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a kid is another remember all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more
Cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99
You must go to 99 pi
Radio.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an actor
The movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com