99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
We've a little different episode for you today but we have to stop
The first is an update to the purple Hotel story that was episode number 58 reported by Gwen
Urban sound
Significant changes since we reported that story
So are we one. Day you on that
The first short story that I performed on the radio
Nkw in San Francisco very very early in the morning
But never released it as podcast so I thought I'd share that one with you today
Here we go
Almond Brown Stroger
Is an Undertaker
Of all things
Kansas City Missouri get its first telephone exchange in 1878
Telephone service is good for local business
The funeral business is no exception
But at some point
Almond Brown Stroger of Kansas City
Notice that he wasn't getting as many calls from potential customers
He got really suspicious
A friend of the family died and he wasn't even called about performing the funeral services
The Story Goes
In the story is
Really hard to verify but I'm going to go with it cuz I really like it
The Story Goes
After some poking around
Stroger discovered that the wife
Arrival Undertaker in the area
What's an operator
The local telephone come
At the time were connected manually
Buy female operators patching lines together on a gigantic punch board
Pick up the receiver asking for the local Undertaker in general or even Stroger in particular
In this case
The unscrupulous operator would only connect to call
To her husband
Undertaking business
Not this Rodgers
In Stroger
Figured it out
If you were allman-brown Stroger Kansas City Undertaker there are few ways you can go when you discover something like this
Number one
Number one for a reason cuz it makes the most sense
You can contact the local telephone company and alert them about the dishonest operator in their employ
Maybe even get her fire
Number to you can take her and her husband to civil court
Sue for damages or something
Borders only option number three
You can invent an automatic telephone switching system that allows people to dial each other directly eliminating any need for
Telephone switchboard operator and thereby completely revolutionising the entire telephone system forever
Almond Brown Stroger
The Undertaker
When with option number three
He wasn't the first to come up with the idea but his contact was the first automatic switcher that worked for more than a handful of phones with Anna
He was awarded a patent in 1891
Of course he didn't know how to make the thing he was Undertaker if I haven't stress that enough already
His nephew and some business partners to help develop a working prototype
It cost more
It took longer than anyone anticipated
They finally got it working
And I finally got a chance to try it out in the real world
LaPorte Indiana became the first place to have automatic operator free telephone dialing
In a speech at the unveiling of the Laporte telephone exchange
The cantankerous Brodeur
Address the issue of the hello girls
Operators who would lose their jobs because of his automated switch
Quote
I'm off until the telephone girls will be angry with me for robbing them of their occupation
In reply
I say that all things will adjust themselves to the New Order
Water will find its level
Telephone replace the messenger boy at this machine now this place is the telephone girl
Improvements will continue to the end of time
Strike where they met
The Bell Telephone Company eventually acquired the technology in 1916
In the strowger switch as it was called
Became standard equipment throughout the 20th century
So I'm next I'm going to play you episode number 58 again it's called Purple Rain about the purple Hotel
Reported by Quinn Maxon and then we can have a really really significant you know it for 5 minutes update
About what happened to the hotel since this was first reported
So stay tuned for that
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The hotel on the very prominent corner of Touhy and Kilbourn Avenue in Lincolnwood Illinois used to be the tap
China's most famous building
The first Hyatt Hotel in all of Chicagoland
Premier accommodation
Top Notch rest
It was Swank
Roberta Flack stayed there Barry Manilow stayed there Perry Como Michael Jordan stay there on his first night
Find in Chicago every 13 year old boy in the area
Had his bar mitzvah there
Hotel was built in 1960
And it looks
So if you're wondering how much potentially anachronistic Lounge music I'm going to cram into this episode
So it's going to be a
Then
Slowly over time
It became Lincoln Woods most infamous building
Changed hands
Got CD and rundown
It was the home of the Midwest fetish fair and Marketplace convention
There were drug-fueled sex parties attended by Shady Chicago politicians later convicted of things like
Torsion
And of course
There was the convicted mobster Allen Dorfman
Who was gunned down in the parking lot
But that's not why everyone in the area knows the building
If you know nothing of its history it's still
Pretty hard to miss
Because
It's
Really really
Purple
Growing up nearby I always thought it was really really
Ugly
Lots of people dead
Lots of people didn't
But everyone had an opinion about it
Brooklyn Max infl talking to you now by the way noted SAS public radio host
You can't resist it,
She has a secret
About the purple Hotel
My father
Designed it
My name is John Maxey I'm a retired architect and
Former professor at
UIC
I designed a lot of
Just a building
Don't interrupt
I don't have time for the long by odesza
Okay I designed a lot of apartment buildings
In Chicago
We're here to talk about the purple Hotel
I need you say I designed my name is Jonas. I'm an architect I designed to
Purple
My name is John mexeye I'm an architect
And I was the designer of the purple
Finally
Now you have to understand that when I say the building is purple
I don't mean the kind of purple of saying Iris
Score a plum
It's purple as an lavender
Lavender purple glazed brick all over pretty much the entire thing
Which needless to say makes it stand out
Depending on how you look at it
Like a prized Jewel
Or sore thumb
What are the few buildings if you see it once
You know it
You single forever you can't feel
It is so purple that after it changed hands the new owners renamed it
The
Purple
Hotel
WBEZ architecture critic
Wee Bey
I think that it's worth looking at
Absent the break the brick I like
But I wish you could eat a little Plum last-second filter it out so you don't see
The Brick
At least in one trip
And really see how the building hold yourself together structure
Good the way that John was able to put the support to the outside of the hotel
Get larger floor plates in the middle
And then I get a little mix of green space in the way back
So the buildings can I stick together with a lot of good things going on there
The thing that everybody notices first
Including architects
Wood beads
I mean I think that if anybody saying that it's not the color that they're lying
Because you can't really look
Purple
So it's the only purple building
Around but then
You know after that initial wave of color hits you you notice really what a great modern a structure that has
Structure
Express tan
Side which is also not something you see everyday anymore
I think it's a wonder
That was Jackie cool founding principle of the architectural firm coo and Associates
Will get back to her in a minute
The first the story of why and how the building got to be so
Purple
My dad
John Mack sign
It was commissioned by the pritzkers
The Benedict family in Chicago
And it was
The first Hyatt Hotel
In the Midwest
It was called
Hiatus
Have nothing to do with it
The purple by the way the purple came
Because one of the pritzkers A and the big man among the
Fiskars in the family
Ask
Color
Play style I want to use
And I wanted to use Gray
Adhesive that's doll
I like something brighter
So I made a mistake of showing him
The samples
Books
Having gun in sub
Color samples
It sure enough
Deepika purple
And you don't argue with a n pritzker
My father tells me the story but I suspect differently
He's always gravitated toward bold color choices
Our current argument is over bright orange balconies on a building that we always passed he loves them
And I hate them
When I was growing up his favorite color was blue a color that to me is suspicious
Sisley clothes
To purple
In fact every house we ever lived in
Brick bungalow summer house in the woods
Suburban Barn shaped house
Mustard colored siding all had bright
Blue front doors
That my father painted
My elementary school bus driver used to call me Blue Door
Upon interrogation
Father coughed up is strange Hungarian logic
In the near East
That ultimately I come from
The blue color on the doors blue and green
Is to keep the evil spirits away
So that's a reason
I always suspected
The
Entrance to the fair
Houses
Blue to keep the evil spirits
If it did
Do you think it worked
Hotel
So you don't think the purple kept away the evil eye from the hotel
Not really
Because
And that was a murder in the hotel actually there were two
But I digress
The beauty of that building is the exposed
Concrete stain
How to color inside
Pulled out of the structure
Showing
This
It's like a human being
The skeleton will be on the exterior
Partially
That would be weird right now that's that's the
The building is that column set
Hose.
The slap site
Slightly pulled out
It's a Building B
Reveals its structure
And that is architectural e
The interesting thing about
Dudley lullaby
It could be green
Okay
It would be the same good or bad built
So as an architect I have to ask you
This is a perfect example of
What the what the difference between what the public sees
And what the Arctic
Absolute
Because the public sees purple brick
The architect is sitting here saying the purple is so
Unimportant
In the scheme of the building
It means nothing
It's just such a tiny thing but to the public that's all it is
That's right because the public is ignorant
Truly ignorant
Well you can't really argue with him there
But in our defense and I count myself is
One of the public in the scenario
It's really really purple white how far the purple Hotel fell from its original Glory.
Dilapidation the murderer the drug-fueled sex parties and a demolition order
It was not torn down
Time passed
Economy fell to pieces
Mid-century architecture
Slowly came back into Vogue
Mad Men was on TV
Purple brick was kind of retro cool however dim was starting to shine on the building and its future
Then the purple Hotel was nominated for landmark status a place on the historic registry
There was talk of finding a buyer talk of renovation and then while I was searching and interviewing for this
Dairy story
Purple Hotel
Went up
For auction there was a lot of Pomp and Circumstance in the beginning of
You know the auctioneer yelling
Saying
Are you ready
Booming voice
And then
Really
There was only one bidder so
And that bitter was Jake Weiss of Weiss properties in Skokie which happens to be right next to Lincolnwood
He bought the purple Hotel
And why why is a shrewd businessman with a Keen Eye and good instincts
This particular purchase
Was also
A labor of love when you have some of that really is just not realizing of the value and its potential
That is such a prime piece of property it bothers you you know it is part of your neighbors Carter community
And it's something that you really want to see be an asset to the community instead of a blight
Here comes the love part
Separately from that when my and more importantly I think
We almost lived at the purple hotel for a period of time
Maya
When my grandfather passed away and my father was saying the traditional Thai Dish
That's the Jewish prayer for the Dead
There was no synagogue anywhere in close proximity to where he lived at the time
And because we're Orthodox when I drive on the Sabbath
That was a little bit prohibitive to say the kaddish
There's a very
Convenient show right down the block so I'm
Every single shop is 4 a year
How we would move into the purple Hotel
Had to accommodate my father's responsibility to say the kaddish for his father
So we lived there for about a year every single weekend
And you know me and my sister at the hotel was our playground
And the architect Weiss has chosen to redesign the purple hotel and bring it back to its original luster
Is Jackie COO of Jackie Cooper and Associates
Also
Former student of my father the original architect
John Maxon
We're looking into is more of a historic
Restoration of the building
Especially since we have some of the old drawings the original drawings from the 60s
And there are a lot of pieces that are still left in the building such as this wonderful
Monumental Terrazzo stair with this wood wall behind it I mean you can really see it as a
Kind of
You know late 50s early 60s kind of Mad Men era
Pan Am sort of
Hotel
That really could
Be very current in today's Hospitality environment
That culture today especially in the hospitality Market
For some reason purple is a predominant color not necessarily the color of the break but in order marketing I mean you'll look at the
The neon lights and the color of the key fob cards and the
Brochures that get printed for some reason
Purple is popping and I'm not quite sure why
Have any of your buildings
Had
This kind of
History this kind of life cycle
But you know
None of them
The same way that a person they go through life and you might go through different Cycles yourself and
Everybody goes through different rebellious x +
Ups and downs I think the same holds true for
A property like this that really was a character of itself the building was
Really a product of the environment around it at any given time and
And I feel certain extent the fact that the building did change
With
The
Decades and the environment around it
It really is in the building's character
And while it's true that this character is building this structure of Nine Lives such empty at The Bowman
Surrounded by board traffic and an empty parking lot
It may just be crouching
Gathering is mustard ready to spring back to life arresting that traffic
Filling that parking lot
And spreading like a proud peacock
A purple one
I'd like to thank Redman tail for National Wrecking Company
For doing all that
Andis company
To make this a reality
Girl baby
So
It turns out that after all of the gargantuan efforts to save the
Purple Hotel
It would have cost
40 some million dollars
Prohibitive
So despite so much Goodwill on the part of so many people
Who wanted to see it survive
The purple Hotel
Was torn down
Or I should say is in the process of being torn down
Repeat the process of tearing the purple Hotel down began with some ceremony
What everybody can start finding a c we're going to get started
On August 27th 2013 the parking lot of the purple Hotel was filled with local dignitaries from Lynn
Lincolnwood Illinois
Even the mayor was there
So much for being here
So on the day of the demolition
It was really
Really beautiful they had a huge white tent
They had purple flowers they had purple napkins
They gave my dad a purple brick
With a plaque on it I mean it was just really really beautifully done and it was a loving tribute
To the building
At the same time it was a little bit like going to synagogue
Because Lincolnwood
Is a
Predominantly Jewish suburb or at least it was and so all the people who have such strong feelings about the build
Largely we're Jewish
Okay good morning good morning everyone
Thank you all for coming to my bar mitzvah today
But this wasn't exactly a bar mitzvah when John Max I took the stage
He said it was a little more like another rite of passage
So you don't turn around
Which by the way cannot be avoided
Curious Thing That
Architect has invited
Cutting down of his building
The typical moment a piece of architecture and a piece of Journalism coincide is when the building is first constructed
This is like riding the biography of a person
What year she is born
The real story of how the structure influences the environment
Peligrosa
Miss fortune changes
And even
How it dies
Though this wasn't really the end of the purple hotel anyway the wrecking ball took up
Couple of whacks at the building and then they stopped
5 months
To tear it down
Because 75% of it needs to be recycled
As a matter of law
Brick by purple brick
They're taking it down
So the brakes would just get thrown into a big pile and shipped off to wherever they get recycled
Is there wasn't such a high demand for them
It turns out
That everybody and their brother wants a purple brick
I was married at that hotel
I lost my virginity at that hotel
I used to go to that hotel every weekend with my parents that played in the pool at that hotel I heard Roberta Flack
Quebec Motel
Everybody has a memory associated with it until everybody wants a brick and
I can't even tell you how many people have asked me for a brick
Not the least of which I might add
Was you so badly I'm going to get you at least it's
It's not a brick
As long as it has some part 1
It will have the iconic purple glaze on it
99% invisible was produced this week by Gwen Max ice and Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife isn't another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sounds
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
To find the show and like a show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars the same
Right now you can find pictures of the destruction
Of the purple Hotel
And also some nice pictures of a day
99 percent invisible
. org
Listen to right now is go to okay akumi we use a lot of them
On this radio program along with fans like
Melatonin and melodium and orcas
If you want to score your life like an episode of 99% invisible
Go to our web pages 99pi.org and look for our Spotify playlist
And then you don't go buy something up their ass because all these bands are awesome
Thanks
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an actor
The movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com