99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
Norman Moore
This is the story of an ad campaign
Produce for the 1992 Olympic Games in Barcelona
Perennial runner-up in the sports shoe category Reebok
Just trying to make it tomorrow
And take down Nike
It was two athletes pluck them out of obscurity
Give them Reeboks to wear
And turn them into household names
Spending 25 million dollars in the process
That was more than Reeboks entire marketing budget the previous year
This ad campaign is pretty much remembered as a disaster for Reebok
Recreated
From nothing
Epic drama that pitted two world-class decathletes against each other
And it resulted
In so many strange twists and turns
All because someone thought it was a clever way to sell my shoes
I love this story
Is the first episode
A 30 for 30 podcast which are original audio documentaries from ESPN
These are stories about sports but there
Sports stories that I like that delve into their impact on culture politics and more
Here's host Jody avirgan
The guy to
Through the trials
Dan and Dave
Live at the Metrodome in the Twin Cities
Minneapolis and st. Paul Super Bowl number 26 so I had a party at my apartment
And I got the 6-foot Subway sub
That was that was the centerpiece was the 6-foot sub
And I already know
I had a little money and was like man I bought all the booze all the beer
Are quite a few people come over
And
It got a little while
Super Bowl 26
January 26th
Almost 80 million people watching on television
Many of them from parties like the one at the end of Brian's house
Everybody was drinking beer
And then we got into the hard alcohol and
It was really fun
Dan is watching from Moscow Idaho
Dave Johnson is watching from Los Angeles California
I probably had
30 or 40 people at my house with multiple TV setup and everybody's there and I kind of kept a little bit of a secret
I just let him know wait till you see what's going to be on here
It's the first commercial comes on
It's super short
It's in third quarter
Just before Pepsi ad featuring Cindy Crawford
The first Dan and Dave commercial runs
Featuring old photographs and grainy videos of two toddlers
Daniel Bryan
And Dave Johnson
Dan can 110.3 seconds Dave can I jump 6 ft 10 in
Three-quarter inches this summer those battle it out in Barcelona for the title of world's greatest athlete
The voice-over expounds on the men's athletic
But the visuals are just the photos of the two toddler
Me and a bathtub
Dave on a bike
It was just little kids and that's it
And everybody kind of looks around like
That's it
What the heck was that
Then later in the same commercial break
Another short add run
Dan can throw a 16 lb shot put 53 ft 3 in
More pictures and home video
Only in this one the kids are a little older
Maybe five or six
The second that ends the same way as the first
Quick Reebok logo
And a promise
Is Summerville battle it out in Barcelona for the title of world's greatest athlete
I don't know what to expect they didn't show us the commercials before
We saw them at the Super Bowl
Reebok Wrentham or commercial
Making four in total
All during the third quarter
And all of them just 15 seconds long
Jan won the decathlon at the world track and field championships Dave won the decathlon at the Goodwill
Games this summer they'll battle it out in Barcelona for the title of world's greatest athlete
I remember people really being confused at first and then eventually they
They're going man that is
Genius there to talk about how amazing that that Reebok thought of
Doing small little commercials all the way to where
There's a culmination of what they're really were talking about
Genesis 2 athletes that are going to go to the Olympics this year and can be settled in Barcelona
By the way the game
It's pretty lame
With Washington beating Buffalo 3720
The ads
Have made their input
When the Super Bowl was over in the party was over
And everybody got out of there and
It was a little bit shocking really it's like wow we're here to
Celebrate
Commercials that I was in
Remember
Sitting with a group of people that I had their and they're all coming and going
I can't believe I'm sitting that were here with Dave and I never really thought of myself that way that somebody would think it's cool to be with Dave
That was the first time I really sat there is going if you know people are going to know who I am now
Remember
Almost being scared you know what do you do with that
In 92
Reebok was known primarily as a shoe that your mom wore to take
Aerobics classes in and they were desperate to increase their
Athletic credibility
In 1992 Rick City
Worked for shiet day
The Ad Agency hired to put together Reeboks latest campaign
The task was pretty daunting we've got two guys no one's ever heard of in a an event no one really
Cares about
All of the the best-known athletes wear Nike athletes
The Michael Jordan's of the world most famous professional athletes in the world
If you wanted to stand out we needed to do something else
Basic idea was in sports circles the winner of the decathlon is the world's greatest athlete
And so
It wasn't hard for
Reebok to get excited about a campaign that said who's the world's greatest athlete
This Reebok athlete you've never heard of
Or this other Reebok athlete you've never heard of
The decathlon by Nature
Is in my opinion the toughest
Of all the track and field event
The decathlon is so tough
Because it combines so much
10 events contested over the course of 2 days
Each one adding to the competitors overall point
They won is a hundred meter dash long jump shot
High jump and the 400 meter run
D2 is 110 m
Fiscus pause Javelin and last
The 1500 meter run
They need to track some really interesting
Individuals
We don't say that athletes find the decathlon we saved at the decathlon
We'll find those athlete
That's what happened to me I think that's what happened to Dave
Born in 1963
Dave Johnson grew up in Montana in order
By his own admission he was hardly the model young man
I was one of those kids that was in a lot of trouble growing up I was
I was actually throwing snowballs at cars and and I think I did definitely learn how to throw
So well because I was able to stand farther back than anybody else and throw that apple or throw that snowball
Prophetic Rock
I remember the first time I've coach told me
What the decathlon was said
You should do the decathlon I thought he said Marathon
I coach know I'm the hurdler I don't run distance
You're no naughty of the decathlon he said you know Bruce Jenner
And I go well Bruce Jenner that's a guy on chips remember watching television there's Jenner was on a
A show called chips at the time he was doing a cameo with Evan
If I just knew him as a Hollywood TV Guide
He said no you know he was an Olympic medalist
Dave Johnson was hook
Dan O'Brien Auto Group in Oregon
Just a few hours south of
In a small town of Klamath Falls
And he also had his ups and downs before finding his sport
Growing up in southern Oregon
Tumi
Always felt
Like I was at a place
You know we have six adopted kids in the family
I have a sister who's biracial like myself a little brother who's Hispanic
I have a Native American sister
And then to Korean sister
Well when you're the only kid of color or
Kids of color in your entire town witch
The O'Brien family was it's it's interesting because all you want to do when you're young
Is fit in
Blend in
Go along get along and there we are
Looking like the Rainbow Coalition
Every time we get out of the car and go to church
The movies
It's a very
Weird feeling when everybody's watching you
I can just remember thinking
You know why are people staring at me why are people staring at us
This is just our regular family in
It wasn't until I got into sports that I really felt like
I belong
I always thought that
Sports was The Equalizer
There for me
Didn't matter what you look like or where you came from
If you were good at sports
You were good
And then was good
He became a star athlete in high school
Landed a scholarship at the University of Idaho
And there
Started to compete in the decathlon
And in his senior year
The first cross paths with Dave Johnson
A few years older and already well-established on the scene
You know Dave was the best American up until that point
But then star was Rising quickly
And others in a tight-knit track Community we're starting to know
I'm Jackie Joyner-Kersee the world's greatest female athlete
Jackie Joyner-Kersee can say that
Even now
Thanks to her six Olympic medals and the heptathlon World Record She set in 1988
It still stands today
When you see this young Talent
It's just a matter of time
They don't have this big breakthrough
Well it's interesting Jackie Joyner-Kersee made the comment that I could be the next Bruce Jenner
And that was what I was striving to do
You know most of my career he he was the hero that we all needed in 1976 and he was the gold
Golden Boy and Dam was that very explosive
Athlete
I mean he was just this young kid very raw
You know very talkative and
He had a personalities at
Kapoor people to him
We're a perfect combination I think he and I were
A great Duo that was meant to be where we were going to push each other to the level that we ended up going to
And by the time the 1992 Barcelona Olympics have come into view
Dan and Dave pushed each other to the top of the global stage
Dan won the decathlon at the world track and field championships
You know usually the multi events are dominated by
The Europeans
And finally
In America
The Breakthrough in and I all of a sudden it's like wow
He still I seen this young Talent
Put it out
Together
And Among The Observers who took notice or the executives at Reebok
Your mom's apparel company was on the hunt for athletes
Get into business
Dan and Dave
Two dominant competitors but unknown personality
With a perfect
Here to Ashley's put not sport
You know in the Limelight
To have that
Commercial showing doing the Super Bowl was
Wow
And we kind of looked at each other like wow you know he's too young little decathletes were getting a lot of attention and it's about time
I'm track and field athletes got that
The decathlon
Really us
Unheard of
I can't believe they're asking us to do this this is what
Jordan does Michael Jordan own
Bo Jackson all the best basketball football guys doing
With Dan and Dave
Reebok was looking to promote
The new cross trainer to the masses
A shoe design for you
Across multiple Sports and workouts
The greatest athlete at the time was
Bo Jackson
Eddie played two sports
All new everything Nikes campaign went
But the truth was
Dan and Dave were more equipped to back up that claim
So when I look at Bo Jackson he's a great baseball player he's a great football player but you know what
I thought I was a girl greatest athlete because I could do 10 events
And that thought played right into the case Reebok was trying to make
As they rolled out more and more ads
After the Superbowl
World's greatest athlete here to talk to you about Reeboks you running cross-trainer world's greatest athlete
Here to talk to you
Does baldness
Of Reebok to come out with two people
Was really incredible
My name is Steve Miller
And at the time of Dan and Dave
I was the head of a US Sports Marketing
For Nike
And we became very aware of the fact
The Reebok was onto something very special
What you're looking for is a consumer is somebody who does something
That you can't do
Or something you aspire to do
Or somebody who inspires you
And Dan and Dave
Caught the eye and the ear of consumers
Throughout the Country Inn in globally as well
Each time the Reebok
Rand commercial
And revised it and upgraded it
You you became more
Affectionate towards the two athletes
And so people pick their favorites or Dave Dance Mom
Dave's mom
Dave dance dentist damn Dave's mailman dance girlfriend
Stan's ex-girlfriend definitely
Dave
To be settled
In Barcelona
Reebok had a hit on their head
I remember being in meetings and Reebok was just talking we're going to compete with Nike
We're finally
Getting there
Reebok hitfilm the dozens of commercials
The air during the Super
Emerald and Dave had already known each other as rivals
The filming brought them closer together as friends
We were competing against each other to
To be better actors
But we're both not
And I think we both kind of knew that
And there was plenty of downtime to bond on the 2nd
I couldn't believe for a
30 second commercial
Setting up cameras and all kinds of stuff it would take two days of 12-hour day shooting
You just sit around
Deschutes 30 seconds
Finally they called for you and you do an hour's worth of work
And Dave and I looked at each other couple times and I was just we said
I can't believe we're wasting time
By late February Dan and Dave were on talk show Danny they were giving joint press conf
Dave and Ava being profiled on local morning TV
Dave and I got to shoot a commercial with Sinbad the comedian
He was the most incredible guy because he was so chill off camera but then when the lights are on he went crazy
Hey everybody I'm sitting down here with Dan today and we're playing basketball today
Ionic at the end of the day my stomach hurt because I was laughing so hard and Sinbad
Was maybe the worst athlete I had ever seen
Are I was one of the top five sports celebrity figures in the US
Everybody knew who Dan and Dave was
Remember
Dad and I were just going to what we do with this
Will an athlete's life is pretty simple
You get up your train eat
You go to bed and you just repeat that cycle each and every day
When the Dan and Dave campaign was going on
You know my life got complicated
I couldn't go anywhere
I mean there is nothing that I couldn't I'd go to that an outhouse and come out near the camera
There there
See if I wash my hands I guess that's what I wasn't prepared for its is to understand that you know what
I just wasn't another face in the crowd we got to a point where I told the matter is we can't do this anymore
We just stopped appearances
We've got to get this thing going
I mean I got like four months
Pick up until the trial
The trial
The first Dan and Dave ads are.
At the Super Bowl
January
Of 1990
The Olympics were in Barcelona
In July
When Reebok approached
Dave and I
The first thing both of us Ed
Was
You know neither one of us around this team yet
We still have to go through the Olympic trials
In 1992 the United States Olympic track and field trials
Where held
Attack Gormley
Stadium in New Orleans
The last week
I arrived in New Orleans and I think the
First thing
That I noticed as soon as I got off the plane was
It was hot
The heat was blistering
Upper 90s with 99% humidity or something
Proof like
Nothing I've ever experienced
Before
Everywhere you went
Dan and de-dan and a Dan and Dave
All eyes are on
Who is going to represent
The United States and who will go on and when the go map
Do you have the pressure a little bit for me with Reebok and
The money they'd spend the night I better make this Olympic team was in my mind
Because everybody's wanting to know who's better
We got to see who wins in Barcelona that's the commercial
Meanwhile the trials were Reeboks last Big Marketing events before Barcelona
And the company took full advantage
I noticed everybody was wearing these white t-shirts
And hats
That either had an or Dave on
They either had a red Dan and blue Dave's
And when you get into the stadium
Everybody's wearing the t-shirts
It was almost like somebody dropped them from a helicopter
To all the people in the stands at least half the people in the stands were wearing these white t-shirts
The top three finishers in the New Orleans decathlon would qualify for the Olympic
And the first day of events
Saturday went according to scratch
With Dan and Dave both racking up tons of fun
Dave as usual with solid or Dan the reigning world champion
Shot in the first place
Somebody was telling me that I was ahead of world record pace so that made me feel pretty good
Dan was on fire
If there were any concerns for either of them it was a lingering foot injury for Dave
But he was the best
2nd Ada caffe
Of all time
And the headlines leading at the Sunday we're all about whether or not he could catch
Who is arch rival
They've dominated the airwaves now their final really begins Dan O'Brien and Dave Johnson
Who will win the decathlon
What were the first two events of the second day
Hurdles and discus
Dave started to close the gap
And then
Sure enough we got to the pole vault
The polo
The most stressful time I think
A decathlete or the coaches
Is the start of the pole vault decathlon
Any coach will tell you
That's where they're the most
In the pole vault
Competitors aim to clear increasing Heights one by one
The higher the bar the more points receipt
Each vaulter gets three attempts on a given height
And each can choose whatever height they like to start at
But if they fail to clear the bar at
They get no points
To start learning relatively High Point
Immediately
Dan and Dave made the same aggressive choice
To begin their fault
15 ft
9 in
Qdoba hire vaulters it takes a while to get to your turn to vault at your starting height so you warm up and
They might give you a few other warm us but it's never enough
It's the eighth of an
You're feeling your legs a little bit
And the Sun
It was really starting to get hot
While we're sitting around the
Cameras are in our faces they're following us wherever we go
And
I remember just thinking how distracting that was
Well by the time the warm-ups ended
It was almost two solid hours
Till I took my first jump
I bought it for sure I remember that
And so I made my first height
And had no problem with it
Other than my foot was still getting more and more sore
Chat Downing
He was battling the heat again and I remember seeing his first attempt at that same height
You know once they call my name
I cannot
Look down the runway kind of assess the wind look over at the code she gives me a thumbs up
All I remember is putting my hands up way too late
And so literally I just went straight up and straight down with hardly any band in the pole
He looks like you've never voted before he's just something
Way wrong then thing I've ever seen him have
And so on my next attempt I make all the adjustments
Come down the runway good takeoff good plant
I feel like I'm way over the bar
And I come down on it slightly
And the bar falls off
And then I start to thanks like no
I'm on the third attempt
You don't want to be my third attempt
Add an opening bar
Add an Olympic trials
Has a lost maybe I'll chance he had been on the world record pace and now risking not even close
That's when I sat up and I'll go
What is going on here in it and it was kind of a
There was kind of a quiet in the stands there wasn't as much
You kind of see the crowd
Begin to stir a little bit
Other athletes sit up
And it look over your direction
LeBron got to mrs.
Is opening bars as opener or did you make with no I thought I saw you make one
Let me hear the people talking in the crowd as well as
No no he made one I saw him make one about an hour ago
No I was a warm up
This third attempt
He might have taken a
A little run and then stopped and went back
Final attempt and it goes down the runway in stock that was not as soon as I start my run on the 3rd at 10
I get a big gust of wind
Coming from the right so I stopped
He just didn't look confident
He's not on the team if he doesn't make his height and he knows it and it's going through his mind
I just tell myself settled down just relax just relax and so I get back there and I take off and down the road
One way I go
Look on his face like
I'm just going to go and I'll make sure I make it
And I feel pretty good
I plant the pole the next thing you know I'm stalled out on the top
And I'm looking at the bar and I think get over it somehow
And I can't and it's not even close
I'll come crashing down to the pit
And I'm just in a daze
What happened what what up what up what happened in the end in at that moment you just I wanted to turn to somebody and say
Help me
It was almost as if
The Sun
All that heat
That it became
Cloudy
And it became dark
Because you knew
Something
Bad habit
I
Blew a chance to go to the Olympic Games
I'm not on this Olympic team
It was
It was devastating
I was devastated
I just tried to get away from people
But there's guys with cameras there's people and so I tried that I didn't make the team
I cried that I let everybody down I was kind of in a daze just
Yeah I kind of freaked out by all of it
Stop never ever
Cross my mind that
Dan aude
We're not make that Olympic team
I like that just wasn't
I thought
My main goal is to win an Olympic gold medal hair
And that was what my coaches and I thought all along
And we were so
Not ready for it
We're not we were not ready to
Fail
Did not make this team to not win this meet
It was hard it was everybody was still in disbelief there's
You could hear the buzz in the stands
Oh my gosh I can't believe it
You are the best athlete in the world
And I knew
It was
Hard to deal with
Dealing with all the commercials and all the hype
And everything that went into it
It it was too much it was a lot to have to deal with all at once
And the first thing I thought about is
Got to get to him and tell me it's going to be okay
Because I cared about him as a person
You know we were Dan and Dave singular
And everywhere we went we had to be that that that person
It's one of those things where
Dang the perfect situation
Wasn't happy
Happening the exact same that would have been what
Everybody wanted to see wasn't going to happen
Suddenly I was alone
Yeah I was able to become Dave again
The real Dave not today Reebok
Johnson and the javelin competition knows he's thrown a beauty right here it turns out to be
An American record of 244 ft
Date places first in the overall competition in wild and fails to qualify
When it was over
Dave came over and said I love you man
I love you man you're going to be alright
Decided
He needed a hug
Give him a big hug and just said I'm so sorry
That that happened
And I just
I couldn't even hug him back
You know I was just kind of hands on my side it's just like what the heck just happened
For the next 48 hours I walked around in a daze and
I didn't think much about Dan and Dave
Some people asked me will what's Reebok going to do and at the time I thought
I don't care
But I
Got the real stance that
You know somebody was getting yelled at somewhere
There was probably some yelling going on at the attic NZ
Rick sittig
Was watching the event that afternoon on television from New York
It's a bad situation
The mood at the agency is just dark crap
Reebok has made a huge investment in these athletes to
To puff up their credibility in the athletic world and they've got media to
To fill and
The future of the company is kind of resting on the outcome of this
And and it's now just
Going to hell
And in my head I'm going on now
We were planning to
To be on Johnny Carson we were planning to be
Hosting Saturday Night Live all those commercials station Corky
Made
They've made 10 or 15 commercial set
We're going to play
During the Olympic Games with Dan and Dave there
Steve Miller
From Nike
Was in New Orleans
With a few of his colleagues in a small section of seat
In the middle of the stand
Watching the drama play out
Sitting in the stands and watching it was
You know was like a dream come true
4 months
Steve and Nike have been secretly fantasizing this exact
Scenario
Yeah we're actively don't make that something bad would happen. I don't know I don't know how else to put it I I'd like the Lions
Say no it didn't make a difference but it made a difference of course
The truth is we were just being happy and you would have what
It was one of those moments
Where you feel so good you get a little lightheaded
Is the first moment in time that I can ever remember taking pleasure
In somebody else's pain
Reebok
The creator of those Dan and Dave commercial says that it's cute
It just needs a slight Readjustment
The Readjustment
Came in the form of a new series of ads
Embracing the change in the Dan and Dave story
Reebok rebooted its campaign on the Fly
They have new ads out within 48 hours
In the coming weeks there was an ad with Dan coaching Dave
I've got some free time I'm helping Dave drink yesterday
Porsche
When was Dave consoling Dan
You should be happy you're going to represent your country you're going for the gold
I just wish you were going down
And that's saying that all to announce the new role
For Dan O'Brien in Barcelona
I am going huh I'll be up in the broadcast Booth you mean the coffee in Barcelona
Together again
You wanna hug we already did that
Okay the decathlon resume this morning at Olympic Stadium American Dave Johnson expected to contend for the gold medal
When you're the broadcast Booth it's really hard knot
Put yourself out there on the track or Dwight stones
And the guy who might have been Johnson's toughest competition at the Olympics
Stan O'Brien
It was a little strange now looking down there at guys who I thought
I could be for the Olympic gold medal
Yeah it's just really too bad he always hate for it to come down to your third at sampton and maybe
There were moments when I wasn't horribly complimentary today what do I looks to me like Dave is just lack enthusiasm
All day long
And I just saw him struggling and I was and I kept thinking this isn't the Dave Johnson that I saw spring
This isn't the Dave Johnson that I saw
At the Olympic trials
And I thought
Izzy Izzy crumbling under the pressure
Dave was underperformed
But not because of the pressure
His foot injury from the trials and only gotten worse
The public didn't know about it
But a few weeks before the games
David met with a doctor
About his
The doctor said you she can't go we shouldn't go to the Olympics
Cuz it's going to break in half
Wait a minute I'm the Dave guy from the Reebok commercial
Dad didn't make the team didn't you see somebody's got to go
In Barcelona on a broken foot
Starting Day 2 in 9th
Place
Dave toughed it out
And finished third
Dave Johnson becomes the first u.s. medalist in the event since Bruce Jenner back in 1976
You know he did his absolute best
Which was phenomenal
Take walk away with a bronze medal
Even as a stepped up in
Received the bronze medal
Yeah we saw the American flag go up I was thinking man
And overcome
He noticed this Dan and David
Campaigning
Does a broken foot tendon and just the career of 14 15 years of training and out of so
So fortunate to be able to step down from that
Metals
Ceremony and go to the people that really knew me my family of my coaching
And the people that really work
They're in my life to get me to that moment
Dave
When's the bronze medal
Robert smell like
Comes home with the gold from the Czech Republic
Neither Dave nor I
Claim the title of the world's greatest athlete in Barcelona
And I think it was
Two or three days later
In USA Today
Reebok
Has a big ad that says congratulations to Dave Johnson
For winning the Olympic bronze medal thank you Dan and Dave
For a great year
And I think for me at that particular moment Dan and Dave ended
Dan and Dave was over as an ad campaign
With Dave coming off of major injury
Dan and Dave looked to be over as a major rivalry 2
But Dan O'Brien was already thinking about what was that
All I could do was really think about what was down the road for me
And the great thing about track and field is you don't have to wait every four years for a big event
I knew I was going to get another shot the following year at a world championship
Starting in the fall of 1992 just a few weeks after the Barcelona games and for the next few years
Dan O'Brien went on the best hair of his life
September that same year I break the world record the winter of 1993
I win the first heptathlon World indoor championships I break the world record I win a u.s. outdoor tile
Title in Eugene Oregon score over 8800 go on to defend my world title in Stuttgart Germany
When a third world outdoor title in Gothenburg Sweden
But no one
I remember eating lunch with Bruce Jenner and Bruce
Kept telling me
Only thing people are going to remember is the Olympic Games and I thought to myself
Man this got crazy
He doesn't know what he's talking about he didn't have World Championships when he was a competing act like I get
To compete at World Championships every two years
But it wasn't until later that I realized man Bruce was right
So Daniel Bryan set his sights on the next
Olympics
And the chance to win a medal people would care if
But even as he was winning meat after meat
Dan felt he needed help
Because he was still struggling with the mental side
The decathlon
I used to get so nervous before I compete it
That I would question why I do this
Almost throwing up
Wanting to quit
My name is dr. Jim Reardon I'm a sports psychologist from Columbus Ohio
Dan who comes to dr. Riordan
Talk about that anxiety
Facebook for every comp
Dr. Reardon
Suspected there was a deeper element
At play
The Fallout
The Mist pole vault
In the world
What can happen is
People come in for for treatment from trauma
And the first thing the therapist wants to talk about is the trauma
And the last thing the person wants to talk about is the trauma
I just made the decision pretty early on
If he brings it up and wants to talk about it we'll talk about it
But if he doesn't
Then we want because
He'll know when the time will be right
And so we didn't
For almost
Years
The poll mountainous didn't come
They talked about other parts of the decathlon
Their personal
The real real
But never
New Orleans
Until one day in August 1995
311 days until the next alarm
Trials
We were having this conversation and
He kind of started it out by
By saying
You know what
Last night was weird
I had a dream about
Pole vault
From 1992
He said I haven't thought about that in years
And I'm thinking to myself
Okay I guess this is this is the moment
Over the coming months
Reardon decided that he had to take a big aggressive
Dan had to watch footage
Of his failure
In New Orleans
Somebody got me
Copy of
And I had a couple of back in those days DVDs made
I kind of
Caught him off guard
And I said I got something I want you to look at
And we watched
How hot it was oh my gosh it was hot
And I remember thinking to myself holy mackerel
I relive the horror
Of missing on a third attempt
And coming down landing on the pit
And just being in a complete days and it was absolutely ghastly
To go through those emotions again
The video continue to roll at show Dave come over to hug me
I couldn't I couldn't I didn't even know what to say afterwards
And I said
What do you think he said I don't want to look at
And I said okay
And I replied it
What do you think he said
Should I feel like
Feel like throwing up
And I said
I said you know what
I would much rather have you feel like that in a hotel room in Chula Vista in December
Dad on the runway
In Atlanta
Tianjin
I wanted him to get to the point
Where he would have seen that video so many times
That he would just get pissed off when he would think about
And develop the mindset that
Pressure is nothing pressure is going to bring out the best in
It's a double header today both slow and bypasses you have competition from brackenfield here at the Olympic stadium in Atlanta
Impremedia trials for the 1996 Olympics were held in Atlanta
Which would be the site of the games themselves
Later that summer
And once again the decathlon competition
Titian feature to familiar faces
Dan O'Brien and Dave Johnson
But no one was talking about Dan and Dave in 1996
No Reebok campaign in fact Danville the Nike ad
By this point
And Dave
Was living the typical Battle of the injured ass
One problem piling up on top
These trials were not about who would be the world's greatest athlete Dan or Dave
The storyline was all Dan O'Brien
I would say that the 1992 Olympic trials debacle by Dan O'Brien is a part of track and field lore and Legend at this point
I was nervous going into the 96 trials I'll be honest with you
I can remember
Waking up the morning that the decathlon started
I put my head in my wife's lap and just sobbed
Because I was nervous and I was scared
You know but I needed to get that out the Kathy who compete now is affected by his no hide in the pole vault
4 years ago I would submit that this will be the hardest track meet the dental Bramble Everett
Even if Dan had felt like you
Put 1992 behind him
The organizers in Atlanta
Wouldn't let him shake it so
I'll never forget
As I walked
To run 200m the start of the very first day at the Atlanta Olympic trials
I look up at the big screen
On the North End
Other side of the field and they're showing
My failure in the pole vault
When I saw that footage I was pissed off
I don't even know to this day whose idea it was
It really didn't upset me that I saw the video I kind of almost chuckle
I laughed it off because of the training the Danna done it
Became just not
I was ready
Proving he was ready Dan got off to a great start going in today to he was in second place
And he remained there through the hurdles and The discus
And with seven of the ten events complete next the dreaded pole vault what must be gone
Going through his mind
I get a little nervous and
You know just I'm tired of sitting around 20 minutes has gone by and maybe a half hours since I took my last warm-up jump
Dan was cooling off
And just like in 1992 he was losing his rhythm
So he made a last-minute decision to change history
2 bars before I'm supposed to come in
I get a little antsy
And I walked over to my Coach Rick Sloan and I said
What do you think about me coming into the next bar the it was a scheduled Bar lower than I was supposed to come in and he's just like
You feel good go for it do it
I didn't tell anybody else
Look at my coach and all of a sudden I took my sweats off and I step up to the runway and they sell Brian up
And I think that surprised even my competitors at the time decision
The height one foot below what Dan started at 4 years ago and everyone in the stadium
Holding their Collective breath
I'm on the runway I got my starter poll
Don't even think about missing just think you know what I'm here to bolt head down the runway
And think to myself look I'm probably not as warmed up as I should be I push a little harder than
Then I normally would on a first attempt jump as I take off the ground my top hand slips
About an inch and I regrip real quick swing up go over the bar
Can I get a first attempt made and by virtue
Do that first attempt make I'm on the team
You are so sweet irony
Pearl Bryan it looks like
Daniel Bryan is going to gain the lead in the decathlon
Because of his performance here in the pole vault the event that was his undoing 4 years ago now also
Later finished first in the trials decathlon
A stark contrast to four years earlier
In 1992 it had been Dave Johnson watching damn struggle
This time the roles were reversed
Find a place at 6
And pretty much knew that was my retirement after that event after that Olympic trials and
You know I just remember just being able to encourage Dan to go on in Atlanta and represent the United States
And here comes dad O'Brien just left the crowd carrying home here he is finally going to be
US Olympic team
Daniel Bryan was world champion record holder exercise the Demons of New Orleans
Now the only job left to do was to win the gold 6 weeks later
The trouble is when you want everything except for the Olympic gold medal
And you feel like it's the last thing on your list
It's not as exciting as it could be
It was stressful I was trying to just not make mistakes
Atlanta Olympic Stadium where the decathlon competition continue today and fall report on date
Decathlon let's go to Whitestone
In Atlanta
In his quest to finally settle that question
Who is the world's greatest athlete
Elif first been asked for years earlier
Daniel Bryan's first day of competition
Went off without a hitch
As prepared as I was for the Olympic Games
Sometimes what you're not prepared for is what other people are going to do
This crazy young guy from Germany Frank Guzman this young kid he had
Personal best after personal best
He was going crazy
So on this new stage Dan suddenly had a new rifle
Huisman the German was right on his heels
True day 1
To the pole vault and right up to the decathlon spinal to event
Javelin in the 1500
Erase that has never been damn strongest
I need a big lead before the 1500 m
And when I got to the job and I didn't have as big a lead as I would have liked
He was a little too close for comfort
Let's head back to the track
The two-day decathlon concluding tonight with a report on
And so as I got into the javelin it was the Twilight of the night
Olympic stadium was packed
With Hometown American fans rooting on Dan
Anna noisy contingent of Germans rooting on Boost
Each of the competitors selected a javelin
And took their first throw
Dan's first attempt was
We tried to stay calm
Scanning the crowd
As he waited his neck
I look over and see a guy in a
Red white and blue jersey USA Jersey
Anastasia Johnson
He's got his Oakleys on the back of his head backwards like you always used to wear them
Bonifas down in the front row
You know just kind of hanging
David been standing with the US coaches
Quietly watching the drama play out
But now he was noticing something
Christian through his first throw I think
Yeah I could tell her the job and he was throwing wasn't flying exactly
As well as it should be for his type of throwing
After the second throw another disappointment
Then came over to consult with his coaches on the side
With Dave
Standing right nearby
We had that eye contact
And I say to Dave
Which Javelin should I use
You got a hundred to choose from out there
I had him pick out the javelin that I knew
Would work really well because I
Jalen is just my best event
Dave Dave said the 90 M or Nemeth
And I knew exactly which Javelin he was talking about
And I said all right
Something about him being there
Put me at ease
It was
Just refreshing to my soul I just felt good
That he was going to be there
To witness my greatest moment
Denim stepped up to the line for his third row needs a question for the 1500
The unreleased a five-and-a-half personal best
Maybe
In my mind I might have stepped out of myself and went out into his body a little bit
And I got to be Dan for for about 20 seconds in and help him throw that thing
Smoking
Daniel Bryan
I threw farther than Frank boost men so I didn't give up any points I didn't give up any ground this is
Is what it's all about
Olympic gold medal
When Dan won a gold medal in 96 I was just glad that it came for
Being able to go through but stick through and not give up on the sport
And it was great to see him finally being Olympic champion
I think it would be tough to talk about Dan and Dave if I hadn't come back in 96 and won the gold but I
I think failing in 1992 gave me an opportunity to rewrite the narrative I had to change
People's minds every time I stepped out onto the track people when they think of Dan and Dave the room
Remember something went wrong Reebok they had this big campaign that we both were going to be at the Olympics and the
Then only one of us went so it was a failure because of that but that the reality of that situation is the campaign was
Huge success they sold more shoes of that particular running Cross Trainer shoe than any other shoe
Two of the year-and-a-half that they're promoting it that whole year was such a such a
Great experience except for 2 hours on the second day in the eighth of a of the decathlon
I meet people who say I remember where I was when you didn't make that
Third attempt in the pole vault they have they have where were they stories when Dan O'Brien didn't make the Olympic team and I think
That's just in our human nature we are just programmed to remember the bad times a little bit better than the
Good times people remember the field goal that was missed people remember the free throws that
The guy didn't make nothing prepares you for you know really having your dream
I'm just kind of slip out from underneath you but a personality a great performance
Can change an athlete's life
To be settled
In Barcelona
The trials of Dan and Dave was hosted and produced by Jody avirgan with reporting by Andrew Mambo
Soundesign original scoring by Ryan Ross Smith
Julia Lowrie Henderson Rose Eveleth Taylor Barfield and Kate McAuliffe are the other producers at 30 for 30 podcast
You can find the series on Apple podcasts
Or a 30 for 30 podcast. Com
The first season is V documentaries the latest one just came out this week this is story
But a huge Casino Caper with the world's most famous poker player and his mysterious accomplished
When millions of dollars
Using a flaw in the design of certain playing cards
Check it out
99percentinvisible is a project of radiotopia and kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
You can find the show indoor discussions about the show on Facebook you can't give me at Roman Mars in the show at 99
NPI org run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to if you've always wondered what those big two digit codes
Painted on Airport runways meant you can find the answer on our website in 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com