99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Recognize the possibilities of nuclear war in the middle age
But not all citizens knowing what they should do
And where they should go
If bombs Begin to Fall
What date are your responsibilities
And that of course is President John F Kennedy speaking on July 25th 1961
During the Berlin crisis one of the various moments
In the Cold War where we came very very close to engaging in actual war with the Philippines
Tomorrow I'm requesting of the Congress
Coupons for the following
Media objectives
Do identify in Mark's face in exist
Instructions
Public and private
It could be used
Fallout shelters in
Stock the shelves
Water
Earth Day tips
Another minimum potential throughout the Bible
Basically what Kennedy is saying here is it's a real possibility that bombs are going to start falling and
We need to figure out where you can all go to take shelter if they do
That's producer Katie Mingle
And after Kennedy made this horrifying speech
As you can imagine
Phones
Started ringing
Immediately the Kennedy administration was besieged by people
Wanting more information on
Fallout shelter
I'm Kenneth D Rose I wrote One Nation Underground
The Fallout Shelter in American
Are businesses that had previously been making swimming pools
Now declare themselves to be
Experts at building shelters
They were door-to-door bomb shelter salesman shelter displays at malls in county fairs
But by the time Kennedy made that 1961 speech
There was one place that already broken ground
Funny unique shelter
Artesia New Mexico population 11000 is about 40 miles south of Roswell in the southern part
State near Texas
And in 1962 they opened a brand-new Elementary
Trade school
Completely Underground
Quit to the morgue decontamination showers and a stockpile
Food and Medicine
Because the school it was built to double
Of the town's nuclear fallout
This was a
Pilot program
With the idea of
Protecting
Schoolchildren and also members of local
Humanity in case there was a nuclear attack
During an attack to school
Supposedly with shelter it's on students
And those from other schools
Or the first 2100 people to show up
And those who arrived late at the school
Which lines are entry blocked by 1800 Town steel doors
Story online
IPic branch.com
Is 8
21 and a joining us in the studio this morning is Katie mingle she's up from Oakland California
Good morning how are you
What is going on
Let me explain I went to Artesia
And because small towns are amazing
Invited me to come on their local radio
Ksvp
And put a call out for
Are people who have gone ABO elementary school as
Good deal self anybody is has information or stories you want to share about Apple and then tribute
Student there were administrator or
Maybe you worked on or whatever give Kitty call once again her phone number is
Do people actually call you yeah they did and we'll meet one of them later but first let's go look at the school
Abu is tucked away in a quiet little neighborhood not too far away from the center of town
You can easily miss it driving by since it's mostly Underground
But there is a sign out front and you have to squint to make it out
But it says
ABO Elementary School
And fallout shelter and that's course original on there
That's Scott
Timer my name is Scott siemer
And I'm currently the director of maintenance for the public schools for Artesia Public Schools
I met Scott and Thad Phillips
The current assistant superintendent of Artesia schools
On the roof
Of ABO
The school is closed now but kids doing school there until 1995
The roof of Apple school is a concrete blacktop at ground level with basketball hoops and 3 cupboards
Stairways that go down underground and into the school
Like if you're in first grade you went down this this set of doors if you're in
Second third you come over here
And then 4th and 5th graders would line up at this one
One mother described the scene of kids entering the building as looking like ants lining up to go into there and he'll
Got in bad actually both went to school at a bow in the late 70s early 80s
And they said that even though the sign out front says fallout shelter and even though their school was entirely
Really underground they never really knew what that meant
I never knew growing up that it was a
Built as a bomb shelter was just a school to me is a kid you know
And then once you get older and you if you you know you hear stories and
All these to have a morgue down here and
Hubbell Elementary was designed by an architect and civil defense Enthusiast named Franks and hard
After he built ABO school he went on to design an underground shopping mall / bomb shelter that was
Never actually built
There's a this is our shower room
It's the
Contaminants off of you before you come into the rest of the people on the ground
The decontamination showers at each entrance were easy to miss
As where the blast doors which were swimming up against the wall
And not used
Starting normal
School days
Solid steel door
You can close it then it has
3 four different types of latches to latch
So nobody can get in or out
I never knew that
This door just until I start to work
We go down a couple flights of stairs into the main hallway of
School
Basically
Just looks like a school
I mean it's windowless
I'm kind of drab since it hasn't been used in almost 20 years
But otherwise it looks a bit like others
Schools Acton in
Kitchen area whenever you came to lunch from the classes you always came to this door
Now you see back there they had a big
Stage back there where we put on our productions for
I was in a few plays
During during great school so that's what that's where it all happened
The kids at elbow actually got to vote on what the school mascot would be
Inappropriately
And adorably
They chose to be
The ABO gophers
But yeah we're underground just like the Gophers are and so
Right through here is
Our generator room
To keep it up and running for the
People that are coming in inhabitants or whatever
Townspeople that are coming here for the Fallout
It also has right over here in the corner Tumwater well
Underground
And as you can tell right here
You got door you got close at 1
Survival open listen for survival
And you're sitting ventilation shafts and open ventilation shafts and trying to keep
Batter out of
Scott and sad weren't sure which room doubled as the morgue
The elevator
That's what I heard there's a little room but it did
I didn't ever see where it go
You know what tremendous number of bodies
What is the typical classroom
Turn there's not any windows or not any sunlight
But
We went upstairs
Two three times a day for
The recreation
The teachers reported that they generally like her school because the students weren't distracted by starting out
All the windows and I think the students themselves were generally proud
Hauser School
But once again this creates a huge debate with many people saying that the needs of schools
And I need to shelter people during a nuclear attack or not come
That's kind of throws again author of One Nation
Underground
And he says in fact there was a lot of debate
Going on at the time about Fallout
The subject was virtually in Escape
Football in the early nice
Every newspaper was running
Articles on shelters
Potential for
Survival Time Magazine published
An article called guns I neighbor in which they interviewed a guy who said
Chattanooga's neighbors tried to get into a fallout shelter during a nuclear attack
He would kill them
Today you can watch shows like Doomsday Preppers on cable TV I think about what it would be like to prepare for the upon
Michael Epps but in the 1950s and 60s
It was a brand new idea
Also back then it wasn't a fringe idea
I mean the president of the United States
I was telling people to build these things
And the whole country was involved in the debate
On one side of the debate
You had people against shelters
Those against shelter sad
That you're
People who burnt burrowed into the ground to save their own skins were no better than moles or gophers
Shelters would militarize America and turn the United States into a Garrison
State
And after the nuclear war had ended
Shelters would sort of the Americas pyramid
All That Remains
Wasted
Define civilize
And on the other side people for shelter said
Wait a minute
This is just a precaution
Like any other
They compared Fallout shelters to Lifeboat
Here's a sarcastic letter that a proponent of shelters wrote to the Harvard Crimson in 1961
It's been brought to our attention to certain elements among the passengers
Who favored the installation of lifeboats on the ship
Although we share their concern will remain unaltered Lee opposed to any consideration
Other course of action for the following reasons
The letter gets increasingly sarcastic
It demonstrates a lack of faith in our cap
Your parents security which lifeboats offer will make our Navigators Reckless
These proposals will distract our attention from more important things
IE building Unsinkable ships
You will only be safe for a worse fate inevitable death
On the Open Seas
So far from song
I think in the school letter you can see
Some of the issues
Are being debated
Like what kind of world will you emerge to if you survive a nuclear war
And whether the shelter system could somehow make our leaders more likely to engage in war
It's a very complicated calculus
This whole issue
Weather today
Build a shelter or not
For the town of Artesia
In the early 1960s
The calculation seems easy enough
They needed a new school anyway
The office of civil defense
Agreed to pay the difference
Between building a regular school and a fallout shelter
Artesia was near Walker Air Force Base
Is closed now but at the time it was the largest Strategic Air Command base of the u.s. Air Force
It was also close to the White Sands Missile Range
These and other factors
Made Artesia feel particularly vulnerable to attack
New Mexico has always had nuclear programs going on
That's John Williams her friend's mom is one of the people that heard me on the radio and got in touch John Wick
When Dabo Elementary in the 1960s when cold war tensions were still really high
I do remember them
Going through
White Sands Missile Range
Every once in awhile you see a missile going up here thinking well
How often do we have 30 minutes to live or what
It's kind of a creepy feeling
Lakeside and Scott gave me the tour of ABO
Johnny didn't know it first why her
School with underground
The teachers never mentioned it and her parents and tell her either
They didn't tell us anything
And don't ask real questions
Will lie to you
But most kids have that one friend in elementary school that knows about sex
Well Jonah had fidelia Brennan
And she knew about nuclear war
Adelia Brannen
I'll never forget
She's the one who opened my eyes to that kind of
I guess reality or unreality
She was
Very intelligent
Course I had a fallout shelter in their backyard so I'm sure they had already gone through the whole survivalist thing
Growing up and
You know knowing the kids and her family it seems like they were taught things like
How you could survive
Nuclear Holocaust in
I know I had kind of a freaky
Feeling about that after that
Like oh my gosh we're all going to die
Oh there you go
As Donna and I are talking an alarm starts going off
It's an emergency test alarm that the oil refinery plays every Monday at 6:30 p.m.
Artesia is a large oil refinery with another thing that made them feel vulnerable to attack in the 60s
Refineries are often targets during Wars especially the ones that make that people like the one in Artesia.
It's almost like a nuclear raid sound isn't it
What song is I Love Lucy was coming on when I was a kid
When Ava was built at got a fair amount of media attention
Dan Rather did a story on the CBS Evening News in nineteen
52 and more than 60,000 people tour the school in the
Its first few years
The Soviets found out about it and we're critical
One Moscow newspaper criticized artesians for
Indoctrinating pupils
To be inevitability of War
But actually while the rest of the country students were doing Duck and Cover drills
Probably strange
Scary for
Some kids
Johnny doesn't ever remember having to do one at a bow
But we never did any
You know
Like nuclear raid test where you had to drop tuck and roll and all that kind of stuff
We were already down there we were sick
So
Be sure to remember what Bert the turtle just Advance because everyone of us
Remember to do the same thing
That's what this feeling is all about
Duck and Cover
This is an official symbol.
Officials in the Soviet Union were putting down to us
For their preoccupation
Occupation with the
But in fact
The Soviets built a very elaborate
Secret shelter underneath
Moscow
And of course our fearless leaders had their own hiding place has the most elaborate one being the bunker hidden below the Greenbrier
Maya Resort in West Virginia
Build the house all 535 members of Congress and their staff
But not
Their family
It was decommissioned in 1995 and is now open for tours
Remember the speech that we heard at the beginning of the story and which Kennedy vowed to allocate millions of dollars to find place
Places where Americans could take shelter from nuclear bombs
Well it took place in July 19th
Do identify and Marsh faces
Construction
Republican primary
In the fall of 1962 during the Cuban Missile Crisis
Kennedy asked for a status report and found that his shelter program was far behind schedule
The government hadn't been able to find all that many places where people could take shelter and the ones they had found weren't fully stocked
Winsupply
By 1962 the
Private shelter
Ice was also
But it wasn't in decline because American stopped being afraid of nuclear war the Cuban Missile Crisis was arguably
The most frightening moment of the Cold War
Kenneth Rose thinks Americans rejected shelters
Score a lot of Ra
They couldn't afford them
Cost of a decent shelter it was about $2,500
That was about half of the median family income in the 1960s and doctor is also believes
Americans simply did not like
DND image of them
Cells
Cowering Underground
I think
Yet
Dog at American
Pride
We think roughly
Something like
200000 shelters
Is were built
From the beginning of the Cold War
To about 9
And
You could say that
Well 200,000 that's a lot of shelters
It's about 1
For every nine hundred
People
But
In an era when a majority of Americans
Actually believe
That there was going to be a nuclear war between the
The US
And the Soviet Union I would say that 200000
His ass is actually a
Small number
Highway
Not go
Down under the ground
Does Summer come in round
Not carry myself down to die
Let me die in my footsteps
And as far as a bow Elementary if thankfully never had to serve as a fallout shelter and they got rid of their supply back
I can 1989p rid of all the bedding in the food
The medicine
UNIF you body bag
But the school stayed open until 1995
When they stop using it as a school it wasn't because they were tired of being Underground
Here's assistant superintendent
That's it
It is a little low
It is a little sad after grown
Throwing up in the school
To see you
To see it not being used her to see it in this type of
A shape butt
We understand as a as a district ID
To renovate
This type of building was was more than
And what the community was willing to to put into it so we built a brand new school right on almost on top of it
It's still slightly to the West
The new school is called yeso Elementary yeso in a bow are both named after geological layers of Earth
Yeso being the layer just above a bow
Clever
Yeso is above ground
But in the spirit of ABO Elementary has
Very few windows
Now I bow Elementary is used
4 districts
Storage
Oh and one other
Being used as a Act
Shooter training facility
Before the federal Armed Force
Training Center
They go through all of their scenarios in and use it
Practice for
For situations that none of us want to think what happened but
What do you mean
Text school shootings that to you know been around the nation
This has been a
I really good facility to use cuz it's all downstairs no windows and they can do everything that they need to do and nobody
Nobody sees
The twice-a-month the federal law enforcement training center goes into a bow and practices
School shooting
Running drills
Firing at Big targets
Something ever happens
You want to be prepared
Don't think you can never be prepared enough but
In case something does happen
Because if there's one thing Artesia has
Always been good at
It's being prepared
And protecting its
From whatever dangers
99% invisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and Mero
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced
Offices of arcsin architecture in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Percent
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastland episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's omigod. Info podcast
Oh my God. Info
Do you like the stories on this program you get more and more and more of it I Facebook Twitter and Tumblr
But photos of a boa weight
I-99 pmi.org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com