99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Around the corner from our office in beautiful Downtown Oakland California is delauer's news
It is been there since 1907 for the people who live and work downtown it is Central to our existence
Everyone goes there to buy drinks
Lottery tickets little packs
Fruit flavored cigarillos and occasionally
Even a newspaper
But about eight months ago it became clear that even though delauer's wants a bunch of people inside the store buying things
They don't want a bunch of people outside their store hanging out on the sidewalk
Here's how you can tell
Delauer started playing really loud classical music
Speaker outside
And although I still see a fair number of people hanging out in front of them
The owner says
It's not nearly as many
Sophie change
Who was Master Hung go outside and you know just
They playing dice on the street outside the door and it was crazy
Fastenal
Even the customers getting gas station
I'm the owner of the larceny 6th and my name is fuzzy llama
When you have classical music
People who are young and cool don't really hang out there
So that's a way
That is selling the seven
Zendaya
Co-author of the
Research project about
Unpleasant design
Playing classical music on loudspeakers is an example of what selling a call
Unpleasant design is something that works well at deterring
Certain behaviors in certain uses
From a particular public spaces
Along with her partner Gordon the Savages
Selena collects and catalogs unpleasant designs
Unpleasant design was
Pure since we started designing puppy
6 pesos
Cities unpleasant designs are mentally start a kind of social control in public by targeting people who spend a lot
Taco Time in public spaces
Especially the Young
And the homeless
And the designs often end up pushing the so-called undesirable people out of one's face
And into another
Music is only one method
Ledford attorney
Teens from public space
In 2009 the Nottinghamshire housing Estates in England in
Pink lighting
To keep kids from congregating
Pink lights
Witchwood
Emphasized
The skin like blemishes and on teenagers
Which should
Results
In teenagers not hanging out there
That's one of my favorite
Mine too although there's not a lot of evidence that proves how
Effective it is
Pink lighting that preys on teenagers insecurities he's funny
And kind of devious if
A little far-fetched
Another more substantiated example of targeting in trying to eliminate undesirable Behavior with light
Is the presence of blue Lighting in public restroom
I saw this in UK train stations quite a bit last time I was there
Blue light up
The particular color makes
Davines
Slightly less visible
You can't see your veins Through Your Skin So it's hard to find
The target if you're an intravenous drug use
Then it became a very popular solution
Transfer all kind of publicly excessive
Toto Toilets
And even sometimes in buses
When your veins are
Not visible to you you're obviously not going to be able to
Taken herring
According to selinunte lights are one of the original forms of public social control
For example
There was a bridge in a small
Town in Bosnia specifically in the kasbah of Visa grad Bosnia
In the early 1900s
Where the Austrian government
Kind of annex
The country
At the time decided to implement Street lighting and that was very unpleasant to the
Locals in the locals with
Destroy the light
Every night
And the government
Reinstall it every morning
Intermedia that lied to something unpleasant
Work
Free
Expression in public space
Is something to be
Completely forgot
We've since become so habituated to public lighting that are primary experience
Street lights
Is that deter criminal activity and make us feel safe
Unless you're someone who laments the lack of stars in the night sky or live in an apartment with a window right next to
Premier League brake bulb
You might never View street lights as unpleasant at all
Which is one of the reasons why the unpleasant design project wants to point it out
So that it gets recognized
Isis being part
Of an overall design scheme
They can take on a much uglier manifestation
Woody's studs Miami be a few centimes
Cool but I've caused a big debate
This is from a BBC news story from 2014 the reporter Nick Beek is pointing to a set of angry
Looking spikes that were installed in the concrete
Floor of a small Alcove by the entrance to an apartment building
The spikes are clearly meant to stop people from sitting or lying
Is this a legitimate way to prevent rough sleeping and possible answer
Sexual behavior
Rob a symbol of a heartless approach
H one of the answer
That spiked a huge debate and the
Even the mayor of London reacted and said that they should be removed and that the
We should not have a dress
Let's keep on this way
The grocery chain Tesco also at its bikes to areas outside the intro
Thanks to one of its stores in central London into
They were removed after days of public protests
The way we
Treat homelessness and is that something that we just
I want to remove from apus
Space
Or is it something that we should
Summer structurally
Address
Spikes to stop people from sitting or lying down evoked a wide variety of reactions from the public
The first time I saw someone lying here
Homeless couple actually
I didn't like it
Because
Buy them
So when I saw those.
I thought good idea
A lot of people are bothered by the presence of homeless people
But some are also alarmed by just how aggressive the spikes are
It's almost
Looks harmful
You know if you lie I know what you're gonna get spiked
So it sends a message which I think is wrong
It's worth saying that these fights are not just in England
We have them in the US to
Outside of our office is a window ledge
That's where you naturally want to say and sure enough
Beverly's black metal door knob looking things
I keep anyone from rusting there
And one thing that makes me spikes and similar features especially frustrating
Is that they're just there
They're not moving
There's no arguing with
Mac have a policeman who prohibit
People from sleeping
Interpark
I think there is still some possible negotiation
And I think that's
Good that's what Society is about
The ongoing negotiation
And ongoing change
But when we start
Using things that are immutable and
Unchangeable like
Metal spikes there is nothing that is going to
How to change until they rot
I think that's the most important
Criteria
The calling some
Unpleasant
The design
It is something that you cannot
Negotiate with
We have all tried and probably failed to negotiate
With one of the most common and aggravating forms of unpleasant design
Public seating
Weather Winter Park
Or the bus stop or an airport
There are countless ways
There's have made it so you cannot get comfortable
And most especially
Cannot lie down
A classic is the bench with armrest in between
Which
Corselet to you
Rest your arm on
On the arm rest but at the same time
They restrict
Any
Other kind of use
Then sitting up
Right
The only way to spend can be used as spy
3 people sitting next to
Teach other not looking
Which is not
The only thing you
Can do it on a bench
Especially it's not the owner
Normal and legal things
Events
Cylinder things that limiting the ways something can be used
Is problematic
By attacking or addressing one
Particular problem
You actually generate Money More Problems and reduce complexity
50 year old Behavior
Public space
It's not just the biters and arm rash
Any unpleasant design book they also point out benches that are mounted so high that
Your feet can't touch
Touch the ground
And therefore they're uncomfortable
Hunter short period of time
Any document in increased prevalence
Leanings
Bus stops
You can rest against while standing but they do not accommodate
Sitting or sleeping
But the object that's so not considers the masterpiece
Unpleasant design
Is the Camden bench
Basically it is
A design Solutions
222 I think
Antisocial behavior problems
The only thing
It does not
Datura sitting
The Camden bench so named because it was commissioned by Camden London Borough Council
Is a streams
Angular
Sculpted
Solid lump of concrete
With rounded edges and slope
Unexpected place
Critikon medium named Frank Swain called at the perfect
Antibiotic
Anti sleeping because of shape makes it uncomfortable to sleep on anti drug dealing because there are no slots are crevasses in Wichita
Hydra anti-theft because the recess is near the ground allow people to store bags behind their legs and away from would be
The criminal anti skateboard because the edges on the bench fluctuating height making grinding difficult because
No services are crevasses
Or literal can accrue anti-graffiti because it has a special coating to repel paint
And all those goals are pretty noble
Except for sleeping in skateboard
I don't really want the other activities happening in public spaces I go to either
But someone that's of itsfunneh's this Litany of antimatter
Demoralizing
It discourages 22 things it encourages to
Sitting and sitting together
When we expect
People to do bad things to the bench
Before we think of
Anything good
People wouldn't might do it
To dispense
I think that's a very
Sad approach
Public space
It's also a contagious approach to public space
Is a chapter in the unpleasant design book this devoted to all the unpleasant designs used to thwart pigeons and cities
Anti pigeon spikes
Nets are everywhere
And even if your likes Elena and I wear of these measures
Skeptical of our war on pigeons
You might not have a choice in whether or not to use them
A week after we have
Publish the book
We had a confirmation of this
We didn't even notice but on the balcony doors
We actually had empty pigeon
Spikes
And then
Do to somebody hanging out on the balcony with
I don't know
Clumsy
And and they destroyed
Spikes on one side
And we
Didn't even notice that
Send me the balcony with
With pigeons
Pigeons might not be overwhelming if the population is spread throughout a city
Cody of pigeons by
Wax concentrate pigeons in the few places where there are no spies
Selena argues that's when the problem is created
And that should not be the weight
Solve any kind of
Interest conflict
/ a
Space but yes
We will immediately fix star Spike
There is always an aspect of
According to design
Design is used to get you to buy things
Use your iPhone a certain way
Sometimes without you even being aware of
And these pieces of hostile and unpleasant architecture are no
Design is something that
Is supposed to transmit a setting
Use
This object
Otherwise
It would have not been
Designed
However
I think it is very problematic when we started
People by Design
The reason we need a critical theory of unpleasant design is so we can recognize the cores in this taking place in our public space
We need to know when replacing human interaction and nuance and empathy
With hard
Physical
Non-negotiable Solutions
And this is what we wanted to
Achieve with this book
Start the debate
There will always be people who believe
Is it good weighing people
Well thank you terrible
And we have some extreme in our opinion we really The Observers
And now you're an observer 2
Whether you think a certain form of design is exclusionary but
Serve the greater good
Or just
Hostile and offensive
It's important to be aware of the decisions that are being made for
Because most likely
Unpleasant design is put there to make things more pleasant
Or someone just like you
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall Kolstad Katie mingle Avery trufelman Sharif Youssef and
Roman Mars
A bunch of the music this week came from our pal melodium your life will improve immeasurably when you buy an
Great melodium into your daily routine
It'll be like being inside a 99percentinvisible episode all the time
Find melodium on bandcamp and on abandoned building record
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again
Again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook you can follow me on Twitter at Roman Mars and on Insta
And had to be Roman Mars and the rest of the 99 Pi crew or all on Twitter and Instagram as well
Wellness Resorts around you'll find
But the best way to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world is the click around
Bobby hundreds and hundreds of cool stories
99pi.org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com