99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I once went to a small business and Tech Conference in San Francisco and among all the people hobnobbing and hoodies are
Khakis
A man emerged in full military attire
Dark green uniform with ribbons on his chest and Tiny pins are perfectly effects
Crew cut Whole Nine Yards
He was a Marine lieutenant colonel and he was by far
The most
Lewdua
Anyways we parted ways
He handed me this
Queen like that
I mean it was bigger than an inch and a half in diameter ornately decorated with the icon of the loot
Tenant kernels unit
I keep in my wallet
I felt
Incredibly honored
But I didn't know what it was or what the hell I was supposed to do with it
I also got a coin like
The Pentagon
Ask him what it was and he was like
Just something we do
I told my housemate been about my coin and he was like oh yeah I have one of those
It was my grandfather's
Your dad's been up before I came to work so we sound really sleepy
So his coin is from the hundred first airborne
Scott the
101st Airborne insignia
Choose a cup
Apple up there
Places
Vietnam World War II
On the back
Rex's rendezvous with Destiny which is there
Autoflex
Credo now
Trivet
Caillou Lego
I actually never met him
This is the only thing that I have
His
Avery and I figured out that these coins are called
Challenge coins
And they are coins
But they're not currency
And they're not quite metal
Challenge coins are something different
Everything that I say here today is my own
Personal opinion
Reflect the position of the Marine
Roger that
Carrie Fisher is not in the Marines cultural anthropologist
At Marine Corps University
She's encountered challenge coins many times throughout her career
Except for brand new
People coming in
Everybody will know that they exist
The degree to which they are used
Varies a great deal
This can depend on which military branch you serve in and your rank
But it goes further than that
There are so many different uses so many different
Kinds of things that the coins can symbolize depending on the context
Extinguisher
Looking at them or somebody is giving them
Carrie says that one of the meanings of the coins is made apparent in the act of giving or
Exchanging them
The coins are literal tokens of gratitude
Depreciation or love
Sympathy
There are powerful and tangible form of connection within an institution that is not known for being very touchy-feely
Billy can be difficult
In certain context
Express emotion especially if it's across the ranks
Band
I do think
The coins are used in that way
It's a physical symbol of
Love affection or gratitude people might be given a coin for a job well done
Because they're only so many ways to show appreciation within the military
You can't give a person a raise you can't give them a promotion
At least you can give them that symbolic
Indicator of our feelings about
What you're doing
Of course as Avery and I learned these coins are occasionally
Most of the time I would give
A coin just to say thank you for
You know helping me out
That's Chris McGrath
He's a chief petty officer in the Navy
And
Collect and trade
Challenge coins
Chris says he gives coins out to co-workers old friends anyone who does a massage
And for that reason you end up finding these coins in places where you would not expect to find any connection to the military
Do you know like millions of wimpy podcasters like us
Unicorns are way to establish relationships
Outside of the inside
Esthetician
Queens get sent out there
Physical reminder
The fact that the military is
Is there but perhaps more importantly
That it's not some
Faceless
Monolithic
Structure sitting in the Pentagon
There are human beings involved and they are human beings who can develop
A professional or personal relationship with somebody outside
The military
When I received my coin from the Pentagon tour guide
He just got of unceremoniously handed it to me
But within the military
What a sailor or Soldier or Pilot or Marine gives a coin
I don't just hand it over
There's a traditional handshake
Of course there is
You'll have shakers is used whenever someone is transferring one of the coins over and essentially you have the coin you know sitting in
In the palm of your hands and then with a coin in your palm
You firmly grasp the hand of the person you want to give the coin to
And then you flip your
Flip your hands over sweating
Chris has an amazing collection of challenge coins
Some don't look like regular coins at all
I've got one here shaped like a ninja star I've got another one
I'm shaped like a
Crown
You know this one is it shaped like a cougar
Profile view butt
The teeth are open
And you can actually use it
What is a bottle opener
The bottle opener could actually be quite practical
Because in addition to being gifts
And heirlooms and tokens of appreciation
Challenge coins are used
Two-player drinking game
If you're in possession of a coin
You can be in on the game
Jordan Haynes a veteran of the Air Force plays like this
If I was at a bar
Have the coin in my pocket and if I felt you know embolden at pull coin out of my pocket and I would
I would throw it down on the bar
Carmike tapet
And maybe holler out coincheck
Nobody's and crew members would take out their coins
We expect them to reply with their
Coin doing the same
Thanks so now you've got
All this craziness going on
Cuz people slamming the swans down and yelling out
Coincheck
And they go down a line and each person pulls out their coin hopefully what happens if somebody doesn't have the
And if they don't have the coin
Then boom
The person without their coin buys everyone a drink
But
The person who died
Is liable for round of drinks
If everybody does have their
So starting the coincheck is also a Gamble
Not all of the branches of the military are into the drinking game
I will say that I have not seen Marines initiate that kind of game
If somebody from another service
Did that with those who play the game are in It to Win It
Always
That little useless coin pocket having your jeans
That actually found a use for it and it's
For my child going to be on your toes you know I mean if you're in the shower you know
Take your coin with you
If you're out running
Whatever you're doing you carry a coin with you
You could be going right here in the studio
As far as the history of challenge coins
There's sort of an apocryphal story that traces them back to World War 1
What an American army officers
Supposedly had some special coins minted for his men
And then one of those men was captured by French soldiers
Who mistook him for a German and then he use his coin
To prove that he was in America
So the coins have also always been about identity
They do tell a story about how the union for the organization wants to be pursued
Received
What did they sing car
The most important things that they can communicate about themselves to an outside audience in it graphic form
Instant identity in the military has a lot to do with hierarchy there is also a hierarchy with challenge
As you move up through the ranks EOS
The challenge coin
Valuable
Heart attack
It's harder to get up
Cuban evil operator
Steven harder do
To get a secretary
Incredibly hard to go
Yes the president has a coin As A really lovely video of Obama giving his coin to a woman who lost
Monster brother in Afghanistan
And the military isn't the only institution to use town
Although they were the
Now some police departments make coins in
Fire departments
NASA gets coins minted
Sports teams have coins
Jimmy Buffett have a coin
That's Jordan Haynes again he's the one who told us about the drinking game
A lot of these performers you know
But they're doing a USO tour
Still have feathers
Coin with them
Return
Whoever presents the McCoy
In addition to being a collector coins
Jordan is actually in the business of making coin
He's made over three million of them
Including Jimmy Buffett
I am the founder and CEO of
Coinforce.com
Coinforce is one of the private men's that designs and manufactures challenge coins
I'm holding a
Coin that I
I brought with me
Studio
A diamond shaped
Coin
That we made for astronaut Lindgren
It's got his name on it
Translucent
It's like
Just super
Oh my God we do also
You don't have to be a president or an astronaut or Jimmy Buffett you too can have a coin you can design your own and then
Just go online and order it
It's basically with the military.
Most of the time a unit gets together and talks about what they want on their coin and then gathers the money for it
Themselves
So we're not using tax
It's all by our own for our own
Phone so we are swear fundraising internally or we're doing car washes
Because coins are not in the budget there's no set procedure for making
And no rules
Which means the design process
This is very informal
Nine times out of ten in the Navy
Someone take that sketch
And they
Use clipart put into PowerPoint
And then send it off to
Manufacture PowerPoint
Microsoft
PowerPoint
PowerPoint is installed on every government computer and it
Mosquito for us
It's free and then Jordan at coinforce
Or whoever the manufacturer
Will take that Mark up and finish
Final design
Unreal professional-grade software
A design studio does not use power
Point
To design a challenge
Oh that's a relief
The individual coins take on a whole new meaning when a bunch are displayed together
And a lot of military folks make a labret displays or even custom furniture
Sure to show off their collection
Of course some displays are much simpler
In Clinton's presidential portrait he's posing in front of his collection of challenge coins and there in a simple way
Wouldn't display but these coin displays are not
Like a flashy show of achievement at all
It becomes less a display of
Look at me in more a display of
A lot of long quiet hard work over the course of decades
The coin show all the professional and personal relationships established over the course of a career
So if you're in the Army and I'm coins from the Air Force in your collection
It shows that you've collaborated across military branches which can be really hard to do
The coins are physical proof of hard-fought relationships
Tumi
The coins are full of interesting contradiction
Their combination of
Gravitas in Tradition
With levity enjoy
Like my friend then if you wanted to go take that heirloom of his grandfather's time and World War II and Vietnam
Win a beer with it
The same coin
Contradictions that you find all over
Military life
The world is regulated and rigorous
Is that of the United States military
The coins of this
Fluid quality about them
Are different coincheck rules for different branches
Coins you some popularity various
The history doesn't have a set telling
The design doesn't have
Set rules
There is
Obviously a very
Aspect
To the military but
Challenge coins and a lot of other
Things that are routine parts of daily military life
Mitigate that structure
Challenge coins are a reminder of the human elements of the massive US military
A reminder that some servicemen constantly carry
I've been coin checked at the airport
Quite check at trade shows I've been coincheck
Everywhere
Now my now my home is off limits
Don't be like crawling up my balcony at 3 a.m. to do a coin check on me on my property
But you catch me outside of my property then you know game on
There's no way I'm climbing up on that dude's balcony at 3 a.m.
99% invisible West produced this week by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Ben glass for waking up so early
We are project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
An architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
MPI fade
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a new Wii
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you a long for the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Now before we go
This is not an advertisement I just want to tell you about something I wasn't Radiolab I've been making her last few months
It's a very cool experiment and if you happen to be in Austin your head there for a South by Southwest her if you live there
You should check it out
Radiolab is made up story
That you can only hear
The GPS triggered audio iPhone app called detour
The reason I specifically wanted to mention it is because a few weeks back
Avery to the story about Austin tower
And one of the story is that
Hans the origin of the towers
Is the legend of the servant-girl annihilator
And that's a lot of what Radiolab saucin stories about
The writer O'Henry was living in Austin back then in 1885
He wrote this one letter I'll never
Forget
He said
Town is fearfully doll
Except for the frequent raids of the servant-girl annihilator
Make things alive
Play
During the Dead
The murders all happened during this big moment of change in Austin's history and it really showed Austin
When the servant-girl annihilator showed up in Austin we never heard of us
Serial killer
Nobody
This was way back
Before Jeffrey Dahmer
For Son of Sam even before Jack the Ripper
So if you want this totally immersive
GPS triggered guided prequel
To the Moonlight our story
Radiolab
Has done it
I'm going on a tour with Radiolab literally the best thing you can do in Austin during South by Southwest
I've been there many times
So I just thought
But if you're already there are you going to be there for the conference
Download The Detour app
And load the door that's called the year that broke Austin
Totally free and you're totally going to dig it
We are a member of radiotopia from the RX if you subscribe to all the shows and radiotopia to me at Roman Mars
And say
Imma radiotopia
Caffe Starrett
I don't praise your good taste
You can subscribe to the mall and radiotopia. FM
You want to see pictures of challenge going to beat you got a lot of them at 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com