99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
With our Golden State Warriors in the playoffs we thought we'd rebroadcast
This piece about the design of basketball
So will give you nerd something to say when everyone is talking about playoff
It's one of my favorite episodes
Hope you enjoy
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Tomorrow night 15000 curing time for pike Madison Square Garden in New York City the witness
You're not cheering crowd sitting in row C seat 11
Will be a mother
77 year old man
He made possible the game
Miguel going to meet him now
That tape is from an old New York radio show called We the People
The guest is James Naismith
125 years ago in 1891 Naismith was a PE instructor at a small College in Springfield
Field Massachusetts
When a particularly bad snowstorm straw
4 days the students couldn't go Outdoors
Show the began roughhousing in the hall
We tried everything to keep them quiet
Something had to be done
One day I had an idea
Call the boys to the gym
Divided them up into teams of 9
And gave him a new soccer ball
I showed them to Peach basket side nailed up at each end of the gym
I told them the idea
What's the threw the ball into the opposing team's Peach Pass
Sports don't have such a definitive point of origin
But this one does
I blew a whistle
The first game of basketball begin
That day in 1891
James Naismith
Invented basketball
And what rules did you have for your new game
Indoctrination
Well I didn't have enough
That's where I made my big mistake
The boys begins Tech
Kicking and punching in the country
They ended up in a free-for-all in the middle of the gym floor
In subsequent weeks Naismith would go on to make more rules for the game
Some of those are still around today
Like the one that says players can't run while holding the ball
They have to dribble it
The temperature rule but a design decision that he made back in 1891
That continues to define the way the game is played
He had to decide how high to hang the peach basket
That's Cari Champion she's an anchor at ESPN and host of the be honest podcast and she's going to help us
Large toy today
Naismith chose to hang the peach basket at 10 feet above the porch floor
There was a running track that went around the court at that level
But otherwise the decision was pretty random
And just a little higher or a little lower
And everything would be different
That arbitrary decision
To put the basket at 10 ft
Cause the game of basketball to take shape around the tallest player
But it happened gradually
In fact in the beginning the game was played by shorter less imposing
In the very early days of the game
People didn't really have a conception of height having really
Any importance of
Mets writer and journalist Andrew Heiser
So a lot of the other high scores in the very early days
Guys who like sex
But all it was not until
A few decades in
That
Team started
Recruiting really tall guys
Accident at the time they were sort of refer to often as
Goon
Nowadays if you play a little rough or dirty you might be called a goon
Back then big men were sometimes called goons just because they were big
The first so-called going to have a major impact on the game was a big white dude named George Mikan who played for the Mini Apple
Who is Lakers from 1948
He was a 6-foot 10 monster who wore big round spectacles when he play
Notice the comparative size of referee Ackman
Miken towered over his opponents
Ambrose scoring records with his strength inaccurate
Mike and with such a force they actually had to change some rules in the game to offset his advantage
For example the rule against goaltending came about because it might
Goaltending is the act of catching or
Batting away another player shot as the ball is on a downward path for the basket
Mike and was so tall he could just stand under the basket and SWAT away Shots by the other team
Goaltending was banned in 1945
But rule changes didn't stop George Mikan or his fellow big man from dominating defensively and offense
You start seeing people saying like it's too easy to score like they actually were really swerve disgusted they thought this should be a Triumph
Have to get the ball in the hoop not something that happens a hundred sometimes
The ease with which these super-tall players could put the ball in the basket was
Alarming people
The traditionalist didn't like the way the game was going
But they had no
Idea
What was about to hit them
Bad dog
Sometimes called the slam dunk
The first one in organized game happened in 1936
Donkey didn't really get going in basketball until the 1960s
Man the traditionalist
They hated the dunk
But not just because it was a new unconventional way to put the ball in the basket
The dump became political
The chi year
Is 1966
My name is Matt Andrews I teach American history of UNC Chapel Hill and I have a particular Focus
Tucson Sport and Society
So it was in 1960s
In the NCAA champions
Game Texas Western
With an all-black starting five
Easily defeat 8 off for UPS all white
University of
Kentucky team
This win by Texas Western against Kentucky was a big deal in the college basketball world
Kentucky was one of the last major college teams in the country
It still didn't have any black players
The coach of Kentucky with a guy named Adolph Rupp
Mini View dim as a racer
According to the sports correspondent Frank Deford who is in the Kentucky locker room that night
The language rap use against the Texas Western players
Send a chill
Down his spine
And there was this moment
Right at the beginning of the game
We're Texas Western David Lattin gets the ball and makes a move toward the hoop
The defender in front of him is Pat Riley
He go on to win nine NBA titles as a player coach and executive
And Latin flies over him
While he's like 6 foot 4 stockley belt
And Latin just rises above him and slams The Ball
Texas's Victory and Latins dunk were seen as direct challenges
Stuby establishment
After all this was 1966
There was a lot going on in America
Black Panthers have become invisible force
In Oakland the Panthers had armed and organized themselves
Protect their communities from brutal racist police
How many white Americans were worried
A Revolution was about to take place
Black Power
Was this new evocative free
So that the failure to pass the Civil Rights bill isn't because of black power isn't because of the student
What's so interesting about this phrase is it
Lack of specificity no one is exactly sure what black power mean
Into this context comes the duck
Everything seems to be black power manifest on the basketball
The dunk
Is
Physical the dunk is
Forceful you know when you lay the ball in your laying the ball in but when you dunk you're doing it to
Someone and at a time when so many white Americans
AR
Uneasy with the Specter of black
Violence
The dunk
Becomes
Suspect
Then to scare people like a tall frap even more comes a player called Lew Alcindor
He would later changed his name to Kareem Abdul-Jabbar and become one of the most exciting and famous players in the history of the game
But in 1967 he was a young man
7 ft
2 inches tall
And already tearing up the college game with his vicious dunks in fast movement
Alcindor surrounded by white shirt
Unstoppable
So the NCAA Betsy National Collegiate Athletic Association made a decision
The only way to stop this guy with to get rid of the thing he did best
The slam dunk
In 1967
They banned the dunk
And for 10 years
There's no dunking in college basketball
Lew Alcindor AKA Kareem Abdul-Jabbar
Was not happy about this
In fact he explicitly said that the only reason for the band was because they were scared that black guys like him we're going to take over
For the game although he was much stronger word
Regardless
The slam dunk was done
In college basketball with sent back in time
For 10 years
Basketball was in a bad place
The NCAA administrators had made in
Arguably racist decision to ban the slam dunk
Meanwhile in the professional League the NBA
Players can still dunk but fans were losing interest
Here's Andrew heysel again
This is
For the NBA
Considered like
The low point of the
The NCAA administrators had made an arguably racist decision to ban the slam dunk
Meanwhile in the professional League the NBA
Players can still dunk but fans were losing interest
Here's Andrew heysel again
This is
For the NBA
Considered like the
Low point
Of the week
They're all of these pieces written about how
The game is dying and nobody wants to watch and there's all these
Questions about why
Naismith original accidental design decision to put the basket at 10 ft
I didn't Brittany given us this beautiful and exciting slam dunk
But it also caused the professional game to revolve too much around these super tall player
The game you got jammed up around the net
People weren't passing as much
They just hand the ball to the giant guy and he'd stand under the basket
Trying to put it in
This had the effect of slowing down the play
And that slowness was draining the game of its
Excitement basketball needed a design solution
People suggested a lot of fixes
No backbone
Contacts backup
A smaller basket a bigger ball
A smaller ball
I know scoring Zone around the basket
And even a hike app
Another group of coaches called for the hoop to be raised to 12 ft
None of those changes caught on
And then
This guy comes along
We feel that those people who are not
Under contractual obligation to
Would you like to take a look
To remember George Mike the original NBA goon 6 foot 10 inches tall with
Big round specs
Will in 1967 he was working as a travel agent in Minnesota where he used to play
When you get to call from a couple of guys asking if you want to head up a new professional basketball league that would compete with the end
NBA NBA friends have to say about his new job
Good luck
I mean it really was just sort of making up that you go on
It was
Simply let's get an idea
And let's see what we can do here
That's Terry Pluto who wrote a book about the founding of this new league
They called it the ABS
The American Basketball Association
And George Mikan became its first commissioner
They were trying everything to get fans re-engaged in a game
Sometimes they featured Cow Milking contest for entertainment
And 1/2 time show in Indiana
About the wrestling bear called Victor
Beautiful Brown
Bear looks to be
That he weighs at least five
Most of their ideas didn't stack
A lot of times good ideas are like that they're one of 12 things at
People stuck to the wall in and out of the 12-1 became really good
One helped a little bit in the other tenor almost embarrassing
In this case one of the ideas was really good
In fact it's the design solution that arguably saved basketball
In the secret star of the story that were telling right now
The three-point
Shot
So all you sports fans know this
Smithfield we're all worth 2 point
But the aviators innovation
Which they actually borrowed from an earlier defense wig
What's the draw an arch line
About 22 feet away from basket
In any shot made from behind that a lot
Was now worth
Replay
The ABA was trying to please the fan
Fans get excited when they see a 3-pointer
But they can also go and practice the shot at home
It's more egalitarian Ramona Shelburne senior writer for espn.com
If I practice hard enough
Don't have to be the most athletic guy in the core
I don't have to be
An incredible dunker it's it's something that when fans watch it they think I can do that too
In 1976 the NBA merged with the ABA and three years later they brought in the three-point shot
At first it was about pleasing the fans
But they slowly came to realize something about the three-point shot
When you study if you shoot
35% on 3-pointers
And you shoot
45% on 2.0
Just break it down
It makes so much more sense to
Build a team around 3-point shooting because
You're going to score more points in the point of the game
And now some teams have decided that the way to win
Is the concentrate
Country boy shot
When NBA first introduce the 3-point shot
Games featured
Only a couple of 3 point attempts
This season
It's more than ten times that
And if there's any team that's demonstrating the value of the 3 point shot right now
Is the Golden State Warriors from California
And Mister Steph Curry
Hurry
If you don't know who Steph Curry as he's about six foot three so he's short by NBA standards but this hasn't stopped him from being the
Star of the team end of the whole NBA
I think every kid growing up in American I was trying to be Seth Curry
He is
Skinny and
Doesn't seem to have anything physically dominant about him
And yet when you watch him play He's Alive
Curry can hit 3-pointers for Golden State
From really anywhere Eli
Text which makes it hard to defend against them and balances the influence of the big men
Because of their guys like her who can score from
Anywhere
In the 7-foot guys have to move away from the basket
Weather most useful
Could have been
And once you allow players to score an extra point
From shooting further out the game
Spreads out
You got a whole new game
The game has changed for the better
Is no doubt about it
That's former Indiana Pacer Jerry Harkness
Harkness was a player in the NBA and the ABA
Because the game is exciting
The game is running shoe
Quickness
Defense
Opening the game up
Making it more aggressive
But even though the three point shot has had a balancing influence
Some traditionalists
Still don't like it
Eagles basketball
You're like a circus sort of thing when we were five points.
7 point shot
You know what is it stop doing that sort of thing. Just old school that San Antonio Spurs coach Gregg Popovich
Speaking to ESPN about Steph Curry's Golden State Warriors last year
What Popovich is saying kind of Echoes what people said about the dump 50 years ago
That it's a trick
A departure from the fundamentals of basketball
And I kind of agree with Coach pop
But even Popovich seems to think that the 3-point shot is here to stay
Do certain degree you better Embrace are you going to lose and every time we want to Championship 3-point shot was a big part of it
Instead of Designing the beautiful powerful dunk out of the game we designed a counterbalance
The 3 point shot
And now the game is more inclusive than it's ever been
You got these little guys I can shoot bombs from anywhere on the court
And there's still room for the big guys close in
The three-pointer and the dunk
And become the yin and yang
A basketball
All of this has sort of been by axe
The 10-foot tall basket to dunk
The 3 point shot
But then again the game wasn't
Carefully designed in the first place
Really it came about because all James Naismith wanted
What's to stop some rowdy kids
I'm getting into too much trouble
And the whole thing
Started with a couple of peach baskets I put up in The Little Gym
48 years ago
I guess it just goes to show
What you can do if you have
Yep
Nope
Did it happen in one day
Never know what kind of
Yep
The Houston Rockets actually broke the Golden State Warriors record for most threes in a season this year
But the Warriors
Your sled by Steph Curry are still dominating the NBA from Beyond the three-point Arc
In game 2 of the 2017 NBA finals
Golden State set a new record for the most three-pointers
In a final game
This episode was a collaboration with our friends at ESPN is part of a podcast miniseries they produced called donkey
Collection of stories all related to basketball slam dunk
It ran last year
Still available on ESPN mobile app iTunes or wherever you get your pie
Joe Sykes reported and produce the story for us and for ESPN with help from Ryan and tell
Emma Morgenstern
Joe Fuentes in Kevin Wiles
So thanks to Jody avirgan for Okinawa
Also check out carry Champions podcast beyond us where she has candid conversations with some of the biggest names in sports music
Entertainment
This piece was inspired by a vice article by Andrew heizel of a link to it on our website
Play 99percentinvisible teen senior producer Katie mingle did the heavy lifting on this one with a breach of them in Delaney Hall
Fitzgerald Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
Percocet is the digital director and Taryn Mazza is the off
We are probably going 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
If you want to learn about another little game design Innovation that save the game of basketball
Look for episode number 77 of this program is called game changer
About the shot clock
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
But it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Confine 99percentinvisible and join sessions about the show on Facebook you can to me at Roman Mars in the show at 9
99pi org
One Instagram Tumblr and meta 2
But the Nexus of all things 99p I exact
99 pi
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com