99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers
Stop auto insurance
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for
And how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Weather.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right
Nighttime and connecting with us
When your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
I love you too
Target your customers were their engaging every day when they're ready to make
Make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn
You have the opportunity to build long-term relationship
Sex with your customer
Those relationships often turn into
High quality leads
Check traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help
Target your customers
Decision
Down to the job title
Company name
And Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a mess
What they care about
Which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Open LinkedIn.
Dot-com invisible
A free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Everyday workers at grocery stores and convenience
First thing I do when I come on in Isaac go check the rotation on my milk past check my days of
Of course in Carson
Is dairy manager at a grocery store in Montana and every day when he gets in
Check the sell-by date on his milk
If it's past the date
Milk must be thrown out
These are all Twenties that I'm pulling off
This one is dated the 18th and I will have to pour this went down the drain I have probably six
Ken is originally from Washington State where he also worked in the grocery business
When I came here for years ago I had no idea that they were pouring down as much milk down the drain
They have been in fact it was repulsive his sickening the first couple weeks here I was
Hundreds of gallons
There's nothing wrong with it
Bring out milk happens to some extent in grocery stores all over the country
That's reporter Meredith
Hannah. Montana throws much more of it down the drain than most places
Because the sell-by date on the milk is required by state law to be just 12 Days After pastor
Translation
The industry standard is 21 days
After these 12 days
Montana Law requires that the milk be thrown away
It can't be sold
Or donate it
Seem such a waste
Family Zoo
Journeyed
And we're doing this
Montana is throwing out so much milk affect the price of milk there is about $2 per gallon higher than it is in Surrey
Surrounding states
And it's all because of the state label
In theory Montana strict State label law is about food safety
And protecting the consumer
But it hasn't been updated since the 80s
Date labels of course aren't just on milk they're on a lot of Prada
Use by
Sell-by best-by best if used by
But then out some products expires on or like having aex
P witch
Is it shorthand for expires this is Emily broadleaf director of the food Law & policy clinic at
Harvard Law School
She did a tally of all the different kinds of date labeling what we found was that 41 States
Required a date label on at least some food product she says they're huge inconsistencies not Justa
In the wording
But in the meaning of these labels
Some states require them only on Dairy
Salmon shellfish
Summon any perishable foods
And then 20 of those States actually restrict the sale or donation of food after the date
Some of them are quite strict some of them I flat-out band salary donation of food after the date
And some of them just say we're going to make it complicated
The powers-that-be have definitely succeeded in making a complex
Did to decipher these
Or to know how to act on them
For large retailers and individual consumers
Like this is
A bad system it's not making people safer it's leading to food waste and the dates really aren't safety
Debased
That's right
The date labels on our food are not about food safety
And
They were never actually meant to be
But let's back up
It All Began in the 1970s
Americans have moved farther away from their food sources
They were eating more packaged food and getting more of their food in supermarkets
And they wanted a way to measure how fresh their food was
Most manufacturers already put encrypted dates on their products to help retailers rotate stock
And consumers craved access to this information
In 1977 the New York State consumer protection board published a booklet called blind date
How to break the codes of the foods you buy
The booklet told consumers how to decipher the encrypted date codes on their favorite products
Deboer distributed more than 10000 copies and posted the booklet in supermarkets
Eventually
Consumers started to demand that these dates be put clearly on packages
But they shouldn't have to get a special book
Decipher a code
And that seems pretty reasonable
Cuz you're not ask for at 8 labels
So retailers in grocery stores responded but at that time everyone acknowledged this is really about quality in about fresh
No one's that I want a label because I'm afraid it won't be safe so a few states begin to regulate these date labels
Massachusetts was the first state that actually required date labels on food
Even though there were a number of attempts
And one Congress I think from 1973 to 75 there were 10 bills on date labeling standardization
None of them pass
Lawmakers disagreed about what the system should look like and who should oversee it
The Food and Drug Administration is actually said
We could do that as we know we have the power to do it for the foods we oversee but since these labels were about freshness and
I'm not about safety
Ultimately the FDA said
It's not something we want to spend the time and energy on
Still consumers wanted freshness date so all kinds of different ones popped up
Summer stamped on some printed on the label
There's no consistency and how this information was displayed
Or the language that was used
Used by all viabestbuy
Buy tires on
Some companies even tried to promote these dates to sell their products like
Hey by Pepsi because it's going to give you the date to tell you what's fresher than all the other soft drinks
Don't need to tell you how fresh they are diet colas
Hyundai Pepsi introduces
Some date labels were meant for consumers While others were just meant for retail
Taylors
And as is still true now there were no clear definitions for any of the phrases
No consistency even within the same brand or product
Dates could differ from state to state
Manufacturer to manufacturer or store to store
And over the years we've lost track of what these labels meant in the first place
Grabs just being used to having labels on their food no one
No one's ever said to them what they mean and what they don't
So we've made some false connections to people in their head of met this link and thought well I heard about
But someone getting salmonella or E coli
And I see this label on my food and these two things are somehow connected to one another
But Emily says as much as we might want them to
These dates are not going to tell us if our food will make us sick
People keep saying but I just want to know when it will be safe until
It's scientifically impossible to sort of say there's a date after which it will become unsafe
Example
If you run a few errands on a hot day before getting your milk home
Your milk will spoil faster
And once it's in the fridge it'll last longer it's a 35 degrees than at 40 degrees
There's just too many variables
But here's the thing about spoiled milk
Spoiled milk doesn't mean it has pathogens in it
Json process along with most other bacteria
The big misconception around 8 label
Is that people think that old food will make them sick
But for the most part all food doesn't make you sick
Contaminated
Food does
The longer a carton of milk exists the more teams that has to come into contact with contaminants that could grow and flourish
Inside that milk and hurt you as long as it's properly pasteurized about the age specifically that makes
Dangerous to drink
There is however a small handful of food
Can become unsafe with age
Deli meats unpasteurized cheeses smoked Seafood
Stuff in the deli section of the grocery store basically
These foods have a high risk for Listeria
A bacteria that can be life-threatening
And in these cases listeria risk
Does increase with time
But I current date labeling system doesn't treat this small subset of foods
Any differently than any other date labeled item
Mo State labels are arrived at by conducting taste test
They hit people around a table and then they have everyone eat their product
Say It's Your Birthday
They taste a batch made that day
And then they taste some from the day before
And the day before that and what did you think was it good that was a tasty did it have the properties you expect for
From yogurt or whatever the product is when the manufacturer comes to a badge the people say
I don't really like the way this taste
They said okay well by for that many days are products not going to be at
And that's where the date really comes from
Companies
They just got
They said you're not so awful about it but we don't have money to bring in and do this whole
Taste test we just
You know we look online for an estimate of what this few know how long this will be fresh or we just kind of
You know I only keep it in my refrigerator for 3 days I'll put 3 days on it
There's some of them are very unscientific about where that date actually comes from
And yet today
According to a report that Emily Bradley co-authored
Majority of consumers believe
But eating food past
Its sell-by or use-by date is rift
Their health
And as many as 90% of Americans throw out food based on date labels
At least occasionally
Billions of pounds of food here in America simply because of misunderstanding lascaux dates
Former president of Trader Joe's
He's been in the grocery business for more than 40 years
In 2015 he founded daily table
Non-profit retail store that
That sells pre-made meals
Source from food that would otherwise be wasted
We waste staggering amount of food
The average American waist summer between 20 and 25% of the food they choir
Just wasting the food is wasting the water to grow at the transportation to get to supermarket everything that goes in the ghetto
Getting food to your place
Doug and Emily both say
But to make date label service better
And to waste less food
We need to consider the language were using
Sell-by use-by enjoy by like what does that mean you know
And idea of an expiration date
Is problematic to
For some reason expired it's dead
Do credit cards expire the dead can't use it
Heaven forbid your dog expired you know
Justin Moore like no one's an expired food
Eating dead food
I actually prefer most of my food that is this
When food is perceived as an edible
You can't do anything with it nobody wants to eat at any can't give it to a food pantry
States have laws that forbid the donation of so-called expired food
Emily suggests only using the term
Aspired
4 foods that actually do become unsafe
Is unpasteurized cheeses
Send deli meats
For everything else
She would go with best if used by
Today would be to labels
Expires on and best if used by
And this would be a standardized system used all across
The country
Creating standardized easy-to-understand date labels is a design problem that must have a design solution
Maybe Emily suggested labels or maybe something else entirely the fix doesn't seem like it should be that hard
And yet
Most of the time when we say this is an issue needs to change people say I agree it's a terrible issue
But then people really got stuck up on what which phrase should we use and
How do we decide which foods have which one
70 different this time is now a part of a national conversation
The EPA and USDA announced a goal to cut food waste in the US and half by 2030
And having a better date labeling system is one way to get there
But for now
Emily is happy to help settle your more micro-level disputes
Basically
The answer is
Trust your taste
Not the date
To the story that I heard most
From friends and family from colleagues and I continue to hear now is that you know there's someone that I'm so glad you
Put this report out because I've been telling my wife for years of the days don't matter now I'm really Vindicated or universe
Vice versa
Instead of arguing over date labels you should take part in that other which will that happens between spouses in the refrigerator
Will you open up a dodgy carton of something rather and ask
The smell okay to you
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Meredith hoddinott and Kate
Greenspan Kurt Kolstad and me Roman Mars
Batavia word at the beginning of the story with the Montana grocer was collected by the Harvard food Law & policy Clinic
And racing horse productions for a short film they produced about day labels special thanks to Rebecca Richman Cohen and
Nathaniel Hansen
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin and architecture and in
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs
Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
Time in rio
2 analects
All hearing
Add voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the
Human and adding and somebody
Apple sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
We're presenting to
Special episode
Those from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Power
Takes a look at the story behind
A different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 launches
Between episode 1
Take you inside
The love Israel family cult
Episode about uncovering the
Scrolled in a newly discovered star
Love letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted
A family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get
Podcast
And find out why they say
Every house
House is haunted
We need to talk about
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is fresh
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back
Again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time
Sea Cow
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God
. info
Podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
Before we go I want to tell you about
About the body G
Series from Bellow radio TV show
The truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That wines
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous act
Jack'd playsuit
Superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or
Psychopath
Or put on for
50 lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get
Huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead
In my Prime
Private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech way
Weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to
Clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley
And I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth
Dot-com