99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage you're looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Reconnecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn opportunity to build long-term relationships with their cousin
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name in India
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible fear free $100 at
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I grew up mainly in Ohio
And in the 80s
I only knew about New York City from the movies
And all the movies every single one of them had this one establishing shot at said
Audience
We are in New York City
It was a graffiti-covered Subway
All beautiful
For me it Suburban kid from Ohio that graffiti was exciting
But it didn't seem
Artistic or complicated it was just
Scary hooliganism
Too bad you can't think
The graffiti was a total mystery to me too
Preacher and hepperman grew up in Nebraska also far far from New York City
It was like Technicolor hieroglyphics
You doing the Bowie MD
Oh he's doing it
Back and front
All of these intersecting lines and colors I mean I knew that they were letters I just never knew what they said
New York was another planet
And graffiti was its language
Is only 26 letters of the alphabet
But somehow
Graffiti Writers manipulated
And it make it theirs
Strange looks so cool on the outside
But the inside was a whole other story you would not have gotten on that sub
The place where
Sophie
The train smell
They were dirty the floor is stuck to the floor
And
You got stuck in the tunnel
In the car is filled up with smoke
And I mean it was
Scary place
The beat
In the 1970s and 80s says this guy David gun
The New York City subway was like
Some kind of
Don t and hellscape
Fire in Bloodshed and gangs
There is definitely a sense that you know this is Subway's work
Totally controlled by wild gangs of teenagers
No you Boppers out there know that amongst the Gang
Who are the Rogues
The Gramercy riffs
Everyone's favorite the baseball Furies
Of course
The Warriors
I want everybody to know the warriors were
Artist Caleb neelon Wheels Amin spray-can himself
But even he admits
Graffiti was
Simply just a symbol that
The city of Lost
Control and
It was a symbol that
Who knew what the future lay
What cities
It could be terrible
And nothing pisses people off more than writing I can't read
So starting in the early 70s the mayors of New York City to eradicate graffiti
First
Mayor John Lindsay
He took office it really like one of the worst times for any New York mayor Lindsay forms of first anti-graffiti test
Task force
And he turned graffiti from a nuisance
Took it out of the category of
Lettering or something like that into a crime interview
You know what a misdemeanor
But subway graffiti persistence
It was the problem that wouldn't go away
For two decades the Metropolitan Transportation Authority also known as the MTA
Failed miserably trying to fix its graffiti problem
Sometimes laughably
I could time they decided to repaint 7000 subway cars
All white
They called it
The Great White Fleet
Oddly what the graffiti movement needed at that time was new real estate
Before you knew it
Tire
Subway car
Car covered in spray paint
There was Ed Koch's Berlin Wall method
Conscionable. Defenses in the yard
Plus
Attack dogs
Here's maricon
But I said
Go to fences and have
The dog run between the two fences and that will keep people out and protect the dog from stepping on the third rail
And the responsible as well maybe some of the climb over the fence
And the dog will bite them I said what I thought that's what the dog was for
In the razor wire top defenses and the German Shepherds worked
Realize that they could distract the dogs with food and cut through the fences
Desperate people take Desperate Measures
And the transit officials were desperate
No one knew what to do
Hello David Gunn
David Gunn
And I was
President of the New York City Transit Authority for 6 years
David Gunn
Would you write up in front of subways in Boston Philly DC
In Toronto
He headed up Amtrak for awhile to
He seemed Invincible New York City in 1984
Reaction was no
Because it was
Just looked to be a hoax
Situacion actual words were suicide mission
But then his mother stepped in
At that point she was in her eighties
She said
You better take that or you'll see everybody will think you're a coward
You got love Mom
Hit the ground running with something he called the queen train program
I cleaned up the cars
Yeah we did we got the car is clean but we also
The clean train became sort of
Symbolic of the fact
The thing work
And here's the difference between you and me and David gun
When we see graffiti
We think about it in terms of Aesthetics
Like it or hate it but we're reacting to it visually
David Dunn
Looks right past all of those wildstyle letters and sees a transit system not doing its job
Easy graffiti you got bad name
Because
Having equipment clean
Is part of maintenance
For decades people in charge treated subway graffiti like it was a sanitation problem
Gun says that all wrong
It wasn't just a sanitation problem
It was something else entirely
Gun says the root of the problem was MTA deferred maintenance program
New York City was broke
And the City
A big chunk of the transit authority operating budget
To reduce its budget
The worst decision
They cut back on the things that kept the Subways running
Routine inspections
Replacing Parts even Subway mechanics
And what you expect to happen happened
The subway deteriorated
Breakdowns tripled
Nearly every two weeks
And get this
In 1981
There were 1800 subway car fires
When there's 1800
Suicide mission
Billy took it on
First he hired 1500 non-union managers and increase repair staff
He rebuilt
Thousands of cars
Can you control cases rebuilt trucks New Motors air compressors motor alternators
The whole nine yards
Here's the thing about maintenance
It's not sexy it takes years to see improvements
People needed something now
Or in this case not see something
My Approach
Was to drive the bastards out
And to clean up the mess it made
And fix the
Equipment
And we gradually drove the little bastard
Estrogen to a corner
My little bastards if it's not obvious
Gun net
Everyone vandalizing the trains
He figured out a way to do it systemically line by line
Again that's artist Caleb neelon
Like the a line or the one line or the two line
Off the map for the for Graffiti Writers while they're fixing it they didn't allow any graffiti on it
And a graffiti artist
Bob the Train car
Bombed in this case means covering the outside of the train with graffiti
If an artist manage that
Bmth
Hold it from the system
Even during rush hour
It was tough going
One day I ended up pulling
500 cars how to service
And it worked
If people knew it
Because they could see it
Ghana Chief The Impossible
He got rid of graffiti on New York City subways
There is even an official date
May 12th
People
Remember
Ve and VJ Day
Generation moment for the people who ran the subway system
What time when they were declaring victory
The transit authority held at ceremony that day
It was up at
77th Street shop
All of the MTA employees were there
Premier Ed Koch was there too
Privately I get it in love
The fact that I bet it never thought it's you that day
He said I was right
Commemorative t-shirts
They were red
And I hit the
Stay at the old New York City Transit Authority logo on them
Down below at hip
Graffiti free in
Date
It's fun to ride the subway and imagined that there ever was so much graffiti
I mean I've lived in New York for almost 10 years now and no graffiti-covered Subway has ever pulled
I was wondering
Where did the Cassini go
I thought the answer might be more complex
But this time for once the answer is simple
You can point to a man
David Gunn
David Gunn Twitter
A lot of New Yorkers was this
Need a white knight coming into to fix the subway system and you know to be writers who is this
Darth Vader character
Ultimately was better at taking away their fun
Then they were at sustaining it
May 12th 1989
Bidet subway graffiti died
The story's not over
Graffiti didn't actually in that day
There's still subway graffiti but because of David guns clean training program
It's almost become a
Possible for us on the outside too
To see it almost never leaves the train yards
MTA Cruiser on patrol their constantly looking for graffiti and hosing it off with these
Crazy solvent that they see any
And they see it
An international gallery of it in fact
So the kid from Munich would go paint Subways in
Paris kitten
You know Paris would go pay Subways in Amsterdam today or kind of like stamp collectors
Heading to balance tube on the Paris Metro and the London Tube to put into their album
Collections are judged by two things
Size
And value
The subway graffiti completist would have to hit 190 systems
54 countries
And as for value
There's only one that matters
There's a real way of thinking
Kane graffiti which I don't think it's entirely wrong with that
You're not a real writer until you got here or
Peace on the New York subway
Kind of like the Holy Grail of all trains yunnan
Right now spray painting a New York subway car is a felony
If teachers get caught it could mean jail time and thousands of dollars in fines
Graffiti artist have to ask themselves
Is this worth it
I'm pretty nervous talking on the phone right now even about it because
Nina
It's not really something that
People are crazy
Very nice
Thank you for doing that
This is Joe
Or at least that's what he wanted me to call him
Joe is a graffiti artist
From South Africa
It's trains and countries around the world
Didn't want to say if he was going to hit New York
EEG headset
We disorder Jose boys to protect his identity
That's the only way that you would agree to talk to us
Just never been caught
But it's been closed
I've loved
Seeing a flashlight
Turned around to tell the guy that someone
Is coming for us
And when I turned around he's already like
Running
We we actually
Caught a couple of guys from Australia just last week
School trying to breach of security and go into a yard
And now Vincent demarino
He's the vice president of security for the MTA and New York City Transit
He sees guys from all over the world in New York train yards
Demarino didn't have hard numbers of who gets caught from where in the yard
But when a train gets hit in New York
The graffiti artist is more likely to be from say
Spain or France
Not from New York
Someone put the ratio at something like a D20
The international folks
It cost a lot of money to do
If I was to get on a plane I'd go somewhere and sit on the beach
I wouldn't buy an airplane ticket to go commit a crime in a train yard
Graffiti artists that's part of the draw
It's a rush to break the law
Now I want to get over this
Fence Potter that that's exciting at first when you go inside to
The yard in East on the floor not on the platform and you see how big is
This train ready is I me when you're on the platform and train the train when you're on the
Floor next to it outside
At 11
Smile and the sound is so much more intense because you already likes
Novice
Look what's coming at you what is it
There's not much that could beat that
Feeling
Better than sex
That's like better than money better than
Set back that's why people do it that's why someone address
What colors on a train
I seen as Europeans going it
Somebody why New York
Do you think doing it like this way it's from this way was built that like
I see no but let me bring the trains back
This is beauty
I spell it c e t e
And then I have a 2 letter c t
The same thing between trains
If you don't get it
CT tells me he always feels like an old soul
I call in a romantic
I seen it on the trains and
Icing Subway online
Damn I missed
Time
City bombed not one but two trains the
The first was the R Train
It was a Spy vs Spy theme
I think about 11 cans in an hour to paint
But days and days
The preparation of these Minds
I studied the workers because
If you could find a lazy worker one day and you could do a lot of stuff in this
MTA
You have a lot of
The second thing they had was a B train
This time with a Pink Panther theme
We had the whole day planned next week on Mission
Here's what size CT and David gun together
Both men
It's been a lot of time
Scrutinizing the weak points in the MTA system
Dreams of bringing back New York subway graffiti
But the number of hits a rapidly declining
In 2007 there were 75 yard hits
So far this year only nine
Bmth please Forest can take some credit for those numbers but there is another Factor
I find it hard to think of
Graffiti Writers who were much under 25
People that I know
AR
In their 40s
Honestly
Graffiti is an art form a two-stage out at some point
And if subway graffiti did die out
How do we even know
The artist know that their work will never be seen by the public at Large
Immediately after the subway cars
Scrub to clean by MTA workers
The art form is totally ephemeral
It reminds me of those Tibetan sand mandalas made to disappear
If you thinking your stuff is going to live forever is not
Everything you do with tenants in one day
Pretty much all that keeps that from happening right now is social media
Naira invitation-only Instagram account
Subway bombers post their work before it disappear
Those painted trains that cross are movie screens on countless establishing shots of dirty New York City in the night
1970s
They're just a little square on your smartphone now
And by the time you see them
They're already gone
My love is the train is always going to be trains to the casket drop
Dogs going to be trained
And yeah
What's wrong
Until the casket drops or until the NYPD anti-graffiti unit
Which is what happened to CT
He was arrested and charged with more than 180 misdemeanor counts for things like possession of a graffiti
Instrument and intention to damage property
Along with some felony charges
He took a plea deal agreed to pay nearly $19,000 in restitution charges
And is now on probation
99percentinvisible was produced this week by and peppermint with help from Julie Barton Robie Flores Sam Greenspan
Katie mingle Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of Arc
Arcsin the coolest Architecture Firm in beautiful graffiti adapt Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
Listen to an Alexa
Is talking to me
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman use a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting special episode
What's from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
Family ghosts
Skinner podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
If you like fun you can keep up with this show and all the people make that show at Facebook Twitter and Tumblr but if you want to see this 5
Spy vs Spy subway car
You have to go
The 99 pci.org
Call Bob
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Master your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com