99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Today we start out with something a little different
Love
The typical and atypical story
Love story
Kostas meat Setauket says it's a typical love story
But it's not that typical
It began like this
The early 2000s he was living in Greece where he's from
When
I meant to say Spanish girl
Her name was Sandra delpozo
One thing broke the other and we decided to
Ami I decided to give up everything
And sell everything and she decided to give up her job
Batu Bata small RV on eBay and started driving across Europe
In the direction of Spain
Mercante restaurant
She told me once
Will you think if we go we go to see my grandma
Sandra grandmother lived in a small farming town the northeast corner of Spain called
Sodexo
About 300 little farming Villages that the dictator Francisco Franco built in Spain in the
The 1950s
He wanted to bring people and aggregate
Culture to some of the more desolate parts
Of the country
Producer Katie mingle travel to Soto Spain recently
All the towns built during this time looks similar and Sodexo is no exception
There's a church in the center of town and one bar
Which is also the one restaurant which is also the one place to hang out
As far as I can tell
They're about 200 people who live in soda so permanently all in homes built from Stone the color of Sam
And with red tile roofs
The met you always see at the front of the main house in the back of the
Let's Coast he's giving me a tour of this little town
After he and Sandra came to visit her grandmother here
They ended up staying
So that sounds
Oh and Sandra Dacosta
They're not together anymore
They actually broke up years ago
New boyfriend of Sandra
Daddy-O
Girls
Narcos season Sandra broke up they both stayed incident though
Went on with their lives
And then something
Really incredible happen
Something that brought everyone in this small town into the streets to celebrate all day and all night
Into the wee hours of the morning
December 22nd 2011
Almost everyone in this town
1 a piece
Of the biggest lottery jackpot in Spain
By chance
Hostess Meats attack
About himself
In the luckiest town
The world
I've never heard of an entire town winning the lottery
Maybe a group of friends
Our co-workers
But more often than not in the United States the lottery winner is just one person
In Spain though they do Lottery differently
First of all it's a
Countrywide
Obsession
Evic the Spanish Literature
Reba deal
Then that's that completely crazy if you're not from Spain if you cannot understand that you are surprised by the therapy
People are taking the day off
To watch
The lottery
There's more than one lottery in Spain but the one that Kostas is talking about that
People go nuts over
It's called La Loteria de Navidad
The Christmas Lottery
And it has incredible buy-in from the population about 75%
Spaniards participate
Christmas Lottery is also the oldest running lottery in Spain and one of the oldest in the world
The drawing has happened every single year since 1812
This includes the years of the Spanish Civil War
And all the way
To the Franco dictatorship
For Better or Worse lotteries have long been considered a useful way for governments to raise funds for things like
Infrastructure projects and public programs
Colonial America was basically built using Lottery Revenue
But in the early eighteen-hundreds opposition to the idea of lotteries was growing all over the world
Especially in Europe
Lotteries were
And still are by the way
Thought to be a regressive tax on the poor
Churches found lottery Play to be blasphemy
Superstitious
Mid election was like Karl Marx
But that public libraries were a Sinister instrument of the capitalist state
Designed to convince the proletariat but there was an easy way to escape poverty
In 1826 the British outright bans the lottery for nearly a hundred years
In 1862 Spain responded to the opposition as well
By redesigning their national lottery so that it wouldn't take as much money from the poor
They decided to make the the tickets very expensive
Irrational
Babies R Us
An affordable poor people won't buy them
Let's pair tennis table light
She's an economist at York University in Toronto who studied Spain's Christmas Lottery
She says the Spanish government figured that if they set the price of lottery tickets
Really high
Only rich people would buy them
But that's not how it worked out
What happened is
Disabled people
Not buying a lottery anymore they decided to turn to their Networks
Istara syndicate
People began syndicate
We're playing in groups
New Lottery became more popular than ever
Two people in the same neighborhood
Or family or friends that would buy one ticket
By putting together their money
The Christmas Lottery works like this there a hundred thousand possible numbers ranging from
0 99999
When you go to the lottery office they'll tell you what numbers are available in your area and you pick one
But it's really expensive to own an entire number like tens of thousands of euros
What is much more common is that an organization will buy a share of a number
And then sell of even smaller shares the individuals
50 shares
Two-year-old shares
Thousands of people may own small fractions of the same number
The smaller the share you have
The less you get of the total jacket
If your number should when
And one of the things that this is done is to turn this Christmas Lottery into a
Huge
Social event
Local organizations sell tickets at a markup for fundraisers so your soccer team might be selling shares of
The number the school your kids go to maybe selling shares
Different number
Most Spaniards have a stack of tickets all different tiny shares of different numbers that they've been
Talked into buying by someone
The numbers go on sale in the summer
And then on December 22nd
All of Spain Tunes in to watch the drawing
Every year is being done the same way in the same theater
Madrid
Start relaxing at 8 in the morning and the TVs and the Raiders are always everywhere on
Showing listing
If you turned on Spanish TV that
Here's what you'd say
There's a stage and on it are two giant golden orbs
One contains balls with all the possible lottery numbers Prince
The other smaller warm has balls with the prize money in it
But one orb spits out a number
The other drops down the corresponding prize amount
After the balls drop a couple of Catholic school kids and their uniforms sing the numbers and prizes out
Loud and it kind of
Gregorian chant
The whole thing goes on for several tedious hours
And the kids aren't
Particularly great singers
Hike
They are a bunch of small price mounts that drop
But at some point the orb spit out the
The biggest prize
The day and its corresponding number
Listing price is called
El Gordo
The fat one
The total jackpot for El Gordo can be close to a billion dollars
Video
When El Gordo drops reporters all over Spain rush to figure out who has won the jackpot
But it's almost certain that the winning number isn't held by a single individual
It's held by hundreds
What do you mean thousands of people who probably all live in the same geographic region of Spain
Reporters scrambled to find out where the winning number was sold
And on December 22nd
2011 everyone looks
A little farming town in the northeast corner
At the country
I got a phone call from a friend of mine that he was on the train
He keeps telling me that
Something is going on inside because I'm in the train and everybody's on the phone talking on on the phone and I hear old
All the time
That was the lottery number that aguanto Bordeaux
The winning tickets have been sold all over so that though by the housewives Association
A group of women who host parties and activities in town
The association sold lottery tickets door-to-door
46 euros
5 Euros for the lottery share and one Euro for their fundraising
Call Ashley Medical number
Is your Schofield numero Dela Loteria number
And I chose the winning number in so they don't
When I was the Secretary of the housewives SOC
When Mari Carmen heard that their number had one El Gordo she started calling friends
No one could believe it
On a PA system that the town normally only used to announce
Water shortages
The mayor came on inside
Congratulations so. Oh we have just won the lottery
Come to the plaza to celebrate aside experiencing
That experience
You kindly explain it
If you need to leave it
You can't imagine
If you had been there in the moment you would have thought
These people have gone completely crazy
The residence of soda.
Frantically searched for their tickets
They bought one from the Housewives
H-60 tickets the housewives that sold was now worth a hundred
Thousand
Euros
How many did each person have
Soon the entire town was congregated in the closet
People chanted their winning number at cars drove through the streets honking their horns
Anna the bartender had one
Paco the farmer and his wife Marisol the hairdresser had one
Rosa the mayor of the Town had one
It seemed
Every single resident of the small town of soda throw had bought a lottery ticket from the Housewives
And want a piece of El Gordo
The whole village
Everyone
Except one
Yeah there was
One person
Who didn't have a ticket
And who was it
That was me
Coasties did not have a ticket coasties who would move to the town for love and stayed
Even after he broke up with his Spanish girlfriend Sandra
Who yes
How to take a
Coasties lived on the edge of town and somehow the housewives had missed him when they went knocking on doors
They drove everywhere
Except
At my place
Which they didn't do it on purpose
He just is the only one which is outside you know
From the village show
They do feel a little bit guilty
The people of so data we're not the only ones to win on the number 58268 in
A few thousand other people also had small shares of a number
Mostly scattered around in towns nearby
I told Jack bought that year for El Gordo was about 750 million euros
But it was divided by thousands of people
Enzo detto the people who bought more tickets
Got more money
And everyone got at least one hundred thousand Euros
Everyone
Except Coast
6 years later coasties still lives inside at though
Hand sander good friends now she lives in the center of town and he just outside of it in a barn that he's turned into a
House
It still feels
Kind of like a barn
He has a couple of big German Shepherds
You can hear one of them jumping into my mic
When I asked him if he's if he felt or still feels any regret or jealousy about not having a tick
He laughs
It's like it's a ridiculous question
For a while after so that those when reporters swarm the little town
They especially wanted to talk with Kostas
The one unlucky guy was left out of the lottery
But Kostas doesn't feel unlucky
In fact is anything he feels like
He got something that day too
He's a filmmaker
And the David Town won the lottery
He grabbed his camera and went to the plaza
The moment that happened
He was literally like somebody was giving me a script in
He filmed all the celebrating and he's been filming ever since
He says it's been really interesting
See what happens when a whole town gets well fall at once
The whole thing is like a social experiment with really
Fast results
Study
And see what an event like this can do to people
Is not always for good
Cuz he thinks the people and said it. Become a little more insular since the wind
More focused on the nuclear family and less on the town as a community
You do see how it's affecting how they have changed how they have
Closed
Before that
All the doors were constantly
The way he talks about it makes me wonder if the people in the town will like the film when they see it
Because he says
Do you think they will
Mostly
Maybe if you do small things they might not like it
But that that's reality
One thing about set at though
Thoroughbreds
A lot of them
Luckily this is also one of the things I'm able to say in Spanish
Another thing about said that though
It's hot
Mari Carmen the former Secretary of the housewives Association tells me it's not usually this hot until later in the summer
This heat she says
I just can't
What does he
As we walk around so that those she's pointing at a few houses that have been fixed up with Lottery money
But mostly Mari Carmen says the town hasn't changed that much
So that was the town of farmers and some of them installed new irrigation
Thumbs are bought new tractors
Some people made modest additions to their homes but nothing that extravagant
Get overnight service
I'm like kosice Mari Carmen hasn't noticed the town being more closed off since the lottery
She thinks there's been some little jealousies here and they're not everyone one the same amount
But overall she thinks it's been an incredible thing for everyone in this little working-class town
To live without the worry of death
She's been battling cancer which keeps going away and coming back
And the money's allowed her to stop working
And not worry
I need the phone number for me personally
The lottery has juice
Broad sense of calm
I don't know like
To have they do they cover that you know
And that's the thing with this Syndicate style Lottery
Unlike the Powerball
I bought which keeps hundreds of Millions on one or two lonely winners
The money from the Christmas Lottery get divvied up among thousands of people
And they don't generally win enough to buy mansion
Yachts
They want enough to pay off their debts
Maybe buy a Honda Civic
The lottery brings wealth to a whole geographic area
Distributed relatively evenly
At least among those lucky enough to have a ticket
After a short walk Mari Carmen and I arrive at the new office of the housewives Association
Which now to be more modern is officially called the women's Association
Everyone still seems to call it the Housewives
Association
Back in 2011 when they were selling lottery tickets
The group kept
Or for themselves
Which ended up winning them
Thousand Euros
The time
Enough to cover their budget for the next 200 years
With all the new money they fix up an old school building in town and made it into their office / Community Center
As a nice kitchen for parties a laundry room and a fitness center
Queso Panela Dinero
All of these was made with Lottery money
These living room was built
Description
And the association gave coasties some money for his film
Is Olivia
I don't remember how my
MattyB was 15000 Euros or how much
I don't know it was a good day
But she also mentions that
He hasn't finished it yet
Everyone is waiting
Either is or anything
The people here in the village are waiting like what's up
Mari Carmen isn't the only one to mention this to me
It actually seems to be the Talk of the Town
A little later that day I run into a group of older guys
When I tell them I met with coasties one of them says
El Que hizo la pelicula
The one who made the movie
Paranormal represent
But he hasn't even come out with it yet
I told him I think it'll be another year before the film is finished and he says
But it's already been five
Another guy comes in and says
Didn't win the lottery but he's done quite well for himself
He says
He's been getting paid for all the television interviews he's done
Then they talked about how much he's been getting paid
Mucho
I could have you.
Idaho
For the record Kostas told me he's never been paid for any interviews
Conspiracy theories aside I got the feeling the people inside at the like
The strange Greek artist who lives on the outskirts
Town
But I also wondered if they see him as an outsider and if the lottery is made this even more pronounced
When I asked Marie comment about this she says
No
He's one of us
We just wish you'd come out with that movie
Economist have long struggled to figure out why people play the lottery
It's not a rational investment of your money
The odds of winning
Are terrible
Worse than blackjack
Worse than slot machines
Worse odds
In any other form of gambling
And yet
It's the most
Popular form of gambling
But in Spain
Pretty obvious why people play This Love
It's a social thing to do
You buy a ticket because the housewives Association will pester you
Until you do it
You buy tickets because your friends are buying tickets
You buy because you don't want to be that one guy in town
Who doesn't win
You don't want to be
Coasties
The housewives Association continues to choose a number each year for the Christmas Lottery and sell tickets and soda at the
And in the surrounding little towns
And while they used to knock on doors for months they don't have to do that anymore
Now the people come to them and tickets sell out in a few days
They were lucky ones and they could be again
People say
And no one wants to be left out
99percentinvisible which produces we buy our senior producer Katie Mingle
Mix into production by Sharif Youssef
But digital director is crook.
Includes Delaney Hall Avery Chapman Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman Mars
Find out more about coasties as movie which he's working on this film partner Laura Sorensen
Cuando Toco. Com website because I am not going to spell it
While you're there and check out some beautiful animations of this story by Benjamin star
Music in this episode was composed by Jenny Conlee drizos John neufeld and a query
They were part of the team that also scored the genie chance story and Tour live with us
They are.
We had additional songs composed by our own Sean real
Carmen Vidal
Did the English voice over for Mari Carmen
Special thanks to Roberto Garcia and Zach Froehlich
We are project of radiotopia and kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Define the show into a discussion about the show on Facebook you can't wait to meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
One Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
If you want to read Kurt story about that time we tested guided missiles
For postal delivery
That really happened
You can find out all about it on our website
At 99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
5 part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com