99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It's safe to say that Woods Hole is exactly what you picture when you think of a town on Cape Cod
Old houses covered in Wood shingles are sailboats Oceanside restaurants
Super traditional super East Coast
Town There's this huge Dome it looks like a three-story tall golf ball it's this crazy looking
Totally out of place next to the Old Colonial houses
The reporter Kelly Clarkson went to check it out
Hello
Katie brought some friends to
The back door was unlocked
Like it's not like anything you've ever seen before
Inside it smells musty
It's creepy
Look at this old
Wallpaper
There's a wall made entirely out of the
Interlocking triangle shaped windows
The cast of web of Shadows on the floor
There's an old kitchen
It looks like it might have been part of a restaurant
I found some
Yeah there's a whole pile of Old Salt and Pepper Diner
When we left
I needed to know more
What Katie found with a geodesic dome designed and built by the late Buckminster Fuller
Don't feel bad if you never heard of Bucky he did go by Bucky by the way big deal back in the 60s
Drawing of Bucky's head made to look like one of his domes was on the cover of Time magazine in 1964
There's a Bucky Fuller postage stamp
He was even given the country's highest civilian honor
Presidential medal of freedom
Bucky Fuller is also responsible for the title of this radio show he said 99% of who you are is invisible
Civil and Untouchable fan he discussed the 99% invisible activity that is coalescing to Roche Park
Our future he's a very quotable man
He is from the film Buckminster Fuller the Lost interviews
To do mall was last
So that you might sometimes do so much with so little they might be able to take care of everybody
And make all the politics invalid
Jay Baldwin was one of Bucky students
He just wanted people to use less stuff
He said it was all going to run out
We gotta think big
And take care of everybody said as long as there's one person starving
You're going to have wars
Fuller called himself a comprehensive anticipatory design scientist
She wanted to invent things that would make human life sustainable on this planet
Decades before anyone else was even thinking about Green Building
And for that people have called Bucky the Leonardo DaVinci of the 20th century
Devore Institute crew
Counters that Leonardo was the bucket
Before medieval times
So here's the deal with the Woods Hole Dome
Buggy wanted to change the world
Starting with building
So he started making these weird structures which he called geodesic dome
Geodesic refers to the geometry of Curves
Surfaces
The golf ball building in Woods Hole is actually the oldest of Buc-ee's domes that are still standing
The structure of the geodesic dome is based on a lot
Complicated math
But I'm sure it's dealt with a lot of triangles
A triangle is a very strong shape
And a dome made out of triangles
Is extra strong
That meant that domes could be made of lighter and cheaper materials than normal building
Like plastic and aluminum
Instead of Steel and concrete
Back in 1952 but he was just starting to build them
They caught the attention of an architect and aspiring restaurant or a man named Gunnar Peterson
And the early 50s 1953 he bought some property in Woods Hole in
Decided to build a hotel in a restaurant
Joe Peterson is Gunner son
He did make a deal with Bucky Fuller
I don't remember how dad Madame he
Call the track him down anyway his wife
Came and looked at our house
They decided they build the Dome restaurant
A geodesic dome has a way of standing out but in Cape Cod it really
Stands out
And that upset some people
Wow it isn't there shingled Cape Cod Cottage
That's for darn sure
I'm in the feeling is this is going to
Change Life as we know it you know this again I will never be the same again you know this is just
Horrible
One building
There was
Stuff that happened there was things stolen from you I mean it was
Paint poured on things that what that was
There was just
Lots of stuff
Stuff here meaning
People didn't want to talk about this on tape
But I just have this mental image of a really ugly mob up in arms about this
Dome
That's probably an exaggeration but
You get the idea
Despite the unrest the Dome restaurant opened in June of 1954
And according to Joel it was the place
To go on was
The most elegant place around I mean at that time
Shortly when you went out to eat in the 50s on Cape Cod
In a place like the dawn
You are tie in the women wear all spiffed-up it was a festive
Occasion
And they had a live musician
She played the zither
And I don't know if you've ever had dinner with soothing music
It's rather Pleasant
Restaurant is right on the ocean
And you're far away from City so he could just look up at the ceiling and you're looking at the star
Sally Brady was 14 years old when the Dome restaurant open your house
This early fifties we're really quite an amazing
Moment because everybody could buy cars people who survived the war all those men were home and they were job
10 people were
Making the American dream come true and I think that
A symbol of the America
Dream in a way it felt like a prosperous optimistic time
It makes sense that the Dome represented the future for some people
It turned out that there was some real structural problems with the Dome
First the structure acted like an acoustic amplifier
So all that zither music got blasted across the neighborhood
And a building was that much glass work like a greenhouse
Got hot inside
After the first season they cover the Dome and white fiberglass the block out the Sun
Diamond Diner couldn't see the Stars anymore
Geodesic domes don't have any support beam
Those triangular window frames do all the work
Each frame rests on the one next to it
What can be a problem if the building materials are flexible and move in the Wind
Here's Arnie grapes dad he worked at the restaurant
Saturday night
Horrible weather outside
And this particular night
There was a party of four
Lascala's Matt were they having dinner and they were regular customers local people
Around 7:30 with a
Shuffle restaurant
All of a sudden this.
Dropping a table 113 and I can remember it
Seeing them sit there
And Jane took her umbrella
Opened it
To a huge
Floss
From everyone in the restaurant
It was just funny
But the fact is
The geodesic domes most of them looked like
Say it again Jay Baldwin Bucky's former students
I have a photograph of Bucky inside is dumb
In Carbondale
With an umbrella in one hand
A book in the other
And a flashlight in his mouth
Reading the blur
And if the umbrella
Is needed
I told Becky I'm going to find out why I don't sleep
And he said
Don't sleep because they're made my amateurs
And they built it with holes in it you wouldn't build a boat with holes in it would u r r
I said I don't think they're leaking
Because they made a move
I said I think
Are leaking G
The owner Joel Peterson
Does he pass
A lot of week
Eventually Joe wanted to retire from the restaurant business
He sold the property in 2002
It's been sitting vacant ever since
Ask Joel and Arnie to give me a tour
I can't bring myself to tell them I've actually been here before
We have to push aside branches to get to the front door
It's been a few years since I've been here
And
To tell you the truth I never really wanted to come because I mean
Babe is incredibly overgrown I mean it's just
Sad
My gosh isn't this amazing it actually is
I'll tell you what this is not a pretty sight
I told you about Ruth welcome in the zoo this is where she played
Now if you want take a look at the kitchen
There's a walking
This really has been like
I certainly I wouldn't mind seeing it restored on the other hand
Think it's going to be a tremendous expense to put this back
So it sits with two
Opposite emotions that you look at it
But you have to be realistic and
Understand that things change human life
In 2006 a real estate development company plan to build condos on the side
And for a while it looks like the Dome might be torn down
But then a funny thing happened
There was a public outcry to keep the Dome
This is the same building that residents fought against
Tooth and nail back when it was being constructed in the 50
Now in order to build on the site the developer have to
Store the Dome
And that's going to be a
Expensive
So the whole thing is in limbo until more condos are pre-sold
And real estate transactions are not moving quickly these days
If a developer Camp FreeCell enough condos
To justify the cost of restoring the Dome
And the whole deal could fall apart
If that happened the Dome would stay as it is now
Continuing to the k
Waiting for the next out-of-towners to come poking around with a flashlight
The person who seems least sentimental about this
Is Joel Peterson
If I were doing the project that they
Talk about doing
I tear it down
Beyonce
It's it's
It's a building it was yeah it was part of my life it's a building
Sally Brady grew up next to the Dome feels differently
Maybe it will
Be reborn the different way that will be better
Why not
Maybe you'll be a beautiful transparent place
People will go there and do
Fantastic energizing work
It will help Humana
What do you think we would lose if if it was torn down
What would you lose
Well it's very good example of this
Boo
Anything was possible
Yeah I sort of agree and then and then what does it mean that now
It's just in such disrepair
Well I think it means that we
Groudon
And that dream
Sort of yeah I think it's
Kind of broken dream right now
Depressing isn't it
Maybe it's finished
Kinder
Buckminster Fuller claimed that his ideas were 50 years ahead of his time
Announcement over 50 years but domes have not replaced traditional building
But you know what
I'm rooting for the Dome
I think it represents Bucky's optimism
That we could solve The World's problems with good design
And even if you couldn't you could still stargaze through triangular windows
Looking out
Over the sea
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie Clarkson with Sam Greenspan in me Roman Mars
Can you produce a different version of this story at the transom story Workshop which aired on the PRX house sound
Podcast
Both of those are run
Great
Super punk rock
Rob Rosenthal
Do they owe us a living
Thanks also to Erin chesky
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world
Handmade sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God.
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about
About this story including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero and
Any movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com