99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
At their peak in the mid-90s there were about two and a half million payphones in the US
Adoption of cell phones has brought that number down further and further every year
Be fully enclosed outdoor telephone box you know the one that Superman changes in
That is exceptionally rare
Only four of those are left in New York City
After several decades these little pieces of single-use architecture just disappeared from the landscape
They simply weren't popular enough to justify their existence
But there's always an exception to the rule
20 years ago
A man discovered a phone booth in the middle of the desert that became his obsession
An obsession that he then passed on to the World At Large
From the great radio program snap judgment of Oakland California producer Joe Rosenberg tells the story of a very
In the middle of nowhere
Okay
So the story starts out back in the mid-90s in Phoenix we're Godfrey Daniels given name is Godfrey Daniels but I
IDOC
He's heading back home after seeing this band girl trouble
Odesza concert
Remember scenes if not
Don't worry
Free internet
Nature magazine
So as I was walking home I was kind of flipping through it and
What about the
34th page of a couple of letters to the editor and one of them mentioned
That there was a phone booth
In the Mojave Desert
Miles and miles from a pavement just sitting by itself
And this for dock
Just made no sense
I wasn't sure they believed it
Why not
Well I didn't have any reason to play
I mean I don't know if
And the in the age of cell phones
If it's the same
But when you were on the desert and those days
You are on your own
You can call people
So the idea that there could be this f****** puth
Just sitting out in an uncontactable place
It's kind of like if somebody was on the moon you know when you can talk to somebody on the moon
Where did he say it was exactly
Nearest
Recognizable landmarks
He didn't say it was a really short little paragraph
It was any solid information other than the number
Okay
Why not give it a shot
Captain the number and it just rang and I let it ring for a long time
I was just imagining making a phone ring how where presumably
Hear it except the coyotes but then there was also in the back your mind the thought what if
What if somebody's wondering why who would be out there
Who would pick up it just really grabbed me and so
I hung up and then
I just kept thinking about it I kept thinking about it
All Night Lights was thinking about it as I fell asleep and it just it just
Somehow got me into its clutches
So the next morning I called again
I just kind of became obsessed
Founders of confounded all the time
My friend visited his house he put their arm and make them call it
Supposed to know in the bathroom here it just said did you remember to call the Mojave Desert today
It turned off
I didn't need it because I used to call
Many times to take
Like how many times
If I was supposed to be working I was probably calling at least once an hour
And again this is all assuming that actually existed which I had no proof of
Like on speakerphone or like you would
Stop everything
No no no no cuz that would require explanation
I would just didn't have it and have the the phone kind of cradle against my ear
Yeah just listening to it rain
Stop it was weird
Keep calling a number with no one on the other end
If he was ever pressed about it
It was like being a ham radio operator
Little person
Sending a signal as far as you couldn't to be either
Wondering if another person without their
Waiting to be contacted
That uncontactable place
So I figured I would be doing this
Forever
I really didn't think anybody would ever pick up
Then just one month after he started calling
Just doing my daily call and
I got a busy signal
Actually mastercorp that call
I look I look like I'm an idiot
Because I keep saying wow
And
I thought well
I must have misdialed
So I dialed it again
Send it was a busy signal again
I realized okay either something has gone wrong with the phone company here or
She is using imabi phone
Right now
I was
Totally hyperactive my main thing was I didn't want them to get away like I was thinking I need to catch it right when they a
Hang up that phone so I just read and then it rang and
Earring for five times
And then
I Heard a Voice say hello
Deadly
Dog was only able to properly record his own words
This now historic moment
But as many times that I called
I had given
Remarkably little thought
If anyone would say
Hello
Are you in the Mojave Desert
She said yeah
I said
You are
Okay
Why are you in the middle of Mojave Desert
She said
I'm making my calls
And you don't have a phone
I got it when I looked at the transfer it was kind of funny cuz like
You think everything's cool if you're like and she's like
Undermining
Did you like cinder blocks so cool
End
She said that
She never heard the phone ring before
Tell your name
Her name's Doreen
Brain is nice to meet you
Was there was there any sense of disappointment
Disappointment about what
Got it all
Well let me put it this way, it's kind of like
The idea that this phone is ringing out there in the desert
And
Anyone can pick up
But then finally someone picked up and stiff Lorraine
Oh no no see I look at it the exact opposite way
Somebody did pick up
And I and I had no
I had no right to expect any one ever would
So this was great
To hear to hear a human voice
In place of the ringing you know I mean this with this was
This was a payoff
It just encouraged me more
And the instant I hung up I kicked myself because I had forgotten to ask her what
Probably the most important question which is where was the phone booth
Of course
Haddon Heights
I have no way to get in touch with her except
Define the thing
Soda called around doesn't sleuthing in a few months later gets his hands on the equivalent of an x marks the spot map showing
The supposed location
A blob that we're all set stove my friend
And I took off traveled all day for the Mojave Desert and this is in the middle of August and so scorching-hot just scored
Basically as far as you could see you saw Joshua trees and then we saw this little dirt path
That was Mark Trevino danger danger warning not maintain blah blah blah
That was the road we were supposed to take
Yeah we're just going along go along in the first I thought this is not bad at all
But the further along that we went the road would narrow and the thing was it the sun was going down
And the daytime you got these Grand huge Vistas and you kind of have a sense of where you are but when the darkness drops
It's just whatever you can see right in front of him and we were ring by storms there was lightning
Almost in every direction is so then I started to think we have any kind of a problem unless we do find
The phone booth
Letting people know we're really in trouble that at a certain point
Just barely in the reach of the headlights I thought I saw a line of telephone poles
And there was a little a little jet to the left and then a little jet to the right and I brought the van
Stop with the headlights just shining right on the Mojave phone booth
It was really quite a moment and it's full of holes in it there's no class it's all busted out
It's kind of a wreck you know but to me it was just it was beautiful
I needed to hear that phone ring
I needed to hear
What I have been
Causing to happen
Conference time out there so I called the
I called my friends
Pager
And here I am
Out in the Mojave surrounded by Joshua trees
Lightning
Desert and now that's a familiar
Twist it was so loud
It was really loud
That was just
Crazy loud
Pray for me that was kind of D moment
Is
Hearing that phone ring
It was everything that I had been imagining when I was calling
For that
The story was over
They keep calling me
After all
Turn up to pick up
That was just for him
I never really expected anyone else to care
Until we did something which would not seem risky back in 1997
Today is obviously very
Barry
Naked Juice
What page
And in those days the internet there wasn't that much on it that's why I thought that was about
As far as it would go
But yeah
What happened
Next thing you know how to go to my PO box and there would be
Clippings about the Mojave phone booth some newspapers
In languages that I didn't read
It just spread so I thought well this unexpected
Initial visit
They got their this phone
Wing out in the middle of nowhere
It was ringing off the hook
You didn't have to call anybody
It was just
As soon as you would hang up the phone
I was just crazy you pick it up and
Who's the Spurs going to be
Where are they going to be
And you had no idea it could be somebody from
Vietnam
Iran or just anywhere
Some people would call
And you couldn't talk to them because
Didn't speak English
And again you know most of the time it wasn't about the content
You know you're not really saying anything it's really not the point
It's just it's just the connection
An old trucker guy called and
I think he just wanted to be listened to
He wanted to tell stories about his Trucking days
And I didn't have anybody to tell him to
How many calls did you end up taking up there
It would be over a hundred guaranteed
Nan admittedly he said he shouldn't phone rang after awhile be like you get to know you get its return you get it
Eventually had to take it off the hook so we could sleep
Going to put it back on the hook the next morning
So they can leave there wouldn't have been a way to leave
In silence I mean
You work you were going to have to dry since it was raining all the time you were going to drive away from a ringing phone
Just calling
They were visiting
Traveling all the way out to the desert
Just for the honor informing collars that yes the phone booth
Was real
Reality
This is from short documentary made about the booth
Montage of people from all over the place
Taking calls from all over the place
Right on bro you're presenting yourself to the world in a way anybody who wanted to could call you
There was no control
Over who could call that phone
Store for the circuit
Quadriplegic or paraplegic
Circus
Best friend slept
How long were you in a coma
Yeah me too I was
Everybody wants to tell their story and they want
They want someone to listen to story
You should come out and do this
Did you like the fact
That it became popular
Would you have preferred it to remain
The hesitation came about just because once something like that
Gets out of control then then you know that
Equal and opposite reaction is going to come
The only question was when
And then I met a 2000 Lorraine's brother on the way out to the mine stopped
And answer the phone
It was ringing a course
And talk to some guy in England who is he said he was sitting there with his fiance
Having tea and crumpets
And he talked to him for a little while
And then continued on to the reins
And then in the morning when they were leaving
Miss Kate Equinox a reaction that come in the form of the National Park Service
Turned out the Bluetooth on the smack dab in the center of a new National Preserve on the phone at Lake Norman
No problem
The park officials haven't taken kilates Albany foot traffic
Or for that matter the ringing
By the time I figured out what was happening
Was already too late
Did you go out and see this for yourself
No no I didn't go out until
I think about
Call 2009-2010
Long
Long after
I mean once I knew it was gone there was
I didn't want to go out
Why not
Just be too sad you know I mean
A lot of fun there
Hilton it was funny to is that
People did keep going out
And they would go
And visit the concrete pad
Abu that stood on
A guy made a really nice Tombstone for the booth
And everything that anybody brought out there the Park Service hold off
And eventually they came out and broke up the concrete pad took that away to say it was like it was never there
Yeah
When I was there the only thing left was a few pieces of glass
The broken windows
And people would say I will it's not your phone moving out so yeah I know it's not my phone booth
It's my fault
You know it wasn't as though I set out to make a phone booth same as far from it
It's just had I known
I might not have done it
May I might still I don't know I might not have
Even given that we can now
Reach
No idea
I mean that that's something that I that I have thought about is is whether it could have happened
Even five years later
And I just don't think it would have I mean that was kind of the magic
Of being in contact
In an uncontactable place
And I don't think I don't think you had that feeling now
Did you ever
Try calling that number again after that
Of course
Camacho
Anime let it ring
For a long time and they left
Even though the phone was not there
But that even make sense cuz you're not even making a phone ring anymore the desert you're just making a kind of a sure I would know that but still
It would be like listening to a song that meant something to you
I guess I did just like calling out to the booth and here now raining in the end
The Mojave phone booth was produced by Joel Rosenberg
Oakland's own snap judgement in 2014
Dog has a book coming out about all this called adventures with the Mojave phone booth
Why the link on our website
Today if you call the Mojave phone booth number that 760
9 9 6 9
You connect to a conference line where you can talk to people from around the world if no one's on the conference line it plays a recorder
Meaning of the book exploding the phone is really great book just listen to it
But for the next week you might just find someone from 99 Pi on the conference line
That 760
9 9 6 9
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan to Lani Hall Pro Kolstad Katie mingle Avery troubleman Sharif Youssef
Roman Mars
We are production of 99% invisible hang up project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco
Introduced the offices of arcsin
The finest architecture and Interiors firm
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad to take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Ubuntu show and join the fun Community people who like to show on Facebook all fave every 99
MPI coin I see on Twitter and Instagram
But if you want to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world a recommend
Can you spend some time perusing 99 Pi. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com