99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 app
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the 1940s there were as there are today a lot of great Art and Design schools in New York City
Pratt
Cooper Union
Parsons
And there were then as there are today a lot of young talented artists and designers that those schools
Who would go on to have great careers
But in the 1940s there was something else
Some of those artists and designers
How to do
That's our own Katie McCall
There was a war going
World War
And the Army needed artists
Because well
They had
Kind of a crazy idea
And it was a crazy idea that came out of one of the most conservative organizations you can imagine the United States are
That's Rick Beyer more about Rick in a minute
And had to go up the line
High-ranking generals appetizers Eisenhower himself
To get approval
The crazy idea was this
The United States Army with design a deception unit
A unit that would appear to the enemy to be a large Armored Division
Thousands of soldiers
Tanks
Trucks guns
Only this unit
Would actually be equipped with fake tanks
Fake truck
Fake guns
And Man by just a handful of soldiers
And it really is something
Unusual
Rick buyer has a forthcoming book about all of this
And also made it
Film about it
Hold That Ghost Army
People say to me well did the Germans have something like this
Did the Japanese have something like this
And when I said is the Germans and Japanese did deceptions
But I haven't found anybody
Ever
Who had
A unit
Quite like this
But I like groups began landing on the northern coast of France this morning
Strongly supported by Naval and Air Forces
D-Day
Want to start of the most critical. Of War
The Allies landed on the beaches of Normandy and began to liberate France from the Germans who had occupied it for 4 years
At that point
They were ultimately Marching for Berlin
And the success of the Normandy Landings on
D-Day was due in part to deception
Using a variety of techniques
The Allies tricked the Germans into thinking The Invasion would happen at a different time and place
But a couple of US Army men
Ralph Ingersoll and Billy Harris wanted to take deception to a whole new level
They wanted to create a mobile deception unit
I'm going to put that on the battlefield and give that to the generals to use
For whatever set of circumstances
Come up
What were the circumstances in which a unit like this
This would be needed
What's the American forces are guarding a border
But there's a hole in ones
And it's a German the realize there's an unguarded spot
They can use it to break the line
But the Americans
Don't have any troops
To fill that hole
Sometimes they can't send the real truth because the real troops are needed someplace house and sometimes they can't send them
Because
They just don't have enough or they can't get them there in
Time that's where the ghost Army came in
This top-secret unit was officially called the 23rd headquarters special troops
And nicknamed The Ghost Army
After the war
The so-called ghost Army would impersonate a larger Armored Division might be the 6th Armored Division
Vision or some other one it changed but a division that was made up of say 15 or 20
Thousand soldiers when they the ghost army or actually only about a thousand men
Make it seem like something is there that isn't there
And if you want people to do that you're going to want artists
The Army was interested in recruiting people with art with an art background
Do installations of sorts
That's Jack Macy
I'm jacked Macy
I served
The ghost Army
Before the Army Jack was just a kid in high school pretty famous High School in New York City called
High School of Music & Art it's now called LaGuardia high school
Yung Joc is shipped off
Tear up to join the camouflage unit
Where he discovers that a lot of the other guys in his unit are also artists
A good 50%
And one of the things all of the artists have been working on
Was designing steak
Tanks and trucks
By the time Jack got done all their R&D
Undecided rubber with the best material to use
And so that's when I discovered my first
Inflatable tank
Inflatable rubber tanks
R A crucial part of the visual deception unit
Souffle
In about a half hour
From nothing to a full tank
Was rather quite interesting
Okay
But the visual deception unit had more than just
It stank
And trucks
And artillery
Angie
And all sorts of vehicles virtually every kind of vehicle the Army has
The ghost Army had
Inflatable versions of
Musically
Anything to make themselves appear to be the full size armored divisions that they were
Pretending to be
This stuff was all meant to be believable from a distance
Four planes flying overhead or maybe people looking through binoculars
And at a distance Inflatables were super realistic
You had to be careful
About certain details
Sometimes
The barrels
Of the tanks
The Seroquel of course that was a mess
Plastic gun barrels never a good thing
But there were other details to consider
A real tank weighs 40
Tons and when it drives across the field
It leaves
A set of tank tracks
Text that are really obvious
To Ariel LeConte
So the deception unit would actually use a bulldozer to make fake tracks around the fake tanks
But there was one cardinal rule Jack says about working with inflatables
Never
Under any circumstance
Will you ever
To carry an inflatable across the road
Obviously two dudes carrying a 40-ton tank would look
Wrong
You weren't supposed to casually pick up and move an inflatable vehicle in a place where you could be seen
When the artist soldiers weren't busy with their dummy tanks
Jack says they did what artist
Still spent that time sketching
Local people local architecture
Churches
All through Normandy
Across France
And into Germany
During their travels through Europe when they weren't sketching local architecture the ghost Army was often
Acting
And they call it special effects
And I call it play-acting
Because that's really what it was
And the idea was supposed to go into town
And sit down at a cafe
So that anybody watching us
Remember the Germans occupied France
Dance for four years at this
Yeah there were spies
Everywhere
We wanted them to sink
That not only did we have
Actual tanks which of course we didn't
But that we actually were members of the 2nd Armored Division
Witchery factory wiring
They stenciled fake unit numbers on their trucks they made fake patches to put on their sleeves
Sometimes they seem to be having a little too much fun with this part of the job like the time they stole a bunch of
Two cases of expensive cognac from a Tavern just to piss off the tavern owner they knew to be a jerk
German collaborator
They're hoping that he is Dan going to be so angry at them that he's going to go to the Germans and tell him
Will not only do I know that the 6th Armored Division is here with their General was at my Tavern today
The whole point
And the ghost Army
Want to make sure their presence
What's known
The ghost Army needed to be
Seen and heard and perceived by the Germans as being real
I'm turntable one goes a recording of trucks moving in
Which brings us to the deception unit that I probably would have been drafted into
Sonic deception
So they would record the sounds of
Tanks going down Rose or the sounds of truck
Except man reaching a certain point in all the men jumping out and then be able to
Play them back in such a way as to make the enemy think that those things are really happening
This was also new and strange that the Army made a top-secret
Film what explain how sound can be used to deceive the enemy
Init
Actors
Badly portray a group of German officers who were in the midst of being punked
But it's Sonic deception unit
Thanks
Oot here
Report Stephen it sounds
Tanks moving in
Assembly
About that
The movie goes on to explain that the Germans in that scene were fooled
A Sonic, they had convinced them that an Armored Division
Under cover of Darkness
That moves along the river lacrosse
Tank destroyers unreserved up here
They moved into position
And they waited
And we crossed down here where they were
The phone goes into great detail
About the process of recording and playing back
Sounds the best loudspeakers
The speakers can project sound as far as 50
Tmall
And there was a huge library of
Sounds to choose
He's from
For example
Engines make different sounds depending on the terrain and they had all of those differ
Kinds of sound
At the little Hill this one projected the sound of Tanks going up
This one projected Banks going down
They would look at what they're trying to simulate what are we trying to make people think
And then they would take all the appropriate child
And mix them together to create a
Sonic
Stewart
People who heard this
Say that it was
Unbelievably Erie that it was so realistic that
You started seeing vehicles that weren't there
The third component of the ghost army or the radio operators
It was well known that the Germans listened in on radio communications of Allied troops
So the ghost Army was trying to impersonate a real Armored Division
It have to send the right kinds of Transmissions
They bring in
Trained radio operators from All Sorts about
Units
To have the very best operators
Depart of the radio deception
All of the units paid incredible
Attention to detail
But the radio operators
Had to be perfect mimic
They had to learn the exact keystrokes of an individual Morse code operator in the unit they were in prayer
The way a radio operator in the
The 4th Armored Division always starts his messages with 4
..
Because that's just what they do
And if you don't do that
The German intercept person listening
Is going to say
Will wait a minute
Does that really from the 4th
Armored Division
They have three different units visual Sonic and radio and their operating separately but they're
All organized by the same people so they're very carefully working on different components of the same plan
The three separate units might only be vaguely aware of what one another were up
And everything was kept completely secret from the rest of the military
It's a fact of their mere existence ever lead to the Germans
The whole deception
As well as the safety of the ghost Army
Could be compromised
The ghost Army carried out 21 different deception mission
Between
June 1944 and
March
35 pretty much the entire time
The US Army was operating
Rick says one of their most important missions was Operation bettembourg
Which took place near the border but
Between France
In Germany
So picture this
There's a river near the German border the Moselle River
German troops are on one side and American troops are on the other
They're part of a front butt
Hundreds of miles long
General George Patton
Realizes that there is a 75-mile gap in his line
Unguarded 75 MI
But the Germans come across the border
If they knew about it
So they bring in
The ghost Army
So they they arrived in
About middle of the night
It is in September 44 and they using all three units
Visual unit with insulated
People tanks
Radio guys
But especially the Sonic design
Option unit
Because most of the Germans are on the other side of the Mosel River
There within earshot
In other words
And so it's a great opportunity to use sound to
Build it up and make it
It seem like so many
Hank Snow moving in and so many troops are moving in
The deception goes on
For 7
Days
7 days is a long time to fool any
The ghost army soldiers are getting nervous they've never done a deception for this long before
And even General Patton is nervous he wrote a letter to his wife
And he says one bad spot my line but I don't think the Huns know about it yet
We're holding on to it by the grace of God will have it plugged by tomorrow
And the next day the 83rd division Moves In
And takes over for the ghost Army
And the Germans never caught on
To the ghost Army
During that operation
Or any other
Over the course of the war the ghost Army lost three soldiers and had several dozen wounded but overall it was one of the safer
Assignments of World War II
Being in the camouflage unit I always felt
I was kind of lucky
That's Jack Macy again
Camouflage unit was just another name for the visual deception unit
Wish I had friends
Lahore in the Infantry
Shovel workout
But being assigned to the camouflage Corps
Away from the front lines
It's true that the ghost Army suffered far fewer casualties than other units
That's probably because they were really good at their jobs if their deception was ever uncovered by the Germans
Would be catastrophic
For the men in the ghost Army
They're operating without any heavy weapons
They don't have any real artillery
So they're kind of putting on this show of force
In a very vulnerable place
Jack remembers the Armenians
Extremely fondly
He got to see Paris
See Paris
The great cafes and the Beast Rose
Completely
Fabulous experience
After Jack Macy left the ghost Army he went to Yale
School of
Garden architecture
GI Bill of Rights
Thank God
After Yale he went on to design some amazing things
He designed the kitchen used in the American national exhibition in Moscow in 1959
Would a famous debate between Nixon and Khrushchev took place
He work with Buckminster Fuller on a geodesic dome for the 1967 World Expo in Montreal
And Jack Macy wasn't the only artist
In the ghost Army to have a great career
Remember all those artists that were constantly sketching around Europe
Well some of them became pretty famous
After the war
Ellsworth Kelly the
Minimalist painter and sculptor was in this unit
Arthur Singer a wildlife artist to Illustrated birds of North America and many other books
Bill Blass
The fashion designer
Jack Macy and Bill Blass we're good friends in the army
Jack likes to say that Bill Blass was the only Soldier
That read Vogue and
Is Fox Hole
Not only red
But he made sketches
Skechers wherever he went
Forever working away
Getting ready for the great moment when he would leave the army
The government officially kept the ghost Army a secret into the 1980s because they were hoping to be able to use some of the deception
Tactics in future complex
Some units were told not to talk about their experience
Ever
2NE1
But apparently not everyone got the same directives on this
I was in Company B
And we were never told
That we were not supposed to talk about it
So I was blabbing about the ghost Army II die
Leicester
And everybody I had everybody reduced to
Gigantic laughs
Set amusement wdid as a fake
Yunnan
Pretty amusing thing
It is amusing but
Beyond music
Strange and amazing that they tried this
And that they actually
Pulled it off
Not every operation
You know successful
But there's a number of operation
Where it's really clear that
The Germans
Believed
What they were trying to sell them
And then it happened
Effect on the
So it did help to save lives
It did help to win the war
In the story of the Trojan Horse
After a grueling 10 year war
The Greeks pretend to give up and sail away
Leaving behind a giant wooden horse
Which the Trojans dragged back into their City
As a victory trophy
At night
Italy
Greek fighter as which has been hiding inside the horse
Creeps out
When is able to capture the city of Troy
Victory
My deception
That deception wouldn't have worked very well in World War II
Ghost armies technique
Probably wouldn't be very useful in today's comp
For obvious reasons we can get the Army to tell him what kinds of
They're doing these days
But you can be sure they're doing some
Something because
What this guy said
Deception of the enemy is of course as old as War itself
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
Jim Ingle
Katie's dad
For his help editing in fact-checking this week
Rick Beyer and co-author Elizabeth sales forthcoming book is called the ghost Army of World War II
Full of amazing images and so many more details about specific operations performed by the ghost Army
It'll be out
On April 28th
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
Architecture Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Ubuntu show in Lex on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify
But the ghost Army is haunting the pages of 99% invisible
A 99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com