99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Since the early 1500s when Sir Thomas More coin the word Utopia
Probably well before then
People have been thinking about
How to design their ideal Society
Maybe it's one that doesn't use money
One that
Drops the traditional family structure in favor of
Raising children collectively
1 to check
That's producer Delaney Hall getting ready to visit a sort of utopia
And before she left she packed her bag
Tested her recording equipment
Grab a few extra packs of double a batteries and
I'm just going to fill up
Selected tab of water
And then thoroughly washed every item of clothing that she was bringing with her
Have a
Box of baking soda
Dumping some of it in this
Tub of water
Be more specific I soaked my clothes in a tub of baking soda for 48 hours
Showered with dr. Bronner's unscented soap for 2 weeks
Before I left
Old pair of jeans and putting them into
Delaney reports for the show state of the reunions every episode is about a different place so she travels a lot
But she doesn't usually go to these kinds of extremes to get ready
But this is an unusual reporting trip I'm about to go on
I'm headed to an isolated community in Eastern Arizona
On the outskirts of a small town called snowflake
And the people who live there have given me very special instructions for how to get ready
Because for some people in Snowflake
Utopia just means not being physically sick
Community people who live just outside the small rural town
The medical condition called MCS multiple chemical sensitivity
Intolerant to laundry detergent perfume cigarette smoke car exhaust commercial cleaning products
Community designed around keeping that sort of stuff out people who have NCS can be seriously affected
Sometimes disabled by migraines muscle pain rashes nausea and fatigue
Studies have not shown a strong connection between chemical exposures and symptoms there's no real medical consensus
About what causes the illness and doctors disagree about whether symptoms are physiological psychological
Or both that means that people with MCS are often dismissed as well hypochondriacs
How do you find themselves without sympathetic Medical Care access to services that people with recognized disabilities
There are a subset of doctors who believe in MCS and treat it but most mainstream sza
Additions avoid the diagnosis and so a lot of people with the illness fall back on trial and error
Designing their diets habits and environment
Try and make themselves feel better
My first morning in Snowflake and this is really an incredible landscape very flat
Very dry you can see a long way in every direction and sky is very
The house is out here all built-in really simple Style
They have sheet metal walls pitched roofs
Delaney didn't go to snowflake to find out whether or not NCIS was Godin
Real
She went to learn how people have built new lives and homes designed to fit their very particular needs
Out there on the remote
Grassy plateau
Susan Malloy has short curly hair and a wide grin
Below freezing but all the windows in her small house are open
For people with MCs
Their home is the only environment they can really can
Control
I'm suddenly very aware of
No
I'm worried I didn't prepare well enough
Susan offers me a cup
Coffee
Sure
And then
Just like I worry
I smell cigarettes
What would you like me to do
I'm not quite sure
Okay I'm going to get close to you for just a second okay sir
Maybe
Okay
Reminder
Something else to wear no not at all
Glad you have gift
Okay Delaney is not a smoker but this is the level of Susan sensitivity
Susan is at the heart of this
Community
People have described her to me as a fairy godmother and the Queen
She works with curious Outsiders
Girls like me
She also attends conferences on
Disability Rights
Spends hours each week answering phone calls from people who are sick
She's healthier than lots of her neighbors
But that hasn't always been the case
For me it was just
Real fast
I felt this
Just bizarre feeling in my head
My sinuses and
The palette
Of my mouth and my throat
Foreclosed
Cousins living in San Francisco when she first got sick
Back in the early 90s
Your sensitivities began to
Skate witches
Is pretty typical for the illness
Are allergy to chemicals go into a sensitivity to food
Clothing
Benelect
TriCity
Telephones computers kitchen appliances
How much everything
Became toxic
Furniture had to go
The rug had to go
Had two girlfriends come over and and take my clothes
Susan slept on Friends porches Inn
In her car and her parents
At her sickest
She couldn't even drink chemically treated tap water
And her mom put buckets in the yard to gather rain
Then a friend with MCS invited her to visit snowflake
Rural high altitude
Community with good clean air he discovered it a few years before
Driving around the country trying to find a place where his symptoms wouldn't be so severe
And when Susan visited
For me the Improvement was so radical
You know what you get out of car you feel better
I can walk you don't need the oxygen tank
Here's your speech is clear
I didn't exactly want to move here but my body said yeah we're moving here
Felt like a pass
Like a journey between two different worlds
Like in the old days for someone to get on a ship and go to the United States from
Ireland
They didn't really want to leave it if they weren't able to make it
Anymore until they took
Switch respingada on a ship
Think it feels a little bit like that to me
Gradually more people move to snowflake they came from all over and engineer from Denmark
Marketing director from Toronto a chef from the Philippines
Teacher from San Francisco
Now
There are about three dozen household scattered across this area
All United by this illness
And they're not the first people in history to move
Forever
15 people who had to relocate because
Of particular Medical
Problems or health reason
In fact the history of medical migration
This part of the country goes back a long ways
A hundred years ago doctors encouraged people with tuberculosis to Head West for the same clean dry air that
That brought Susan here
Ended up in Arizona
Attensity sprouted up across the state
And locals gave them a nickname
Runners
Because of the hacking cough that characterize the illness
So this is not an uncommon
Experience for human beings
Right now it's our turn for it
For the new guys
But the complicated thing about this illness is that it's so unknown
Some doctors would argue that the
This place isolates people
Pushes them deeper into their sickness
All the talk about diets and remedies and building techniques only reinforces what might be better treated in other
What Susan told me this place saved
Your life
Kitchens the same
The bedroom
Things the living room
I mean I basically live in wenzhou
Susan. This house herself with help from friend
The people here in Snowflake might be the closest thing there is to a NCS think-tank and they develop a building technique
Snakes that help manage their sensitivities
That means using quote-unquote safe materials
Like ceramic tile or concrete floors instead of carpeting which traps chemical odors
Susan also used foil-lined sheetrock
Which covers her walls
Give me the whole inside of her
Her house is silver sheen
I just couldn't afford to risk
Paint
You know if you get the wrong kind of paint your whole house
Unlivable maybe forever or maybe at least for several months
A couple years
But maybe the most striking thing about the
This house is the way that Susan has isolated most of her Electronics in a separate room
What you can completely shut off from the rest of the
The house
That's because many people with MCS also experience sensitivity to electricity
You designed it pretty strategically with that room in mind of the room at the front of the house
Is the one where you electricity
Comes into one corner of the house
It all comes in right
Right over there
And the rest of the house doesn't have to be as effective
She keeps her television and a VCR in the
A separate room
And she's constructed a thick window to watch TV through
Well keeping the equipment ice
The television is
An ancient
One I mean by today's standards
And it's
Really nothing special other than it's the old
I don't want to have
New chemical emissions
In my house
You know from Plastics and so forth if there's any way around it
This one is old and aired out and
This glass
She in front of it is
To keep the fuse
In that room
Like an open the front door
And let the fumes
Go out
Without contaminating the inside of my house
The house is modest but you can tell how much it means to suzhou
She shows me every corner and every adaptation
It's her Safe Haven
And there are lots of people who are desperate to move out here to live in a little place just like this
When Susan's phone rings it's usually not a good sign
I don't get calls from people for whom everything is going great
You know
Hello
Hi
Charles Place
Is I'm available cuz I am could not be doing worse
I've got to get out of here
Skin is literally burning and bleeding from the portion
Susan gets a few calls like this a week
From runners
People who are moving from place to place trying to find somewhere that feels safe
Snowflake isn't the only community of it
It's kind but it's one of the largest and most established
Don't that doesn't mean there's room for everyone
I'm sorry but there is someone living there
Susan Trax a limited housing in Snowflake
And she breaks the bad news when she can
How about you never know I'm waiting for a miracle to happen
I don't have any miracles
I wish I did
I know you're not asking me to get off but I need to go get some commotion on right now
I'm afraid that's what a typical College
Looks like
You know people who are real sick where they are and need to be in it
Another kind of Housing and there isn't any
Over the years enough people with MCS have come to snowflake that the wider Community has adapted to them
At least a little bit
There's a real estate agent who helps people find MCS friendly property
There's an organic food store which
Just kind of unusual for a rural town of 5000
The owner there will sometimes shop for people with MCS and leave the groceries outside for them
I got so they don't have to
Coming to the store
Which smells like incense
And then there's the dentist
And my EI patients usually come in through the backdoor they wait in their cars
We have a separate and she's right here
VI is short for environmental illness another term for multiple chemical sensitivity
Melissa is a hygienist
. Sierra Dental
Sierra Dental regularly sees about 40 patients
With MCs
They've adapted their practice
To make it friendly to pee
People with sensitive
And I usually tend to see him at 8 in the morning
Because that's
I haven't wiped my room down with chemicals
Because I did it the night before
So I don't have to worry about him smelling the cavicide wipes which is what we use in 10 oz
Melissa also shuts down the X-ray machine opens the windows
And turns off the fluorescent light
Patience
As far as polishing teeth
Are you playing
Thomas
Stone
The other thing we do share in the office
Is
We don't use fabric soft
I actually use a natural
Laundry soap will use a lot of us to
No sprays no smelly lotions things like
Like I understand it a lot of them they're really
Sick because of
Chemicals and electronics in all sorts
The things
Lots of people are skeptical when they first hear about the illness
But mostly just kind of rolled with it
She did research
She believed her page
Complaints
Chief and sympathized a little bit I remember as a kid I spent in a Vermont we went to the
Yankee Doodle Candle factory
And it was my only experience with a migraine headache
What's smelling all of those
The smells
And I don't have
Chemical sensitivities but being around all of those smells all day long was
What's the worst headache
My life
So I equate that with all the time with the
We're back on Seasons porch and she's looking out over the lands
She knows that this community.
Depends on the tolerance
Accommodation
Have people like Melissa
All it takes
Is
1 family building a gas station
Out there on the road
And a lot of acid have to move
In a little while Susan has a date with another friend in the community
She's going to read a book
Which means she'll stand outside his house
Hold the book up to his window
And turn the page
He's too sensitive to let her or even the book itself
Oceanside
It makes life here in Snowflake
Seem sober
Precarious
It is fragile
I know it
And
I treasure it
For being here at all
So I am hypervigilant
About
Always hoping that nothing's going to happen to us
Always having that we're going to keep getting away with
This life that we built here
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Delaney Hall from the public radio show state of the reunions
Did you like great stories about places in the communities that people create
And I'm guessing you do
So true is the show for you
Find out more at state of the reunions
Dot-com
Our show is produced by Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce are the offices of
Arcsin in beautiful downtown chemical-free
Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 99
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
The world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
If you like the stories in this show you get more and more and more of it on Facebook Twitter and Tumblr but 99p ihq is
That 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com