99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the beginning
There was design
At least according to the designer and author will live well
Design is the oldest human discipline
Older than Humanity itself
And will believe
But in this oldest
Of all the disciplines
Everything ever designed
Spaceships
Building
Pyramids weapons clothing artwork
Everything
Can be traced back to a single designed object
Design.
This is as close
To a Genesis object
Ask me that
I need this is where it all began
Set design had its own Cosmos series
This would be episode 1
I think
This is
The greatest
Grandis
Like most interesting story
In the field of design
It has it all
Mystery intrigue
Controversy
We are on the edge of our seats well
Wait for it I need like that the drum roll
The first designed object
Was the issue in hand.
The Australian hand-axe ladies and gentlemen
Actually it doesn't look like an accident
There's no handle
The new metal
Honestly it should be called the issue lien
Hand Rock
Zantac
Is made a rock and its teardrop-shaped
And if you join your hands together is it
Despres fingers together this is almost the exact shape
Incise
The term Australian refers to where the first
Specimens were found which was a dig site
Instinct actual France
But they've been found in a lot of other places
Define the issue lien tools
Are found almost exclusively in Africa
In Europe in South Asia
I'm Terrence Deacon and professor
Of biological anthropology
At the University of California Berkeley
Berkeley has a whole bunch of samples of these Hannah
Another hand axe
You can see that it's not quite so symmetric and
Nice little sharpest Edge
Summer sharp all along the entire perimeter sum art
Summer perfectly symmetrical and summer not
But those hand axes in the UC Berkeley basement aren't actual primordial hand axes
These are replicas made by gradle
Current students
There have been courses here in which
One of the challenges is to make tools
In the point of this challenge for the graduates to
It's a see how involved this process is and making one of these pointy rocks
The way the early humans would
You break off big pieces
With large
Rocks in large strike
When you break off these little edges
To Shake The Edge
Smaller pieces
I just love the image of a bunch of grad students sitting around smashing run together and sometimes I have to do it for a while
Someone weekly practice at it can make
Hi-end accents something like 15 minutes to half hour to make a really fine tool
Probably talking about
Asurion and access
Required time effort and skill to make
They were a product of a design process
The first
Design process
The ensuing hand-axe was not the first
Tool the first
Basically a rock that is
Chips with just a handful of
Major strikes to produce a few sharp edges not very sophisticated tools
All these old lawn tools
Are Homo habilis ancestors use them to
Ash open bones and scrape me off of them around 2 million years ago
Do this kind of technique
Isn't unique
The humans
This can be done
Even by South American monkeys the capuchin monkeys
Get these large
Pine nuts
And they have Hammerstone
The bacon men
List append Bash these things until they open them
What they want to achieve
Buffet
I actually simply go out and select something
Helicopter
Rather than actually design something
Chimpanzees in examples stripping
Believes in the side branches off a little princess
They can stick it down
A termite nest and get the termites to buy it
I asked they can eat the termites that way
So this requires cunning
Yes but crafts
Not really
So early humans understood the importance of oldowan tools
So sharp Rock
And they realize that they could fashion more precise tools by sharpening rocks
Purposefully
So it's not just adventitious products
China's planned production
Spandex he's the first designed object
At least we can find
If there were any wooden tools that are human like ancestors made
Those have long since to centigrade
But even if there are other example
Hand axes are really significant
With issuing a hand actually issue lien
Technology
Showing up
We suddenly now fine people
Making people I say they're their ancestors making tools
With an end in mind and making them in advance
They almost certainly have to carry them with them
They don't just make them on the spot there they take time to make them they take
Thought to make them
And you're shaping them
Towards a particular shape
For some particular use
Which we today don't
We don't know
We don't
Know how they were used
That's the crazy mystery here so
This is where we get into the entry
That will live well again
Dirt their ideas right so smart people.
Are working on the problem and in there are like
Theories
There are more than free if you want me to talk about more theories I can talk about more theories but I'll stop at 3 unless you tell me otherwise
Will ledwell has
3 favorite
As to why the hand-axe.
Theory number one
Right of the powers uses the multi-tool
Set theory number one is that the SLI hand-axe
Was the original Swiss Army knife
Primarily used for butchering me
But it's also good for breaking up in knots and digging up grubs or whatever else he might be
And so the strength
Of this Theory
Is it fits with where patterns do you see on a lot of the hand axes that are found
Here's the problem with Theory number one
In some cases the full perimeter of the axe is sharp and remember this is a hand axe
Holding
Palm of your hand
So if you wanted to use it
There be this sharp blade digging into your palm
Another problem with everyone
Is that some of the axes are symmetra
Which is a lot of extra effort
That isn't really necessary if you're just using it to break up nuts or cut meat
And so to address some of those problems
We get into Theory number two
Nothing this is my personal favorite
The sexy handbags
The current quote
Sexy handaxe Theory
Proposes that these tools didn't have I used
Per se
They were created mostly as a way of showing off
Like the feathers of a peacock
The goal wasn't to create a functional tool
Butchering
Are symbolic tool
For me to track
And making these things is really really hard
Why spend so much time doing it
Unless you're showing off
Raintree showing the opposite sex what you can do
But there are a lot of experts were doubtful of this one including Anthropologist Terrence deacon
Not all of them are beautiful
Teardrop shape
They weren't all that nice and neat and symmetric
There is one interesting except
I mean one
One beautiful 350000 year old exception
Bottom of a kind of whale
In southern Spain
It looks as though
Bodies were tossed down here and one of these it found in this
This whale so to speak
Make it just up
Cave well
Is a hand axe was made of
A kind of
Rose quartz looking Stone
Really pretty
It doesn't look like it was ever used
I'm not a sexy hand axe
But this may be the first indications that they're beginning
To sort of
Grieve over the death of someone
What if there is some kind of ritual issue here
Wichita beautiful
Hand axe
It's about playing a role
Okay
The world's third favorite Theory
It's still a really fun one
Number three is pretty fun
Number 3 in in a closed follow onto my favorite too sexy hand-axes the killer frisbee
And so in the killer frisbee Theory
Right hand axes were made to be
Projectiles
The throne in the passionate
Discus in the Olympics
A lot of hand axes are found near Riverbank
Hunters would wait for herds of animals to come and then
They wouldn't taxes
This might not be enough to make a Kill
But the stones would name a few and give the hunter is an opportunity to charge
This hypothesis right explains
Why it looks the way it does right by the hand axes sharp all the way around
Wyatt so symmetrical Wyatt so aerodynamic
William not all of them are
Sharp all the way around and perfectly symmetrical
He was like a frisbee was use like a weapon
I really have my doubts about that
I like the Swiss Army knife
In part because it looks like it's a one tool fits all
It was clearly something that we see
Again and again and again and again all over
Other world
That means it was very effective
And if you don't find a lot of diversity of tools it was almost certainly use for more than one thing
But whatever the hand axe was used for it must have been a really good job because
This basic design was used for a mind-blowing Lee long time
Xiamen adult
We're literally teaching hominy children
How to make hand axes for more than a million years
Passing the knowledge down from generation to generation
Until you compare that to any modern product life cycle
Write it just crazy long
So long that our human mind can barely wrap our heads around it
Understanding of history is only what may be five thousand ten thousand years
That's our biggest understanding of History
Sonia stayed the same
Culture that was constant
For a million years
That's pretty remarkable
And no matter what the issue in hand axe was actually used for
Just the mere existence of a designed object that is so old
Has huge implications
I often have students or colleagues think that designs a new field
Like a 20th century invention
When in fact
It's the most
Ancient
A ball academic
Before there was mathematics or engineering or science
Where art or music
Her poetry
Before this philosophy literature religion or
Or even language
There was design
99% invisible is produced by the crackerjack team of Avery trufelman Katie mingle the same Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Whether you're building websites for doing industrial design architecture
To have that sense of History
I have those routes to music
Special things to will live well for bring the whole hand axe story to us Wills book Universal principles of design is one of my
To go to recommendations for books about the sign
Insightful
Quick-hit Encyclopedia of all kinds of design principles I consulted all the time but highly recommended
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced at the offices of Arc
An Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds game
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
X-Men episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
You can keep up with all the comings and goings at 99 Pi on Twitter Facebook Tumblr Instagram and Spotify if you say hi
We usually say hi back
And if you're chipping away your own hand-axe I recommend listening to an old 99% invisible it's the perfect length
Per hand axe making
At 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com