99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I swear to fulfill to the best of my ability and judgment
Discover
A man must have a code
Doubt
The fundamental ethical precepts of medicine is that doctors
First Do no harm
Is led the American Medical Association to adopt opinion 2.06
Of the AMA code of medical ethics in 1990
An individual's opinion of capital punishment is the personal moral decision of that individual
A physician
As a member of a profession dedicated to preserving life
When there is hope of doing so
Should not be a participant
In a legally authorized
Execution
It goes on from
Lawyers have an Ethics code journalists have an Ethics code
That shouldn't surprise you that Architects do as well
The relevant ethical standard from the AIA that were discussing vs 1.4
Human rights
Members should uphold human rights
In all there
Professional endeavor
A number of Architects have taken a stance that there are some buildings that just should not have been built
And they don't just mean the ugly
Dubai design
They violate standards of Human Rights Greenspan
He's talking about prison
Specifically prisons that keep inmates alone in cells with little to do
Minimal human contact
Inmates have names for these places
The Box
Work the Bing
On the outside we know them as supermax
Or
The shoe
That's Shu for security housing unit
Now it's Up For Debate as to whether or not the shoe is solitary confinement
Recent being and this is something weird we found while researching the story
There is no legal definition for solitary confinement
The UN doesn't have one to Department of Justice doesn't have one
And neither does the cdcr
The California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation
Cdcr maintains that no prisoners in California are kept in solitary confinement
Has a quote
Segregation unit
But a number of groups
Including Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch
Do call the shoe solitary confinement
And there's a lot of controversy surrounding one shoe at a northern California prison
Call Pelican Bay
Pelican Bay State Prison was designed by San francisco-based Architecture Firm KMD
Candy declined to speak to us for this story
But Jim Miller and architect we can do you work on Pelican Bay
Did talk with architect magazine about prison
He said
Quote
The inmates have no contact with other inmates during the vast majority if not all of the day
They are only allowed out of their cells for very short periods of time for constitutionally required exercise.
Life inside of a shoe
Is 22 to 23 hours a day
80 or so square feet
Nancy Molina radio reporter with life of the law managed to get access to the shoe in Pelican Bay State Prison in
California
She went inside one of the cells and had an inmate Robert Luke
Describe the room
Basically
The cell I don't know what size 6 by 9 or 6 by 12 whatever it is
That
Your bunk is your living room the center of it
You're walking area and
Two steps to the right is your
Bathroom
The official measurements are actually 7 and 1/2 by 12
It's not a space
That's designed to keep you
But it's not these architectural features that concern humanitarian activist
Stan psychiatry
It's the amount of time many prisoners spend in that cell
Without any meaningful activity
Long-term solitary confinement which is
Either for months or years or it goes on forever
As a Pelican Bay
Connected with absolute idleness that is the individual socially isolated to the extreme
But also has nothing meaningful to do
And this causes human breakdown this destroys people as human beings
Terry Cooper's is a psychiatrist
Who specializes in forensic
That is he's an expert on the intersection of Mental Health
In criminal justice
He served as an expert witness on more than 20 class action lawsuits concerning prison conditions
He says there's a whole Litany of the facts
It's solitary can have on a purse
Massive free floating anxiety paranoid ideas tomney depression and suicidal
Thoughts of reprimanded their eyes are destroyed
Because if you do not look
At a distance
Prolong lengthen
Time your eye deteriorate
They have concentration and memory problems and I ask if they re
And they'll say no because I can't remember what I read three pages earlier
Mounting anger
And they almost universally report that they're terrified that their anger will get out of control they'll be in Mortar
Trouble in the novel longer-term
In solitaire
And that's just for a normal stable person
Four prisoners with a history of or predisposition to mental illness
Solitary can bring on a break
Now again there is no universally accepted definition of solitary confinement
And like the law reporter Nancy MacLean it says that compared to other prisons she has visited
There are actually some good design elements in the Pelican Bay shu
Inmates can get natural light from skylights outside of their cells
What's drifts into the doors made of perforated metal
These Forest doors allow for inmates to communicate with
Each other even though there are no lines of sight
To any prisoner from within the cell
But on the other hand cells don't have Windows
Inmates never get to see the horizon
The only time prisoners get to leave the cell is to visit the shower
Or the exercise.
And the exercise yard is an empty windowless room
Not much bigger than a cell
20 foot high concrete walls
Animal many prisoners in the shoe have a cellmate
Terry Cooper
Says sharing a cell is often worse than being alone
So if that's not solitary confinement per se
You could call it a kind of
Binary
And all of this taken together
Some people call torture
In 2011 Juan Mendez the UN special rapporteur on torture
Said anything over 15 days
15 days in solitary confinement is a human rights abuse
Not various other commentators have said that means it's torture
15 days says the UN
Is the point at which people in solitary can begin to have a reputable
Psychological.
I don't actually like the 15-day standard some people fall apart in two days
And what Terry Cooper's calls torture
Happens in buildings specifically designed to maximize the isolation or
Quote unquote segregation
Of prisoners for the duration of their time in the shoe
So if it is the ethical code of Ark text
Promote human rights
What is their responsibility to the people who are incarcerated
And they're building
Did Argentina the military regime torture people in a former Auto Body
That was one of their big torture
I'm not going
Nobody's going to say that the architecture design the auto body shop or somehow responsible
Are you at the car mechanics we just own it or no
This is Raphael Sperry but
When
Solitary confinement
I practice that requires a certain kind of space and when your
Specifying the space exactly for that and making sure
And all the doors can be operated without you know seeing another human being that the outdoor space
This is going to be one that occupied by one person at a time
There's nowhere
What group of people tax
Be together
What happened
Then that is
It's the design at 10
When used as intended
Human rights violations will result
Raphael Sperry is an architect here in San Francisco
And he's the president of a group called a DPS are Architects designers and planners for social responsibility
A few years back Raphael have been following the news from Guantanamo Bay
And reading up on mass incarceration in the US
Not necessarily as an architect
Per se just as a civic-minded social justice oriented
Kind of guy
And then one day in 2010 he saw an article in the San Francisco Chronicle
About the we design
San Quentin prison in California
So yeah the chronicle actually ran a picture that was supplied by the Corrections Department that was the cad model
A kind of three-dimensional floor plan
The execution chamber
Suite of rooms
Sounds like
They're using the same tools
That I use
To make
Residential additions for people to make schools
Only this product is going to kill people
That was totally
Seen the remodel of the death chamber was the catalyzing event but you could argue that there's a difference between designing a death room and does
Designing a shoe
But Sperry views both as a moral and in violation of the human rights that architect
Swear to uphold
Raphael Sperry wants architect
Extend the profession of architecture as a whole at least in the US
To stop building shoes or any structures that are designed
For long-term solitary
Confinement
Or are designed to put
People to death
He's not talking about all prisons or jails just the ones were isolation is baked into the physical structure
Like the AIA architect design shoe
At Pelican Bay prison
Pelican Bay State Prison is
Way up in Northern California near the Oregon border
Hours
Any major city
It opened in 1989
The house the so-called worst of the worst
Suspected gang members
And people who are seen to pose the greatest threat
The officers
Another inmate
It was modeled after prison in Arizona and has since inspired design
Other prisons across the country
Even buildings in Guantanamo Bay
Life the laws Nancy MacLean head corrections officer lieutenant
Graves described his take on the purpose of the shoe when she visited Pelican Bay
In 2012
The key to making this design work
In our favor
Is it is not just
The design of it
But how it's managed
And historically Pelican Bay is is done a very good job of managing
The worst of the worst in the state
This
Prison was designed and built
To manage
5% of the California
Prison population
Those were the 5% that were causing the majority of crimes
In the other prison
Throughout the state
Pelican Bay or any prisoners mayonnaise is the determining factor in what life is like
For prisoners
The way these prisons are used isn't the only way there
It could be you
Prison management could decide that Shu prisoners
Could be allowed to go outside of the building and secure gated area or the exercise yard could be repurposed as a communal.
We're just making these up as far as I know these have never been considered
Sperry
The key here is design intent
Pelican Bay is managed the way it is
And prisoners day-in-day-out are the way they are
Cuz that's how architects
Imagine the place to work
During the design process
Insperity along with the ADP Sr
Architects designers and planners
Social responsibility
Say it's time to stop building the prisons that are designed
For what he see that solitary confinement
Or any other kind of torture or exit
It would seem like the least that architects
To do with that to demonstrate our commitment to public health safety and well-being is to say when you enter one of our bills
It's not intended
The kill you
Which brings us back to the rather minimal statement in the AIA code of ethics and professional condo
Ethical standard 1.4
Member should uphold human rights
In all their professional endeavors
That's it
Human rights
Refers to the international
That is built up around the United Nation
And strongly supported by these ads
Like Amnesty International and human rights
Human rights is not a term that United States courts use and it's not a term in the US.
Black Sea refers to something even bigger than
Bayside membership
Support the US
Sperry and the ADP Sor are petitioning the AA to adopt a new Claws and its ethics
Quotes
Members shall not design spaces intended for
Iqushion
Word for torture or other cruel inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment
Including prolonged solitary confinement
And so if you happen to find yourself in prison you should know that because your prison was designed by architect
You won't be subjected
Cruel inhuman kratom
Punishment for that killed their
So far the San Francisco chapter of the AIA has recommended The Proposal
Which point out here that the AIA San Francisco was instrumental in the creation of 99% invisible
But it doesn't give us any money or servant in the editorial function
Is the NAIA National adopt this amendment
It will become part of the ethics
Code for all AIA Ark
Virtually every practicing Arkansas
In the United States
Regardless of how you feel about prisons
Rehabilitate people or weather
We should lock him up
Throw away the key
It's important to keep in mind
But these attitudes change over time
From the 1890s to the 19th
The US had a really different take on Prison
The emphasis was on curing or rehabilitating
People from a life of crime
Granted there were some really terrible things that happened in prisons during that time
But the emphasis Italy
Was on getting prisoners to become productive members of
Society again
A big shift happened with the War on Drugs
Which a lot more people to jail
And then there was the violence of the prison riots or uprising
What happened to the 1970
So from the point of view of prison officials
Who are in charge of jailing these populations
Blocking people up in their cells most the time
Started looking like a good Ops
Hence
Miss you
But when you create a building with a very
Stream design intent
Little variability
You're locking prisoners into that current mindset for the lifespan of the prison
Tamms Correctional Center a supermax prison in Illinois
Closing early 2013 to make up for
A state budget for
It turns out how Tina shoot prisoner is nearly twice as expensive as housing
Eternal popular
Inmate
Widespread budgetary pressure and
Possibly the influence of anti solitary confinement activist
Is also causing state governments to reduce the number of supermax prisoners in Mississippi
Main and Colorado
Raphael Sperry may find he has a strange and Powerful Ally in this fight.
Stop barking
Text building Superman
Prisons
And that is
Broke
State government
But even if the Mets filleti's fall out of fashion
Three says it's important to establish ethical guidelines that distinguish shark
Profession
It's professional ethics that set a profession aside from other occupation
When you join a license
Profession
Your group has a monopoly
To provide services
But in that sector
9 buddy Ellis
Can be an architect in in fact
My day is Big activities
Is controlling people were holding themselves out as art
In exchange for the public
Monopoly that we get as a group
We as a group have to adopt the professional ethics
That put the public interest first
And the way that we do that is a princess
The doctors do that
To say we're not going to do anything to injure any of
Potentially
This episode of 99% invisible is a special co-production the podcast life of the law
You can hear their show at life of the law.org
This story was produced by Sam Greenspan Nancy Mullane Kaitlin Prest
Julia Barton Shannon Heffernan Ashley Ann krigbaum and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
An American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson bad to take laxatives modify your
Diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but I've loads of more information and a link to buy
Life of the law and 99% invisible
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortals
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com