99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I'm down at the bottom of the hill away from the highway and I'm about to
Cross really old railroad bridge not an active railroad anymore that's jacquot Alico wandering around the
New Hampshire Woods Security View
He's about 10 miles north of the state capitol off Interstate 93
Pretty out-of-the-way place there no signs or markers on the road indicating something special is there
But he's found something
So you get out of this little Island
And the railroad tracks go straight across but what you really notice is this Epic
Looking
Granite Monument
In the middle of the island
It looks a lot like a monument you'd see in a city park except it's on a forested island in the middle of a river
It is enormous
It's 30 ft tall
Wow
It's all granite and on top of a tall pedestal there's a woman she's wearing this down that's fall
Falling off her shoulders
In her right hand she has a tomahawk
And in her left hand she has a fistful of Scouts and on the back of this thing going to run around to the back
Back here is the inscription
Now let's pause for just a second here
If you are a regular listener to the show
You know how I feel about plaque
And always reading them
The reason being that blacks tell stories sometimes they tell really amazing stories
If you can decipher them
March 15th 2 30th 1697
The Wharf
Tomahawk f***** and infanticides were a Haverhill
The ashes of wigwam campfires at night
I have 10 of the tribe
Are here
I got another man
Yeah not a lot of detail there
Honestly the whole island was strange to me
Kind of creepy actually
Not very well kept up this enormous imposing statue with the Erie plaque
The scouts
What's crazy is this statue was erected in 1874 making it the oldest Monument dedicated
12 woman
In the US
So you think someone would come out here and at least over the grass
Well what I learned is that plaque does tell a story though not an obvious one
And I learned there's a good reason why the grounds are neglected
In fact what to do with this Historic Site
Has become a bit of a problem
And it all has to do with the woman in the monument
And what she did
The story starts about 50 miles south of the monument in a town called Haverhill Massachusetts
I went down there and met up with a local historian named Tom spitaleri
In the parking lot of a Dunkin Donuts
How you doing
Jack
Tom nice to meet you too
Tom is a die-hard New Englander
I'll tell you he's wearing a Boston Red Sox jacket on top of a Boston Celtics Jersey
On top of a New England Patriots
T-shirt
Sure
Everywhere we drive in Haverhill Tom see signs of New England past
Particularly from Colonial times and to the time of Hannah.
What time will Royal in what some historians
Most people would know it as the French Indian War
What King Philip's King George's in the Seven Years War
In the 1600s
New England was a war zone between the French the British and the Native Americans by the end of that Century disease
These and War would wipe out most Native Americans in the Northeast
In Haverhill was
The Wild West
I mean
It sounds funny
Putting in today's contents that's what it was we were the album
There was nothing north of us
There was nothing but Wilderness around making it an easy target for attacks by Native Americans
Bands of Native Americans had shifting alliances with the British and the French
The French paid Abenaki used to abduct Brits and bring them 2K back
Then the French would sell these captives back to the British
It was a slave trade
Xiaomi this area was
Constantly
In 1697 a woman named Hannah Dustin was recovering from delivering her 8th
Child
What happened to Aki's rated Haverhill
They killed and captured dozens of colonists and burned buildings that's what the word faggets on the monument refers to
A faggot was a bundle of sticks used to fuel the fire
During the raid Hannah duston husband was outside with seven of their kids
Defending the homestead and his children
But Abenaki is entered the house and abducted Hannah her newborn baby girl that her nurse Mary Neff
The captives were marched North to the Wilderness and shortly after leaving April when Hannah's baby wouldn't stop crying
One of the Abenaki smashed it against a tree
That's where you get the word infanticide
From The Monuments plaque
They kept walking North
Most likely they were heading to the Outpost
That's up in Quebec
At some point the war party handed Hannah Dustin and Mary Neff to another group of Abenaki
A group made up of a couple families
She was sold
To those Native Americans
So the group of Abenaki that ended up with Hannah was made up of two fathers to mothers
A grandmother
A bunch of children
And I already had a white boy with them a kid named Samuel leonardson
Putin abducted from Worcester the previous year
Is it that makes three white captives
12 Abenaki
The whole crew across the Merrimack River to the island the one that now is the money man on it
And they set up camp for the night
In the middle of the night
Hannah Dustin made a decision
She rallied Marion Samuel and led them around the sleeping Evan Aki's
One at a time
They brought a hatchet down on the abenakis head
They killed 10 in total
Two men
Two women
6 children
And then before making their getaway
A scout
Each victim
2 Abenaki is made it out alive
The old woman who was injured
And a little boy
Hannah Marie and Samuel left the island in a canoe
It was a dangerous time of year to be on the river it would have been choked with icing
Full of Rapids
They traveled at night to avoid being seen
15 days after Vanishing Hannah Dustin and her companions landed in Haverhill
To the total shock of her husband or seven children
And everyone who ever lost a family member
To arraign
Hannah Dustin is the woman memorialized in the monument
The Scout she is holding in the Statue belong to the 10 people including six children
That she and her companions killed on the island
That statue isn't the only Hannah Dustin landmark in New England not by a long shot
There are others particularly in Haverhill where she live
Tom spitaleri took me on a tour
They just pull off here real quick this the Hannah duston rest are
This is speedy I always yeah this is it here he is Hannah Dustin Street
Obviously meme
Now we're at the Hannah duston Rock Monument Street got its name from The Monument that's there for Hannah Dustin
Boskone Avenue
Boscawen is the town in New Hampshire where the island is
Tell me even took me to an old Garrison house
Essentially
Where Hannah Dustin live
After her captivity
We do private tours in here
In a glass case is a piece of Hannah Dustin memorabilia I've seen on eBay
In the 1970s the state of New Hampshire commissioned Jim Beam
To make a Hannah duston whiskey decanter
It's an exact replica of the statue in New Hampshire
Down to the little bloody scabs in her hand
It's made of porcelain
Yeah that hits the floor goodbye goodnight
It's kind of
Sexy and provocative
Which popping that would never have happened back in 1697
Where you at remember this was in 1976 they did
It was about selling
Your selling booze with a sexy woman with scalps and an axe
Right and we don't even know what you really look like cuz there is no photographs
That whiskey decanter is from 1976 but the New Hampshire Historical Society still sells ajena.
Dustin bobblehead
And it's Museum shop
On the basis of bobblehead it says
Quote
The mothers
Revenge
You can probably see how these kitschy collectors items might
Feel offensive
In fact all the Hannah duston stuff and Hannah Dustin the landmarks are a problem for some people who know the whole story
But the whole story
That's a tricky thing to pin down
You gotta understand something with two handed
Is a lot of inter
And it's a lot of New England
Canada Sims kidnapping and Escape happen more than 300 years ago
And the story has been told and retold a lot
And actually the reason we know anything about it today
Has to do with the fact
That she scalped her victim
After Hannah came home her husband took her
Sea scallops down to Boston
To sell them
Now if you like me when you heard she had Scouts her victims you may have thought she had some kind of bloodlust
I thought scalping with something tribes did to wipe
People not the other way around
Turns out I was very
Very wrong
Colonial governments paid cash for Native American scalps heads and even hands
They would pay most for a man less for women
At least for a child
They would even pay Native Americans for the body parts of other Native Americans depending on who was Warren with whom at the
So Dustin had Financial incentive for scalping her victims
But if you're the reason we still know the story
When Hannah was in Boston selling her Scout she sat down with Cotton Mather
And he wrote her story down
His name might ring a bell
Cotton Mather was head of
The Protestant Church in New England
He had ties to the Salem witch trials
He was a
Fire and brimstone Minister traveled around giving sermons
These little Frontier Towns at Cotton Mather visit that they were filled with these shell-shocked colonist who had missing family
Members from Native American raids
Mother told Dustin story again and again to wrap churchgoers building Dustin status
As a heroine
Well I think the Hannah duston story has endured for so long
Because it's not just a story about
A woman who
Kill people
It actually
Has become a story about The American Nation at different points of time
This is Barbara Carter historian and professor at the University of Northern Iowa
It was a story about
The colonial battle against
Native Americans in the 17th century
It was a story
Justifying
The westward expansion of the United States in the 19th century
Traits
And
In more recent years
It has been used as
A story
Domestically about culture wars really Qatar has researched how and why the Hannah Dustin monuments were built
And she said it really hit home just how far the story had traveled when I
Happened across a Salt Lake City
Mormon woman's newspaper
In the 1890s that started off by saying
Who has not heard of Hannah.
I mean Hannah Dustin was from Massachusetts
After her captivity Hannah Dustin lived in colonial obscurity
Jackson had seven more kids
And died at age 84
No one talked about her through the 1700s
She was forgotten
Until
In
The 18 teens in the 1820s
United States was a new nation
And a lot of
Intellectuals
At that point in time we're trying to create
A distinctly American
Can culture
And so they started telling American story
And trying to uncover American heroes and heroines
So the country's literary Elite Doug around for some good ole American stories
Hannah duston
Carter says if you were an American in safe 1865
Well the first place you might likely come across her
Would be when you opened your American history textbook in the school
You
Would also come across
Her story if you read famous American Writers like Hawthorne
For John Greenleaf Whittier
Poor Henry David Thoreau
Popular magazine
Newspapers essay collections children's books
Paintings
1800 Hannah Dustin was a household name
Johnny Appleseed Davy Crockett
Hannah Dustin
Bodhi Tree telling of the story
Something happened
People change the narrative to suit their purposes
It becomes a moral problem for Americans that Hannah duston killed children
Especially since I mean they weren't just children they were sleeping chilled
Writers omitted details embellished others and sometimes just made things up
Be completely left out the children she killed
Replacing them with Warriors
That Abenaki child that escaped
The writer said Dustin spared him intentionally which there's no evidence of
Most writers depicted Hannah duston as a sympathetic heroine
Is outraged mother seeking a justifiable Revenge
This was the era of manifest destiny
And then it is America's Destiny to inherit the land to seize it from people dump heathens
And Savages
That's when I think new englanders
Really started focusing on
Hannah Dustin more and more as the kind of heroin they should commemorate
In the mid eighteen hundreds as headlines screamed about the wars in the West
Monuments sprung up in the Northeast
When the monument on the Island was built in 1874
There were a thousand people present
Again it was the first Monument ever built to a woman in the US
But when the Indian Wars die down around 1900
Hannah duston dropped out of the national Spotlight again
But a subset of new englanders held onto her story
1905 Hannah Dustin descendants
Created the Dustin Family Association
They should have littered the landscape of Haverhill with
Memorial Boulders and millstones in her honor
At sites where she landed her canoe
Across from where she was buried
Apparently they put one up at one place where she turned around and looked back thinking that Indians might be
Following her on her way home then all the way into the mid-1900s there was a whole other layer of things named after
After those rocks and statues
A nursing home
A school
Streets
Overtime the namings petered out
Put the names themselves.
So did the Dustin family
Well my name is Cedric H Dustin jr.
I'm a test generation from Hannah
So would that make her my eighth grade grandmother I'm not sure I just haven't counted
Something like that yes Cedric is the vice-president and formerly the president of the Dustin family associate
Station
He's 88 and he's known about hannah dustan since he was a boy
To Cedric Hannah was a heroine
She was concerned about her own life
And those of us companions
And as such
Iceland
She was quite a lady to have two planets you did
And do the things she did
But basically I think this was self-preservation
Just make something clear the Dustin Family Association isn't lobbying for statues anymore
They mostly spend time tracing their lineage and they get together for a barbecue every summer
And Cedric Gaston says he understands why some aren't such a big fan of his grandmother a Generations or
But he is disappointed the statue in the island are in disrepair
Hannah's nose was shot off of the rifle there's graffiti
And the grass hasn't been mowed in years
When I was a young man I could have gone up there and cut the whole thing but right now
Sage won't let me do that
The state of New Hampshire
Should make
Could you
Are the fact that they have in their confines
The first
Statue ever erected to women in this country
Perhaps a new sign should be put at that location
Indicating that
As opposed to the scientists are now indicating the deed that happened on that island
So this is The Islander
This is the island
I went back to the island with a 30 ft tall Hannah duston
With someone who says he's avoided going out there
4 years
She doesn't look very
Brolic gym looks more like an opportunist
Angry oportunista went back and then bragged about it and then
History
Become history
This is Paul I'm Paul pouliot I'm the Sagamore
Roughly translated
The principal speaker
Of
The grand Council
Of the
Kasich band
The pannekoeken Abenaki people
Paul doesn't by cotton Mather's version of the story
The one where the Abenaki smashed Dustin's newborn baby against a tree
He said it doesn't match with other captivity stories of the era
We have
Many many accounts
The captive
Saying that
Being taken
I'll buy the Abenaki was not
A death sentence
Many went to Canada someone for traded back
Paul thinks Hannah's captors were probably treating her well will presumably as well as one can be
Retreat at the in captivity revered children so the idea of a warrior bashing a baby again
Against the tree as Cotton Mather story portrays
Sounds unlikely to him
It's impossible to know how the baby was killed or how Hannah Dustin was treated by her captors
And I hesitate to judge for my 21st century vantage point
What she should or shouldn't have done in order to make her Escape
But it's clear that the Hannah duston story
Is complicated
Paul thinks the monument to her should just be forgotten
I mean I really don't think this
This Monument
Should be preserved
Just let it
It's it's going to last you for Millennia so
It's unfortunate Eeyore's not going away
And that's the problem now
Hannah duston Monument
It's the one on the island and all the others
Are mostly fading relics in
Out-of-the-way places
But every few years some politician or
History buff for Native American points to one and says
Clean this thing up
Every time
People argue
Is she a heroine
Where she a villain
The same thing over and over and over
Just in the last couple months there's been renewed talk about the monument
People are suggesting putting up additional plaques that show the Abenaki history
Or changing the name from the Hannah duston Memorial state Historic Site
To the Kentucky guilin state Historic Site
But even something as small as cleaning up graffiti on the monument
For mowing the ground could be seen as taking a stance about whether Hannah Dustin deserved a monument in the first place
About whether she was actually a hero or villain
Before we left the island Paul pouliot said there was something he wanted to do
Off the Record
Sure no recording
Okay
He pulled out a dram and some tobacco
He paced around the monument twice
One time he scattered a little Tobacco on four sides of the statue
The other time he beat the drum and sang
He didn't want me to record the ceremony but he talked about it afterwards
We don't want to forget
Aransas to the Past
So we weaved alluring song
And we made an offering of tobacco
Kind of purify the ground
Where we were
Walking around the
And does it
Provide you with
Any relief for satisfaction to do that
What's what is
Appropriate
You know just asking Earth Mother
An awning or if Mother take him back
And
Understanding with some kind of closure
Spiritual closure if nothing else
Public decision on how to include Paul's ancestors in this history
Is private ceremony will have to be enough
For now the statue with her shot off nose and big hunting plaque
Remains neglected and crumbling
Which
Actually is probably the most accurate symbol of how we feel about Hannah duston today
Ambivalent about who she was
But not quite ready to let her go
March 15th 2 30th 1697
The Wharf Tomahawk faget and infanticides were a Haverhill
The ashes of wigwam campfires at night
In a 10 of the tribe are here
99% invisible West producer Suite by Jack Road Alika with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery troubleman
Tami Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce of the offices of
Of arcsin two step
Away from me 12th and Broadway BART stop
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa's talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flash podcast
Explore more and more about the show and interact with those of us who make it and fans just like you on Facebook
Twitter and Tumblr
If you want to see the statue of Hannah Dustin
Weather no shut off
That is at 99 PSI
The music you're listening to right now is by 99 Pi favorite okay akumi is a fantastic new album
Right now
Who plays in the background
Okay akumi music makes our show so much better
And that's saying that it can work
Anywhere everyday life
Trust me
It works
Go to okay akumi.com or follow the links on our website
99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com