99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There's this 80s movie that I have a real soft
What's on the theater in fact
Now I get to show it to my kids
It's a good one which is a good thing because when your kids like a movie
You end up watching it over
And over again
It's called The NeverEnding Story
The Neverending Story is a tale of a boy Adventurer name
He and his luck dragon name are trying to save the world from the
Onslaught of a terrible Force called
Nothing but the story also takes place inside of a book that being
Red by present-day boy
A boy name
Pretty much all the dialogue in the movie is written with exclamation
2 points anyway so Bassinger reader
Realizes that he is actually written into the story and it's up to him
To save the storybook world
Vashon wind-up defeating the nothing
Weather alert
By giving the empress
Set the fantasy world a new name
Give me a new name already chosen it
You just have to call it out
It's really hard to hear but he names her moonchild
I didn't know that for like 20 years
The power of one child imagination
Excellent
Seriously
There is a reason why I'm telling you this story
I want you to hold on to that idea
The name
Can defeat
Another
Okay with that in mind here's a producer Sam Greenspan
Hey Roman
Alright everyone I was
Names
Versus
Nothing
When I was a kid growing up in South Florida there was a
Beautiful green place where I always wanted to go play
Look perfect for a kid to run around and throw a ball
Was a flat mole on that just stretched into Infinity
But my parents wouldn't ever take me there
But with good reason it was inside of a giant Highway interchange my five year old self would never have been able to convince
My parents
This would be a good place to play
Because no responsible parent takes their kid to play catch-up a side of I-90
But I don't think I would even have known how to ask them to take me there because this
Place isn't really anywhere that we think of is
Being a
Place there's no name for
Let's call it a nothing
As a kid I couldn't look away from these
Perfect grassy areas
But as I grew up and became a driver I learned to ignore them like everyone else
So what happened
When you give that nothing today
That's totally what I'm doing I'm keeping things in the
This is my friend Graham
My name is graham coreil Allen
Grams in Artisan Baltimore and he has his project where he's trying to
Categorize and classify
All the different kinds of invisible public spaces
That we overlooked
Field Guide for how to spot them
It's part of the bigger project
Called new public site
New public sites is the investigation into some of the invisible
Sights and overlooked features of our everyday public
Spaces
Within cities that are
Not traditionally frames as public
Space
Is important to name these place
Because by giving these places
Succinct
Infinite
Poetic names
We can help
Start a discourse
About our public spaces
And how we want to Envision them for
I'm reminded of the never ending
Sebastian you must give me an a
See
Crank is the story where he puts his language to use
Describing incredibly boring pieces
Baltimore landscape
This is the first
And here we have
I remember the building
Stand here
Blue
Passing through it you can imagine
Acid ghost should a building be standing here would have to actually be
To pass through these walls and now it's the reverse
The building is The Ghost and where
We're passing through its walls
So Graham is really giving a tour of a vacant lot
Big Lot is one way to put it but notice what brand call
Avoid
And if you pull up his book The Grand published
Field Guide to Disney Publix I still see
Hang on
I don't have the book handy but here this is
Command app
Page 14
Void
A framed open-space imbued with a psychic presence of a former Mass
Andorra the profound immersion
Seductively in
Infinite nothingness
That certainly is a something
To find out more about these invisible public spaces
Ramen-san road bike to the edge of East Baltimore to look at a few
Like the one Sam Pine for the kid
It looks like there's a
Small party
We can actually see through right now at the foot of a
Of a small embankment that's probably 15 ft tall or so
We're going to walk up to the edge of this embankment
And meet a low line concrete wall
That will safely separate us from
The Cloverleaf
The traffic right Beyond this
This on ramp onto
Will be able to hopefully actually look into a freeway Eddie so let's let's do that right now
Raleigh traffic
You're looking at there's
Curved Highway
Exit ramp come in front of us and
Teen feet
20 feet ahead of us
This kind of disc
Almost like a Wilderness Area
Instant no trespassing nearby
Maryland transit
Authority
Correct with the invisible public space inside Graham turns to his Field Manual
Freeway Eddy
An interstitial
Fragment of space
Between intersecting curves
Of Highway pavement and there you have it that grassy non place I always wanted to hang out in as a kid
Now is the name
Freeway Eddy
Grams Field Guide to new public sites is full of new identities for these kind of places
So here we have median Refuge
A liminal zone of linear respite between parallels of turning traffic
Elevation Supple terrain providing the ideal incline
From which one make gays
Remote viewing distance Monumental isolation
Loose Parts movable materials
That invite playful reconfiguration
Loose Parts if you ask me triangle Crossing
A three-sided
Concrete platform or asphalt Zone
Providing Solace for Street crossing pedestrian we have
The overwhelming occupation of a surrounding soundscape by site generated
Groaning noise median Refuge of liminal pause of restraint empty signifier opposed
Or Paul absent of its original sign and or meaning
Sears news
If there's a common theme connecting these sites
Is there mostly the empty leftover spaces from.car Centered City Planning
Hot celebration of these nothing places
What's the hell Graham describes the
Beauty beauty beauty that one can enjoy spectacular and Sublime quite beautiful
This is a really beautiful spyware actually stating right now in
The long strip of sunlight that is past the it created by the space
Between these two elevated highways
We're at the
Chinatown Bus Stop across the street for
Turn the Baltimore Travel Plaza
Miles outside of the
The city
Perhaps
The most
Unglamorous way
Interbelt
And yet it's
It's a gateway
A week
It is quite beautiful
Space
What were
Here's what I got to draw the line
Because there's some freezers
Birds
You know there's I guess I'm intense
Masseria
Around here but
I mean
It's basically a big parking lot with
Diesel gas
Across the street is a
Subway
There's a
My bus stop
What what are your grounds for calling this beauty
Let's be clear here
You can call that
Grassy patch off the highway and a freeway Eddie all you want
But I can take my kids to play ball in one
A highway exit ramp at By Any Other Name is still just as unattractive and dangerous
This is beautiful
Because it's
It's a space that shared by so many and yet
It was completely undesign
This place was designed to the parking lot
And it's become
This huge
Nexus 4 people coming in and out of all time
It's so it's not necessarily what it looks like
It's more about what it represents
Yeah there's no denying that the experience of being in these new public sites
Actually pretty terrible
Flipagram the beauty is in there but
Potential
Sometimes everyday unremarkable spaces can become something more simply by virtue of
People being there
It's worth noting hear that zuccotti Park in New York City the birthplace of the Occupy Movement
With a privately owned space
And not a public park
So is your goal is
Finding new spaces for engaged democracy to happen as it is
Instagram
Then you need a way
To redefine the places in your neighborhood
That kind of activity can happen
I think it's important.
Not to fetishize
Public spaces as only existing in town squares or
Yosemite or Yellowstone or something like this not just the National Mall in DC for example but anyplace
Our everyday public space
Spaces that we all share
It's everywhere and we all have access to it these spaces
Are the places where this happens it doesn't just happen over the Internet it happens in physical spaces
New public sites are these physical space
That we can appropriate that we can make our own
If it's only for a temporary
You know demonstration and so be it but maybe it's for a farmers market
Maybe it's for a community garden
Maybe it's simply
Playground
Or
A place where we need to add a few benches to make it a better bus stop
But nevertheless
There's potential there and by giving it a name
Dubai starting that conversation
We can kind of get these ideas moving into reality
All comes back to a name against
Nothing
When you give a nothing a name
You can reimagine it
As of something
If we can create terms or these otherwise
Invisible experiences and places in
Things
That we all share that we all of us share these public space
Is new public site
It's a starting point for that conversation
By giving it a term we can then talk about it
And we all know what we're talking about
That's the first step
The second step is envisioning okay well how does this need to be improved in third step is how do we do that
The naming is where it starts
I don't know if I named anything runechild
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan with help from me Roman Mars it's a product of k a
Kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco in the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man
Handmade sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a kid is another remember all hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound makes
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God. Info
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
Find out more about Grandma's project and his mobile app which will help you identify and even make up new names for your new boo
Public sites in your own backyard check out our website is 99% invisible. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood we're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast. Com