99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage you're looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stuck
Love letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Oh there's a horse
And this is part of the show Sean Cole and that West 39th and 11th in Manhattan
And there's a horse a horse-drawn carriage of course there aren't just random horses wandering around me
They were there probably were at some point that I am actually going to meet a woman
Talk about Cavs
It's hard to believe now now this area is really industrial as a bus depot
This part of Manhattan the westernmost part between SE 34th and 39th streets
This
Was Cow Country late 19th early 20th centuries
Good cattle being herded across 12th Avenue which is now the West Side Highway
Nicola twilley is a woman I wanted to talk to about cows
She writes a Blog called edible geography
12th Avenue Pier showing Cowboys
Long little doggie
Packing District police would like the Meatpacking District
It was nicknamed abattoir place
Bone boilers hide stretchers and lard renders
If you can picture it would have
Disassembly line for every single part
Ikaw the council be ferried across the Hudson River from New Jersey
Here
Marching a few cows across 12th Avenue to the slaughterhouse was fine you can hold up traffic for that but then came
More and more folks in their carriages
And then the train came through
And cars all the sudden cows are in the way I mean cows move at a different pace and so
There were reports this epic cow jams
On 12th Avenue
I think it was his people about like
Cows and cowboys and cowgirl thing on 12th Avenue is no longer Modern Life
So this is what we're here to talk about today and I cannot wait neither here we go
That's why people invented things like the cow tunnel
How to have the best
Cowtown
Countertops
Whatever you say it's funny
Avenue have to love
Cow tunnels
Cow titles
In Manhattan or is Nicola called them in a piece she wrote for Gizmodo the Lost Cow tunnels of New York City
When Nicola says the people invented things like the count tunnel
For the purposes of this story that really could mean one of two things
Either people invented the tunnels
To March the cows underneath 12th Avenue to the abattoir
Or people invented this crazy cock-and-bull story about the count tunnels from or Escape
Because everybody loves a good
And so
Nicola twilley has been on a years-long quest
To figure out whether the cow tunnels ever actually existed
Because after all the idea of cows loping along under your feet in New York City at least how we think of New York's
City now
Is insane
Generally about food
And place
And if anything exists at that same intersection
It is the cow
Tunnel
I just did dedicated infrastructure for animals like that
Write a new genre of Arc
Texture freak out when you think about all of the tubes and tunnels and
Weird things that are underneath the
Street we have tunnels for cars we have tunnels for subways
We have all these tubes filled with electrical cables in the internet
Subterranean infrastructure to
Nicolas first happened on the couch tunnel Story by chance
Called raising steaks
Bocephus
Steaks of course it's spelled steaks
Yes the kind that could be porterhouse
T-boned exactly
Sirloin
Stripling
Alexandra
Skirt she's reading along
Middle Passage
I'm paid 22
You could miss it quite easily if you are reading
Too fast it Cicero
2 line
Traffic was so heavy in the 1870s
Sedecal tunnel
In quotation
Is Aunt capitalized
Was built beneath 12th Avenue to serve as an underground Passage
And it's rumored to be there still awaiting designation as a landmark
When she just carries on you know as late as 1880 Horowitz rights
Blah blah blah
Want this literally one cent
Exactly
That's weird I wonder if they're still there
So I Googled it
Define
I found
Brian whipp Road
Think of how he pronounces his name
Brian Lippard is a utility specialist for weidlinger Associates in New York
Structural engineering firm what I do for weidlinger is figure out how to get from point A to point B underground in New York City
Con Edison is
Cutting a trench for electrical cables
They need a navigator as well as investigate all kinds of anomalies and strange things that they find at a ground when doing
Brian went searching for the truth about cow channels more than 10 years before Nicola
In 1997 he published an article in a local local newspaper called the Tribeca
Trib
Which is what Nicola found in her web search
The headline
I will summarize it here
Fred just Fred just read the last night and read says he was watching a work crew in
Install a new drainage basin downtown which is by the way nowhere near the side of those old slaughterhouses
They dig and dig and then finally they have this kind of wooden
Barrier
Wooden
They break through it
And it's Hollow on the other side
And then a quote-unquote old man from the neighborhood steps up
And says
Why I see you found the cow tunnel
Sobran walk the story around ask the whole mess of people
And everybody's heard of the tunnel
But when they talk about the facts are never the same
But it's somewhere different and is made of different items
Since it was built at a different time
Brian finally circles back to Fred
Princess
Well
Actually I never saw it it was a buddy of mine I saw it
So again that's how Brian told the story in his article
In 1997
Sitting in his office with me in 2014
He told it this way
We were digging some test pit
For a Verizon
So so
You were there and digging and
Right and so we dug down about five feet and then
Grits
Curved surface that looks like a balti
Did roof
So now the story has completely changed
In Brian's mind
He's the one watching not Fred
Not would you talk this way
For another 10 minutes before he finally stopped and said
Wait a second
Call me in the beginning of this cuz I was
I didn't
100 and even the same damn thing Fred did
Let me tell you how big it is and where it goes
Everyday man
I know I started doing the same damn thing this is what happened with the code tunnels
And why the truth of them is so hard to get ahold of
It's like as soon as you start to retell the story it gets loose
And begins to bend
It's like an instant fishtail
Except it's about cows
And somehow the folklore of it
Stretches further and further out until nobody can remember how the story started
And so when Nicola twilley wrote her first blog post in 2010 she went solely off of
Brian's article
Which uncovered nothing
And that one line in the Betty Fussell book
But around the same time she had published
A little shred of hard ish evidence popped up
Cowtown a version of the Shroud of Turin
It's a coffee table book
Called
New York
In the 19th century
Send there's a picture in here that shows this is an 1877 engraving from Harper's Weekly
Tunnel at 34th Street paddle being driven up through a tunnel
Looks like a wooden tunnel
And it says tunnel from the dock
Huh
Emerging from it's almost like they're
And then they're strung up by 1 foot
Samara Lee X
But
Wow so that seems to be
Evidentiary
Right there is a picture of a towel tunnel
I don't know about that though
This is Nicholas
You can actually see
Where the tunnel is emerging from a tunnel
Photograph
But there's a cow emerging from a
Well and the cowboy in the picture is about 2 foot tall so there's all kinds of problems
The cow is about 10 times
Decisive
I wasn't I wasn't buying it
I needed more
I needed more so she did what she says bloggers like her and never do
When they're researching a topic
She called people
I talked to
Cities director of archaeology and cheese
Without this
As if she'd be nice
Christian Bale
After I read about them the first time that sort of bubbled up on a few blogs and I suppose those people were actually
Probably what she said to me which was
No evidence never found anything
Historic preservation very nice
Very apologetic sorry
I am about
Really fully write these things off as a myth
When I decide
To call CC Saunders
Of historical perspectives Incorporated which basically consults with big projects
Construction projects in that sort of thing and they gauge whether there is historical archaeological
Important stuff
In the area
That's my she called me back
Fairy
On the way back
Vim Staten Island
Of course they exist
Yes no question don't be ridiculous I'll send you the blueprints
Soon as I get home
After all this there are blueprints yeah original at this point but I have
What's the copy that we put into our
Report that we did when we study the Reconstruction of Route 9A otherwise known as the West Side Highway
Is narcisi Saunders
I have never been CC Saunders
With her for about 20
CC Sertraline was basically the count
Alien
At their shop
Back in 1991 the state contracted historical perspectives to do and historical study
Of that former meat packing area at 12th Avenue in the upper 30s
And Faline wrote the report so she did a ton of research
Look at all these old maps and documents and built this picture
The kinds of structures that used to be a long 12th Avenue there
Tenements
Warehouses cattle tunnel
Stop right there
On the very very last page of the report about that meat packing area
Sure will and underground cattle pass
Was built and used by the Pennsylvania Railroad Company it extended about 200 feet beneath 12th Avenue in the shore
Flying to the block between West 38th and West 39th Street
Pardon my bad grammar back in 1991
It was not meant to say that it was 200 feet beneath 12th Avenue it was 200 ft long
And beneath the Avenue
Misplaced modifier
The tunnel was built in 1932 and may still be present
Wait a minute 1932
Yeah and
Yeah that was during when all of this construction is going on in the city
Are being planned at least new Bridges and tunnels
Again like 200
Feet from the dock to the slaughterhouse
So that New York could
At the end of a long day of building
Ham steak for dinner
So how big was it
9 feet wide by 7 feet high
And that was ascertained from a New York Department of Doc
Permit number Manhattan .67
3 - 8
Yes
So
Maxine
Pretty Ironclad
Well yeah I would say it was an ironclad concrete pad but yes
To actually see a blueprint
It was sort of it
You know a lottery winning
Moment
I felt pretty good
The design
For the lost city of Atlanta
Exactly
Exactly having a really I mean I was
I was pretty stoked
What did you say
Well really I thought I have to go out there and
So where
Roughly
Roughly here
After looking over the blueprints Nicola
Pause for a minute to write up a new blog post
To the area where the tunnel had been
See if
Any sign of it any hope
That it might still exist
Some people swear it's intact
That the tunnels in tax
Wait we might be able
How to find an entrance
They've been one of the buildings without having to excavate the roadway at
I don't know I mean bears
The West Side Highway
Music about the Javits
When you think about the Lincoln Tunnel that were standing
Right next to you
Most likely
If Cal tunnel there was once upon a time
It was pulverized and all of that construction
And any void
Westfield in
You have a blueprint of it so how do you know if I'd be built inside of it
Plan on other maps that were made though the area later
Oh I see in and it's in the 1953 Port series from the Army Corps of Engineers
Which I don't really know what that means but there is
And actually in a research that I Nicholas found evidence for that other tunnel at 34th Street
It was in the Harper's Weekly picture
There's this New York Times article from 1875 that talks about it
It says
There runs a tunnel under 12th Avenue where the animals are brought into the shambles
In fact
Cattle are never seen by the outside public from the time of their Landing
Until they are converted into beef
From
Where our food comes
Cities are becoming things
But somehow get fed mysteriously and invisibly at this precise moment
And apparently
Of historic importance in Boston that also exist
Oh contraire Nicola twilley
Oh contraire
So wait the train
Right now
Is going through what used to be a tunnel
We do know whether the couch handle in Boston accept
Medicus Acceptance in Cambridge Mass
I stood on a bridge above it with Charlie Sullivan
By the way the way this neighborhood developed
The cattle market
Was established over on Massachusetts Avenue
Quite early before the railroad came through
Farmers would drive the cows here
Over the road
Charlie's the head of the Cambridge historical Commission
He says it used to be Cowpens on either side of this bridge
Walden Street Bridge
Accountable
Polly Walden Street cattle pass was built
So farmers could drive the cows from one pen to another
So
Because they might
Because they would get loose
Like Lucy
Cows that have minds of Their Own
Anyway
Viscount tunnel is now on the national register
Of historic places
But other than a plaque that mentions it
You never know it was tucked underneath the railroad bridge
Off-limits to the public next to an active rail line which is fenced off
So that people don't get hit by trains
So in short the commission preserve the structure that no one can see who has any access to
Correct
The only way is to hop try to hop that fence
You want to do that
Define it would be fun interesting way to spend the morning
I'm not sure
I'm able to do it
So
Feel free please tell me that you have two hands without him please tell me that you have to fence without him
Sound too
So when Charlie was well out of sight and couldn't be accused of aiding and abetting
And I am in
Twin
I climb down this steep embankment through all these tickets
Oh my God
Here it is
Seen it
Is exciting
Is basically a brick Dome
Original brick
Man
Covered in Grease
DD
In gated with a big black gate
Mu
No Echo
99% invisible was pretty so sweet by Shawn Colvin
Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced in beautiful downtown
Oakland California out of the offices of arcsin
Architecture Firm if the need arises
Amazon you the most beautiful account on all you've ever seen
How tunnel
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
Listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa
Is talking to me
Voice technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic
Trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Percent
We're presenting to special episode
What's from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how our soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
. info
Do you like the stories on this program you can get more and more and more of them
On Facebook Twitter and Tumblr
But there will be California's
At 99 pri.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Chilled Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com