99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stuck
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
If you could recognize any piece of classical music
I bet it's this one
This is true release written by Ludwig van Beethoven in 1810
Maybe it reminds you of piano lessons you took when you were a kid
In my town it was also the song the ice cream truck used
To play
That's producer Avery trufelman
But if you live in Taiwan
And you hear a truck rumbling down the street playing Fearless
It doesn't mean it's time to buy a pops
It means it's time to take out your trash
Because this is what a garbage truck in Taiwan sounds
This garbage truck song isn't just supposed to be cute and fun
Although it is also supposed to be cute and fun
The singing garbage truck
Are all a part of a completely different way of
Thinking about waste disposal completely different that is from the way that we think about it in the United States
In the late 1990s Taiwan recycled only 5% of its waste
Today Taiwan recycles well over half
The country is now among the world's top recyclers
And what changed in this. Has a lot to do with the way that the trash is collected
Okay serious isn't the only song the trucks play
In Taipei the capital of Taiwan
The trucks also play
This song
That's a maiden's Prayer by Polish composer tekla about a Zeus cupbearer mosca
In Taipei City the garbage trucks just alternate between these two songs
Protectors to pledge
Tucson
Stu music didn't
Taipei City
Given the elementary school kids can sing the song
Cell
We have brainwashed
This is Dr Jasmine Wang
And she grew up in Taipei
Since I was a child I knew that every time when it got it
Dutrac
Cubs
We will hear that
Now the singing garbage trucks are such a part of life it's hard to imagine a time before them
But that's fine actually wasn't too long ago
We used to have a lot of Peppa Pig
Dumpster so they have a lot of rats mosquitoes and things like that and it's not
Packing for our house
Just a couple of decades ago of Taipei residents through their trash into massive smelly dumpsters on the streets
Garbage would end up in piles on the sidewalk
Canton parks
Food faster in the heat
It was just nasty
Then taiwan's democratization accelerated in the mid-1980s and created this desire to tidy up
Being a modern country means being a clean country
And when you have foreign visitors coming and visiting your Capital they shouldn't think
Oh this place is dirty
This is Mary Alice Haddad
Charity East Asian studies at Wesleyan University
In Taiwan the
Pro-democracy
Movement
Got
Pulling entangled with the environmental movement
And so as all those things move together
And I'd late 80s early 90s
Then the
Pro-democracy and pro-environment agenda Scott on to the public
Consciousness
Also the environmental movement had a practical and Taiwan was running out of space to actually put piles
The trash
Because it's a small island extremely populous
Small island
There's not that much
Base word us you're going to stick all your junk
Where is in the United States there has been historically a sense of the
Untamed untappd
Endless wilderness
And you could just
Throw your junk Into the Wilderness and it would go away and you wouldn't have to worry about any more not true in Taipei
Suffolk city bus
But it's really clean and the Subways are clean in that
Sores are clean in the sidewalks
To clean and it's really Pleasant to be there
You never know that the city used to have piles of garbage littering the streets
Type A and A number of other Taiwanese cities
Reduce the amount of trash by changing the way the trash get collected
Take a look at my garbage
This is my friend Aaron Newport
She lives in Taipei
Where the garbage truck comes
Five nights a week
EBay
Like after work
Monday Tuesday Thursday Friday and Saturday
In Aaron's neighborhood trucks come twice in the evening at 5 and at 7
I usually once I mean
It's kind of hard sometimes to find the time to always
Be home at 5
5 / 7
Erin has to gather her own garbage and
Cycling and bring it out to a designated street corner and wait
For the big yellow truck to come
Frontier perks for the sound
MP release or maiden's prayer
Coming down the block
Basically this is a business system where a garbage can was system your trash goes right from your house to the truck
Ideally without ever touching the straight
You just have to bring out your garbage in a special bag
I pay my garb
Bye
These official blue garbage bags
Say city of Taipei on them
And each is emblazoned with us
I buy them from the
Convenience store crossword
The official blue garbage bags come in a number of different sizes ranging from 3L to 120
The more garbage you throw away the more it'll cost you
And although Taipei residents have to pay for their garbage by the bag
Recycling and compost
Are free
You don't need to buy bags for them at all
You can just take out your recycling in not official plastic bags
And you can generate as much compost and recycling as you'd like
So residents are incentivized to recycle more and throw Outlet
What's Aaron sort out all of her recyclables into
Perfect categories
These are the cans
Cans and bottle so we have a few tea bottles
So in Taipei every yellow garbage truck is followed by a small white recycling truck
Is basically a cart full of different bands
There's a bin for plastic bottles
14 glass bottle
Different Metals in cans
Papers and cardboard
In a compost bucket for raw food weight
Compost bucket
Overcooked Foodway
Taipei residents have to sort their recycling into all these different categories themselves
Although in the recycling trucks there are officials and volunteers who can help instruct you about which item
Goes where
So Aaron her housemates and I got all of her bags
Trash and differ
Kinds of recycling sorted out
And we walked about a block down the street
To wait with the rest of her neighbors
Who are all clutching official blue garbage bag
A lot of people gathered
Genesis Maybe
Larger than your average
Bridge Trail
Then
The moment we were waiting for
Yeah there was this Mad Dash of people swarming to the
School bus yellow garbage
And the white recycling truck
Okay let's not coughing at end
Swiftly tossing their separate recyclables in the bins tossing their blue bags and the garbage truck
And running away
It was Madness
Like
Extremely well organized Madness
I was so chaotic
And this system for all its chaos has been working
Taipei City used to produce 3296 tons of trash a day
Today the city produces about 1000 tonnes a day
That is according to Jen with you
When is 65 official
Who supervised the garbage trucks and their routes
I met him at a garbage pickup site
Where Jasmine Wong acted as interpreter
Everett
Mr10
And he is
Supervisor
District 10 overseas 20 garbage truck routes
And all those trucks have to make sure that citizens are sorting properly
If it's a Friday garbage tree in the recycling
Back
WWE Raw
Cheap tell them that you cannot do that
One more time otherwise see you again
And how much
Is the ticket 200 US dollars
Podesta maximum
You might think
This is such a drag
There must be some people who Buck the system by tossing their trash into public trash cans
Well
There are hardly any public trash cans in Taipei
They're only in train stations or at bus stops
And those are little they come up just below your knees
So in Taipei for the most part
If you eat a candy or buy a coffee
You just take your empty coffee
Or your candy wrapper
Put it in your pocket and bring it home
Your trash
You put in your blue bag
And bring out to the truck
Yourself
It's hard to imagine a system like this working here in the US
Every city here has a different method of trash pickup but across-the-board
Uniting factor is that our American trash pickup system strive to be invisible
The trucks made great efforts to come when we're working or sleeping or trying to sleep
Keeping out of the way of traffic and not disturbing the flow of the city
We take our trash and recycling out to Benz or down a shoe door to a dumpster
And
It's gone
We don't have to think about it
According to the EPA
Americans recycle and compost
About 34% of their
Which is less than most rich country
But some American cities do a lot better
San Francisco has probably the most forward recycling program in North America this is Robert Reed
Is the representative of Recology
The company that takes care of San Francisco's waste
Recycling and compost
Unlike type A which has a public trash pickup system mini waste pickup services in the US are private
And we are the customers
That's how it works with ecology which means
They got to keep their customers happy
Number one Focus
Provides
Superior customer service
Their next focus is to
Do as much recycling as possible
And to make recycling easy and convenient for customers
Recology has set up
Similar incentives to the system in Taipei
What trash pickup is way more expensive than recycling or compost
For example in San Francisco
Recycling and compost cost about $2 a month per bin
Trash is about $26 a month
Above all
Recology system is mint
To be simple and
Stress
It has to be
If you want people to keep paying for your service
People have a lot of demands in their lives we understand that
Young recycling might not be the very first thing they got the guy
Make a boss happy to go to pay their mortgage
Garbage and recycling and composting might not always be at the top of the list
We understand that basically instead of putting the onus on the citizens to separate the different kind of compost and
Recycling for themselves
Recology does the brunt of the work
Sorting
So we don't have to
San Francisco like a lot of other American cities that collect recycling
Uses one catch-all recycling bin
So you throw your cans or bottles are cardboard all in the same place
And then all those different materials end up and if it
Facility
Like recycle Centre
So this is recycle Central this is the
Large
Recycling plant on pier 96
Where we sort all the materials from the blue band The Bottles cans with paper
We're going to go inside now
The facility is massive
That's where ecology process is most of San Francisco's recycling
Straight bag
Pile of recycling
This is
From this morning
This is from one day
And we're going to get this sorted out
Because we got another big
File coming in tomorrow so we do 600
Tons a day here
That 600 ton pile will wind its way of a huge surreal web of conveyor belt
Where some of the 173 people on staff will separate the recyclables into 16 categories of
Materials
With the help of some Modern Recycling equipment
So we've got a magnet's and we have fish ladders that separate bottles
Zoo cams from paper
They're on a they're on an angle and they temporarily suspend gravity and to make sure everything gets precisely sordid
There's some real state-of-the-art technology like this apparatus that separates clear plastic from color plastic with
Optic sensor
Right here
The scanners looking at the materials as they come by and when it sees a clear plastic like a clear plastic water
Ball and hits it with a puff of air
Can you can hear it
Expensive across $3000000 for this machine
Going to keep for the Netherlands
So this system
With all that worrying twirling conveyors and magnets and machinery and 173 employees
Dazzling
Make less trash by doing more cycling
And recycling
Creates ten times more jobs than landfilling or incineration
Of course it also takes all the direct sorting out of the hands of people who actually create the waist
Charges them for the services
Instead
As a result
Recycling in the US
Canby
I guess that's part of the problem like to the extent that there's pushback in recycling which I've seen some of it in the United
It states now is often about the cost of it and now it's
Guitar cost
And that's true if you're using me single-stream processes function
And it's less true
The household
That's Professor Mary Alice her. Again
Your community wants to recycle all that stuff needs to be separated and sorted
Somehow
What do you use a $3000000 machine from the Netherlands
For compelling entire sweet potato shaped island of people to stand on the corner at night
The Taipei system is
Cheap and efficient because the city has conscripted their citizens as workers
And it's been successful
Taipei has a great example of
I a big major
Global metropolitan area
That did not have a good garbage collection system not that long ago
And I have
Slightly transformed
And it could be an example for us all
Which is not to say we should necessarily
Copy typing system
What's worked for them might not work for the US
But consider the American garbage
Creeping around Dawn or during work hours
Trying to be an inconspicuous
Is it possible
Trying to keep trash
Out of sight
Out of mind
You don't really pay attention to it
But
Everyone should pay a lot of attention
We had to watch our garbage pile-up in our homes without taking it out to the van and had to set aside time in our days to
Catch the garbage and recycling trucks coming down the street
I bet we produce less drunk
But I also think if I had to hear this song twice a night 5 days a week
I would
Murder
Everybody
99percentinvisible was produces week by Avery troubleman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall
Stage reviews f&me Roman Mars
Special thanks this week to Helen sang Here in Newport Ethan young Sam Langton and Jasmine Wong
We are products of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced are the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm
Beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why but it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook you can follow us all on Twitter and Instagram we have a very good Tumblr that
Avery takes care of
But the best way to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
Website
99 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com