99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The United States Marine Corps buys a lot of earplugs
Visit any military base and you'll find
Under the bleachers at the firing range
In the bottoms of washing machines
They are cheap and effective at making noise
Less noisy
Most ear plugs reduce Noise by about 30 decibels
That is Mary Roach author of a bunch of great books her latest one is called but it's about the science of humans at
30 decibels can be significant
Every three decibel increase in a loud noise
Cut in half
The amount of time you can be exposed
Without risking hearing damage
To put that another way in unprotected human ear can spend 8 hours a day exposed to 85 decibels
Without entering hearing loss
That's the level of freeway
85 decibels is also the level of a crowded restaurant
But if you go up to 115 decibels
Things like a chainsaw
Or a really loud concert
Your safe exposure time is only half a minute
Before your hearing can be affected
So without earplugs
You should only be exposed to the sound of a chainsaw for about 30 seconds
But with your plugs
You got closer to 8 hours
In a military situation or reduction of 30 decibels is especially helpful with a steady
Finding background in
Like say a Bradley tank clattering over asphalt
Is it from of a Blackhawk helicopter
But there's a problem with ear plugs as the solution on a Battlefield
I will tell you that I
I've never seen a Marine
Where are closed in a combat
Operation
That's are in a 1/2
It's been 8 years as an infantry marine and served a tour of Duty in Fallujah Iraq
And this is Eric Fallon
Andover
24 years of military experience
I've never seen soldiers put a passive ear plug in and go on a dismounted
Control
Soldiers aren't using their ear plugs because when they do they can't hear what's happening around them
And with unprotected ears a lot of service members are coming home from Battle with tinnitus
Which is a ringing in your ears
Or hearing
It's not uncommon anyone especially in the Infantry
Will
Pretty much tell you that they have hearing loss
When Aaron and his buddies get together in social situations
Everyone speaks a little louder
You know when we get together everybody knows who has the worst
Amount of hearing loss
Are typically fits a good set of friends
We know what year are they
They tend to have hearing loss and I can tell you two or three
Trans right off top my head I know okay yeah he got hit by an IED on his right side
I need to speak to his left ear
Well Aaron's fellow Marines are naturally understanding about his hearing loss
His wife and kids find a challenging
They actually end up getting frustrated with me in it sell
China
Trying to play it off
Pretend like you heard what they had to say in
China
Picked it up later on in the conversation
Figure it out later
Or ask them as though you forgot
Jillian Ashley forget you
I just never heard them
When you really think about the Advent of black gunpowder which is really win
The military became an extremely noisy environment
Think about how long we've lived with that
I'm really without a solution the solution is to put something in your ears
The blocks the sound
And by the way it doesn't just bought the sound that we want to prevent it blogs
All the same
Since World War II the VA has been reporting on what kind of injuries they treat
And tinnitus and hearing loss have always been the number one and number two most prevalent injuries
Deserve as member
Eric Fallon has been studying how to protect the hearing of service members for a long time
He's an audiology
An audiologist is a medical
Professional that is concerned with the audit
Choice system
Eric used to be the chief audiologist at Walter Reed Medical Center
Some audiologist work with patients to give them hearing test and diagnose what kind of hearing disorder they have
But Eric's main focus is trying to find Solutions
The right protective solutions that not only protect their hearing but
Enhance their
Performance in some way
Eric now works for the company 3M
Designing hearing protection from military use
And he's fond of saying that the military has a noise problem but
We have a significant
Quiet problem
What do you mean to that service members in combat need ear protection that works for them in both environment
Because the transition from quiet
Napa Newberry
Very quickly
In a war zone you have to consider everything
Even just walking down the road has a strategy
Ctuit
The quote-unquote killing radius of a fragmentation grenade is 15 ft
If troops walked along in a clump like
Tourist
A single grenade kill a bunch of them at once
So they try to keep at least 15 feet between each other on Patrols
But the more spread out they are the harder it is to hear one another
Troops in combat might walk in the quiet for hours
The only two ways being is a little bit of
Chatting
The sound of gravel crunching under their boots
And then suddenly
This is a video that Eric Fallon likes to show of troops on patrol in Iraq
These troops were just walking along
Avon
And then all of a sudden things got
Genetic very quickly
Are you okay
In the video when the truth comes Under Fire
All the soldiers
Boulder ground who can shoot it it's allowed
They probably aren't wearing hearing protection
But Eric says the pencil damage to their ears isn't the only boy
Their lives are in danger
And they're hearing
Turn on the main things helping them figure out what to do
Just because they're being shot at doesn't mean that they understand what's happening to
They may not know am I being shot at by 50 people or three
What's happening to the left of me what's happening to the right of me
One of the major tools to figure out what's happening in this situation is Radio
With a radio you can connect to someone who has more of a bird's-eye view of the place
This might be another Soldier somewhere on a roof
Or someone monitoring from a drone camera
Communication will help the person on the ground answer all the questions running through their head in that moment what do I do do I
Push through the assault
Do I hold in place
Do I wait for the quick reaction force
Succumb
And help us
How do I call in air support
But it's loud
They can probably barely hear what the other people around them are saying
I love butts on the radio and if I can't hear the signal
I may be missing the information that I need to make the right decision
And so you are seen that video there's a young Soldier laying on the ground communicating over the radio and
And just before the video stops
You'll hear him say
I can't hear you
A point that I try to make whenever I use that video is
That's probably one of the more important communication
That not only that person but his team members will ever have in their life
Because they're under direct enemy fire
Being able to hear the radio and each other is crucial to their survival
Eric believes that he has a solution to this problem
He thinks that service members on dismounted combat controls like the one in that video
Should be wearing a device called TCAP
Soe tactical communication and protective systems or TCAP
I'm all products that are designed to not only deliver hearing for
Protection
But to allow you a better ability to hear what's happening around you so you can maintain situational awareness
Tea cups come in a couple of styles
One style fits inside your ear kind of like a pair of earbuds
Any other style fits over here
And they look like that your love seem like we're while operating power tools
Both styles are equipped with environmental microphones that pick up the sounds around you and feed them into your
Careers at levels that your eardrums can tolerate
And in some cases these products
Integrated into a radio system so that you can have more seamless
Two way radio
With the radio feature you could be talking with a drone operator or communicating with a command center
And you can actually hear what they're saying to you
Because the device is blocking out other noise
And yes
3M the company Eric works for cells tcaps
But he's also an audiologist who's dedicated his career to protecting the hearing of people in the military
Eric sent as a few of the over-the-ear style tcaps
Headsets to dry out
Powerball
Each pair have a power button that allows you to
You toggle between a few settings
99 Pi producers
Katie mingle and Sam Greenspan tested out the tcaps in front of our office where there's been a bunch of loud
Destruction happening all week
Nkt recorded what the world sounds
Through her teeth
So in this clip Katie and Sam are standing on the sidewalk
Rock wearing tcaps
Looking like a
A couple of weirdos
People are walking path
How to spell construction worker is sweeping
And despite the fact that they're wearing big padded earmuffs
I can hear it all really well
Because the environment of microphones are picking up the noise around them
Feeding into their ears
That's am talking to Katy using the radio feature on the tcaps
Mail someone has started to saw through the concrete nearby but the tcaps are attenuating the sound
So that Sam and Katie
Still here at
It's a much lower volume
But if they take the keycaps off
I won't make it within that very long but basically the tcaps allowed Katie and Sam to communicate
Through some very loud construction noises
While also protecting their ears
And when it was quiet they were able to hear the environment around them
Soft sounds
Like sweeping
And people talking
Teacups are also being marketed for use in industrial and construction settings
Just like the one Katie and Sam were standing in the middle of
In the military
They've been used since the early 2000 mostly by Special Operations groups like Navy Seals
But they're not standard issue
Even for troops in combat who would be exposed to the kind of noise that can damage your hearing
The conventional forces
Do what I think that conventional forces of done for many many years they just did
Except that communicating is going to be a challenge
Communication challenges and hearing loss
So much a part of the culture of combat
The Earth says when he was a soldier
He actually wanted hearing loss
So the people would know he had experience
So if you didn't have a degree of hearing loss it was obvious that you were one of the new guys
I meant that you had not really been around much noise and you really have not fired that many artillery
Rounds down range
Well soldiers are actively serving they do have to undergo fairly comprehensive hearing test
Send periodic check out
These tests are administered by an audiologist
But the results of those tests get passed onto the unit commander and he or she decides what to do with them
And a soldier who is found to have degraded hearing
Often won't be taken out of their position
We're just so accustomed to finding work around
With hearing loss
You will sometimes fine soldiers that have a c
Significant degree of hearing loss
But their unit leadership may be so dependent on that
A person
But they also want that person to
I remain where they are
I look forward to the day when we put as much info
Tips on maintaining good hearing
As we do good vision
Eric has found that in order to get the military interested in protecting people's hearing
He's had to sell it differently when I was a young golfer
When I would go out and do a unit briefing I would actually talk to them about how much money the VA spends on here
Because I thought that was pretty
But I didn't really work
It's not a unit commanders job to be concerned of what the VA spends on hearing loss
Eric talked to unit commanders he had to make the argument Tactical
He had to explain it when people can hear they can be more effective on the battlefield
This points to unlock a disconnect between the Department of Defense
Defending the nation
And the VA
Which provides Healthcare
The veterans
If the dod is given the choice
Between spending the money on bonds
Hearing protection
It's not hard to see why they might use
Kick the Can
The VA
But to defend the Department of Defense
They have made an effort in the last couple of decades to do better
There's more testing than there used to be
And in 2009 they established the hearing center of x
Which research has hearing loss
And advocates for more protection
This invisible Hendry of hearing loss is very significant
Big part of our job is to advocate
And build awareness
That's Colonel Mark packer
Is the director of the hearing center of excellence
He says yeah Teacups are great
But they're not perfect
All hearing protection has
Some foul ability
If you're out on a hot mission in the deserts and you have those earmuffs down over your ears
They are hot
Soldiers might remove them
And then be unprotected when they need it
Other arguments against tcaps they are this extra thing to carry and have to be charged and if they break their expensive
Sed to replace
Not everybody needs just $1,500 tactical radio device
There are some solutions
In between tcaps and the cheapest foam ear plugs
There's what's called level dependent ear plugs
Remain to protect against High impulse noises like weapons fire
While allowing other environmental noises to pass through
But Eric and others we spoke to said that these earplugs still make it difficult to hear the environment around you
For that reason a lot of people will often not to wear them
Liberty caps are the solution for all combat troops or not it's worth saying that Colonel Packer and Eric Fallon there
And they're both working sometimes together
Define dissolution to one of the oldest most prevalent and most invisible problem
99percentinvisible was reported this week by Mary Roach and produced by Katie mingle with Delaney Hall Sharif Youssef
Fitzgerald Kolstad same Greenspan Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
This episode was based off of chapter of Mary Roach has excellent best-selling book
Grunt the Curious science of humans at War
I cannot recommend her book
Enough
They are the best time you can have learning weird things about science
We are project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinnerware
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and likes show on Facebook follow all the people who make this show on Twitter and Instagram in the best
Best way to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world easy
The Clipper round the hundreds and hundreds of stories
199p I
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com