99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
The handle or name you adopt to be one-of-a-kind
Are you nice people live in
Radio IBO meaning you do not see the picture to hear the phone
Hear something called
Is a human boy
You never did this is wjjk Monday March 12th
1973 thank you and hear some more his music
Now people
On our way to Canaan land
Here we go there are those innovations that everyone loves and depends on your Big E
Like computers electricity the printing press
And then there are the innovations that made you who you are
Punk rock music
Photo copiers cassettes nunchucks
But if I were to write them I think the two most important technological innovations to my life
Broadcasting in home sound recording
Today at two of my favorite stories from two of my favorite Indie Productions all about the early days of broadcasting and record
Ray utopians Radio Diaries in the kitchen sisters represent the best of what we can achieve an audio storytelling and here they
They are tackling the subjects that are near and dear to my heart
These pieces were first broadcast on NPR as part of the kitchen sisters lost and found sounds.
First step
With his story of Conrad's garage and the birth of commercial broadcasting in Pittsburgh Pennsylvania this is Joe Ricci
From Radio Diaries
Produced in 2001
The sounds that came out of Frank Conrad's Garage in 1919 and 1920
Argon
There were no recordings made and everyone who participated in those weekly broadcast has died
In fact
There may be only one person still alive who actually heard what was going on in that garage
A man named Harry Mills
This is k4h
You
Hello Charlie d1h VA here's k4h you how are you this evening
Henry Mills is 94 years old
Using engineer for RCA most of his life
But the last eight decades
He's been going on the ham radio
Just about every day
Mills first discovered radio in 1919
He was 12 years old
And his parents bought him a copy of the Boy Scout Handbook
In the book
Afterlotto the camping in the setting up a tent in the rain and helping the old lady cross the street and so on
In the back was a
Chapter on how to build a wireless station
I've never heard of such a thing
So I built one
I'll show you how it works
It was gold out of photographic plates and tinfoil the condenser and this is
Weather stripping
This is a Ford coil
Ford ignition coil which would hook onto your antenna on your on the air
This is what radio sounded like windmills were started
Dashes
That's the letter v
What you use for test purpose
The hears me he come back
And we'd hold a conversation
Simple as that
Almost every night
Harry millswood line is bad
And listen to the amateur radio operators signal back and forth
And one night he heard something different
Remember
At 10:11 at night
And all I wants this voice
Appears
And remember
Reading out of Yelp
Sheldon some sort my dad doing
Hey just gotten out of that vast come in wrapped in a towel this because you're always alright
Somebody hadn't happened to me and I said
Dad look I'm hearing this fellow talking
Damn that we shared the headphones only have one pair of headphones
He allowed his I was right
Harry Mills had stumbled onto the experimental transmission
Frank Conrad garage
35 MI
It was talking to me says now I'm going to play a phonograph
It was astounding I I didn't know you could do that voice before
Trinidad that the music
It opens up a whole new world
Frank Conrad was not the first person to talk and play music on the radio
Veterans like Reginald fessenden Lee Deforest and Marconi
I've been doing such experiments as early as 1906
But back then radio was seen as a method of one-to-one communication
Like the telegraph
New Edition radio is a way to reach many people at the same time
To broadcast
Frank Conrad was among the first to use the word broadcasting
It was originally an agricultural term used to describe the distribution of seeds over a large area
In his garage
Conrad help to change the concept
A radio
He did it largely by accident
Testing testing
Testing one two
3 + 1
Frank Conrad from the garage
What it would have sounded like
It's probably fair to say that nobody cares more about Frank Conrad's garage
Then a man named Rick Harris
Harris has an amateur historian who has dedicated his life
To preserving and researching the history of that garage
He's collected replicas of the equipment Conrad used
A microphone
Made out of the top of a Candlestick telephone
Mounted in a small box stuff
And a hand crank victrola
You turn the crank
Rick Harris says the story of Frank Conrad's garage
Really begins with that victrola
Conrad was an engineer for Westinghouse
So we had access to vacuum tube
Allow them to transmit voice over the air
But at the time
ConEd wasn't thinking about Broadcasting
He was simply trying to test and improve his transmitting it
The problem was his voice after talking endless hours
Into the microphone would wear out so
He got the idea one day to put on a record that would give him two or three minutes
To adjust his equipment and would save his voice
This one is an ancient one so I don't know what it's going to sound like though
And as soon as he started playing the music
Began getting requests for
More music and he would get phone calls and letters asking him to play a certain song at a certain time so some
Someone listening with their crystal said could convince the relative that you could actually play music over the air
He found very quickly that there was an unseen audience out there
England call me up at 9
This is Frank Conrad
Recorded in the late 1930s not long before
He died
Anybody got do it
The program
Everyone's in Saturday night
Places that time and I had no idea what
Overtime Conrad garage starting to sound more like a radio station
Along with phonograph records Conrad would transmit piano solos by family members
Baseball scores
And then when he started to run out of Records to play Conrad went to the Hamilton music store
That's if he could borrow some for his broadcast
The owner said yes as long as Conrad agreed to announce the name of the store on the air
So the Conrad was building the one thing the radio industry hadn't yet thought much about
An audience
But the real Turning Point came on September 29th 1920
When did Joseph Horne department store place this ad in the Pittsburgh Sun
Are concert picked up by radio hear the music was from the victrola
And the home of Frank Conrad
Mr. Conrad is a wireless Enthusiast inputs on the wireless concerts periodically
For the entertainment of many people in this District
Who have wireless sets
Amateur Wireless sets
Are on sale here
$10 and up
Diane really caught the attention of Conrad's boss at Westinghouse Amman
By the name of Harry Davis who
Add to Story Goes called Conrad in the next day
And said
Essentially I would like to put you out of business
Because
I would like
Westinghouse to set up its own station
And
I Davis ask Conrad
Could that be done in Conrad set of course
So over the next month Conrad and his team began constructing a wooden Shack on the roof of the Westinghouse plant
They built a 100 watt transmitter
And at 6 p.m. on the night of November 2nd 1920
The newly-licensed station KDKA
When on the air
It is
KD
The Westinghouse electric and Manufacturing Company
East Pittsburgh Pennsylvania
We shall now broadcast the election
The station launched
I broadcasting the returns at the Harding Cox presidential election
Luna recordings about broadcast
But in the late 1930s
Original announcer via Rosenberg
Maidthis Recreation
We'd appreciate it if anyone hearing this broadcast would communicate with us
We are very anxious to know how far the broadcast is reaching
And how it is being received
Well nobody's ever heard of such a thing before you had to wait till next day to find out who won the election
Henry Mills who is 13 by this time
Remembers going down to the local newspaper where they had set up a receiving station
Somebody would sit at the receiver and a crowd gathered outside or number of people and they would watch TV
Returns being updated as the numbers came in bigger
The next day in the newspaper of course the talk was G for the first time
Ever people were able to get the reports before the newspaper was printed
I think it's very difficult for us
Today to imagine
Really quite what a magical moment this was
Susan Douglas is a professor at the University of Michigan and the author of inventing American Broadcasting
She says the KDKA election broadcast
What's a watershed event
And because there were no connecting wires because
There was a concept of The Ether
It was kind of a cosmic connection for people with a
Quasi sort of spiritual event that these voices were coming out of the air
Into your home
In 2 weeks after that first transmission Westinghouse introduced the first radio for the General Public
The areola Junior book sold for $25
The broadcasting boom have a gun
And over the next few years
Radio with move out of the garage
And into the living room
KDKA Pittsburgh
Today KDKA is considered the oldest radio station in the country
History has not been as kind to Frank Conrad's garage
This fall bulldozers began to clear the site it will soon be a Wendy's
The bulldozers destroy Conrad's house
But Rick Harrison a group of supporters called the Conrad project
Manage to save the garage
Piece by piece
The woodwork all of the doors the windows and some 25
Thousand or so bricks the ones that
Survived anyway
I don't know it's it's just
The more I learn about Frank Conrad and what he did and
The fact that he was virtually unknown outside of Pittsburgh
Just something
It feels that he's been overlooked for what he did
Sunday Harrah's hope to reconstruct Conrad garage
And turn it into a museum
Frank Conrad may have helped to launch the modern broadcasting industry
But that wasn't really his vision
Connect Bluetooth to talented engineer cancri late at night in his garage
Trying to connect to people through the air
And that pretty well describes what 94 year old Harry Mills is still doing
Every night at 10
Nobody won UEFA here is gay for each you thank you. Yes I'm reading you very well
After all this time
Caramel says he still feels the same way he felt
When he first heard Frank Conrad's voice
Coming out of the radio
To me it's
It's difficult to describe the fascination of it
I know I use it all the time
How does it happen
Can see the father
No wires going from here to there
You can talk to him
It was a phenomenal it interested me from the beginning
Hey I presume it safe
To say that that is
I never gotten over
Tell her that I'm going to say good night
Thanks for the
USB alarm speaker
A good night Bob and goodnight guy that what you want to see RFK 4hu
Conrad's garage was produced by Joe Richmond of radio Diaries in 2001 the lost and found sound series
Terry Mills who was featured in that piece died in 2008
Conrad garage is still a pile of loose bricks in storage awaiting its final resting place as a museum
Someday
You'll be able to see it for yourself
The podcast part of radiotopia
2 meter stories were featured on
This American Life and Planet Money
Richmond offhandedly said to me when we were talking about Today Show
We'll see if you promoting the radio Diaries podcast on 90% invisible will result in more radio Diaries
Scribers ban Planet Money or Tal
No I don't know if you know this about me but I'm extremely competitive
So I need everyone hearing my voice
Describe the radio Diaries podcast right now
Here's the thing you'll get
Short fortnightly stories of a blow your mind radio Diaries will reach more people than ever and I'll get to demonstrate
Compass fully operational battle station everyone wins
Except when money This American Life
So you got it
Prime now
It's important
I was watching
No I don't want to push my luck here but there's another podcast that you'll want us to try to right now that equally deserves to Rock It Up.
Podcast charts it's called fugitive waves from the kitchen sisters
And if you require proof of why you need to subscribe to another podcast will then I have the perfect story for you
This is probably
One of the top 10 radio stories of all time it was first broadcast on NPR's all things considered in 2004
So I decided to presented as is
This is NPR's All Things Considered
I'm Robert Siegel
And I know Adam soap gun
Each week we begin our lost and found sound series
With this thing
It's called music in marble halls
Is improvised duet of clarinet and high heels crossing a Manhattan office lobby
Was recorded
In my teens
Buy New York audio legend Tony Schwartz
What are the most original an eccentric sound Gathering
It was 1945 when Tony Schwartz first stepped out of his apartment with a microphone
The capture the sounds of his neighborhood
Now more than 50 years later Tony Schwartz has amassed one of the largest and most oclock
The collections
A recorded sound
In the world
The kitchen sisters producer is davia Nelson and Nikki cell
Visited Tony and his Midtown basements to
Where he surrounded by table
Mixing console
Awards photographs
And row upon row
I've audio tape
Their story Tony Schwartz 30000 recordings later
Looks at the Legacy for Mantua
Spanish life exploring
And influencing the world
Who recorded sound
Beginning
Would it work called
New York 19
Non-commercial musical life of my postal
The postal Zone West New York 19th
It's 1019 now
That was the area I could travel in I'm not able to travel
Tomorrow I have agoraphobia
And then walk
I could just go around my postal Zone
Dexter Manhattan
I made the first portable tape recorder
I broke the Vu meter from inside the case
To the top so I could look down and see a lot of things were I put a strap on
So I can have it over my shoulder
That was 19
45 record children in the park doing jump rope
Rhymes and I recorded the street festivals
I made 14 records
Verve folkways records you can see them up there
The children's games Hooda Street cycle
1 2 3 and a zing zing zing
I was interested in the sound around us
Allowed to carry in Texas
1 is
Fish
Other is betting
Are you going to risk my
I had a brush lapel mic
And I would put it on a wrist watch band
And I pulled out my sleeve so I would just
Walk around record that way like when I went into the pawn shop and I did cab drivers
Is that why I recorded by the 7800 cab driver
9th Street
No parking
Call Vallejo and recorded the songs on jukeboxes in the
Restaurants or bars that cater to the various groups
Around my postal Zone
What I would do is get
People
In the restaurant who spoke English to come over and translate it for me
The country in which I was born
He's suffering
Many many years
Economic theme
Amendola
In my country there are always flowers
My Paradise
I won't change Puerto Rico
I will change
Puerto Rican chicken
Buy Frozen chickens in the ice box is here
TD Ameritrade
Natal South Africa
Burlington
Sports
New York
USA
Hello Tony Schwartz I'm bringing you greetings from Pittsburgh Pennsylvania
Folk song from
Tyler the Creator
Hello Chinese my name is Thomas not making from Killarney County Kerry Ireland
When I got my first wire recorder
I asked the company if they would give me the guarantee slips
From people
From all over the world and all over this time
Import three corners
Who said they were buying them because of their interest in music
I would Exchange
Wires with people in other countries
Who are interesting folk music in Maywood
Send me material from there
Countries
My name is Tony Schwartz
Music you hear is approving Indian
Playing his guitar
On a quiet summer evening
This is one of 15000 recordings
I've collected
Recordings of Folk Music and folklore
Recording zywiec
Changed
Was people all over the world
Hello Tony
I received your letter here the other day
Well I'm going to send you a wire.
Stuff that I Jared
Do you know Siri
New York City
Appreciate this kind of music
Folks Round Here
That's how it started
Recording payment from all parts of the United States
From all parts of the world
Recordings on wire
Recordings on tape
One of my exchanges was with a man who wanted
It sounds he no longer heard
Tony I wonder if you do me a favor
I live out in the country
Originally I came from the city and
I kind of miss it
I was wondering if you would record some sounds of the city and
Send them out
I'd really like to hear it
How about it
Part of my answer was recorded in Time Square
Last week later
I found this
In my mailbox
Antonio
Receive your sounds of the city this morning and
I've been playing them ever since
I noticed that you said that you recorded them
About 8:30 at night
Sort of reciprocate
Here's the sounds of
My country
8:30 at night
The voices in music of the world came into my apartment in New York City
Can I travel no further than my mailbox
People talkin there's an innate musicality and in the way
Certain people speak
And also in
The barkers at nightclubs or various places
Showing
Used to be the people vendors going Bryan Street
Poor people singing in the backyard or shouting in the backyard
Now
It's over the radio
Or television
I did a home record on the sound of selling
Vegetable mange shouting apples apples on the street
That horse and wagon selling vegetables
Mom you is why
MyChart
Awesome small chocolate
There were
Men who we go around buying old clothes
Radio
I cash clothes icashcard
It was February 3rd 1956 when Tony Schwartz appeared at the information desk at the animal shelter to ask
Dog
Attending will take
The adoption wooden board
The dog selfie
Is anything is Select
Reborn babies are obedience trained dogs working towards degree
Which of course that's like receiving a college
I did a radio program on sound once a week
On WNYC for over 35 years
I would do it on any subject that
Came up to me during the week good morning
Every year for the last 13 years I've been
Presenting
Historian sound
Of the
Growth of my niece
We've all
Erdos
Time lapse
Photography
Well I'm going to apply this technique
To be
Growth of my niece
Mansi
Insound
13 years
And then
2 minutes
13 second
Here goes
Jack and Jill when
A pail of
Jack fell down and broke
Jill came tumbling
Palisades
I would record the sound of my daughter growing up
I have
Her first cries after being born
I had a microphone over her bed
On a recorder than our bedroom
Anytime I heard her beginning to wake up or anything I could turn on the recorder and record the sound of
Waking up
Tony s
Lillian house
If you have to make in the house broken
If you mix valerian
In the apartment
Cat is slapping with a newspaper
He doesn't do it again he's houseboat
What do you think of the Russian sending the dog up in the satellite
Well
I Hope You Dance
Get hurt
But if he does I'm sure they'll send up a medic
Black woman
Working as a nurse for a child
When she go home at night
Take her out to get a cab to go up to Harlem
If she's hella cab they wouldn't stop for her
Blacks couldn't get taxis
And I interviewed cabs drivers why they don't like to go to Harlem and put that in the program
It's all girls
You messed my hair and it's very special for tonight it's just so I wanted to know page but with a high top
I'm taking guitar lessons
That's fun
I take drama lessons after
The school that's great
And I've been working on the school newspaper I might be edited
Next year
And
I've been discovering boys
How do I come to Lisa ideas
Just from being human
And working with sound
And knowing how to sound affected me an infected other people
Real Lies
Tony Charlie
What's a pet turtle
Dial Journey
February 24
19 C
Skateboard
Who died
Buy turtle
Tony
Pica disorder children
He tried to save her
By giving them hamburger
He died
Fairy hair
Fat giraffe
Sort of a tragedy for me
I'm going to buy tabs
The flag is
Because I like
Just like the president of the United States when he died except the
But he's liking my family
Florida turtles
My Melody
Can a baby show
Anybody can
Oh yeah
Fancy
Well I was born in the beginning of time
Time magazine started the year I was born
Harry Belafonte was a pop singer when I met him
I got him into the Jamaican song
This is another working song it is they banana loading song
Damn Daniel
Dad I found a woman going to cashier at
Macy's
Her name was Louise Bennett and she knew
All the Jamaican folklore
And I played those songs Harry Belafonte
I got from a nightclub in Africa
Songs like wimoweh remember that
And everybody love Saturday night
The way I gave to the Weavers
And everybody loves Saturday night
I gave two
Casino in Atlantic City
Viewscreen singer you also I watch Jeopardy on television ever watch that
Who is the guy that
Where is The Wonder of it
Merv Griffin I gave him everybody love Saturday night
Good morning
Today
Like
Way too beautiful song
Sung by
Call Rose
I think he was one of the great singers of our time
Ciara
Roshan
Couldn't travel because
They called him a communist which is ridiculous you again
Grief in internationalism
He wanted to send tapes to various places around
The world
One I did
To send to England for a speech for him was about peace so I've had his song behind
Then I had his narration over that
Peace and friendship with our great wartime allies
I didn't do anything
Growing out of
United United
I did it for many people who couldn't travel for
W e b Dubois I would
Everycord speeches that he wanted to given
South Africa
Riker and president of the pan-african Congress to the peoples of Africa
Greeting
Then when the
Hollywood 10 was supposed to go to jail for being on American
And many of them had made movies that I love
Infiltration
I recorded all of them the night before they went to jail
Dalton Trumbo telling what he was accused of
ADI submitted ADI labor
Anthony girl
Pro-war
And I've been denied by everyone from Roosevelt down over
The Ridiculousness of this McCarthy era
No he started the whole thing of loyalty Oaths
Most people think of
Evil
As the sounds of
Gunfire or thunder or lightning of something
I found
I believe that's the most evil sounds
The world are the sounds out of mouths of people
I've used media
To shame people
Into proper behavior
Primitive cultures
If someone did something shameful and word-of-mouth got around
The Village
In an hour or so in our culture
The same thing access
But
Give divine
Distance of our country into the speed of sound
If I knew would take a 64th of a second to reach across the country
Buy telephone radio television or anything like that
Did a commercial with the Pope against nuclear weapons
I've been
Against nuclear weapons since 1939
One thing I've done was the daisies front for President Johnson
How is working on sound for six or seven commercials
In the campaign against
Barry Goldwater
One of them was
A little girl counting down and picking petals off a daisy
Then there's the countdown
Denver Broncos horse
These are the stakes to make a world in which
We must either love
Or we must die
What would you say to young people who smoke
I would say that.
My boy
That's why I teach a course for NYU
I also teach media in public Health in Harvard
Both places come here
I have agoraphobia I am traveling not able to
Grandma
I have used the telephone to teach all over the world
And sweet in Japan and South America
Australia
My brother built a 1/2 radio
Which network can I used to go up in the attic
And play a spaceship like
Jack Armstrong
Iowa Social
Physics and the physics teacher was interested in amateur radio
First built my own receivers and huge 20 meter antennas
And I broke my own little Shack
Where I had 16 by 16 and I had my radio station in the front
My bed in the back can I run I
Telephone line up to the house
So my mother could call me and put supper
Armada
Shortwave listener card
Speak to them
On the radio
Larry Cohen
How they're coming in
I think the most important thing we can work on in communication
Is 2
Make the world safer for the people who live in it
People that's what I like
Most interested in
People in there
Verilife
What's a dune
Tony Schwartz 30000 recordings later was Purdue
Just buy the kitchen sisters davia nelson and Nikki Silva
Odell from Timber B
Nina Ellis
Nginx
Mix by Jim McKee at earwax Productions in San Francisco
This week lost and found sound thanks Rena Schwartz
Gabriel Lewis
And station KQED
And WNYC
Tony Schwartz died in 2008 you can still buy his amazing recording than iTunes they're worth every penny
Thanks for the kitchen sisters for introducing me to him
Nikki Silva and davia nelson total Heroes to me
Their podcast is a central listening
It's called fugitive ways
99percentinvisible is Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery troubleman and Mero
We are brothers 91.7 FM kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin and architecture in
Interior sperm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa's talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
New of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Black podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more
A story including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio tupi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Arts on the truth podcast. Com