99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Soup pressurization solenoid switch on
Confirmed connect
Coolant hose
Coolant
Pump on
Francois
We're going to
Waiting confirm after
Suit up
These guys are about to test
Spacey
But this is not a recording of an a******
This is Cameron Smith's ground-floor studio apartment in Portland Oregon
Let's do Lisa Pate also from Portland Oregon
To the creator of the public radio program and podcast called destination DIY
Do we have to say what DIY stands for
Sure it seems for do-it-yourself
You might think build your own space suit at home is a little extreme on the DIY Spectrum if you do I totally agree with you
Is pretty crazy we've talked about a lot of
Kind of do-it-yourself projects on destination DIY we have a very broad definition of
Do-it-yourself Way Beyond the cross and Home Improvement projects
That might first spring to mind when you hear the words do it yourself
And this is definitely up there with perhaps the most daunting of DIY projects that you could imagine
Sure there are commercial companies like Virgin Galactic and explore creating their own space gear and they are DIY
In the sense that they aren't NASA
But Cameron Smith is
Handcrafting his space suit
Under the suit I wear a
Pair of long johns
I showed some socks on to them so they don't slip up on my legs when I pee
I push my legs in
And I sewed I think I'm about 25 feet now of plastic
6 hose
It's sewn into the suit and ice water circulates
Do there and it keeps
McCool
And that's absolutely critical it gets so hot in the suit that you would pass out
I what's the temperature in their eyes
117 degrees
But it's
It's really crude you
See it
I don't have a sewing machine
So I just sit on my bed and I watch
The movie or something and just do it by hand
He's not kidding the sewing looks like something out of Frankenstein
The second layer of the suit
It's called the pressure bladder
It's basically forming a bubble around Cameron's body to hold the air in
The third layer goes over that and that's the
Pressure restraint clarinets made of
Panels
Of non-elastic
Mesh
It looks like a like a cargo bags
So those are so.
Hoover the pressure bladder
Because
If you were to blow up just the pressure
Ship ladder
Contains the gas
It blows up into sort of like the Michelin Man
It in you you could
Survive
But you couldn't do anything
You can't bend your arm
You would be in kind of a spread eagle position
Floating deck
You couldn't do it
Total cost of Cameron Smith spacesuit
2000 bucks
Around 100 of 1% of the cost
Of the latest
NASA space suit
Does technology over the last
48 years has
Become much cheaper and much more available and better
You can essentially build a do-it-yourself space program today and now luckily I'm
Cameron is not an astronaut
He's not even an engineer
He's actually an archaeologist
He's on faculty in the anthropology department at Portland State
But Cameron is an Explorer by Nature
He's been diving in Puget Sound
Survived Arctic Winters in Iceland and Alaska
And some of that Oregon's Mount Hood more times than he can count
The spacesuit is his latest and most
Ambitious
Showing their tits
Possible
To do it cheaply
Is I guess my part of this larger
Movement of
Opening space up too many rather than few
The spacesuit has been three years in the making
You only have to look around Cameron's tiny apartment
To see how committed he is
This project
Instead of hanging art on the wall
Cameron has each of the suits
Three layers hanging side-by-side neck
Odoo is bad
Which is surrounded by bookshelves
Crammed full of NASA patents and other research material
His living room serves as the staging area for the gas canisters and the gondola where he test
The suit
Eventually he wants to connect that gondola
And all of the life-support gear to a balloon that will take him 50,000 feet in the air
He is also showing the balloon himself
At 50000 feet above the surface of the Earth
Cameron will experience
Space like condition
And that means he'll need his suit to protect him from extreme temperatures
And decompression sickness
And that's what you get from
Going from sea level to high altitude less pressure
And you decompress your body starts
The swell up nitrogen bubbles in your tissues start to come out of solution and they give you the bends
Divers kit
Decompression sickness
A suit with even 3 pounds of pressure per square inch
And keep a person healthy at high altitude conditions
And that's just about what Cameron suit holds on a good day
He's worked hard to try to close off all the lights
But it's an ongoing process
And Cameron knows what you think of this
I really didn't want people think I was crazy
And I was
I was really
Worried about that
Because
You know when you say okay
A balloon ended in an open Gondola underneath
The first thing people think about it
They say
Can you remember that guy who went up in a balloon in a lawn chair
Lawnchair Larry
Crazy dude
That's exactly what people think
But not everyone
Cameron is attract
Small team of
Student volunteer
Who are committed to making
The technology of space travel
More except
In the spring of 2013
They started doing we
Shiprock
BG lovers 1 2 and 3 open
Who delivers 1 2 and 3 are open
They check off items on an exhaust
Skip list
Making sure the breathing gas pressure gas and suit Cooling
When are all in place
The most expensive part of the suit and the only part of the sink that Cameron didn't build himself
Is the Soviet Air Force helmet he bought on eBay
The helmet is an exception
To my general rule of
You know I want to build it
Some things that you can easily access
Score
Basically not use things
From
Production system
Typically military
Production systems that have already sorted out all the problem
I didn't want to do that I want to solve the problems
Why I mean why reinvent the wheel these problems have presumably been solved by other people Avi
That's a great question
Why reinvent the wheel why we do the
It is any
Incredible thrill for me personally
Beat my head
Against
Problem and I
I can't figure it out and then one day I'm walking home
Or
I'm on the street
Car
What's a Eureka moment
And it's so thrilling
I got it
I have to almost run home
And build the thing and see if
So for me
You know it's an intellectual Adventure
Oh my gosh
I figure out the math can I mix the gas as properly can I make this thing home
Pressure
Can my mind can I with my mind
Solve these problems
Set a lot of fun
When Cameron puts the suit on
He starts out on the
The floor
He has to Regal and shimmy his way into the
The suits outer layer
So right now
Put my leg up like that and Ben can start getting my
My foot down
Then I blocked the inhale valve on the
Onm
You can inhale
But you can't exhale
It's a minor problem we will fix it
That doesn't sound like a minor problem
What I mean
Is that
The mechanism is so simple that I believe it can be fixed we just haven't got this
It turns out Cameron isn't the only one on the metaphorical floor wriggling into his homemade space suit
Play start a whole new radio show just about the DIY RC were trying to get themselves into space
There's this Danish company called Copenhagen suborbitals
And they're building rockets in space capsules in an abandoned Shipyard in Denver
Mike
These guys have the goal of suborbital flight in mind
Like Alan Shepard bubbles go up
And come right back down again rather than orbiting the Earth was John Glenn
Copenhagen suborbitals and Cameron Smith
The spaceship guy
They've actually been working together
Christian von Bengston is the co-founder of Copenhagen suborbitals and he's talking to Cameron about building suits for them to use
Once they're ready to replace their crash test dummy with a live human being
Christians approach to building his Space Capsule is right in line with what Cameron is doing with her
The suit a lot of the stuff we're buying is you know the Danish equivalent to Home Depot take for example
The heat shields NASA has used some pretty fancy materials like reinforced
Carbon and high-purity silica fiber
Create heat shields for the shuttle another
The Space Capsule we have
A heat shield made of
Of cork
Which is just that bored
Local carpet shop
Did you take cork like
Cork
Exactly
And a lot of people find it funny that we use cork as an heat shield and it might be a bit funny but it's the perfect solution for it
What would be the wood base
Superlative steampunk
Tree puns
Woodpunk
Arbor Punk
Harbor Freight
I like that one
Anyway
Both of these examples May on the surface
Seem as removed as possible from this league
Polished and perfectly engineered products of NASA
I mean
But they all possess the same problem solving genius needed to allow humans to exist environment
No human has any business being
When my favorite scenes in any movie is an Apollo 13
Underground base crew realizes that they have to adapt
Tsquared carbon dioxide air filters from one part of the ship
To fit into the round carbon dioxide scrubber in another part of the ship
Or all the astronauts 168 and die
But the scrubbers on the Command Module
Kingsport Court
Montana went around
Tell me this isn't a government operation
Sisters
Contingency
Remote
The CO2 levels are going to be
Toxic
Well I suggest you gentlemen have been waiting for the square peg in a round hole
That's the sound of a NASA engineers
Throwing all the available materials on the spaceship
On a table
We got to find a way
To make this
Fit into the hole for this
Using nothing but that
Let's get it organized filter
When I think of Cameron I think less
Lawnchair Larry
And more 60s engineer sporting the horn rims in the short sleeve shirt with a tie
He's scaring the parts across the table
Attacking the problem
When I have to design something very specific
And I have to look to how other people have done it if I can
I can't figure it out myself
Almost always it's the Russians
Space suits that I'm
Modeling
They never had as much money
And so they had to do things in a more inventive way
Whether you're in a garage
Where the big company or in a gondola at 50000 ft
The design process is the same
Research
Express the Prototype
Test inside
But with cameras project the stakes are significant
We hire will be so embarrassing to get killed in it
So
I'm going to make it work
Notice that he said embarrassing in that sentence not
Terrifying
Which to me sounds just like an astronaut
99% invisible with princess week by Julissa Bhatia creator of the public radio program and
Podcast destination DIY fundraising on Indiegogo to produce more stories of makers
Is Builders and off-peak creators if you want to pitch in like I did you can do a search on Indiegogo for Destination DIY
Iyo go to destination diy.org one of those rewards packages includes a really great citizens on how to make
Radio 5 a.m.
Many of you will enjoy
Program is destination DIY search for it on Indiegogo
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Avery troubleman and me Roman Mars we are project 91.7 local public
Radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Five podcast
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode
What about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You for the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars sand that Sam listens
Troubleman that's the E before the elf right now on our website if a couple of really fantastic
Pictures of Cameron's homemade space suit it really is a work of art check it out at 9 p.m.
Yeah. Org radio Temple
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com