99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name
And Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman
Watering
Lemons are squeezing
Stomach
Cabal the ads you see on TV or on billboards or on the sides of buses
It's an overwhelming number seem to be
Far food
Bisque
Bulls head
Google turkey
Chicken sausage
Morning I see coax in frosted glasses
Fajitas
Sizzling on the grill
What's in season
Matters
A guy biting into the perfect hamburger on a sesame seed bun
Ingredients perfectly cook
Duke orsino in real life
These Foods don't look like they do in the ass
I'm here with a question from Isabelle Ave from Toronto Ontario she asked why does your food look different in the advertising
In what in the store
The great question Isabel we get off that a lot
And if you want to come with me I'm going to take you across the street we're going to find out a bit more
In 2012 McDonald's Canada put out this video about the process they go through to photograph one of
Their burgers
Let me introduce you now to Noah's Ark
Food stylist
I think it's important to note that all the ingredients
No uses are the exact same ingredients
The video follows food stylist Noah as he painstakingly selects the perfect slices of us
Onion and pickle pee places them on the burger with tweezers
And then precisely melt
The cheese just so
So if I'm jacked melting down
Then he picks up a plastic syringe filled with ketchup and applies it with surgical precision
Maybe I'll put
Mustard ketchup
Actually catch up must
Then they photograph this fancy burger and Photoshop it to perfection
They place a picture of a real burger just ordered at McDonald's
Next to the image of this stylized Burger
And the difference
Is striking
That's reporter Danny Lewis
I would like to eat the burger that Noah styled into symbol
The other one not so much
The last hundred years or so of food advertising have been shaped by this one simple
Real food looks
Bad on camera
Shooting food and even photographing food is always been fiendishly difficult in that
This is Terry O'Reilly
Predict it
He was an ad man
And he now hosts a radio show about advertising
Called under the influence
Terry says the challenges of shooting food are obvious
First of all food is boring to look at when it's just sitting on a plane
Because food is he generally static
Then when you subjected to the Hot Lights of a
Studio the food starts to wilt
It's just simple science
And so advertisers have had to constantly walk this fine line between enhancement and faker
Find all kinds of tricks
To get food to look good
For the first half of the 20th century well after photography it was widely adopted
Advertisers in magazines and newspapers relied heavily on illustration
The reason illustration
What's the preferred method was because you can completely control an illustration
Another word just know lighting issues there's no wilting food issues
A marketer could really completely dick
Tate what that food would look like right down to the to the strand of pasta
With an illustrate
Then TV came along in the 1950s and 60s
And advertisers face a whole new set of challenges
I'm going to show you how McDonald's build a Big Mac sandwich
A lot of them didn't really understand how to shoot food in a compelling way
In this add the hamburger just sits there on the counter
All the ingredients get piled on
It starts here with a lightly Toasted Bun
And then a pure beef hamburger
Sizzling hot
Without compelling visuals
Optavia voiceover
Just describing the hell out of the
The food
Listing ingredients
Telling you how good it tasted
A little more sauce just for good flavor
Crisp dill pickles
And the sesame seed crown
These early tv ads relied on relatively static shots
Advertisers would use a wide-angle lens mounted on a camera
Animated Superman and pain a little but that's about it
There were lots of shots of boxes
And labels
The food did
Just normal food stuff you might see
Something being ladled out of a pot you might see you know a spoon
Serving peas at a dinner table or serving cream corn at a dinner table
So that would be the extent of the motion
On top of the new challenges of television
Food advertisers in the late 60s found themselves facing new scrutiny the Federal Trade Commission with keeping a close eye
Ion TV
Following now infamous
Campbell Soup incident
They were introducing a new brand of suit that has a lot of vegetables in it but the problem is the vegetable sink to the bottom
So what they did was
Put a bunch of marbles in the bottom of the bowl
Just too high.
The
When the FTC found out they threaten Campbell's with legal Act
Event led to a new push for truth in advertising
A lot of the old tricks advertisers had relied on it for now off the table
No more using glue
Milk and cereal ads
No more substituting mashed potatoes for ice cream
But in the 1970s
Food advertising took a radical
Started
Shrimp executing acrobatic flips
Lobster claws cracking open in slow motion
French fries bouncing across a table
Wasn't static anymore
Food was flying
And we've got one man to thank for this new aesthetic
Albert Beauty
You didn't want anything
Everything was always smooth
He wanted to
Romance
The food
Or whatever was in front of
This is Harry Drennan
Who spent years working for Elbert beaudin
That's how he met his wife
Set director Jackie Chan
I've been in the film business for
35 years 40 I don't want to say hello
The ads that can tow in Trenton made with you until his death in 1996
We're on precedent
Working with clients like McDonald's Burger King and Coca-Cola invented a whole new visual language
Food commercial
Sandra Lee Pioneer the genre of advertising known
As table top
Many of the terms and techniques that table top directors still use date back to Beauty
The prep shot
Which tells the backstory of the Prada
Showing all that goes into making the food
You know the ones
Chopping a crisp out of lettuce
Dicing some juicy red tomatoes
He would make these
Elaborate banquet things
Raw ingredients
That was his look
And creepshots
That's when the camera zooms way in and lingers on some tantalizing bite of food on the end of a fork
Sexy and you know it's almost foodporn you know it's
Made it all real tactel to you
And the hero shot
The last magnificent look at the food
On the plate ready to eat
Usually in the final seconds of the advertising
Mutants big breakthrough was that he didn't just describe the food and promised viewers it takes
He made them feel actual
Hunger with his image
His real thing is just food in itself its Essence is really sensual
You know what I mean
Juicy Hamburger commercial
Point of it
And I think that's what he introduced
And you'll never see it any other way now
Kendall and Drennan remember working long days and
Sometimes tomorrow
To meet budenz hi-standard
And to achieve his vision of flying food
Mouth watering clothes
They had to use a whole bunch
Crazy tool
Like giant high speed camera that was burned through 1000 feet of film in seconds
They start shooting
All day long it was something originally designed for the military
Go ballistic but we were the first ones to do it with food
Super slow motion effect
You take a split second of time
And luxuriate in it
He'd have oranges Splash through a sheet of water
Condensation would drip down the side of a bottle
In order to get the perfect egg
Butan started designing strange
Rube Goldberg soda machines album get the job done
These Contraptions were called rigs
They range from simple spouts for liquid to machines that would drop pancakes into a perfect stack to catapults that would
Languages across the studio
And sure the production team could have just thrown The Oranges by hand
But with a rig
They could get the exact
Same result
Over and over
Which meant fewer takes
Which meant less time and less money spell
Also meant that they could achieve a certain level of
Precision and artist
It was so much prettier than other people
It's working
Far as I could see
Is beautiful and Lighting
And then with Iowa once he got into all the movement that me he was it
He was ahead of the curb
Lights roll Steve
To see how beautance techniques are still being used today
Danny went to MacGuffin films in New York okay so just quit
MacGuffin does commercials for Red Lobster Olive Garden Starbucks in a bunch by the restaurant
Today Danny was there they were shooting a chicken sandwich so they are shooting a chicken sandwich
Sure Shot it looks like on a black
Sleep
A little Trail
Chili Peppers and garlic and stuff
A hand model stands near the edge of the table for the sandwiches play so now they're doing the crowning
Crowning means the hand model takes the bun
And put it on top of the sandwich
Does President there alluringly
Ben takes the crown off
Fan brush tattoo
Top of the chicken
Then the ground goes back on again
It took them all day to film this sandwich
The whole shoot precisely orchestrated
Relying on highly technical tool
Downstairs in macguffins proper I'm there all sorts of rig sitting in storage
A lot like the ones that butan develop
But these are way more high-tech
Riggers today use lasers and sensors and pre-programmed Motors
And depending on the shot or the rig
There can be some intense physic to take into account
Like if you're trying to slice an onion into while it's flying through the air break down the elements
Got to get it done yin to a certain height
This is Anthony the robber
He's a special effects technician at MacGuffin films
And he designed a special rake just to get this shot
These two sharp knives come through split the onion and leave you with the sliced in the middle
And slices of onion artfully tumbling across a table
Classic truck shop
But Wellbutrin may have introduced rigs in action to tabletop
Some directors like macguffins Nick fugles.
We're trying to get away from humans Fantastical Dreamscapes of flying shrimp
I think that's a little bit of an older point of view for next few ghosts at images of food that be
Tried to bring to his ads
Just don't cut it in a world that's now totally saturated with food poi
Well Butrans commercials often zoomed-in so close to food that you couldn't see the space around it
Tabletop directors like Google start now frame there food in the space that you might see out in the world
Like at a restaurant or barbecue
And when you dig into a lasagna do you want the sauce to go all over the place
We need to taco stuff going to fall out yet so let's shoot
Let it the flavors mix
It's alright sweet taste good
But the thing to remember is this
On the set of a food commercial
Everything
Is highly orchestrated and contrived
Even if the ultimate effect feel somewhat natural
Because a 30-second TV spot by a firm like Magoffin can cost literally hundreds of thousands of dollars
Who's got to do one thing to make it all worthwhile
Sell a lot of food
I would say the number one rule
In food advertising is that the first taste is always with the eyes
So you trying to create a shot
That makes somebody's
This is Terry O'Reilly again
And he's fascinated by the links people go to sell some
He tells a story about working on commercial for a hamburger company
And watching an actor do take after take
Bite into a hamburger
And I'm gazing into the camera with a log of total satisfaction on his face
Then you cut and then there's this
Right beside the actor then they just spit it right into the pale
And you have any watch that happen 40 times or 30 times or 20 minutes so hilarious to me
Just the mechanics
Hematocrit
The illusion and the reality of creating if that's exactly it in a nutshell
Play 99% invisible wolf producer Suite by Danny Lewis Delaney Hall in Avery truffle
Wicked same Greenspan Sharif Youssef Kolstad and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Terry O'Reilly who hosts under the influence on the CBC on our website
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced of the offices of Arkansas
In architecture and Interiors firm
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Talking to
To me and my wife
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of sun
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is Frost
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
Family goes
Skinner podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look
The story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets
Scrolled in the newly discovered stock
Love letters
Eastern episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The Proud Family ghost
Wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299 pi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous
Actor has to get really
Jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm Evan I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com