99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along for the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
What do Brazilian soccer player scores a goal
Start slow
And it builds until it reaches a glorious crescendo
They do this all over the world now
But it started in Brazil
And there's something particularly triumphant about today
That's producer Joe Sykes
That's what is soccer means so much
Brazil
How can I explain what soccer means to Brazilians without sounding corny but I think I'm going to have to sound corny okay
That's Fernando Duarte
A BBC journalist who wrote a book about Brazilian soccer
Soccer or football as I cool it being British
Arrived in Brazil in the late 19th century
At first it was a game played in Elite Circle
But poor and working-class Brazilians
Struggle to make the game that right
The only time
The elites were
Robbed while they were deprived of something
By the poor people by the
Kung fu
Israel football season
To be a game for the elite and it became a sport
Soccer eventually became so popular and beloved in Brazil that their national team soccer jersey has become as much
A national symbol as the country's flag
Going to see many more people Mizzou
Wayne Insurance then waving the flag
The sense of belonging
No matter if you were
You know peanuts
Picking up olds
Soda cans on the street or if you were a millionaire
When you wear that shirt you just like
One of us
Play shirts or extruder
Playoffs entry light
If I think the word is
Horoscopes
That's the soccer writer and historian David cobra
Eyes shut
The Brazilian soccer shirts are so iconic that non soccer fans all over the world can often picture them
For those of you who can
The shirt is a bright
Canary yellow with green trim around the collar and sleeves
They're worn with blue shorts
Pure primary blue
Compared with other soccer jerseys the uniform is
Joyful and bold
It seems to capture something essential about Brazil
But it wasn't always this
In fact Brazil used to play in plain unremarkable white shirt
The story of how the uniform change goes back 70 years
To an epic soccer game that Brazilian
Never forget
After years of lobbying the World Cup arrived in Brazil in 1950
At the time the country was culturally and internationally kind of unknown
This was Brazil's big moment to show the world what it was made of
The 1950 World Cup was understood by the Brazilian population as an opportunity
Site of the world
Brazil Fitzroy
They need this world cup was that chance to tell everyone
We have mold noise we have been transformed we moved from being
Agricultural plantation economy 2nu
Industrialized economy
And this is my wife showing it
The main symbol of that coming out apart from what was happening on the soccer field
Worcester Stadium
Name the Maracana
In Rio de Janeiro
It looks like the stadium from outer space
I mean it just fish
Fabulous
Flat
White concrete over with amazing flying buttresses
Just like this huge flying suicide that a drop down in the center of the city
The thumb with the Sleep Fred Wilson
Surprise Stadium Pilsen
Do they have the stadium
The people behind them
The government was pushing the tournament whenever possible
Now they needed was a successful team
The expectations were high because of this hope
Klimatyzacja atmosphere of optimism
In one of the earlier games Brazil strike competently onto the field and at what unit
And proceeded to demolish Sweden
7 to 1
Resume absolutely
Fantastic in the ivy rails I was slaughtering everybody that scoring goals over the play
Play Sleepy Spain
They used to be Mexico and Yugoslavia
The tournament was going exactly to
Ulysses home
Atmosphere of like
Sporting Bliss
I have to do is got to draw of Uruguay in the last match
Because of a court in the tournament structure
Uber CEO had to do to win the World Cup was
Tie against Uruguay in that final game
Uruguay historically had been a really strong team
Even though there are tiny country almost 50 times smaller than Brazil
But by the time this 1950 World Cup came along
Uruguay it was a waning power in soccer
So beating them or at least playing them
Seemed totally doable
Not a problem
Stihl Uruguay was no pressure
Especially when they were playing games Brazil
Uruguay actually used to be a Brazilian province
Do they have this chip on their shoulder
About that older
Big guy next door neighbor
The whole thing of
Uruguayan
Going against the odds
Fighting against a colonial power
Spread the Moon
Meanwhile the whole of Rio is now thinking about just one thing
The World Cup final
There really is
My sister about to everybody nice body
Everyone's engaged with it
Everyone wants to go knowing from Schuylkill think about anything else
In Brazil people like sedative everybody who claimed to have been in the stadium that afternoon was actually there
The stadium would have needed to be the size of the Moon
And it was a big crowd
Some estimate that there were 250000 screaming fans packed into this Flying Saucer Stadium
Which is something like 80000 people
Overcapacity
And the players
When they walked out with just head with this rule of noise
The place is noisy is Wilkinson
But in the first half neither team scores
So the crowd is getting nervous
Everybody was getting tense
Then finally Brazil scores a goal just off the halftime
Olosho across the goalkeeper into the bottom corner than that and it's just this relay
Delete that surges
Pool around the crowd
Even the journalist run on and embrace the Plaza
Because basically everyone there thinks the game is all over
That Brazil has won the World Cup
Then Uruguay stores
About halfway through the second half
The description by whoever was days I just ate and fell
Very very nervous and this nervousness
Went to the play It's almost like they were losing the game
And then comes the moments
Everybody we've always in the rain
Alcides jija one of the year ago and winners gets the pool and dribbles down the right side toward the go
I'm just as he's looking out to Boston boo he notices
That's a
The goalkeeper Barbosa was actually walking
To try to anticipate the cross
Which meant Barbosa was out of position
Instead of passing the ball shoots
Older pools talk about the most
Student silence
Stadium
LCD G1 setting in his book
Only three people in the history of the mannequin
Aleister Crowley
Frank Sinatra
Pope John Paul II
Me
It's almost like a gravy
Some of the plays don't even remember what happened
State of Catatonia something
As you probably guessed by now Brazil does not manage to get another goal to Die the game
And Uruguay
When's
If the game ends the fan stream out of the stadium in back
Onto the streets of Rio
He's almost like
Some kind of hopeless happening people just
Went somewhere else
There was a
City of Solitude
This feeling of a
Of numbness
And Rio de Janeiro wasn't a Party City on the night
On the night of July 16
There was a lot of public crying that's a lot of heart Hubley
1 Brazilian playwright cools to defeat
Brazil's Russia
Alright well that's just ridiculous
Which I think is
Bison board price
An exaggeration
Boss
People were really flying away
The recriminations came thick and fast
And soon races accusation starts to fly
Barbarossa the guy who played goalkeeper for
The Brazilians was black
D and two other black players on the team was scapegoated in the popular press
I'm Baba she was even hassled on the street
His life was my difficult that's tragic story he tells lights are in life
Of hearing woman are whispering to a child
This is the matter you might order Brazil cry
Often. The Brazilian team didn't pick another black goalkeeper
To start in the World Cup
Iva 50 years
And this wasn't a coincidence
Off to that game black goalkeepers were regarded as less reliable than white ones
Which is disgusting
But Barbosa wasn't the only focus of Brazilian
Everything about Brazilian soccer
Was scrutinized
Down to the uniforms the players were wearing
Tell towards his father the white shirt was cursed and I think everybody else in Brazil did
Add a bubble that was a
It's time animation
Never
Plain white shirts
It was pretty unusual for a team to completely transform their uniform
Most countries have played in the same colors since the
The first World Cup back in the early 20th century
The Brazilians decided their uniform was a problem
So in 1953 the Brazilian soccer authorities set up a competition
And advertised it international newspaper that's distributed all over Brazil
They wanted people to write in with their designs for a new
The contest had only one stipulation
The color of the uniform had to include the colors of the Brazilian flag
Green blue white and yellow
I designed it would truly represent Brazil
Hundreds of people enter the
Including
This guy
Naomi shimada
Csuci name is OG Garcia
Then I'm found on the board with
Aldea Garcia Chile
He was just 19 when he entered the competition
A young man who had grown up in a little town right on the border
Between Brazil and Uruguay
Slay wasn't designer
He was working a local newspaper as an illest
He says when he first heard about the competition
Ethio it'll be too difficult
Female breast
Yeah the first impression I had was that Jesus was foolish
That was ridiculous because it's rare to have a team with 4 colors
Working for colors into just the shirt
Would have been hard but eventually slay realize he could use the whole uniform to spread out the colors
He tried blue shorts with a green shirt
A yellow and green striped shirt with white shorts
A green and yellow striped shirt with blue shirt
He came up with over 200 different designs
Until eventually
He had it
Blue shorts
White Sox
And a yellow shirt with green trim around the neck in the sleeves
He sent the design off and a few weeks later he look down at the newspaper and saw his design
Staring back at him
He had one
Has any size
Engines for sale
After that was just a party
My feet didn't touch the ground and I will celebrate in The Newsroom where they were
It was like something Impossibles had just happiness
Aa31 Schlegel to bask in the glory of it all
For a while
You went to Rio
Did an internship with the newspaper that expunged
Even live with the Brazilian Plaza
For a few months
But eventually
He returned to his Motown
I'm kind of forgot about the shop
For a while
But pretty soon the shot was
Brazil
In 1962 the Brazilians won the World Cup
In Chile
And they were wearing
Play
Uniform
Players like Pele wore the yellow shirt in dazzled the world with their extraordinary skill and beauty
Ben color TV comes along
In the whole world can watch Brazil in brand-new Technicolor
Like in the 1970 World Cup in Mexico
Going to 5 when the 1970 World Cup was played on ice or Brazil win the 70 World Cup
In shimmering yellow shirt
His soccer store in David dobrik
Mermaid
Skin advisor memories at I think most people had even if they didn't see it
A vassal of brilliance
Of amazing citic Glide
South sunshine
Leopard seal head
Failed in 1950
The following years to success
Office success
They won World Cup off the World Cup
Daniella Chavez
Becoming as much homework
Is that intricate footwork
Dazzling play
Slaves design became icon
A symbol of Brazil
Full of sun and life
But for sleigh life wasn't quite living up to the image of Brazil he had created
He started working as a writer and academic
In a 1964
A brutal us backed military dictatorship
Power
Youku
And It Go like demonstration
Miami Airport
The new military government
Crackdown on people that considered to be severe
Including academics
Like a lot of other professors and students
Today was arrested
Did for basically being on the political life
What do you call a
He was expelled from his teacher
And was banned from leaving the country
Is pussy a man
Yeah I was traumatized
My wife and my children will suffer a lot
Sophia was moving to
The dictatorship lasted for about 20 years but despite the difficulties of living under the watchful eye of them
Military police
Play became a successful writer
I need developed
And academic specialty
Play spent his life writing about the border between Brazil and Uruguay
It was so easy. Don't I am a citizen who has a heart
Antibody divided between Brazil and Uruguay
Slay one
Technically born in Brazil
But less than a mile from the border with Uruguay
Is that when he was a kid
His father helped build a bridge across the river.
Separates Uruguay
Brazil
Your soul
Bluetooth
I am from the era when the bridge was built
My father went to help do the breed
So I always been very connected to
Slave experience growing up between two country
And his experiences under military rule
I've helped shape his feelings about Brazilian nausea
Even though he designed to shut that could be considered more patriotic
Brazilian flag
He's actually very wary of patriotism
NY DEC corn Quality quality
It is an idea that competes with the ones that I have
Geneva. Limit
Live Without Borders
Tingley Beach
Slay may not be a Brazilian Patriot
But the soccer fan in him can't help but be proud of the Brazilian team
Most blessyouboys
Brazil won a championship
5 time
This is a source of pride
Is the owner
For all of us
Which Les has a secret
Or at least something he never used to share with people who knew he was the designer of the famous yellow shirt
Slave routes for Uruguay
Dominium Rizzo this is blasphemy
But not for him
We Are One People
One border community
Even if you have a true languages the people have only one culture identity
But he ultimately had to pick one country's team
Football
Did you feed stomach
Soccer advised me to
So these days
When Brazil plays Uruguay
Slay like lava the song
Fancy suit shop
Annie's favorite jazz
But not the yellow shot he design
A sky blue one
The color of Uruguay
Then he crosses the border from Brazil to Uruguay
I'm fine some quiet bar
Watch the game
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Joe Sykes
Delaney Hall inmate Fitzgerald
Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
Technical production in mix by Sharif Youssef
With music by Shawn real and melodeon
The English voice over for the story with dunbine a auto show
Katie mingle is our senior editor Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Intermezzo is the office manager
We'd like to think Alex Bellows for his help Alex was the first English journalist to write about the story
Penis in the right direction
Jr Mazda and Bobby Orr know they also fix everything up in Brazil and translated our interview which lie
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad to take laxatives
Does routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and doing discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we do me at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
Run Instagram Tumblr and have a nice supper hit too but this week we have two articles by Kurt about the naming
Numbering in categorization colors
Website
99 pi
Dot org Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com