99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Here's a trick if you want to design a good flag
Kickass Blacklick Chicago's rdcs
Start by drawing a 1 by 1 and 1/2 inch rectangle on a piece of paper
Your design has to work within that tiny rectangle
3 by 5 foot flag on a
Pull a hundred feet away
Looks about the same size as
A
1 by 1 and 1/2 in
Rectangle seeing about 15 inches from your eye
2 instead of starting with a big canvas for a wide Cinema display
Try drawing your flag
On a rectangle is 1 by 1 and 1/2 in
You'll be surprised at how compelling and simple the design can be
When you hold yourself
To that limitation
That my friends is Ted k
Ted K I live here in Portland Oregon and I'm involved in the study of flags
When I went to his house in Portland he flew the San Francisco flag out front in honor of my visit
That's the kind of guy to cast I'm in love with the Portland flag Association we are a Loosely organized
Group of people interested in Flags
And we are the largest sub national flag organization in the country with the largest membership
Ship around 25 to Spain number
The most frequent meeting schedule and the greatest amount of publishing a lot of his fellow backs
Philologist
What's a person who studies Flags
Ted is especially interested in flag design mini other vexillologist are more focused on History protocol
Send usage
There's one school of thought that says
We are flag Scholars and every flag is equally
Appropriate to study
And whether we like the design or not is immaterial we should be dispassionate scholar
But then there are people in the second group like
Dad and me at this point actually
Pool of beautiful flags and go out in the world and Lobby
For better or
Those who are in the second Camp have identified it
A name for those
And that's avexa Lanier
An activist vexillologist
You listen to show for a very very long time you know that when it comes to designing Flags
There are rules and principles being
Keep it simple
Use meaningful symbolism
Use two to three basic colors
No lettering or seals
And be distinctive
Extended Stay
But one rule the fourth one
No lettering or seals
That rule for some reason Americans just can't grasp
We have tons of flags
And that's bad that's why you shouldn't have a seal on it
A seal is designed
To be on a piece of paper
To be seen
Close up
Flat not moving
And only one side of the paper
A flag
Is meant to be seen
From a distance
On a piece of fabric
That's moving
And might be seen on the front or the back
Seals don't belong on flags seals belong on pieces of paper
Damn right
What are the Intriguing things about the fact that Ted gay
And the largest sub national flag organization are both based in Portland is that Portland
Official flag of the first 100 Years of its existence
Portland had several flags that had been
Proposed and not officially adopted even though people thought they've been adopted but that was about to change in 1960
C9
A group proposed a flag to the
City
The group was the commercial Club of Portland
The proposed design consisted of a Whitefield
Does the background color
With a
With a city seal
Engulf the center
Flanked by two red roses on either side
And then the words
Worldport of the Pacific on top
City of roses
Below
I think I might have to go lie down
And mayor Terry schrunk
Who was
A very astute politician
Look at this design and said
I'm not capable of deciding on a flag design for the city of Portland this is a job for the Portland Arts Commission
Smart guy indeed
But this decision set into motion one of the greatest tragedies and Redemption
Vexillological history
The Arts commission selected esteemed local artist named Doug Lynch to create a brand new design
Prominent graphic designer that called him a commercial artist at the time
Asking about the city council and the Arts commission which attributes should be on the flag as you might expect
The
Members of the
City Council
Had a different View
What a flag should look like
From what the Arts commission members look like
You don't say the City commissioners were
They wanted realism they wanted the name of the city on the flag
They wanted
Lots of stuff on the flag of the
Parks commissioner said it should be abstract it shouldn't have words on it
Much more consistent with our modern perception of what good flag design is so Doug
Went into The Fray and designed flag
That did not have a rose on it
Did not have the name of the city on it it was an abstract design Doug's design was a
I will call it an offset cross if you go to our website or pull out your phone you'll see a variation of this flag that
Doug Lynch proposed
It's incorporated into the Comfort I love this episode
Two lines crossing from
Top to bottom and left to right in the center
Creating a
Void in a center that
Is called a hypocycloid a 4 pointed star
The blue lines that cross represented the Confluence of the Columbia and Willamette rivers
The flight hypocycloid represented the city of Portland at their confluence
And then
Those stripes were bordered by yellow stripes gold Stripes which represented either Commerce or
Grain flowing along the rivers and everything was on a background of green representing
The forest
It's really lovely
City council said Thank You for Your Design and change the upper left-hand
Corner
From green to blue and put the city Ceylon
And adopted that flag
I know all the graphic designers in the audience were digging half-moon-shaped scars in the meat of their palms upon here
Violation thumb was more painful that this Abomination was so close to being a really good flag
The one that Doug Lynch had originally submitted
A few years to the city council version of the flag made it out into circulation in 1973
But being a
Relatively poor design with that City seal on it most people can't tell it's the city seal even
Hannibal yellow
Blob on blue
The flag was never
Widely Sloan
So nearly 30 years later Doug Lynch join the Portland flag Association
He was in his late eighties
And I invited him to come to one of our meetings
And explain this whole story of how he had
Designed the flag
How it was adopted and how was changed at the last minute
At the end of the presentation
Said
If I had to do it
Over again I would widen the blue stripes the center of the flag over a little
Take that upper left-hand Corner which is blue and change it back to green and he would take that City seal
Off the flag
How to make all those that's how I would do the flag but it's been 30 years
Too late now
And they're like whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa wait a minute
We're the largest of national flag organization in the country it's not too late
Sitting around the table
Are the person who has written the history of the flag of the city of Portland
The person who has written the guide book on flag design
The person who actually manufactures those flags and you who designed it
We ought to be able to get this changed
And with the help of future Portland mayor Sam Adams they presented an ordinance to the city council
To update the flag
My son Mason who had written the history of the city flags
Portland testified I testified
Mike Hale
Who was the owner of Elmer's Flag & Banner who
Manufactured it testified
And Doug Lynch
Testify
Right hand
Doug
Was a revered figure in
Design in Portland and
The commission
Ineffective bowed and said
You're the right person to tell us what this designer to look like
We agree with your decide
And the mayor mayor Vera Katz
What's the time
The mayor said
That's great
Come back next week and will adopt it but bring a real flag
Can you do that
And my tail
Owner of the Flag Company gulfton said yes we can do that
And so the next week
He had his seamstresses sew up a new city of Portland flag
We
Came to the city council hearing
The council
Held a vote on the ordinance 520 they
Adopted the flag
And meerkats said
Pointing to the old flag on the flagpole
Take that down and put it in archives can you put that new flag up
And so one of our members John Hood
Went over and
Put the flag on a flagpole in the city council chambers
Being the first one to raise
Official city of Portland flag
The correct
City of Portland flag
This current fight with all the updates that Doug Lynch wanted is the graphic that's on the front of the podcast
If you haven't done so already pulling out have a look
Handsome
Good flag
Best of all people in Portland actually use it
Especially because of a soccer game
If you don't see your City flag anywhere in your hometown
Maybe it needs a redesign to
But that's just the Vex linear me talking
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco home with a very bad flag
And produced by the offices of arcsin
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Home of a pretty good black
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify
Pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99pi
You must go
299 pi
Radio tupi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com