99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Here's someone you should know Julie Shapiro and executive producer of radiotopia and we're going to talk about showcase
Showcase is a new project from radiotopia in the first series in showcase
Happens to make a good 99% of the
So I asked Julie to come talk to
And this is very much
Your product that yours. So can you tell us a little bit about Showcase in the announcer for the mission of radiotopia
Sure World Showcase directly came out of our experience with podcast which we ran about a year ago where we invited
Anyone and everyone to submit podcast ideas about whatever they were interested in that wanted to make a podcast about
And we got over 1,500 entries muchos wants got your hustle it's now
A show in radiotopia
What's the thing that I'm popular show in a very very proud of anime
He's at the response has been getting a Dutch rabbit
I'm the point was we had so many great ideas
But they weren't all necessarily
Sustainable long-term show ideas and that will what if radiotopia could get
Behind
A podcast that featured
All of these different ideas one after another
I without them being separate podcast that had to go out and gain their own audience and live on their own
How could we
Use the radiotopia name and reputation to help support even more producers with different kinds of ideas that wouldn't
Beyond going shows
And so what showcase is one podcast that has limited run series one after another with you
Are short breaks in between
And these will be shows up
All strikes were really going to play with Forum play with topic
Gina push boundaries
Giving you producers a chance and really
See how we can provide like really high quality listening for our audiences
How do you conceive of something
That
Sort of sticks together holds together enough
To be a
Radiotopia showing to represent
Are values in a certain
But also be desperate enough
You'll make this an experiment worth having
I'm just looking for ideas that I know like I'm interested in automatically I haven't heard anything like that before
But the producer kind of fit the radiotopia profile their independence are highly ambitious
They have
Big ideas about the subject that they're bringing to my attention
But they have sent
Humor and they can play a little bit
And there's sound inclined I think every pitch I'm considering right now has a lot of sound involved because
That's really a Hallmark of a lot of radiotopia shows as a
Careful crafting
Again how to experiment with the farm how to hear from new voices so
Part of it is like what are topic
Text we haven't heard yet you know go in those directions
And also just stopped encourage people to like really
Come up with something
Brand new original something we can
Take a bit of a risk on because
Hoverboard is going to be in
Trying something new and giving listeners like a new listening experience
Typo
Podcast for
Be adventurous listener and I'll reward that
Type of person
It seems like just I'm going to just do this like input my 9 IP I had on a zit from a design perspective
Why all one podcast
Through this format what are you what type of experience are you trying to shape answer cultivate
With the audio
That's a really good question cuz we also talked about all of these series just being separate podcast there's some liability
Here what will people stick with it from one to the next
I really hope you know the through line for all the series is going to be
An original radiotopia incentives
Surprise air quality
And no matter what the topic is hope
Play people will tune in
I'm in your people thinking of it as a showcase
Experience
Just thinking about the series that comes up next Thursday
Really having this like
Comprehensive sense of what this offering is from radiotopia
Right I mean that's the thing I like about it cuz there's something about this where
You know hopefully you you get a little further into it
To judge
You know because
You trust the idea of the channel
Like it it means something
To be
A listener to
To showcase
Ascenso
I'm just really intrigued by the new type of listening that might come out of that
That isn't based around
Building
I had around
A single pot
You know we talked about radiotopia as the account of music label a lot and
So this is kind of like a
Compilation
Record LP to CD series
And so obviously
I have a few lined up like I don't want to spoil anything but can you talk
Being generally about the types of shows that are going to be on
Bring a kickoff with a very sort of essayistic
Sound rich
Series about listening in the digital age how listening has shifted for us through analog technology
Changing into transforming into digital technology
And this was proposed by a musician Damon Creek
Ask who
Was in a band that I used to love Galaxie 500 and then Damon & Naomi
Yeah yeah I had to get over that to begin with when we started talking to him
But he has an ex-girlfriend
Rating on iTunes
So this is a perfect example he's actually wrote a book about this
In the past year and we were talking about how that had to be a podcast it was about listening shifting from analog to digital culture how
How do you represent that through sound
And in a way that people can understand it wouldn't be too Technical and wouldn't be too
In a sort of intellectualize but I'm
How do how does he convey how lives are changing through these technological shifts and so
He came up with six different episodes of sort of based on the book but it's really departed from the book and become its own engines called ways
Days of hearing
And that's what we're going to kick off the Showcase with and I think there couldn't be a better
Starter series because it's really about how we listen how we listen in this age
And I really want to get people engaged with their ears and thinking about you
What is it about podcasting that they respond to
This is ways of hearing
Listening in the digital age
Radiotopia showcase
The first record I made was all analog
Wasn't a choice
That's just how it was done in Haiti
My friends and I lived in an all analog world
There were no computers in our lives
That didn't feel weird
It would have been weird if there happened
The time
Computers with something you saw on TV
During a moon shot
You suck people sitting at computer
Did NASA Mission Control
Ignition sequence start
Wasn't anything like a moonshot it didn't use numbers
Is data plural
Involved
The tape decks mixing board microphones
They all seemed very magical
But they were made of magnet
Gears Motors electricity
Like all the mechanical objects in our lives then
And so my bandmates and I
Set up our instruments and Studio
Recounted off
And we played our songs
In many ways
It simply Nostalgia to think that it was so different
People Are People
Sounds of sounds
And our technology is always changing
Still
There's something particular about that analog experience
Seems hard to conjure back up in the digital press
For that very reason
It feels important to try
Human analog Studio
It was a feeling when the tape started rolling
That this was the moment we would capture
Feeling of time
Moving both more slowly
And more quickly than usual
Like when you're in an accident
Which split-second suddenly so palpable as if you're living in slow motion it would we say
It all happened in an instant
Analog recording
It's like an accident in other ways
Untape
There was no undue
You could try again
If you have the time and money
But you couldn't move
Backwards
What's done
Better
And worse
Today
Life is a musician is very
In the digital Studio
I'm using one now
Everything you do is provisional
That is it can be redone reshaped
Rebuilt
There's no commitment
Because each element of recording can be endlessly changed
You can even be conjured from digital scratch
And entered into a computer directly as data
Without anyone performing at all
This means there's no moment from lived experience
Is captured forever
Unalterably cell
The digital Studio
Which is why it's more than nostalgia
It makes me remember the analog Studio
It's different than what we know today
Because the digital era
Has not resulted or tools for working with sound
Rematch
Removing images
It is changing our relationship
The time itself
This is ways of hearing
6 part podcast from radiotopia showcase
Exploring nature of listening in our digital world
I'm gaming Krakowski
Musician and a writer
In each episode
We'll look at a different way that the switch from analog to digital audio is changing our perceptions
Time
Space
Love money
Power
This is about sound
The medium we're sharing together now
But I'm worried about the quality of that sharing
Because we don't seem to be listening to each other very well right now in the world
Our voices carry further
Did they ever did before
Thanks to digital media
But how would they been her
Apus
I said one time
Musicians note
Time is flexible
Classical players call this tempo rubato
Italian for stolen time
You still a bit here
Give it back there
Jazz players called swing Rock and Funk players
Call a cruise this flexibility of time is something we're all familiar with
Whether or not we play an instrument
There's the time it takes for Don to arrive while you lay awake
After a nightmare
And there's the time it takes
You're out all night with your friends
What musicians terms like Votto swing and groove
Acknowledge
Is it time is experienced
Not counted like a clock
In our experience of time is very
It's always
Changing
Even if our eyes look at a clock
Nc12 equal hours
Are ears
Are ready to steal a bit here
Give it back
Back there
The analog media
We used to reproduce sound
Records & Tapes
Select this variable sense of time
A time that's a last
The first turntables victrolas
Square hand crank
You wound up a spring
Spawn the platter as a wound down
Speed was hardly static
At least never for long
At the opposite end of the 20th century
Hip-hop DJs used speed controls on turntables
To change the tempo of a wrecker
Domatcha to another and keep the group going
Or in the studio
Pileup samples from older records
And make a new one
In 1990
A Tribe Called Quest
Sample Bass from Walk on the Wild Side
Along with the surface noise from the lp
Added it to a drum loop from a Lonnie Smith LP
And made a new hit out of
They also have to give up
Royalty
One of the
Biggest samples
That
We were able to clear was the Walk on the Wild Side by Lou Reed
And
And by clearing that he just took 100% of that song
He did
That's Ali Shaheed Muhammad from A Tribe Called Quest
Frannie Kelley
They host a podcast about hip-hop called microphone check
Yeah that's
This is song 500 we ripped off The Velvet Underground way more than you do
We didn't have to pay them in time
Diastole
How tribe use the variable speed of turntable
To make your own record
I know sometimes we would change the speed on a turntable because
Staple hip-hop turntable is good
Technics 1200 so that has a pitch control we would sometimes
Pitch it by there sometimes
A 33 RPM record you put it on 45
One thing with tribe
We layered
Certain sound and saw you kind of had to pitch them cuz often
They weren't in the same key
Layering sounds
Tribe Called Quest
Discovered something else about their sample
The records we were recording
They might not have been playing to a metronome
And it would free-flowing so their moments with in let's say even a toolbar phrase
That may be a drummer or bass player like we're a line in the first two bars infratemporal seem to be consistent
The last
Three beats of a bar It sped up or slow down
The songs My bandmates and I recorded slowed down and sped up
Just like always Shaheed described
I know because I was the drummer
Who played as steadily as we could
But this was a performance
We were nervous and excited
And we sped up at the Quarry
You might find that a Florida recordings
Or you might feel it's a part of their charm
Musicians have been speeding up at the chorus for as long I'm sure as there have been choruses
Our experience of time is
Flexible
But not long after we recorded that first Galaxie 500 album
The commercial music world
For the most part
Decided that this was most definitely a
Flaw
Bands on major labels
Even bands who came out of our DIY Indie scene
Started recording to a click track
That is a metronome
Fashion to music come and go at the time
Everyone was also using the swirling effect
Call the flanger
No one remembers why
But the click track
Poop more than a fad
It was a change that stuck
Because what truly changed in popular music during the 1980s
With a digital machines enter the mix for the first time
A machine have a different sense of
Time
First drum machines to be widely used in commercial recordings were introduced in 1980
And MIDI
Musical instrument digital interface
The language machines used to share musical information with one another
Was launched in 1983
Together
These tools can lock musical time 2:00
Doesn't speed up
Chorus
Galaxie 500 recorded we played our songs and what audio engineer is now referred to as real time
Real-time as the name implies is live time
Time as we experience it in the analog world
Digital time
Is not live time
It's machine time
It's locked to a clock
Annette clock the time code
Makes everything more regular
In live time
Time in the digital Studio
Is stored in discrete cells on a grid
Like figures on a spreadsheet
And if you've ever worked with a spreadsheet
You know those cells can be sorted any which way and we figured
To most any desired outcome
What this means is that a given experience a digital time is only one among many equally plausible
Experiences
Take this podcast you listening to
Since this is digital medium
You can choose to hurry me up
Without changing the pitch of my voice
Seemingly without changing any of my words or pronunciation
Which means I can be equally fast
Sitting at 1.5 times my normal Pace like a manic
Or
I can be equally slow
Speaking at 3/4 normal pace
Like I'm drunk
Neither newbie how this happened in real time
In fact
None of this need ever have happened
In the sense that we understood that term in 1988
That's a track meet entirely by software
The singer is a program made by Yamaha
Call Vocaloid
Vocaloid tracks have been cropping up in the Japanese pop charts
Score number of years
And are now making their way into other forms of Music around the world
Casper podcast
Adobe is developing a program
Voco
That will read text aloud for you
In your own voice
What could possibly go wrong
Making thyme conform to machines making it regular
Would seem to make it more unify
Like a standardized timeline
That any of us can tap into at any moment
But there's acid
Surprising twist
Digital time
It's actually very difficult
Synchronize
It's a challenge
In digital recording
To whine up the different layers
That make up a song
If you play a guitar into a digital recorder
And then play it back and add singing
Your voice won't line up with the music
Exactly the way you performed
The reason
Is what's called latency
Latency is the lag and digital Communications
Introduced by the time it takes
Computer to process them
Computers move very fast that's what computers are good at
But analog time it seems
Moves faster
Let's consider an example from outside music
Bulletstorm
That's the radio voice of the Boston Red Sox
Joe Castiglione
I don't have a signature home run call because all the good ones were take it and going going gone
Buybuybaby
Russ Hodges
I got kind of used forget about it and because are you know it's gone
Some fans didn't like that sweetheart forget about it's a big home run
Hello the broadcaster is to describe
What you see and what is happening as it happened that's why we broadcast in the present tense
Major deals and it's in there for a call strike
I can't be too soon anticipated you can get burn that way
Sometimes the ball doesn't carry as far as you think it's going through or sometimes it carries farther
You can always tell if a broadcast is behind the action
The crowds cheering and you're still building up to what's happening
You have to be quick you have to be current
You have to be right
On time
Joe is such an important voice here in Boston it used to be common practice
Watch baseball games on TV
But with the sound off
And the radio on
So we can watch the game
The listen to Joe
And then a strange thing happened
On June 12 2009
Joe started calling a place
Before we saw them on TV
That's because on that day
Every TV station in the US
Switch from analog to digital transmission
And that lag in the Digital television image the gap between it
And the real time of the game as Joe is calling it
That latency
It takes time for computers to translate the world into Data
And translating data
The analog
So we can perceive it
Slows things down
Enough to put the tag
After the call by Joe Castiglione
Throw throw in time at his house
Was it all saying radio
When you read it it's history when you hear it it's news
And we're headed the satellite picture on TV so
We are first
And I think the immediacy of radio
Is something that
You're so critical and seoul
Jermaine to it
Back before digital broadcast
That immediacy was audible in the city
You always need when there was a homerun at Fenway
Because you heard of simultaneous Collective cheer all around Boston
From every open window to passing car
The news today
Those shots are staggered
We get splattering of Cheers
Like scatter points on a graph
That's because latency
He is different
Slightly different but different
On each digital device receiving its own particular stream of digital information
Professional music producers and engineers in the digital Studio
Worried about latency all the time
Black and introduces can be very very small
And yet
It's always there
And always threatening to knock the different layers of a song
Out of sync with one another
If a young drummer today
Managest
Cast wide net around beat
Perhaps that's not so different from my own speeding up and slowing down on Galaxy 500 recording
It may be a flaw
Or maybe part of the charm
If there's something very distinct
About an experience of analog time time that flexes
Slower and quicker
Tempo rubato
And this feeling a blurred time
Vim latency
From one
I can't think of a musical term for latency
Perhaps because it's not like anything we experience in live
However
This experience of latency is typical of Life online
For all our seemingly instant
Global digital Communications
Life online is in practice
Field of chronological confusion
Social media like Facebook and Twitter Shuffle posts according to various algorithms most obviously
Popularity
The net result being
The Yesterday's News Bulletin
Can interrupted a string of think pieces about it
Texting to
It's often tripped up by cross posts
Or missed post
What abrupt silences
Followed by 10 things in a row
Temporal hiccups in information exchange that would never happen faced
Face
Conversation in Rio analog time
We can gauge reaction to her statements before anything further is sad
Pause without lapsing into silence
And we can fall silent without ending the conversation
Digital time
It's time to sign from machines
We benefit in all kinds of ways from the convenience that makes possible
But those conveniences
Kommersant
Because when we trade broadcast for podcast
We give up the opportunity to experience time together
Same insta
2R media
And when we trade real time for machine time in music
We lose the ability to share our individual timing with one another
Musicians use Roboto swing and groove
To move us together
Not block
But to one another
Analog time
Flexible but Unified
We share it so easily
Without tinkering with technology without even thinking about it
Maybe that's why we seem to be surrendering it so quickly
But without it
It's harder to share a moment in time together
Like those moments I want shared
With my bandmates
New recording studio
Particular place
At a particular time
On West Broadway
Just south of canal
New York City
This is ways of hearing
The next episode
I'll take a trip to today's New York
And look at the effect of digital sound on perception of space
Thank you for listening
When's appearing as a production of showcase
From radiotopia and PRX
Produced by me Damon Krakowski
Max Larkin and Ian Cox
Sound design by Ian cross
Thanks to Julie Shapiro
Alex bronstein
Recorded the PRX podcast garage
In Allston Mass
Arthur theme song
Trickle-down
By Robert Wyatt
Find out more about ways of hearing
Radiotopia
Tok FM
/ showcase
This series Waze. Reminded me of one of my favorite night night GIF episodes about music and Design
If you wanted people who never go through the back catalog
I thought I just resent it to you here
Short and fun
The first
I should pay some bills
Because thanks of These Fine sponsors
Yeah we're allowed to listen to all this for free
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa is talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Five podcast
So this is very old man ipin
You can tell because I sound like a very young
And much less exhausted
But it's an all-time favorite
Enjoy
Goethe said that architecture is Frozen music
That's lovely
Of course that was before audio recording so now for the most part
Music
Is Frozen music
It's only very recently in the history of music that we've been able to freeze music into an object
In my life the form of is object matter to lie
I once bought vinyl albums and cassette tapes
And there were two first songs per album side a
Inside B
The energy of a first song
Made it stand apart from the other songs
At least my head
Then the CD came along and eliminated side B and there was only one first song
And the actual number of the track that you can see prominently displayed on the CD player URI
That became my index for sorting songs
An MP3 is jumbled my sense of track order and albums began to feel more like
A loose grouping of individual pieces rather than a conceptual hole
I can do this all day and you're welcome to try man let's just left totally has the sound of the waves
But my point is this
When it comes to music the form of the thing matters
But no effect has been his world changing as the original Innovation freezing Music In Time on
Recording
Or a single version of a song a single performance of a song
Became
The song
This inherently mutable method of communication
Was fundamentally changed
Songs
Astonishing things really
Even know what they are
That's the songwriter composer and producer Jon Brion
No I didn't talk to John Bryan
But I know people who did
Jim derogatis and Greg caught are the hotel radio program I'm a huge fan of called sound opinions
It's a rock and roll talk show and it's certain
Michy snarky corners of the internet
Have darkened or concept of Music journalism
What sound opinions
Is your beacon of light my friends
Anyway
John Brian came to WBEZ in Chicago to talk to sound opinions in 2006
And at the time
Brian Tedesco produced
Kanye West album late registration
He was also already well known as a film composer of a lot of really great movies many by Paul Thomas Anderson
I heard the show broadcast on WBEZ while I was sitting in my car in a parking lot of a Taqueria in Logan Square
And I thought about this section of their interview about
Songs versus performances
At least
Once a month
Since then
For 6 years
But only recently did it. I mean that this is a perfect 99percentinvisible story
So here it is
John Brian sound opinions in mm
I distinguish between
Look for lack of better terms I call songs and performance pieces
And
What most people like are specific
Performances we've grown up in an era of
Recording
Add to note the very thing one of the very things I love
Recording has
Killed people's ability to hear songs purely as core change
Melody and lyric
It's a very
Strange and beautiful art form cuz when it's right
Do you know it
But
What we have sort of Lost
Is
I don't have the best example I cried give would be
Led Zeppelin
Those things are the ultimate performance
Pieces and I'm a big fan
I think they're just absolutely astonishing
The sort of Dynamics they had
Sorely lacking in music
Today
Record making is
Great
A true band in the sense that you really could
Tell who the individual
Remarkable thing
And
I don't
Consider most of those things
Songs
And the way I can sort of prove my point is
Have you ever listen to anybody else play Led Zeppelin song and got all that was a great satisfying experience
Except for dread Zeppelin what people like
Specific guitar sound that specific performance
In concert with that specific drum sound with that
Pacific drummer playing that
Pacific Park
And it's beautiful it's a beautiful thing they're all different types of art
Creative expression
However
If I were to sit and go here
And I can play
Ghetto 30 others that that's the thing
You know I know it could sound like a snobbishness
It's not
I love these records
They're great
However it is
There's a difference between
Is that
Anna song
Say a Gershwin song
You could actually play in the style of Led Zeppelin and have it completely
Satisfied Spirits all the time
When you start playing Zeppelin songs in the style of the 1920s music it's suddenly it's late
Oh no it was about those
People in those people were in a
And it was great and I loved it but I considered a performance piece
I consider
A lot of rocks people listen to
To be
Performance
They're not
Necessarily song
I heard you had to tell him you work here recently in tears
Guy who's the songwriter
Comes into the band and goes
Here's the thing I've got and then they you know rock with holy hardness and and all the greatness they've got with
Part of what makes a band like Radiohead
Stand-out you know when that second record came out we all collectively went
Oh my God
Somebody actually songs in this guy's an amazing singer
Yeah I mean
Okay here
Google Music
Costco
Was cool with
Punk rock
Popular he had it factor for
4 days
But
If
You take the average punk rock sound is that Same Led Zeppelin meltys another hated Zeppelin so much
Punk songs there's a big difference between that
I mean
I can sit here on grand piano plan unaffected version and we can all go oh my God
My spine tingles anytime
Play that Melody over those core change
Different it's in the same realm is being able to go in
Where
Uno
I like most people I remember exactly where I was
First time I heard lithium
Remember back of the friends car
And it came on
And
I just
Freaked out I mean I was nearly in
Interior sunlight
Oh my God that guys
Better than everybody
It was so palpable like
That's one of the best chord changes I've ever heard
It absolutely as good as
Thelonious Monk or
Any great things
Suggested
It was John Bryant talking to Jim dear goddess and Greg caught on sound opinions in 2006
Sound opinions is produced by WBEZ Chicago
Distributed by
TRX
But not more
It sound opinions.
99% invisible is Katie mingle play mehall Sharif Youssef
Emmett Fitzgerald Kolstad Avery trufelman Taryn Mazza xian real and me
Roman Mars
We are project kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the best most Innovative shows in all of podcast
We are supported by the Knight foundation and coin carrying listeners
Just like you
You find the show Andrew inspection about the show on Facebook in between me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi Oregon
Morning scream Tumblr and Reddit to
What are fabulous home on the internet with more design stories and week
Nevermind it's too
Here on the Pike
Is our website
99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com