99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The best James Bond
Is either Sean Connery or Daniel Craig
I lean towards Daniel Craig
The new movies are just better
But the Sean Connery film definitely had the best of valence there's blofeld of course who's so iconic that he turned
The active cat stroking
Into a thing that supervillains do but bonds flashes nemesis
Has to be
Goldfinger
You expect me to talk
Do you expect me to talk
Yai yai
There's this dorky fun fact
That the bond villain Goldfinger
Was actually named after a real person
That's trouble
Original
The author of the James Bond books
Ian Fleming
Named Goldfinger for a man he found so dastardly
So terrible
That he immortalized him in pop culture
The real Goldfinger Was An Architect
Erno Goldfinger
Anime Giant
Hulking austere concrete buildings solace
Inhabitants claim to suffer health problems and depression from spending time inside them
Some of goldfinger's buildings were vacated because occupants found them so ugly
And yet many architects
Praise goldfinger's belt
Is trellick Tower which was once threatened with demolition
Has been awarded Landmark status
This device
This hatred
From the public
And love
From designers and
Tends to be the narrative around building
Like gold fingers
Which is to say
Gigantic imposing buildings
Made of concrete
What some people refer to as
Brutalist
Architecture
And a lot of folk
Beyond the creator of James Bond
Love
To hate them
We are in wurster Hall which
To migrate
This man frustration
Is often
Considered
The worst building on campus or wurster Hall more like worst
I met up with Sarah Briggs Ramsey in wurster Hall
I've realized building at UC Berkeley
Locking up my bike
Outside and I overhear undergrads
Walking with
Their parents
Ironically
This is the ark
Architecture school and it's the ugliest building on campus
Yep wurster Hall
Is the architecture school
Sarah completed her master's there
Buildings like this are pretty pervez
Pacific Rasmus
American Inn
Canadian
Campuses
Yeah there was a big bulky concrete building on the campus where I went to college
And I hated when I had to go through it
It just reminded me of a bunker or a bomb shelter
You think concrete buildings just like
Omni out
Absolutely I mean it it has these connotations
United soviet-era Construction
Sometimes third world Construction
Movies negative associations this is Professor Adrian 40 author of The excellent.
Concrete and culture he's been researching concrete for around 10 years now
Apart from aesthetic criticisms concrete buildings present environmental concern
Unlock these buildings
Dosage time when energy was cheap and
They use on putting with lots of energy to heat and cool them
Concrete buildings were built with the illusion of plenty
That we will always have enough energy to build and heat and cool these massive inefficient structures
As harsh as it looks
Concrete is an utterly optimistic
Building material
Arguably
To optimist
Really from the 1920s
It was seen as being the material that
Change the world
It had the potential to build things in a way that
Hadn't been seen before
Concrete was this material that seemed to boundless
Readily available in vast quantities
And who created massive spaces unlike any other material
The concrete spring up everywhere
Second most heavily consumed
Products in the world
The only thing we consume more of than concrete
Is water
We use concrete for sidewalks Bridges tunnels and highways and of course
Giant buildings
Weather retro camper
Stager
Auditoria
Or condominium or gimnasio or planetary act programs all over the world
Loved concrete
Particular in Soviet Russia battle simulator in Europe
North America
It was used
For welfare welfare state project
Concrete presented the most efficient way to hell is huge numbers of people
And philosophically it was seen as humble
Capable
An honest
Concrete was just out there and all of its rough Glory
Not hiding behind any paint or layers
Saying here I am Love Me Or Hate Me
And his concrete buildings came to signify humility honesty and integrity
They were erected all over the world as housing projects
Courthouse
Schools
Churches
Hospital
And City Hall
You'll stand outside
And a tour bus will go by and
Ladies and gentlemen voted the most ugliest
Building in the world Boston City Hall
How do you compete with
Chris Grimley is up against a lot
But he's trying to restore Boston City Hall
My name is
Chris Grimley
My
Fellow
Passyunk
Chris Mark and Michael have embarked on what they call the heroic project
Chronicling the concrete structures in and around Boston
Rather than referring to these concrete buildings as brutalist
They prefer the term heroic
Because like so many superheroes
These structures
Have the best most noble intentions
What are sorely misunderstood
Also just generally brutalism is a big broad label that gets used inconsistently in Ark
People tend to disagree on one precise definition
Any brutalism also just sounds intense
Even though it's not actually related to brutality
It comes from datong Brew
Interlock concrete
Heroic
Feels like a better term
Especially in Boston
We're concrete architecture swooped in and save the day you have to
Scituate Boston
In place
50 is 19
It is America's First City
It is
America's most
Historic City I think I'm not really but I get your point and yet it finds itself in the doldrums
Boston like a lot of other American cities was plagued by loss of manufacturing jobs and white flight to the suburbs
Boston had the highest property taxes in the nation and almost no development
There is this recognition
From
Civic authorities that something needs to be done
Something nice
To be done quickly
So Boston set an agenda to make the city great
Big
Soaring capable
Thoroughly Modern buildings made
Of course
How to conquer
I know some of these buildings were celebrated
Fathers were really not
What we call the third rail
Concrete modernism
City Hall in Boston City Hall was built in 1968
Critics were put off by this concrete Style
It was called
Alienated
Nicole
And since it was a government building this criticism became impossible to remove from polyp
Boston City Hall became a political Pawn
Mayors and City Council Members kept trying to win public support with promises to get rid of the building
Like John Tobin did when he ran for City Council
Modern architecture
And I think we can do a lot
Former mayor Thomas Menino actually started a study to really look into tearing it down
It turned out at the Ritz
The study that you would need something like a nuclear grade weapon basically.
Droid
I don't think it would say so heavily over built into concrete
And so when they couldn't tear down City Hall
Officials chose to ignore it
People that occupy
Building
For decades and decades didn't like it
Wanted to see
See the building go away
This is called active neglect
It happens with a lot of concrete building
They're intentionally
Unrepaired unrenovated and uncared-for
Which only makes the building more ugly
And then more hated
And then more than Ward
Increase this vicious cycle
When the public hate of Boston City Hall
Feeds itself
And then
Discussion years on really big
Came about
What the original
Not failure
Maintenance
When people don't these Mammoth concrete structures
No one really thought about maintenance
It seemed indestructible
In the early stages of concrete people
Assume that this was an everlasting material
But wouldn't need any attention at all
And that's wrong
We know that it does need
2B look soft
It does to Terry Wright
Does takai
But it can be hard to tell when concrete is to
They came to think of Breakin Timber
What's a guy takes place
Omnicef
But with concrete the
Deterioration
Is internal
Concrete deteriorates chemically from the inside out
Part of this has to do with a metal reinforcements that help hold up most concrete building
The rebar
Why can Ross
And the rest
Eats away at the overall structure
But Adrian 40 says
Tearing them down is not
Spencer your cruise as soon as you tell them down
Then
You have a problem Festival what you do with the picture
Black
And secondly you cup to replace them with something else
Use up
A lot more energy and creates a lot more CO2
In building something in that place already used up all that energy when they were made
They're already there
We can adapt these buildings to make them Greener and make them more appealing places to be by any windows for example
The basically
Professor 40 thinks we can all develop the capacity to love these concrete boots in all their home
Glory
Show people blunt
But you know as well
Any
Form with her it's
Uproar
Pain sitting or glitch
The more you know about it
The more you
Get out of it the more you'll appreciate it
And this is especially true of concrete building
Architecture students appreciate them because they know that concrete actually requires a hell of a lot
Skill and finesse to work with
To do architecture in concrete
Is
Proof you are really are an architect
It's the test being a naughty
But a concrete building every little detail needs to be calculated in advance
Concrete is wildly intimidating to work with
One support
There's No Going Back
With a concrete building it's like the result of an Immaculate Conception
The whole thing is
An integral monolithic hole
It has to be right
And aside from the interesting design challenge
Deposes
Concrete itself as a material can be subtly beautiful
If you look close
You know what we think of is
Adjusting monolith
Homogeneous
Pictures actually
Really rich
Action
Has a lot of
Sarah Briggs Ramsey the one I spoke with at Berkeley's wurster Hall did a year-long project
Traveling around the world
Looking at concrete buildings in Europe and Asia and South and North America
To create a global comparison of
One material that I think is so
Assertive under considered
It's like the background of all the cities but no one asked
Samsung
Luck we call the city
A Concrete Jungle
To talk about the artificialness
The urban landscape
But concrete can actually be a very natural expression of the environment
Concrete color and texture
Can be dictated by local climate local Earth and local rock
The Harvard
Game Center
On the Harbor
End
It's got a grape
Tripoli
Really pronounce
Purple color and
That's the ground
From the site
Concrete can also be an expression of local style and custom UK concrete has big
Thick textured chunks of Rock
All Japanese kanji
Is very fine
But the beauty of concrete architecture is
When you can just observe the building like pieces of sculpture
Without actually having to live and work in them
Springs in concrete surprising Ally
Photography
Concrete looks good in Facebook
We provide this kind of neutral background
It provides a wonderful setting for
Peoples
Skin tones
Color of their clothes
Fashion photographers realized this first and then pockets of the internet started to appreciate these concrete building
There are lots of
Blogs
Sure
Kind of extraordinary enthusiasm for concrete photography is allowing a new audience of non architects
Appreciate these buildings for their strong lines
The crystal shadow
And
Increasingly
The idealism and body
They represent
Ideas about
Taste of the wild salmon what the future has imagined to be that we want to preserve
You should remember what
People were thinking
50s guy
Retirees buildings down werewolf
Lose all the fat
Architecture whether we want to admit it or not
As a sort of shellfish
A time after which buildings fall out of fashion
And then are allowed to fall apart
Back in the 1960s victorian-style building
Things were considered hideous
Falling apart
Impossible to repair
And we were tearing batches of them down
All the while erecting big
Concrete building
Victorians were saved that today
They are these beautiful lovingly restored
Treasures
Brutalist heroic
Whatever you want to call it
Concrete architecture now finds itself at a potential inflection point
Too outdated to be modern
Too young to be classic
Context architecture enthusiasts and preservation us
Would like us to just wait a bit
NC
Maybe with a little time and love we might discover some architectural Diamonds in the Rough
That we just can't see right now
99% invisible with produce this week by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle same Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to our pal Allison area fats per along with Michael Abramson the curator of the beautiful sight
Capitalism. Tumblr.com
There's nothing to Rene tap
And arcsin Zone Nathaniel Mueller
The book heroic
Concrete architecture and the New Boston will be out in October
We are project at 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced by the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm
And beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
. info
Flat pocket
Melodium
Who is music I'm talking over right now is a new Mini album called beneath
For sale on Bandcamp
Pay-what-you-want so be generous he's one of the good guys and he makes the show so much better
Go to Millennium. Bandcamp.com and took my albums and walk around as if you're in and out
Episode of 99% invisible all the time that's what I do you can find the show and like to show on Facebook
Book where all on Twitter I'm at Roman Mars Avery is at troubleman Katie mingle as at Katie mingle and Sam Greenspan is a
Sam listens we're also on Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but you can listen to every single episode of 90
Percent invisible at 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com