99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
If you grew up watching Warner Brothers cartoons
And I really really hope you did
You might remember seeing the words
Directed by Chuck Jones in big letters in the opening credits
Chuck Jones worked for decades
Cartoons like Looney Tunes
From the 1930s until his death
In 2002
In addition to being a director he was also an animator
Get Bugs Bunny that cocky slash
I gave Daffy Duck those mischievous eyes
Biting Bugs Bunny's Bar Mitzvah stack of Daffy Duck is insane
He made a mute Wylie Coyote
Hold up signs at commented
On the sad irony of his
Kisscartoon
In 1996 Jones accepted an Academy Award
For Lifetime Achievement
I stand guilty before the world
A directing over 300 cartoons the last 50 years
60 years
Hopefully
This means you forgiven me
Chuck Jones is the name most people remember when they think about those cartoons
But I want to talk about another guy and artist to work with Chuck
A guy who wasn't just important to Looney Tunes
He changed the entire art
Love animation
Yeah the amazing thing about this guy is that he never drew Bugs Bunny or Elmer Fudd or Yosemite Sam or any of those characters he threw the back
Backgrounds
Behind those character
Duck Dodgers in the 24th and a half century
Jackie docklands on this weird futuristic
Take planet
Or you know the Road Runner cartoons that jacket
Bright abstract desert
That is the work of Maurice
Noble
You're helping us tell the story is reporter Eric molinsky
Hey Eric used to work in animation as a storyboard artist on the Rugrats
And a couple of other cartoons for Nickelodeon
So breakdown press with the layout artist does in the hole animation
Hartwell so today like a TV show you would start out with
Or in the case of Looney Tunes it probably did start drawing story sketches to figure out the gags
The camera angles
Stop
And then before the animation starts
The background
Designer or layout artist has
First crack at drawing
This world
And those drawings are then later
Painting by someone else but you know the layout artist like Maurice Noble is really accomplished would actually have a say in in the color choices
As well
And so this is actually really important to imagine you're watching cartoon
Can any of the layout or they going to the background is sometimes the first image that you see it
Pops on screen for a second
And your brain use to instantly register Where You Are
In what mood you're supposed
So let's get on say watching Road Runner cartoon you cut to this
Big boulder
Perched on top of a really high narrow cliff
You're going to immediately feel dread for the coyote
So the layout artist is kind of like the straight man in the comedy duo
Setting up the gag
For the animator hygge
Funny guy right credit I mean they're literally in the background they're creating the painstaking work of
Bart for somebody else
Plop their drawings right on top of it
So you have to keep your ego in check
Reasonable spent most of his career working for Warner Bros
Cadence are outdoing new wacky cartoon
Asian man he wanted to be a fine artist
Painting desert landscape
When he graduated Art School Maurice found work at Walt Disney Studios
His first job is paying an apple and they said it was
Dirty toilet tedious process of exacting process of just putting the colors downgraded to match
You know he didn't think so at the moment but it was definitely
Pampering him creatively
This is Bob McKinnon who wrote a biography of Maurice Noble
He said that even though Disney feature film that is really realistic and settle background you see every leaf on a tree or the shine
Hang on a door knob
Maurice felt like he was slumming it
Squandering his talent on
Commercial Art
1941 Disney Studios was torn apart by a strike
The artist wanted to create a union
In-wall took the walkout very
Very personally when it was over
He got rid of anyone associated with the strike
Concluding reasonable
I think it's a strike and not happen he said he would have had a job for life time it is
Dbd I think he was with a stay there forever
But Maurice wasn't unemployed for long
World War II broke out and he was drafted into a unit that made propaganda film
Is featuring a cartoon character
Name the private snafu
As you can probably tell from that phone clip which has the very distinct voice of Mel Blanc in it
The propaganda film crew
Was full of people from Warner Brothers
Including Chuck Jones
So I also talked with Todd
Pulse and who's working on a book about Maurice's artwork
And he's as Maurice found their style to be
Liberating
You know everybody was involved with those
Those films for the Army definitely were able to finally Express themselves
And then after the war
They got Maurice a job working at Warner Brothers
Cuz I was sweating you said
No one knew
How little he knew about that particular end of the business and
According to him he was flying by the seat of his pants layouts before but
I'm like 30 short films per year
And just to give you a sense of how crazy that is
So today in OTR lease when I worked in TV going to we would ship are storyboards to create
Today they would probably
You know email them to Korea
Eyewear near cheaper labor will fill in the animation or you could use a computer base program like Flash 2
To speed up the workflow
And I just make 22 Episodes for a season
These guys are doing more work
And doing it all by hand
Unlike that first
Painstakingly realistic Apple that he painted for Disney Maurice Noble come to embrace the idea that backgrounds
Should be flatter and more cartoonish
More like the characters
Yeah let me like another example would be
Jungle Book and then going back to Disney
One of my favorite movies cuz the animation is totally amazing and it matches so beautifully the voices of those actors
I've always been bothered by the fact that
The characters are kind of flat in 2D
But the jungle is rendered with a subtle colors and Lighting in the trees
Three dimensional shading and I can never really
Suspend my disbelief that those characters are actually living in that world
Maurice felt the same way about Disney
Bare necessities
Forget about
Joe Webb
I mean
He always felt animation was a flat stylize medium so he wanted the background to support that
Then like use of airbrush you is felt the background of some of the studios were
Fighting the characters in
People talk to him and say while you were you inspired by Monday and this time he says that I don't think that way
He says you are working in a completely new medium this is a completely unique art form
Emory Center of changing what Warner Brothers was doing because he's pushing the cartoonist
Set the background until they the same sass is bug
Bunny or the delusional Insanity of Daffy Duck
Roadrunner cartoons the coyotes real antagonist isn't really the roadrunner
It's the desert landscape
The Acme Corporation
Conspiring to make his life miserable
The earlier cartoons that were done before I got there because
They're a little more realistic there a little more just straight ahead and went when he got there he started to use
Goldie different techniques and then
What are you called
Stop registration colors with Adelines of the the rock band lineup with color behind them
You said I was to give you a heat Shimmer
Which he knew all about cuz I grew up in New Mexico
PP grew up in that kind of thing you played in The Rocks me sorry I'm sure all that influenced his take on
On the desert when he did the Roadrunner cartoon
And this is how Maurice Neville becomes a hero to layout design
Remember his work is not supposed to
Detract from the character
Supposed to support the animation and make it
Stand out
He does that brilliant
But he also developed a unique and recognizable
Style
And it's almost like he build a stage for a show but the stage is winking at the audience
So I started animation at calarts
Enzo baby watching a cartoon like Duck Dodgers in the 24th and 1/2 century
And we would burst out laughing
Because Daffy Duck Atlanta non-plan attacks and Marie cedron.
Clouds in the trees in the shape of
Giant Exeter
I'll just bet that if we follow those planets
How do I do it
As Noble as coming into his own he's starting to get co-director credit on some of the phone
But Chuck Jones is still reaping most of the Acclaim
Todd Olson wanted Maurice's protege
Says that
This became a point of tension between them in the six
Cease when they're working at MGM
It was a working relationship
And I became more and more strained as
Chuck
Became more successful especially in the 60s
And in that came to a head when they made on the line
Did on the line with an adaptation of a children's book
And it was about a
Ted.
That falls in love with a line
And it's a story of their Romance
I talked to Hans with the director on the short but he was having trouble figuring out how to adapt it
City Executives Montgomery
Well
If you don't involve Chuck
I can make this work for you
It's so Chuck brought the stuff and threw it down on his desk and stomped out
Andries wouldn't show up as working on
Once upon a time there was a sin
Straight line
Who is hopelessly in love
With it.
You're the beginning and the end The Hobbit all the contestants
Cut the frivolous.
Wasn't a bit interested
Precio lyrics for wild and unkempt squiggle
Never seem to have anything on his mind
Charming film
It's probably the most personal of all of Maurice's films because it's really
Just him on the screen is pure Graphics there's no
Classic characters that you might
My think of them is just dots lines is purely abstract
But really beautiful
The film is is this
Pure distillation of Maurice's work
And he's telling a story creating emotions in humor with just basic shapes
Colors
But talk to on Cell. Direct
Credit
Of course
It won the Oscar
But he said that the
Didn't
Everything came and Todd says that even though everyone knew it was Maurice's film
Maurice wasn't invited
The Oscars
Search up Jones and Maurice Noble kept working together they worked on How the Grinch Stole
Christmas in a bunch of other
Dr. Seuss adaptation
But they fell out of touch for about 20 years
Until the early 1990s
When Warner Brothers reunited them to make cartoons that play before feature
Your films
They hired a bunch of young artists who just graduated from calarts
And one of them with Scott Morris
Maurice Noble Maurice Noble where do you where do I know that from
So it's because it was one of the names that preceded directed by Charles M Jones on all of
The cartoons that I grew up watching every day of my life
One of the first lessons that Scott learn was that Maurice's fantastic backgrounds were not
Invented out of thin air Maurice did a ton of research
Everything he exaggerated was based on something in the real world
You get an assignment like
Oh you know
Bugs Bunny Cindy stuck on a desert island
Thoracic on the jungle
So they should be palm trees and should be all this stuff
Okay great
And I come back with a drill with a
Withdrawing any do I put is this and I'm like their pomp reasons like those are stuck as what were you looking at and it's like a will there's a pump.
You got to learn your trees
But Murray's wasn't really that Gruff after work he talked to these twenty-two-year-old animators like he was just one of the guys
Maybe like
Let's go let's go to baseball
Let's go do this other thing you know
Would you go to museum
Pretty soon you realize he's more like your grandpa
Who
It's just a really cool guy to hang out with
The Scott Morris mystery Novartis became known as the noble
And Maurice push them to develop their own style but his sensibility really seeped into their work
Scott is at Pixar now which is the home of 3D animation
Is the complete opposite of
You know the flat Landscapes of Looney Tune
But you can really see Maurices influence on the Pixar films
If you look for it
Like the song
Think about that
How scary by a massive amount of balloons and lands on the very edge of a cliff and Wally.
Cute little robot is scooting around these big
Menacing towers of garbage
Yeah those are layouts that make you smile
That's good
Classic Maurice
In May of 2001 the noble boys were reunited one last
We all got another call to Maurice he was in the Hospice place me at home
It was just natural causes that he that he was
Dino that he was pretty sure you know everybody's pretty sure that that night was going to
Maybe be the last night we all came over and hung out with him
And Chuck Jones did call them
I remember being in the room with Maurice and somebody brought in the phone as I checked on the phone
Colin Morris is like okay I'll
I'll talk to him and we all know for a fact they hadn't really talked
4 months if not a couple years at that point
And I just heard Maurice's side of the conversation but you know you could definitely tell that they were
They put everything behind on their fur
You know it was nice
And I did again I don't know exactly what
Chuck said on the other end of that line but
With a very sweet
Mama to be able to see that
And know that people could go through a lot together in life and still
I respect for you
Up to the last
And
Kind of celebrate what they had created together
To some extent Marisol the noble boys is his real Legacy
He was proud of the fact that they had blossomed into well-rounded artist
If Maurice could leave behind this idea in other people to do their own thing
We would never be in the
Backgrounds like he was
But it was a beautiful
Beautiful back
I actually met Maurice number once
Oh yeah yeah
Hey I went to calarts and I came in her class on it like a Monday night
And I had
Having a Godly offer the day before
The Weeknd
And I was thinking about how often those guys made fun of opera on their cartoons
Little buddy
And I asked him
Did you guys actually go to the author regularly or
Weirdest kind of making fun of it as a sort of
You know highfalutin cultural Institution
And
He asked me
What opera did you see
And I said
La Traviata
And he said
Violetta
A Gatsby
And that is a man who knew a good day
Funny song
99% invisible with produce this week by Eric molinsky with Sam Greenspan and me Roman more
We are product of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Inn
Institute of Architects
Sex in San
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast oh my God
Fox podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but right now we have Maurice Noble
Layouts the down the line short film and the strikingly politically incorrect private snafu it's it's really
It's Time at 99% invisible. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com