99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 2005 I took a job at WBEZ in Chicago
And I was so excited to be moving there
I was excited about the job
But I was also very excited
About
Sigrid
The streets of Chicago and the address numbering system are beautiful
Starting from the 00 access point downtown streets conform to a rigid
Grid pattern
Were the major streets are exactly
One mile apart
And have address numbers which are multiples of eight hundred you don't really have to be able to picture this but I know that if you know it you're not in your head
Seriously but just know that it's amazing
And I was mesmerized by
So much so that I made flashcards with
Chicago street names on one side
And the corresponding address number on the other
So that my wife and I cook with ourselves
On a 2000 mile road trip from San Francisco to Chicago
Yes I was always like this
Division is 1200 North
Armitage is 2000 North and therefore one mile north of division
After living in the jumble of San Francisco streets for years
Daughter moving to a place
Were people playing the city to help people know where they were and where they were going
My lizard brain
And gave me peace
As humans have developed cities and built environment we have also needed to develop ways to find our way through
Signage goes back at least as far as the Roman Empire
They constructed Milestones along the roadway
Which is to say if you're relying on anything besides natural features to help you find your way around
You are relying on things made by people whose job it is is to help us
Figure out how to get from all of our respective point is
Do your point B
A producer Sam Greenspan would like me to tell you that he has a fantastic sense of direction
I really do
I'm sure I get lost sometimes I'll minute
It's the worst
I get so mad at myself on happens but now
My life is completely different
Ever since I started thinking about what it means
And wayfinding is a thing
Wayfinding innocence
Is a branch of environmental graphic design concerned with helping people find their way
I love knowing this because now
When I get lost at the hospital or
Complicated freeway interchange or
At an airport
I have someone to blame
Yeah that's one way to look at it but lot of times it has nothing to do with the signage
User error does apply sometimes
Fair enough
Let me introduce you to Jim Harding
My name is Jim Harding
I'm an environmental graphic designer basically I tell people where to go
There's an environmental graphic designer wayfinder or maybe just a kid with magic marker behind every sign
Turn here to merge onto the 101
Concourse C is this way
Bathrooms
Straight ahead
But there is a lot
Lot more wayfinding than just say
Signage is probably the least
Effective tool away funny
Good architecture is one of the best
It's not that Jim hate sign
Rather the best forms of wayfinding are
Invisible
They're baked into the built environment
I first heard about Jim Harding through a writer named David zweig
I'm David zweig I'm a writer my book
Is called
Invisibles the power of anonymous work in an age of relentless
Self promote
David zweig book is a series of portraits of people whom he refers to as invisible
Invisibles are people who are
Highly-skilled professionals
People who are really important
Whatever
Enterprise are Endeavor that they are part of that their work really has a big effect on the overall outcome be at who are
Largely unknown
Never thought of by
By the public or the end-user
Jim Harding director of environmental graphics for Gresham Smith and partners
Is one such invisible
Jim Harding is one of the best in the business
Jim work on the new international terminal
Hartsfield-Jackson International Airport in Atlanta Georgia
The world's busiest
100 million passengers move through it every year all of them needing to know where to go
Cylons are so important
Cuz you can see your destination you don't have to rely on side
I meant gym at the Atlanta airport
And he walked me through some of the Cutting Edge wayfinding
Techniques that
He employed at the new international
National Terminal
Like right when you walk in from Curbside
Physical space tells you everything you need to know about how to move through it
Without you even realize
What started the first thing you want when you enter the airport
The ticket
You're not
Lined up on on a 90 degree axis angle
Okay
A lot of times the ticket counter to meet you head on when you walk in and then you're left Wonder okay if I go left or right
What is angled ticket counters subtly push you in the right direction
The angle
Stairs you
Down and around a ticket counter
And heading toward the
Go to checkpoint
As a counter is pushing you
You're also getting pulled by this giant three-story glass window that looks out onto the tarmac
UC playing to see the apron the jetway where the planes are parking
And so intuitively your drawing
Do you're playing cuz that's what you want to go you want to get on that plane right and there are less obvious
Excuse to like the tile pattern
In the floor absolutely they see the grid
Instead of being on a 90 degree axis
It's only 45
Annie's tiles going off at a 45 degree angle
They just begging you to follow them
It's so if you do that you inevitably head toward security
But there's even more going on in the floor than that
And here's where this gets a little banana
You turn around and look back here Sammy
You see where the black
Starts at the door curbside
There's another set of tiles inside the dominant grid pattern that I didn't even notice it first
It starts black and then it's joined by a set of yellow goldish tiles the kind of Cleves out this corridor
Negative space
Which cut straight through the hall going directly
To security
I already have my ticket I'm not checking any bags
I will need
Check in on at
The counter I just Follow The Yellow Brick Road song
I think that
Exactly what this is
Light bulb
It's pretty cool
And all this Jim says is 100% intent
Absolutely
Are interior designers
Just went through a number
Flooring pattern design scheme
Until we arrived at this one
On the other side of the
Security we enter what Jim Harding calls the transition Hall
Here's where traveler has some decisions to
Weather defined
Here or whether to get together
The Concourse
Take a Subway call the plane train for that
Or whether to head to baggage claim
This is the part where passengers are going to be asking themselves
Where am I
Where am I going
Paladar the best way to get there
Where there are decisions to be made
This is where wayfinding is needed the most
Yeah the visual wayfinding which is the signage
Now that you can see each
Chicken read it
You can interpret it
Bajwa round
There's also information desk and a newfangled interactive display
I walk with Jim towards the gate
Pictures of seven of nine
So it looks like the odds are on the left
All right
That's funny to see there
This Concourse is pretty streamline
Elegant
But at older less well-designed concourses which are definitely present at some other parts of the ATL Airport
This is where you find yourself in a visual morass
You've seen this before
Neon signs and brightly-coloured displays all trying to get you to buy magazines
Nicolo's
Or hot dogs
We have advertising
Yeah concessions marketing
All those visual elements compete with the primary message of just
How to navigate to airport
Answer the key here is to make the signage Stand Out by being dull
And drab
And playing
Yeah it's very neutral
Neutral palette gray and white basically
So you can spot the signs just like
Tuning out all the glitch
Now even though this new international
Terminal is fairly minimal
There are still people trying to sell you stuff
Just beyond the transition Hall towards the gates there's
This to level Commerce area
There shopping at ground level and then up an escalator are some food options
And of course it's all angle perfectly so you have a direct line of sight
Into all the shops as your walk
Nearby
Is unintentional decide to have a shopping Down Below in the
The food up above
Yes
Why is that
Well more curb appeal
For your retail tenants
People
If they're hungry they're going to go find the food wherever it is
Right
Airports in a struggle to
To generate Revenue
Really yeah
And so anything they can do
To help increase non-aeronautical Revenue
Thanks that are not generated Bob
Playing on Airline
So
Improving their concessions
And Retail
Yeah they get a percentage
Of all those sales
And that's when I realize why there are people like Jim Harding who are paid to do this work
It's not just at airports one
To have a pleasant experience
It's because there's money on the table
Think about it
So you're trying to make a connecting flight you don't have a lot of time you don't know where you're going
I'm stressed
And I don't think I'm going to catch my flight
Am I going to take time to open my wallet
Techno
But if I'm cool calm collected I found my gay and I know where I'm going
I'm more likely to stop and buy whatever
So
Yeah that's where we fighting
Has a real
My financial impact
Yale to airport
Bottom line
Until it turns out
Wayfinding isn't just about helping you figure out how to get where you want to go
It's about steering the masses anywhere that companies hiring the wayfinders want the masses
To be steered
How much more
If your consumer choices aren't going to make money for the powers-that-be inside of a closed system like
Beijing Airport
Don't plan on the making it easy
David zweig the writer who introduced me to Jim Harding
He noticed this kind of thing to their job isn't always about creating the best system
For us
The Traveler
Sometimes it's
Who's paying their bill
When I
Flew to Florida
With my family
We
Going to Fort Lauderdale
And we
Who is wig
Chose an off-site car rent
Rookie
Yeah big mistake
We thought I'll say it but you take a shuttle bus
Well what happened when you arrived there
There's
Huge signs for her to give us all the companies were there
If you're trying to find the off-site car rental companies good luck
Even if you try doing that with two little kids until
David mention this to Jim Harding wayfinding failure and he said well
The airport
Is far more interested
And helping out the people who are paying them
Who have on-site facilities they have no incentive to have you leave the airport
Let's go to someone else
Generate no Revenue
Yeah so they're young
Citizen
Yeah that's not to say though that there's not the Sara Lee a dichotomy between capitalism
Good user experience
Why do we do what we do for a living is wayfinders
I think it is to
In a little way
Improve overall quality of life that that they customer experience
Passenger experience
Is he working a project like the international terminal in Atlanta you want me working for years
And
After all that time
It's built
Can you get to walk through it you see like we are today
You see people using the space understanding the space
They aren't stressed
The freaking out about missing a flight
It's like okay
Wow
Call work
We did a good job
And you just come away with a nice sense of satisfaction
Welcome aboard the plane train
In theory wayfinding should work whether you're literate in it or not
Learning to see the subtle wayfinding cues in the built landscape
Can help you understand
How you make your decision
Or I can make you question if you're the one even making your own decisions at all
After I parted ways
Jim Harding I passed a food
And I noticed
Right outside in the floor where these big black
Curvy tiles
And actually seem to be
Steering people
Towards the concessions
So you know
Next time you find yourself at an airport food court eating a Cinnabon that you didn't even want
Check out the sign-in
The shape of the tiling
The height of the ceiling
The quality of the light
It may just be
Do you have an environmental graphic designer to blame
But you know
User error does imply
99% invisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan with Katie mingle Avery
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce of the offices of arcsin
Our favorite Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing.
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode
It brings you along to the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
You could only listen to these episodes of 99% invisible and be just fine
But if you want to be at 12 level 99 Pi Paladin
You should follow us on Twitter
We're at Roman Mars
Sanlitun Katie Mingle
Joann office hours announcements can be found most reliably on Facebook
We're also all over Tumblr Instagram flicker SoundCloud and
Spotify to
You're always welcome at our house on the web at 99 pi
. org
I'm buying a Cinnabon
At the airport
That I arrived at
You understand why that's extra disgusting right
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com