99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Five steps to keep in a defecting population
Step one
Build a 12ft reinforced concrete wall
Bill the second wall right next to it
Creating a no man's land in between then there was a
1020 M wide strip of land which
Absolutely nothing that's me man's land that was sprayed with chemicals that not even grassquit
And it was rate everyday that you could see the slightest clue that there was a Skype
Step 3
Build a narrow road for vehicles of the secret police
The Stasi
Step four
Add electrified barbed wire and also at 5
Signal wire signal wires that if you touch it immediately and one of the watchtowers
There was the alarm ringing
At its peak the Berlin wall with a hundred miles long
Today only about a mile is left standing compared with other famous walls in history
This wall had a pretty short life span the Great Wall of China has been around for 2500 years
So have the walls of ancient Babylon
Although it's most famous part
The Ishtar gate is actually in a museum
In Berlin
This is Daniel gross but even though the wall dividing Berlin into east and west
It was only up for 30 years
It had a huge impact on the psyche of the city
It broke families into
Now let's remember how we got here
In 1945 Berlin was the Fallen Nazi capital
The weary Victor's could agree on two things
Hitler was bad
Germany needed a big change
After that they did not agree on very much
Berlin with carved up into two sectors
With Western countries controlling the west of the city
And the Soviet Union controlling the east
West Berlin had a booming post-war economy life was tougher
Annie's Berlin
So in the decade that followed more than two million people fled from east to west
East Germany was losing its most skilled workers
Jobs
And reunite with their families across the border
And East Germany with losing face
Whatever you East Berliner who chose to defect
And that's why in 1961
East Germany close its border to West Berlin
With a wall
But this isn't a story about the design of the Berlin Wall
This is a story about one design
To get through it
Or relay
Underneath
Rob Thomas
Who's there
The tunnel had a diameter of less than one square me
We have to
Save
Space the less we excavate
You couldn't sense
You were laying on your back
Girl
Affronted
Weather feeds we were driving the Spade into the front
You couldn't dig for more than 2 hours
In 1964 Roth West 21
At the Free University of Berlin
Rapha studying civil engineering at school he made a lot of models and did a lot of math
But you haven't really ever built anything and like virtually everyone in West Berlin Roth new and wizard
Related to people in East Berlin parents brothers sisters cousins classmates
How could they get to the West
You couldn't have trouble with a woman
Couldn't fly over it
It was the only way
Ticketon
In 1964 westerners could still visit the East if they were in good standing with the East German government
That year Ralph took a trip with his parents and sister
From the West
To the east
To visit extended family
My cousin
Approach my sister and me and said can you do something
For me I must get out of here
Rumors have been going around of tunnels popping up beneath the city
So when I get back to
Timberland
I had an idea
Who was involved here
And I approached him
People living together in the student Salvatore
I approached him I asked him and
40 Slater was in the tunnel
Better be clear the kids were tumbling from west to east they were tunneling into communist eastborough
Ralph of defunct Bakery along the border
It it closed because too many of its customers were stuck in the east
Near the baker's entrance you could actually see East German guard towers looming over the wall
And in that Bakery young berliners were tearing into the ground
Trying to dig a tunnel under the wall
East Berlin
We were digging
Vertically down
Until we got to the ground with tape
If you don't want your tunnel to flood it stay above the water table
And from there we said okay half meter above the ground holder table we dig for it
Straightforward horizontal
Very simple
Very simple in theory and practice Berlin is a nightmare underneath the surface
The city is a swamp
The ground is so wet and Sandy that to this day construction workers have to pump water out of Berlin soil
In order to build new Subway tunnel
They even use mobile Refrigeration units to freeze the ground solid
In trouble spots
But the soil over by the bakery
Happened to be perfect
For tunneling
Because he was
BD geologic soil is
Consisting mainly of
Play
That means if you dig there a hole in it
It is self-supporting
Rats and collapses
And this is one of
Very very few
Areas
In and around Berlin
That you have such as sulfur make that made it for us so
Interesting of course.
So from an engineering perspective this Bakery seemed like the perfect place to dig a tunnel
But strategically it seem like a terrible choice
This was the spot where right after the wall was built
Some Germans in the East try to jump out of their apartment windows
Into the West
Which Middle Eastern government extra careful about security
During the lifespan of the wall
5 people died
On this stretch of border
Talking about a bunch of twenty-somethings digging a tunnel the length of 1 1/2 football fields
With a garden Spade
And a wheelbarrow under one of the most fortified borders on Earth
Ruffles actually joining the second tunnel that this group of Doug
The first tunnel in stretched nearly 500
Eat a six-month effort
The day they reach the backyard of an apartment building in the east
It was snowing
Because the air inside the tunnel was warmer than outside
They left a small circle of melted
Snow
Which basically told the Stars ain't you there's a
Tunnel over here
Within a few hours the study found out
Flooded the tunnel with water
But Ralph, says that being 20 years old and free Berlin
They were all naive enough
To try again
One of the student leaders Wolfgang Fuchs
Proposed a bit of reverse psychology
Wolfgang
Who was really smart guy
Take a note
The Stasi
Buffoon
He would not even dream about that we use the same location
For another Channel
So idiotic nobody could be
I need break
And also tunnel rail started working on in the summer of 1964
The bakery where the tunnel started was in the basement of an apartment building
For the retirees
A group of 20 or so students going in and out all the time
Would have been suspicious
So they had to be stealthy
They can only come in and out every couple weeks
In other words
They had to live there the bakery had become a makeshift home they slept in military cots
And warmed up canned food on a little electric stove that ran on borrowed electricity
Of course we need more power
Then that retired couple
Is using normally
The most stupid man of power company would say
My goodness normally that pay you back I know about $20 a month and now
They consume for 200
So wonderful
Our
Friends managed
To get to the power supply cable
Before it went into the distribution board
For the power was metered and registered to the various apart
The windows were painted white on the inside
To minimize suspicion
But maximize lighting
In the bakery storage room
Flour and salt and sugar
I've been replaced with heaps and heaps of dirt
And when they need fresh supplies
Bike tools baked beans
Spare parts
Soda
That was where Ralph came in
I had a job as a student on the weekend
To deliver
Drinks
Home service
Station biggest station wagon
And that was of course
Perfect camouflage
Airport
Bringing in tools
Spare parts
Ken's Branch drinks
In these boxes we're normally the bottle spray
How much
Boiled you think you moved
The shaft going down that had a size of two by two
12 meters that is
Intuitive
It's already almost 50 cubic meters yeah and then
20:45
I never thought about it
Never thought about it could be close to 200 cubic meters
Crossword
An 18-wheeler truck can haul about 50 cubic meters
It's a wheelbarrow after wheelbarrow
Through the summer and into the autumn
Rubbing his friends scraped and carved and heaved enough dirt
I feel for 18 wheeler big rigs
All the while worried the Stasi would spot them coming in and out
Or detect them with special acoustic sensors
Fall 1964
They finally reached they eat
They tamed for a basement just like last time
But again they miscalculated
The one who was on Judy on the front face of the tunnel
Quebec
With a little plant
He's so low
And that was gross
They hadn't noticed that the Border Zone slope
Slightly downward
Which is forgivable given the fact that they couldn't properly survey the land but this time they were lucky
That come up inside an abandoned shed
Soon after the tunnelers left the shed
They sent a crew of Messengers above-ground legally into East Berlin
To alert their friends and relatives of the internet escape the message included a time a place
Ana pastor
At a time the radios were buzzing with the news at the recent Olympics
Tokyo is dressed in her holiday best for the opening
The 18th modern Olympic
And so the password
What's Tokyo
Ralph and his friends took turns standing watch in the east
Holding pistols they hope they wouldn't have to use
Back in the West
Another students should watch on the roof with a walkie-talkie
Dentist office on Glenside
Gabriela Cruz a very precise plan
8:20 p.m. there is coming a couple
At 8:30 p.m. this coming a small family with one child
And with the walkie-talkie
Gave us the information oh yeah
Refugee number so-and-so is coming
We gave the information
Show the front end of the tunnel in the east
That our
People could prepare
To open the door if the refugee
Comes knocking at the door
Anderson Jockey Lot
1byone East Germans entered the shed in the East and came out in the bakery
In the West
It was after 10 p.m.
Ralph is now on duty in the last
She parked his VW bus around the corner
I'm going to drive the escapees to their first night of freedom
In this pass it was so silent
Nobody talk to me
Just sitting there like
Like an iceberg
And then
I heard
1 whispering to his neighbor
Who knows whether we are really in the best
Part is it flooded
Another trap
I never heard that that that
Was like an electric shock
These are East Germans who have disc
Crawled to Freedom through 500 ft
Of mud
The freedom have been Out Of Reach for so long
That they didn't believe it when they saw it
The Ralph decided to take a quick detour
He thought to himself
You go with them not the
You go through cool.
That they see it with their own eyes
Christendom was the center of West Berlin
Site of the second largest department store in Europe
Is covered with neon lights and advertisements for Coca Cola and Marlboro
What you'd never see in the east
Out of a sudden
Tripping the rift joking
Laughing
We made it
As if it had been yesterday
Still in my head
The tunnel operated for two nights
But among the students was at least one spy
At the end of the second night two plain-clothes policemen knocked in the apartment door in the east
Tipped off by one of the spine students
They did not know the password Tokyo
One of the students standing watch open the door
A moment later and East German Soldier appeared
Pushed his way into the building
And cornered the student at the door with a Kalashnikov
Ben another student
Fired a shot
All of them sprinted to the backyard and into the shed
Well the East German police fired shots after them
By the end of the night one East German Soldier was dead
The tunnel have been destroyed With Grenades
And 57 people had escaped
Into the tunnel became known as tunnel 57
But the one person Ralph was trying to get out
His cousin
Was not among them
After the tunnel was destroyed
East German newspapers wrote about Western gangsters
To Eternal denim killed one of their soldiers
The East German government install the plaque where the Escape had occurred
Condemning this violent assassination
The Western student sent a letter over the wall
Using balloons
It read we speak on behalf of our group which over the last half-year
Built a tunnel through which 57 fugitive splat
And the entrance to which your son was shot
First we would like to express our sincerest sympathies
Verso heavy Outlaws
They were taking responsibility for the death of this Eastern Soldier
The letter went on
But the real murderer is the system that addressed the massive flood of its citizens not by removing the car
Cause of the problem
But by building a wall
And giving the order for Germans
Deschutes German
Mystery persisted for exactly 30 years
Longer than the wall even existed
The story that in helping 57 people escape
Western tunnelers killed in eastern Soldier
Use of the Wall came down in 1989
Josey records revealed that the Eastern Soldier was actually killed by Friendly Fire
In all the confusion
The six steps to controlling it affecting population
Build a wall around information
And preserve the regimes reputation
We destroyed the world
Down to its roots
And only a year later
Head over to McAfee done with with our own answer
No clue only
Here
Hundred and there's a little bit left and that was entry Reserve
You must understand that from situation
The best Bolognese never let me say they were fenced in
Living like prisoners in
Infragard
There was such hate
Emotion
Yeah
Turn it down Destroyer
Never never never ever again
This is kind of a paradox of the past
In Berlin
Destroy it
But never forget
This is a city with layers and layers of History
I get much of it is gone
The bunker where Hitler died for instance
With mostly demolished
Predicting it was totally unmarked
To prevent it from becoming a symbolic site for neo-nazis
The government finally installed the plaque in 2006
Even the largest remnant of the wall
The East Side gallery
Which is covered with paintings from International artists
It's slated for partial demolition
To make room for luxury apartments
Milkovich became a transportation engineer
He digs tunnels for a living
How many tunnels have you helped build
Subway tunnels
Korea China
Thailand
Ross spent his entire engineering career digging Underground
When you finish school he got a job at the German engineering company that worked on railroads
They made him an international engineering Consultants
An underground train systems all over the world Taipei Railway tunnel
Types of a tongue
Essence
2 Metro lines
Complete Metro lines
What else
These tunnels were way way bigger
And it's crappy tunnel he dug with friends under the wall
Pepper off all those tunnels lead back at least in his mom
The tunnel 57
Let me say it is a little bit like a joke
Apprenticeship
Hangzhou
99% invisible with braces week by Daniel a gross
With Sam Greenspan Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
And please welcome the newest 99 VI producer her name is Katie mango she comes to us all the way from Chicago
From the Third Coast International audio Festival
If you happen to see her in the Berkeley Bowl say hello
And pointer towards the good tortilla chips
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And produce out of the offices of arcsin of brilliant collaborative Architecture Firm
Located in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Hawaii and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and likes show on Facebook I tweet Roman Morris and tweeted Sam listen to Avery tweets
We mingle the new Katie mingle she tweets at
Katie mingle school pictures of tunnel 57 being made and then all the old episodes everything you need
To be a listener of 99% invisible
99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com