99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1914 in Manhattan
The city government took ownership of an apartment building belonging to a guy named David Hess
They use illegal power called eminent domain which allows governments to seize private property for public use
In this case they want to expand the subway system
Has fought them and laws
It was all said and done his building was torn down
And he was left with a triangle shaped piece of property
And when Roman says triangle-shaped
He means the property has was left with was about the size and shape
Very large
Slice of pizza
He was not amused
That's a producer Katie Mingle
Later the city tried to get him to donate his pizza shaped
Property so they could build
Sidewalk
He refused again they build the sidewalk anyway and in the middle of the sidewalk is hess's triangle
With the tile mosaic that reads
Property of the Hess estate
Which has never been dedicated
Republic
In other words get off my triangle
Lyrics it's still there by the way on the corner of Christopher Street and 7th Avenue in the West Village
People like David
That's who refused to sell their properties are called
Holdouts
An eminent domain only comes into play when the government wants your property for public use
If it's a private development that wants your place and you refused to sell there's not much they can do
Although there have been cases where eminent domain has been controversially used for private development
But that's another story
In China they call their holdout houses
Nail houses
You may have seen some of the pictures of single houses sticking up like the head of the nail
Everything else around them bulldozed
Hand carved owl
Basically anywhere there's a lot of new development there are bound to be Developers
Plans to make lots
And lots of money if they could just get that one stubborn person
To move
Which brings us to one of the most stubborn and
Steadfast
That's ever
Edith macefield
I always call her mrs.
That's Kathy Milady she's one of the only reporters who ever got an interview with
Mrs. masefield
Avicii achieved through unwavering persistence good manners and proper attire
Later I asked her I said what was it that made you decide to talk to me today
And she said I like your skirt
Edith macefield lived in a Seattle neighborhood
Salt Ballard
Ballard had once been its own little town until it was annexed into Seattle in 1907
To have the feel of a small town
A lot of single-family homes and small businesses
That started to change around 2005
When
Development really started to sprout
Terra Condominiums we started hearing some
Push back
From old-time residents in the neighborhood Who felt that the neighborhood was changing
Too quickly
Ballard became so iconic of this type of Superfast high-density development that
Hoods we call it the
Ballard ization of my neighborhood
So in 2005 when Ballard was in the middle of bean Ballard I
A developer wanted to build a shopping center that would take up the entire block where Edith macefield have lived
The last 50 years
Edith macefield house was in a more industrial section of Ballard and her black was mostly empty besides
I've heard tiny house
Just so you can picture her house you know when you're a kid and you draw
A picture of a house using a little square with a triangle on top then you put a little front door in a couple of windows on each side
That is exactly
What Edith macefield house look like
The developers offered her seven hundred and
$50,000
Monster House
Which was appraised at about 120000
And as you can
Probably yes
She said no
And so they said no problem
We'll just build arm all around you
Like literally
All around you
Hi I'm Barry Martin
I work in construction is a project superintendent so I'm just the guy out there in the sight making sure that
You don't get all gets done
Barry was hired
Oversee the shopping center project
And he heard that some Ballard residence
Weren't happy about all the nude
But he wasn't too worried
I mean
Just a job for me
You know I didn't really think about it
You're really one way or another
He hadn't yet heard about Edith macefield
So when I got closer to where I was going to start the project
My wife asked me if that was the one where
There was a little lady down in
Ballard would move
I said no that's not it cuz you know
These guys would have told me
I called them up and they said oh yeah didn't we tell you
Whoever said you can't stand in the way of progress
Is never tried to step over Edith macefield
Old lady being bullied by Developers
The story was classic David and Goliath
Edith macefield
Versus the big bad Developers
And Barry Martin wasn't super
Excited about all the extra media attention on his crotch
I'm thinking this is a lose-lose
Proposition because
All she has to do is
You don't complain
Adele somebody at the TV station or the
On the newspaper
Llamacolombia
Pretty big deal
But even though the press was clamoring to talk to mrs maysfield
She wanted nothing to do with talking to them
Kathy mullady had been one of the few exceptions
Here's mrs. masefield turning down help from a CBS reporter as she
They took out some trash in her front yard
As Mrs macefield thank you very much
Later in the segment
He knocks on our door
And you can hear muffled
Go away
Is there any chance okay
Unfortunately that muffled recording of a
Cranky mrs. masefield is the only one week
Define defer
She passed away in 2008
Which will talk about more later
Love my second day there
When walking by eat his house and she was out in the front yard
With the flowers and her little dog that was blind
The workers started to demolish the few other building
Think that we're on the Block and dig up a bunch of soil that was contaminated with lead and all the while their neighbor
Mrs. maysfield
Went about her business
Day after day just like she'd always done
Should get up in the morning and feed the
Bert
Anthro
Bird seed on the sidewalk
Most of the time the bridge he would be there when we got to work
And if the birds eat wasn't there by 10
We knew something wasn't right
If they didn't see the birds
Marywood knock on her door to see if she was okay
And she would usually yell at
Get the hell out of there and go away and leave her alone
And I just tell her that
Okay I'm just checking on you
A lot of people thought that once the construction started
Ernest Edith macefield would fold
The noise and the encroachment on her privacy would just be too much
The Architects even designed the building in such a way
But if mrs. masefield ever decided to move
They can easily incorporate the space Warehouse was into the building
But she didn't fall
The developers up their offer to $1000000
Plus they offered to find her a similar home somewhere else
And pay for a home health care worker
She turned them down
Beer past
In the building around Edith macefield house got bigger and bigger
The image of it was really something
Amazing pictures of the house especially if you're from Seattle
The building powered 40 feet above Earth
Colonel house was
Was Bohr
Dirty well
It wasn't just a big building sitting next to a tiny house
It was a big building completely enveloping at Kani House on three signs
So close
Mrs masefield could practically lean out her window and touch them
As the building moved forward the construction workers
Checking in on mrs. masefield and occasionally bringing her lunch from McDonald's
She reportedly loved
Chicken tasty
And Barry kept dropping off business cards
Telling her to call if she needed any
And then one day she
You finally did
Said that she
Didn't feel comfortable driving that day
Could I give her a ride to go
Get her hair done
You don't got her in the car and started driving over there and we are kind of talking about how
Ballard was changing
And sort of
Edith macefield wasn't angry about the way Ballard was changing
Cheap wasn't even angry about the mall they were building more or less
On top
Love her house
She said cuz it always changes
He said 20 years from now they'll be carrying this down and building something else
She said that's just the way it goes
I felt like she was
Happy that we were there
She said she didn't mind the noise she said I was through World War II
That's Kathy Milady again
And
She didn't mind the attention from those a young construction workers who walked by her house and the wave to her or
Smiled or checked in a little bit
She's been there for fifty years
That point in time know she was 86 years old
Money didn't really mean much to her
Anymore she couldn't
Move around very well
She knew where everything was in her house
She had
No reason to move
She didn't have any family
So
Getting the money so that she could leave it for family didn't exist
Mrs. maysfield didn't have any living family to leave any money to
By the same token
She didn't have any family to help take care of her in her old age
Pretty soon bury started
R2 all of her
Lenny started making them
I got concerned that mrs. masefield who was getting more frail by the day was going to burn herself
Under stove
So
I just started
Swing by there after work and making her dinner
Twink in a microwave so
I guess I have to
Cook for social don't have to worry about it any
Pretty soon Barry was making
Her lunch and breakfast as well
One day I woke up and I'm making a free meal
Today
And then I had to come in on Saturday and
Sunday
Because
Spending all this time together
He got to know mrs. masefield pretty well they listen to music together watch old movies
Mrs. masefield also had
Crazy stories about her past
She told me that she was a spy for the British
That she had been
Captured
Spine
And they put her in decal
Then she escaped from there she also said she
Taking care of a bunch of War Orphan
England after World War II
And on top of all of that she claimed to know a bunch of famous
People
She told me Benny Goodman with her cousin
She had met
Tommy and Jimmy Dorsey and then played
You know saxophone and clarinet with them
Her stories were so incredible
But they were hard for people to believe
But they were harder to dismiss than you might think
She came across to me as
Very sharp
She liked
To talk a lot
About the past
But she also watch the news
And new
Exactly what
What's going on
Barry took care of mrs. masefield
For nearly a year-and-a-half
Making all of her meals visiting with her on weekends and after work
Sometimes she call in the middle of the night
Tell him she'd had an ax
And she needed him
You know she had very few wishes one she wanted to die in her house
You live out her last days in her house
But if I wouldn't have been there
At some point in time
They would have
Put her in a state-run facility
And it wasn't a reason for that
And then she's going to
Being happy
The last days of her life
And for what
When she was diagnosed with pancreatic cancer and began to die
She finally agreed
To a home health care work
But very became / power of a
Attorney
The person she put in charge of her
Her final decision
Edith macefield died in her house on June 15th 2008
She was 86 years old
She left her house to Barry Martin
The construction superintendent who became her friend
While simultaneously sandwiching your house between a Trader Joe's
In an LA Fitness
After she died very begin packing up her house and he look for things that would
Confirm this is masefield
Crazy stories about her
You never found anything about her escaping.
Caring for any War orphans
But he did find a Benny Goodman record
The written inscription
It said
To my cousin Edith
With love
Bunny
After people found out that Edith macefield had left her house to Barry Martin
There were some who called him an opera
Ultimately it's hard for anyone
Other than Barry to know what his motivation
Menswear but for what it's worth I did talk to a couple of the Home Health
Care workers who took care of mrs. masefield before she died
And they both had a very high opinion of
Said he was there every day when no one else was
I love you seem to care.
Deeply for mrs. masefield
Barry eventually sold Edith macefield house to an investor who had various plans for it
None of which have materialized
And recently the same guy asked Barry if he'd be interested in buying it back
He said no
No and if I did eat it would probably
Probably hot
For that
She told me to
Hold out until I say
Got my price
And then to
You know
Use the money to help get my kids through school
The house is all boarded up now
And no one's sure what will happen to it
Which is sad to some people
The berry says mrs. masefield didn't care what have
Happened to the house at
After she died
But she never really cared about the bigger story that the outside world had
Created about her
She had her own personal reasons
For staying in her house and they had nothing to do with it
But whatever her reasons were for doing it
She stood her ground
When she became a symbol on whether she wanted to or not
There's even a tattoo shop in Seattle that does a special tattoo
In honor of the Legacy
Edith macefield
A picture of a little house
And underneath it
Steadfast
99% invisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and knee Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of
Arcsin and Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
X-Men episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
If you follow me at Roman Mars on Twitter or the
Jalan Facebook
You know that I'm in London right now I walked 12 miles today along the X and yesterday I visited
BBC in Saint Mark kermode and Simon Mayo
Come true
And if you follow me on Twitter and Facebook you've already seen the pictures and if you don't then you're missing out so get on that
Play social media is not your thing you can always stop by our place at 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalize Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com