99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1933 several Nation States including the US got together in Montevideo Uruguay to defy
Define what it means to be a state
The treaty that came up with include 16 articles
Each of which lays out different rights and duties of statehood
That's producer Julia DeWitt
But the most famous article is number one
Which set out the four basic criteria of Satan
Basically what it takes
Country
The state
Person of international law
Chip possess the following quality
Undefined
Permanent Poppy
Chelation
State government
Add capacity
Enter into relation
I think a good flag is crucial to but that's just me to flag the criteria for because
Seem to some people surprisingly simple
So simple that a lot of people thought
And sorry for a lot of people that just
Triggered I suppose an idea that that meant that they could just
Culverhouse an independent country
That's John Ryan
Disa
Countries that might even just be
Be somebody's
Backyard
It could be an area that climbing for one reason or another
To be
An independent country John Ryan is the co-author of the guidebook micronations
The Lonely Planet guide to homemade Nations
And yeah this is the same Lonely Planet that publishes Taurus guys to places like Mexico
Citgo in France
John says most of these micronations are just kind of for fun
They aren't expecting anyone to take them seriously
And they don't usually mean all four criteria laid out by the Montevideo convention
Places like
Molossia
Witches in Nevada 15
1 guys
House is such a lovely guy president
Kevin bow and
He runs this great little micronation
He gets about
In military regalia
Reflective sunglasses
He looks totally like that
In a Central American dictator from the
70's or 80's
Is currency is pegged to the price of Pillsbury cookie dough
So don't go up and down in value
Adidas
Few years ago malossi was present bow started the micro National Olympics were micronations compete
Against each other in events like Checkers and the boomerang throw
Crazy project
But then
There Are Places
Like Sealand
Probably.
The welds
Most interesting and
Fascinating micronation is Ceylon
MC LAN
Cannot be dismissed so easily
The state as a person of international law
Chip possessed
The following qualifications
A defined
If you search for the principality of Sealand on Google Maps
It comes up as a little red dot off the east coast of England
Zoom in for some photographs of the place
And you'll see a metal platform
Sitting atop two concrete pillars
A stilted structure
Surrounded on all sides
Weather NYC
The platform is about the size of a football field
So
Pretty small territory as countries go
So how did this platform in the sea you become a micronation
It all started with rock and roll
Full scale out that but I
In the 1960s the British government wasn't giving out enough licenses to accommodate all the music that the kids were
Suddenly demanding
So a bunch of DJ's decided to take matters into their own hands
They set up pirate radio stations on ships in on abandoned British forts in the North Sea to broadcast rock music
Back to England
This week from the Spencer Davis Group it's still keep on running keep on
Wushiland itself physically isn't open photos built in
It was built in an old safe defend the United Kingdom against
Gemini across the world
Floating the River Thames at the London bombing London
That's Michael Bates
Prince
Sealand
Back in 1967 Michael said Roy was one of the DJs trying to turn these old abandoned forts in the sea
Inter radio stations
But don't be fooled Roy wasn't just a rock and roll love and hippie he was a free-market capitalist
He is being interviewed about his Pirate Radio Ventures
Every song about the time
In any case Bates and the other DJs kept getting slapped with big fines when the British government
So Michaels adroit change course
Describe the idea of a pirate radio station and decided to go for something even
Bigger
The challenge
I was talking to his lawyer friend Monday
My father system
Roy Bates wanted to start his own country
And learn with his principal no you can't do that
My father went ahead and did it
Roy's at the Fort was uniquely suited for Independence because of its location
Is 6 miles off the coast of England
I'm at the time England territorial Waters only reach 2 3 miles offshore
3 miles because that is how far a cannonball can fly and break through a foot of Oak
So it's sort of a date at law
It's been since change to 12 miles
Yeah we got
Better cannons now
But back then with the three mile rule
Consider the fort
Which again was just a platform perched onto concrete hours out in the ocean
Reconsider this claimable territory
Hidden by the platform cuneiform missions
Just gathered up his family and move them there
The government might call is squatting
The Bates family
With nation building
And sew on a Blustery Day in 1967 a nation was built
Sealand has a national anthem
And they have a flag it's actually a pretty good flag it follows all the principles of good design it simple as 3 color
Where is red white and black
Were the ratings for Roy
The Black History station part radio
On the white line down the middle of it is
The pasta
Purity
But he travels today
I think he was slightly tongue-in-cheek on that
The country's motto is
From the sea
Freedom
The state of the
International law
I possess the following qualities
Define parity
Permanent population
The population of Sealand consisted for many years of four people
Roy Bates
Founder
What's his wife Joan
His daughter Penelope
And his son Michael
My name is Saint Michael Prince
And his daughter princess
He didn't call himself King now
Before Michael was a prince
He was just a kid from England
He was 14 and importing school when his dad move them all out to sea land
I envisage six months like a bit of an Adventure Pass
That would be the end
Michael and his dad ended up living on sea land
For about 25 years
For the most part it was just Michael and his dad mom and sister out on the platform
About the house
Set up water Gathering system and filled some of the rooms in the towers with canned food
Nowadays the rooms are fully furnished
There's a non-denominational Chapel
Generators for power there's even a gym where you can work out
But back when they first started the place was pretty bare-bones
Sometimes when the weather got bad and their resupply boat didn't show up
They get a little hungry
On those days they would eat fish that they caught
And biscuits from a box
When Michael would get sick of being on a metal platform out in the middle of the ocean
Cute hitch a ride on a boat back to the mainland
Divine Kids Zone age
When I came back up here
Retinol night club or something like that have a good time
The same as do when they want to hit Pole.
And sometimes he would even bring friends back to Sealand
Nicest muggle women out there
Translate Illuminati
The state of a
International law
Possess the following koala
Define Doterra
Eminent popular
Government
Sealand of various government posts apart from the monarchy
Where is their Minister of Foreign Affairs
And the caretaker that stays up there when there is head of Homeland Security
He's the one that issues visas
And stamps your passport if you visit
Their legal code is pretty simple they basically have all the same laws as England
Install the same laws
Unlike England seal and allows guns
Prince Michael loves gun
But I never really had to use them
Except once
There are a lot of ways to make money on seal and which meant the family was always trying to come up with money making scheme
And sometimes a scheme that got a little weird
In 1978 Merle Michaels.
Started talking to some businessmen from Germany Austria and Belgium
They wanted to build a Leisure Island around sea land and put a casino on it
I'm one day Roy and his wife went to Austria
Talk with some funders about this deal
That conceal and Michael who is 25 the time
Was figuratively holding down the literal for
When a helicopter showed up in a group of men lowered themselves to the platform
First Montana recognize
One of them was tired of stealing government its Minister of Foreign Affairs
A guy by the name of Alexander awesome box
But according to Michael auchenbach was trying to shut Michael's family out of the casino deal
He was allegedly staging a coup
And so he says to Michael
Find C land over to me
It's mine
Am I going to head it feels like
No way
Apache helicopter
Drinks and as he's doing this
Michael says auchenbach and his goons slammed the front door and barricaded
Tribbing Michael in his own home
Close lights out
After four long days Michael captors put him on a boat to Holland
Exiled in Holland Michael gets in touch with his dad
To confirm that of course he hadn't signed Zealand over the awesome box
They made a plan to take their country back
The call of a friend who has a helicopter company
Explain the situation
Is it okay I'll take you out
Before they take off they remove the doors from the helicopter and tie ropes to the runner so that when they get to Sealand
They can slide down the ropes Navy SEAL Style
And still on the platform
They take off in the middle of the night
Play flying out of the note C with no doors in this helicopter
In the dark
They slid down the Rope onto the platform of Sealand
Loosely down ropes in The Hobbit the first one down the building
Shouting in German and running around Michael climbed up onto the roof of the building
With a shotgun
In case you didn't catch that he said he had a sawed-off
Shotgun
And then I jumped off the roof is that true or false
He jumped off the roof and according to Michael the gun accidentally went off
Boom it went off
Every times what happened here
That one shot was enough to scare the Invaders into surrendering
Roy and Michael let all the non-citizens a seal and go
But the Minister of Foreign Affairs Alexander Rockenbach
Did not get off
So easily
Achenbach had betrayed the crown
They charged him with treason and brought him to trial
My father was presiding judge
They held Offenbach prisoner until the German ambassador actually came out to sea land
Negotiate press release
Eventually they let him go
Was that all hostilities
Brandon
When the German government sent their Ambassador out to negotiate the release of one of their citizens
This
Says Michael
Has been entering into formal relations with Sealand
Which fulfills the fourth and final Criterion
For being a state
State of the
International law
I possess the following qualities
Population
State government
The tickle of the box
This very little
That you can say
Swiping from
Legitimacy really
We decided not to come
Who wrote The Lonely Planet guide to micronations
Well he might concede that seal and fulfills the criteria for being a real estate
Most experts
Do not
Oh definitely no it's not
That is your a vidmar
Your aunt is a fellow at Oxford and an expert in international law
He thought a lot about what makes a statement
Sealand is Justin
Abandoned platform it is not really a viable place to live and buy
Explaining that incident us
Relations with another state
I mean
They're trying to fit
Their case was in the convention but I mean it's the joke that was that was taken actually quite
But far doesn't mean that the Monday vidao convention is worthless
It's just not complete
What really matter is Siri says
Is recognition
The end of the day
It is political
If
Say
Country Tonite Estates of this world recognized
Sealant is being an independent state
I think there would be no doubt that it was Independence Day
But this would of course never happen
There are a lot of places that meet the Montevideo criteria that rightly or wrongly the US does not consider naysh
Patience
Palestine for example
Is recognized by 135 other countries
But not bother you ask
And then there's Taiwan
Tywanna meet all the criteria
It has a permanent population a government
Define territory and they're able to enter in the diplomatic relations with other countries
Taiwan is currently recognized by 22 countries
Mostly small countries like tuvalu and Burkina Faso
The China still considers Taiwan to be a Chinese province
And because we don't want to piss off China we also don't recognize Taiwan
Estate
Although the US government does send ambassadors to Taiwan
We just technically make the ambassadors resign when we send them and then we reinstate them when they're transferred
To another post
So if China says anything about it we can be like ambassador
What am I asking
So many state has more a matter of degrees
Some states are recognized by 120 legitimate countries
Or the others are only recognized by 5 or 10 country
As of this moment no one formally recognizes Sealand
As a state
Not even tuvalu or Burkina Faso
As for the population of Sealand
As Roy Bates the founder got older
He found it easier to live on the mainland
He died in Essex in England in 2012
Can't blame her didn't like life out on the platform so he moves to Mainland England
Into
It's just a head of Homeland Security that lives out on the platform
Prince Michael likes the idea that is there
If he ever wants to move back
Sealand will likely never have two sovereignty but at the same time England has never formally reclaimed it
Probably because doing so would be harder than just letting it keep being what it is
You know that little Windswept
Platform on the sea might not be much
It is there
And the flag still flies
At least for now
99% invisible West produced this week by Julia DeWitt and Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery truffle Manan
We are product of 91.7 kalw San Francisco
And produce at the offices of arcsin
Oakland's Premier architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and like a show on Facebook will all on Twitter and Instagram with Spotify playlist all kinds of stuff
For your home base for all things 99 Pi is that 99 pmi.org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that.
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com