99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On May 3rd 1978
Construction workers in San Francisco we're digging a foundation for a new building on Sansome Street
Right next to the tallest skyscraper in the city
The Transamerica Pyramid
In the heart of the financial district
They were about 20 feet below street level
When their shovels
Hit something totally
But expect
Who is the hull of an old ship
That's reporter Edmund Fitzgerald
Archaeologists immediately came in
And start scraping away all the dirt and mud
And
After a few days
They don't cover the
Full skeleton
120 foot Gold Rush era vessel called in in
Preserve perfect
New York Streets of San Francisco
As the archaeologist did their work
Hundreds of people gathered to watch the bizarre scene
A massive
Massive ship being pulled out from beneath the pavement
As Speaker
Construction hoarding was put up people were carving holes in it
To look in and see Niantic emerge from the mud
That's James Delgado
I'm an archaeologist
Then the historian and I'm the author of
Gold Rush Pawn
The maritime archaeology of San Francisco
Delgado was 20 years old then
An archaeologist in training and he was part of the excavation
Inside the ship he found
All kinds of artifacts from the gold rush
Brush that have been preserved Underground
Ric's nails
Tin plates for sheathing
Boots
Jackie
Saddle
Shovels
A lot of booze
49ers like to drink
Delgado even pop the cork on a bottle of 150 year old champagne
Tasted
But the excavation of the Niantic launched his career in Marine archaeology
Inspired him to study the ships
Spinning San Francisco
Because
Isn't the only one down there
I see that they're probably as many as seventy ships that were buried that in some way shape or form remain even
If it's fragments
In 1994 city workers were digging a tunnel for the muni train when they hit the side of another gold
The ROM
The decision was made to drill through it
They tunneled right through the hall
In today thousands of San Francisco's travel through the ship every morning as they ride the train between Folsom Street
In the Embarcadero
Severally marked in the tunnel but for those of us who know when you take that turn you're passing through the gold rush
Ship rum
To understand how all of these ships ended up buried underground beneath the city we need to go back to the
The 1830
When San Francisco was just a
Tiny little pork
Call yerba buena
It was an outpost of a few buildings with Tiny Town Square that's it
By 1847 the population had grown to a few hundred
They renamed the port San Francisco
But it was still just a small town
But in 1848
All of that changed with
The discovery of gold in
January the gold rush
Titlewave of prospect
California
And by the end of 1850
The San Francisco waterfront
Clogged with more than
Thousand ships
And the town had grown into a city of
Thousand
So you're looking at a city that was in a decade
Has gone from being a village to being the
The 12th largest city in North
But the land around San Francisco was mostly sandyhills
But not well suited to this
Scale development
So to meet the surging demand for Real Estate the cities sold off plots of water in the shallow Title Zone
A person could buy a piece of water
But it was their job to turn it into usable ground
Some people dump sand
The garbage into their plots
To try and make plans
Other Strokes
Steaks in the mud
And build platforms on top of the
And a lot of people repurposed the ships that had brought them to California
The ship's help
Because they came many of them were sitting idle the cruiser gone off
Did the diggings or hit run away
So the owners rented them out or sold them outright to become floating
Houses warehouses
The town jail offices
You name it
Over 200 of them became floating building
Commercial life
References
What you had the Apollo Saloon which was basically a restaurant they sold
Donut in a cup of coffee
Two bits they said
You had the euphemia which was turned into the town jail and later became an insane asylum
You also had ships that served as water cistern
You had other ships that worked as government offices
And another ship
The Good Ship Panama
Was used as a seaman
Church
The city looked like a forest of masts
And playing
Schenectady ship
Creating a grid boardwalks perched above the water one visitor said that San Francisco was Venice built
Pine
But they were obvious downside
Next to a floating city and little by little
People began to fill in areas between the shifts
Using whatever they could get their hands on
From garbage to unwanted cargo to
Dead bodies
You name it
Everything was thrown into that
And with this gradually began the process of
Feeling in the mud
In this way the shoreline itself begin to advance
At this point the harbor was a patchwork of
A freshly filled Lots
Ships and buildings on stilts
But then in May of 1851
A massive fire broke out in downtown San Francisco
The wind
Fans the flames
And by the
The time the next day had dawned
More than 2000 buildings
Gone
The Flames were so high
That they could see the glow in Monterey
Some of the ships caught fire
Leaving their half chard holes in the muddy water
By the time they managed to put the fire out
The Waterfront was just a mushy mess
ESO smoldering Timber
And that mushy mess was too unstable to rebuild on
So you some of the Worlds
First steam powered excavator
Describe sand off of nearby Hills and dunes and dumping
On top
By September
Of 1851
The old Waterfront had been
Buried
And with it the Niantic
The Rome and all of the other Gold Rush ships
InTune
Dennis manufactured ground
After the fire at San Francisco continue to expand
Feeling in more and more of the title Zone in deeper
Burgundy for water
And eventually the states Dept
They built a sea wall
The cap the production of new land they drew a line instead San Francisco you can go no further
And today we know that line
It's the Embarcadero
The walkway along the Eastern edge of the San Francisco Wharf
But by that time a city at build up
On top of all this sand and dirt
Garbage
And over the years
San Francisco continue to develop
Today what
Had been the title Zone
Is the heart of the city's Financial.
Throughout history the absence of ground has proven to be a
Surprisingly small Lobster
For people who want
How to build stuff
San Francisco isn't the only city that is built its own land
Large portions of Boston Seattle Hong Kong and Merced
We're built on top of fill
It's not uncommon to see it another City's New York
Manhattan built out
And filled
Theory the World Trade Center sits on
What's landfill
Ashley found a ship when they were building the original World Trade Center towers
What is now Mumbai India used to be a 7 Island archipelago
Before the British colonial government turned it all into one continuous strip of land
Tokyo has built 60000 acre
Over the last several centuries
The process of building new land along the water
Is often referred to as
Land reclamation
Which
Is kind of ridiculous
Land reclamation is another one of those
Words that
Made up band
Masquerades what's really happening you're creating
Land where it didn't exist before
Or even creating a whole country
Like the Netherlands
Does a very
Extraterrestrial
ICP the Dutch making their own country
That Stephen Graham
Professor of cities in society at Newcastle University and author of the book vertigo
The city from satellites to bunkers
Most of Holland
Most of the Netherlands currently constructed
Isn't engineering construction is a huge project of
Land reclamation land manufacture touchdevelop
Writable techniques
To build land in places that were actually below sea level
Let me see fingernails is Medieval Times by launch Dykstra constructed
Large pumping systems were constructed
To create a dry country underneath the sea
A proud of this history
Does a popular saying there
God created the world but the Dutch created the nether
Humans have been making their own ground for a long time the process has reached New Heights in recent years
The historic
K-Love
Land reclamation along money factor in the building up to
Longanisa
Absolutely miniscule
Skyler White
What's going on today
More and more cities are building waterfront property
For airports
Skyscraper
And housing
Urban economics
If you create you
Supply in an area weather is amazing levels of the Mountain at 4
It's very possible and new dredging technology
Have enabled developers to build land faster
And on a grander scale
Often at the expense
Of the environment
I mean they use
Cute ships for example which ethical rainbow
Dredging cyst
These ships suck up massive amounts
To sand and gravel from sea floor
Shoot it through the air in a giant parking rainbow Muk on the area where they're trying to build new land
This technology has been particularly useful
For creating artificial Islands
China is using these rainbow dredging ships
To turn uninhabited Coral apples in the middle of the South China Sea into larger Island
I could support human settlement there actually manufacturing land in the hopes of staking territorial claim to highly
Contested Waters
And then there's to buy device of poster child for this process where the wealthy desert Emirate has been
Built a series of artificial islands for wealthy Elite
Three of the new landforms are shaped like massive Palm fronds another project called
The world is a cluster of islands designed to look like a map of the world
But Dubai's Reclamation project has stirred up so much sediment that they buried coral reefs oyster beds and Seed
Grass fields in the Persian Gulf and some of the islands that make up the world
Are already starting to a road back into the sea
Dubai is also running out of sand
At least
The kind of sand do you need to build
Desert sand is too fine for
Construction
And Dubai has used up so much of the sand around it
East Coast
But they now have to import it from Australia
Globally humans use over 40 billion tons of sand a year
The two largest uses of that sand
Are concrete production
Inland manufacturing process
And it's created a global
Sand shortage
Is forcing countries to go to extreme lengths
In their efforts to build new ground
Most famous example here is Singapore
The wealthy island nation is one of the densest countries in the world
At constantly looking to expand its territory
Those plans to make
Singapore 20th 30% bigger than x full 258
True Manufacturing Uline without enough sand of its own Singapore has had to look
Elsewhere does being a lot of evidence that
Best extended blind manufacturing around Singapore the basis for its growth
Tiny Island City
Is is based on basic stealing Sandy Islands from the
Poor countries like Cambodia and Indonesia and Burma
Removing a material physically
Land itself
Is Flowing from poor countries
The wealthier one
Those countries
Made
Sam
Illegal
Because of this
Signs that they are losing their own
Parrot tree
Blade manufacturing isn't Justice
Expanding territory
In some cases it's expanding upward
On the coast of Nigeria
Developers are building a new luxury City
Called Eko Atlantic
On top of manufactured ground
Install thing about Eko Atlantic is it's about 3 or 4 meters higher
And the rest of Lego Sand is being designed
To be more resilient to expect
Sea level rises
On the rest
Pacetti
Lagos has a very poor lowline City that's extremely vulnerable
The sea level rise
This is very disturbing
Apartheid CC amazing hair
Where Elites are able to build their own Escape Routes from
Increasingly powerless
Auditions
True going higher
Into manufactured loan
In theory building new land could be a part of the solution to sea level rise
But Stephen Graham says these new land projects are often built exclusively for the rich
Tell me about private projects for those who can get in and can afford it
They're not being built
Public projects very often
To protect
Cities as a whole
Massive Reclamation projects like
Eko Atlantic are the most obvious
Of manufacture
But even if you live far away from the coast
The ground beneath your feet
May have been partially created by human
People are continuously impacting the surface of the Earth
We dig up Rock from one place grind it into cement
And build a sidewalk somewhere else
The book skyscraper
Dump the rubble somewhere
And build a hosp
And all of this human activity
Is actually created a new layer
On the surface of the Earth's crust
It made up of Old Brick
Ground up cement
Rusting metal
Archaeologist and geologist
I've started calling this later
The Arceus fear
The ark is fear isn't
Totally unnatural
It's filled with soil roots in earthworms
Symptoms grass
Cross on top of it
And that makes it hard for us to notice
Stephen Graham says that this idea
That human activity has actually created a geologic layer on the surface of the Earth
Is bringing archaeologists and geologists
Together
Traditionally archaeologists study human artifacts within the ground
Well geologist study the ground itself
But what if the ground itself
Was made by human
Archaeologist of increasingly working with geologist in Lacey
The ground is as a gradual accumulation of the leftover stuffing sheets of rubbish
It's the bodies of the dad it's the leftover materials
And it is increasingly Bob the Builder by my thing that's really important
Important for 1 because we need to understand what the ground is made of
If you want to build safely on top of
Manufactured round can be unstable
More susceptible
Earthquake
Sanlitun
Big sample in China in Shenzhen
When the construction material it was
Keep top on a on a hillside spot of the
Grace
Expansions not CT
Basically
Slumped down this a great big slide in the
Does by 80 people
Killed in that as well so
We need to become much more water in creating around geology where will SEC racing around hazard
But the Arceus fear is also a resource to be
Explored
Despain estimates that this is much copper
And not
Artificial ground
Azaleas in all of the copper mines in the world
So in Scandinavia
Starting to mine
The disused industrial ground off their own industry
When you walk through a city
Cota's and pavement and covered in buildings
It's easy to assume that the ground beneath you
Is ancient and natural
Does a does a tendency always just to say the ground is something that's always been there and always will being there
Bethesda
She's about evidence that cities built around grounds
Cities of Rage
Thanks for making their own geology
If you look at a brand new land reclamation project like Eko Atlantic
It's obvious
The ground is manufactured
Right now it looks like a
Giant Sandy construction site
But
If all goes according to plan
Pretty soon there will be parking lots
Skyscrapers
An apartment built
And right now it's hard to imagine that such a blatant example of artificial ground will one day become seen as
Just an ordinary part of the Nigeria lids
But you probably could have said the same thing about
About San Francisco
Then 1850
99percentinvisible was produces week by Emmett Fitzgerald with Katie mingle and Sharif
Boston Bruins fans Ladyhawke Kolstad turn Mazza Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
Special things this week 2 archaeologist Matt Edgeworth who's writing about the Arceus.
That's a lot on this episode
Also Steven Graves new book vertical
Vital link to it on our website
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Percent
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Family Guy
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and a new week
Who discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We've a lively community on Facebook I'm on Twitter at Roman Mars
Way way way too much
But you want hundreds and hundreds of stories to make yourself
Really interesting
Parties
I recommend you go immediately
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com