99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stuck
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
At the end of World War II
As the world began to process
The powerful and devastating effects of the bombings
Hiroshima and Nagasaki
Humankind entered a new era
Enero defined by the destructive potential of nuclear weapons
And the global arms race
To acquire them
Ghostface without Panic the reality of our time
Preparing for survival
My understanding and well the violent applications of atomic weights
Search had already been proven
Governments and scientists suspected Atomic science also held promise for good
Peaceful applications that could bring the world into a new age of scientific progress and Technology
It is not enough
To take this weapon out of the hands of the soldiers
If must be put into the hands of those who will know how
Do strippers military cases
The Arts of peace
Let's President Dwight Eisenhower addressing the UN in a 1953 speech titled Atoms for Peace
In it he proposes creating an agency to oversee and promote safe secure and peaceful nuclear technologies
While also continuing to build up the United States arsenal of nuclear weapons
That agency created in 1957 was called
The international atomic energy Association
Experts would be mobilized
To apply atomic energy to the needs of agriculture
Another peaceful activity
These efforts to find peaceful applications for nuclear research would spur growth in nuclear energy
Which now provides around a fifth of the United States electricity
And expanded use of nuclear medicine
Giving us Imaging techniques and therapy still used for cancer treatments today
That's our own Sharif Youssef
But then there were ideas that seem kind of crazy in hindsight
1 science writer thought nuclear Alchemy was possible
That we would have nuclear factories that manufactured gold
He also believed we could create artificial Suns to control the weather
And others believed we could shower plants and ionizing radiation
Can you take them into better
Stronger crops
But unlike the others
That one
Actually happen
When I ran across it I was just kind of gobsmacked
You know I was just done
I meant
So surprised
I mean there was very little
Scholarly writing about it
That's Paige Johnson
I have a hobby of
History of gardens Johnson is one of the few experts on the often forgotten Atomic Gardens of a 1950s
He's in 60s
Gardens that use radioactive materials in attempts to mutate in breed new plants
I would benefit
Mankind people kind of assumed it was some sort of a conspiracy
Oh this was all hidden from the public wasn't it
And this is a part of the CIA or it was a part of the propaganda age
Actually it wasn't
It was widely talked about in speeches
It was written about in popular mag
Magazines Atomic Gardens have been largely forgotten
But they weren't top secret government projects
Purposely obscured from
They were right out in the open
And they produced
New kinds of fruit
Sand grains and vegetables
That we still have on our grocery store shelves today
Botanic Gardens of the 1950s and
These were part of a broader interest in atomic research that ramped up
During and after World War II
But they were also part of a much older
Debris better heart ear crop
Humans have been messing with plans to suit our needs
This for a long time
But you understand the history of using radiation to mutate
Plants
We need to take a step back to the 1920s
And a relatively new technology of the
X-ray
In 1927 Herman Miller conducted a famous genetics
Where dispose fruit flies
X-rays
A form of ionizing radiation
So basically ionizing radiation is just a nice form of electromagnetic radiation that has the power to
How to penetrate matter
So it has the ability
Potentially go inside the cell
Can actually alter the genetic
Material
The x-rays change the genetic makeup of some of the fruit flies
And some of those changes
It's those mutation
We're heritable
Meaning that they could be passed along to the Next Generation
In the 1920s and 30s
Some plant breeders started using x-rays on plant
And hope so they could induce mutations that can make them grow faster or produce more fruit or create interesting
Flowers
But enthusiasm for those techniques
This would soon die down
And for a while the world lost interest in how radiation could alter plan
Fast forward 2 World War
In a top-secret mission spearheaded by the US government
The Manhattan
A new branch of the Army Corps of Engineers was established
To administer work on military uses
The US began doing research not only on how to make atomic bombs but what their effects might be
After the nation
In concert with a kind of
Weapon base
Experiment
They have started to try to try to monitor what the effect
Of the nuclear radiation in Fallout would be on plants and animals
Well that research continued after the war in a project called operation cross
What are US tested nuclear bombs around a small cluster of islands in the Pacific
The Bikini Atoll is where the US
Testing the atomic bomb
And that's the first place where they really start intentionally
Planting play
And seeing how their effect
Researchers wanted to find out how plants would respond to the Heat
And the cameras but the bombs came off
The US also duck boats nearby filled with rats and goat
Awesome pics
See the effects of bombs on living animals
A lot of them.
On the blast as well as the radiation
But there were other strains of nuclear research going on much
Closer to home
Particularly in National Lab
For the government was willing to throw funding at the new Hot Topic of nuclear science
Even if those projects were directly related to weapons
Enter the Atomic Garden
Add a new quest to alter genetic material in plants
Something we're still doing today
Modern genetic
Education techniques
We have the ability to go in and very carefully slice the genome with the scalp
The radiation experiments B Tomic Gardens were essentially just
Getting the genome with a hammer and see what would happen
What are the most fascinating examples of us
Research was happening at Brookhaven National Lab
So the gamma Gardens of Brookhaven in New York for probably the largest Gardens in the US governmental ever
Devoted to Atomic radiation
Plants
The Brookhaven gamma Garden was created in 1949
And its original goal was to study the effects of
Prolonged exposure to gamma rays on plant
But eventually they begin to research whether they can use gamma Gardens to induce beneficial mutation
The essence of gammagard is it looks like a big circle
I'm with pie-shaped wedges and at the very center of the pie is a radioactive
Eversource
It was usually contained in a pole and would be raised above the level of the ground
The column Gardens actually makes them sound smaller than they were
Many of these gamma Gardens were five acres in size so they were really massive installations
Because of the wedges
When viewed from above almost looks like a symbol for radiation Danger
The center pole contain the radioactive isotope
Usually
Kobalt 6
That would shower the field with gamma radiation for about 20 hours a day
When it was time for researchers to go in and see the results
They would lower the source into an underground bunker made of concrete or lead
Step inside the Fieldhouse
Defense
And inspect the plants arrayed around the center
Generally the at the very front of the source almost all those plants
Die
Pretty much where they be shrunken and shriveled
As you got back towards the back of the
Glad you see plants
Sober living that might look normal but which were going to be evaluated
To see if they had any abnormal growth
Mutations naturally randomly occur in every living cell
Adhere the researches
For Henry the place with radiation in an attempt to
Increase that rate of mutation in the plant's DNA
So in a sense the scientist hope to speed up evolution
They were hoping to create crops that could withstand harsh growing condition
Never more resistant to disease that can produce more food
To help feed the world
I was struck again by just what are utopian Quest
Rebuild plant than in World famine and make the world they even use this language
Smiling Garden of Eden
This Quest wasn't just taking place in the US
By the late 1950s
Similar experiments for happening around the world
In Norway
Sweden Costa Rica and the Soviet Union
Among other places
And that all of these efforts were run by the government
Fancy research universe
Somewhere done by curious citizens
The Atoms for Peace movement began to support the idea that home experimenters could run their own nuclear projects
As part of its Atoms for Peace effort it was really actually designed to enable Atomic entrepreneurship is
1215 starling
You know it's like kind of if the startup culture. Today existed
Only you can get a radioactive source
Switch to run your startup company
In the late 1950s
An oral surgeon in Tennessee became one of these atomic
Entrepreneur
His name was CJ's
Skis
Annie build a little bunker in his backyard where he started a radiating seed
And selling them to home gardeners and two children looking for science fair
These irradiated seeds weren't dangerous to handle
Just because something's been irradiated doesn't make
Get Radioactive
One of species biggest clients was an English woman named Muriel Howard
It was an Enthusiast of all things
Atomic
And all things gardening
Tri-form something called the atomic gardening Society
And its purpose was really to engage
I'm the lady gardener
In the sorts of atomic
Experiments that were taking place the National Lab
So she wanted to provide them with irradiated seeds
And they would hopefully discover useful mutations in people's
People could become members of her Atomic gardening society and Merle would ship out the irradiated seeds and ask them to see
Send back any data they could about the plants
This is really an early example of crowdsourcing
That's what she was doing
And her Atomic gardening Society was just
One of Howard's efforts to get people involved and interested in nuclear science
Previous to the forming Atomic Garden
Society she had published something called the atomic Digest
Byline was safeguarding the atom for the Layman
That digest was part of another Society
She started called the atomic Society for the Layman Albert Einstein to be the first patron of her Society
She was invited to Gatherings of the Nobel Laureate
Who acknowledged her to say our goals are much like yours
A lot of atomic scientists like the idea that their work was being used for something
Besides making bombs
So the atomic scientists were very concerned
Did the power of the atom would be kept kind of only for evil and only for weaponry
And felt like the safest route for it was for it to be brought out into the open
An into the realm of the laborers
Person in into these more peaceful
What causes
Imperial certainly made great efforts to help his cause
She had a lot of atomic Gatherings an event
So there were film screenings I'm about an ectopic Sarah lectures
I'm never parties
And she was particularly unique and that she spoke explicitly to women about this
In 1950
She even saved an elaborate
Performance in which actors pantomime the basic structure
Picture of an atom
And it was reviewed by some
Pretty major publication
So here is the review of a
The performance in Time Magazine
Before select audience
250 raptor ladies and it doesn't faintly board gentleman
713 bosomy atomic energy assoc
It's in flowing evening gowns gyrated gracefully about a stage and Ernest imitation of
Atomic forces
By the 1960s popular interest in atomic gardening was coming to an end
Members of the atomic gardening Society group
Tired of seeing very few promising results from their seeds
It was extremely rare to get a beneficial mutation
Invitations were hard for
People without sign up
If you're training to detect
Backyard Atomic gardening basically reached its
E-quick Mario power
Radiation plant breeding didn't completely die
Disappear
Japan has an Institute that uses our radiation field very similar to the Brookhaven gamma Garden
Any International atomic energy Association and the food and agriculture organization of the United Nations
David Joyner
Plant breeding team
Still conducting research with radiation today
And there are still varieties of plants in our food system
I'm thinking about from radiation experiment
A strain of durum wheat Italy
Varieties of rice throughout Asia
Certain pairs in Japan
And a breed of sunflower in the US
Just to name a few
Also the Rio star grapefruit came about because of radiation breeding experiments and now accounts for about 7
25%
At the grapefruit grown in Texas
A producer Delaney Hall used to live in Texas
And can confirm that it is delicious
Yeah I can confirm that it is
But despite some successes
Radiation plant breeding never managed to live up to its ideals of ending famine
Intermingle world into a quote
Smiling Garden of Eden
Basically after the 60s
It was clear that things didn't live up to their promise
It definitely didn't live up to exasperate
That's Helen and Curry I'm a senior lecturer in the history and philosophy of science at the University of Cambridge
She's also the author of evolution made to order
Plant breeding and technological innovation in 20th century America
Curry thinks that over time especially as environmentalist movement started
People may have become less intrigued by and more wary of all things new clear
Including radiation breeding
Weather it's going to create
Horrible things in the field that I might not want to ever eat anyway
I'm I wonder if radiation lingers on the seeds in my
Pose a threat to me
So I think this view becomes much more mix
Text about
What does the
Possibilities
Some historians believe that the Atoms for Peace movement was just a cover anyway
A way to put a positive spin on Atomic research at the US continue to build up
Its nuclear Arsenal
When Eisenhower assumed office in 1953
The US had about 1000 nuclear weapons
We left in 1961
There were around
Eisenhower needed people to believe that there was hope and nuclear research
Not just fear
So that we wouldn't turn away from nuclear weapons completely
He wanted us to keep pursuing nuclear technology even if it scared us
Because the Soviets were certainly pursuing it
And I was even scarier
At the time
But this March
Toward mutually assured
Destruction would leave us with other world-changing non-military Innovations to
Like nuclear power
Expanded field of nuclear medicine
Course
The unarguably delicious
Rio star grapefruit
Paid Johnson run the blog Garden history girl
In the nanotechnology company 1090
She's also collecting oral histories of the backyards
Potomac Gardens so if you or someone you know planted some irradiated seeds
Go to Atomic gardening.com
Dad your story
Do you want to learn more about the history of radiation breeding as well as a bunch of other cool stuff that we could fit into this story checkout Helen Curry's book
Evolution made to order
Plant breeding and technological innovation in twentieth-century America
It's available from University
Chicago press
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sharif Youssef
Delaney Hall
Avery Chapman
Edmund Fitzgerald Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Katie mingle is our senior editor
Percocet is our digital director
Turn Mazza is our office manager and Sean real
Post all original music
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why but it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show in join discussions about the show
On Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
We're on Instagram and Tumblr to
If you need to catch up with all the stuff we did
Frank Lloyd Wright
Or learn how to properly adjust your car mirrors
That was a really popular article
This week
You have to go to 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com