99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Adam for his actions on special orders everyday that typically Pacifica council member and now
What you're hearing is an Oakland California city council meeting that took place in July of 2014
Announcements does a whole bunch of different issues on the agenda everything from allegations of funds being misused
No manipulation of funds
Okay and it's been a big rip-off with those funds do announcements of neighborhood parties
Football pick up games still games face painting
Zumba dancing and producer Mickey capparis after the entire meeting like a good reporter does
To hear them say this
Move the item Madam president move by Vice married
Technic by Miss mcelhaney and by consensus
This will adopt the ends in the
Actually say it directly
But by adopting the items of the consent calendar
What happened there is the city of Oakland
Finally legalized
For the first time since the 1930s
Pinball machine
I Michael Sison the founder and executive director of the Pacific Pinball Museum
The Pacific Pinball Museum which is a collection of really cool mostly older machines that you can still play
Isn't Oakland's neighboring City Alameda
Until recently
Coin operated pinball machines were also illegal in Alameda and it's the reason
That we started out as a
Admission based
Establishment
And everything is
Free play most of the Museum's pinball machines look a lot like the ones you've seen before in your local bar
But there are few really old ones that look completely different
In Pinball's design history can help explain why
It was illegal for so long
And why after nearly 80 years
Abena slightly sketchy leather jacket wearing there dwell
Pinball can now go legit and claim its place with Pac-Man
Has good clean family fun
Was it more like Billiards
YouTube the ball onto the field with a pool stick
In the 1860s the pool cue turned into a spring-loaded plunger that you pull and release to Launch
The ball they were simple wooden boards with last tops no electricity no flashy art or colors
And the game was made small to fit on top of a counter at a bar or drugstore
Mechanically gamer similar to
Basically did one action
Pull the plunger
The ball would shoot up the right side of the board and onto the Playfield
Where there were little pocket
That we catch
And then they were usually
Stamp
Point value
Indoor pens which look like tiny nails of obstructed your way into the pocket
That's where pinball
In the first games warrant
Coin-operated
Bars would buy one
And they would rent it out to
We wanted to play it and gamma
Was kind of like running
Out the car.
By the 1930s pinball games work when operating
He find his little countertop cans all over the place
Bars in drugstores you know you buy an egg cream to drink and some horrible tasting Elixir at the local drugstore
Can you use your change to play some pinball
And maybe you'd want a pack of gum or cigar and you have fun doing it
Then they move to
Just straight up gambling
Where instead of being awarded a prize
You were given cash
And it's around this point the pinball became Electric
Lights and buzzers started showing up
Along with other stuff
Netflix bumper
Bounce off of
Get more points
Points that needed to be tallied up on a scoreboard which led to what is now referred to as the back glass that's the part of the pinball
A machine that faces you as you play
And the art on the back glass became one of the most iconic things about the pinball machine
On the newer games a lot of the artist license
Spy movies like the 1991 hit Blockbuster The Addams Family
But if you go into the Pinball Museum in Alameda
Almost all the old games from thirties and forties
We're done by one of two artists
Sid George Blanton and Roy Parker
Dar was meant to appeal to men and boys
Teachers pictures of pretty lady
The back glass of a game called marble Queen depicts a group of women in swimsuits and high heels
Gathered around in a circle
Playing marbles
They're surrounded by a big tall fence
Almost like they're in the clubhouse
How do you see that the guys that are
Let you know picking through the fence and
It's pretty funny
The Ultimate Fantasy of a boy from the 1930s
Women in their bathing suits
Playing marbles
The lights and buzzers in women in bathing suits
Sometimes people were just playing to win a free game
Other times there was a bigger payout
But it all added up
These things made a ton of money
I can't emphasize enough of that because
The mafia got involved it was all cash with so much money disappearing in the pinball machines
The authorities started cracking down
It really got it
Heated in the 40s
More and more laws were being an act
To make
Pinball Gamble
Pulling harder manufacturers would try to get around this by labeling the machines
It says right here for amusement only no prizes no wager
Maybe they put that right on the machine
And everybody we knew that
Well that's
Exactly what it was
For it by the end of the 1940s pinball was banned in most major cities including Chicago and Los Angeles
But perhaps nowhere was the pinball Crackdown so Extreme as a New York City
Where 1942
Mayor LaGuardia ordered the NYPD to round up all of the machine
Then
In a press event
Damier personally shattered some of the machines with a sledgehammer
It had to be dumped into the Hudson River
LaGuardia later reported that mm new police billy clubs would be made from the wooden legs of old pinball machine
Perfect for knocking the heads of pinball plain Hooligans
LaGuardia did not succeed in ridding the world of pinball entirely though
It was still legal in some cities
And even in New York
It didn't totally does
Disappear
It just moved
In the City Underground established
Meanwhile the game designers were still developing new features
The most important of which
Were the flippers that first appeared in 1947
It allowed you to swap the ball around the play field by pressing two buttons on either side of the machine
In other words
The flippers gave you some control over the outcome of the game
Remember when pinball machines were first band
The games are considered a game of chance
He basically put your quarter in
Pull back the plunger and hope for the best
When The Flipper was added to the pinball machine
It should have changed the games legal status
It wasn't a game of chance anymore you can finally control the ball
If only they could find some way to
Prove it
Ladies and gentlemen I give you Rodger Sharp
I guess it one point I was considered to be
It's not the best player in the world one of the best players in the world
Nearly 40 years after the introduction of The Flipper
In April of 1976
Roger Sharpe was called upon to prove that pinball with a game of skill
Before a meeting of the New York City Council
On the day of the hearing tensions were high
It was packed
Lot of camera Crews
The New York State coin-operated Amusement game Association
How to arrange for the hearing
Need hauled to pinball machines into the meeting room
When that shark was to play
And another that would serve as a backup
In case the first one suddenly died
Start going over to
The game would have been designated
The council have been pretty antagonistic to Sharp
They thought he would cheat
And right before he was supposed to play
A council member stopped
You should know
Not that game
That came over there
I think that the head of the city council thought the vacuum was somehow rigged
Let's go with the game that's been turned off and nobody paid any attention to this over there in the
Corner
The council session took a 20-minute recess
So that the camera crews could change the lighting from the original machine
Into the new machine
And then Rodger sharp steps up
Then starts playing
Back that I was able to really show off
So it was very nice to be able to call my shots and just do whatever I want to do
Breaking Bad cams and shots for right to left or left to right
And then for the grand finale
Wanted to prove that even the first shot
The one that involves just pulling back the plunger and Let It Go but even that shot can be perfected
With skill
Return to the council members
Says if I do this right it's going to land right down the center
Hold back the plunger
Straight down the center
And the guy was Hershey concert at represent
And I was right which way to keep on playing. It was having fun
City council voted 6-0 to pass
The legislation
Sharpen said in the past that he got lucky with this Sean
But now he says that he was being modest
That his Plunge
Was not luck
To do what I did
That was skill
To have done it the way that I did it
Was
Pure naivete
Pinball was legal again
In most place
This is across the country
But not in Oakland and Alameda
Whereas we heard in the meeting the show pinball just became legal in 2014
Even with the rise of video games the pinball industry continue to experience waves of success until the 1990s
But over time people lost in
The last big Corporation to manufacture pinball machines lost millions of dollars on its pinball Division and decided to
The shutdown in favor of a more profitable operation
Making slot machines for casinos
After decades
Fighting to prove that pinball could be a game of skill
It turned out that the most lucrative bet for game Acres was on games of
Chance
Gambling
You know Bally's Casino
They used to be in the pinball business
Any took their name from their first hit pinball machine manufactured in 1932
Call Ballyhoo
Welcome to
Xxi
In 1999 pinball try to make a comeback with a game that integrated a video screen on the back glass
With a mechanical Playfield
Welcome to
Pinball
Mm
Welcome
The new image
In Denver
That was a promo video for pinball 2000
Despite the Reverb and the medicine taking clock
And the mountains of hyperbole heat on the promotion of the game
It never really caught on
Which is probably because if pinball still has any appeal
It's actually the Vintage
Analog Nostalgia feelings
We like it because it's not the few
The past
Back in the Pacific Pinball Museum Mike she's thinks pinball it making a bit of a comeback
It is because people are longing to get away from screens and from games that they play at home alone
So was Tim all you can kind of
Gather around and watch your friends suck
That's the other thing that's really cool is that anybody
Can suck at pinball
I mean it's a great equalizer you don't have to be smart
You don't have to be
Physically
DiNapoli
I think what you means is that anybody can suck
And anybody can be great
It's a nerd
A rebel
Underdogs
What are the best pinball players in the US right now
Is young guy with autism
Cooking memorize the geometric pattern
Thanks for the ball makes on the place
And then of course there's that deaf dumb and blind kid I heard about once
Never saw him play
I heard he was a really good
99% invisible was produced this week by Mickey Capper and Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman
Tami Roman Mars
Make it another piece about pinball and fruits in Chicago for a program I love called curious City
Not really
Like that's a show if this newsgathering experiment basa WBEZ where people submit questions
About Chicago and curiousity investigates and reports if it's genius website
We are project to 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce of the offices of our
Arcsine Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us her on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99
You must go
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I got a Thang
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com