99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
For the ancient Greeks
Sirens were mythical creatures who sang out to passing Sailors from rocks in the sea
The music was so beautiful it was said
It's Sailors were powerless against it
It would turn their ships towards the sea nymphs
And crashed into the reefs around
In Homer's Odyssey there's a story where Odysseus and his men are traveling near an area that Sirens are known to inhabit
Odysseus knows that if he hears the sirens song
This ship is going to sink
He still wants to hear what they sound like so he comes up with a plan
Odysseus has his men tie him to the mast
So that he can't take control of the ship
Then Odysseus has his men Fill Their Own ears with beeswax
So they can't hear anything
The plan works
Odysseus gets to hear the sirens call his men don't
And they sail on to safety
With Odysseus
Pleading with his crew to crash the boat
The whole way
And for over 2000 years or so
That's what a siren was
Preacher that made a beautiful sound
That all changed in 1890
French engineer named Charles Canada tour
Decided
Call the artificial noise maker he was working on
The siren
In this new mechanical siren became one of these signatures
Sounds of the modern world
Sirens warned people about eminent bombing raids during war
Elise
Thanks in part to the siren the world of the early 20th century had become a lot louder than any time in human history
And we can probably assume that these aren't that people heard and said he's all over the world
Sounded nothing like the siren songs of Greek myth
At least to most people
One man that composer named Arsenio oblomov
Heard music
The cacophony of the modern world
Any try to create a composition
Symphony
The clatter of the newly-formed Soviet Union
In this little bit of a departure from the typical 99percentinvisible program
Maccabees producer Charles Maines investigated the legend of afremov
And is forgotten Master P
And then we're going to fall out
Popular classic 99percentinvisible about Soviet design
The first
This is the Symphony of sirens Revisited
November 1923 a man named Arsenio Brahma full climb onto a rooftop in Central Moscow you will be killed
2 Flags
The day will be November 7th
And the Soviet Union USSR will be celebrating its sixth anniversary
Birthday of the one and only portrait Revolution this man
A promise is a communist he's also composer music and they're on this roof near the Kremlin he will link the two
With what might sound like a strange idea you conduct the symphony made up an entire city
You call the symphony the Symphony of sirens
Let's be clear this isn't his first time
But it will be as most important attempt so far
So to speak
So this is what I know about a rhombus this is all I know and I know what I know from a different man the man I'm going to see
Now
His name is Andre smirnov he is a man who studies these things a man who writes about these things
He is a man
You can answer with a clean now become our common questions
Or so I thought
Even said it was impossible to classify of Ramos
Family and it worked for the circus
He was a fountain of ideas
A ladies man
And if you couldn't depend on his personal life
Was even more so with this work
Can one testicle
Composer
He was like
She studied music
Nissan dealer
Xhaka clearly
Lotus Thai
Like most people interested
Rover little about
Because almost
None of it survived
So you could say there was two
Display
His experiment
Videos ideas about
Future of music
Music that was never written down
Japan
The music
Reply
Music
Planet
So what's that called what kind of music
The road or would have risen
Give the music
Survive
Well we just done now
So yes
Music composer
But he's a
Decomposer
Based on
The missing part was based on a flair for the dramatic really on Heap nicknamed himself would have ours
Opera the revolution of Arsenio gromov
Kid friends to poets Engineers musician
Cinematographers
In the first Decades of the twentieth century they dreamed of ideas about the future with the arrival of the revolution
Remove any other set up to turn them into reality new art for a new world with support Seminole told me
Elite
Emotional distress
Dewpider Ultra ski
He had very strong support from one high he had support from Trotsky
And as far as I know
Lenin supported him or at least he tolerated it all
Iterative is cultural Praises as part of creating this new future
Resort
Avant-garde
Would teach the past
Send workers
About the future of our oceans
Along the way of a developed far-reaching theories it would sketch out the concepts of electronic music biomechanics
For the use of sound and Cinema and then there was the Symphony of sirens
Aramis music of the future
The reason I come
Archival footage of parades in Red Square that they November 1923 showed clear skies
Cold fall day
What's the first time apparently the Kremlin
Helmsman airplane
Going to the tape I couldn't find any evidence of Rama
The irony
Smirnoff told me was that the pilot may have been the only one
Make sense of a Brahma
Liquor store
Performance
Because demonstrations were going on
The same time in Red Square
Airplanes were flying overhead
And most people probably
I didn't realize
Siren
For their own
Moscow zip code
But even for the people who are there
The song was so loud it blew them off their faith
Despicable Me 3 supposed to be in China, made in 2000 performance didn't understand those who were there
Couldn't hear a thing
And nobody had even the slightest understanding
What bus going on
ILearn
One other detail that day
Although new recordings of the 1923 performance existed
A young composer in St Petersburg have staged around the symphony just a few years back
I bought a ticket and caught the first train out of town
Proposal
Replay the recording of the sirens to an unsuspecting public
Kiss Mark told me that Aramis believe every city had its own Symphony
Saint Petersburg
Constructed his version according to ramazan notes from the 1923 score
Kanye West
What does Symphony of sirens to detail description
So we can read it and hear what it might have sound like now heads
Hotels out of the water of Everett
Flintstone MD
The sirens
When the cannons
What should go off to watch Zuckerberg
Full filled out and breaking down clearly
And it's obvious why a gram of diesel
Sold at the symphony could you play Not only by music
Additions
But by any person
New house
Kiss model splice together sounds beginning with a promise so-called megestrol
Set of steam whistles Sirens constructed to play the workers hymn
Any other revolutionary choirs and planes horns whistles
Machine guns
More horns soldiers get the idea
Collectively they formed a sort of industrial hemp sovita chisme
City United
Audience performer
Stage
And I promised telling the siren Call to work
Once sell oppressor
To become something
Celebrate in the workers state
It was the music of the future signal by the Cannons Roar
Sirens of Ramos Up on the Rooftop with a Flags telling the Cannons when to fire
3D ultrasound of absolute
It was loud his mode of conceited
And the sirens get the tourist
We continue to walk around pupil Fortress when unexpectedly we came across an exhibit for the American
Composer John Cage
Avant-garde artists could heard music in the sounds of the environment around him
My mind cage was around
Born a few years later
And with a different passport
The Coincidence was odd we enter
It doesn't move me she said
Innerview cages biggest defense was his most famous work
4 minutes and 33 seconds in which no notes are played for that duration
The song consists of whatever sounds around you at that moment
Lasted 4 minutes before she gave up better they pay me a hundred
Suggested there might be other American composers more pleasing to her taste
No thank you she said
Not at that meant more of the likes of John Cage
The cages ideas weren't new I mentioned the Russian avant-garde explode the same ideas in the 20s
Idea
Baku symphony of sirens
Something for every city
Who's this
Yes she said Petersburg sings
What city is the symphony
As if it was the most obvious thing she'd ever heard
Back in Moscow I found myself review in the archival tape
Red Square again
I still couldn't find a rama
But this time I was struck by something else
A simple idea really
You can never go back
Places on red square that they were full of excitement for new country
They were literally Boys on bicycles
But soon they would grow up
Go to war
I couldn't help but think that many wouldn't return
November 1923 was the last time he would attempt his Symphony in Skyrim
He didn't fall victim to the Soviet repressions and he didn't die fighting the Nazis
According to Andre smirnov avant-garde they were just forgotten
Country grew up
And the wild Ambitions of the 19
Twenties
Gateway to Soviet officialdom
Stagnation
And ultimately
Cynicism
What she order
Smoothies
Estonia
Truth adult
The problem isn't just
Majority of the public
It said they don't know the
Directions work
Convince long ago that
The Soviet Union
Producer
Set everything good was in the West
Hanover
Could do was make
Macbeth puppet Suburban
But it's not like that
And the history of
Bankers and Syracuse really proved it
Summer
But this song
She's having themselves looms large
That's how we were raised
Hopefully
Someday it will change
Quick
That night
Fireworks ring out over cities all across Russia
It was a holiday
I'd almost forgotten
Abramo stop music was the ultimate communal experience
And it was hard not to agree
Here we all were looking Skyward at the drums
But if I close my eyes and listen carefully I could hear a car lot
Steps on pavement
Laughter
But I mentioned other parts of the city chiming in
Crowds gathered in protests trains racing in the tunnels moskos never-ending traffic
Just the home in den of an average day in the city
Didn't have to like about music of the future to know it was happening
If I couldn't find the man well it was comforting to know the music and never left
That was the Symphony of sirens Revisited by producer Charles me
That story was part of the global story project presented by PRX with support
The open Society Foundation
And that piece there was a mention of Soviet design and it brought them on this early episode of 99% invisible that I'm sure many of you haven't
So we thought we just tack it on here for fun
The question you have to ask yourself is this
Are you ready to bow down before the glory
Acute hazard
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
My friend Julia Barton that's me
Editor of
Made in Russia
Samsung icon
What's the bed design in Florence apparent that sounds exactly like the building's door bus
No matter how hard we try cut out Lawrence
He denied
But maybe that's okay because I know if new book on Soviet design isn't the stuff of ordinary so
Soviet life cigarettes drinking glasses subway token machine
And it might be hard for Outsiders to see
What does seemingly random collection of Soviet consumer goods have in common
But I don't believe there's something that unites them all
Did you find this aesthetic you first need to realize that most of these items were
Rip offs of Western sources you know varying
Qualities
They are imitation
By the way Lawrence the parent is imitating the door buzzer
Onelook the items in this book even though they are Shameless invitation
You'll see that the Soviet stuff is
Unmistakably
Soviet
Take your Soviet soda machine in those
Carbonated drinks came not in bottles
But straight into a communal drinking glass
Something chained to the machine
In the excruciating Soviet arcade games were designed by the committee on amusement
Most Americans have any Mancini's artifacts but in a way we're responsible for them
Bass Crudo goes back to the kitchen debate
1959 the rooster Swaddlers successful American exhibit
In Moscow
Vice President Nixon showed Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev around the exhibit
We stopped in front of a model Suburban home to address an audience
Before New American color TV
There are some instances where you may be ahead of us in the
Development of your of the rest of your rockets for the investigation of outer space
There may be some instances for example color television
In order for both of us
My God I said that despite cruise ships wombat
Send the recent success of Sputnik
The Soviets were humiliated
Buy all of America's
Stuff
Chris have decided the Soviet people needed stuff to
But with a huge struggle for the Communist Party to switch Soviet factories from producing
Tanks
10 Rockets
Take a set.
Sex and hair dryers you know some party guy with the wood
Come back from a foreign trip and then
Bringing you know a German radio
And give it to the engineers make
And then they would just reverse-engineer at 2 and then they would look around for you know the guy who draws well
Can you draw the logo and that would be the logo that would last for the next
40 years
Assistant produce a lot of strange stuff but sometimes the Soviets did better than there is
Take the unbelievably cool magazine Krug azure
Kroger's or supposedly based on something cruise ships all while in the United States a magazine with a record in it
I don't call it the original podcast
Taxi South Lake public
There would be an article in the magazine and then
Of the
Contents of
Vinyl
This would somehow illustrate the art
Another would be
The sounds of the
The Foresters
Square or false
Songs of
Talk some far-flung tribe or is this
What started happening over time was
No sense the people who made this magazine
Had access to
But something
Unbelievably awesome for the Soviet Union which is you know vinyl of foot breast
They started slipping in a little pop music and there
It was the round tear out discs in Krogers or that gave Russians their first non bootleg recordings of everyone from Barbra Streisand
Send to Pink Floyd
Michael Jacks
The main thing that unites the designs and made in Russia is that they're often the only design
Micah light off didn't pick from shelf loads of sage
Different kiss
Sad recorder
Most Soviets had won the Vesna
The BK Electronica personal computer
Probably made Russian
Hackers
The best in the world
Through its sheer awfulness
Nobody had any other choice
Far be it from me to suggest that this is actually a good thing
But it certainly simplifies
Getting to know one another because
If you grew up in the Soviet Union and you know my age or older I already know so much about
Including the song I put
To the bed at night
Do you know if you grew up in the Soviet Union
It it's just seared into
I can I can sing it
I think it goes
Toaster
Gross gif
Used skis
This scene from a children's puppet show aired every night at 8:15 on Soviet television
You can't really call the crude animal puppets
Icons of Soviet design
But I don't put them in his book anyway
Spell.
Because of their bright eyes and worn out for crucial the Pig and stepashka the bunny represent a lost unit
11 time zones closed off from the rest of the world
Making their own stuff in their own way
The tired toys are sleeping now
That's how the song
Goodnight Roman
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
The Symphony of sirens Revisited was produced by Charles Mains and The Unsung icons of Soviet design
What's produced by Julia bar
We're project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound makes
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 990
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my
I got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and annuity
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio tupi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com