99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
We've all done it
You go to the store for a pair of socks and come out with a mega pack of soda
Go out to get shampoo and come back with a fancy razor
It's hard to stick to what's on your list
I challenge you to go to IKEA
And leave with only the thing for what you game
Just try to buy a lamp without buying a cutting board it can't be done
You absolutely knew this but retail spaces are designed to do this to you
Producer Avery trufelman
The store is trying to look so beautiful
So welcoming
The items so enticingly displayed in such vast quantity
That you cannot help
Be drawn in
And then drawn towards something you don't need
This is the Gruen effect
The Gruen effect
Or sometimes called the Gruen transfer
If that moment when you walk into a store and the design of the store is so overwhelming and
Dazzling
That you being mindlessly consuming
The Gruen effect is named after Victor Gruen
The who was growing
He's a complicated complex contradictory guy
Jeff Hardwick wrote the biography of Victor Gruen
Who is born Victor grunbaum born in Vienna
In 1904
And he is Jewish in Vienna leaves
1038 good call Groupon
And makes his way eventually
New York City
Once a New York grew and made a name for himself designing shops and Retail spaces
And this was a particular challenge during the lean years of the late 30s
People had no money
I just wouldn't go into shops at all
Accruent figured out how to lower people inside
Basically by using amazingly appealing window displays
Go into these window
Display area
Look at
Jewelry
Handbag
Chocolate
And then you die
Tempted
Lured into
The store I mean that's the Gruen effect
Gruen argued that good design equals good profit
And he
Equate though
Wonder Woman
You do more
People are going to stay there longer
And spend more money
Bruins started making storefront all over the country and he moved from New York to Los Angeles in 1940
Gruen was from the beautiful city of Vienna
Which is lined with shops and Greenery and places together
Most Americans were just riding around in their cars all the time
Cut off from the city in from each other
He knew this problem was
Even worse
In the suburbs
The sub herb black what sociologist Ray Oldenburg calls
Food places
I think of home as a primary place
Work as your second place
And that third place is where you go to build communities hang out
To Simply feel connected
Gruen wanted to give the American suburbs
Third place
Image of living conclusive communication with other people
Image of
Heading see possibility from work to one place to another
That's archival footage of Ruin from the University of Wyoming
See image of participating in events outside of your own little house
Become a desired effect
Victor Gruen imagine designing an environment
Full of greenery in shops
An indoor Plaza
A modern for him
Island of connection in the middle of the sprawl
One that would only be accessible to pedestrian
Because
Old man Victor Gruen hated cars
He Rants and Raves
Against cars
One technological event has one that is advent of sale rubber wheeled vehicle to private
Car photography playlist
As means of mass transportation
The human life intense is Justice great
Effect of exposure
It's hard understanding with the tape hiss in the accent but what Gruen is saying there is
The threat of cars that human life and health is as great as the
Supposed
Sewer
So gruhn's objective was to get people to park their cars far away from these third places
And walk
Troll with in them
Has grew inside
His structure would be an architectural Panacea
It would remedy Environmental
Commercial and sociological problems
With the creation
I'm a single building
And so Gruen presented his solution for America
The shopping mall
Good actually wanted the shopping mall to be more than just shops
You want some be mixed-use he want
Apartments
Send offices or medical centers attached to the shopping center he
Cases that have
Childcare facilities Library
Bomb shelters
A whole range of
Different
Function
Ingrown dreamed and wrote about the enclosed shopping center way before he ever built one
Until he finally land the commission for the very first
Indoor climate controlled Shopping Center
In Edina Minnesota a place not known for its welcoming climate
Southdale represents an entirely new and dramatic
Didn't retail merchandising
Southdale Center opened in 1956
And it was the mother of all shopping malls
Seriously
Gruen subsequent malls were all mostly based off this original Edina design
When he's doing
The first enclosed shopping mall
Southdale
In Edina Minnesota
Gruen really emphasized
And with the media ends up
Celebrating
Is this massive
Center Court
This court is in close in sky like a
Store
Photoshopping cyborg
In fact the whole area in front of the stores
Is air conditioned and temperature control a year-round climate of 72 degrees
4 Gruen
He's creating a
A Town Square
Southdale Center wasn't quite mixed-use
Migraine imagine
People didn't live in it
And something like a daycare center or Apple
Post office couldn't afford that rent
What Southdale did have local shops
Sival kind
And plenty
Southdale
Tomorrow's Main Street
Today
But from the outside
Southdale Center is not much to look at
I mean it looks like a mall
Ominous Amorphis boxy shape
In designing a shopping mall
Gruen ended his Razzle Dazzle storefronts and window displays
Southdale hardly has a
Exterior windows at all the moves away from the original concept that in some ways they're going to
Attract
By being Austin
The drawn now is what's inside the mall
Congruence mind it should have
Pretty much of a blank facade no signage on it
And then you enter that
Space and then you walk into the shopping center and that's that
Set of transformational Gruen transfer moment muldaur designed as the sort of suburban pilgrimage sites
Which of course
You have to drive to
It's a commitment
You're driving 20-30 minutes
You're parking your getting out of your car your walking in
Good new that Americans love to drive
To the mall with his compromise
You had to walk and stroll once you're inside
But the customers could drive over
So he just hates
The automobile but he never will acknowledge
That he's creating the shopping centres which are
Largely
Only accessible through car
Was Ryan
Americans loved
Driving to his Smalls he got commissions for them all over the country
But over time
Truancies that in erecting these malls
Is Tiny Suburban cities
Is helping to drain the real City
So for a while
Current shifts his Focus
Urban planning
B12
Qrcp
Which because we have neglected
It's a Gruen ends up being involved in urban renewal project
I swear
He draws directly on
The Lessons Learned in his
Suburban shopping malls and
Proposes bringing him back down
Municipality Tire Gruen and Associates to make their downtown's more like malls
Gruen turn City centers into
Pedestrian-only spaces
Full of public art
And Greenery and line
Wood shops
He made plans for Boulder
Fresno Fort Worth Kalamazoo
Actually
His plan for Kalamazoo became the first outdoor pedestrian shopping mall
Open the u.s. to turn Fifth Avenue into a pedestrian Mall
Close down 5th Avenue for a couple weeks as a test
What is City's downtown is not a mall
Not so easily quote-unquote fixed not so perfectly designed and controlled cities were
We're going to become the Pleasant
Sterile shopping environments That Grew and wanted them to be
After
The Riots of the 60s he is shocked into the taken aback by those and it was
It's very much
And I think that may have been somewhat of his reason for the retreat to Vienna
In 1968 Gruen from Los Angeles back to Vienna back to the greenery and Plaza
I've been trying to imitate
But he could not Escape his own creation
There's a shopping mall that's being built on the edge of Vienna
And he points to that
As how that shopping malls destroyed
Downtown Vienna
Congruent mind Vienna was already perfectly planned
It didn't need a mall like the broken American suburbs did
As he saw it
His original Vision had been completely skewed after being in Vienna about 10 years
He gives
The speech in
Paper where he says
I refuse to pay alimony
Is bastard
Victor Gruen the mall maker
Became the foremost Mall critic
Meanwhile America's love affair with Mall's continued
Do you want to catch them all pretty girl like you doing sitting alone in the middle of this Monument to consumerism
I know I remember in my own experience
Growing up in New Jersey when the first Mall opened anywhere near me when I was in high school this is Ellen Dunham
Jim Jones she's a professor of architecture and Urban Design at Georgia Tech it was cool to go to the mall
But I mean literally it was air condition
My home wasn't air-conditioned my school wasn't there conditions
Today most of us are
Spending our days and our nights in completely thermally controlled environments
A lot of us are craving
Being able to
Be outdoors
In recent decades our tastes have beard away from climate controlled environments and away from the indoor mall
Small construction actually peaked in 1990 it's been declining ever since
And
By 2006 those really the last
Brand new
A standard conventional Mall
That's been dealt in the US
And a new product has entered the scene
I kind of shopping center that the icsc the international Council of shopping centers
Called a lifestyle
Lifestyle centers started appearing
In the 90s
And they
Tend to be open air
So when you don't have that roof anymore
But you have a lot of boutiques and a lot more restaurants
Lifestyle centers are malls disguised as main streets
And even though they're full of chain stores
Lifestyle centers are sunny and walkable and bustling
And kind of what Victor Gruen imagine
And some of the old style indoor shopping malls
Are being repaired
Several of them are being
Retrofitted
Into the Hispanic community centers
Like in Plaza Fiesta
Outside of Atlanta
A lot of the stores have been cut up into much smaller mom-and-pop
Small shops selling Western Wear selling quinceanera dresses Plaza Fiesta also has a steady
The events calendar
Performances
In this two was kind of what growing imagined
We sort of community malls are truly places together and spend money
In the Shell of the failed design
Most people architectural historian
Especially
Hickory when was a horrible Act
And you know
I I can see where they're coming
Because exteriors of his building
Are uniformly boring
It's a grueling that wasn't the point it was the interior
We're really the point
Does fountains the cheesy statues
Elevator music piped in through all those speakers
Those are all part of the Gruen effect
And they helped turn shopping malls into spaces where we felt comfortable staying and spending time and money
A lot of the original indoor malls are abandoned now
Growing weeds inside
If your website this becomes a graveyard of dead malls called deadmalls.com
Users can log on to submit stories of the Dead malls in their towns
There are around 450 malls listed are submitted as sort of oral history
In particular what
Interesting I think about deadmalls.com is
How to spell check
A lot of fishes and it does make sense
So many Suburban communities became the de facto Town Center it was really the center
Sure of social life other than the school
I would be very sad if all the
Victor Gruen Smalls were demolished we should certainly
Work to preserve
At least one
The most famous Mall in Minnesota maybe the Mall of America with its roller coaster at zipline at the
Aquarion water park
The most architecturally significant law its grandfather
Is it one that's just a 12 minute drive away
In Edina
Jeff Hardwick book is called Mall maker Victor Gruen architect of an American Dream
An Ellen dunham-jones book is called retrofitting Suburbia
Social things to Claire dority
99percentinvisible
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced of the offices of arcsin in architecture
Interiors firm in beautiful downtown mall free but Lifestyle Center rich
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing.
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show and Lancaster on Facebook you can follow my international travels on Twitter at Roman Mars
We're on Tumblr Spotify and Instagram two
3 / 160 episodes of 99% invisible are waiting for you
At 99 Pi. Org
Radio Javan
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
Personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com