99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1941 the journalist and screenwriter Leo rosten Road
Is Hollywood as an Istanbul or Sioux Falls
The rich hasten to express their wealth in betray their fitful groping for status
By erecting homes of unnecessary magnitude and splendor
The man who built
Many of Hollywood's homes of
Unnecessary magnitude
Splendor
Was Wallace Neff
Neff was a starchitect
I know many people find the term starchitect a pretty contemptible portmanteau but never really was both famous in his
His own right and an architect to the Stars one of his most famous projects
The renovation
The state owned by the iconic silent film actress Mary Pickford and her husband Douglas Fairbanks
When a couple moved into Pickfair
The house sat on a nameless Street
Empty neighborhood called Beverly Hills
If you were lucky enough to be invited to dinner at Pickfair
You might find yourself seated next to Babe Ruth
King of
Spain or Albert Einstein
Life magazine called Pickfair
Only slightly less important than the White House
Much more fun
Best Los angeles-based reporter David Weinberg for Charlie Chaplin Judy Garland and Groucho
Mark's designs houses for all three Marx Brothers Madonna is owned enough house
Diane Keaton
A blonde from
Reese Witherspoon
She actually honestly and we could have fact check this the living Ranch in Ojai
Jeffrey head is an architectural historian
And the author of a book on that
I checked and Reese Witherspoon does infect on the Libby Ranch
At the end of his life Wallace Neff could have lived in a grand estate on the coast tour
Huge mansion in the Hollywood Hills
But instead
He lived in a 1000 square foot
Concrete bubble
Enough believe that this simple Dome
Was one of his greatest architectural
The story of the bubble house begins when morning
When Death was standing his bathroom
Shaving
Is 1934 so it was probably a straight razor
Netflix down and noticed a small soap bubble
4 minutes
You reached out and touched
The bubble held firm against
Fingertip
That was the moment the idea
Struck him
You could build with
Are
He can build
Bubble houses
And never wanted to build them by the thousand
Near the end of the second World War
Architects were anticipating the postwar housing shortage
And working on very Solutions
Neff had a larger View
In wanted to create a solution to me
Demand for housing worldwide
Jeffrey Haynes book about Neff is title No Nails no Lumber
Because the bubble houses
Did your nails
Lumber
Headsets that never saw the bubble houses as a way to make money
He saw them as a social responsibility
A way to provide low-cost housing fee
He really didn't make money
Trauma in fact Spence
A great deal of money
Money from his other architectural practice
I input it into the bubble houses
Plusnet was already rich
Remember he was building mansions for the Hollywood Elite
And his grandfather was Andrew McNally
The Cartographer who created Rand McNally publisher
And this idea of a dome-shaped dwelling was not entirely new indigenous cultures in the Americas had certainly Explorer
For that territory even during this lifetime another guy Buckminster Fuller was creating his own circular solution to the housing show
A geodesic dome
Yeah and I think it was a misunderstanding people
Look at the bottle house Anythink oh
This is a variation on Bucky Fuller
And it's it's really not
It's more of a
Variation on a
Forum
Caring nature
That someone has
Adopted
4 human scale human years
What was original about Nest design was the way the bubble houses
4 built
Meth invented a new method of construction
He called it are form
Here's how it works
First a big slab of concrete was poured in the shape of a giant coin
Now picture of giant balloon
Shape of half a grapefruit
Flat side down
This balloon was tied down to the foundation using steel hooks
So once the
Balloon was tied down
It was inflated with
Through an inlet valve and it took all of five minutes to inflate it
After the balloon was inflated it was coated in a fine powder
And this this would happen before the gunite process
Yes
Gunite let's take a minute to talk about the magical substance that is
Gunite
Or maybe you prefer the generic term
Shotcrete
Yeah so the gun I was shot out of a cement gun and the gun had two hoses
That came together at a nozzle and the other was dry cement mix
And water in the mix
Came together under high pressure
To form the gunite when it was more than twice as strong as regular concrete
Neff Lovelace
What's the bloom was coded in gunite
A layer of wire mesh
Play Store for that
Then a second layer of gunite with spray tan and Bam
That's it
Two men with a balloon and a gunite machine
Could turn a bare patch of soil into a bubble house in less than 48 hours
And after the gunite dried
The balloon was deflated
Pulled out through the front door
Soda be used again on the next top
More earthquake-proof
And even more bomb-proof
Been any traditional structure
Net was so confident in his design
He would often invite people to bash the walls of the bubble with a backside of an axe
Movies at the back side up for some reason
Using the backside of Acts
What meth like best about the bubble houses though
Was that they were incredibly cheap
After Neff fine-tune the air form process
He went in search of a client
Someone with money who would hire him to build more bubble houses
I found one
Federal government
The first Waffle Houses were
Done
During the war
Create
Quick housing
Government worker
World War II and escalated
Any us needed homes for military work
Turneffe convince the government
To build an experimental bubble house community
In a forest
Falls Church VA
Virginia
In October of 1941 fbn construction on the 12 bubble houses in Falls Church
That would eventually be nicknamed
Igloo Village has no lighting of a
Funny condom the street
And we arrived in the daytime
But
It was still quite dark
Because they were so many trees
Kathy Miles grew up in one of the Falls Church bubble houses
When she was five years old her dad who work for the military
Drove the family into the forest
Show them a new house
He hadn't told his wife and two daughters
That they would be living in a village of bubbles
The woods
It was dark and damp
And isolate
And I can remember coming up the street and there was
A a cleared area with still many trees and very little
Grass
Tiffany
And there were Flagstone
Sounds and there was this
House
It didn't look like a house to me at that time
But there was something
Rising up from the ground
And it was white
Enlarge
Had two large lumps
And they were held together
In the middle
With a smokestack
And of course I was with my parents and I don't remember what they were telling me but I'm sure it was something
That we were going to live in this
New kind of house
Do you remember what your mother's reaction wasn't
Croissant
Her over reaction was to stay calm and carry on
I think she was trying to make the best of it
And hoping that we wouldn't live there long
Soda come to something that look like this
I think she was truly horrified The Falls Church community consisted of two single bubble houses
And 10 double bubble how
Kathy lived in one of the Double Bubble
The double bubbles were made by connecting two smaller bubbles with a rectangular cinder block structure
That house the kitchen in the bathroom
Kathy says that growing up an Igloo Village
But incredibly isolating
Animator standout
One time
When she was in first grade I set out to draw a picture of my house
And of course we colored it and I couldn't color it because
I kept insisting there were no white crayons
And
So when the teacher looked at it she kept saying it's trying to explain to me that I was supposed to draw the house
I lived it
And I kept saying I do live in this house
So
Finally I felt that I wasn't doing what I was supposed to and she clearly
Had no idea what I was
And of course when we passed all the
Houses
Around to our friends to look at
Pictures
The other children
Laugh
And
Mets
So it was
Pretty daunting as a and is in introduction to first grade
For me
And sometimes Cathy would be made to feel like an outsider in her own neighborhood
People were constantly driving into Igloo Village
Tagalog
The weird families
Live deep in the woods
Inside strange Hobbit
One of the things that
All of us children
In the early days were uncomfortable with I think was that when we were outside playing
In the yards
People would drive up the street
And they again it was a dark
Street with the cousin
To the trees
And they would drive up very slowly
And as even in the summer as they would come up the street
They would roll
The windows of the car up
And they would all be pressed against the glass
And you would see them pointing
It was very much a
Zoo like feeling
And I can even remember when I went to the zoo one time as a child
I remember thinking about how I felt when people were watching me
And I thought about how the animals were feeling
With us watching them
So it had that much of an effect that I was able to make that trance
Esperance
Life in the bubble house
Was especially hard on Kathy's mom
Because there were no straight walls
Couldn't hang pictures
Your family photos
And the circular rooms were difficult to furnish
But living in a bubble wasn't all bad
Fracassi
He discovered
But you could easily climb up the side of the bubble
The roof I was always a climber in those days you called it the Tomboy from the hole
These houses were really weird
Really I believe in this area and this
Time this place
It was kind of Doom 2
The failure
Even though Igloo Village in Falls Church Virginia did not flourish
Neff was still able to land a few more clients
In 1942
The Southwest cotton company
Hired him to build desert colony of bubbles in Litchfield Park Arizona the Southwest cotton company provided the cotton it
Goodyear used
How to make meth
Giant half grapefruit balloons
Neff also got a contract to build a bubble house dormitory
Loyola University in Los Angeles
And in 1944
Pacific Linen Supply Company
Tiredness
Design the largest are form ever built
Was 100 feet in diameter
32 ft High
Messed up
Pacific linen bubble with its Grandeur and prime location downtown
What finally convinced the world
The airphone construct
Derived
Not just because bubbles or practical
But because they were beautiful
But still people just did not want to live in bubbles
Eventually everyone in America moved out of their bubbles
And they were all them all
All of them
Except for one
Which happens to be in Pasadena
10 miles from my apartment
It was dark when I arrive at the bubble house
It's in a neighborhood of unremarkable suburban houses from the 19
30s
When I got to the front yard
Side of it stop meme
My tracks
Smooth Dark Mount against the night sky
Newsela spooky
Breathtaking
Standing there looking at it
I immediately thought of a passage I dread and Jeffrey heads book
The passage
What about this very house
One turns on to a small residential street
Is confronted with a house that looks nothing like a
The fact that it has a front door and a few visible windows
Only adds to its incongruous
Presence
Looking at the house which resembles a smooth mound of
Hurst
Feels as if some ancient space station has suddenly falling from the sky
And upon Landing
It has mysteriously embedded itself
Into the wrong context
It's present so strange
Seems to have traveled through both space and time
That passage was written by the artist Steve Roden
Steve knows a lot about the Pasadena bubble house
The last 15 years
He's lived in it
The only reason why I drove out here to look
At the house with my wife
Just because
Price was Sochi
And that the image was so strange
And so when we turn the corner and
Saw this
Strange Brown Dome
In the middle oven
Unbelievably
Conservative neighborhood
It was sort of
Looks like
What the hell is this
Steve was fascinated by its history and all the surprises that come with living in a bubble
Like the way the light moves
The curved surface
That's really cool in the living room at night
Is when cars drive by the lights coming through
Through the window
Projects on the Dome form
It's like crazy cycle azarian or something Keynote
It's really amazing
None of the walls that separate a room in the house go all the way to the ceiling
Rick steves wife
Is in the bedroom reading
Fingers cast Shadows on a ceiling
He can see from the living room
But perhaps
The very most badass thing about living in a bubble
Is the way sound travels through
It becomes a whispering eye
When Kathy Miles and her sister were growing up an Igloo Village
They also discovered this
Parabolic imperfections
In the wall
And they use them
SM secret messages to
I think early on my sister and I learned that if you stood in certain places you could hear people whispering
And if you stood in other places you couldn't
And I remember conducting experiments to see where we
Best here and best not here
Just depending on whether we wanted our parents to hear us
Or we didn't want to be her
Steve loves his bubble house
It doesn't have the same problems that plagued The Falls Church houses
Guess custom furniture design for a circular room
And he's an artist
He likes standing
Given how much Steve loves his bubble when can argue that perhaps the bubble houses might have endured a different fate
If there are piloted here in California rather than Northern Virginia
But there are plenty of people who aren't sad
The bubble house have died out
Like this guy
I think was a bad idea
Is an architect who's quite happy
Living in a world without bubble house
It was a good idea when it came to me some industrial uses it was a very poor idea when it came to
Housing and how it may very uncomfortable swelling
Heather ly dare
Assembly into neighborhoods and so on
It did not very informed by Regional by Culture by climate or any other way for Stephen us architecture works
When it takes into account the context of its environment
And respond accordingly
Bubble houses
Their uniform
You can spray gun I undo grapefruit balloon in Virginia or California or anywhere else and it's going to look and function
Exactly the same
One of the shortcomings of this house
He said it's really
Mostly Focus
On the method of his contract
Stefanos took me on a tour of his office
A Spanish Colonial building
He says
An example of great Arkansas
Show me a balcony on the 2nd
Flor Martinez partner sometimes do work it's a favorite place of hours in that
We are also urbanists and we dedicate entire life fighting sprawling
Trying to reorganize the world properly and
We have nothing in front of us here with a better magnificent view of sprawl
This is our frame into the world you know
It's like a panoramic view of what the rest of our lives going to be about going to fix all this mess
Imagine if the view from this balcony with a c of bubble houses
Nothing but thousands of identical industrialized own
Stretching into Infinity
It would be a dystopian nightmare
And even though he lives in a world of sprawl
He has his office to take refuge in
This building is my walls
This a perfect building for the hot dry climate because
When it's 80° outside of 90 or 100
You keep the building tight clothes then it's at
Six-Guns after you open up doors and windows
Any events down in no time
Explain how the arrangement of the windows
Provide balanced natural light
Throughout the entire day
Design
Was based on the combination of Mediterranean and Spanish style
Because Southern California has a Mediterranean climate with
Spanish route
These are the things the bubble house
Can't do
Be culturally relevant and adapt to the environment around it
This office was designed by an architect who spent his entire life designing buildings that did adapt to their environment and work
Culturally relevant to my surroundings
This building was designed
My wallet
Snuff
Classic Wallace Neff
Porch this chair is actually reconstructions of Methodist and F design
It was his office before it belonged to Stefano
Is Stefano why he thinks meth did this complete 180 when he created the bubble house
Why he made something that was so antithetical to the rest of his work
Stefanos thinks it had something to do with the birth of modernism
UCF was known for Spanish Colonial houses
White thick walls with red tile roofs in a labret wrought-iron window coverings
The really popular in California
They're everywhere
But there was this new movement happening all around Neff
Architects like Noah trailer
Schindler and Frank Lloyd Wright
We're making simple boxes
Concrete
Cleanline
Lots of glass
They look nothing like next elaborate mansion
People were beginning to look at younger Architects Maybe
With what we know
Wilder ideas and more relevance maybe the daily life and so on
You think it was sort of like a like a midlife crisis kind of thing
ProSource I mean I I think grade argue they continue to sync their entire life and
There comes a moment in which you look
Look at the movement taking the world over it's like a wildfire
So you have to ask yourself
Am I the wood doesn't burn or shall I become part of the Wind
But the modernists were not impressed with Nest bubble house
Steve rodent the guy who lives in the Pasadena bubble house
Tell me almost the same thing
Young architects who are trying to like
Bring modernism forward
No they thought he was
Dilettante
You know and I think he was an outsider probably because he was hobnobbing with movie star
I mean imagine if like
Barry Manilow started a metal bands not like anyone would take that seriously
Right no matter how great it was
Ironically great but you know like what if it was great
We none of us would buy into it
And I think that was part of his situation you know he wasn't
Like a hipster
Cute he wasn't an unknown crazy dude
He was a guy with a very
Strong practice who
Made giant houses for rich people
And yet that's never stopped believing in the bubble house
He continued to make variations on it
Designing bubbles with straighter sides and flatter roofs
Ones with big holes cut out of the side
Even at the end of his life long after it was clear
The bubble house had no future
He saw it as when I was
Greatest architectural
He believed in it so strongly
Did he spent the end of his life living in a bubble house
In fact
He lived in the same house Steve Roden now live
I don't want to play the bubble house off as just some failed idea
Navigate to be a symbol of a design inspired by the highest ideal
Beauty
Efficiency
Affordable housing
Willingness to take risks on crazy ideas
Experiment
With making the world a better place
Maybe the structure itself
The concrete show that house the idea was fly
Maybe people don't want to live in bubbles
But their legacy deserves reflection
And so does meth
The guy invented a way to build houses out of air
That's being awesome
And hardly anyone knows about him
All the remains of his idea
Is this one last bubble house
Jobs in Pasadena
Actually that's not entirely
True
It's the last bubble house in the United
States that were bubbles in Pakistan Egypt Liberia India Jordan Turkey
Nicaragua Venezuela Cuba there was an air form gas station in Brazil but the largest colony
1200 bubbles
One community
Was built in Dakar Senegal some of them are still standing
All their dumb Glory
Bangladesh producer Juliana friend found the Dakar bubbles
Juliana said that there's actually a sense of Pride colors
In comparison to other buildings in the area
The bowls are pretty old they were built before Senegalese Independence
Yeah they're hot and uncomfortable
But it's part of our heritage
So I'll never know
So it turns out
That it's just Americans
Don't want to live
Bubbles
Or at least Americans are the ones who can afford to have the choice
Because bubble houses were
Cheap and required so little material
They were way more practical in the developing world
So
Innocence
Neff actually got what he want
99% invisible with produces sweet by David Weinberg Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
An earlier version of this story was produced as part of KCRW independent producer project
This episode is part of these stem story brought
Made possible with funds from the Alfred P Sloan Foundation
We are product of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects in
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
Sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife
Wife is another remedy for all hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flat pocket
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
David has his gray podcast called random tape you should absolutely check it out
Right now if you want to see amazing pictures of bubble houses and bubble house is being made you have to go to 99
9% invisible. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com