99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1968 the police department in Menlo Park California hired a new police chief
His name was Victor so thank
And she still think is his main goal was to reform the police departments in it
Which wasn't great at the time
That's our own Delaney Hall this was the 1960s
And even in Menlo Park
A small City with manicured Lawns and wide Suburban streets
It has been a turbulent decade
There were big student-led anti-war demonstrations at Stanford University which is right here by Joan Baez
Folk singer created a communist called struggle mountain in the Foothills above the city
And leaders in the African-American Community organizing protests to demand better treatment and services
The Menlo Park police had clashed with these Pro
Sometimes violently
And after years and years of this
The department had a pretty rough reputation
Had a reputation for being a very tough Police Department very aggressive Police Department
And somewhat of a very
Anti race
Kind of a police
That's Dominick peluso he was hired in 1970
Buy Chiefs is Anchor
The guy who wanted to change this
He just he's one of these type of guys that would come into a room and we just fill in the room
You know and everybody kinda
This back in
I think we better listen and go along
Chiefs has anchors had hired Dominic right out of the Jesuit Seminary
Where Dominic had been studying to be a priest
Does angus like hiring officers
Words from non-traditional law enforcement background
Saint with higher level
Education
It was just one of the strategies for reforming the
He also let his officers grow their hair out
And have beards and mustaches
He changed all the pseudo military titles to more corporate
Sergeant's became manager
For example
And lieutenants became Direct
Officers in the department had mixed feelings about all these changes
Is but one with more controversial
Then the others
Berlin time officers in Menlo Park had worn a variation of the tradition
Dark blue police uniform
But she still thinks about that style was
Too intimidating
An aggressive
To the Chief came up with something totally different was really a nice kind of a dark green blazer with
What's the black thread in it
We wore pastel colored solid shirts with a tie and slacks instead of
Silver metal badge the Blazer exported in embroidered patch
That sort of look like a coat of arms
Guns and handcuffs remained hidden under the jacket
All in all the officers
What kind of like grown-up Rhett school students but with guns they even had pocket protectors with the Menlo
Oak Park police logo on it
I would slide into the pocket of their dress shirts
It seems like the the total effect is he was trying to
Demilitarized
The looking at it
The department
Yeah I think that would be a correct
A statement
A lot of the guys who join Police Department
Funny military and because of the nature of the work
It can be very militaristic
Dick shall we say an organization
And training and all those guys
He was trying to
Calm it down
But you think this was also messing with a tradition that would prove extremely hard to change
Because the blue military-style uniform had a history that went back more than a hundred years
What we've asked police officers to wear over the years says a lot about what we've expected.
And how we feel about them
Even says a lot about how they feel about themselves
Back in America's colonial days law enforcement
Really differ
Print then it does now
In New England there were these informal group
Generally known as The Watch
The patrol neighborhoods looking for crime
No uniforms no sort of
Organizational policies that they had a follow is basically every able man
Chad pozek teaches in the Department of Criminal Justice and criminology at Georgia Southern University
If they saw somebody that needed help a fire
Crime on the corner it would just be an informal group to exert a respond to that
So that was in the North
In southern community
Leading up to the Civil War
There were roving Patrol
That were responsible for
Suppressing slave revolts and tracking down runaway slaves
They worked for large Plantation owner
So very much in the South Early policing was tied to us
Slavery were in the north it was more police and crime
Chinese large urban area
These unofficial patrols were how early law enforcement work for decades
It wasn't until the 1820s that modern policing began to take shape
Thanks to a British Statesman named Sir Robert peel
Before people came along and London looked a lot like it did in colonial America
Informal and Loosely organized
And Peele recognize that there were problems with the
This model people not taking it seriously being drunk on the job not showing up falling asleep and so he what he wanted
To do is
Korea police department
FaceTime answered
Principles
In after years of pushing for a form peel succeeded
In 1829 he helped found the London Metropolitan Police
The first modern full-time city-wide Police Department
British officers are still known as Bobby
In honor of Robert Bobby.
In Ireland they call them peelers
With a little less
Fuel required his officers to wear uniforms that would distinguish them
Citizens they were meant to serve but peel was also sense
Stuff to help British people might perceive this new please
Yes that was a huge concern
Because for so many years the people were ruled by
The military in it in military
Tri-State peel wanted the new police uniforms to
To stand apart
From the red cow
Did the British military
Now sort of we forget our first blue uniform that is it was
Very professional-looking
When was actually stood in stark contrast to the red
That you saw
With the military
Gradually peels ideas and his blue uniform
Made their way to the United
It states
By the early nineteen hundreds police departments across the country
Adopted aspects of the style and approach
Pioneered by the London method
Alton Police
This included a quasi-military structure
And the goal of crime prevention
But there were still some problem
Most early police departments in the US Allied themselves
The rich and the powerful
Local politicians in business
And you might be thinking
Still like that now
And you might be right
But it was worse than
Like a new mayor would get elected and then would appoint a hand-picked police chief
Chief with higher
Their family their friends
Come the officers
I'll dad Department
So very political in and obviously
True the police chief you sort of work for the mayor local politician
You're going to serve there
Purposes first
And the community Maybe
Secondarily
It was a patronage
And in most departments recruits didn't receive any special training
They were just handed a badge
Animated stick
And sent out on patrol
Despite the spiffy new uniforms and their newly organized approach
Public trust in the police
Was
Dismal
So a reform movement begins to grow a
Across America
And then in 1929 President Herbert Hoover convenes a group
Called the Wickersham Commission
They conducted the first national study of the American
Criminal justice
They look at the system from Top
Tabata
And they basically saw the infiltration of politics into
Huge profit
And they said that
We need to change
How We Do
The Wickersham report shocked the country by exposing widespread police abuse
It described police routinely beating suspects in holding them illegally for like they questioning
And you might be psychic
It's still like that now
And you might be right
But it was worse than
The report included some pretty disturbing a
Like a suspect who was held by the ankles from a third-story window
And another who was forced to stand in the morgue with his hands on the body of a murderer
This report the Wickersham report really was sort of
Is turning point and we need to do something different in
I think that's what led into this
Professional air
This new professional era which continued up into the 1960s and 70s
Was characterized by the emphasis on policing as a skilled profession
This old educational film
Called your police
Ways to Die
Police departments use modern science to protect you
Photography
Two way radio
Expert firearms training as standardized by the FBI National Academy
Accident prevention installation
Now police were trained to use modern tools and technology and one of the leading voices for this new me
Message was a guy named August Vollmer the first police chief of Berkeley California
And he helped her write the Wickersham report
Boomer got his officers to use motorcycle
Golden patrol cars
Instead of just
Walking around
That way they could cover bigger areas more efficiently
He was also one of the first Chiefs in the u.s. to insist his Department use
One blood
Fibrin
To help solve
Crimes
And under his influence California became a hotbed of police reform from the 1920s the 1960
Weeding of course
The stuff like cheeks as I kiss his Blazer uniform experiment in Menlo Park
Birth years it seems like Chiefs to think of his reforms might be working
In Blazers and ties and
Pocket protectors the Menlo Park police definitely looked less intimidate
Here's Dominick peluso again
Eventually became assistant chief under says thank
It wasn't like we slacked off
And became you don't like oh mercy and
Forgiveness
I love and peace and all that kind of stuff you know know but the way we did it and
The style that we
We gave two people ice
Made them feel a lot better about us
And he built up a lot of reading
Repore with
There was even an early studies suggesting that altercations between citizens and the police had to climb because of a Blazers
The study was later challenged but when it first came out
Where begin
Spread a few other departments across the country
Adopted the Blazer Style
But the uniform experiment also drew a line within the
On one side there were the guys like Dominic
Lights with the Blazer stood for
They embraced the to think is one of the department to have
A comme Amour
Professional image
There's a lot of guys who want to do this job
But don't want to go out there and knock heads or
People are you know whatever like that
Are they just want to
Do the best for the community
And I think with our uniform people
For applying
Got more the sense that we really work community
Minded
Helping
On the other side with the old school police officer
Who Miss
Stitches no uniform and all that it represented
The enjoy
The eagle stuff that goes with it
They also enjoy that sense of authority on that you show
The clearness of who they are with the Blazer it just wasn't always that clear
Do you like stop a personal safer violation
And I'd walk up and say can I see your license
They look against the wall
What's your life
How are you
Vineyard Point Village
Apache salon
This is retired Sergeant band Trask
He worked under Sancus internally he like the chief style and approach
But he admits that it caused some complications
You you didn't have that much
Recognition as a cop so you
Kind of
There's a tendency to get more
Who are you you know
Yunnan the place
Many officers got so frustrated that they quit
The numbers we've heard on this very
Ben said about half the department lab
Dominic thinks it was even higher
I would guess
That in his first
4 years
Police chief
We had about a 7
25%
People just
Left and went other departments couldn't take his his overall thinking
Out of the box thinking
Abandoned
And eventually says ink is low
Take over as the chief of a police department in Stamford
Connecticut
You know there's some talk that. He was actually kind of encouraged to leave
And not long after you left
Department switch back to the traditional uniform Style
Does angus passed away in 1980
The year that has anchors join the Menlo Park
Park Police
19 6
68 represented an important Turning Point
For law enforcement in the US
The community policing approach
Champion device
Would continue to gain traction through the 80s and 90s
Departments across the country tried to build
Better less combative relationship
What's with their local community
But there had always been a tension between the more community-oriented side of policing
And the more military song
And that was about to intensify
In recent years crime in this country has grown nine times as fast as population
At the current rate the crimes of violence in America will double by 1972
We cannot accept that kind of future for Honor
In 1968
Richard Nixon ran for president on a promise of Law & Order
Captain to all the paranoia and unease that had grown during the turmoil of the 19th
The campaign ads were full of the scary images
Urban unrest
Myoden
Amended with his slogan
Written across the
The screen
Vote like your whole world depended on
I pledge to you
The wave of crime is not going to be the wave of the future in America
Shortly after taking office Nixon vowed to fight the war on crime
Which had been started by his predecessor Lyndon Johnson
He also declared a War on Drugs
Again criminal justice Professor Chad pozek
One I think the language is very important
Right
You don't have
Drug prevention
Or crime prevention
It's the war
War on Drugs
The war on crime so you do see an escalation during the
This time I'm how
Crimes responded to in
Just responded to
Like they're responding to war
Warrior course requires specialized
And around the same time
The government established
Law enforcement
Assistance Administration
A now-defunct federal agency that gave lots of money to local
Police Department
So they could buy a newfangled
Crime-fighting
UCS up ticket and it's
Support for
All sorts of policing but especially riot gear in SWAT team
Armoured vehicles and weapons
Bulletproof ass in those types
Something even small ruled Apartments were getting their hands on stuff
Like helicopters
Serious crowd control gear
Mike Shields and helmet
A new paramilitary divisions of the police
Like SWAT team
Begin using this
Some exchange the traditional blue uniform for camouflage outfit
Known as
The battle dress
Baby come to look normal
As it's kind of equipment and style spread
So did more militarized policing tok
Conducting raids
Crackdown
And
Partially enforcing laws and their behind the mask
But they wear in riot gear
How are the big huge vest that they wear in the SWAT team
This trend continued to the 80's and 90's and lots of police
Departments across the country
Accelerated in many places after 9/11 as police department's became closer with federal law enforcement
Agencies and started thinking of themselves
Part of the first line of defense
Get a new war
The war on terror
New federal programs emerge that sends Surplus military equipment from Iraq and Afghanistan
Two local police departments across the country
Which brings us to today
Across the country there been highly publicized protests
Against police shootings of unarmed
Black men
And these protests have spark bigger conversation
About police violence
And also how are police
For several nights this week this was Ferguson Missouri
Hey
Combat gear assault rifles
It look like a military operation
The current mistrust of police seems to me or what was going on in Menlo Park
Back in 1968
Pre Blazer
But on a more dramatic
Scale
Back in the 1960s it was big conversations about the role of police and the community
That led Chiefs to think is to make changes to the memo
Park uniform
Today at least so far no departments have taken steps
That drastic
But in Minneapolis
For taking a small step
In that general direction
Minneapolis
Appear less than
Imitating
February 26th
The Minneapolis Police Department
Change the color of their SWAT unit
From a military green to a more traditional navy blue
This happened about four months after the city saw widespread
Protest
After the police shot and killed an unarmed black man
Name Jamar Clark
The Minneapolis Police Department declined to talk with us about the uniform chain
But they made it clear in other interviews that this color change
Is about public perception
And rebranding
We are police we are not military we don't train with the military
We're not associated with military
Weather Minneapolis Police Department and
We want to be reflective of our own community on our own
Image
What's not totally clear is if the color of the uniform
Actually matters
And
Rubber bullets
And me
Brain teasers
And everything else
This is Candice Montgomery
She's an activist with black lives matter and she's taking part in protests in Minneapolis
A color is not going to change that Dynamic and entire overhaul of the policing
System
Is going to change that Dynamic and people's responses
Of course the problems we are facing today can't be solved by uniform change alone but a change in uniform
Can be an important symbol away from police departments to signal to their communities
But they want to have a better relationship
In the case of cheese does Angus in Menlo Park do uniform experiment did help lead to bigger
Changes
Requiring officers to wear Blazers a certain kind of officer was drawn to the police.
The kind who was willing to get on board
The more significant reforms that says Angus wanted to make
And even though the department eventually abandoned the Blazers
Many of the other changes.
Here's former Menlo Park
Assistant chief
Dominick peluso
Dick was definitely ahead of his time
And you know
With most people who are ahead of their time
You don't have a crowd of people that all kind of stand up and cheer for you
But it would be very interesting because
Within it 10 or 15 years
Almost every police
Department in our area
Even though they didn't change the uniform or the titles of the organizational chart we're taking on that real big
Community
Bellissima
It went ahead and did it take us that was a sign of the times
99% invisible West produced this week by Delaney Hall with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Sharif Youssef
Avery truffelman and Miramar
Special things this week to Darryl Lindsay of the Menlo Park Police Department Richard Johnson Robert Morrow David Cooper and Tom.
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce out of the offices of arcsin
It architecture and Interiors
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Sea kelp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastern episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You run the show and likes her on Facebook and follow Saul on Twitter and Instagram for the best way to explore the 99% invisible
Visible activity that shapes the design of our world
Hundreds and hundreds of stories
199p I
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com