99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
So here we are in the 99 cent store in West Oakland
Any dollar store in the United States
And you'll find the same kind of stuff I've already got the Christmas stuff out
Santa stuff everywhere
Little Santa booties that you can put on your baby a little Santa costume that you can put on a wine bottle
In u.s. dollar stores there are grocery items and cleaning products
And some of them are named Brad
But then there's this other category of things for sale
Little
Bags of
Plastic festive gourds
A slotted
Yeah everything is like this doesn't have a brand name like where is it
From
Toys and jewelry and Nick nacks that seemed to have a sort of
Generic
Cheapest Tesla
Blueface
Temporary generic-looking razors
Little
Fake plants
You want this chocolate toothpaste
Dollar stores aren't just a US phenomenon
They're in Australia and the UK
Turn the Middle East
Mexico
They're all over the world
And a lot of that stuff
That generic peeps
Stuff that lines the shelves of these doors
Comes from one place
A market in China
Kung Fu tea NY
If the future Market
Where all this stuff comes from it goes on for
Tomorrow in Miles I'll just be tiny little stores
That's documentary filmmaker Daniel Whelan
The food chain Market is about 43 million square feet
Or round 10 times the size of the Mall of America
You could answer the market and walk around if it dies and never say the same store twice
Daniel is co-producer Tobias Anderson off of them
Made a documentary film called Boku
And about the futian market
And the city in China words Loki
Evo
This about 2 million people here completely dedicated to making this stuff for us
City of evil is about 200 miles Southwest of Shanghai
The market City
It's not
Incredibly livable City and Incredibly lovely Grain City
So does bucolic
Mountain town
To what kind of seems a cookie cutter industrial city now
In the late 1970s
Communist China begin to open itself up
Capitalist
It would no longer be illegal to run private businesses in China
The province of json where you is Loki
The history of being a center for trade
And the people there were eager to join the new economy
The village of spent all day at Satellite sightings on cheap
Industrial equipment
And started producing
Items that were really easy to make
Playing cards
Or
Christmas decorations or old wooden toys
And soon a market opened up in the city of Iwo to sell
The Market Street Market
People started making not Christmas decorations and
That's awesome crafts
Mobile paper site companies Market
Enterprise grown up
This is Nigel crop
He's a British Trader who lives and works in Iwo
And he really came to the city just to have an adventure and teach English
So I started teaching English training center
And I was teaching adults
Bosses and Trading Company bus
So
About the same time how to do the business hell
It's just showing me around
The Street Markets grew and grew and eventually came to encompass
Spore huge building
Things connected by skybridge's in
Roads in parking lot
And each of the buildings is divided into different products
You have the jewelry building
The toy building
The Arts and Crafts building and the clothing building
Every day thousands of foreign Traders visit this massive market and he will
They're haggling in Chinese looking for things to buy in bulk that they can sell $2 stores and other vendors in the
Their home countries
Nwankwo
Once you get inside to look different to a to a normal Shopping Center shopping mall it's
Thousands and thousands of Market stores
WiFi fake
Don't usually run by one person or two people and they're sitting in that surrounded by their products
Another product
Office is in there and say I want one key ring
You have to go inside
I want
1500k rings
That's exactly the kind of volume Nigel the British Trader who lives in Iwo is looking for
He heads to the market
And we need to find generic
Animals
What kind of ocean animals is okay
Outside gecko
Lizards
Because the market and that spot give surprise
And then we do the Audrey
The goods are delivered to my warehouse
Leash I have is it on the west or speak English obviously
And I have the Westin Hawaii
Products to sell on Etsy expected
Important
What are you over here says hi
That's what I said at the Fulton Market my business is mostly Book Sales of electronics Antigo
This is Wang Xiao yuan
She has a stall in the food chain Market filled with hundreds and hundreds of
Plastic Santa
How many kids are saying us is how old is JoJo
We started this business in 1992 that's when my dad started it
7 days away
She's in the shop completely surrounded by
Santa
Santa surfing Santas climbing out of chimneys centos
Riding motorcycles with raybans on
Someone said song
Gasoline station
Before we started this business I never heard of the concept of
Christmas I had no idea what it was
Golite Salmo salar
Santa is a very kind old man whose lights through your chimney on Christmas
Brings you gifts
And happiness and good fortune
Christmas is a holiday for people overseas but for us Chinese people
We don't get any time off for it
Bombshell young and Nigel are just two links in the economic chain that starts in China and ends at
Your local Dollar Store
The Hub of that economy is certainly the food chain market and you woo
The whole show John province is involved
Neighboring towns to eat
All have their specialties
XSport witch brooms
And this might these brooms
There's a
You go to the town
Toys of wooden puzzles or Christmas decorations H-Town at its niche
And most of these little toys and trinkets are being produced in small operation
Maybe a family has been able to buy one piece of industrial equipment and hire a few work
There's a scene in Daniels film where some migrant workers are sitting around in someone's garage making cheap costumes
Jewelry
Pouring molten metal into a machine
That's sending it in a mole
An ad set of finding it down and checking into a container
Then later that died
A guy will probably come by and grab that that bucket of
Jewelry
And take it to a different part of town where someone will put it in the packaging
And then the next I will come back and pick all that up and take it to the market
And for many people in The Province this isn't even there full-time day job
This is just a side business
Everyone
From the age of sort of
22 to 80 and 90
They'll work in the farm and then I'll come back at night and stop making witches brooms
A bit like the cottage industry back in Industrial Revolution in England
Mets Nigel crop again
The British Trader who lives in emu
Great Britain 200
20:30 is
And you can see the effects of this super fast growth any Wu
The city grew so quickly and it still hasn't had time to build basic infrastructure
You say Senpai neighborhoods with without roads with no paved roads because they just
Need people
Immediately move into the building
And and start making stuff in the basement
What do you use after moving a tuna Nigel met his wife
An evil look
Who started the trading company she had a booth in the mall
I do so she was she was one of my students
Jesse's family is one of many anyway to benefit from China's turn toward a free market economy
Joshua
Upstairs
Play something
Play Coldplay
Always felt Poppy Family
Now that I felt I needed
Nigel's wife's great-grandparents
Prince can remember Iwo before it opened itself up
Capitalism
What was that
Did we lift your since we were born
We built our own house
In the old days it was suffering
It was a really terrible
But tonight was great grandmother in law
Gong Jin Shan
Ruth Elisa
Just mentioning the suffering time I feel so sad I could cry
Bahia colitis
Life was so tough
That a single sweet potato was divided into
Pieces for several meals
In the old days there were no cars
Now
A lot of people can afford luxurious sedan
Google
Taina I'm so comforted by the chain
Of course capitalism has also taken its toll on China
I think globalization
Is
Ruinous
Unchecked
Like it is in places like
UC landscape almost completely
Destroyed
United live the mountains are all the dog out is people burning
Rubbish everywhere
It's muggy all the time and you said it like
For what
And then you say why
It's people who
Spent years almost completely malnourished now being able to sit around with a giant
Family
I know 8 and have a lovely time
But now people in China who have been able to move out of desperate poverty
What more than to just make a living
And those people
A demanding about a lobster
Make a make
We are at the market everyday everyday
Everyday it never changes
That's one shot young again
Her business selling Santa's has grown substantially since our father first started it in 1992
It's allowed her family to move into the middle class
But it's also swallowing up her existence
She's there 7 days a week
From sunup to sundown
Cuz maybe everyone has some regret in their lives
If I got to do it again I would study harder
Then I would not have to rely on the business that my parents ran for my entire life
Like a lot of middle-class Chinese people want something more
My dream is to travel all around the world
The first place I want to go is Egypt
This is the place I wanted to go ever since I was a kid
She doesn't want to just
So santistevan dies awake until she's able to get his daughter to do the same thing
And then continue on forever
For now though one chaoyang just has to work harder
Because cost in China are going up
Enter profit margin is getting slimmer
Lehi momentum
Oren's Hummus
Sanya
Our cost for workers in China is increasing yearly
Every part of production
Starting from the smallest fitting part
2 assembly cost
It's getting more and more expensive
Has the cost of Labor goes up people seek out cheaper labor market
Bangladesh Vietnam
Laos
There right there
And that got the facilities to do it
And
They ready to take that work and I have time to type that work wife from
M-paisa sake with
The Chinese government is also interested in moving the country away from its reputation as the world's Factory
I don't want to be
I'm wet without all of that junk comes from they want to be the next South Korea or Taiwan or Japan.
Computers and Kaizen
And dumb
Are solar panels and things like that
Buty Wu is the city that cheap junk built
We're really only half belt
City grew so fast that basic infrastructure has not caught up to the growth
In the coming years the people of Iwo will have to find ways to finish building their City
And then new ways
Is to survive
As the global economy changes
The world's dollar stores will continue to be full of plastic Santas and cheap trinkets of all kinds
But soon is stuff maybe made in the basements and garages and factories
Some others
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sharif Youssef Avery trufelman Kurt Kolstad sandwich
Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza Delaney Hall and me Roman Mars
The English voice-overs were done by Shawn Wynn and Claire showing the story was adapted from the film bulk lamp by Daniel Whelan
And Tobias Anderson Auto Plaza
The whole film is about an hour long and puts a bunch of other really interesting characters that we couldn't fit into this radio piece you really should see it
It's called bulk lamp
You can buy a copy of it on amazon.com
Gentle Touch razors oh my God oh my God
Oh my God
Oh my God there's a Justin Bieber
Toothbrush that will display
Words to song
Definitely they only come in Justin Bieber
We could do some music this week my friends okay akumi from the always fantastic hell audio and right now I'm
Speaking over a new song from our friend melodeon who has an album out on November 29th on audio drugs recordings
The album is called Low Gravity
Look for it
And buy it
We are brothers 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced on radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating it doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
You can find the show enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook and treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi or
Run Instagram in Tumblr to the Nexus of all things 99p aizat
99 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com