99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in Beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
The always stunning amazing award-winning radio Diaries
Here is Joe Richmond
It was strangely cold and foggy
On the morning of July 28th
The World War II is coming to a close
In the mood in New York City on that Saturday with cheerful
Millions were eating breakfast running errands
And 120 year old woman was on her way to the 80th floor of the tallest building in the world
Her name is Betty Lou Oliver
Did she spend her days going up and down up and down the Empire State Building
As the operator of elevator number 6
What Betty work that morning in her crisp uniform smiling at passengers
She couldn't have known that outside the building a young US Army pilot
On his way to LaGuardia Airport
Was lost in the thick fog
Flying low over Manhattan
You couldn't have known that the pilot of that B-25 had just narrowly missed hitting the Chrysler Building
10 Grand Central
She might have heard the Roar of the plane as it got closer
She might have wondered what it was
Has she got called up to the 80th floor
Just before 10 a.m.
At the exact moment
Plane slammed into the 79th floor of the Empire State Building
Very experienced every elevator Riders worst
Nightmare
Down she fell
Floor by floor
More than a thousand feet to the sub-basement
What happened next
Put Betty Lou Oliver in the Guinness Book of World Record
Somehow
Air pressure built up as the elevator dropped
Slow in the fall
At the same time thousands of feet of loose elevator cable
Recoiling up on the bottom of the shaft
In the elevator car reach the bottom
Those cables acted like a giant spring
The cushion The Landing
It was not a gentle impact
But he broke her back
Bowflex
But she was alive
There was a great roaring inside my head
She said
And black
Every chapter of history is made of lots of little stories
That was especially true on July 28 1945
Today airplane crash
Into the Empire State Building
This is the view from the 79th floor
My name is Torres
40 Wheeling
In 1945 I was 20 years old
And I work for Catholic relief serve
On the 79th floor
Of the Empire State Building
My name is Gloria Paul
In 1945
I was working for the Uso headquarters
I was on the 56th floor of the Empire State Building
It was just
Exciting every time I got off
The train
And went up to that 56
Explode with excitement
It was the Empire State Building
Tallest building in the world at that time Rising a quarter of a mile straight up into the clouds
Tallest structure the Empire State Building
Observation platform visitors look down on the New York skyline
1200 feet below
Everyone on the ground looks so small
The cars of the people
You will really part of the
The clouds
The Empire State Building
A giant of Steel and Stone
Hamacas 20th century progress
I'm off of Weingarten I wrote the book
The sky is falling about the B-25 Bomber
Crashed into the Empire State
The pilot of the
The plane was Captain William
Franklin Smith
A highly decorated
Early in the morning
On July 28th 1940
Captain Smith
Massachusetts
Took the New York
Area
That morning was Misty cloudy day
At the Empire State Building
We could really see the ground from the 79th floor
It was so foggy outside I was looking out of the window there's nothing to say it was just like pea soup is like a London Fog
It was very foggy in the office
This morning Minami B-25 twin-engine Bomber passed over LaGuardia field and ask for a weather report
Captain Smith
Called into LaGuardia field
NSAID
I request clearance to land
Power said we have almost zero visibility here
I suggest you do not like
Here at LaGuardia
The product was warned that the weather was bad and at the tower of the Empire State Building a landmark for a man in this area
Could not be seen
Smith said thank you very much
And sign.
He ignored
After / 50 missions in Europe
Flying in the worst weather conditions imagine
What could possibly happen to him here in the United States
And so he started to make a little bit of a turn which brought him over Midtown Manhattan
And as he started
To straighten out
The clouds broke up enough for him to realize
He was flying among skyscrapers
Foggy Saturday morning five blocks north of the Empire State Building
James Yeager
Dictating into a soundscriber machine
I let her to Dean Crawford
University of Michigan
By the sound of a plane rolling down Fifth Avenue
And you can hear him
Dictating the letter as the sound of the engines get louder and louder
Louder as it passes by his office window
Voice stops in a second or so later on the tape you hear a dull thud
Which is the impact of the bomber into the Empire State Building
At
About five minutes of 10
I got up from my desk
And that was the end of the office as it existed
We are delaying the start of our regularly scheduled program to bring you a special news report on the crash of an airplane into the empire
State Building
Columbia Station
And all of a sudden the building felt like it was going to just talk about over
It just
Really across the room and I
Landed against the wall
People were screaming and looking at each other and didn't know what to do
Play the newest is a bomb but what happened
A B-25 Mitchell bomber on a flight apparently a routine flight from Boston to Newark
Or New York City
Crashed into the 78th are the 79th story of the Empire State Building
At what the final toll will be there is no way of telling at this time
On the other side of the office
All I could see was flames
Mystic Mountain
Was walking through the office when the plane hit the building
Then he was on fire
His clothes were on fire his head was on fire
Six of us managed to get into this one office that seem to be on touch
By the fire
And close the door
Before it engulfed us
It was no doubt that the other people
Must have been killed
The 4 alarm fire is gone every piece
The fire apparatus to the busy scene of 5th Avenue and 34th Street
In the heart of Manhattan
And hundreds of office workers with trap 2/5 of a mile above the street level
It was a very small Universe at that point
DeSoto
Ducks
And then Island was firewall around us
Couple of women had to had passed out from the smoke
And I
Had a handkerchief in my pocket
And so I use that to cover my nose and mouth to protect me from the fumes
But I didn't expect to get out alive
Somebody opens window
And I'm sitting there
And
I thought about my rings
I figured somebody else might as well
Have you thought of them
So I
Took them off my fingers
And
Throw them out the window
We have
Contact that I Witness
But the bill Kirby at the Grand advertising agency contact with him by telephone
The Caribbean
I look out of the window and it was very very smoking terribly
Go to the window and I saw two girls
Crap, 78th floor that's above our floor is he I'm going to 76 that you fly to
Period stories down
You looked up and he signals up to us
I think Charlotte was sitting
Is always hot legs dangling inside the office and
We were holding on to her
I gave her a better view of what was going on
Get back now Baby Got Back
I guess he was trying to give us a little solace
I know that you're there don't worry
And that was a
That was a connection with the rest of the world in it
We all felt a little better to know that someone new
We were there
When the plane hit the outside of the building it kept on going and the engines
Continue about 20 feet into the building and went down through the Elevator Shaft
What Was An Elevator Shaft
When the plane hit
Parts of the engine
Fluid head and severed
Lyft
Steam table
Of the elevators that had been at the 79th
Floor
Sitting in one of the elevators
Was
Is a young
Elevator operator named Betty Lou Oliver
She started to plunge down the Elevator Shaft from the 79th
Floor tables of two of the cars were sheared
Sending both elevators crashing to the sub-basement
All the Empire State Building
She was alive
She broke
Her pelvis
Back
Nick
But you survived
Reverend John Jay Morrison has just come in and he has just given the last rites
Nomad Hotel
And landed on a parapet I think it's on the 16
65th and 66th
I think
My name is Sharon during cizauskas
My father was
Paul Deering
My father was in a corner office
On the 79th floor
Either was forced out by the
The crush the concussion or
Or he actually had to jump
When I saw
Whole place on fire
It's more likely that he had to jump
You know if you were up 79 floors and looking down
To think of someone having two
Jump out of a window up there
That's what I think
We're speaking from the Empire State Building
Near the top of the building 79th floor where fireman
Picking up the debris caused by the crash of a Mitchell B-25 Bomber
End of this building
Write about 40 feet from where we stand
All of a sudden he would do a fireman and that they're coming to rescue us YouTube
All dressed up in their raincoats and whatever they wear in over there
It was just
Wonderful
We climbed out screws
Broken glass
I was just grateful to be alive
The walls are still hot the brick and stone walls that we have our hand on as we talk
Are still hot with the
Claim that has been out for over an hour now
112 flights later
We got to the bottom floor
But we do know what happened
Until we came out of the building
I see crowds of people are kind of looking at each other
What happened what happened
And he pointed up to the 79th floor
I saw the
The tale of a B-25 stick
Well we're going to get off here here very shortly because we have
The story told now
The B-25 to engine Army bomber crashing into the Empire State Building built a few minutes before 10
Good morning
People
Guide
In the offices
N3 in the play
I Will Forte
Don Goddard and this is a national broadcast
The music of the first piano quartet
The view from the 79th floor was produced by Joe Richmond Samara freemark and Sarah Kramer for radio Diaries
If you ever turned on NPR in the afternoon any hear some beautifully composed sound
First-person documentary that Knock You Out
It was probably radio Diaries do yourself a favor
Go straight to the source and subscribe their newly revamped podcast it's so good
You can find it
At Radio Diaries. Org
99% invisible in Sam Greenspan Avery we are project of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made site
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a kid is another remember all hearing that voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast oh my God. Info
Flash podcast
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
I can find the show and like a sale on Facebook I tweet at Roma tomorrow at Santa Rita Sam listens Avery tweak
Truffle man but you can keep up-to-date on all things 99percentinvisible including the launch of season 4 week
Play episode starting February 4th at 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero in
In the movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast. Com