99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is attorney blah blah
You watching money for your blablacar injury
Broken bones burn paralysis
This song
Victim, call me call me right now
Our friend Sean Cole has always been impressed
My lawyer at I would say
Totally confused
By lawyers
I mean I'm just like like really like is
Disaster footage or your cousin wearing a judge's robe
The best way to represent your practice
But I start looking into them these Lorazepam for
Fly by Night
Bottom feeder receiving line
And alive
Fell down the well
Into the Byzantine
Krazy sub
Mediterranean Wonderland of lawyer advertising regulation
Which has air is to it and factions and there's this seemingly endless Civil War in life
Nation about whether lawyer should
Advertiser services at all
But first let's just enjoy
And indulge ourselves in
Some of the more excessive
Nae Nae
Surreal
Examples
Of
The genre
Maestro
Perrigo
If you've been in an auto accident here are a few important tips
These are the kinds of commercials you see at 3 in the morning on basic cable when everything is going wrong in your life
You got your sort of Central Casting lawyer in front of a bookshelf
Forest Moon every syllable and hand gesture is a fertile
We understand the seriousness s that an auto accident can have on your life
But then you have your
Performers permanently injured
Size matter
The bigger your check the better
The Hammer Stanley
I love Lowell The Hammer Stanley
Are images of Airborne cars engulfed in flames playing behind him right now
I don't stop hammering until the size of your check
Satisfies you
Call me
How to talk about size
More than one hammer in this
Tool bench
There's even more than one hammer name to Jim
I'm him
I swear to God I thought this one was a joke
I cannot handle their severed head
What
I can hunt them down
Those are the Crusaders
I mean it's still all about money but
You know they have a cow
Captain America pre
Air quality about them
In a few of these things
Pure unfettered crassness
I was in pain
And I called Spencer and Associates and he change my pain the rain
At which point in money falls all over
Everybody
Usually happens on the strip club The Pain Train alchemical process
Is fundamental to lawyer television
Your injury is
Commodity
And apparently
Cashing in
Call me
It's just that easy call one eight seven seven
And you don't look I granted these things are
They're almost Majestic
Terrible right this is Bob Garfield
Co-host of the NPR WNYC show on the media
For 25 years he was the ad critic for advertising age magazine
There is no attempt
For Saturday
It is
The hard
Cell
There has been a few of these lawyers over the years will try to be funny
You know a lot of personal injury lawyers sometimes
In order to cast them
Themselves in their own
Will do some sort of
Nominally
Comic scenarios
How can you tell when a lawyer is lying
When is lips are moving
That is funny and lawyer jokes are gray
But basically it's the key words are
Call
Now
Call the ReliOn group
Because like obviously the
Pinnacle View is like
Here are some
Show the Goldwater Law Firm now
If you or a loved one has had a hip replacement
Certain dri to respect having
Looked over and over and over
For 25 years
Extremely art
Actual execution
Fairly obscure creative idea
I'm so delighted
To see somebody say
I got something to sell
I think you should buy it call now
You know honestly it's honest
No sometimes of dubious legality because the ads themselves
Frequently
Skirt
The legality of
Solicitation
Different jurisdictions
Have different rules
This is what I was talking about in the beginning rules regarding what you can and can't say in an ad
Who can appear in your ad and what they are allowed to say about you
All that is regulated
To try to release your degrees by each individual State Bar Association
And state supreme court
Because
As proven by history
Lawyers will tell themselves exactly as loudly
As they're allowed to
Back in the 19 century you see ads for attorneys on the front page of newspaper
Alongside ads for doctors in
Saddle and Harness manufacturer
But in 1908 the American Bar Association putting new rules
Saying all instances of
Self laudation that's what they called it
Self laudation Define the traditions and lower the tone of our high calling and our
Intolerable
Business cards were okay
That band lasted about 70 years
And then in 1976
The lock Clinic of Bates and Osteen
Ran one little classified in the Arizona Republic saying
Do you need a lawyer Legal Services at very reasonable fees divorce adoption bankruptcy with you
And in short the Arizona bar got mad
Suspended the two lawyers
Dayton Osteen
Healed all the way to the USA
Supreme Court
And in the now infamous
Bates vs. State Bar of Arizona
The Court ruled that lawyers have the same freedom of speech as everybody else
Gobble gobble
Lawyers can advertise then all hell
Hell broke Luce
This is Elizabeth tarbert the ethics counsel for the
The Florida bar
She runs the department that regulates
Lawyer advertising there
There was kind of a wild wild west
Situation where lawyers were
Advertising anyway they wanted
Because I want regular
Where there had been.
Flatout prohibition
So Florida actually
Had
A couple of different
Blue Ribbon commission and they adopt
Did the first set of
Rules and because
Art leadership
Very concerned about
Statements
Lawyers for making Anna Roberts
Elizabeth Herbert wasn't with the bar back then so she doesn't know what those ads look like
But an attorney I talk to you names
Steve Miller
Nose look at when I first started practicing that he's a divorce lawyer with offices in Florida and Mass
Massachusetts I work for a woman
In Florida
Doing personal energy work
And she was one of
I want sushi was one of the first on TV but
She did a lot of TV advertising
And her add when something like this
Here car crash
You hear a car crash
See hear the sirens and then they threw a doll
Baby doll
Into the picture
Which
I'll never forget I won't say her name
But it it was just the worst thing that I ever see everyday and so I'm sure that had something to do with the bar
Come in and say and look
You can't you can't do music you can't do dramatizations can't have your clients come on 2K
Can't do that
It actually goes way beyond that
Florida has some of the
Strictest guidelines in the country for these ads
For instance testimonials if a lawyer
Writes the testimonial him or herself that would be Miss
Bleeding that's not.
Experience
If it's not the person's actual experience with a lawyer or not
Qualified to judge
Think of how many lawyer commercials you've seen that used
Testimonial
Assurance company
Kept asking me to hurry up
Sign a release
I was thinking
What's the rush
Of course
Horse some of them are written by the attorney
Were there advertising consult
Often time the actual client doesn't even appear in the ass
I'm Jason Smith he is not Jason Smith
He's an actor performing a testimonial
Which is also prohibited in Florida
Nor are you allowed in Florida to have actors playing authority figures like cops and judges
Saying how great the lawyer is
Nor are you allowed to have actual cops and judges saying how great the lawyer is people inherently respond to it
Here is whether they're real or not
So we prohibit their use
Does Robert Vaughn fall under that category
I wouldn't consider Robert Vaughn and Authority fee
But he would fall within the probation in the same rollabouts
Using the voice or images
Again
Kind of pervasive in other states tell the insurance companies you mean business
Tell them you hired Jacoby and Meyers
They go after your rights piece by piece by piece until justice has been served
Elizabeth Herbert says the rules are meant to protect the public
That people should pick a lawyer based on what she calls objective selection criteria
Other than Fancy Pants promises and sound effects
If you break the rules the penalties
Are not really that dramatic
The worst that might happen is
Then you'll get what's known as a public reprimand
Bar sent out a press release so your reputation is kind of marred
But it's not like you're going to be disbarred
A few other states
Iowa
And
Texas weirdly given that it's home to one of the Hammers
Massachusetts and Connecticut are still
Pretty wild Westie
And if you are National firm
Operating in a bunch of jurisdiction
You have to comply with multiple sets of rules
That's what Lucian Pera has to be
He's a lawyer with Adams and Reese in Memphis
And among other things he advises Nationwide firms on their
And sometimes he'll be looking over the disclaimer rules for example
Going to be like
State I said you got to say this but stay busy if I say what state I said state is going to say why can't say exactly that
So I got to
Weave it together somehow
It is a morass
It does what it's I think in my opinion
Intended to do which is
Guitars
Lawyer advertise
To some degree
Now lucian's State Tennessee is pretty loose
In fact it's been widely reported as late as the state where you'll see lawyer ads featuring space aliens
Giant robots
And both dogs and cars
That can talk
Talking cars
And even now more than 35 years later
Lucien says there's a cohort of lawyers
Who will see an ad like that
And say
Look watch Bates vs. State Bar of Arizona have brought there are many lawyers today
Many
Lawyer stay
You feel that
Much that was
Was that is wrong with
Profession today if not all that is wrong
Fashion today
Play dates from
That lawyer advertising
Turned us
From a
Professional
Business
And they just think it's
Unified
For lawyers to be on television
Pitching their services
Generally
Much less talk
And the dog
Orale
They just think that demeans the profession
And you don't have to look too far down the road in Tennessee to find one of those lawyers
Namely Matt Hardin
My personal injury attorney in Nashville with his own practice
I'm sorry I've got a big bunch on this
The first half of its about the history of
History of advertising
Last year he and the Tennessee Association for justice
A group of plaintiffs lawyer
Filed two petitions to the state supreme court
Asking them to change the advertising rules in Tennessee
So that they
Essentially look more like the ones in Florida
Is a public comment. Some First Amendment Advocates got involved
And ultimately
The courts at now
But man is determinism
To keep trying
And I asked him in and so do you think Bates was
The sort of the beginning of the end like the the big bang that created the downfall of
The sort of stature of lawyers
I do I mean if you look in the
You know what our history in the 50s and 60s
Do you have
Lawyers being seen as a
Proponents
The Justice League
You have things as far back is like to Kill a Mockingbird
But those
What I would call the Halcyon Days of
A positive public perception
Attorney seem to be long gone
What most people see
Unfortunately is this unsavory
Advertising
The lawyers
Matt Everett
But might you know my biggest
Concerned about this is how it affects
The jury pool and make people
So you're just a furry
Easy money
That is if people start thinking plaintiff's and their attorneys are just out for easy money they might get cynical about the process
And cynical people become cynical jurors and no one gets a fair trial anymore
That's
The calculus
And by the way that's not opposed to advertising writ large
I advertise myself none on TV
You ever doesn't movie theaters and online his that sound like this
Matt Hardin law your experienced personal injury Law Firm
Selena
Very different town
And Visually to these they're just images of gavels and ionic columns
And Matt
Which makes me wonder if maybe there's not something more basic
What is objection
What's to the
Dog and robot commercial
Is it just that you think the ads aren't
Classy
No
I don't think it's up to
Anyone else
Make a judgment over what
What the class of an ad is
But do you think they're not
I don't have it
That's not really
I'm trying to really cuz I think all of us have an affair
Turned off
I don't I don't think they would do it
If it didn't work
You think it works
Absolutely it does
They do work yes they do work for those that they appeal to
This
Is Lowell The Hammer Stanley
They are the mail
Wow
That is it's just it's
Just like watching
YouTube
I don't think I mentioned Lowell The Hammer Stanley practices in Norfolk Virginia
He's been a lawyer for more than 30 years
And
Truthfully I was a little nervous about asking him what the hell was up with his ads
But he answered the question before I even got to it
Sophisticated
I'm glad that you know that
If I saw my ass
You personally
I would never call me really
The apps do not appeal to me
They are over the top
And
Somebody
But
They are not designed to kill
People like me who
Listen to NPR and watching
TDS
Their there they are designed to appeal to
People to walk
Watch
Shows like them
A Jerry Springer
Things like that or good and fine
Decent people
But they are used to
Commercials
Anda
Stable always going to fight for them
And that's what those ads are designed to
It sounds a little like a classic
Will it be up
If you are an educated
Person is
PhD or Banker or
You don't need
To get your lawyer
From a from a
You go to that
Sign for
Hard-working
A blue collar
Bus driver
A little league coach
Somebody was
Who's her and doesn't know where to turn doesn't have a lawyer
I want somebody's going to fight. That's what they're designed
Who killed
True
They're almost
Certainly people in Florida whom Those ads would appeal to
And so finally I asked Elizabeth Harbor the Florida bar if I called myself the hammer and screamed
Pinhead flaming blazing behind me
Would that
Bok
There
I think they're a spy
That are not objective
Is required under
That you Hammer that
That is subject
Right
I can't prove that I hammer
Attention
99% invisible was produced this week by Shawn Cole collectively we are Sam Greenspan Katie Mingle
Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
A version of this story originally appeared on the podcast life of the law which I think you really like and it was edited by
Superstar Julia Barton
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced in beautiful downtown
Oakland California out of the offices of arcsin a firm of Architects who are collaboration junkies and weird enough
Want some radio producers hanging around
God love
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Five podcast
You can find the show and likes on Facebook I tweeted Roman Mars ass and wheat the same listens
Katie mingle could learn a thing or two about tweeting from her mom Pamela mingle we also have a Tumblr that Avery maintain
Are the headquarters of all things 99 Pi is at 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com