99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The night of February 27 2010
Luis henriquez was getting home from his job at a lumber Factory
In constitucion Chile
Isolated
It was around 3 in the morning
I was watching TV with my wife and a neighbor and all of a sudden we started feeling the Earth
Shake and it was just getting stronger and stronger
Couldn't stand up producer Sam Greenspan translating for Lewis Lewis was in an earthquake
A bad one when the shaking finally stopped he was relieved to see that his wife and their two kids are all fine
But Lewis knew they were still in danger because into a everyone is taught from childhood that after North
Quick hits
The first thing you do is get to Higher Ground
Which is what Lewis and his family did
They got in a car and they sped to the top of a nearby Hill
From its peak
Please look down from the hillside To Where the River male men
Pacific Ocean
Severe and severe you can see it happening
Supercloud you can see it super Clear Lake
You can see the waves
Coming into the city
The earthquake that Louise is describing was tremendous
A magnitude 8.8 second-biggest that the world has seen in the past
50 years
The quake and ensuing tsunami completely crush the seaside town of constitución chile
Ray Lewis live
By the time it was over more than 500 people we're dad
And 80% of the city's building
It's were ruined
As part of a relief effort
An Architecture Firm called Elemental was hired
To create a master plan for the city
Which included new housing for
4 people displaced
And the disaster
But the structures that element all delivered were a radical
And somewhat controversial approach towards housing
They gave people
Half a house
Picture of simple two-story home with a pitched roof
A square with a triangle on
Basically how a kid would draw
Only in these there's a wall that runs down the middle
Peak of the roof
All the way to the ground
Splitting the house in half
One side of the house is finished
And the other side
The other side is a completely empty space there's a roof
And an exterior wall
The rest is just an open boy
The Architecture Firm Behind these houses
Santiago based Elemental
Has made a name for themselves
Building these half a home
And not just as disaster relief
Either today element all has done about 10 low-income housing projects across Thule
All design so that the homes would be largely unfinished when the residents moved in
And the response from the architectural Community has been immense
In 2016
The firm's founder Alejandro aravena
Was awarded the pritzker prize
The top prize in Market
In there jury citation the pritzker architecture prize set that quote
Alejandro aravena
Epitomizes the Revival of a more socially-engaged architect
Especially in his long-term commitment
To tackling the global housing crisis
And fighting for a better Urban environment for all
This for building disaster victims
Another poor people
Unfinished homes
To understand where these half-built houses came from
You have to understand them as an attempt to solve the problem
Global Urban migration
Over the past several decades people the world over have been migrating from the countryside
The cities the driver city was
Creating spell
So
The results of squatting
This is George gattoni
An architect who grew up all around Latin America
Mostly in El Salvador
George saw firsthand what happens when a population grows
It's supply of building
The housing deficit
Of San Salvador the capital
What's something about
10000 units
A year
And growing
The backlog
People
That had no service
It was
It was unbelievable
George wanted to help solve this
But I was struggling with how to make a house
Affordable
In the 1970s
George heard about a new master
Program that MIT program called Urban settlement design in developing country
At MIT George found a mentor in a professor named John FC Turner
John FC Turner of British
Urban planner
Wisp irritating
Idea that
People can build for themselves
In a 1972 essay called housing as a verb
Turner made the case that housing ought not be as static unit that is
Package
Handover.
Rather
Housing should be conceived of as an ongoing project
When residence
Are co-creators
And from this thesis Turner helped promote an idea this idea that was emerge
This site and service
Sites and services also sometimes called incremental build
It basically means instead of building people completed homes
Government should just build the
The key parts of a home
The people have the hardest time building on their own
Like concrete foundations insulation Plumbing electrical wiring
To provide services to those sites
Road drainage sores that latrines whatever the case may be garbage collection you got to write your
Tracks to the schools
Does gradually over time people start to turn their basic sites into suitable housing
With materials they Source themselves
On their own terms
What people have to be to donate of Their Own
Is
Labor
The cost of Labor
And the cost of materials to expand
But in the end
They own what they built
It's their investment
They have the ability
And governments cannot build
Old as well
As
Quickly
And no way that makes sense to these house
Since finishing his studies at MIT in the 1970s
George has done these kinds of incremental building projects
All over the world
In Latin America Kenya Indonesia
Annies projects
Can take different forms
Sometimes it's just giving people a concrete pad with utility hookups
Sometimes it's just giving people a one-room house with a kitchen and bathroom in the expectation that they'll build extra rooms on to
It sounds odd but
Believe me
These ideas that Georgia Tony and his contemporaries and MIT pioneered
Sacraments
Report people building for themselves and then let them on what they build
Began to spread through the developing world
And so when the architecture from Elemental got their first commission to do low income housing in chili
They took the ideas from incremental housing
As Point of Departure
Absolutely
To make something that can be improved
By time
This is Juan Ignacio Cerro though one of the principal Architects at elementary
Sarah told me that in 2002 Elemental got a commission to build a hundred units of low-income housing
In a city in Northern Chile called
He gay and they had to deliver it on a tight budget
$7,500
Unit with only $7,500 allocated for household
The most straightforward and cost-effective way to house all 100 families
Was the cram everyone into big block style apartment
When they
What about blocks
They said if you dare
To propose to block we started hangers
Because it's the worst thing ever
According to Juan Ignacio cerda
The community threatened the hunger strike because an apartment block would be extremely limiting
Sure they were living in a slum before but at least they had control over their own space
They can make expansion some adjustments when they wanted to
But with a block style housing project
They be confined to a small static space
Which is worse
Because you are not able to expand a house
Into what element all came up with
We're tall rectangular houses separated by empty space
Each unit was
Just big enough
Give me Chili's minimum standards for low income housing
And then residents could on their own time however they wanted
Expand into the empty space adjacent to their home
Element all spent the early 2000s iterating on his concept
Building homes that just met the basic legal requirements for low income housing in chili
What was room to grow
And then in 2012 after the earthquake
Can Constitution
Elemental got a commission
To help create a new map
For the city
Which included creating a new neighborhood
Full of incremental building
It would be located on one of the tallest Hills in the city
It would be called
Via Verde
Okay we are on our way up to be a better day and
Oh wow here it is
This is it right here
Wow I was really big
The same went out to see Via Verde with producer Martina Castro
To get to Via Verde you drive straight up one of the tallest heels and constitute
You pass a traditional looking apartment complex
Also built the house
People act mm
And Quake
Once you're on top of the hill you get some just
Staggering views of the town the ocean and the river male below
It's like a whole bunch of
These little boxes on the hillside
Looking over let the river male
Via Verde is made of neat rows
Simple two storey house
Half of each house is identical
Play Windows steam color kind of a Farmhouse Red
The other half of each house though
Is completely different
They have different doors different windows or
Pieces of tarp where windows will go
And it's on houses
Half the house has nothing there at all
Half the house is missing
And that's an Ender funny vows
Full Tilt out
When people get their houses beside that comes pre-built is pretty bare-bones
The walls are unpainted sheetrock in the floors are unfinished concrete and plywood
The kitchen comes with just the sink no stove no refrigerator no cabin
Houses are Spartan
To say the least
But their habitat
Practical and well-insulated
Martina Castro and I spent a couple of days walking around Via Verde talking to residents
And is there that we met Luis Enriquez the earthquake Survivor We heard from earlier
Is some of them program in California
When we met him Lewis and his wife were outside
Working on a gravel walkway to their home
Lewis invited us in
Martina Translate
When you when you moved in more the most important things that you wanted to do right away
Cuando Cimarron air quality
Compare 4K
Evil lair
People say lalala
Yeah just make it bigger because it was a really small space
So we had to
Build it out to be comfortable
With help from his wife and his brother who also lives in Via Verde
Lowest laid concrete on the empty side of the house to make a floor
And put up exterior walls and flooring for the second
Story
None of them had really done construction before
But they had direction from workshops on building techniques
Elemental health
Facilitate
The homes also come with a user manual with directions for how to expand the house
Expansions can be done with standard size building materials
The residents don't have to pay lots of money for a custom cut pieces of lumber
So far Lewis has focused his efforts I'm just getting the house to be big enough to accommodate his family
And so inside the walls are still in painted
The downstairs floors are still just unfinished Concrete in upstairs it's unfinished plywood
Louis knows they've got a long way to go on there
But he doesn't just see the bare walls and course floor
He sees what it all can become
If and when the Enriquez family does have tiling in
Carpet
Painting baseboard on the walls
It'll be way nicer than anything that they ever could have afforded on their own
Or what they could have normally gotten through state-funded low-income housing programs
And some now
Louis is the owner of a four-bedroom home
It keeps out the cold won't get flooded then won't fall down in an earthquake
Yoakum, Senora
Telemundo
La vida dificil
You know my wife and I
Japan
So finding out that we were going to be owners of our own house was just
Incredible
Not everyone I talk to it Via Verde was enthusiastic about having to build their own home
And some thought Elemental contractors could have done a better job
But for the most part people there seemed really happy with their homes
Even people who had an expanded there's at all
One resident of single mom named Camilla Hernandez Rodriguez
Admit any Edition
Aqi
Yeah so of course you know when when dream
Can you think that you're going to
Just have everything ready all all is one
And so I wanted
Build out the house and everything but the
Then I just focused on
Small things
Most people in Via Verde are further along with lyrics
Camilla
And everyone seems to have some prog
Some residents have been opted to use their extra space to start businesses
Lakeville stores that
Sell bread and candy and
Cell phone minutes
If you only got from residence is that they felt invested in Via Verde
They like living there
I felt safe
It all kind of made me wonder
Why haven't we seen this approach in the US
I don't think this could work in
There's a lot of things going on here which are
Really Innovative and there's a lot of things
Where things go wrong
This is dr. Jennifer stoloff a researcher with the consulting firm
Econometrics
Before that I was a social science Analyst at HUD and the office
The policy development
For about 14
Dr. stoloff is an expert at evaluating government programs
Particularly those that pertain to housing
She's also an historian of public housing in the US
I told dr. stoloff about the Via Verde project
There's some pictures and she says yes
It does
Kind of a line with the US ethos
Pulling yourself up by your
It is very bootstrap
It's true but it's also very risky
I mean and I mean in a safe
The way
Not just in a financial
It is both
First off someone could get hurt building out their house
Which means you'd have to do with both a medical and illegal emergency
In the States you know there be
Litigation
Issues
Right I mean if you
We're working
Building your floor ceiling
And you fell down
States maybe you was
Sue the developer
Look for Doctor stoloff
The biggest hurdle to an incremental building project working in the US isn't a matter of safety
Legality
It would be embarrassing
Rights of the United States of America can only build poor people have a house
Movie ashamed of ourselves
Even though in fact that might end up providing way Murphy
People with adequate housing
At the end of the day
But we couldn't do it it's like we lose face
Because unlike Thule
United States
Does have the money
And perhaps also unlike July
We don't like to spend money on poor people
I think everybody should be able to
Find their own way out of poverty
And it's just not true but that is the expectation
And
We are not in a scarcity
And we could afford to
People and Tire
But by and large
We don't
The US it's not a matter of scarcity
It's a matter of values
Elemental however
Has come to see scarcity as a tool
A tool which Juan Ignacio cerda
Find vital
I'm sure that in the states
Everything have rules and controls so you don't leave room to all those new things and came up
From Latin word
That obviously come comes from
So if you had if you're doing this project
Unless it's at the very last minute
Had to go okay we're going to double your budget
Would you would you would have made
Everyone Full House
Theoretically
You still want to go
It's a good thing to deliver whole house but if you give me double the money I keep their houses it is
And I improve
With all that money the public space surrounding the house
The neighborhood
Providing the infrastructure that people can't provide themselves like parks and libraries and public transit
Is at the very root of the sites and services approach
Building half a house
Might be the best way
To make a community
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan
Katie mingle Sharif Youssef Kohl's that Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza Delaney Hall and me Roman
Special things this week to Austin McCann Karla Paloma Martina Castro Dave Humphreys Salon pay burnout Marcela Espinosa
Ricardo Segundo Kiara Valdez Maria antonieta Bianchi Diaz Christian Martinez and Francesca
And special thanks okay akumi who's chill music
You are listening to right now
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299.
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com