99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Earlier this year I saw the movie Trading Places again on Netflix and I thought
I've seen this movie over and over again but I'm never really understood what happens on the trading floor at the end of the movie
Great things about working in public radio
Is that it's a pretty small world so
I've met Robert Smith warrant so I just wrote on that Planet Money And I said
I want to do a story
Were you help explain the economics of Trading Places to me
And for everyone else like me who also doesn't quite get it but loves a movie but doesn't quite get it
And I want to share that story with you guys it was so much fun working with them
And I really like this or that
Back in the 1980s
Louis winthorpe the Third
Was a big deal in the world
The futurist
You work at a fancy from in Philadelphia
And this guy knew
Commodity
Pork belly
I have a hunch something very exciting is going to happen the pork belly Market this morning
The best
He was about to get married in the future looked bright
We are going to make a great
We're going to have a great
Life
Until his boss is Randolph and Mortimer Duke
Took all of that away
And so begins
The great parable
About what happens when the rich become poor
The poor become rich
A con man inherits the Earth movie is Trading Places
Hello and welcome to Planet Money on Robert Smith
And I'm Roman Mars
Looking good ramen
Feeling good Robert
Roman Mars is the host of the podcast 99% invisible
It's about all things design and architecture
Buddy today because
Actual question for us about this movie
What I love is movie I saw it when I was
Way way too young I was probably 9 or 2
And I just wanted to know
Is this
The most sophisticated depiction of the inner workings of a financial Market in the history of Cinema
That is the perfect question for us Robin because we have the ability and we shall
Bringing an entire panel
Experts in the Commodities and Futures Trading world too fat
Check this movie
Today
On Planet Money
What the Movie Trading Places can teach you about financial Market
And
I know this
It's of particular interest to running
We are finally going to explain one of the great enduring Mysteries
What the hell
Actually happened
At the end of this crazy
Oh I definitely need that
So it's been a while since you've seen Trading Places
Everything is going really well for Louis winthorpe until
Bosses
They have an argument
Mad about nature versus nurture and the evil Randolph Duke that's his
Maybe even slightly more evil brother Mortimer Duke
That he can take away Lewis's job
His fiance
And his home is friends
And they can turn it
I'm into a car
While at the same time the Duke brother
Pick a comment from the street
Name Billy Ray Valentine
Rockies play by Eddie Murphy
Any given Louis's
Empire life
Job
Home his Butler
And they try to turn him into a Hotshot commodity
It's kind of a modern-day Twist on Prince in the Paw
Guinea pigs they find each other
And Lewis and Billy Ray conspire to get back at the Dukes
And they make a brilliant plan to make themselves really rich
And put the Duke Brothers in the foreground at the same
It is a crazy complicated
Plan that involves Futures trading at
Commodities and cornering the market
And Frozen concentrated Orange
Right there that's my first question
Frozen concentrated orange juice
Central to the move and when I first saw it
I totally thought that was made up as a commodity
They just to be fun
In the real world
My thinking was
You just trade oranges
Who would spend their lives
Trading little cans of Frozen
Concentrated Orange
I found some
This guy
My name is time for honest and I'm a commodity Trader I'm just coming back from
Before the New York Mercantile Exchange
Where I can have spent the last 4 hours
Buying and selling orange juice options
Futures
It's real
It's totally real estate doesn't all day long
Call Brody you give me a first expert on all things Frozen healthy orange
And women are second expert in just a moment
We're going to use both of them
Fact check this
Grandmas
Ramen
The Trading Places
Basically could be a university-level course
In financing
Commodities
And as someone who explains economics for a living in this is my job
Take my hat off
To the writers of this movie
Just listen to this scene
The Duke Brothers
In the scene
Weed Eddie Murphy
Billy Ray Valentine
Wood table
Enchantment table
Beautiful breakfast
Guys already have breakfast
This is not
Emil.
We are here too
Tried
Explain to you what it is
We do here
We are
Commodities broker
What are commodities
Commodities are agriculture
Products
Like
Coffee
For breakfast
Sweet which is used to make bread
Pork belly bacon
Which you might find in a bacon and lettuce and tomato sandwich
Eddie Murphy
Did deadpans right into the camera
I suspect that sometimes Planet Money listeners
History
I don't know either come out of this like
Frozen orange juice
And go
Of course
Gold doesn't grow on trees like orange
Clear so far
Yeah
In reviewing the movie they really really did a good job I mean someone
I'm there
Knew what they were doing
This is our second
Bob Lassen Trello
He's a Commodities Trader in
Chicago
Can use to trade cattle
Like Roman you might find any roast be
Cheddar and
Tomato sandwich
Of course if you watch that scene you might think of these guys
Trade-in physical things the physical things that you see on the table the bacon the weed
The cans of orange juice
The temperance says that in that words use Market that's not quite right
Yes. Store just a little candy had to probably have large refrigerator type units for them
All the stuff you have no idea what it looks like know and as a matter of fact if you trade agricultural Commodities most
Commodity Traders go their whole careers without ever seeing the physical product am I used to trade pork bellies and live Hogs and
I would know a pork belly fat dropped on the table here
Yeah the recent Tom fronis wouldn't recognize a pork belly on the table
It's because people like him who do this in real life or Trading
Country
On pork belly
Or technically
The future promise to deliver a certain amount of pork bellies at a certain time at a store
Price what really is a
It's a wager the bet on whether you think something is going to go up or down in price and
Mortimer and Randolph Duke in the movie
They make money
Weather goes up or down
As a good part William is that
That no matter whether our clients
Make money
I lose money
Duke and Duke
Commission
Well
What do you think Valentine
Sounds to me like you guys are
I told you he'd understand
I know this whole contract thing Macy
Theoretical
But the bats are based on an a
Actual contract when an actual real thing
The traitors just hold the contract for just a few minutes or a few days
Enough time to make a little money
But before the contract
Spires and the actual good have to be delivered
That traitor
Needs to unload the car
Need to sell to someone who actually
Wants
Thing underneath the car
Who actually wants
The oranges
Who wants the bacon
What's the life cow
Remember that's what Bob Last Cinderella trailer
Live cattle
Moana
How he just wanted to make a
Bet on the future
Prices of cow
But once popped
Did you ever receive an actual cow
Oh boy did I
Yeah not a cow 40 of them
And more than 40 you made a mistake
You made a mistake and somebody called you on the phone and just said
We have
I don't hear from you wear them a trucker's oh yeah they're in the pain there actually off the truck in Independence
What it is and so when the guys in the East st. Louis Stockyards found out that a Futures Trader
Delivery on some cattle
They generally aren't super hopeful about
They don't really give you a hand letting you
Tell him that
Think they kind of
Sticky with some extra fees and
You know they they they don't like us guys they picked it in it and it's Times Like These Guys
Sort of meddling in their world
Now back to the movie
Billy Ray Valentine
Now called William Valentine by the Dukes
Is learning this commodities
He has some talent for it
Because it's not
Just about knowing the facts and the figures of the contract
Commodities
A lot of it is about knowing psychology
Tell me just quiet think the price of pork bellies
It's going down
Christmas time
Could we please buy now Randolph
What are you trying to say what
Okay
Potbelly prices
I've been dropping all morning
Is everybody sitting in the office
Hit rock-bottom so they can buy cheap
The people on the park by the contractor going back
Christmas is around the corner by Joe with the Kung Fu grip
Okay
And my wife ain't going
My wife want to make love to me cuz I ain't got no money right
I can feel it
Oh my God
I wait till you get to about 60 for the night by
If it at all the seconds by then
Of course Billy Ray Valentine makes them a ton of money
Baba blessin Giraldo has a small quibble with
He says people don't really declare a particular price for a commodity no one ever says
It's going to 64 and really know exactly
But people make bets on whether things
Just go up and down
Is that right to people to weigh up to Lungi what would happen
You know their guys would just
You'd be standing around and you'd have to start to have a feeling that the market was going to go up or down and then you would trade accordingly
It's sort of like
Your brain
Processing all this information ends up manifesting itself is
What's called
A field and then you buy resale accordingly
So far according to rxp
The Movie Trading Places
Is nailing it that is Commodities thing down pat
But then it gets a little Hollywood Lewis Winthrop are down and out Rich Boy
He teams up with his former Butler
And a prostitute with a heart of gold
We do not fight
Fact check that one
You don't even need
It's a given
Exactly Emily rata con man turns trading Savant figures at
Women I've been played
A joint with Winthrop
Hatched this plan
How to make millions of dollars
And bankrupt
And it's the end of the movie where I have my biggest question
I was a kid I saw it and
I know that
Something important is happening on the trading floor
The Underdogs
When
I get rich
The Dukes go bankrupt
But I didn't really understand
When I watch it again
Funny thing is I
I still don't really
I understand it as an adult
Ed before I don't think I would have gotten
But I have now study the movie over again we've talked to the experts and we are going to
Break
This thing
Down
Because Roman
If you were paying attention
This movie has already taught you
Everything you need to know about commodity
And how to Corner the market
Now
Remember the orange juice
That was in the breakfast
Yes
Frozen concentrated Orange
Okay so in the movie The Duke Brothers
Have bribed the guy to get an advance copy of the
Neuropathy in his copy of the USDA
Orange crop report
Which of the totally real thing you stop reports come out every month to tell you how much of a
Commodity is out there
Now this if they know it in advance how many oranges are out there
They will then know whether the price is
Is going to go up
Remember understand
The crop report
Is going to say
But the supply of oranges
Is fine
Plenty of good cheer
Orange juice to go around at the normal day in the market
Except our heroes are going to trick
The Duke Brothers
They're going to pull the old switcheroo
So they slip the brothers
Fake
Crop report
A report that says
Oh my god there was this terrible Frost in Florida lots of dead oranges
Fake report would make
Any Savvy trade or no
The price of orange juice is going to go through the roof
Saudi Brothers think that
Get the supplies low prices
To go up
And they're willing to bet everything
They are so long
Ciroc
Are gyros
Billy Ray Valentine and Louis winthorpe
Former Trader gets screwed by the Duke
They know the truth
They know that the orange.
Why is fine
And they know
Did the prices going to go down
Silver Spring back roj expert Tom peroneus and we're going to watch this final scene together
And get a play-by-play
Are gyros
With their stolen Insider information
Our heroes are striking out onto the trading floor
Of the New York Mercantile
There's
My old place of employment
That's the World Trade Center office in that building right there that's that's where the exchange was
Inside
You see all the traitors in their ugly vest
Gathering on this large floor staring up at
The clock
Why don't you and it's pandemonium song
This is exactly what was like before computers
Maybe not quite so many people excited about frozen orange juice but still
Cuz make me nostalgic
4 floor base Trading
Now once again Roman get to keep all these things in your head if it's still excess
The Duke Brothers think there's going to be a shortage of Orange
Because according to their fake crop report Harvest
D-BAT
The prices should go up
They tell their guy their Floor Trader
We want you to buy as much OJ as you can in the instant pot
Don't worry if the price starts going up just keep
Play starts at $1.02 a pound
Prices to go up and thought their bidding up the price of orange juice
And the rest of the traitors started notice
They know something I can feel it.
Okay I got to tell you here Roman the actor who says
They know something I can feel it
That is Jack Davidson father of play nobody's very own Adam Davidson
And as I will say it really is
It really is the most critical line in the entire movie delivered by his father
That's
What is actually important for the plot because
Everyone starts to buy orange
The price was higher and higher dollar temp
A dollar $28 30
Everyone now thinks there is an orange shortage
The only problem
Is a
Of course we know it's the audience
It's based on a lot
The Billy Ray Valentine Louis winthorpe stand
Quietly
In The Madness of the trading floor round
They know the prices
Just too high they know it's getting higher
And they know it's about
Collapse
And so they want to do a little trick
Have heard of called Short Selling
They want to sell orange juice while the prices High
So
When the price gets 142
Dan Aykroyd looks like
And he screams
Is a good candidate for the second most important line of the movie with all respect to Jack Davidson and I totally
Mystic Ivory watch that movie again and again I have no idea
What you says they're what
Dan Aykroyd Seth
Do we have time explained
Sell 30 April 142
What you doing you selling 30 Futures contracts at a price of 142 per pound
And there's kind of a Feeding Frenzy driving the market higher but these guys
Have what they believe is the real information and they're selling it at rally
So selling it to the rally means you think the price is going to go down
Yes
I'm starting to get this
Billy Ray Lewis they're selling High they're selling orange juice
To everyone who thinks that is going to go even higher than that
Yet it's a really
Tricky
Find point
Here but I'm just going to say this
You don't have to own any orange juice
In order to sell it
Because
They're selling a promise they're selling this thing I will promise to deliver you orange juice in April that was April part of that
And you will pay me this large amount of money
Sometime in the future
Our Heroes have until then
Find some
Cheap orange juice and to fulfill their contract
If you heard the old saying like Buy Low and sell High
Yes that one I know
It's
Turns out though and this is the key to short side but keep the entire movie
Is you can do it the other way
You can sell High first
And then turn around quickly and Bi-Lo
Make a ton of money
Aunt
Our heroes are about
To get to buy extremely low because the crop report
The real crop report
Is about to come out
It's kind of crazy cuz everyone on the tree Ford to stop
Looking TV
Ladies and gentlemen
The orange crop estimates for the next
And I mean this is obviously a Hollywood moment prater's don't really just stare the TV and there's not a long awkward pause while the Secretary of
Culture
Come on
This is dramatic tension Robert
After calculating the estimate
From various Orange
Music States
We have concluded the following
The cold winter has apparently not affected the orange Harvest
That sound you hear is a bunch of people who just realize that they bet the wrong way but there's no shortage
The Dukes
And everyone who bought with them including Adams dad
Now own a lot of various
Expensive orange juice
Way too expensive
Another real proper Port is out
The price is dropping
It's 102
Plunging.
7264 everyone who bought high now once
The cell
And cut their losses
And it's driving the price down even further
And remember our heroes
New
This was going to happen
They sold a ton of orange juice at a crazy high price
And now the entire
Trading floor
Including the Duke Brothers
Guitar Floyd's begging
Excel them orange juice
Crazy chief
Estrostep
As the chaos clear
Other people have promised to buy orange juice from
At a price as high as 142
And now minutes later people are promising to sell orange juice to them
As cheap as $0.29 a pound
Billy Ray and Lewis
Get the pocket
It is a Epic Movie
Probably a significantly bigger one day move in the orange juice Market has ever had in it
Entire history
It surely fictional move but you know
And enough to enable these guys to retire in
We had our Commodities guys watchthisfree closely
But it's hard to estimate just how much money Billy Ray and Louis made on this
Scam
We see the price of orange juice futures
But not how many contra
That's all we know at the end of the movie is that
Brothers
They are Bank
Yeah they bought all of that orange juice when he was a crazy high prices they bought High
And if and when they sell it
It's going to be at
Terribly low price
They did the
The opposite
What you need to do to make money in the market
They lost nearly
400 million dollars
Tarzan the way trading works
I hear is probably pocketed most
And as far as villains
The Dukes they get their come up
At the end
Training Day
Turns out they borrowed a lot of that money they just lost
Margin Call gentlemen
You can expect the exchange all accounts to be settled at the end of the day
Without exception
You know perfectly well we don't have 394 million dollars in cash
Put the Juke brother seats on Exchange up for sale at once seized all assets of Duke and Dubuque
Randolph and Mortimer
And this dramatic
Crazy clearly Hollywood ending bad guys lose everything they get
Booted out of the rich
Positions in the market
This really happen sometimes according to Tom
He says people would borrow money
Bet it all on a market move
And when I went the opposite direction
Better pay app
Most Clearing Houses had
People who are referred to as leg-breaker
There they were like a real
Mobster you know leg Breakers but the they were the ones who would say alright you know the time to Pony up alright well you know we want your house
Yes we want your IRA
It would happen right there on the floor
That's a little over dramatize but it would happen that day or the next day another there wouldn't be much
The time lag
He said there's one more unrealistic
At least in today's world
Computer Trading
Took over the Commodities Market
That climactic scene
If they remade the movie today it would sound a lot like
This
Tall people staring at screens
Today you know it is this kind of obvious trauma is gone from
It would be a very quiet
Yes Klymaxx Brothers will be in their own private hell you know looking at a computer screen
Head buried in their hands
Tom perona says and this makes me very happy that people still bring up the movie when he says he trades in orange juice futures
And even among his fellow traitors as a sort of
Reverence
For the movie
The lines from the script I become part of the lingo of Commodities Trading
Definitely some of these these lines to become stock phrases like over the years especially the ocean Market I heard people say like sell Mortimer sell
El Amor De Marino
Duke and Duke is buying I've heard that too many times
Account it's definitely become part of the boj lure
It wasn't much OJ Lord
The stuff from Trading Places makes up a significant chunk of it
Did this whole scam with illegal
Are Hue hose basically stole inside information
Basically stole the crop report
They took all this money not just from The Dukes but
From the market and at the end
They're sitting on a Caribbean Beach
And I thought oh
They're on the Run
From the law
It turns out
At the time
Insider trading with knots
Strictly illegal in the commodities
China makes
Sense because there's so many people involved if you are a farmer training corn you have the ultimate inside information
How about corn and everyone in the agriculture business that's a little something that someone else doesn't
But
If the part with a steel across report that seems way way over the line
Yeti 75 the actual fact of
The suitcase would happen
Invite movie
You shouldn't steal which is illegal in every respect but the actual way in which they made money with stolen in
Information
That was legal
And I learn this because
When Congress was coming up with the banking
Reformed law Dodd-Frank
Can mm
They were
Debating what should be in the building
And it came up with the
Special provision
It seems that the chair of
The commodities
Future Trading
Gary Gensler
He said we need this thing
It is called
The Eddie Murphy
A rule that will make what happened to Trading Places
And it made it in
Dodd-Frank section 746 with Paisley says
Federal employee can't
Leaked information about the price of a commodity so that someone can make money off of it and a person who gets that leaked information
They can't use that to make money off of the market before this into effect
What Eddie Murphy
Billy Ray Valentine
And Dan Aykroyd
Lewis Winthrop the Third
What they did
Misappropriate information and then use it to Corner the orange juice Market
Was not
Got away with it got away with it
Oh that makes me so happy
99% invisible it Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Art
Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of May
Man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a small hearing. Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take
Laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars that you always catch up with us online at
99% invisible. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you'd
Days ago Wesley Stern in actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com