99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Downtown Oakland where we work
Is beautiful
But it doesn't cut a very distinct Skyline
Sure they're the cranes down by the port was a pretty face
But in terms of Downtown Oakland proper
It's pretty much just one building that defines the night-time Skyline
The Tribune Tower
He used to be the headquarters of the newspaper the Oakland Tribune
Paper moved up the street
So now the tower is an office building
That's producer Avery trufelman
The Tribune Tower which happens to be our office
Was the tallest building in Oakland in the 1920s
The 22-story tower
Top of the copper coated pitched mansard roof and a Sandy brick exterior
Really unique architecture
But that is not why it's the most distinctive building in Oakland
It's famous because it says
Tribune in gigantic orange red neon letters
Side of the building
And each side has a neon clock
Whitney on hands
And it's always on
Every night
Never flickering
Rarely the letter out
Because the Tribune neon has a secret weapon
On the top top floor
Of the Tower
Take the elevator to the 20th floor
There you'll see a door
Limited access
There's a slight of nerve
Up the stairs
You'll find a man
John Law
The keeper
Avineon
We are on the 20
Second floor of the Oakland Tribune Tower
What type of tiny
Office space in one corner and
The current owners have a wonderful Ranger with them and you know
Rent the place from them and I'll keep the
Neon signs going
Betrayed John Law is a sign installer and maintainer
And he is the one that keeps the Tribune Tower neon Blazer
Nowadays A wraparound neon clock on the 20th floor of a building is
Fairly rare
They're more in the 30s
4 days ago
Buildings with me with some signage on them in the n on the other almost all gone
The Tribune neon like many many neon signs and had periods of darkness and neglect
Most signed of the signs have been allowed to flicker out and die
But thanks to John and the owner of the Tower
The Tribune Neon
After a period of neglect has been on consistently
Since the late 90s
This is no small feat
Back of one of the
Ford Flex
John can repair some of the neon from within the tower
What about to get out of the face work on the neon on the letters I have to clip into I've
Full body harness
Antenna
Step onto the face of a letter
Will a butt hanging over a drop
Drop of something like 300 feet
But John loves height
And he loves me on
Let me know what other light sources
I don't have that
Kind of fuzzy otherworldly look to it that you get with me on him
Neon signage you have to be very beautiful in a lot of
People in the past considered to be cheesy and ugly and representative of some dying commercialism that they found
Unpleasant
People like philosophers SAS writing
Critiques
Of late capitalism
The use neon as a metaphor to express
Third Estate
Vijnana Howell that we all live in
Kristoff Rabat is the author of flickering light
History of Neon
Can I teach American studies at the University
Spotify
Germany
Professor ribbit
To study me on
History of America
A blinking in the night
And some American
Diner
Let you something if you're coming from the European background
It has a really kind of aesthetic power
It is a great metaphor of American culture even though it's not in the bag
Product
Press the gas neon was discovered in 1898 by a British scientist named Sir William Ray
It was a new gas
So we named it for the Greek Neos
Meaning new
Do you realize that if you run electricity through this new gas it would burn bright bright orange and red
But he basically said that school and then forgot about it moving on to find other gases and ultimately win a Nobel Prize
But Neon Lights as we know them
We're made and popularized by another account
Who is this
Frenchman
Play around with these
Neon tubes
That was a pretty good at business man I thought well we could do something with us
Made his first neon lights in 1910
Eventually quit chemistry to start a business
Call the Clyde Neon
It was the first to sell this new lighting
For Decor in for advertising
The first neon signs were up in Paris
The barbershop
The first shop ever tap in the outside
And then really spread around the city of Paris from Paris
Spread around the world may have been the father of neon lights but he was not a good guy
Yeah it's hard to fall in love with them
You trying to tell an Ardent follower if not
Did Germany
But neon swept the United States
It was brighter and more efficient than incandescent lighting
Americans were giddy with it
By 1924 the company Claude Neon
Had franchises in 14 major cities across the country
By the 1930s there were 20000 neon advertisement in Manhattan and Brooklyn
Most of them
Made by Claude Neon
Neon signs were the embodiment
As Prospero
Sony on Amazon respectable upscale spots
Movie Palace March
Opera
Nice places
It started with the charges and the
Fender for stores and then the car dealerships
Institutions and signified became the symbol
Of life in the big city
Play 40s
Peggy Lee as a singer in those days she had a song
Adidas neon enthusiasm at that. But the initial excitement fades
The popularity of downtown Wayne
People move to the suburbs
Cities grow dark
The Neon
Plickers
Years later turn 20 years down the road
Then it would take more cheap bars cheap hotels
And then
I have the CD
Equality
And then by and by trying to
This metaphor
People who you know more less critique
Loneliness in society
Best out of country and western
Getting drunk by the neon sign
And sending me on which used to be assigned luxury trains and a symbol of poverty in the rundown City
Neon is also hard to maintain in a broken neon sign is a bright
Flashing sign a Brokenness
And that's why we came to symbolize
Abdicate
Neon tubes are Madewell
They can last about 30 years
Sometimes up to 70
But they are glass
So they can break
And they're out there in the elements
The electricity can flicker out
What a neon sign goes out you can't just screw in a new tube or order up a cheap replacement
You would think
Like a machine made product right that there was some sort of big neon Factory that
Just trying it out
Neon assembly line
And that's really not the case
30 Craftsman whose safety sign
The band The Tubes with their hands
That's really just one person doing this person like Shawna Peters
A neon glass blower is not a glass blower it's really called neon tube bending
That's the trade
42 Bender
Jonah Peterson has been bending since 1987
She says color is a good way to decode these signs to know what's inside of them and what quality they are
Are the most basic
And the most popular
And that's like a reddish orange
And that's the
Standard neon red
That is
Short Neon gas
Does naturally burn fat color
And then there's blue neon also pretty basic
The cool secret about blue neon is that is not actually Neon gas its Argon gas brightened with a little mercury
Bowie still called them neon signs
And for a while almost all neon signs were just red and blue
Pier neon or argon Mercury
Clear tube
Then the industry came up with a way to make any color you want
There's a place for powder coating on the inside of the tube
Vendors can use tubes with different phosphorus on the inside of the tubes to create more colors than just red and blue
Use a fuchsia use a green a lime green go for lime green you know
Use of color
Dunwell is nice
Now just to be clear those neon beer signs at the bodega or the standard open sign
Candy and often are
Made on a massive scale in China
Those are still hand blown that's the only way to make neon
That's like one person makes only the letter e all day long another person makes
Only owes
And these signs are lower quality
Cheap signs for beer brands or generic open signs are often color with a coating of color plastic on the outside
Side of the glass tubes
Usually it's so cheap you can chip it off with your fingernail
But if you're looking at a sign over your local bar or hotel or sometimes even a neon sign over a chainsaw
If it's
Large and you haven't seen it anywhere else
It was probably painstakingly crafted
Probably logo
Neon tube Benders get glass from the manufacturer and 4 ft long tubes
And they draw out a pattern for how the bend and fuse it
You're bending the word Apple you never start with a
You have to map out in your mind
Where those curves are and how they're going to change direction and generally going to start somewhere in the center of the
That word
And work your way out
Ishawna has a number of different burners and tools to manipulate the tubes
Bell curve to hold the glass tube on either end over an open flame burner
When I'm using it it sounds like this
Shawna has only
Few seconds
The Ben put glass into a perfect shape
Before it hardens up again
So she has to act quickly
Imprecise
Sneezing is a tube benders
Nightmare Moon China processes the bed tubes with a machine called open barter
It's his whole process where he heats up the tubes really really hot and vacuumed out the impurities before filling the tubes with
Neon or argon Mercury
Infuses the electrical source to them
In Creed summary is the craft
Expensive
Difficult
And there aren't that many people who can make neon sign
And that is why
When they break that usually get replaced with LEDs
And
People in the LED industry will tell you it's so much brighter as well Randall and Homan and Albina are the publishers
And photographers of a book called
San Francisco Neon
Survivors and lost iPhone
All of these signs are part of our cultural heritage in San Francisco
Treasures we need to hang on to them Randall and Ali tours of some of their favorite neon around the
Many of the signs are defunct
For hangover businesses up there no longer affiliated with
This is my very favorite
Sign
This article of peacock has no fewer than 17
Concentric circles
Of neon and it's really a feet of tube bending
No the business is long gone
Kind of a miracle
But it's still here
San Francisco was once
Covered in neon
Look at an old picture of Market Street from the 1950s and you'll see it looks like the Vegas Strip
All aglow
Flashing lights
Then in the 60s there was a campaign to get rid of all that flash and beautify that part of town
Animals all those neon signs were removed
Around the rest of the city pretty regularly stops on Randall and Al's neon tour will just
Ventshade seats divorcing and awkward to bring it to a group around the corner to talk about a sign that
Doesn't exist anymore
Neon signs
If you're interested in photographing them or painting them
Do it as quick as you can because they can disappear overnight
And it's not just San Francisco
New York also went from having tens of thousands of signs in the 1970s to just a couple hundred today
Hong Kong is losing a lot of it's spectacular neon display
Signs change
With their cities
But in some spheres neon is having a little Revival
If Union vendors around are getting a lot of business
From high-end restaurants in
Hotels
Companies want quotes illuminated on their walls
Are artists who are commissioning me on pieces
Now a custom neon sign represents an emphasis on craftsmanship
InStyle
Tins with a bit of nostalgia
I'm sure this all sounds very artisanal and stuff
But this might just be the way that neon craft survive
At its core the ingredients are simple
Glass
Electricity
And gas from the air we breathe
Embedded into something
Spectacular
99% invisible with Presa sweet by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan crew Kolstad and Mero
But Alexis week to Jim Rizzo of neon Works in Oakland and Tom Downs author of walking San Francisco
Randall and Alice Photography book San Francisco neon survivors and lost icons is now in its third printing
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced at the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flat pocket
You can find the show and like us on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but you can listen to every single app
Episode of 99% invisible
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really
We jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com