99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
At some point in your life you probably encountered a problem in the built world something that was poorly designed and the
The fix was obvious to you
Maybe a door that open the wrong way or a poorly painted marker on the road
I know this is kind of stuff all the time even more so now after creating the show
I'm sorry if you do too because you listen to this show
And mostly when we see these things
Weed crumble on the inside
Do nothing
There are all sorts of reasons for inertia
We don't know how to fix it
It's not ours to fix we could get in trouble
That's producer David Weinberg
You might notice these little design flaws for years
Silently fuming until
One day
He called me and said
NOK we're doing it
It was early Sunday morning
August 5th
2001 Los Angeles Califor
Richard ankrom and a group of friends were on the 4th Street Bridge
Over the 110
Freeway
They were about to commit
Give me a high-profile dangerous situation
Natalie can I get arrested I could kill somebody really I was terrified of that
But let's back up
About 20 years prior
Richard ankrom an artist living in Orange County was driving north on the 110 freeway
Is he passed through downtown Los Angeles
He was going to merge onto another freeway to I-5 North
But he missed the exit got lost
And for some reason
It just stuck
Years later when Richard move to downtown Los Angeles he was driving on the same stretch of freeway where he got lost today
Decade before
We looked up at the Big Green rectangular sign suspended above I realize why I missed the exit
It's because it wasn't
Adequately signed
Bad wayfinding
The exit for the I-5 wasn't indicated on the green overhead sign
There was even a big open
Space weather should have been a blue and red Interstate Shield
And above that
It should have said north
It was clear to Richard
Caltrain
The California Department of Transportation
I made a mistake
Sir Richard and artist and sign painter decided to make the Interstate 5 North Shield himself and install it in the
The place he thought it should have been all along
High above the 110 freeway
He would call it an act of Guerrilla public service
All I do is to be
Certified public servant
Bored
Roxy to show
What you can do with artwork
You can put in plain sight have a functioning working thing for everyone to use
Richard started by studying LA freeway sign
Holding up Pantone swatches
Perfectly match the paint color
He dangled over Bridges to measure the exact dimensions of other sign
And most importantly
He downloaded the Necronomicon of
California road signage
The Mad kid
The mutcd the manual on uniform traffic control devices
Quotes
To provide for uniform standards and specifications for all official traffic-control devices in California
It's not a beach read
I have a horrible Lazy Sunday Afternoon read
All the specs are online so
People can
Bid on
Projects
Richard wanted his sign
To be built to the exact specifications
Caltrans
Which were designed to be read by motorists
Traveling at high
The
Shield with a v on it
3 ft
Roughly High
WYD
It's less than 1/8 of an inch barely needs
Stick woman
It's still pretty strong
And above that I put the word North
And that was all about 14 in by 5
And again I use the same typeface that was there in the same signs
The tried to match everything
Close as I could so it wouldn't be obvious
Caltrans didn't do it
Richard's brand new edition
Had to blend in
Perfectly with
The existing signage
Which have been collecting dirt and smog
For decades
I sprayed the whole thing with a really thin glaze
Gray
The knockdown
After he finished it Richard sign his name on the back of it
The black marker
Painter signing a
Canvas
Then came the next phase of the project
The installation
Cheap land
Decision of a bank
He bought a disguise
A white hard hat and an orange vest
So he'd look like a Caltrans worker basically looked at partes as best I could
Animal decal for a pickup truck meant to look vaguely official that said
Aesthetic deconstruction
The night before the installation
Richard drove out to the site
Hit some of his
Supplies to the BET to get to the next morning
My interview.
He took me to the spot
Show me
Stashed his stuff okay we're basically here
Right now the ivy isn't that fit but it was a lot thicker and I had
Basically behind that trade stashed the ladder and the signs and stuff
After he hit his things
Climbed a tree
Going through everything
I just heard a call myself down by being there and hanging around with it tonight
Richard was worried that he might drop
The sign
Or one of his
Tools part of the road below
Drivers going 60
Plus miles an hour would have no time to react
If something landed on the road in front of them
Or worse
Onto their car
That was a scary
Thing about hope
If somebody got hurt
Apple ID with that
And then the project that after scan it cuz
It would have defeated the whole
Idea
But despite some reservations
Richard was pretty confident
Call the Whole Thing Off
And he gone too far to turn back
And that brings us back to the morning of August 5th 2001
Richard did not act alone he asked several friends to film the insulation from different Vantage points
Amy inoue was one of the friends he Enlisted the film
6 a.m. or 7 a.m. on Sunday morning
It was 10
Because we all thought we were going
Richard had chosen the Sunday morning to put up the sign knowing that there would be little traffic and The Morning Light Rising
In about the skyscrapers would be just right for filming
What he hadn't anticipated was that couch ranted also picked that morning to do work on the same stretch
Yes they happen to be doing some other work
On the freeway
Just salad
That's fine
When they saw the Caltrans workers
They thought about turning back
But I had surmised after all this is
It's pretty large city there be more than one sign
My assumption was that think the other guy was
Richard Park his truck
When everyone was in position with their cameras
He went to work
The hardest part was getting over the razor wire
With the ladder
Once he was up on the catwalk
Delete 30 ft above the highway
You started screwing in the new sign
Careful not to drop any screws
On the cars below
Halfway into it
We just
Don't like okay he's going to get away with
Amazing or what
The whole thing took less than
30 minute
As soon as it was up
Richard pack up his letter rushed back to his truck
Blended back into the city
I think we all went out to
Super relieved
Only a small group of people knew that the Interstate 5 shield with the word North hanging above the 110 freeway
Was it forgery
He didn't say to us.
Don't tell anyone
So are
Friends on new whip
Happy
But it never
Tweaked-out
For a while
For nine months the secret stayed within a small community
And then Richard sprengeri
Repeat the story
What the hell Gary why can't you be cool just be cool Gary Richard Secret
Without the Caltrans
And the Press from the fake magnetic sign on his beat up blue truck to a work order proclaiming rush
But he did is against the law to capture and says it has no plans at all to file charges against him actually found out what
What happened apparently they send a crew out there to inspect
Richard was hoping to get it signed back from Caltrans after they took it down
He was thinking he would hang it in an art gallery but Caltrans didn't take the sign down at past
The Caltrans inspection cuz that's really that the final
Cast of how am I how good the artwork is
It stayed up for 8 years
9 months and
14 days I believe
It's not exactly a coup
Pretty close to that
An interviews about the incident with other news organizations
Caltrans didn't exactly
Condone rich
Handiwork
They're pretty kind about it
Here's the Caltrans spokesperson at a time
And in fact you did such a good job that I'd like to offer him a job application
More than eight years after Richard son when he got a call from a friend who noticed some workers taking it down
Richard contacted Caltrans to ask if he can have his signed back by time I tracked him down
It already been crushed into a bale
Going for China
Who knows what it turned into could be a waffle iron by now
After Caltrans took down Richard
Consign they replaced it with a brand new one
But this time
They Incorporated his ideas into the new design
They out of the 5 north and the shield not only
That's fine
But the two additional one up the road
A little epilogue
Richard's highway sign is a happily Ever After Story the sign worked
People appreciated it no one got hurt thankfully
Even Caltrans was
Really pretty nice about the whole thing
There's another gorilla sign story out of New York City a group that calls itself
The efficient passenger project has been hanging signs in New York subway station
To tell people
Where they can board the train to make the most efficient transfers
The project is not at all affiliated with the Metropolitan Transit Authority
But the signs look just like MTA signs
Black with white helvetica lettering
They say things like
Bored here for best transfer to the 4 5 and 6 trains
Or board here for best transfer
F&M train
It's the kind of knowledge that you build up over time as a regular Subway Rider and this gorilla sign maker is offering
Bring it to everyone
I know some of the plot of the signs
Not all New Yorkers
Are pleased these are secrets some say
That people should have to earn they will unbalanced the cars they say
Leave signage to The Experts
The MTA for their part
Is taking down the signs as fast as they go up
MTA spokesman Kevin Ortiz
Toeless in an email that quote
Posting of the signs
Is considered an act
Vandalism
Point being if you decide to undertake an act of gorilla Public Service just know it mean
99% invisible with produced this week by David Weinberg with Katie mingle the same Greenspan Avery troubleman and me
We are project 91.7 kalw san francisco and produced at the offices of arcsine in r
Architecture and Interiors firm damn good one in beautiful Downtown Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can find this show and like a show on Facebook will all on Twitter and Instagram a reruns a Tumblr I make a Spotify
Playlist of 99 songs
99pi.org
Radio TuneIn
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com