99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
There's a subgenre of
Kid videos on YouTube that are named things like
My toddler Master the iPhone &
Baby Works iPad perfectly
Some of these video titles also say things like must see
In all caps
But like all things that same IC
It's not true
You can totally do without seeing these videos
Oh you want to change the background
Blue
Mostly it's a bunch of babies drooling and poking and iPhones
These tiny drooling iPhone stalkers are actually able to execute commands
Open up programs they want to use
Play games and take photos
And despite what we parents believe
It isn't because our kids are smart
Smart manager
Smart picture seems pretty smart
That's what these are Louisa back
The mostly it's just that iPhone
Actually computers in general
I just incredibly easy to use
Today's user interface in the modern computer is what I called Grunt and point
It's
Very primitive communication
So that's why I call it grants
That's Christina engelbart
Her father Doug engelbart
How to vastly different vision for what computers could be than these super simple devices that toddlers
Doug engelbart division required us to actually
Learn stuff
In order to really
Push the envelope of
Of human Effectiveness an intellectual effectiveness
You don't want to be confined to just a very small vocabulary of Grants
NCLEX
So you want to actually have a full language
Doug engelbart was a Pioneer in his field
And his main goal wasn't to make computers that toddlers could
He wanted them to be as powerful as possible
And imagine that if we took the time to learn how to use their devices
If we became fluent in their language
Their potential to make us smarter more efficient humans would be huge
Doug engelbart who passed away in 2013
Grew up during the Great Depression on a small Farmstead near Portland Oregon
Do-it-yourself is a radar technician in the Navy during World War II
He was a West Coast Optima
Who studied at UC Berkeley and was influenced by the 1960s counterculture
Would you later had his own lab he made his researchers attend personal development seminars what they talked about
Feelings of Life philosophies
It is time Engelbert ideas for lofty and unique
Idealistic
My father was considered a coupe
I knew what he was not widely respected
Or even widely known
Engelbart's name may not be widely known
But if you work at a computer you use one of his inventions everyday
I don't know why they call it a mouse
Sometimes I apologize
Started that way
We never to change
Best single bars showing off his revolutionary invention in 1968
Computer mouse
Engelbart's Mouse
3 buttons
Do you would have added more if he'd been able to fit.
End it was meant to be used in conjunction with another device
It's called the key set
Which looks like a small five key piano one key for each finger and was controlled by your left
This device over here
We always have to
Justifying
Explain it
Provides
For you
The one-handed football
What you can do with a keyboard
The idea was that with your left hand on the key set in your right hand on the mouth
You could do almost everything that you would need to do without moving your hand back to the keyboard including
Typing out characters of the alphabet and executing shortcut commands
The beyond the shortcut commands that we use now with a keyboard
Engelbart's Mausam Ki set opened up a larger vocabulary
We could use when communicating with a computer
So
So we could do like my dad
Dad
Your left hand
I visited Christina engelbart at the dog and go bite Institute
Which is an educational Consulting NC
Petition that aim to promote his ideas
It's house at Stanford Research into
Keytruda Menlo Park
The very place where her father and his
Collaborator Bill English
Built the first
Prototypes
Mouse in 19
Christina showed me the key set and I tried to get a feel for what it would be like
Type my name with
So there 26 letters to the house
That and what's the
So what
Number one
I mean you can go
Basically eat
Finger and the key
He said is assigned numerical value
My thumb is assigned to one
And my pointer to
So that one is three I need to press down my thumb and pointer because they add up
Then we map numbers
2 letters
Exactly
Right
With each letter map to number aiding one you can imagine that it gets harder once you reach the middle
Letters of the alphabet
Yeah I have no idea of the top of my head what number of the alphabet o is
Right well there's a chart you can hang up next to a desk to reference
What number each letter is
But the point is all of this take
Subtract
Still I could imagine how with a lot of repetition you could get fast
Doug engelbart felt his mouth and key said would allow us to communicate with computers more fluidly and the fish
Efficiently you know it sounds pretty hard to learn as a single bite was against user-friendly devices
But you just believe that if we were willing to put time into learning computers they could do so much more fat
He thought they could help us communicate and collaborate to become better humans and more effective
So that meant how can you make humans in groups and organizations be
Dramatically more effective how effective can you make them is there a limit
Maybe the idea that computers can help us collaborate doesn't sound that crazy now but Engelbert was working at a time
When most people thought of computers at Giant calculators
Their purpose was
Automate tasks
And in my father's Paradigm why would you ever automate
How you do things now a computer affords a whole new way of working
What way would you work if you weren't
Limited to the old technology
In the early sixties
Angle backup funding to start his own life or he could have
Experiment with all of his ideas
Is lab hosted one of the
3 centers of the arpanet
Which is one of the
The key ancestor
Pictures of the internet
Engelbert actually helped invent the internet
And throughout the sixties and early seventies
Is group building Tire online collaboration
And included video conferencing and collaborative text
Editing
Curious presenting those things and what
Became known as the mother of all demos
I need to know what terminal you are on Bill
Okay I'd like to have him see my texts
Cancel the special thing if I table 13 will switch
Switch
Over Sonia's display he sees my text
Executed
And sure enough it does
But what's that
Running around
Well he's okay my texts he like have something to say about it
The reason people call it the mother of all demos is that in it
Engelbart show the world so many revolutionary ideas
The mouse of course
But also a bunch of things that didn't catch on until decades later
The time most people hadn't even heard of personal Computing let alone the internet
And here was Doug engelbart demonstrating the ancestor
Pictures of tools
Like Skype
Screen sharing in Google doc editing
In the 1960s
Despite all of this by the early 1970s
Engelbart's lab ran out of funding to continue his research
Much like is three-button Mouse and key set his other ideas were seen as interesting but complicated
And not particularly marketable
And meanwhile another computer Visionary had under the
One that unlike the ganga Bart you've probably heard of
A guy by the name of Steve Jobs
Steve Jobs was never satisfied
With the first of the second Raven 210
Pass and making something simple
That's Larry tesler Apple from 1980 to 1997 S&P and chief scientist
How simple you made it he would come and say that's pretty good but I think you can make it simpler than that
And then he would leave us like will how
Once in a while he would make a suggestion but usually he just walked away
And we had to figure out a way to make it simpler
One thing jobs wanted to simplify was engelbart's Mouse and key set
Jobs had first seen the mouth and key set at Xerox Parc
Which was The Cutting Edge Computing research facility at the time
In the 1970s when engelbart's lab started to disband
A lot of engelbart's researchers and some of his prototype
Ended up at Xerox Parc
Jobs
Complicated to use he dismissed the case at all together
Do Apple employees saying that the mouse Apple was developing with only have one button
Years Apple held onto it's one button Mouse
Even as competitors developed
Two-button mice
He was very attached to it considered including engelbart's
Keyset companion to the mouse
It was too costly clunky and complicated to learn
An apple we wanted people to come into the store
Look at the software try it out figure it out
In the first
2 minutes
And and plunk down a credit card and take the computer home
And
It wasn't okay to say will take it home
And work on it every day for several hours a day and a six months you'll be really good at it
And suddenly
Computers were for everyone
Even better
Beautiful that's a beautiful
And that it's helped a lot of people
That's Christina engelbart again
Problem is
Gwen
That's
The whole mission
Christina thinks that when we prioritize simple user-friendly devices over more complex learnable ones
We limit ourselves
And we might miss out on important ideas
And for a while at least
Steve Jobs did exactly that
When job showed engelbart the brand new Apple computer Christina said that her dad responded like this
My dad said will G1 about
Communication to
You know today
Networking
In other words
Document sharing video chatting and all the collaborative stuff that was excited about
Brindle Bard collaboration was the most important thing
Computers needed to connect
Pepper jobs
At this point anyway
Simplicity whiskey
And Steve said oh no we did
That you don't need that
Everything you need to be on your desk
Is a personal computer is
Is all you need
At the root of apples
Success lies the world's first personal computer
The Apple II
Small inexpensive simple-to-use
The first computer and individual could take out of the box
Plug-in
Dandruff
Bringing Computing down to a personal level
One person
One computer
That was paid from the 1980s
Free promotional video for Apple
Here's jobs in South
Talking about missing the importance of network
When it was first demonstrated to him at Xerox Parc in 1979
100 Alto computers all network using email
Excetera excetera I didn't even see that
I was so blinded by
The first thing they showed me which was the graphical user interface
I thought it was the best thing I've ever seen in my life
Of course jobs eventually came around to networking but I take Christina engelbart's point
Are the designer being married to some pussy
We might also be limited by Simplicity as user
Example my dad used to like to go and I think this was really appropriate is the difference between a tricycle in a vice
So
Anybody can get on a tricycle
Especially if you see somebody else ride it
You know
You can just get on and ride it
You don't need any
Training
Do it and figure it out
But that's fine if you're just going to
Go around the block
A couple of times
You trying to go up a hill a tricycle is a pretty bad way to go
You want to bike with gears
Can you learn how to balance tear in chain gears because it gives you a lot more power
You can cover a lot more steep ground
A lot of people
I made the point that
My dumbing-down computer is so much that is easy for anybody to learn
We made it so that
Most people don't
Go to the trouble of learning something that
Could
Give them more
Leverage
More power with their computer
And I think that's a fair criticism
That's Larry tesler again
He agrees that early on Steve Jobs Overlook Network
They also thinks that jobs was right
To push person
If
You make it as we did an apple
So that
Just about anybody
Can do
Things that they do everyday on on a computer or on a smartphone
Then
You giving them the only opportunity
But they're probably ever have
Benefit from
That power
Doug engelbart might look at the world now and say they're all on tricycle
Spaceship Beyond bicycle
Nothing is
Are tricycles have gotten pretty awesome
They become so powerful and so well-designed that were actually able to get around without ever learning how to ballet
Balance on two wheels or shift gears
Maybe that's the world we're living in today
When were a lot of engelbart's ideas
Come to fruition and almost anyone can access
Including you
Your mom and Grandad and yes
Pretty soon
You're drooling iPhone poking toddler
But I think Christina would say there's still more we could learn
And a simple interfaces have sort of hidden that path
Is hung a curtain over the complex
It's tough to keep us from having to face
And in doing so they keep a stranded in Grand and
Appointment
My dad always said for sure easy to learn easy to use
Fine for the beginner
Once you do something for a year or two or five why would you sit down and use the computer the same
What year did the very first day UK
Okay man that's
You need to have a clear stream lionpath
For advancing into a much more sophisticated
Holistic way of interacting
With a computer
Maybe the question is what kind of users do we want to be
The best design may not always be the one that's user-friendly at first sight
It might be the one that allows is the degree of virtuosity if we think investing the time is worth it
Or another words it's the one that helped us
Switch from tricycle riding to bicycle riding
So that if we want to
We can go up some really big hills
99% invisible was produced this week by Louisa back with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman in
And me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in Ark
Architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
We canceled it a ton of people who are very generous with their time for this episode so special thanks to Mark Webber
The Computer History Museum
Theory bardini Bjorn Hartman in Eugene Eric
Kim Joe Blaylock James yurchenko Glenn Fleishman Harvey laitman Martin Hardy
Carolyn Rose Laura oberg Wesley Willett Fred Turner and Bryan Crabtree for their help researching the story
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show and like us on Facebook I tweeted Roman Martinez follow me at one of those two places you'll be aware of all the talks and I meant that
Serbia coming up
We've cool Tumblr at our Spotify playlist will make you feel like you're living inside of a 99 Pi episode but I agree
YouTube for the entire world of 99% invisible. Org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com