99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is the American dream
Freedom on wheels
I know the movie Babe
Traveling on time-saving super highways
Futurama
The 1940s 50s and 60s were the Golden Age of road travel
Cars have become cheap and roomy enough to carry families comfortably for hundreds of miles
Bitter state highway system it started to connect the country smaller roads into a vast Nationwide Network
Finally Torres could make their way from New York to California with the windows down and the
Wind in their hair
See the Grandeur of America along the way we have become
Motorized Mobility
I never dreamed of before
But of course this freedom and Mobility wasn't available to everyone
That's a brand new producer and splash of cold water Delaney Hall
Because in 1956 the year that Federal funding made the interstate highway system possible
Jim Crow
Was still the law of the land
Racial segregation was enforced by law
And had been since shortly after reconstruction
In many parts of the north the codes were enforced in practice
And these codes could make a simple road trip really complicated for black Travelers
How is this
Is that a good level it's are you picking me up well there
This is Curtis Gray
Hey my name is Curtis Graves and I'll go in 1938 so I'm a little older than most of the people who are listening to this
Curtis would eventually become a Texas State representative
And then he'd go on to work at NASA
And then he become a photographer
What is a kid he grew up in the segregated South
And for many years
His parents tried to Shield him from that reality
I've often said that both my mother and father were the best lies that I knew
For instance we sat in the back of the bus
Because it was cooler there
We rode in the front of the train because
Are you could get off quicker
Wish that upstairs in the movie because
You had better seats in the upstairs
Of course that ruse can last
And by the time Curtis with a college senior in Houston Texas in the mid-1950s
He was fully aware of what it meant to be a black person living under Jim Crow
There's one experience in particular
That stands out in his mind
He was just 21 years old and getting ready to drive to a college meeting in Waco about 3 hours Northwest of Hughes
Degree to take a couple of acquaintances
They happened to be white women but I said to myself I might be in for some
Difficult times here
But you know I had to sold you on
To get to Waco Curtis had to drive to a stretch of East Texas that was Notorious in those decades for racial
Violence oh yeah those communities pretty bad
Around dusk The Travelers got hungry so they pulled over at a Roadside Diner
As soon as we got in the front door
The guy said I'm sorry but you can't come in here
We don't serve black people at all
So the three of them went back outside and Curtis devised the plan
They try another restaurant
Right across the street
I said to them the two of you go in get a table
And after you seated and the waiter or waitress comes up to you
Tell them that you have a boy
That's driving you
And that you want to know whether he can you can bring him in to eat
So the women walked inside and they asked the waitress of Curtis could come inside to join them
And ladies hit of course
No problem at all
So as long as I was that boy
And their driver I could eat
With them at a table
Vienna Restaurant
But if I were equal to them I could not
This kind of humiliation on the road was routine and had been going on for decades
Many people wrote Into the NAACP around this time
Describing experiences
Just like curtis'
Don't make him CERN
Before starting my recent vacation trip to several eastern states
Yes sir I am a member of the NAACP
Anna Nicole
Incident occurring on January 1st at a gulf service station in Macon Georgia
I went to the restaurant to refresh my cell
Then found a vacant table
10 minutes passed and no one came to serve
He informed me that the restroom for the color was in the back
It seems to me
Dealer should not be permitted to sell gas and oil
And not provide these Comforts for us also
Some Travelers would drive all night instead of trying to find lodging in an unfamiliar and possibly dangerous town
They packed picnics they didn't have to stop for food
Some people would even carry portable toilets in the trunks of their cars
Knowing that there was a good chance they'd be turned away from roadside restrooms
But since 1936
A guy named Victor Hugo green I've been trying to help with some of these problems
Make life easier for thousands of black motorist
State-by-state they've been putting together a travel guide
Listings of restaurants hotels and Service Station
That would welcome African American Travelers
He called it the Negro motorist
Green book
The green book
For short
Victor green who died in 1968 lived in Harlem New York during the height of the Harlem Renaissance
His apartment was not far from Duke Ellington
His office would eventually be situated near small Paradise
A famous nightclub
Richard and have the most obvious background
For starting a travel guide
Begin working tourism
He wasn't a writer
He was a mailman in Hackensack New Jersey
But he kept hearing stories about discrimination on the road
So he would
Go do his route in Hackensack New Jersey come back home and work on the green book at night
Compiling these addresses typing them up and put them in a book for
This is Calvin Alexander Ramsey
Playwright author and filmmaker
And years ago
Calvin started researching the history of the green book
He learned that the green book wasn't really the first guide of the
Science
In fact
Victor may have gotten the idea from Jewish travel
Because the Jewish Community was also having
Issues on the open road
It's a lot of places saying restricted
And it was a cold war
For Gentiles only
When Victor published his first green book it just covered New York
And he heard from around the country from other carriers and other people saying we really need this Nationwide
But it wasn't that easy to gather information from across the country back then
Long distance phone calls were expensive
And that Calvin says
Is when Victor green realized
That being a mailman
Was his secret superpower
There were African-American let it carries all of United States at the
This time we talked about 1936
And so he knew about you know
The relationships that the mailman have with their
Homeowners or apartment dwellers Delivery Man mail so just like today the mailman is part of the
The community
So Calvin says Victor tapped into the snap
Spreading the word about his guide through the National Alliance
The postal and federal employees
A letter carrier Union
Calvin says postal workers across the
The country scouted potential Green Book locations and their cities and towns
He says it's some even asked families they delivered to
If they'd be open to hosting Travelers in their home
And if they agreed then
They will send the information to Victor Green in Harlem
Victor was able to get a feel for us
Of letter carriers
Who are all over the country
Acquire material and names and addresses and businesses for him
Where were there was a black mailman
You got a green book salesman
Call recruiter
Pretty quickly the green book caught on
Businesses many black-owned began getting in touch with Victor
Hoping to advertise and hoping to be listed
Black newspapers signed on as sponsors
Victor eventually retired from his job as a letter carrier
And started working on the guy full-time
Even opened an Affiliated travel agency
Github Torres deranged traps
But still there was the challenge of distribution
How to get the Guide into the hands of Travelers who needed it
That happened in a few ways
United States travel Bureau signed on to help out
And then there would be more informal Networks
Spell churches
Pullman porters the Urban League NAACP
The Masonic lodges
There was a very wide very distribution
Process in place for these green book
And there was an important corporate sponsor to
A big one
Gas-X extra fine
DSS
Make
The Motoring
So also known as Standard Oil and now known as Exxon Mobil
Was one of the fuel oil companies back then then actively pursued Black customers they franchise their stations to
African American operators
And he had a black representative on staff
James billboard Jackson
Who helped plays Green books in many of those stations
As well as the white on one
Also may have done this out of a sense
The fairness and equality
Johnny Rockets
Who founded Standard Oil in 1870
I married into a family of abolition
Who were part of the Underground Railroad
And he voted for Abraham Lincoln.
And the day
But I probably did it for another reason
Until money honey
It has to do with money
Remember Curtis who had the crappy experience driving across East Texas
Just had operated
One of the first black-owned Esso stations in New Orleans
Where Curtis was born and raised
It was called the Bootsy and Buddies
The economic logic of stocking the green book was
Pretty simple he says
If you want black people to buy your fuel
Why don't you give them an opportunity to see that they can travel
And find places to stay
While they're on the road traveling
The Curtis's dad kept
A shelf of green book
Or his customers
You know if somebody came in and said no
Nobody on me
I'm thinking about taking a trip to Chicago my dad would say well
Yep do you know where to stop between here and Chicago and other person would say no say what happened
Green book will tell you
And it gave you a sense
Security
Into the green book came to cover listings in all 50 states and even some locations in Canada the crib
Being in Mexico
They printed about 15000 copies a year
Wintergreen head change travel for thousands of African-American Torres
He wrote in a 1956 introduction to the guide
Now things are different
The Negro Travelers
Depend on the green book for all the information
This guy has made traveling more popular
Without encountering
Embarrassing
But as a civil rights struggle continued
Some people began to question the value
The green book
Black people many of them began to feel that this was
Accommodating to Jim Crow
Susan ruhe is a professor of history at Brigham Young University
And she says that the green book begin to seem a little out of
Step with the times
It really took on an overtly political Town especially in its early days
And they were actually other black travel guides
Published around the same time the Dead
One called travel guide
Princeton
Travel guide listed where the n-double-acp
CP chapters were
In each City
They were much
More attuned with civil rights
Much more political tone
Eventually the n-double-acp made it clear
And the n-double-acp said what we're striving for it we're striving for integration
And so that's their stand
Sheepey built
Based on race
An ended Jim Crow
Around this idea
Of total integration
In fact when the n-double-acp testified during the debate over the bill
They drew on all those letters they received about discrimination on the road
Appeal to that vision of the iconic family road trip
The freedom to explore America by car
Roy Wilkins
Defective Secretary of the n-double-acp
Spoke before the Senate Commerce Committee
In 19 6
E3
As soon as Congress gets out they're all going to
Heading to the station wagons and go back to their home just
Its July
In Washington
It's really hot
Will confess to send it to imagine what it might be like to travel as a black person
Would you like me to read what Roy Wilson said
How far do you drive each day
Where and under what conditions can you and your family eat
Where can I use a restroom
Can you stop driving after reasonable day behind the wheel
I must you drive until you reach a city
We're relatives or friends will accommodate you and yours for the night
Will your children be denied a soft drink
Or ice cream cone
Because they are not white
Please appealing to them and they're at the most basic level of Their Own
Love for their own family
And Susan thinks this may have been one of the things that help
The Bell
By Framing the narrative
Of civil rights as a
Family Travel narrative
They were able to convince the
The Senators
About 4
In 1964 President Lyndon Johnson signed the bill into law
The Civil Rights struggle was not over then it's still not over today but for Victor green it became clear at some
Some point that is green book had a limited shelf-life
He wrote in the introduction to one of his guy
There will be a day sometime in the
The near future
This guy
Will not have to be
That is when
We as a race
Privileges
United States
Ensure enough
2 years after the Civil Rights Act passed
The green book published its last Edition
Who actually could you just described where we
We're at the
Public Library downtown the central branch in Los Angeles
And I were down in the bowels
Force down
Underground
And history and genealogy Department
And you have a stack
Of books are in front of you what are the who they are Green books
They're just little Jewels I mean I just
Spas with
This kind of
Good energy that I do
I just feel like all my God they're at
Actually here
It's amazing
That's amazing
Can Daisy Taylor is a photographer and a cultural documentarian
The guy she's holding her small
Baby Baden
By 5 in
They have green covers
Each with a different destination featured
And there are pages and pages of listings inside
There were Beauty parlors
Barber shops
Taylors
Taverns or nightclubs
It was really a social network it was anything you might want to do in that town
And the resources that were available to you
Can they see has been traveling the country
Documenting old green book locations from California to Oklahoma to New Mexico
Many establishments are now run by people who don't know much
Anything about the police's history
Some of the buildings are gone and what's left is just an empty lot or a patch of grass
Even need original copies of the guide are rare now
Smithsonian bought one at auction recently
For $22,500
Wow
Look in your if you're listening to
Can you know your parents you don't live during
Jim Crow look in your attics and see you might have
If 20 + thousand-dollar
Guide
$20,000 is a lot of money
But back in 1936 when the green book first appeared and could be purchased for $0.25
By The Travelers who needed it the most
It was arguably
Even more
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Delaney Hall with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman
Instead to refuse f&me Roman Mars
Thanks to backstory with the American history guys for the recordings of the letters to the n-double-acp
Red by Alicia Floyd
Steven Tolliver and Leslie telephone area
And I'll listen
Do play the part of Victor green thanks also to Orlando Gonzalez at the National Association of letter carriers
And Jackie Moore
The National Alliance of Postal and federal employees
Define a link to Ken Daisy Taylor's images of old green book locations and learn more about Calvin Ramses film about
The green book
Visit 99 Pi. Org
We are production of 99% invisible ink a project of kalw San Francisco of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
If you visit the brand new 99 piaa.org you'll find non audio articles with all the things you love about
E9pay without me prattling on
I'm really excited that we get to take on topics that are either to visual for the show or require such a quick turnaround that we did
And put it into the audio show production schedule
But I also need to pay for it and we're trying out this play at access to the marketing funds
Imma cool
Design my new company and like supporting original and fun journalism about design for just pennies of you
Go to the sponsors page under the about menu at 99% invisible. Org
They will be the best other people's money you've ever spent
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer
Composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloat
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Instagram and Spotify but the best way to
Explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
Is to go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about
The body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Steve your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com