99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars a couple of years ago we presented a story.
Play Peregrine Andrews about how certain sounds like the sound of skis on a cross-country track or hook
Horse racing track or Faked on Sports Broadcast it ended up being
Provocative episode over mainly because people really taken aback by the notion that any part of a sporting event
Might be fact that episode was just a small excerpt of a much longer documentary called the sound of sport
And we got a number of requests from the audience over the years asking where they could hear the entire piece and today my friends
We are going to present it to you in its full Glory this is a fascinating Exquisite Libre
Deep deep dive Amazon in sports broadcasting
I've never even considered before that's just one of the reasons why I love it keep in mind that was originally broadcast in twenty eleven
What's after the World Cup in South Africa and before the London Olympic Games in 2012 so just the place
Proper Sports history contact
This is the sound of sport produced by Peregrine Andrews for fallen tree Productions and presented by Dennis Factor
I like listening to sports
I can close my eyes I can hear every single one
In my head
It's my belief that people have
Ingrained in them a memory of certain sounds
And if that sound is not
Field then the Mind knows that there's something wrong
There is an expectation of what foot
Ball sounds like
And it certainly wasn't vuvuzela
Plastic horns who's noise have been driving people mad
Just that continuous hum
Which action drowned out all of the meaningful noises
The sounds of the World Cup in South Africa in those damn vuvuzelas
How many people this was the first time they'd really thought about house Porsche sound
Please what I spend my life thinking and dreaming about
I'm Denise Baxter and I designed the sound of sports for television
Another 20 years I work exclusively on the Olympics
As their staff sound designer and engineer
I decide how to capture each event sonically so that it brings as much drama and excitement into the home is possible
Play getaway pause time Palace got a very good stop going to Texas and gearing up for London 2012
Is going to be a big job
I'll be using a team of 350 sound mixers
About 600 sound technicians in close to 4000 microphone
I told you
Bush born in Atlanta Georgia 1954 and essentially I think that I
I've been a sound person my entire life
When I was about eight or nine years old my dad bought me a cassette recorder and I was recording everything that I would
Going to the bathroom my mom would be on the toilet
And I'll just pop into the microphone start recording her
Michael had a restaurant and I washing off a lot of dishes when I was 14 years old enough money to buy a real drill
Recorder a thousand dollars at the time it was a staggering sum in 1968
This is the size of a big suitcase
Couldn't drive so I used to hitchhike and carry that recorded to the churches and to the high schools and record just about anything that I
I could possibly record
I was a veteran so I went to school on my GI Bill and study economics
Taught me a lot about borrowing money
So at the end of my college degree I had done my final papers on the recording studio and had convinced the back
To lend me the money
And before I knew it I was several hundred thousand dollars in debt
That recording studio dream is a misguided dream
You going to make your own music and live happily ever after and then all the sudden you
Struggling to get people things that you don't want to record and frustrated with the situation
What does minutes away from the first event on the ESPN schedule
1982 I found another and more profitable use them all your skills at the newly-formed sports television channel
ESPN
Set of musicians now is capturing the sound of car racing
Tennis
Baseball football whatever they sent my way
Your majesty
I humbly ask you to the
Where are the Olympic
Games
Open
That was the first Olympics to be televised by the BBC
The fewer than one hundred thousand homes had television the time
Tavolo V
Best way to test false negative
And it's erections count toward the Finish Alexander sweet and wild in Spanish
Michigan here there is a much more than commentary to be hurt
Baptist and seventh nankivell
My own relationship with the Olympics began in 1992 when I was off with the first full-time job as a sound center
I went back and listened to every single sport
Trying to understand
Why we were covering the sports the way that we were what sounds
Were there
And
What sounds were really missing and why
I came from music I came from a recording studio and I want to apply those techniques and standards
To the live world
And one of the first things we implemented the Olympics with a lot more clothes Michael
This is where you put the microphone as close as possible to the Sound Source
If you use this technique you need a lot of microphone because each microphone can only capture a little piece of the whole picture
But you get more detail and definition
And a hell of a lot better sound
The parallel bars in the uneven bars for the women's gymnastics
When you put the microphones
That close to the athlete
You hear the flexing of the barn
You hear the breathing you can even hear the rustling of the clothing
My dad was variant
I rock and roll and he goes okay
I was just thrilled
Welcome Christmas mornings he got me a guitar and it was an acoustic guitar with a Chet Atkins record
And I love Chad axes to this day
What's the next 2 years after I got the acoustic guitar all I was trying to do
Was make it louder
National Lacrosse a contact microphone which is a device a microphone that you
You actually can stick right onto the top of the guitar to amplify
It takes up the actual vibrations of the wood and consequently the sound of the guitar
30 years later
I'm looking at gymnastics
The balance beam
Is a synthetic
Resin type
Material that athletes they balance on they do summer songs they do
All kinds of routines on top of it
And I mean to balance beam assembly that has a certain resonance in there
Is it we cannot
Hear that someone probably has never heard
Is that a new texture that we should put into the mix and by the time we put
The contact microphones on there
He gave a new level of depth
Because the contact microphone hears the vibration in the entire bar
Giving the athlete on the bar and getting the death
And the movement
Roger Federer
Here we go
In 2008 the team responsible for the sound of the Wimbledon Men's final was nominated for bafta award
I love atmosphere
That is
My job as far as I'm concerned
It's the atmosphere
What you generate
Makes people
Beaver
I'm bilston and I'm leasing supervisor
Who did the
Sound Foley 2008
Wimbledon Tennis finals
Against
That's the sound of a moving
Hush
The bouncing of the bull
On the course
Atmosphere
Is
Sort of thing that I am trying
To bring into the home
When everybody is
Fully expect
Something brilliant to happen
Call Tina
Does lots of microphones on the court
Basically the
Courses covered
Very nice small
Stereo mic
Stuck on the back of the course
Just above the
Simple on judges
Head
So they gave me cold is an interesting moment when they Shout
And there are other Motrin stores around
The course
Youku
Back of the clouds
Buff the crown to get a general atmosphere of the
Inside Lacrosse
Raven devault
Call Tina
And
Hugh
Will no doubt have seen them close-ups
Should I wouldn't lie
Contesting saw sitting
Are the sons of the cheddaring
Change service
That you have
Underrated microphones
I'm supposed
Oh used to these days
Ever since wisdom Mcenroe's outburst
Neutron pick up anything that's interesting
I'm set to the Empire
Vacuum Center
Sankofa drives
The way things used to be covered
Way Back Inn
The only days
What is currently have
What was Kohl's in apple and biscuit microphone
But stikbots
Over the top of the empires chassis go to the vampire on this as well as the
Go the Distance
Smashes of the bull
Back
Gables,
Volume four
Movie lights
Crawford return for service
And the top
Good night rest
Join. Stockbroker
I'm still doing Moana
It was
Early eighties and exhaust
To do cool to
In Stereo to save
We could develop
Techniques
I'm came to
In the end using quite a potions expensive
I'm not very
Weatherproof
Microphone
Pictures of beautiful stereo microphone
Ready
Normally used
Taqueria molcas dress
Then
Butts
Mensa
Your
Players rushing moving around
Restaurants as they run around the court
That's not evolve into
Surround technique
Well you have another need the crowd on the players in front of you
Crowd also goes all the way around the back of you so
When you're in the middle of a cheering crowd
NetSpend
Cuda 12 surrounds really involves you in
Play if you like
It's like actually being the
The
Dynamic range
Difference
Between the causes noise
Doesn't have keep you on your toes
If you've dropped
Pools
Mix
I'm afraid that I need to take my fader
Down
In anticipation of it getting very loud on the course
And you do it ahead of time
Euronews
What you got to do is time it's in such a way
Search
II
The bus
Quantum
Sphere changes
Into the huge rule from the crown
You go to Split Second
Free downloads
Affect
Over the edge
-2 developer
The sort of sixth sense in a way
So I can
Guess
Pretty much known entendre
What to do
Getting that exciting
Stillness
Patient
Then this huge rule when it's old develop
Pretty wonderful
Of course given the context room tour
That would be the right time to sell your first Ace
Dial now
With a second set point
What was brilliant about
That particular
Final
Well they left
Breathe
They didn't talk Oliver's all the time
I have had the number people say to me is there anyway that we can
Have a feed Willows commentator
I think that would be something that people would really appreciate
Because your income
Juices of the old school
Rotella compensated
I don't think many do now
I'm very Davidson few years have been a commentator on
Embarrass things
When a goal is scored
I would
Just
Lycoming televised producer just 4.6 seconds
Why not the sound of the crowd and then they can come in
I used to try to make it
Fortune my mind that if you count for what to say say nothing
Which is the best policy
But
Environment
Euro 96 when Germany in the semi-final
I can remember very well
I would have thought
Something close to 10 minutes
The TV came out
Good sound from around the stadium
Just for the funeral
Observation the commentator
Everyone join again
The famous physician
Panthers
Only well noted at Freddy's
Puking baby on the way
What I'm trying to achieve but if you've got
A bunch of people sitting at home going
Donauschwaben
Terrific match
Isn't she psycho from the Santa Fe
But you know that's a summer
Autofit
The football match what we do
Is to have
And then
12 mics around the pitch
Which you
Trailer down at the ball moves up and down
Another was chasing the ball around
So you can get the kicks from me
Definition of a shopping list.
The difficult technique to get across to people who haven't done it before
It's anticipating where the Bulls go
Personally I don't favor the system of fixed Michael
The bill describes
I prefer to use for roving operators who each point a directional microphone at the action
They follow the action
I believe this gives a better more defined kicks on and it's a method of use at the last four Olympics
And we use in London for the 2012 football dance
What you doing now is a game for the Athens Olympics in 2004
Live Olympic Games I try to rush up the excitement and entertainment.
And certainly winter sports are fun because you're trying to convey a sense of speed and motion
I've always enjoyed the sound of bobsled
Vancouver there were 44 cameras
At each camera position there was a distinctly different oral perspective and I was trying to put
The view or The Listener in the place of the athlete
And I made every camera position
A sound Zone
Some people may say
284 microphones
What is a bit excessive
But you have to remember that every camera
Perspective every visual perspective
For the viewing audience has a different sound texture and a different sound
It's like a piece of music that you just sit and listen to the crowd
You here like how it swells and Dives and
Peaks and then suddenly burst
Sounds to me like an orchestra
I'm Rob Nokes
I mean
Sound effects recordist for movies in Hollywood
I get hired by the movie studios
Record sound specifically for their movie for example if you have
Pacific sports movie
Be a horse racing hockey figure skating football basketball
They bring me into
Capture the essence
The crowds
And the game itself
The sound of the basketballs
The sound of horses
Does Hooves horses breeding players tackling each other
So they bring me in so that they can recreate
The feeling
Have being really into that event when you see the movie
The game of their lives it was the greatest team in any sport I have ever seen
The game of their lives as a football movie about the 1950 US men's
National soccer team that was competing in the World Cup
In Rio
In Brazil
And they went on to beat England
Which was shocking at the time
Because England was the best team in the planet and
America was probably
What are the worst teams
I was asked to go down the record football crowds
For the movie
In North America we don't have football cards that are that exciting
And
Rambunctious
I went to Brazil and I recorded
Football games I went to murambi
Stadium to record a game between Brazil and Bolivia
And the crowd was
Insane
I was just your move around stadium and listen for pockets of
Chanting and cheering or loud fans
And listening for the energy
They are
Out of their mind singing
Huge 10-foot drums
When you can feel someone screaming in
Their guts are coming out as they're yelling
That's going to translate when you hear it in the movie
I'm looking to record people that are really passionate and Intuit
And so I would set up near them
I had a handheld recorder
I try to not let them know I was recording
So I didn't want to change their
Performance
Do you have people in the loop group will actors
They're not going to go that deep and scream like a fan in an audience will
It's amazing when you can recreate with real people that energy that's the way to do a sports movie
Sound puts you in the actual environment and it really does create an emotional response
My name is Gordon Doherty I am the studio audio director at Electronic Arts Canada
Pacific 3D Sports video game end of the company
Play games like a FIFA hockey
Soccer
American football
Golf pretty much the entire range of sports
We're taking
A scientific approach to a very emotional process which is
Directory analyze how crowd
Set up this big boss of sound everything is happening at once
Is that guy in the corner that whose face is painted purple and he's got his team shirt on
He's got a big drum and he's trying to get his corner of the stadium.
Maybe a wave starts
Around the state or maybe it doesn't
So
You are future pushes let's get into actually modeling
How crowds behave
And how these different
Particles of sound actually interact
Decorate a large bag
We work a lot
How can we keep improving
The actual game experience
We try to bring it down as authentic as possible but then we have to go beyond
Because normally you would not share
What are the details of the sound on the pitch
On TV
But of the game so you expect
Butterfly South African World Cup
Retired people in South Africa record
The crowds
We have to build a game quite a few months in advance
Abby event
Beehives going on
What is this
The thing is it's part of the EU have to have this was not authentic
3 actually put
A mute button on finally say that you can eat it or or lower the volume of it
And then when the actual World Cup start in South Africa
How come the TV channel catches put a mute button like they do in the actual video game
He's another one of my favorite sports
Is a great example of Greeley trying to isolate the micro sounds of the spa
Really separate the above sounds
In the swimming hole in the below sounds the underwater sound
Really conveys the sense of a focus in the sense of isolation of
The athlete
Your microphones on the handrails
Divers walk up
You can hear their hands you can hear their feet you can hear them breathing
We have a microphone at the bottom of the pool
Under the water
We actually goes under the water we shifted perspective to just them in the underwater sound you hear the
Bubbles
You get this complete sense of isolation complete sense of the athlete
All alone
Archery
I like the sport
After hearing
The coverage in Barcelona the 92 Olympics
They were things that were missing the easy things were there
All the sudden impact of the target
That's a no-brainer in a little bit
Show The Athlete is there getting ready but probably goes back to
The movie Robin Hood
I have
A memory of the sand
And I have an expectation
So I was going okay what would be really really cool and archery
To take it up a notch
And the obvious thing was
The sound of the arrow going through the air to the Target
Lipozene
So we looked at a little thing the color boundary mic
They would lay flat or sliders in a pack of cigarettes
Apollo windshield on it and I'll put it on the ground between the athlete and the target
Hey it completely opened up the sound to something different
For some reason directors don't like to see the microphone
They do like hearing good sound
There is a resistance
Can actually see microphones in the picture
Which is one of the challenges that we have in the boundary microphone
I feel that challenge because youku
Creep the microphone closer to the ax
Source
That's the lineup The Boat Festival in
Landfill
Straight
The umpires being Donnie came down about the car tomorrow to go
To line up the acoustic version
The engine of the lawn to start it up
I want if you can have them on this
Will we find ourselves on a glorious day down on the Thames of the boat race
Absolutely
Pool Davis
Executive producer with BBC sport look after
Tennis Rugby Union
Boat race
A few other things
Sound is it's a hidden Jewel isn't it really I mean I think it's one of those things that one take
Facebook granted
Because strobis reasons you can't see it
No one should refer to it when it goes wrong
There is literally at at
The deathly silence
I'm a huge supporter of sound
In outside broadcast television
And I think the guys that we would with Rudy respect that
My anxiety James on the science advisor
We're at the end of the bike race at Putney and
My job is fat
Open to seeing
With what you hear
Whenever I look at a shop I want to try on best rate with us and that that's what was my inside pool cuz already
Ritika short of the cruise then you can see the looks on their faces I want to hear every bit of effort that pussy into that
I had to make sure every show
Who cuts up
We can match you excited to make it even better
Give up the old sleeps
Boathouse is Anais love balcony that's great clip
Quite often a lot of the motivation for directing outside broadcasted is visually driven
Nothing I can come from sound as well
If we have two very
Motivated Cox's
And that both Mike topping that delivering some outstanding
Sound
Then this real motivation 8 to hit up sound to understand
What bad delivery instructions
Enwisen
Atmosphere as well
Octonauts usually most amazing and Sons a going visually to that cameras to see the Colts
Delivering it and then how the roads are overreacting
Intuit as well so
Those motivational reasons for hearing sound all things great
Rather than it just being wallpaper
Passing the boat house and now we're just going to take the outfit strike
Bleeding through GOG but again
3 + 4
On the boat race we've got about six different show signs within the course with you the moment we choose
Weather
And we've got various stereo effects mine something in the toe pain and then as we move from site to site moving down the car
We have effects Mike's Adit raiderlink back to us here where I can mix them in
Mind science
Wheels that have mics on the crew boats themselves
And on the choice votes
So
We can pick out the various different
Effects that we need has the best movies of down the river
But time has come
We saw the first off the broken will be a presentation element when the
Provinces will be introducing what's going on February movie with us
And this is the time that time good afternoon it's just going to be online
What's the first element
Itself and I'm basically moving
Sandestin restaurant
Starting
Just give us five minutes Joe
Vitamix and SKF
I'm starting from rest and then., Coventry mic stand with end
Is so important Hospital code 600 more to come but the first one is
The platform
Ferris High distance effects might one up on The Voice which gives it to panoramic view of pain today
Then we move on down tools Ultimate Fighter 41 by now or into Mike's in the boat has themselves
You're not ready
Cambridge Health Douglas box again
Family Clinic in 2 the races health science of the race time we go to unpause but at the end Pockets the race.
Tennessee sells mr. affects mods. Hopefully pick
Cut the sound of the rowing
Peacock says only boats have on them
Sometimes the language that comes from the talk season 4 Constable so we have to have no tentative
I'm not part of the life cycle workout
What does the saying is it transmittable
Benevolus what we're saying is it really good information
Turn on the fan
Battery saver on
Then we're into the berry show sites
Said Sana.
15 Titus down there actual sites which will be able to pick out the crowds that are late for the washing
The birds are places on the right state of color because they're all having parties
Prevent throwing up
The multi-layered
Oral picture
Heading towards Victory Arizona
Alternate tunings behind
Problems by
Max Gundam temperature of 1 K me to one by
Two and a half lengths
Okay
At 1
The boat race of 1933
Cambridge still with a slide
A suspect
Way to UNCC vertical the race you'll see the stars with initials somewhere in between
What we can do you think she can buy an atmosphere throughout the whole race for the view ICU and she done much better experience
In 2011
The spoils everything
Cambridge
Things to know about layering
With pictures there's a degree of layering but it's
Spell Eclipse. Little cutting between pictures
With the sound I think you can build up the layers
Covering Anthems for example during six nations of whether you when you go to the anthem shorts of the teams
Are you tracking along
They close up to the players do you actually want to hear the choral singing of the stadium
What do you want to hear
It would respect the Fairly poor singing of the individual players
That's an interesting mix.
Sound guys have to deal with
Cuz you want the personality and
I know the words but often that
No son very well
But you didn't hear that sounds
The tool
Then you feel a bit cheated
Okay alright
When we do the rugby these days
We have a rigid Mike
Envy
Referee
He has refused to sit
With a radio mic
On the referee but it wasn't transmitted
Xiamen eventually
The Rugby Union officials
Sagittarius
Wonderful addition to the Coventry
That's what it is it's probably country
I don't think it had so much
Don't think you could use the
Technique for football
Take the hits please I'll contact you make sure you go straight to take the pic
What is your take on this side
So the addition of a microphone on the rug be rough trade open up another dimension
But she brought into the game
You can be the player
I believe that is the future sportsound microphones on the athletes and players themselves
If you can persuade them to wear them
And here's another sport that benefited hugely from this technique
Curling was introduced in
To the Olympics in 1988
When do the Winter Olympics went to Calgary
The rest of world on curling curling
How we going to make curly excite
How we going to introduce curling to the world end early on we started putting microphones wireless microphones on the curlers
Russell knows it's pretty big pocket you freeze in the back wheel nuts
Their strategy they are encouraging each other the talk in the console
There's a lot of screaming it's a very very vocal sport
Copper oxide sensor
It brings the intimacy
To the audience and it has really been a
A huge boost in the ratings in the interest in the sports
What's a video game interesting position
In that you are the player on the field
You're also the viewer of the game so you sort of in this weird place where
You're sort of a spectator but you're also an active participant
What we found with the sound is that we had to pretty much exaggerated
Princess on a boxing game you know we have to record the real boxes but we just don't get
Clean sound to get like things like Grunts and groans and punches and impact
Thought we go into a studio and sometimes will we create a boxing ring to do the defeat in the Falls
And then what we'll do is we'll close mic
It's called a Foley artist it's basically the people that do the footsteps and all the sort of hand props and everything
Fortuna television
We'll have the person that punch a punching bag or side of beef or whatever
And just get all of the actual punch sounds
The high low medium hard different angles
Still at the boxing sniffs and all the grunts and groans and we've been will do things like you know break celery and Larry didn't to
A body impact sounds get like a cracking rib type of sound
So all of those elements weed
Cheerfully craft in a studio environment
And then
Crossing the venues and
Dress it all up
The whole
Net effect of that is that it does feel fairly authentic
Legendary
On the tennis game how Grand Slam Tennis
From the French Open
Similar I got some tapes from Wimbledon as well
Number of matches with different players
And different sizes of venues and just basically extract the crowd from there
Anvil Mcenroe or the William sisters and shrieks and screams at tennis players do
I think it was Venus said wow you know it sounds just like me serving
American car racing they call it NASCAR
This particular race was a half mile oval
And essentially
What would be considered a
Football type Stadium
With very high banking
The cars put out a hundred forty decibels of sound maybe more than you put 40 of those cars on a half mile
Call track
And it just sounds like a hornet nest
There's no real definition
Then I was in the show is over and they're supposedly is the Roar of the crowd
But the producer screaming hot I can hear the cry. Near the crowd
Is a
Drake basic
Physics
Issue
The sound that I want are being Master being drowned
Buy these cars
Learn my lesson
I went back
To my home studio and I started pulling up some crowd samples and building different textures and things like that
So my next race yeah when they show the crowd that start sneaking some stuff in it
And when it came to the end of it
There's a very very nice crafts with
And the same producers that you know
How to get the atom away so you know this is great this is what I want this is what we're trying to achieve
And then a week later he found out that I use this amp
And then I get a call if you're cheating
XHamster
All right
Who am I cheating
Am I cheating the audience
Know the audience sees
The crowd
The audience has certain text
Muttations you see I cry You Hear My Cry
There's some sports that she just cannot
Capture the nag
Cross country skiing biathlon his another one
How because of the size of the course and this has been further complicated because it's the camera lenses have gone up
Honor 10 Hunter 2000 3842 1 these cameras are able to see
A half a kilometer maybe McClung on the course
And how do you replicate that sound
Essentially if you got cameras that are
That far apart from each other you're putting 20 or 30 microphones
To feel
Is the athletes are coming to you
Which is not
I am not a purist whatsoever in sound production
I truly believe
Then what
Ever the tool takes
To deliver a high-quality entertaining
Soundscape
It's all fair game
And that has caused some issues because I use samplers
What a sampler is
It's a keyboard is attached to
Cecily a digital recorder
When you hit the key on the keyboard
It triggers
The sound
Add to playback
And with the keyboard also triggers with sensitivity
Means that if I hit the key
Real hard
Don't have a little bit more of a heart attack and you can vary the pitch
If I hit the Cenote that has a stamp
And then I hit a d note of the same sample it will be upstairs
Sofas and get there
Rick Craven pension still hold the lead the French in third we could do without saying never a mother
In Atlanta one of my biggest problems was rehling
Rowing is a 2km course
They have
For Chase boats
Following the rowers and they have a helicopter
That that's what they need
To deliver the visual
Cover job
Okay but the helicopter in the chase boat just completely wash out the Santa
Don't no matter how bad the microphones are
You cannot capture you cannot reach
And isolate sound like you do
Visual
But people have expectations
Okay if you see the rollers
They have a sound that they're expecting
So what do we do
That afternoon we went out on a canoe with a couple of rowers and recorded stereo samples of the different
Type of effects that would be somewhat typical of an event
And then we loaded those recordings into a sampler and play them back to cover the shots of the boats
Australian something back from Great Britain
Standby
Under a sink
Good evening spatula Victoria sponge has dropped back to last 31st to begin on the Plaza
Side is dancing shoes out there in the early stages going fast to is what we doing who's racing you looking to get somebody run
Around the pool softer the horses
Sno-Way on occasionally you will come across pretty close up pictures of the horses of the Pharcyde
Which is done off one of our driving cameras
What you have
Engine noise in my case
So that's why you wouldn't want to microphone on that cuz I'll leave it here is it called reading out when they come around cussing
Basically
The way you cover all that sort of stuff
Is to run a tape
Which has the sound of horses galloping
Which is actually if I remember rightly
A slowed-down buffalo charge
If that doing hurdles she will have
At 8
Which has
The sound of somebody falling through hatch
Through or over hopefully the Huddle UIC fade this up
Show you
Very level a little bit so it sounds like several of his going through together
That's pretty much
Start playing the same recorded Live use for you
Some horse racing events sound strange to me cuz they have this constant thundering sound and I can't tell if it's real or not
It's like in horse racing movies like
Seabiscuit and all hat you can hear the jockeys yelling and screaming at each other when they get
On a turn you hear the whips gone
I recorded an Arabian horse
Arabians have a different gate than thoroughbred
And I put for wireless microphones on each hoof
We wanted to control the speed of the horse so
We had the trainer run the horse in a circle
With a rope
We want to control the movement cuz we have $12,000 in gear on the horse
He did take one microphone off
Being charged for the sound of a real event
I would want to do like the Kentucky Derby and use microwaves around the track
And have some on board mics
And then have
Mike's
In the crowd
And have Mike's on the gate
Horse racing fans bigger
It really crazy when they're cheering
Those people are yelling
They're like screaming at the top of their lungs and yelling
Stop Google. Fun so you know we like to have fun as well the same
So what we do is we use the real sign of the Dawn
Hitting the ball to trigger some samples
And we play around with Kick Drum the snare drums been spoiling everything else we can find an 8-8 just
A bit of fun ready to what kind can I get a bit repetitive
It's not real but it's not on
That's something that I think most of us involved in sport
Trying to try and humps the experience
We tread the Middle Road between what's real and what's unreal
If you're sitting at the side of a basketball court from the TV point of view
The Producers want to hear the ball as it goes through the net the swishing of the net
And that's certainly something that you do not ever hear in the basketball arena do you only hear that on TV because
This exciting
Samuel L Jackson became tfboys and you became men
Coach Carter
For a Coach Carter the supervising sound editor wanted me to get the sound
Of the basketball
But he wanted
There's a pain I don't know if you ever heard of basketball
When you bounce it goes
Bounce
It kind of has this
Hi Arie ring
We did this great room stuff like Rim slams Rim head
Net wishes and then we're trying to capture the sound of the
This pain and we are right under the net
And I'm like no that's not it it just sounds like the big side of a basketball and the Reverb in the room
But then we went into the corner of the room
And I got elevated on the bleachers
And iPad my microphone above the ball and the guy slam the ball on the ground and then as the ball was coming up to
To my microphone you hear that
The Ping
I've always taken the approach to record the sound
Documentary-style like accurate
And then I tried to then find the next level up
To go hiking reality
Sometimes you actually have to
Cheetah sound even bigger to make a cake
Cut through
The thing that Hollywood does differently is
It sounds huge
The movie sound big they sound rich
It's definitely more the app
Patrick old and real
Just think Fast and Furious order
Die Hard
As we've been doing this over the years sort of emulating broadcast and enhancing a
The broadcasters have been listening to what we've been doing
And
Then using our techniques back
In the actual broadcast
Broadcast
Push up the witches on the bats what they do now
You know when you listen to a baseball game
Now versus 10 years ago
Because they have mic located very close
Capital sound
Many years ago the Olio that people would have been used to
Expecting from the Philippines
Where I can I expect to hear every kick
Every grunt
Every whistle referee
Cuz that's what they get used to hearing on video games on films of being posted
So we're always trying to match my Solace and
The challenge for me to make sports on TV is engaging is filmora video game
If we don't
We're going to lose out
But it's a challenge I welcome
I'm gearing up for London 2012 for the games we presented in high definition picture
And certainly in surround sound
I'll be pushing to create the best
Most involving most detailed sound ever thielen
And one thing that makes me very happy
Cuz I hear that the boo boo zoo was
Will be banned from the game
LED would one of my favorite sounds
Equestrian jumping event
The sound of sport was presented by Dennis Baxter and produced by Peregrine Andrews it was a falling tree
Production originally produced for BBC Radio 4 in 2011
99% invisible the same Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are project
Kalw San Francisco and produced out of arcsine in Oakland
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
Got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
The 99 bi experience isn't Justice episode your hearing we are also all on Twitter at
Roman Mars Sam listen to Katie mingle and truffleman
Ross on Facebook Tumblr Instagram Flickr Spotify SoundCloud
If you pick something out in search for 9 amp service but you're probably going to find us there and you are always welcome to stop by
Fireplace
Adnan olympia.org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com