99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Sound design is one of the more overlooked asp
It's so critical to our enjoyment of the world
Do you sound pleased me more than the satisfying
That my car doors make
I get inside my VW
My current least favorite sounds are from credit card chip readers that Blair and I'm noxious Morning Buzz
Play clearly signals to normal humans that something has gone wrong
Even though it actually means everything went right
It's time to remove your card
Hahaha
My love of sound and story is why I was excited to find a new podcast
Twenty thousand Hertz
Tells the stories behind the most recognizable and interesting sounds
And I'm pleased for that one of their episodes today
Heroes Dallas Taylor tells the story behind them
Famous sound in Bronx
This is the national
Broadcasting Company
For being only three tiny notes the NBC Chimes of had a colossal impact on media and culture for nearly
90 years
It was back in the late 1920s when NBC started using this for the first time to identify itself on the radio
WEA F New York
They became so iconic and so popular that they were the very first sound to ever be awarded a Nadia trademark
And that's hard to get
Take for example the Harley-Davidson engine sound
After six years of litigation and challenges from other companies they withdrew their application
Courts also denied Motorola's request to trade markets
Chirp
Saying that among other things
They didn't do a good enough job promoting it as an actual sound mark
Budweiser even tried to trademark the sound of an opening beer can
I think I'm going to go to the courts on this one
So
They're only about a hundred sounds that I've actually officially become us trademarks
And most of them are incredibly iconic
Ho ho ho
You got mail
The concept of the trademark is that it's something that's generally accepted
That can't be confused with something else
That you can make the case represents your Prada
That's Rick greenhut
Used to work for NBC and was actually the last person to ever officially play the Chimes on the NBC radio network
An audio trademark that doesn't have any lyrics in it
It's very hard to say will this represents my Prada
And the reason NBC could actually trademark that
Is they been doing it
For 40 years before anybody thought to trade market
Today whenever you think about branding you think about the visual Mark the visual logo
The back in the 1920s the most powerful form of mass communication was the radio
The only way you could brand yourself would be through sound
Everybody heard that in the 50s or 60s would instantly know it was NBC
The Chimes were everywhere they were so popular that they even appeared in some pop songs
This is announcers Blues recorded in 1936 by Paul Whiteman and his orchestra
The artist behind this next track NBC I love you remains a broadcasting mystery
To understand where the Chimes came from we have to go back nearly a century
Stations were using Chimes gonz all kinds of different musical devices to
To create a sound signature for themselves
This is John Schneider
A radio historian
Chimes in particular would have been an easy choice
Due to how common they were
Dinner times were often used to summon guest to the table and it was also used to indicate the start-and-stop of intermission
NBC created a
7 note sequence in the idea was that at the end of each program the announcer is that the microphone
Who sang this is the National Broadcasting Company would strike a 7 note
Chime sequence on a set of hand chimes that he held next to the microphone
As you could imagine since this is being played live by the announcer
It was really hard to keep him
So they shortened it
3 notes
Originally the three notes were caf
Which had the same sound that we noted a chest in a different key
Eventually they use the notes
Gec
Would some people think stood for the General Electric Company
That would have been the coolest branding story having the gec chime stand for the General Electric Company
But the truth is General Electric didn't have much to do with NBC until later
Eventually because
It still wasn't being done uniformly on the hand chimes they went to an electronic device
I remember getting a tour of the technical facility
That's right green hat again it was the
Strange thing back in the rack
I said what's that they said
It's a Chimes machine
NBC hired an electronic Oregon Pioneer Captain Richard Wrangler to build more of an automated system for playing the show
Chimes
Not only did the Chimes server branding purpose but it also solved a really big technical challenge
When they would change Studios
They would be literally plugging and unplugging these patch cord
And it would make kind of clicks and pops on the air
Since we end each show with the Chimes
Each Studio would have a take control button and a chimes
When you push the x button it would take that studio off the air under the sound of the Chimes
I didn't hear the click
Aside from its iconic cultural status the NBC Chimes also played a really important role in history
Outside of radio the only other form of mass communication was through newspaper
There was no medium that
Past news or information or entertainment to the public
In real time
Again John Schneider
And all of the people who were Pioneers they had to invent
Techniques that we take for granted today
It must have been
Fascinating time to participate in birth
Modern Electronic media
One of radio's most important moments came during World War II
For the first time in history news from the front lines of War can become available to the Mass public in near real-time
Radiohead discovered its importance
As a news medium and not just an entertainment medium
During the war NBC at 1/4 time to covertly notify announcers that important breaking news with eminent
If the normal chime was gec
At the end of a program they would buy the chime gec
See
National Broadcasting Company will continue its network service throughout the remainder of the night
And you will be important but so far unconfirmed reports from overseas
This is vernacular Broadcasting Company
That fourth note
Which probably most of the radio audience
Never even noticed
Was a cue to the radio stations pay attention listen on the line between the program and be prepared
For something momentous to come along
When it rains all of us at NBC spring into action
Wherever we may be
The Points Guy means to us
Call the office
You're down here big things are happening
During the invasion of D-Day NBC fourth time with played alongside the morse code sound for the letter v
Indicating that The Invasion had just begun
The time the fourth time means news of the greatest World Imports
The first time riding on D-Day
The fourth time will ring again on v-day the Day of Victory
Thankfully the fourth time was only played a handful of times in the history of the network
NBC was huge
All the other networks were still up and coming so NBC commanded all the top talent
We bring you a man who paddled here all the way from Hollywood
People who are getting the ratings in the people were the next day's water cooler conversation
That would be the radio show from NBC the night before
So NBC to me always had seemed like
The Cadillac brand
It was a brand whose name you remember
Whose logo you could picture
And when you heard the sound to picture the logo when you saw the logo you heard the sound in your mind
The NBC chimes
At least on the radio came to a close in the late 1980s
When Rick greenhut played them for the last time on the 9 News
We typically which I'm out of every Network feed we did
And it about 8:45
The newscasters already in the booth the producer sitting next to me
I've got the commercials in the machines for each of the time zone
And the general manager comes up
And he said I wanted you to be the first to know that the radio network has been sold
General Electric acquired NBC radio through the purchase of RCA this meant that NBC radio no longer
Operated as its own entity
The NBC Chimes were not
Part of the sale
Because they're the NBC chimes in the TV network is keeping those
9 hour comes we do the network News gas and it 905 30 the news
News caster says Doreen on NBC News New York
I played the Chimes
I then pulled that tape cartridge out of the machine where I played it well no sooner at
General manager shows up
And he just looked at me and he said make sure no one else can do that I did that by taking it
At the cartridge home and it's sitting on my shelf
The NBC radio network came to a close
But obviously the Chimes still live on through promos and special programming and news
But the sound is bigger than Comcast or NBC or General Electric
It's something that's deeply embedded and weave through our history for the good
Did the bad
The most important moments of our Collective lives together
This sound has been with us for almost ninety years
It started as a sound that just fixed a small problem
But
Has become something that's completely ingrained in our culture
Twenty thousand Hertz is a production of defacto sound you can find it at 20K. Org or wherever you get Podcast
This episode was produced by Carolyn McCulley
Sam's nearby
Belinda Barton
Milan Fitzwater barrows in Dallas Taylor
Sound design in mixed by Colin Navarre
Special thanks to Rick greenhut and John Schneider
99percentinvisible is a product 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Hey beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating it doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
You can find this show and join discussions about the show on Facebook
Tweet me at Roman Mars at the show at 99pi Org
Run Instagram and Tumblr to
But in addition to all the episodes you've heard there is a treasure Trove of Design Story
+ 39 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com