99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
September 2015 Duke University's football team promoted its backup quarterback to starter
This was a little bit of a shake-up because the new starting quarterback was a total rookie stepping up to take
Take command of the team Dukes new quarterback may have been inexperienced but he sure did look the part
Who is exactly the kind of person you cast in a movie about a team trying to turn around
Dude at 6 for 225 lb
Has boyish good looks in an object's grin
That's all Shucks producer Sam Greenspan
Meanwhile
In Orange County California
A public defender was making headlines for his work investigating how local law enforcement
I've been stacking the deck against defendants
Newspaper show him in a standard suit with wire frame glasses ducktail hair and a goatee
He's Got The Look of a 20-year veteran of the courts who's managed to keep hold of his ideas
Meanwhile
In the West African country of Burkina Faso a group of armed soldiers in military fatigues
Forced their way into a cabinet meeting
And asserted their control over the government
In each of these cases the quarterback the attorney the coup
Newspaper articles about each of them describe them in exactly the same way
They were all written up as being
Straight out of Central Casting
Calling something or someone
From Central Casting
Is it kind of cultural shorthand for a stereotype or archetype something so visually perfect
That it's like it's been design
The first time Barack Obama flew in Air Force One he said to the pilot
If you do a new search for the phrase
Straight out of Central Casting
To get tons of hits about athletes
Business Executives politicians billionaire philanthropist
But every now and then you'll find an article that makes reference to a proper noun Central Casting
In Burbank
California
Morning
I'm going to Temple casting please
I've known the phrase straight out of Central casting for a long time
But I never really stopped to think about where it came from
And so
I was quite
Surprised to learn that Central Casting
Is a real place
I can know right
It's like learning the Acme is a real company
And they still make anvil
Give my taxi driver both longtime resident of Los Angeles
Even he didn't know Central Casting was real
Central Casting is in Burbank California in the San Fernando Valley and it's where the vast majority of extra
What's come from
Okay I am on South Flower Street
In Burbank California outside
Of the Central Casting building
It's a nondescript two-story office building
The kind of place you'd expect to find an orthodontist
And every Monday Wednesday and Friday
Starting in the very
Early early morning
People lineup
Outside Central Casting
When I got there at 8 on a Monday morning there were about 50 people in line
It would grow to about a hundred over the next hour
And at the very front was a woman that named Carissa Guerrero
In the morning
3:10 a.m.
So it's already been a long day
Yeah it has
The people in line at Central Casting aren't there for auditions
Carissa and everyone behind her in line are there for the chance to fill out some paperwork
Take a headshot
And get entered into Central Castings database for extra
They will not be harassed for speaking roles
No many if not all the people in mind
Are hoping that a director or producer will like their look
And give them some dialogue
Just like old John Wayne and Marilyn Monroe
And Brad Pitt got started
Blind Hollywood hopefuls stretches down the sidewalk
Some people have brought lawn chairs or blankets to sit on
And now look
They look like they're straight out of Central Casting
There's a handsome Texan in a suit and tie fresh-faced to the prospect of showbiz
Friends
Call me over
And I'm from Texas
So he was like a you want to do some background work
Central Casting can go over there there's a female bodybuilder fitness competition so I'm trying to build myself as a brand
And that industry as well
A guy who calls himself
Kid Radioactive
I'm going to be
Famous
Even though it's already hot and most of the people here have been waiting for
345 hours
Be more cheerful
Optimistic
Men
Around 9:30 a guy emerges from inside Central Casting
He's heading up his laminated slips of paper they kind of look like oversized bookbar
These are the tickets in at 2 today is registration
In process
You'll make it halfway down the line when he runs
You didn't get one I'm sorry
No ma'am
Thank you
Come back on Wednesday
Wednesday morning
Maybe 5 in the morning
Central Castings bouncer is named Russell LeBlanc
I'm safety Specialist of passing out the cars this morning
Right so your people's either best friend or worst enemy in the morning cuz he has pretty much
One person protests and if you ask Russell about exceptions but most of the 60-odd people who didn't get to
Retreat to their cars wordlessly
Then
The door to Central Casting opens up
In a 50 or so left golden tickets in hand
Slowly violin
The first job that any aspiring film actor gets is usually as an extra
Known in the industry
As background Act
The other people
To really make
The film without your being aware that that fencing
That's Anthony slide
My name is Anthony slide
I am the author of
76 books I believe in
Count correctly
On the history of popular entertainment
And one of them is Hollywood unknowns a history of Hollywood extras
Standings
Bitplay isn't stunt people
Even though the industry has shifted to calling them background.
Anthony slide still calls the next
They will always cold extras in the early years
Theodore Dreiser the novelist called them
Spherion
Pictures of all the noise
If your director you need Atmos.
Because if you tried to shoot a film out in the world with regular people the risk you take is the people walking around the Sun
Aaliyah where they're being filmed and said there's something going to stop waving at the camera
A mugging or whatever plus you're going to have to shoot the same scene a bunch of the
Different times
It's what you need to be able to tell your actors background included
Where to go and what to do
You need people who are paid to listen to you
It's about control here
In the early days of Cinema
The Hollywood Machine had near complete control of extras both on the set and off
People would come from all over seeking fame and fortune
And it work
People converged on the gates of the movie lights
Hoping to get cash for the day
They were desperate
Many were exploited
So many horror stories were emanating from Hollywood
That by the 1920s
Hollywood headband nickname
The port of missing girls
It's a place where
Women flock
In the hope of getting into films
And they were all very vulnerable they will be lied about the men at the studios Batiste the casting directors
The assistant directors
Who would hide them in a lot of times these men would simply ask for sexual favors
Are in a movie for a dollar a day
Extras who did get hired were often not paid what they were promised
By 1925 the state of California was
Threatening to investigate Hollywood
If they didn't clean up their act
And so as a means of regulating industry
And keeping
The government off their back
The motion pictures Association of America the MPAA
Established
Central Casting
A centralized Clearing House to match people who wanted to be extras with the people who wanted to hire them
Now
Instead of just picking one of the major movie studios and just
Standing around the gates
All day hoping to be picked
People who wanted to be extras could register with c
Central Casting
So now they could wait by their phone
Hoping for a call like
Strip club
Extras also called into Central Casting
The Operators developed
Super quick ways to relay information if there was no work they say Nook but they wanted the
Extras to try again later they say
But as Cinema took off and as silent films gave way to talkies the need for extras only grew
And Central Casting how to get more sophisticated and it's
Packing and recruitment of a
This is the team that's doing the registration today
Back in present-day Central Casting
Executive vice-president Jennifer Bender is showing me around
Then afterwards they'll come over
Here
And get their photos
Take it
This office is one of
Central Casting is now in Burbank New York
And New Orleans between all three offices we've got about 90,000 almost a hundred thousand
It's like there's a small City
Living inside their computer servers
An extremely diverse and infinitely indexable City
Nice to meet you
Jennifer introduces me to Brandy Hawk
I mean Brandy Hawkins and I believe casting director here
I kept stand-ins photo double dead bodies
Restaurant patrons
Circus acts
Everything everybody that's not
Brandy take me on a test drive of how the Central Casting database work
She opened up a window on their custom-built software which has just about every search parameter for a person you can imagine
Tight race
Shoe size bust size tattoos location of tattoos missing lens
How much nudity you'll do
Now she just needed a Target
You want to look for like your photos will my God yeah let's do that
This is what I would do
No please
Why would you like
35 range
And I would do Caucasian male like 66162
Good
Why would you like 6 to 6
I would do hair color
Why are brown
Coat
But 4042 some morning
I'm good at this and like 32 ways
I told him we would just do a search and one-by-one a stream of tall brown-haired 30-something white dudes
All scroll Buy
And then we just kind of scroll through
And see kind of who we think that life might come up that anywhere near
I would submit him it was like you'd be like your long lost brother
Oh man that sounds
So unsettling it was a little unsettling
I just want to stand up and shout know I'm unique
I ask Brandy how she got comfortable talking so explicitly about what people look like
It was very difficult first because I came from a human resources background and there were so many things you couldn't
Dude like you couldn't
Hire people based off of their looks
Where is now that's what it's all about like they'll literally say I need African American male
6ft tall Etsy sizes
And you know like if you pray in a basketball team
It's going to look like a realistic basketball team if they're all these are nice looking guys were five foot four
And so to do this Central Casting and pretty much every casting agency that deals with background there are plenty of others
There callouts
Can be pretty blunt
Central Castings Facebook page is full of descriptions such as this is a real one quote
Looking for hip attractive men and women who appear to be Asian in their 20s
The trendy wardrobe
No visible tattoos
To an outsider
This language can really feel abrasive
It's clear that this line of work demands that you categorize and stereotype
Kristen Barona is a senior casting director at
Central Casting
And to get a feel for how she works I've asked her how she cast a couple different okay
Starting with a diaper
A dive bar I would probably do an older
Caucasian guy bartender kind of maybe on a little bit on the bikery side or little bit on the sketchy side
Because they're always at a dive bar
Did I would probably do a second bartender that would be like a tatted-up
Hypstar
And some women that have probably been
You know
Through it
Auto body shop
Auto Body Shop Auto Body workers
Mostly Hispanic
Alarm guys I would do definitely
Guidance for these kind of punch you with maybe a mustache
And then some younger guys that are
Kind of running around I would probably do a female on her
50s
That's the receptionist
I mean I picture myself in the place and what I would say
Background actors are supposed to look like they belong there
Show casting directors plate or expectations about how we think the real world looks
And sometimes in doing so
Banda perpetuating
Applications
Casting directors are trying to strike a balance between authenticity and expectation
They're constantly looking at the real world and wondering if it matches the way they would cast it
Here Central Casting Executive Vice President Jennifer bendery
The other week I was in New York and I was walking down the street and there
This is just so silly
There were
Warm blonde
Justin Burnett
And
What's very stereotypical
Forecasting a New York City
Street Scene is they don't want any play
Because
People think of New York
Thoughts to myself
If I would have cast the steam
3 New York Street Scene I would be fired because this
It doesn't even look
Like it should be really here
Back in the registration room the people who were waiting outside all morning
Set of chairs facing a PowerPoint presentation
Central Casting employees
Out there for quite a bit the Central Casting orientation it's pretty much like any new employee orientation
What is the I-9 form
Dope every now and then there are some forms to fill out that you would not find
Find at most
On to level of nudity
Everyone is alive
Wednesday
Everything apart
No is
Swimsuits for women
Impartial
Would be
There are boxes to check
Tattoos Piercings missing body parts
If you can dress in Drag
You can dress like a clown
Can juggle there's also information about how the payment system works
In a session on identifying the signs of heat exhaustion
And who to talk to you if you're feeling a little on Sat
After about an hour of document signing everyone gets ahead
And that's it
They are released back into the world
Where they will wait
Rural
There's a cynicism that one could take here
But Central Casting is about turning humans
In two objects
It is one of the only if not the only job
Where you are hired solely for what you look like
On the other hand though
One can argue that this is progress
Cheer
Everyone will be seen
The young the old
The short
The tall the housewife the ex-gang member
The bombshell the amputee
This is a path way into Showbiz thats
Not about nepotism
Cronyism
Torque wheel sleep with
At Central Casting
People fill out an I-9
And get some knowledge base about what to expect on Sat
And actually get paid
And maybe
Just maybe
One of them could be
Become the next Brad
Oar Maryland
But until then
To check Facebook
And wait by their phones
For the call
Hey Joe this is Jimmy from Central Casting
Hey I'm going to see if you want to work American Crime Story tomorrow
Alright so you're going to be media-type at 9:30 a.m.
Correct
Awesome thank you Joe
Of course I have a bye
Hey Jessie this is Jimmy from Central Casting
Hey how's it going
Google Doodle tomorrow
Awesome
Media type at 9:30 a.m.
We're booked up on the Cajun spot
So we need one more African-American one Hispanic or Nation
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan with Katie mingle Avery trufelman Kurt Kolstad and Mero
Special thanks to Davey Nelson Ellen Lewis Grant wilfley Claire Tanner Andrea Hume Bill Marinella
Devin Brown Jack Wallace Alana Goldstein Raquel lamothe and everyone at Central casting for letting us in the front
The people you heard online worker is Aguero Carolyn Mahar and Eric Byrd AKA
Kid Radioactive
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in architecture and into
To use firm not even remotely out of Central casting in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like to show on face
All of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spa
Pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com