99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Is today you pitch me the idea of the US Postal Service
There would be no way you can convince me that it could actually work
I mean it's up perfect as it is but the fact that you can put
49 cent sticker on an envelope and have someone deliver it
Across the country in two days
He's amazing
Just take a second
To imagine all the systems that have to work together to pull that off
Postal services around the world are pretty great
But with any complex design system there are failures that occur
Mail that never makes it to its destination
And can't be returned to the sender
And it's into this rabbit hole that producer Samara freemark fell when she began searching
For all the Lost mail
Once upon a time I lost
Something in the mail
Maybe this is happened to you
It probably
It has happened to you
But what makes my story different is that I went looking for what I lost
So you didn't come
And the place I ended up was
So strange
To dream Lake
Outside the box
Movie
But let me backup app
It was 2007
August
I was moving from Minnesota to Michigan to start grad school
I packed whatever couldn't fit into my station wagon into three cardboard boxes
And ship them parcel rate
Books mostly
The first box arrived at the leisurely Pace the book ship parcel rate usually do
And then
I waited
Four weeks the second box never showed though when I say that it never showed
I mean that most of the Box never showed a piece of it eventually did arrive it came in a large envelope
I need rectangle of cardboard the box top where I had written my address someone had taken a razor
Very carefully sliced it off the box and enclose note on Postal Service letterhead in Pharr
Remind me that my address label had become detached from my box and so I was thrilled when I came home one day
Months later and found my third box waiting for me on my doorstep my lost box was here
But something about the box was different
11 torn apart and then lashed back together with plastic zip ties
When I cut it open the cookbook side
Carefully packs were in disarray
My 4 inch thick hardcover Joy of Cooking have been torn apart down the spine like a weightlifter and used it
For some feat of strength
The two halves were sandwiched around the cookbook I have never seen before
Someone else's copy of Sophia Loren's recipes and memories
Sophia leered at me from the cover
Cleavage was distracting
I was perplexed
I told my mother about it
Oh yes she said that's happened to me too
She had shipped a box of books
Come from Europe and when she opened it
This box was filled with other people's things all from different countries
It had a Bible that was in Russian
A magazine
From
Germany it had some candy from the Netherlands
What's like everyone's European
I was
Just
Astounded
My friend Helen had mailed some boxes
And she had a Story 2
When I got the box
Does open
They looked like
They've been put in a washing machine
Dried
Like the Box
Verso mutilate
And when I open them
The box with all the food Maggie
Half of the issues were
Were taken out
The rest of the boxes were all
All like
Vintage cookbook
And in place of that
I put all of these
Southern home
Saturn have
I'm living whatever
Cookbooks from the 90
80s
Deviled eggs
As though that was like a reparation
My loss
Helen and my mom shrug this off and they let things go
But it's not that me
Who was reading my books
Who's copy of recipes and memories
Guiding me through tiramisu
And just
2 head switched
Now if you ask enough questions like that you'll find yourself in Atlanta on a day so hot the pavement Shimmers
Driving past the Coca-Cola museum past the world's largest aquarium
Past the CNN headquarters and finally turning down the service road and pulling up in front of a nondescript sober
Bourbon Warehouse directly across from Six Flags
Amusement park
The mail Recovery Center
Where lost mail goes to be sorted processed and sent back to its rightful owner
Or barring that
It's sold off
I walked up to the door of the warehouse and open it on
Opening bid $500 in auction
200 people lined up in folding chairs
Waiting paddles in the air
And in the back
Fins upon bin
Hundreds of fans of lost mail
Everything that Americans have ever
Stuffed into a mailbox and never seen again
All sorted by
Benz of pillows benzo
Tennis rackets
Benz of coffee maker expensive stuffed animals computers Bibles electric guitars
Benz of stuff you can't imagine anyone ever thought it was a good idea to mail
Fins of stuff you didn't know it was possible to mail
Like tractor trailer tires
And all these Benz
Being auctioned off by officials of the US Postal
44507 paddle
A middle-aged man sporting faded jeans a sweat-stained baseball cap and a handlebar mustache came up behind me
Stabbing at an auction list
He was a buyer
My name is Ricky
And he was here with his wife Cindy
I mean I got some stuff in here that's Irreplaceable like they got some vintage stuff in here from the forties in the fifties
I got one in their Scotto
Life Magazine with John F Kennedy on it
How much is that worth to somebody if it
Do yuan be worth nothing
Today I can remember the day he got killed
You know
Buttons
Kennedy
So you know what you know who you are and how much
Apparel accessories
Close
Starting bid
$500
Cameras accessory starting bid $2,000
Ethnic items
$500
I don't know
So what do you do with all this stuff
I was the reason everything would get that's what you're saying about
They'll be people
Sitting out in the parking lot on eBay before they leave here
I'm not kidding
Intercar they've got buyers waiting
Ricky and Cindy were hoping to get lucky
Today as lucky as they got once almost a decade ago right after September 11th
We got a whole boat
Oh American flags
You could not buy American flag know where in the United States everything was gone we ended up with American flag pins
American flags over time
Earrings
We had 5 box
McDonald's
Little arches with American flag on it
McDonald's didn't have them
So wait wait wait come out smelling like a rose on that one
And just then
Gordon Plymouth
Swept out from behind the wheel of a baby blue 1960 Cadillac
Heads turn
People whispered
Mr Gordon was mail Recovery Center Royal
He was 80 years old with a pink face
White hair bright blue eyes
I swear he even twinkle
He didn't seem surprised when he saw my microphone it was almost like
She was expecting me
You come all the way down here from Brookland AR
So you didn't come here specifically to
Find out about the pot
Quit the pot
Yeah yeah
Last Tuesday night
Of course he was
Mr. Gordon has been buying stuff here for 10 years
Takis Benz home and pack them and resell the contents
At the last mail Recovery Center auction he is bought a bin of painting
One of them was especially pretty
An orchid in a vase
He tried to resell it at a different auction for $25
But no one was biting
So
Will they put it back on my truck
And as they put it back on the truck
Chip dip and felt something inside the Box
Moving the frame was a box
Consult
So
One of the guys helping me
Took a screwdriver
The back off of it
And inside
$5,000 worth of marijuana
Mr. Gordon and I sat and thought about what kind of person would send $5,000 worth of pot through the mail
And how that person must have felt when they heard about mr. Gordon on Leno
And whether they filed a claim for the painting
Or whether they were just relieved that the post office has lost its oh absolutely
But it couldn't be traced back
Original sender
And then mr. Gordon headed to the
Florida bed
But first
He look deep into my eyes and he sang me a song for luck
Solomon
I'm in lobby in addition to being a mail Recovery Center celebrity
Mariachi
At a restaurant in Alpharetta Georgia
You belong to my heart
Now and forever
And into this reverie walked Lionel snow
The director of
And Michael Miles postal service representative
Escorted me out the door told me I was violating post
Service policies
Post politics
Hawaii
Do I have to be I have to be like 50 feet from the center
And led me across
The parking lot
Here's what we would we would clearly be prepared to talk to you about
I thought you were going to walk around in here trying to get the ladle and see what
However whatever kind of documentation that you're trying to do inside that's where we run into a problem
Did he get security
That's that's among other issues but your security sign is one of them
That's that's nothing the critical issue
Critical issue
If it was you something I don't
Movies
There were 250
There's body parts possibly ashes and stuff to spend every year we would like to get things back to customers everything
But we're unable to
This sounded
Well to be honest it sounded troubling
Because if the Postal Service could accidentally sell $5,000 worth of marijuana to Gordon Clement
Didn't that mean that they could accidentally auction off
Those human remains
Bashas
Yeah
Set of small woman and acid wash jeans with frazzled hair standing behind me
My name is Joe
My fair lady I know bought dishes in a gray powder all over it
And when she finish unloading our dishes there was a
All the paraphernalia for somebody
You know Memorial it was actually 10
So that was funny
It was someone
Yes
Yes all over in cuz it was in the bottom
I wandered around the back of the building where postal officials were unloading bins with a forklift
Auction winners for queued up waiting to collect her purchases
One buyer was hanging two
Decide
My name is John Smith
I'm pretty sure that wasn't actually his real name
John came to the auction a lot he said and he specialized in buying book
He might have bought my book
Once Upon a Time jumbled up with thousands of others
He sympathized with my loss
He knew what it felt like he said
It just happened to him
Let me tell you a really funny story
We should the case of us want him to us we bought books
And we got the same box taped up like it's been through the through a tornado and inside it was a bunch of
Screwdrivers and pliers
It was tools inside the same box nothing was said
Just he go here's your package
And they just replace it with
The same weight I guess with screwdrivers and Hammers and stuff but
My books were gone
Did you ask him what happened to they just what I don't know who got lost in the mail I guess
Poor Man cake
The auction was still going on inside but Ricky and Cindy that couple who had bought that thin of American flags back
Back in the day
They were leaving empty-handed
Crazy
Some woman paid $50 for a box of VHS tapes what do you do with VHS tapes
I thought maybe was having money problems
There's nobody here got money problems today
I'm leaving I may not ain't nothing I can touch that I want it
I'm going back home
First of all we're going to go find lunch and we going home
I watch Ricky and Cindy Drive Away
I was hot
Sweaty almost in a daze longing for home
But before I left I turned and stood for a moment
And I watch
The river of other people's things pouring out of the loading dock and into truck
Send moving vans
Those clothes you should
Home from college and never saw it again
That fancy perfume your grandmother swore up and down she sent you for your birthday
The model Eiffel Tower that your dad says he are mildew from Paris
Your complete set of Southern Living cookbooks
The ones with the deviled eggs on the cover
All those things that you thought were lost forever
They're all here
They're all in Atlanta
Across from Six Flags amusement park
And they're all going home with
Someone else
Hello
And then there was nothing left to do but get in my car and drive home
And when I got home
I made eggplant parmesan
You can find a good recipe for it on page 153
I'm Sophia Loren's recipes and memories
99percentinvisible with produce this week by Samara freemark originally for the KCRW program on fictional and we've done
No doubt about it via the Third Coast International audio Festival
American radio works you can find her on Twitter at asked freemark that's s
Freemark
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Court Kolstad Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in architecture
Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Five podcast
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify
I need to listen to every single episode of 99% invisible and see pictures that go along with all the stories
99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com