99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On the evening of May 31st 2009
216 passengers
3 pilots and 9 flight attendants boarded in the Air France flight in Rio De Janeiro Brazil
The flight was headed across the Atlantic Ocean to Paris
The warning this story might not be a good one to listen to if you're sitting on a plane right now
Best producer Katie mingle letting you know that the closest exit
Could be behind you
The plane that took off that evening from Rio with an Airbus
Free xxx
The take-off was unremarkable the plane reached a cruising altitude of 35000
Passengers read and watched movies and slept
As they flew over the Atlantic Ocean passing the equator a lot of thunderstorm activity
Quite typical nothing really unusual
About that
That's William long of Isha he wrote an article for Vanity Fair about this flight and has written
Extensively about Aviation
He also used to be a pilot
So I spent
Many many thousands of hours in cockpits
Tell the story of Air France
Flight 447
Is a long flight
So they had to co-pilots
I noticed first officers and one cap
They would fly the plane in chef
Student flight
We know that the flight proceeded normally for several hours
And then then with no communication
To the ground or air traffic
Troll
It suddenly disappeared
Some pieces of the plane and several bodies were found Days Later floating in the Atlantic
But it would be two more years before most of the wreckage was found deep in the ocean
All 228 people on board had died
When the wreckage was found they also recovered the cockpit voice recorder and the flight data recorders
And they were in good shape
The recordings were able to tell the story about how flight 447 ended up in the bottom of the Atlantic Ocean
And the story they told was about what happened
When the automated system flying the plane suddenly shut off
And the pilots were left
Prize
Confused
An ultimately unable to fly their own plane
Automation in flight has been around for a long time
The first so-called autopilot was invented by the Sperry Corporation in 1912
And it allowed the plane to fly straight and level
Without the Pilot's intervention in the 1950s the auto Pilots got better
So that you could program an autopilot the following route
Notjustok
Keep the wings level
And this was making the Pilot's job a lot easier
But there was still a lot to think about in the cockpit of an airplane
Control
Hydraulic
And because of all this most planes had three people in the cockpit
Two pilots
An engineer
Flight engineer sat behind the Pilot's and they manipulated and manage these
Increasingly complex systems
But by the 1970s all of those complex systems were also automated
In Flight Engineers lost their necessity
By this time the jet engine have replaced
The piston engine
Making claims much more reliable
And Sons were showing that most
Accidents were being caused not by mechanical error
But by human error
In a French company called Airbus thought that they can make planes safer by letting automation carry an even bigger
You're part of the burden of lying
Airbus was a leader
Airbus has always been quite radical
Unix design philosophy
Led by a guy named Bernard Ziegler
Airbus set out to design what they hoped would be the safest plane yet
Plane that even the worst pilot
Fly with ease
Bernard Ziegler he famously said
But he was building an airplane that his concierge
Ziegler's playing not only had autopilot it also had what's called a fly-by-wire system
But basically an autopilot just does
That's what a pilot tells it
To do
Fly-by-wire is a computer-based
Control system that can interpret what the pilot wants to do
And then do it smoothly and safely
So if the pilot pulls back on his or hers
Stick
The fly-by-wire system will say
I see that you want to pitch up
And here
I'll do it for you
Adjust the right angle and rate
Importantly the fly-by-wire system will also protect you from getting into an aerodynamic stall
Are assault happens when the engine stops turning
But in a plane stalling is different
Basically getting so slow
That the
Wings no longer function correctly in the airplane
Loses out
A stall in a plane can happen when the nose of the plane is picked up at
Too steep an angle
Steep angle can cause the plane to lose lift
And start
To descend
Stalling in a plane is not good
Stop it long enough and you will crash
But fly-by-wire automation makes it impossible to do
As long as it's on
Unlike autopilot
Fly-by-wire system cannot be
Turn on and off
By the pilot
You can't turn this automation off
Here's the thing they can turn itself off
And that's exactly what it did on May 31st 2009
Best Buy 4470 through the night sky over the Atlantic Ocean
At some point
Having flown
Normally for
A few hours
The captain
I don't back to sleep
This meant the to Copilot
That's where in control of the plane
They
Encountered some weather it wasn't rough
Are they deaf never hit significant turbulence
So far nothing out of the ordinary
And then
Suddenly
They lost
AirSpeed indications
A pressure Probe on the outside of the plane had iced over the automation could no longer tell how fast the plane was going
At this point autopilot disconnect it at the same time the fly-by-wire system
Degraded
Like one step so the autopilot turned off and the fly-by-wire system shifted into a different
Mode a mode that did not protect against aerodynamic stall
None of this was ideal but it also wasn't a reason to panic according to William
The plane was still basically flying straight
Unsteady
The airplane was not upset
Had they done nothing
They would have done exactly
What they needed to do nothing
But that's not what has
The co-pilot in the right seat put his hand on his control stick
A little joystick like thing to his right
And he pulled it back
Not just a little he pulled it 3/4 of the way back
Why he did that
Is
The major question
Perhaps he was startled or reacting to some
Turbulence
It's important to note that he did not
Tell the other pilot in the cockpit
The guy in the left seat what do you do
Just done
If you had
Maybe his co-pilot would have known the dangerous situation they were about
2bn
In an Airbus the two pilots have separate control sticks that move independently of each other
In other commercial airplanes the controls would move in unison so that you actually feel the moves your co-pilot was making
On their controls
This design variation they also have contributed to what was about to become a very bad situation
In any case has the pilot in the right seat pulled back on his deck
The airplane
Old put his nose up and started to soar upward
Install protections are in place the plane won't just warned you not to pitch it it's an extreme angle a physical
We will not let you do it
Remember the plane it shifted into a mode in which it wasn't offering that underline protection
Every angle that steeper and steeper the air can flow smoothly across the wings and the plane begin
And the stall
The plane was angled up trying to gain altitude but it actually began to lose altitude
The plane couldn't prevent a stall but it could still warm that's always happening
It's at stall stall stall
Stole stole
Soul Stone
And you think that if you heard this alarm someone would say hey I think we might be stalling
But this never happened did say
But he didn't say we've stalled
Indian man in the right seat we was flying the airplane the junior copilot you put the nose down a couple times then bring it right back
Look up again
The copilot's began to ring frantically for the captain to come into the cockpit at one point one of them says
Where is he here playing with shaking all kinds of alarms were going off
1 minute and 38 seconds after the episode started the captain came into the cockpit and asked
What's going on
The copilot's did not say we're in a stall instead one of them said
Quotes
Completely lost control of the air
And we don't understand
We tried
Everything
The captain have walked into a difficult scene to under
1st and everyone was
Confused where they descending or climbing
At times it couldn't seem to figure it out
Finally they seem to realize they're in a fast descent
Losing thousands of feet per minute
But why they couldn't figure out why
The captain never assessed
Correctly what was going on
He was obviously trying to it wasn't there to drink coffee or suck his thumb
But he was never able to figure out what was going on even though it should have been
Amply obviously
Going on
But for whatever reason it wasn't obvious to them what was going on
They didn't know they were in a stall
They realize it William says
The fix would have been clear its basic
Pilot School 101
The recovery would have required them to put the nose down
Power doesn't matter
Get the nose down get a below the horizon
We're game at flying speed
And then pull out of the ensuing.
The plane continued falling down at a jaw-dropping pace losing several thousands of feet per minute
But since they started at 37000 feet
For a while there was still time for a recovering
So for quite a long time
Is a normal crew
I would have been able to recover
And at the very end around 16000 be the best crew in the world
Only probably would have been able to recover
And below that out
No crew
Would have been able to
Recover cuz they simply didn't have the space beneath them to execute the die before hitting the water
But in any case they never try to do it
Until the road this airplane down
Expressing confusion the whole time
And finally expressing
Certainly that they were going to die
4 minutes
And 22nd
After the incident started
They pancakes
Into the water at a very high descent rate
And of course it kill everyone instead
6 years after the crash of flight 440
7 what's clear is that the pilots didn't understand what was
Happening to them
The big question is
How
How could they have a computer yelling
Stall at them a not understand they were in the stall
There were various things that contributed to the crash of 447 but automation which is overwhelmingly made airline travel
Safer
Also played a role in this accident
However much automation
Has
Help
The airline
By increasing safety
It is had some negative consequence
In this case
It's quite clear
That these Pilots had had experience stripped away from them
4 years
William actually did the math on this
The captain of the Air France flight had log 346 hours of flying over the past 6 months
But of that time
There were only about four hours in which he was actually in control of an airplane
Takeoffs and Landings
The rest of the time
Autopilot was flying a plane
Pets 4 hours
In 6 months
The co-pilot would have had even less time at the controls
This is not to say Pilots do nothing when autopilot is on they still have an important role to play
What's a good pilot
What to do in flight
They watch the systems
They handle navigation and communication
They
Occasionally
Program things in flight path changes a deal with anticipation of weather
They think about fuel management
Increasingly Williams us
Pilots have become automation managers with fewer and fewer chances to actually fly the plane
He believes this lack of experience at the controls let the pilots of 447 unprepared to take over when
Automation turned off
Pilots were hideously in combat
That's
I think no one would disagree with that
So I have certain you heard that
Position from other people before
I think we all have to be very careful none of us was there when the
Sex rehab
That's Nadine Sartor a systems engineer at the University of Michigan who studied a lot of aviation accident
Related to automation
My approach to things is different I guess
These Pilots were in that airplane with the passengers and I'm sure they had every motivation
To keep that flight safe
And yet they didn't say so then I try to understand why why did they not
Did they not have the right information that they not have
The proper training
When one of the co-pilot called back on a stick he pitched the plane into an angle that eventually caused the stall
But it's possible he didn't understand that he was now flying in a different mode one that would not regulate and
Smooth out his movements
This confusion about how the fly-by-wire system responds in different modes
This is referred to as
Athlete has
Mudkip
And it's come up in other
The plane switches into a different mode on suddenly
Pilots funny gif
Youku to understand what's going on at that
Pointy do not exactly know
Whether the system is still taking care of the airplane
Or whether they're in charge now they don't necessarily understand whether all of it has disconnected or just part
Parts of food have disconnected a lot of what is happening is hidden from View
From the pilots
It's buried
But the airplane starts doing something
That is unexpected
And the pilot says hey what's but now it now wouldn't it would now it's
Doing
That's a very very standard comment in cock
What's it up to now
The pilots of Air France flight 447 never quite say what's it doing now but they say similar things
William wasn't the only person to point out that what's it doing now is it commonly heard
Good question in the cockpit
It seems to be almost a running joke
Look in the industry
A joke that everyone agrees
Is a serious problem
What's the most often asked question in our cockpit
Best American Airlines
Captain Warren Vanderburgh addressing a group of pilots in 1997
People have been talking about this issue way before the
The crash of flight 440
7 it's just that no one's really figured out how to solve it yet
We have become what I call Children of the magenta
The children of the magenta are too dependent on The Guiding magenta colored lines on their screens
No we think we have to have those magenta lines on the map
And that magenta vbar that steering us for that line
The children of the magenta are too dependent on Automation in general
Vanderburgh recommends in certain situations
Turn off the autopilot and fly the plane mirror
Can you deem the situation is right
The practice your skills
Turn off your autopilot
Fly your plane
Maintain your skills
Knitting starter agrees that
She also recommends more and better training using simulators to let Pilots explore different kinds of emergencies
Scenarios
And then of course there are people who think the problem can be solved with more and better automation but this is a
Paradox of automation
Automation accommodates in Compton
In fact it's designed to do that
The Airbus was designed after all for Bernard Ziegler's concierge to be able to fly
We appear to be locked into a cycle
In which automation
Begets
The erosion of skills
Or the lack of skills in the first
When this then begets more automate
Maybe Insider things
It's a mistake
To throw more automation at the problem
The position I would have dropped is one that has been termed a human centered automation
Where we see what you need to do instead is make the animation that you have
We could eat me be smarter
But importantly maked what we call a team player
End
Part of that is to provide better feedback part of it is
Have you automation communicate more effectively with the pilot
No one I talked
Two is advocating going back to the bad old days
For automation
To Automation in January the fly-by-wire systems
All of those certainly do increase safety I would argue
And even though a lot of the exit
Since we see these days have to do with the interaction between pilots
And automation
William says
You have to remember
One of the reasons for that is that because of automation there hardly any other accent
And as far as how we should
I feel about Air France
Flight 447 and other acts
Involving animation
Should they be seen as an acceptable loss in an industry that's become mostly safer
Through automation
I think as a society the answer to that is yes
You know
For the individuals there's no such thing as an accept
Civil laws
Alright I'm in this weather
Terrible trash
Terrible in for the pilots who died as well
Airbus planes are not any less safe for any more safe than any other plane on the market
Planes have accidents
But it should be sad
That they're pretty safe to the accident rate for air travel is very low
About 2.8 accidents for every 1 million departures
And there are plenty of Pilots out there that know how to take control in an emergency
Abbreviate everyone just with
Tony okay
It's true there are lots of good pilot
What's out there
But in a far-off future we might be flying and pilot list
We're a long way from that
But the technology is definitely coming
And we will this will happen it just makes a lot of sense
I don't think anyone is sort of loudly saying great that this could be a wonderful thing
But I think reason why people are not
Are also not tearing your hair out about
Because by the time it happens the automation will be so good and so reliable
The humans with all of our human emotions
Human fallibility
The children of the magenta
Oh really
Just be in the way
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Ma
We relied heavily on the reporting and expertise of William long of you show for this piece of special thanks to him he would
Above and beyond for us and if you wanted even more in-depth a minute-by-minute analysis of the crash of flight 447
Check out his piece in Vanity Fair it's called the human factor
And on the next episode of 99% invisible we're going to take him this idea of the automation Paradox and use it as a lens to
View the next great design Challenge and automation when we all potentially become the children of the magenta
When are self-driving cars
It's our first two part Series so stay tuned
Now last week I mentioned that we have a new addition to the radiotopia collective and I'm pleased to announce that Nate dimeo The Memory Palace
Is doing the game
When I was first
Thinking about starting 99percentinvisible Nate was one of the first people I called because I really loved what he was doing with the show
Between these poignant historical moments
And I wanted to do something in the same spirit
Stories about design
And so more than any other program I can say if you love 99percentinvisible you will love love
The Memory Palace
They are friends and he wants recommended history book to me
An unpaid 325i noticed a couple sentences
Just a couple of sentences
That work
A tiny but really striking digression from the main narrative
And I'd like to think that I would have noticed the charm of its historical footnote on my own but the real reason it stood out to me was good
I knew it sparked an episode of The Memory Palace
Most Memory Palace pieces start on page 325 or some book
I'm what you just heard is Nate dimeo The Memory Palace has a special way of zeroing in on these moments in history
The light up your imagination in
Hit you in the gut
Or make you smile
I have noticed that there were these historical things that would jump out
From Longview no Ken Burns documentaries or
The One Moment In some historic home tour when like at that object on
The mantelpiece like actually jumps onto
Is wow that's amazing
Beautiful
The things that move me where these focused things they were
Recognizing the single object they were using credible twist
Someone story
And I wanted to find out on some level if there was a way
Cut to the chase if there was a way to focus so tightly
Aesthetic
The artistic challenge like is there a way that I can
Replicate this feeling of being moved
Or having my you know head blown off
Or
Having my heart broken
The Sting that like I have once.
Is there a way that I can
Get people to feel that same thing
Can I
Retell the story
In such a way that they don't have to take the whole historic home tour
Or they don't have to sit through all nine and a half hours of this documentary series
Is there a way to to crystallize
Internist
Sweeping historical
Full story into
Pop song
But the Memory Palace is never just a simple historical anecdote there's always something more going on
There is a subject and then there is meaning
Like there aren't there are scenes which is different
Plot the sum of all I'm not merely trying to
You know Talent historical story I'm trying to conjure it
In the listener's mind
4 bit
And then Melt Away
I really liked his show so much that had a hard time
Selecting which episode 2% so
I asked Nate which episode really stood out to him as the one that did all the things he was hoping to achieve and Memory Palace
Any pic
This episode
Enjoy
This is the Memory Palace
I need to mail
The rule of Two Worlds
Despair
In the exposition universelle in Paris
The exhibits in the grounds were unparalleled
An impact
Let the center of it all was this issue steel structure
It managed to be imposing
In Elgin
In the tallest thing on earth in unmistakably free
French all at once
Paris have the Eiffel Tower
In the man planning the next fair
The Columbian
Position in Chicago
Just a couple of years away
Needed something bad
Good
Something Eiffel Tower
And that wasn't easy to find
The proposals ran from the ridiculous like a structure that would soar more than a thousand feet above the Land of Lincoln made in Thai
Harley out-of-stock logs in top with a replica
Of age boy at home
To the extra ridiculous something so tall that visitors would take an elevator to the top of a slide that they
Drop them off in New York
The fair's organizers
We're panicking
They demanded the Americas designers and Engineers Step Up
In a man named Jorge Perez
Step forward
When his Ferris wheel was completed that summer
Did Rose 264 feet above the ground
Which was a lot shorter than the Eiffel
Tower
But whatever
Didn't even move
The idea that something so massive
But that
Looks so fresh
Like a bicycle wheel spokes look
Too thin to bike
Thrilling
Imprint terrifying
Despite what the engineer said
Despite the math and laws of physics
Despite the many assurances of the fair is organized
There were people who were sure that this Ludacris machine was going to be a disaster
People going to die
Not only was there no way that that flimsy thing could stand up to a Prairie Wind or Gala
The lake
Even if it did
The prospect of tumbling through the air in a cage 20 stories above Chicago
Mulan craziness
Who in their right mind was going to wanna ride
Hundreds of thousands of
Despite the fact that during its first test
Hundreds of bolts in loose Parts rain down on Spectators below
Despite real stories of panic Riders
Trying to escape Through the Windows when they realized exactly how high 200 feet
Despite apocryphal stories
Suicide
Can severed limbs
Ferris wheel
This thing is basically a kiddie ride today
Was a bigger Thrill Ride than any quintuple Loop open Carver Swiss Rock
Poster they might have
The papers
Even someone France said it was the Marvel of the age
Better than the Eiffel Tower
That almost mundane sensation we have now if looking down from above
The moving through space now
Down and back around
Nuna never felt this things before
Of course now we
Can't really feel them again
Be done around too many times we Loop too many loops
Be back in 1893
You can pay your 50 Cent
Climb into a car right after sunset
During the golden hour
And experienced something entirely new
You can rise up above the world fair
We're down below Americans were eating hamburgers for the fur
For Buffalo Bill and Frederick Douglass and Mark Twain or sightseeing
Where entire Villages from Egypt and Algeria have been brought Enriquez
Were people heard Ragtime for the
The first time hula dancers
Belly dancers
You can come back to her
In walkout
Be among the first people in humans
Walk around it
Lights on
Book Fairs end
The shutdown
Pack up and leave
And the ferris wheel.
They moved it up to a different Park in the north side of the city in after a while then now if you was gone
And the ferris wheel
Became Christopher
The Salvage
Butterfree Grande
Glued up with dynamite
Consult the pieces first
That's the Memory Palace from Nate dimeo
Now from radiotopia
After a couple years of not putting the show out very regularly username
TV shows
I'm pleased to say he's releasing weekly episodes through the summer so get on board you going to want to
Set aside 5 minutes or so
To listen to at the moment each new episode comes out that's what I'm going to be doing
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npit
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook you get little hints of what coming up on the show if you pay attention to Facebook we're also
Twitter Instagram Tumblr and Spotify to do you want to learn all the things there is to know about 99percentinvisible
99pi.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com