99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There's an old story and it goes something like this
A visitor arrives at the Pearly Gates in St Peter
If you can meet the greatest General who ever lived
St Peter points out one of the people in heaven incest
Darius the greatest General in the world
Military shot
No way
That's not the greatest General I mean
That guy isn't even a general I knew him on Earth and he was a cobbler
I know
Respond Saint Peter
But if he had been a general
He would have been the greatest of them all
The Bitcoin Essure
But the story raises some interesting question
Mets General Avery truffle
How does a person discover their greatest
Creative potential
Their best skills and talents and capabilities
You might be a brilliant novelist
If you can find the time
Or maybe if you have the training you could have changed the course of modern dance or particle physics
You know I've been a great General
So
What makes brilliant and creative people Tech
How did they get that way
Today there are thousands of self-help books and counselors consultants and websites
I promise to help you find your creative Athens
82 the habits of successful effective and creative people
But this idea that you can study something as elusive as creativity and learn step-by-step how to be more
More creative
It was unthinkable
Back in the 1950s
Creativity
Has always
Had something
Magical about it
Unexpected
It's surprising
That's why people
Thought that you couldn't study creativity it was
Nebulous and unconscious and not accessible to
Scientific
Inquiry
This is Ravenna helson my name is Ravenna helson
I'm very old 91
What what else shall I say
Ravenna helson is a very prominent personality psychologist
And she got her start in an unusual department at UC Berkeley in 1949
It was called The Institute of Personality assessment and research
Also known
As I par
What
I-4 was was a Institute with procedures for studying
Personality in a fairly new complicated way we thought we were working
King on something really unique and good for Humanity the scientist a type are attempted what many
People thought was impossible
Set a time when creativity was thought to be this kind of magical inexplicable Force
The tie bar set out
Capture it
Study it
Chemist article scientific way
Identify the specific
Personality traits
Make certain people
Creative
Ipar invited a whole variety of creative people to come to Berkeley and be studied
Authors of fantasy for children women studying at Mills College
And writers including some real Heavy Hitters
Like Truman Capote in William Carlos Williams
But one of the biggest and most successful studies that I parked conducted was with architects
It's always important with architecture
Joe Nichols
Play where the largest sample and clearest in some ways
Over the course of four weekend
In 1958 and 1959
Ipar brought together 40 of the most famous and important architects in the world
Observe them gave them test
And ask them all kinds of questions
Including
Some fairly ridiculous one
Next 45 minutes
We would like to discuss this notion
That is what man had developed the Third on
Where am I
That is an actual recording from the actual study
IPod got really famous architect
Richard Neutra
IM Pei Louis Kahn
All the big names of Modern Art
And I love that at one point
They were asked to discuss where
A third arm should go
On the human body
I would suggest that the most effective place would if it came right out of the top of your head
I disagree with that
I think it all to come
Straight Outta This back between the shoulder blades
Ipar scientists observe the Architects if they filled out questionnaires made mosaics out of colored tiles
And discussed hypothetical problems together
And what they learned help transform the way people think about creativity today
It all started with one of the first personality psychologists
The man who founded ipar and led the charge on the architect study
His name was Donald MacKinnon
McKinnon like to start his speeches with that story about the visitor to heaven in St Peter
Which makes sense McKennan himself had a vested interest in finding the secret great General hiding within the cobbler
Because during World War II
Kids served in the office of strategic services
What was the precursor to the CIA
McKinnon's job was to assess the personalities of American troops to see which of them could perform well in,
When the war was over he joined the faculty at Berkeley and founded ipar in 1949 to continue his personality
Research
But in the mid-fifties ipar switch from studying combat Readiness and efficiency
2 creative
In large part
Because of
Sputnik
Soviets
Launched the Sputnik
And.
Gave us a huge priority
The study how can we make our
Folks
The Americans
More creative so that we can be
The Russian
The space race was part of why I par embark
On this mission
They wanted to study the personality that particularly creative people
Play categorized a group of analytic creative like scientists and mathematicians and the second group of artistic creative
Like painters and writers
But then it was just hybrid where it was neither one nor the other
They was both and they put architect in. Group
Architect himself
And author of The Creative architect
Inside the great midcentury personality study
A book that Chronicles I pars Market
Because they thought Arkansas
Four perfect mix
Mathematician and artist
Architects were also interesting study subjects because understanding their creative habit
Potentially apply to a lot of different kinds of people
Successful Architects have to master numerous rules
They have to be businessmen artist
Engineers lawyers philosophers psychologists and educator
All rolled into one
Ipar one today
Huge
Test sample architect
Small firms and large
Somerset surveys
The participated from a distance
But an elite group was selected
Come to Berkeley
In person test
That was the first
Step
Identify Radioactive
Everybody will come up with some names then they were raped
Ipar rally to selection of architectural magazine editors and Museum curators and professors
Help select the most
Creative architects
Alive and working in the United States
So they came up with HR
And out of that
The circuit is write letters of invitation
So some folks
Never return
Buy Frank Lloyd Wright never answer
But they actually did convince
40 of The Architects on their list
Come down on four separate weekend
And they warned them
This is not going to be easy
Uses the grueling
United furnace
McKinnon said this is not going to be a relaxed
The Weeknd
The test began pretty much right away
As soon as the Architects arrived at the fraternity house that I par had borrowed for the study
They had just 15 minutes of introduction before they took their first test
It was constant over the course of the weekend
The Architects would be asked to make mosaics to assess their aesthetic sensibilities
Good in-depth interviews about their childhood
And even see if they could be hypnotized
And during the downtime they were still being observed by researchers with clipboard
Even cocktails and dinner is it
It's the time of study
It's a very very tights
But my favorite test The Architects did
Was one I park called the ethics problem
The ethics problem
Groupon I like it because it deals with a question that comes up all the time or I could
Enter creative
People all kinds actually
It's about whether a creative person
Should be willing to sacrifice part of their Vision to
Please
Client
At one of the test Type R did
Were they actually work
Where did the architect
Having this
Discussion in the course
Without you
Realize
Self-absorbed
Collegial
Architect
Group number for
April 25th
So in this discussion group on April 25th 1959 we're going to focus on three characters
And to keep them all straight we've got a musical cue for each one
The first and foremost is architect Eero Saarinen
Who designed St Louis Arch
The Dallas airport Dynamic soaring structure that blend sculpture and architecture
He is Iconic today and was a superstar then
It was a huge deal that he participated in the study
The second character we're going to talk about in this group is
Philip Johnson the minimalist architect responsible for Lincoln Center and The Glass House
Work is very Square their tithing actually the selection committee described Philip Johnson as
Perfection of certain limited aims
Very disciplined all of his work
Completely destroy
Regards human beings
And the Third characters will focus on
Was a promising up-and-coming architect
Victor Monday
36 years old
He was the youngest and least
Established in the group
The very small but very impressive
Portfolio
Okay so the virtuoso Eero Saarinen
The perfectionist
Bill Johnson
The young upstart Victor Lundy
Along with two other architects
Reserve cocktails and given a hypothetical situation concerning a hypothetical architect
Mr Brown
Mr Brown is faced with a
Difficult decision
Is just finished
The preliminary drawings for very challenging and important
Structure
His client has told him that he likes me
Nebraska postal very much
I will accept it if he will change
One fairly important aspect
Basically the client would like to design altered in a specific way and says he will have to reject mr. B
Brown's proposal if
The changes made
Brown really hates this alteration
But
This commission is highly prized and prominent
Coarse Brown want the client to be happy with the building
And he has to support himself and his practice
Factors
Phone ring
If you were Brown
What would you do
The architect
Then had to decide
Should Brown accept the change
What is the project
No I would like you to discuss the issue candidly among yourselves and rejoin
35 minutes
This archival audio has never been heard in any public way before like maybe only 10 people have heard it
So just sit back for a second and listen to the architect
And the ice
Clicking in their glasses
Discerning the Visionary
Starts the discussion
Sean should I dissipated
Concerning says that since Brown doesn't have any other solution prepared
You should walk away
The job at this
Let's fill up this regard to human beings Johnson butting in
It's a problem that's contrary to experience
It sounds very much like you've been reading iron rack
It sounds like you've been reading I am round
Johnson is referencing the book The Fountainhead
Where the main character is a fiercely independent architect
To blows up his own building rather than compromise with a client
Make no mistake Johnson would also refuse the clients changes
But he just thinks this whole scenario is it
Absurd
No good architect
Would let this happen with a
I answered there that I would
And I never heard of it happening
Have you actually seven and has been challenged by a client on a recent Commission
And
Is threatening to quit
Monday I have to get to
Quit
You expect to win by quitting
I say that
The only part
Yes
Would you say that the case is
Hopeless as intended
Victor Lundy the Young Gun piping up
I confess that I have to admit the possibility of the
Maybe there is a
Something
And what the client is leading to
Result in a better thing
The work of architecture
Really really good
Well then
The owner will say it
Sam dubs
Well know I'm young but I've seen some old thing
You Givin now the design can only get worse and worse than you worse for your reputation because of the function represented by
What is the future look
At the end of 35 minutes the group concluded that Mr Brown should reject the clients changes and walk away from the broad
This was the conclusion that all of the different architect groups ultimately came to
Having this option is for the luxury of being a very famous architect
I hope in all of this that
John brown was right
After 3 grueling days of tests
After all the Architects went back to their respective practices all over the country
The state still wasn't quite over
The Architects were mailed surveys and questionnaires
To rank each other
Some Architects refuse to rank themselves and their peers
Others
Jump Right In
Philip Johnson rated himself number one
Not surprisingly
But Saturday and Brady Johnson number 2
After himself
Frontier number one
But the fact that people put themselves number one also talks about
The conception of
Clearly
And The Architects conceptions of themselves messed with the findings from a lot of the other studies that iPod
Far had done over the years
The researchers began to notice
Certain patterns
Cross creatives of all professions
All genders
WeChat
Funding
But we got the same characteristics associated with a
People who were rated highest whether they would chemists or artists
Another feels
It turns out all different kinds of creative people met similar descriptions
Has an interesting interesting personality
Is non-conforming and has high aspirations for self
Also creatives preferred complexity and ambiguity over Simplicity in order
Creative had the capacity to make unexpected connections
Easy patterns in daily life
But
Creative people didn't necessarily
Have to have high IQs
Intelligence isn't as important
The creativity is
People thought it was
So I guess that's another thing we found
Average intelligence will do
And it's not as if this is directly related to intelligence but the school grade point average for the architect
What's a salad
B minor
So I par found that creative people
NTB non-conforming interesting
Interested independent courageous
And self-centered
Pretend to be they don't have to be a certain traits and they come up over and over again unless the creative person
But it doesn't mean that they're going to be exactly
I feel like I kind of couldn't guess all those right
I think it's a lot easier to
So we should have known that all along after weave
Found it
This idea of the creative personality was remarkable at the time
Ivar's findings were lauded and spread
But over the years
People began to think about personality differently
In the seventies an argument with emerging but maybe
Personality wasn't something innate within us
Maybe
Personalities are the results of our environment
Social expert
I part and their mission work
Called into question
The 1970s
Was it
Durable. For personality psychologist
I should tell you about that
We had trouble getting grants we had trouble
Getting Papers accepted and
And we had this horrible empty feeling ourselves
Ipar ended in 1990
Became what is now known as Apes
The Institute of Personality and Social
Which is expanded focus a lot more on social and cultural context
Beyond analyzing individuals
But just because people aren't using ipart's methods does not mean the study was all for not
I parred did proof that creativity wasn't this mysterious Untouchable thing
The study
This is ocean vartanian
At the University of Toronto his area of expertise is creativity and Aesthetics research
You take any kind of course
Creativity
Because they're considered to be the
First place
The scientific study of creative personnel
Today researchers don't study creativity as a complete concept like iPod tried to
Instead of studying it as a whole topic
It kind of break it up into
With a chunk that I'm particularly interested in is
The neuroscience
What
Rainbow
Ocean also studies architect
And their creativity
Rather than using
Say hypothetical discussion questions
He will put them into an fmri machine
To look at blood flow in the brain
Biggest northern
People design
As a person
Coming up with the room
And pasta
Braintree Mall
But even though oceans techniques are really high tack his research has its roots
Cine type-r studies
He thinks that they were really significant
Major countries
Backstreet show that
Personality
The Bible
Studies
If you want to understand create
And if nothing else
The lasting Legacy indeed ipar studies
Maybe these recordings of these great architect
Is a discus essential creative problem
Like where
In the body
To put up there in arm
Then it would be rather unsymmetrical
And I I don't think it would be as pleasant as if we could have could we have four
Destiny forums
45 minutes
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trouble
Katey mangels protocol stats and Greenspan Delaney Hall Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
Special thanks this week to Raymond nutria and Elizabeth peel and Robert Levinson of ipser original music this week by Shawn
Unreal of the band Little T
The archival audio recordings are courtesy of ipser UC Berkeley and Monticelli press
The publisher of pierluigi book
The creative architect
Inside the great mid-century personality study the book goes into more depth about the architect study and his images of
All these interesting surveys and documents
Including pictures of the mosaics The Architects were asked to make
Picture Monday for example use the whole rainbow of colors
Philip Johnson use only three colors
An Eero Saarinen
Use only one color
You can see them for yourself at 99 Pi. Org
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and even though we can still feel their warm
Embrace
We are no longer produced on the other
Boxes of arcsin
So you guys should stop
Coming by unannounced because they got jobs to do and we're not there anyway
However we do remain
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taken away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Can find the show and like the show on Facebook follow us all on Twitter and Instagram for the best way to explore the
99% invisible activity that shakes the design of our world in the browse around the hundreds and hundreds of stories
Epi.org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com