99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1957 a few months after the Soviet satellite Sputnik
Became the first human object in space
United States launch
Explore one
And with that
Space Race was underway
In the two world powers began launching more and more satellite
Every year
A lot of these early missions
Failed
Before they ever made
Into orbit
That's producer Emmett Fitzgerald
But there were two successes
Andrew my little space started to fill up
Which human made object
By the summer of 1961
There were 115 satellite
Circling the earth
It was during that summer that the US launched an unmanned rocket carrying the transit for a satellite
And about 2 hours after launch the rocket blew up it was the first
Known object to unintentionally explode in space and it created about 300 fragment
Of totally useless space junk some of these pieces got pulled into the atmosphere and burn
Burned up
But around 200 are still up there today
At the time most people weren't all that concerned about a few bits of metal floating around in the vastness
Space
Watching The General
Training was it space with big
I'm a tweaker
Object satellites
Open to space without Willie
Having any consequences to that
This is
Hugh Lewis
Space junk expert at the University of Southampton
Back in the early days of the Space Age
While the universe may be infinite orbital space
Raise the region where objects revolve around the Earth
Is finite
And the amount that we use regularly
Is even more limited
Most satellites end up in a few particular Orbitz
Almost like
Freeways on the traffic on most freeways is actually
Conscious and that's where the Problem Child 3 marriage
As the traffic increases
So does the chance of collision
One of the regions of space that got busy pretty quickly
Is the area called Low Earth orbit
Special region of space that extends up to an altitude of about 2000 km
Baby heavily congested
And my satellite stops working in low earth orbit
I can stay in that region for hundreds of years
By the mid-1960s
They were already lots of old into Funk satellite
Floating around
And nothing began to look into this
Based on your reading think about the potential issues of space debris opal debris
Might pose in the future
That was an activity that was really loud by don't cash that it was that not sure of the time
My name is Don Kessler I started the orbital debris program at NASA
Kessler is retired now but when he got started at Nasa he was studying media
And specifically what happens when two meteoroids
Collide and break apart in
And a smaller piece
Eventually Doncaster started doing similar research
Unspaced
Orb
Orbital.
Debris
Cancer was studying what happens when one piece collides with another
This is what you
Every time you have a breakup you increase the
Probability of another Collision
And that eventually just causes the whole population to continue to increase exponentially with time
This idea that space junk multiply
Like as more and more objects Collide and break apart
Came to be known as The Kessler Center
Intestinal predicted that the growth in space junk
What eventually
Snowball
And that cascading phenomena after
100 years
Gets to be
Well out of control
There's not much you can do about it and give it
Created environment
Very hazardous to space
It's a growth
In space junk went totally unchecked
Tesla predicted that space could become so filled with the
Debris
It would be difficult to
The fly a spacecraft without getting hit
Kessler's findings were discussed
Throughout the speech
And in 1979 NASA started its orbital debris program
The study and monitor space
And they appointed him delete it
Around that same time people began to use face more and more
Countries all around the world were launching weather satellite
Military
Communication saddle
Amateur radio satellite
Because space isn't owned by anyone government in particular
Low earth orbit
Began to experience a tragedy of the commons
Lots of different countries were leaving trash
Everywhere
But no one was tidying up
The amount of junk in space continue to grow throughout the 20th
Mid-century
But it wasn't until 2009
Long after Donald Kessler ever
If people really started
Csuci
Communication satellites
800 kilometers
On February 10th 2009 the Iridium 33 + active us communication satellite
Struck a defunct Russian satellite called the Kosmos 2251
It was the first collision between two fully intact satellites and it created thousands of pieces of debris
Donald Kessler wasn't surprised
40 years prior get predicted the first major collision between whole satellites of the size
What happened around the new millennium
For most people the Collision May the problem of space junk
Feel much more urgent
Iridium Cosmos
Collision
Rudy was a wake-up call
Spark the new wave of research and funding even facts
Space debris
Matthew Lewis again
Lewis says that it's hard to estimate
The total amount of space debris out there
But scientists can track anything larger than 10 cm in diameter
You're talking about maybe a population of objects that are
Shuffle songs
About 30,000 objects in orbit at the moment everything from small fragments
What's 2 old rocket body
Two satellites
The size of a bus
And that's just the stuff that's large enough to track
There are potentially Millions
It's of millimeter size bits of
Debris
Shards of glass
Screws Flex
And even that tiny stuff
Can cause real problems
20 whipping around the Earth
Add up to 17 thousand miles
Per hour
Yeah the object does not need to be big in order to carry a lot of energy
Substantial amount of damage if it worth anything
The most vulnerable thing in orbital space is the International Space Station
Which routinely has to make Maneuvers to avoid collision with larger pieces of space debris
The International Space Station is also equipped with expensive heavy-duty shielding to protect it from smaller bits of space
Astronaut Tim Peake recently took a picture of a sizable divot in one of the space station windows
Repeats of debris penetrated several cm into the glass
Select the constant reminder for the astronauts on the space station every time I look at that window
Recognition of the
It is not just a threat to astronauts
So much about technology here on Earth is dependent on vulnerable satellites
Are pretty much everyone in the UK in the US
Smartphone with GPS
Capability on it
Master Services provided by spacecraft
My money think about navigation signals are they used for
Flying in the sky
Everywhere and I'll tell you lying I'm not just UNIF a convenience
International Telephone communication weather for
Keeping track of time
In different parts of the world
All of this it's dependent on satellite
Global banking systems full down if we lost signal from space
These risks are causing scientists around the world to look into how they can clean up this pace environment
Now when someone wants to put a new satellite into space there are viewing guide
If it say you have to come up with a plan
To dispose of that satellite within 25 years
There are a couple issues with these guidelines
You're not being followed by everyone
And two even if they were more closely here to
It might not be enough
To make space safe
Because there's already so much stuff up there and is Donald Kessler discovered
Space junk X
Even if we stop putting any more stuff up there
The number of pieces of junk will continue to grow
And then we start to think about okay how do we address the problem
Captcha bit more proactive we how do we deal with the stuff that's already up bad
All around the world Engineers are dreaming up ways to remove debris from space
In many cases by sending it down into Earth's atmosphere to burn up
Destroy objects
Harpoons
There are proposals for space-junk slingshot
Solar sails
Carry a piece
Junk out of a dangerous orbit
Robotic arms attaching a booty to the object to try and bring it down attaching solar blanket
No matter how you do it removing an object in space will be expensive and politically complicated
But right now the European Space Agency is planning a mission to remove one of its derelict satellites
And they're considering these kinds of ideas
That mission
Is scheduled to take place
In 2023
So we all
On the cusp of this type of activity
But even if we found the perfect technology to safely destroy all of the space junk in Earth orbit
Not everyone is on board
I completely agree with
This is a problem we need to do something about
I think the way that it's framed
Leave that a really vital
And that factor is human cultural heritage
That's Alice Gorman also known as Dr space junk
I'm a senior lecturer in the
Department of archaeology
When does University end
Baidu research
Particularly looking at space junk
In low earth orbit
For much of her career Alice Gorman Dr space junk
Researched Aboriginal culture in office
Australia professional archaeologists
How many years
And I was
Wishing on a consulting job in Queensland
And looked up at the
The sky
And
Realize
Just that some of those
Coin supplies
But not stars or planets
They were actually
Schubin manufactured spacecraft
And some of those bits
Was space junk
And that's kind of what I kill it just do we refocused on the stuff that people discovered the
Stuff that throw away the garbage of humanity
So while the rest of her colleagues continue digging in the dirt
Gorman turned her attention Skyward
And began to study the archaeology of space
Because I'm it's the scraps of floating debris are some really remarkable artifact
A lot of those things account Nicole space junk I actually caught
Stroller I object
I have so much to tell us about
The early history of the Space Age
I've got a lot of favorites
In low earth orbit Vanguard one
Is definitely one of the
Launch by the United States in 1958
Vanguard one is currently the oldest intact object
In space
Is little grapefruit-size
Aluminium sphere with
4 + 10
On the side
It's flooding around up there
Along with the most recent satellite
Along with
Yunnan technology that's so incredibly different
And there are objects in orbit that look nothing like a
Traditional saddle
Like the Westford needles
Which were these small copper antennas that were sent into space in the 1960s
I would really tiny
So they will only like
A centimeter
Big
May I do with styrofoam
I reflect
Did halo around the Earth
But radio signal
Could be bounced from
Using radio waves for Global Communication
Never really took off
But some of the needles
Are still up there
Bunched together in little clumps of
The copper I find them really
Probably a lot more as ice
Stories in Urdu
Tell a story of technology that could have gone in One Direction
But it paid off in another one in
Instead the Gordmans all-time favorite piece
Might be the track
Which the US Navy launch from Cape Canaveral in 19 6
And it was
The first
Satellite to have a poem
Ennis written by professor of Italian literature at Yale named Thomas Bergen
And one stanza of the poem
Describe tile medallions
The panels inside
The satellite
So it's kind of already conceived
Give us a cultural object
And that cultural object
Is still up there
Orbiting the Earth about 1000 km
The poem reads
As we come to claim our promise place
All of these objects might seem far away
INXS
But the day will likely come
When we can go and visit
You can already get to the International Space Station for a cool 20 million dollars
Gorman says that one day we will be able to
Fly coach into space
It's quite likely that
You know what it's
Accessible and affordable things to do people will go into space and maybe set some fats
The Overton Hotel
And the two things we know
From
What's happened already that they will want to do
Is take a lot of photographs
And have sex
But after a while that's what's going to become old hat to
And what happens when zero g sex gets boring stores
That's what
You might have
Different kinds of toads as a satellite to you might say let's do the Cold War satellite
Or you might say
I'm not going to see all of the satellites it come from you. My nation space agency
So yeah I totally think this stuff
Is going to happen
It's going to be one of the things people to want
We actually have a space
Tourism industry
That people can afford
But the irony is in order to have viable space tourism
We need a safe orbital environment
And so if we don't find an effective way to clean up some of the junk in space
We might never be able
To go and see the good
It's kind of frightening it
In that much
Extreme version
Having you know ventured out to the moon and
Spacecraft
You know the Voyages
Beyond the solace
We would actually be shot back on us
So Gorman is all for cleaning up Spa
She just wants us to think carefully
Before we destroy something that we might want that
Because she can imagine the archaeologists and historians
The future
Trying to wrap their heads around Humanity's first trips into space
I'll be so many Mysteries so many things that I make
Make sense
So many
Stories that
You have
A little bit here a little bit there
And you trying to
Fill in the gaps
And those future archaeologists will thank us
For leaving some space.
Right where it is
99percentinvisible with produces week by Emmett Fitzgerald with Sharif Youssef same Greenspan Katie mingle Kurt Kolstad
Avery trufelman Delaney Hall Taryn Masa and me Roman Mars
Special things to okay akumi of Hell audio for some of the music that we use this week
We are product 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced on radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sign
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Message Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Belo radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I got a Thang
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com