99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
It really is almost everything
Infrastructure is just about everything that makes
Civilization physics
Possible
Rhodes
Bridges
Water supply
Sewage removal
Dams
So forth the physical
Part of civilization is
The infrastructure
Mets Henry Petroski
Well my name is Henry Petroski I'm a professor of civil engineering and history at Duke University
He's written a number of books about catastrophic
Failures in engineering
And also one about the history of the toothpick
So he's one of us
His most recent book is all about
The name of the book is the road taken the history and Future
America's infrastructure
Couple weeks ago I interviewed.
Trotsky about his book in the
The state of infrastructure
The US
The first of many things that I learned that
Xiaomi
Was that the word infrastructure itself is actually kind of new to English
What we call infrastructure today used to be called Public Works and did America Public Works
Was probably
A familiar term up until the 1980s
But Public Works became a term
Closely associated with what was called
Pork barrel
Which was
Also considered
Rent a rather pejorative term because
It had to do with
Building things that were considered unnecessary
Or wasteful
Pork barrel is government
Spending pushed forward by a congressperson
Casoli benefits
The people in their home District
It was associated with politics
Start
Was a tit-for-tat
You vote for my poor call vote for yours
But the connection between Public Works and government corruption got even worse than trading votes it reads to
It's pecan 1973
There was a major Scandal that one of our vice presidents of the United States had to resign Spiro Agnew
New because he basically
Was
Taking money for Road contracts in his home state of Maryland
Send the 1980s when shrinking government was becoming all the rage and pork barrel and earmarks were our biggest enemy
Did the Soviets
The term Public Works
Fell out of fashion
Infrastructure
Became a term
That replaced Public Works
Generally
But the term was still so new that in the 1980s The Wall Street Journal put in first
Within quotation
Since infrastructure is the physical part of civilization it's hard to generalize
Which government body or private party is responsible
Fergie to individual part of
So when our conversation we tended to focus on the big
Well let's take roads
We tend to think of Rose especially Highway
This is one of the wonderful things that the federal government
Well that's pretty much why
Rhodes
Today
In the United States are
Largely the responsibility of
Municipalities
And
States
One of the reasons that that's
Complicated like this is that the
Federal government
It's not authorized
Bye
The Constitution
To build roads or bridges are even
Fixing them up by itself it has to go through the state
Article 1 Section 8 of the US Constitution states that the Federal Government Can Build
Post Road
Meaning
Routes for the post office to operate fact
But no other kinds of roads are Spotify
In fact in 1817 when bill was passed by
By Congress that approve the funding of
Internal improvements in the country like roads
Ben Canales
It was vetoed by then President James Madison
Cuz he felt it was unconstitutional
And you should know
Because he wrote
Constitution
The federal government can give
Awards to the states
You give grants to the states or municipalities but it it can't do it
Itself
But what the feds can do is put a tax on gasoline to raise money for roads
Could stay then give to the states
10 cities
This has been the case since the Revenue Act of 1932 which was
Pacify her
Hoover which re stacks
Sazon pretty much ever
Presently it's 18.4%
Per gallon
And that gives the federal government
About 30 billion dollars a year to distribute to the states
And that distribution the federal government X
Exercises Sun control
And enables it to provide some standardization to the roads which I consider a good thing
Me too because he don't really want to drive from one state to another and fun at the roads
Are completely different
It was the federal government that
Brought all the states
Into unification with
The
Colors of the
Lines on the roads yellow lines divide traffic when different ways white dashes divided Lanes
The same way
Federal government making money contingent on following a standard
Is what
Make that happen
But the 30 billion dollar Federal Highway trust fund which is fed by the national gasoline tax
Isn't keeping up with our current needs
One easy solution of course would be to
Increase the gasoline tax
It hasn't been increased since
Quiet
While
Because the federal gas tax has been so stagnant
State state upon themselves to Levy their own State gas.
And funder road projects that way
Increasing the federal gas tax is not popular
So politicians have trouble
Will doing it
But even if they could
It isn't a great solution
Obviously if you're going to depend upon the tax on gasoline per gallon
Or replenishing the fund then
You have to project how
Many gallons of gasoline are going to be used in weather
That
Volume of consumption is going to the Be steady or increase and generally we
Expect things like that to increase
Right now people are driving more electric and hybrid vehicles than ever before
They still use the roads but they spend less money at the gas
So Prius owners maybe saving the environment
But they are mooching off our roads
It is so hard to do right
So now there's an option to separate the collecting of taxes needed to maintain the road
From the consumption
Can of gasoline
Instead of
Taxing the fuel that used
You text
The mileage that the vehicle
Travels on
State roads
Regardless of
Weather at uses fuel or not
And just to be done in a variety of ways
At present there are a number
Of pilot program
That are trying this out
There are pilot programs that involve self-reporting the number amount edry
But the obvious
Is David gps-based tracking device
Inside each car
And we'll see if that goes anywhere
Because if you're someone who gets freaked out about
The constitutionality of the federal government building roads
I'm going to guess that you're not going to be too keen on the federal government installing a tracking device in your
Cardizem
I suspect it will take at least a decade to replace the gas tax entirely
But it will probably come
Infrastructure is all about choices
When a new bridge is proposed
There are countless discussions about whether the bridge
Purely functional
Cheaper or if it should be a signature piece of architecture that attracts International attention
Their cases to be made on either side
Signature
Myself
But even mundane features like roads involve choices that reverberate for decades
Most roads today that are Interstate roads
Are made of asphalt
Asphalt advantages of course is it at seamless
There is a real pleasure and driving on a new
Black asphalt road
Plus asphalt can be laid down quickly it's relative
Cheap and it's easy to patch and repair
The downside is
It's not especially durable
You actually have the patch repair quite a lot
Alternatively you can build a much more durable concrete road
Concrete doesn't offer that smooth seamless ride that ass
Does because
Physics
With concrete we need
What are so-called Expansion Joints what appear to be
Cracks
What are really deliberate lines
Cut into the concrete to allow it
The crack in a controlled way
The cracks are there so the throat doesn't break into pieces in the concrete contracts and expands due to Bigfoot
Fluctuations in temperature
But the tires of a vehicle
Going over there making noise in
Vehicle feels it when you're driving on a concrete road
And the ride is not as smooth as quiet as a
Can be on well-laid asphalt
In addition concrete roads are more expensive than
Send it to repair and they take long
But they aren't is prone to potholes and can last a lot longer than asphalt road
So decisions have to be made
Do we go with the cheaper quicker easier method and save money now
I'll go with the more expensive
Slower and less pleasing method and hope to save money on repairs and replacement cost
Overtime
Since so many of these
Decisions are made in a political context
By people who
Know that they are going to
Probably move on
Before the Patriot Paving has to be
Done
Will generally opt
For the Lesser expensive
Choice which means ask
Asphalt is simply cheaper than concrete
And therein is
One of the main reasons
That we have so much Asphalt in the
Country
But there is a more radical choice
In Montpelier Vermont there was a road
Call Bliss route
Which was in a terrible
State of disrepair
For many years
It'll finally in 2009
Unpaved the road turn it into a dirt and gravel road
It's in 27 States
It's have also unpaid some of their roads for the same reason
I wondered if it was a clever solution or just
Demoralizing
I've heard about that
And that it does seem like a pretty clever solution it's
Probably not a very popular solution among the paving contractors
For example
It would it would depend on the nature of this road if this is a road that doesn't have especially heavy traffic
Not a lot of heavy truck traffic
It might work from an engineering
Point of view
When the Eastern span of the Bay Bridge
It's about to open in 2013
They set aside a day
Pedestrian
It's to walk the bridge
What's like people did in 1883 when the Brooklyn Bridge
I was all set to bring my kids
Celebrate this new massive piece of infrastructure
But because of last-minute repairs the event was cancelled
And the Bridge open to traffic with
Much less public involvement
And I really didn't get a sense that people were all that upset about it
We collect we just don't have the feeling that
Infrastructure warrant celebration
North Central Pride like we Once Dead
Is October 12th
Why he thought that is
Oh I think
We
The electorate has
Your garden naturally lazy about the affair structure like we have
About a lot of things we tend to focus on
WhatsApp immediate concern to us
We we might worry more about our driveway
Dundee Highway that is nearby
I do think that celebratory events
Are important
And that do help generate that
Pride and almost responsibility because everybody's up
Part of all this
Different things that we we vote for in pay for in our our taxes in
And fees we're really part owner of of all that stuff
After we should worry about it is
As much as we do our
Our neighborhood
What do you think about the idea of reclaiming
The term Public Works
You know to reflect the fact that it is owned by all of us and that is is
Public
That's a good idea
Haven't given it a great deal of thought but
That would make it more explicit
It's for the publican
By the public in in a in our way infrastructure is sexual
What is it a latinate word that
Makes it more apps
Trachten
Remove
So yeah that's that's an interesting idea
Well
I just thought about how good I have a proposal
Send out to the world
39% invisible is Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall
Pirkle's Deli
Turn down
Katy Bingo Avery truffle Venture reviews
F&b Road
Special things to Oliver s
That's for answering some questions about
Paper that I had on Twitter
We use Music this week from the trifecta 99 Pi All-Stars that's okay cannoli
Melatonin and melodia
Weather music
I can make your life better
Will have links on a website
We are project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Besides routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptom
Comes come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find this show and talk about this show
Facebook and photos all on Twitter and Instagram or Tumblr curate School design stories from around the way but the easiest way
Way to listen to all the past episodes and read more cool stories about design it's go to our website
99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com