99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% in this
I'm Roman Mars
Do you know I was talking to John Marr he's the guy who first sputtered this Bedrock 99 Pi mantra
Always read the plaque
We were talking about the show and he said you know what you should do a story about
It's one of my favorite places in San Francisco
So I went to the address when I checked it out
I kid you not
He sent me to a gas station
On Van Ness Avenue in San Francisco
He told me to look around and discover what was weird about
In almost every respect is that normal Chevron gas
It has a blue awning
And the red and blue Chevron logo on the side
But
The sign and Awning don't say
Chevron
Standard
As in standard oil a massive oil Monopoly broken up in the early 20th century by the Sherman Antitrust Act
When the independent companies created by that break up
Was Chevron
And for some reason
Even though
This gas station is a modern Chevron station in every way
It's called
Standard
Did you call the Station they will answer the phone saying Chevron and the attendant cannot tell you why it's a standard on the side
But trademark
Like Amanda levendowski
Can't
Trademark can be any
Word names
Device used by someone who has
Bona fide intent to use the mark in Commerce
And are using that word symbol device
Hugh
Identify the source of their goods
That phrase bona fide intent
Means that you want to keep a trademark
You have to use it
In this particular case
When General oil was busted at
Standard Oil trademark
Still retain a lot of
Goodwill in value
And if for whatever reason down the line Chevron wants to take advantage of that value
The name standard
Has to be used
And I have to be used in connection with whatever the underlying
Goods or services are so
They couldn't dress
Prince
Templates
Occasionally used mix Chevron standard branding and say that they were still using it for oil and gas
Matthew prominently use the standard name in conjunction with oil and gas services
If they want to keep
So that's why there's a standard gas station
All intents and purposes operates as a Chevron station
In San Francisco and 15 other locations in the US
This week
You should do a story
We're researching and presenting short design stories requested by our listeners and seen where that path takes
And in the spirit of the exercise
We're starting with what I think is the most requested design topic of all time
Here's our digital director Kurt Kolstad
I thought you with me
About
Desire path
As the name suggests desire paths are these unplanned routes people just really want to take
And their sheep by repeated use
And I think part of it is that they're found
Everywhere you can just see them all over the place
And the most common type of UC
Are short
Which are often just visible as
Ruffner Trails through you know grassy areas
Is insidious
The most commonly when you think of Desire path you think I would like
Imagine like
A circuitous or maybe like a 90-degree turn on a sidewalk
And then there's this like 45 degree
Dirt path
That cuts across
And create a shortcut and that's
The most common idea what it's Sour Patch
This is people want to take the shortest path but
Desert pets are not always
Back sometimes they end up being a long cut
And this can happen for all kinds of reasons in some places
There superstitions about walking under utility pools
And some people end up taking his long way around and you can see that box in the dirt
Or like when there's like
A slope going down to a to a crossover underneath the road
And normally in a biker with bike down that hill and then bike back up the other side
But often there's like a way to just you know take the grass
And go off to the side
Indians of being a longer path
But I want to go up and down hill
So it's like a shortcut in the center
Energy it'll still take them less work ultimately but it also is just kind of weird because it blows out to
Besides
So this can be really frustrating as an urban planner because a lot of reason
You designed things the way you do is that use the built environment to shape the behavior you want
But
Deserve us can also be eliminating because
They can really show a designer how to make their design work better for people
Right sometimes they frustrate the plans of urban planners in trailmakers but other times these people can actually
Evaluate
The behaviors that people have naturally
And use that to inform their designs
So for example college campuses have been known
To map out a basic grid of sidewalks
But then leave some sidewalks unpaved and just sort of see where people walk to fill in the gaps and then they
They come back in and they pee fat
Based on the natural behavior of those people walking
And in Finland
Park Winters have been known to
Watch and see where people walk after a big snowfall so there should be a blank slate
And people cross the park
And they just trace the pause then use that to inform a year-round pathway for that
Which I see reminds me of my favorite form of
Snow base
Desire path the snake down
Which is a portmanteau
Snowy and neck. Which is kind of hard to picture it's like a
Part of the car but you can imagine like a straight
Street
And then like a little bit of a bump out of the curb in extension of the
Drug is called a neck down
So how did the people use a snake down
So like those finished Park planners that are evaluating
Where people walk after snow falls
Urban planners can use
Smackdown to evaluate workers drive after a snowfall
And more specifically they can look at where they don't
So when the fresh snow
Covers the road drivers in the following there or pass
And then other cars follow in that narrow path which leads a lot of area actually untouched
And this results in what is effectively like a temporary curb extension
And can also form for the traffic islands in the middle of streets
Where cars just don't go
But didn't did they ever take this information and like use it for other parts the year when it isn't snowing
That's really the key is
Erlanger's can evaluate where people don't go
And use that information
Advocate for curb extensions and traffic islands where they don't it currently exist
And the argue is pretty straightforward I mean if the cars
Don't need to go there in the winter
Why do they need to go there at all right
PetSmart I like it it because you look a little
Sandbox to plan once the snow falls and all the sudden
You realize that you can have this opportunity to replaying your city and these two little tiny waist
Oh wow this analysis is really kind of lovely it's
Like people go out and they take pictures living videos and then they trace over these places where the cars don't go and suddenly
It was very clear the cars
Actually need that
1 reasons why desire paths
Since I found her soap that resonates so much with
Awnings and not because they're urban planners
It's because there's this great metaphor for design in general
Yes and a lot of people use them
And usability design and think about them
In terms of
Interface design
So
A really common tactic is to not just
You decide we're going to make this thing this way and people going to use it this way
But instead to actually look at how people are already using something
And then take that and get it a more official way to work
The word example on Twitter you know apps and hashtags
Who's built in with Twitter
Users of all those
Overtime
And then put her images that o
Well if user using them we're going to support this usage and you know evolve
I never really thought about that at Saint
Hashtags for basically desire path created by the user
Digital desire
You want to take a deeper dive into the hash mark
Four octave work is a
For the calling
Average of Mendenhall episode about its Origins
Turn your hymnals
New episode number 145 you will fight
Ministry suggestions we get come through Twitter someone
Twitter login
And we'd a lot from emails to but this suggestion
Came to senior producer Katie Mingle
In person
Yeah so this was after our recent live show that we did in La a fan came up to me
And he was like nice job
Also I've story idea for you
Ugly it on me and he start telling me about it and it was like about electrical current clock
What's the time in Southern California win
Switch I I don't know I didn't absorb that much of it at the time
What did you tell me it did kind of sound like a bar alley so I went back I started looking into it and
Basically the story starts back
In the late 1800s
The Los Angeles area and through surrounding the other towns in Southern California
We're starting to get there first
Power plants in the main motivation at the time
Listen to bring Refrigeration to the Citrus Growers
So they can play
Oranges inside
Refrigerators
Exactly for cold Orange
Of course
And so back in these early days
List of electricity there wasn't a national standard for like what frequency of
Current these power plants should deliver us
What is an Alexa
Really mean and then what are the option
Do you have to work
I'm still at school
Now the part of the show her I explain electricity
No I don't want to actually do the complete the service of
Talking too much about the physics of electricity but
The way I understand it is at electricity basically comes into our homes in waves of alternating current
And you can actually think of them like pulses
And the number of
Pulses per second is the frequency of the current
So if you're on a 50 Cycle System or like a 50 hertz
System
The pulses are coming at 52nd and then 60 hertz would be
60 second
I'm 50 and 60 are sort of the two most
Common
Frequencies
And why would you use one like
They're both fine they both do all the things we need them to do and you can deliver current at lots of different
Frequencies
But if you slow it down enough likes a 2:30 Hertz
When you screw in a lightbulb
You apparently
Can actually perceive a sort of
Stop pulsing in it
Service perceived as like a flicker
Inverter
In the light bulb
So in the early 1900s Southern California so Lake Los Angeles Burbank Pasadena
They all start from getting on the 650 Hertz
System
And meanwhile the rest of the country is getting on a 60 hertz
For the most part and there's like
Some exceptions
Right in civil right now that's not that big a deal in the early 90s
But eventually this greatest. Going to all meet up
Would not be
Right I'm so it starts to become a problem and one of the things that becomes a problem is like manufacturer
Had to make different products for people in Southern California
Because anything with like an electrical motor that was designed to work on a 60 Cycle System is not going
To work as well
50 Cycles
System
And one of the things that definitely didn't work as well was Electra
Clocks
So if you had a clock that you got a New York City and then you moved to LA and you plug in your clock
It would actually lose 10 minutes
Every hour
Yeah
And that is because
Electric clock
Actually use those
Pulses of current
Keep track of the time you know some clocks
Have pendulums but
Keeping track of those
Pulses of current is it is the way that electric
Clocks know what
Time it is
Or when to move
And at that point electric clocks were really popular like a lot of
People have them they're not
Common anymore
3:00 swear problem other things with motors
And then in the thirties California started to receive
Power from new dams like the Hoover Dam
And this power was coming into California at the wrong
And then the power companies with
Convert it
And the conversion process was difficult and expensive
So in 1936 the city of Los Angeles decided to
Switch all there
Customers to 60 Cycle
Current and then in 1945
The Southern California Edison Company decided to switch
Everyone else in Southern California
Over to the the sick
Dixie cycle
And that must be crazy because you're talking about every Appliance
Plugs into
The wall
He's now like being running
Suboptimal
Frequency
And therefore you have to change everything
Yeah it was nuts it was a huge undertaking like they weren't just like okay sorry like throw out your stuff
They sent
Cruise into people's homes to retrofit their washing machines
They sent people into factories
To make sure all the Machinery worked right
And it was
Hundreds of thousands of
Customers like I think nearly a million
Customers
Spend another power companies also had to change all their own equipment all the electric meters
And then
Four clocks you could actually go and drop your clock off at it
At 7 call the clock Depot
And there were just like rows and rows and tables of
Clocks being worked on and serve men sitting there working
To make your clock work
Riddles is like
You have this big
Such a project and then everyone just got to work and made it work for everybody
Quite a few
So by 1948 all of Southern California has
Switched
To the new system and the final
Tally was like 500000 clock
Almost 400,000 lighting fixtures
58000 refrigerators
And if you think of
How the population of LA
Exploded in the following years it's
It's so lucky
That they decided to take this on when they did
I mean you can possibly do it now
No like no way and that's sort of why you'll never see like
International
Standard for electrical current
So you'd be may know if you've traveled to Europe that you have to buy like a little adapter
Cuz most of Europe is
Still on A50 psychosis
And they'll never change cuz it would just be
I was just be too much I think the United States and Mexico
Chicago and most of like
Central America maybe South America or R6
Cycle
And Japan is actually I think the only country that still uses two different frequencies
In there one country
So basically one half of the country has
50 hertz
Send the other half
Is using 60 hertz
Open MySpace
Yeah it actually like was a really big problem after the Fukushima at
Accident because a big portion of the country lost power there was a tsunami
They were trying to send power from one part of the country to the other which is
Fairly common thing that
You know we do
But they couldn't do it you can
Convert
From one frequency to another but it's hard to do it
In really big
Quantities
And sold every so often in Japan actually there will be this little movement that bubbles up that's
Like we should all be on the same frequency and then
It just like really quickly dies because like once I was like well we're not going to switch
Every Other Side Cycle where is definitely not going to switch either
And that's the end of that
What stays the same
So it's
Say the same and yeah we
Can think of those early
Pioneers in La that were like let's go ahead and do this before Things Are
Control
Thanks
Those guys
And thanks to Jake in it
Yeah I think
PJ Cannon
And you talked to a couple other people that you want to say
Talk to a horologist named Ken Randall for the story I thought the story was actually going to be more about clocks
Send it ended up being so Island
Anyway she was great
I asked him if he'd heard a sound he said no of course I immediately sent him a link
And then I also talked to an electrical engineer named Darrell Heinrich
Who is also really
Really helpful
Longtime crew clothes that has been obsessed with
European style tilt and turn windows
Really ever since he was a kid living in viroid Germany
I can't really explain them in audio with a really functional and
Worthy of his design obsession
What about them recently on the website
And several readers shared and appreciated his design session
And to some they were completely new
And there was a bunch of Europeans were just confused because they didn't understand that these windows weren't already everywhere
Half the readers were astonished these things exist and wanted to have them and the other half
Shocked that anybody would think they were shocking because they were totally ordinary everyday window design
So this web article prompted a bunch of our audience
It's to send in suggestions for other clever Regional design Solutions
That we should also do a story about
What are the things that
Somebody suggested right off the bat
Which I was instantly fascinated by
Are these things called
Finnish dish drying closet
They're also known as dish drying cap
Okay tell me the truth
It's osteon
Cuy
Valve
Scopy
Xian Cuevas comp
That's what it's called that's what it's called
Asean cruise by icamp
Okay so go ahead
So the design has a pretty simple premise
If dishes can drive themselves and Storage
There's no need to drive a manual
So instead of having a drying rack next to sink
You put your dishes away in the cabinet above the sink
And this cabinet has special shelves with slots
The waterfalls down through each level
And it lands ultimately in the sink or on a sloped surface
Richland Transit
And of a nicer of
Design by product
This end up cleaning up clutter in your kitchen so you don't have this
You know just drying rack is always half-full dishes sitting next to sink
So your dis Trainwreck is essentially the same cabin
You put your dishes away in exactly the one step process
You just get out of take the dishes
Put them away they drive themselves
I love it
It's so beautifully simple
They should do that
We should have those everywhere
So this Regional design match
It was suggested by
By Anton
Now that he lives abroad
Anton says
I have to dry my dishes
Anorak
That's it from the counter
Biker bar bear
Truant on I agree with you
We are Barbarian
So you wrote an article about that when it was a huge hit
And then it cause people to send in other little Regional
And suddenly I had a lot of
Regional design Solutions work with
And one of the first ones that
Came out was this could Tatsu table
Which is a Japanese burnishing that doubles as a heating
Show picture of really tall coffee table with
A quilt
Over the sides that you
Put your legs on
And I underneath the tables there's a small space heater
Endless top layer of the table it's a large picture but just like two two two panels sandwich this blanket so you
You have a service that you can set things on but you also have
Is blanket or comforter extending out on all sides
Instead of sitting around in an arc facing a fireplace
You can actually sit around in a circle
And face each other and pull up sections of this cover
And then to interact around this this Central Heating
Why is this a Japanese thing
Historically been really useful in Japan specifically because
Home insulation is often sparse
And whole house heating can be difficult and expensive
And then traditional Japanese clothing also lends itself especially well to this form of space Heating
Because warm air can flow up to the folds of a spacious kimono and then out
The neck and arm holes
I mean that's what I like about it is
It has a lot of very specific reasons that it comes out of Japan
But a lot of those aren't necessary to add function either
A lot of those things would work for a really unique place
With the way that it's optimized for a kimono suggests that
It didn't used to be
Electric heating oil
No historically they came from a food cooking system that was in the floor so they have these charcoal burning
Who took hers in the floor and this morphed into a system
Where they would try to use that to keep the home that eventually in on the modern era
The certiport dangerous
ConEd fire solution was replaced by an electric
Local heating system
Cool one of those
Kotatsu table
These would be great everywhere as long as they burn your legs is there any incidents
Did you hear about anything about
Advisories
The daylight don't fall asleep under your couch
2 table legs
Lead to injuries and things are perfect
Sleep under tables in general probably
So it's really important to use
Table as described
But that is not like our next
Design solution was one of its powers is
The versatility
Of this on
It's called The Hills
The hills hoist is effectively
The opposite use case it can be used for everything
That is not designed for
Basically it's a rotating clothesline they have a central metal pole that sticks up from the ground like the trunk of a tree
The smaller clothesline Sports
The branch out from the top
And then this thing sits
Awesome backyards and it's been slowly Breeze drying clothes on a series of lion
That just a circle that
Central Pool
And where is the healthways
Hills hoist was developed in Australia
And
Pioneered by this guy
In the 1940s was coming back from the war
I decided to basically build his own backyard
Rotary close
It wasn't the first of its kind but his really took off
Commercial success
Now that company sells millions of
The things
This is not just a thing for drying clothes
Backyard like this
Is become and iconic designs
Really tied to
Australia
Yeah it one of our listeners wrote In
The really great
Very detailed explanation of its role in Australian culture
And basically
As she explains it
It's
This kind of critical fixture of the Suburban Australian dream
When you get this quarter acre lot with
Beautiful backyard
In your beautiful backyard you have the seals
Is any sort of an incomplete picture
Without that
Iconic thing
But unlike the single-use case of the Finnish cabinet
Or even though
The kotatsu table
UC
Pictures of hills hoist being used
Things that kids hang on and spin around and
Pinatas or whatever like anything that you can hang something and want to spend it
The hills voices
The perfect solution
Yeah it didn't
There's a great YouTube video that out there
Of these guys who
Hooked up
Lines the thing
And a motor and have it spinning super-fast in like they're whipping kids around on a on a water slide on the ground
And if there's like a wedding or holiday party you decorate your Hills hoist
There's a drinking game where people hang bags
Wine from the thing and spend those around
Emily kind of one of these I kind of love about it is that
Like every stage of your life
There is some activity that you do whether you're a kid
Who's swinging on the thing
Or somebody is much older and sitting in the shade
You put on top of the thing
Everybody has
Some use for that
Righto if you combine the ubiquity of this object with boredom of sitting in your backyard
You will get some kind of creative solution
Or something yeah yeah yeah yeah I think it's this big thing and it's a knitted vert
Into inevitably people figure out new things to do with it
Five Below
Hanging clothes
So hats off to the Hills
It's something special
Thanks to Alyssa Stephens for letting us know
About the hills hoist
Do you want some pictures of any of these or if you have a regional design solution from your home country or state
We'd love to hear about it
You can reach us
And 99 pi
. org
99percentinvisible was produced this week by crook hosted Katie mingle and me Roman Mars
Respa team is Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall turn master Sean real Avery trufelman answer review
We are product of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Mapreduce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Ubuntu showing during discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 PI work
Instagram Reddit and Tumblr to
But they're still a raging debate
About the best way to depict
Ellen ending on a road sign
And 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
A treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com