99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There's a pretty famous novel about the old American West
Called lonesome.
Published in 1985 and won a Pulitzer Prize and was later made into a TV mini-series
It's one of the best books ever written I think
That's our own Katie mingle in the book A group of cowboys from Texas Cattleman as they were once
Call Dr the huge herd of cattle through the great Open West all the way from Texas up to Mom
Montana
It's an epic adventure story the writing is just gorgeous
Here's a path
As they rode North they saw more Buffalo
Mostly small Bunches of 20 or 30
The third day north of Yellowstone they killed a crippled Buffalo Calf
And dying on its liver
In the morning when they left there were a number of buzzards
And two or three Prairie wolves hanging around
Waiting for them to leave the carcass
It was a beautiful morning
Chris for an hour or two
And then sunny and warm
The country rolled onto the North
Has it had four
4000 to miles
Brown in the distance
The prairie grasses waving in the breeze
The book which is fiction takes place in the 1870s
And the reason we're talking about
Is that basically everything about that scene was about to become impossible
The whole premise of the book really
Was about to become impossible
In just a few years
Cattle drives would come to an end
The West will become populated with people in towns and Railway
And almost all of the Buffalo
Would be gone
This change would come about incredibly
And a lot of it
Would be brought about by one very simple invention that would come to be known as the devil's real
But let's back up just a tad
In the mid-1800s not many non-native Americans had ever been west of the Mississippi
When Frederick Law Olmsted visited the West in the 1850s
He remarks that it was like a sea of grasses
Batman and swells after a great storm
And they were so tall that
In order to
See where you are going to get your bearings you have to stand on a horse's back
That's Joanne Liu
Hi my name is Joanne Liu I am a texas-based writer and editor
You had to go far west you had to go to the West Coast of Washington Oregon California to Seymour
Said it was out there
The middle of the country was divided into territories in apart from Texas
Summit
On the maps up until I would say about 1850s 1840s
They just label that whole region
As a great American desert
They later change the maps to say the Great American Plains
But still
The middle of the country was a vast unknown
It was sparsely populated
Mostly by Native Americans and by Cattlemen who are supplying beef to the people on the East Coast
And then in the mid-1800s
People in the East start thinking about manifest destiny
And about settling the West
The American government
Wanted to settle the American West
And they didn't view Cattlemen
And Native Americans are suitable Settlers of the West
What they wanted out there were people who would actually
Farm tallinn
Put down the roots improve the land with buildings and communities
And they look to the Yeoman farmer to do that
Ye Olde Yeoman farmer
So in 1862 President Lincoln signs the Homestead Act
Which basically says if you move west
Settle on a piece of land that
Other people and farm it
And you do that for 5 years
The land is yours
160 Acres
Free for the taking
Of course the young man you know us common Folk
Started heading west
Free land that can't be hard right
Right
Guys
It seemed like a great idea
Stayed
Really didn't think about how difficult that would be for
People going out there
No toy stores no schools
And of course no
No fencing material
And it turns out fences were crucial to Farmers
But that sea of grasses
Was not a sea of fencing material
In other words
There weren't many trees to use for lumber
Yeah this other start going out there and what they found was that the land was fertile it was great for farming
But
There was cattle everywhere and so when they start to plant their crops
The cattle just simply wander onto the field trampled and Destroy every all their efforts
To keep cattle out of their cross the farmers tried using these really thick and thorny Osage orange edges
Is for fencing
They work pretty well but they took five years to grow and if you had to move the boundaries of your property
Tough luck
Butler's also tried smooth wire fencing but the cattle could just bust right through it
Everyone was getting really frustrated lot of settlers they move west and found that they had this
This problem on their hands and there was nothing they could do about
And then they left
Fencing became an issue of much discussion there was talk about everywhere you went among farmers of
Course but also in newspapers agricultural Publications and in the US government
Department of Agriculture that I think was the land office did a study in 1870
And they basically determined that
It was
Not feasible
To settle the West
Because there was no fencing
What's impossible
Our destiny could not be manifested without solving the fencing problem
And the solution
Barbed wire
There were a lot of different patents filed for barbed wire like fences around this time
Twitter attempted to replicate the deterrent properties of the thorn bush
Ultimately the barbed wire design that prevailed was from a guy named Joseph Glidden
In 1873 Glidden was at a County Fair in his hometown of DeKalb Illinois
When he saw a fence that inspired him
Strip of wood
Withnail like spikes on it
The strip of wood was meant to be attached to a smooth wire fence
And he realize he could he can improve on that
Glenwood home and created what we now know as Barb Wire
Sharp metal barbs twisted around a strand
Smooth wire
And from then he intertwine a second smooth piece of wire
So that
The Twisted bar could not
Slide around
Gwen went into business with a guy named Isaac Ellwood and they said about trying to get barbed wire into the hands of Western
Settlers but people were skeptical that barbed wire would work against the kind of cattle they were raising in the west at the time
The Texas Longhorn
Texas Longhorns for the most unruly
Belligerent cattle
And so the idea that this little piece of barbed wire could
Keep them out of
Anywhere
Laugh
So The Story Goes
That Gooden in Elwood sent a fast-talking salesman and compulsive Gambler known as John bed
Add a million Gates
Down to San Antonio
To sell barbed wire and bet a million Gates basically tells all the farmers and cowboys
Together up there most unruly cattle and stick them inside this barbed wire enclosure
But she built in the Town Square
By the other day
There's a huge crowd
They put the cattle in the enclosure and they got them all riled up
And the cattle just went crazy
They rushed up against the defense
And immediately we are back
Cuz they met up with a barbed wire
Eventually the cattle all just kind of meekly settled down better Mill and gate start taking orders
Right then and there
Word spread and so did the barbed wire all over the West
1874 when Glendon Elwood first started they produce
10000 lb of barbed wire
1876 was the same year that Betty Milton Gates went on San Antonio
They
We're producing nearly 3 million pounds
Before barbed wire hit the West
The Cattleman had just been kind of watching and laughing as that Yeoman farmers
Struggle with their
Fence shrubs
Remember the West
For the Homestead Act
Was in large part
Populated by Cattlemen and the various Native American tribes
Has been made of the animosity between Cowboys and Indians
They have this one kind of striking thing in common
Neither really believed in fencing off the land and hanging no trespassing signs
The west of the American Cowboy before the Homestead Act
Was governed by something called The Law of the Open Range now I'd always thought that the Open Range
It was a figure of speech
Like it just meant big open pastures
It was like the way things were done
It was a big deal in the West
So
It just
Became practice
Common practice that became Unwritten code of law
I don't need to rearrange Farm why to fatten up
And for cattle to get the grazing lands they needed the land had to
To be open
So you can probably guess who was about to ruin
Everything
ELD Yeoman farmer and their barbed wire fences
It was in direct contradiction of the law of the Open Range apart from that people also thought that barbed wire
Water was cruel
A lot of the cattle you know they would be injured by the barbed wire and they would their wounds would become infested with screw bar MN
Double die
A whole side business of elixirs for wounded cattle sprung up
Briefly people try designing more Humane barbed wire fences
They were made to be easier for the cattle to see and avoid
But they didn't catch on
In any case
The Cattleman weren't happy
If you ever seen the musical Oklahoma and
Oh I have
You might remember this little ditty called the farmer and the Cowman should be friends
I'd like to say a word.
D, Weston field a lot of fences
I'm right across. Cattle range
The chorus of the song and floors all territory folks to stick together
But in reality Cowboys and Farmers wouldn't become friends for a while
Cattlemen resented the farmers as they put up more and more fences
And that's what's up
Yeah defense carnivores
The fence cutting Wars
They started around 1881
It began with Cowboys cutting down illegal fences the people were putting up around land that they didn't
I'm even have a rightful claim on
What happened was as this sort of momentum built
I'm a lot of people start joining in a lot of Outlaws and
Rustlers and they started
Cutting
Illegal and legal fund
Anytime and followed suit
And it just it just
Erupting chaos
Starting in Texas
And it spread northward all the way up to Montana
The Cowboys cut fences at night
With masks on
But even had fans cutting gangs with names like the owls
Blue Devils
And the land League
This all went on for about 4 years
Most of the damage was in property value
But there are a few dots on record
Eventually the Texas state government and the FEDS got involved and the fence cutting finally died down
Around 1885
During the 1800s the Buffalo that roamed the American West died off in huge numbers
Partly because settlers were killing them for their hides
But also because of fences
Buffalo needed large areas for their migration
And just like it did for the cattle barbed wire and peaden's Buffalo's access to grazing lands and water
Poor white people live in the west it's estimated that 65 million buffalo live there
But by the end of the 1800s
There were less than 1000
By the time Barb Wire hit the West
A lot of Native American tribes had already been forced onto reservations
But somewhere still relatively free living a nomadic lifestyle that follow the migration of the Buffalo
And of course the native cultures also lived by the law of the Open Range
Even if they didn't call it that
And once a bar went up
I'm for the Native Americans the way of life
Was just obliterated
Native Americans ultimately came to refer to the fencing as the devil's Road
By the end of the century the West was basically covered in the devil's rope
The fence cutting wars were over the farmers had one
Even the Cowboys have come to accept and use barbed wire
And then
Appliance
Summon agricultura
Economy as a
A very
Specific political military
That's Alan Krell and I'm the author of
The devil's rope
A cultural history of barbed wire
Ounces at World War 1 is the first time barbwire really becomes widely associated with being
Tool of War
So if you could imagine
Trench warfare
Had a remarkable intimacy
To it
You have a lot of credentials
And then
A hundred yards away the enemy had their own line trenches
And
The area in between is so cool no man's land
The side of the Snowman
Bob wire at 4.
Vacations
The barbed wire kept the enemy out of your Trench
But soldiers got caught and sometimes died in it
There's a British army song from that time that captures this
Called the old bark
Navigate home
Barbed wire shows up again in World War II
With an extra Sinister innovation
Electrified barbed wire
Is a double heart
Electrified barbed wire was
Part of the architecture of the Holocaust
It was such a ubiquitous part of the scenery that in fact
There was a term coined in the death camps of World War II for committing suicide by throwing oneself on the
Electric fence
Embracing
The Wire
Bamako
Embracing The Wire
In the 1960s you get Barbed wires evil spawn razor wire
Also called ribbon wire
And of course now you see that stuff at prisons all over the world
Bob wire
Ease nausea
It's menacing
It's
Transparently
Terrible
As useful as the fencing may have been to Farmers
The settling the West
Alan says that has always been about control and possession and separation
They keep sitting it keeps off
Except
For once
There's one instance where the stuff was actually used not to separate us
How to connect
Right around the same time that barbed wire was invented
Alexander Graham Bell received a patent for
An apparatus for transmitting vocal or other sounds telegraphically
The telephone basically
And his telephone company is when about stringing telephone wires in cities
They weren't really interested in the world market
The farmers wanted phones
Needed them really
Which meant they needed a network of wires that connected all the Farms
I think you see where this is heading
Simsbury
Clever people said well
We have wire
Already we have
Barbed wire fences
David Cecilia he's a professor of business and economic history at the University of Maryland
It wouldn't
Transmit a signal
Quite as clearly as say it nice
Pixelated
Copper wire but it
Worked
A dozen or so Farms might connect to One telephone Network
So we're about 25 bucks households could buy a kit that included everything they need to rid themselves up to this system
2 dry batteries load sure
Rincon death
Magnetic light
Arrester 10ft
Thousands of these rural independent telephone Collective sprouted up all over the West
Midwest
In 1907
Cooperatives
An estimated
Million and a half
Rural housing
Because of this
Farmers ended up being the earliest adopters of telephone technology
In 1912
More Farm
Household
Telephone
Kingston on
Farmhouse
Epic music
Invent
Subway
Of using
The circle
Devil's Throat
By the 1930s the national Bell Telephone system had penetrated into the remote rural regions of the West and Midway
Farmers no longer had to create their own telephone collectives
And barbed wire went back to doing what it does
Keeping us in keeping us out
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie
Greenspan Avery troubleman and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to WF strong for his reading of Lonesome Dove and for Haley Howell for recording them
One part of the barbed wire story that we didn't explore as its wide representation in art and popular culture
Book The Devil's rope is a really great resource for this
It does seem to me
Openstack
Character calligraphy
241 minutes
You can forget about all these other uses of papaya
And just look at it shapes
Do I Lugar drop peace Road barbed wire the fence that changed the West in Vinings to both their books
On our website
We are product of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa's talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
But it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can follow along with my Adventures at Ted on Facebook and Twitter but the home of all things 99percentinvisible
Is nine 9 p.m.
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalize Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com