99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Picture with me if you will India
During British colonial rule
What's a run the year 1865
Picture of government office in Bombay
SSID with unknown
Two British officers are discussing Uprising that has been challenging Britain sovereignty over the subcontinent
It's May
Hottest month in India
Temperatures of Swords over 100 degrees Fahrenheit
The office
Search bar sweating
There's no air conditioning of course but they have a serving
Who brings them to ice cold drinks
The officers takes it
So their drinks and swirl the ice in their glasses
In at this moment
These cold drinks
Stripping with condensation
Do you like a small miracle
Boobies
Wankers
But actually
The ice
Was the kind of miracle
That's our own Little Miracles Sam Greenspan
Because in 1860
B5 no one had refrigerators
It wouldn't be for another half century
Until they started appearing in the US
Little loan India
Think about the ice in those officers glasses
If you were to zoom out from those glasses
In-N-Out
And then zoom in on the United States
On Boston
On a frozen lake in the dead of winter
There
You find men working
You see a lot of men and horses and
A lot of activity going on and then you'll see horse-drawn plows
Pikes and and Pusher bars or poles
That's Rick Smith
Amateur historian of the American ice trade
All these people together we're on the lake
Harvesting ice
What are some cut ice out of a frozen pond
Haul it to Port
Put it on a ship
And send it on a
4 month journey to India
Any ice that British officers in colonial India would have had in their drinks would have started out
On the top of a pond
In Massachusetts
The tools of the ice trade vary by location but generally it went like this so the first step is to measure the
There's a small drill hole that's drilled in and a measurement taken of how thick the ice is because it had to be at least
14 in thick of ice was thick enough
The hold the team of workers and horses that would be assembled
Usually the day after Christmas
Clear off snow in debris
And then the horse-drawn ice plows would start to score the ice and they would do this all over the ice until
They had made a grid a grid on the ice
They going to make a checkerboard let's say
Workers would use giant hand saws Bandai spikes basically big sticks with sharp ends
Break up the squares of ice so that they were floating in the water
A steam powered conveyor belt with all these cakes of ice out of the water
And they would go through a planer
So each cake would become smooth
Then they be stacked in the nearby ice house
Hans device
Ice houses often had a railroad siding
So the ice could be loaded up onto a train and fight it off to the city
Using the Disney movie Frozen the ice harvesting scene is
Actually pretty accurate
At its peak
Ice harvesting happened on lakes all over New England New York Michigan
In the Poconos region of Northeastern Pennsylvania it was at one time
The major industry
My father actually worked on the ice harvesting back in the
1930s and 40s and in even into the 50s
This entire area the Poconos that was pretty much the only thing that you could do in the winter time for work but now
It's gone it just disappeared entirely
It's a bit sad in a way that
An industry it melted away is it
Here to also remember the Natural Ice industry is Gavin Weightman
I'm Gavin Weightman I live in London and I rights
Social history books Bailey
And one of my most successful book
What's called the frozen water Trade One edition of the book is actually titled the frozen water trade
A true story
Maybe because even Gavin Publishers thought the prospect of cutting frozen water out of American lakes and shipping
Overseas
Sounded made up
But that is exactly what happened
Ice was being harvested from all over the American Northeast
Tacked onto railroad cars and ships
And sent out to the southern us
The Caribbean
And British colonists
In India
The development of the International Ice trade can be traced back to one person
A man who
By the end of his life would come to be known as the Ice King
A guy named Frederic Tudor
He was the son of Bulger today
Willow
Boston
Family
I think it'd be a very old broke sorry I shouldn't use the Webelo if it's an English stuff
Tamisha message Centre
Mount router did not invent the idea of moving frozen water from one place to another
The practice actually began in Europe and South America well before Tutor Time
People would go up to the mountains and bring down ice and snow
Oboe tutor might not have known about this
But he did know that new englanders had a local tradition of cutting ice at a local lakes and using it to keep food cool
When Frederic Tudor was a young man
Pharmasset they did keep ice
Which I collected the winter and then when they were taking saved us about hits
In the summer they would take if it of this ice
In order to prevent it from melting
Chat with you on a small scale in that way
But it wasn't put into drinks and that sort of thing
And it was very localized
When Tudor was in his early twenties he and his brother William took a trip to the Caribbean
Enneathought
These people
Need ice
Chutas idea was that he was going to make his fortune because
I swear
A frozen assets of New England it wasn't being used
He felt he could set it
Particulator country switch over
I don't have no eyes
At least he delivered it to them
From Boston lakes and ponds
And he was absolutely
Crazy
The tutor was convinced that this could work
Hockey
He wrote that selling ice would make him quote
Inevitably and unavoidably Rich
Tudor set up shop on the banks of a pond called Fresh Pond in Cambridge Massachusetts
Just about 2 miles Northwest of Harvard Square
And after he learned how to get ice out of the lake
Tudor started looking for new ways to keep Ice Frozen
Experimented with all sorts of insulating materials because remember this is more than a hundred years before refrigerator
Has began appearing in people's houses
He discovered that sawdust was a remarkably good insulator
Can you could get it for next to nothing from Lumber Mills in May
Kept inside of a dry ice house in pack
The sawdust
Eventually discover that he could keep ice stable
4 years
To all tutor had to do was get the ice onto a ship
And send it to hotter climates
His first attempt to settle ice outside bus
Was made with a little shipment
Jamal Siddiqui
Triple student leadership ice
Ridiculous cargo
So he fitted out to ship himself
The ice made it to the Caribbean no problem but Martinique was not equipped to deal with a temperature-sensitive product that
Literally melts into something worthless without the right infrastructure
It was a bit of a failure really because when it go to Varsity
Lebanon New Hampshire
Keep ice erosion trailer of using entry of it is.
The fact that people
Rap that piece of ice and blank is Eduardo for wondered why was it disappeared when they got home
The newspaper's ridiculed
Tutor tutor would not be discouraged
He went back to the Caribbean and to the Southern United States
And show people their how to build more effective Ice House
And it worked
Frozen water carved out of lakes and ponds was being transported hundreds
Thousands of miles
He had a rough time getting it
Bankruptcy
A couple of times but he did
Banished in the end
But for all of tutors innovation in insulation and
Supply chain Logistics
Is true genius
Was as a marketer
For tutor
Pyside mostly just been used to preserve food stuffs
Frederic Tudor
Pioneered the radical idea of putting ice
Indie beverages
What do fish drink
Cold drinks like that when you were not used to it
It's going to shock
She had to persuade people that what he was setting
Was it luxury Edwards
Painful
Tutor with couches ice around
Mm song
Alfred from free try this try that
He have to persuade people
That what he was
Setting Woods
A guide to improve their lives
It wasn't self-evident to them
The first one as they say is always free
Tudor Road
Once people had tried chill drinks they were hooked
And would no longer tolerate tepid water
He was a bit like a soda drug pusher
And like any drug pusher
Tudor soon found himself with a lot of competition
Rival ice company set up shop on tutors Fresh Pond and staked a claim to it
In fact they had to go get a Harvard Professor to devise a map
Carving up boundaries
For the ice rights of different parties
All on the same Lake
And of course it wasn't just Fresh Pond because now anybody water that was frozen thick enough to support the weight of a nice huh
Harvesting fruit with a hot commodity
Ice began to get harvested all over New England and York Pennsylvania in Canada
What is Twitter's competitors the Wenham Lake ice company
Base. Of Wenham Lake about 30 miles north of Boston
Somehow they managed to persuade their buyers that their ice
Was premium product
Ice
From Lakewood B sodas especially.
It was nonsense really but it was a way of boxing you know all rights is better than yours
Legend has it that Queen Victoria would only use Wenham Lake ice
And maybe you're thinking why would England need to import ice all the way from North America when there are plenty of really cold
Places that are closer Norway wondered the same thing
Norwegian business man tried breaking into the ice biz
Even going so far as to rename one of their Lakes Wenham Lake
In an attempt to profit from the Wyndham Lake ice companies prestige in
Name recognition
Predators company never made a play for the UK ice Market which turned out to be a pretty good business move because I sniff
Never really took off in England
Even in the 20th century
American gi's in England were shocked to find nothing but warmbier
And there was several in the Air Force
Who said they would put their drinks in the back of a plane
Add flight to about 25000
Feet
Chill a little bit
At least
But there's one place where Brits
Could not get enough ice
India
So this is three months
In the hold of a ship
Bicycle seat playset
It was quite a remarkable
Survival rate for the ice which was eventually
Unloaded in Palm Bay is it was
Cold then metris
Casa
Despite all this
Tudor never really became an inevitably and unavoidably Rich like he predicted
Is whole life
He was in and out of debt
End debtors prison
And he eventually became
Particular
Well enough off
Auntie Porsche this state
Outside
Boston
And
Lipstick kind of
But still
It wouldn't be until
40 years after Tudors death
Squarely in the 20th century
Did the Natural Ice industry began to shift
The earliest refrigerator started appearing in the 19 teens but the early models broke all the time
The physics of cooling proved
Harder to master than eating
And of course you had to have electricity
Which most home in the US didn't have until the 1920s
Slowly but surely the technology kept improving
And consumers began to have a choice
I'm getting Natural Ice scraped off the top of a frozen pond
Or ice made in a factory
Where the water can be better control
Sand filter
Which started to get more important
Because as the charm screw
As buildings grew up around Fresh Pond on the other
Lakes that we used for supply
Sewage would get into them
It became a health hazard
I just became a great problem
Sinatra license
And to make matters worse for the naturalized trade
The Northeast experienced a Spate of unusually warm winter
The ponds would have been supplying the world's eyes weren't freezing as well the newspapers will calling it an ice pan
Supply region shifted northward
Towards Main
Where the climate was colder
And the water less polluted
By then
The writing was on the wall
The Natural Ice trade was on its way out in the 1920s but hung on in some places
Especially brutal places
Until as late as a 1950
And Ice Harvest still happen in some places
There's A Renewed interest in the tradition
In Pennsylvania and all over New England
There are some ice Harvest Revival
But you know what some updated tools and it's all Morpher Heritage value
It's only people are still putting frozen pond water
Are there drinks
But as for the actual site where all of this started Fresh Pond in Cambridge Massachusetts
The ice trade might as well have never existed
When was researching the story
I stayed up in Cambridge
And I went out
The fresh pot
People with joking around
Update they were confronted by me this
Dematting disrespect excuse me
Juno
This ice used
Speed
Transported to India
From this pain
Get me as if I was completely
Mad
So at Fresh Pond there's no
No
Cambridge Massachusetts has finally found something to not
Commemorate
With a plan
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan with Katie minka-lavery truckman Kurt Kolstad Delaney Hall
Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Rosie Weinberger Steve Arlo Tejada and Dylan Garrett Smith who reached out to us about this.
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in architecture and interior
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs
Charter of our devices
We're immersed
Cluttered world of man-made sound
If
Listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
But it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook that shows Twitter is at 99 PSI Oregon my Twitter is
Roman Mars make sure you tag me if you have a picture of a coin that you'd like to share we're all on Instagram
Lauren Spotify to your mission is to spend some quality time with the new beautiful 99 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really
Jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com