99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
So earlier this month
We wrapped up the 99 percent invisible kickstarter fundraising campaign
And it was amazing
We had 5661 backers
Raised over a hundred and seventy
That was not what I was expecting
Huge show support for the program around the world it was the highest-earning
Federalism project in Kickstarter history
So we're gearing up for season 3 and it won't be long it's going to be in September so just a few weeks couple weeks
But I've got a few thousand envelopes to stuff and we got to get salmon pack and get everything
Working in order another word together
And rather than doing repeats or just making you wait for the new season
I'm going to prison stories from producers that I love
But who didn't actually produce these stories for 99percentinvisible
When you hear them
I'm pretty sure you're going to figure out why I thought that
Be perfect for the show in terms of the subjects they cover
And why I thought
You love him too
Our first
Short story
Verity
Very short stories from Ireland it's a series called Language by
Language
Story
Doors opening
Have you ever wondered why in levels are floor in a building is called a story
Doors closing that's a word we associate with a narrative or tail
I'm actually it's not far off the origin of the word we associate with architecture
And it's used Texas back to the 14th century
The word story comes from the ancient Greek word
Astoria
Meaning account of events
And it's hurting hundreds architecture in the habit of decorating buildings
Stained glass
And stone carvings are sculptures
These carvings were on the outside of the building and they depicted actual stories
Ancient myths
Legends
And on churches and Cathedrals they often depicted Bible stories
So you can see where this is going
The higher the building the more stories that had
And eventually the word story was used to refer to an entire floor or level
First story
Language bites is produced by Colette kinsella sound design by Lachlan
The series was produced for and first broadcast on RTE choice
In Ireland
Are the extra pieces from Nate dimeo the memory Palace
They produced episode number 27 of 9 amps in the visible long ago but his connection with the show does not in there
They was one of the first people I called when I started 99percentinvisible because essentially
I want to do stories like he was doing on the subject of history but I want to do the about architecture and Design
So if you're already familiar with 9 episode invisible deal here they share DNA
The Memory Palace
This story is called Dam
This is the memory
Anita Mann
The height of the depression
People began hearing that you're going to be jobs in Nevada
Dunedin men there to build an enormous dad
That would be named after President Herbert Hoover
5000 man
Former Commodities Traders former Austin
Actor families in drove to the desert
Some of them leaving behind the plywood and scrap metal Shanty towns that were also named after Herbert Hoover
When they got there they found that there were jobs but that the houses in schools in movie theaters that were supposed to be there
I've been built
So they Hammerton post into the ground
And strung up some sheets that could keep the Desert Sun off
Kids and their wives
He went to work
96 of those men died
When the harnesses that fasten them to the canyon wall
800 feet in the air
Snap
When the hearts are 50 year old man who are you still selling women's hosiery
Teaching geometry
When their hearts give out after working 10-hour shifts
130 degree heat chipping a mile long tunnel beneath a Desert Ridge
When others fell into wet concrete
Young people now
Before they die then before the concrete set
New became a permanent part of a large Public Works project
But not long after they finish the Dan
Orange groves in alfalfa
Fields
In baseball.
In whole city
Grow in the desert
There's a monument at Hoover Dam
32in normous bronze angels
That are supposed to embody the spirit of the man who designed and built the dam
American progress or whatever
But my favorite part of the monument
Everything but the whole damn damn
There's an article astronomical
Done in Toronto
Interesting texter that tells you that on September 20th 1935
President Franklin Delano Roosevelt dedicated to
The text goes on to explain that the chart on the ground
Does the precise alignment of Heaven
Exactly 856 when FDR spoke
The same moment that a flagpole
It stands between the two angels
Beijing street at the heart of the Sun
Because they were sure we would
There's a separate section of the chart
But supposedly depicts the precise astronomical location of an Egyptian pyramid
When it was a line
Hoover Dam flagpole
With the Yonder star that the frankinson stone in Wiseman
Baby Jesus
Thereby ushering in the Christian era
I love it
Because it means it's so convinced where the makers of the Hoover Dam
It what these men had just built with so world
Sonu epic extremely awesome
Anna Paquin suffice
Survey designers chart
Working with astronomers at the Naval Observatory at the Smithsonian
Thousands of years from now
Even in an apparently post English world
When the text right there next to the chart
But somehow been rendered useless
Artcraft anyways
To be able to do the math and figure out the exact moment
When FDR had a clear in his calendar to say a few words
Now the 35th largest hydraulic
According to the state stores in website
The 9th best thing to do in the
Number 10
So that's the special 99percentinvisible for this week season 3 starts and very very soon but I thought this
Be more fun than
Playing a repeater waiting a month for new episode
Reporting new episodes a video episode a new website it's all coming this season M&M service
If you haven't done it already or this the first time your
During the show
Go download the 60-something previous episode of 99% invisible that are actually produced by me
Girls shorts
They're Evergreen meaning the Third
Is timely now as they were when I made them
Inderal
Good they're pretty good
Is it by work I'm
Quite proud of absorb better than others but as a
There was a hole
All worth the time
Going to links to language bites and the Memory Palace on our website at 99percentinvisible. Org this program is a fraud
Kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a hearing. Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and annuity
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take
Laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
Can find a show like the show and interact with me on Facebook
A tweet at Roman Mars
We can always catch up with us online at 99% invisible. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
A movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com