99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Cast your mind back
Too late
We have ignition and Orbiter as we continue to explore the mysteries of the
It's the late 20th century
And as a threat of Y2K and rap metal crossover Loom large in people's minds
Inessa satellite blasts off towards Mars
Ex-producer Joel Warner
The sum of all parts
20 seconds after liftoff
Everything continues to go well
So this satellite weighing 338 kg
At 745 lb
Yeah yeah we'll get to that
338 kilograms
Hurdle through space
What's the distance
Planet
It takes nearly a year to get there
And when it gets close
The satellite fires its main engine
To go into orbit around Mars
Up until that point all data from the spacecraft appeared normal everything was running smoothly
The engine burn begin status of spacecraft disappears behind Ma
Mission Control weight Sports Therapy
And they wait
And white
And wait
The spacecraft
Never imagined
The Mars climate Orbiter
Is lost
I'm sorry to report that we have a serious problem with the Mars climate Orbiter we may in fact be fake
Chasing a lots of mission we believe the spacecraft came in at a lower altitude than than we had
And that depending on on
On a low that was into something weird
Confirm it
Italy resulted in
Scientist at Nasa began to pour over the data
Looking for Clues as to what might have gone wrong
And before long they figure it out
The spacecraft was supposed to approach the planet at an altitude of 150 km
3 miles
When in fact
Its approach should be lower
Much lower
The post-mortem at NASA found that a pretty simple arrow was to blame
A conversion error
Vanessa investigator board confirm the cause of the
The failure of the 125 million dollar spacecraft
The NASA team at jet propulsion laboratory assumed they were using the metric system to measure rocket
NASA was using the Matrix
The international standard
Word calculations
But one of their contractors was using us customary units
The proper term the American system of inches
Pounds in gallon
Years of planning
Hundreds of millions of dollars literally Up In Smoke
Burned up in the Martian atmosphere
An oldie called someone give the right calculation
In the wrong unit
This wasn't the only time a conversion error resulted in disaster
Old me disaster
In the early eighties and airliner run out of fuel mid
Fly after metric conversion errors
How to make an emergency landing
Ending 2001
The LA Zoo learned a seventy-five-year-old Galapagos tortoise to an animal Management program at a local
College
Is it one that Clarence the tortoise was
Big and needed an enclosure for an animal weighing 250 kg
Pounds which is only a hundred
13 kilogram
About Hafiz actual weight
But not in his new home
Clarence destroyed it
But these kinds of failures haven't been enough to get the US
The switch over to the measurement system used by the vast majority of the world
We Americans measure things our own way
Units that are basically inscrutable to non-americans
Maybe all of whom have been brought up in an all metric environment
They use meters
Liters in kilograms
Knot yarn
Gallons in pounds
You might have noticed that I'm a non-american myself
And while I've never left the spacecraft to a distant planet run into other problems
Like ordering way too much deli meat
Too much is never a problem Joel
I live in the US for a couple years in Wild
Culturally elect amiezii
I never really adjusted to your measurements
Australia where I'm from
Is being a metric country for over 40 years
Optometric
I don't really have a sense of how much
Half a pound ways of how warm
60 degrees Fahrenheit
When to use wasn't enough
Change that
So when I looked in the Stateside routinely head out in cold weather without a jacket
Oh Come Home With
Too much bacon
So why with so many Industries and people like Joel Crossing Borders with so much fluidity
Has the US not fully committed to the system the rest of the world uses
As you might guess
It's complicated
The metric system has a kind of complicated history in United
It states this is Stephen meme a history professor at the University of Georgia and the author of a forthcoming book
On the history of standardization in the United
States that's in the 1790s when the United States was first fumbling around
Toward fulfilling the Constitutional mandate
To create a uniform system of weights and measures the metric system was at that point just a glimmer in the eye of a
French revolutionaries
And there was some discussion at the time led by Thomas Jefferson that the u.s. adopt a decimal base system kind of like the oven
Metric
The idea didn't gain much traction
So when it came time
Systematized American weights and measures we ultimately through a lot with what we were working with
What time which was
The bushels in pounds
America had inherited this old
System of measurement from the British
It had its roots in Roman and Anglo-Saxon units
And then evolved over thousands of years before American independence
Around the same time
French revolutionaries were heading in a New Direction
Tempted to throw out their old system
Which I found this
Pleasingly irrational
And switch it for new system
The Matrix
The metric system is a decimal
What is the meaning relies on Multi
Perfect 10
10 millimeters to come one centimeter
100cm become one meter
And so on
The French begin promoting the system internationally
Arguing that it would encourage trade and bring the world together
And it took off
By the mid-nineteenth century there was a growing adoption
Existen worldwide
And As the metric system spread some people in the US started to feel left out
Educator
They wanted the US to get with the program and officially
Go metric
The Glens of really well to scientific
Research and inquiry
And for educators
It's really easy to teach turn it and send it makes a lot of sense
But abandoning the US customary system did not sit well with a lot of paper
It was tremendous resist
The resistance came from a few different quarters some of which overlap
But the most interesting
Was a group of
Astronomers theologians
And cranks and keep in mind that those categories which week
Consider separate and distinct today we're not at this time
And so those
People
Changeable
That there was a Biblical basis
The end
And at that biblical basis was Mark
And the Great Pyramid of Giza
And the architecture of that
Mystery got more and more elaborate and gain a lot of followers
Has the astronomers and theologians combined scientific arguments with other
Wild and nonsensical ideas
Welded it all together into
What was for many people
Compelling argument that you abandon the Eng
And then all of the other way
Weights and measures
Was it go against God's
So
Science in education with this new shiny measurement system
Verses religious zealot
Clean to what they know
Fearful of change
It's a good story
But it's only
Harvest
In the US in the 1870s the real core system
Came from a different Griffin tile
Some of the most Innovative Industrial
List of Dead die
The answer lies
With engine
And with machine tool industry in the late 19th and 20th centuries
Who had tooled-up
Enormous
Vast factories in a vast industrial base
Dubai the 1870s
At the heart of what was now the large
Army in the world
This vast industrial system included everything from lathe
Two devices
For cutting screw threads
And it was all based on the edge
The manufacturers did not want to retool
They said it would be way too expensive
And not just that
They also argue that there was an intuitiveness
To the customary system
You have an inch
You have a half inch
Quarter inch 8 inch 16 and so on
That kind of division
On the shop floor
Maybe not for scientist on the shop floor mix
Huge amount of sense
Very simple
It's very straightforward it's very easy to learn
Is very easy to build
Machines around that
Concept
An older cuz everything is simply doubled or have
Arguments of these late 19th century industrialists
Proved incredibly influential
Put this into context this would be like today the tech sector in the titans of the tech sector pushing back
I can say
You know
Metric system over our dead body
And so the industrialist
And the Kranks
Win this round
Subsequent Generations make attempts to introduce the metric system to the US
And the air mattress
Subsequent generations of resistance
Congress repeatedly brings up legislation to make the metric system notice legal
Mandatory
And each time the legislation goes down in flames
The thin in the 1970s
About a hundred years after
First big push for metrication and on the back of a wave of metrication around the world
Another attempt is made to bring the Metra
System to the US
And this time
It really catches on
Congress actually passes in act in 1975 declaring the metric system the preferred system of weights and measures
The United States trade and commerce
And then President Gerald
Bows it up with an executive order
In both cases adoption of America
System is deemed
Voluntary
But the government really trying to make it happen
Take that America to they're in the metric way to simple system based on tens that you can start
Today is more accurate Universal to
The US Office of Education ren'py essays like
This one
People started painting take me to your leader buttons to the jackets
That's liter
Does a popular post to sell but teaching a woman in a bikini with the slogan think metric above her
And her measurements
In centimeters below
Tent that you can be sexist in metric
To take 10 minutes
Cc200 or board
But the 1975 metric conversion act didn't really have any teeth
It included the word
Voluntary which meant that businesses and organizations could opt out of using it
There's some organizations and industries went metric and others did not
That decision to take a voluntary approach to metrication with
Difference in the way a lot of other countries approached it
But I talked actual laws and made it mandatory
Taking a softer approach meant that the US adoption remained incomplete
Invulnerable to opposition
Once again to Auntie metric forces began together
And once again this resistance
Came from multiple
Directions
For one they were the Union
Who escaped the moving to an International System of Measurement would make it easier for big corporations
The ship jobs offshore
Various writers and thinkers fought against the metric system to
People like author Tom Wolfe and futurist Stewart brand
The creator of the whole earth catalog
Rand argued that the US system was quote
More suited to humans
He pointed out that a human foot was about to linked
The foot and the yard was about the length of a person's outstretched arm to the center of their body
It was more intuitive
He said
And then finally there was also a political acumen
I can't see US going metric
As the Jimmy Carter of the mid-1970s gateway to the Reagan Era of the early 1980s
A variety of movements rise up against
Globalism and deleted
This is the issue of this Alexa
Why do we believe in our capacity for self-government or whether we abandon the American Revolution end
I confess that a little intellectual Elite
In a far distant capital
Can plan our lives for us better than we can plan the myself
Beyond
The US economy was hurting and the nation's Pride had taken a few hits
And as a result
Anytime metric opposition began to take on
Kind of defiant
Nationalism
Demetric
Campaign withered I think in the face of the
That's because it seemed to be
Yet another example
For conservative
Of the United States are selling out at
Patrimony
2 ml largely Europeans that seems to have been the kind of xenophobic
Subtext
You can imagine this
And we lost in Vietnam and now we're going to
Adopt the metric system what is the world coming through that's
What
This was sort of perceived as it was the pendulum swinging too far
To this kind of
Namby-pamby International
That sounds weirdly familiar
An old basement that efforts to metric height u.s. Willis stranded
Halfway between the old and the new
I need the typically American why
It was left up to the market
To decide who went metric and who didn't
Which has led to this weed situation where
Get these
The US is already about halfway there
That us really is metric Nation
We just don't know that where I'm at
Truck Nation
Sally Mitchell is a high school chemistry and physics teacher in Upstate New York and a passionate advocate for the
The metric system
I mean she's even written a metric cookbook we use the metric system
Everywhere
Liquor stores
Medicines everything is in grams
Leader
I have a water bottle here right now it's 500 ml
It's there
It's just our choice
I can look at this bottle and see 16.9 fluid ounces I can choose to read 1.05 pi
Or I can choose to read
500ml
The US is on what's called a metric continuum
The fields of science and medicine almost
Polymetric hated then with little controversy
But in the business realm it's a mix
Some businesses fully matriculated
Not at all
And a lot of left
Somewhere in between
Here in the United States we have
Large international business
Elizabeth Gentry is symmetric coordinator in the office of whites
And measures at nist
The National Institute of Standards and Technology
Nist is the organization that
Standardized measurement in the US
These are
Companies that
Have international
Supply chain
What they're looking for is the ability to sell their product and many marketplaces and they get
The components for the product all around the world and I need to fit together
And how about really reliable products
These are companies like Xerox and caterpillar and Levi Strauss and they went metric during metrication push back in the nineteenth
And then you have on the other end of the spectrum
Small business
What's the score in the United States
Anthony's
Small local businesses the economic imperative to Metrotech
Just isn't there
Like think of a Dairy Farmer
And it's just one thing that really holds
Back is milk
And milk comes in a gallon
And milk is not shipped
Internationally so the farmer can't afford
To retool everything
Put it into leaders and so it's been a gallon
Yet another unit that confused our Intrepid Australian reporter Joel when he shopped in American grocery stores
Back home Joe's milk comes in litres not gallons half gallons in quarts
And it's it's funny because most people don't know
Fort and leader
Which ones
Yeah I thought I'd say which ones
Yeah I have no idea
Well this is how you remember it
A leader
Is a leader bit more
Fantastic
Sorry you've got the huge multinationals on one end of the spectrum
And then the Dairy Farmers in Hypoluxo
Smoothies
It's on the other
But you both took a lot of business caught somewhere in between
Which is where it gets really tricky
Some companies end up having to maintain
Two separate production lines even two separate warehouses
To manage all the different versions of their products
It's a total headache
Expensive to
So that's where we're at
We got a nation stretched out across a Continuum of metrication dual units and conversion confusion
History of near-misses bad timing
And it's all mixed in with a serious cultural resistance to the system of measurement adopted around the world
This cultural resistance highlights the difficulties of introducing a new system of measurement anywhere
Even the average French citizen
Hated than you
System but it was first introduced back in the revolution real
The bottom line is this
It's really difficult to get people to change from a measurement system
We've been using their whole life
Inertia
Resistance to change
Is a massive obstacle
To overcome
Yeah when I think about
Alright what's harder occupying a country conquering it and putting it under your
Coquille or getting a new adopter unit of weights and measures that you can do the first
The second one can really
Rizzoli
Rough you up because it
It's even if people do it
On the face of it they're constantly converting back into the to the ghost units that are
That have been banned
Discontinue
How to do it
But resistance to the metric system in the US continues to have a subtext that goes beyond just preferring a familiar
Your system
Today maybe more than ever
Resistance to metric is about the rise of a new kind of national
North Country
Take the case of Sally Mitchell who you heard from earlier
She's the high school science teacher from upstate New York
Back in 2014 GMC step
Right into the middle of the whole metric vs. US units debate
Moka bros
It actually started out in Syracuse when the airport had gotten a new sign
Syracuse airport is an international airport and the old sign and display the temperature in both Fahrenheit and Celsius
The Matrix
Systems preferred unit
But the Selfies option had been activated on this new sign
Is only showing Fahrenheit
So I called and they said I'll be forgot to program it let me do it'll be ready by tomorrow and I think I posted
Did something online it said
Don't you worry
It'll be fixed by tomorrow
And then the next thing you know what the newspaper with calling me and they wanted to do a story on this I said no no
Not a story
Please don't know her story on this
But they did a story anyway
And then a radio station
Cold and did an interview with
And a host of that radio show with decidedly antimatter
And they said do you want a teacher that wants to drill her
Metric agenda into people's heads
How dare she and things like that
And they were mean and they were awful
Next thing you know it phone calls
School I had
Threats on Facebook
Threats through email
I had people writing to me demanding that I be
Tired
Because I just wanted the sign to display Celsius again
It got really crazy
The threats were so bad
And I had to report that to the police
And I thought wow people need to get a life or something or
Or really
Why why are you doing this I'm doing this
For science I'm doing this for International Communication I'm doing this as an educator
Sometimes When Sally Mitchell talks about the metric system you get the sense she's talking about
A lot more than the Metro
People like me
Are starting to speak
And we're not going to have it anymore
This is not the way we are wearing intelligent Nation
And we want what's best for our children we want what's best for our communities around us
And so that's why I'm speaking up now I'm more vocal than I
Ever
Ever been
And I'm just not going to take it anymore
I'm not going to let the ignorant
Beeville Audi
But those antiemetic trolls that Sally had to deal with
She's pretty much guaranteed to have the last laugh
Because those customer US units inches and pounds
Actually defined
Relative to the metrics
Keys Elizabeth Gentry of mystogan
Usually
Consumers are
They're at the grocery store they made by a gallon of milk
Or they're at the gas station and they buy a gallon of gas they think well
I'm using all of these us customary units all the time in my life
That must mean the United States hasn't really adopted the metric system
But the system that make sure I gallon of gas in Oakland is the same as a gallon of gas in Omaha
That system relies on Metric standard
A gallon is officially defined as
3.78541178
So just below the surface
Metro
It's metric
All the way down
You might think the debate about the metric system is over in the US
Candidate in the most recent Democratic primary actually ran on a pro metric
Platform
Weather alert
He did not get very far
What about that
Ravenous
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why but it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
In June 2015 Lincoln chafee
The former governor of Rhode Island announced that he was seeking the Democratic nomination for president
He said he would be running on a platform of bold ideas
Like this
Earlier I said what's people
Let's join the rest world
And go Metro
Believe me it's easy
It doesn't
Before 34 degrees
Only Myanmar
Kcm's of dropping out just 4 months later
He didn't do well in the debates and he wasn't raising much money in his poll numbers were low
It's like he just did not
Quite have his finger on the pulse of the nation
Here's Stephen meme talking with Jolla
You know his first
Or the business was to pick the metric system are reaching into measurement
It just became like
Really like that that was
Laughable
He wasn't really really ever National toner I was it
Exactly
That was not part of make America great again
This episode was produced in collaboration with Joel Werner
Use the greater and hose with new podcast from the Australian Broadcasting Corporation
Called sum of all parts
Tell stories about numbers
Measurements and data
Take it out and if you have a story that somehow involved
This episode was produced in collaboration with Joel Werner
Use the greater and hoes a new podcast from the Australian Broadcasting Corporation
Call sum of all parts
Tell stories about numbers measurements and data
Take it out and if you have a story that somehow involves a number
Email the show
At soap
At ABC
Dot net
. AU
From our team Delaney Hall edited this be since reviews of detect production and mix
Some real compose the music
Katie mingle is our senior producer Kolstad is the digital Direct
Russell staff includes Avery Chapman and it's Cheryl Terry Meza and me
Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
You're beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight foundation and coin carrying listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible Antone discussion about the show on Facebook you can't we meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99.
I will work on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Article about the oldest national monuments in the US or any of the other Design Story that we released every sing
Single week
You have to go to our website
Sunday 9 p.m.
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com