99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Ronnie Johnson still remembers the first time he went underground
He and a handful of other Coal Miner's piled into a little trailer and descended into the mine
We're going down to their hitting bumps
Running over Little Rock
Stop
And I remember laying in that little trailer and
The roof was actually so close to me
Betabel by my hard hat with almost 50
Route
When they got down to the bottom Ronnie's boss handed him a wrench and told him to open a nearby waterline
But someone had forgotten to
The water off
Blackwater just started
Brian May
Sprite all in my face
Can all of them out something wet
I just like
Spell up against the real
You know the wall or cold
And I thought to myself what have I done
As a new minor in a dangerous industry Ronnie had to go through an intensive orientation process before
This first trip Underground
Best producer Irina zhorov
Ronnie's actually my partner's father
He lives in Northern Alabama and
On a recent visit as a family cook dinner
Ronnie and I went out to his Workshop
He likes to sit
Smoke
With only the dogs and cicadas
S4 company
Somewhere else you want to do
I don't care
He told me about how he saw through 40 hours of training and safety classes
Before going down into the mines
At the end he was issued a hard hat
That identified him as a rookie
The hard hat was yellow
It was like you stood out from here to the Rogue
Terrible
It was terrible
Was a terrible cuz you'd get
You get like crap from the other men
Oh yeah yeah everybody knew you would have a rookie you know and
Just you know practical jokes
Nothing serious
In addition to this terrible yellow hard hat
The safety man that is mine
Also gave him
Sticker
Yeah it was there
Take a right here
It's a red rhombus about 2 by 2 inch
With a reflective White Center
ABC
Amy Says always be careful
But ABC was a company named Alabama
By Products Corporation
Ronnie got a few of these stickers back then
He put one in a box and one on his brand new yellow hat
This was just the beginning of Ronnie sticker collect
After 34 years is a minor
He now has several photo albums
Filled with thousands of stickers
Some are inside jokes
Some commemorate big events at work
Lots of other coal miners across the
The country have collections just like Ronnie's
Miners use the stickers for
Safety and for communication and as a kind of currency
Down in the mines
It would just walk homeowners did you know kids collect baseball cards
In a coal mine
You know that's all you had really would
To collect
You can always
Call Monica
One of the darker
List of all working
Underground mine
Since the beginning of underground mining
One of the biggest dangers in the
Has been the darkness
Wood shutters
Open flame
The darkness makes accents more likely and even though technology has improved to make Minds brighter and safer
Still an issue the culture of mining to a certain degree
Has been shaped by the level of risk involved
What cultures
Have very strong cultures
Especially
I want that face Danger
Like mining of firefighting police work
The military
Deep sea fishing Etc
This is a lame Cullen
She's an occupational if not
And she spent a lot of time with minors
Like actually down in the mines with them
Money has a very strong cultural
I think the reason is
Because people who work underground are well aware of the fact that every day you go in you don't know if you're coming out
The first time Colin went down into a mine
She was told that she had to have something reflective on her
Hard hat
There's a lot of heavy machinery move
Nothing around
Trump buses
To the shears roof bolters and other tools
Yeast extract
Cole people get hit do they get run over they get crushed by mobile equipment
And so reflective material increases the visibility of the people underground
We put a strips of
Reflective tape on the back of a hard hats
But then it became pretty obvious that other people had other things on their hard hats
And these were stickers
The stickers had originally been little advertisements that the manufacturers
Of mining equipment handout
Even before the late 1960s when mining safety laws started
Requiring reflective materials Underground
Miners use those stickers
Stay visible.
To each other
What is time past the stickers evolved
They became more personal
It's hard to tell minor stories
In a mine companies themselves started printing stickers for their workers
They went from simple ads to signaling and identity
Knees are sort of
Their symbols
Symbols of the mining industry and that you're part of it
Picture of minor
After a year in the Alabama Mine Ronnie swapped out his yellow hard had for a black one
Which meant he was no longer a rookie
With that
Kenmore stickers
Stickers always came in twos
One went on his hard hat which he actually brought out to show me
So where's your 6 inches of reflective tape
I probably coming out my nipple stickers
Alabama stickers
The other sticker he saved for his growing collection
A minor showed Ronnie how to keep the stickers organized so
Each week
Sit down and put the new stickers in an album
What's this one
The Grim Reaper looks like Donna
It says umwa I say
Union sticker I'm sure you've got some
Going to do with black long
Managers and the safety man and his mine gave him stickers with the my name
And is Union game stickers with Union messages on them
One of his favorite stickers has the state of Alabama outlined in red and inside it says
Alabama coal miner
That kind of a
Pride thing though you know Alabama coal miner
As he gained more experience he got stickers commemorating his accomplishments
She worked at a company early on that counted the amount of coal mined by the number of cars feel during a shift
Something like a hundred cars with
Was okay
But Ronnie has a sticker that says his team mind 150
E-cars in one shift
And then they sticker says 150
Car club with a little Play Bunny
Playboy Bunny on there
He also has one commemorating 225 cars in a shift
Which is a big deal
You have a big run in the next night you're
Outside and all the guys that didn't have such a good run or whatever and your boss is going around
Giving you these stickers and every other star
How many Senate
In the 1960s and 70s a number of major mine safety laws were passed in the US
Anna Lane Cullen started working at a new agency that was responsible for studying and enforcing safety in the mine
For years she researched mining culture
In the 2000s the National Institute for occupational safety and health a federal agency
Heard her to develop a safety training program for coal miners
By that time
She knew who she was dealing with
So she knew she might be facing some skepticism from the minors she was trying to reach
I don't look like a minor
I'm a woman and
Most of them are not
So
Getting them to work with me especially when I was a representative of the federal government and you know they
Our little Leary to
Going to work with government
Maryland had seen that the miners were really into the stickers
And she figured she could use them
To gain their trust
And to convey messages about safety
But you knew just putting work safe on a sticker wouldn't cut it
She needed something to grab the miners attention
We were working out and
Eastern Kentucky
It was a money in community with the
Cultural ties to coal
And she started to notice
She be walking along with the safety guy
And
As we would approach another minor
He would squeal like a pig
I finally asked him I said Jessie
What's going on here why are they doing that and he said oh they're just saying they know I'm a Cole Haan
What is a Quahog annies
Quahog is hungry
Call Greedy for call
Can't ever get enough
Meaning
But you're ugly minor
Took the idea and design a sticker with a big muscular pig with a
Hard hat on and it says
Coal Hogs work safe
So what we were doing
Putting those two ideas together
That's you can be a Quahog
But you can also work safe
The miners loved it
Oh gosh I think we printed 3002
To begin with and I have
One little packet left that I'm kind of keeping as a
You know
Keepsake
Semicolons other designs were dead
13 made one with a dead Canary
Canaries were once used to check for bad air in a mine
But that was a long time ago
And the younger miners
Didn't get it
Other stickers catering to the raunchy humor in the mines
Didn't pass muster with her bosses in the federal government
For example they designed one sticker to remind minors to check
Check for gas in the mines
So what the this one was a
The back end of a donkey
And have the donkey kind of looking back
Back at you
And it said
Don't be an ass
Check for gas
I kind of have this little Cloud coming out
Gas can be really dangerous Underground
And donkeys were once used to carry coal out of the mines
NOAA weather
Thea
Folks in Washington didn't like that one but the miners loved it
Unless Elaine visit your mind it be hard to get one of these stickers
A lot of the stickers were Specialized or localized depending on what organization or company design them
That's part of what made collecting them fun
I have
Over 26000
Different stickers in my collection
And I've I've kind of come to believe that you either are collector or you're not
And if you're not a collector you just don't get it and if you are a collector you just really can't help yourself
This is Lenny Hanner
And I'm
Coleman from Southern Illinois
When is worked in coal mines for 40 years
He's a major sticker collector
At the height of his collecting in the 1980s
Heat exchange stickers with other collectors
Across the country
And go to sticker swaps almost every weekend
Those are meetups where miners Exchange
Pieces
Lenny says unique stickers were like currency in the mines
Way to buy or sell favors and help
Princess say you're a trucker and you rolled up the money for the big
Load of supplies
You asked him to minors
Help you unload
The first thing they wanted to know is
Do you have any stickers
Without stickers the miners wouldn't exactly rush to help
So
They all learned that they they had stickers in that truck when they arrive and that's the
Tend to get unloaded the whole lot faster that way
Lenny still works from mining company but above ground these days
He lives in an old mining town and a house that was once owned by Mining Company
Annie's got a full room devoted to mining memorabilia
I'm I'm married to the you know the most
Understanding woman in the world
He keeps his stickers in 27 albums organized by type of sticker
What's pretty by mining companies that one's equipment manufacturers gave out the ones focused on safety and Union issues
Some of them are especially sentimental
I have a sticker that I got from a friend of mine and he recently passed away
And I have just a couple stickers in my collection that really make me think of him when I see them
The sticker albums function just like photo albums
Reminding minors of their milestones and stories
They are just little
Pieces of our history of our past little mementos
I guess maybe like a postcard if you travel that you might pick up a postcard that
It remind you of something from the past
We can just see our past mining history there on the pages of the album
Of course just like with photos
Some of the darker memories don't end up in the album
In 2011 after more than 30 years in the mine
Signs my partner's dad Ronnie had an accident
We're living a thousand miles away in pace around in my living room as news trickled in
Eventually learn that his hand got pulled into a machine
And it took a finger
Down in Alabama he was rushed to a hospital
Useful to call his wife
Deborah
At first he didn't want to call
What happened in the mind stayed in the mind
But the nurse insisted
And Deborah happened to be nearby
I remember dad but looking at me
What you came in the rain
If at Ron Johnson how'd you get so dirty
You know like I mean I've been getting that wife for years
And I guess you never saw me
Diana my rubber boots
My wife was all black and
My hand was all wrapped up in a manual
He never really shared much about his life in the mine with her
Ace family
I guess I had never saw me like that I didn't I didn't I didn't tell him what I went through
The Seeker album stacked up in his cosy house
Only tell their stories to those who know how to read them
Ronnie says before he lost his finger
Keep Calm 31 years without spending a night in the hospital
He never ridden in an ambulance
I never had an accident in the mine
That made him lose work hours
I caught up Rob Lowe 31 years in one night.
Ronnie never got a sticker
For that
So what are you do with a mind that no longer productive
Lots of things that turns out
Kurt Kolstad tells us about his favorite examples of adaptive reuse
Happiness
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flash podcast
We were attracted to the coal miner stickers because it was a cool way that design and the
Cultural mining intersected
And it brought to mind another
Interesting juxtaposition of design and abandoned mines
Kolstad Road about on the website
So I asked him to come to the studio and talk
I think a lot of people tend to have this
Idea that mines
Are these
Rickety
Dangerous places to go
I was rotting Timber frames holding up sections of a tunnel that could
Collapse on you at any moment
The reality is a lot of mines
Are much bigger than that and much more stable than that
And really I have
Promising futures
Doing much different things and they were designed for
What's a good example
So one example would be there's a really cool mine in Romania
That was actually first mine for salt
Nearly a thousand years ago and it's been used on an office's fault line ever since
So to really deep and it's really complex
And recently
I decided we're going to turn this into a fraction
So they made it a museum they made
Theme park
You go down there
And like
Boat around on this water and the pictures are just sort of Mesmer
They really let this place up so you can go down and really get a sense of the geology but also
Experience Underground
Cool are there any in the US
Yeah in Kansas there's a
Data Center
A little less exciting but it a little more functional
Does that I sent you the
Uses
The natural
You don't even temperatures in the protection of this mindspace
Old Limestone mines
Thousand servers
And you can imagine in a
If you're just trying to keep
E-service running
You know
Doing any kind of weather
The perfect place is just
And there's also
A research facility
That is doing experiments on dark matter
Far underground in South Dakota in an old gold mine it's about a mile deep
And
It turns out
That there's a lot of particles that
So just float through space and Bombardier atmosphere on a pretty regular basis
And getting below the surface they can get away from a lot of that noise and a lot more
Chemiclean experiment
Yeah totally
Unethical
And you know if they decide to destroy the universe
At least they're a mile Underground
Yeah I mean yeah right hope the hope the hope is that they'd only just destroy their lab in the mountains
So what's your favorite
My favorite is probably the Louisville Mega Cavern
Which is this
Huge
Huge underground space
In Louisville Kentucky
If you
Buy the argument that it's now a building
It's the largest building in Kentucky at about 4 million square feet
And
Basically this mine opened in the 1930s The Dugout Limestone for decades
Ali Karver this thing out
In the 1960s
Actually talked about using it as a fallout shelter
In case it the Cuban Missile Crisis went the wrong way they were paying it back
10 mm
The people in there
And then eventually it sort of fell into disuse
And
Tamiya investors can long to hey
We could do something
And they did
Basically they bought this thing
And they started you know putting businesses in there they started using it for
For storage because it started yet temperature Stables good place
Extra storage
And then
Ladies in the kind of weird and they started adding all of these kind of theme park element
Stuit
She can go take tram tours of the underground you can go take zipline tours there's a Ropes Course
At the heart of it all
One of the biggest functions is this
Huge huge 300000 + square foot
Bike Park
It's is like a BMX
Parkwood jumped and all that stuff
And they build those out of
All the sudden
Bill that was already carved out instead of laying around for the miners rights all they have to do is just going to pick up the dirty or shoveling over there
And they can make entirely new course
And we have some pictures of bees on our website a picture isn't a video of this on the website
Awesome thanks so much that's so cool
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Irina shur off with Delaney Hall
Play production and mix by Sharif Youssef
Music by Sean real or senior editor is Katie mingle Kolstad is the digital director
Reza staff is Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald during mass
And me from in Mars
We are project of radiotopia and 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoy discussing about the show on Facebook you can't read me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 PIR
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
What are beautiful home on the internet with more design story than we ever tell you inside this podcast
Is our weapon
99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com