99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In San Francisco the area south of Market Street is called soma
The part of town north of the Panhandle is known as nopa
Just north of our office is a part of town that Oakland is trying to Brand as Kono
Short for
Koreatown Northgate
But no one actually calls it that
I live in a part of town at the intersection of North Oakland Berkeley and Emeryville
A neighborhood real estate brokers are calling
Nobi
Best producer Avery trufelman
Home nobody thing makes me feel Pretty Ricky
Is abbreviated neighborhood names are
Such cliches
Like there's an episode of Southpark where part of town gets rebranded as
South of downtown South Park
Or
Sodosopa
There's a certain quality
Vibe and energy
That is so dumb
Independent merchants and unique cafes
Rustic charm of a mixed-income cry
The episode of How I Met Your Mother 2 characters buying apartment in
Dobies atripla
Oh I see you're not New Yorker
Here in New York
We just shorten the names of all today Soho Tribeca nolita
I'm from New York I know this neighborhood
Joey's a tree pot turns out to be short for downwind of the sewage treatment plant
Are brokers who are we naming parts of harlem as soha
Parts of Little Italy
Estelita
Marketing the Bronx as SoBro
He represents New York's 8th congressional
Which is Brooklyn and parts
Queens these are names that
I created out of thin air
If fantasy their fiction
It made up solely in my view
To artificially inflate prices
Before Congressman Jeffries was elected to the House of Representatives
He was a member of the New York State
And he saw these neighborhood abbreviations creep into his jurisdiction
Real estate brokers
Or we naming parts of
Crown Heights
As Pro Crow Crow Crow
Cro cro which is a combination apparently of the Prospect Heights neighborhood
And Crown Heights
Properties in Prospect Heights have generally sold for more than those in Crown Heights
I'm making this new neighborhood
Pro Crow
Brokers could sell Crown Heights properties
Prospect Heights prices
Congressman Jeffries did not like anything about this he didn't like the sound of pro Crow and he didn't like with an a
I was trying to do
So we tried to stop it
Show me research the issue
It turned out that it was no
So the governmental entity
Involved in the designation of
Neighborhood
In 2011 Jeffries proposed the neighborhood integrity
Which set out to create guidelines and regulations for new neighborhood names and boundaries
But it turned out that it's hard to pass a law against names
The neighborhood Integrity act didn't gain traction
But neither did the name Pro Crow
Some names don't stick Pro Crow was just silly
And thankfully
It was abandoned
You never really know which of these names will stick around
Like there's a part of Midtown Manhattan that was recently renamed nomad
Are north of Madison Avenue
People are starting to use it
You can see it on Google Maps
And it's weird there's not really a name for the naming convention
Like NoHo SoBro Noma
You're not quite acronym sonar Quake portmanteau
They're not just abbreviation
The office we've been calling them
Acronyms
Agnes Agnes it's too much as I can be a thing
Find their acronyms
And they trace their lineage back to Soho
Short for south of Houston Street
In New York
It's really interesting house Soho
Developed first as a local neighborhood brand
And then became globalized
Sharon zukin is a professor of Sociology at Brooklyn College and The Graduate Center of the City University of New York
You have neighborhoods
Of
Boston and Washington
DC
And Seattle and
Denver abbreviated
As low-dose o dos o Mas Alla trading on the brand name of
So now they're already was a Soho District in London but as the allusionist Helen zaltzman will tell you that
That is not
Most of the evidence
Point Street having being a hunting cry
Soho
Liked
Because Soho stands on what used to be hunting them
Other people will tell you that solo is a shortening of south of Hoboken
Butt face people ignoring the fact
So he's actually
West of the area of harbin
Which would make
Soho
Weho
Which it is
London Soho may have been first
But the American abbreviation of Soho and the birth of the acronym
Can be traced back to 1962
And a fellow by the name of Chester rapkin
He was an urban planner and
Eventually a member of the New York City Planning Commission
From the lake
Extjs
To the late night
And he was asked
To investigate the conditions
In what
He called or what the City Planning Commission called
The South
Houston industrial area
A lot of people think that the resulting paper known as the rapkin report
Invented the term Soho
I have
Recently read that report
And I do not believe that rapkin used
The term Soho
In that report
It's also been said that rapkin coined the term Soho in conversation
However it happened around this time
People
Seized upon
The term Soho has an abbreviation which is certainly better than the South Houston industrial area
But
Not nearly as badass as its previous name
Held Hundred Acre
In the 1950s and early 60s for industrial Manufacturing
At the time rabkin was writing the report
It was not the most Pleasant part of town
He mentioned in passing the Grim caverns of factory buildings in SoHo
That's absolutely true
The South Houston Industrial Area was threatened with demolition
Brick buildings with cast iron facades were seen as ugly outdated
Eyesores
I mean they were factories
Smack in the middle of downtown Manhattan there had been a major pressure
The part of city government as well as
Probably the real estate industry
To demolish these
Worthless building
And replace them
With one of the new residential projects
This was in the early sixties when New York City under the influence of Robert Moses was trying to tear down and rebuild
They were wrecking ball happy
But the rap game report made
A plea to preserve
The factory
And the city held off on their plan
Rapkin
Said
The manufacturers in those buildings were viable
And it would be
Interesting
Maybe even great
If the manufacturing buildings
Wer
Renovated
For manufacturing use nobody foresaw that the area
Would become colonized by artist
Artist rented the manufacturing spaces for Studios
Soho
In the 1970s
Quickly gain
The identity of an artist District
The Loft
Weren't supposed to be residential
They weren't up to City housing standards
State Standards fire codes
Anyting
For while the city skirted around this problem by classifying artists as
Machine
Who manufactured art
And conduct stay in the fact
Overnight
Performers and Painters and musicians out of their lives
And these attracted attention from Arts Publications and newspapers
So how was if not the very
First Industrial District
To be trance
Formed
Into
Live work
And living
Space
It was certainly the most
Prominent
In the media
To the success of Soho the urban planning department wanted to do on purpose would it happen by accident in SoHo
They set their sights on a nearby area
The triangle below Canal Street
Or as they called
Tribeca
Tribeca was also a former manufacturer
Chaoyang district
But it was intentionally rezoned for mixed-use
Chanel factories and Residences in gallery
This could exist
Side by side
Legal aid
You know the story from here
Artist moved into the old boss
Made them seem to have been desirable
In higher-income residences and businesses slowly took over
And now of course
Soho and Tribeca are fancy fancy places
Full Boutique
Send high-end residences
All housed in the architectural
Skeletons
Old industry
So how was
Able
Intubate
And disseminate
All of these trends that became so important
In interior design
In the 80s
+ 90
It'll probably on in to mm
Soho and Tribeca warrant just the rise of acronyms
They were the birth of industrial chic
They created the whole
Static that comes to mind with these neighborhood
In SoHo artist embrace the best judges of the batteries they were living and working
They found the big metal fixtures and beams loading dock
Charming
And this became a kind of
Expensive minimalism
That marked
High-status
Taste in interior
Design exposed brick walls distressed floors big Windows large Open Spaces big beams
Bronze fixtures
The old factories became trendy
And new wealthier residents
Added layers of conventional luxury
Now people install
Very
Expensive
Marble bath
Send floors
Wine Vault
Into former Industrial
Loft
So that the simplicity
Of the first generation
Of industrial chic
Has turned into the excess
Of
Current
Multimillion-dollar
Loft
Lawson is genuine old buildings now go for millions of dollars
And new condos and development
Are actively trying to look like old warehouses
And in other parts of New York and other cities around the world developers started to copy Soho
Not just an industrial area
But in all kinds of neighborhoods independent of whoever was already living or working there
Real estate developers around the world copy this and they say let's
Bring some stores let
Let's encourage some performance
Space is some art galleries
Let's
Make this area interesting let's give it a name
And as time went on
A new name
Especially an acronym
He came he big indicator
At your neighborhood
What about
What we're seeing is it something as an air of gentrification
This is Jacqueline Wong
Postdoctoral research fellow at Princeton University
2006 she did a comprehensive study of residence in a section
Have South Philadelphia
Where he basically went up to them and asked
What do you call your neighborhood
So in the section of Philly most of the minority residents referred to as South Philly
White residence
Spann real estate agents in Craigslist post
That list of the properties
Most commonly they use the name graduate hospital so named because of Hospital used to be in that neighborhood
Other people have referred to it as G so-so
Which is supposed to represent south of South Street
Ghoe or so-so
These newcomers really identified more
With graduated
Hilton South Philly
Now just to be clear neighborhoods do shift and change names periodically
But Jacqueline says the recent name in Russia
He's different
I would say that
There's an intention behind this and sort of a power
Play happening
Yeah there's a group that's
Redefining it while another group is trying to
Hold on to this older name
As Cities boom and gentrification Rises
New neighborhoods get made
A new names
Proliferate
I'm not saying neighborhood changes not
Good for these neighborhoods they certainly needs investment but I think that idea that there is
This
Displacing
And evaluate the previous name in order to make the neighborhood
Change doctor
This gets at the
Achiness
I feel about using the term Nobby to describe where I live
I don't want to be the newcomer who alienates the old residence
By using some term
Bed to me by real estate
But nobody is also useful
Because it's specific
And it's efficient
I mean saying I live in Novi is obviously faster than saying I live at the border of North Oakland Berkeley and Emeryville
Well I live in Adobe
Which is downtown Berkeley I just made up the damn Dobby
That is comedian and longtime Bay Area resident W kamau Bell
I was thinking about my neighborhood and gentry
Application
When I happened to run into him
Appropriately
At the South Berkeley Farmers Market
I know they called the South Berkeley Farmers Market but I've lived in the very long enough to remember when this was called Oakland right here
This feels like South South South
South
South Berkeley
Camille feels uncomfortable with these acronyms to
Oh no
It's a kind of magic
Downtown
Koreatown Northgate photo
Oh no
But he says if your focus too much on neighborhood name
You might be missing the point
Let's just symptomatic of like
This is like the neighbors name is like
The old log in the woods and he looked up in a room and you see all the bugs underneath and that's the best interpretation
Navigate to focused on the name you're probably not focus on what's going on Into the Woods
Acronyms are easy to Lampoon
They're ubiquitous to the point of parody and often
So we may see a shift away from these names
Real estate developers will start using less silly sounding names to Market neighborhoods to higher-paying customers
These names might sound more authentic like graduate Hospital in Philly or temascal in Oakland
But they're different names for the same thing
The same log over the ants of Education
And as far as what you should call your neighborhood if you're a newcomer
I mean I feel like the bigger issues to respect the neighbors are moving into
If you respect the Neighbors movie until you aren't trying to
Be the change you trying to be the blind then you should have been whatever people they would call it then call it back
So I took him out
I walked in on my block
Can I ask people
What do you call this neighborhood
I met a few newcomers like me
George just as confused as I was
Was it Novi was it be
Bart region the Golden Gate District
The Lorin District
But the neighbors have lived here for a while
All said the same thing
Just
North Oak
Henry we
It doesn't need to be called anything else
#life goals
99% invisible with produces we buy Avery trufelman and gold Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall
If you said that me Roman Mars
Special things this week to Jeff Bliss ultimate you should already be download
Queen Helen's radiotopia podcast The Illusionist on your favorite podcasting app
But if not
Take this opportunity
To remedy that
Camilla Belle Jose new radio show and podcast called come out right now which I highly recommend it's a live talk show Bass
He's here in the bay
Pretties by kalw the greatest radio station in the world
We are product of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in architecture
Interiors for
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remedy for all hearing.
Voice technology
All she talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
It's frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and join the fine community of people who like this show on Facebook
I save every 99 Pi coin I see on Twitter and Instagram
Every single one of them
Make me happy when I see them
Please keep synonym
But if you want to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
I recommend you spend some time
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get relief
Jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to
Clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com