99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into
High quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help
Target your customers with
Decision
Down to the job title company name
And Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
A few years ago anastacio Mark still Salcedo was making lunch for her kids
And
So like most moms I will Lotto
Lunches
And
When I do that I usually
They trying to find a balance
Between
Healthy and not so healthy not quite so healthy side she might pack some cheesy crackers
Depend on the healthy side she make her kids a sandwich
Or at least she thought the sandwiches that she was making more healthy
Until she look closely at the ingredients
I realize that I
Cold
The packaged deli meat out of my fridge
Brad came for my bread box
And I've been sitting there for awhile and it
Sit in the supermarket and then
I've been
Way back when
Anastasiia got to thinking
It is kind of a natural for food to last this long
Is this really a healthy lunch
Butts Tina Antolini hosts of The podcast gravy
Helping us tell the story
Anastacio looked at the package deli meat the store-bought sliced bread
Processed cheese
As it happens she's a journalist
She writes a lot about food
And so she started looking into it
I went through all of those ingredients that you just sent me including them
The EMES
Start and the mayonnaise
At least two of the items
The packaged deli meat and the supermarket bread
Docker research ultimately
To this
Skier US Army base
The Natick Soldier systems center
This is very strange what is the Army doing in
Considered
What the Army is doing in food is
Of course feeding the troops
And by strange extension
You and me
Military organization did actually been involved in food production ever since the earliest combat rations
The first combat rations
We're probably
Eaten by the Sumerians
Beijing carry with them into battle garlic
Kegs beer
Green onion
Back in the early days of organized Warfare
If you were marching into battle and didn't know when you get home again
You needed to bring something that would keep
All of these rocks
War base
Traditional
Methods of preserving food
Drawing
Saltine
Smoking at pek
But the real Innovation with coming up with a preserve protein
Ancient Egyptians went to war carrying dried fish with them
And in the 11th and 12th centuries
The Mongols
Preserve their meat
By storing it under their saddles
And the salt from the horse
Would enter the Meet the Press
Secret this preserve me
Salted by horse sweating
Impressed by your butt on the saddle
Mongolian method designed for some 2000 years military food rations pretty much stay the same
Flower
Beans
Hunk of salted meat
And some hard
I kind of twice baked biscuit
Or in the case of Napoleon's Army
Soldiers would just go plunder the countryside and eat whatever they found
Which became a problem when soldiers went MIA trying to get food
And there was a battle to fight
And so in 1795 the French government and the agriculture Department decided they needed a new way to
To preserve food for the troops
They announce the contest
12000 francs to anyone who could come up with a new method
A man named Nicolas appert responded
He was at the time these celebrity chef
He cooked for kings and queens
And a pair of found a way to cook and preserve food using Glass and Metal containers
This is canon
And it revolutionized the war
This was the first time that the military had taken on a big problem in food technology and solved it
The military's would continue to innovate around food for Soldiers & Sailors
Fast forward World War in the United States
During World War II the country had
To ramp up for feeding
Thousand soldiers to ultimately
Sex
Million
American troops had packs of meat and cheese and crackers as well as canned goods of course
But these Russians didn't survive the rigors of War II well
They really haven't been sufficient to feed so many soldiers in so many different locations
In so many different climates and conditions
The military had been unprepared to feed their soldiers during World War II
The government said
We don't ever want to
Just horrible to have to ramp up
So let's
Maintainer cell
In a state of preparedness
And so preparedness became policy after World War II
The support that
They created a system of 700 Federal Laboratories
All devoted to developing military Technologies
And one of them is the Natick Soldier systems center outside of Boston
Pretty much like Suburbia with the exception of the
Intense electric fence except for that barbed wire fence
Shenzhen the guard posted at the gate
The Natick Soldier systems center looks like a normal office
But this Office Park is the epicenter of the modern military diet
Is the home of the combat feeding Direct
Which has been here since the 1950
First of all can I have you introduced yourself to me secretly I'm Steven Moody the director of combat feeding
I hear at the Natick Soldier
Development and engineering center
Steven showed me how military food technology has evolved over time
Ken's for instance
Since been replaced by flexible lined pouches
Because can they're bulky and heavy troops have been eating their meals out of those pouches
And what are called MREs
Meals ready to eat
The first MRE contain a lot of freeze-dried components
A freeze-dried meat Patty that you would have to add water to
And then heated and
Having having eaten a few of those in my time
As an active-duty soldier at you had to get it just right it was always either a little bit too soggy or a little bit crunchy at the end of
The combat feeding directorate has been tasked with overcoming certain challenges inherent in
In food
It's spoiled
It grows more
It loses flavor
And if you're trying to feed a vast number of people in climates ranging from the desert to the human jungle over long.
The time
You have to figure out ways of making food that will avoid its natural tendency to go bad
So
The combat feeding directorate has whole teams of microbiologist
Engineers
Leather scientists working to extend the lives of food
Food engineering preservation and stabilization for instance wood
Be the ones that would would try to figure out how to make that product shelf-stable for
Two three
5 years five years without Refrigeration exact
And then there's the little detail of
Taste
Making the stuff actually palatable
The modern MRE has come a long way from that chewy freeze dried meat Patty
Today's high-tech pouches come with another pouch
Instead chemically heats the ration the US military now offers 24 different entrees
It's from cheese tortellini to lemon pepper tuna
Jambalaya
Jambalaya for instance
Trying to make sure that jambalaya Atwood would laugh
3 years at 80° in a pouch is a challenge so we we tweaked the spices
Tweak the ingredients so that we can make sure that the flavor is optimal at the end of the shelf life
As well as the beginning
So that Soldier on a mountain in Afghanistan can enjoy a flexible pouch
3 year old jambalaya
I mean that's the goal
But it's not always the reality when you open an MRE
That it was I just like this gelatinous BBQ Beef
Does pungent smell to it Louisiana native Ben Armstrong spent five years in the Marine Corps
Don't even get him started on the jambalaya MRE
For a Louisianan
I'll never try
Into the military isn't just working on MREs they're also trying to blow up foods that
Look and taste more like
You know what you
Eat it 3 a.m.
You're like really really hungry and your judgment is somewhat
Impaired
We actually took
Something like a Hot Pocket that you find in the freezer at the grocery store and made one that was shelf-stable
And we did that by controlling the water activity and the
The pH of the
Components within the product
So that they wouldn't allow bacteria to grow
They packaged it up with something called an oxygen scavenger
A little packet of iron filings that absorbs oxygen
Keeping it away from the bread from old wouldn't grow on the bread
And we designed hurdles to each
Step within the process
That might allow spoilage
To the point where we now have a sandwich that will last for 3 years at room temp
And this leads us to the Holy Grail of military food diet
An item that soldiers have been requesting
Since time immemorial
Pizza
Pizza that is shelf stable
For three years
This is a pilot plant even took me inside a massive industrial kitchen
Full of giant kettles mixers ovens
I see a worker and a lab coat and hairnet
Standing over an enormous pot
Stirring vigorously
In another corner of the pilot plan
A different worker is slicing up a pizza topping
Bad at first
I thought I misheard
Did you call this as Maroni
Asma Rani
Cosmo room
Is Moroni or osmotic pepperoni looks
Like a roll of toilet paper made of meat
Athena sheet of beef rolled up
The layer of plastic to prevent it from sticking to itself
It's preserved using osmotic dehydration
The technology basically involves running thin sheets of meat
Special water bath
It removes water from the meat itself
Preserving it
Oh I probably somebody just serve me that I would not have even questioned what it was
It tastes like pepperoni I would probably increase the amount of pepperoni flavor but those are some of the things that were working on
The Army is a mean to have shelf-stable pizza in combat zone by 2017
And maybe
Soon after that
In your local grocery store
This is another part of the combat feeding directorate
Ever since its Origins after World War II
When the military decided it needed to create a back-up plan to feed troops in the event of a sudden War
And so the US government made it a requirement for these labs to share their findings with the commercials
What we trying to do
When we come up with a new technology is make sure that it's not military specific
So that there are commercial applications for a 10 and that can only help us
With economies of scale
If something is military unique and it's only produced for the US Military
The cost of going to be a lot higher than ever
It's produced for
The commercial said
As well and it's not just caused
If there's ever a large demand for these combat rations
Like in a time of War
It's good for the military if there are companies out there that already have the technology to make these kinds of products
And of course if the private sector has these Technologies they'll use them
Oh no
This means there is evidence of the Army's insulin
All over the grocery aisle
For example your children can thank the armed services for their favorite food
Cheese powder in the mac and cheese and then you'd have it also in me TV snaps
Might be around
Starting with her children's lunch
Read a book called combat-ready kitchen
How do US military ships
The way you eat
So at this point
Chicken walk into a grocery store and point out all the foods that have the military's fingerprints on them
Which is exactly what she did with me
TV dinners turkey tetrazzini
Meatloaf and gravy and turkey pot pie the TV dinner the Frozen entree was developed by an army
Contractor to feed bummer troops
On overseas flights
This prompted the military to come up with what became the microwave
Yes
The microwave is a military innovation
The military also developed freeze-drying technology
So instant coffee teas
Soups the Army also Hit Upon a game changer
What they call intermediate moisture food
Foods that are moist and also bacteria resistant in energy bars
Calories sliced bread and packaged cookies one thing that cookie makers that is once they understood
Just started making this soft and chewy cookies in the olden days
As you go through the grocery store
Anastacio stops in
Squeezes packages
She gets excited about a package of
Thai Basil and sweet chilli stir fry sauce
OK Google
To feel the packaging
This is a retort pouch
Which was developed
By the Natick center of the same packaging from the MREs but now it's bruised
Easy applesauce and yogurt
Tuna and sauce packets a little bit hunting with you go grocery shopping
Military everywhere I started to feel like I was walking around looking at ghosts of
Russian time I think about it when I when I'm with my kids because they do seem to prefer this
It's not just anastassios kids
These food products are beloved and ubiquitous
Panchito's
Chewy granola bars
Military innovations have a tendency to get work
Ginger diet
And most people don't
Stop to question our packaged cookies you can remain soft for eternity
Okay I'm not going to worry about it
We go for that
Anastacio says
Unclear how or if these food preservation techniques are affecting our health
There a lot of ways that the military has changed the chemistry of differ
And not all of them have been studied
But
She's definitely hesitating before putting these types
Foods in her kids lunches
The average civilian doesn't need food to stay preserved for years at a time
But it's showing up on our shelves thanks to military
And we're buying it
This is what we're giving
Be shelf-stable and the mold resistant meticulously designed to stimulate the fresh
And the familiar
So if in a few years you happen to buy a shelf-stable pizza in your local supermarket
Be prepared
That pepperoni
Might actually be
Ozma round
99percentinvisible was produces week by Tina Antolini with Avery troubleman Katie mingle same Greenspan
Kurt Kolstad and me Roman Mars
Tina Antolini hosta podcast gravy which is a production of the Southern foodways Alliance
You can check it out at Southern foodways. Org gravy
Shadows book
Combat ready kitchen how the US military shapes the way you eat
On our website that's 99 pi.
Product of kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of arcsin in architecture and interior
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs
Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If I'm
Listen to an Alexa interact
Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Voice technology
All she talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
IPic
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways
Our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into an answer
Questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 5th
Peep featuring in episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stuck
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Infos Life podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flat pocket
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get
Eject play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com