99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launching first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
Your attention please this is 99% invisible
Resetting a new exciting radio program
I'm Roman Mars
I'm willing to concede from the get-go that I might be wrong about the entire premise of the story
But Superman has never really worked for me as a character
I prefer the more grounded Marvel comic book characters like
Spider-Man who lived in real cities
And human thoughts and feelings
Superman is basically
Invincible
Unrelatable
And
Used
Establishment
And even though I really love the first Christopher Reeve Superman movie
It contains a perfect example of why I don't really dig the character
The business a twenty-five-year-old spoiler alert but at the end of the 1978 movie
All the greatness of that film is nearly undone by the fundamental flaw of having a character that is all
Powerful than Superman
Flies around the Earth
Backwards
And turns back
Time
Person got to get clear is that he's not share
He doesn't turn back time
Superman one that's Glen Weldon father of Superman the unauthorized biography
Grasping for an explanation
Flies faster
Speed of light
Travels in time
So that's exactly what he's doing except he's just spinning round and round
So the reason everything goes
Backwards
He's not because he's actually
Spinning your ass backwards on it
Axis making time go
We're just watching
Kim travel back
In time we're seeing it through his eye
So that's what
What's going on this is my Wackadoo series that I'm going to a standby
Fork friendly
Despite the fact that there's some stuff in the in the movie that kind of
Contradict
I still plugged for this music that I'm talking over is from the Superman movie soundtrack you know what it's called it's called
Turning back the world
I'm teasing Glen Weldon because I feel like I know him because in addition to being
The unauthorized biography for a Superman
He's also a panelist on NPR's pop culture Happy Hour podcast which is
Great it comes out on Friday
I listen to it
Friday
So I got in touch with Clan because I thought if I can appreciate Superman as a character
Maybe I can appreciate him
As a design
A supremely successful design
And the first thing Glenn told me is that I need to dispense with this notion
That's Superman
Should be relatable
The thing you have to understand about Superman
Is that he was
Never intended
The character that we identify with
He's not a hero like Batman
Set a hero like Spiderman
Man who have
Psychological Hang-Ups that we recognize
Empathize
He's not the hero
We identify with
He's the hero
We believe in
Different he's an inspiration he supposed to be
Better than us
That's right there in the name
Movie called Superman for a reason
He exists to say
We can be better we can achieve these eyes
Ideals
There are so many things that the creators of Superman Jerry Siegel and Joe Shuster
Got right in the design is Superman from the very beginning the first thing they got right
Was being first
1st and Market
It difficult to pinpoint which character qualifies as the first
Superhero
Yoga Master Hercules or the Phantom or the clock
It's worth looking into the clock
But Superman is certainly
The first of a type
The dominated popular culture from the moment he debuted in 1938
Any idea
Was simple
Well he was created to be basically a circus strongman
What's that word
Design the costumes
And that's what Siegel and Shuster intended he was just like us
Only
Bigger stronger
Better so he could do everything that we could do
You only do it
More that's where the Superman ID
It's very simple that's why this character stuck around
Cuz the iconography of simple
Red blue and yellow even the color blind can see red blue and yellow that's that's important
You have to keep everything about this character as simple as possible
Couldn't fly at the
He denied any of the other sensory
He was at the guy that Siegel and Shuster would drop into the middle of a scene
With a bunch of fog
And they would try to attack him and he would shrug them off
This was the engine of the story this is where the
The adventures
Funnel
Those early stories came from
Just him showing over and over again
That he was wrong
Thundamentals Siegel and Shuster
Nailed it they did they created something great
And everyone knew it
Read Superman endured
They had this fantastic public R&D.
They just keep upping the ante
They kept making
Bigger
And more powerful
Started throwing in all these other
Door trying to
Mission trying throwing all these other powers
Song which really didn't
One of the first
Weird
Powers he had early on
Was the ability to contort the muscles
Look as face
To change his appearance and pass himself off as somebody else
Now that doesn't Square
With the iconography
Hi who's really
Better than you can just
What we can do
Only more
It went away
Because it's not the power of a superhero That's The Power of a
Adopting somebody else
Disguise
Can go undercover
It's not that doesn't square with
And when you have powerful enough iconography you can make mistakes like that
And it doesn't have a lasting effect
The other powers
Are things like
Super hearing
Super
Vision diesel
And telescopic Vision x-ray vision these things
Are about
Traits that we possess
That just
Skip boost
That's what the
Is characters about
Later on the course we get things like super hypnotism
Man super ventriloquism
Products of an age
Of comics, Superman
When things got really
Happens to be my favorite era of this character
Because things just get bananas
And
Superman has become so powerful
That the focus starts to shift away from
12 Lois Lane
The people around him
Superdawg
Super Monkey the super cat
Super horse all these other things around
Can you become to the
Patriarch of this
Extended family
Of people in blue long john
But beyond the comic book superfan none of that stuff filter too far out into popular culture and stuck around
The one power that they develop later
I got folded into the very core of the character
Was flight
Original you could just jump around
Turn on the page that's fine you see him in mid-air
But as soon as the Fleischer animated shorts
The very first couple
He jumps around
And it looks
It just doesn't work
So very soon
In on the radio show you know the sound of him jumping around
Suspended sound of
Wind noise
It was clear
Flying through the air
Defying Gravity
And that's what happened in the Flasher
Bridge of the comics a long time
To agree that y'all cake
Because
Beat the thing you could do was be better than us
But this idea of somebody being able to hover in mid-air
Was just too much of a break
From from the kind of
Grounded
Grounded stories
Matt Siegel intrusive
Retallack
But once he did
Once he did become a
A capable of
Flying Defying Gravity
You will believe a man can fly
Because there's something Primal about
That there's something that
Man is always wanted to do and so we got this guy
Can bring it along.
Unemployment
You can do it and that's what we looked
Recognize
Now today but it wasn't always the case
As you go to the history of Superman England weldon's book
You find a character that adapts in strange ways to reflect
The Zeitgeist and anxieties of the time
But certain qualities get written into Superman zna
The phone the real basis of what makes Superman
Superman
And it has nothing to do with the way he looks
Ultimately what I found over the course of the
Writing a book is that a lot of the stuff comes and goes
What's the red shorts can come and go espectro goes away it's comes back
Gets a different costume you gets this
Weird electrical blue
Costume in the 90s everything psycho
But
It's not what he looks
Even though that is considered the iconography
He looks like
It is what he does
Number one he puts the needs of others
Overdose
And be he does
So those two Elam
Either one of those two elements are missing
Our brain instinctively reject
Don't feel like a Superman
Which makes telling compelling and nuanced Superman stories
Pretty difficult
Butwell Nikes
And you want is not what Superman is about age where we don't trust altruism
That's what he's there for he's there to represent it is there to say
Here's truth
Is what looks like yours just as usual
Looks like your compassion
Is a big part of
And also you know he's called the man of tomorrow because that's been part of his DNA from the
Beginning of Tomorrow long before
Organs called The Meadows
Original
Nickname
Because you help
Put away the future to say here's what we can be
Hughes
If we're better to each other
And better ourselves
Here's what we can do
So that's that
It it easy
Douchebag
Is one area
About this character
I believe in mm
99% invisible exam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Jess getting her from the NPR for recording Glen Weldon for us we are project of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco
An American Institute of Architects
Shenzhen
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Sea kelp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flash podcast
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode
What about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars but you always catch up with us online at 9
10% invisible
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero and
Any movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast.,