99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
View of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their History season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is the record-breaking kickstarter-funded season 3 of 99% invisible
Give yourself a round of a
YouTube
The picture of
Pneumatic
Pneumatic pneumatic
Of course
Are gases
Donnie
In the wall where the tubes go
Away
They never come back
Does it work
Will never know
Vacuum
In the world before telephone and email the task of transmitting information
And moving material objects was essentially
The same challenge
The way you send someone a message with pretty much the same process as sending someone a package you had to send a piece of physical media
Lea to the post or on the ship
It was the telegraph that divided telling someone something
Remember every day people didn't speak Morse
So the message had to be deciphered written on a slip of paper
And that it was delivered to the recipient
Even though you can probably guess already that electronic communication eventually killed most of the need for pneumatic tubes
You may not know that it was the telegraph itself that also put pneumatic tubes into widespread use
As Telegram
Blew up
Amanda cost drop
Did the volume Rose it became very difficult to quickly deliver them to their destinations
And so
But they needed to do was come up with another way to get messages across the city quickly
So if you can't send something with that newfangled electricity stuff you have to figure out a way to do it all
Sending a message as a physical object
The Last Mile problem
Getting to an end
Customer or an end recipient
Can be the more difficult
Call problem
And it came up with the post pneumatique or the pneumatic post
Doing that
That is Molly Wright steenson
Researcher PC student and aficionado of all things pneumatic tube
Pneumatic tubes are systems of subterranean
Bourbon
Postal services that delivered messages underneath
Cities
All across the world in major Financial Centers
Those were the large-scale implementation
Splitter on the right number of smaller pneumatic tubes
More familiar to people today are producer Sam Greenspan spoke with Molly through a difference
I had similar experiences with pneumatic tubes growing up
When I was a kid
Used to go to the bank
Down the street
And to the bank with my Dad we go to the drive-thru and he put his deposit slip or whatever inside the
Plastic canister
My mom would enroll her window and she gets a canister
From this big are making device
And she put in whatever checks she wanted to deposit and then I would see it shoot up
Clear tube
Through this clear tube and it would shoot across to the bank
And then the ladies in the bank
Candy Girl
Lollipops for me and my brothers and dog biscuits for the dog
And it just seemed
And they also hearken back to another era
You may only know about pneumatic tubes in the context of a Bank drive-thru
When they were invented they really set the stage for what communication would look like over the next century
Pneumatic post first started in London
In 18th
3 but the technology transfer
Very quickly to other cities
Tiananmen
Say Munich Milan Lynn Lewis
Australia
Pneumatic post
In every major
On every
Antarctica
Antarctica is always slacking
But know where we're pneumatic
Choose more expensive in
19th century
Totally redone paris's Urban layout
Putting in those big
Boulevard
Circular Plaza
He also put in sewers
So not only did the sewer carry potable water
And eventually
Electrical cables butt
It carried
Pneumatic tube
Annies tubes inside of tubes
Square head
My 1919 Paris was processing 12 million pieces of pneumatic post a year
Mai 1945
They were 450 km of pneumatic tubing lining Paris is underground
Making it possible to get a handwritten note across Paris in less than 2 hours
Without even breaking a sweat
Here's how it works
You write something on some special
Stationery closet
Postage
And you get at your local two piece
That's what you
Call one of the people who sends pneumatic post
The envelope in a can
And let me tell you about the
Happy birthday gif
But over time they became more aerodynamic
Begin to resemble Little Rock
Anyway
The to beat Rings an electric Bell to alert the two beasts on the receiving end
There's an incoming canister and then
It's hurtling through paris's underbelly so fast
The descending to Beast that actually hear that
The canister arriving
Destination the description
From the 19th century
Talk about the shop
The noise of the shocker
Pneumatic post arriving
The only
Provide enough for switch
Beastie
And so they were checking antics
Steam engines
Underneath the hotel de post which was the central post office
Westin Paris
And they would produce the
Compressed and rarefied Air
That would serve to push or pull
Pneumatic tubes through all of the kilometers in miles and miles of two
That we're underneath
The streets
They're also even buildings
Simply existed 2
Produce are for the tube
Services
The biggest pneumatic tube systems had problems that required some creative troubleshooting
Paris Hutton
Twisting mechanism
In case there was a blockage
Did someone win
Fire a gun
Into the tube
And then measured
Soundwave
And be able to figure out to Within
I guess two metres or so where the blockage was
And then
They would be able to go under
Ground and
Undo the flan
French and
Bring out the offender
Canister
I guess it's better than what happened in
In Berlin where they just poured copious amounts of wine
Into the tubes in order to unfreeze
Stop canisters
As exciting as all this sound electric communication evolve
You're up other Technologies like telephone and tell facts and proved that way cheaper
And so off The Last Mile problem
It was another form of physical transport that put the nail in the coffin
The thing that put them out of business in the United States was
The invention of the truck
The truck was in bed
Dentist in 1912 and and that's kind of what
What did it
Trucks are fine and all but they just don't capture the imagination like a massive
Pneumatic tube Network
As silly as such a thing might seem today
Moline I spent a good deal of time trying to figure out what exactly it is about the tubes that leads
Be fascinated
Mysterious about
Why you mad
Tubes are magic
I think the Inspire Wonder
Because
They're alive
Or it feels like there alive there
Reaching out through the city they have tendrils and 10th
And they breathe
And they feel
Much much
Bigger than we are
Inspire Wonder because
They manifest
Medication
4S
Today when we think of communication all the ones and zeros and digital things that we move
Don't feel real tangible
To us anymore
But I also
They felt pretty magical 2
Two people
Back then to that they were
Kind of electrical and breathing connections
Communication
You could send to handkerchief
And send it to your lover by a Pneumatic
And it would still smell like you
So I mean
We're romantic as well and I think
Weather today to
So in a sense they're both alive and mechanical both high and low Tech
And there's also something to be said about the Journey of a tube canister
That you can imagine it's making its way through these Underground
Passageways
Carrying your message
And so this idea of being able to go somewhere where you wouldn't otherwise be able to go is
It's amazing
Message this made that entire underworld Journey
In order to surface in the hand sub
Recipient
More than their widespread use
What might be the most surprising thing about pneumatic tube systems is how long they
Stayed in you
The post pneumatic operated in Paris
Until as late as 9
Before
Even ran over the Brooklyn Bridge until 1953
And took a force of nature knock them out of Prague
The city was using them until a flood in 2002
Lots of places
Still use
Hospitals
Used pneumatic tube system
And that's what
Cuz you really can't
Digitize tissue or medication
And so the next time you find yourself in a hospital take a look because you'll find them by the nurses station
Munson in the emerging
Chelsea room
They're also used it places at grocery stores or big electronics stores usually that kind of delivery
Pneumatic tube so that
It's not any
Where where the store could get robbed
When Molly was doing research on tubes at the New York City Public Library
She found her requests were being dispatched
Buying a Matic 2
But there's one other tube system in New York that moves a lot Mormon
In Roosevelt Island pneumatic tubes are used
Four for garbage
Roosevelt Island if you don't know is a small island in East River between
In Queens New York
And as it happens my good friend Hannah Jamal grew up there
Hey how's it going nice to hear from you so I asked her about the pneumatic tubes
I get flustered when people ask me about the garbage
Because to me
How you take out your trash
The most fascinating thing about it
Yes I am sure that there are thousands of fascinating facts about Roosevelt Island but let's hear about those garbage tubes
Aaron is only about three miles long and about 800 ft
Wide and when the other was being developed for residential living in the 1960s planners determine that the quality of life would be
Better without big garbage
Trucks on the road
So instead
The dispatch with their trash
With a pneumatic tube Network
And I have one friend and put
Particularities my friend David and
He can tell you more about how it works
Brooklyn-based producer moods ad
Hey to go meet Hannah's friend
I haven't got a mood
Guy named David Finkelstein
Stanley and I live in Roseville.
Tell me when you want start time out the trash.
There's not much to say about it
The beginning of the processes I guess the same as what most people deal with
Just like they have the trash to take your trash bags and then take out
Tie it up
Man we got fat here coming
Florida
Urumqi
Rack Room
And my whole life
If it's the same thing and at least all the
The original buildings
The newer buildings
Floor has a
Ours is Right neck
The stairwell
You open it up
And it's not a lot in it
Tiny little
I'll get like space and there's
A place for recycle
Recyclables
Cute
Handle that you pull and you
Open the door and throw your garbage down the champion and
And that's it
To be honest like it wasn't until after I left Roosevelt Island that I realized
Other people don't have a vacuum
That's not
I remember
Precisely when I learned about it
I think it might have been awake
Pediatric I like double check that I knew it pneumatic man
Amazing
Well my dad
In fairness the tubes might have made a bigger impression if Hannah and David had the
But there
Trash bag in a rocket ship
Canister and fired across the island
But there's still something about a visit to Roosevelt Island
Makes you feel like
You're on the cusp of the future even though you're clearly not
A payment when can I try Siri
Okay if you think about all the technology we were promised the Future Would
Hold from something like Star Trek
A lot of his come true right like we have little touchscreen computers we have hand communicator
What are things that we don't have and will probably never have is
The Transporter
You know the thing that can disassemble something somewhere
And reassemble it somewhere else
And I wonder if that has to do with why the tubes feel both so ancient
And so futuristic at the same time
Like it's the closest we ever got to transmitting a
Physical object instantaneously
I think that's definitely possible that you could get something instantly
It's again that you could communicate
But you said that you could not only get it
But but
You could have that feeling
Sensation or that information right away it's the Nexus of those two things
What is more than just information
The scented handkerchief that are rhymes
After traveling through miles of Paris underground or even
The dog biscuit from the bank teller these
Are romantic because they have physical intimacy
I mean maybe that's why we keep coming back to it and maybe that's why
Steampunk
Seems important
In a digital age
Actually we do need physical things and
You know we've we never did get our check
But we we do care all the more about things that are real and tangible that come to us and I think with
The pneumatic post represents
What pneumatic tubes represent
Is the possibility that that could happen
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars with help from moods a day
It's a project of kalw 91.7 local public radio in San Francisco in the American is sumac
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Call hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Sea kelp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flash podcast
Can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
Actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast.,