99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
People who make horror movies know that if you want to scare someone
Use scary music
And when we want to explore the design of music
We call rishikesh Railway
The podcast
Song exploder
So here are two fundamental ways to make something sound scary
According to evolutionary biologist Dan blumstein
The first way is to use lots of screeching irregular
Animals when they're scared
Are blowing a lot of air across their vocal cords or cross their syrinx if there are bird
And the sounds of Screams are something that is
Arousing
And makes people feel negative
It's biological your lizard brain hears Bernard Herman's knife stabbing music and psycho and Sassy
Something terrible is happening right now
The second way sound can make you feel uneasy
To go the other way
Make really low ground
Another biological Cube that might lead to fear and anxiety is hearing low frequency
The lowest frequency of a species can produce as a function of its body size so low frequency
Probably should scare you
It it might mean if something big is around
Makes those both together and you're on your way to creating classic scary music for scary movies
Good horror movies aren't just meant to be horrifying exciting fun so it's sometimes nice to have a
Driving beat
The music from the movie Halloween by composer John Carpenter will always greet me out
And also give me kind of excited
And some Sahara movies I certainly know that I respond
Sound in horror movies in ways that are complex
Soundtrack Sorrentino
That's a very specific thing that provokes drag
David Slade is very good at evoking dread himself
Maine Savings play died
Pilot for the first
Episode of Hannibal and unexpected from the show and I pretty much time makes every
Episode
I've been binging on the TV show Hannibal for the past couple weeks and it really gets under your skin it's the story of it
Serial killer named Hannibal Lecter who you may know from
Silence of the Lambs and Manhunter
This is kind of a prequel to The Story
Hannibal
Is a nasty character who commits brisley and unspeakable crimes
The other main character is Will Graham FBI profiler with a knack for getting inside the heads of serial killer
Taylor is to try to catch them
Trust me
There is nothing fun going on inside Will Graham set
An inside will Graham's head is exactly where the sound design of Hannibal
Trying to place the viewer
Program for July 16-17 recognizes patents as what he does he reconstructs things in his head
It's a mental issue
Synopsis
These are things that we want
How to make an audio
This is from the first episode of Hannibal
All the classic horror movie music we mentioned before exist outside the world of the story and other words it's not
Being heard by the characters being depicted
It's just being heard by the audience but composer Brian reitzell score for Hannibal feels different
You get a sense that it's even being heard by Will Graham inside his own imagination
Our whole goal with horror really is to
Transport people into the other reality and it's a scary reality it's a tense reality but it's a
The beautiful place to
But to do that I find the most effective way to scare people is to throw sounds of them
That are unfamiliar to them
So Brian construx new sounds that the audience can't place
Create Anis
Guitar what is that
A lot of what we do is create all of the sound so we turn all the sound effects off
And the ones that we think are important we try to make
Tell me that resembles that sound or feels like that sound
I don't differentiate
Really between
Ambient sounds like a motor and
Abase
So in this case
She's on a motorcycle I had to be really interesting to
Make the feeling of what it would be like
Being on that motorcycle
Rush of adrenaline in the Wind
Sound of engine which is underneath you I mean all this is very powerful
Stop self
The first idea I had was to do it with an upright Bass
Just listening up and down the neck
The Q starts with with the motorcycle starting up
So we do lots of little things in there too
Mimic
Or hinted those sound
On-screen Racine the key turn
Castanets
Can we see the
Flames from the engine
The sound of sheep
Is me bowing a wood block
River by and sounds
The more I work with the different instruments the more I understand what you can get out of them
Almost all the towns in Hannibal start out as an acoustic element from Brian rifles Workshop
Then the effort is made to strip it of identifying characteristics that would ground the sound in the real world
I'm constantly trying to d guitar a guitar or
Drama drama
Best Brian placing a wooden Chopstick on a snare drum and pulling a violin bow across the
Chopstick
You could never tell by listening that Chopstick bow or a drum made this sound
Brian doesn't just take regular instruments and make them weird he also takes weird instruments and makes them weirder
I went around Brian's Studio as he pulled out examples of the instruments uses
For example the sound of synapses firing inside will grab his head
It started out as a newton
Gradle if you don't know a Newton Cradle by name you definitely know the sound
I already knows it's it's on your desk
You know it's at pendulum toy with a stainless steel balls hanging from strings
But what I do is I used it as it
I use it to Trophies rhythm
A synapse in your brain
Stop
And did some different treatments at those and use those other
Percussion instrument because he actually broken in the process they were originally five balls that were a perfect unison
Even the most innocuous answer
Can Sinister in the hands of
Play sleigh bells I I just used in this first episode of Hannibal because I had
Snails
And I had to use macro shots of snails
But really it's ceased
David Slade calls the sound design of Hannibal
Free associative
They look at the footage
And talk about the characters in the feelings are trying to evoke from each scene and design from their the big bad guy in anabolism
Hannibal Lecter also is wrestling with his own demons
He has green like visions of a demon they call the windigo that represents both the evil of Hannibal and the eve
Evil growing inside Will Graham one of the character
Developed
Time
What's the wendigo character which
Is the bassist
Off
And we wanted a sound that indicate
The coming of that character
That sound
I knew it was sucking
We didn't know why but we knew I was right
And I took what David said literally and
I got a bull Roar
Have a basically it's a piece of wood
On a string
Smokey oldest
Instruments but it sounds incredible
You spin it in a circular manner
Slices through the air creating this
Turtle sound
Once we put it against
Sweeney
Very physical sounding
Sort of cutting through the air
Spinning around your head
Making it
Surreal yet also
Gary V
I also did things
2.2
I pitched it down I could sit up
To make it scarier
Mission accomplished guys
Richie case her way is the creator of song exploder
Which I'm very proud to say is now a member of the radiotopia collective
I'm so excited song Exploder is when my favorite podcasts in the
Premise is just perfect
Musicians take apart their songs piece-by-piece to tell the story of how they were made
If you've never heard song Exploder before I want to present what I think is my favorite episodes so far featuring Ja
John Roderick of the long Winters but
I have a hard time picking a favorite I really think
You just download them all and pick your own favorite
Now from radiotopia this is song exploder
My fellow Americans
This day has brought terrible news
Great sadness to our country
At 9 this morning
Mission Control in Houston
Lost contact
What are space shuttle Columbia
A short time later
Debris was seen falling from the skies above text
The Columbia is lost
There are no survivors
That was President George W bush
Addressing the nation on February 1st 2003
Couple years later John Roderick singer and songwriter of The Long Winters
Recorded the song about the space shuttle Columbia on that day
Is it broke apart while reentering the Earth's atmosphere
It's called
This episode is made from an interview I did with John Roderick in front of a live audience in Seattle
About how and why he made the song
I feel
I am John Roderick
I have my pilot's license when I was 17 my dad was a
Small plane pilot
And that was the way my dad was one of the ways that we bonded
In a small plane
I'll try to make it over amount
So I had a lot of experience
I always loved
Supply and when the
Nose comes off the ground
I always
Feeling chart
I didn't want to be a
But at that point
In 2005
We were still
Pretty close to 9:11 and the space shuttle
Disaster followed
Pretty close on the heels of a
But also there were all those smaller
The Alaska Airlines
Crash that happened off the coast of California where
Or they lost their
Vertical stabilizer the Jack screw one
The pilots were aware there was a problem everyone was aware there was a problem and just flew around and then
Flipped upside down in Plymouth
And then there was the one off of Long Island where maybe the gas tank exploded
And then there was that Learjet
That
Lost compression and everybody in it
Gone until it ran out of gas
And all of these
Disasters stuck with me
Digitally the ones where there was a sense that the people onboard knew that they
We're lost but they were still alive
The unfolding Dawning realization like you know we're not getting out of this
And what's your reaction in that situation do you do you scream you probably don't probably everybody is real
Situation in
The astronauts
On re-entry there was something wrong with
They were
Worry about it but everybody had convinced them in
And there
Performing their duties
They're having the peak experience of their lives and maybe one of the peak human experiences like we are coming
Back to her
Having just
Look down at Earth and had that feeling how beautiful that kind of dumb little stuff is the Butte
Beauty of the mundane
Boys and girls in cars in
Dogs and birds on Laurens light
Sing it baby
Like no one else
Dogs
Online
From here I can touch
The song
Did you sit down at the idea that you were going to
Write a song about this
Space shuttle disaster
Yeah but I didn't know how it was going to
Work
Every once in awhile you get one as a songwriter where you sit down at your instrument
You have an idea
You have a first line you sing it and
Compose the entire song in
In an hour
When you go I don't know where that came
I resisted piano lessons
As a kid but sometime in high school
I started to sit at the piano voluntarily
When no one was home
And trying
Figure it out
And I got as far as
You could go if you were just practicing for 11 minutes at a time
And I didn't really learn the piano until I was in my thirties
Learn the piano as much as
In the early 90s
In Seattle especially
There was a mentality that you didn't want to over learn
Your instrument
Right because that was going to affect the authenticity of your feelings
And I embrace that Hook Line & Sinker
So the producer of this
Track was Tucker Martin
Tucker head up just a stand-up parlor piano in his living room
That was recorded
Now we would probably just
Record at 1
Measure and lupus
But at the time I had to sit and play it
For 5 minutes and then I would get to the end and he be like
Let's hit it again
Eric Corson
Long layers
And my chief
Musical park
He sat down at
At the micro cord which is not an instrument
What she knew
But he worked with it for a little bit and
Figured it out
There are
Five or six moments in the song that without Eric
Part
It would be so much
Less of a complete
His part is very cinematic
As the song unfolded
It just starts to go sideways
Every successive
Stuff
Most of The Long Winter songs are
About relationships and they are
Intentionally
Difficult to parse
Because they're meant to communicate in an emotional language rather than in a literal
And so as I was writing this song I
As I made my way through the emotional
Story I was trying to tell I did arrive at a place where I was
I need to
Give a
Blue
The crew compartment
I was embarrassed
To say the crew compartment
Breaking up
Because I felt like
It was too little
And so to say the crew compartments breaking up the first time I went through and I was
Let you know
But it needed it
The crew
And the thing was
You sing at once
The second time everybody gets it the third time
They've heard it now the 4th time they're like okay alright
56 time it starts to get annoying
And then a new kind of
Gravity enters in
Restart
Fuel
The emotion
And when
When I perform at live if I'm not careful I will
Start to cry.
Dollar Tree
Bailando
We tried to get a little string quartet to come in
We ran several passes
We took that and
Play double speed
And they did their own version of this kind of swarm of bees
So we didn't have a drummer and it was like we should we get should we call that one guy because like or I could get the best drummer
Any
Producer would make that choice if he had
Matt Chamberlain
And Tucker
And he managed to
Not just introduced swing into it
But make this piano part which on its own is very Square
And on top of the beat
And he played to it
Introduced swing to it
Played a little bit behind in a little bit
With this tremendous sort of
Breath and energy
And watching it all happen
Was Revelation to me as a musician
I understood how much I have to learn
So what Matt did
He he came in he set up his drums and he had one microphone
But he pulled out of a bag
Set up himself
And we all just for watching him
You know like you would watch a black panther that came into your kitchen looks like
What's it going to do
Any put the microphone in front of his drums and he was like okay you know record me
And so he plays for about a minute and then he's like play that back from Annie listens to the track
And then he stands up he walks around and he moves the microphone
Sit back down and says
Any plays all the way through the trash
And I was listening to it and going like you know I'm the songwriter and kind of the main guy here and I was like
Yeah it was pretty good I mean I got some comments
And here we got to the end he was like
Okay roll it again
You know when you didn't
Wait to hear any comments from the songwriter which is like
All right
He played through it again
And I was like most interesting
You know kind of variation
He was like give it to me again
He did that five times
And then he's like Alright
You know I'm coming into the control room
He comes and he sits down he's like okay
Can those five tracks
Hard left
Middle left Center
Middle right hard right in the order that I work
5 mono drum parts
And he
Heather Forsyth
That there are drum fills that start on one track
And continue through all five track sleep
But this was something
Truly amazing
Asperger's drunk and I forgot to mention he has a piece of
Rusty
Just attached to a clam
And he starts to go up to this treatment like
And all of that sheet metal noise
That she was creator
The whole end of the tune
Where the spaceship is
Part
He was
Making that
Sound on
Rusty
He had a vision of the song that I didn't
You know the title of the song was
Clear
Until
Right about this point in the
Recording
And so then if the Commander's you know thinking aloud
Why is he telling us this
Story
Suzhou
That's his
His Last Vow
Do you have a sense of who he was addressing
I don't
Publicly out myself as a
Utopian and a
Keep on lover
Because it's not my brand
But I'm an idealist Anna and I love humanity and I imagine us as all on a
Together
All
With a common cause
And
Space exploration seems like the ultimate
Freshen up
Human being
Doing their best
Work
So I imagine he is springing that back
Plus all of us
Something
If we could only
Share that
Sympathy
Why the hell do we go up into
Go up into space to bring
That little Tanner
Vision of the Earth being a borderless
Place full of
Birds
Boys and girl
Here's the
The commander thinks aloud
Why the long run
In its entire
Sprint
Because
Risque Chartway is the creator of song Exploder now from radiotopia find out more at song explode
Charter.net
99percentinvisible is Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are product of 91.5
Seven kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin in architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook or on Twitter Instagram Tumblr and Spotify to but if you want to tell offendable
That's a fan of the show Hannibal about our show the best place to send them is 99 Pi. Org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com