99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Starting up
Women have you do when you get on
I'm going to have you just
Down for a few seconds
And then when I tell you
Hiiraan
That is the sound of producer Phoebe Flanigan jogging on a treadmill
Tubing observed by Legend loss
One of the world's leading experts on sports bra
Boston uses all kinds of fancy equipment like a 3D imaging machine
Understand the biomechanics
Breasts and how they move when women exercise
The pretzel rise up and then has to go down again
Changes
Directions constantly
Accelerations
Which is either speeding up or slowing down where the
The nipple is changing direction give me very high
I did a little research and I said you know a 30
D nipple can go from 0 to 60
Faster than a Ferrari
Really
Much faster
Hookah
The past 30 years Lawson has worked as a researcher and consultant do Champion athletic wear
She specializes in sports bra design
Sports bras are a piece of clothing that women might take for granted today
But they were totally revolutionary when they were first invented
They opened up whole new Realms of sports and exercise to women
Studying at do I say this
I know from
Conversations
Literally
Of women
This is a game changer
Today we're going to feature a story from our friends at the outside podcast from outside magazine and PRX
They did a whole episode dedicated to the design and history of the sports bra
Start back and lots of laughs with reporter Florence Williams
Beyond the lab which is also got a sports Broad Museum
Stop the decades worth of vintage model
Some are more mystifying than others
There are so many straps
This cannot be any weirder
What's it called the demon jogger with
I called the
Daemon jogger
And
There were instructions
On how to get this
On
Which
You put your legs through it
What
A poet up
Look at all the options around the room it's
Crazy to think the modern sports bra didn't even exist, Jane was growing up
Ashley when I started High
School we weren't allowed to run full court because
With the assumption that girls for 2 weeks
And we couldn't run any races
Longer than like
So
Women participating in sports and having needing a
Sports bra
Is so recent
Recent and surprisingly controversial
Wilma Jean started doing her research back in the 80s she actually got some serious pushback
What's a fun letter that turned up at her office
Letter said
If
God had intended women
To run
He would not have
Put breast on them
So it's sort of like
There was a hole
Socio-cultural stereotype
How women should
Behave
And it wasn't
Vigorously and badly it was
It was
Need more
Carmen Suite
And have
Comport
Self with more
Daddy
And not
Assertive
Doseum
Compassionate
To understand how the sports bra change all that we need to go back to 1977
It was the same here that James fix
How much does blockbuster bestseller The Complete Book of running
It was just a few years out from Title Nine
Women were finally wanting in on the Sports Action after being told for generations and generations that there by
Bodies just weren't built for sports
Started walking
Congratulations I got in shape I began to run
Now I Run 3 days a week
Family and
You know my whole generation
Started
Exercise
This is Lisa Lindell
She got caught up in the craze
I
Had a friend who introduced me to
What was then called
Jogging
And a new term
It was
I went out and started
Chalking up at the University of Vermont indoor track
And just to get around that track once was
Painful
And I remember the day that I got around that track four times in
Completed a mile and you would think I had won an Olympic medal
I was
So proud of my
Lisa broke a mile
N2 N3
She started running outside
Before she ran
The more she realized she had a new problem
Actually two problems
Her 360
When you have a t-shirt
Over
Bouncing nipples
You get chafing
So the answer to that
Is to put a bra on
Because I did try running without any Braun and then of course I got a lot of
Comments from
Passing motorists
Male runners
Things haven't changed much
Unfortunately not
So you wear a bra
Of some sort
And then that poses new and different product
Like the straps
It slip off your shoulder so you're all
Checking them back up
Hardware that can dig into your back
And they're hot
Sweaty
Lisa sister started running to
And one day she called The Rock
And she said what do you do about your
Actually that's what she said I am so uncomfortable when I'm running
What she said when I was talking about
The fact that I had no great solution
Was
Why isn't there a
A jockstrap
For women
That's when we really laughed we thought that
That's hilarious
Lisa couldn't let the idea drop
She started working the problem
What would that bra have to look like what would it have to do and I sat down at my
Dining room table and wrote out a list that was alright the straps shouldn't fall off
They should be wide enough that they don't take in
Ideally I was hoping that it could
Be modest enough that I could
Take off my t-shirt on really hot summer days
Because I had a running partner who
Would do that he would
Take off in the middle of a run his T-shirt
Over his head stuck in the back of his shorts and I was
Jealous
Because I couldn't do that
But I didn't hold a lot of Hope for
That in the beginning
And then you're somehow your husband became involve your husband at the time
Yeah also
How to roll hair
He did because
What happened is I mean part of the irony of this story Florence is that I
Don't
So
But
Living with me at the time when it was was my
Good friend Polly who
Had become a costume designer and so boy did she so
And I went to her and said Polly help me make this and
So we started making
Prototypes
And
Having difficulty because
Really bras
An engineering
Proposition
Yeah things need to be cantilevered
It's like building a bridge
But we didn't know that
So we were sitting in the living room Polly and I be moaning
The latest
Prototype that I had gone running in and was not cutting it
And my then-husband came down the stairs and he had pulled one of his jockstraps
On over his head
And across his breast and said
Hey ladies hahaha here's your new jock bra
And
We just thought that was very very funny and rolled on the floor and
I got up and and
Took it off of him
Tried it on cuz I had to get in the act
Pulled it over my
Dress that actually had breast
And when
I went running the next day in this truck
Backstrap contraption
And knew that it was
This was the
Product that was going to work
And
Probably went to New York City and found good elastic
Found a new fabric that would work for the cups
Wella we had a working prototype
How did you come up with the name jog bra
Well
There is no such term is sports bra the time
And so we are calling it jock brought I like that and
We heard from some people in the south
That jock was not such a nice word
And
We didn't want a name that offended some people
So we change jock to jock
And it became jog bra
Lisa started shopping her new job brought around to different sporting good stores
What's the buyer to look at her like she was crazy
Why would a running store sell women's underwear
I was very clear from the beginning that
This was not going to go into lingerie
It didn't look like lingerie it was
Considered ugly
And so it needed to go into Sporting Goods so that when a woman went in to buy her shoes she could also get this
Bra
And
So I had to contend with men
Who are the buyers
Or because of women's undergarments
Had never been sold outside of the context
Lingerie
Correct
To put it in lingerie would be to be minimizing its importance
Minimizing its functionality
It's so was not about lifting and separating and
Making a woman more
Attractive according to
Some
Fashionistas
It wasn't about the bullet problem
No
It would and it was about functionality Emmett smushed
The breast
Ferguson
The chest wall
There was a little bit of a uniboob issue right
Yes Absol
There was a eunuch
Asian of course now
You can have a very sexy sports bra now
Write the fact that it was really about function
100%
And it took off
And it was immediately success
Our average growth rate was like 25% per year
And we just kept growing
Fundamentally 80s everywhere she looked Lisa was seeing Runners and others wearing sports bras
But it wasn't until the 1999 Women's World Cup that she realized just how far her vision to travel
US soccer team have just beat China or the winning goal by Bri
Brandi Chastain
Rose Bowl in Pasadena
I was
Home in Vermont
And all of a sudden my phone started
I ran to the TV set
And of course they were replaying the moment
And I went oh my
Word
Annapolis let me just describe it
She made the final winning goal
Xi'an
As soon as a goal
Hit the net
She ripped
Off her shirt
And she was wearing a black jog bra
And she pumped her fist and she showed her muscles and she was
Swarmed by her ecstatic teammates
I end and it was really the jog bra that
Was seen around the world
The driver that was heard around the world
And I think I think what you said was it was her confidence
And her preparation and the long
Journey
That came to fruition in that moment
And that
That is just
Perfect because that's exactly
You know what I could say about my
Journey
In my life really but also the the
Jogbra
In a way that moment also really represented the culmination of your dream that one day women could
Run around with their shirt exactly it
Women do I see it all the time and I chuckled to myself and see women running down the
The running path of the greenway here in and they're in there
Running shorts and their sports bra
And that's it
So the jagras revolutionize women's participation in sports
If you were still geared toward women with small to medium-sized chest
What about the subsets of women who were the most discriminated against of all in sports
Do women with really big butts on guys
An often plus-sized body
Back of the champion bra lab Le Jean Lawson says the coming up with products for large breasted women was the obvious Next Step
Also required some Next Level engineering
When you're running their ground reaction forces coming up through your body that are
Two three times your bodyweight
And those impacts
Are transmitted through breast tissue
Are skeletons are pretty bony they were acting a certain way the breast
Is her the Scholastic
And can respond even
More
To the Empire
Stretch and distort out of shape
The larger the breast The more mass of the breast
The more impact
Can affected and create
Very large displacement
But yeah
Nice is a big factor
That was certainly proven to be true for renelle braaten
Oh I would try doubling up on sports bras
Shoot a hairdresser in Montana
And she been playing volleyball and running track
Triple d's
When you start getting up in the
CD double d triple D area
You got
You got to have a lot more going on there too
Containers
Give me pictures of how big triple D breasts are like do you know what they weigh for example
Oh not really
But
If I were looking at a triple D breast
You know in front of me what
Would it look like
So apparently you don't have triple D
I so do not know I'm a b r u r
I tell you what they can be very annoying
Because every time you want to do anything mover
You know I remember when I was playing volleyball
Get on the ball with
Florida Court
And I just stand there and let somebody else go after it because I was
Running after that thing
When I was Fed Up and eventually it occurred to her to just try to hack the dog brought and make it a much sturdier
Feat of engineering
That was a 1985
And I tell you the first bra that I made for myself was not pretty we just
We just use my
Mother's leftover fabric from different things and
But I really didn't care I didn't get that's that's the thing with me is I don't
I don't care what it looks like I just wanted to work
What were the big Innovations in in your bra what made it
Different from the jogger
It was more there's more fabric
There's less stretch
In the fabric
Because of you
What it what I always say if you can
If you can take a sports bra and
Stretch it out
Enough.
Pull it over your head
It's only going to stretch when it gets there
So we knew we had to do something that had a closure in it and I wanted the closer
In the front
I make it easier to get on and off
So
It looks like a vest
Basically
So you were able to distribute the weight a little bit through this design
But we're not why do you think large breasted women had been so ignored until this
You know I think it's probably a couple different things
There probably wasn't as many
Of us out there I think there's
The be more of us
So so you think that breasts are actually getting bigger now
Yeah I think they are I think people are getting bigger
Breasts are getting bigger
Feet are getting bigger
I mean if you look at an antique
Pair of shoes from way back when
They're tiny
I mean really tiny
Oh yeah I think people are getting bigger
Yeah well I've certainly heard that anecdotally I know it's it's not something that's really easy to quantify think of
Not really measured in your annual doctor's visit
And also
I think
When girls
Start to develop
If they develop like starting in junior high early High School
And they're playing sports and all the sudden they've got these boobs
Dinner
Causing problems
The alarm
What do you think is behind that
I don't know
And I'm not a scientist I'm just a big boob blond
Grinnell may not be a scientist but we did find a woman who actually studies
Hi Michelle
Can you can you press can you say your name and briefly what you do
My name is Michelle large
And I'm a senior research associate
And I'm
Department of sport and exercise science
Comparing universe
Portsmouth
We call that Michelle because we wanted to see if her nails instincts were right
In spite of all the Innovation sports bra technology
Boobs could still be causing girls to drop out of sports
Something certainly is
Yeah this is a kind of a really big issue I guess worldwide just the general participation levels in sport
And I we looked at it in school girls in the United Kingdom
And as it is about 12 % of 14 year old girls
Are cheating kind of exercise guidelines
I know that as a nation we're getting more obese and patting my Mastiff has the implications
So we need to try and combat.
We actually found that
Breasts are
One of the barriers of why these guys might be dropping out which are not reaching exercise
Skyline
Wow so what did you find in your research
Yeah so we find
That
Release the breast
The biggest reasons for lack of participation in essays I guess
Is this press pound
So
I'm disconnect fascist movement in breast that grows every subconscious office
This again it was
Changing in front of each other so in school they weren't comfortable case their breath might be closer friends
This was
Gain more prevalence
A large breasted girls
This is interesting to me I mean it's not necessarily that it was sort of a physics problem
As much as it is almost a psychological problem
Yeah definitely
In terms of the physics I mean having a good
Sports bra with no will reduce
The mount depressed mood ring high or low or any kind of
Activity
So we can
Easy ultrasound physics
Suppressed movie
What is the psychological
I think that they probably need education on that can cut have bigger impact Maybe
50% reported that they never wear a sports bra during Sports
And for auspices
One of the main educational aspects that we can kind of communal as well
If you get a good sports bra you can reduce this
Bounce
I'm doing Spartan with my dad
School girls engaged in sport then
Do you think there's an economic fees to this as well
Possibly
Boys I think that
We see a lot of good for Fresno that are not necessarily very expensive
So I think that is becoming more accessible for people to have
Fourth prize in general and
Well for me sports bras
Huh
This is really sort of an understanding area and looking at access to health
You know we need to get these girls in the right equipment
We also found that
Dakshin massive concerns about their breasts 73% reporters
I'm having one breast specific concern is bored
I thought they were looking for Education that they'd be happy to take in breast education
I'm with a just wasn't there in the schools for them
I think it's
As soon as a taboo subject talking about breath and we really want to make it out that this is not
A taboo
It's something we should all talk about freely
And that we can kind of educate them further on
It's been forty years now since the first jock bra hit the market
Annual retail sales of the sports bra or in the billions worldwide
Umbrella
And it's all continuing to track with a phenomenal growth of women's Athletics overall
Next 40 years will likely offer better materials
Smart bras that keep track of your vital
Ever cuter sturdier and flashier designs
And hopefully more education to make these Jr's Contraptions of Structural Engineering more accessible
Girls who could use them
Because girls need to run and play
Emu
Even if they don't want their breath
To move quite so much
So here's to the basement sewing session
The high-tech boob lab
The dedicated Enthusiast who made it all possible
From all of us
Happy 40th anniversary
That was for rent Williams
This story was produced by Phoebe Flanagan and edited by Peter Frank Ryan
With music by Robbie Carver and Dennis Funk the story originally aired on the outside podcast production of outside
Magazine and PRX
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa is talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
What about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Five podcast
I'ma 99p ice staff Delaney Hall brought this piece into us and Sean real made the music
Senior producer is Katie mingle Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Images Gerald Terry Meza and Avery Chapman round out the Plucky Ensemble along with me
Roman Mars
We are probably the 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
And coin carrying donor
Just like you
Ubuntu show enjoying scussion about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and a show at 99ci Oracle on Instagram
Tumblr and Reddit to
You can stop by our place anytime at 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com