99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
There currently more than 31000 post office
Citizen United States
They're a grand old ones
What's the take up entire city block
And there are smaller number ones
Hideaway in the backs of General stores in towns across Rural America
But this one in Arizona
Maybe the most rural post office in the continental US
The Supai post office is located at the bottom of the Grand Canyon
My name is Vivian Campbell
And I am the postmaster of Peach Springs Arizona
She says there are only a few ways to get mail to the bottom of the Grand Canyon
You either have to
Pipe down there
Ride a mule or Rida
A horse
And so every day rain or shine
Male gets packed on 10 rules to make a 2 and 1/2 hour trip into the canyon
Post offices there to serve the people who live on the havasupai reservation
Havasupai meaning blue green water people
Name for the waterfall at the bottom of the canyon
The Falls are just Magnificent the water is so blue it's not even it's indescribable
The opposite 5 receive a lot of food supply
But otherwise there mail is pretty standard fare
They get packages from Amazon they get first class mail they get
They get bills just like you and me
The Supai post office was established in 1896 and its existence speaks to the links that the US
US post office has gone to connect people with each other
Do night outside the country
Ever since the service was founded in the late 1700s
I was sitting on my back porch in Wyoming one night
Sun sank in the Golden West
And I just jumped up out the chair
Like shrieked at my husband's the post office
This created America
That is author and historian Winifred Gallagher
And she would have booked
Based on this Revelation called
Appropriately
How the post office created America
History
Gallagher argues that the post office didn't just create an efficient and inexpensive way to send a letter from Oakland California
Into the Grand Canyon
The service was designed to unite a bunch of disparate towns and people under one flag
And in doing so
The post office actually created
The United States of America
For thousands of years governments have had ways of sending information across distances
But for most of History
Email was limited to correspondence
Dublin's military
Eventually
Wealthy people
Who could afford to pay for such a service
And that's what the postal system of early colonize America was like
The crowns post was put in place by the English Monarchy and was mostly used to get messages from England to America
What's the mail
Landed from
England into America it would be
Circulated by a fellow called a post Rider who just like he sounds he wasn't a man on a horse there were no
Road suitable for a wheeled vehicle
What's the time the colonies with dotted the eastern coast from New Hampshire Down to Georgia
Work. Interested in communicating
With each other
The colonies were very fractious
Disputatious siblings they were
Add very little to do with each other they were a clamoring for the attention of mother England
Started to change when an enterprising fellow named Benjamin Franklin became postmaster for the ground
As postmaster
Franklin was in charge of making sure mail in the colonies got to its proper location
And he was determined to improve the barebones system
He actually visited every colony
This is back when
What's a real pain in the neck
Establish milepost so you could
Charge fairly for the distance the letter was going instead of
Just estimating it
What is Franklin work to improve the crown system
He began to see the colonies different
I believe
That the process
Going around and thinking about
These 13 colonies
As
Not just
Disconnected
Links in a chain
I think this
Started him thinking about ways that they could
To come together
As a people
In 1754 at a meeting of colonial representatives in Albany New York
Franklin proposed a plan for uniting the colonies
He actually kind of sketched out of federal government where the colonies would elect their own Representatives as opposed to having them
Appointed by the crown
England didn't appreciate Franklin's ideas and colonist weren't quite ready for them either
Between years later Notions about American Self governance were spreading
Revolutionaries in the colonies needed a way to communicate about the growing movement for Independence
And they knew they couldn't use the Ground Post
Because if they use the crown system
Their letters would be intercepted and they'd be arrested
In 1774 these American revolutionaries created their own system to communicate called
The Constitutional post
Before they fought the revolution
Or had a system of government
For the Declaration of Independence
The Constitution
Americans hat
The post
The underground constitutional post
Was crucial in fomenting the revolution
Which gave America independence from England
It was still a very limited system
There were fewer than a hundred post offices in the entire country
In the system didn't serve that many people
It was basically a tool for political Elites
Communicate with
Founders wanted a better pose
One that would serve all people
And their information
Help them stay United
Under one flag
These people who are already spreading over the Appalachians Into the Wild West
Tell Ohio in
Founding Father Benjamin Rush especially
We believe that the post office will play a
Crucial role in the new democracy
He was obsessed
With the idea that the post office should
Circulate
Newspapers
To every American
You can have an educated electorate
The people weren't literate and they didn't have up-to-date political information
But this would be no small undertaking
They needed
Roads in the workforce
This government has very little money it was running on fumes
And yet he says we're going to have
This very very ambitious Postal System much more ambitious than anything
In Europe
It's really kind of astounding
In 1792 Congress passed the post office
Under the ACT new postal routes were Savage
Sensorineural stealing mail
Became a punishable offense
In all newspapers can be mailed at the same low rate
Promote the spread of information
It's about the huge explosion of newspapers from all sorts of political view
The post office was the main way
Sometimes the only way
People got information
It was the media
Wait we were news junkies back then the founders ensured that we would have
And an uncensored LiveLeak
Contentious political culture because they wanted the people to be
Be exposed to all kinds of
Views
And argue it out and then vote
We've been arguing and gossiping and spreading information not
All of it true
Since the very beginning
In a way you know you could take the attitude from second a source of created a Frankenstein butt
In fact it was by Design
Around the same time in the late 1700s
Stagecoach was becoming a more popular way to travel
And a better way to carry mail than just
Packing a bull rider on a horse
The post office started to contract with
Private Stagecoach companies to carry mail
And these companies work with cities and towns to build roads
In this way
The post helped
Carve out
The early Transportation infrastructure of the country
Connecting this
Bridge communities
When a group of people settled in a new place
The residents would petition the government for a pokestop
Gave him the address
New place on the map
And then that town would be connected to another town down the road
He started to have this kind of network as it sits
Develop not just our physical landscape
Apus roads but a social landscape
So you could start to talk about this huge country with like some locations
In 1831 when the French diplomat and writer Alexis de tocqueville toward America
He was amazed
Aeropostale
He's riding in a stagecoach through a
Someplace in the Michigan Outback
And he sees people coming out of these kind of crude Huts minnow cabins
Desperate to get them newspapers and able to talk about not just
American politics
Text but what's going on in Europe East flabbergasted
At this point the male in the US was mostly about sending and receiving newspaper
People didn't really send letter
Because they couldn't afford
They kept the rates for letters Hi and they use that Revenue
From letters
To pay for the
Delivery of newspapers to Alma
Most people got like fewer than one letter a year you get a letter saying you know
Has died where you get like Aunt leticia's will
And unlike today with a person sending a letter cover
The cost of postage
Back then
The recipient
Had to pay
You go to the Post Office you'd stand in line see if you had mail
And then pay for it if you want it
It created the Fantastic backlog of
Unclaimed mail because so many people
So many people didn't
Want to
Hey
In the 1840s and 50s the population of the country exploded with new Emma
In all these new people wanted a less
Expensive way to communicate
A movement for cheap posted started to form
This movement wanted people to be able to send letters anywhere in the US for one low price
Using a new toy
The prepaid postage
They argued that the volume
Of the mail would increase
2 degree that would make up for the revenue and they were correct
Because the volume of the mail really went
Gangbusters after
Cheap postage
Postage stamp allowed regular people to send letters
People sent enough letters to fill
Thousands of Ken Burns documentaries
It was the Victorian era and letter-writing became an art form
Even books with advice on how to refine your letter writing style
Address your correspondence by his or her title
Not the first name
Dear husband beloved brother dearest friend on its own
No matter how close you are
Don't address him by his first name
Begin your letter with
I take Pen in Hand
Please pardon the poor paper
Scratchy pain
The ungraceful language
Women especially
David letter-writers
Women's actually started wearing little locket
Cats around their neck
But there
Stamps inside
With more women using the post office the place itself began to change
Post offices historically
Have been off in the back
Tavern
They were men's social
In all there were prostitutes at the post office flying their way or
Pickpapa famously
Pockets when women started sending letters
Post offices added special ladies window so that
Ladies could pick up their letters without coming into contact with these unseemly elements
Slowly post offices transition into more professional spaces
By 1860 there were some 28,000 post offices in the US
People were sending thousands of
And newly invented greeting cards
To each other
But they were also using the post
Just like the founders intended
To disseminate political information
Abolitionist
For example were using the mail to spread ideas about ending slavery
In the 1860s when the Civil War was being fought over some of those very ideas
American post office would bifurcate for a Time
No mail would be sent between North and South
The Civil War brought another big change in America's postal system
Home delivery
Postal employee in in Ohio named Joseph
Briggs
Found it
Heartbreaking during the war because
People
Desperate for news of their soldiers away
We have to stand in long lines at the post office
Often these people would be receiving news of a loved one's death
And they were just scenes of
Terrible terrible grief and in public they didn't even have
Privacy
And he found it so heartbreaking that he
Ran this pilot program of bringing people to mail
Home delivery caught on and by the mid-eighteenth six
Mini cities were off
About 30 years later
People living in rural area
This would also get
And delivery
Do all people in the eastern United States entered a letter-writing boom new settlers in California felt isolate
It was hard to receive mail
On the West Coast
South America go by
Train to Missouri but then it had to be hauled by
Stagecoaches
Through
Really terrible condition
The other option would be to send a letter on a 13000 miles six month trip around the tip of South America
Iboats Californians became work
Powerful bite
The Gold Rush era
The succeeding years
All became outraged by the fact
That they had this lousy Postal Service and they
Demanded to have a reliable Stagecoach mail that would
Depart and arrive unpredictable times they got what they wanted
By 18/57 post office had a Fairly reliable route from east to west
It took 25 days
Which was better than had been
Still not great
A group of businessmen led by a guy named William Russell
Thought they could do better than the US Post
Russell thought his little start-up company could get the mail from St Joseph Missouri
To Sacramento California
In just ten days
In fact he did it
People didn't think he'd be able
What to do it Russell's competing service was called
The Pony Express
Riders on horseback
Good race at full speed for about 10 or 15 miles
The relay station
Where they would trade out for a rested horse
This change was supposed to take only two minutes
Horses were to carry no more than 165 lb
Including the writer
Exhausted horse collapsed on the trail
The writer
What's the run on foot
Tunex location
This bag of mail
It was a very
Expensive endeavor
And it didn't last long
About a year-and-a-half
Which is okay because by 1861
The Transcontinental Telegraph Woodridge California
Unreal server
Would soon follow
Trains would eventually deliver mail all over the US
And I just deliver it
Become moving post
Subsidies from the post office allowed the rail system to occur
Expand throughout the country
Trains couldn't afford to run on passenger Fair alone
The money they got from the post office was crucial in helping them expand survey
Years earlier these postal subsidies had done the same thing for Stagecoach
And after World War 1
The post would do this again
Abbreviation
Plane door not a viable form of transportation until the post office
Cord money
Into the industry
The aviation
Industry wasn't able to pay for itself
But passenger services
Until well into the 90
1840s
The industry survived and expanded by carrying mail for the post off
Insight before Charles Lindbergh made his historic nonstop flight across the Atlantic
He had another job
Charles Lindbergh was a night pilot you know he carried the mail
If the post office truly Creed in America and I think Winifred Gallagher makes a pretty good case that it did
Is now playing a more supporting role
Unless 40 years or so
Congress has cut back considerably on services
And if you've noticed longer lines the post office and delays in receiving your mail
That's why
In my opinion no one should be mad at me
They should be mad at Congress
Congress
Has prevented the post office
From modernizing and
Running itself efficiently and
Tragically going digital which it should have done back in
The 80s
Tell you believe the post office missed an opportunity to
It's what they email and other digital communication
But she argues the US Postal Service
Probably isn't on the brink of death either
Conservative talk about privatizing the whole operation but right now
Gallagher.
What's that this is possum
Actually the private
Competitors neither FedEx or or
UPS's
Is equipped to handle the volume
They would certainly
Risk bankruptcy
I tried
The post office has an unparalleled delivery infrastructure and employees in enormous work for
And we still need the service they provide
Because unlike FedEx and UPS
US Post Office cannot pick and choose where they deliver based on profit
It is obliged
By law provide pick up
Send deliveries to every community in the country
Even if that communities local
In the bottom
Of the Grand Canyon
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle with Delaney Hall Sharif Youssef Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Sam
Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Percocet is our digital director turn Masa takes care of the office and all Sean real compose all the music
Michelle Lafleur
About the post office
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing.
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info / podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and Joints Cushing's about the show on Facebook you can't we didn't meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi or
Run Instagram and Tumblr to do you want to read a story about the British Navy building an unsinkable ship
Weight of ice and wood pulp instead of Steel
Real thing
Do you have to go
99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
A treacherous personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com