99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Cities
Like living things
Evolve slowly over time
Buildings and structures get added and renovated and removed
And in this process
There are bits and pieces I get left behind
Little vestiges
Humans have tailbone
But no tails
Whales have pelvic bones
But no legs
And cities
Have stairs that lead to nowhere
Telephone poles without wiring
And pipes that carry nothing at all
That's producer Avery trufelman
Most of the time
These architectural leftovers rest or crumble or get taken down
But other times
These messages are not removed
And they remain in the urban organism
And sometimes
Even though they no longer serve
Any discernible purpose whatsoever
They are actually maintained
They get cleaned and Polished
And repaired and repainted
Just because they're there
These architectural leftovers first caught the attention of an artist in Japan named a Cossack Elegante
This is a 1972
One day he was on his lunch break with some friends
And as they were walking to lunch they came across this
Staircase
That went up
And then back down
But there is no door at the top
He basically just walked up
And then walk back down
And there was a piece of the railing that have been recently fixed
Something clicked with him when he saw that
Is Matt Fargo
He's translated into English
Himself doesn't speak English
And he's up there in the years and he's not currently doing any interviews but his passion for these City vestiges
Bread to Matt Fargo
Very rare for 1
There's not a lot of
Facets of our life these days that are allowed to be
Completely
Urban leftovers as artistic byproducts of the city
He photographed all the things you can find that were both
Vestigial and maintain
It began publishing his findings in a magazine column
Company by musings about each object
Set for example
This is what a casa Gala wrote about those stairs to nowhere
Everything in our capitalist Society
To have a purpose
So where does that leave this particular staircase could you even call it a staircase
But I would let you keep into a window
Of course you can
You can only call it art
A work of art
Shaped like a staircase
People began to senda casa gala pictures of similar architectural leftovers that they found
And it is call him a casa Gala would evaluate their submissions on two criteria
Were they truly completely useless
+ 2
Had they been recently maintained
In 1985 a casa Gala published a book of these collected photographs and writings
Which Matt Fargo translated into English for the first time in 2009
And of course
Now Matt finds these things everywhere
And they've changed the way he sees his around
Architecture is
Changing it
Being amended
So it is fun to think about how how do we end up
Where we are right now
Instupendo weapon roof of how it
Formed over years
Static immutable thing
The changing nature of the city was especially clear to a casa Gala as a Japanese artist
Japan's rapid reorganization after World War II
Created a lot of these City vestiges
Akasa gawa
Coined a term for these kinds of urban leftovers
Those that are again
Both totally purposeless
And
Regularly maintained
He called them
Thomason
It comes from
Gary Thomasson
Who was a
Baseball player American baseball player
And I really good one
Gary Thompson played for the LA Dodgers the New York Yankees
And the San Francisco Giants
And then he was snatched up by another team
Also called the Giant
The yomiuri Giants
Which is like the Yankees
Japan
They win a lot of title
And also incidentally Otsego is favorite
Baseball team
Look at it in Tokyo
They hired him to come over
And if it is an exorbitant amount of money
But in this new country on this new team the great Slugger Gary Thompson
Lost his stride
You got there and
Could not
Hitler Japanese
Picture for the life of
He actually set the all-time strikeout record
In Japan in 1981
And he remained in this rut
Until his contract ran out the following year
So you basically ended up
Sitting on the bench
And collecting a lot of money
Miss after miss
Gary Thomasson gain the nickname
With human fan
You know for
Swinging about around and only move in the air
And so this kind of
Useless player that was being
Fiscally maintains
What's up
For these objects
Finding aftermath translated a casa gawas original book
Which by the way is entitled hyperart Thomasson
The American Publishers wanted to get a conversation going stateside
They collaborated with a team of artists and photographers to
Define thomason's all around San
Which is where the publisher was based at
It was partly its own project it was partly to promote the buck and the idea
And she and collaborator Alan Manalo took us on their own, some tour can you find them all of his City
Marshall will go down all the time assassin's that Claire and
Allen founded San Francisco their favorite ones
Set political
How to draw bridge
Right in front
AT&T
Home of the world
Champion Center
Allen's of big Giants fan
And outside the stadium on a drawbridge named after former giant Lefty o'doul be on the Plaza named after former
Willie Mays
He found some objects unofficially named after former Giant
Gary Thomasson there's two on one on each side they look like little
Robot
Sentry guards
So picture this
There's a drawbridge
And on either side
Adidas lifting arm Gates
You know like the barriers that lower at railroad crossings to keep a car from moving forward
But next to these modern lifting arm Gates
Are the old model
Or what's left of them
Their arms were
But the bass
Still there
And this
Old useless Bass
Is still maintained
They actually took the trouble to move the damn thing
But they didn't remove it
And they had it painted before
So we we
Cannot figure out why it still here
They like to do the same color as the bridge black
It's kind of industrial black and these thomason's were some of the only indisputable examples that Claire and Allen found
There plenty of things are in the city that are just derelict
It's the maintenance
That makes it
A true Thompson
Clarin Allen drove us to a loading dock by the San Francisco Marina and pointed out a staircase that let you know where
Classic Thomasson upon closer look we weren't so certain I think
I don't think it has been repainted
If you look at the bottom
Topeak Fades into inches
Railings over there they're all
Yeah in Ruston
So that
The four of us huddled around this
Railing and try to figure out if the rest was painted over
Which would mean that it was a Thomason
Or the paint was rusted over
Which would make it not a Thomas
It looks like it's freshly painted but then we're figuring it wasn't in that it
Hasn't been used on
So that's why I didn't look like a
He doesn't have mixer
Haircuts on it
Business course is part of the fun of Thomason
Anyone that does look at broken-down City parts
But it takes
Active examination and attention
To assess if this object
Is
Truly useless
And has been cared for
Is detailed look and debate
Is what a casa Gala was encouraging his writings and publications
I'm so we thought we would imitate that with our website
Clear teamed up with Matt Fargo
The translator
To create a blog where people could offer up their own potential Thomason
For analysis and debate
And I'm so people were actually using it and sending in there at the Thomas and small over
There are submissions
In this commentary as to whether or not they met the definition of a Thomason
And we got a lot of really beautiful pictures that's transmitter Matt Fargo again
And then one day
They got a submission that was definitely not
Thomason
Or maybe it was the truest Thomas end of the mall
One day we got one that was to
Big picture of a middle finger
And it said Thank you for
Making
My family
Forever famous or something like that
News from Gary Thomas
Daughter
That middle finger was a pretty clear sign
The Thomasson family
Is not pleased
If indeed that is actually gay Thomas and his daughter he submitted it
But either way the family declined to comment for this story
Brings us to another debate
Me on whether or not something is a
Thomason
Is it fair to call these things Thomas ends
At all
Gary Thomasson with a remarkable baseball player
Bro long time
And just being a professional baseball player in and of itself is amazing
Hitting a baseball going 90 miles per hour
Is about
The hardest thing to do in professional sports
If you are
Fantastic attic
You'll fail
70% of the time
Combine that with Thompson getting on in years the stress of living abroad
And any number of other things that could have been going on in his life at the time
Totally understandable that he wasn't the Slugger that he was
The San Francisco Giants
He followed baseball
Google
Yusuf
Of Gary Thomas
It was a cuz I got was big fear we know when we told him we want
I don't know about
In a publishing an English because it might be really embarrassing for
The Thomasson family in
Don't want to hurt anything like he's a
Is sweet man
Matt himself was pretty nervous about the Thomas and Family's reaction I can't imagine what he would say
Yeah I was hoping
No Theta
Nothing but love for him in that
Better cuz I got was
Really really nervous about that
But not so nervous takasegawa wouldn't publish the book
And unfortunately
The name Thompson
Works well
Cassie
And maybe it's kind of mean
In fact when I first heard about Thomas Hobbes I thought it was really mean
But then I tried to remember all the baseball players I could from the 1970s
When I came up with
Something like
Board games
And now because of a casa Gala
Gary Thomasson
Has transcended
Even
Pete Rose and Reggie Jackson
Enjoying the immortal ranks
The eponym
Cardigan
Leotard
Guillotine
Sandwich
Silhouette
However hurtful the useless title might be, one could argue
Is ultimately a positive one
Thomason's are delightful
Define
They have inspired artists
Translators performers in urban explorers around the world
Thomas and our Treasures waiting to be discovered
And analyzed
Plus if you need to get a gift for the Urban Design Enthusiast who has everything I'm thinking on Gary Thomas and baseball card
Beef
99% invisible with Bruce this week by Avery truffelman
Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of
The vark sign Reggie Jackson of architecture firms in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastland episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
You can keep up with all the goings-on in neipa on Twitter
Facebook Tumblr Instagram and Spotify view say hi we usually say hi back if you ever need a place to crash
You can always hang out at our place at 99 pmi.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com