99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the spring of 1992
The Baltimore Orioles open their baseball season at a brand-new stadium called Oriole Park at Camden Yards
It's that right along the harbor
In downtown Baltimore
The stadium was small
And it's meant it was built with brick and iron trusses a throwback
The classic ballparks from the early 20th century
Columbus Day it was the future
Masterpass
All the fans
Camden Yards
Camden Yards was really popular right from the store
Here's a TV reporter interviewing a bunch of Orioles fans on opening day
Outstanding outstanding day for baseball outstanding Park and an outstanding year for the oriole
Incredible it's just unbelievable here beautiful
Baseball writers from around the country
Cheap praise
It's on the Orioles new park
That's pretty Sir Edmund Fitzgerald
Tim kurkjian wrote in Sports Illustrated it's magnificent
In an understated baseball only
Real grass open-air Corky cozy comfortable
Cool sort of a way
All the national attention took the team by surprise
We were just out to build a ballpark that worked for Baltimore this
Football Blue Collar city
Hermit crab cakes Natty Boh and boog's BBQ
One of the designers of
Camden Yards
You know we weren't looking
To create
Something that would change the Paradigm of baseball parks
But that's exactly what happened
The success of Camden Yards set off a building boom in base
A city after City built new stadiums based on the architectural principles laid down in Baltimore
That design Revolution change the experience of going to the ballpark and the relationship
Between baseball
Insidious
But to understand what made Camden Yards feel so special
We need a little bit of hist
In the early 1900s Most baseball stadiums were relatively small
And built in dense Urban neighbor
But in the 1950s and 60s
As white populations flood downtown for the suburbs
Baseball Fallout
Teams built stadiums on the edge of cities where they would be more excessive
To middle-class fans who drove to games
In cars
They often were acres and Acres
The parking surrounding
The stadium
And the stadiums themselves were these massive concrete cylinders
Designed house more than one sport
From Pittsburgh to Atlanta to Milwaukee everyone had this big round Hawking concur
Stadium
It generally house both
Baseball and football
But these multi-purpose Stadium
Square concrete Donuts if they were sometimes called
Really weren't great for fans of either
It's a joke what they became multi-purpose list
They were perfectly round to fit both a football field and a baseball diamond
But that meant that the seats were often really far away from the action or
Tangled in weird directions
So it ended up being a shape that accommodated everything but
Serve nothing well
And the multi-purpose stadiums were just way too big
For baseball
The old Urban ballpark
How about 25
430 thousand
But these had 50000 or more
Is that 8 interested in work
You know except for
A playoff game you simply weren't
Selling that many tickets
So the stadiums often felt empty
And critics also complain that they all looked
Exactly the same
They were
Not distinctive enough you didn't know if you were in Three Rivers Stadium or you were in Riverfront
Stadium Bar you were in Veterans Stadium
You really didn't know what city you were in her or could be in
This is Larry luchino
He was the president of the Orioles in the late 80s and early 90s
And during that time the Orioles played in their own concrete
Free donut Memorial
What did 1000 Baltimore's football
The Colts
But in 1984 the Colts abandon the city for Indianapolis
A long agonizing frustrating 2 and 1/2 months of waiting and wondering
The Baltimore Colts would be leaving town for good
It has happened to shock is setting in
Emotions
And the Colts
Cited the inadequacy
Beijing Memorial Stadium as a reason for leaving
So there was a concern that unless something
Creative was done
AAA in Baltimore
For the Orioles
That we might follow the example of the Colts
And I leave town
For real
Greater ballparks if you will
The team's owner
Edward Bennett Williams wanted to build a nice new multi-purpose Stadium
So that the city could try and Court another football
Came back to Baltimore
But Larry luchino had a
He went to Edward Williams
And said to him
Let's look at the most
Successful baseball franchises out there
The Yankees in Yankee Stadium the Cubs said Wrigley Field in your Red Sox in in Fenway Park
And what did they have in common they all played in a baseball only facility of facility that was the
Sign for baseball
And it did not
Compromise architecture late for other sports
Do stadiums actually have another thing in common
They were really old
Some of the last
Holdouts from the pre-war era of urban ballpark base
And unlike the concrete Donuts the ballparks built back then
Had all these architectural quora
Fenway's Green Monster
Wrigley Field iconic brick walls covered in Ivy
They're all a little bit of a different flavor of ice cream
Always thought that something was lost
When baseball moved
From those kinds of
Facilities
Generic multi-purpose
Stadiums in the 60s
7 days
Makena wanted to break out of the multi-purpose paradigm
And build a new kind of baseball only Stadium
One that felt
An old-fashioned traditional baseball park
With modern amenities if we use that phrase once we use the
10000 *
In fact
Luciano became so zealous in his commitment to building a old-fashioned ballpark
Betty band Orioles
Employees from even using the words
Stadium indeed we find people $5 if they use the S word Stadium
Instead of referring to our project as a ballpark
Stadium connotes something very different in terms of
A size in Monument tality did you collect on those fines
Yeah we did collect a little party and I don't remember how much we got but it wasn't insubstantial
The Orioles struck a deal with the Maryland s word authority to build a new baseball only ballpark in
Using mostly public money
City and state government saw it as part of an effort to revitalize downtown
The stadium Authority higher the Architecture Firm hok
And the Orioles brought in their own design director Janet Marie Smith
My assignment was really tough
Take those words that he used over and over again of an old-fashioned ballpark with modern amenities
And try and make certain that we were really being
True that
It wasn't an easy task
I no one else had moved into a center city and said
We want to be a part of that tapestry
Bengali Maybe
70 years
How are we going to create something that feels
Like it's woven into the
The city of Baltimore I like it
It's always belonged
Janet Marie Smith turns the ballparks from the early 1900's for inspiration
What made those older ballpark special
Is it they were kind of wedged into a very
Tight Urban environment
And by wedged
She means that the urban environment actually dictated the shape of the field
Each ballpark had different dimension
Depending on the plot of land on which it
It was built
We can only really happen in baseball
With most sports the dimensions of the playing field
Totally standardized
But not basic
The Roosevelt and feel they've got to be in our you got have 90 feet between the bases 60 feet 6 in
From home plate to the
Pictures ma'am but there's no rule about the out
And so a lot of the early American ballparks were totally a cement
Ebbets Field built
In a Brooklyn neighborhood called pigtown
Had a wildly irregular shape
The left field foul pole was over 50 ft further from home plate
And the right-field foul
That variety means that some ballparks are better for pictures others are better
Cheddar's
Some ballparks give up more home runs to right-handed batters others
Lefty's
So the
The Park at
Self
Really does shape
The outcome of the game
Larry lucchino wanted in a regular playing fee
Feel like those old-time ballpark
But he felt that the shape needed to respond to the built environment around
A site to make sure that just ballpark was integrated into its Sun neighborhood
It didn't feel like I'm flying saucer that descended and just
Landed in the neighborhood
The Inner Harbor site where Camden Yards would be built had one distinct architectural feature
The B&O Warehouse
Extremely long brick building built at the turn of the 20th century
It was abandoned
At the time end
A lot of people thought that the Orioles should just tear it down
To give themselves more room to build on
An opening up of YouTube
The water one sports editor wrote that it was a
An empty rat-infested firetrap
And it should be done away with
But Janet Marie Smith didn't want to do that
We felt strongly that tearing down the very context that might give form
To an asymmetrical playing field and asymmetrical seating Bowl
Was running
Against the grain of what Larry wanted so they left the warehouse
We would eventually sit just beyond right field
And design the shape of the playing field around it
In fact lukino says
The decision to preserve the warehouse really dictated nearly every other design decision that went into Canada
From the shape
The Stan's
Down to the materials that they used in construction
It gave us a set of brick Motif that we use de in the
Ballpark
And it gave us the iconic symbol
All this small park for Baltimore and it looked a lot like Baltimore and felt a lot like Baltimore
If you go to Camden Yards today it's almost hard to tell where the stadium ends and the warehouse begins
Larry luchino and Janet Marie Smith
We're both at Camden Yards on Oak
I could tell you that we were all anxious she no hair standing on her back like what if it's what it is you know what if it doesn't work
We know any number of things that ran counter
To the norm
And
Sports
Stadium design
That could have gone wrong and any number of things that were normal
That could have just gone wrong he know the toilets not flushing I don't know pick anything
But nothing went wrong
Ticket sold out
Toilets
Blush Dress Barn
And the Orioles did their job on the field
Arizona says yes indoors motion Sorrento
Janet and I found each other just as the game ended and embraced each other
Shattuck she said it plays it plays
There was a
Big head line across
Front page of the Baltimore Sun the day after opening day that said it's a hit
East Highwood big 2 and 1/2 inch letters
As if we won the election or something
All that your people kept coming out to the ballpark
Park in drugs
When we opened in 1992
The attendance
Went from something that I like
2 point
2 or 2.3 million
23.6 million
In the second year was 3.7 million in their first two seasons at Camden Yards the Orioles have II
Highest attendance in the major
And pretty soon other teams started to take notice
Owners from Texas and from
Cleveland and Colorado
Came to to visit us rather extensively
Then in 1994 another old-fashioned baseball only ballpark
Call Jacobs Field
Open in downtown Cleveland
And that was just the beginning
It became impossible
Build a new ballpark and not have it look
Like an old ballpark
That's mark lamster
Architecture critic at the Dallas Morning News
Fellow at the Harvard Graduate School of Design
And that what I like
We could joke that
Baseball owners
Square
A bit like
Teenagers
What the first cool when does then all of a sudden everybody else does
So if
One person has a retro ballpark in its successful in the conventional wisdom becomes
In order to be successful you have to have
A retro ballpark
In the 25 years since Camden open there have been 20 new stadiums built
And there's not a concrete donut in the butt
And just like Camden Yards most of these new stadiums have been built close to City centers
And all but one of them
I've been paid
At least in part
With public money
Camden Yards the formula right
This is Neil demause
A journalist to study Stadium
Hear something
Supposedly a win-win
The win for the team because they get the fan
Stadium that they love
And it's a win for the city because they get to revitalize a district
The most Economist agree that if you want to revitalize a neighborhood there are plenty of better ways than building a ballpark
Mama says it when a new stadium gets built you'll see some sports bars pop-up nearby
But most businesses can't rely on baseball crowns as a customer base
81 games a year that means there is
You know 280 days a year when there's nothing going on there
That's an awful lot of
Makeup for
There's also the more fundamental question of whether the Publix
You have to pay
4 privately owned building
Mark lamster says It's Tricky
Sports teams occupy this strange space
They're both businesses
And public amenities
Sports are really important for cities they help
Create
And identity people love them they bring cities together
Southern
There is some justification for a cities
Supporting
Even a privately owned
The Leinster says
Most cities have much more urgent spending needs than a new baseball
Like education
And it's hard to say what level of taxpayer contributions
Is fair
Especially when
It's going
Straight into the pocket
Very very very wealthy individuals
But these difficult questions haven't stopped the Retro ballpark building boom
Across the country
Baseball teams have done everything they can to follow the Camden template
Write down to iron the same architect
Hok sport
Distance spun-off into its own independent firm
Called populist
It's almost a law
At the new ballpark is by populist
And like Camden most of the new popular Stadium
Yams are small baseball
Only ballpark
With comfortable seats
And fancy food out
And aesthetically they're designed to look like the ballparks from the early 1900's
The palette of Camden Yards has become a cliche
Ballpark design
That is
The Brick
The
Green painted iron
The Green Seed
Some
Typography
It is all of a piece
It became widely adopted
All across the country
Each of these new parks had an asymmetrical plane
And like with Baltimore their Dimensions were often determined by the surrounding cities
In San Diego is Petco Park the historic Western Metal Supply Company building dictates the length of the left-field line
Instead of building a fountain
The team just painted a yellow stripe down the corner of the warehouse
AT&T Park in San Francisco is squeezed
Right up against
The San Francisco Bay
The right-field line goes all the way to the water
Getting fans a spectacular View
In creating a unique
Local drama
Splashdown home runs
When someone hit the ball into the bay
A flotilla of kayakers to send on the souvenir
But not all the new retro ballparks were so successfully integrated with the urban landscape
Take Citi Field
New Mets stadium in Queens
It has an asymmetrical shape
But not because it's wedged
Into a tight Urban lot
It's actually set out in the same place that
Predecessor Shea Stadium was
In the middle of a parking lot and it has all these idiosyncratic dimensions
No reason
Before it's an idiosyncrasy is not driven by any
A particular
Constraint
Of the area around
Entirely
Artificial
When you're at sea
Citi Field Mark lamster says you can feel how hard the Architects work
To manufacture a sensor
History inauthenticity
He says that
Everyone in the league has been so focused on building these old-fashioned idiosyncratic ballparks like Camden
That they've actually created a new architectural orthodox
They all have exact
The same DNA they're all designed by
By the same firm they all kind of look the same
Except the whole idea is that each one is idiosyncratic and individual
It sits at the tall tale
Despite is 40
Mark lamster says there's no denying the post Camden ballparks are better places
To watch baseball
Any old concrete
Even Citi Field in New York the stadium lamp Syracuse
Trying a little too hard
It's still way nicer than its predecessor Shea Stadium
Can you describe Shea Stadium I mean
Can I describe Shea Stadium yes I can describe Shea Stadium
Think of a toilet
Put seats in it
That's a stadium
It wasn't a nice place to watch a game no
Is the new place a nice place to watch the game
Absolutely it's a much much nicer place to watch
Watch the game at the really great
To watch a game
And being a nice place to watch a game is
Important for
In recent decades
Sports television ratings have started to slide
But attendance numbers are strong
Kennedy's ballpark
Are part of the reason why cuz they're fun places to go people enjoy sitting there
Watching the game
And for me enjoying the game has always had a bit of nostalgia to it
I don't even follow baseball bat closely
But I'll go eat a hotdog and listen to the organ music
Because
Feels like a fun tradition
More than any other sport
Baseball is about its own path
And plays to its
Nostalgic
History
That obsession with history drove the Retro ballpark Revolution
But as an architecture
Mark lamster is ready for some team out there to embrace the future
Why were we looking back
Nostalgic Lee when we designed
Baseball parks instead of
Looking towards new materials in new ways
The building in Newark
Annie's Camden Yards has taught us anything
It's that when someone does come up with a great new way of building a ballpark
Every team in the league
Is going to want one
Of Their Own
99percentinvisible was pretty so sweet by Emmett Fitzgerald what's a production in mix by Syracuse
And music
Marshawn Rihanna
Katie mingle is a senior police recruit Kolstad is the digital director Intermezzo is moving down south to be my GF
The rest of the team at Delaney Hall every government and me Roman Mars
Jalen Hurd I create a new podcast
What Trump can teach us about con law
Really fun and positive reaction to all the
Crazy political news
I released it on the field last week I hope that you heard it
Liked it
An abusive cry
Is currently the number one podcast in the country
Show me Apple podcast charts of thank you
Amenorrhea
I think you'll like
And other side project news are composer Sean real he's music you're listening to right now
The new album
Call Timothy monster
What songs were recorded at different house shows and in his home studio which
Also where he produces all the music 499 pi
Stay tuned to the end of the show that you're a sample from the new album
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco in produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another room in Brawl hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
We are proud founding member of radiotopia
From PRX
Supported by the Knight Foundation
And listeners
Just like you
And now here's a sample from Shawn Mendes new album empathy monster
Recorded live in a house
Here's the song
Simple machine
It's amazing
Replacing your drug with
Traffic
Me proud when I do
Empathy Monster by Sean real is available at Sean real. Bandcamp.com
Or digital download
You can find the show and when discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we meet at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
We play 156 home games a year
At 9 p.m.
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com