99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1939 an astonishing new machine debuted at the World's Fair in New York City
It was called the voter
Short for voice operating demonstrator
It looks sort of like a futuristic Churchill
That's our own Delaney Hall
An operator
Known as a voter at
Would sit at a curved wooden console
Behind her there was a huge wall with an art deco image of a man's face
The spirals of curly hair
His mouth was a giant speaker
The butter Atwood Place her hands on two keyboards in front of her Peach with
5 or 6 white keys
Should use our feet to work to pedals down below
But instead of musical notes
The machine produced a voice
That would you happen repeat that in a hypothyroid
And now in his best pay
This is from a demo recording of the voter produced in 1939 around the same time as the World's Fair
Each of the keys on the keyboard control the particular frequency band
1 foot pedal controlled pitch and the other foot pedal controlled whether the sound would be muffled or
Operating this machine required incredible precision and skill
Boater hats with train for up to a year to make the voter actually talk like a person
Or
Sing like a pro
About to sing a song for us
Weather
Well how about Auld Lang Syne
Remember this is all happening totally lie
Motorhead is not triggering pre-recorded words
Instead
The keys and pedals of the voter
Imitate the effects of the human vocal tract
Releasing the most basic building blocks of speech
The butter at is playing them in an intricate sequence and she's actually synthesizing speech
Real time
The crowds at the World's Fair went crazy
What is Talking Machine
It created a sensation
This is John Paul
He's an engineer inventor and his story
It was the first time there had ever been
Working speech synthesis
Anywhere's
People had no conception that you could even do it
There's voters imitation of a cow
Was invented by
And Homer Dudley
Area of expertise was Speech science
Dudley worked at Bell Labs a research facility that belong to AT&T
During the 1920s and 30s Bell Labs was doing the research into the human voice
How to synthesize it electronically
How to compress it so it could be sent across at Norman's distances quickly and cheaply
How to encode in disguise
In all this research help AT&T basic goal which was the phone system in the United States
It was a novelty offshoot
Related to This research
Merchant dispute
But it was closely connected to a number of Dudley's inventions at Bell labs
That still shape our world today a lot of f basic research turned out to be things
Which have impacted our modern day
Technology in the world
Enormously
Stuff that became critical to the development of digital media for exam
On top of all of that
Dudley's inventions helped us win a war
December 7th
A date which will live
In infamy
United State
Just a couple years after the voters debut at the World's Fair
Japan launched an early-morning attack on Pearl Harbor in Hawaii
It came as a profound shock to the US
And the next day President Franklin Delano Roosevelt announced the country would be entering World War
With confidence
Armed Forces
Determination
People
We will game
Being knowledgeable
So help us God
World War II would be the most widespread war in history
The US would be fighting in Europe and the Pacific and parts of North Africa
All at the same time
And it was a huge challenge to coordinate troops across that much territory
It was obvious the only communication possible would be by radio
And that radio
Was of course insecure
The enemy is listening
In other words there wasn't really anything besides radio that can stretch across the distances involved
The radio is easily intercepted
Answer
The
Problem of encryption
And secret messages
Of military importance became more and more
Serious
At the very start of the war US military still relied on an old-school piece of
Technology
Fritz sensitive Converse
Crustaceans
We called the 83 scrambler
It works by scrambling voice frequency
Swapping high frequencies for low
And low frequencies for high
Garbling the sound
Here's an example of what it might have sounded like
But it was easy to decode these scrambled conversations
Has been compromised news not secure
That's Dave Thompson
Choose research the history of various
Synthesizers and their connections to music
German intelligence
They're essentially
Descrambling
Sony's conversation is between FDR and Churchill in real time
And the US military the German code-breakers were listening in
VR US government
Cave Bell Labs the mission
Of creating an Unbreakable
Speech encrypter
And Bell Labs went to our old friend Homer Dudley
The guy who invented the Talking Machine of the World's Fair
Dudley
Need you to figure this out
Really fast
They were under
Tremendous wartime pressure to produce this thing quickly I think the whole design took about a year
Thankfully Dudley had already been working on
Technology-related
This problem for years
It all went back to the voter
And to another related invention of Dudley's
Is called the Vogue
Music nerds might know that turned vocoder because it's the great-grandfather of the machine you here in all kinds of pop music today
Vocoder with short for voice in
And the Machine could break down a human voice
Separated into its basic components and then compress and transmit those components via short
You could transmit the minimum amount
Signals required
To reconstruct that message at the other end
This process was important
Revolutionary actually because it allowed the human voice to be digitized and compressed
Send across big distances
But the vocoder didn't fully disguise the boys
The transmission could still technically be pulled out of the air and decoded
To Dudley and his team had to add a layer of unbreakable encryption
And that's how the bolt cutter became just one small part
How much larger and more intricate apparatus
Military leaders in
Strategic locations around the world
The talk in total Secret
It was called Project X aka the greenhorn
AKA
Sig Sauer
Which was short for
Nothing really
It was meant to be
Confusing
Which Sig Sauer machine was enormous
Way more than 50
Tetons
Pretty complicated Behemoth of a device device it was a room and itself
It occupied about 2000 square feet
It was made up of 40 racks
Needed
Air conditioning
Because a lot of the electronics was so delicately
Balanced
That if it got too hot or too cold it would not work properly
Infected device was full of so many finely calibrated tubes and gadgets
Vision of Engineers whose sole job was to maintain the machines
The 800 V
Signal Service Company
We're pretty much in charge of the installation and operation of a system
For he listed he was an amateur radio operator from Omaha
And he was one of the engineers assigned to work on Sig Sally
Reporting for Duty in Washington DC and spent his first two weeks
In an intensive class
Where we learned all this
The technical details
And the operation has pretty much on the job training
The first Sig Sally terminal was installed in the basement of the Pentagon
And it was connected to several conference rooms upstairs
Elegantly furnished
Apus wine-colored
Thick carpeting on the floor
They were beautiful rooms
This is Lieutenant Colonel Dorothy almada
But my nickname is Meg
Meg
I was in charge of the global encrypted Conference Center
The conference center is where dc-based military leaders would meet to
To speak over the sea
McSally cyst
So while I was down in the basement running the machine
Maggie's upstairs
Coordinating conference calls with the military brass
Cheetos did everyone from President Harry Truman to General George Marshall
She sat in on their meetings
And transcribe the converse
Any of the men who had the responsibility for the conduct of the war and had to make their
Phone calls came to my conference center
How to do it
Communications is the most important thing
You have to do it
With Safety and Security that
You know nobody else is
To dinner
The Sig Sally terminal in the Pentagon was connected to a network of close to a dozen other sigsaly terminals around the
These were located in the most strategically important places where politicians and military leaders would need to be talked
Working with each other on a regular basis
Algiers of London and Paris eventually in
Hawaii and Guam and Australia
In a row being shipped
In the Pacific
Beautiful strategically-important
Oakland California
This network allowed leaders in Washington DC to talk securely with any location that had a terminal
All they needed was a shortwave radio connect
And one other key component
Pair of photograph records
Of totally random noise
This is where the encryption Park
Because for every conference that happened over 6 dali
Both the sending and receiving terminals
Had to have identical record
Which played the sound of noise
The noise would combine with the boys components as they were transmitted via shortwave radio making it impossible
Dropper to decrypt
On the receiving end the random noise will be extracted in the voice restored
In cryptography these records are what's known as a one-time key
So here's how they work
Random noise would be generated
And then pressed on a gold master
Normally a phonograph record you would reproduce
Thousands of them
From a single master in this case they made exactly to record
Be identical and now totally unique records would be assigned a matching code name
Annies code names were awesome
Like red strawberry
Wild dog
Circus clown
So what's a President Harry Truman in Washington DC wants to talk with prime minister Winston Churchill in London
Truman keeps one of the two records in Washington DC
The second one
Would be sent
To the station at the other side of the ocean
And then placed on this special Precision turntable that was a part of the
Fisichelli terminal
At the scheduled time for the conference sigsaly engineers in DC and London would tune in to WWE
12 minutes
Which is the
International time control station
So that we can synchronize our control clocks
Exactly
Then they get their identical records
Spending on their respective turntables
At exactly the same moment
Once the records were synced
Truman would speak into a handset in Meigs conference room at the Pentagon
This is the president
Mr. prime minister
This is a reenactment of Truman and Churchill greeting each other
When they talked to be at 6 Sally to discuss a German surrender Pro
Proposal in 19
The signal would go down into the basement or Don was running the Sig Sally terminal
The terminal with digitized Raymond voice mix it with random noise from the record
And then transmit that signal across the ocean via shortwave radio
On the other end the 6th alley terminal in London would reverse the process
It would remove the noise
Reconstruct the boys
Beat it through Churchill pants
After so much processing and such a long distance
The boys didn't sound very good
Like gibberish
Orated from the bottom of a
Barrel
But it wasn't Elitch
You had a kind of train your ear abish
Anyway
Then Churchill would reply
And the whole process
In this way Truman and Churchill could have a completely secure real-time Converse
Crustacean
Planning plotting
Strategizing
When the conversation ended
The two records
Remember
Are contained the top-secret random noise
Key
Would be
That's because if anyone was recording this communication as it traveled over the ocean the random noise record would be the key
Key to the Kryptonite
It would allow them to subtract the noise in the same way that 6 lb Engineers did at each end of the transmission
So the records were the most classified and sensitive component of success Ali
By the end of world war
2 there had been a total of about 3
Thousand
Top secret strategic conferences
In other words at least 6000 vinyl record
That were pressed
Delivered
Used and then destroyed at the end of the
DeBary today or if they run a memory type technology but
By that time it was
Even thought of
Voice Communications in terms of being digitized
And because of my voice
So if
People were listening in
To that signal if Germans were listening in
What would they hear
Nothing but random noise just
Total white noise
I mean it might have been so unintelligible that they didn't even realize they were listening to anything at all
Never
New of the existence of the system
And they never had any inkling
That it was an encrypted
Speech
Exactly that's why I said Sally was nicknamed The Green Hornet after the popular 1940's radio show
Because an intercepted Sig Sally transmission sounded like nothing more than a hornet's but
Sig Sauer was involved in pretty much every major military operation after 1942
It was even critical in the planning of the Manhattan Project in the dropping of the atomic bombs over Japan
Scripting and listen in on those six conversations
Even though he didn't know at the time the meaning of the code words they were using
And I'm assuming that she is coming over in the Titleist Manhattan Project
But I question know what the Manhattan Project was
John didn't reflect mod
John the grave implications of those meetings he overheard
He was an engineer
Doing his best
Keep the equipment running
You didn't pay that much attention to everything that was said you're more concerned with the transmission
But he knows it would have been hard for the Allies to win the war without Sig Sally
It's hard to say what we would do if we didn't have it
Even if that Victory sometimes came at a brutal price
At the end of the war the six Sally terminals were dumped in the ocean
Almost
Every encryption device
Was intentionally destroyed when the war was over
Security purposes to the extent of destroying
The plan
But not before the military develop successors that were smaller and simpler and easier to set up
These new devices still work in the same principles of encryption as Sig Sally
And there were used for secure Communications during the Cold War the Korean War
Negotiate the Cuban Missile Crisis
A lot of the information related to Sig Sally wasn't the classified until the mid 1970
When AT&T sue the US military under the freedom of
Information
Once it was public
Technology that originated with Sig Sally
When on two entirely new realm
The vocoder for instance went on to have a whole new life in music
In the 1970s electronic musicians like Kraftwerk began using a smaller version of the machine to cry
Create weird robotic vocal effects
From Germany the vocoder spread to the Bronx
In Brooklyn
Where hip hop and Electro Funk group started playing around with
Now you hear it all over the
But the vocoders reach actually goes Way Beyond
The robot voice
You're also using vocoder every time
You use your mobile phone
But of course in a much much reduce size
The giant clunky machine of the past
Now occupies the space of a tiny chip
Impressive speech and allowed hundreds of conversations to pass through a single cell phone tower
And a lot of the technology used to transmit media on the internet
Can be traced back to Dudley to
That includes MP3 music
That includes video compression give thanks to Homer Dudley every time you watch something on the
The internet
All those millions of viral videos would take up too much space
Can you decompress
Jollibee
Double rainbow all the way across
Everything
In our modern Digital World of media
Can they trace back
To Dudley's vocoder
Andis Excel
In the end
It started its public Life as a silly novelty gag
Making animal noises for crowns at the 1939 World's Fair
And here's a pig
And Meg Mattson
The vocoder enlisted
It did it survey
Tell the Allies win the biggest war the world had ever known
And now
It's back to civilian life
Making silly noises
Once again
99% invisible with producer Suite by Delaney Hall with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman Kurt Kolstad
Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
Special thanks this week to Dave Tompkins author of how to wreck a nice Beach
Vocoder from World War II to hip-hop
His book inspired this episode and gets into the history of how the vocoder jumps from the military
Into popular music to been any vets in Knack of nucleus David Kahn author of The codebreakers anstey
Stephen Jackson and finally thanks to Pat Metheny Miller who played the voice of President Harry Truman
Winston Churchill was played by our new staffer
Man of a thousand voices
Profusa
We are project on 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
The East Bay's Premier architecture and Interiors firm
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
Cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Message Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
MPI fade
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Hawaii and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find the show and like a show on Facebook follow us all on Twitter and Instagram
But the best way to explore the 99% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
Is to become good friends with our website it's 99 pi
. org
You have less vocoder
Okay I'll ask
Halo Kotor
Sounds great
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com