99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% in the
I'm Roman Mars
So just velcros onto the base
The fan
And then we're just turning on the unit
You see them on street corners at gas station
At shopping malls
You see them at blowout sales and grand openings of all kinds
Their wacky faces hover over us
And then fall down to meet us
And then rise up again
Their bodies
Slop they flail
They are men
Men made of
Tubes
Full of air
Producer Sam Greenspan is full of more than hot air
You know they say
A vinyl column perched on top of a fan
Skinny little arms and
Big dumb grin
Blowing around goofily on street corner near you
People familiar with it but when they're driving by it's just that
You have to look and turn your head
You know for is
The best
Return on your advertising.
If I some stretch of the imagination you have never seen one of these things in person
You have probably seen them around the internet
On TV
I love him
They are either full of ridiculous joyful exuberance
Or the tackiest thing in the world depending on your taste
A number of cities across the US have actually banned the use of tube guys
An ordinance in Houston and acted in 2008 / claims that the dancing tube guy quote
Contributes to Urban visual clutter and blight and adversely affects the aesthetic environment
And quote
Don't you go ahead and try to imagine An Origin story for these
Used car salesman bison Park in a leaf blower and messes around in his garage
Slide bounce house designer goes Rogue determined
No no no no
The real story behind these it's so much
And I'll start
Pizza Man Show
Born
Take me to my mother
True Georgetown Guyana
Where I was born in the General Hospital in the embrace
Trinidad Trocadero
Peter Mitchell ladies and gentlemen renowned Caribbean artist who could easily have a second career narrating nature
Batteries for PBS
This is the word indigenous
Trinidad which is where I'm talking to you
From now in Trinidad and Tobago a moss man is someone who works in the carnival Arts
Peter Mitchell made a name for himself in park
By making these larger-than-life puppets that dance to the street to the beat of a steel drum band
His work was featured in a book called Caribbean Festival Arts
Which wound up in front of someone on
Steering committee for the Olympics
We just how in 1995 Peter Mitchell found himself in a stadium in Los Angeles working with a bunch of different
Trying to figure out ideas for the opening ceremonies at the Atlanta game
The following year
As mental health
He was trying to do something using inflatable tube
But it wasn't working out
Episode
Sitting in the bleachers
Vero Beach
YouTube side by side
Somewhere
How to behave
I just got
Colombian flag
Join them at the waist
Don't want you
Porcelain divided
You might
Dancing
Boom the dancing to guy is born
Mental realized these figures made from a tube hooked on an air source
Good dance just like the people did back home in Trinidad and Tobago
I'm so it might to another person seem like a great leap
I'll be imagination to me it was like jumping into water like a little.
Peter Mitchell knew how to make giant figures
They always been powered by people not air
And so well Peter Mitchell was in that moment able to Glimpse upon the possibility of
Giant undulating inflatable dancing tube guys for sure
And so well Peter Mitchell was in that moment able to Glimpse upon the possibility of these tall boys
He knew he needed help
They got the call from the Olympic Games from a Peter mincha
And he asked me if I came to create the human shape
And then
So difficult that can be done
This is Tyrone Gazette
Another artist
Who like Peter Mitchell I got known in the Olympics planning
He done some work in the 84 games
News in Los Angeles
If there's one guy who knows about making things full of air
It's him the wrong because he first got interested in inflatables
When he was a college student visiting the US
Casitas
Israel
He saw someone making balloon figures on the street and got obsessed
Was doing that himself
Isolde balloon animals
Streets in Jerusalem
And this day he still carries balloons around with him in his pockets
And I like to say that we don't use the B word
All about inflatables
Petit founded a company called air dimensional design
Objects in sculpture
And so after he got the
Call azita his team headed over to meet Mitchell
And see if they could make the
Cowboys reality
Which actually turned out to be a pretty big engineering challenge
I had to find the right two strong powerful motor that will be able to give me enough safe am in the right
You get the idea engineering physics
And eventually
These tall boys came to life
And it looks very much like the two guys we
BC today
With two major exception
Once they were bipedal their legs divided at the base each with its own fan and to these things were a norm
They were 30 years
If you hyperventilate
And that was the first the world that ever seen these inflatable men the 1996 Olympics in Atlanta Cayman Way
And so at this point in the story The Two Guys the tall boys
Are out in the world
But how did it go from a thing we saw at the Olympics once
Basically as an art piece
How do they go from that to a thing you see it like every used car lot in America
Here is where the Mitchell camp and The Gazette can't begin to diverge
Apetamin pills account
A few months after he returned home from Atlanta
He got a call from one of his collaborators at the Olympics
He recalls him saying
Hello
In La who made those
Because I think
But he's making them
Later on mental caught wind that the wrong disease had gotten a patent on the
The tallboy the dancing vertical inflatable
Cuz it says that he wanted a patent because he put a lot of research and development into making the tube guys work
And it was already starting to see other people rip off his effort
The Chinese company just took my designs and toes
Pictures that they could they just imitate it in the copycat
Tyrone Gazette
Was awarded a patent for
Apparatus and method for providing in
Inflated undulating figures
10 mm
Azitra first of them as Fly Guy
Peter Mitchell & Dawn visit both
The breed of a dancing
Inflatable figures
Instrumentals
And they both agree that cuz he turned that idea into a reality
Where they disagree
Is whether or not it was
Cool forgas
Cheat to get a patent on
Without informing
Division
He was asking for you
It didn't exist before that and then
And I very very very very much respected put them in Chinese in an amazing how to write to an artist and
Doing good for the work at night was it
In order for me to work with you
Cuz he says his attorney told him that in the eyes of the law menchel would not begin
Ininventor
And took his seat was surprised to learn that
Dementia 11 angry with them
He says that since then he's reached out to mention the number of Thai
But never her
Peter Mitchell says it it never occurred to him to seek a patent on the two guys
I don't
Pace
I'm a naughty boy from Trinidad I don't know what the law is
My instinct tells me
The time before he could do any such thing
It is his duty
Teacher Consulting
Is heat meanwhile continues to make money off of the tall boys
Fly Guys
Whatever
He licenses his
Patents other companies
Like look our way
Which sells Inflatables here in San Francisco
That's what you heard from earlier
This is like our ways Nick Sonic
Yes or the technology weed license from them has to do with
The way the air escapes the inflatable
Airscape
From threat top of the head
Is well
Which one of the farm
So that you know after testing that is what gives
It's Dynamic motion
Kind of the special sauce and why it's so effective
Look our way has their own name for these things
Air dancers
And even though they may be licensing pre-existing technology
They also invented a whole new use for them
It came to them by way of a farmer in Eastern Washington State named Gary long
Little setup
Scary keep apple orchards on his property and he started having a really severe bird problem
Starling
Eating tons of adapt
Like literally
10 tons a year
When season 2 of 20000 at a 40000 lb of honeycrisp apples
Affidavit
Pecked out by birds
And rendered unsellable
And so Gary long was looking for ideas
I was talking to a person that was selling his products that he grew on this Ranch
And so he wanted to attract
People that come to each one of these
Are dancers out there
Wiggles and Giggles and they all they hoping that people would see that the dancer and come over to it
Well it didn't bring any people and other
But the thing that you know this was
Hubbardston bother him they weren't coming into a Fruit Stand and pecking on the fruit
Gary bought a few air dancers from look our way hoping to keep the birds out
The result is the dancer started dancing they took top
And went to the neighbor
Enchilada
This looks like it's got possibilities
With the air dancers in place Gary was able to get the bird damage down from 20,000 lb to
Ready for this
They got bird damage down to zero
Zero damage
Gary long called up Nick cassavetes from look our way and made some suggestions for how to turn the air dancer into a bona fide
Hide scarecrow
They added bits of reflective material to the Head
Give me some Angry Eyes
Scary teeth
And transform the thing from an air dancer
To an air ranger
The air ranger section of the look our way website reads
Dynamic unrepeatable dancing motion
Keeps birds away Time After Time
I meant to the are Rangers that Peter Mitchell
It was the first time he'd ever heard
Next time I open up a packet of corn flakes
I'll smile
Yes or no bitterness on Mitchell's Park
Even though he's not making any money off of
Actually he loves
Two guys around
Can you imagine
How I feel when I'm driving down I don't drive actually when
My friend is driving me down from a house
Who are we
A factory building place in chaguaramas
And I see a sort of
Diminutive version of a tall boy dancing up a storm by a gas station
Look at where we reach
And I'm certainly aware that the dancing couple gas stations all over the
Apartment meet can't help but feel
Delight
Nutella
Look at what you and your Island have given to the world
I don't know how much money do around is eat is making off of
What is too bad
But whatever it is you can't really say he didn't earn it
Sure
Maybe it was Peter Mitchell's idea but because he'd actually made this thing
And as you really wanted me to point out
He's done a lot of other work with inflatable since then
But I also love knowing about Peter Mitchell
Cannabis things are kind of like shopping plaza ambassador
From the streets of his Caribbean island
Because that is how we dance
Limpid
Andaluz
Stop the music
Ramzan
Street
Solace
And with that in mind
Inflatable figures
The two guys that tallboys the Fly Guys the air dancers the air Rangers
I discovered a whole new join them
They probably won't convince me to buy a new car
I will Delight in seeing them try
And when I look upon them
I will know to listen to the distant whisper
Of a Calypso band
99% invisible
Was Prince this week by Sam Greenspan with reporting from Sam Dean who wrote about the two guys previously
The online magazine reform
Edited by our friend Sarah rich
The usual crew of Katie mingle a breach of human and me Roman Mars we helped out
Special thanks to Todd kulick
NBA standing
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced
Are the offices of arcsin
And architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world of man-made
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
Family goes
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled into weed
Who discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God.
You can find the show and hang out with other people who like to show on Facebook
All of the 99 Pi producers are on Twitter and you will find us and you can follow us
But you're always welcome at our place
99pi.org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com