99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When the Statue of Liberty was dedicated in 1886
It was a dull copper color
Statue is covered with a layer of
A copper metal about the thickness of two pennies
But after about 1900 the physical processes that govern the known universe began to take their toll
And the copper skin oxidized into a greenish patina
They can be seen on the Statue to this day
When the statue underwent a massive Restoration in the 1980s
Be Head and Shoulder where we line
The point on the crown that have been digging into her arm for a century was shortened
The defects in the internal skeleton were thoroughly addressed
And of course
The weather beaten exterior was cleaned
But there was no notion that the statues skin should be returned to the dull copper color
She was born when
But if they had signed up Lady Liberty to her original copper color
The people of New York City
Probably would have reacted
Like this
I don't like looking at
This is not someone from New York as you can probably guess that's Barbara Clark five generations of her family have lived in store
Stirling Scotland
Manning spotrac Clark
And I've lived in Sterling on my life
Apart from when I was at University
Sterling is also the home of Stirling Castle
Truly marvelous place they just love to visit that sits atop a giant
Craig
Or Hill
Overlooking the whole town of Sterling
Some Council has been there since the 12th century and maybe before but the current buildings date from the 15th and 16th century
Well obviously it's part of our Lives to see every single day in his children with Khalid in it
Banana
When we think of medieval castles we usually picture a grand structure
Subdued dark
Stone Mason
But when you gaze upon Starling Castle today
The down below
You will notice that one of the buildings is different
From the others
Since 1999
Dromon restoration effort
The Great Hall of Stirling Castle
Has been
Bright
Yellow
Best bright yellow building
You know was sticking out like a sore thumb
And people would just
Horrified after I can remember just thinking
This is a nightmare
The story of how the Great Hall of Stirling Castle came to be painted bright yellow illustrates the unexpected comes
Lexi in the art of restoration
It comes down to this question
When you choose to restore something
Which moment and time are you restoring it
Some kind of nameless group of people
Reach that decision
Hyundai
Don't question the motives
My question that understanding us if
Ficked
That it was going to have
On
People's feelings towards
Mikasa
Who made that decision
Oh I know
It was a guy
My name is Peter becoming my work with the Snorks compliments my title noise project manager
I joined the start skeleton 1991 tour, starting up a project
Historic Scotland is the government organization charged with educating the public and safeguarding Scotland's historic Treasures
They took over the care of Stirling castle and started the Great Hall Restoration in 1991
First let's get some Castle facts
The castle of people have this fairytale Disneyland thing in their hands were it's all one huge building with
Most medieval castles were a collection of buildings for certain things
They have a chapel that a palace
They would have had kitchen the Great Hall is one of those key buildings in a castle
And quote Bill Bryson his book at home
No room has fallen further in history than the hall
Now a place to wipe feet and hang hats
Once it was the most important room in the house
It is a huge Gathering space the one here at Sterling was also for the parliament of Scotland
So the King was stopped here they would set Lowe's they would have Banquets and Feasts
David entertain lavishly Peter Buchanan adopted the Great Hall of Sterling
It was in an awful state
Stirling Council up until 1964 was a military Garrison
From 1800 to 1964 the castle was owned by the war office
And they did not treat the castle as a historic artifact to be preserved
Most of the buildings within the council were used by them
The great hole was used Park accommodation turning one big fancy room into Barracks meditating
Lord Altrincham Windows replacing the ceiling really changing everyday
What's a military left the place was got it
And when Peters team took over in 1991 the building with a shell
It still happened to reform it
But it was left with a huge question mark after what we should do with it
The typical Mandate of historic Scotland is to preserve historic places in the state they were found
The Great Hall of Stirling Castle required some drastic measures
So what state do you restore to
Do preference the military. From the 1800s or the medieval and Renaissance
Strategically the castle had been important for hundreds of years at rule
History of Scotland
Husband St toxins
Excluding earliest times the first recorded King
Castle Hill Overlook sebagh on one side and the bridge over the Fourth River on the other
2 / hundreds of years it was the place that control trade for the whole region
Mary Queen of Scots
It was seen
The cultural significance of these things art Wade
The significance of the military.
Using this logic they decided to restore the Great Hall to estate it was about three to four hundred years in the past
But that kind of restoration is not
Simple
First of all the records aren't all that consistent
Have a series of etchings
What's great hole
Before seems like a whole show slightly different sayings
Traditional you have read the Beast heraldic beasts on the top
Grateful is our big stone statues of unicorns and lions that sit on the apex of the roof
Laurentian's show these but they show different numbers of them
The edge
Can I give a customer to look like a tool for restoration
They weren't much use to help figure out where the recipes should be placed on top of the building they had to figure out
The original structure of the roof
Sometime in the 20th century the roof had been completely replaced by the military
Original Hall had this glorious
Hammerbeam roof
Is a medieval technique
That uses
Wood beams as a network of cantilevers and trusses on the inside to make the roof strong
Wide open room
You can see all the timber when you look up from inside the hall lights
Stunning
It's a jigsaw puzzle of beautiful
Triangles that are amazing to behold
Pringles
Because the ridge Beast Wade 3/4 of a ton they can only be placed where the hammer beam roof was the strongest
This is as true now as it was 300 years ago
We got, being rich constructing makeup know how everything works left we want to get it released but we need Clues to be over
They found one diagram of a cross-section of the hammer beam roof of the Great Hall from 17-19 but
Since it's the only record it's hard to know if it's completely accurate
Since there was no other information about what the roof look like they began researching the surveyors from 1790 New Jersey
The diagram and they found that other diagrams they drew of other castles were very accurate
So here's our leap of faith this is where
You start
How to use conjecture in your restoration
To make value judgments
And we've decided that we will put the whole of the structure back
So this is what we're basing it on
So using that one historic document they reconstructed the roof which determine where the heavy Stone Ridge Beast would be
Placed on top
One Discovery begets another and another and the original building comes into Focus
And that's the detective work of restoration careful research Discovery verification sometimes conjecture
Leaps of faith
It's this beautiful amalgam of history science and art
The hammer beam roof was completed in 1999 and everyone who sees it including the Sterling Folk
Singer Gray
It looks really great
So far
New controversy
But as We Know
The roof was not the only thing to change
So the controversy is coming
The building was almost completely gray stone that was none of the original
But in one corner just under the Best Buy
There had been a little lean to shelter
Built in front of the door
I want me to get my refund the complete panel
Of the original lime wash
Limewash is pure lime calcium oxide. The green citrus fruit
It also contains earth-based pigments
It's a coding that's meant to protect the stone masonry
Navigate to Sterling they found a significant yellow ochre layer of limewash
The bright yellow was very intentional hundreds of years ago that built world is basically Brown
There was this great
Yellow piece of ostentatious bling that signaled for miles
That this was a place
Burger King
And we did huge some puddles all the time which is around the building
To show people what open mics have look like avocados might have been
And we brought a lot of people from the starting area to see this as well
Guess what we were intending to do
Based on the analysis and information had
Was to put the finishes by
And that is exactly what they did which is why the Great Hall
Is yellow
Did not exactly go over well with the people of Sterling
Strangely in restoration terms
It's the one element that we had the most evidence for
They actually had physical pieces of exterior limewash all over the castle
The hammer beam roof on the other hand
Was based much more on conjecture
It's not working right
When Peters team was putting on the yellow finish the Great Hall was completely covered in Scaffolding in plastic
This may have contributed to the intensity of the reaction from the locals once it was unveiled.
Sterling resident Barbara Clark again
The entire hole was shorter than tarpaulin
18 years
Nuvoton usually what was going on when you the Battle of stonemasons up there
But nobody knew anything about anything else
So when the Great unveiling came
It was a total
Surprise
It just
Loot
So awful
And to this day I don't like
Pet
When I asked you to be Cannon what he would have done differently if you had to do it all over again he says
He would do all the same Restorations but he would have been more aggressive about Outreach we could have tried harder
Wii setup
Couple weekend Stone in the center of starling
To explain what we were doing
Lots of groups around to see the samples before we went any further but really getting that message out at 3
To the media and getting people to understand that is very very difficult
Tell me when it is a change on the scale
I think that possibly
A bigger marketing campaign
Should have come up there this was 15 years ago before Twitter and Facebook made it easier to reach people certainly wood
Experience from the great hollow as to how I think we should be getting messages
If people really understand what you're doing and raylee
Buy internet from day one
Then I think it makes it alot easier
All Restorations are unique
I don't think the Statue of Liberty should have been returned to Copper when it was restored
As a landmark
People fell in love with it and it gained its significance when it was Green
It made sense to keep it that way
But I found being in the bright yellow Great Hall at Stirling Castle
Really exciting
I'm sympathetic to the fact that the color was shocking to the residents who grew up with it looking completely different
But it's brightness brought it to life for me
It made me reinterpret my faded and ultimately wrong image of the past
It's nearly all the Greek and Roman sculptures that we know and love were painted bright vibrant colors
Even though most of us
Can only imagine them as white marble
When I see color reconstructions of ancient statues
I think they look
Ridiculous
But I can't help but feel that I know the Greeks and Romans a little bit better after seeing what they thought look good
I feel the same about the Renaissance artist who designed the color schemes inside and outside Stirling Castle
They were mixing colors that ready not much
They were using them in extraordinary ways they were having great fun and showing an awful lot of wealth and power in the Press
But this is probably the first and last such restoration for historic Scotland
New scanning and 3D rendering technology means that you can quote on quote
Store a place and teach people would it look like
At any point in history
Inside the virtual world of a computer exhibit
Without doing anything drastic to the actual physical structure at all
Approach
We can do extraordinary things nicer technologies that we couldn't have done 15 years ago
It's a really really easy way to educate people to show them up things might have been like
With White Fang too heavy-handed to the monument remain as Unique Restoration
Miss North Dakota's history
Which totally makes sense
But every once in awhile
It's nice to be bold and daring like our ancestors were
A slap on that bright coat of paint
And see just how Vivid
The world
Are my friends
Helen and Martin work on the great podcast answer me this together which is one of my absolute favorites in phone
Tons of awards it's incredibly popular in the UK
And when we started radiotopia
I talked with Helen about the idea of her doing
A new show specifically for us on whatever she wanted
Helen is a language and etymology fanatic and she pitched us The Illusionist which I'm going to describe as
99percentinvisible forwards
Mainly so everyone who listens this show will understand that if you love 99percentinvisible
You'll love
The Illusionist
You can find out more and subscribe at The Illusionist. Org Illusionist within a butt
As a little summertime treat I thought I'd just play through the latest episode of The Illusionist
Welcome to The Illusionist
Helen zaltzman
45 Magic linguista
Beans
Coming up in the shower
Word games
To prepare yourself which has a game Word
Game as in the genre of meat
Is so-called because it was obtained through the game or sport of hunting
This is 3 Lux in venison
Which evolved from the Latin verb venari meaning
Tangerine mystery the old French venison
Wichmann the meat of a large game animal usually dead or wild boar
Clues to why the animal is called a dick until the point at which is being eaten or appointed
The same with parents like
Pound beef and Pick-n-Pull finnsheep muffin
The words for the creatures in the living state to the Anglo-Saxon ones where is the meat was originated from French
Of the Norman invasion of Britain in Tennessee
Chrissy was speaking French
Once you for the food we eat the meat
Korean writing
Say that you got me towards
On with the show
Brown's children
Grandma's go to story about how we have to make our own fun
A long boring Journeys
We had like
Or indeed any equipment to do a build vocabulary because who hasn't had to wall the way I was talking to call rauf
On the bus or train
Playing word games
That's fun
I spy why your listing boring things
All The Minister's cat
Listing adjectives
The number plate game where you have to name things
Start with the same letters as you
C on the number pi
The call you've been stuck behind in the Trap
John Parappa
Replacing words in songs with rude words
All the old family favorite
Guess how many words you can say before the drive in Shelton
Just shut up
Do you have to sit in silence
The two hours
Bonus points if you go beyond 4
His money issue with these games
None of them actually much fun to play
Except for the replacing words in a song with regrets game
Which stupid again
But really most of these well games
That was fun as filling in the spreadsheet
CityVille fill the function of obliterating adult consignment
It's about everyone having to think of conversation
Put the prize in winning the game
So you don't have
How to play the game
Also what is the real name of the place
Only average day you'll be deploying
Will taking in many thousands
How do you take these things
Pictures
What are the elements
Top Notch wood gay
Leslie Scott
Barry vicious-looking founder of Oxford game
Has created more than 40 games
A lot of which a word
Such as anagrams where you can put on a ground
Speed
The children's literature game bookworm
I'm bluffing games flummoxed inspiration and ex libris
But she's probably best nine
So no more game
The build a Paris tower out of wooden bricks game
Jenga
A game
Otherwise it will be cold enough
A different occupation
Let There be Rock
Company
Make Cooperative game
In a funny way changes the most cooperative
Game that I know
But it still has an alibi
Somebody leaves
Lucky winner
If you don't have that element to it
It's another another game in my opinion
We need to bring out people's the malevolence
Becoming the worst person in the room
Safford of Leslie's games
Simple flask
Text you have to write a definition for word from a foreign language
End in ex libris
The first or last
Sign of a famous book
Anthony case convinced the other players but you was is the real one
Peter Brady have
Play the games
You just have to be a good liar which is found in an etymological
Because fun
Original
Explore trip
And of the verb to make a fool of someone
About to go people is
Fun fun 2
For a little while anyway
Because another crucial factor for a good game according to Leslie
Is speed
I love Scrabble
Until about halfway through the game
And then it just slows down
The point where
You're waiting and waiting for people to
7 tiles around
I just got
Scrabble
But it's a variation of a game
70 people that love
Scrabble
Is that supposed no pressure
Me before you
Anagram
I would have said my favorite when I gave you folks
Which is
Rickie Fowler
3 minutes
That's another thing
If you'll stoking the competitive spirit
You don't need the adjustment
Suburban nuclear indicator Victor
Google operates on a pretty straightforward points
System predicated on the quantity of words
But it's supposed to be scoring on the words qualities
All the more complex to
How many people
Realize it actually
Scrabble
The ultimate word game is based on the fact that it was designed by as fast as
Pick it up
The skorys
Word game where you
The score
Is some basement he was such
Absolutely incredible
The numbers of times a particular letter is used
I think it's called with the New York Times
Spaghetti
Counting how many times any comes up how many times
Does Ed comes up with something say
Suzhou numbers
In the sky
Start with
With FaceTime on this and then and then the actual story
Black dancer play of the game
Sorry scrap
But again where you can try them
Just by memorizing every two letter word
Never have my affair
I don't want Leslie to think I'm coasting a special
Words of free
Play with the car games like I spy in number plate
How does she get people to pay to play games like
Flummoxed or ex libris which you could play
Using
But you already have a new show
Make sure you
Make yourself a chest
If you want to tell you
I think it's just empty that you open the box and
And you sit down with your group of friends you don't have to run around trying to find
Books suitable
The shop to be sitting on your bookshelf
And some accident need 212 dictionary exactly
Go to copy of
EX libris
You get on with it
More important
The plot summary
That we've written
Kathy written
Then don't just the back of
The submissive style
What's the cheapest the back of the book
Sometimes two
To lead you down the wrong path it often said that the
I didn't know the names the same message doesn't come up as a complete surprise that you're incorporating their names into you
Festa last night
Back to court long time
And because Lexie is also
Because you can play the festival.
Offline
It does.
Suits of limit volume books
Not all of them have
Brilliant plus unlocked
Abusable
Still paying for the duration
Execration
When you've invented your game you need to name it
Something that indicates what's involved
Anagram of tales
The story Anne Hathaway fun
Hasn't already been nabbed by someone else
As he is going on this guy's got more and more difficult to
Come up with a name
For a game that has already been
What is a game on the show me the whole process of naming
China products
The part of the process that I quite like
People tried talking to science
I'm not sure what
But there is something
It was like they Viagra
But something
TT.
Expensive
Vitality
Musa flag
Army games
It is tricky cuz if you do want something snack to eat
Like Jenga
Swahili
It means bill it's imperative
How's the weather
Contenders to build
I gave it to Swahili name because I grew up in East
African speaking
I thought if I did the name that
Had no meaning
To anybody who
Swahili
There was a there was a chance one day
If you said the word Jenga
People just think of
The game the time
I just put on the market
Desaki
Swahili word for Bell
Quite a short word
Easy for people
Speak Swahili
You think it would be easy to pronounce
I have had people telling me
A category
The game score
Myself
Switchmate
Has took it home in the states
They said they lost
The game but they absolutely hated the name
I'm so we had a little bit of
Read with all my stuff
I just said to you
Do you think this is going to be difficult enough to sell
Nobody's ever come across anything like this
I'm going to have a name that meaning
Names
Give you some idea of how the game is
Play the game
Stocker block
Will you stop to a gun
I did
What a great name
Typical
Easy enough
Turo rental
But all the
Rip off tank
Allowed to be cool Jenga
If you come up with the name but is
To descript
70 demonstrate
There was another side to 2
You come
Cool
Any ol
Stackable blocks
Spenga
And has baby definitely down on you like a ton of bricks do you selling
Michael Thomas
Leslie Scott
Is the founder of Oxford game
Which you can find at
Switch games.
I'll be playing ex-libris with some friends
Will probably be losing a
Clippers to my friend
Adobe phone number
Separate Ways
Randomly selected words
Today is
Imagineer
Noun
A person who devises a highly imaginative concept or technology
Especially the attractions in Walt Disney theme parks
Try using it in an email
App Store
Asking when they started doing product
This episode
Amy Holland
Thanks Emoji no strikes at providing music and editorial
If you have invented any word games I would love you to tell me about them
It's been so interesting to hear your responses to the last episode about step family time
Some of you come up with some very good suggestions I think for attentive Tennessee step
Bonus like the Danes in the sweetie
Forney parents
Someone came up with meta
Metamora
Pretty cool
Anyway keep in touch
@twitter in Facebook
Smocked Illusionist
And The Illusionist.
That's your little taste of The Illusionist. Go subscribe for yourself and every two weeks new life will be better
That's 99percentinvisible for this week we are Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are brothers 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin and architecture and interior
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic
Trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake
Human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting to special episode
Words from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Thanks to MailChimp the Knight foundation and people just like you we created radiotopia from PRX
Home to The Illusionist and many other fine podcast
Get to know them all at radiotopia. FM in a few of a company or project and you want to underwrite us
Which is a good idea I had to work Monday
Email sponsor at radiotopia. FM
You can find this show and like a show on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but right now
Now you can see pictures of a bright yellow capsule
Really bright yellow castle at 9 p.m.
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com