99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Hey there beautiful nerds
Last week A bunch of us from radiotopia We're on our West Coast tour and it was a blast
The allusionist Helen zaltzman and I hosted the show
Which feature stories from Criminal The Memory Palace mortified The Illusionist westwingweekly and 99% invisible
For the 99 Pi locks
That's the way we went back
Back to my favorite writer and musical collaborators gone welham
This information to bring players but
You know them as members
Of The Decemberists
And black prairie
Performing this story in front of a live audience was a privilege
Unlike anything else I've ever done
And I couldn't wait to share it
I hope you'll
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It was the middle of the night
On March 27th 1964
Earlier that evening the second biggest earthquake ever measured at the time
And scene 9.2 had mangled Anchorage Alaska
115 people dying
Houses turned literally upside down or skidded into the sea there was no light
Power in the city
And for a long time
Virtually no communication with the outside world
But there was radio
It was a station in Anchorage running on backup generator is in a Crock transmitter
What station in Fairbanks picked up that signal and repeated it
And a man in Juno somehow picked up at Fairbank station called a radio station in Seattle and let the
Broadcast play over the phone
Bill Noble would like to get a message if they're all right
Like that a voice from Anchorage touch the lower 48
Assignment city was still there and soon the degraded signal broadcast in Seattle
Relaid and relate again until eventually people across America then
Around the world I heard the same woman's voice
Mary sweet is asked to contact your mother
Mother is at home
The president of that Anchorage radio station happened to be on a Goodwill tour of Japan
And when he turned on a radio in Tokyo
He couldn't believe in it was the voice of his own news girl back home
The woman's name was Jeannie chance
John Wang and the brink of players
Have her story
1964 Anchorage was the fastest growing city in America
The generation earlier it had been a Frontier Town Without a single concrete building
It was mostly military buildup in oil speculation
The city felt like a bubble that
Pot Alaska is only been a state for 5 years and is 1 minute
The feeling that everything is temporary we weren't all going to leave but you know
We might
Insecurities made every new construction feel monumental
He was real like the brand new JC Penney building downtown
This is one of the first Big Chain retailers to build in Alaska
It was huge
Nothing said
Sophisticated civilization
Rising out of the wilderness
Like a five story department store full of lingerie and blender
Beginnings of genuine culture
Volunteer Symphony conducted by on Moonlighting bulldozer Opera
The Anchorage Little Theater
A community troop run by a Cosmopolitan guy in a turtleneck
Anne Frank Brink
Bring found rules for everyone in his plays Housewives
Judges Air Force officers
Any work does actors Hardy just ages own 3 hour Epic
Of Alaskan history called Cry Of The Wild Ram
I know it sounds a little bit like waiting for guffman
They were good
Meanwhile covering all this life in the city or two daily newspapers
Local radio stations
One of them Ken I prided itself on being
State of the Union
And one of Katie and eyes biggest on-air personalities
Was a woman named Genie
Jenny was 37 she's grown-up for in Bonham Texas then come to Alaska with her husband if
A few years earlier looking for opportunity
The only sort of found it the first
He sold used cars and she watch their three kids at home but Genie loved radio
So she started working construction every morning in exchange for childcare
Then go to work all afternoon at one of the local radio stations
Back then
Women were usually made to cover cooking or fashion but it came and I Genie turn yourself into a
Reporter driving all over Alaska with a mobile broadcasting unit in her car she fluid smokejumper
Covered Arctic Warfare exercises
Reported from Inuit villages in Crab boats
Her voice was part of the city people trusted are respected her in Anchorage I don't know way women journalists were in Ohio
Who is respected in 1964
Later a New York papers celebrated rise
Alaskan housewife and mother of three children who does a man-sized job with a radio microphone
Late in the afternoon of March 27th
Jenny was driving her thirteen-year-old son to a bookstore downtown
Wizkid Friday and lots of people would already gone home from work for the Easter weekend a banner across Sports
The Avenue advertise that weekend's opening it Frank bring
Theater
They were doing the Thornton Wilder play
Our town
Curtain was going to go up at 8
But
At 5:36
Cheese first thought when your car start
Started bucking at the red light was that she must have blown a tire
But then through the windshield she saw people knocked down in the street
She saw a line of parked cars at the gas station slam together and separate and slam again
Do you watch them fold in and out and thought
Like a grotesque accordion
Later one man would say it felt like the Earth was whipping the city around like a dog shaking an animal he's killed
Building listed off their foundations issues ground waves move through the asphalt
The roads were liquid
The JC Penney building a school kids stuck in the elevator watch the book
Suddenly levitate off the elevator floor and hang weightless in midair in front of them
Split-second was like he was in orbit and that's when he knew the elevator was falling
Quick went on like this for almost five full minutes
Ben
Stop
Peninsula did
Genie
Direct car in gear
She was a reporter after all and still not realizing how severe the situation was she raised to the police station to get
Quick story believing broadcast
Inside all the filing cabinets were thrown over
Ceiling plaster sheets on the floor
Then a second juul hit
We got off came running around the corner shouting
An enormous concrete panel at shorn away from the JCPenney's exterior in Fallen now the entire
Building with sagging and running over can you watch the second panel lerch loose
Drop with a roar the scene was brutal
Geez the brown part of a body in the snow
The person split into by the falling debris
Chevy station wagon was flattened but you could hear a woman still alive inside calling to the crowd
Route
Then
Genie rounded a corner
Saw the whole impossible panorama
1 in tire size
4th Avenue
Just
Dropped
42 block
Everything was 12 or 15 ft lower
Intervene that it opened Thunder Hat
Street
The crazy part was buildings were still intact down there
Cars were still perfect
C park
Are there meters
Men looked up from outside of bar it doesn't feet underground like
Stunned minors
I'm still hanging there
Over the street
Like a cruel caption over the cereal record
What's the theater Banner that read
Our town
The Quake did not genius radio station off the air but now the static on the transistor radio she was
Suddenly gave way to music
An engineer started talking engineer at the radio unit in her car and cut in
She was surprised later when people told her she's
It sounded calm
It has become obvious that the earthquake that struck Anchorage less than an hour ago is a major one
We are to each and everyone of you to seek shelter check your emergency supplies
As much as possible so that you can retain the Heat
Check your neighbors
See if they have Transit
If they don't possibly they could move in with you and share one for the
It seems like it's going to be
A Long Cold Night For A
So prepare to batten down the hatches
And stay tuned to kemi
Think of what it means when we say
A person feel shaken
In Anchorage
This wasn't a metaphor
Those city of been thrown
It only been about an hour between the
The quake and Nightfall
With the power out
Snow falling through thick fog in the dark
There's no way for everyone to tell just how badly their world had been jumping
The feeling of vulnerability
Total dislocation
It's hard to describe
One guy put it
You don't know if anyone else is alive
Maybe you were the last man
Who is comforting to hear another voice
Start talking to you
Especially Genie chances
After making that first announcement on the air Genie drove back to the
The police station
Authorities realize that
With the radio unit in her car
She was the only voice they are able to address the entire C
I told her to keep talking
Senegal are broadcasting from inside the building and rounded phone calls to her as the lines reopened
Who's up to Genie to decide what information to relay to the public
The first it was mostly just her
1K United employee remembers that the newscaster has been on the air when the Quake struck
Hot Shot they just hired away from a big station in Los Angeles
I've been so wigged out that II is shaking stop
Get walked out of the building without a word he resurfaced a couple weeks later calling from back
California
Officially quit
Gene was shaking to the week later she's breakdown out of nowhere and weep all night but now
I kept trying to forget the unforgettable scenes eyewitness thousands of terrified people were huddled in there
Unheated shelter
Construction
So she started doing your job talking to people on the radio
Before long the rest of her colleagues and other stations in town we're back working the airwaves to the
So often felt like Genie was the one at the center of things
Directing things the turbine site needs diesel fuel should say or here's where I
Electricians report
Men
She started reading the personal messages
Pouring into
Mr. and mrs. Dick Fisher are still here at Police Headquarters waiting for any word of their children
Read a message from Northwest Airlines saying that the
Stewardess Beverly Jones
So many people were desperate to locate or reassure each other
Howard Forbes would like it to be known that he will be as Mike Whitmore
Shout across the fractured City
Kenneth Sadler mrs. Sadler is fine a message to Walter Hartley heart is fine
Meanwhile ham radio operators were relaying those messages to families in the lower 48
And when reporters around the country finally got through to Anchorage
It was often Jeannie still sitting in front of a radio microphone who took their call
No she assured them the city wasn't swallowed in flames
I know it wasn't under martial law
She talked to Omaha
New York
London one interview she did was rebroadcast in more than a hundred other places
The same day
Friday night if you come Saturday morning by then
On Saturday afternoon
Saturday night
For the first 30 hours
I talked constantly after 2 hours sleep
She was right back on the air
It's probably worth stopping for a second
Say this out loud
Earthquakes
But I mean
In an existential way to
It must have been
Watching reality suddenly Buckle around you
Watching your city oven
Infallible right angles
End
Who is enough to change a person's worldview
More than 50 years later a former mayor of Anchorage
Even though I can look at this Solid Ground out the window and know that it's not permanent
You can change any time
It just moves
Everything
Understand
In 1964
Plate tectonics was still just a theory
It's hard for people to accept that the continents we stand on
We're actually in motion
They were just sliding around randomly
Violently colliding
Rock
Nothing is stable
But everything runs
Pure chance
That's what the stories about really
Champs
Maybe that's obvious
Steven the woman's last name
But
The question is
How are we supposed to live
On the surface of such unbearable random
What can we grab hold of
Fixed
I want to hear the old recordings of Jeannie on the radio that weekend
All the other voices working too
A picture of them as saw it up
Like wires
Crossing
City of Anchorage
State of Alaska
Further out
Crossing each other to like a net
Kind of alternate
Schumann
Snapping into place
For the built environment
Gateway
Episcopal Church
Time right now to evaluate
This one I'm very happy for not
Okay
Northern Hotel
Your family has been contacted and everything is okay
Headquarters
I really hadn't stopped to think how worried and concerned my parents must be I understand that
Kfar in Fairbanks is monitoring us and is relaying messages to the South 48th
I wonder if the person in Kfar would take down a message from me and get the word to my family
Right and Bonham
Second chance
Family is all right
The chance family is all right
Received
We have another message here to
Late on Saturday
The day after
Jeanne read a list of the missing and dead on the air
No one told her to do it
But there didn't seem to be anyone to ask for
Permission either
The next day was Easter Sunday
Ministers talked about death and Resurrection
The staff of the Anchorage Daily Times picked up all the pieces of movable type
Thrown all over there printing room
Managed to put on a noose
Do JCPenney Executives declared we will build again
Bigger and better than before
Eventually the Little Theatre resumed its production of our town too
What are the actors told me that after the Quake whenever a restaurant in Anchorage reopened or a church held a mass
There was never an empty seat she said
Everyone wanted to be with someone else
I never something especially poetic
About the sold-out crowd at the theater that first night
Because that kind of togetherness is basically what Thornton Wilder's play is about
Play about daily life in a small town
The deaths and marriages
Tragedies
Spurts
And how I wonder all that
Flux their stability
Every community over time
In Anchorage
A city that worried it was temporary
Realized
It was temporary
At least all its buildings and houses in Rhodes
But it was discovering there was something permanent about itself to
All night at the theater the character of the stage manager talks to the audience directly narrating the story of the play
Kind of like I've been doing tonight
Now when the curtain rose on the Final Act
He came out for his monologue
Now there are some things we all know
But we don't take him out
And look at them very often we all know that something is eternal
And it ain't houses and it ain't names
Earth and it ain't even Stars everybody knows in their bones
Is that something is eternal
And that something has to do with human beings
All the greatest people ever lived been telling us that for 5000 years
And yet
You'd be surprised how people are always losing hold of it
Me and Jeannie chance stayed on duty
Kni for 59 hours
That weekend
When things finally calm down
She sat down to write a letter to a parent
They'd written to her right after the Quake pleading with Jeannie to send her three kids to live with them
Well that battered City up in Alaska
Figured out what's next
Think of the kids safety
Depart of Jeannie thought it was a good idea
She had another more convinced
We must be together
As long as we're together
We are confident of the
She explained to her.
That Good Friday night
I knew we had survived miraculously
And for this reason there must be a purpose to our lives
Apparently the children must sense this to
Remain calm
Steven fully aware of the emergency but if not
We are proud that they are such Dependable responsible young
I would not undermine their confidence in the future
In themselves by sending them away for their safety
What is DC anyway
How can you predict where or when tragedy will occur
You can only learn to live with it and make the best of it when it happens
These children are not afraid
Their father and I are not afraid
Please don't you fear for us
What is safety anyway
Virginia seemed to be conceding that there is only randomness
Only chance
And if everything Beyond this is chance
Maybe the only Force we have to survive a world like that
Disconnection
By then
It must have seemed so obvious to her
Take me to each other
Thank you
John Willem to bring players Jenny, trees OS on a quarter
Antoni queer eye on base John Bowen on drums Chris Funk on guitar
And John neufeld also on guitar and that is Miss Avery trufelman as chimmy Chan
Thank you
99percentinvisible was recorded at the Moore Theater in Seattle on the radio Topia live West Coast
We were lucky enough to be joined in the audience by several members of Jeannie chances family
Came from Alaska and Texas
Which is why I nearly crying at the end of the store
Who directed by Lynn Finkel post-production mix by Sean Real and True future
Words by John William and music
Weather Brinkley
Fitzgerald in Taryn Mazza this music right here is by Sean Rihanna
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room
All hearing
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You've been so enjoy discussion about the show on Facebook you treated me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi org
Instagram Tumblr and have a nice
Subreddit to
Would you want to read about dangerous skyscrapers and gorillas wayfinding in the New York City subway system
Those are really good popular stories
Visit our website
At 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about
The body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Master your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
Actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com