99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The United States leads the Olympics in medal Awards and is just about Supreme in
On October 16th
American sprinters Tommie Smith and John Carlos climbed onto the podium at the Mexico City Olympics
To accept their medals today
They came in first and third in the
200m Dash
Smith had one goal
Carlos
Edwin Braun
As the national anthem begin to play the men
Both African American
Bowed their heads
And raised their fists
In the black power salute
Best producer Claremont
They kept their fists raised until the last note of the anthem faded away
The gesture was a statement of black pride and defiance
It still considered one of the most overtly political statements made in the history of the modern Olympic Games
But that wasn't the only politically significant moment at the Olympics that year
Mexican hard learning enriqueta basilio became the first woman to ever light the Olympic cauldron
Gymnast beat out Soviet gymnast for the overall women's title
Does two months after the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia
It was also the first time a Latin American city or even a Spanish speaking country that hosted the game
It was a big deal to have hundreds of thousands of international Travelers come visit next
The Mexican Government saw the Olympics as an announcement to the world
Mexico City had arrived
As a major International Metropolis
So almost everything about the 1968 Olympics
Felt revolutionary
Including the design of it
The images and logos associated with the 1968 Olympics
Ubiquitous
They were plastered all over the city
Is complete design campaign will become one of the most famous in Olympic history
And it would set a whole new standard for games to come
But these government commission designs would also be co-opted by local activists
Who wanted to reveal the darker political reality in Mexico
That was hidden behind the beautiful glossy imagery
Of the 1968 games
In the decades leading up to the 1968 Olympics
Mexico has gone through. Of major economic growth
It became known as the Mexican
Toomics an air-cooled typically units historian conventionally speak about it as a. Standing from the
Mid-1940s to the late 1960s
The country had rapidly industrialized rapidly urbanized and its capital Mexico City
I have grown into this enormous
Sprawling Metropolis
Citigroup
Faster than it ever had in Mexico's modern history
That's Luis Castaneda
He's the author of spectacular men
Mexico design propaganda and the 1968 Olympics
Because of its size and layout
Mexico City was a challenging place to host a major International Event like the Olympics
Mexico City with sprawling
Spreading
Still at the height
It's a miracle
I mean even until the Olympics are literally about to happen there all these doubts about whether
The Mexican Government will be organized enough to undertake the whole
Spectacle of that magnitude
The Olympic organizers needed to show The Parent Trap
Safe navigable cohesive
Exciting
They wanted to create a visual identity for the Olympics
Do wheelies L Mexico City to all these visitors seeing it for the first time
So they decided to hold an international competition
Define a designer who would create a logo and graphic design campaign for the Olympics
They wanted something that looks Cosmopolitan and contemporary
Distinctly Mexican
And this is where an unlikely character comes in
I'm Lance Wyman I'm a designer I work here in New York
In 1966
Lance Wyman was a 29 year old graphic designer
We heard about the competition
He knew that he and his design partner Peter Murdock
Had to get on the short list
Chicken tenders
This list included design teams from all over the world who would come down to Mexico City for a two-week trial run
After their two weeks
Each team represent their design for consideration
And we got on the list to go down in November of 1966 and
Peter and I had just started out we didn't have any money so
Willie could only afford one way tickets
They hopped on the plane with their one way ticket
And landed
In Mexico City
By the way neither of them had ever visited Mexico before
They didn't really know
Anything about the country
If they were going to design a logo
To represent Mexico
Wyman and Murdoch would have to learn a lot
And fast
They started where most tourist
By visiting museums
It's been a lot of time at the Museum of anthropology
Where they studied artifacts from pre-columbian Mexico
Like the Aztec sun stone
An ancient Mayan murals
I actually was
Floored by some of the early cultures because they were doing things in the Contemporary way with Jama tree with graphics
The Bold lines and bright colors and geometric shapes reminded Wyman of a kind of Opera
Art that was popular among contemporary artist back in New York
Op art or optical art
Uses contrast geometry and other tricks to give the viewer the impression of movement
And so informed by both indigenous artifacts
And modern
Wyman came up with a logo that Rift on the 5 rings of the Olympic symbol
I realize that the geometry
Of the Five Rings
To be integrated with the
The year of the event 68
He superimpose the digits
6 + 8
Over the classic Olympic rings
The circles on the Rings rated out on the circles in the digits
And it created a hypnotic
Stripe effect
It's from that I develop the
Typography to make the word Mexico
It's this very groovy looking typography
Made of three parallel stripes
Wyman created a logo that he considered both very modern
Anne Curtis
Essentially Mexican
The end of the two weeks came and we started making prints of the next bus 68
Logotype
And people from
Publications people from
The public relations they wanted copies of it
You ain't working like crazy making copies and doing all of that
And then one realize that no one actually told him that if he had the job
So we asked one of the organizer
Did we win the easy cuz like I guess so
Woman who created this stunning logo in Taipei for the competition but choosing this white guy who would never been to Mexico
Before it was a bit problematic
It's not that unusual for people not born in Mecca
Bicycle for artists and people in the culture and the Arts to be involved with these kinds of state-sponsored campaigns
Set entirely unprecedented but it's still a very unique situation
Especially given the fact that
You know this is a this is a very very significant project
That's author Lewis ksenia.
What is very
Striking almost shocking perhaps
Is that
The fact that of course Lance Wyman is is very much unproven as a designer is very young and he hasn't had much time to
Did you much yet
And yet somehow he is given this
Very
High degree of responsibility as part of the design camp
Wyman and Murdoch ended up staying in Mexico
For two years to work on the campaign
And along with a team of designers many of the mechs
Mexican they came up with ways to use their typeface logo and other designs
All over the sea
Hypnotic Stripes were turned it described uniform
As for the events workers and volunteers
The patterns and colors used in the logo ended up on hats
Postage stamps balloons
All sorts of
What's the hype theme wedding games
And these these objects range from very small objects all kinds of memorabilia
You know things from ashtrays and
Furniture r
Apparel all the way to the stadiums
Stadiums across the city were painted with these
Radiating op art pattern
Bright colors decorated sidewalks
Walzem Plaza
Chinese bright hypnotic designs and just give the Olympic Games of visual coherent
The graphic design language of the Olympics
Expanded into an entire system
That helps visitors navigate
The mass of neutron
To do this
Wyman Made Simple color-coded icons
Represent every sporting a
They were
Not stick figures but they were they were focused more on no part of the body or piece of the equipment or combination of the two
Gymnastics for example was represented by a hand gripping a single suspended ring
Track and field head its icon boxing head its icon
So on the ticket you knew what your ticket was
Or
Play the icon only
If you're visiting from Japan didn't speak any Spanish you'd see
Save the soccer icon on a green background
And you follow the green signs of the stadium where the soccer was
In the system wasn't just for sport
Wyman the team made universally understandable icons for 19 cultural events
Happening around the city as well
We had children's painting we had folk dancing we had science programming
By following these cultural icons visitors could continue to entertain themselves
Explore the city after the sporting events were over
The 1968 Olympics have been decreed Los juegos De La Paz
The games of peace
So Wyman designed a little outline of a dove which shop owners all over the city were given to stick in their windows
Between the logo the typeface the colors the icons and the doves
Wyman created a visual identity that saturated the whole city
It was everywhere
It was a total design campaign
Holes I can pay right this design that every single
Thing Idea Place object
Associated with the Olympics is immediately and Powerful recognizable part of a whole
In the completeness of the campaign would set a precedent for years to come
I think it's safe to say that
Although
Design and architecture and
The Arts in general have been
Very powerful associated with
Olympics
Before Mexico 68
It's really after Mexico succeed it becomes a kind of
Standard expectation
Design campaigns associated with
Well Lance Wyman was designing the
This extensive campaign
He was holed up
Swamped with work
And he really didn't get a chance to go out
Nose to the grindstone really almost through the whole thing
We're pretty isolated at the Olympic Committee
He didn't see the protest movement growing in the city around him
The movie was led by students who believe the long-ruling institutional revolutionary party
Cater to wealthy next
Rather than the poor Rural and working-class
Country have been experiencing
Huge economic growth
The millions of people have been left behind
The Mexican miracle
Hadn't reached every
The government was talking of the Mexican miracle
Even though
In the reality of those days
Things were note that says
Happy
Are they appear
These are excerpts from interviews with students involved in the protest against Mexico's single-party government
Courtesy of our friends everyday.
In 260 Sweetwater Steilacoom
The government control everything
President Swift
Equivalent
Monarchs
I mean
It was forbidden to demonstrate
You could not go on
Express jewelry
Descendants
And for the students
Protesting the government mint protesting against the Olympics themselves
The so-called
Games
Olympics are attic Baby By Design By definition always about propaganda on some level or another and so
What the Olympics start to present as a
Kind of a happy picture of social harmony and as a n
Very sanitized idea of how modernisation happens
Was of course not
The reality of what many of these inhabitants of the city experience
Tens of thousands of protesters took to the streets
Repeatedly throughout 19
Wework Urban middle-class
No middle class
Bunch of drunk people
It was
Miss Molly weigh
The Clash
Clovis New Mexico
Answer
Alone mix
You have the middle class
Eyes closed
Group of students
Saying
These was not a democracy
This is not working
Again and again please have come out and violently dispersed protesters with clouds of tear gas
As the Olympics near
And as International attention turned towards Mexico City
The government was desperate
To make the unrest go away
On October 2nd just 10 days before the games of Peace were set to begin
Thousands of students gathered at the local Square in the northeast of Mexico City
To demand the release of people who have been locked up at a previous protest
It was a quiet Gathering of people with signs walking slowly around the Plaza
And with look back and there was all this
Infantry troops
They started to Advanced what's a crowd
And at some point
We heard
Sub shops
We didn't know where they came from
And seconds later
How do you say in English
All hell broke loose
Soldiers opened fire on the protesters
To this day we don't know exactly how many students died in the massacre
But the number is likely in the hundred
Strickland
The scene was cleared before there can be an accurate body count
The blood was washed away
Thousands of protesters were arrested and locked up
The government took great pains to cover their tracks
The amount of student War
Shot and many others were in prison
I forgot some time with you no cover.
The government claimed that the students had fired first
To provoke the military
Evidence has since come to light
That disproves I claim
A shocking event
For a long time, sir Preston in Mexican national memory and in many ways it is the the Crocs of the cry
That's that
Set the stage
For the Nevada day Dramatics
For the Olympics themselves
The massacre was so horribly devastating
But of course
Lance Wyman heard about it
When I heard about it
What how severe it was
It was difficult situation because I felt as working for the government and
I couldn't do anything about it
But he says he really empathize
With the student
I wasn't much older than they were so late I had that feeling the car
Might have felt good if I just walked away from the whole thing
Wyman felt Stuck in the Middle
But in a way
He didn't need to choose between the governments in the protesters
Is designs found a way to serve both sides
Students began imitating Wyman's images and co-opting them
It took a poster he made with a silhouetted image of Runners racing and turned it into silhouettes of troops
Beating people with baton
Do you say signature typography to create ant
A government post
And that very simple image of a dove and all the shop windows
Students went around the city spring a small burst
A bright red paint over the doves chest
Like I've been shot
They were playing with the propaganda of the Olympics
And hinting at a darker political reality
And Wyman
He like that
Email design campaign so ubiquitous
So resonant
Better resistance
Could use it to
And I've always been questionable where you feel good about that
And I guess that's why because I was in a situation where I was
Kind of
Torn
I was very sympathetic
As far as what was happening to the students
But I was also very
Not wanting
To see the Olympics be stopped
And they weren't stop
On October 12th
The games began on schedule
As if nothing out of the ordinary had happened
Mil novecientos setenta y Ocho
De-cluttering
Los juegos olimpicos de Mexico
The 1968 Olympics Winona become one of the most important in history of the games
Marked not only by athletic achievement
But Buy open political defiance
You think you're represented all black athletes and doing this
I can say
I represented
Black America
I'm very proud to be
A black man
And also to have won the gold medal
Mexico 68
Also set a new precedent for how governments would use design
To promote their country's image to the International Community
For Better or For Worse
The 68 games also left a permanent mark on Mexico City's infrastructure
Mexico City is one of the largest cities in the world
If the largest metropolitan area in North America
Around 4.4 million people ride on Mexico City's Metro System everyday
Including producer Claire Mullen
Who visited a couple months ago
I'm in the Metro on the pink line
At Cuauhtemoc
Which
Has an eagle
Icon
Mexico City's Metro is incredibly crowded and very extensive
And yet it is often recognized as one of the easiest rail systems to navigate
Partly because of its iconography
La catolica which is a big ship it looks like a pirate ship without the pirate symbol
And then we have Merced where there are
Those icons are there thanks in part
Lance Wyman
The Metro was supposed to make its debut during the Olympics
Excavators kept unearthing ancient architecture in the path the tracks
And the opening was delayed
But women was still involved in its design
Specifically it's a map
He employed the same visual system he developed the Olympics to help International visitors navigate the trains
In the Olympics we relied on the graphics
And I thought well why Kansas City do that
The Wyman color-coded each line and created a unique icon for every single stop
So even if you're visiting from Japan and can't read any Spanish at all
You can say to yourself
I want to take the pink line to the stop of the grasshopper on
The station at stopped at the chapultepec
Park
Chapultepec means grasshopper Hill
In the nahuatl the Aztec language should I use the grasshopper
Again
Some Mexicans took issue with his young Foreigner coming in to design something that would be such a huge part of their City
But eventually Mexican designers took up the project and made it their own
UI design the first three lines of the Metro
Are all the they have 12 lines
Now and they were designed by Mexican designers and some of these are better than I did in the original lion you know
After the Olympics
After the Metro
Wyman did some more work from EX
Like the design for the 1970 World Cup
But he went back to the US
Why did went on to design more map
Big ones
Like for the National Zoo in the DC Metro System
Although none of them use symbols and icons and colors as completely as in Mexico City
The clear iconography of the Metro system is a reminder of a complicated and sometimes terrible. In Mexico
Cities history
It's a simple design and invites you to explore the massive and complex metrop
It's a design that is true
If you get lost
No matter where you're from
What language you speak
You can find your way around
And see the city
For your self
99percentinvisible was produced by Claire Mullen and Avery trufelman technical production and mix by Sharif Youssef
With music by Shawn real and okay akumi
Our senior producer is Katie mingle Coal City is the digital director
Bristol Staffing
Turn Masa
And me Roman Mars
Thanks for the team at Radio Diaries Who provided us with some of the tape from their documentary a movement a massacre in Mexico
Does 50-year search for the truth
Tell the story of the student protests in 1968 and uncovers a secret on the government's bloody Crackdown
You can hear that story on the radio Diaries podcast right now are you Diaries is one of the OG radiotopia probe
Definitely be subscribing
If you aren't already
We are brothers on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Even the show endurance questions about the show on Facebook you can't we do me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit too but we have all the old episodes and a bunch of design stories that you can only
Read with your eyes
On our website is that 99 pi
Gardevoir
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com