99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the Bay area where I live for a couple of decades now
I watch the front line of gentrification move further and further east
This show is based in Oakland As you probably know
In Oakland quite big and heterogeneous so you can definitely talk about it as one thing
The last couple years rents have been going up
In the fear is that rents will continue to go up to a point where only wealthy Tech workers can afford it
This phenomenon is not unique to the Bay
East New York a residential neighborhood on the Eastern edge of Brooklyn is going through this now too
In the 1960s East New York rapidly transform from Mostly white working-class neighborhood
Do an underserved community of mostly black and brown New Yorkers neglected by both society and policy
But now as New York City rent Skyrocket
East New York is staring down a wave of identification that will forever change the character of this neighborhood
At 120 thousand people call home
WNYC in New York and the nation magazine have teamed up for an in-depth look at the gentrification of
Brooklyn they called her series
There goes the neighborhood
Today we're showcasing an episode from this ongoing series that we leave fantastic
It turns back the clock and looks at how this new
Rather unlikely hotspot for justification
Got to where it is today
This is episode 3 of there goes the neighborhood
Turf War
Presented by Kai Wright of the nation magazine
How to make a latte
Other day I was walking in my neighborhood and I saw a black elderly gentleman
That I haven't seen in a couple months and he literally his eyes who opens that you're still here
And I wait yeah
And you're still here
Things have changed happened today
And we were like yeah
Black folks are disappearing
System fenomenon everybody sees everybody feels
But somehow isn't in the center of the discussion where it needs to be
I'm of course talking about gentrification
When everybody gave up on the neighborhood we didn't we stood in the neighborhood
We worked it out
And we made it the better place that everybody wants to invest into now we live on Bobby
We all there for you.
They have also the political power to modify think they can go and sit with Commissioners in with Highway
People and say I need an extra block
All I see is overpopulation the city with others the only ones that can afford this rent is people that's not from
New York gay and my income doesn't even give enough for a room in East New York was going to give me for apartment
Craigslist
The neighborhood
I'm Thai right and I'm an editor at the nation magazine and my WNYC colleagues and I have been looking at this major dim
Demographic change that happening all over Brooklyn
Gentrification is one term that supplied
A lot of people who are sick of hearing that term feel like hay
This is just the law Supply Adam
Is relatively cheap property available and all things being equal
The people who can afford it grab it
And the people who had it earlier they reap the rewards
But all things are not equal they never have been
Four-decade
Public policy stack the deck of Economic Opportunity against black
Writer Tallahassee Coates has spoken a lot about this fact late
And making his case for economic reparation
Give me the link to gentrification succinctly during a recent talk in Brooklyn
Change all the time
Indian makeup in the ethnic makeup
The problem is
Black people don't really have the same level of self-determination to decide whether they want to stay and whether they want to leave
When we built the middle class in this country
We made decisions about who was going to
We decided black people were a part of that
When we get to the point talking about gentrification
You got to dig deep you got to go further back
So today we take a long look back at
East New York
The Brooklyn neighborhood that Ed we started exploring last time
Is now standing right in the path of gentrification
The first developer to set his sights on East New York
Colonel John
Way back in 1835
Family got rich on cotton and slaves but went broke in the cotton crash of 1837
It was like 2008 but back then the bubble was cotton nuts of my mortgages
Anyway Picton losses shirt
Crash butt
Not before launching this neighborhood into existence
Bought a bunch of farmland
Milton shoe factory and called it East New York
Brooklyn's famous Pitkin Avenue still Bears his name
The Long Island Railroad came about a year later and with it factories to process food from Long Island
Fart
The low-rise Housing Authority find the area Skyline came next
Denver rail line
Connecting the area to Manhattan and the rest of Brooklyn and it just kept growing
All the way through the middle of the 20th century
East New York became
A thriving suburb for the European immigrants who worked at all those factories
German
Dalian eventually Jewish families came here to feel well
Successful
An American
It was
Go to the suburbs in the city
The place where
People strive to go
That's Ron Shipman
A community organizer an urban planner has been fighting the development Warriors and Brooklyn since the
Grew up in Westchester but spent a lot of time in East New York is a high school kid in v
My First Girlfriend actually was in East New York
Travel from
Lower Westchester County to meet her at the
The long commute commute.
Daughter of a judge lived in
East New York
He paints and almost Norman Rockwell portrait of the
It was attached housing but everybody had their own porch and it was a
Is a middle-income
Upper-middle-income community in many ways
Aspiring community
It was not
What we
Think of today
It was a white Cami
And then
All of a sudden it wasn't
Over the course of just four or five years the neighborhood changed
Dramatic
From middle-class
Sapore
From largely white to nearly all black
In 1960 East New York with 85% light
By 1966
It was 80% black in Puerto Rico
Why
What created such a star-change
A lot happened really fast
But there was a key moment
It happened on a hot summer night
On July 21st
Nineteen
That's the day 11 year old black boy
What shot
Jim O'Grady has
Here's a little hint that East New York was
Crimes for racial tension in the summer of 1966
Some of its citizens got together and started a little self-help group called
Sponge
The society for the prevention of negroes getting everything
Oh 1966
Of course the group was whites only
Its members part of the 20% of the neighborhood that hadn't become black or Puerto Rican
A neighborhood that is Kai said
Ethnic White indominus
Demographically economically culturally
Until as recently as five years
Before
Anthony mamina was a teenager when the changes came down
He was born in Tunisia
But he's Italian
A lot of the whites in East New York or Italian
I remember where I live
Santa was mostly all white
Anybody cross
Euclid Avenue
Black kid with cross that
They will chase him back there
In the beginning it was sort of like playing chicken
The thing was with them was the game
Subway in the black kids used to come I think for the same reason you at all
Let's get away
Kids to chases
Think about how disorienting it was to be nice New York in the early 1960s
If you're white you seen your tight ethnic Enclave
Flooded with newcomers
Your friends are gone
If you're black or Puerto Rican
You're moving in for the affordable rent
Or the American dream of homeownership
You might have also migrated from the south to find a job
And Escape segregation
But now these cranky Old-Timers are telling you
This ain't your place
And you're probably thinking
Dude if this neighborhood is so wonderful
Why did all the white folks all at once
Like a herd of antelope
Move to Long Island
I used to
Deliver the year Brooklyn eagle
And when are used to get to Broadway
I see one side of the street was black in the other side of street wear
Was right and I couldn't
Understand that
Then when I was in junior high we got two black girls and then that was a big thing going on you know
I still don't understand it
Then I had a friend of mine live across the
Austrian went down Alabama
And he got beat up
For the simple reason you got up and gave a black woman a seat
When he came back to Brooklyn
Two black guys
So yeah race relations in the South were obviously not good
But in 1965
America was reminded in a big way
They're not going anywhere
This is a network news report from the time
August 11th 1965
The bloodiest riot in 40 Years of America's troubled begin
Los Angeles California the district called what
34 persons died 40 million dollars worth of property
Destroyed
Almost 4000 are arrested
The American Negro The Invisible Man breaks out in a screen look at me look at me
Know me for what I am
Look up a if you can
So now it's a year after images of La burning have lit up American TV screen
Is the start of the summer of nineteen
And every major city is wondering
Could the Watts Riot happen
Here
New York's new mayor
John Lindsay
Fixated
Unprevailing
Lindsey has been Gathering a national reputation for walking the streets of New York at night without a security detail
Mostly in poor neighborhoods
As a gesture of concern
Here's how he describes the tension in places like
East New York
City governments have been largely absent
From the ghetto
Their Chief presence usually has taken the form
Other policemen
And it has been hit on happy life
To be the lone representative
The man
White
And by extension
The entire public and private establishments
Lindsey's chief of staff was Jake Regal
Who is 26
What's the time
Today he's white haired executive with the real estate Giant
Related company
His office has a
Power Brokers view of Columbus Circle where he and I talked
When I emailed kriegel to
The set up the interview
I asked if he remembered
Particular incident from that summer of 19 6
The shooting of an 11 year old black boy
Named Eric
Dean
He wrote back
Like it was yes
So this instant begins with a conflict overturf
The classic Turf Battle of a something called a triangle right below these New York subway station
It's a battle between Italian kids
I've always lived there
This is their turf
And blackheads for newly moving in
Shouting match
Is fist fights by all accounts the neighborhood was on the verge of exploding
Lindsay decides to go out to East New York which as you know is a long way away
From City Hall
Because there's an eruption of violence between the two communities
And
Lindsay and
Three of us race out there
And go to a little pizza parlor which is right under the subway station where Lindsay meets with
These kids
Kriegel says
The sit down at
Frank's Restaurant on New Lots Avenue goes well enough
Except for the group of whites who march by shouting 2 4 6 8
We don't want to integrate
Lindsay leaves around 10 p.m.
And then the explosion happened
Accountant the New York Times says about 30 whites from
Sponge remember sponge
The society for the prevention of negroes getting everything
They start picketing at a traffic Island behind police barricades
A group of black counter-demonstrators form and the groups exchanged words
Sponge members burst through the barricades and give Chase
The group's don't physically Clash
Put a block away
Near group of blacks
A gun goes off
A witness later tells a jury that nothing happens for a minute before quote
A little boy stands up
And lays down in the gutter
Is Eric Dean
He's taken away by ambulance
Soon.
The time says groups of black residents than roam the neighborhood
Some throw garbage cans
Restore Windows
And Bricks at police car
The disturbance lasts about 4 hours
It's City Hall the next day Maryland Zoo causes AIDS in and ask them who knows East New York
What's going on
Who were the players
Jake Riegel says everyone sort of looks at each other
Previous Mayors could have gotten these answers
Quickly
Because previous mayors
We're Democrats
Lindsey
Is a Republican
The city had been run by Democratic Mayors using the Democratic machine
So the city wanted to know what was going on in East New York
Call the local disk
Calculator
He'll call the lope
The clubhouse and that was really the city's branch office in these communities across City
Kriegel says this is why today we have Community boards with professional staff
The boards existed in 1960
But they were voluntary and they were pretty
Sleepy
Lindsay beef up their powers and gave them money
So he'd have locals on the ground to talk to when stuff hit the fan
Lindsey also oversaw a change in police tactics
Bringing the cops into a community early
For the afternoon rather than
Then 9 tonight to the doctor 7 cops run down the streets in the dark with are scared cuz I don't know where they are the people are scared
To see an army Marching In
Cops come in the daylight
They stand around they talked
Two people they get acclimated they see what's around in the people
Crystal says
Cops were instructed to leave their nightsticks
At the priest
To not use
Forced into not stand on rooftops
Smith rifles
Those tax
Helped
Tommy's New York
Besides Eric Dean
No one died that summer during public unrest
A local black teenager was later charged with the dean shooting
And put on trial
But a jury acquitted him
In the end
Lindsey managed to keep New York relatively
Free from the major fires in fatal racial violence
That ignited around the country
In places like Newark and Detroit
And other cities
But within a year almost every single white family moves away
From East New York
White flight then
Spread through neighborhoods around the city
Especially the outer boroughs
But the turf wars between teenagers were just one symptom of Allah
Larger process that was unfolding whites and blacks were in Conflict but they were being pitted against each other by much
Much larger forces
Brooklyn was in the process of absorbing two great migrations Southern blacks coming north
In search of industrial jobs and Puerto Ricans fleeing the decimated economy of the island
What segregation limited these migrants housing
So black and Puerto Rican neighborhoods like Bed-Stuy in Harlem quickly became overcrowded people begin
Desperately searching for places to live and landlords and Real Estate Investors saw opportunity
Desperation tactics that have shaped neighborhoods all over the country ever since
Fear induced white flight
Predatory
Sell your home as is all cash
At no cost to you
And your home can be sold fast
Even if your face
30 in the years after World War II
In a stretch of tenements on the neighborhoods Western
The white families who live there were already frustrated with the landlords
Neglect
Owners want to do the least
Get the most out of the
What's something larger was about to
Play out we were very much afraid
A v atomic
This is Ron schiffman
Urban planner has been working in central Brooklyn
And that's right he said that atom bomb
The fear during the Cold War
Herniated America
Coming out of World War II
The policy of the federal government was to disperse
Essential population
To allow people to move out of the cities to allow Manufacturing
An essential Industries to move out of the city
So why tenants were giving it out
The FED begins subsidizing mortgages and highways and what became a wildly successful effort to create a new class
Suburban homeowner
But only for those
Essential pop
Essential populations
Were considered to be white and educate
And wealthy
And all of the major real estate Lobby groups advocated for restricting black buyers from the loans and neighborhoods that our
How much dollars final
Annies New York
White ranger seized upon the chance to buy home
And the landlords were happy to see them go
They got a pain in the butt
And now they're all of these black and Puerto Rican renters
Face the housing shortage and could be priced
But it didn't stop there
The real opportunity that segregation offer for Real Estate speculators
Wasn't flipping the houses the East New York's Italian and German and Jewish immigrants had owned for years
But to make a profit off of that
They had to get those white homeowners to
Sell for cheap
People would come in literally and hire somebody
To go out on the street and get into a fight in front of your house
All right to scare you from leaving what you feel like there's violence in the neighborhood even pamphlets put out
That work
Attributed to black people
When you read this
It was obviously written by a white pretending to be so
Because of this
Or something or other
It was scared
Dick's going on
There were people coming in and basically saying that if you don't sell you're going to lose the value of your home
It would just show up and knock on the door and say hey
They went and solicited door-to-door knocked on their door
In a way saying
We're willing to buy your house for all cash today you may not get this tomorrow
What we now think of as
White flight
Guarantees
I remember one
One person she had a house up
Forbell Street
Again Tony momina
They came one day has started want to sell
She says no
Making the next day you want to sell
That's no
After about a week
Pick it up in the morning
And the front doors on a floor
A little something to focus the woman's mind on the offer
The next day the buyers were
Since you want to tell him now it said they took the Money and Run
This is blocked
And it work
Well Teenspot in the streets
The parents fought over proper
And the blockbusting
Set up a next stage in the process
Test for Real Estate
Predatory lending
They set up these fast foreclosure scheme
Where they would buy cheap from the white families
Resell it at a higher price
Two African American and Latino families
The aspiring black or Latino homeowner would sign a contract with the investor
The arrangement would look a lot like those rent-to-own deals on appliances
To be on the hook for
Way too much money
More than they can afford
And more than the house were
After two to three months they couldn't make that payment
So they finally move to evict them
I'm within a year or two they be evicted them and they had the housing back
In their own hands and sold them again
So they turned these buildings
Where are you talking about the sixties are the early 2000s that are foreclosure crisis that sounds very similar to the
It was very similar
Throughout all of this
Racial tensions of course emerge
They always blamed each other for what happened
Primarily the white families blame the blacks moved into the neighborhood
For the abandonment and the decay of the neighborhood when it was really the real estate manipulation going on behind
Mercedes
This played out in fight between Tina
Does fights blossom in the Gang
The Summers of 1966 and 67 were marred by console
And then
Teen got shot in
By the end of 1967
Broad swath of East New York where is much
If 97%
Black and Puerto
Today Tony is in the same house
But he says he can count the other whites in the
Surrounding area on
One hand
Do you watch them
One after another
Eat at the Howard Beach show out to Long Island
I don't know if people have a picture better
Then where I am
The whole thing is
They have the name
I would be
A lot of people are afraid
Chase New York
When somebody ask
Atomix New York
Proud of it
That pride is not a small matter when it comes to neighbor
Development
The decades after Eric Dean was killed when
Public and private investor
Drained out of the play
The real difference between the dark stereotypes of East New York and the reality of community
I've been residence
Shear wall
Tony retired from driving delivery trucks
33 years ago
He spent most of that time volunteering at Cypress Hills Local development
He's been part of dozens of an issue
From Watchdog in the local police
Precinct
Working with banks
Define building
And he's not alone
Harold green and his wife moved here in 90
When they bought a house
Up on the hill by Highland
What is still one of the tone of your part
It was
Nice
It was very nice it was very quiet
It was
Transportation accessible
And the price
The price was on very affordable at the time and we have a nice two family house
By the early 80s he was volunteering at the Development Corporation with Tony
One of my neighbors
Who's on the board of the Cypress Hills in
Championship
Come down and you know that volunteer your time so again I can't be no
Pain Management Associates Services I had something
Communication
The scales and I've also had some
Financial Bank
It worked out
Today laundry tired
He's the board chair
He drove me around and showed me some of the stuff they built during the years
A grade school with a greenhouse
3 and 4 story apartment building
Affordable units
Senior housing for which they've just Broken Ground
You have to do for your community because no one else would do for you
And now like most other property owners here
He's got mixed feelings about the city's plan to
Spur more development
He's more than happy to see the new resource
And even eager to see new people
With their new money
It's just well what will happen then
We've been watching from Williamsburg
Fort Greene
Bushwick
So we are aware of what's Happening
Are we just trying to
Position ourselves
How to get the best results
What's the best response
Ministration
To make
Help
Make East New York
Cypress Hills
Broadway Junction
Ocean surrounding area
As vibrant
I-safe
And it's livable as fast
But you don't forget is like Tony
It's been livable for a long time
Why did you never miss
My son's got a big house up and no bark. Could have moved their you know no problem
Everything on the main floor and everything
But what am I going to do that
Once a day watch the armadillo go across the ground
Stew drink
The water
That's the most
Excitement over here we have a little shooting we have a little
Car accident yellow
You get to
Go outside talk to the people here on different views
I still don't understand this black and white.
Different you know
I treat people
Eye stye treatment
This black and white
We're still talking about
And we're hearing about it in every neighborhood we visit with this pod
It comes up with foreclosure and the history of racially targeted subprime Lending
It comes up with the demographic shifts
People are seeing now and it explains a lot of the anxieties people have about the city's Redevelopment plan for play
Places like East New York
Because after generations of flip
A blockbusting to chase out white
Predatory lending to bring in blacks and Latinos
A decade of Abandonment that followed
People are skeptical of manufacture
That was turf wars and episode from the series there goes the neighborhood from WNYC Studios and the nation Maggie
Using recorded in mix by Casey means research by Sean Carlson in and out what you want
Digital production Miley Hill Delaney Simmons Kevin France Frank Roberts and Annie Shields
It was reported and produced by DW Gibson Rebecca Carol Jim O'Grady and Kai ride and edited and executive
But Kieran from
Give me the rest of this series really should it's just fantastic wnyc.org neighborhood
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Delaney Hall
Protocol stack Katie mingle Avery trufelman Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
Intro and outro music this week by our friends okay akumi on Hell audio that's Utah's finest Electronics
Music label
We are brother good 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produce though the offices of arcsin in architecture & Interiors
Beautiful
Downtown
Highly desirable
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating.
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their hair
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
Episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastern episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find this show and like to show on Facebook and follow Saul on Twitter and Instagram the best way to explore the 99
9% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
It's become friends with our website it's not even IPI
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com