99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
Let's start with some Pittsburgh humor
This is comedian Tom usual on WDVE in Pittsburgh Pennsylvania
My dad's birthday few weeks ago
I thought you know what I'm going to get something really nice for my dad something you really going to like
What time does GPS system you know how those nice ones with it
With the sexy voice that talks to you while you're driving right
Tom's dad of Life on pittsburgher
Couldn't make heads nor tails of the DPSS directions because I am told
No one in Pittsburgh actually called anything by its official name
It's not Interstate 376 it's the parkway it's not the Liberty tunnel it's the tubes
So the joke goes looking up his dad out Tom downloaded a special plug in that makes the GPS device give tours
Directions like
Apus
Get on the parkway going towards time
Get off like you're going to candy or you're going up a hill
Under a railroad track
And you're making a left and right the same time
Go pass that crazy Church upper on stilts
Make a right and if you go past where Swissvale High School used to be you went too far
Otherwise
Sometimes the stories of what used to be can have more meaning than what actually here now
The philosopher guiborat a word for using your emotions and memories as a way of wayfinder
He called it psychogeography
That's the philosopher Sam Greenspan geography is particularly useful in Pittsburgh
Bob's Diner Bob's Diner that we just passed used to be a car dealer
And I know that because it was a car dealership when I first moved to this area Family Dollar across the street
There used to be a grocery store and I I don't know that one first and that's just
This is Pittsburgh resident Mike Nielsen
Rifle things that used to be things
It's like kind of like history and it's not history like George Washington and the Whiskey Rebellion
This stuff is so history Mike is not from Pittsburgh
He grew up on the other side of the state
So he moved there
You have a hard time figuring out how to get around
Because pittsburghers are always telling him to
Turn left
That's something that
Isn't there anymore
It's a one-day Mike was hanging out with his
Buddy Tom
That is Tom usual the comedian from a minute ago
Tom was trying out the pit
Pittsburgher GPS routine on Mike
I see that the kind of told
Ways it was normally
Weather used to be like ash day
Json or whether you
Italian rest
Yeah I tell you know that's kind of funny but I think anyone telling of the Joker
Or somewhere along the line
He said something about you know
Oh yeah where they used to be that Pizza Hut
The light went off
I said yes
Is the Pizza Hut
For Mike
The former Pizza Hut was a beacon of light
Shining through a thick fog
Impossible directions
Because here
It is Friends comedy routine
Was the one Pittsburgh East Direction he could give that anyone
Regardless of where they from
To comprehend
Turn left
Did the place that used to be a Pizza Hut
They're two Hallmarks of Pizza Hut Arkansas
One the whole thing is built out of traps
The windows are trapezoids
Enter frame for this kind of trapezoidal
Paneling on the exterior
If you remember your geometry you know that trapezoid is a four-sided figure with
Two parallel sides and two non parallel sides
It tends to look like a triangle
With the top chopped
I see the trapezoid windows then you know it's an old
Pizza Hut
And then there's the roof which often has oversized trapezoidal awnings
And were they all connected
The top is this big bump that just shoots into the air
Whole thing looks like a lid for the building
Bratz
Actually one of the
The kid I thought
Hot and Hot
Same thing
Thank you Pizza Hut
Now Pizza Hut Stone all look like
Franchise owners have a lot of freedom and how their stores look
Thought every Pizza Hut has the lid roof
And the trapezoid features and some might be
More distinctive than others
But there's still enough commonality in Pizza Huts
That
Once you've seen one
You can
Usually identify any other
The Pizza Hut School of Architecture is so distinctive
The even when a Pizza Hut goes under and gets converted into a different business
You can still totally tell
It used to be a Pizza Hut
And every town across the world
There used to be a pizza
Most of them are still standing in the most of them are not still Pizza Huts and so it's
It's this image that we just all happened when we're all so familiar with
Okay Mike is definitely overstaying in here
Not every town in the world has a form of
Pizza Hut
And I can get numbers on whether or not the majority of the old-school trapezoidal window Style Pizza Huts are still
Active Pizza Hut
But the fact remains
There's something really funny
A little sad but mostly funny about seeing a former Pizza Hut get turned into something else
The satirical newspaper the onion thought so too
They once had a headline that read
You can tell Area Bank used to be a pizza
It's funny to unvalidated
It's a Mike Nielsen did the only logical thing to do when you get obsessed with some
He started a Blog
Anna's blog
It's called it used to be a Pizza Hut
Which is a Blog about
The current uses of former Pizza Huts
It is a global atlas of
The buildings that used to be
I can't defend
So I'll just go ahead and say yep that's what I've been doing with some of my spare time
Even going to work for them
I guess they're not bad
You know what you get when you abbreviate used to be a Pizza Hut
Utba
Aph
Though I don't like my kid
Does that sound right
I mean that sounds horrendous
I guess that's
That's just what it's spelled out the bee should have done a better backronym I should have thought of something that would spell out something really cool
Mike started documenting like bath surround
Pennsylvania
Like fat pocket Pawn
In North Versailles
What is trapezoidal Windows don't open a can of seafoam green
Yellow trim
Pretty soon you start getting submissions from across the US
And from Australia and New Zealand
Through this data set some trends
Barstool pizza restaurants what I think makes sense to they probably had pizza ovens in them
Maybe stuck around there's Sopranos Pizzeria in York Pennsylvania
And La porchetta in Auckland New Zealand there are even cases of Domino's Pizza moving in.
Smug all and then there's a class of non Pizza rest
Mexican and Asian rest
Chinese rest
Chinese Hut in Toronto Ontario Souvlaki Hut
In Dandenong Australia the structures that has these businesses All Began life unmistakable
As Pizza Hut
But there are some more interesting ones so I think one of the most popular posts on the Block is the Des Moines Police Traffic Unit
On that in trademark rights and I quote
We all love the idea of the police chief telling all the cops get their act together and get
Get traffic violations under control they will have to work at a Pizza Hut
And then the mayor coming in
Breaking the news that they would indeed
I'll be working in a Pizza Hut evidence room in the cooler interrogations happening in the booth
Secretaries playing tabletop Pac-Man instead of Solitaire
That is how I picture this one
And I love it
There's a funeral home in Australia
That is in a former Pizza Hut Olson Funeral Homes in revesby New South Wales in a crown jewel of all
Call Advance
Brisbane Australia's Kaos adult
Concept
Cancel
Case it was an adult bookstore and had all the windows kind of boarded up
Adult bookstores 10/2
Window coverings
I can see that Mike doesn't have any particular affinity for
He went there as a kid
It's a personal pan pizzas plates
Tabletop Pac-Man
Pepsi ad
Red plastic cups
But it's only Jesus
Funny
I'm a pretty easily amused
And so I thought it was funny but I think a lot of things
Funny I think it's more than funny
Nice project
Points to the fact
There aren't too many companies
Whose very name describes their own signature brand of mass-produced architecture that they themselves
Although Pizza Hut never meant for architecture to be the focus of their brand
At least
Not at first
Pizza was founded in 1958 in Wichita Kansas
It was actually founded by two brothers who were
Students at Wichita State University
It was sad you know
56 years of later it's grown into the world's largest pizza company with more than 14,000 restaurants around the world
Where is a public relations director at Pizza Hut
He says that when Pizza Huts founders
The brothers Frank and Dan Carney bought their first building
Take a sign that only had room for 8
It had room for Pizza on top and it only had room for three characters are three letters underneath hat
Did any Scrabble player
They're really only so many
Three-letter word
Pizza dad
Pizza sad
Pizza Peel and they kind of look at the shape of their building
Anti
Is Colace like a hot
Show me we call Pizza Hut so they have four letters maybe we can call the pizza shed
Mosquitoes don't eat or something like that
Don't be real Pizza Hut he's still around
Don't knock knock
It's an up half it's a move to the campus
The founders alma mater
Wichita State
Just outside
Their school of entrepreneurial ISM the first Pizza Hut is commemorated with a plaque
And if not for that plaque
You have no idea what it is
It just looks like a
Painting brick house
Area trapezoid anywhere
Pizza Hut signature look came later
That was the work of an architect
A friend and classmate of the Carney Brothers
The guy by the name of Richard Burke
Brooke wanted $32,000 to do the design
The carnies counter-offered with $100 per Pizza Hut to subsequently out
Burke accepted
And created a lot of the features that we can now recognize today irrefutably
As Pizza
And from their Pizza Hut architecture and their corporate image became intertwined
And so the carnies and their franchisees began lining the American landscape
With hot after Hut
But in their ascendancy
Pizza Hut couldn't
We're simply wouldn't imagine the time
When the people would not come out in droves
To enjoy
Personal pan pizza
Radetzky breadstick
As market trends shifted away from the dining experience
Shandong delivery
Mini Pizza Hut closed
And as their trapezoidal Windows went dark
And the roof hump
Rosa empty parking lots
It was as if a company had a litter the world with monuments to its own.
Klein it reminds you that there used to be Pizza Hut's everywhere and that there aren't
Anymore
We see the old
Pizza Hut's laying around
Set of the dead carcasses along the road
And now Pizza Hut's architectural Legacy
She is one that will remind passersby
Other companies failure to thrive in every single place it ever fail to thrive
But Doug terfehr of Pizza Hut
App Store
Triumph
We're pretty proud of the fact that
Our business became so recognizable
That you can just look at a building and recognized even as it got turned into something and then maybe even turned over into some
Something else again that one you just look at it people know that used to be a Pizza Hut
That that's really cool to us
I have to say
I think I'm with Doug on this one
Guess the hubris of Pizza Hut is the stuff of Greek tragedy
But this is not a story about failure
It's a story about hope
What can be reclaimed
About the possibilities for what might emerge
Couldn't have ever been dreamed up from the outside
In a hermit crab moves into its shell
Pizza Hut
Is actually curbing the rise about that
In the late 1990s and early aughts
The company shifted towards a carryout and delivery model
Today
About half the Pizza Huts in the US operate out of generic
Glass box looking structure
No trapezoids no sloped roofs
They don't stand out
In fact a newer style Pizza Hut near my apartment
Just went out of business
And if I hadn't ever seen it in operation there be no way to know what it once was
Now that I've seen the next generation of faceless used to be a Pizza Hut
I think that if Pizza Hut phase out their signature buildings
It will be a
Huge mistake
Because Pizza Hut has achieved a level of great
I mean how many other structures have there ever been in his
Who's true Essence and shine through whatever might come after it
If you open the hamburger joint in the Great Pyramid of Giza it will always first and foremost be
The Great Pyramid of Giza
Turn left at the place that used to be the Great Pyramid of Giza
Like the pyramid
The Pizza Hut
The Humble Pizza Hut
Succeeds in edging its identity
To everything else that will ever come after it
It is at that level
The Pizza Hut
Manages to constantly remind everyone hey
I was here
I am the place with a personal pan pizzas
With a translucent red plastic cups
With a tabletop Pac-Man
So what a stand in all of the mighty Pizza Hut
Which more than just about any other once-beloved establishment since crumbled beneath the sands
Signs of time can reach into the future and Proclaim
Just try and forget about me
Just try
99% invisible with produced this week by Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars would help
From Margaret Krause
Thanks also to Andrew Wasson who wrote about the history of Pizza Hut architecture for the zine in Derry River
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced
How did the offices of arcsin a brilliant Architecture Firm
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Flask podcast
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and a new week
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastern episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You've been show in Lancaster on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars Sam Sam listen to a retweet
Couple minutes we also have a Tumblr that's really fantastic but if you want lots more about up bass photos of the original
Pizza Hut complete with a plaque in a completely different comedy sketch about Pittsburgh directions that also references
Pizza Hut go to 99 Pi. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast.,