99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The Bowery
In lower Manhattan is one of New York's oldest neighborhoods
So it's been through a lot of iterations
In the 1650s a handful of freed slaves were the neighborhood
First residence
This was back when you work was still a Dutch colony called New Amsterdam
In the Lower East Side of Manhattan was
Farmland
By the early 1800s the neighborhood was a bustling through affair with elegant theaters and taverns and shops
By the late eighteen hundreds and become a city or place
Boots women's dance awesome prostitution
And by the 1940s the Bowery and become New York Skid Row
The place where down-and-out men could go and rent a cheap room for the night
And where the neighborhood too many flop houses
Mail course there's no room for a skid row in the Lower East Side of Manhattan
And the Bowery like the rest of the area
It's full of expensive places to live in fancy grocery store
But back in 1998
Before the last of the Flop House is closed its doors
Dave I say and Stacey Abrams and made one of my favorite radio documentaries of all time about one of these
These producers knew they're making a time capsule but I don't think they knew just
How fast and complete a transition New York was about
How to make even though most of New York City has moved on from these kinds of voices
Stories
You'll never forget them
After you hear Nathan Smith riveting guided tour
Of the sunshine Hotel
Welcome come on in if you got the rent money
David Yang
This is a needed in beating Hotel
Normally people come in and stay for a day or two and get out
But for some reason or another people come in they like
Interstate 4 year
2 years
You know another way that like to give you aggravation
Davido if you like aggravation
Come to the sunshine
It's a lovely place in the bed
I had place I scratched all night the whole time I was here
Yeah Roaches on the wall mental abuse short of funds and you need to lay your head
Down for a couple of hours we hope to make your
Stay classy
But don't ask me for towels
So we don't have it
We do not have those luxury
Want to see ID
Pictures of the kind of hotel where everybody gives an AKA
You're welcome
For very nominal
Okay you are my friend you're all set okay you can squeeze yourself away this that and the other
This is the last
Of the last Welcome to the
Sunshine Hotel
Hi Google
Okay
What's up God what's happening
Alright my man my name is Nathan
Smithline the manager of the
Sunshine
Yeah what can I do for you
I'd like to pay my rent
This hotel in 1998 probably look
The same as it did in 1920
Like almost all of them
Blops the lobby is on the second floor of a narrow flight of stairs
It's just a large room with wooden floors on a cup
Chad
I sit in a
Acadia front running
There's only one telephone for the in
Gentile Hotel Wiki
Keeps a pretty
Busy give me a 10-4
Eddie Eddie Eddie do me a favor
See if you can get a oil sensor
Teller lets his mother
Headed to the John you got to see me
You weren't able to
Half the lobby you'll find the living
Quarters for a hunter
25 residence
The sunshine is one of the last
Places in the country where people live in a cubicle
Maybe it's a little hard to imagine for those of you living in wall Florence Circle
Picture of long hallway with a
Series of doors on the Eagles
Beside these
All the cube
4 x 6 no window
The cubicles are only 7 feet high so this chicken wire along the
App to keep the guys from climbing over into the Next Room
Really it's like living in a
Play Centre fogelman the living room 36a
Basically it's like the size of
Lego jail prison cell
It's all got a light
And bed
Mattress in a blanket
Without
Scream on the top
And basically that's about it
Very tiny
So small
You have trouble making the bed I've been in prisons jails
Living upstate
Dos
What's 5 times bigger than my room
So it's not the Waldorf but where else can you find a room in New York for
$10
If it wasn't for this hotel a lot of these guys wouldn't have any place
All you have to do is look around like over there
You see that old guy there with the Snow White and the guitar
Eddie Eddie Bauer
The new day sunshine so that's that's good hey
Eddie sits all day in a corner of the hotel
Looking out the window
Play my playlist Johnny Cash the way it's mine
The funny thing about it is that he always plays the same songs over and over
Over again maybe I might sit down and come up with a new joint in my mind but by the time I pick up the guitar don't forget the tuna
I had my mind but he had a mental breakdown and ended up
Any news about it
Honda Hitomi
Play back so we went together then that's how we started that was 30 years ago
Eddie's Philly
What am I playing
Somewhere
Lean on you for another
Sunshine is the last.
On the one hand it's probably as close as you can come to living in hell
125 dysfunctional guys crammed together in this old hotel
On the other hand it's
It's pretty interest
There was some hotels on the ground I did everything
Free store
You wouldn't believe the characters that stay here at
Parentheses see that little elf and white guy walking through the lobby
That happens to be the only when you crack a Bitcoin
This is don t you love this place
Do this is awesome
Sue maven
About Russia
He sues everybody in town I think he's doing the pope now for malfeasance
Oh Father
What happened
This is Benny this is Benny Hill
Why what
Village Academy
Cubicle 25A
Benny has throat cancer
Talk to the voice
Asbury
I've been 87 years is man's like my adopted father
Vinny looks a lot like a famous mob boss Vincent the chin Gigante
Rumor has it that
Guys is Uncle although I don't know
I gay maybe cuz I was in the shower when I didn't want to bother my damn way anymore in Lodi
And I will be there until I die probably
That chirping sound you hear is Vinny's two lovebirds he spends all day in his cubicle taken care
Ladyboy
Vive
Joe many leave alone really like you need something you know that we do everything or you're not going to make
K-pop
Tell me something slick Anthony
Tell me what's going on Anthony Coppola cubicle 4B
Everyone here calls him fat Anthony because he weighs 400
25 time
Sometimes an aquifer
26 oz can of Chef Boyardee ravioli
That is for 5 people to family
I'll be in a cold radicand
That is a load
That's a lot of grub there
Anthony's in Norfolk
Who came to the Bowery is a
Teenage robot
20 years
When I first met Anthony was a normal
Side purse
But something about this
Please call him
I need
Delete
Anthony has gotten so loud he doesn't
Clothing
What's around the hotel rap
And almost never leaves the bills
Why should I go anywhere
I could if I wanted I just open up the window
Turn on my fan little higher when I got here
I've been trying to get Anthony
Move to a house
But he won't go
How much like home
Too much like home
You best in a place I was supposed to
I'm
People get to be like family
You don't want to leave
Let with the stem filaree
Little white snake
That's Bruce the hotel's Runner
Delivering two bags
Chinese food
Fat aunt
That's another part of life and he's old
UC
Up here in the sunshine with totally isolated from the rest
The world so weak
Create our own little Society
Anything you want
Can get from another
Yellow long chaga
Drug dealer guide
As long as what
Couple of bucks
The room cleaner
And Bruce runs errands
But tips
Yeah that's fine
All day Bruce it's in the lobby waiting
Rosanna soon as somebody calls them in for
The Optima EX Monarch non filter large Bacitracin one fact
There you go
Tea 2 sugars
Rolex
Bruce Lee the Vietnam vet and find him running errands is kind of like going into fat
It takes constant concentration constant alert
The main thing is do the step
Get the order
Remember who gave you the money
And remember how much they gave you
Cover
Steps and most of momentum
He Two Sugars one roll a two packs of Monarch and walking all the time you got people
Constantly distracting
Distraction too big
Houston
Anis a tea with Two Sugars you get to the store and see what YouTubers
You get the store you got to realize
But you got to constantly be on guard
Constantly on guard you're in the Hustler
Whose capital planet
Every third person you meet is trying to hustle you out of your money
Store clerks included
Okay I'll give you a dollar and Yuan every kind of a person that's out for money in the world
And you got other people's money on you
You got to defend it better than you with your own
Because that's your livelihood
You bought once you could ruin your career
You don't blow it want to make sure everything's alright my reputation is my busy
I don't blow it
I know bull 37.3 $0.70
Okay
Pizza
All day
Showtime Showtime at the Apollo
Why is the phone business
Sunshine give me a chance for not hating come in yet
Cookie wants $20
So when the long-shot comes in I'll tell him leave $20 for cookie
Cookie cookie
In fact when I can have me a set of Choppers
My name is Optimus and I'm six
3lau
I came to the sunshine Hotel
Bedtime
It was a ball
All over
Virus
23 Walden everblock
I would like Broadway and never close
And the whole Barrel filled with nothing but alcoholic
Most people I know who that was on the borrowers didn't I
Cost of alcohol
I'm lucky to be alive and I know that
About it New Years in on the buyer in them
Rough living
Yeah really roughing it
Commenced article facts about this
The sunshine was opened in 1922 by God name
Frank Massaro
Cubicles World ammonite
His son called took over 1940
Fatherland place until a couple of years ago when he sold it to New Orleans
Now they're looking
He should make this building Landmark status
Street lot of guys here please
What wise men do not dwell
This place is The Last of the Mohicans
Like all of them flops
The sunshine is a men's
Only if
Establishment
Some of the hotels left on the Barrio
Still whites-only but I let every
All Races all ages
Is all kind
Story
We all have
One thing in common
On our
We are all at home
But for some reason we left
Got thrown up
Take me for exam
I used to work at
Bank of Georgia one day many years
You know I was injured on
Job they find man
Sometime later my wife
So I came down to the Bowery and I
Then you ever
What to do in the back
Time I'm taking it back some of my guys in the Euro drug addicts or alcoholics
Summit just off Rikers Island
Others
Just drink too big
I'm going to be a me a thermal Resort
For basketball court
I have a round oval 440 track
Trackmate track
I mean what you just do one thing
I'm having a summary going and this is what it's going to be composed of
Some of my guys here at
Sunshine of working in
Trying to save
Some are hiding out from the law
Some
A donkey about
Psychiatric
Emotionally distraught people
Find a home in the sunshine Hotel
And I found home inside me
Whitest girl color black is Boy Color blue is emotion
Where is Jeffrey mangonel
How I live in the sunshine Hotel I'm profoundly a multi-billionaire
Mother's multi-billionaire to my sister
And then there are those of us
2 and up here because we're dreaming
And just don't seem
Fit in anywhere
Like my relief
Clerk Vic
Big spends his days in the corner of the hotel hot Stovers Daily Racing Form
Press
But it wasn't always like
In my case
I started off the lights
I could probably so many people maybe everyone for all I know
Whitworth
Sweet dreams unifreight grew up in Ohio with an alcoholic mother and
He always
Spelled like a misfit
Zoe Baron himself in philosophy
Play in poetry
And then set off for the Bowery in 1960
Future live cheaply while undertaking his metaphysis
I had some
Crazy soaring Ambitions of figuring out everything
Freaking out ever
I was all the old an impossible Quest
For truth
It's like singing from that song what's it all about Alfie
Who hasn't wondered what it's all about
Imperious ambitions
Along those lines
I don't seem like a
Was making some progress was in toxic
After while it seemed like it was some crazy pipedream was they say you know
Figure that have been
I want more substantial heavy weights and Me by far
Through history you know and they didn't seem to come up with the answers
The big answers
Yeah
So where do I get off
Thinking I had it but you know
Cancel.
Seems like one of those stories better left Untold
To me it seems
Can I get name last year for the sunshine Hotel 241 Bali one of my tenants
Is very ill and mr. Marshall
80 years old
Senile
Dumped here by his son about two months ago or he doesn't eat anything but Oreo cookie
Can't walk to the bathroom so he goes on a floor
Ariel now he's down to 80 lbs now and jaundice
Marshall wouldn't last another week here in this
I called his son last night but he doesn't care
David come on outside
I mean it happens
In a place like this you know they're young we're very popular
With people being dumb
Give me the new map don't reach out to grab
Just lean back
Lights
Yamulee screw Wheels list of Marshall Island Edwin. Porter
Gas mask
Clean up crew put in a bag and put in a bag
Flies everywhere
Smells like nothing you've ever
Smell before
Urine all over the floor
A lot of Auto
Milk carton full of full of urine
The worst part
Cleaning up room like this
What were you going
Delia's gone
Robinson's gone
Dave Rodriguez is gone
Late afternoon at the sunshine my shift is almost over and I'm sorting
Google Mail
Rodney's deceased
This is the guy that got shot by the maintenance man here in the lobby
Google Fiber
Marcus is gone
Skagen
It's like a death house
Okay 7 months I've been here
Five guys have died
Okay
And these guys will never leave the building
I need months and months at a time
One guy I knew that leave disability for 1 year
He says Donald says I'm going to die in this
End.
Guess I can't go no lower than
I can't the only thing I could do it now it start
Like a little chicken stock
Call Nan VA wake up in the morning
And
Sit in the bed
Smoke a cigarette
And save myself Donald
What the hell are you doing here
What the hell you doing with mostly people just lay
On their bed all day and their cubicle watching
TVR listening to the radio or staring into space
If sleeping in
Just keep
Vegetating
Annie's a little cell
With fluorescent light overhead
Coming through the chicken wire
No
The Starlight
That's a guy will call Max
Thought you didn't want his full name
Cubicle one
L
Max's of 30 year old Russian image
Skinny kid with a ponytail and
Glasses
Unlike the other guys you meant Max is one of my short-term tenants
He left his wife and kids in New Jersey and Kami on a heroin binge
2 months ago
Is my chance
To get away where I just
Don't have to do anything for anyone and
Indulge
The maximum width Alabama
Being worried about what anyone's going to say or
I'm going to affect others no one knows that I'm here
It's just a complete getaway
Max's in Arkansas
And even though he's only been here for a short while
He managed to make it
Cubicle homey
Lit with candles
Piles of books on the
Floor
Imposters
There is a painting of ball
Saint Jerome was
A hermit
Yuan
To the desert
Look by m sulfur
A very long time to try to
Seek knowledge
Achieve illumination
In a sense that's what I'm doing till I guess
It's some protest
I enjoy it
It's like that movie The Cook the Thief the wife and her lover
Experiences so
Disgusting secret asking their son grow
But they make
A narcotic
I'm kind of making an art. Of experience in this
A couple of days later Max
Is arrested at the sunshine
They crashed him up against the wall several times
Handcuffed them took them out of here
And that means his room is available
Where anybody wants rent
He's just a clean out now
Nothing person
He's a cleaner
I'm going to clean them out
Sellersville maybe tomorrow
I'll probably sell it tomorrow
More than life
Trying to get my friend
One tenant leaves another
Checks in Bethalto
Hotel NOVOTEL
The sunshine will always be a dog
Wake up every morning with
Chicken wire just above you
Walls having you in on all sides
Alone
The stunning
Sad play
Sometimes that the sunshine I close my eyes and
Ripped off
I forget where I am just for a second or two
Suddenly I'm not in a flophouse
Hotel the sitting in some family
A cup of coffee
Then I wake up and I'm back at the house
Just like everyone else you're hoping for break
Waiting for that day when I can
Final
Check out
Sunshine Hotel
Wolverine
I hope you enjoyed your stay here while you were here
I always tell my tennis the same thing when they leave welcome to come back anytime
A good luck buddy
Good luck
Where were they going the next place I hope it's not
The same as this solvent a little bit
But I always do
Good luck
Good luck at all I'd say
Okay woman
Are you going to help good good I'm Nathan
That's the sunshine Hotel
God bless buddy
Chattanooga Choo Choo
The sunshine Hotel was produced by Dave I say and Stacy Abramson in 1998
The narrator of this piece in manager of the sunshine Hotel Nathan Smith
Died from cancer in 2002
This documentary was a production of sound portraits which went on to spawn storycorps which is dedicated to collecting chair
Sharing and preserving people stories
They probably made you cry during Morning Edition on Fridays but I'm here to tell you they also have a podcast that's much longer than what
Turn on the air and it's hosted by storycorps producers who offer more backstory and podcast exclusives and some older.
Documentaries like this one
So you like these kinds of moving and affecting stories of Everyday People subscribe to the storycorps podcast wherever you find
Podcast
More info about storycorps can be found at storycorps.org
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are a production of 19
Win7 kalw Sanford
Cisco and produced are the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Escape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Back pocket
You can find the show in likes on Facebook or on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify that you can live
Listen to every single episode of 99% invisible at 99 pmi.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com