99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I want you to conjure an image in your mind of the White Stripes
Not those white stripes but the White Stripes that divide the lanes of traffic going in the same direction on a major
How long are the stripes you can spread your arms out if you want to
Over the course of many years of psychology researcher named Dennis Shaffer at Ohio State
Costumes from many different parts the country
This question
And the most common response was
Two feet
So do you like most people you estimated that those white stripes are 2 ft long
Maybe a little more
But if you did
You be very very wrong
This is Tom and Jerry
When was Tom Vanderbilt summer writer in New York
And author of traffic why we drive the way we do
And what it says about us
Every three pages of Tom's terrific book traffic I can probably turn into a 99percentinvisible episode
But back to the highway
What early on in my research I was talking to a highway engineering if your car is ever broken down on the side
Are the road if ever been to force to get out of your vehicle
On a highway just take a moment to notice what a strange landscape it is you're having a stent in your
Road sign
Is there a huge they're not meant to be
Experience as humans on foot they're meant to be experienced at 75
Miles an hour with the Clearview typeface perfectly visible retro-reflective
And then there are the whites tree
You actually kind of got out of your car
And were able to walk on a closed Highway
Walk from one end of those
Stripes to the other you can find that
And I mean years ago United States
Highway standard was 15 feet long
Which is longer than
Cartel
Current Federal Highway Administration guidelines suggest a length of 10 feet with 30 ft between the dash
That's something that that is shocking to people
And remember most people in the Schaefer study said that those stripes
Or two feet long that's such a vast
Golf there between
You know that there are
If I see without them
Margin of error going to sing
And it goes back to this fundamental point that when you're in a car at high speeds you're experiencing only a sin
Of the landscape
Rather than the actual answer
This kind of sense the landscape has been presented to you
To make you feel comfortable and to make a highway work at what are wheelie evolutionarily
Ridiculous speeds for a human to travel
You have this big
Flat wide open no kind of stretch of road that
You even if you have a 65 mile-an-hour sign
The message of the road is telling you something entirely different and I think
Especially where a lot of our Behavior comes from
Speeding willful
La breaking but a lot of it is just
People are paying attention to the visual messaging the road not to their speedometer
Long dividing lines in clearvista
Give the illusion
That you're going at a reasonable speed
As soon as something encroaches into view
You get a sense of how fast you're going
That's one reason why those
Temporary concrete walls that Cruz put up
Right next to the road during construction
Are so unnerving
The air in perception of white stripe length
Is attributed to the fact that when we drive
We tend to look
So far ahead
That we usually only experience the dashes in gaps
When are very far away in an angle where they look shorter
But there's no consensus as to why people all over the country
We're so consistently wrong
With the two Fiesta
My favorite cocktail
Party
In a pack
Stump the driver
Does White Stripes information
I don't want to leave you with the impression that the Y dividing lines are UNIF
You won't find Juno 10-foot
Highway lines
San Jose Boulevard in New York City
And you probably won't find 10 or 15 foot stripes on Bridges or Highway on-ramp
Or let's hope you don't do that soon
Government
Entirely
Designline
Which for that
Space
Limited access highways are designed for a very precise purpose
The Highwaymen
Uninterrupted
Fast flowing traffic get people from point A to point B
Quickest possible with no interruptions
Sort of environment does not work
Cities were or suburbs the problems when that approaches grafted into places where it doesn't belong
Paying the price
Right now and some
Suburban environments where you find these
Arterial highways that were built
Almost to Highway engineering standards
Again these long sight lines
Wide roads encourage
We go fast and then we went and built all kinds of development along those arterial highways was never really supposed to be there
But with so many people driving on these roads they became absolutely irresistible to,
This is score of the new American Main Street right where you have
Are Costco's in your ear
Fast food in
All sorts of in and out
Parking lots driveways drive-thrus yet people also going very fast and
Annenberg Dunbar
Does a lot of research suggests these are releasing
What's the most dangerous places
The drives in America not
Crowded
Urban cities
The whole approach is called the forgiving Road
The idea was that
First try to minimize the
Potential at a crash
Could happen
Through
Again through lack of obstacles
You know General sightlines all these rich
Crushed it happened
Mitigate
The effects
Survive what would happen to not punish the driver
For the mistake that he will inevitably make
According to language in the time
So you see that nowadays in things like in California will have your
Guardrails that are
Wire guard rails that
Car strikes
That guardrail at 10
The catch
On the guardrail rather than
Bounce back
Backing out into traffic
Another series of collisions
So this forgiving road is a positive thing in terms of good safety engineering
But they were they were so seduced by it that the call was made to bring it into the even the Surface Street Network
So things like Street trees began to be deemed a hazard
Buy Engineers just outright hazard
That makes sense on a high-speed country road but
If you're talking about a residential street
We're not supposed to be going more than 25 anyway
Is the presence of a street tree on the side of the road where it's providing
Shade and Comforts pedestrian snow is that the same sort of Hazard is it even a hazard at all
The conclusion many planners
Trees are a hazard
Define pre-war suburbs
You have a son you have the
The street
Set of trees and then
The sidewalk
Post-war the Starship again happen where
Trees removed on the other side of the sidewalk
Suddenly pedestrians were put into the position of being the buffer
Between drivers
And those menacing trees
As you move those trees away
The visual sensation of the road
Became wider
And if there's one
Iron law of traffic engineering it gets into this visual perception thing as well as the wider a road is or
Is perceived to be the faster driver speed dance in Grease
Of course you know the final if you look at
Suburbia that they just kind of eliminated the sidewalk in the trees
All together
The final
Final solution
And Tom Vanderbilt size you can almost data subdivisions development based on that shift
Road engineering is that humans tend to consume
Extra
Engineering measures have been built in for their safety
Much in the same way I like to draw the analogy with
So the research has been done on food packaging by by Brian wanzek
Cornell University experiments where you give people
I just ran over people large buckets of popcorn
Filled to the top with popcorn to get them a smaller
Smart popcorn in a smaller package
Don't don't just eat more of a larger pack
It's whether there it has nothing to do with their level of hunger it's just
The size of the package
Influences their behavior
Varmints
Over-engineered for the safety and then we
Time to consume a lot of the extras getting us back to this kind of
Homeostatic ads that were
We're always kind of
Playing with I think
99% invisible is Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars that the project
Public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Another
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast oh my God.
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook
But that's where a lot of the discussion and interaction happened so join us over on Facebook we're getting pretty close to 10,000 likes
That's what I would really enjoy
A tweet at Roman Mars
And we have links to all the stuff that we've been talking about in this episode
Had 99% invisible
. org
One more time
And every other creative audio lover owes a huge debt
To the Third Coast International audio Festival in every year
I'd send them a little something to make sure that they keep going
When I buy t-shirt and they have hands down my favorite t-shirt design in the whole world
Across the front
Is the word listen
Written in Braille
Six of them in every color
It's a must-have for any radio lover
You can find out the various ways
How you can support the Third Coast International audio Festival
At Third Coast Festival
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com