99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Your world has not been designed for you
Large part it has been designed for the average
Brought your education you've been given standardized tests and been graded by how well you perform compared to the average
Building codes
Trans rights Dow Jones
All these measurements are based around
Concept
And it's okay we know you're not at
You're really special
Well I mean it you're not average
No one is
Not completely
But the concept of average
Texas all
Everything seemed to be based around this reference point average
And obviously everything about societies Built This Way
But I never really thought of it
Until I dug into
7 part of this is
Todd Road
My name is Todd Rose I am the director of the mind brain education
Vacation program
At the Harvard graduate school education
He's also the author of the book
The end of average
But he had to that first we have to
Start with the
Beginning of average
Because it wasn't always a thing
The concept of average as we know it was pioneered by a Belgian mathematician and astronomer named out of Kevlar
So Kelly is the person who actually
Coins the term the average man
And he is
In like the 1830s
She is actually an astronomer in Belgium
Today the way the most people get a handle on any set of numbers
Calculate
Catalyst
Astronomers were some of the only people who did this
Basically averages were a way to compensate for the imprecise tools that astronomers were working with
In 1830
If you were trying to time
The movement of Saturn you would actual scratches on your glass of your
Telescoping as soon as it crossed one you start counting and stopped counting after across the other
But you can imagine you're off by half a second
It's going to be a lot of error
And so
They they realize if they wanted to make sense of
Painting heaven
They needed more
Precision in their ass
And they realize that if you had saved
10 measurements
They were all slightly different
You added them together and divided them by 10
You got a better approximation of
True measure
If you just average together are measurement
You're way more likely to be closer to the truth right end
You end up getting kind of a bell curve of measurement error
Cadillac was the first to take this tool of astronomers and Appliance
Two people
In the early 1840s
Is Cadillac find a data set
Of the chest measurements of 5738
Scottish soldiers
Kelly added together each of the measurements and divided by the total sum of the soldiers
Net result
39 and 3/4 in
Was one of the very first time
Scientists had calculated
The average size
I like humans
But he brings with it the idea of Truth
That the average
Chastise is true and that all the individuals are like error
That nature striving for the average Soldier
This means the average measurement is the
Truemeasureman
Platonic ideal
The perfect Scottish Soldier
Another joke
What is 39 and 3/4 inches
According to Cadillac
So he's the one that decides not only is average mathematical useful it's morally the way to think about people
And so he basically find averages anywhere he can possibly find them
And he measures all kinds of other people and averages them he create something called The Catalyst
Measuring ratios of average height and weight
Actually we still use it today
Just now it's called the body mass
Index
4 BMI
Hillywood say
If you talk about height
Everyone if they were optimally fed if they were under the same environmental conditions
Would have been average
So his view was that
What you're striving for
Is the continual Improvement of the average of the group
And it wasn't all just physical
Timberlake homes through various data sets
It's for marriages murders and suicides and calculates the averages for them
He figures out there such a thing as a normal suicide rate which is really really bizarre the
But I'm almost scandalous
Nowadays when we're so used to the stability of big massive amount of data
That is hard
Put your
Stuff in their shoes but like
Back then they really thought that
Something like to say
Suicide
With such a personal
Decision
And I couldn't possibly be any pattern there
But some of the word patterns
Body size intelligence
Birth of death
People became statistic
The behavior starts to become
Predictable
Suddenly human life
Went by the numbers
So obviously at the first interpretation is we'll wait a minute maybe there's no free well maybe there's laws of society
You just like the laws of physics
Black kick-started
A whole bunch of people like me like Karl Marx
To love cuddly
Until it becomes a huge star
This Time Cabaret was up there with the likes of Sir Isaac Newton
Is science of averages was this remarkable cutting-edge way to assess the health
Wellness and progress of population
He's really active in the 1820s and 1830s 1840s
I'm all the way up like the 50s and
The 1860s brings us
The US Civil War
Do another Super Fan of catalase Science of averages
Abraham Lincoln
When the Civil War
Is going in the North Lincoln
Actually
Kind of cleaner bucket Frank
Because this war had guns
So huge and unwieldy
Lincoln doesn't really have
Handle on the Northern Army
And
He's like we don't even know who our soldiers are we don't know
I will said they are we don't know what kind of armor they need we don't know anything about them
Lincoln decided that the Union Army needed more information about its soldiers
In order to best distribute resources
So he ordered this enormous study to assess the Union Army physically
Medically and Mentos
And then it explicit obedience to catalyze new science averages
Calculated and reported
They actually say basically we're following
The father of this new field cantlay
Bees freshly calculated averages
Informed the distributions of food ration
And the design of weapon
For example if you were going to create muskets
Well how far is the trigger
And you could actually calculate average reach for Soldier this also affected military uniform
Switch used to be all custom sound but in the Civil War so many people had to be outfitted
The custom uniforms would be impossibly expensive
So the uniforms had be mass-produced
But they couldn't be just all one big floppy size
And so now they're letting go
Will you know if you break it into into subtypes
Broad shoulders small medium large
That's going to carry over into the way they think about the mass production of clothing
Yep the sizes small medium and large
Which might be on your T-shirt tag
Those came out of this massive Civil War
So you can thank cataleya and Lincoln for that
This study in the Civil War was the basis for the American military's long-standing philosophy
Standardized
Average base design design philosophy
From the Civil War forward
So in 1926
When the Army was designing it
First ever fighter plane
Engineers measure the physical dimensions
Hundreds of male Pilots
And use this data to standardize cockpit
Quite the possibility of female pilot
Never considered
The size and shape of the seat that distance the pedals
Stick hide the windshield
Even the shape of the flight helmets were all made to conform to the average 1920s male pilot
Change the way the pilots were select
You basically then select people that fit into that and then exclude people that died
Design works okay
Up to World War II
What happened was though is that
In World War II
It became
An Air Force War right after the first time when the air force would be the determinant of
Who is going to win the war
And we we actually ran out of Pilots
The government recruited hundreds of new pilots
An expanded military Aviation
It's been a bunch of money on fancy new planes
Although
The cockpit
We're still design for the average 1920s male
And this new big bad military force was going to fly to fast
Listen to highest
Be the best
But that's not what happened they actually had a pretty massive decline in
Performance
Including to the rash
Pilots were dying all the time
Even after the war ended just in training they could not control airplanes it became kind of part of the culture of the
It's just really dangerous to fly
No one knew what was going on
Some people thought propeller planes anymore maybe these new pilots just can't deal with the new aviation technology
And then they were like well maybe you got to train them better and they did their better training programs and that didn't work
After blaming the pilot
The training programs in the technology
Finally dawned on them
What is the cockpit
Maybe it doesn't this anymore
Their first instinct is to think
We just got bigger the people so the old average for 1922 is just too small right which is bigger and badder
So in 1950 researchers at Wright Air Force Base in Ohio
Tasked with finding this new average
And one of those researchers
With a man named Gilbert s Daniels
Daniels was a Harvard graduate could written his thesis on the average sizes of his classmates hands
It was 23 years old
Small skinny nerdy
Not a military man at all
And he travels all the countries are Air Force bases
And his job is to take these tape measures
And just measure like 147 different dimensions
Tedious job ever and is Daniel's is traveling around
From Base to Base measuring thousands of Airmen
He's realizing this
Portable variability from person to person
Even within this limited demographic of young men
As he was measuring hands and legs and waist
4 heads
Daniel kept asking him
How many Pilots were actually average
So he reports back
So he goes limited like I think
I can get a problem with the average and he says I just want to do this
Decide study I want to know if we take the 10 dimensions of size that matter most
For design
Like save shoulder-width
I8
Chest circumference sleeve length
How many of these Pilots are actually average
Daniel's crunch the numbers
Andaba 4063 Pilots he measured
Not
Single Airmen
Was close to average
In all of the
The 10 dimensions
Naughty
Not one
And it got even worse like if you just used
Three dimensions of
Size
Less than 5% of the pilots were hours
So he quickly realizes like
Wait now you know the problem
If you are designing something for an average
Pilot it's literally designed if it nobody
And in this new era of jet-powered Aviation
Four Pilots were making split-second decisions that could be life or death
It really matter that Pilots could reach what they needed to reach in the cockpit
The military spring2action pretty much right away
For the military
Three willing to
Basically drop generations of
Design philosophy right it doesn't take them more than a few years to just be like you can't design an hour today
Air Force engineers and contractors designed adjustable foot pedals and adjustable helmet straps and flight suit
Adjustable seats
I just can't believe that we are building plans with no adjustable seat
That's how much faith we had in the average person once all the adjustable elements another design Solutions were put into place
Pilot performance
Sword
Of course now we take this for granted
What equipment should fit a wide range of body sizes
Instead of standardized around 1 Ave
You wouldn't buy a car
Crazy and it seeps into their pretty quickly in terms of automobiles
And then you see
What's interesting is the whole idea of
Ergonomics
That all comes off of the street at
What word jump-starts the science of ergonomics
Text which is not just for officer
Well it's really the study of work
Is what you
You could boil it down
But it really is a matter of matching
In people's
Capacity
To the job this is Professor Carissa Harris Adamson
Director of the UCSF UC Berkeley ergonomics
Program
It's
Really important not to go with the average
A lot of the time
If we want to
Incorporates a handle
Well we'll look up anthropometry data and
Make sure we identify
Span
Or if we're designing
Crank and we wanted to be at a certain height
Then we will go back to them
Data and figure out
What makes the most sense
To accommodate
Keeping in mind that in the US
Most of the measurements we base our designs on
Still
Company USR
Not
Primarily the
The source that we use
And
Say ergonomic bucks or when
What we found is that those numbers are actually all
Pretty representative today
Except for weight
An abdominal girth
Which is part of why the world is so hard for heavier people to navigate
The military might be considered a more fit pop
And then the rest
So does this mean that like military measurement
Affect
The way our cars are
Absolutely
The measurements of our military personnel over the years
Sfax just about
Military measurements are the most
And they work okay
You're not perfect
Sure but they're getting more
They've done a really good job in a company name or the population
Given that women are
Now very
Vibrant part
Of our military
When the military opted to design for a greater range of
People they designed for a greater range of opportunity
Take for example
Kim Campbell
She was a fighter pilot
And
She flew
A A-10 Warthog in it's worth Googling it is like the baddest looking
Playing you're ever going to see
That's tyros Again by the way helping us tell the story
Captain Campbell
In 2003 Campbell was sent on a mission to assess submarines who are trying to take a bridge in a rock
They were under heavy fire
But either way back or playing
Shot
And she loses all control
She has the option
Big Jack
Right there and save her life but then the plane
Spirals into Baghdad
I didn't kill too much
She stabilized what I don't know how you do
And she flies back and then she says
I think I can land This Plane
And she lands the massive damage.
Uncontrollable playing
It's an incredible heroic theme
Really I'm president
Of course Kim Campbell get Awards and distinctions
And she is someone who could have never been one of the best
Pilots in the world
Had the military not change their design philosophy
She's the beneficiary of a cockpit
Wesley design
Five four
Ralph n
And don't look anything remotely close to an average sized pile
When Kim gets into a cockpit she has to put the seat all the way up and pull the pedals
All the way out
But it fits
Does idea of equal fit as the foundation for How We Do
Think about real Whopper
Trade in society
SiriusXM
Future of design
In this concept
That's it makes opportunity
It's an important one for
Because he believes that we can design environments
Equipment and even entire system
To accommodate more and more
When we think about how we design environment
You know in a lot of fields
We made some progress around
Accommodating wider range
The people but actually in things like education we still actually design
For this mythical average person
Under the assumption that if you design something that fit an average person it would actually fit most
People
By re-examining the concept of the average
Etymology its limitations
We can maybe start to consider other ways of assessing and categorizing test scores
Clothing size
Wellness happiness worth
We can pave the way for more people
Or outside
Because
Really
No one
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman
Which refuse have Katie mingle Emmett Fitzgerald Kurt Kolstad Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Do want to know more maybe you want to know how average
Came to being subpar instead of ideal
Check out Todd roses book called the end of average
How we succeed in a world that values sameness
Play music for Apple okay akumi this week and lots of lullatone love lullatone full tracklist and links to
Purchase at 9 p.m.
We are project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced on radio row
The corridor of Broadway
We're all the radio is made
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Black podcast
We're taking off next week to take some deep breaths and recover from the extra work we've had to do with different people being
Away on vacation so look for us in two weeks
I hope you're taking some time off to
If you find yourself in need of a story I bet you can find when you didn't hear the first time on Monday.
Npr.org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
Maven
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com