99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Picture for a minute
Los Angeles
The Grand Marquis downtown
The Spanish style mansions in the Hills
The Jetsons like diners and Drive-In
Los Angeles is an architectural potpourri
It's a kind of place where if you want to go and build a house that looks like a Dutch
Colonial
Or a mansion with Doric columns
Square sleep modernist flat roof thing
That's fine
Anything Goes
That savory truffles
In Los Angeles architecture late there are no rules
No unifying Style
Because her people flocking to Hollywood in the 1930s 40s and 50s
The growing city gave them an opportunity to build whatever kind of house they wanted
French Chateau futuristic modern Italian Villa whatever
And there's this one particular architect
You can do it all
Do it well
And his name
Was Paul Revere
Williams
Paul Williams contribution to American architecture can be described in the number differ
This is architect
Phil freelon
It was a incredibly gifted
A residential designer
And on the West Coast
Quickly in Los Angeles
He was known for Designing residences
Of a number of Hollywood stars
Paul Williams design Frank Sinatra's bachelor pad
A mansion for Lucille Ball and Desi Arnaz
You made additions on the Beverly Hills Hotel in the Palm Springs Tennis Club
He also helped design the stately and sparse
LA County Courthouse
Have you ever flown into LAX
You can see this really space-age you looking structure
Looks like a flying saucer with long legs
That landed in front of Terminal 1
That's called the theme building
And Paul Williams was part of the team that made that
And the sheer volume of this work he produced over 3,000 projects in his career in his 50-year career
And that's
That's quite
Achievement
No one is exactly sure how many built
It's certainly in the thousands
But still
He was largely invisible figure
Architectural history
As well as Los Angeles
This history
He designed everything from mentions luxury hotels and car dealerships to hospitals housing
Republic schools
In addition to the variety of Williams commissions he could work in a huge variety of styles
Seriously if you pick two of his buildings at random
In most cases
You never know that the same Market
Text made them both
So you really didn't have
A particular signature move or
For more material usage
That you can drive up and say that's a Paul Williams building
But if you look at the body of work there is a level of
Excellence in
A consistency in the quality of the work not in this early in a in a stylist
He is the architect who helped make the multi Style
Style
Of Los Angeles
And Los Angeles intern
Helped make him
In Los Angeles Paul Williams was able to build a career for himself
30 probably couldn't have had anywhere else
South America
As an African-American Oregon
Poems
African American architect
Who is much more than an African-American architect
Simply one of the best
20th century this is Karen Hudson
Paul Williams biography
And also is granddaughter
As we're closer micro blackway
Hudson says the Los Angeles her grandfather grew up in back in the early 1900s
Was pretty different from what it is now
Community Open Spaces
He was born
Downtown
8th and Santee
Your downtown was a heart of La in 1894
And in 1894 when Williams was born Los Angeles was pretty much a small downtown surrounded with
Beanfields in Orange Groves and the wild Pacific
In the population of LA was skyrocketing
From 1890 to 1900 the city doubled from 50000 to 100,000 residents
In just 10 years
The growing city was full of people that had come West for a better life
Paul Williams as parents were from Memphis
And had moved to Los Angeles just before he was born
They came to California for their health
Because they both
Had tuberculosis
And that's how he was orphaned before he was 4
Williams was raised by foster parents
Get a brother who is 9 years older than him who was raised in a different family
And died at a young age of pneumonia
That much of a family of his own
William spent a lot of time in the neighborhood
Downtown LA
Which is full of immigrants from all over the world
I mean he talks about
Learning
Conservation in
Gardena things for the Japanese kids in the neighborhood and
Cesar suck down that up
In this diverse group of kids all went to school together even though Paul Williams remembers being the only black head
There were no segregated schools in LA
Blackheads
But the ones I go get it this would be instrumental later in life
When his High School connections would prove
Very valuable
And Paul Williams is career
It's hard to say exactly where Williams desire to be an architect
Came from
He did have a natural talent for drawing
And then
Somehow he learns that architecture was a profession
And then resolutely decided it was for him
What is kind of incredible when you think about it
He never knew another architect never relieved
Heart of another rock
When Williams told his high school guidance counselor that he wanted to practice architecture
He was told to give it up
He should not try to be an architect he should be a doctor or a lawyer because black people always need doctors and lawyer
And why people would not hire him as an architect in black people can afford them so
So he should just give up
Didn't happen
Williams didn't go to architecture school
Instead he attended different art schools and engineering school just cobbling together the skills he needed in draft
Landscaping materials
Before he was certified as a contractor in 1915
And then came the challenge of actually getting hired
His own notes he said he got
Dressed in his best suit and
I wish you're probably only had one for church but
Best suit Hazel briefcase
Wood knocking on doors
He approached all the architects in the area that he admired
And show them his portfolio
They all
Said no but they smile when they said no
Then he went back the next day
And kept knocking
I finally got two offers one for $3 a week maybe five and one for nothing
But he took the job that was for nothing because he thought you would learn more and being a better person
Paul Williams work for landscape architect residential architect and a commercial
Attack before he was licensed to practice in California in 1921
The following year he started his own firm
Paul R Williams
And Associates
Williams's first
Solo Commission
Was a house for a well-connected high school friend
And is neighborhoods in Los Angeles blossomed word about William spread
In a 2003 thirties if you go to dinner at somebody's house
Do they have a new house as if we drive Jacksonville has one more one more one more
Williams had an impeccable sense of scale
And he knew just how to situate a structure on a property to make best use
Beautiful views in sunlight
He helped create what would come to be known
As the Hollywood style
That opulent mixture of Mediterranean European and Colonial influences
With swimming pools and sweeping staircases
It's a rich and Sumptuous Sensibility
The pole Williams kept these Mansions very clean and classy
Paul R Williams & Associates group quickly
And became renowned
Although some clients would be taken aback when they met with
Because you know they may have read about him
Anime of heard about him but they didn't realize
He didn't want people to be uncomfortable
And often they were
I mean one thing
The hire somebody it's one thing
To think that he's the best around you want the best around it's another thing.
Many of his white client had never interacted with a black professional Buffet
Williams had to find ways to work around white people discomfort with
He would not put people in a position where they felt like they had to shake his head
So you would put his hands in his pockets or behind his back
And Williams also recognized that many clients wouldn't want to take a seat next
And
So to make them feel comfortable and to
Possibly persuade people who aren't sure
About having this black man
He gets in a one-sided sqb on the other side
And he would ask you
Yo
Do you want a formal living room do you want a formal dining room do you want to
Add an because you have little kids
Do you want this to want that
And then
Facing the client opposite the table
Paul Williams with sketch out of vision of the house
Upside down
So that it faced the client
And he was sketching upside down and come alive
Before your eyes
I said I never interviewed anyone who saw him do it
Who did not just light up
You should have stayed a
You've heard the expression Ginger Rogers did everything Fred Astaire did except backwards and in high heels
Bill polian
Did everything is white peers.
Except upside down
And better
Williams was not the first architect
Draw upside down
But it's indicative of the lengths he went to accommodate his white client
He always dressed impeccably
And worked
Tirelessly
He wants word about a meeting with a potential client who warned Williams that he was also speaking with a number of Other Ark
The potential client as how soon Williams could submit preliminary drawings
For tomorrow afternoon
Set volume
The client thought it was impossible because all the other Architects had asked for two or three weeks
And you can bet that yes Paul Williams delivered that planet for the next day as promised
They didn't tell the client that a work
22 hours straight without eating or sleeping
He felt like he had to be light years
Better just to be accepted
And you know if he wasn't accepted
Sometimes Williams was unwelcome in the very places
He was designing and even after he earned the respect of his client
Kid to tolerate mistreatment from subcontractors and Painters and plumbers
Can you hire him
Do your home
And then
Some of the sub people
For working on a Hummer like
Taking orders with black guy
Is a regular kind of thing
Throughout his career
Even as he designed mansions for wealthy clients
Williams also designed affordable homes
From middle-class angelinos
Republic books of inexpensive construction patterns that anyone could use
To Build A Home of Their Own
You could send them for $10 and get floor plan for your house
Williams also worked on a number of projects specifically for black institutions including buildings on Howard University
Duke campus in DC
And the 28th Street YMCA
Which is in a historically black neighborhood in LA
20th Street why was very important to him
He put in the facade
Likenesses of Frederick Douglass and Booker T Washington
People leave
Thaddeus young black boys could see that Excellence every day as they walked in or make
Kind of person
He did a lot of charitable work
He
Did lots of things for children and not just an African American
What he designed st. Jude's Research Hospital in Memphis
He did it completely
Free of charge
And he simply was one of the most prolific architects of his time
Of any race
Keep produce thousands of projects in his 50-year career
He died in 1980
And his funeral was held in a church of his own design
Toulouse France
Family
Impact client
Paul R Williams & Associates
Continued working without him
For a while
Well after he died in 1980
The office went on for a couple of years I'm not quite sure how long it but it
Essentially came to an end sometime by the end of the 80s
This is Leslie leavers of the University of Memphis
And then all of the material
From his
Practice was stored at a branch of the Broadway Federal Savings Bank
And this Branch was a building Williams design
He designed it but the more important thing was that one of his daughters
Marriage the founder of Broadway
Federal so it was essentially a family
Relationship
And most of Williams documents and records were just there in the bank
Stored in a room
They weren't even in a vault
But then in 1992 after a group of officers were acquitted of the brutal beating of Rodney King
The city of La
Fit into violent protests
That branch of Broadway
Federal burn to the ground and everything in it burn to the ground and that was
Pretty much the end of everything available about Paul Williams
This is where the Paul Williams project comes in
Nicole Williams
Project is
Primarily a research project that seeks
Text to accumulate information photograph
Etc about
Paul Williams Pennsylvania his career
And a big part of this project was actually collecting information
And hunting down which buildings were designed by Williams
The project which is based at the University of Memphis
Send a photographic team to Los Angeles
Palm Springs
In Las Vegas
To start a catalog
Paul Williams building
But they were not always easy to find
Because he was a master at. Style
So
He would have
A
Spanish style house next door
Volume style house next to a
French
Provincial style house or gothic style
Okay
The project has found less than half of Williams were
Who knows how many of his buildings have been unknowingly torn down or renovated beyond recognition
And the poems project is always hearing about more buildings to add to the catalog
Mostly in Los Angeles but not exclusively
Williams buildings are all over the country
And there are few were brought we discovered them all the time
And then we verify we verify every house
So we go to the
City documents
When pulling permits
All of that
They are constantly checking and correcting themselves
But it's really tough word because they have to go buy accounts and Records which were mostly burned and then
You know Williams of style is just all over the place
He just didn't stick the one thing he was always learning and developing
And
Of course you would listen to his clients
Trying to respond to
What they needed
And what their desires were
That's architect Phil freelon again
And I asked him
If Williams had to be responsive to his clients
Flexible in his style
In order to survive the black market
I think that Paul Williams desire to satisfy his clients is something that many Architects chair
It's not necessarily
Tied to race
Although I will point out that
He had
To make
Certain adjustments in his
Approach to clients
Because of who he was and
The time. In which
She practice
By the way I feel free line is also a big deal
You worked on the Museum of African diaspora in San Francisco the center for civil and human rights in Atlanta and moose
Most recently national museum of African American history and culture
On the mall in Washington
Where I was the architect of record
To Fremont had already gotten into an architecture program
And before he had even heard
Paul Williams
How's baby into my third and fourth year of school before I learned about
And that was really on my own
It wasn't anything
In the curriculum are in architectural history that mention him
Let's make this clear
There are a lot of black architects who get left out of the textbook
Paul Williams was not the first black architect in America
But he was the first to be accepted as a member of the AIA
American Institute of Architects
The American Institute of Architects is the
Leading Professional Organization
The US
Relations.
Saxon and others
In the profession
Paul Williams join the AIA in 1923
And every black architect I know
I know who Paul Williams
And
Haven't met a wife
Architecture
Knew who I was talking about if I were to mention that name
Can we need to change that
And this is why Phil freelon nominated Paul Williams for the AIA highest individual award
The gold medal
It's basically the award that welcomes an architect
Into the Canon of all-time great
Previous winners include Frank Lloyd Wright
Mies van der rohe
Bugaboo CA
Thomas Jefferson
And now
Paul Williams will officially join their ranks
37 years after his death
This award means a lot to freelon
And other African American architects
In terms of General visibility a few African American architects
Working in this country
Relatively speaking
Go 2% of licensed architects
Does country or black
And one of the ways you
Would want to combat that is to raise the visibility into
Make sure people know
Great profession in the young people see it has a
That's a possibility
And as an option
For them
And ultimately this award is about recognizing a master
A recognition that is long overdue
Paul Williams develop The Eclectic style of the California home and helped shape the look and feel of Asia
Just as much as Los Angeles
Shaved him
The man who can draw magnificent plan in any style
Upside down
And better
Did most of his peers
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery Shuffle
Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman Mars
Speaking to me Roman Mars I'm up for a People's Choice Webby Award for best podcast host
So please vote for me I would like to win that
Link to it in the show notes
Katie mingle is our senior editor that is the digital director intern Meza is off
Be all original music in this episode was composed by Sean real
Social things this week to Taylor Hamilton Bonnie Boswell and Bradford Grant
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God.
You can find the show angel in discussions about the show on Facebook you tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99p
Cyborg run Instagram and Tumblr to
But we were released at least two articles about design and architecture
Every week on our website
99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com