99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Almost without fail an architectural Draft starts with one straight line
Another
And another
Succession of clean orderly lines until eventually
A building emerges
And it makes sense that straight lines form the core of our built environment
The cost-efficient materials like wood and steel and pipes
Demonstrate linear units
LOL that's a bit of a tautology
But it's certainly easier to calculate structural loads on rectilinear surfaces
StraightLine dawnlod
Predictable
And they are completely devoid of humanity
So says producer Luisa back
Actually it's not my argument
It's disguise
Play straight line is called Le saint-amour LV straight line is not a crazy flying
Southern imitating Lyme Alliance
A color-blind
This is thousands of credence like being tagged
Donkey bones
Hundertwasser
In German that means multi-talented peace filled rainy day dark-colored hundred Waters
It's a name he gave himself
Yeah no kidding which makes sense because balloons
Radical selfie
Expression was everything
Ohms buildings are subject to censorship
Cages of savings
This is from a speech who never gave in 1983
At the architectural Association in London
He was known for giving talks
Wear mismatched wild colored
Socks and wacky hat
Showing up completely naked
He was fully clothed
She looked out into a room full of Art Attack
And told them they were criminals
Planning lifeless rigid structures that restricted human creativity
The time has come for people to defend against it from find my Uber chemical structures like is enough
What time is in cages
In confinement versus aliens
One of us I was born fleetlease to Vasa in 1928
He made a name for himself
How to speak
As a painter
Does known for squeak abstract nearly psychedelic
Paintings
And in 1985 he completed a building
Apartment complex in its home city of Vienna hundertwasser house looks as if one of his paintings have been made manifest
Full of a symmetrical shapes wacky colors clashing patterns mismatch windows and undulating on
Even floors
There are no Godless
Straight line
What's inside
Working together with Architects and engineers
Una taza went on to design more build
All over
His work
Really sticks
Out in that
City
Almost all the other buildings there are stately baroque
Draw the 1980s and 90s
Una pasiva Naja design all kinds of other stuff
Structures
Like gas stations heating plans in schools
And his well-known extended Beyond Vienna
She was hired to design buildings in Germany
Japan
New Zealand
He made one building in the US
A winery in Napa Valley
Is architecture is festooned with golden orbs in onion domes
Zigzagging tiles
Trees that grow out of apartment Window
Dreamed of creating indoor Moss
Hardwood floors
Though he was never able to get that
I think you get it
Thunder roster design some crazy looking building
Mini architectural circles dismiss Hunter Vasquez work as catch
They look like buildings from dr. Seuss or Pee-wee's Playhouse or any number of children's cartoons
I actually got them built
And to him they weren't ischemic
Real
People live in his belt
Just trying to reframe what the built environment can be
To reimagine what architecture is
Supposed to do
Today architect
Today architecture is criminally sterile
He says
One of these Hornets outside buildings
Brandon McGee blog
The city where I was born
MacBook is in what used to be communist East Germany
And it's one of those cities full of endless grids and straight line
It's rows and rows of
Gray's soviet-style apartment blocks in postwar Arkansas
Until
You walk onto the Main Street in the city centre
Unaccounted
Huge
8 story tall
Castle
In this Castle is bright bright pink
Salmon pink
And it's decorated with brown tile
Squiggles
Like big ceramic Vines creeping up the
Pinkwall
They're almost 900 Windows of all different shapes and sizes
And 150 different lollipop looking columns
Hold up the building
Dance floors
On the roof
Eight golden spheres rise triumphant
Like sons of the doll homogeneous block
Around them
Parts of the roof slope all the way down to the street and it's covered in trees
This is why even though
The building is mostly pink
It's called the green Citadel
President of monster bull crap
With what to make of this gigantic
Treetop
Salmon pink
Castle
Everyone has different opinions about it
Including my grandpa
Who live about a 20 minute walk
Jack from the Beanstalk
$2 in my pocket
I talked to them about it the last time I went back to his
And I understand.
My grandpa says he thinks it looks like a monkey
Things you don't see nothing hours
I asked him why
Any grants about the colorful facade and wavy surface
It just doesn't fit Adam you're the fattest
At my grandma she likes
In fact
She like to live in
Ebates
The same as I do
It's so typical
Instrumental
What does my grandmother describes it
Quotes
The 40 communist years we lived in the same concrete high-rise
And here is an apartment building that represents the unique
Each president
And who never realized
In my opinion she says
It should be more buildings like
Too bad he passed away
Plants of the green Citadel began in 1996 after the fall of the Berlin Wall
Hunter Vassar died in 2000 while at Sea on the QE2
The green Citadel was completed five years later percent of the green Citadel
Covered in grass
In the building has 100 PSI called
Free tenant
Trees that were planted into
Special rooms inside of people's apartment
And his ideas about how to incorporate Flora into buildings
Didn't stop
With plants and trees
When did father was also really into mold
Like the kind of mold that grows in the back of the fridge
Animal
Exhibits unusual characters
David moss grows over to give it the changes
Open house
Together with mushrooms and vegetation
Life moves into a dollhouse
And it's delightful at Hunter Bowser's warped and kaleidoscopic buildings are
The exaltation of mold
Is where he and I part ways
At least we know we didn't suffer from allergies
Instead of TV is it better to watch nature Grovyle
And grow out of human control
For instance in the case of
Spontaneous
Oh boy was big on manifestos
He had another one that he called
And I am not making this up
The holy manifest
Every time but use the flush toilet
Rethink it isn't hygienic accomplishments
Button factory violet
The laws of nature
We pray before we eat in Boise Grace afterwards
But we do not pray Vanquish
Everything taking humans away from nature or any of our
Natural processes
Was an affront to Hunter Vassar
So his buildings were designed to keep us more in touch with our disgusting organic reality
If we do not treasure hours
And if we do not transform it into hummus
In honor of Cottontail belt will lose all right to be present on this Earth
Hummus is the part of the soil that's rich and dark with organic matter
Moon opposite had proposed
To plan natural urine purification systems and compost toilets in his building
Although his investors wouldn't back indoor compost toilets in the green Citadel when Louisa was last in Germany
She talked her way into the building
Is it the shower that he put in
For the bathroom they use
Is blue tiles as a rim
And also knows
There's no straight line
None
I visited a bathroom in the green
Citadel
I didn't see any composting toilet
I didn't even see anymore
What I did see though
We're crazy pattern
Do you have
Round corners all over the apartment there are no
Sharp and crisp
Furniture
Nicole Zendaya and her Partner's apus
Austin live in the green Citadel
Set with two bathroom
First one with the top and one with the
Just a shower
The bathroom tiles are
Staggered and slightly shift
It's sideways
So that they don't line up and call them
In some places there tells a diagonal
A shattered and their fragments put back together to form a unique mosaic-like pattern
They showed me around their play
Are you see this is a different kind of window
It opens up all the way in
I got that
Round on top of it
Now we'll get into the parts of Hunter vossers Manifesto Bladen worldview that is
Blissfully free of mold and excrement
And appeals to our sense of individuality
Set the goal was to construct
Creative life
Style for the people who live
And worked in and around
The green Citadel
He designed the building to encourage residence
Individuality to shine Ford
And it wasn't just in terms of how we build
Part of it with the rules that governed
Apartment house tenant must have the freedom
Julion Alvarez
And as far as his hand raised to change the outside walls of his feelings
When is the second curridge residents to lean out of the window
And paint the facade around them any Colour and design they want
He called this concept
Ben Stein
Play Store
Right of window
Chainsaw Transformer is outside his searching as far as his arm
So that from 584 Bay Street everyone can see the eclipse in Miami
Who distinguishes himself
From his neighbor
Then
The other place
When he says prisoners he's referring to you and me
Betty White
Clothes are your second skin your home is your third
If we choose our own clothes why shouldn't renters choose the colors for the outside walls
At least around the window
Hunter monster believe that residents painting their Windows their homes
Would be a form of Their Own self-expression
He wasn't explicitly demanding that residents clean out their windows and paint the borders around them
But he was hoping to design and environment
I would encourage them to do it of their own free will
I asked Sebastian and Nicole the green Citadel residents if they thought about taking them up on his right of window idea
We didn't but technically the righteous there
A trip hanging out the 4th floor
Of your window to try to change something I'm not going to do that
I'm having a hard time cleaning the windows
So far only one person has taken hold of us up on the right of window here
And the modifications were pretty minor
And now residents need to apply to claim their fence to ride the building manager told me that he hasn't received a c
Single application from anyone else requesting to paint the exterior facade around their window
To exercise their fence.
We took a quick pull here in the office and both Sam and I would be a little too intimidated to haphazardly paint the out
Outside of our window on an already amazing building
Avery would be leaning outside to paint on day one
And Katie would be out there on a window washers rig painting up a storm in a hot minute
I definitely love the right window idea even if I wouldn't necessarily participate
But it also feels a little like
Forest fun
Like being required to take a day off of work to play wacky games their co-workers and a company retreat
Or audience participation that stick
Dinner theater
We're having a pop album appear automatically on your phone
It's mainly fun for people designing the experience
Stop the irony in all of this
When did Father fought against architectural Doctrine
So that people could be free to
To express themselves
Loneliest
She wanted them to
In many ways in addition to being brilliant objects of Art
Underbosses buildings were like concept car
High fashion
Three wheeled car with a bubble roof for
6ft tall fur hats are not meant for the mass Market
The radical concept smooth Norm forward
You certainly do not want house for the mall
You really don't it's terrible
But just try to find an urban s these days
Who is not all for green roofs
And that's what the big talking naked speech-giving Manifesto Riders of the world
R4
99% invisible with Bruce's sweet by Louisa back with Avery trufelman Sam Greenspan Katie mango
Go and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced in beautiful down
Downtown Oakland California out of the offices of arcsin
We check in with on so many of our stories
I think as a reaction to Eastern European Soviet Bloc style architecture
It makes a lot of sense
Well I want to see this become the norm probably not but
I think it's always healthy to have a variety of things
This is about
A city who has the
The foresight to say yeah these are pieces as architecture
Are important
I shudder to think at the number of little mistakes we would make if we didn't have Adam and Daniel in the whole crew dark sign
It's right next to us to answer our questions
Thanks for being there guys
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
I can find the show and
All of us
Story Hinckley
Pictures and links
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com