99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
As baseball fan probably know the Washington Nationals came to the US by way of Canada
They used to be the Montreal Expos
The team packed up and left Canada in 2005 and they left behind their name
Logo
Their uniforms
And maybe most importantly
Their mascot
UB
That's our Canadian friend Andrew Norton
He has a special connection to you B
It's actually my dad who had the special connection to you B
He died about eight years ago and his relationship with UB is something that I'm still trying to
Square
Okay so
A little bit about my day
He was the boring
He always fell asleep at the movies Pinocchio
Toy Story
Dude was out cold
Family trips were playing with
Efficiency and Thrift as the primary object
And at our house
We subscribe to the one newspaper that didn't have a comic sex
He was definitely not into things that could be classified as
Fun but he had this one quiet obsession
It was rotund
Orange
Free
Six and a half feet tall
UB
U p
Spelled you
PPI and always with an exclamation mark
It's French for
Yippee you know like
Mangia
Honestly haven't looked at you pee in a while
That's my sister Jessica
Wearing her basement while her kids are asleep and we're looking at photos of you pee on my phone
Daiso UPI no
Orange fuzzy wearing cleats Expos hat
Ill-fitting axle shirt
And then like
Googly eyes
But an approachable face
UB looks like an orange haired bearded Lumberjack cross with a Sasquatch wearing a baseball jersey
You can picture that right
It was one of your kids at my sister and I started noticing our dads affection for you p
He light up when we see him at Expos game
I need look for him on TV
He hated when
The game would get cut to commercial because like that would be prime up time
You keep right on the side of my dad that we just didn't recognize
All of a sudden like you're just a
This guy who love
The mascot
To the point where you
You clip a picture of him
Are the newspaper
And put them on the side of the fridge
An article on the fridge might not sound like a big deal
Before this the only other article here
Ever posted up
What about Canada's new sales tax rate
Then suddenly it's
It should be noted that when the Expos move to DC to become the Nationals
You be switched
Sports and found a job with the Montreal hockey team called the Canadiens
My dad died just after that and all these years later I can't help but wonder what it was
About u p that spoke to his long-repressed
Whimsical
And it's not just Andrews.
So many grown adults can't resist hugging and posing for selfies with mascot
Even though it's just someone in a concert
Darren Tran
Well I mean is the definition of a mascot like it it comes from actually the the French word mascot
A little slang word which actually means which
That's a jmass writer for espn.com and author of a book all about sports mascots
Call yes
It's hot in here
He was also the dude inside the Mr Met costume from 1994 till 1997
In 1997 when Bill Clinton was visiting Shea Stadium the Secret Service pulled AJ aside while he was in his
Mr Met costume and told him
If you approach the president
We go for the kill shot
According to AJ the word mascot
Came to America in the late 1800s through a French
That was called
La mascot
I'll buy
A guy named Audria
The offer is about a down-on-his-luck farmer who's visited by this girl named
Patina
As soon as she rolls up
Magically his crops are doing well in his life
All thanks to this mysterious woman
And it became very popular in the United States
Stand
Terminology
Kind of caught on when people realize and recognize head mascot means good luck
And this idea of a mascot
Fit right in with a notoriously superstitious
Is world of pro baseball
You know there was a situations where like there be a kid in the Stanwood smile at a baseball player in a slump
He get a base hit and he give the kid tickets for the next day
And you know and suddenly he's going a big hitting streak and so he would be like
Hey I want this kid to hang around all the time and that's kind of where mascots became these the human good luck charm
Like John the Orangemen
Who was well
A Man Who Sold oranges outside the stadium at Harvard
And Yale adopted
Handsome Dan Bulldog they walked out onto the field before games
Anything that was sort of a round at the time of a team's hot streak
Could and would be claimed as a mascot
It was pretty much all animals and bystanders until the second World War
That's when one baseball game altered the idea
Mascots in sports
Yeah this game took place in Hawaii and it was an exhibition game made up of servicemen
Pitching was kind of a lanky goofy looking guy
Find the name of Mac
Patent
The legendary Joe DiMaggio stepped up to the plate and hits massive home run off
The Story Goes it's a Baldwin into the Pacific Ocean
And packing just snaps
Ski jumps off the mound
This is the picture okay he jumps off the mound
And runs after DiMaggio
People thought he was like going to attack him or something but actually he just
Ran behind him mimicking his home run trot
And the crowd just went nuts
So he kept doing this act throw those servicely exhibition games
A picture
His dick was sort of a mix of Jim Carrey in Ace Ventura
Meets the dance moves of your drunk uncle at a wedding
Meats like a Parisian mine
And when the war was over packing stop being a picture and was hired by the
The Cleveland Indians
To do his thing at home game to help dry and cracked
It was the first time a mascot did more than just stand around being lucky
He entertained people
God knows people need that a baseball game
So now thanks to pack and we had this idea of a mascot as a diversion
But there's still a big evolutionary step to get to the mascots we know today
Yeah that the turning point
Certainly has to begin and end with the chicken
The San Diego chicken who can really only be described as a dude in a chicken suit
In 1974
The San Diego radio station KGB FM higher. College kid by the name of Ted Ginn newest where at
Chicken suit and do promotion for the radio station
Ingenuous got into it
Like
Really into it
The chicken have bravado
He had Swagger he was like an obnoxious frat boy and a bird
He danced on the field at San Diego Padres game
Grab people's beer and pretend to chug it
And the Padres were such a bad team that people started
Going just so they could see the chicken perform
And that's where the San Diego chicken kind of was born he was this
This marketing tool for the radio station that kind of
Suddenly became bigger than the team itself
She was eventually fired from the radio station because
On such a life of its own
Seokjin ules got his own chicken
Keppra forum
The station actually suit him
Embossed
Because it's you can't
You can copyright the idea of
Guy in chicken suit
Kids
You can't copyright the idea of a guy
In a chicken suit
The chicken was a big deal
Even though he wasn't in
Official team mascot
Kid become a Nike
He created the modern mascot movement
Even so by the late seventies the mascot scene was still pretty Barren by today's standards
Only a handful of baseball teams
Technically had Mass
Like the Philadelphia Phillies
They had a pair of characters called Phil and Phyllis
Steel prop
They weren't mascots they were props
Picture if you dressed a couple of those
Big Boy Restaurant statues in colonial garb
They were these big
Plaster characters that would
Kind of waddle out for the national anthem or if there's a homerun
So when the Philly saw with the chicken was doing in San Diego
They were like
We got to get us some of that
The Phillies found someone to custom design a mascot to entertain their fans
And before she came on board
They warned her that
Fans in Philly could be a little
Unforgiving
They said well we just want you to know
Our crowd
In Philadelphia booed
The Easter Bunny
Best designer Bonnie Erickson
And The Bling the Easter Bunny story is actually an urban legend
But Eagles fans did one spelled Santa with snowballs during the game
Bonnie had no experience
The Sports World when she took the gig
She and her husband and business partner Wade Harris and had just started their own design outfit
And they got
Phillies job
Thanks for recommendation by Bonnie's
Former employer
Jim Henson
V jimin
Muppets Fraggle Rock Sesame Street
Bonnie Erickson designed Miss Piggy
In The Muppet Show hecklers Statler and Waldorf
I wonder if there's anything she is
Choosing what show to be on
She also worked with Henson on making life-size version of the Sesame Street care
Doctors for their Sesame Street on ice
So she knew how to make a costume that people could perform and move
Which was A New Concept when it came to mask
Chobani got to work on this new mascot in the meantime the Phillies had to find someone to
Stuff inside of it and face those Santa hat clean crowns
They needed the lowest man on the totem pole the intern to raise his hand and say yes
Message Dave Raymond who was that intern
He was brought on board to do things like
County all star game voting
He had no background as a performer aside from some dabbling with
Disco
Nevertheless
She would be the performer inside this new mask
Because of some delays we didn't see the costume until the very night that I was going to wear it end and that that's when I started getting
Little bit distress because I started realizing everyone else thought this was a stupid idea
And and I was truly going to be thrown to the wolves
The Phillies weren't even promoting the fact that they were getting a new mascot
In case the whole thing just
Completely backfire
They can do like mascot mascot did you see a mascot I didn't say mascot but I was reassured when I first
I opened the box and I was blown away with how
How perfect it look
The Phillie Phanatic was born
If This Were a superhero movie this would be when the dramatic music comes on
But the fanatic is definitely not a comic book superhero
It's all green fur like very furry fuzzy fur
Very very large and rotund
Pear-shaped body with a huge belly and a kind of a duck butt
Stirrup socks Phillies hat in the Phillies Jersey
Perfect you know that's not all make sense
No no it doesn't make any sense that the Phillies mascot would be a big googly eyed monster
But it turns out that every part of the fanatic is like
Omastar
Glass in mask
For starters
He's green
Not the standard Phillies red
Right exactly
Police always easy to
To spot The Fanatic in any of these
And the Duck Butt
And a pear-shaped body no matter how you move in that costume if you're a human being and you put one leg in front of the other
That costume looks funny
Now when I look at the fanatic it's so clear that there's Muffet DNA
Even the placement of a cartoon googly eyes
Is something that Bonnie learned from her time designing Muppets
You are asking for all my secrets
Well if you put ice
Tie on a fish
Figures
Face
They will look older
He put them down closer to
To the nose
They'll probably look younger and more childlike
Plus there's other mascot first that she borrowed from the Muppets
Like she designed the fanatic with licensing
In merchandising
Toys t-shirts
And like all the characters
The Fanatic even has his own origin
He's supposedly from the Galapagos Islands
The Paddock is Goofy
You know he rubber ball dude head or rip off the hat of someone cheering for the wrong team
And usually he gets away with it
It's just damn near impossible to get irate with a fuzzy green thing
The one time he did get pummeled by Tommy was sort of the coach of the LA Dodgers
What I had
Had it with the fanatic on TuneIn
That's the quickest time he's moved all year
We got a Mark that down
The quickest Tommy Lasorda moving
Was after the
Philly Phanatic
And of course that just made the Phillies fans love him even more
Dave Raymond play the Philly Phanatic from that first game in 1978 until 1993
He only ever missed five home games
Now all but three major league baseball teams have mascots and most of them are big
Infirmary
Goofy in a googly eyes
Everyone sense with an addict
China
In a way copying
Intercourse Bonnie
Captioning work
After we did The Fanatic
The next one that we were asked to do because of the popularity of the character
I was for Montreal for the Expos
Yep Bonnie Erickson also created you
And when I told her about the inordinate amount of a
Affection my dad had for the mascot
She recalled once seeing a big Burly guy coming to the Expo stadium with some up dolls in the shop
Dieta position them so that they would have their heads
Sticking out
As if they couldn't breathe
If they fart
Skip it and I thought that was very touching
The mascot still lives in the sort of limbo between the two worlds he's not quite part of the team but not
Quite part of the fanbase either
I think that's the power for mascot
What fan of a team wouldn't want to be able to have that freedom to mock the other team and get a response
I think a big part of it for my dad was this aspect of living vicariously
UB what's your spirit animal
The Brad Pitt to his Edward Norton
You be good belly slide across the Expos dugout
Take me up to task will the whole stadium cheer them on
Steal a kiss from Celine Dion after a show-stopping rendition of
Oh Canada
UPS have fun dude
I can see that
Maybe
Secretly
My dad was to
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Andrew Norton with Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman
Mars we are product 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
An architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter and Instagram Avery runs the Tumblr I make the Spotify play
List of 99 Pi songs but I encourage you to explore the entire world of 99% invisible
1099 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com