99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
Logos used to be a thing that people really didn't give much thought to
The last decade the volume and intensity of arguments about logos have increased substantially
This is just the internet being
The internet but logo redesign in particular a lot of hyperbolic vitriol
I was wondering what this felt like to desiigner so I talked to one of my favorites
Michael bierut is an aiga medalist and partner at the international design consultancy pentagram
What is work includes brand identity logos book design and packaging
At this point I'm talking with them I just thought I'd put a conversation hours it down episode
Many of you might be familiar with the logos be discussed but if you need a little help jog your memory this is a great episode
Go to listen to as you scroll that the images
On this episodes webpage
At 99 Pi. Org
Michael says that for a very long time
No one understood what his job
As a graphic designer really meant
But recently
That's changed
Aren't you at now a lot of times people will say
Also do you do logos or though alright ask me what I think of
Awesome logo this in the news and this is entirely
New and
Kind of startling
Unnerving
What is the most recent logo they've asked you
Let me ask about your own logo
Oh yeah oh yeah yeah I know I was like as if they didn't know
Absolutely I was back in early 2015
I was engaged in a secret project
Which was to design a logo for
For the campaign of
As of yet on
McLaren Canada
President Hillary
Quinton
And
It launched there was a
Huge amount of attention
Chivas logo witch
Became ubiquitous
I think the age with the arrow in it
And at one point before it was widely known that I was a designer but I got an email from a magazine say
That they were convenient
A bunch of
Designer is to volunteer to say how they would
Design the logo
Cuz it was so horrible
And so like we'd like to know how would you design if you could have done anything and I sort of
You know I just said all you know
I think I'll pass
So tell me a bit more how they Hillary logo
It used to be that people would run for
Political office and they didn't understand
But they needed a while ago and maybe they didn't
Need a logo
Barack Obama changed all that in
2008 Duran and
He had this now famous
O for Obama
In blue with sort of
Red
Stripes leaving
Into the center of the o with
The old-time symbolizing
A setting or probably more likely a rising sun
And that symbol was so ubiquitous both
In 2008 the fact that he one kind of sealed the deal
It appeared
Over the next eight years representing his candidacy in the world
Go on to Brandeis Zoom
Foundation
Library
Post presidential activities
With that kind of established as a
The benchmark
For political campaigns
By the time
2016 rolls around every candidate
One way or another had one bailout logo and very early on in
Beginning of the year I got a call from
Team that was
Was Consulting with Hillary
Frequently asked me whether I
Would volunteer my services
Create a logo for secretary Clinton
And what we wanted to do was exploit some of the
Characteristics that
People would come to appreciate I think
Possibly by accident
And about the Obama wall
One of which was that it could be adapted
Two different forms you could have
You could kind of why customized at four different groups
The Boulders are different
Locations
Senso
We have this idea like what if we had a symbol that you could
Change every day if you want
If you can make it
Celebrate
LGB
Meteorites one day and celebrate Veterans the next day and then modified
For Memorial Day the day after that or Halloween the day after that
Listening very simple
So we can wrap this very simple h
With an arrow going
Kind of symbolizes
We thought that the candidate was moving
Country forward and also
Forgiving us
A way to
You kind of
Point that age that other thing
Meaning that Hillary
Or better in
Meteorites
For me
And it just kind of like proved to be a really
Malleable weibley
System in the air
This sort of
Device
For one thing no one really
Boats
Logos they both
Candidates
Play button a boat for people who they say
Think will improve their wives and some actual not
People that flashy logos
You know often if some
Tangible symbol will crystallize in the voting Public's mind
10 lbs and see what a candidate is and I think
Just as
You know Hillary perhaps had that
With an arrow in it
By the time
Election day
You know I was seeing it everywhere and
And certain way
You know what the convention
Tencent Javits Convention Center that night
For the
Party
People had an embroidered on
Temporary tattoo
Leatherface is it was every
You know the same time her opponent had a red hat
What's up with the slogan on the front of it you know in that in a way was a logo for that
So I think there's a substance of what people are promising
And there's
Sort of the
Tangible bit of shorthand
Thumbs up
That promise is
And I think that in the commercial world that's what symbols have always done
You know you're meant to
Kind of ascribe all sorts of higher
Transcendent values of things like a
Basketball sneakers end
Soda
Soda pops in Owen instead the transcended values with them athletic achievement
Refreshment
Respectively
And somehow devices
Spike's wishes or dynamic ribbons or whatever you want to say
TriStar kind of meant to be the holders
Does that mean ain't that
Is then
Reinforced Viagra
Fertilizing and buy
Hopefully actual for Santa
Experienced with
Product
Is interesting I never really
Thought of
The Hat being a logo
Could you sort of
Pull-A-Part some of its qualities as to what it's convenient to you and why it works
I think what was interesting about Donald Trump
Red make America great hat was that one it's very it's very
It was sort of thing
It's clearly not something one Associates
With Coastal Elites you know who are intellectuals although I know
Now and then so maybe I'm not going to leave now from Ohio after all but I mean it is sort of a r
It's definitely not suited for a black tie or business
Satire is meant to be sore.
The kind of thing you associate maybe with them
With hard-working
Salt-of-the-earth Americans
The bed that is red is sort of making a really
Clear statement about on
Read America let's say
And the slogan
Make America great again
All caps
Caprock
Yelling athlete
Kind of reminded
People of the
Candidates on
Delivery
Those words
And I think most importantly
Wasn't an underground thing was very visible if you sort of wars
Porter
You put that thing right on your head
You know and it was like if someone's looking at your face they would look at that hat made read those words to know
Wearable Brands like that sort of
Tattoos are sort of the bitten a big commitment you make to kind of advertising someone else
Calls himself
I assumed that he had boughten
Custom stickers
Signs and stuff like that but that had witch
The Warren
Was like really calling on P
I personally identify with that candidate in a really on a
So the Hillary H with an arrow logo is released in people react to it the way they
React to any logo right now is really active discussion online whenever a new one is
Done
It is also in the context of this political campaign
She got
Unbelievable not a criticism no matter what she did but I remember people reacting to
The age of the arrow
Willie strongly some of it quite an egg
Were you
Prepared for that in any way
Would have taken me aback
What I should have seen coming is that logo was I actually personally thought was and still think was really good I mean
No it was exactly the one that we wanted
The campaign to use we are confident that over
The course of the campaign will be used in all sorts of ways that would win people over and I think I was largely proven out
I mean I think by
The time November came around if you sort of like went on the
Pantsuit Nation
Facebook page you would see a million different expressions of a tall homegrown and
Grassroots in really really fun
And I remember saying while we were working while we were looking all the different options logo I remember saying you know
I want something
It's so simple that a
First grader could do it with construction paper Elmer's glue in
Kindergarten scissors
Christina I didn't want a fancy thing you needed to know software programs
To create I wanted something
What is easy to draw
Heart
Or a
Peace sign
Horse smiling
Face you know something that could be that ubiquitous and I think we
Got pretty close to
It's just a very simple piece of geometry into
2 primary colors
Now
Really
Doll
What happens
When somebody that has warrants
Just put out there in
To you know
The uncaring world
People treated as a it's open-endedness Ashley at that moment works against it is
Treated as a Rorschach blot and everyone project
Jingdong
Standoff this happens
What's sports team
Names that happens with colleges
Beijing University
But I think I underestimated
Headed to the greed of which would happen with the political
Call candidate wear
Someone is well known as
Secretary Clinton you know has
Why do people have opinions about already and then suddenly there this
Convenient thing upon which two
Reject opinions I may have already had
Or pinyin
So they just thought were clever or whatever it was and so suddenly
You know what I kind of would Marvel
Sometimes I would say it's just
Some straight line some 90° angle sum
45 degree angles
Listen to primary colors it doesn't mean you know what's it's at me and I said was an age
Because it's that's the
The candidates because of age
It's a narrow cuz she wants to move the country forward and it's red white and blue
Because of America
And yet
I was I was kind of taken aback but I shouldn't have been actually and I have to come down to the campaign who
Resolute about Thera
Commitment to attend in fact really brought us a wife and made it really sing over
Summer months
Still are in contrast there was a notorious cell logo that was unveiled
When
Donald Trump
Identified his running mate
In the form of governor
Pants
And I had this TP like a chair that a lot of people thought they saw you know unsavory things in
Fan made fun of it and animated it in in ways that
Salacious
And it was like it just was mated
Disappear
And all kind of
Blink at you I know it's going to be a while ago and you really are committed to at the worst thing you can do is hurt a boy
Oops forgot that we're making that go away and forget you ever saw
If you stick to it it just act like you really mean it eventually the world will get used to it and then eventually if you wait longer
People be outraged if you try to
Redesign it into
Do you remember the first time
There was a public
Fight about a logo where normal people like got involved
Soap for years kind of
Like logo redesigns was
Very esoteric thing
For people like me who would gone
Art school to learn to be graphic
Designers would sort of
Did you see they change the UPS wall
Blower for UPS
Delivery trucks and I know who designed the original logo I know who did
The redesign I know what kind of
Things to say about it and everyone sort of like wood tok
You know chat rooms on websites
Comment for days on the
Pros and cons of
Things like that
Public was
The gap
Loaded
A redesign of its logo
It appeared online and suddenly someone said oh my God the Gap the
The retail store the Gap is going to read
Redesign its logo
And
Price of the gap
Aldi's
Consumers started getting like really
Agitated about him started
I'm saying it out
Save the old Gap logo you know where this new logos
Ridiculous
What's usually the criticism is wise to
Is that my four-year-old could a design that new logo 92
I think that's a good thing I like what was that for
Call but on the most people they started seem like logos
Those are sophisticated things that need to be
Design with complicated equipped
Mumbai
Scope of people
And they also assume that a lot of money was spent
How much was someone paid to do
Staying in Osaka
I remember that the gap
And sort of what this logo
Float around out there that was
Not the
Blue box
The highway condensed serif Waters ga
Familiar with
What it was
Lowercase helvetica with this
Superimposed faded Blue Square
Put off center on the letters
And for some reason it just really
Aggravated people I even I was surprised by that and people ask
My opinion other than a normal person
Google logo before
That's became that there's somebody started happening more and more in this in
The years to follow so I
Something about social media something about the internet County
I was unable to
They definitely blank on that
They sort of I think they denied they ever meant did you know that was just something we're experimenting with don't worry we've heard
Loyal customers loud
Claire Randolph
Never fear we shampoo
Changing the gap
Logo
Daniel was interesting is that of course that's a logo
Doing exactly what it's supposed to do
I mean when
People are being sold logos are told that they will be the
Receptacle
All the passion
That the
Consumers have for a brand which is this
Is kind of weird
Hard to express thing otherwise but now all the sudden
This will be the focal out
Which all that wall is going to
Aimed and
Naturally then
The customers think that they own
Can a company like you know has the
Temerity to change it without asking anyone
Permission suddenly the customers who have been told
Wildest thing
Officer
Be the focal object
Upon which all that wall is going
How to be a man
And
Naturally then but
The customers think that they own the logo you know and then when the company you like
You know has the temerity
To change it without asking him
Permission suddenly the customers who have been told this
Marvelous thing
Awesomest change ottoman without warning and they get like freaked out you think that General design awareness in the public
Has made your job
Easier or harder
Oh I think it's it's made it easier and it's made it more fun
And I would say
I've always thought that what I do
Why do we sing the most important
But I always thought it was him
Devoted my wife
Define daft
People notice that
And I don't think we can ask people to notice our work and thinking
Can about and then presume to tell
People
But you can only say positive things about it's an hour I think you I mean if it's if he were to talk about
Inform people about it
Empire large people like I think negative comments are always more fun to read them positive
What's a rave reviews a little doll tree but I mean
I've never had anyone forward Mia of positive rest
Yeah like I'm the other hand if it's the restaurant or the New York Times takes a restaurant
Heart
You know the relative
Which all that writer will describe every dish is just a sight to
Bhldn
And I think you know so I think you know it's criticism is much more fun to write and more fun
Read and unless we want to go back to having no one notice what we're doing and pretending like
Doesn't matter at all we should do
You stalker
I have
I mean is there a way
To get you
To criticism we can be figured out what's your sword Jiu-Jitsu method of dealing with it
Jana partners and I
Michael gareki and I
Redesign the logo for the Big Ten football conference
Prince and the needs to be redesigned because it was called the big time but it had 11
Teamcenter
That and the other
Clever logo that combined
The words Big Town written out with the number 11
Kind of hiding by the
74 town
So we sort of like you could do with simultaneously read
10 and 11 while looking at it which I just thought was
You know it's a nice solution to a problem which actually
Shouldn't be focused on you know I mean let's not celebrate this weird
Disconnect between
The name of the conference
The number of actual
And they were going to 12
The whole thing was they decided to kind of what just come up with a logo that wasn't
Based on
The actual number team
Call the Big Ten Conference so we did basically a logo that was
Made out of the letters big4
Big and then we did a treatment
The eye and big in the G and Biggs would have a double reed
The number to
And so when that was unveiled
Oh I actually got voicemail about if
Trampoline
What's wrong with you people are those people are the loyal fans and I remember someone at all the big tank on
When this logo launch sort of telling me
This is the
This is the passion that kind of makes him sit in those seats when the weather is terrible and
And the same pasture to make them take it personally when you put it with the logo f***
What happens is
Once people get over the shock
If you can hold on tight
Don't get
Used to the new logo and
If it's any good at all it'll soon be the Beloved
Big Ten logo and people will sort of like then
Lumberjack the next time it's changed as long as people still care about the big toenail care about it every time is change
And I have to admit we're entering a stage now where
I have work
The clients on
Doing logos and doing updates to logos where I can tell
The worst thing that could happen
When is if no one react
Acted at all
The best thing would be if every analog dead
But the
The worst will be of no one knows
Is there like happiness or white tape
The outrage just
Because
Wow people really care about us it's easy people to care about a sports team or university
It's a little bit harder to make people
Don't care about her
Retail brand but people don't do Steve's
Feel buried
Retail store
Put those garments Reddit
Antibodies
And I think it's actually
What harder to make it will care about Finance
The more abstract
Two-player amor
Disenrolling our wives
All of them now I'm will get comments on Logo updates and I
I think that you just you that you use to sort of whether it is he just sort of think
Well people are going to react to change
You should strongly sometimes but the strength that reaction is Ash
Directly related
The depth of feeling they have about the
Brand that you're
Representing
So
It's a little bit bad news equal
Have you ever had a
One-on-one interaction with a
Person
Buckeye fan
Enraged and and how did it go
With those Buckeye fans
I had this policy of
Responding
They found out somehow it came out that we're done in the people found our emails and I start getting forwarded
These emails that had a lot of
How dare you were out of here how much you charge you should be ashamed of yourself for
Tell my father who is class of
23 is spinning in his
Musgrave
And I would always write back in this really kind of courteous way saying one
It's always disappointing to work hard on something to know that people don't like it
I can only hope that you
Overtime
Come to
At least get used to it
Ideally come to like it as much as we do or at the very least not having bother you quite as much
But I know that
Team values
Is the strong feelings
You have about them and as a fellow fan
That's the thing that we all really
I would write something like that and then I really meant it to I really meant every element
And that about
Two-thirds of the people I would Raichu
Would write me back in this
Chastened sort of tone
Where they say old of things I'm sorry I thought I was going over the top a little bit I still don't like it but I
I was happy to hear explanation and
I'm sorry I kind of like fire that off to you in the Heat of the Moment
Apologize but clearly the one that was there was really obvious was that the
The thing that really bothered them the most
Was their sense that giant
Impersonal
Temperate forests
Worm
Arbitrarily
Changing
Things that they cared about personally
With no
Thought of
Who they were you know as fans and what
Gene Juarez or anything like that in the idea that there was a human being with a name and a boys who might
Share of their feelings in any way whatsoever
You can tell it wasn't with your pics
It's a very satisfying Target
If you just think somewhere up there in a horrible people are messing with
What's something that I like an hour
Ruined I hate you you know
And then if see if I fall is something that person shows up in person it's a little bit kind of going
Turning point mean that so
These people I'm just like I sincerely feel bad
I'm not trying to make people mad I want people to like the thing I design and I'm sort of
Almost
Always convinced at the moment that eventually if the thing I've designed
Is well-crafted and is
Really
Appropriate for its purpose
Misfits the team
It's the audience eventually
Welcome to
Play the same role little lies
Did that replace
And in logos or interest
Because I designed a lot of things out of science
The book covers
And a book cover that is one moment
Truth when you're
Find a book in a bookstore you walk down the aisle and
She catches your eye and then you think of
This looks interesting you pick it up
And you decide to buy it then you experience the raft
There is basically
Walking self and the world
Isn't
Consequential
What was so you're one of the few things that appreciate in value as their
Used if you picture
You know really simple logos that are iconic in the American
Commercial land
Like
A Target logo sale
The Nike Swoosh
These are things that you know
84 year old
Define are really simple looking
Have no inherent meaning well the Target logo has
A meeting about that people find exasperate
Great hanging out with you
If you're hiring some fancy design from
Google logo for company
Target may come back and they say we came up with something
Really great
Here it is and it's a Target
How long did it take
But I mean think about think about how much they've been able to do with the Simplicity that Mark thing about how they've been
Manipulate very simple
All sorts of
Thanks and I would argue that that logo
Google Now
We all sleep aid
We're back in the sea
Commissioned
It's worth a hundred times
What is your least favorite aspect
Of the heated
Russian around
Logos are we
Knights when they have a
What's the type of criticism where you just like that's not
If you design something new people for some reason are so
Desperate to reconcile it with something already
Familiar with that they'll say oh that looks exactly like this other
And sometimes
Depending on their frame of mind they'll say that looks exactly like this other thing that could be
Something Bailey
Smarty like
Male or female
Anatomy or something like that looks like so much of that goes around
And no matter what you design you know they have this very human need to kind of turn abstract shapes into something
Figurative that means something
Really I mean what logos are meant to be
Empty vessels
Into which meaning is
Poornima meaning
When they work right is the meaning that your first-hand experience
Represented by the logo
And I thank God
When someone just says oh that looks like a
Did you see it you know this sort of is tough also
I've never actually committed this are all the way but
If you're practicing graphic designer. Young graphic designer out there I'll one bit of advice I have is if you're like working on a
Logo
That is like a say it's us
Quasi
You know it's a geometric logo with a
The four parts
Kind of thing
The kind of Hazzard
A rotational angular rotational aspect
If someone says
That kind of reminds me of a swastika
You won't just
You know that's a signal you should
That that logo will not be
Presented
To anyone just put it away actually that sort of his life that that's close to me you can say it looks like a penis and like
You can actually get over that but I mean
What was
It's just like really
I remember I was going to a meeting with a
A client
Privately had a little twins with a really light and it sort of had these kind of geometric
Characteristics
Carry the thing
It's about meeting and not even being a minister me in there
It was like an intern in The Intern
Sad
Like almost like
Bursting into
Cheers and say now you've ruined everything I going to me I said this one
Yeah I'm sorry
I guess I hate that the most
Someone says
It looks like an emblem of the most evil political and cultural force of the twentieth century that's not good
And I just want to show you about that was the swastika was this perfectly abstract
Harmless and even kind of benevolent symbol
Centuries
Spiritual insignia.
Hawaiian Over
Application in Easter
Culture
And then. Hijack
Bayou
One guy of failed artist
And they turned it into a what
Turns it into a
Just goes to show you
Got me somebody notices it that's a good piece of criticism because obviously
Do you want to say
Yeah
What is this look like what does this remind you of anything these days particularly abstract logo designers
Have the same problem
Combat
People coming over
Names
Products
You know where
It's not
Good names
Taking all the good URLs are taken and frijole all the good
Simple
Abstract geometric
Logos are taken
It's really hard to find one that hasn't been
McDonald ready
When you do the same
Things you have to do this
Illegal searches
How to make sure the
Houses used it
You can find one that's Tyson
Simple
Is a bail bond
Do you feel like you've discovered
Continental
Oh my God
Want to buy a gun
Wendy Clarice
Sharing
Have you ever
Seen a new logo redesign logo
And
Overtime had the most change of heart about it like a
Strong reaction and then cut
Begin to love it or do you remember anything like that where your point of view changed either for the more positive or for the more negative
Partly because of the way I've been
Trained and
Having done this for so many years
My snap judgment about logos is probably more refined
I should be so they're ones that I saw when they're brand new that I didn't like much
And I still don't like even if I don't like it I sort of get what they were going for
There's some better chest out right I just
Plane don't
White
You here in New York
We had a
The long-standing logo of the Metropolitan Museum of Art
Was replaced with
With a logo
That
Replace a
A drawing of an atom with
Sweaters
With water saying the mat
And a lot of
Why can partly be
Replacing something
They're used to
And partly because I I would concede it was like really
Really idiocy
Democratic and weird
But the same time I was thinking out but if you go to the mat there was a big complicated idiosyncratic
Place you go there and get lost
It's like really
Labyrinthian
Inside it has so much stuff there
Please try to represent this thing with something that could
Look like it was for
Baby doing at Justice
I need some
It kind of feels
Complicated and idiosyncratic
Perkins Pacific
So I remember I looked at in the ICU
Even now when I see it it's still kind
Taste me back some
I was used to the old
But I can recognize that in the long run I think
Get well if they stick with it ice
It'll work
B
His beloved as
Its predecessor
When you say
That you plain don't like something
Just like in general
What are those things that you play Don't Like It Is there a way you could articulate
Those qualities
I mean I hate to say it but just like everyone else I'll look at something and say
Oh my goodness that's
Rather ugly isn't it
You know in like you know I mean something like I mean for rent since we want to talk about another another design
The design for the
2012 Olympic
Rex Ryan London
Widely criticized and I think right
It's right to criticize logos I can really cyp
People criticized because I think that that was like
Adan
Funny looking
It's like no like a presidential campaign logo it's sort of own it it had the mark
Moment in time it wasn't designed to be this enduring thing that would last forever
It just had to kind of like symbolize what was happening
In a specific place
Pacific time
And would be further associated with all these kind of
Feats of athleticism that would be the last
Real experience of
Just woke
And so when away
Idiosyncratic
Pacific
Come to stand for all those other things however I still think
I just like just like ugly it's a Ramon gainly it's like weird looking
I couldn't I could never quite I have to admit
I personally and privately need
To make up a story that
Wayne said
Sounds like a lot of stories for the metal although I can make a lot of stories
Barbie logo I've ever designed
To me it's sort of the same pleasure I used to take as
A kid
You know sitting on my dentist office
Just looking at Highlights magazine they have that
Call hidden pictures
In the picture above
Can you find you know
A teapot
A hairbrush
Yo a basketball and then and then you can see any of those
Is nuc oh my God
Quite the hairbrush is
The drapes on that window and the basketball is
That plate that's in the pantry and then all the sudden you're finding all these things in there such
Weather in discovering those things
And if you got a logo that has that bit of
Pleasure embedded in it and I think with black friends
Since when we embedded the tan in the eye in the gene that they in the Big Ten logo
We were trying to do something like that the most famous sense
Probably within
Temporary logos
Does the arrow that
What's hidden in the FedEx
You know but I think of you know those also promo catalog on sale all those luggage
Pictures are meant to symbolize
Connection that's not quite as
His phone is finding a
Airbrushing
Window curtain
Spotted saw
Something
It works for me
These many years later
So last year there was a redesign of
What's the Kodak logo and I interviewed
Keira Alexandra
Work order who did it
And when I talked to her she purposely talked about how
They just pulled it out kind of low-key and they didn't make a big
I'll believe about it I mean still got criticized in different ways and largely lauded
But
You know it was kind of a reaction to the
Brand new thumbs up thumbs down
You know what what do you think of that is that a
Good idea. Do you also do feel similarly inclined or do you like to throw it out there
And have it be a bit of a Bloods
You know like what would its what is your take on that
Well I used to
Tell Mike
Clients no one will care when your logo goes out
There don't take out an ad in the
Bold New Look same Great Taste and I wish you know like no one cares you know
Honey honey kids come in your nose
Amalgamated widget just change their logo you know no one cares
Then we pass through this weird thing where became this funny kind of like social media and Abel
Bloodsport where like in
You know amalgamating Wizards can change its logo in 3 2 1 game on you know and it's like 10 on my 4-year
Girl could do that how much they pay for this piece
It turned it is like thing that people didn't
The throne and others amusement
I still think though that these things
Succeed to the degree that they are actually reflecting
So something of substance is really changed in the thing that's represented by the
The case of Kodak
When they updated that logo it was meant
Mark
The
Rebirth of a beloved
American company that too
Certain generations of photographers really was
The gold standard of
Adjusted ubiquitous kind of element
The photographic
Process
Associated with
Five-letter word Kodak
Especially with the yellow box and with that very simple logo.
They have
And when
Alexander and her team updated at
They asked you were really careful I thought insensitive to extrapolating every
I think they were doing
From
Examples
Past and I know
Pleasure she took
She did one big bold move which was
Instead of writing Kodak
Horizontally Shiraz
Vertically she Stacks the five letters
I want to talk to each other
Stand is able to make a kind of ready for it
The 21st century and all the requirements
Logos half
They have today in
Reproduction
Dissemination
She made a really nice logo with that move and
Rachel pleasure in finding
A couple of examples of
The weather is being stacked in the
The same way
From deep in the past
Summit companies
She was able to kind of give the whole thing this
Imprimatur
Endorsement
From
Almost beyond the grave from
The deep in the history
The company which I think
Satisfying and icy very effect
Is there a God
Fashion
Right now
That you wrestle again
Or or maybe one that you think is right me like simple for example is
I don't think it's I think it's cuz I'm always been
Somewhat of a goal and logos but
It seems
A real
Guiding principle right now maybe more than
In the time when somebody wrote a Coca-Cola
How is a long
Script
Is there something
Here today that
You really love that you think is is a fundamental principle or do you think
What is a fashion or anything like that
I have two men I like Simplicity of
Form but I kind of
Some of them so little suspicious of Simplicity and typography
You know so I love this typeface called helvetica which some people would argue is Hmong
Now it's a very simple clean and ubiquitous typeface that off
And all that has
This represented over the years everything
American Apparel
American Airlines
Chances are no matter where you are
On something that you can see from where you're sitting and if not
Just take out
Your wallet and
Ebony America
Currency
That big number 5 on
Your $5 bill is
And I think
There was a time back in the White City
States where you can take any logo resetting El vaticano look modern contemporary in
Mike ready for
You know the millennium
And I think I'm going to throw out of favor and I think I'll be his comeback a lil
Little bit song
Among other things
In a very recently Diane Von Furstenberg has been redesigned so in
Instead all by
Friday DVD
Dvf
Monogram
Dog that's what they had before now it's two words Diane by
Firstmark login
And it looks clean it looks neutral looks smart but it also kind of
At its worst
You know you're not not answering this case but I mean
Sort of has that same sort of
Guam and
Impassive
Band
Kind of
I am really I'm too cool even to acknowledge you exist
How to face that supermodels will have in certain fashion shoes for they just are expressionless and kind of almost zombie like in
I am so cool download
Camino please look at me not like that I don't know who you are
Go away you know
And some have that quality and I just answered you can be a mean withholding sword
So I have a bunch of listeners there be no design aware their design engaged
And as a person who knew puts things out in the world and and mixed logos and makes new
Logo systems for people
What would you want them to know when they interact with you
Like what what type of criticism
Would you
Like to hear or not like to hear
Ice or do you want to field we're like almost like a lot of the things that
Define
When I do
Comes down to really boring sort of
Sayings
It's like don't judge a book by its cover
Or on the other hand you only get one chance to make a first time
Compression
Until they all kind of contradict each other you know and you know
The advice I give is that on
At the end of the day
Graphic design is
Really important
But it's also kind of
One of those cosmetic things in the world to know if you can read an exit sign you're going to get out the door you know
If a door has no door knob on it with snails
Close in all these are all things that are real and Padme
It's what that exit sign can be in any type face you want
I'm still going to find the door
And so I think it's some now you can make a handsome exit sign that actually fits the architecture around that you can make one
One that's hard to read
And that one is going to be dysfunctional
But there's a lot of different ways to do it and usually it's not a life-or-death thing
I think there's a lot of things that are like really life-and-death matters in the world and really important are worth getting agitated about
I think that probably logo design
Shouldn't be one of them
There's people that are paid alot of money to
TUC care desperately about the way logos look and
I aspire to be one of those people I think that
If your not getting paid to do it's like trying not to
To do it too much only do degree it entertains you but then move on to more important
Michael bierut is a partner at pentagram
I'm the proud owner of a signed copy of his book how to use graphic design to sell things explain things make things look better make people
People laugh make people cry
And every once in awhile
Change the world
Plus he's a co-host along
Jessica helfand of the podcast the design of business
The business of design
It's really good
You're looking for insights into the world of design
Designers
You need to subscribe to it and it's sister podcast
Debbie Millman
Design matter
Just like the OG
Design park
They're essential listening
So after the credits and I'm very important announcements first but we have a special bonus interview at the end of the episode
Which is a clip of a live event I do with my friend Kevin smokler
About the places
Both real and imagined
From your favorite 80s movies
Kevin's new book is called Brat Pack America
Superfund
Especially for anyone who grew up on those movies
Or places like
Shermer Illinois Hill Valley goondocks Sherwood Ohio
What characters in and of themselves
Stay tuned for that
99percentinvisible is Emmett Fitzgerald
Delaney Hall
Katie Mingle
Sean real
Average Hoffman Sharif Youssef
And me Roman Mars
Astute listeners from over the years might notice the name missing from LA
Sam green
Sam starred on the show is a remote intern based in Baltimore
When was just me and my apartment in Richmond California
He was the very first person I heard the show actually you guys
Part of during the first Kickstarter
He's been a critical part of our team over the years
He's moving on to do his very own project
We're all really excited about
It's too soon to tell you anything about it yet
But I want you to remember this word
Bellwether
You can be one of the first to know what he's up to by following him on Twitter at Sam listens and sign up for his tinyletter email
Email newsletter
Sam Greenspan.
Good luck Sam
We at 9 ibih Q
In the listening audience
Miss hearing you
Inertia
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
Radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
So few weeks ago I had a conversation in front of a live audience at
Spur in Oakland
With my pal Kevin smokler about his book Brat Pack America
Which is this like 300 Page Love Letter to all the places where your favorite 80s teen movies were sad
I really enjoyed the book and our conversation but after I record it I learned that if you aren't as well versed in the 80s movies
Genre as I am you might get a little lost
End the conversation just worked way better on the website we could have bed all the pictures of places that were talking about in the trailers from the movie along with
The audio of the event
Is where the coolest web features we've ever done so I hope you check it out
Here's a little clip
Quora conversation
Locations in Ferris Bueller all within the downtown Loop and Wrigley Field
I mean that's one thing that struck me I watch Ferris Bueller again
A couple nights ago
And
Havoline
Sense of Chicago
It's really thirsty like they're not they're not there because they really know Chicago
There there
Doing the exact same things that
A literal field trip from school would take them to
Yeah I need the
For kids who live like 3 train stops away from Chicago that they act like they're there from Cody Wyoming
For something like a slice of deep dish pizza like they've complete
Day of twisting around
Chicago
To be fair and this is only very slightly so
John Hughes was a White Sox
Not a Cubs fan and so he wanted to shoot the Wrigley Field seen at Comiskey Park which would have at least taken them to the south side of from
But the socks were not in town
That that weekend until they had to fill my
I barely feel so yeah it is it's a really like not adventurous day off and the funny thing is John Cusack
Simself even though he was very aware of himself as a dweller in the
North suburbs
In Chicago
Well heck all over the place like I put a lot of time with one of his kids
And John Hughes wrote everything down
And used to use the write down like all the concerts you would go to any art exhibits you would go to
Is a teenager
The guy the guy mapped all of Chicago on foot
And somehow we get this very
Myopic parochial picture
Chicagoland
Can ferrets
Do the full interview trailers pics and links to Kevin's book
Brat Pack America on our website
99 pi
. org
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
Talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and liked it comes come back again and again
You don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flat pocket
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this
Story including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299 API
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com