99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The date September 11th is of course very significant for people in the US
The country of Chile also has an important September 11
And their history
On 9/11 1973 using both airstrikes
I'm grounded a military Junta violently took control of Chile
At the time I president Salvador Allende
Producer Katie Mingle
Zendaya become president of Chile in a free and democratic election
After the military coup
General Augusto Pinochet
Took power brutally as a dictator
Until 1990
After taking over the country
The military dissolve Congress
Took control of the media
And what about dismantling all of the Socialist and Democratic institutions that I India's government had built
And somewhere in the midst of all of this
The new military regime discovered something in a nondescript office building in Downtown Santiago
It was a room
A very strange room
I've heard people compare it to something out of
Kubrick film
Star Trek
That's eating Medina professor of informatics and Computing at Indiana University in Bloomington does
Driving the strange
Place it's quite striking in this bright
Technicolor
Oranges
Wood paneling
Picture of the deck of the Starship Enterprise and you're not that far off
The room was hexagonal in shape with 7 white fiberglass chairs arranged in an inward facing Circle
There were colorful space AG screens is playing chart
Fangraphs
Town hall 6 walls
When Pinochet is men found this room they didn't
Quite know what to make of it
It said that one of them began stabbing its colorful display screens with a knife
And it's no wonder they didn't understand this
There's never been anything quite like it
This operations room
Was the physical interface
Extra complicated system called
Project
Cybersaint
Project cybersyn have been designed helped you a socialist
Experiment work better
It was just one of the ways that former president in they have been trying to do socialism differently than it is
Never been done before
So let's back up before the coup
For the Sci-Fi operations room was built
Salvador Allende have been elected in 1970
He was the first Marxist president ever elected democratically in any country
That's his campaign song you're hearing right now it's called vinceremos
Or We Shall Overcome
Finn by the band she left it was one of many protest songs and chants to come out of in days campaign
Poor and working-class people sang Enchanted and finally voted in day into office
They loved
And I and I hoped he could show the world that she lay was going to be different than the communist and socialist experiments
In other countries
Is Government after all have been elected democratically and it was deeply committed to
Protecting civil liberties
So it did not want to get rid of it
Constitution it did not want to
Censor the Press
It wanted to preserve freedom of speech
And right away the government raises employment and wages for people across Chile
And they start a program of agrarian reform to redistribute the ownership of land
And they also begin a program to make consumer goods that previously had been reserved for the elite
To try to make them more broadly accessible to the Chilean people
Toward this end I end a formed in industrial Design Group in his government
He believed design was political
We where's thinking that we we're doing something great for short people than good
That's Fernando Flores
He began working in the IND Government after the election
And he says to say it was an exciting time is an understatement
It wasn't just excitement
Was like being in love
Why would someone do I sink in the 24 hours a day
We will
Working
United Country
What's an adventure for
For those people that believe
Pool country
What's an adventure for those that believe tonight end
An adventure
But also
Ton of work
So the central problem
Is a central problem in socialist Revolution
Which is the government must go about turning all the private businesses into public businesses
You just think about the challenge of bringing the most important industries
In your country under State Control
And not having the experience
To do so
The government eventually took control of 150 Enterprises
Including several of the largest companies
In Chile
And this is the not-so-fun part
Us socialist Revolution
Management
Only people that don't care about money
Did Ikea
Fernando Flores cared about manager
Any other idea for how to manage chillies complicated
Economy
He wanted use a relatively new site
Called cybernetic
Cybernetics is a science that became popular around World War II
As humans develop new kinds of machines we became interested in developing systems for controlling those machines
Cybernetics looks at how to design intelligent self-correcting system
Cybernetics is based on the word kubernetes
Which is Greek
For steersman the goal of a steersman is to get the ship to the destination taking into account all
All kinds of feedback from the environment like wind currents
All cybernetic systems have goals
So you can think about the heating and cooling system in your home as a cybernetic system
The goal is to keep your house at a desired temperature
The thermostat does this by telling the heater or the air conditioner
When to turn on and off
Depending on feedback it's receiving from the environment
It's an intelligent
Self regulating system with a goal
In England in the
A consultant named Stafford beer was applying concepts of cybernetics
In business management
He believed a business could be thought of as an intelligence
System
If the goal was to sell more product or work more efficiently
You could using the principles of cybernetics design the system to work toward those goals
But Stafford beer had never imagined he get to apply his ideas to helping a whole government 6/8
And then I said which way must change my life
It was from the technical general manager
Estate planning board of Chile
That Stafford beer in archival tape from 1974
The letter he got was from Fernando Flores
Tok in this letter
Oh that he had City termite works
It's late
Together
And what are things coming to take it over
The distance to stop me on a on a journey which
Make me travel 8000 Miles
Over and over and over again
Meeting
Between London and Santiago for 2 years
Stafford beers first trip to Santiago was in 1971 when he arrived he and Fernando Flores and the
The team that assembled in Chile
When about designing
Cybernetic system
I can help them manage the bureaucracy of the new Chilean economy
They would call this project
Cybersn
Stafford beer had long stringy hair in a long beard
He look like he should be leading yoga retreats not
Teaching major corporations About Management
Beer was particularly interested in using cybernetics to help companies redistribute power within the system
And chili
Was interested in this to
How do we make
Institutions
I'm non-hierarchical how do we distribute decision
The first thing bearded was map and model chilles entire economy
This was a really complex process
Uninvolved understanding how each part of the economy was affected by other parts and by outside feedback
On paper it looks
Like a big block diagram connected with lines and arrows
Now we have the economy
These are
Big major branches of India
Evian
Niacin
Materials industry
It wasn't enough however
Berta just
Understand how all the parts are two ways economy connected
It was also crucial that the different parts be able to communicate with each other
Beer wanted factories to be able to send and receive information
He wanted to create a vast computer network that connected all the factories in Chile
Idea
This was pre-internet
Computer networks weren't really a thing yet
But there was a problem with
This idea
There are only a handful of computers in all of Chile
And beer
He only had access to one
These guys they had to create a computer network using one computer
Which is pretty amazing
So they improvised
They realized okay we can't put computers throughout the
But we can do is we have these Telex machine
Telex machine looks like a typewriter but it's hooked up to a telephone line
So imagine you and your friend you both have Telex machine
You can type a message on the keyboard hit send
And your friends talks will receive it
And literally type it out to a piece of paper
It's like super steam punk Gchat
I think Gchat is a great way to think about it
Everyday someone for a fact
Would send data via Telex
To another tablet
Where it would be received by an operator
And then entered into the Central Computer
The kinds of data that people
Might send
Could include raw material
Right how much cotton
You have how much
Cold you
The central computer software program
Cyber strike
Was able to analyze the data
Warn about potential problem
This is
What your worker absentee level was today this is what it was the day before
This is what it was the day before that what is it going to be tomorrow
Are you going to have a problem
Decisions could then be made about what to do
And this brings us back to that bizarre hexagonal room
The one that look like something out of a Kubrick
Or Star Trek
The operations room
It is a
Futuristic decision-making space
Deptford beer wanted to build a
Physical space for project
Cybersn
Actually he wanted to build several of them
Oliver chili but only one was ever finished
The room was inspired in part by Winston Churchill's war room
So you can imagine the general sitting around smoking their cigars
In this case
Petroleum sitting around smoking cigarettes and perhaps
Drinking pee
But unlike Churchill's war room and this is a key difference
This was a room for non hierarchy
Decision making
Stafford beer imagine Factory workers and higher level bureaucrat
That's a like
Making decisions together
The projector is there so what
That's guidon CFA
Originally from Germany
I have been working in Chili's industrial Design Group and was busy designing cool products for the masses
When he was taught to help design the operations room for project cybersyn
Eventually he realized Stafford beer wanted the room to be so much more than a standard meeting room
During the project I became more and more aware of the
Complexity
Bentley admission office
Face
Which made it possible for the users
Use the system
The room needed to be Democratic and state-of-the-art
Please
No tables
Stuff for PSN look
This is room
For making decisions
Music for reading
Meatballs in talking about
Add notes
He was very categorically
The room was designed to quickly convey information about factories
All over 2A
You have charts and graphs of factory production on the walls
You have a photograph of the factory that is discussed
You have flashing lights that show whether there are emergencies
7 people would sit in a circle discussing and deciding how to proceed with various
Problems
7 because it's an odd number to facilitate voting
A in a circle so that no one would be prioritised over anyone else so it's not a rectangular table with
Ahead
Each chair the operations room had a place to set your whiskey
An ashtray
And a set of buttons one could use to control the display screens on each wall
It's Mad Men
Meats start
Dobhan champagne since they weren't consciously trying to make it look
Futuristic
Certainly was not our idea.
Science fiction
Inmate
Science reality what you said
What's something different
But to me there is a bit of fiction in all of it
It's an Immaculate piece of design but it conceals
Monkey technology
The buttons on the chairs for instance were connected to some wires
That ran under the floor and behind the wall and eventually connected to 3 slide
And depending on the combination of buttons that you pushed
It would advance
Once I Carousel or another or tell the slide Carousel to move backwards
I'm as a way to
Pull up the desire
These screens couldn't display information in real time you can only display and discuss slides that have been pre-made
So it says image of modernity but behind it there's just a lot
Human labor
Going into to making this illusion possible
Well project cybersyn was coming together and the futuristic operations room was being designed and built
Things are not going so well for the agenda government
So all of this is taking place during the
The heart
The Cold War
And Latin America has emerged as
A Battlefield
The u.s. have been actively working with people with in Chile who were unhappy with the government
So the US was intervening in Chile
In many many many different ways
That the IND
They had been
Involved in denying Chile
Farm Credit
It became increasingly difficult for Chileans to get ahold of
Us
Machinery if you don't have the parts you can't keep the machines running
The economy was collapsing
Inflation had started
Skyrocket
So people are having trouble getting
Basic
Items
And then just
3 years after Allende was elected
And She lays September 11th
September 11
Insensitive
Weather
I don't want to talk about that
EBay memories
That's Fernando Flores again
I wasn't in the palace with depression and some other people
Who has landed well pumps.
Claims
While the presidential Palace was bombed
By a military Junta supported by the United States
Allende gave his final radio address to the country
Long Live to a long live the people long live the workers
Pisang
These have been my last words and I'm certain that My Sacrifice will not be in vain
I'm certain that at the very least it will be a lesson that will punish felons cowardice and season
Those explosions were recorded in the actual radio broadcast
Salvador Allende took his own life that same day shortly after giving that address
It's estimated that during pinochet's rule about 38000 people wear in prison
And most of those prisoners were tortured
Close to three thousand people were executed
Another 1200 people went missing
I'm two hundred thousand people were exiled
The other countries
In fact
Chilipitin the band that wrote in days campaign song was exiled
France where they wrote a new song
The people United will never be to
If you did
The song became the anthem of resistance
10 seconds Pinochet
And the chorus is continued to be a chant at leftist protest
Across the world
Project cybersyn never got fully up and running
The Telex network was set up
System restarting
Receive data from back
They were slow to come in
And the operations room
Was finished
And it hadn't really been put to use
Grievance eBay managed to escape chili with the one color photograph
Ever taken of the operations room
And various other documents related to cybersyn
It was for me
The meeting at the intersection
Scientific Technology
Politics
Ant Design
This does not happen very of my WhatsApp
Cybersyn was maybe just a bit ahead of its
Time and network piece together with Telex machines and one computer
Just a couple decades before the internet made this kind of thing commonplace
An operations room designed to convey information as quickly as possible
Only you had to crawl behind a wall and put a new slide in the carousel
When you wanted to show something to the group
Severson's technology was probably never up to the task at hand
But then again it was a technology designed to help socialism succeed while the United States did everything in its power
Where to make it fail
Maybe no technology was up to that time
Heaven's Sake
At that time
We were so inspired
Bicep possibility
It is possible to change
Society
When you look at the operations room I mean how can you not look at it
And see that this is someone's dream
Right that this is someone's utopian vision
There is
There's a kind of hope
About it
When Pinochet took over Chile
He destroyed the strange futuristic space
Been embodied the utopian dreams of the eye in the government
Piano used
You're such a thing
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Katie mingle which refuse at Sam Greenspan
Holsted Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza Delaney Hall and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Patrick McRae Sarah Henry and Paul Pangoro
Fernando Flores spent three years as a political prisoner in Chile and was eventually able to escape with the help of an estate
International
Stafford beer continue to lecture on cybernetics until his death in 2002
Eden Medina's book cybernetic revolutionaries technology and politics and Ina chili
Has so many more details about cyber set
Find a link to it and CD One glorious color photograph of cyber Systems Operations room at our website
99 pi.
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI feet
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Flash podcast
You can find the show and join the discussion about the show on Facebook and tweeted me at Roman Mars and the show at
99pi org wear on Instagram and Tumblr to
But everything 99 Pi comes together and 99 Pi. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com