99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
A free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When it comes to sports
The uniforms matter a lot
Jerry Seinfeld famously set
Loyalty is a kind of hard
Justify Indiana
You know I love the giant but when you think about it
Who won the Giant
You know what I mean
You know what I mean it's different guys every year different guys right teams will move from City
The city the players come and go they get traded they retire they leave via free agency
But you keep
Rooting for those colors
And that logo
And that uniform
You're rooting for clothes when you get right down to it
I want my change clothes to beat the clothes from the Pacific
There's nothing really wrong with that laundry
And the measure of its according to Paul Lucas the creator of uni watch website devoted to the obsessive study of Athletics
Aesthetics
Is this
Passionate New York Mets fan
And I really really hate
The New York Yankees
But if the entire
Mets team
25 guys
Is traded even up for the entire Yankee
Today
Who do I root for tomorrow and tell me the answer is obvious it's a no-brainer I root for whoever is wearing the Mets uniform
No matter who it is even if it's a bunch of guys who were wearing the Yankees
Uniform the day before
To the identities of the players are almost irrelevant is the uniform and that is an unusual
Strong form
Of brand loyalty
Because if I like say
Certain brand of cereal
What's that like Cheerios while I identify with the box and the logo and the colors and all that the package design
But I also presumably like the
The product
And if I
Find that the quality of the product has changed if it doesn't taste good anymore or if it's some aspect of it. If it doesn't
Stay crunchy in milk or whatever
I may give it one or two more tries based on my my brand loyalty but eventually I will leave that for and I will
Banded it if I find the quality is no longer there
But in sports
The content of
The product and the quality of that content
Meeting the players
Is changing all the time you can be really good one year really bad the next year your roster can turn over so the content of
The product
Is constantly in flux
But we stay loyal
To whoever is wearing that uniform
And that is an unusually attempt to my mind it's a unique
Form of brand loyalty there's nothing else like it
In our consumer Alliance
Like Paul Luke is my friend Jesse Thorn also obsesses over baseball uniforms
Although he didn't make a career of it
He has another job
I'm Jesse Thorn I'm the owner of Maximum plan.org and the host of the NPR show bullseye
There are certain things about a uniform that serve a purpose by being uniform
They help the players identify each other they help us rally behind our team
They give us something cool to buy
But there are certain things on the uniform that aren't uniform
Things that a player can choose
The number of things that a player can choose are very very small I mean it was a big controversy
When I was
A kid when Ken Griffey jr.
Shag balls in the Outfield during batting practice
With his baseball hat on backward
It's a big controversy now when a baseball player
Where's his
Cap brim totally flat
In what you might call the hip hop style
As opposed to curved kind of like
Is that what you mean yeah well I mean that literally make a device that you can
Buy at the sporting good store order via mail order that will give you a quote on quote the perfect
Curve your brim
And I I mean I remember as a little Leaguer obsessing over getting the
Brim of my
Hat to curve exactly right and I was not the only one
We had Jesse Thorn talk with Paul Lucas I mean you watch any discovered that Paul also zeros in on the settle Express
Tiana baseball players uniform
I'm always very alert for any glimpse
Of the underside of a players
Cap Brim
Because over the years a color of that element is called be under brim or the under visor
Has changed when I was a kid they were green and they changed to gray for most teams and now they are mostly
Black
And some players
Will write something
On the under Brim
Fewer players do it now that they're black because you have to use with a white or a silver Sharpie back when they were gray players
And players with ripe unusual things their inspirational messages with a name for their children or whatever the case might be in.
I always Timmy was an inch
Startup stealth area
Of uniform world with a universe
What to call it
The other thing
You like that continuity in the universe
But when you get to baseball uniform aficionados like Paul and Jesse together in conversation there is one area of the
The baseball uniform that they truly get out about
The intersection between the pant leg
And the sock
Basically the whole area
Below the knee
And it's the the least legislated
Least regulated and released uniform
Part of the uniform
Even though baseball teams have been historically named after the color of their socks there is no rules governing the
The length of the pants or whether or not you will actually see
And that has really changed
Last generation
Tickle a lot over
You know the last century or so
Early baseball uniforms
Had essentially knickers
And what do you wear with knickers you wear
Stockings
And that's what really baseball
And over the course of the 20th century
Those knickers started getting longer and longer and they said
Tripping a little lower a little lower and then
What's a mid calf
Pain in lower calf and then
Little lower and now we have so many of the players
Who wear their pants all the way down
Are there shoe tops like footie pajamas
And then you have a handful of players like
Say Alex Rodriguez and
Curtis Granderson Ichiro Suzuki Hawaii to hike their pants up high so there are minority but there is a faction of
You do that but there's no uniformity
And I think it's a shame
Tragedy
That we got the
Is players who wear the
The pants all the way down to the shoe tops because when you cover up the socks
You're basically dishonoring
Baseball's hosiery
Heritage
So let's break it down
Today baseball pants are stretchy polyester they used to be wolf lamp
So
The pants that they have now
You can wear them kind of tight or loose
And you can wear your pants at a variety of different lengths
So
They can go down all the way to the top of your shoes and in fact some players have gone so far as have a strap
That goes underneath their shoes to keep it keep from showing any socket all
You can wear your pants up swerve at the bottom of your calves
Which shows a little bit of sock that's probably what most players do and they just kind of let him sit there
You can wear your pants up all the way over your calves
At the top of your calves
Like they were
You know sporting pants from the early part of the twentieth century you know like they were
Greek store
Plus user plus
And if you wear your pants in that style with the bottoms all the way up to your knees you can either wear song
Colored socks
You can wear socks with a stripe up the side
It's meant to simulate a stirrup socks
Or you can wear actual stirrups
These choices
Stirrup socks are the ultimate in baseball Hosiery for the die-hard old school fans
If you need help a tree in a stirrup
They're basically
Two layers of socks
There's a bottom layer that's a normal Old Sock
There's also an exterior socket that's a different color
At the bottom of that song
Is just a strap that goes underneath the arch of the players foot
The idea behind stirrups goes back about a century
Baseball pants used to be just knickers and you would wear stockings
With them but in the early days of baseball
Baseball is a pretty rough-and-tumble game players with off and get spiked and there were some players like the Great Hall of Fame
Cycop would famously sharpen their spikes
So that when they slid into second
Enter third day stay with
Cut up the infielder
And if you got spiked in the shin
You get cut in your stockings and
The fabric dyes
In those days we're not colorfast
And so if you got spiked
Die from your stockings could get in the wound
How to get blood poisoning
Orsova
I don't know if there any documented cases
Got blood
ISO someone got the idea and we don't know who someone
Unisom great hero who deserves a statue or the statue to the great unknown stirrups
Innovator
That
If you
War on under sock
An extra layer of sauce
You would have an extra layer
Protection of sanitary Ware
What is under sock
Became known as a sanitary
Aorta pair of socks
Became known as sanitaries or Sani
And then
The / stocking
Great Wall Beijing one you have to wear
Does the stocking over the under sock because now you be wearing two pairs of socks
Your shoes wouldn't
And so they decided to
Cutout
The foot area
The Overstock
And creative Little Stirrup opening and that's how baseball stirrups were born and originally
That opening with
Tiny was just enough for your foot to fit
And almost immediately
Players began
Pulling it and stretching it higher
And so
More and more of an opening appeared and Mattox
Exposed more and more of the sanitary under sock with
Usually White
So you started having the sort of interplay of color
Of the ever-widening opening up the colored stirrup
And white Under sock and by the 1960s they were players
Like Frank Robinson
Baltimore Orioles
Who are actually
Cutting
The bottom part of the Stirrup the park
The loop under your foot
And adding more fabric to it
So that they could pull their stirrups even higher higher than the manufacturer head-to-head intended
Well Service may have had this functional origin they quickly lost that
And they just became incorporated into the visual language of baseball
I think from many people myself included
It's what we think of
When we think
Pick up a baseball player it's interesting to note that in the pages of the New Yorker
Weekly Magazine
They run a lot of
Cartoons that are a baseball team
And they're cartoonist
Almost invariably
To pick baseball players wearing stirrups even though most actual baseball players today
Do not wear
I played in
Kids baseball league and
I remember how official seeming
And functional Stirrup seem to be
Despite the fact that you know with contemporary soft technology they are rendered essentially function with
But it seems that the romance is gone by the time you get to the big leagues
Shadowsocks
Why do you wear your pants down and in the answer I often get is
It's just so much less work
You know if you leave your pants any shoot oxy.
Leaf blower maintenance
Essentially
You don't have to worry about your socks be
You don't have to worry that your stirrups are both started at the exact same
Hi Tor level
You don't have to keep looking and checking to make sure that they're just so
Just like most of us know when we walk around with
Get out slacks or jeans or whatever
Pants that you wear your pants love you really have to worry about what's going on underneath them
And so it's it's just easier and I understand
If there's a villain in the story of baseball hosiery
That role would be filled by George Hendrick
Who played for the Cardinals and A's and some other teams in the 70s and 80s he's now the first base coach of the Tampa Bay Rays
He's the one that's most often credited or blamed
As the most influential player in the move towards long pants
And he White
To wear his pants down
Toward his ankle which by today's standards is pretty tame but by the standards of the year he played in
Wisin is radical
He showed very very little of his socks are stirrups and
Some people thought it were
Weird
Dumpy your dignified or whatever but there were other players who thought it look
Different and therefore Innovative and therefore
Cool
What major league baseball players
As sock style do you most admire
At this point I mean it's pretty Slim Chickens In terms of Hosiery Heroes nowadays because there aren't
Many players who wear stirrups
Begin with N and even fewer who wear stirrups
The way I like to
I like the style I like
The best I would say is a pitcher named Josh
Outman
Which is a great name for baseball right out now
He's a picture
Fires out
Where's a real 1970
Freestyle stirrups
I love
What about the people don't
How much but he's number one
Reed Johnson
Who's an outfielder you wear Stirrups in a not too shabby way
But the fact that I have to search my
Medical database
To come up with three or four players
It's just not that great interns
It starts now there are other players who do
Hike their pants up high and just
Wear solid color socks and and do so pretty nicely
Play Curtis Granderson
He looks great in uniform
Stephen Strasburg of the Washington Nationals
What's the young Phenom pitcher
Does something great called blousing
Is he doesn't just hike
Pants up butt
Stocks under the
The cop in a way where it just sort of
Blouses out a little bit
Sit under
Instead of just watching them up the way Alex Rodriguez does for example
And that sort of a lost art
Clausen Jim Thome
Retired Slugger
Play from any team
Great great browser
All-time browser
So
There are lots of little elements here
There is absolutely no doubt
V the Final Cut
Peace in clear see-through saying
Jim Thome former Slugger for the Cleveland Indians
Great glauser excellent
Excellent all-time great blaster
Oh man
99% invisible was produced this week by Jesse Thorn within Greenspan Avery troubleman Katie mingle and me Wilma
Jesse Thorn is the host of the NPR program Bullseye the best pop culture interview
Program around today.
Stop it is
Fantastic if you want to learn about the good stuff in popular culture
TV movies book
Music video games this is essential listening in iTunes or go to maximum fun
One.org
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce
The offices of arcsin
A group of Architects who would never dishonor architectures Hosiery heritage
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer
Composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24
Right here on the 99 pi
We need to talk about some
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info
Podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We have more stories about design all the time on Facebook Twitter and Tumblr
We keep our pants rolled to our knees and our syrup straight
I-99 Beyond
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Cost of your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth Park
Dot-com