99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind
A different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
During the Cold War a so-called Iron Curtain separated eastern and western Europe
Communism capitalism
The Soviet Union
From everyone else
In some places it was an actual wall like in Berlin
In another place is it was just a bar
Wire fence
This border was Wong
Stretching from northern Finland through Central Europe
It covered 12 and a half thousand km
Or almost 8000 Miles
Is 8000 Mile border
There was a no man's land
Couple hundred yards across
Where there was almost no human activity
When the Cold War ended and the walls and fences came down people notice something interesting
Beth reporter ended Fitzgerald
This neglected strip of land
With Forest
Stanfield's
It was a Haven
Particularly for migratory Birds
Soon after the Berlin Wall fell conservationists from east and west
Came together to protect this
Accidental Refuge
For birds and animals
Because the no-man's-land was so long
They realize that it could link habitat
Throughout Central Europe
Today the so-called European green belt
Traces the path of the Old Iron Curtain
It connects National Park
Books and nature preserves
And helps animals move around in a landscape
Dominated by humans
It's what's known as a wildlife corridor
Wildlife corridors can link to extremely large habitats like to National Parks or to National Forest
National forest and National Park
Across a very large freeway
Or it can link relatively small hat fragments of habitats within very developed metropolitan area
Louise Mozingo
She's chair of the Department of landscape architecture and environmental planning at the University of California Berkeley
And she says
The wildlife Corridor doesn't have to be a massive Greenway for Europe
Tubidy is something as simple as our
Concrete pipe or a small kind of vegetated ditch under
Freeway
Wildlife corridors might be the most critical in urban areas
Because
Sprawling cities and highways have fragmented a lot of wildlife habitat
And if forced animals into isolated pockets
What is the problem
Because animals need to move around
In order to find different food sources
In Southern California in abandoned highway underpass
Began to link two important pieces of habitat in an otherwise industrial area
What they found is that
Both of these habitats zones actually were able to support much larger populations than expected
Because this
Relatively small concrete underpass
Was able to connect the two habitats ranges
And so you had
Even very large a predator species like mountain lions being able to be seen
Supported
Buy these
Fragments of habitat in a very urbanized situation
Today the abandoned underpasses purposely protected
And maintained as a wildlife corridor
But Wildlife corridors don't technically have to be court ordered
They can be any piece of design the facilitators the safe passage of animals through the human built environment
From one piece of habitat to another
And they're not
Always a product of accident and neglect
Sometimes they're very intention
And carefully designed
One of the oldest examples of humans designing a passageway for Animals is the fish ladder which helps mug
Dory species of salmon and steelhead trout get over dams that block their annual migrations up river to spawn
First patented by a Canadian lumber mill owner in 1837
The standard fish ladder is a series of Terrace pool
With just enough space between them
Slowly climbing the ladder to the other side of the dam
The design takes a natural ability to swim upstream
Rapids Andover small waterfalls
So quick lesson in Salmon migration
7 babies hatch in the upper reaches of a river and immediately
Are making their way down the river to the ocean they hang out at sea for a few years and then
Miraculously swim their way back up the exact same river to lay their eggs using magnetic fields
Can smell to navigate
But in the early 20th century
Company started building giant hydroelectric Dam
On almost every major river
In the United States
And they were way too big for a salmon to jump over
And so at some of these dams Engineers installed fish ladders
To help the salmon out
And fish water temp worked well over the years
Part of the problems with fish ladders is that they
They tend to be very expensive
To build that's Todd delegan
My name is Todd delegan I am the vice president of Business Development with whoosh Innovations
You'll understand where the name music
Comes from
Amazon
Today there are about 8288
8000 barriers in the country that
Have
An elevation of 5 feet or more
88000 dams that fish have to get around a little hard to tell how many actual fish Passage
Installations are at these barriers
All around.
Check the country
But it is somewhere between
10 + 15%
We estimate
There are a lot of places where a lot of fish aren't getting anywhere
At all
Because of the barriers that
Exist
And that's where Todd's company
Whoosh
Comes in
Becoming flying fish
The whoosh
Fish Cannon
The salmon
Cannon & Cannon actually started out as an apple
The founder of the company Vince Bryan
Owens Orchards along the Columbia River in Eastern Washington
Any notice that the pickers were
We're spending a lot of their time carrying fruit from the tree to
The storage bin
What's in the center of the orchard
It was inefficient
So Vince and Todd built this softube
Kind of like a fire
Inside the tube
They generated a pressure differential capable of sucking an apple hundreds of feet
And depositing it gently in a storage bin
So they have this effective device for apple picking
But pretty soon they're thinking
Bigger
In the Pacific Northwest
Nothing is bigger
Insane
The Columbia was once one of the world's great Salmon Run
But today 14 Dam
Block the fishes path home
And the Columbia salmon migration is a thing of the past
We were
Working in the or apple orchards in Eastern Washington right along the Columbia River
Visit Todd could actually see two of Columbia's dams from The Orchard and Wheatley serve looked at each other and said will what if you could
Put a salmon in the tube
The idea seems ridiculous
The first
But they couldn't let it go
So Benton Todd head back home to their shop
We set up a fruit tube in our shop and it was about
25 Ft Lauderdale
And we went to the store and bought it
A dead salmon
Small dead salmon in a couple dead trout
Did they put the fish in the tube
Popped out on the other side
And then we went out and bought some live tilapia
To see if he was transported through our old agriculture or air filter tube would cause any effects
The fish are the fish going to live
And attitude was about 22
25 feet long also
Hawaii floppy anma
Went flying into a tank of water and they just
Slammer and immediately and had no issues
Use I in a WeChat I-5
It was it was great
So from there they said about retrofitting there apple tube
To transport fish
And a few months later the salmon Cannon was born
But
Okay it's not
ReliaCard
They aren't being blasted out
In any way shape or form
Canon by whoosh innovation
Works like this
First they have to get the fish to swim into the tube
Salmon evolve to swim upriver
Pass Rapids
Hanover waterfall
And they're attracted to
Well
To the company built a false rapid
In front of the
In essence
Samaire small waterfall with
Spinoza fishing float
To get the
The salmon to a particular place
A Wong the barrier
They are attracted to the flow
Up and over they come over this way
First
Step
And literally they will
Speak directly guided right into our tube itself once inside the tube
A pressure differential moves the fish forward
So that fish then
Accelerate
Through the rest of that to Weatherby
50 ft
300 ft
They're traveling somewhere between
15 + 22
2 feet a second
Inside the tube it's soft and slippery
With almost no friction
They are in essence
Say slippy slide
And see some videos where the Fisher actually
Almost swimming they're doing their natural
Swimming action through the tube itself and when they reach the top of the dam
Then they find themselves
Right back and right back in the river
So they can continue their jaw
On the other side of the
The salmon Cannon is still pretty new
Right now it's being used on the new Sugar River in Washington State
And they're trying to sell the system to fish and wildlife agency
Throughout the region
A lot of scientists who have tested the system seemed excited particularly because it seems to cause that's little stress
For the fish
But not everyone who cares about
It's so gung-ho
It seems like if your
Need to resort to a cannon
To get a fish
Moving through a river system
That maybe there's something more fundamental wrong with the infrastructure along the river system
This is David Montgomery
I'm a professor of geomorphology at the University of Washington
And I'm the author of the book
The king of fish the Thousand-Year run of salmon
And David's point is look
The fish can it may very well be able to get an adult salmon over a damn safely
Ncpa
But that's just treating a symptom
A deeper problem
In some cases
Rivers with lots of dams are even really Rivers anymore
Just look at the Columbia River
Lititz a series of lakes
Let me you can go water skiing on it on the Columbia
Reservoir
And that creates
Problems that things like fish ladders and Salmon cannons camp
When Salmon eggs hatch
The babies need to get back down the river
To the ocean
They just got out of the car
Oriented themselves and the river took them to the Sea
Now what happens if the river is no longer River insist series of lakes to swim all the way down
They didn't evolve to do that
This has been a problem for a long time
But not enough
On some Rivers
People have resorted to transporting baby salmon Downstream with boats and
David's not trying to single out the same thing
There's been a whole host of Technology
The people have experiment
Really the underlying problem is that you've ecologically turned a mighty River into a series of lakes
The Washington state government spends millions of dollars every year on fish ladders and other efforts to get fish around
Dams but the numbers
Are still way down
Around the Puget Sound where I live around Seattle
We're estimated to be down about 10% of the salmon that we had historically
Throughout the region it's somewhere be like 5 or 8% in the Columbia River at his down to 2% by river
Salmon decline is complicate
It has to do with several factors
You're such as overfishing and habitat
And I think that that's
Characteristic of a lot of environmental systems they're actually more complex
Then we realize and the worry is that many of these technological solutions to environmental problems
Only saw the piece of the problem
Without dealing with the overall health
Tobiko
You might be able to get the fish up the river
The river itself
Is still broken
With that in mind
People have recently started calling on the government to remove old dance
And return entire Riverside
Their free-flowing stay
The idea that you
Could actually take a major Dam out
20 years ago is crazy talk
I mean that was just not something that you would certify
That people would talk about as a serious political or social possibility
But now it's happening
After years of protest
Spy indigenous people and conservation groups
Danza come down on the Sandy River in Oregon
And the elwha river in Washington State
And the salmon have begun to come back
We're not going to get rid of every damn damn in the country
But a lot of them are reaching the end of their structural lifetimes and some are just not
Profitable anymore
And in those cases David wants us to look at each one on a case-by-case basis and ass
Well what about this damn
Does this one still make sense
Todd deligan
Supports taking out
Nonprofit
Spell concern for anti-dam act
Devices that Technologies like the salmon Cannon
Could slow down these effort
Or even enable more dams to be built because companies
Don't worry about the same in migration people design solution so that
And that's a worry with Wildlife corridors more generally
Why my quarters cannot be a substitution for preservation of
Quijada
That's Louise Mozingo again from UC Berkeley
The reconnection of fragmented landscapes
Should not
Be an excuse to destroy existing really high-quality have
That's we have too few of them
And we need to preserve the ones that are functioning really well that are supported large and diverse
Iyy population
Corridors only really make sense she says in places where habitats have already been fragment
And now you can knit them back together in ways that support if not a robust population it
Adequate population for the species to survive
Situation
Humans have already had a huge impact
Design for the benefit of Na
Could be the key to keeping Wildlife around
We spent most of the twentieth century carving up and dividing the landscape with impossible objects
Made up Asphalt and concrete
If you zoom in
You can see the effort to stitch together habitats with the tiniest of threats that can make all the difference
Crab ladder hair
Salamander tunnel there and that's great
But if we're honest
We can't fix every problem we created by building something new
For a species like salmon to survive in the modern world it's going to take a patchwork approach of addition and
Subtraction Sometimes the best thing for wildlife is for us to just do our best
To stay out of the way
99% invisible West produce this week by Emmett Fitzgerald
With Katie mingle Sam Greenspan
Delaney Hall Kolstad Avery trufelman Sharif Youssef
And me Roman Mars
We are product of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced at the offices at Mark Center
In architecture and Interiors firm
Beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the beat
Bongs
Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm
Listen to an Alexa interact
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Voice technology talk
It is a creationist
Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights.
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can find this show and like a show on Facebook Rowland Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but right now you can be
One of the first to see our brand new completely redesigned home on the internet that's fully responsive in a
Achingly beautiful it's a 99 Pi. Org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get
The jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com