99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Over the years I guess about 20 people have written to us suggesting that we
We do a story about The Mysterious Giant concrete arrows that. The US landscape from New York to San Francisco
You don't know these are about seventy feet of what looks pretty much like sidewalk Concrete in the shape of an arrow pointing
Bakery
West the date for the 1930s and they were part of the Transcontinental Airway system that help planes carrying mail
Find their way across the US before the age of reliable radar and GPS
When they were operational they were painted bright yellow were accompanied by a tower topped with a bright rotating Beacon
Today the towers and paint are long gone but many of the giant arrows remain
Sometimes with weeds poke
Do the cracks like a
Crete
They're super cool and fun to find on Google Maps
That's about it
There's not too much more of a story there
I'm glad I know it I'm pleased about it
Totally of 99% invisible
Story
And I'm honored when people learn about them and they think
I need to send this to Roman
But ultimately
The arrows are not something on which we can hang a whole episode
We come across these kinds of stories all the time
Not Justa suggestions from the audience but in our own research
There are tons of little
Interesting
Would be 99 Pi story
Cut out of an episode or just
Don't want it 6 weeks of production in 20 minutes of airtime for whatever
But we still kind of love
So as a little change of pace we thought we throw them all together
In a couple of episodes featuring me interviewing the 99 Pi crew
Talking about their favorite
Mini store
That's what we've been calling
I think you're going to take it
I certainly had fun talking to
So without further ado
First.
Is Sam Greenspan
What are my favorite things about this job is that I get to go to research at the University of California at Berkeley Library
In the environmental design Library
And it's a smart building
The library itself has all these Vasily chair set
Might actually be able to buy house but
Anyway
I was over there I was doing research on the story that would eventually become the plot of Zion which aired on the show last week
Yeah that's that this is worried about those were the founders vision for the Church of Latter-day Saints in
Pinto Lake City in their efforts to create like an Urban Brick of really big
Exact
Exactly
I was reading this article just in my research there
Called the Mormon Village
Genesis and antecedents of the city of Zion plan
By Richard H Jackson published in the journal
Brigham Young University studies 1977
Here's the author of this article talking about how most towns west of Appalachia all kind of developed
The same way and so Roman if you would read this quote from him
The cities and towns which were founded during this period were remarkably similar
With the exception of Circleville Ohio
Most town-plots consisted of a regular grid pattern
With straight streets Crossing at writing
Ashley I
I grew up
In Newark Ohio which is only about 30 miles away from Circleville Ohio so I know Circleville
I don't know if I've been there like it famous for
Mountains like an Indian Barrel
Funny you should mention that will Circleville is also known for something else or maybe not known for something else but it has
A quite amazing history
Up urban planning
To look so what did you find out
Okay so from that one glib note in this
In this journal article about morning villages
I found this other article in the Journal of the Society of architectural historians for 1955 Sky name John
BMW wraps
And it had an article entitled
Redevelopment in the 19th century
Colon
The squaring of Circleville of Circleville power broker
Pickaway County Ohio named Daniel Dreisbach
Was deputized to establish a new town will become the county seat
Dreisbach decided on a piece of land to head to Native American Earthworks
Mounds basically one in the shape of a square and one the shape of a circle in central Ohio
These types of melons are like
Will incorporate into landscape still life
I grew up going to Indian Mound Mall Newark Ohio and so they're in Newark they're in Circleville
They're all around there's a big their big part of the landscape and the carnival or
And the Mystique
Central Ohio
And they really are like
In the center of the city like there was no regard for them they just put
City on top
Of the mountain
Circleville is totally case of that Daniel Dreisbach
Just wanted to plop a city right on top of this
Native American Mound
But what he did that his contemporaries found so weird
Was that he used the circular
Earthwork
To build a city with a circular grid
So normally so imagine we're kind of like
Floating over a city you can kind of see
They're floating over Chicago right now
Big
Salt Lake City all kind of crossing at right angles
It's just sort of like you know grid-like wrap paper
So this looks more like
The wheel of a pirate ship
Right what's the steering wheel of a pirate ship
There's a storage Central node
And an Android box plan there was the the county courthouse would be in the middle and there's kind of a big closet around
And then there's
A circular Street around that and then another circular Street around that one
It'll be sort of
These roads that I'll shoot off from the courthouse that all kind of connect
Outwards that all lead back into
The center of the Earth
Which is all being formed
Mighty circular
Indian male
Yeah I was sort of the framework
Matt was going to give me idea
Established
The early eighteen hundreds
People start moving in
But to the founder Daniel Dreisbach sis may
The circle villains
Heat it
Like really really hate it
It was dismissed as
Childish sentimentalism
People complain that the round Street
It's made for awkwardly shaped Lots
The Builder house is kind of in a weird ways
So 1837 about 30 years
The people were so fed up with this circular grid
They appealed the Ohio State Assembly
They just wanted some Ohio
Squaresville more less so
They hired a company
Call the Circleville squaring company yeah
And squaring company was hired to D Circle Circleville
Two decades but eventually they were successful so
Today if you go to Google Earth and you look up
Circleville Ohio
Zoom in
It just does a grid it looks like
Every other
Bordentown
In central Ohio to Circleville square and Company was extremely excited
They did their job
For sure All That Remains are a few around the buildings I hear I haven't been there
Never been changed
Reminder have not yet called it squaresville
And the City of Municipal seal
That's pretty nice it's like it's like
It looks like the original Urban plan
I believe that's Daniel box
Original
Drawing
Or some some kind of
Reproduction based on Dreisbach
Original plan where you can see the courthouse in the middle and you can come see all the
The other radio streets coming off of it
Yeah it looks really cool pretty good co
It reveals some good history
That's so cool I mean don't put on a flag that's a good to you
Yeah I think it's like she just beat you know the
History of the Pirates
That would work
So I'm Kurt Kolstad and I am the digital director
At 9% invisible
As well as I went
What is that mean
Basically means I manage
Content and design on the website
So we produce articles for the website
We also please companion piece
For every episode
That contain additional materials
Videos
Lynx images
So
People listen via episode can go on the website listen to the episode but also surf around 4
Traditional media
Right
So if you are listening tonight
But you never been to the website
You are missing out because there's at least
Two and maybe three more stories a week
Better on the website
That
Have nothing to do with what is being
Write 2 in a lot of cases we have
An idea for a story and there's just kind of not enough there for
As to make a full episode
But it wouldn't be long enough it wouldn't be in-depth enough
Or simply to visualize a lot of cases
If it's something that
You need absolutely need to see a graphic
An image or a video for
The subject matter to make sense
We're going to have to make that into an article instead of an episode
But the topics are really the same it's you know it's built environments it's
CNN News
99% invisible things you see at the world
Do not make sense of
And it's a lot of cases these ideas they've been kicking around in the office for years and now they've kind of finally
An outlet in the form of what
Which one is like
Quintessential
Really popular one that
That would be
So the Dutch reach
Has been a real hit this year and I don't think anybody expected
It's a pretty short piece
How about a pretty simple fix
Two pretty common problems that just resonated with listeners and readers in a way that nobody could have
So what is the Dutch race
Dutch reach is basically a technique
For keeping bikers
Cyclist that is
Scrum getting doored
So
If you're driving along you got a Viking Land on your right and parking to the right at bat
And you pull over into a parking spot
And you go to open the car door
And a cyclist is coming
You might not see
And that's because in part
You're opening the door with your left hand
If you're an American driver
And
You're just you know you look in the rearview mirror you might not spot them
But there's one simple way to make sure that every time you open a car door you're looking to see if cyclists are approaching
And that's by reaching over yourself
With your other arm to open the door
Saloniture I have this
So you pull over
And instead of opening the car door with your left hand which
Inclined to do
You reach over with your right hand
And it causes you to come
Westin look over your shoulder
And really check
If there's a cycle
Exactly
And
It's very simple solution
Doesn't have any Associated cost it doesn't take any extra
Time Italy any driver could do in any bites of this
Be grateful that
The driver is doing
It's a solution we can all relate to it something that deals with a problem built environment
Probably isn't going to be fixed anytime soon other ways
It just costs too much and takes too much time for cities to overhaul these systems course and Ideal World we'd have protect
Bike Lanes
And I need to know everything to be perfect
But
In the world we live in this Dutch reach solution
Which comes from Holland
Hence the name
It gives drivers a way to
To do something simple that will help improve safety
She for everybody involved
Interested
What's all that
I just shared it
Like crazy because it was something you could like understand quickly
It's giving sort of common sense but it's one of the Great
Like a perfect sort of story like the exes
You witness early figure out on your own
But when you see it
It feels like
Exactly it's the kind of solution that once we
Eurostar
Teaching people to do this and driver's education
It would just become second nature and we wouldn't even think about it as
The Dutch reach it would just be
The way you open a car door
Cool
All right
Thanks
Tell me who you are
Yeah my name is Emmett
Fitzgerald
To use came on like a few months ago
Yeah I came in
Help out when
Delaney
Wizometer
We decided to
What kinds of little stories that maybe
You'll be researched as producers and reporters butt
Don't really quite qualify as a full nine NPI stories were there like little things were cut out of other stories so
So what is you are a minister
This is a story about a special soccer stuff
TDM in the northern Brazilians
State of amapa
Like a super remote status
Order something
1000 people
And
90%
Amazon
Rainforest
But there are a couple little
The capital city
Maca powder
And
Maca pot
Is known or is assertive
Visit there one of the things that
There
Write on me
Equator and the number of landmarks
Signifies
Where the equator is in the
City including
One of the Central Street is called Avenida equatorial which
Rotten
Supposedly along the Equator and has a red stripe
Center of
Of the street and another thing that sits
Right on the equator is that the
City soccer
Which is
10000 person
Arena
That's called estadio Milton Correa
Local soccer
Bureaucratic
But everyone just calls me meme
The big 0
After after the stadiums
Urbini equator is the 0
The stadium itself sits on a latitude line video on the equator but that
The equator runs directly
Down the Midfield line of
Death of the football pitch
Soccer field
And so
Small Brazilian
Professional soccer clubs but because of the midpoint lies the equator it's like
Each side
In the game
Is representing an entire hemisphere small local Club games are are really like
Battle between North and South
Middle East in Asia
Teen suicides
And you know it
That's kind of all there is
My look up on YouTube some games in
And she are you know for the sake of it here's a clip of someone scoring a goal
The big 0
Tell me your name
My name is Delaney Hall
What are you doing here
I'm a reporter and producer
Sometimes I edit
So what is your mini story
So my mini story actually came to us from one of our listeners
Woman named Carrie Nugent from
Because I was at a conference
And
She had on very memorably
A camouflage baseball hat
With orange letters that said
Asteroid
Yeah I mean she is an asteroid Hunter she's an asteroid scientist at
Caltech
And she actually has her own
Podcast called space pod
Where she talks with different scientists who study space
So our listeners right in a lot
Saying you should do story about this so you should
It was right about that and
Kerry suggested one that I
Really like
So what is about
Before I can tell you
What carries suggested I have to back up a little bit so earlier this year there was this enormous
Discovery in astronomy
And there's an experiment called the laser interferometer gravitational-wave Observatory
The shorter way to refer to it as ligo
And scientists working on that experiment detected a signal
From space
They turned into a sound
So I'm going to play the sound for you
Am I listening for the one that one that's going
What that sound that sound is the sound of two black holes collide
Riding an unleashing
The energy of a million trillion Suns
Doesn't actually sound like much and that's because the black holes Collide a bill
Million years ago
And so the sound has been traveling through space for all of those years getting fainter and fainter as it goes
And by the time it actually reached us here on Earth it was just that little boy
But the scientist amazingly
Heard it
Why is it so amazing
Because it is the first
Direct evidence of gravitational waves
Which are
Physically ripples in space-time
And gravitational waves were predicted more than a hundred years ago by Einstein in his theory of Jen
General relativity
And that Siri totally reimagined the rules of his
Basically instead of a static framework
Einstein had this Theory
That matter and energy
Could actually do
Stewart
The geometry of the universe
And create these ripples of grab
And so he had theorized
Do gravitational waves exist
But this sound was the first evidence that there
Real
And so it basically was evidence that this wild Siri that Einstein had that have been mathematically prove
Prevent
It seems like
Well
Yeah yeah it was
Kind of mind-blowing
The discovery generated at
None of news
Obviously
But as carry our listener Rodan to point out
There is a design angle
I'm always in favor of design angles
What she was interested in and what she said you should really look at is the instrument
The machine that detected the sound
Is amazing
An extremely
You know it would have to be sensitive in order to pick up a sound that's been
Traveling through space and decaying for a billion years
So Carrie said you should do a story about this instrument
The detective the sounds
Why did we do that story cuz it's so hard drive its like the Somme
How much technical detail will probably
Saying things that are wrong right now even in a mini story it's just it's
You know it's too technically complex and sort of difficult to describe on the radio I mean the machine
Peanuts office light
Part of its in one part of the country and part of its another part of the gun is like
Like stretch
Really complicated but
There was this one element to it that that I love and that I think
We can do justice to right now
So basically the detectors on this instrument
They had to be totally isolated
From the vibrations and noises of the outs
World
Because
Environmental noise might have interfered with what
The scientist
Actually trying to hear
So they're trying to hear this tiny faint sound
And then meanwhile there's just everyday noise all around them
Trucks driving by
People talking rumbles of the Earth
Wind
At everything
There might be a thunderstorm
All of that noise
Can meth with
So basically to deal with that
The scientist first of all tried to isolate the
And they put them in giant
Isolate them from from all that outside noise
And then on top of that
The experiment employed
Two people
Who were environmental Mana
So their job is to figure out
How environmental sound
Might interfere with the experiment
Terry actually talked
To the guy who ran the Explorer
Dr. Dave Ramsey
He's the head of ligo and here he is
And they do tests
So dope
Speakers
In the vacuum time either vacuum tanks and you can
Play your favorite Symphony and
Measure its effect
Yeah so they they play these recordings they did stuff like Brew play recording the
Howlin Wolf
And they even had a staff member
Ride-away on his Harley to record the effect that the rumbling motor had on the
Experiment
Is a great entry
By the team that was doing the environmental monitoring
Bubba rides off in a motorcycle
Facility managers in Hanford and he was doing a test for
And so over time they generated this
Huge library of
What different kinds of Sonic interference might do to the experiment
Genuine signal appeared
They would know
That it wasn't just
Environmental noise
I thought I was in love
Did it wasn't Bubba
It's hard to convey like how crazy it is
Is the day were able to detect this sound
Another crazy thing is they detected it
Like right after they turned the experiment
It was my mistake this is one of the biggest
Side effects
Discoveries ever yeah yeah and I I I really love this kind of science story or
Or this detail about sort of depressed
I'm just all the mundane everyday
Stuff that can
Get in the way of that grand Magna
That's okay
So we should thank you
Yes yes
Tom so thank you dr. Carrie Nugent
She's one of our listeners
And she did a whole interview with dr. Dave racing
Is the head of ligo it's on her podcast
It's called space
Pod
And she just know so much more about
If you have any questions or complaints
To read them the doctor New Delhi
So that was many stories volume 1
In the final episode of 2016
I interviewed all the 99 Pi producers for this project
So you hear the rest of the crew on the 1st
Episode of
In the meantime
We're all going to take some time off
But I'd also like to use this time to collect a few mini story suggestions from you is kind of like
That I can talk about in between the stories
Katie sarife
Andy Breon mini stories volume
To get in touch with me the contact page on a website that's 99p I. Order on Twitter at Roman Mars or at 99 Pio
Or or you can comment on the Facebook post for this happen
If you are sad that you will not have a new 99percentinvisible episode for the next couple of weeks
Go download a bunch of the old one
We almost never run repeats but they're all there in the feet
Just waiting for you
Most of you probably haven't heard everything and if you have heard everything you probably won't remember everything
I barely remember them and I was there when we made them
Just go download every month
I hope you have some good time off from your way
I'll talk to you next year
99percentinvisible is Katie mingle Delaney Hall
Better if you save Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza
And me
Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God.
Ubuntu show into instructions about the show on Facebook and tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99pi org
We're on Instagram and Tumblr to
Did you want really fully understand the show until you spend some time
. org
Twin boys metal and Carver huge chunks of my days were spent pushing them around the Hills
Rules of East Bay in a giant double stroller
Listening
Podcast
So this is in early 2008 and that's when I discovered my first
True love in podcast
The bugle
Audio newspaper
Provigil world
It was one of most popular comedy podcasts in the world presented by Andy zaltzman and John Oliver who at the time was newly at
The Daily Show after it finished its run of the Times online it went independent
Donated my own money that keep it going
They would follow for a bit while both John and Andy got busy with other things
And a while ago I heard from Andy sister radiotopia Zone Helen Salzman
That Andy was looking to make it his primary focus again
And I'm incredibly excited that is now part of radiotopia with Andy and a rotating set of coop
Including Wyatt Cenac
Mr. Kumar and my favor
Helen zaltzman
With everything going on in the world
Really excited that we have a hilarious news satire program with a Global Perspective
React to what's going
Please welcome them to radiotopia And subscribe
Some people
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
Evan I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com