99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When you're a comic book fan there's always a surge of excitement when they announced a film adaptation of the
Character you love the chance to see your hero punch
In Twisted movie through the air to make spaghetti
But there's always that fear that Hollywood is going to screw it up that the screenwriter won't get the care
The way you get the character because you know how it's supposed to be you know Mary Jane came after
Gwen Stacy it doesn't make sense the other way
But the first indication whether you're going to be buzzing with eager anticipation while you're in line on opening day
Card reading each step while you're in line on opening day because let's face it you're going to go no matter what
First indication of how good or how bad it's going to be happens months before when they reveal the design
Of the suit
Superhero suits made real with a real Fabric and real people are very hard to design
But we will judge them not know why
That is our job
You reckon much more mellow over the years or the suits have gotten much much better
Eric molinsky has noticed this too
Eric has done a couple of great episodes for us at 9 p.m. over the years but now he has his own podcast called imaginary world
About sci-fi and other fantasy genres
How we create these worlds and why we suspend our disbelief
This is an episode that he produced in 2015 about designing comic book costumes for movie screens and I really like it and I
I know that you're going to like it too it's called fixing the hobo suit
Let's not stand on ceremony here
If you haven't seen The Dark Knight Rises
Tom Hardy plays the villain
Bait
And for some reason
The voice is a cross between Sean Connery
And Darth Vader
Given that the character is supposed to come from a fictional Latin American country
It was a very weird choice
Darkness is your ally you merely adopted the dark
But it was so weird
It was kind of amazing
And led to all these really great parities
I believe I would like two packs of AAA sauce thank you
But for all the buzz Around The Voice
I was surprised more people didn't talk about the
Costume
Which I thought was ingenious
So in the comics Bane looks kind of like a Mexican wrestler
He's got a black hood over his
With a white design the middle that
Kind of looks like a skull with red eyes
His strength
Comes from tubes going to his back that
Pum pum full of liquid
Steroids
And back to shoulders are so huge and bulked out
Artist like to draw his head below his neck
It's no way you could do a literal version of that
But that didn't stop Joel Schumacher from trying
In his 1997
Catastrophe
Batman and Robin
Freehold
We Are Evil killing machine
I call this little number
Of course Christopher Nolan's Batman to play some kind of a semi-realistic universe
So he and Lindy Hemmings costume design
Turn beans liquid steroids into a gas that he inhales
But it doesn't make him super strong and actually dulls physical pain
His breathing apparatus is the same shape as the design on the hood in the comics but
The breathing apparatus is black in the design in the hood with white course not wearing a hood in the movie
Instead we see the actress bald head so if you squint
Beans head in that movie looks like the exact same design as the comics
But the negative image of it of course they couldn't give Bane like cartoonishly huge
Shoulders
So instead he wore a coat
They had a very high round wool collar
They gave him the same silhouette at the comic books
Like I said it was a brilliant design solution
Impossible
Superhero costumes used to be
Cringe-worthy
Even the cool ones like you know Batman from the Tim Burton films
The costume was so bulky
Michael Keaton couldn't turn his head
Or fight unless they bad guys basically ran into his fists
So what happened how did the costumes get so much better
I Michael Wilkinson and I'm a costume designer for film
Michael worked on Manor
Steal any upcoming sequel Batman verse
Superman
He got a lot of heat from a new bat
Because the first images
It look like Ben Affleck
Was wearing a thick rubber
How it wouldn't be able to turn his head with
Feel like a step backward
But newly released images
Show The Dark Knight turning his head
I feel like I play When the world has a really good look at the the Cowell then we're as
I have people like it's a lot of work went into
The construction of that is all sorts of amazing
Things going on inside that cow
Let's make it
Easy to move in and I have a full range of expressions
Superhero costumes stand-alone works of fashion which over
Time became dated
Cringe-worthy
Even if they were designed by a genius
Like Edna Mode in The Incredibles
What do you mean
Distracts from the now
If ground beef
Something classic
She had a crazy look in the boots
One of the big changes is that costume designers
Are now looking more closely The Source material
When Michael Wilkinson and his collaborator James Atchison worked on Man of Steel
They research the history behind Superman's costume
The Genesis of that idea was
That you know II perform as the weight lifters and
Strongman
Had this look around you know
Ellabel Jazzy tights when they're so short
Over the top
Superman suit was kind of like a combination of the weightlifter
In the ringmaster who wore boots in a cave
Also swashbuckling Heroes like Zorro wear capes so James and Michael thought
Best to communicate strength power Adventure
But I will be going to resolve those silly Redondo
So we went through
Dozens and dozens of drawing
And I remember that pretty much just got smaller and smaller and smaller until one day they took
Kind of once they're on the illustration.
That was the look we decided to go with
What's the S stand for
On my world it means hope
Sammy Sheldon differ
Had a similar experience working on X-Men first Class
The previous X-Men movie
The mutants were wearing assertive
Black leather outfits
Just a few distinguishing characteristic
But the director first class
Coupon
Told Sammy that he wanted to go back to the original comic
The X-Men or yellow and blue jumps
I'm sorry
Given the LBC
Pheasant is a very simplistic
Join that was on the
I just started researching into
The. Of the time
Why they were drawn The Way They Were
What the colors were represented
And what immediately came out with
In 1963
Discovered
Tesla
It felt to me like maybe that's what they were trying to represent in the comic
So we kind of went down this route
Seeing if that would work for us and also what natural
The Advent of the nuclear age
May have accelerated mutation process
Individuals with extraordinary abilities may already be
Among Us
She pulled it off the costumes with cool very six
But honoring the source material is
It's Tricky
Comic book
Illustrators
Not that they don't understand but they don't need to
Make a logic of the lines of that drawing
The where it goes from the front to the back of the body round over-the-shoulder it just won't look school on the page and sells the
That the dynamic of the character
When you put that into reality
You got to follow those lines around the body three
3 + 360
And those characters are wearing skin-tight clothes to show off their
Ridiculously well-defined muscle
For some reason
Is completely believable in the comics
One thing we discovered is that no matter
What incredible shape and actor is in
Once you put a leotard on them then everything is kind of
Smooth out and all that fence
Traffic definition in that I've been working so high
Is kind of negated
The next big leap away from cringe-worthy costumes
Was Tex
Now the old days,
What's going to be printed in a few limited colors
That's why the costumes were usually just one or two maybe three colors
What's good I mean I kind of left off the page
But for movie like man of
Steel
Want to get rid of Superman's red Underpants
And the yellow belt
The suit is very blue
And that's boring to look at in HD
So they created a silver layer that one under the blue give it a metallic quality
And a 3D printer
Detector
To get muscle definition
Ana pattern of ridges which creates visual interest for lighting in cinematography
And they create a backstory to explain that text
It was chainmail
They went under the armor people wore in the Planet Krypton
Another track
Which Sammy's all the different light
Is mixing and matching materials on the same costume
Movie X-Men
Costumes they wear
Layers and layers of fabric soulwax into your
Piece together and then
You know connecting things
If you stand away from they just look white blue with yellow baseball at you when you go in close
Kind of intricately
Stitch to make it textured and
Tunnels in the leather pieces and then
Kevlar in the middle
Auto design
If it's going to be interesting is that you have to take risks
And the thing about superheroes has a fabulous Arena
Take risks
The problem is it's a huge amount of money
So you better make you can take the rest
You better make sure that you
You come up with a good
Because it's an
Open expensive process to get around very angry fans I'll let you know if they don't like it
Define
The producers
Still waiting on this
Somerset saying where where is it
Finally it needs to move
James Atchison had a devil of a time working on the first Spider-Man film
The one with Tobey Maguire in 2002
It's been three months making nearly 70 versions of that suit
How to get the colors right
Making sure the textured webbing seitan
When was finally ready
They took it for a test
We had a stunt man on a Wire
I'm a fluid straight into a tree
And the whole
Suits
Half the webbing
Unglued from the suit I mean it was like it was sort of like a
Terrible waffle
Hanging in the tree
It was such a
Step
Itsfunneh superheroes are supposed to seem indestructible
And maybe there's a scene at the very end where like after the soup
Superheroes been roughed up
Is costumes
Like a little bit tour
But in real life these costumes are
Extremely fragile
Soda solution
It's create 20 or
30 versions of the
The same costume
But each one
Is tailor-made
For the specific needs
Each scene
When Sammy Sheldon differ work on Marvel's Ant-Man
Even that was a
Duke has power
The man harnesses
You should be able to shrink
And grow on a dime
What's your size
Always suits your needs
They want someone to
You know 10 over and over and over
Tumblr
Inet
4 in a rubber floor and then they kind of got well he can't do it and these boots and you have to
You have to go
Okay we have to wait for
Boots that look identical to
The Harry Potter books
And almost like that for
It's a grueling job
Michael Wilkinson says
You really need to sort of step back and realize that
This is really a conversation
Tapping across time
Among designer
You know an Asian. We're over the centuries you take
The figure of Buddha or something like that on
And over the centuries they are refining they putting their own soda stamp on
On these these cultural figures
I don't like that
I feel with
Without making it to Grand
Without superheroes because you know h
Iteration of a superhero reflects a lot about
The society
In which states did they duration was born
He's been giving this a lot of thought
Because he designed the first
Movie version of Wonder Woman
Who will appear in Batman verse
Superman
Carmichael this was a
The dream assignment
The Wonder Woman
You're not close to my heart growing up
She was
The one that really
Captured my imagination and in the strongest way
Really why
There's something about Lynda Carter's performance
They really crossed into this kind of magical world I was fascinated by the
Her backstory
I was lucky enough to actually work with Linda
Picada
On a film called Sky High when she played
The principal
Hefei high school
Pacific Heroes
I had a kind of Seminole experience shopping with her on Rodeo Drive that I Pro
Probably never really
Get over
It was very exciting
I think the reason why costumes have gotten so cool
It's because the designers are now constantly asking themselves
Why
I don't think you can just get away with doing if you need Tommy the funny helmet I think you have to make
Send
Why is that person wearing that suit what does he do with it does he have a power or is it something that the suit gives him
And then a list questions
Lead you onto
How does that work
That's one of the reasons why I love the new Daredevil series on Netflix
In the first season they're actually separate episodes to answer all those questions
Why does he need a padded suit
Why does the suit have to be red
Why does it have horns
She used to say be careful of the Murdock boys
The evolution of Daredevil costume
Becomes the story of the character realizing who he truly is
The costume is like an expression of his real self
The one that he has to dig down and find
Below the surface of his alter ego Matt Murdock
The best costume designers are storytellers
The fans will nitpick but
I don't really feel like there any wrong choices
So long as they make us believe something that's
Wonderful and Ludacris at the same time
I remember spending many many
Many nuts
Set an alarm
In Manhattan
Trying to get
The right color
Screen printed on today
Is Suits over
New York is my favorite
That's great
It's funny too because I am
Because of those films was Spider-Man films when I walk around New York and I've lived here for 11 years
Every so often I look up and I just imagine how great it would be to see Spider-Man swinging through those
Those Canyons of skyscrapers
Yeah
Seriously it kind of bums me out that we don't see him up there every so often going
Will be finished before your next assignment
Bye bye bye
I only need a past job
Sentimental reasons
I'm going to cost to fix the hover search
You're the best of the best e
Fixing the hobo suit was produced by Eric molinsky imaginary worlds
News about the cultural impact of Star Wars
Of course he has
It's a really great show find it an imaginary worlds podcast. Org
So Eric and I both really love the music of melodeon
At least I knew melodium Electro album to celebrate called friendly vehicles
Right now that album is pay-what-you-want on bandcamp or you can get all 29 of his albums
488 Euros which is insane to me totally worth it
Make sure you let me know if you buy his whole discography because you and I
Should be Twitter friends at the very least if you do that
I'm in your life at melodium. Bandcamp.com
99percentinvisible the same Greenspan Kolstad Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars we are project
91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
The finest architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
I got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show in likes on Facebook we're all on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but you can listen to every single app
Episode of 99% invisible. Org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com