99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional net
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is blueprint
I'm Roman Mars
This is sight unseen
This is an ear for design
I'm Roman Mars
This is 99% invisible
The name is important
Tip of the spear with any product
And you're bombarded by thousands of names everyday
And the daily barrage of names only the names that are most interesting
Most Pleasant on the tongue
Can survive in your memory
If it's any kind of consumer product
Like from
PNG or
Sony
It's going to be a name
Company that did it you might not know it but
And naming companies
Event companies that name thing
Are responsible for many of the proper nouns that you remember
Naming it
Weird little area and
Their business right
And then there's Market
And then there's Brandon
And then there's naming naming is so small they're so really there so few naming companies there's like 20
And Laurel founded one of them
My name is Laurel son I'm one of the co-founders of catchword where a naming from here in the Bay Area and cats word
Comes from those guiding words at the top of the dictionary
Those are the cats words
Most people don't know it doesn't matter
It just is
What we do so we're about words
And where about where they're catching
She and her team of worked on everything
Align of yogurts for Chobani
The Palm Pre gaps customer rewards program
They have named
As they put it
Everything except
A car
You might think hey I need my dog or my kids or my band or my
But
There are a number of things to consider when designing the name
Just think of all the associations with every word
Take for example
Photoshop
Sweet name Photoshop
But we did
Come up with the elements
And that word
Took a lot of work because Photoshop was looking to Market a lesson
Expensive version of their software that had all the same capabilities as regular Photoshop
Just without all the bells and whistles
You would think that that would be easy but it wasn't so they didn't want to use Photoshop template for Photoshop basic or anything that sound
Founded compromise
So we went through a really large
Operation of
All the different ways that we could
Say just as good but
Not as
Full
Pledge
And with the essentials wheel
Just every word elements
For its subtlety
Elements are the most basic
Parts that
Can have but they're essentially have anything
So that's the word that we eventually chose
And that's why you hire that
To consider this stuff
And they don't come cheap
The
Vast majority of naming companies like us
Are pretty expensive
Maven companies don't just make up names
They also check what names are available for URLs in for trademark
And they see which names mean bad things in other languages
We can take
I need list of names and check them in any language in the world and say
Is it pronounced
Does it have negative meaning and outside of the u.s. is it is there a brand already existing in your country or
Some of like a TV show that has the same name that we should be aware of
And you can't underestimate the importance of linguistic checks
Once they were naming a little Gadget toy
And one of the names that we could come up with
For them
Turned out in Japanese to be a word that meant a small device that doesn't work
But more than anything else Laurel and her team at catchword Just Produce 8
Con of names as Laurel see that there is a direct relationship between quantity
And quality
You know the first 500 names that you come up with are going to be really obvious things are already taken or not going to be that in
Interesting
You kind of have to get that out
So catch word
Will generate
Over 2000 names
And they present
3252 the client
Because
They come up with names across the naming Spectrum
Spectrum
Because we're talking about languages
So at one end of the Spectre
You have descriptive
And those are names that absolutely just
Describe what the thing is
Classic example
Raisin Bran benefits of
Descriptive names
They are self-explanatory that's what that stuff is right it's a box its brand and it has raisins in it
You would never
How to explain to anybody with this stuff is Shredded Wheat
That's what that is it's weird and it's been shredded
They are hard to own normally you can't trademark names like this in fact Raisin Bran and shredded we are not trademark
Anybody can have cereal and call it Raisin Bran or shorted me so a lot of descriptive names tend to get modified
International Business Machines
Freedom descriptive
Overtime they've convinced that
IBM the other big drawback is that descriptive names can be limited if you remember there were companies called things like
Like
Stamps
Right
If you ever want to do anything but sell electronic stamps you're screwed
On the other end of the spectrum
You got so-called
Arbitrariness
And apple is a great example of
It doesn't tell you anything about what they do
Which allows
For flexibility they used to just make computers now they do media
They could do anything under that I mean they can make cars
Associations maybe Apple implies learning
I don't know but it doesn't apply to me
Arbitrary names can also just be completely made up
And these kinds are called empty vessels
Some examples of Hulu or Exxon or Xerox or Kodak Kodak has absolutely no meaning
They only chose it because that great hardcover sound is very
Acoustically relevant that is it really cuts through we tend to say that things that start with that hard k sound
Are strong things that start with T
Also the same way it's kind of a strong or aggressive sounding name whereas an F sound is very soft
Too harder to hear it and people just don't respond as well to it the benefits of arbitrary names and empty vessel name
They're easy to trademark
Easy to get the domain name for and usually good in languages around the world
Explaining to people even get a lot of money behind these kinds of names.
Tell people what they mean
Right okay so you've got this
Descriptive on one end of the spectrum
An arbitrary on the other
And most names fall somewhere between the two
And Laurel called all these names in the middle suggestiveness
They're not exactly arbitrary and they're not exactly descriptive
Like Microsoft
Microsoft
Software for micro computers right it kind of says what it does but not really because it's those two words that
Taylor Swift together
Microsoft
Is an example of a coined word
A word that doesn't exist in the English dictionary
But it's made up of familiar words word parts
Or sounds Spotify and Nescafe and Netflix are also coin worth
They sound like English words but they're not in Laurel and her team generator
A root words
You try to find the right vocabulary for the client and what they trying to convey in this name make a list of vocabulary and then you
Okay
How can I modify these words and then we have lists
Prefixes and suffixes in English
And then you just start pairing them up
For example take the route name
From there you can get name Ling namely rename name spot name proprof name
But okay let's be honest
There are lots of websites that can match prefixes and suffixes to words and generate big long list for you
But websites are not linguist
They can't tell you what names are actually good that's where the skill and the creative Talent comes in is
Figuring out what's a good word
And you wouldn't think it
But suggested names are really difficult to create
Because you want them to have meaning
Walmart Aiken
Taken for domain names and trademarks
And as Laurel sees it it doesn't hurt to have
2000 option
But it doesn't have to be this way
There are other people who do a very differently they do
10 names at a time
That works for them I think it depends on whether you come from
More strictly an evening background or whether you come from an ad agency background
Didn't you do it that way
We tend to present around
12 names
Because
To present too many in the value of any given name
It's drastically reduced
Eli Altman is the creative director at a hundred monkeys
Another name a company only a few miles away
Riders you're bound to get a good name
It's kind of a joke about the process
They give their client a list of 12 names
It's not like a hundred monkeys produces
Fewer names because they're lazier
You guys just have a really different philosophy
Safita Nae Nae
Some people think that naming is about linguistics
We are not of that philosophy
Names are all about the stories that they begin to tell
Eli and his team do not make coin words are empty vessels
I just don't think
That's
Think about names
Things like that
We're much more interested in
History of a word
Backstory
Really these guys are very intimate ology and narrative
At the meeting I said in on
What name was the small town in Europe where a famous mathematician was born
Others were inspired by anatomical charts and constellations
100 monkeys has the dinner party in mind names that lead to conversation
And in this way
Eli and his team have named front porch senior living communities
The lot
Which is the Rhode Island state lottery
Start here the Microsoft Windows tutorial
Yeah their names a lot of different things
Company's product services
Mysterious
Slim series
Yeah it's true it's called condition diaper eating
Theory for
How
Fast food
Companies
Design food to make it irresistible
Okay condition type reading was kind of a departure for a hundred monkeys
Normally that go for more poetic names
It's just really about
Finding as many
Interesting words as you can
Secret Service codenames 2
Rundown
Theaters to
Types of wind
Ocean currents
And so where is Laurel season naming Spectrum
Eli Envision sort of a name taxonomy
And the classifications breakdown
25 species
25 categories of names
Which he listens book
Don't call it that
Names that are
About people
Tesla
Invented characters
Jolly Green Giant mr. clean
Crown Royal
And it's not like some of these categories are good and some are bad
They're just a lot of option
It mostly comes down to what kind of story if any you want behind your name some clients really want
I'm meeting with name
Remember made up names are easier to register domains are trademarks for and are less likely to offend
And if it's a meaningless word if it's just a completely coined made-up word you can make up any story you want around it
Anemic Hulu for example
As far as I know doesn't actually have any real meaning I know that Hulu the the inventors of that have a story around
And that name I don't think it's true it's a cool name because it's short it's easy to remember
Visually it's very interesting looking
So now you don't need to have a story around
Is this
If you got enough money you could pick any old name to do it
You could pick a name as meaningless as hello yep moneytalks
If you have a ton of money
Basically the name could be any
Remember when the iPad was about to come out
Everyone thought it was the silliest and you heard all kinds of sanitary napkin jokes but now do cheer
Force of will and advertising dollars
You don't think twice about it
But with a name like iPad at least you can pronounce it
Can you imagine reading Xerox for the first time
X0x
Sirope
Fair Oaks
Before they get their new name companies and products usually have little internal codenames or nickname
Like Project X
Store they get named after someone
Cat or something like that
Sometimes
Unfortunately
With the companies will often happen they will have a code name
That someone internally has chosen which is actually pretty good
And people get buried
To it
And then we have to convince them that they can't use it
Because
It's probably not available as a trademark
So
Sometimes we have a little
Ceremony
Like a grave
Seriously we've actually done this where we we have
In our briefing
Will put up a little slide
Where it shows
A grave and then we'll have the code name on there almost okay now we could have a moment of silence for your code name because you can't have it
So you have to let it go
We also there for
Name
So what should we name this episode
Was going to call it what's in a name
I will I will slap you so hard if you call it what's in a name
I really will so yeah apparently everybody's use that title to talk about naming
And then I thought I'd go for something you know settler
Like
A rose by any other
90% of the articles that we've been quoted in have either been what's in a name or a rose by
By Any Other Name
So I don't know what to call this episode
Help with recall I don't know I don't know
I'd have to give it some thought I can't name on the flashlight
Title TK
Wait I don't get it what
Ytk
Title TK meaning
Title yet to come like it will fill it in later
You working in a newsroom you know like you don't know what the headline has or some little piece of resurgence of stopping and
Figuring it out
Is stipend TK and then your editor knows he's going to go back and fill it in later
China PTC taste it out better on the page so that you won't miss it when you're going back and
Remind
Mexican train
99% invisible with produces week by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin and beautiful
Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family law
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives to modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify
Pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299 PR
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com