99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds
Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Every morning
I wake up
Rollover
Pick up my phone
In check Twitter
Not proud of this
Just the way it is
Twitter always struck me as the social media platform that was the most like Broadcasting
It's an ongoing conversation
Angela power
It's a lot like scanning to a radio dial
Telling you about their day
Reacting to shocking news making jokes
Quinceanera round legs
I tweeted Roman Mars by the way if you haven't heard me say that before
And sometimes I tweet at truffleman
But if you want to find out about the show in general
Does a hashtag for it
It's
#9 9 p.m.
The hashtag of course is comprised of two vertical lines intersecting two horizontal lines that looks like a
Play tic tac toe board
In the current Digital World the hashtag identifies movements events
Happening
Brands topics of all time
Hashtags help people gather
That's incredible power to give to like individual
As a character
I mean awesome
It's got like this little
Typographic superhero story now
And this superhero story Stars Chris Messina
I'm Chris Messina the inventor of the hashtag
Designer
And translator
Human culture
That's probably a little bit bloated
Chris was the first one to use a hashtag on Twitter
Before it was even called a hashtag
Tag back in August of 2007 when he was going to an event called barkcamp
It's a nerdy thing it's everything it's it's an event that you go to
That's completely unstructured in unplanned and the participants.
So the participants needed a way of organizing
Which led Chris to tweet the
The very first
Hashtag
Even though at that point it was just a pound sign
How do you guys feel about using
Pound
Barkcamp
Four groups
Putting a pound sign in front of the word barkcamp helps the other people at barkcamp take out the
The word bar camp in their Twitter stream and encourages all the other bar Camp distance to use
Conversation
Some people got on board and agreed to use the pound sign
Most were like okay you go do that
The pound symbol had already provided other corners of the web
Internet relay chat AKA IRC
Use the pound sign to represent chat rooms or conversation Channel
There's another social network to the time called Raikou
That also have these Channel
So there was other stuff that came before me
But Chris was using bunch of pound signs throughout his tweets
I was putting
Pound symbol
In front of my word
Bieber like I don't understand what you're doing
You're putting all this strange punctuation info
Your stuff end
It looks dumb
But the True Believers did by the sign
One Twitter user called it a
A hash
Tag
Because hash
Is the British name for the
Sign and these are being used
Is a category
Tags and then the hash and the tag. Conjoined into one word
Chris actually brought the hashtag idea to Twitter headquarters directly
But they thought it would never catch on
Monkey
Then a few months later in October of 2007
The purpose of the hashtag was fully realized
A friend of mine was down in
San Diego his name is Nate Ritter and he was using Twitter basically pulling all the stuff together around these fires at work
Are going on in San Diego
Wildfire in San Diego
He was
Prefixing all of his tweets with sand space Diego space fire
So Chris told Nate but he should switch to hashtag San Diego fire all one word and then other users would imitate
It worked
People trying to find out about the fire knew exactly where to look on Twitter
And this was a moment where everyone went that's what friends are for
Clarify
Hashtags were nothing that Twitter planned on
And they kind of drag their feet on incorporating it
There must be a better way to organize all this in
That's fine
I'm weak I'm looking for
The hashtag and
Andy lorek
Letting employee at Twitter officially brought in the hashtag
The users brought in the hashtag
Like what all I did was
#Detroit
One line of code
Give me about fifteen
That one line of code meant that when you click on a word with a hashtag in front of it
You'd see a page with all the other tweets that also contained that hashtag word
And basically this help you round up everyone was talking about a specific
And now the hashtag is a tool used in advertisements social movement music videos memes TV shows
And in conversation
#sometimes
Hey Justin what's up
How much Timmy hashtag Jones
The busy working has that Rising even Chris acknowledges how irritating this
Mostly when I'm being annoying or ironic but I'm I'm coming to sort of except that that's the phrase
It's getting to the point where the hashtag is erasing the symbols other uses friend of mine actually saying
He is delivery guy showed up and was looking for a hashtag to a though I'd hope that most people who made deliveries for a live
#SMH
We know it more
Does a number sign
In the states it's usually called the number sign
The pound sign
In the UK is often called a hash mark
Because of the way it looks and everything else
This is Keith Houston
He's the author of a book
Call Shady character
The Secret Life of punctuation symbols and other typographical marks
I got a whole chapter on this
Anna has a lot
Of other
Random uses
As well as used in chess
To represent
Remove the results
Checkmate
In proofreading
If you see a hash symbol this means space
Should be in Sac
It's used on Swedish Maps
Tehmina lumberyard
Hash pound number sign
Lumber yard
Whatever you want to call it however you want to use it
The symbol traces back to ancient Rome
What time Libra Pondo
Pounded weight
The word Libra
I like the constellation mean scale
Bounce
Libra Pondo
And these two names were interchangeable so Romans referred to this weight measurement as a Libra or a Pondo
So the word Libra was often Abreva
Lowercase L lowercase b
Which of course
We still use
ABC V
Mien Phi bibra R5
Time is it
This is also why British currency the pound
Is represented by a stylized L4 Libre the abbreviation lb becomes a thing
And often times it was drawn with a little bar across the tops of both letters
Just to show that the L and the b word connect
Scribes
Our writers
Ascorbic careless so they write faster and faster
Fosters
B&M
Dependent
The paper before it
Barcroft
The Talk
I'm so this seems to have given
Rise to
Symbol for hash mark
Or lumber yard
Overtime the symbols meaning started 2 by 4
It was used like lb for the unit pound and also started to be used
Just as a number sign
It had a lot of various uses
What is important enough to wind up
Typewriter keyboard
Which is
Kind of
The keys thing
Is the thing that symbol had to do in order to
Survive because symbols that didn't make it onto the typewriter keyboard got pretty unpopular
Like the interrobang
The pilcrow
For the manicure
Poor thanks
Fast forward to 1963
The invention of the touch-tone telephone
Hi this is a bell systems new
Hyundai
The touch tone phone used buttons instead of a rotary wheel
So unlike previous phones the numbers didn't have to be arranged in a circle on the dial anymore
Bell Laboratories a research subsidiary of AT&T
Experimented with a few different designs for the telephone keypad
They try to arranging the numbers into rows of 5
A circle across
The step pattern
But they ended up using the numbers 1 through 9 in a three-by-three grid
Can you put zero alone in the bottom center
Years later in 1968
Why not add keys to either side of the zero this would make the keypad into a rectangle
View more options on the phone menu
To repeat these options
Press the star key
Because unlike rotary phones
Touch-tone phones allow you to continue to dial after the connection has been made
So you can punch in extensions and navigate automated menus
Press 2
Originally Bell Labs wanted
Pretty shapes on the 2X
Star buttons
That made prototype phone that had a five pointed star and a diamond
On either side of the zero
But an engineer named Doug Kerr
Would have none of this diamond and five point star business
That's because by that time a new thing of coming to the picture
The possibility of customers dialing directly from their phones into a computer for such things as checking bank balances
Is there validating their credit cards or what have you
Doug Kerr wanted to make sure that the two new symbols will be one second
Computer could recognize
Ones that appear on a keyboard and were part of the computers vocabulary
So there would be no uncertainty
About how a certain button
Would be recorded
And the data that went into the computer
Bell Labs was pretty set on their star and Diamond idea
To the compromise was an ass trick for the star in a pound for the diamond
Because
You know the
Center
How to look Diamond like I guess
For a second AT&T was like can we at least call it a diamond there's no reasonable reason
It's not a diamond that all AT&T didn't know what to call this button in their manuals
And this led to the creation of what some people including Keith Houston consider the symbols official name
The octothorpe
One day I was out with my
Engineering partner
And we got to talking about it and thought maybe we should come up with a new name in marketing for AT&T
During the time being is engineering partner look at the symbol
And saw that I had eight line sticking out of it
So we'll put the word cocktail in there
Tendentious audited are we just a wealth phe RP
In there too
Because it sounds kind of Greek ashamed
Davidson stature
They called it an octothorpe
But that morphed into octothorpe which rumor has it came about because someone at Bell Labs change the name to turn it into a trip
Olympic Athlete Jim Thorpe
But no one really knows
G is it proper to spell It Off.
For president
There is no proper
Doug called it an octothorpe Lauren called it an octothorpe
Buttock
Joe Thorpe
Seems to have the most widespread use
That with you is not widely
Originally the only reason octothorpe ever caught on with him Bell Labs was because Engineers thought it was funny joke
The manufacturer
Totally hated that
And pretty much killed in the 70
But today for a lot of typos
Octothorpe
Is the sign
Real name
In typographic
You might think
Topographic nerd like Heath love it because it feels the most neutral and official
Print using this symbol
Whatever it's
Doug Kerr and the other Bell Labs engineers
Really understood that we would be using telephones to communicate with computer
This is exactly the same reason why Chris Messina chose to use this symbol
Back in that tweet in mm
7 of the time we had
Blackberry Smirnoff
Hardware-based
Keyboards
SMS because that's the way the
Republic
Which left Chris only two choices
A star with a pal
Lockport whatever
It's
Probably one of the most dense symbols
And so
When you're reading a sentence or you're reading a tweet it stands out
On promotional materials on other social media platforms on protest signs in your annoying friends conversations
Just saw my dentist hashtag hashtag Dental Care
#have any free hashtag
That's how we do and this is all probably going to sound so dated in like
5 years
For two years
Or maybe a few months
Getting hashtag out loud I'm going to sound like someone reading a telegram
Mr. Gower cable do you need cash stop
My office instructed to advance you up to $25,000.
Sam Wainwright
In a telegram has on Twitter
Are speech changed to accommodate the machine
The hashtag is a way of
Changing our language to be more computer friend
And what we're needing to do is actually invert the Paradigm where the computers become more friendly to you
So we're probably not going to be using hashtags
The way Twitter uses
Hashtags
Forever
But this won't mean the end of the symbol itself
It started out on paper but then it leaped to typewriters computers and phones and it seems like it's probably going to stick around
Whatever we decide to call it
#hashtag
#pound hashtag number sign
#lumberyard
#tic tac toe
#musical sharp if you really lazy
Stop
99% invisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman the same Greenspan Katie mingle and me Roman Mars
We are project to 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of our
And architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
I also invented the caps lock key
People curse me everyday when they
David engaged and wish it was disengaged
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a
Cluttered world
A man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room and another hearing.
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled in a new Wii
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and hang out with other people would like to show on Facebook
But you're always welcome at our place at 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com