99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive
I'll show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage map
Limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Reconnecting with
Your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
Allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready to make
Make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn
You have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their custom
Those relationships off internet
High quality
Website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name
An industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message
Carabao
Which in turn
What's Trust
Terdema
A free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launcher
The first campaign go to LinkedIn.
Cam invisible
Linkedin.com
Invisible fear free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
Visit 99 percent invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It's really hard to get a sound trademarked
Brother X
MGM has won for their roaring lion at the 20th Century Fox
Best 99p izone Katie Mingle
Damn
Harley-Davidson famously tried to trademark the sound of their motorcycles that Potato potato potato sound
After years of litigation they finally withdrew their application
So if a bunch of Burly bikers can't do it it must be really hard right now there are fewer than 200 active trade my
Mics for sounds even those sound can be super important to Brand just ask these guys
My name is Joel Beckerman and I'm Tyler gray Tyler and I wrote a book
Call the sonic boom
How Sound transforms the way we think
Ponb
Uses and that would be
Play Kim Possible to trademark but Tyler and Joel say it was crucial to building up the brand It's associated with
Oh man I know that sound I know it's so well
When I was just a little kid on a cul-de-sac they build a Chili's in my town
This was before they were really chain restaurants where I lived so Chili's actually felt kind of Novel and exotic
My family was pumped
My favorite thing to order
If I he does
They don't
Really sell the steak they sell the sizzle
In their book Joel and Tyler use Chili's and their sizzling fajitas as an opening example to illustrate why
Companies should think more about sound
You're sitting in the Chili's at the dinner hour at 5
And let's say it first nobody's ordering the sizzling fajitas
But then
Maybe about 20 minutes 30 minutes into the dinner hour and and I've seen this
All of a sudden one person order sizzling fajitas
As the server brings out the sizzling Skillet of fajita meat and onions
And you hear that sizzling sound literally every I every single person in that restaurant
Their head
Turns to the server
Walking past them and they follow that server with their eyes
And then they smell
The burnt onions in apple and now you're hooked
And now everyone orders the sizzling fajitas
And in the back instead of making that one order they make 15
Yeah they called the fajita effect
My family fell victim to the fajita effect
Too many times to remember
We may even have initiated the original fajita effect
Patient zero of the fajita effect
Chuy's by the way did not invent that distinction goes to a Texan by the name of Sonny Falcone
He was selling a subpar cut of meat called the Faja in figured that
If you cooked it out in the open with law spice people didn't care about the quality of meat
It got to Chili's because Larry Levine was the founder of Chili's
Had seen restaurants around the Rio Grande Valley so they do their version of it
He had the idea to make sound the star of the show and so when Chili's opened up
They put that sound of sizzling fajitas in their first ever commercial fajitas sold like crazy
In the wake of their massive success Chili's printed up T-shirts for staff but said
I survived the summer of fajita Madness
Now they
They serve enough fajita meat to fill to nuclear submarines a year
I really hope someone feel to nuclear submarines of fajita meat to get that measurement
It's surprisingly difficult to get people even really creative people
To think about sound
To Value it in the same way they value the visual environment
But sometimes there's one person who gets it
An Apple computer is one of those people with a guy by the name of Jim reekes
Hi
My name is Jim reekes
I'm the only person you know whose name is it
Complete sentence
Jim Norton Apple for about 10 years starting in the late 80s
Titles
I don't even think I had business card
But whatever his title was
Jim was working on sound for the Macintosh computers
Which was neglected stepchild of
All things Mac no one really cared about the sound until the end which is unfortunately typical
Exception
He's a composer and a musician and he understood the importance of sound more than most of his colleagues
And Jim have
Strong feelings about the startup sound that was on the Mac at the time
I just hated it I could not stand it
Here's what it sounded like
Here is a couple more times cuz it goes by really fast
So when Apple
First start it up it was
Makino
The computer is far from perfect
They crashed a lot
And every time you turned it back on you heard that jolting sound
So Jim set out to make a better one
Mac just crashed
Again
Your work
You're waiting for this thing to boo'd up
Again
That's
The Odyssey
Just a bunch of pissed-off frustrated people are super annoyed and you're wasting their time that's a hard audience place
I got to change everyone's mood
So I was thinking
Zen like
Meditative
Sound
Similar to a gong or chanting ohm
Of course we're all familiar with the sound he came up with
Oh that's nice
So much better right
Only problem was Jim ask for permission to put this new sound into the Prototype
For the new Mac and
I was
Tell him I couldn't do it we already have a sound you're not allowed to change it was just on and on and on
But Jim knew the people who were responsible for building the Prototype
I played it for them and then
They liked it and so
When no one was around
We put her into the build and the Quadra 700 shipped with the sound in it
That was back in 1991 when the Quadra 700 Mac cost
$1,000
Jim says he never got any props for the sound
Just grief
And yet that sound with a few minor tweaks
Husband the Apple startup sound ever since
So I think we can assume that Steve Jobs liked it
It's his big giant
Two handed
C chord c major chord that makes you kind of
Feel welcome
To this very stable very
Substantial world of Apple
It's probably the single most
Connected
Sound with the Apple brand
And brand is just the experience
Or
Apperception
Prior to
The expiry
So
Everything that shapes the
Perception matters
Lbnl like imagine a really beautiful car
That just had this horrible engine always backfire
Actually there are people who make sure that beautiful cars sound beautiful
Or at least they sound right
One of them is Sean Carney
Hi my name's Sean Carney
Mustang powertrain sound quality engineer
John works on Mustangs
And there are all kinds of things he and his team can tweak
To get the sound they're looking for
Inner tubes have different shapes and different perforation synonyms of the whole pattern Venom
Kind of like you can control the sound of a horn by placing your fingers over different holes
Chongqing control the sound of the Mustang
And it's an easier job for the standard V8
But then sometimes they'll put out a specialty Mustang
In 2008 Mustang decided to put out a remake of a Mustang that appeared in the movie Bullet in 1968
In the movie is a pretty famous Chase sequence where Steve McQueen drives his Mustang all over the Streets of San Francisco
Show me the team wanted to make the 2008 Bullitt sound similar to the 1968 Bullitt
Dora come see a car like a bullet it's about in his car the whole movie
Strong you back into those old memories
If I was like that for 4
Yamoto band
They're trying essentially to make a new car sound old
Which is challenging because cars made in 1968 or built completely differently
Battle of the carburetor and we use a fuel injection for Thurman
Play all the things
Completely change
How the engine confirmed
Sean was never going to be able to duplicate the sound of the Bullitt car from the movie exactly
Sing in the movie was enhanced with sounds recorded from a race car and apart from that
It's actually illegal in most places to drive around in a car that loud
A big part of what we try to do is
Which better identify
What are those key characteristics of being played
By that classic American
V8
I found the tent in the movie came out people talk
About the sound
And most people thought Sean and his team have gotten it right
Here's the 2008
Bullitt Mustang in action
Sound is
Actually
In front of all of our senses
It's the one we react to quickest
Even quicker than touch
That's Joel Beckerman again
Brands that are not paying attention to this
Not paying attention to sound in association with experiences
They're really going to get punished
Case in point
In 2010 Frito-Lay decided to come out with a new biodegradable SunChips bag
Only problem was they never considered what that packaging sound
Here's a YouTube video someone made about the bag
Delicious
Sentence level
Things that I cannot get over is the noise that this bag make I don't know what it's made
If you ever want to
Do you want to get one chip out of this bag
Good luck
Mega on YouTube was not the only person to notice how noisy the bag was
Someone created a Facebook page
Called sorry I can't hear you over this SunChips bag
And I got 40000 likes
And it became a national news story
Bad to pull the new back and go back to the old bag
Good intentions bad execution
John Tyler refer to this kind of sound as a Sonic
Trash you know you never let somebody to
Take a note take a bunch of trash and throw in your front lawn
But we allow
Cities
Our neighbors
Brands
To really invade our Sonic space it dump garbage in your ear
Joel and Tyler imagine a world where all the sounds we hear have more thought behind them
More intention
It would be very rare that you would actually hear the sound that something made
That thing would trigger a better sound
In Tyler's World they can make the SunChips bag sound like this when it's opened
Every time you get a chip you're like
Love ya I said that sound it's actually on that very short list of trademarks
So hands off
Whatever
99percentinvisible with Presa sweet by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery troubleman and me Roman Mars we are
Project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco introduced
Are the offices of arcsin in architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
I hope
When I die
There is a button on my Tombstone and you can press it and it would play the sound
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
Time in rio
2 + Alexa
Interacting with Alexa
Is talking to
Can me and my wife is
Voice technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of
Trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions
With technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake
Human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights.
80%
We're presenting to special episode
What's for 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th
Anime 20
Right here
NPR
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways
Star families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Fame
Takes a look at the story behind a different person
Family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on Mayfair
Peep featuring an episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets
Scrolled in a newly discovered star
Love letters
Moon episode
It brings you along for the hunt
Container of missing Chinese food
It's haunted
A family for 25 years
The Proud Family ghost
It's wherever you get your podcast and
Find out why they say
Every house
Haunted
We need to talk about
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is Frost
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God
Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweeted Roman
Play Spotify playlist that will provide a nice soundtrack to your work day
But I encourage you to explore the entire world of 99 per
Anthony 9 p.m.
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about
The body gym
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
We're looking the part
My car
Master your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get
Billy Jack's to play Super
Superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main got to know how
A few days ago Wesley Stern
And after that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private jet
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com