99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This is from Twitter
Hey Roman Mars and 99 PIR
Have a burning question for you
Why do us flags on military vehicles and uniform
Always appear.
That's from Michael McAuliffe
Well first of all their only backwards part of the time military regulations state that when a flag is displayed it must give the effect
That flag flying in the breeze is it the person wearing it is moving forward
Till the patches on the left arm
The flag is displayed as you normally
Take a bath with that blue star field in the upper left-hand corner
But if the flag patches on the right
It's the reverse side flag that's display
With the blue star field in the upper right-hand corner
Singles for vehicles the blue star field always points towards the front of a vehicle as if it's flying North charging
Forward to Victory
So if you're looking at the right side of a tank or an aircraft
You'll see
The reverse fly
This is part 2 of the mini Stories episode where I interview the staff about their favorite little design stories that don't quite fit
Go out the entire episode for whatever reason
They are cooled 99ci stories than the last
Plus in between the staff stories I'll be telling a few mini story suggested by You Beautiful nerds
Who enjoy having me paraphrase Google search results Android
Up first
Senior editor
Katie Mingle
My name is Katie mingle and I am the senior editor
What does that mean
I do the same stuff that we all do in some ways which is like
Find stories and report on them and make them but I also edit a lot so I look it
Other people's stories
On paper before they go to like a larger group at it and I
Cut like
5 Pages out of every story
I probably cut like
4 minutes
Send
Sometimes do some restructuring and just kind of try to get it ready
So that it's
A little more smooth when the whole group looks at it
In every story
You have worked on every story because you've added it almost
Yes I'm lurking behind every 99 Pi story
Do Pit stories and so part of
Coming up with story ideas is basically just
Trolling around the internet
Trying to find things to turn things into
Stories NFL
Yeah he was amounts of time just like
Following links
That's sort of like how this one came about and I ended up on this YouTube video about this place called the biker
The wall which is
Is in Newcastle England
And it's being narrated by the swimming and wearing this amazing stuff double-breasted suit jacket and shoes
She's just super super 80s her name is Beatrix Campbell in the video she started walking around outside
The biker wall or the biker estate
A pig
Small
It's cheap and cheerful
It's Tricky
Clever
I don't really know how it's big and small but and I'm not sure that ever week ever really figure
You're that out so the structure or the sort of estate that she's talking about
It actually replace
An entire neighborhood
So let me just give you a little background
In 1963 in New Castle England
A 17000 resident working-class neighborhood called biker
Sault Sainte the same name as
This new place
Was demolished because it was considered a slum and I think there are a lot of vacancies
And the neighborhood was made up of sort of Victorian Row Housing and like if you've ever seen the movie Billy Elliot
And you can like picture hands are dancing through these like
Brick houses and
Really really close together narrow streets and that's
That's the old biker
At the old biker and I think that movie was actually filmed a really close to
The old biker neighborhood
Street-by-street the old songs with cleared one straight line straight the new bike it was built
Neighborhood of brick row houses this architect named Ralph
Skin
Built
The new place
Which is called biker wall or or sometime
Biker estate
And it's a community of public housing that
Is enclosed by this
Great big wall of
The wall is a mile and a half long and it provides a barrier to winds coming
Kind of off the North Sea and also
Highway noise there's like a big
Freeway
Bestway nearby
And it kind of
Creates this sort of microclimate within the
Community
So it's basically this big wall that should have wraps around these other buildings and closing them
Campbell at she has some very
Vivid
Descriptions on but she says the way it's constructed
I'm laid out never mind her
Pomegranate
It's kind of like
Prodigious
I saw sweet places inside
Yeah
And if you're feeling like
At all
Like that was a little sexual it gets like there's more
What does all this mean for architecture
Is it mountainous
A postmodernist
Pusher
It's a bonus use aggressive family confidential all those gray erections
To the skyline
Previous vulva
It's round
It goes with the Contours of the landscape
It's an enclosure rather than a disclosure
What does nooks and crannies
Layers and levels and surprises
Annies
Yeah if you didn't hear that is aggressive phallic architecture
And it was great erections
Skyline Boulevard
Does gray directions
So great
So I found this
Please send I was sort of like
I want to put this on me are basically just to get
This lady and her
Volvo architecture theories
On our podcast like I don't know if there's a story here but I want there to be
A little cool things about by Corso
It's kind of neat about it Ralph Erskine the architect
He was a socialist and a Quaker and he really wanted to build a place that fostered
Community
And he'd also studied buildings in the Arctic and how they were constructed to sort of Shield the inner Courtyard
Words from from winds coming in from the outside and she wanted to do something similar but
Not Justa Shield it from winds but also just to enclose the residence in this
Fulvic Unearthed contrived
Really really hard to involve a bunch of the residents from the old biker
In the redesign of the new one
But
Despite his
3 best efforts not that many of the original residents ended up living there
Eventually in the 80s the place kind of turns a little bit back into a slum there's a lot of
Was crying and in vacancies and a lot of the places sort of fall into disrepair
The guardian
Said this about the biker the New Biker estate
For all its faults
Biker wall was an Exemplar of both design and an attempt to involve the community in the changes
Plan for them by those in power
That it failed in so many ways reveals that it's rarely in the interests of communities to demolish the home
They live in
Yeah so that's to me that's just sort of like
You can try really hard to do it right
And it
Still
Mike
Come out wrong
So in Beatrice Campbell the the YouTube lady she she admits that the place is flawed but she still
Explode a car but at least unlike most of its contemporaries
Both monumental
It's a social space
Undomestic
There's something about this place
Okay so I don't know if you can understand her last line there but she says there's something lighthearted about this place something love
Audible
Eminem if I love that if you scroll down just a little ways that the comment on the video says
They didn't tell them it was Carl orff 24/7 in this place
Carl orff I think with that comment is getting at is that it was real
The kind of dark
A place to live because Carl orff wrote this
That's pretty dark
Liquor well
Thank you Katie
Yeah
In 2014 the biker Community Trust are they multimillion-dollar revamp up
With lots of improvements including Broadband in every property
It's not all Carl orff
If indeed it ever was
Tell me who you are
I am sure effusive assistant producer
99 pi
What does that mean what are you
I've sort of do a lot of the pro tool stuff so I'm working with the actual tape for a lot of The Producers stories
Scoring sound design a lot of the pieces I do research in fact-checking so I basically do
Whatever needs to be done it's a what is you were
So things that are
Creative are relatively simple to copyright
Erratic song
Copyright
You write a book
Did you get copyrighted it's easy to prove that you've done this thing
But a question arises
When
You tried to copyright something that is
Based in fact
Some sort of objective reality like the definition of a word in dictionary
Entry for a person and inside
Or
In this case
Maps when I know you like a good math story. I love a good night story yasso
This story is about a town called
Agloe New York
And it was in the 1930s
The general drafting company
What's creating a map of New York State
So they put in a lot of hours and lot of Manpower detailing all the rivers and gorges and Finger Lakes and
Pounds and he said we put in so much work you know we have to protect our investment
So they set a copyright trap
Near the northwest corner of Pennsylvania
Just a couple miles into New York
I've a put a little town
Next to Roscoe New York
Call
Idaho
An aglow I believe is actually
A jumble of the initials of the founders names agloe
And so they put this on the map
And
They know that if
Another map
Shows iglow New York
That person was copying there
Yeah exactly
So they create this fictitious town
It's on the map
And it's like soldan Esso stations around movie
The state
And for a while everything is all honky
Chidori
But then several years later
Another map comes out
And they open the map
And
Lo and behold
I got it was on it this company is called Rand McNally drafting
Busted busted
Yeah that's what they thought so the general drafting company goes yo Rand McNally you stole our map and where
Going to sue you and Rand McNally is like no no wait this is an actual place
Let's go and take a look
Intelligent
And Company people are like
Okay sure take us to a glow
So that goes place where I glow
Should be
And lo and behold there is actually a big General Store there
Small General Store actually
And it's called The agloe General Store
And there a couple houses maybe 2 at its peak
So The Story Goes
Some people maybe from the neighboring towns wanted to this place wanted to build a general store
Saw that the map said I glow is here but nothing was there
So
When they wanted to build the story they just
Slapped on me I glow name so this place that was created as a
Fictitious copyright trap
Start of spring up into reality
So this sort of
Became famous because author John Green
I wrote a book
Call Paper Towns. Miss settin agloe New York and he gave a tedx talk
About I go New York and about
The concept of paper
Paper Towns as well since turned into a movie
So we thought the story might not be a great
Fit for us because people in our audience minority
Be really familiar with him yeah but we can talk about it a little bit and if you want to learn more
You should look up John Green because he and his brother Hank
If these great videos
But you are all kinds of things I know people
You like the show
Totally love
What they do on you
And you are
I'm Turk Cole said that I'm the digital director at 99% invisible and describe what that means
Sure I produce a web stories for the show
And I take care of all of our digital
So
Several
Years ago
But I remember being
In the waiting room waiting
Maslow's
In surgery
I got an email
From a firefight
And she said
Do you know anything
About Knox
Which of these little invisible elements you see everywhere in urban environment you probably never noticed
So please tell us
What is
Enochs
Yeah Knox Box in simple terms is a rapid entry system
It allows emergency personnel
To get into buildings quickly when there's a disaster
So for example
When there's a fire in your apartment building
And the fire department is trying to get in quickly
They show up they open an Xbox get out of key
And into the building
So the Scarlet like physically so it's like a little box that sort of
Up against the wall
Typically be found within a few feet of an entryway to ilvl the black box
Usually
With a little red on it so it's easy to spot
To the fire department shows up
They grabbed hold this little box
And the user master key to open it and it should be
And there's a fire inside
Didn't want to break in in
All the doors and windows they just if there's a key available they can use it
Write an emergency they're not worried about you know the property damage of course
That's a vibe
They're worried about injuring themselves right so they have to break glass door and jump through through that glass door
That puts them at greater risk
The building this season time
Reduces injury injury risk and Chestnut
Is why does the whole system work so they they have a master key that opens up all the knocks boxes
Right so their master key
Out of all the black boxes
For all the different buildings and that means when they arrive at a building they don't have to sort through bunch of keys figure out how they're going to get into a particular building
I just whip out their one key
Stick it in the lock box open it up and inside of that
They will find whatever key they need to access that particular bill
What is the name Knox
Knox is a company that produces a lot of these box
And technically generically you might call the rapid entry system
Knock make so many of them that
If he has become an everyday sort of household name for these
Knock knock
Cool so like if you were in any populated area
You
Will see a ton of these right
There everywhere you are surrounded by Knox boxes
Basically anywhere you go
You probably pass
A dozen or so of these just walking down the street everyday
So on every block very city you'll find some equivalent of a Knox Box
Ashley outside the building and once you start seeing these
You will see them
At a high level they're made to be seen and yet they're somehow strangely invisible until you start notice
This is one of those great examples of a short story that was just
It's an anecdote multi-story so it made sense just put it up on the web
And
In Call of Duty
Rick Astley have a whole website tomorrow at 9 p.m.
Thanks to Nikki Leigh
Former firefighter putting Knox
Suggestion all those years ago
Last week I got this mini storage suggestion from Tucson Arizona resident Megan Phillips
In Tucson
Roads running East-West or called Street
Rhodes running
South record Avenue
Makes sense but what is unique to Tucson
Is that any Diagonal row
Roads are called
Stravenue
A portmanteau
Street
Penn Avenue
That is an official designation it's not just slay
Letting that's pretty cool
When I got me cuz. I was sitting next to famous portmanteau skeptic Helen zaltzman of The Illusionist
It's where you took his acclaimed Word podcast and I asked her what she thought
I know your dental opinion portento is
Pretty
Negative I think
Leprechaun size a used for
Is to express a concept
You don't have a proper term
And it's 7 related to Concepts that you do already have * 4
However
In this case
I feel like the hunters
Fixing a problem that doesn't really exist
Unstoppable miss the people of Tombstone
Adjust very much too dependent
I'm things either paying streets
All avenues
Anthem
I am come from Britton which does not have such a binary right naming system
Say that you might get a street
They School the street or roads
On Avenue or Crescent
Apple Lovato not even have a roadster mitul
And It Go in any direction
Live and Let Live Tucson
Is it very prodesign progrid show I'm sorry that you had to hear that minor
But I assure you
Helen zaltzman The Illusionist is a fantastic podcast that will teach entertain you about words in the strange consequences
Language
They won't have Helen planning my city
Cuz grids rule
Man
I'm so excited to
I was about to say I'm so excited to get this story out of my system but honestly I still think it would make
I think everyone who's wrong and I think I'm right and I wanted to
REI
Don't be a Groundswell that they need to know the whole story at the end
Maybe maybe I'm just worried that people hear it and be like oh yeah I know it
That doesn't work which would mean
Totally crazy
I'm Avery truffelman
What are you doing here
I'm a producer at 99percentinvisible
So we're telling all the type of stories that we
Can't tell on the radio for various reasons maybe they were
Little parts of stories that got cut out because they're too confusing maybe they were
You're like a little too small to constitute like putting the whole episode about
But this one
This one this one is different
Why the difference
This was supposed to be my magnum opus
The One That Got Away I mean I mean it like
2 years ago
And so at the time it was
This is it I was already planning out like the t-shirts we would sell about this episode
And
It just it didn't happen
Okay so what is this doing
This is about the most
Iconic
Poster in the world
Is a poster we've all seen
Is it supposed to say we have all been forced
See
It is this
Can you read that line there
D a o
It is that pyramid arrangement of black letters on a white background
Is usually got a biggie at the top
Nice line of letters get progressively smaller
Is a vision chart
And it has
Official name
What's the name
Is called
The Snellen chart
After the Dutch ophthalmologist
Herman Snellen who invented it
Eevee
Otz
Perfectly
The way it works
Is that you read off the series of letters
Annie's line
And he get the majority right
You get to move to the neck
Went to a bunch of ophthalmologist
A bunch of times
And according to
Mira Lim
This
They kind of pomologist
To work at the street from us
By convention you always use the Snellen chart
This just works well it's what everybody has
And a big part of why the Snellen chart works really well
Is because
Easy
Memorize
And a lot of
Ophthalmologist
Eye doctor
Have memorized their chart
ESL ca va
D806
Eg a new 5S BBD for
Oflc
Team
Apeo 25 e.
There you go
Wow so that's just her
She just read a little about it then
They don't have to like
Squint with you to like make sure you got each one right or they don't even have to follow along in a paper like if they have it memorized
I ended up wrong and they can assess you really quickly which if you're not a doctor you're doing this
Every single patient and then this makes
Add minutes to your day
You have it memorized
So the Snellen chart
Is Iconic you can see it online
Mugs and tie them whatever is everywhere just that layout is classic
An obvious problem
The way the test works
You read the line you get the majority right
And then you get to go to the next line
But if every line has a different
Amount of letters on it it's basically a different test every time
You can get
One line is okay to get
Arirang the next line it's okay to get whatever
Foreign
Is a different test every time you have different odds
If you got
Three out of five right in the 2020 Rio you will be
Peking 2020
If I Stay
Let me repeat that
And you only got two days
In that same row
Now you would have
The shockingly imprecise it's unbelievable
That is Doctor Ian Bailey
And in the 70s he helped design a more precise vision chart
That has
Five letters on every
Single line
I think at chat design could be
Compared with
Designing a ruler
Where you say why don't we make the markings on the ruler
Of the same size
It seems obvious
And so he has
5 big letters at the top
5 letters
Find five letters in the next line
All space
Equally apart
Very precise
But if you visualize it for a second
Instead of one
Giant letter at the top
There are five
Giant letters
At the top
Which means that it is a physically bigger
Chart it's just wider and also that means it looks more like an upside-down pyramid
T25
Really big letters with.
And then five smaller letters in it
Smaller letters
How to get tiny tiny tiny but it's still always fine exactly and then he also had to pick which letters
To use
And so some letters are more confusable like
CNG
What is a very distinct like Z
A
And so he also had this like design challenge of making sure that you wouldn't have one line of lifo either letters and one line of difficult letter
To make sure they distribute
And you also to make sure
But there wasn't like
Cuz he designed it in Australia and you want to make sure nnz were next to each other people be like oh New Zealand and like
Create associations with with shapes
So yeah it was like it was a really tough
Start to design
Battlelog bar chart chart it is one of many improved charts but the
Problem is so yeah the chart is a lot bigger and wider physically it takes up more wall space
It's a lot of offices
Can't actually accommodate
And since there are five letters on every row it means
There more letters for doctors
Memorize
And actually
Dr. Bailey
Exactly
I can still remember the Snellen chart that I used to have when I was in
Private
DCB
Dln
Long story short like
The memorization is really cute to why the Snellen chart works
It's like what everyone is used to the old pyramid shape is like easier to memorize
The division chart presents was really interesting question about what really makes a design good cuz on the one hand
You have
Charts like the logmar chart like Doctor Bailey start which are standardized and precise
And it's a better
But a little harder to accommodate in a little harder to use
And then
On the other hand
You have the classic
Melon chart
What is less precise
Way easier to memorize
Which means that the more efficient test for doctors
Plus if it's conveniently on a wall
It is memorable quick easy
Imprecise
There's probably more scientific ways of measuring Vision but it's a pretty good
It's a pretty good way of assessing how well you can
Function so it's good it does work and it's a lot easier than
The other wizard
So you see both versions of the chart around and just next time you get your eyes checked
You can see which
Design your doctor has opted for
If you see of the traditional pyramid Snellen chart shape that means it's more efficient for the doctor to use
And if you see the upside down log Mar
Shape
That means it's just a more precise tool for measuring vision
But like
Both are good designs
Justin really gif
Waze
So we just gave the most cursory explanation of vision charts and the design implications of each of them but
When the whole story was with being scripted
It had lots of different details and it ended up getting more and more confusion about what 20/20 vision
Actually wasn't
All this weird stuff in the eventually
We just decided
The Killer story
And not I could produce a full version of it
Which is ongoing tragedy we are reminded of all the time
I thought that this would never really be
I researched the hell out of this I'm fertile subscribe to the Ophthalmology
National newsletter and I see this chart everywhere and it and it
Really
Baby pisses me off
I've had this day flying around forever I even made
I even made this really fun medley of songs
Check it out
20/20 vision
That is the end of the mini stories
Happy 2017 ever
Normal episodes commencing next week
Let's giggling but we might try this again a couple times a year if people are into it
We had a huge response the last episode soap if you have a mini story suggestion
Send it our way and maybe we'll address it at the end of the year
99percentinvisible is Katie mingle Delaney Hall
Kolstad Sharif Youssef Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and Mero
We are project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating it's not that bad you take laxatives
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my
I got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook and tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 9
9 pi org we're on Instagram and Tumblr to to get the full 99p I experience
You need to go to 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com