99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
30 days has September April June and November February has 20
He ate alone all the rest have 31
Except in leap year that's the time when February's days are 29
That doesn't even rhyme
The poem I grew up with was
Slightly different
Thirty days hath September April June and November
All the rest have 31
Except for February which has 28 days clear and 29 in each leap year
Okay I think that rhymes actually worse both poems to say the same thing which is that months don't make any logical time
A month is hardly a unit of measurement
I can be anywhere from 28 to 31 days
Sometimes it's four weeks
10 * 5
1 * 6
You have to buy a new calendar with new dates
Every single year
It's a strange design
Well the year that we now have
And basically consider almost a writ of God
You know somehow it's just indivisible there it is
Actually has had an amazing history
That is David Ewing Duncan I am the author of
Calendar
Humanities epic struggle to determine a true and accurate
Goodyear
The calendar that the world really uses right now
Is mostly
A sort of joining of the Roman Calendar in the Egyptian calendar
It's basically when Caesar and Cleopatra
What kind of hanging out and doing their thing
Which is to say when Roman Caesar and Egyptian Cleopatra we're having a torrid love affair
This was before Cleopatra got together with Marc Anthony
She was 21
And Caesar was 52
But they got together and they did what lovers do
Discuss the true nature of the Earth
Flirtation
And Egyptians long before the Greeks came
Actually discovered
The true length
Of the year 365 days
The Egyptians knew about the length of the year
Because of the Nile River
It was basically a series of steps that went into the Nile
The Nile
Actually flooded
At the same height
Virtually every year
It's on the same day
And they were just simply Mark each year
When it hit its height
But the Egyptians also figured out that the year isn't always exactly 365 days
So they added an extra day every four years just to make sure that the calendar matched up with the season
In other words
They invented the leap year
And this was all fantastic news to Caesar
Because he had a feeling that the Roman Calendar wasn't quite right
The Roman calendar year at the time was around 354 days long
Obviously that's a few days show
11 days
How to Short
Natural solar
And when you lose 11 days
Year after year after year
The season starts
Spring in the winter
Winter in the fall months
And those 11 days were missing because the Roman Calendar had always been base
Based on moon cycle
Cleopatra inspired Caesar to switch to a calendar that would be consistent with
The Earth cycle around
The Sun
When Caesar return to Rome from his dalliance
Cleopatra
He introduced the leap year
Call Julian
Julius Caesar also added back those 11 missing days
And the Julian calendar was instituted throughout the Roman Empire
Just to say
Still a bit
Did you encounter wasn't entitled
Accurate
Itself
11 minutes 14
Each year
Eventually you had
We are losing days
And then
There was a week
And buy 1582
Pope Gregory
The 13th at the wherewithal to say
Okay we are actually we have an inactive
Your calendar will worship
All of our holidays
And with a few small adjustments to realign the year with the seasons we have the Gregorian calendar
Named after Pope Gregory
And that's what's on your wall or your phone
We all use it we don't think about it now
And
For that reason
There has not been a huge
Momentum to try to
Change things
Basically live with it
But there are a lot of smart people out there have been for centuries
And come up with better calendars and there are better,
One example of calendar redesign came after the French Revolution
The French decreed the first year of the Revolution was the year one
Animed the week 10 days long this was actually instituted for over a decade
Then Napoleon put the kibosh on that when he became emperor
And later another Frenchman created these so-called
Positivist
Calendar the positivist calendar was created in
1849 by Auguste comte
Organized mind of History
Moses Homer Aristotle Archimedes
Caesar
Saint Paul the great white men of history
Dante
Gutenberg
Shakespeare
That's my friends by the way my name is Mark Burns I am the visual editor for citylab
Wonder didn't really take off
It was mostly meant as an inspirational Memorial to glorify great thinkers
And Fina patriarchy
However
There was another radical attempt at calendar reform
That actually
Kind of happened
I wrote the death and life
13 month count
This was a highly rational 13-month calendar meant to appeal not too romantic
But to industrialists
Because the wonky weirdly divided Gregorian calendar was difficult for accountants
Who had to track monthly numbers and for the people who had to make the trains run on time
And Moses because it's worth
Was both of those people
Moses B cotsworth
Was analytics guy
Mostly working in the
Railway industry
Codsworth was a British Railway Man and he was all about efficiency
The Gregorian calendar wasn't cutting it for him
So it's a
There's a month where this extra Monday
What is a month for the next Saturday that would throw out the numbers
A month to month
And that kind of frustrated cotsworth
So he created his
13 month calendar
In 1902 codsworth presented a design for a calendar of 13 months worth every month was exam
Exactly 28 days
No more
No less
Perfect week
And this meant the dates were all standardized as well
You always know that V was a Thursday
No matter the month
First was always a fun day
Attempt was always a Tuesday
There be a Friday
The 13th
Every single month rational railway man we're not
Superstitious clearly all the months names would stay the same
And then that additional month
Another 28 even days
Would fall between June and July
And this additional month
Would be called
SOL SOL SOL
Standing for
The month where the
Somersaults
And leave your day would be added at the end of Soul not February
So every 4 years old would have 29 days
Alright so 20 days * 13 months
Is 364 days in a year
That is one day less than the actual solar year of 300
How to make it 300
Codsworth added a new holiday
Right before the new year for lecture day at the end of the year
Called your day and your day was just a floating day not part of any particular month and it would be a sword
Global Sabbath
And aside from your day all other vacations would be moved to a Monday
Holidays would always be practiced or observed
Don't worry about certain months where
Wednesday
And maybe since I have Wednesday off they want to schedule Thursday and Friday off
No Wednesdays off
Codsworth pitched his perfect calendar around the United States
Giving talks about its Myriad benefits
You can find many takers
Except for one of the wealthiest and most successful businessmen of that time
George Eastman
The founder of Kodak
Mr. Eastman had a lot of
Unique interest in addition to his company and his philanthropic work but this I have to say is probably one of the
Weirdest interest that he hadn't pursued Cathy Connor is the curator of the George Eastman house in collection in
Chester New York
When he had an interest in anything he always put a decent amount of money into
Getting other people to buy into his ideas as well and he did exactly that with the 13-month calendar
Eastman basically took it upon himself to promote cotsworth calendar design
And he started a calendar League headquarters in Rochester
Income tax office gave a little office to this
Calendar reform
Group and it was there that they
Published in printed some different Flyers to hand out a local businesses actually convince a few local
Benefits to switch to a 13-month calendar including of course
Mr. Eastman Zone company
They adopted it at the Eastman Kodak company in 1924
And they continue to use it until 1989
So that is 65 years
Until 1989
Apparently employees found it useful
When I did sales
Porting program
I didn't have to worry about love this is a 28-day month is a 31-day month is
I acclimated it very quickly
John saracco worked at Kodak
From 1986 to 1992
He actually like the calendar so much
He tried to bring it with him Beyond Kodak
A couple of times I've actually tried getting company that I work for
2 going use 8:30
Team.
You know
4 weeks * 30
Calendar but like Moses cotsworth in George Eastman beforehand
John Scirocco just couldn't convince other businesses to take it on
That said
Even within Kodak
Eastman couldn't fully Institute the 13-month calendar and it's
Truest form
The calendar as John do it
Was kind of a modified version
I only knew it as this is the financial calendar
Company
Kodak employees didn't observe solar year day or change every holiday to a Monday
It was like how some bankers work in quarters or some schools function in semester
Kodak's internal schedule with organized
It's a 13.
Just called. One
2. 30
Instead of saying that today was March 2nd
We would say that
Today is
The third. Date
They use the 13-month calendar as an organizational tool for planning finances and production schedule
We programmed in
You wrote In
Redesigned application
To work within
The Kodak
13.
But we'd still lived our life the way the normal Gregorian calendar was
The world was still on the Gregorian calendar
Renaming and reorganizing the days and holidays would have been a total drag
And this is basically the same reason why I would be so hard for the larger world to adopt
13 month calendar
The explanation
Forhow July 4th
It's kind of like
The perfect
Example of how Campo
Mentally adjust
New calendar
That's journalist Mark Burns again
Okay so on the 13-month calendar schedule
July 4th would have to be moved to a Monday
Like all the holidays
So then they'll really be July 2nd
But when you add in Soul and Shuffle the dates around accordingly
That actual day on the solar calendar wouldn't fall in July
It would actually be Soul 17 but
That falls on a Tuesday
You got to make
That Monday so would end up as Soul six
So there's nothing is
Patriotika celebrating
This is why the calendar and it's
Truest most regulated form
Couldn't fully work at Kodak
I mean you have to give your employees a vacation on July 4th
Even if it's not on a Monday
So Random holidays in off-days persisted
Kodak couldn't do it alone
He would have to convince the rest of the world to make the switch
He and mr. Cox worth
They went to bed
A few times
In front of a lot of different committees at Congress
And in our government to try to justify
Explain the rationale
And this was taken completely serious
Calendar reform
Became an actual
Issue of
Debate forum
League of Nations the League of Nations as in the precursor to the UN there are a hundred 85 plans
Before the League of Nations to look at
Four County reform
And
Codsworth
Eastman
Puzzle was one of the
Few finalists
Even after George Eastman passed away in 1932
League of Nations continue discussing calendar redesign
Basically
League of Nations can come to a consensus
And then
The rise of Hitler and World War II made
Thoroughly
Unimportant to them
Hitler ruins everything
And we just haven't really considered calendar reform since
Perhaps because
When designing time and the way people operate you have to consider custom and culture
It has to be done entirely and completely
Or not at all
So who knows perhaps if everyone decided to adopt it
A regimented calendar could really work better for
No finances and planning but on the other hand
I think it's kind of fascinating that are year is not
Perfectly regiment
Out of our control
Sometimes your birthday is on a Tuesday
What time does the Saturday
The Gregorian calendar is this
Organic instruments
The Ebbs and flows with the season from the rotation of the Earth
Got to spend too much time in California
It's
Really
A bizarre anomaly of History
That this calendar the starter was his
Cleopatra that
Performed by
Hope
That was really the Christian calendar
It it's now
The calendar of the world
And all we have to help us remember it is a stupid rhyme
That doesn't even rhyme
By the way we talk to another longtime Kodak employee for the story my name is Robert
Hours for Kodak for 35 years
Robert wrote a book about how Kodak film was made called making Kodak film
It's manufacturing process used to be top secret that Robert got Insider access to kodak's facilities
40 days
Photographing in
Factory
165 photographs
Shows
All the equipment and explain the process
This is like its own separate episode take it out here and say it's making Kodak film.com
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman with Sam Greenspan Katie mingle and me Roman Mars
We are a project of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
Picture into your sperm we're designing a new chicken and waffles place in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
I'm so excited about the chicken waffles
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
Routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called immortal
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com