99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
I want to start with a letter
And this is reporter Matthew kielty
This is the letter that got
Send out to a couple hundred people back in 1990 so
Roman View
You had a letter
Dear so-and-so
Be safe disposal of nuclear waste is one of the most pressing issues facing the United States today
Total skip down past that I mean that's just about how
We're planning on burying a bunch of waste out in New Mexico desert
At this place called d
Waste isolation pilot plant but if you go to another paragraph
You have been nominated to participate in a study sponsored by Sandia National Laboratories
Kinds of marker should be placed as witb sites
Philip a marker system that will remain operational during the performance. Of the site
10000 years
There it is
That is that is the part
That I love
I had a moment of wondering if it was a joke this is John Lambert
He received one of these
Which makes sense
Giving his line of work
I'm an artist
And I work on projects involving unusual communication
Do spent time in 70s working with Carl Sagan and Ann druyan on the Voyager golden record
One of NASA's attempts at communicating with aliens
No usually you don't get asked to design something that's going to last 10000 years
That's twice the span of recorded human history
The federal government
Really was calling on him
To help protect people
10000 years in the future
The waste isolation pilot plant wipp or whip
Pursue art
Which ordered into existence by Congress in 1979
The thinking was
The US ought to have a safe place to put radioactive byproducts from nuclear weapons manufacturing and
Nuclear Power Plant
And a quick refresher even though you don't see radiation
And you might not feel its effects right away
Exposure to radioactive materials
Can destroy your body at a molecular level it can leave Burns
Can cause cancer
It can even mutate your DNA
You think about radioactivity
Is that it is very spreadable
Say you've got a tool that
Text a piece of plutonium now that tool is radioactive
And say a worker was wearing protective gloves while using that tool
Chances are those clubs are radioactive to
The waste isolation pilot plant was designed to store all this stuff
And keep us all safe from it
The website is in New Mexico
Deep in the desert
About 26 miles east of
Carlsbad
It's
It's a really cool place and it reminded me of kind of the headquarters of Spectre or doctor know and it's
James Bond
Novel
Cuz it's it's it's a big underground facility filled with no technicians and income
Coveralls in a color-coded depending on what they did in person when he accept
Imitation from Sandia labs
Go be a part of the big group thing on designing a 10,000 your warning for the place
Happy you turn it down this was in 1991 so took John into An Elevator Shaft
And they go down about a half a mile beneath the surface
Bissonnet where John saw these enormous
Caverns
They've carved out this repository in basically assault
Deposit
Salt deposit
200 million years old
And
And we think of Saul as white
But this salt for reasons I don't understand was kind of a salmony pink color
So the walls of this place we're all crystalline
With this
Sort of shot through with the excuse of of salmon and
And pink and orange
So we actually quite beautiful
All this Radioactive
Stuff
I'll be loaded in the thousands of oil drums
Pact
Entities Cavern
And then
Underground chamber
Will be sealed up
Left alone
Years will pass in those years will become deck
Those decades will become centuries
Centuries will roll in the millenia
The people above ground will come and go
Cultures will rise and fall
And all the while
Below the surface
The salt will do what salt does
It's with the right temperature and pressure
Will slowly
Creep
Wiki Nick Cave
Old ways
Smaller and smaller
Smaller
Until the salt swallows up all those oil drums
Crushing it
Solidified in the Earth
Clubs in little bits from
All-Star Radioactive
Poisonous
More than
200000 years
Basically
Forever
Storing something dangerous Safeway forever is a huge design problem in fact the jury still out
On whether they sell the basics of the story's problem at all
In February of 2014 a leak was detected that expose several workers to low levels of radio
Malaysian and whip has been closed
Incense
The department of energy now predicts that it could be up to three years before whip is fully operational again
We know these facts
Because we can look it up
And read the news in a shared language
The problem that Jon lomberg was brought out to New Mexico to solve
Was not about communicating the danger of whip to people today
He wanted to figure out how to tell people Millennia from now
That this place is dangerous
When Jon lomberg arrived in New Mexico he met the teammates he be collaborating with
There were geologist language
Astrophysicist
There was science fiction writer Gregory Benford
The archaeologist
This is Maureen Maureen Kaplan
An archaeologist with a consulting firm ERG
Do you remember what you thought
Of the people that got together like me first song
There's like
Oh my goodness
She was
Kind of starstruck
Lumberg
Wait a moment Orange
The one who
Did the picture of that went off into space in terms of trying to communicate with whoever might
So I was impressed
Happy Hollows and whatnot the same to you folks split all these Smarties into
Two different groups
So they'd have kind of two separate thinking process
John was in Kirby Marine Group and then
Delete down the ground rules
They told us to assume
That we're designing a warning marker
For humans
Not aliens not cyborg
But for a human being biologically identical to us
But who's alive 500 or 5000 or 10000 years from now
How can you make a message
That not human will understand
And why
Why
10000 years
As far as I can determine the the logic seem to be well if we told him to design a marker to last two
150000 years is that clearly or ridiculous and absurd proposition
2000 years doesn't sound quite so crazy
It was it was just pulled out of the air
In other words even though this site is going to be radioactive for hundreds of thousands of years
This panel is only responsible for keeping this place efficiently labeled for humans
The next ten thousand years
Let's get some perspective
Think about where Humanity was 10000 years ago
Back then there was a hot new technology taking the World by storm
It was called
Farming
Before the Agricultural Revolution humans existed as gatherer Hunters
Biologically we are the same people we were 10000 years ago going back over 40
A Thousand Years
But culturally we share almost nothing with these people
Definitely not language
Well no cuz the linguist
Tell us that language
Changes language has a half-life
Just like radioactive materials
Have a half life
And it's half life
Isn't very long
Think about Shakespeare
Cousin Westmoreland
Name I fat cousin
Alack what
Poverty
Call General Zaroff clothes.
Some of the words
Flash
Pink one
But you know high schoolers to get to read Shakespeare was only four hundred years ago 4% of 10
And out in ears
What's go back to Beowulf Old English
Failed cooning at 3
Doolin Dalton
Basically incomprehensible
Ln fremington
Offshoot
Shaving
Yeah
It's like a different language
And I know you can't see this because this is
Radio but trust me
It's just as confusing on the written page
You can recognize most of the letters
Just being part of the English alphabet but they
Barely correspond with how we use those letters today
And that's from your 1,000 10% of 10000 years
There are some languages that are very resistant
The change
That is languages to get in Shrine in biblical texts in religious texts
Latin Hebrew Arabic
Those aren't sure bets either
The oldest written text go back to ancient Sumeria
About 4600 years ago
And those languages are long since dead
And that's not even the halfway mark of our time frame
Both team a and Team B at the whip
Brainstorming session
Realize pretty quickly that
Every language on the planet today
Could be gone
Well before 10000 years
And
How can you start a conversation with somebody that you have no common language with
Both group swing
Sure about this
Got to be something
Belgian language
Symbols
Simple pictures
There are some facial expressions with your pretty Universal
:-)
Two dots rise hats
Mouth
Puppy and take another one for like
Symbol for mystery Yak if you were alive in the 80s you know this one
Teriyaki
Mystery
Is
It's a logo of a green face with squinty eyes and a stuck out tongue
The face looks like it's about to be sick
It was designed to be put on cleaning products and other household poisons to let kids know at whatever's inside
Is going to be horrible for you
And so thinking along those lines
They considered another logo
Which they thought might be Universal
Actually Carl Sagan proposal
Seguin couldn't make it
But you sent him a letter saying this pole marker problem was easy
You just need the right symbol
And
Can you just the one
Skull and crossbones
The Jolly Roger
Death incarnate
Well
You know where the skull and crossbones came from
No no I don't leave earliest
Uses of it
Orin
Religious paintings and sculptures
From
Middle-aged
We're at the foot of the cross where Jesus is crucified
There's a skull
With two bones in the shape of a cross not an ex
The shape of a cross
Huh at Adams School
And the bones are the symbol of the Resurrection
So instead of it being a symbol of death
It was a symbol of resurrection and rebirth
But fast forward a couple of centuries
There's a lot of trade going on Merchant ships traveling to and fro and in the ship's log
If a sailor died
The captain would put a little skull and crossbones next to his name
And a lot of the sailors came to associate that symbol
With death the rebirth part of it was kind of lost fast forward another Century you got time
Without marauding on the high seas they plundered other boats and stole their cargo and along the way some Pirates realize
We could use a symbol to let their targets know who they were
A branding campaign to terrify they're targets into compliance clear
Pirates and if you don't surrender
We're going to kill you if your guess
But there are actually several different icon
That pirates used
For example a heart
With blood dripping out of it
That was a popular pirate flag and an even more popular symbol with an hourglass
An hourglass an hourglass
Matt
If you don't surrender in a certain amount of time
We're going to kill you all so The Hourglass for a while was the was the most feared
Pirate symbol
But then one of the Calico Jack Rackham
Was captured and put on trial
In the legal proceedings
It came out that two of the Pirates and Calico Jack's
True
We're women
And that one of them was
Pregnant with Calico Jack's child
This was
D tablets game of the day
Everyone in England was reading about this trial
Anyway it just so happened that
Calico Jack symbol
Was the Jolly Roger
Though in his case the bones were replaced with a pair of
Crossword
Quick aside
The name Jolly Roger is probably an English Corruption of the French
Joli Rouge
Work
Pretty red
Because the original pirate flag
Or red
Not black
After that trial
Installing crossbones started showing up on book covers
Treasure Island kind of novels and crossbones with permeating culture as a symbol of danger
Jump Ahead to the late 1800s
Dye factories in Germany started using the skull and crossbones with the symbol for poison
Half a century later than Nazis adopted it as the symbol for their SS death head
Division
Skull and crossbones
Came to be associated with danger and death
Around the world
But
Did it become Universal
Not really
Think about what's happened with
Discount crossbow
Last 20-30 years
Gone mainstream
Now you'll see it on kids book bags on onesies for infants
You can even buy water bottle
With the skull and crossed
So much for the whole
Play something
In the original meaning as it pertained to Adam and the resurrection is long gone
We took from this
Is that
Symbols
Can change
Iconographic adrift
Haven't
And we haven't even touched on cultural interpretation
Like there's a candy company in Mex
Call la Catrina
And their logo the logo that goes on the packaging for their sweet
Is a
Call
And so to bring us back to the website in New Mexico
Realize that symbols couldn't be trusted to mean the same things over.
Next idea we could tell a little story
Using sticks
Visual storytelling
Let's stick together like any five-year-old can draw
A circle on top
Trunk two arms and two legs
Why
Well there are two things
It seemed to be Universal
Inhuman or
What is a stick figure
And you find them or drawing on the walls of the caves in the cave paintings that are 25000 years old
Which by the way maybe the only piece of graphic art survive in for more than 10,000 years
Art food we can draw meaning
And John says there's another convention that is universal
A sequence of events
First this happened then this happened then this house
So like a narrative
A story storyboard a comic strip
You just find it everywhere
And in fact
You can even Define a symbol
Using stick figure
Check it out
Let's do a simple comic strip
First brain
You put the small child
And the child is in front of a small plant a sapling
Second brain
That child is a little bit bigger now and the sapling behind him has grown a little bit
Next to the child is
A barrel and on that Barrel is the symbol for radiation the trefoil symbol
And the child is touching
That Barrel
Go to 3rd frame you got a full grown big old tree you got a child that is now
An adult human being except
The person is lying
On the ground
Presumably dead
X's over their eyes frowny mouth
And the barrel now with
The Triple L symbol is open
It's clearly the idea is
Don't touch
Anything with the trefoils symbol or at least not a barrel
Of course you read it from right to left and it's a totally different story the old guy who is sick discovers the Fountain of Youth
He's reborn okay
All is not lost
Maybe you could use
Arrows
Bears RB Universal or maybe you can situate the various comic strips in a sequence
That you can only see sequentially
Based on how they are arranged in space
So I don't know maybe it's possible.
Create a universally recognizable warning sign
That way
Regardless of whatever symbol were trying to come up with or whatever story that we're trying to tell
You can we actually build something
Make some
Metaphysical
Tangible things that can last
10000 years
The brainstormers that whip thought about building something from solid gold
What what's going to happen they're going to get stolen
Marine Kaplan the archaeologist
Purple eyes
Same thing middles we're going to get recycled
Took no Bronson aluminum that basically leaves you with rock
Androx can Road
And who knows the chine monolith
Could be useful to some future desert person
You could get on
Tip it over on its side and then you have
Foundation
For your house
Here's the critical moment where all the obvious choices have been exhausted
Language
Symbols
In storyboards
Weren't going to cut it
And here's my plan for the website start getting
Really wacky
There was this one guy in Marines group
Name micro
Architect
And an artist
Realist
Send passed away
But Marie remembers
Intergroup
Girl have this revelation
You don't actually need to transmit information into the future
All you need to do is make somebody
Scared of being in that place
He was
Trying to
Don't
The landscape such that it in itself gave away
Morning to people who are coming there he was thinking on a massive scale
Scale greater than I'd ever imagined like one drawing which might called the
The landscape of thorns the drawing of needles sharp pointed
Angular up from the ground the Earth itself became
The land itself hominids and impossible but
The last thing you want to do is
Draw people to
To see this incredible work of art
You gotta see this thing it's all
A half-mile of these
Giant Spike
What the hell is it so
It's already built a hotel for them
Stay in and they decide
How to dig a well for water and there you are you just cause exact
How to avoid
When all was said and done both groups submitted their proposals but Sandia Labs found most of the ideas a little too pie-in-the-sky
Gears Rodger Nelson the chief scientist at the department of energy Carlsbad field office
Which owns and operates whip
If we build any markers that need to be constructed at a reasonable cost because it's just not right to
Ask
Real current generations of real people today
Comcast to sacrifice through their tax dollars or whatever
To invest in protecting a hypothetical Intruder into some very far future from a risk
So which there's likely no
Palm Coast
In fact the panel that met to figure out the whip marker system was actually not the first instance of thinkers being brats
Together to consider how to communicate the dangers of nuclear waste over time
There was one such meeting in 1981 for the Yucca Mountain project
Which was eventually scrapped
Mountainproject had
Probably the craziest idea proposed an even though it was never suggested for whip
It's become the 99 pi
In house
Favorite method of communicating with people 10,000 years in the future by probably reason why we're doing the story at all
Call it
The Ray cat solution
My hands-down favorite approach
Came from these two European philosophers
Francois bastide
Palo Verde
It goes like this
The two of them got thinking that the most durable thing that Humanity has
Ever made
Is culture
Religion folklore belief system
Sure they morph over time but
Essential message can get pulled through
And so it's speed in free said you were going to do
We're going to genetically engineer
Species of cat
It changes color
In the presence of radiation
Then release them out into the wild
Become
Feline Geiger
Let's just step number one
September 2
We will create an entire system of folklore about these cat
So we will sing songs about them we will drop pictures of them we will tell stories
About them
And like any good story there's more
That when you see the cats turn color
Run
Bar
Far away
Radiation
What's the Stray Cat folklore
Competitive
Into our culture
The knowledge it contains
Can evolve with us even if their language
10000 years from now these songs
Cindy stories may sound in comprehensible
But as long as they communicate
This idea
But it's not safe
Beware the cats
Colors
We will have done our job
Met the right cats
Keep us safe
The plan that Sandia labs
Decided to move forward with
Does not involve breakouts
Sadly
Or a landscape of thorns
It doesn't even involve the skull and crossbones
Conceptual design includes a big berm
30 feet high
Construction
Round the supremely repository that's Rodger Nelson again the chief scientist overseen whip at the end of the day
The powers-that-be decided to go with solutions to the Pamela said pretty much cast aside
They're marking the area with large Granite monuments large Granite Monument
Chili's Corner in the Meadowlands
Buried
Libraries they will be information in seven languages the six languages of the UN Arabic Chinese ink
English French Russian Spanish
And also Navajo
Because it's the
Most prevalent
Indigenous
Language of the area
The plan is still being finalized but keep in mind
We're talking about protecting people that are great great great great great great great great great great grandkids
Will never know
We have a duty to warn them we have a responsibility
Cinemark
Area
After a certain point
Yeah I started wondering like
A bit ridiculous
What was researching the story
I read about this town called Taliban
Small family African American
About our
I want to have south of Tampa
Florida
The
The brilliant process
Was set up in the middle of
Plant manufactured components for nuclear bomb
And also Bill pieces
Is the Hubble Space
Anyway it turned out that this plant was never very good about dealing with it
Beryllium dust and other toxins made their way
Into the town's groundwater
Alabaster
Always got that water from the shallow well
Resident started noticing that a lot
People were he diagnosed
Cancer
And other diseases
Including berylliosis
Which you get from
Exposure to beryllium
Tell dust filed a lawsuit against the company that owns
Lockheed Martin
And lucky Spencer
Years
Dragging out the lawsuit
The reason I bring this up
It's because Lockheed Martin happens to be the
Parent company of Sandia National Lab
The corporation that runs the website over in New Mexico
And this piece of Taliban
Is hardly unique
There are literally thousands of towns across United
Many of them
Low income or communities
Color that have become contaminated
It in similar ways
And so the 10000 year with marker system
But maybe a little misguided
I am all for taking care of people 10000 years in the future
Play the best way to do that
Is to start taking care of people that are alive
Today
That way there might be humans in 10000 years
And cats
Keep your color
Keep their color
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Matthew kielty and Sam Greenspan
With Katie mingle Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to a bunch of people for helping us with this story filmmaker Rob Moss
Stroud and Jordan oplinger over at the verge
Amen Lewis
Vdoe Carlsbad field office
Steve Lerner author of sacrifice Zone and Emperor X AKA Chad Matheny
Composing original song
Don't change color Kitty
Your head for ten thousand years
We are product of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced of the offices of
Of arcsin an Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is from
Frustrating it doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
We are founding member of radiotopia from PRX a collective of the most interesting Innovative Saundra
Which radio programs in the world and this week this week
All the radiotopia programs are putting out a new episode every single day around the theme
The long shadow
Stories where one person or place
Cast an outside influence across time and space
In this week on radio Diaries the long shadow of Asa Carter speechwriter for Governor George Wallace who panda
Segregation now
Segregation forever speech
Well I am just an old rapper recommended all I am
And I don't want no part
For nothing that I don't
This is a sicario
May God bless you
And I thank you for that
And that's the last time
ASA Carter
He just vanished
I keep dropped off the face of the Earth
And this week on love and radio
A woman ready to leave everything on Earth behind
To set up
Settlement
On Mars singer probably a lot of things that I'll miss
My family and pizza
A beer especially
If nobody's actually read about it or like looked at the website I can get a can of sound still crazy and many most people think that I'm like
Getting sucked in some weird cult
The Longshot everyday this week a new episode from a member of the radiotopia crew
Do not want to miss it. Dominus was gradual mall and then like
Changing all together into one gigantic block of awesome radio
You can find all the radiotopia shows at radiotopia. FM or search for us in iTunes
You can follow along with the various exploits of this show on Twitter
Facebook and Tumblr
If you want the full song don't change color Kitty by Emperor X
You have to go to 99 pi
Daughter
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com