99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If I ask you to think of the most famous architect in American history even if you don't think you know anything at all about architecture
I bet you could take a guess
And I bet your guess would be
Right
Frank Lloyd Wright Frank Lloyd Wright perhaps the greatest architect of the 20th century
Has been called the Pacesetter of modern-day architect
One of the most extraordinary men of all time for dinner
Patience and new ideas in the field of architecture
Frank Lloyd Wright left a legacy of some of the most iconic and gorgeous buildings in the United States
Like the spiraling Guggenheim Museum in New York
The falling water house in Pennsylvania which
Straddles a waterfall
And the futuristic Marin Civic Center
Which is the backdrop for Gattaca which is an awesome movie
And that is producer Avery trufelman
By the end of his career
Wright was on a level of celebrity usually reserved for actors and rock stars
The household name
And he was on late night talk shows
Some quarters of denounce right as an impractical Visionary in the pompous windbag
Yeah
How how do you feel about sex
Mr. right
The rape wasn't just known for being a genius architect
He made headlines because he was a character
You up and wear this outfit that included a Flowbee cape and a hat
Kane
He wrote Manifesto is launched insulted other Architects and loudly critique politicians
Religion and Society
Declared himself the greatest architect who ever lived
He was punishing
I chose honest arrogance
And Frank Lloyd Wright had this wildly scandalous private
There were suits against
Property
Divorce the raw materials are big
Spicy headlines
Frank Lloyd Wright was a darling of The Sensational press
But
This bombastic character ultimately
Change the field of
And introduced a new philosophy of building
Deformity of right iconic and famous structures were completed
Before falling water
For the Guggenheim
For the Marines
His most significant contribution to our everyday life
With something much
More modest
Small sturdy inexpensive
And most importantly
Very beautiful house design with the American working class in mind
And it all started
With a journal
From Milwaukee
1934a Milwaukee Journal reporter
Are named Herbert Jacob
Was assigned to take a drive over to Spring Green
In Central Wisconsin
Who told to write about
Taliesin
Frank Lloyd Wright's home and Studio
Jacob's didn't really know anything about architect
And at that particular time he wasn't really interested in learning anything about it
Because Herbert Jacobs had other things on his mind
And that November
His wife was very very pregnant
The night before his reporting trip
He brought her to the hospital
They stayed up with her until dawn
The nurse is a shared Herbert that he
We could go on his reporting trip
Missing my birth
And so
She set out that morning
Alone
.
Completely unprepared
He drove 120 miles to the chill gray Wisconsin Countryside for his assignment
To meet with Frank Lloyd Wright
Wright was 67 in 1934
Couldn't have cared less about his appointment with
Herbert Jacobs of the Milwaukee Journal
Actually
Write forgot all about it
Which wasn't unusual
He was known to blow off journalists
When Jacobs arrived at Frank Lloyd Wright's compound completely distracted by thoughts of his wife and their baby
You learn that the architect was actually on his way out the door
They got to talk for just over 10 minutes before right left
Abruptly saying
Some of the boys will talk to you now
The boys
Where Frank Lloyd Wright
Princesses
They've come to him from all over the world
And they're part of a fellowship program that right established at his home and Studio
ICampus he called Tallahassee
Taliesin
El Welch word meaning shining brow
Welsh because it was built on land settled by his family were farmers from Wales
But The Shining brow
Also has to do with rights building place
Taliesin actually is built on the brow
Just like your
Brow of your head
The main Taliesin building curls around the side of a hill
Almost like a crown
He felt that you should never build on top of a hill
Because I've destroyed the Integrity of the Hill
This is Floyd Hamlin
Is an architect
Exit Tallahassee
Also
Part of the faculty of the Frank Lloyd Wright School of Architecture and
I've been here since starting
As an apprentice back in
Hamblen works and lives at Taliesin full-time
Kieron Frank Lloyd Wright's family land
We're right used to play at the boy
So yeah where it where are we now where are we we are
This is
Just outside of Spring Green Wisconsin
It's a very beautiful green
Valley with Rolling Hills
So he
Spent a lot of his
His Summers
Working this land so he's very
Familiar
The landscape
And this
Connection
With the outdoors
Was really formative for right
He thought that architecture should help people live harmoniously with their environment
Rather than
Shield them from it
The house
To become part of nature
If it was made with local materials and had
Big windows and was oriented for
Just the right amount
Sunlight
The Orion
The house
Just wright
So that you've taken
Advantage of what Nature has
The offering
You're living with nature rather than trying to
The fight against it
You know living on the brow of the Hill
Knot on top of that
It's all folded into a concept
Frank Lloyd Wright called
Organic architecture
You wanted to spread this gospel to the Next Generation
Which is why he returned to the valley he knew as a boy
Established
The Taliesin Fellowship
Fellowship with the thing that the Milwaukee Journal wanted Herbert Jacobs to cover a news article
When Jacobs drove into Taliesin that morning in 1934
The fellowship had been going on for two years
It was hard for the public to wrap their minds around
Including this NBC announcer
King is Frank Lloyd Wright
They are such a right as the fingers of my hand
The apprentices had to pay $1,100 a year to attend the Taliesin Fellowship
Nearly 20 grand today
And it wasn't like an accredited institution or anything
Students had to do a lot of grunt work
Baling hay
Diamond fields in making meals
But they got to learn Frank Lloyd Wright's philosophy of architect
And live with them
And work with them
Even though often times has meant serving as an unpaid labor force
When Jacobs was getting his tour of Taliesin
He described the apprentices as
Rather long-haired smiling and polite young men
Who tried their best to explain to him what organic architecture
Sure means
Organic architecture is
Architecture of its time and of its place
You're not trying to make it
Look like something
But it's not
Write thought that there should be no wallpaper to cover things up
No paint no plaster
Would should look like what
Stone should look like Stone
Concrete should look like concrete
When Frank Lloyd Wright
Worked with
Why would he like
To leave the edge of the plywood exposed so that you saw those layers
Aaron that became part of the
Ornament
Detail
Which was different from
Really traditional European style architects
Roco gold ornaments
Clawfoot chairs
Parlors full of knick knacks
Just think of Victorian houses
Stuffed with lots of tiny rooms
Covered in bright paint
Macy curtains
This idea of organic architecture wasn't just a break from these tradition
It was a break from new trends in modern architecture 2
Cities all over the world we're building huge boxy glass and steel structures
Designed to be hypersleep machines for living and working
Wright explains that these were simply not comfortable
Bremen animals
I like goldfish and a globe
And these houses that are so classified as they know how they're not sensible it's
Houston
Privilege Center
An abuse of material
Frank Lloyd Wright took the traditional old materials and put them into Sleek modern forms
Is organic architecture was a new style
Born in the United States
An organic
Picture of a new sense
What constitutes
Humanity under harmonious condition
A harmonious
Pleasant Register living I'm on his way to living in
But Frank Lloyd Wright didn't
Playing this
Grand philosophy
To the journalist
Herbert Jacobs
Because right wasn't there
The apprentices did the best I could but again
Jacob's was very distracted
And was only thinking of his wife in the hospital
He thanked the two young man who showed him around Taliesin
And got back in his car
Jacob's ladder rope
Finally I started back to Milwaukee
Learning on the way to a telephone call to the hospital
That I had become a father at about 11
Clock that morning
At the very moment
When I was interviewing right
Herbert Jacobs
His wife Kathryn and their new daughter
Lived in Milwaukee for 2 more years
On his reporter salary of $20 a week
This was in the mid-30s
The Great Depression
So when Herbert Jacobs was offered a slightly higher paying job with a paper in the state capital of Madison
The family moved by the way
Finally got the Madison I couldn't find anything within our price range in a newspaper man's Place rains it was
I would we figured would be nice to live in
This is the voice of Herbert Jacobs himself
From a 1956 NBC interview
We can Catherine move to Madison they didn't see any houses they like
Or that they can afford
Do something for us
Jacob's didn't really remember much about his first visit to Taliesin two years before
Any murmured something along the lines of
Very interesting
Which is wife's cousin took as a yes
But he made an appointment for us to go out there and we went along with that idea
On the way house we were
My wife and I were trying to think
What is it The Weeknd
Jealous great man
Architecture Rich Prime
Hercules
Grease Monkeys
In the past when Frank Lloyd Wright had designed private homes they had not been for people
Like Herbert and Katherine Jacob's
Write a design
Gorgeous wide homes
Broad rooves
Expansive living room
You're welcome
The constructions were master
It works
New expensive
So we put it as a sort of challenge
What the country needs is a decent $5,000 house can you build one
In today's money $5,000 is about $85,000
That's a pretty reasonably priced house in most real estate market
Millwright had long wanted to make a more democratic form of housing
Even early in his
Given playing around with inexpensive methods
The building and other stuff
I need a lot of Concepts that had been scheming around urban planning
But now
Write have a chance to make some of his Concepts
A reality
She had the Willing science
And
He had time on his head
In 1936 he was in a bit of a slump in his career
People can afford fancy big new homes
Again it was The Depression
A number of big projects have been
Cancelled and also write had already been practicing for decades
He was slowly getting written off as a has-been
And then in comes this young open-minded couples
Wright could tell them his philosophy
And teach them how to live well for good architecture
Do you really want a $5,000 house
She said most people want a $10,000 house for 5,000
Are you willing to give up the things that you have to give up
Mr. Wright made a list of the things that the Jacobs would have to do without
Really wanted a $5,000 house
Tile bathrooms
Extra trim finishing things like that are you willing to give those up
We didn't know anything about it we said sure that's okay with us
Herbert and Katherine Jacob's didn't know it at the time
But that modest little house that Frank Lloyd Wright was
To build for them
Would be the most
Classical expression
Of his ideology
The Jacobs would own the first house in a movement that right called
Usonia
The house that Herbert Jacobs built was the first of the usonian houses
Usonia was Frank Lloyd Wright's name for the United States of North America
In Wright's vision usonia would be a country full of modest
Well made
Beautiful comfortable little house
Is that the working class could afford
These usonian homes
Woodin
Spire
Educate and write believe
Create a new culture
For all Americans
I believe now people are going to know what constitutes good architecture
And of course good living has to go with it
Good Conduct also
Good dressing to because you wouldn't dress
Download and vogelweh and a quiet and beautiful room
All is good things
Are dependent Wireless one on the other and add up to something that we call culture
It's only by a natural girls
Who can attend Coachella
Write believe the way to build a better American culture was not on mass not in apartment buildings or cookie
Cookie cutter development
It was to be catered to the individual
Kosher not for the cross country as an individual
Sing
And that's what our forefathers
Struck
Band-Aid that
The individual is
Shower
Wichita Frank Lloyd Wright
I meant that the masses should be unmasked
You should spread out
Away from the city
Weather city of course is a
Thing of the past
There was a time during the Middle Ages
When
Said it was the only source of culture
There's no way of acquiring
This thing we call culture except by direct contact
That wasn't true anymore
People were connected to culture through radio and telephones and Automobiles
They have
Transportation
Speed
Listening this
Cherry where
Using now
It's no longer essential
For people to crowd together anyway
These were all parts of Frank Lloyd Wright
Vision for America
And this would start to become reality in 1936
With the Jacobs
Which would come to be known as Jacobs one
Or
Usonia 1
Jacob's house was
One of the first ones built there was this
Was just left wide open Farmland when it was built out here
This is Bill Martinelli
Manager of usonia 1
It's in a Suburban Street at side of Madison now lined with little suburban houses
But usonia one really stands out
Even if you don't know what it is and you're just driving by
Because I'm a street
It almost looks like a beautiful wooden wall
The house turned its back on the road
Well when you get inside her if we go around back you'll see that whole back of the house so I'll glass it's all open
Come to the back and he only did that intentionally the kind of close it off to the street and then
Open it up to the back
As right site the point of the house would love to have a big facade to show off your neighbors
With a useless and wasteful patch of lawn in the front
Cinegrand entryway
No
House
Should be built for residents
Not on lockers
Also from the street you can see that there's no garage
Car is parked under a wooden awning
Just a little flat roof with no sidewalk
This is the carport
The term that Frank Lloyd Wright coin
Well this is the
Carport of the houses
Considered the first
Named carport it was a turn that right came up with
This was one of the many tiny ways right cap cost down
And also the carport was an education in lifestyle
Without a garage that Jacobs wouldn't have space to store their junk
Adaptive simply minimize their possessions and toss what they didn't need
The carport isn't purely utilitarian
The woodwork on the carport roof
Has this lovely geometric pattern
Who is like these boys
Kind of stripes in the
Funny when I've seen Matt heard about the carport and like seeing pictures of it I didn't expect it to be so
Beautiful in like
Really nice
Nothing in this house the more you look around more
Moore UCLA
But the ceiling here
Carport
Expect that
Get inside the sea the same thing
Usonia 1 is full of small elegant details
Sure
Warm in here
Oh wow
Sun
Red
Every like the brick in the wall
Florida
Here I kind of gets drawn in
Usonia 1 is 1/4
And inside it's pretty much one room
And loud
Cat
The space is all open no walls
Between the living room dining room kitchen
That was kind of innovative for the time
The kitchen is an Alcove adjacent the living / dining space
Face with no door
It's a very
Barry
Tiny area this is this is the kitchen
It's just a little bit wider than the length of my arms I think weight
But eat footbike
8 foot square rug
Is a small hallway width
Tiny bedrooms
But mostly the one main room is the focus
That's why you're supposed to eat relax
Read
Live all together
Again Herbert Jacob
Advocate of the open-plan and housing
Bee removal of a boxes within boxes
You don't have
Many petitions
Temptation music
Be together much more
The open-plan was pretty novel
And it was cost-saving to not have many walls
Usonian house is full of these clever
Less expensive solution
Like the lights on the ceiling
So that's just
Steel Channel with the wires just
Land in there and then bare socket spare bulbs
Let's consider the first
Track lighting
Another first
To the house
And now you see track lighting everywhere
Where do you see lights
Its or bulbs
Fix to a single beam
That's a usonian invention
Other Innovations usonia popularized include the use of flat roof
Built-in furniture
Heated floors
Herbert Jacobs
Love those heated floors
Poor Heating
No very general
But at that time there were no floor he did resident Susan this country
All of these Innovations Were Meant to help the family live well
Frugally
They saved money while they lived in the house
And they also save costs
In the construction of the house
But right you some other cost-saving measures that were kind of
Cheating
Like he stole some bricks from another building of his
But he was constructing nearby
Well right didn't steal the bricks himself
He sent a bunch of his apprentices over to Racine Wisconsin where his design for the Johnson wax building was under
Construction
He told the apprentices to grab as many bricks if they could
And bring them back to Madison
If you're familiar with the
Johnson wax building
The corners are curved
So you can see
Some of these bricks are
Convex or concave while those were
Like Corner brick
Another way right cap cost down was by taken
Huge pay cut himself
Bill I paid was for $5,500 which included Mr rights fee of $450
By hook or by crook
Brighten it
He met his challenge of building a beautiful house
At Herbert and Katherine could afford
I mean
It wasn't
Perfect
The total adjustment for the family
In the house had problems with rain drainage and little things were missing like initially right forgot to put
Screens on the windows
Which one of the kinds of complaints right got a lot
He mostly focused on Aesthetics and principles of building
Rather than practicalities
And ultimately
The Jacob's house was
Small
After Herbert and Katherine had two more children
They couldn't fit into the house anymore
I'm so after 6 years of living in usonia 1
The Jacobs family would move off to the countryside
We're Frank Lloyd Wright wood design them a second usonian house
But Herbert Jacobs thought of their first home very fondly
Living in that house was
Fantastic
Mister Wright thought so too. Everybody should live in a house
Design by humans
Dishes and clothes
Designed by him and all the furniture
He did design a lot of his furniture
And at least one case he did design a dress for the wife of
This was all about changing culture
One home at a time
Frank Lloyd Wright wanted to redesign America
And by that token Americans
Good design he thought would make a Kinder more beautiful
More enlightened country
You don't need a guy
You'll know my 1939 right head Built usonian Homes all over the country
Including houses in Alabama California Illinois
Michigan
In Virginia
But he wanted to build more
He wanted have a central Factory that made prefabricated usonian parts
Modifiable for each client depending on their needs for space insight
And originally the whole idea was
All these walls would be
Manufactured in
Factory
That never really happened this was all site-built
Frank Lloyd Wright's Factory for usonian homes never came to power
And it became increasingly clear to write that the $5,000 price tag for usonian homes
Wasn't feasible after the Depression
Also right career picked up shortly after usonia 1
He started building bigger Commission
The ones we all know him
Like falling water
I'm on the right house is none has been more widely publicized and the Pennsylvania home of Edgar Kaufmann
Which battles of waterfalls
Right worked on usonian homes up until near the very end of his life
But it was a group of his Apprentice
Carry on his vision
By building
Entire community
I'm usonian houses
Turn right on usonia Road
Next time on 99% invisible
A trip to usonia New York
To see what became of Frank Lloyd Wright's vision
NY these little houses have effect
The ways we live
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery trufelman
Wish reviews
Delaney Hall
Emmett Fitzgerald Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Katie mingle is our senior editor posted is our digital director
Sean real compose all original music for this episode
Intern Masa
Is the baroness
Special things this week to John and Betty Moore John eifler gym Sharp
Christine Ingram and Jody McGuire
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
Doesn't have to Define constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show enjoy discussions about the show on Facebook you can meet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Pi org
Run Instagram and Tumblr to
But if in the course of your life you find yourself in need of really well told beautiful design stories
You should seek out and spend time
Onomatopoeia
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
American
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy's you know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com