99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On April 9th 2017 United Airlines flight 3411 was about to fly from Chicago to Louisville
Flight attendants discovered the plane was overbooked
I tried to get volunteers to give up their seats with Promises of travel vouchers and hotel accommodations
But not enough people were willing to get off
United ended up calling some airport security officers
Board the plane and forcibly removed a passenger name doctor David down
The officers ripped out of a seat
And carry them down the aisle the airplane nose bleeding while horrified onlookers shot video with their phones
Busted his lip
You probably remember this incident in the outrage a generator
The international uproar continued over the forced removal of a passenger from the United Airlines flight
Today the airline CEO Oscar Munoz
Issued an apology saying quote
No one should ever be mistreated this way
I want you to know that
We take forward
But why doctor
How did he end up being the Unlucky passenger that United decided to remove
Immediately following the incident
Some people thought racial discrimination may have played a part
And it's possible that this played a role in how you
Treated
But the answer to how he was chosen
Was actually
An algorithm
Computer program
It runs through a bunch of data
Looking at stuff like how much each passenger I pays their ticket what time they checked into off Nicky one United
And whether they were part of a rewards program
The algorithm likely determined that dr.dao was one of the least valuable customers on the Fly
I got the time
Algorithms shape our world and profound and mostly invisible ways
They predict it will be valuable customers
Or whether were likely to repay a loan
They filter what we see on social media
Sort to resume
And evaluate job performance
Inform prison sentences in Montour or hell
Most of these algorithms have been created with good intentions
The goal is to replace objective judgments with objective measurements
But it doesn't always work out like that
The subject
Huge I think algorithm design Maybe
The big design problem of the 21st Century
And that's why I wanted to interview Cathy O'Neil
Okay thank you so much so cuz when we start can you give me one of them sort of npr-style
Introductions in to say your name and what you do
Sure
I'm Cathy O'Neil I'm a mathematician data scientist
Activist an author I wrote the book weapons of math destruction how big did it increases in equality and threatens to
Call Krissy O'Neal studied number Theory and then left Academia to build predictive algorithms for a hedgehog
But she got really disillusioned by the use of mathematical models in the financial industry
I wanted to like have more impact in the world
But I didn't really know that that impact could be really terrible I was very naive
Every. O'Neill work as a data scientist.
Couple of startups
And through these experiences
She started to get worried about the influence of
Poorly designed algorithm
So we'll start with the most obvious question
What is an algorithm
As most basic
An algorithm is a step-by-step guide to solving a problem
It's a set of instructions like a recipe
Cooking dinner for my family
Do in this case the problem is how to make a successful dinner
O'Neill starts with a set of ingredients
She's creating the meal
You constantly making choices about what ingredients are healthy enough to include in her dinner algorithm
Accurate that data because those ramen noodle packages
Exclude
And therefore imposing my agenda on this algorithm
In addition to curating the ingredients
O'Neal as the cook also defines what a successful outcome looks like
I'm also defining success right I'm in charge of success success
If my kids eat vegetables at that meal
We know different cock my define success differently
Define success to be like
Impose
Origin.
O'Neil's main point here is that our them aren't we object
Even when they're carried out by computers
This is relevant because the companies that build them like to Market them as a jacket
Claiming they remove human error infallibility from complex decision-making
But every algorithm reflects the priorities and judgments
David human designer
Of course that doesn't necessarily make algorithms bad
Right so I mean it's very important to me that I don't
Get the reputation of hating allowed
I actually like algorithms I think algorithms could really help
Brunilda single out a particular kind of algorithm for scrutiny
These are the ones we should worry about
Are characterized by three properties
That's very widespread and important so it's like they make important decisions about a lot of
Number to that their secret that the people don't understand how they're being scored
I never treated their destructive like one bad mistake
In the in the design if you
Will actually not only make it unfair for individuals butts
Categorically unfair enormous populations As It Gets
Scaled-up
O'Neill has a shorthand for these algorithms
The widespread mysterious and destructive
She calls them
Weapons of math destruction
To show how one of these destructive algorithms work
O'Neal points to criminal justice
For hundreds of years key decisions in the legal process
Like a mountain belt
Sentence and likelihood of parole
I've been in the hands of fallible human beings Guided by their instinct
And sometime
Personal bias
The judges are super famously race at some of the more than others
And that racism can produce very different outcomes for defendants
For example the ACLU has found that sentences imposed on black men in the federal system
Are nearly 20% longer than those four white men convicted of similar crimes
And Studies have shown that prosecutors are more likely to seek the death penalty for African Americans that for whites convicted
The same charges
So you might think that computerized models fed by data would contribute to more even-handed treatment
Criminal Justice System think so too
It is increasingly try to minimize human bias
By turning to risk
Assessment algorithm
Like crime risk what is a chance of someone coming back to prison after leaving it
Many of these risk algorithms look at a person's record of arrest and conviction
The problem is
That data is already skewed by some social realities
Take for example the fact that white people and black people use marijuana at roughly equal rates
And yet there's five times as many
Blacks getting arrested for smoking pot as whites
5 times as many
This may be because black neighborhoods tend to be more heavily policed than white nearby
Which means black people get arrested for certain crimes more often than white
Risk algorithms detect these patterns and apply them to the Future
So the past is shaped in part by racism
The future will be to
The larger point is we have terrible date
For the statisticians
Involve the data scientist are like bliley going forward and pretending that our data is good
And they were using it to actually make important decisions
Risk assessment algorithm is also look at defendants answers to a questionnaire that supposed to tease out certain risk
Understand questions like you know did you grow up in high-crime neighborhood
Are you on welfare do you have a mental health problem do you have addiction problems
Did your father go to prison
Eproxies for racing class
What is embedded in the scoring system and the judge is
Given the score and it's called objective what is
What is a
Judge take away from it or you know how is it used if you have a high risk to send you to prison for longer
Incessant
Is also it's also used in bail hearings and parole hearings you have a high recidivism score
You don't get girl
And presumably you can take all that bias
Import data
And say
This High chance recidivism
Means that we should
Rehabilitate
I mean that you can take that pill that same stuff and choose to do a completely different thing with the result of the algorithm
That's exactly my point exactly my point
Say oh I wonder why people who have this characteristic have so much worse recidivism well
Let's try to help them find a job that'll help
We could use those algorithms those risk scores
To try to account for our society
Instead O'Neill says in many cases were effectively penalizing people for societal and structural issues that they have live
Little control over
And we're doing it at a massive scale
Using these new technological tools
We're Shifting the blame if you will from the society which is the one that should only has problems to the individual and
It should be said that and some cases algorithms are helping to change elements of the criminal justice system for the better
For example New Jersey recently did away with their cash bail system
Which disadvantage low-income defendant
They now rely on predictive algorithms instead
Data shows that the states
Pretrial County Jail populations are down by about 20%
But still algorithms like that one remain unaudited and unregulated
And it's a problem when algorithms are basically black boxes
In many cases they're designed by private companies who sell them to other companies
Any exact details
And how they work
Secret
Not only the public in the dark even the companies using these things
Might not understand exactly how the data is being processed
This is true of many of the problematic algorithms that O'Neill has looked at
Whether they use for sorting loan applications
We're assessing teacher before
Is there some kind of weird thing that happens to people
In mathematical scores are trotted out
They just start
Closing their eyes and believing it because it's math
And they do I feel like I know I'm not an expert of math so
I can't push back
And that's not something you just see time and time again you're like why didn't you question that this doesn't make sense
Oh well it's math and I don't understand it
Right now it seems like
Because of algorithms in math
It's just a new place
Place blame
So that you do not have to think about
Your decisions as natural company
Because he's things are just so powerful and so you know mesmerizing to us
Especially right now
Making music
All kinds of
Nefarious way almost magical
Yeah
Hatsune
Scary
It's scary and I think I think I'm going to like I would go one step further than that I feel like
Just an observation that these algorithms
They don't show up randomly they show up when there's a really difficult conversation that people want to avoid
They're like oh
We don't know what it's what makes a good teacher and different people have different opinions about that
Siletz
Just bypasses conversation by having an algorithm score teachers or
We don't know what prison is really for
Let's have a way of deciding how long to sentence up
We introduced these Silver Bullet mathematical algorithms because we don't want to have a cover
Station
In a news book she writes about this young guy named Kyle B
Who takes some time off college to get treated for bipolar disorder
When's he's better and ready to go back to school supplies for a part-time job at Kroger
The big grocery store chain
His friend works there who offers to vouch for
Kyle was such a good student that he figured the application would be just a formality
But he didn't get called back for an interview
Is application was Redline
By the personality test be taken when he applied for the job
The test was part of an employee selection algorithm
Developed by private Workforce company called Kronos
70% of job applicants in this country take personality test before they get an interview so this is a very common practice
Kyle had that screening and he found out because his friend worked at Kroger's
But he has failed the test so most people never find that other just don't hear back
And the other thing that was unusual about Kyle is that his dad is a lawyer
So his dad was like what
What were the questions like on this test
And he said well there's some of them are a lot like the questions I got at the hospital the mental health assessment
The Tesco got at the hospital was called the five Factor model
Integrates people on
Extraversion agreeableness conscientiousness
Neuroticism and openness to new ideas
It's used in mental health of Ally
Potential employees answers to the test
Are then plugged into an algorithm that decides whether to
The person should be hired
Something's father was like well that's illegal under the Americans with Disability Act
Does father and he's figured out together
But something very fishy had been going on in his father's actually filed class action lawsuit against Krogers for the
The suit is still pending but arguments are likely to focus on whether the personality test can be considered a medical exam
If it is
In the illegal under the Ada
Anil gets a different jobs require people with different personalities
But she says a hiring algorithm is a blunt and unregulated tool that ends up disqualifying big categories of people
Which makes it a classic
Weapon of math destruction
In certain jobs you wouldn't want neurotic people or introverted people like if you're at a call center
We're a lot of
Really irate customers call you up
That might be a problem
In which case it is
Actually legal if you get
An exception for your company
The problem is that these personality tests are not carefully designed for each business
But rather what happens if these companies just sell the same personality test
To all the businesses that will buy them
A lot of the algorithms that O'Neill explores in her book are largely hidden
They don't get a lot of attention
We as consumers and job applicants and employees
May not even be aware that
Coming along in the background of Our Lives
Piles in categories
But there is one kind of algorithm has gotten a lot of attention in the news lately
Social media has been able to infiltrate
Politics
Social media is a technology
Title is all depends on our conversation started talking about
The recent election and the complex ways that social media algorithms shape the news that we receive
Facebook shows the stories and ads based on what they think we want in a horse what they think we want is based on algorithms
These algorithms look at what we clicked on before and then he has more content we like
The result is that
We've Ended up in these information silos
Increasingly polarized and oblivious to what people of different political Persuasions might be seen
I do think this is a major problem you know it's the start of the sky's the limit we have built the internet in the internet
Is a propaganda machine
It's propaganda
Delivery device
If you out
And that's not
I don't see how that's going to stop
Yeah
Especially if every moment
Optimized
Find algorithm it's meant to manipulate your emotions
Right let's go to Facebook's Optimizer algorithm that's not optimizing
Chartreuse
Optimizing for profit
And then they claim to be neutral
But of course nothing's neutral
And we have seen the result
We've seen what it's actually optimized
This kind of data-driven political micro-targeting means conspiracies and misinformation can gain surprising traction on
Online
Stories claiming that Pope Francis endorse Donald Trump
And that Hillary Clinton sold weapons to Isis
Game millions of viewers on Facebook
Neither of those two
Betrayal
Fixing the problem of these destructive algorithms is not going to be easy especially when they're insinuating themselves and then more
And more parts of our lives
Romeo thinks that measurement and transparency is one place to start
Like what that Facebook algorithm and the political ads that it serves to its users
If you were to talk to Facebook about
How to
Inject some ethics into their optimization
What would you
Do would you make a case for the bottom line of Truth being a like a longer tail way to make more
Money or would you just say
This is about ethics and you should be thinking about ethics
To be honest if I really had their attention I would ask them to
Voluntarily
Find a space on the web to just put every political
Add
And actually every ad just have a way for
For journalists
And people interested in the concept of the informed citizenry
To go through all the ads that they have on Facebook at a given time
Because even if that article about Hillary Clinton and Isis with shared thousands of times
Lots of people never saw it at all
Just show us what you're showing other people
Because I think one of the most pernicious issues is
The fact that we don't know what other people are saying
I'm not waiting for Facebook to like
Actually go against their interest
I'd like changed their profit goal but I do think this kind of transparency can be given
O'Neill also says it's important to measure the broad effects of these algorithms
Can't understand who they most impact
Everyone should start measuring it
And what I mean by that
It is relatively simple and it's
This might not be a complete
Start but it's a pretty good for
Stop witches
Measure
Perfume this fails
Meaning which population
Are most negatively impacted by the results of these acronyms
What is the harm that befalls those
And how are the failures distribute
Across the pond
So if you see a hiring algorithm
Feel
Much more often for women
That's a problem
Especially if the failure is
They don't get hired when they should get
I really do think that a study
A close examination of the distribution of failures
And the harms of those failure
Would really really be a good start
You're not mad enough about how algorithms influence your life
I've got a doozy
These messages
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
We are currently experience
Higher call volume
The normal
Please stay on the line
And then
I'll be with you shortly
Just one that I think is kind of
Fun because it's annoying and Secret
But you would never know it
So if you call but customer service line
I'm not saying this will always happen but it will sometimes happen
That your phone number
Will be used to back
Track like who you are
Ubisoft
As like are you high value customer or low value
If you're high value customer
You'll talk to a customer service representative
Much sooner than if your love
Put on hold
That's how businesses make decisions now
You are caller number
Your call is important
Please stay on the line
99percentinvisible with bruises week by Delaney Hall
Tecademics production by Emmett
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kolstad is the digital
Some real composed all the music
Staff includes a breach of immense refused
Turn master and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Ryan keasler and
Courtney riddle
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco
Produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99% invisible part of radiotopia from pra
The best most Innovative shows in all app
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
Coin carrying list
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can't we do meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99p
Gyorgy
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
The lovely home on the internet with more design story than we can ever tell you here on the radio
The podcast
Is there a website
And 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com