99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Hrishikesh hirway has a podcast called song Exploder the concept is simple but
Brilliant I ask musicians to take apart one of their songs and go through it piece by piece and
What listeners hear what's going on inside some of the tracks and reveal the secrets
Of
What went into making the song whether it's
The Sounds inside of it or just
Memories of what they were going through
When they were creating song
Palms are sweaty
I don't think she would mind me saying but it's
Hidesign show
About music
Play 99% invisible for song
On the very first episode of song Exploder Richie interview Jimmy tamborello of the band Postal Service
Invited him to take a deep dive into each individual element of the song
The district sleeps alone tonight
If the song is playing mind me now if you don't already own the loan Postal Service album
You made some poor choices in life
I'm serious
Anyway this is Jimmy tamborello isolating the backing Vocal Track sung by Jenny Lewis
So here's some of
Jenny's background vocals solo.
So Timber Ella was looking to add more texture to the Final Mix the song
Any had these beautiful backing vocals
It might have been just an accident with a delay pedal but
Lips a little bit of Chinese vocals
And made into
Texture in the Sun as one of the last things
That we put into that into the district
Play that part
This vocal Loop comes in after the second verse when it's kind of going into the
More Dancy Down trailer
Here's her schedule away from song Exploder again
I'd heard that song The District sleeps alone tonight I mean
So many times since it came out in 2003
I knew that part and I knew that sound I have no idea
But that was a
Human voice
Making that sound until he took everything away
And that was the first episode that was for like the pilot before the show is called
Song Exploder before when I was closer to figuring it out
And when Jimmy play that part I was like oh this is it this is
This is the reason why I want to do the show
And a radio show was born
Podcast whatever
As opposed to like a magic
Trick where the intention is to
Fool the audience
You thinking that
Their experience is something that they aren't
If you're learning all the secrets of a song
The idea is still too dress
Create a musical experience for you that you enjoy
And
I feel like you'd like to know more about it then you can have a richer enjoyment of it at least that's
How it is for me
So say we all
Today we're going to feature a recent episode of song Exploder all about the theme song to the Netflix original series
House of Cards
This is one of my favorite episodes because it reveals so much
About all the thought that goes into making a theme song
Turn TV show
She spoke to the composer Jeff Beal and his home in Los Angeles and he describes his collaboration with
Series executive producers David Fincher and Beau willimon
How they established
Tone and musical palette of the show
And how the music theme change from season 1 to season 2 even notice
Turn off go back
Indifferent
You currently during the season 1 version
By the way there's a House of Cards season 1 spoilers ahead
So you've been warned
Here is composer Jeff Beal
Talking to her skate Shaarawy
On song exploder
I'm Jeff Beal
Composer I do the music for House of Cards
I had worked with David Fincher on a commercial
Probably about 6
Six or seven years ago
This was around the time I have been working on Rome
HBO
So I saw the trades you know this show is happening with David's name attached and I kept in touch and we never worked together since and I thought this might be
Good match for us you know
Bad watch little bit of the British show and that was something that's part of my pitch to David is that cuz I saw her use the wrong thing I said well I said
Even around with a. Rama was very much about politics
Operatic scale cast and storytelling
After I first met with David disorder talk about the project and got his initial thoughts about music makes or put our heads together
Based on his sort of
Way of thinking about music and how much music informs his choices he actually asked me to write some sketches
Before he started shooting at a course before
We had the meeting or before I wrote this sketches they shared with me I think about four or five Scripts
Early drafts of what became season 1
So it was very much and Bose both sense of language in the way he sort of created this world that inspired
Some of the early early work
The thing I like about the British show with his sword dark humor to it
And I said yeah did the music definitely have to find a way to sort of give the audience permission to sort of the laugh the sardonic
Darkness once he
Call me and you know he gave me some of his thoughts on it which were interesting and some of the surprising to me she was one song you really like
Like the Supertramp
Crime of the century
Great song
The section of that song towards the end where
It just becomes a sort of driving
Kiest
Had to send some sort of
Operatic for a classism in and
Sort of Gravitas but
But it also had a very gritty
Birthday almost Jazzy or bluesy
Transportation of rock and roll
We knows we distracted that together and sort of thought about why that spoke to him
That's the show the show is
It's all about the underbelly of Washington
The dark Corners what you don't see and what really happens
Supposed to sort of The West Wing you know heroic
More aspirational
The storm Hail to the Chief you know Washington than your typical sort of the film score gestures about the capital and Pollock
I wrote about for sketches
For David
One of the things we talked about in our first meeting you was he said was we kind of need a call to Arms
And when you listen to it
It has a lot of the elements that became the main title theme it's got that bass line it's got that sort of cloud dark Electro
Proceed at like a
Like a fog or something
And the tune is there although in this case it was displayed by the piano very simple orchestration
And then just in the second time it goes around the snare drum comes in
Very simple but there's a tune in there there's a little sequences
Of chords and Melody
Part of the reason sketching is useful is because it's like the bones of something
If the structure of the skeleton is it has integrity
It should be able to stand without
An abundance of sort of instrumental
Embellishment
And so by sketching and by doing Simple versus themes
You are able to sort of make sure that you have an idea
I always thought of this is sort of the Puppet Master theme the idea that like
Kevin Spacey's character is
Serta manipulator who's a virtuoso at pulling the strings on people and getting them
Do what he wants them to do
But the reason I'm sharing this one in the context of the main title is
When we got around to finally doing the arrangement David said he would be cool if the main title felt like the sort of
Stu
A lot of different elements from the score
Which would then be deconstructed into its individual parts
So you'll hear this sort of descending chromatic line in the high piano
That became
One of the signature the main title sequence
As-built sketch grows the electric bass comes in
So it's the sort of
Homeless piano Motif by putting that bass underrated sort of gave it at attention of something that's pushing against it
Dave and I talked about the piano little bit cuz I was in the Supertramp q&c instrument I like a Laden
It felt like a good instrument for Kevin's character because it can be very precise and very
Through mechanical in a way
Which I love about it
Those are called arms things that was dropped into the main title sequence and it never left once it was in there that was what we're going to do
And I started you know if you passes through
I start to work on the arrangement
The story of the main title sequences visually
Lyric on flowing but then I remember this came straight from sort of those original scripting of the main title
Just basically the whole idea of the sun going down in Washington uni started in really broad daylight
And as a sequence
Progressives you end up at night
So you so there was a way in which you went from something very open and and Airy and light just like the.
Darkness falling
So that was that was a little bit of a visual storytelling thing I tried to play off of
The first thing we hear is the fog the fog of
The Cloud of Doom it's this is sort of low since Brown
Shortly after that comes the Baseline
Which I know David affectionately referred to as the riptide I was like that describes
It's kind of like the idea of something that pulls you under basically a combination of several things it's
Analog e model 10 things that I designed some of my head for a long time and it's a couple different
Playing the part
Who is a Wonderful Young musician he's actually Now setting jazz bass
Patient with getting big enough I actually recorded the bass an octave above it gives it enough Midway contents so that when all this other stuff
Is happening at basic still driving one of the fun things about the composition for me with that
The harmony change is a lot over that bass line in fact bass is always playing in a minor but the harmony sometimes goes to a major
Can I create this very strange dissonance
Innocence of collision
I know because it's ingrained it's got its own logic to it so much like Frank will push through anything he doesn't care he's not going to
Stop playing those notes
My original sort of call the arm sketch two times through which is kind of the original demo with almost long enough to cover the main title sequence
I need some more time
And I also had this direction from David to sort of work in another theme
So what I did was I kind of extended the intro I had a lot of percussion
But I also added that little Puppetmaster Rip but did you know that thing
It has a slightly different
Cadence because this isn't for 4 in the master theme of those in three
Prices are broken up a little bit but it's sort of it's still got that descending chromatic line
Another layer that was sort of one of the last things I came up with but was really useful as the trumpet
McLaren
Again it's the most
Expected cliche thing you here in old show about Washington would be that sort of
Military trumpet kind of thing
Because we're seeing
The sort of iconic shots of Washington
It just felt right to have something that references that icon cuz obviously the rest of the composition is telling you that this isn't the heroic
Version of the Lincoln Memorial and the Washington Monument and there's a way in which is sort of lonely too me too I like this riddle
Loneliness
One of the things David visually did
Was to pull out
A lot of the people in some of the time-lapse shots he has
It was much creepier seeing some of those shots with no people in them
They just made it feel like he was a ghost town or was that the sorcerer real
Quality to it
Basically in talking to David Fincher
About the second season
That was a sort of surprising to me but
If we were spotting the first couple episodes YouTube
Guitar to give me notes on the main title that what he wanted different
You know David saw the second season is even more operatic and darker to which is
Shocking meager
The first season was pretty dark
You seen who who Frank is and what he can do you know in these killed somebody in the first season I mean
Obviously very nothing's going to get in the way of what this guy wants to do
In general for main titles you know people get attached to push when they like something
Does very careful you know to like steer the ship enough
But not so far as to make it feel like your old friend was not your friend anymore so
I added some voices some voice samples to a lot of it
I also added some some low strings
To the intro
The high string line that used to be in the Celli
2 Gannett slower everything sort of
Skewing Downs doing darker
Insulate It Feels Like This Cloud is sort of
Come over the whole thing
The sort of lightness and
Sense of that type of energy is dissipated you know he's no longer the Puppet Master return to the vice-president season 2 we know he's
He's very much in command so there's less of a game going on and much more of a
It's it's like you sent to the phone
I think somebody networks or even the filmmakers are afraid of a real main title sequence a servant old-fashioned idea but the whole idea of a
A little mini film that settles you into a world and get you ready
To experience something is a wonderful sort of a
Storytelling device
You know it's sort of frames a moment for you and gets you settled into
What you're about to take in
Now here's the season 2 version
The main title
That would song exploder
99percentinvisible
It was produced by which case your way
Results of the driving force behind the band The One AM radio
Playing Barney right now
Song Exploder is partly maximum fun network with shows like the Memory Palace Bullseye with Jesse thorn
Judge John Hodgman my brother my brother and me all kinds of good stuff
I've been a listener and monthly donor for
Years
You will find a show you love at maximum Farm. Org
99percentinvisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery truffelman and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce out of the offices of Arkansas
Collaboration minded Architecture Firm in collaboration minded Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listening to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology talk
It is a creation of Sonic trap
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
Representing two special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
It's frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek out
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
You can keep up with the show and all the people who make this show on Facebook
Twitter and Tumblr
We are very interesting in all of those places
But our home on the web is 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Michael
Cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get relief
Jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to
Clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth
Podcast
Dot-com