99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind
A different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
Podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the 1960s American cities were in crisis
Infrastructure
Crumbly traffic and pollution
Terrible
Cities particularly nice places to live
White people were able to flee Urban centers for the suburbs thanks to Federal help with mortgages and new freeway
That process would come to be known
As white flight
Meanwhile black populations in cities were dealing with housing discrimination and police brutality
Riots were breaking out in cities all over the country
And this awful time was referred to by Scholars as
The urban crisis
Methrone Katie McCoy
The Civil Rights Movement was happening in parallel
Go to the urban crisis but it wasn't really addressing the problems for black people
The overarching
Question
Can the cities be saved
How can we make
Urban life
Better for people
For all people
That's Rodger biles
Professor of history at Illinois
State
Varsity
In-N-Out
There were some folks
Situation in
Now we just
We just can't Salvage
What's here
The answer is
Starting Over Again
In other words urban planner thought maybe the problems facing cities were too big and too complicated to fix
And it's within this context
Of the urban crisis and the Civil Rights Movement
But the federal government
Would come to consider an idea like Soul City
Call for the nydia today a new city to be built in the country in North Carolina to be calls so
And to be populated mainly or entirely by Negroes he says would move there from the
This tape is from a 1969 NBC national news broadcast and this new city was
Being proposed by a civil rights leader named Floyd mckissick
Publishing on new city in North Carolina
We will create new jobs
A new career for black people
As a response to the urban crisis
The federal government had announced plans to provide financing to about a dozen brand-new town
Floyd mckissick wanted seoul City
To be one of those persons will be able to control their own destiny
We have the power to actually
Be a part of
Building a town come-ons it's a story of America
And to be a part of it
That's Jane Ballroom she was working as a secretary for mckissick and Harlem when he first started developing the ID
BF4 Soul city which would be a place built for and by black people Al and black oportun
Unity in rural North Carolina Jane says going to Seoul city was like being a pilgrim
You know we had our own Mayflower ship we came down the card you know it's the same thing
But really hard
The pilgrims did have it really hard
But this wouldn't be easy either
The government would eventually come to support this project but there would be politics and compromises and very strange bedfellows
And that was all before breaking ground on Soul City
When Floyd mckissick first pitch the idea of an all-black town
There was one question he got asked a lot
Visibility of a city like this
Form part of the trend toward separatism
This is a reporter at an early press conference
A lot of people were curious about
Was Soul City a departure from the idea that black people and white people should integrate together in society
Was this instead of black people starting their own thing
Separate from white people
And you can hear mckissick struggle to answer
It does the same thing as the Chinese have done in New York
Chinese area Chinatown
To understand all the ways that this question about separatism was relevant
You have to understand a bit about who Floyd mckissick was
This Photograph here with kill my
Barbara
I'm left here hand-in-hand with dr. King this is Floyd mckissick
II
He's a lawyer and a state senator and he's showing me pictures of his dad that are hanging in his office
Durham North Carolina
Freedom famous March on Washington Dr King gave his I had a dream speech
My father and daughter Kayla said that Mark that day
TDC years after that March Floyd mckissick senior would become the executive director of an organization called
LabCorp
That's the Congress on Racial equality
And he was part of the handful of
Really important civil rights leaders in the 60s
Along with people like
Dr. King Wilkinson NAACP
Whitney Young of the Urban League and Stokely Carmichael of
Snake
Snake being the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee
Because of these leaders and the members of their organization
Huge legal gains were made in civil rights and integration in the 50s and 60s
And then in 1966
There's this kind of pivotal moment
The movement
A civil rights activist named James Meredith is shot by a white gunman while leading a March in Mississippi
Stokely Carmichael and Floyd mckissick both go down in Mississippi to continue the March
Carmichael is arrested
And when he gets out of jail he makes a speech
Recess
Don't be afraid
Don't be ashamed we want Black Power
And we back the president with the federal government
That's all we've been doing back in Vegas
It's time we stand up and take over
On that day in 1966
The Black Power movement was born
And mckissick of core
And Carmichael is snake
Become two of the most vocal advocate
And this New Movement
What do we need black power when we need it now
Starting my dad will probably the two leaders in articulating what that meant
For Carmichael and mckissick Black Tower was a step further than civil rights and integration
It was essentially the idea that black people should control their own communities
Should have proportional representation in government
Again Stokely Carmichael in nineteen
We have to do whatever group in this country did we got to take over the community where we outnumber people so we can that.
The Weeknd
So we can have deeson Road
So we can have json
So we can have.
Injustice
Mckissack & Carmichael both very much believe
And the idea of black power
But in the late 60s
They began to diverge
About how to achieve it
Carmichael and many others in the Black Power movement thought that capitalism was inherently exploitative sis
That would always leave someone at the bottom
Another hand mckissick began to believe that
Capitalism was the answer
Mckissock
Actually Associates himself
Very important
Tendency
In Black Power
That's Sundiata charge you a professor of history and African-American studies at the University of Illinois
Urbana Champaign
And the Tendencies talking about is one toward black
Capitalism
What it means since we is that black people should
I want to control
Their own caplis Enterprises
And it comes to suggest that
Business ownership
Is the path
To equality freedom justice social transformation
Too long have we attempted to divide
Economics
From Politics the question that becomes Paramount in saying 1970s is strategy
General principle
That's Floyd mckissick an archival interview with political writer Walter DeVries
Cooley pragmatic you might lose everything that you gave at all those games that you've made
Mckissick believes that the time for idealism was over
What time for black people to claim their piece of the American Pie
Now what the hell are you
What are you going to do to become a full-fledged America
Actually Stokely Carmichael Africa
Leaving behind the black power movement in America African people
Revolutionary party
And Floyd mckissick did indeed stay in the states
He resign from core to start
For-profit company called mckissock Enterprises
And set his sights on building
Seoul City
The town he hoped would create as much Economic Opportunity for black Americans
Opossum
And we can bring together the private sector Industries
Educational resources to really build a town
The building of black tiles is an expression of a desire for autonomy
Mckissick Soul City wasn't a first for Blacktown building in the US
Quite a few towns were settled in the Great Plains between 1890 and 1910 by African-American sharecroppers
Shoppers Food in the south
But these weren't intentionally planned communities with government support
Amazingly in the late 1960s just as mckissick
Becomes convinced
Building a new town
The way to achieve Black Power
The government
Struggling to deal with the so-called Urban crisis
Announces their program to help Finance several new cities
Art of the urban growth and new communities Act
The legislation was passed
Which provided a process
Rebuilding me
That's historian Rodger biles again and he says these new cities would be meticulously planned in order to avoid
Play the problems of existing cities
Now we're going to bring all of the knowledge and all the insights
Urban planning
To doing it right this
The program would be managed by the US Department of Housing and Urban Development also known as HUD
Private developers could propose ideas to hide for Newtown
If they were approved
The New Towns could sell government back to bonds to investors on Wall Street
And as mckissick starts talking to people within Hood about this all-black Town idea they're like
Look there's no way we're going to approve something that's perceived as being separatist so
Mckissock dials back the language he was using to describe Seoul City
If you look at the things that he wrote and said before he fills out the actual applications
Right it's all about you know at least he's talking about building
Ideal black communities
After he's going through that process
In the literature is about building
Middle class
Communities that are open
Mckissick never envisioned a place where white people would be specifically
Excluded
He did a Maginot majority-black town with majority black leadership
He couldn't really talk about it like
Politics concessions must be made
I'm the next big one would come in the form of an important
Ally Brooke Jessica understood that to be approved to build one of these new cities
He leave friends in high places
He first pitches the idea to the current president
Lyndon Johnson
Andre Johnson teams interested
But then he decides not to run for re-election
And so in 1968 mckissick looks at the new field of presidential candidates and asks himself
Who is the most viable person to support
Seoul City
That's Devin Fergus he's a professor of African-American studies at Ohio State University
Varsity
Sport Richard Nixon
We've had enough of big promises a little action the time has come
We're honest
Government in the United States
Shockingly nixon-egli
Nixon believed in Black
Capitalism because Nixon believed in capitalism
He believed that when people own property and businesses
They had more of a stake in the car
Tree
Apart from that the Republican Party wanted to bring in Black
Vote the party early 60s and 70s was a was a much more
Big tents
Party the way to win in a way to create a door wood Republican Party
Is by casting Suarez
It's unclear how much Nixon support help makesex cause since the final decision was made by an agency with
Pain hard
Early 1970s
Soul city did become one of these 13 New Towns to receive government backing
And Floyd mckissick
Black power leaders
Became a Republican
And one of Nixon's most vocal black supporter
Of the 13 new cities
Seoul City
It was the only so-called
Free-standing New City
Meaning it wasn't being built right next to an already existing City that it can lean on for employment opportunities
An interest
It was being built on an old tobacco Plantation
About an hour away from Durham
Warren County North Carolina
We really were mine is cuz
Youku
Dunno but this
Facebook
It was a farm it was the green dude Plantation and
59 slaves there
That's Jane ball Grimm you heard her at the beginning of the story and Doris Terry Williams
I interviewed them together and Jane's house in Warren County in 1970 Jane packed up her family
And left her crowded housing project in New York for the wide-open farmlands of North Carolina
For me coming out in October
Randy was safe
When Jane got to Warren County there were just a
Handful of other new settlers living in trailers
These early planners had developed a 30-year strategy for soul City that laid out everything
Including their plan for 3 residential villages with mix
Income house
Clothing
Floyd mckissick II actually got a degree in urban planning to help his dad design Soul City
The design was inspired by the planned community of Columbia Maryland
What which was meant to have racial diversity and a small town feel
Soul City had a choir 3600 acres of land
They hope to have a population of about 2,000 people by 1978
By the end of 30 years they wanted to be up to around 40000 people
Jane says his early days at Seoul City just felt
Olaf
Potential
Growing up in America even New York
You know you have limitations because you were
Nick Rowe
You have to understand that
You can understand that you got my point
Then you here you get all of this
It's a miracle
David seems to me was just an amazing time to be
Young
Gifted and black
Floyd mckissick continue to support the Republican Party
We spend some time traveling and campaigning for Nixon when he ran for his second term
President
But most of mckissick time was spent at seoul City when he was here
She was
In the middle of the community
He was never a part of above
You know I didn't have his education to have a statue
But he was
He's my brother
Mckissick I decided on Warren County because he grown up in North Carolina
Estate
But also because black residents had left the south in droves during the Great Migration to cities of the North
He wanted to give Urban blacks up place in the South to return to if they want it
And give people who are already there
A reason to stay
In order to create jobs makesex Hope was to attract
Industry
She wanted a big company like
General Motors to come down and build a
But before that can happen Soul City needed basic infest
Like Water and Electric
Soul City built-in electrical grid and partnered with a few other counties to build a huge Regional water system from a
Nearby lake
Between 74 and 76
Vance's growth in the morning out here bulldozes outside I see the trucks coming in
Digging up the bread by putting down concrete
What is everyday you smelled it was so fantastic
How many C
They build a health clinic
Elko public swimming pool
Both of which brought people from all over the county the road
And they built a huge sick
60000 Square
But industrial building
Divided into separate sections with loading dock
Call the soltek1h
Soltech one completed in 1975 was designed by architect Harvey Gantt
And it was meant to be an incubator for new industry could get started and then moved bigger facilities
If need be but despite there being moments where I felt like real growth was happening
Soul city was not hitting his targets
By the mid-1970s the population was fewer than 200 people
Do small manufacturers set up in the soltec building
But no one that could offer a substantial number of jobs
Without enough residents it was hard to attract industry
It without the industry
It was hard to attract new residence
And then there was the problem of the name
And then the name
So
I meant they were people who said you should change the name
Have a project and though you know Floyd just refused
To do that
We have three Souls on my cell phone
It was a time to receive the name as being to Black
SolarCity was not
An all-black
In fact Gordon Carey who played an important role in the leadership was white
And some of the residents
But it could never really escape the
Perception
Being an all black
Town
And in some ways
It never really wanted to
How many people over the years have said oh yeah why is it all black
I'm not just after an old enough to say now
Why not it was a multiracial community always was
Still got it
After all the years we've been through what we've been through I look at my my history
Why not
Apart from Soul cities identity issues mckissick Sally in the White House President Nixon had resigned
I'm in disgrace and the economy was in a slump
Console City
17 negative articles over 8 days
Accusing seoul city of all kinds of Wrong Turn
Put a payoff cronyism nepotism in financial misappropriation
And then with this expose as rational
Tim North Carolina senator
Jesse Helms
Ready to battle it was Soul City
Here's Floyd mckissick II again
Helms
Launch attacks against Old City then
Literally brought development to home
During his long tenure as a Republican senator in North Carolina does he Holmes gain the reputation of being
Enough
Seoul secret racist
And he just like the soul city project from the beginning
Remember
Mckissock Ann Helms when the same political party
Stihl Helms was determined to destroy mckissic city
Senator Helms ordered
Fiscal audit on Soul City and HUD
Froze funding until we thought it was over
I never found any wrongdoing
They already gave us a clean bill of health
But it it damaged us
Significantly
In terms of
Public perception
It's true most of the charges leveled against Soul City by Helms or the Raleigh News & Observer or not substantial
Cheated during the audit
The bad press had further scared away industry and investor
Growth in Seoul City
It was at a standstill
And after a certain point again
Historian Rodger bio
Bankers in
And HUD
Simply withdrew to the position that
Well we're not going to advance you anymore loans were not going to invest in this anymore
Until we see some growth
Ann mckissick
Come back why
Roswell
The point where the growth isn't going to come unless we have more in fast
Despacito
10 years ago Floyd mckissick a civil rights activist set out to build a city for blacks
Mckissick said that in 30 years it would be home to 46000 people
But today Soul city is a broken dream in the government has begun foreclosure action to seize the property
It was forced into foreclosure
And most of the land at Seoul said it was sold off
But if the Thirteen towns develop just part of the urban growth and new communities Act
Solecity wasn't the only one.
Fail only one of them actually
Thrived and that was
A place called The Woodlands which is
Is just North
Buy Houston
The Woodlands was more generously subsidize from the beginning
And had the benefit of being on the outskirts of
Houston Texas during an oil boom
The other twelve towns all failed
Meaning
People might still live there
They did not continue on autonomously
Some became suburbs or neighborhoods a bigger town
Summer Maine unincorporated
Most of the failed towns
Cited a lack of investment
Is the primary reason for failure
Butthole City face
Additional
They were the only stand-alone town
So they were truly starting from nothing
Is that a strong dose of races
That might be the way you laugh when you ask
Actually want to
Scream
In any case it's not hard to imagine that racism played a role in Seoul City's demise
There was the investigation by Jesse Helms
The negative press
And the government play junior size was always looking over their shoulder
We will always under a special level of scrutiny
Any special level of review
To make the right turn at the yellow sign down there that was the Mets
Entrance to Soak City
I'm driving around with doors Terry Williams in what was once
Seoul City
It's now an unincorporated part of Warren County
This little strip right here was built as the beginning of
Kind of a commercial place there were several little businesses
Still feels like a really rural area
There's a pond and some Woods
Few clusters of houses
Some of the buildings are abandoned like the health clinic
And this building here on the aleph this was healthco healthco
When we get to a new building
Big one
One that was built after the soul city project
Failed
And this is the prison
In 1993
The Warren County Correctional Facility was built
It's a high-security prison designed to house about 800 inmates
And next door to the Press
In the building that used to be sold techone
Is now correction Enterprises
So take one remember was the building designed to incubate new industry in Seoul City
Add correction Enterprises
Prison laborers make janitorial products
Soap
About $3 a day
All of this on the former slave plantation that Floyd mckissick had to transform into a place for black
Black people to succeed
It's not hard to see the tragic irony in this
Back at Jane's house I asked her and Dora's how they felt
When the prison came
I lost my freaking mind on Beyonce shirt
Cereal industry
Instead of a prison
Black person
It happens all over
You know Road America particularly low-income and and and communities of color
But the promise that is going to bring jaw
It is an insult is an insult to Floyd memory is an insult to all the
The things that he was trying to do here
Floyd mckissick passed away in 1991
So he didn't live to see this final insult to his
City
Before he died he served as a judge in North Carolina and as a pastor
The First Baptist Church of
Seoul City
He found a way to continue
The struggle
But Soul city was a hard defeat
To get over
This was his architecture this was his
This was his Fountainhead this was his this was it it is and it is his legacy I mean can you imagine and I tell you I
I sort of resent him he was just a different man
You know something happened shaken away
He wouldn't tell you
But something happened shaken away
Itsfunneh
I never heard of mckissick
I heard of a lot of his contemporaries in civil rights Martin Luther King jr. of course Roy Wilkins and Whitney Young
I also heard of a lot of his peers in the Black Power movement
People like Stokely Carmichael
Assata Shakur
Huey Newton and Angela Davis
But not mckissick
These younger Scholars who do what called black power studies
They tended to study the right about the organizations and individuals
Home AC has her Roy
That's Professor Sundiata judge you again
Supports
Richard M Nixon
In Georgia Republican Party
Mckissock isn't seen as heroic
But that doesn't mean he's not important
He still a less appealing character to Scholars who are interested in the more radical ideas generally associate
With black power
So we get written out of the history
Mckissock
Is fairly well known and loved in North
Carolina
Pandora says Soul city has had far-reaching impact
State
Because when you think about the people who came
Through South
Who gone on to do
Just amazing thing I was talking to abdulrashid
The other day
Doris and Jane going to list several people who are influence
Batman kissing
Second Sole City
And went on to start social programs in the area or even be elected to public office
Eva Clayton
All of the folks
Can people still live on the land that was Soul City
Making use of the water and electrical systems that were built as part of the project
Driving on those roads
Living in those houses
Jane Ballroom still owns her home and soul City
MacKenzie's dream was
You know ownership of oneself and pride in oneself
To me I realize that
In my arms in my little capacity
And if Scholars are riding mckissic out of
History because they don't see him as a hero
Well they're certainly not going to convince
Doris Terry Williams
Are Jane ball groom
Mmm walking around with that hat on we had this
Cowboy hat
Beautiful hat
He was just
Kane Brown
You're Cana, some people really really cared about
People he was he was just
He wasn't perfect
But he was magnificent
99% invisible West producer Suite by Katie mingle with Delaney Hall
Usef Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Megan Reed
The archival tape you heard of Floyd mckissick came from the southern oral history program collection at the University of North Carolina
Chapel Hill
We are product of 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced out of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors
In beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking
To me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remedy for all hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episode
Those from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info / podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
Do you find this show and like the show on Facebook and follow us all on Twitter and Instagram that the best way to explore the 99 verse
% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world
Spend as much time as possible on 99 pi
. org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about
The body gym
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
My car
Do your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get real
Delete Jack'd play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
Actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com