99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 2014 President Obama expanded the Pacific remote Islands Marine National Monument
Making it the largest Marine Preserve in the world at the time
Pacific remote Islands Marine preserve is farther from Human settlement than any other us
The president expansion of the reserve today will close 400,000 square miles
Star Ocean 2 commercial fishing
Underwater mine and you look in the map
Preserve
Really is nowhere near the United
It's thousands of miles from the US mainland
That's reporter Emmett Fitzgerald
It's not even that close to Hawaii
It's somehow President Obama was able to protect this piece of
In the name of the United States
And to understand how the United States has jurisdiction over these Waters in the middle of the
We got to go all the way back to the 19th century
When for a brief period
US Sailors scoured the ocean
Looking for Rocky island
Covered
Iguana
With a lot of people think I was.
Just bat poop
I think most people think of guano is bad poop but it but in this case we're talking about
Birds and seabirds
Sosie bird poop
That's Paul Sutter
A professor of history at the University of Colorado at Boulder
In the mid 1800
It's the United States became obsessed with a quest
Define incel guano
To use as fertilizer
Terron Farms
People believed it would revolutionize farming
And it did
At least for a little while
But the Quest for bird poop ultimately had even bigger ramifications
The use of sea bird poop as fertilizer starts in South America
Originates
I will deposit off
The coast
I approve
Southwest Peru and prickly three
Islands are called a chinchilla
Islands
Potential Island on the middle of a nutrient-rich current with tons of Plankton and massive schools of fish
And there are seabirds that live on the
Getting fat off all these fish
They're gorging themselves
Financial View
And they're defecating all over these islands across
Hundreds if not thousands of years
And it almost never rained on the tenth Island
So over time
Keeps piling up
And as a result these deposits build up
100 feet deep
In places
Exercise with 10-story building
Of poop
For centuries
Is the quechua people
Going through
Wood mine is guano Mountain
And spread the bird poop out on their feet
And it worked they were real a successful farmer
And the Spanish who colonized the region begin
Noticing this
And and and really dabbled in it
But scientist in Europe didn't really get interested in guano
Until the same depression naturalist Alexander Von Humboldt
Visited the Peruvian
Coast in 1800s
He's all laborers unloading ships full of bird poop
And you took a sample and brought it back with him to Europe
In the early 19th century a German chemist named Justus Von liebig began arguing that soil fertility basically
Came down to just a few critical nutrient
Nitrogen
Bosporus
And potassium
And that
Soil fertility can be
I restored or maintained
By adding those nutrients
Those
Chemical or mineral nutrient
To the soil
Peruvian guano had really high concentrations of all three of these new
Especially night
It was the agricultural analog to discover
Ringgold
Peruvians began to mine guano on a commercial scale and they struck deals with British merchants to sell Peruvian guano
Go back in Europe
And they set up shop on the chincha islands in and they initially rely on
On local
Semi coerced labor but eventually they
Get into importing
Chinese labor
This Is Us
Form of of bonded contract labor so they're also
Paid very little
It's a very abusive labor system
They are
Mislead in terms of
The terms of the Steal
The miners lived on the island
Intense and Bamboo Shack
And I have to wait at the guano deposits with shovel
Send pickaxe
Practice 17 hours a day
They're chipping away at the Squanto they're they're sending it down giant shoots
Often right into the holds of ships
This is incredibly accurate
Caustic
Stop
It gets in their lungs
It's really debilitating
Mattoon Farmers all across Europe were using Peruvian guano on their fields
Two of the companies profiting the most office New
Trade war w j Myers from Liverpool
And Gibson
London the result of slogan that said the house of Gibbs
Made their dibs selling the turds of foreign Birds
Word of the fertilizing power of seabird poop eventually reaches the United States
Where commercial farming
And particularly on slave plantations in the south
Head strip the soil of a lot of its neutral
Is Dorothy Farmers would plant cover crops
Practice crop rotation or raise cattle for manure production in order to keep their soil healthy
Or they would just perform a field until they had exhausted its nutrients and then move on to a new piece of land
But British merchants began advertising a new product
It would help American farmers stay in one place
And maximize their yields
Peruvian guano
Planters begin to experiment with it as a way of increasing
Their yields and in some cases have
Really good results
Soon agricultural Publications in the US
Icewarp raising guano
Magical properties
And Farmers throughout the country began using it
How to fertilize their fields
By the late 1840s the United States was in the grips of what historians have called
Guano Mania
Importing tens of thousands of tons of bird poop every year
The US was birdshit
Crazy
But because British firms had a monopoly over the Peruvian guano trade
Guano was expensive
Farmers began to petition Washington to help them get cheap Guana
At one point of the president of the United States Millard Fillmore
Ennis 1850 annual dress
Makes guano security
A kind of
Important point
Nevada trash
Peruvian guano has become so desirable in Article 2
The agricultural interest of the United
States that it is the duty of the governor
To employee Albany
Is properly in it
Power for the purpose of causing that article to be imported into the country at our
Reasonable price
But
Fillmore was mostly talk
Iguana prices continued
Just sore
And so us business
Start to take matters into their own
The beginning going out looking for other islands with new sources of guano
Empties bird poop Prospectors come across an uninhabited island in the Caribbean
Call Abba
In 1854 a group of Americans
Landed there
What to Mine
The guano
And attempted to claim the island
That's Christina Duffy ponsa
And I'm a law professor at
Columbia
Influenza says that us guano mining on all that set off a minor diplomatic crisis
Venezuela felt that the island belong to them
And they ended up sending a warship
The kick the guano company off the island
But when they got home the guano Prospectors asked Congress
To pass legislation
They would protect them
If they try to claim New Island
So US citizens could feel like they had the backing of the US government if they encounter a controversy
Like military.
Meaning
You guys can go out
Take these off
And if anyone shows up with warships
Will bring ours to
And in the debate over this life
Politicians argued about guano prices and other details
But there were also some Senators who expressed a larger concern
They worried that by taking over islands for the purposes of mining guano
The United States could be perceived as having Imperial aspirations
Secretly trying to set up
Colonies and engage in territorial
Expansion
By claiming Islands
In the Atlantic and the Pacific and all over the world and a little context
Is important here
This is all happening
Against the backdrop of European Colonial
Great Britain is about to establish its colonial government in India
And various European countries will soon colonize nearly all of Africa
The United States had taken over much of North America and violently stole territory from indigenous people
But political leaders at the time didn't think of this as colonialism because the US always Incorporated new territory
Into the country
Rather than maintaining colony
The US also prided itself
On being a nation born out of a revolution against
Imperial power
So the United States
Did that and has always conceived
Of itself as
An Anti-Imperialist
Country
And distinguished itself
From European powers who in this. In the 19th century were acquiring territories
All over the globe
And so even though in the case of the guano Islands they're talking about cleaning uninhabited rocks
Some Senators think that this looks a little too close to colonialism
Converse
So they work on developing language that will mitigate any fears
List of the US
Is trying to set up overseas colonies
So
Eventually
As the Senate goes to a series of drafts
The way that the Islanders
Describe is not as part of the territory of the United States or subject to the sovereignty of the United States those words drop
About they are described as appertaining
To the United
It states as in
A sort of fancy old fashioned way of saying
Belonging to
Appertaining
I think about that word was that at the time no one really knew what it meant from a legal perspective
But it was softer than saying we own this
The towers
The Senators also included in abandoned
Which said that the United States could relinquish possession over the islands once the guano had been exhausted
And with all these caveats in place
Congress passed
The guano Islands
And at that point
American citizens
Start cleaning
Islands
All over the place is really companies that want a Mindless guano start sending people out and telling them to claim these islands
In total us companies claimed over 70 Island
Throughout the Pacific
And the Caribbean
Indigenous Polynesians and Hawaiians mine guano for us companies
It's on far-flung Pacific Islands
And after the Civil War
Guangzhou companies recruited
Free black men
Tomine guano on Caribbean
Like in Peru
Us guano mining was
Brutal
And workers were off
Coerced
Horribly
Automania didn't last all that long in the end
By the 18
70s
The bass guano deposits on the island
Almost gone
Many of the islands the United States took didn't turn out to have very good Guana
And synthetic fertilizer
Just around the corner
And while the history of the guano trade isn't often talked about
It had lasting impacts that are still incredibly relevant to this day
The guano trade introduced the idea that soil fertility could be bought and sold
Set of carefully attending to their soil on the farm
Farmers can just buy this one supplement and sprinkling on their field
This paved the way for the fertilizer fueled industrial agriculture that we see today
And the guano Islands Act
Set a precedent
That would help and Mabel future Act
Some American imperialism
On islands that were very much in half
Around the turn of the twentieth century the United States goes to war with Spain over the
Occupation of Cuba
Ban the US win
So after the Spanish American War what happens is the United States
Cakes
Puerto Rico
And the Philippines
And Guam as
Basically part of its War booty for defeating
Spain in
Cuba interview clear these territories were taken as Spoils of War not
As part of the guano Islands Act
But when the US annexed
Is Island territories in 1898
It sets off a huge debate about what to do next
You could make these places in the states
But the white political establishment
Wasn't too excited about absorbing a bunch of islands full of people of color
It's about race
More than anything else white Americans
Want the nation to be a white Nation
So this is the same. Of time
In which American start tightening their immigration laws
But politicians were reluctant to give up territory with real strategic value
In 1901 this question
About the status of Puerto Rico and the Philippines
Makes its way to the Sea
Supreme Court
In a case involving Goods that are shipped
From Puerto Rico to the United
The dispute arises around a shipment of oranges from Puerto Rico to New York
When the shipment arrives in New York the Customs collector and poses
Duties on the oranges as if they were coming from a foreign country
And the
A company shipping them challenges the duties
Saying
Puerto Rico is part of the United States
The Constitution says that you can impose duties on any Goods be
Ship within the country
This case
Taxi Norwich
Decide this case
The court would need to answer a bigger question
What relationship do these islands have
To the United States
In the end the Court ruled that imposing a duty is okay
Because these new places Puerto Rico Guam the Philippines
Or not
Fully a part of the United States
But in their decision
The justices make clear that they aren't foreign either
The famous phrase from these cases is that there
Foreign
To the United States
In a domestic sense
It's a it's an odd phrase
At the time no one really knows what it means it basically creates a limbo and in between status
Some of the justices
When did to the guano Islands
As a justification for creating this
In-between status
And went on to say that these new territories were
Fortunate
Appurtenant
As in
A burkini
And there's that word that word appertaining
From the guano Islands
When even then and after then
Still lawyers trying to understand what that word means
Can't quite make sense
They're never quite sure what you know all we know is this is the way of kind of holding a place at arm's length while still controlling it
It's impossible to know whether this case would have been
Differently if
If the US had never gone looking for guano
But the guano Islands setopress
And
That gives
La Corte familiar and legitimate
Mode of reasoning
In creating a status that was really an invention
A territory that belong to the United States
Wasn't a state
And some of these territories still have this limbo status
Puerto Rico
Still has the status of a foreign
In a domestic sense territory of the United States
And that's also the case
Before other territories the US Virgin Islands
The Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands
Guam and American Samoa all these places are in a form of limbo
In the United States ambivalent relationship with extraterritorial Island all started with the guano Islands Act
A legal framework that allowed the US to take control over a place without making it fully a part of the country
Puerto Rico isn't a state
Nor is it an independent nation
Puerto Ricans are US citizens
But they can't vote in US presidential elections
And Professor poncy who is from Puerto Rico says that being stuck in this colonial limbo Apple
Pertaining but not belonging to the United States
Has stalled progress on the island
For over a hundred years
Puerto Ricans have spent a lot of time and political energy trying to decide whether to pursue
Statehood or Independence
And it is done a great deal of harm in Puerto Rico
Because it distorts politics
When you're when you're arguing about questions is foundational
As should we be a state or not
It really Hans Puerto Rico's political life
The guano Islands Act
Is still law
In fact in the 1990s a man from California named Bill Warren tried to claim the abandoned island of navassa
As his own private guano
EBay
But the US still holds claim over a few of the old guano Island
Pacific
Some of these islands ended up having some kind of strategic value was Landing strips and they had other kinds of military uses
Amelia Earhart was planning to land on a guano Island
To refuel
When her plane went down
In the Pacific
And President Obama used guano Island possession
Expand one of the largest Marine
In the world
The guano islands in the Pacific that the u.s. still controls are now called the United States minor outlying Islands
They don't have any permanent rest
A few military officials and scientists live there throughout the year
These little rocky Island
What's our ongoing projections of the American Empire
In a reminder about the time
Guano Mania
Gripped the world
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Emmett Fitzgerald with Sharif Youssef Katie mingle Coast at Avery trufelman saying
Greenspan Delaney Hall Terry Meza and me Roman more
Special thanks to Professor Dan Margulies of Virginia Wesleyan College in our pal okay akumi was a new album
Previously unreleased tracks it
Bandcamp
Really enjoying it a whole lot right now
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can quit me at Roman Mars and the show at
99pi org
Run Instagram and Tumblr to
If you want to be super interesting at your holiday party I recommend you spend some time reading a few stories
At 9 p.m.
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com