99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
You can picture there
Line under stomach in the dirt
Arcing her camera up towards the building
Tilting the frames
Stark rectilinear building transforms into a striking asymmetric
Composition
You can see her taking her time
This photo
Adjusting the focus
Exposure
She releases the shutter
Impressing the negative image onto a glass plate
90 years later this Photograph by Lucia moholy
Is one of the most famous images of the German article known as the Bauhaus
Meaning the word
Build in German
And house meaning
Mediocre German speakers Sam Greenspan
The Bell House was founded by architect Walter gropius in 1990
The school start diffuse art with industrialization
Do use new ideals of modernism
To create beautiful
Functional things
Which could be mass-produced
The betterment of society
In the beginning of the Bauhaus Rose From the Ashes of World War 1 end
There was a
Very hopeful
Bear utopian. Of
Craftsman and artist all creating together
Teach architectural design history at
At The courtauld Institute
Art in London
But I'm America
The Bauhaus was a magnet for European designers Architects and artists of all kinds in the early 20th century
Many of whom would go on to achieve International acclaim
The photographer Lucia moholy did not become one of those famous
She joined about house in 1923 but not as a teacher or as a student
Her husband Laszlo moholy-nagy
I've been hired on to the faculty of the Bauhaus
And so Lucia said off of them
To become part of this new
Exciting place they come to the bath
Lucio like the wives of the other about house faculty did what was expected of her
Which was to do some kind of work that would help fulfill the mission of the sea
Unpaid of course
Lucia had some training in photography
She had the darkroom skills in
Should really
Excellent technical skills of the. Kind of document
She made portraits of the
People their of the things that they made
End of the architecture of the school itself
Walter gropius design school with campus in Dessau
And those buildings became a major theme of Lucy is work
Cheap photography workshops
The dormitories the Masters houses
She said about showing the spaces where these new methods and philosophies of design we're being met
You can see the way in which this year's photographs of Walter gropius is architecture
Express the same ideas that he wanted to express in the Arctic
Textured self
And this is not by chance
Lucy is photography like gropius is architecture
Is all about Clarity and simplicity of form
It is utilitarian
Document in the world as it is
And it's all so beautiful
Revelling
Can clean lights in stark contrast
Only what's needed and nothing more
From the dark room in her and Lazlo's home on the Bauhaus campus Lucia Master collection of
Fibrous
100 photographs
And she couldn't have known them the impact
These images
Would have on the built world
Or on her own life
The Bauhaus aspired to lift Society up out of the wreckage of World War 1
And into a new world of rationalism
UT
Good art
And good design
To bring its braniff utopianism
Into the World At Large
But for all their efforts the world did not become more Utopia
The national socialist government put the bath under increasing pressure in 1933 it was closed down
I'm by the Nazis
Many members of the Bauhaus for force
To flee immediately because they were
Jewish
Or because they were involved
In very last
Radical politics
Text and they had to go
Amidst all the turmoil of the Nazis rise
The power Lazlo and Lucia had separated
Lucia started dating
The Communist Party member
Parliament
One day in 1933 he was arrested in Lucy's apartment While She Was Out
Sochi
Was not able to return to her apartment because she had
Interfere
That she was arrested immediately
T2
Somebody told her don't get back to your apartment
This is Ross socks
He teaches at the University of Czar broken in Germany
And he knew Lucia moholy she had to emigrate immediately so what you did was free to her check
Text Emily
So she went to Prague first
And then she went to Paris
Via
Austria
Via Switzerland eventually Landing in London in 1933
Lucia had left behind nearly everything she owned including the glass negatives of the Bauhaus
As she fled the country for an uncertain fate of broad
Lucy left the legacy of the Bauhaus to an uncertain fate
At home
Lucia weathered out the war in London
She arrived in the city
Basically nothing
And it wouldn't lost everything again when her apartment was bombed by German war planes
But even in all the chaos of War
Lucia found ways to work
She wrote a book about the history of photography
100 Years of photography
Ghost published by penguin United 39
And at the same time she was
Baidu
Successful
Portrait photographer for the high society
And for the most part she put the Bauhaus
Behind her
Set
To me that she didn't know that the bowels was more than an episode in her life
She stopped thinking about it
At least until after the war
I supposed it in Nadi 46th Street received amoma catalog of 90
That must have been the first
Hidden Falls
Back in 1938 completely unbeknownst to Lucia
Walter gropius had work with the Museum of Modern Art in New York MoMA
To put together an exhibition on the Bauhaus
And because the war was still going on at the time
Moma hadn't been able to get many of the Bauhaus as objects
Out of Germany
And so the exhibition was comprised mostly of photographs
Images of the products they design
The people who made them and the buildings were they worked and lived
Images of the dormitories
The Master's house
The workshop
Photos that use interesting angles to transform Stark rectilinear structures
Do striking asymmetric
Composition
Those photographs
Published in the museum catalog
The book that accompany the exhibition
She whips
Seen her own photograph
But not her name
The 1938
Catalog and other catalogs
And books coming out from the US do not credit
Again historian Robin Schulz
She also begins
See
New articles that mention the Bauhaus that are
Do streams good reproductions ever photograph
Following World War II there was a surge of interest in the Bauhaus
All of their ideas about rationalism and modernism had caught on among both were Architects and designers
More and more books
Articles about the Bauhaus we're getting published and Lucy is photographs kept getting circulated
And the quality seem to be better than you'd expect from duplications of old prints
Lucia begins to think that
Just maybe
Recollection of 5 by 7 in
Glass negatives
Might have made it through the war after all
And she begins to think
What are negative might have
Somehow
Survived
So she starts to try to get
Are negatives back
Lucy's first move is to write to her ex-husband Lazlo
Woodson's emigrated To America with his second wife sibel
Lucia asked
If he had any clues about where the negatives she had left behind
Might have ended up
Sibel couser that they in fact left
These cumbersome negatives and gropius house
Ingrid Pierce
Just basement
Gropius
Completely unbeknownst Lucia
Actually taking her negatives with him to the US
We need emigrated more than a decade earlier
Likely because he had friends who were higher up
UPS in the Nazi party
And so when gropius left room
He didn't have to flee in a hurry
He was able to carefully pack up his belongings
Lucy is heavy fragile glass negatives
Among them
And bring them with him
The harbor
Where he recently got a job
Lucia right to gropius
These negatives
Irreplaceable
Commence
Be extreme
Only useful
Now or
Walter gropius right back
Long years ago in
You gave all these naked
These photographs are extreme
So I hope
Deprive me
Lucia response to gropius same basically
I never gave you my negative
Shirley
You did not expect me
To delay my departure
Order to draw up
Formal con
Stipulating
No formal agreement
Could have carried more weight
Friendship
It is this friendship I have
Always relied
And which also is
I am now in Boca
But when invoking friendship didn't work
Lucia hired a lawyer
Orochi gropius
Did his holding onto Lucy is negative
Was like a firefighter saving a house and then claiming ownership of all the stuff inside
But still gropius was not giving them back
You stood never anything for anybody
Except
He didn't have her you wrote some very kind letters set yes yes
We have to think about it we have to think about it we have to think about it and he did not
This whole argument raises the question of who owns the image of a building
Intellectual property law on photography has evolved the years
And it still varies by country
But generally
If you take a picture of a two-dimensional thing like a painting
Doesn't show any Artistry on your part
And therefore you have no claim to the ownership of that image
But if you take a picture of a three dimensional thing
Like a building
You're making decisions about
Position angle lighting
Framing
You're not just reproducing with quote-unquote really there
You're making something entirely new
And so generally
Copyright on those images
That is not just the negatives but also the prince that broke his would have been making from
Legally
That all belong
In any case
Gropius kept making prints
Kept publishing them
Kept circulating her representation
Kept telling the story of the Bell House
Through lucias photography
Architecture is
In many ways understood and consumed through photography
We don't get to simos
What's the world's iconic
Weezy pic
And this turned out to be especially true of the Bauhaus
Because after the start of the Cold War the West
Access to the Bauhaus
Campus was cut off by the Iron Curtain
Even in East Germany it was incredibly difficult to photograph
These buildings yes because there was no possibility of visiting them properly and there was apps
Absolutely no chance of taking a photograph with
I've been there
For the first time in my life
The 1970s
I went to desl on whenever
Took off my camera somebody came up and said no you can't photograph here because
The Bauhaus building
Set that time was surrounded by Soviet
Military building
Photography was banned at the Bauhaus campus and Dessau
From 1950 until 1980
And then later after reunification
The buildings were altered
Slightly
I'm so to this day
Scholars like Robin Schulz and Fry
Say that Lucy is photographs are the best representation we have of the Bell House
In a way it's like those photos
AR
About house
And so even the slides that I myself was
Thought about the Bob house
In the 19
Mid 1990s
Many of them are still these
Black and white images because they are such good
Quality after years of legal disputes
Lucia moholy finally succeeded in getting nearly 300 of her negative
But it was
Innocence too late
For her and so
I think that part of
This story is unfortunate
Lucia moholy died in 1989
Turn negatives went to the Bauhaus archive in Berlin
It is from Lucy has photos that Architects and designers Drew inspiration to rebuild the postwar world
People who rebuilt Europe Drew on the ideas
Of the Bauhaus
They look to its modern rectilinear asymmetric architect
As a counter
To the building
What's the Nazis
Fascism head use this kind of new class
Aesthetic
Court houses that were built in the postwar period In America post office
These buildings were all built in the modern style
And this is where
The modern-style does finally take off
Our modern world owes a debt to the Bauhaus
And the house was it that to Lucia moholy
Whether anyone knows her name or not
But we should know it
Today
About 90 Prince of Lucia moholy Bauhaus
Rafi are housed at the busch-reisinger museum at Harvard
They were donated by Walter gropius
And are considered part of his art
The museum has overtime actually been going through this archive
And crediting Lucia on photos known to be hers
Like the photo that Lucy I took lying on the ground
Pointing her camera up towards the Bauhaus building in Dessau
So we're looking at a photo from around 1920
6 gelatin silver print
It's a kind of worms I've you so were
I looking up
At this glass curtain wall
And we're looking into the workshops of the Bauhaus
Rob wiesenberger is a fellow at Harvard
Who works on the Bauhaus collection
The backside of the photo
Says in German in purple ink
Photo Lucia moholy that's how Luna allowed
Play production football
Without permission reproduction is for voting is not allowed
Are not permitted
This was the intellectual property of
Of Lucia Molly
99percentinvisible was produces week by Sam Greenspan
Reviews of kitty mango court cost at Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Sarah bory at the University of Edinboro whose research on Lucia moholy cut
Started on the story
Thanks also to Jeffrey saletnik Gloria Ferris 3B Quadrophenia
Xi'an tushy
And Wooten was the voice of Lucia moholy and Sharif Youssef played Walter gropius
We are project on 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio Row in beautiful downtown
Oakland Calif
Umbrella Omar says if there's a revolving door and you use the one next to it isn't evolving then you're a monster
Is there so efficient ingrate
Can I ask you a question just for a while
Might just go to a podcast
If you would have me I would love to
Said to get over there I have a lot of good ideas for like
Not like this show but like
Yashow like
SmartStyle
United mean like
Finger
Not like
Eye cancer
Not like this show
But like
Smart
Mike
Erudite podcasting
That's how I feel like my true calling and where I really feel like my light under a bushel wasn't
Weird backdoor pilot
Right stuff with Justin and Robin Wright now and
Give us a topic you might discuss on smart
Edmond okay
So I'll kind of leave black or his partner
You could try later but I'm just going to leave blank for like the Roman Roman Mars I'm going to steal your brother.
So it'll go something like an erudite, smart podcast
Like yeah yeah like a podcast where you know the host knows the word are you
Yeah yeah yeah
Marketplace
Hello everybody Welcome to Smart stuff
I am your host
Justin McElroy
I joined it's always stay by Roman Mars what smart thing we discussing today
Well this week I was excited to learn why there are so many time races in swimming so in the real games
Last week there were three second place finishers at the exact same time in the men's 100-meter butterfly
The most Olympic events are measured in thousands of a second
3 units by the Dozen
But swimming is only measured in the hundredths of a
And the reason is because of the pool itself it's virtually impossible to construct a swimming pool with lanes that are eggs
Exactly equal International Swimming regulations allow for a variability
About to 3 centimeters in length
Breeze Lane
This is enough of a difference if you can't guarantee that a swimmer is thousands of a second
Or that the lane is
Just like a centimeter short so they drop that third digit to the right of the decimal point in only measure
In the hundredths of a second only measure in hundredths of a second
Leavenworth High races
LML
Well folks that's all we have time for a smart stuff today
If someone can get Roman Mars
Cut out this bit of the podcast and actually try and fill in the blanks there that would be stellar
My brother my brother and me between the McElroy Brothers coming hard on the maximum fun Network
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you a long to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Putting cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
Define the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com