99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers
Stop auto insurance
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Weather.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right
Nighttime and connecting with us
That audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions
I love you too
Target your customers were their engaging every day when they're ready to make
Make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn
You have the opportunity to build long-term relationship
Sex with your customer
Those relationships often turn into
High quality leads
Check traffic
And higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help
Target your customers
Decision
Down to the job title company name
And Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a mess
What they care about
Which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Open LinkedIn.
Dot-com invisible
A free $100
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
New Yorkers are known to disagree about a lot of things
Who's got the best pizza what's the fastest subway route Yankees or Mets but
I would bet that if you pulled every New Yorker
All 8500000 of them
They would agree on one thing
Temptations suck
That's a never been our friend and reporter in New York who also hates Penn Station
There is nothing joyful about Penn Station
It's windowless
Airless
Crowded
650000 people have to suffer through it on their daily commute
Stuck more traffic than the Region's three airports combined
Luckily though
I'm not one of them
Where in Penn Station now
We tied along with our unlucky friend Jonathan menjivar he's a producer for This American Life and commutes from his home
In Jersey to Penn Station
His experience of Penn Station is like
Being a Black Friday sale at Walmart
Everyday
Always
I'm like the whole time people are pushing you squeezing through a tiny Stairway to get down to the tracks
Play sandwich
People are like actually touching your ass and you're not supposed to say anything about it
The air is off a hot stuffy
It feels like
Whatever Wizard of Oz is behind Lake that they are just watching in their little Tower and watching like
I'll look at them crush each other look at them on to eat each other
It's it's awful
It's off
And it's my best way to get home everyday
Poor guy
And you can also see some Penn Station hate in popular culture about New York
Lichenous episode of Broad City
Where one character Abby
Get dumped
Because her boyfriend
Would rather end a relationship
Then take a train out of Penn Station
Penn Station
Mercante
It's disgusting
It's kind of a dealbreaker for me
But here's the worst thing about Penn Station
This drab
Low ceiling
Uninspiring unexceptional building
Was once the opposite of all of those things
That
Space building itself was the
The fourth largest building in the world
That's Jill Jones describing the original Penn Station
Shirt a great book about it
Called conquering Gotham
The original Penn Station in New York City opened in 1910
It was Majestic
Imagine the Parthenon but for trains
The facade was a line of massive Doric columns
You walk through them descend down the grand staircase and into a waiting room design to remind you or
Roman Temple
Woody's very high ceiling
And very
Spectacular light
Coming through
That ushered you into all of these
Staircases that took you down into the
The train track
And the guy behind all of this was Alexander Cassatt
The Head of Pennsylvania Railroad
With the original Penn Station
Cuz I was fixing a problem that had planned to New York for years it was a complete pain in the ass to get from New Jersey
Jersey to Manhattan
People commuting from Jersey had to schlep Across the Hudson River on a slow Ferry
Train tunnel to run under the Hudson River it was considered one of the greatest engineering feats
Never I know we say that all the time but we really mean it this time Penn Station terminal
The crown his Monumental achievement
The architecture celebrate about the past and the future
It was a combination of this
Very ancient
Grandeur and
This extremely industrialized
Form of transportation
Really powerful
Pranks
Newspapers called Penn Station the 8th Wonder of the world people call a lot of things the 8th Wonder of the world
Everyone loved it
Everyone that is except for one other railroad family that owned a little station right across town
This then made
The existing
Grand Central Station
Which was
Owned
By the Vanderbilt family look really shabby
The time when the original Penn Station was built
Grand Central Station was not anywhere near as Grand as it is now
But the Vanderbilts just couldn't be outdone by the
Other train station clearly how embarrassing Grand Central needed a little touch up
The Vanderbilts decided to tear it down and build a newer shinier
Grandeur Grand Central Station
The one we know today
So there was this very early connection between the two
So Penn Station and Grand Central
Started out as enemies
But as the years passed they were like the last two drunks at the party trying to keep the night from coming to an end
Country was in a very different sort of mindset that
Who was good and flying was good and cars were good and transfer bad
Penn Station was only 40 years old at this point but already it's days were numbered
Passenger trains just weren't as popular anymore
Pennsylvania Railroad was just bleeding money
The company couldn't afford the upkeep
Penn Station's grandeur
Everything that I've been glorious about it really
I got sort of covered with Grime and it was dirty and they didn't fix a broken windows in there all these
Pigeons flying around it's really hard to wash pigeon poop off of Forestry Arch glass ceiling
So
People did not
Feel that this was this
Glorious place
They felt it was really crummy a lot of people Penn Station had become a money-sucking albatross of a stage
They also set of precious Midtown Manhattan real estate
Remember this is New York City
Real estate in New York is in the airspace
Pennsylvania Railroad Executives knew that they can make tons of money
If they could rent out the space above the station to a big tall building
There were proposals to build a parking garage Amphitheater
40 story office tower
But the one that one out was the futuristic sports and entertainment Palace known as Madison Square Garden
The deal that Pennsylvania Railroad cut with a developer Irving Felts
What's the keep the tracks below Penn Station and sell the rights to the airspace on top
And blow up
Penn Station in the process
Here's what I wish we could say that the whole city banded together to save the station
But actually no one really cared except for a small group of activists architects
The action group for better architecture in New York
Agony
The terrible acronym
But definitely a cause I can support
Peter Sampson was one of those architects
I went over to his house on the upper west side
Let me look through old photographs from the only march to save Penn Station
Is me
Oh I think this was my sign
Right here that said
Don't sell LCD short
The date was August 2nd
There were 200 Rowdy architects
We would have to wear
Respectable clothing
Cuz otherwise they wouldn't take us seriously
Just kidding about the Rowdy part these were Architects the men wear suits the women wear white gloves and pearls
Weed sort of pride ourselves on
I'm doing better lettering than the next sign they marched up and down 7th Avenue shouting powerstone tomorrow
Save Our Heritage things like that is what we would say
Keep in mind
We know none of us were ever on a picket line
You don't say still
The protest made the front page of the New York Times
Architects fight Penn Station plan
But it was too late
September 28th
At 9 a.m.
Jackhammers Turin to Penn Station granite slabs
The demolition took a long time
About three years
Edward was like a great animal because
Are you saw the black on the outside
And then you saw the inside which was all this beautiful pink
So it was like the flesh
What's open now
With a knife
And after three years most of the original Penn station remains
Dark column the granite and travertine details
All of that
I've been dumped into a New Jersey swamp
And of course they gave us a new Penn Station
One that was summarily hated by everyone
1968 architectural historian Vincent Scully famously remark that whereas before
One entered the city like a god
1 skulls in now
Like a rat
How did the destruction of Penn Station mayor Robert Wagner created the first landmarks preservation Commission
The group helped pass the city's first-ever landmarks law
Submit something as drastic as the destruction of Penn Station could never happen again
But the landmark laws were flawed it was a joke
New Yorkers are so blunt
That's Roberta Gratz
She wrote award-winning stories about the problems with the cities Landmark laws for the New York Post in the 1970s
For those of you who are too young to know that the New York Post used to be a really good newspaper
There are number of problems with the landmark laws
The biggest one though was that the landmarks commission didn't mean all that much
Playmat for 6 months
Every three years if you missed your window to get your favorite New York City building landmark
Tough luck and in the meantime the bulldozer operated at will has a lot of
Even after the landmark laws were passed
Like the singer building which was once the tallest building in the world
In the old Metropolitan Opera House
And the Astor Hotel
And then in 1968
Penn Station's old rival Grand Central Station
Was poised to be yet another pile of rubble
Beer in the casino like places of the terminal itself Robin heart of a nation's recovery
You have a right I love Grand Central Station
Hands down it is my favorite place in the city
Welcome to Grand Central terminal
Kent Barwick is just as excited as I am to be here
He's been involved in Saving New York City's historic buildings for decades
We're standing under Grand Central beautiful vaulted green ceiling which is decorated with constellations
I just love looking up at it
You and every other person
It's rare to communicate without
Finding somebody
Take me to picture or
Look this one races
Grand Central feels like a throwback
I feel like the old Penn Station must have been like just like the original Penn Station
Grand Central was a hard building to keep clean
Kent bar with points to a small patch of black
Far corner of the ceiling seems to be
A piece of dirty limestone in the piece of dirty ceiling I think that's the
Chose
But the ceiling was like
Which is essentially nicotine coatings
Hours for that everybody smoked all the time
That black ceiling Square was left on purpose to remind people what Grand Central was like back in the day
In the 1960s Grand Central history was almost a carbon copy of Penn Station's they were losing money
Because the building was so expensive to maintain and fewer people were taking trains
Just like Penn Station needed to sell the air space on top of the station and invite
Developers to build
When the 55-story office tower being nice on top of this baby
And most of its interior
But here's where the story of Grand Central and Penn Station The Verge
Remember those landmark
Happened in the years after the original Penn Station was demolished
They did manage to get Grand Central designated as a landmark
So the city denies the railroad executive plans
The owners of Grand Central were not placed
They wanted the money they were going to get from selling there are rides the space above Grand Central
So they sued the city
The case was a long one
It went on for nearly a decade
It was a bit of a nail-biter grand central nearly lost in 1975
With a state judge ruled against the city's designation of it as a landmark
The new mayor Abe beame almost an appeal the ruling
Saying that the city was poised to lose millions in court costs
Socat Barwick and others
Is created the committee to save Grand Central with one member who was a bit of a game changer
I think if you're is afraid effort even if it's at the $11 you can succeed and I think
And I know that that's what we'll do enter Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis
Grand Central Press Conference held in 1975
By the municipal art Society was at that press conference he says it was Jackie O soap
Currently involved
The fight went from a New York title to a national one
And people began to write in Iowa would a $5 bill and close
The case went all the way to the Supreme Court
And on June 26th
Highest court in the land
Ruled in favor of New York City
Landmark laws
Justice William Brennan Road of Grand Central architecture quote
Such examples are not so plentiful in New York City that we can afford to lose any of the few we have
And we must preserve them the meaningful way
Info
In other words
Grand Central would not suffer the same fate as its old friend and foe
Penn Station
To The Landmark laws with a lot of help from Jackie Onassis
Squeaked out a win
And all of these years later
One of the ways people Comfort themselves about the loss of the original Penn Station
Is with this idea
But the laws that came out of the destruction of Penn Station
Save Grand Central
So you know it's okay
Because it died for a Cause
I don't think Grand Central would have been saved without Penn Station
Penn Station
Sacrifice itself
So that grandcentral could live that was Peter Stanton you heard from him earlier he was one of the Architects that fought and fail
How to say Penn Station
But the tie between the destruction of
Penn Station
And the saving of Grand Central
Is actually kind of tenuous
Ferber the grass
It was Jackie O
Not the landmark laws
Save Grand Central
It's all very romantic
Assume that the demolition
Something so historic
Would have
Precipitate
Strong land
It just
Isn't
A sacrificial lamb like Penn Station can only do so much
People have to actually fight and win like they did with Grand Central
The laws that have teeth
Roberta Gratz was actually one of those people
The reporting she did on the landmarks Commission
Is just one of the things that led to the landmark laws ultimately being strengthened
And of course the Supreme Court
Holding those laws in the Grand Central case
Set an important precedent
Perceiving future landmarks
These days it's still a fight to save a building
But the laws are there and they're stronger now than they once were
So if you're a beautiful old building in New York
You don't have to rely on a celebrity endorsement
Or ragtag group of architect activists chanting polish don't demolish
To save you
Cooperating
99% invisible was produced this week by an have Herman thanks for the WNYC archives and Julia Barton
Uber help in editing % invisible is Sam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are products 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produce of the offices of arcsin
Architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs
Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world
A man-made sound
If I'm
Anteroom listen to analyze
Jackson on Alexis
Talking to me
All hearing.
Technology tok
It is a creation
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer in
Composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights.
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation
But taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
2%
We're presenting to
Special episode
So it's from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to tok
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloat
You tell yourself
It's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
It's frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time
Nancy kulp
Go to oh my God. Info
Podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info
Launch podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Power
Takes a look at the story behind
A different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 launches
Between episode where they take you inside
The love Israel family cult
Episode about uncovering the
Scrolled in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt
Brooke container of missing Chinese food that's haunted
A family for 25 years
The proud family goes wherever you get
Podcast
And find out why they say
Every house
House is haunted
You can find the show and hang out with other people who like to show on Facebook all of us
Fascinating on Twitter
The search for 99% invisible on YouTube
We have a great Tumblr but you're always welcome at our place
At 99 pi
. org
Radio
Before we go I want to tell you about
About the body
Series from Bello radiotopia show
The truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That wines
Treacherous
Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous act
Actor has to get re
Jack'd playsuit
Superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on
50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm
Being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping a
Huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead
In my Prime
Private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech way
Weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to
Clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley
And I'm going to do
Whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth
Podcast
Dot-com