99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
What say you lived sometime before 1860 and you wanted to fire a rifle
First you need to pour gunpowder into the powder charge to measure the amount of gunpowder you need it
And then you pack down your gunpowder and then bullet into the rifle with a ramrod
Can you pull back the hammer and take something called
Pull the trigger
That was one shot
Then you going to reload wichman pouring out new gunpowder stuffing the gunpowder and the new bullet down with the ramrod
Pulling back the hammer
And then you could shoot again
The whole process took at least as long as it just took for me to describe it
And as you can imagine this was all really inconvenient if someone
Was shooting at you
But then came the Winchester repeater rifle
That's reporter and then against their dads
The Winchester 1866 repeater rifle was a thing of beauty
Nickname the yellow boy for its bright brass receiver the gun was sleek
Gleaming and deadly
You could fire off 15 shots in just over 10 seconds
In the Winchester repeater arrived in the market just in time for the rise of western expansion
The huge
Sweep of manifest destiny
And people migrating
To the western part of North
America
That's Mary Jo ignoffo
A California historian at deanza College in Cupertino
Weapon
Became a source
Of survival
Sun protection
4 people
The next iteration of the Winchester repeater
The 1873 model
Was an even bigger hit
It was lighter more accurate and it became synonymous with Westward
Expansion
It came to be known as the gun that won the West
But probably only by people who think they won the West
The Winchester rifle company was very success
The most successful Arms Company in America in the late
The Winchester family became fabulously wealthy they live together in this palatial Mansion in New Haven Connecticut
They were harmonious
Rich
And happy
And to make matters happier William Winchester the heir to the family business and Fortune
Married the Girl Next Door
The beautiful and intelligent Sarah Pardee
In 1866
Sarah gave birth to a daughter
And then came with string of parable
Tragedy
They found a baby Annie couldn't absorb protein
And even with all the money in the world
Sarah couldn't stop her daughter from starving to death before
For her eyes
Then five years later Sarah's beloved husband William
Passed away from tuberculosis
He was only 43 years old
After losing her husband
Sarah Winchester then lost her father-in-law and her eldest sister
Sarah was not alone
Half a lifetime of loneliness lay ahead of her iconic black and white
Film actress Lillian Gish
Generating an old documentary about Sarah Winchester
With plenty of dramatic flight 1881
So Sarah advised her to seek the services of a well-known Boston median
Mr. Adam Coon
And as the legend goes
Through this medium Sarah was able to
Contact your deceased
Husband William
But William had some bad news
Her husband's voice told her that she always be haunted by the spirits of those who had been killed
By the Winchester rifle
Someone please give this poor Widow a break
Instructed her to
Duplicate them by building a structure that would never be completed
A house
Which rooms would constantly be added
Provide shelter
For the ever-increasing number of Winchester rifle victim
Finally
He told her that by doing what he had prescribed
He would gain immortality
Winchester rifles had killed a lot
The people
Is there a way to appease Argos
She would need to build a very very big house
And she had the money to do it
Having inherited her late husband stock in the rifle company
She was now one of the wealthiest
People in the car
And where better to build an ever-expanding structure
Then in the Wide Open West
California
Sarah Leff New Haven to begin a new in California
She bought an eight room farmhouse in San Jose and dove into the remodeling project head
At any given time there might have been a dozen people working on the house
Carpenters
Kyle Siders painters
Electricians
Some reports estimate their house wild from 8 to 26 rooms in the first
6 months
And others claimed there was no end to the construct
That Sarah Winchester's crew worked on the house in rotating shifts
Twenty-four hours a day for
38 years
As the construction March forward the house became a tangled Maze of halls and a mash-up of turrets and stained glass
You know it has a kind of Haunted Mansion quality
That's architectural historian Mitchell Schwartz
Doors that lead nowhere you know
Staircases
Is it stop halfway
And because she built over so many years the house was also a wild combination of architectural styles
You know every five years or so there was a kind of New Movement
Ainu types of ornaments
Curves are introduced in the 80
90s
But for a long time no one was able to see the
Hodgepodge
Styles in ornaments in this house
Except Sarah Winchester
Well Sarah and her staff of 18 house servants
13 Carpenters 8 to 10 gardeners and to private chauffeurs
Because Sarah Winchester kept to herself
Mrs. Winchester did not entertain and she did not open her doors to visitor
Supposedly Sarah Winchester was also always shrouded in a veil
And she never spoke to strangers or members of the press who inquired about her odd
Building in Denver
And because she didn't respond they started formulating their own suggestions
Maybe she's superstitious
Maybe she feels guilty that all that money came from guns
Maybe she feels like if she keeps Building she'll never die
And so those little stories BK
Came
Factual
Analysis
Winchester
It's unclear how much of the Sarah Winchester legend is true
We don't know whether she commune with ghosts
At least
She was communing with ghosts
What is she built a huge house to placate them or whether she felt guilty about her Fortune coming from guns
But after her death those Legends and rumors about her
I lived on
After Sarah's death and entrepreneur named John H Brown saw the possibility in the old decrepit estate
In 1923 he reopened mrs. Winchester's property as the Winchester Mystery House
And ever since it's been the subject of all kinds of
Sudo documentaries on haunted house
Said to be inhabited by ghosts
Inspired by Madness
It has the deranged design of a carnival Funhouse
When I walked in my my head I get tails
The workers
They're still building it on the others
For $33 you can buy a ticket and tour Sarah Winchester's house
Maggie and I will be your guide
Today on this day
65 minutes
Beautiful bird and
Hebrew Victorian man
I brought my family there we drove an hour we waited in line Michelle. A whole lot of money for tickets because we've never been there and some
Bay Area landmark
And if California historical landmark number 8
If you have a look at
The tour points out all the bizarre things about the house
Like the staircase
Is that lead to nowhere
Nowhere
And even a door to nowhere
I know I can point out that Ms Winchester had the number 13 all around the house
Account search
13 stone
You are going to see a lot of 13th on your tour here today
But the highlight of the tour is definitely the Seance room
This is the day on shrooms in the middle of the house
This is where Sarah supposedly received directions
From the spirit
Legend has it mrs. Winchester would come up here every night
To speak to the spirits
Winchester rifle
They seem to be selling the story of the haunted house
And of the haunted mrs.
In a lot of people seem to be buying it
But not everyone
The mythology about her
It's not only insulting to her
It's insulting to me as a consumer of
Popular culture
Insults
A person's intelligence
That's Mary Jo ignoffo again
And she doesn't believe the haunted mrs. Winchester
She wrote a book about Sarah Winchester the challenges of the myths
Sarah herself didn't write a memoir or speak to the prize
The Mary Jo did find documents that helped her understand who the real Sarah Winchester may have been
There were incredible original sources that hadn't been used by anybody else
Letters that she wrote
Correspondence with her attorney
Property records
After pouring through documents Mary Jo has come to believe that a lot of the really strange things
That we see today and that are emphasized in the mythology about Sarah Winchester
Are completely explainable
The stairs to Nowhere for example they probably did lead somewhere once rooms were constantly being tweaked and Ramon
Plus the 1906 earthquake had a major effect
There are no original blueprints for the house
But we do know that the earthquake destroyed the front of the mansion and the third and fourth story
She felt like
The defects of the house
Really
Came to the fore in the 1960 earthquake
And so she kind of was chagrined at her own workmanship that this would happen
Instead of rebuilding
Sarah had workers
Clear away the rubble and make the place safe
And then just boarded up the front of the house
It's very possible that the stairs led to a room that got destroyed in the quake
As for all those thirteens Mary Jo doesn't put a lot of stock in them
And she believes that some of them might not be from Sarah Winchester
Couple of the man who worked on the house
They stated in the 1920s that those references to the number 13
Where added
After her death
As to whether Sarah Winchester conducted seances in her supposed Sam's room
It's possible
Spiritualism in Santa's we're actually fairly common practice in Sarah Winchester's time
But still Mary Jo find it unlikely
Partly because of the location of the room in the middle of the house
Anybody who knows about spiritualism or seances know that those are really public
Affairs
Social Affairs at the very least if not
Public and you would have that in your front
Parlor
Then again Sarah was a very private person so maybe she did her seances alone
The ranch Foreman also
Stated that he had actually stayed in that room and it was
Not related
Spiritual
Or superstitious
Events at all and lastly in the popular legend about Sarah Winchester her whole building Endeavor was set in
Lotion after seeing a medium by the name of Adam Coombs when supposedly put her in touch with her dead husband
But Mary Jo gained access to a list of mediums and spiritualists that would have been practicing and New England during
Sarah Winchester
Does lifetime
The name that usually associated with having seen Winchester is not there
Adam Koontz may never have existed at all
There's some things we'll never know about Sarah Winchester
But with Mary Jo does feel like we can know for sure is that Sarah wasn't out of touch with reality
On the contrary
She was rational and savvy
This is a woman's so far ahead of her time in financial math
And her real estate invest
And her
Bond Park
Portfolio
It's
It's really remark
So why does a financially savvy
Forward-thinking woman build such a
Crazy never-ending house
Mary Jo has a different Theory
No ghost involved
She was an architect
Want to be
Sarah Winchester wanted
To be an architect
She loved doing
Building
Experiment
I love that Arie
Sarah Winchester lived at a time when it was highly unusual
To have women architects
And she wasn't license
So her own house was the
The perfect place the only place
For her to practice architecture
And it became her playground
Sometimes in the middle of a project she lose interest and move on to something else
From all this emerging odd and frenetic Confluence of architect
Butter house
Isn't
Only a collection of Oddities
There's some legitimately Innovative elements to
There's a Solarium with a zinc
Floor it doesn't rest
Hilton for the water
To run off and be used in
In the garden
There are also these amazing zigzagging stairs
But instead of going up a steep pitch
Rise and shallower in Chrome
Sarah Winchester had debilitating right
And these fairs made it possible for
Her to move about her
The legend says that Sarah and her crew worked on her house 24 hours a day for 38
Years
And that upon hearing of her death or work crew finally sat down there Hammers and walked off the job
This is most likely an exaggeration
The house was certainly a project that consumed mrs. Winchester's attention
Predict games
Finally he told her that by doing what he had prescribed
He would gain immortality
And of course
She didn't gain immortality from all of her building as a spirited
Supposedly promised
But she did live into her 8
In the end
Whatever her motivations were
Sarah Winchester built a house with over 150 rooms
2000 doors
47 fireplaces
40 bedroom
40 staircases
17 chimneys
13 bathrooms 6 kitchens three elevators to basement
In one shower
And spent nearly all of her life
Being
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Nina Gensler jobs with Avery trufelman Katie mingle Sam Greenspan and
We are project on 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
Arcsine in architecture and Interiors firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa Model X
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrated but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black Box
Family goes
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets crawled into weed
Who discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You can find the show and likes on Facebook roll on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify and you can listen to every single episode
Totem 99percentinvisible and 99 pi
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find the
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com