99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Is a well-known literary technique called chekhov's gun
Mater the Russian playwright
Basically a gun appears in the First Act
It better be fired in the following act there are no unnecessary detail
If you're gone
That gun gets used to shoot
I have a corollary principle of my own invention and relates to movies where there is a scene at a construction
And it is this
If on the screen you see an ugly shaft of exposed rebar
Somebody is getting impaled
There's something about rebar
If nothing else because there are very few things that invoke a fear of being skewered
Like pathological preoccupation with metal reinforcement bars dovetails nicely with a structure in San Francisco
Kind of become obsessed
Tiny Bridge
In Golden Gate Park
This is the Alford Lake bridge by Ernest Ransom
This is when lemon he teaches architecture at the California College of the Arts and he was the first person to tip me off to the importance
Of this humble little structure
On the very Eastern edge of the park the entrance to the park
From the hate side from the kind of
Hippie slacker
Haight area
Right at the edge of the park
Turtle eating into the children's playground
It's not a place that most people really want to linger
What is a spot for drug dealing in
Various
Still listen to assination
And that is Robert Corlin author of concrete Planet giving us a lay of the land in the
Albert
Lakebridge
One of the earliest surviving reinforced concrete structure
Pictures in the world
The bridge was constructed in 1889
It may be the least appealing sort of Monument above of architecture civil engineering
Inside of crack with a birth certificate wrestling through its
Covered in mold and lichen
Inside it's a
Surrealistic tunnel of
Stalactites that
Really
Going to look like some sort of folk art
No impression of what the surface of Mars might look like he looks like the inside of a giant colon
Unappealing
The pass through it
I'm it's not well kept up at all well there's nothing remarkable about it is an arch
It's actually as much a pedestrian tunnel was a bridge
Pioneering structure in the shape of a dumpy in the
Neglected little Bridge
But that's really sad because it is
One of the pioneering buildings in the story of reinforced concrete
There are plenty of candidates for the most overlooked most visible part of the
Has a good claim to being the most invisible of all
Because if it's made right you never see the steel skeleton underneath
All the concrete structures that
Work and drive over walk under reinforced concrete is concrete that is strengthened by the
Mission of initially iron and then later
Steel
To give it tensile
The thing about concrete is it graded compression meaning
Withstand a lot of pressure in terms of
Wait
But it's not very good intention meaning when you put expanding long distances assertive can collapse
So if you see concrete going high in the air or spanning a long distance
There is metal inside
And you have this unassuming Vanguard of a bridge and its engineer Ernest rants
To thank for that
Ernst ransoms the principal claim to fame is that he's the father of modern reinforced concrete
The experiments done with
Reinforcing concrete with iron previous Terrence ransomware just one office
Experiments a cottage in England
House in New York and Daya rowboat in France
Ernst Ransom experimented with
Different forms of iron reinforcement until
Hit Upon what we now call rebar which is
Too short for reinforcement bar
And his technology was Far Beyond any of the others
Who are experimenting with reinforced concrete at the time
A lot of people in Europe and America are playing with
Putting in bars or are metal into concrete at this time
There's many different techniques and everyone's experimenting
Ransom's
To the major Innovation is he takes the square bar
Any Twisted slightly
And that gives us an adhesive quality
Choota concrete Excel
Interstate together much better
Ransom
Said to come to this idea he found a twisted rubber band in his pocket one day and thought well that's what I'm going to do to this iron
Twisted
Search of spines of The Conch
Better
You can see a diagram of this Twisted rebar and ransoms 1884 patent
By the way if you're anything like me Google Patent Search
Which is the best way to spend time in front of the computer
I can lose hours
Jumping for patent
Anyway
This innovation of messing with the bar to help it bond with the surrounding concrete
Is still used to this day
We put
Formations on the reinforcing
So the concrete will
Hold on to it that's going is probably why I find Rebar
So ugly and on satellite
That's about right there right there
Show the concrete reinforcing
I called this cersi
The full scope of what reinforced concrete means
Adult World
Over exaggerating I would save it to the
The significance of a reinforced concrete is that modern
Society is not
Well is humble is the Alvord Lake bridge is
It is a direct
Precursor
To the Engel skyscraper
Built just
15 years later and Cincinnati Ohio the world's first reinforced concrete
Skyscraper
It also led to Bridges
Dams
Freeways
Streets
Of reinforced concrete reinforced concrete
You would only be able to build a series of unconnected asphalt roads it's a very humble beginning but
It was from here in San Francisco that the reinforced concrete Revolution
Take over the world
That's why we talked about it being the foundation of civilization
It's also a foundation of modern architecture
It made possible forms that were never possible before
Like Frank Lloyd Wright's Guggenheim Museum
And more recently and Jeanne gang Aqua Tower in Chicago
Mimic flowing water on the knee
Floors
There are no two floors of the
There's no truth
But the problem with reinforced concrete
Great especially if the rebar isn't covered with enough concrete and is it
Exposed to water and salt
Is that the steel inside
Can Ross
And as it rusts it expands
The expanse almost fourfold its original diameter destroying the concrete around it while
Blue steel itself
Is being destroyed by the rust
Corrosion
And when that happens which it will eventually
Reinforced concrete doesn't last the 1,000 years that aren't as Ransom in the early reinforced on
Opponents.
For many many years design life is about 50
Interstate system
50-year design
CJ's
Old insulation and others are work
What's the federal government
Instigation
75 in
100 Year design
Modern reinforced concrete frames in case inside of a building super
Structure with normal maintenance
Will last a lot
Lot longer so don't worry the Burj Khalifa
The tallest tower in the world in the tallest reinforced concrete structure
Is not coming down anytime soon
Weather clock
Is taking for most of the reinforced Concrete in Frisco
Structure that was put up in the middle of the 20th century in the US
People have to realize it
All this that they see around them will eventually have to be
With a few exceptions
Will have to be torn down and replaced because we built was
Steel-reinforced concrete
And the cost of that it will be trillions of dollars
Unbelievable amount of money
Seriously
The stuff that wasn't properly maintained
Is coming down
And as you can imagine
A lot of our infrastructure
Was not
Properly maintained
Republic agency
Square
Aviary Franklin
The message
Lesbian and in some cases still is a reactionary policy rather than a well-thought-out
Maintenance
Karrueche
Even though concrete has the illusion of permanence is not that way at all
You just don't forget it
You have to
You have to account for going back
Taking care of it like you would any
Anything else
Bernice Ransom left San Francisco soon after you completed the offer Lakebridge
It is book reinforced concrete buildings published in 1912
Which is not the most scintillating of text
But in it
You can detect a tinge of bitterness and ransoms words
As he describes how his
Twisted rebar
With quote last down
But a technical Society in Keller
California
He left for the east
Thinking that his revolution of reinforced concrete
Would have a better chance out there
He left thinking that no one here would fully appreciate
Is Alvord Lake bridge
And no one here would appreciate
Miss literal Bridge
To the modern world
Looking at it today
Sad
And he was right
99% invisible in Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project at 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
In the American Institute vodka
Tax in San Fran
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is in another room and we're all hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
IPic
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info slide podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God. Info
Flat pocket
Family ghosts
Play the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our families
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into unanswered questions about their
History season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode
It brings you a long to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
But this week
My
Goodness we have amazing photographs of the Alvord Lake bridge
This Photograph by Eddie Joachim
Just makes
The ugliness in
Creepiness of that place
Beautiful in
Stunning
You have to check them out
Threat 99% invisible
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous personalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com