99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
By the late 1980s
AIDS have been in the US for almost a decade
We look through timeline from this.
You see the records of 100 people that a thousand
People that a million people that
AIDS becomes the number one killer of young men in New York City
Then of young men in the country
Then of young men and women in the country
So what you don't see much of in the late 80s is public acknowledgement of AIDS
Beth reporter Audrey Quinn
Millions of people were dying of this mysterious new disease
But there was so much stigma against talking about
You kind of felt like you were living in a war zone and there was no reported
It was a Bizarro world
He was really involved with the Manhattan arts in the late 80s
Community where can be hard to think about anything but gave Christ
We would spend days
Going to St Vincent's to visit someone
Going to readings for a funeral and then getting
On your answering machine message of somebody flipping out because
It just been told
To Patrick and a group of other artists
Turn their focus to AIDS
Yeah why why were you making art and response
In 1988 O'Connell and his collaborators begin calling their Collective
Visual aids
They held public events to raise awareness
There was slideshows
Gallery shows
But of all the work they did the thing that had the biggest effect
With a simple little symbol
That at the time was a novel concept
The AIDS awareness ribbon
It all started one night in the spring of 1991
The visual aids artist caucus
Hilton meeting in search of a symbol
They wanted something that could be created that
Could
Be put out there for people to wear
That's a couple he's a costume designer and was at that meeting
He's now director of costumes for the New York City Ballet
That's a lot of driving around upstate New York
This was at the time of the Persian Gulf War we started to see a course at the time yellow ribbons or
Tied around trees which is
You know in reference to that song for servicemen
It's been so long
You know we just were like
You know
Why can't we do something like that
And we talked about it you know what it really be around a tree and that just seemed a little like
I don't know not right
Then it became like
Oh
Maybe not around the tree but maybe folded
With a pin on your lapel
Then it was time to pick a color
In the meaning it also came about that it was like yes it should be red because it represents blood
It was just so obviously right
The local ribbon supplier donated spools of half inch wide red grosgrain ribbon
Greens that ribs ribbon you might have worn around your ponytail growing up
And we started just in these meetings like folding them and doing different things with them and force it just
Started out just like folding it in half
But then it came
To actually folding it in that
Way we now know it so well
With a safety pin
The loop
Inverted V shape
They're on the streets of the
City
Within
10 weeks
Search something with them
Patrick O'Connell again
By this time he was director of visual aid
And at this point the red ribbons were essentially in art
The visual aids artist caucus members help but they called ribbon.
Think like a quilting bee
Bunch of people gather to work
Hand-cut
Fold and pin
Thousand
I'll just a hand out for free
In mid-may
I had this very foolish idea that we should be
Telhio
Which left us
Approximately two weeks
Apache
Condense everybody
Not going to be disrupted by
Something they should embrace
A number of visual aids members had Broadway connection
Beihai gold with the organizers of the Tony Awards
And Coke
Celebrity dressers into pinning the ribbons on their clients
Before the ceremony
Mark Hoppus Studio was mad it was stabbed
We were Distributing the more
Typically size 2
Ribbon tweeter
We're going to ruin everybody's dressing and dinner jacket
So let's make them big and stupid
Set pack for the presenters
Status of the camera could like really capture
The night of the show came
June 7th
The night we all kind of went home and everybody was crossing their fingers because we didn't know they didn't know if anyone would actually wear
Are the ribbons I mean
We we handed all the stuff out and all these word of Supervisors and only stretches on you
They said
Sure we'll see what we can do can't promise much but will try
Live
From the minskoff theatre on Broadway
Tony Award winner
Jeremy Irons walked out with a red ribbon on his lapel
I mean I'm emotional now because he was like
You know it worked
I found the full show on YouTube
Jeremy Irons is so handsome the slicked-back hair and a big red ribbon on the left lapel of his black tux
The first winner of the knights this little girl the basic vegan star of The Secret Garden
I don't think I can talk
She's got this poofy sleeve black and white dress on
And a little red ribbon on your chest
Thank you
Then there's Kevin Spacey
Lost in Yonkers
Because up to accept his award with the more medium sized red dripping
Thank you very much
Next DC Penn and Teller wearing big red ribbon
By the end of the show I was paying more attention to the presenters not wearing ribbons
Totally judging them for missing the memo
What you also notice watching the Tonys is how new the awareness ribbon was
Everyone was wearing them
In different ways
Somewhere loot
Summer folded
Sharp angles
Some of the ribbons have their ends spread wide like wings
But here's the
Crucial thing
Doing
Explain the ribbons on air
Rumor has it the network
Threaten to go to commercial break if they did
Turns out this degree of mystery provided some incredibly good press
The one thing that was kind of exciting as the next day there was a little blurb in the newspaper that was like
What was that red ribbon and it was every
There was two days of print media
Wondering what is Red Ribbon
So
You know that really
I think for us and for
The Red Ribbon at cell
Was just the point where at
Exploded
Within days the ribbon with stopping traffic
We ran into this
Seemingly very successful businessman and his wife on the street
And
He saw his wearing everybody and he was like I saw that
Isn't it isn't it that's about AIDS cuz no one actually said it
I suppose yes
How did you get what I said well actually made them it's our project
I filled up a hundred-dollar bill and gave it to us
When they found out what
Was for I think a lot of people really got on board and just for like
I need start wearing red river
And it just really pushed it over into being kind of almost
Piano
Just a much bigger symbol than I've ever had been
And I think that we ever
Really thought it might
Be so quick
The next step for the ribbon was the Emmys
Then the Oscars and the Grammy Awards
And the members of visual aids continue to gather to make them
Cut
We will be watching on TV
Famous people where are they
While we sat in the Loft making ribbons together
Very meta that say now say
No David said it would have
Danberry Pomo
School groups in church group started contacting visual aids artist
Ask me how they could start their own Moon project
Patent.
Wechat
Becomes this phenomenon
Which we were
Surprised by
When did it start
Ribbon with out of your hair
Well probably by 90
The end of 92
In terms of
The introduction of Vicodin
Bejeweled leatherback
Crystal pave red ribbon
Etc they were Red Ribbon diamond necklaces
Red Ribbon Christmas ornaments
Red Ribbon t-shirt
There were some of us thought that visual aids should
Trade market
And
So that any time it's used the money had to come back to fish late
It's one of the reasons we didn't was that
I would not have been embraced
So willingly
Kentucky University
If we had if everyone had to come
And say may I have permission to do the
It would have been contrasted
Spirit of the Earth
Oh yeah I haven't
Tie waist visual aids have a nickel for every ribbon settled in the world or Ribbon object
Adapt after
The ribbons graders
A backlash from other AIDS activist
A person just wearing the ribbon felt like a radical a
Publicly acknowledging that aids existed
The people were suffering
That you cared
What is the ribbon became more ubiquitous
Some activists called wearing it
An easy out
A way to look like you cared
About people with AIDS without actually doing anything to help people with AIDS
Basically the same criticisms that net the Livestrong bracelet
And the ice bucket challenge
Couple says that's okay
What we wanted to do was create something that
A mother in Michigan
Cookware on the lapel of her blouse
And you know maybe her son was living in New York and living with AIDS and she
Wanted to do something
I think it was just
Who is also a symbol that we created the
Somebody could wear
And somebody might go up to them and say
What is that
Why are you wearing that red ribbon and hopefully that person would say
Here's why
The ribbon was doing its job
People were talking about AIDS
The New York Times declared 1992 the year of the ribbon
President Clinton set up the White House Office of national AIDS policy
The National Institute of Health expanded its AIDS research
And the government funded the national HIV epidemiology study
Overtime you gotten so much attention for AIDS
That more than 200 other causes
Best Buy Arlo
Account now use a loop
Awareness ribbon as their symbol
Well it's interesting that
We almost 25 years later
It's everywhere now and everybody
Space
Indifferent
Colors
There's the pink ribbon for breast cancer awareness
An indigo ribbon for bullying awareness
A teal ribbon for anxiety disorder awareness
Actually the teal ribbon is also used for ovarian cancer awareness
Tourette Syndrome awareness
Tsunami victim awareness
Thermal causes that want ribbons and there are colors of ribbon
And the ribbons Ubiquiti eventually reach the point of parity
When the Band Death Cab for Cutie wore light blue ribbons at the Grammys in 2009
People wondered
What about second hand smoke awareness
Adrenocortical carcinoma awareness
It turns out
Death Cab for Cutie had started their own cause
Auto-tune abuse awareness
You know on 7th Avenue to call that
A knockoff elsewhere you call it a rip-off
I think it's great that people
Cook that
Simple
Little ribbon with a pin and made it their own
You know and used it for whatever cause they
They were fighting
I'm
Totally fine with that and I think you know it's
It's
There for people to use
In whatever way they want to and however they want to get a message out
Imagination when I look at it is that it
Such a perfect phone
Yusuf all
Economic in terms of its design
And that is
The best kind of
Design that's Michelle Miller Fisher
She's a curatorial assistant at the architecture and design department at the Museum of Modern Art
And this last month she helps make the red AIDS ribbon an official part of the Museum's collection
She remembers first seeing the ribbon as a kid in England in the 90s
The very first time I saw it I realized it
Advocacy and passion even understanding it is a very young child
Imbued in a very simple design
The MoMA hasn't collection one of the hand-cut visual aids ribbons pinned to an original ribbon project handout
Explaining its meaning
I love the fact that
I can see what someone has cut this
And so I wonder whether
This was someone's like 50th weapon at the end of the day
The Momo plans to have the ribbon out on display in the next year
I will always think it's irrelevant
Kabul again
Because
You know
AIDS is still with us it's still out there and we still have to be aware of it and we still have to raise money and we still have to fight
We still have to
Care for people in
So on and so forth
No AIDS isn't the killer that used to be at least in the US
But that doesn't mean the disease is gone
The number of people living with HIV in the United States
Is now higher than ever before
Patrick O'Connell also says he'll keep wearing his AIDS awareness ribbons
Back at his apartment he showed me the ribbons in his wardrobe
Sure they're on
330 Ravens
Yeah that he doesn't even take them off when he washes his shirt
Just keep them pinned on
Is anything that has
Do you have the ribbon you don't
Wait NF
We had fun that we did bizarrely we had fun
I'm telling you why
Remember me
Explain
Urinating
Domingo with the old times
I am sad that I be there
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Audrey Quinn with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and Mero
We are project of kalw San Francisco and produce out of the offices of arcsin
An architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
The inspiration for this story came from WHYY the pulse
Cancer ribbon
Willing to the balls
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Size routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find this show and like the show on Facebook we're all on Twitter and follow me at Roman Mars anyone has bought
Meet the balls over the weekend my wife is away
Whales have a Tumblr
. every single day
The more info on this story in the entire 99 PR catalog can be found in 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com