99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with your cousin
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with
Precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Fear free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Water-based in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Which is a port city
On the San Francisco Bay
Massive container ship
Travel across the Pacific
End up here
From miles away
You can see the enormous
White cranes that pulled Giant
Uniformly sign
Metal boxes
Does off the ships
People say the trains are the inspiration for the AT-AT walkers in The Empire Strikes Back but that's not true
It's a good story to tell when you pass by
Under bridge
The Port of Oakland and its container ships have always captured my imagination
It turns out
They also captured the imagination of my colleague and friend Alexis Madrigal
I went out and visited a ship that was docked in Okla
And when I went out on the ship
I walked into this
Room that's all wood
Paneled in this
Old Romanian captain
Walks in with his Marlboro Reds needs to come down
On the table he looks right in my eyes mean
What is your
Tent
And I was just thought I was in love like from his love at first sight I was just like no one else
Ever hear these voices there so amazing
The car to head people on a ship one of the cats and the other is the chief engineer down in the engine room
And so we can we look at Bridge
And we went back to that wood-paneled room and the chief engineer comes in another Romanian dude
Enikos
You visited the head of a ship
Top Chef
Now visit the heart
He takes his time into the engine room you know where these is a
Wrenches that are like you know 5 ft tall
I really cannot imagine not doing
A series of stories after that
And I went home and I had some wine and I was like drunk tweeting about how amazing would it be
Just tell the stories of all these
People on earth
Supply chain
And that's what happened
Alexis decided to embark on an eight-part series called containers
About how the shipping container
Has changed the global economy
We're going to feature one of the stories from that series on the show today but first
I wanted to talk a little with Alexis
About what the world was like before the container
So like before the 1970s or so
Starting with the ports
So if you want to think about what a port was like
In the old days
Go just look at the
Appears look at how they're shaped
Are these long fingers coming off
The shoreline
Will the ships would have pulled up into what those are
Finger piers
And then we would have unloaded their stuff they would have probably hundreds of people running around
And they would have unloaded their stuff directly onto this. Which would have been gone into cargo
So you got guys working winches you know, like little Mini Cranes on the boat
And you got all the stuff stored inside the hull of the ship
That was
Container
They're dropping it onto the docks
Other people are forklifting around trucks are pulling out there's all these
Is Cruz running everywhere
And so that the notion of the docs
Like the water
Charismatic play
The people know understand
It's because they were
All these people from all over the world
And the goods themselves literally the stuff coming from all these places is visible to your view
So
You can smell the coffee
When the spaceships come in you'd smell the cardamom
When there was something that was disgusting like hides that was being worked
You smell green hide being handled by
You have seen big rolls of newsprint
Way the world worked
Was actually served
Boast you before it got reput into factories
Simpatico
It was actually it's incredible
Citing an old longshoreman
When you graduate high school
But only High School
He said you know there was an entire education about the way the world war
Just looking at the goods
They were sitting on the docks
When people started shipping things in containers Goods could be loaded in offloaded more easily
The container is full of stuff could go directly from the ship
Two trucks and trains
And everything was standard
All over the world
Containers unlimited a lot of inefficiency
She's from the system
Imports
Completely change
Airports nowadays
Long flat bursts
The ships come in they dock
And then you at least
Largely White
Container cranes drop over them
Those cranes are really a wild thing when you think about it the reason their necks are so long that called The Boom
Because the ships are so wide
And they go out over the whole ship
And then a little
Person in a little cab
Go out
All the way
Across the ship they look down through their legs
Drop this
Then call the spreader
Auntie Dee's
For locking mechanisms on the box they pull it up and bring it they drop it onto a
Intermediate truck that takes it into the holding yard
Venom Rio Drayage truck comes in drive-thru West Oakland spraying diesel all over the community and then takes it out to it District
You should Center in Tracy or wherever it is you know and that's kind of a pretty normal flow
But container is didn't just have an effect on Imports
Band effect on port cities
All over the world
Oakland included
Cuz absolutely
Everything about the way that cities work and global trade War
Was changed by the system of containers
They should not just the Box
But everything that went along with
The locking mechanism
The operations of the yard the ships that had to be developed
In order to carry more containers
In a one way that I have thought about it
Is there were computers
Before and it was networking before
Then there's this thing called the Internet Protocol that allowed
Like a package to be moved around no matter what was inside them
And that allows for the sick
Explosion of networking
That's essentially what containers do
For Stuff
You can just
Put NEX thing into a box and it can go to any port
And as I was reading this
Defining work on this process
Containerization called The Box
Canon Mark Levinson is in the series
There's a
Droll Four Oaks
For most intensive purposes Sealand is a first major container Shipping Company
They really get there
Explosive growth
How's the Vietnam War shipping things from Oakland to Vietnam
And that was so fascinating to me
Particular because almost immediately
They go to Vietnam to
Container
Rapport-building cam ranh Bay
And they start going back by Japan
And if they go back by Japan
People trying to come back to you
California Science
And that
Becomes
This dominant mode
A trade in the world and it
Literally reshapes
The world economy
And it's coming from these three you know
Cranes that are sitting over there still sitting there unused
In the Port of Oakland
How is not a better known story
After you get started after
Talking to your Romanian
Captain and Trump tweeting
What were you most surprised by
We started doing this
Bluetooth
When is the
Credible
Containerization
Had on cities
And it continues to have on cities
The first wave of
Containerization
Wipes out so many jobs
In urban America
Urban Coastal
Really really
Does bad things
For a lot of cities
Like you know that empty Warehouse Brooklyn aesthetic
Like that was the warehouse that used to before we Goods
And then containerization came along and wiped out all the warehouses and that's what created the ability to have these kinds of
Creative workspaces that you have now that's your leader in the energy in the carcass of the old system of trade
When you're in one of those space
That was what I didn't I just had no idea that this happened all over the world in London and New York
San Francisco
Even though the invention of the container wiped out shipping jobs all over the world
There are still a lot of people working in the industry
What those people do and whether they will be able to hold on to their jobs as the shipping industry continues to change
Is what Alexis Explorer is in episode 3 of
Containers
And you have all these
People out there
Good job
Is Arlington one way or another two things made around the world
And most of them tend to
To be in place
It's like
California Virginia New York
These big Coastal ports
And their job
Send what those jobs are
I had no idea it like what is it
To work in a warehouse what is it to work
On a tugboat what is it to work in a
Port there no stories about these things ever
Take away from me is Maybe
Collage
Of all these different work experiences and trying to get
The texture of those lives
How those
People see the world
I like the point
Containers
This is episode 3 of containers
Call the ships
Buttocks
And the poor
Here's Alexa smack
You need a lot of tough people near the docks
Intense Captain's Burley longshoreman salty Skippers rugged old timers
But I want you to meet the most hardcore person
I met during my time reporting
On the waterfront
And I thought to myself well I'll go in this career in this industry and kind of see what
I'm not thinking that this is my dream
To grow up and be a ship captain
This is Lynn Court watch
She became the first female captain of an American cargo ship
Under remark
Circumstance
And during those first years I had the opportunity to sale
Initially as a
I made on an oil tanker
And was in Southern California when a tanker blew up
Inside me and maybe this is really not
The gig that I want
So she joined the master mates & Pilots Union
And began selling on all kinds of ships around the world
I quickly kind of decided that you know going to places like
The Far East
And South America was a little bit more of a challenge you know in the 1970s and early 80s they had never seen
Women on ships
Every time she entered a poor Chadwicks
Explain to skeptical dockworkers
But she wasn't the captain's wife
And that the men had to listen to her
The stuff work
So she decided to try to work her way up at the American shipping line mat
Wood Randa
It still runs
Ship from Oakland to Hawaii
I have the opportunity over the years to advance
To the chief mates position at Mattson they were very good to me
And
When an opportunity came up to be promoted on a temporary basis to Captain
When did turn it down
Yeah of course not
Why would you he never knew when that opportunity was going to come along again
Only one hitch so despite the fact that
I was 8 months pregnant there's no doctor on board a container ship
Let alone OB or Midwife or a doula
I said God
You know I think I got to do this
And who knows you can appreciate being pregnant is not handicapped
Or
You know something that should limit your opportunities it's
It's just something that happens and you kind of carry on with life
So that's what happened
I was 8 months pregnant
Probably more than 8 months pregnant
And said yes
Let's go
What's your plan if you got into labor
It was kind of funny because my chief made at the time
Had recently delivered his own baby in his car
So he was delighted with the idea that all man I get to do this and won't that be really fun
You needless to say it didn't turn into a reality
But what
Did kind of complicate the situation was after I got off the ship
About five days later I did go into labor
And found out
15 RMB notes to me
My son was breech that means feet first
Which makes for substantially more dangerous labor
So should I have gone into labor on the ship it would have been a much bigger challenge than I think any of us ever into the
And to link or watches
Down-to-earth groundbreaking woman in the field of shipping
And the longtime part of the bay is maritime economy
She's respected by all for her toughness
IntelliJ
Her track record made her natural fit to become the head of the San Francisco Marine Exchange
Which may be the oldest institution in all of California
So the Marine Exchange is an organization that was founded back in 1849 to really kind of track
And monitor ships as they arrived in San Francisco Bay
We put the telegraph on Telegraph
Kill in order to communicate that information down to our Maritime partners
We had several
Relay stations around the bay
You know I'm primarily
Yeah we were
Moving that information around
There was
The trading floor
So that when we pass this information down to our
Our membership
You know they were traded Commodities right then and there on the floor
They knew that the shipping
Coming from
South America
East Coast
China Beach
Because that would be
Do semaphore
Orthrus
Flags
It's not a stretch to say that San Francisco
And all the surrounding towns exist
Basically
Because the bay had a good poor
San Francisco became a part of the global archipelago
Important cities
The Waterfront area
Along the Embarcadero is where those brake bulbs
Came
Announce really
You know where
Economy of Sanford
Gruen Gruen
Kangaroo nowadays
The Marine Exchange nips together the many different pieces
Of the current Maritime economy
The honest broker
Did everyone works with to address stuff like
Trade stuff
Mission really haven't changed we do exactly the same thing
We don't control ships
We don't directions
Weimar
Because we do have management part of our organization as well as labor
We
Have become somewhat of a neutral provider for services
And one of those Services is that they publish a book A book
Redis entire series
That you're listening to
It was all the businesses that ply the waters
Anchor chains indexing barging boating Services boiling water tree
Tabs
MTG variety of businesses
By the Waters and the supply ships
The people who bring supplies and service lifeboats and make ropes and haul trash and so anchors so many
Types of businesses that you need to have a functioning
Maritime economy
Container ships are the big animals these companies are the little Nimble creatures that make the ecosystem work
Like inside
One of these small businesses works these jobs
I want to know so I called appetite but companies listed in the Marine Exchange handbook a few days later I was sitting across from
Ted blankenburg messy office inside a manufactured building
Right at the foot of the Bay Bridge
What you say he was
Adventurous
Young man
Went to college and spent a couple years in the army
On the modern pentathlon team running
Swimming
Pistol shooting
Fencing
And taking a horse
Hopefully over a course
Ted works for Eminem
One of the tugboat companies that service
Eastbay
Like the rest of the maritime economy
Voting is inextricably linked with a business
Global Shipping
He's also worldclassbullshitter
Hilarious
Well that's a picture of me falling off a horse into a brick wall
He's been around the type of mystery for
30 years
I was tending bar
And a friend of mine's
Mother on the tugboat company
And my friend heard my line of
Pattern from behind a bar to go to we got to get you on the air we need a night
Dispatcher
So I started working
3 days a week this is the best job I ever had
3 14-hour days a week from
Fortnite
Till 6 in the morning
And you could sleep a few hours on
On the job tells a good gig but the business of voting is changing
The customers the big Shipping Lines
I've been locked in Fierce competition with each other
And I mean let's be real
They've been in a race
To the bottom
I did that in the shipping companies in the past
Probably since 2008
Convergence losing their
Shorts
Mumbai
Billions of dollars a year
Two consulting firms
Drewry NC intelligence estimated 2016 shipping industry losses at 8
Maybe 10 billion.
Nissan dealerships
150 million dollars
So you have a big old invest
And
United making money you're going to
Paula Stern
How do you stay in business
I seriously don't know
How they got to this point
Was
Mirrors
Twitches
The biggest
Shipping Company the world are Danish
Decided to build
Ships that work
Twice as big
As as all the other ones
Nazca Lines New Tripoli class will be the world's largest ships a record 400m
As long as 59 meters wide Triple E stands for Energy Efficiency
Environmental performance
A bunch of Shipping Lines followed Maris lead and building mega mega mega show
This creature is Spike in available shipping Supply
The man did not
Follow suit
So you might expect
Prices have
Plummeted
That's really really cheap shipping for people importing exporting
Historically
The Journal of Commerce says that it cost about 18 hundred or two thousand bucks
To ship a box across the Pacific
Right now the price for a big retailer is more like seven or eight hundred
If you're making
Brake pads and pantyhose and toothbrushes in China
UShip animal versus Nebraska
They're going to get shipped
Somebody's going to ship them
In the shipping companies are really
And that means they become desperate
Somehow survive
They're scared
The number 7 in the world
Went bankrupt apply for bankruptcy protection
Your calls means less revenue for all the companies that service ships
Coming in
Industries getting tougher
Suffer to survive in
No slack left
System
The local companies that respond with
Consolidation themselves
Antonym for example was purchased by the Marine Resources Group
Which became fast Marine which is owned by the seattle-based salt check resources Incorporated
A conglomerate that controls 30 logistic
6 businesses
Everybody needs some bigger entity
Protection
And that was before Donald Trump started at least
Talking about its so-called America First Trade policy
In which presumably more things are made in the United States
Unless things are made in Asia
If you've already got too much shipping capacity
3 out of the ocean
Let me USMLE start importing fewer things
That could send an already stress industry
Into implosive
Decline
And the blast radius
Extend far beyond
The West Coast ports
12%
Of US GDP
Roughly 2 trillion dollars worth of the economy is dependent on Goods flowing through the West
With that and you're literally gambling with the national economy
And yet
Little Maritime businesses Soldier on
Doing the work
Despite the corporate
Squeeze and the Darkness on the horizon
Just like all the rest of the companies
And unions
Make the supply chain go
Every time a ship comes in this like putting on a wedding
When you've got
A myriad of details
And you forget one
And
It's just
Awful
You got to notify the Coast Guard and Order of Longshore Gangsta unload ships and
Line handlers to tie the big boat up
Tugboats in a bar pilot
Pilot the cargo ship into the bay dressing movements
The Tugs
Bishop shows up
12 miles west of the Golden Gate Bridge a pilot will board
And take it in
2 into the bay all the way to its birth
Learn about the business I wanted to see what the actual work was
I just work get accomplished
What's a tugboat do
And he got me in a boat called the Patricia Ann
Will is the skipper of the Patricia Ann
Our job for the afternoon is to guide a medium sized container ship called the cap Palliser
Off the dock and out of the Oakland shipping channel
It's tied up at Birth 59 of the Oakland Container Terminal
It's a pretty standard to Tugboat job
We'll be pulling it off the dock taking it up to the Turning Basin turning Basin spinning it around and
Pipe getting released somewhere along the Inner Harbor
Ship up here by the stand
The industry
It is
Enormous
By any other standard
We cruised past the cat Palliser and we'll Snuggles the tug up against the dock to await orders
Waiting for the call
We look at it the big Oakland International Container Terminal
One of the busiest terminals on the West Coast
There's stacks of boxes bearing the name of the big Shipping Lines
Maersk
MSC
CMA CGM APL
Costco
It used to be that individual lines operated ships and their own terminals
Now what it called stevedoring companies run these places
Leasing the land in the Port of Oakland and servicing a bunch of different ship lines
This particular one is run by SSA stevedoring Services of America the guys unloading the ships are all members
ILWU the Longshore Union
What was looking out at
Is it huge and highly diverse slice of the working class
Call Doug
Angotti and good afternoon
And Patty so wanted to turn will have you a question on the four battle once we make art
We have a line on our tag that attaches to a line on the ship container ship
The tug stays attached on these ropes
Very very strong
Peanut partially woven
Kevlar
Once this line gets up we'll get receive a signal and then what I'll do is I'll come back and push on the side of the ship so that they
Taking the lines in the ship will still be pressed up against
Longshoreman release the lines I'm sure to keep the ship from bobbing around
You often see tugboats in this position Fresh Step at a 90 degree angle to the ships are about to work
Now it's time to start pulling a cat Palace or off the dock
Easy way Packaging
It happens almost imperceptibly the ship is so huge and it moves so slow
Slowly and smoothly and it was so calm that was not actually sure what was going
Ship off the dock we power down to What's called the turning Basin the wide area of the shipping channel
Spin the container ship turned around to exit the bay into the Pacific Ocean
We pushing from the other side of this massive ship causing it to spin like a revolving door
Daddy
Incredible moment being right up against this thing
Crunch more or something to really feel like we were muscling it but it doesn't
Sound of metal straining Pawtucket hardly seems to move the water simply Parts in the wall
All of metal looming above us rotates the last
Get a ride alongside the ship as we head out the tugs active brakes to the big ship doesn't get going too fast
We're going alongside right now so some OC ships that are like if you put it in
Terms of a car their first year is like eight knots for 9 knots
So that's only 9 or 10 miles per hour that kind of speed and an arrow shipping channel
Can rock the other ships alongside the dock
Damaging them to the tugs dragged backwards on airlines
Stop and dry patio released to go home to take our line in
A couple of hours the most of the action takes place in just a few moments
Soon
We're back at the dock
The truck to begin streaming into pick up containers from another big ship
That come to shore
What bigger ships mean less business for the tugboats
It also put pressure
On the truckers
As a whole they need to pick up more boxes
And they still only have the same amount of time about
4 days
Clear the containers out of the terminal
That creates a bigger trucker demand Spike
Causing congestion around the court
In other words
If you were bigger ships
Makes the water to empty
In the land
Too crowded
Who is Sharon Oakland
Some places have done very well in the mega ship error
In general the China One port
Has been increasing
Centralization
So
Imagine a map of the world
Wood lines connecting differ
Imports
In the sickness of the line represents how much stuff gets shipped along that route
In a free container day
Should be lots of skinny lines going all over the place
Is containerization too cold in 1970s
And later China enter the WTO in the 90s
The lines connecting China
To a few ports on the west coast get really fat
Swallowing up other trade
The way it played out in the US
Is it the San Pedro Bay
Which is were the competing but connected ports of Long Beach and Los Angeles are located
Begin to dominate everyone
In 2015 for example these two Port handled 78%
Are the import containers along the west coast
All the West
Sky Sports
62% Imports came from China
Dinner 50%
All the import trade from Asia to the West Coast is just running back and forth
From San Pedro Bay
China
I end up talking all this over in a conversation with Tim Wong
Berkley educated lawyer and local polymath who published the container gajda
Wonderful little book on the shipping industry disguised as
The Dockside
Companion to spotting boxes
Imports
Azan ships he said
Everything has become a lot size
Efficiency
Can you get big enough to stay alive and keep your whole Maritime business ecosystem healthy
Oakland was able to survive for
Period of time
Technology gets better
The cost of choosing one poor or
On
The Western
Rat the office
I'm in the same trouble that's happened
With the Container company
Where they're basically selling
Commodity
Which always is dropping
Overproduce capacity
In ways that completely
Lee Drive everybody
Or make it so that only the large
Just company thickens
Jaime pennies out of
You know huge numbers of transaction
Actually can survive
And I wonder you know food
Accurate time basically
Geography
Esports
Backin it up all the smaller Regional One
Much larger
But as both get
You know more efficient
Way they move
Suddenly
They basic
Pee on the same footing with
Sports
Ends in there than geography
Does it help you anymore
Like what we're really trying to help you with
Can you really scallop
Maybe Oakland
Expanse
Across the world
More and more businesses centralizing if fewer and fewer ports
Anything need to maintain the whole ecosystem of services like tug boats and all that stuff
The import game is never going to be that much bigger for Oakland at this point
But they might be able to scale up their exports
That's because geography remains important
Think of it almost like a watershed for cargo
A cargo ship
If you will
Oakland naturally drains
The whole Central Valley
Not to mention Napa and Sonoma
Which are some of the most important agricultural region
Country
So the port officials
Want to expand on that strength
Building a huge refrigerated facility
That would allow Midwestern meat producers to put their pork on a train
Isn't it all the way to the ocean
Teleport
From there
It shipped out to China
You end up with this capitalist
Virtuous circle
Deficiency of global Shipping
Allowed for the production of electronics and all kinds of other stuff in China which helped create their middle class
And now that virgin group of wealthier Chinese people
End up importing
American Goods
Driving around
But that only works if American Producers can send those goods to China
Prenup in a trade War
Does pork and wine exports
99percentinvisible is Avery Chapman
Katie Mingle
Kurt koester
Turn Mazza Delaney Hall
Sharif Youssef
Fitzgerald Sean real and me Roman
We are project to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produce
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland Calif
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
It's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again
Again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us are on Twitter Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com