99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
The world each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled an annuity
Who discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
And this is the sound of
Well. I'm going to play U2 sound and if you're old enough
You'll be able to identify it right away
That's the sound of a brand new cassette tape being unwrapped and put into a cassette deck
That's my friend and fellow radiotopia and Benjamin Walker he hosts the show Theory of Everything and he's definitely old enough
You know that sound
Yeah well so are you pal
Benjamin is sitting in a car a car that happens to have a tape deck
With andreea heart who works with these sub pop record label
Started doing
Every release you're not familiar with subpop it's kind of this small but between money record label that is signed to the best
Indie bands in the last 30 years
Nirvana sleater-kinney
Postal Service beach house
And Andrea has a job at sub pop that a lot of people might not imagine exist
Any modern record label
I work at sub pop records
Cassette printer
It's crazy as something of even held
Look at that in my head
For a long time
This job handling cassette production at some pop it disappeared completely for a while
The recently record stores and Distributors have been requesting sub pop to release their titles on cassette
And sub pop asked Aundrea to oversee the operation
2000 +
Teen
The plan is
For every
Your release is
To get a
If to get a kiss at release
I don't like this. It for the sake of it and it's clear to me why two sets of been replaced now a couple of times over by more
More convenient medium
Mediums where you can actually skip tracks
And you don't have to rewind when you're done listening
But I do think they're a lot of good things about the cassette
First off
You can fix a messed up cassette
With some patients
Pencil
Plus
There's never been a better way to make a mix
You can have a tape floating around on the floor of your car per year
And then throw it in your tape deck
And it sounds great
Well it's not okay and never really found a great
In any case
Subpop is betting that some of us will want to hear our favorite albums on cassette
Again
But
There is one population that never stop listening to music on cassette
That's filmmaker Alex Lambert we've been working together on this story
Actually I'm just going to hand it over to her now
The United States prison system has the largest prison population in the world
And when the more than 2 million prisoners in this country have access to music
It's often on cassette
Will my number 132 Chief around here is
My Walkman
My Chase
Legal papers
SF bottled water
Do they have everything together
That's Adolfo Davis at 14 years old he was involved in a gang-related shooting he was tried as an adult and sentenced to
To life in prison is 39 now and he's serving his sentence at Stateville Correctional Center in Illinois
Listening to music on tapes is one of his only means of Escape
I made it so far because I have a good imagination is
I just closed my eyes to my earbuds
I just be gone
In 1990 the year Adolfo was incarcerated
Everybody was listening to music on cassette tape
Adolpho had some with him when he went to prison
Is
Big Mike's
Yeah when I leave for sale drugs I have a fanny pack
And I have my Walkman in my fanny pack with my taste
It obvious to the Walkman while watching out for security for the police
A fanny pack
Couch but
Just a few years after Adolfo was locked up the cassette tape would be all but replaced by the CD out here in the
The Free World
Put in prison
The cassette they've gone
I need to order cake
The younger generation that I can talk to
And not just any old cassette tape is allowed in prison require a very specific type of
Cassette tape has to be clear it has to be
Sonically welded so it can't be taken apart and put back together
And the box that goes in has to all be also be perfectly clear
That's deep step
Owner of National Audio company America's pre-eminent manufacturer of cassette tapes
The reason you can't have a 5 screw cassette
Or maybe a colored cassette that's opaque
Is they don't want
Does a razor blade are Narcotics or something else to be enclosed in a cassette
They do have people in the correctional facilities who
Look at and inspect incoming materials and they have to be able to see through or they won't allow them at
Steve has gotten familiar with this subfield of cassette tape manufacturing even though it is not the focus of his business
Mostly he makes normal cassette tapes for a number of different markets
Music labels spoken word audio books
See's factory in Springfield Missouri produces both blank tapes
And tapes with audio already on them
Machines Kool-Aid all those parts together
Transfer the cross on a conveyor
And then wrap them with cellophane and put at airstrip in
Steve was one of the first people in the cassette industry
And he's one of the only people still in it
We're the only people I know of most of the people left in the cassette industry are
Mom and pop shops are small operations
If you purchase a cassette recently from anywhere
RadioShack are from the merch table of some pump and you just so live it probably started out in Steve's Factor
His company ships out up to 100,000 cassette today
Any small number of those cassettes are special orders for prisoners
Made with clear plastic and without screws
Once the tapes leave here we don't really see where they end up
As for why cassettes have stuck around in prisons all these years
It's hard to get a definitive answer
Because every prison is different
But there's one Theory we heard from a few different people
Tapes are allowed because CDs are easier to weaponize
They say that
It's the most safest way
For them to listen to music through the CD you can break and maybe cut somebody with
That's Chris Barrett this Abraham was recorded a couple years ago for a short film
Chris used to run a service that help families send packages to people in prison in New York state
Get a warehouse full of items that had already been approved by the prison authorities
Everything from food
Clothing
Boxer shorts
Gazette
Instead of CDs
Three never really understood the logic behind it
They let me sell
Tuna fish cans
That
You know you pull off the top
And that thing is metal like
Much more dangerous and a CD is my point
Tuna fish canned india
I don't know why bae
Come up with some of the rules and they come up with we just try to stay
Within those guidelines
Chris whose package sending service recently went out of business
Also sold a lot of cassette Walkman
Walkmans used to be available for purchase in prison commissaries
They generally heart anymore
Which makes them extremely coveted items
Max my Walkman break I'm out of there so I'll take good care of it
Blinky lights
And wear-and-tear is not the only threat to the life of a Walkman
But when it's like amazing shake down and they bring other officers from other institutions
They will just break your TV break your radio
Take those cheesy take your radio take your cassette tapes
Washington
Destroy my Walkman
I cannot get another Walkman
This is probably one of the most prized
Items
It'll try to hold out as much as they can
Singapore checked in as much as possible
That's efren paredes Jr
He was a fifteen-year-old honor student when he was tried as an adult on a murder charge
And sentenced to life without parole he's always maintained his innocence
Efren is 43 now and during his 28 years in prison he amassed a pretty big collection of music
Call my favorite Kendrick Lamar
I like Young Jeezy Rick Ross
Meek Mills
I like Lil Wayne
At Muskegon Correctional Facility in Michigan where Ethan is serving his sentence
Prisoners can actually have MP3 players
Inmates can purchase an MP3 player through the prison commissary and then download music to it through a kiosk provided by
Company called access entertainment
Before downloading the app to transfer money to the company and receive a credit for a certain amount of songs
But there's a catch
Michigan there's a policy that
They try to restrict as much
As much music
What do
Labels at parental advisory
In other words the state of Michigan will try and sentence a 15 year old as an adult
The winning becomes an actual adult
State won't let him purchase music deemed inappropriate for a teenager
It's interesting that you know that the Department Corrections has never
Taking any steps to restricting
Cassette tape purchases
We couldn't confirm that there were no restrictions on cassette music but efront hasn't encountered them
And that's why he says a lot of inmates still prefer cassettes
They listen to them all the time on their personal walkmans and sometimes out loud
Actually as long as we're talking right now
A gentleman in the bathroom
Washing clothes
What is radio on
Playing
The song play at your own risk
Writer needs a part of the prison or Ephraim is locked up is the one that houses the prisoners in solitary confinement
Who is here guys all the time yelling up to music
Rick Ross
Turn on Meek Mills
This what they been waiting for
You know something so they can hear down there
Something
Music from upstairs
I used to pray
Times like this
So I had to
I like this in a matter of
Time I spent
Patty wagon
Prisons tend to be late adopters of technology so maybe one day all prisons in the US will just make the switch from cassette
To digital
Or maybe they'll go to CDs first at the beach
The logically chronological
Whatever the format the most important thing about music to Efren and Adolfo
Is escape and connection
Here's Adolfo again
Music
Allowed to escape from this place
I can't I can't
Do without my music in a day
I bought Walkman with somebody else
Slot go to sleep
The days that you don't have you
I play my Walkman like 3 days then I'll let it rest like 2 days
He rests his Walkman
That is love
99percentinvisible was produces week by Benjamin Walker and Alex Lambert with Katie mingle Sam Greenspan Sharif Youssef
Pickles that Delaney Hall Avery troubleman and me Roman Mars
The audio you heard from Chris Barrett the guy who sent packages to prisoners
What's from the film the prison in twelve Landscapes by Brett story
For more information about where and how to see that film go to prison Landscapes. Com
Special things to Elyse blennerhassett she introduced us to both Adolfo antifa
Slightly different version of this story will air on Benjamin Walker's Theory of Everything
Benjamin is one of my oldest friends and radio and you should definitely be friends with him too
But in case you don't already listen
This is one of my favorite Clips Miss program that has a little bit more Benjamin Walker in it
There's this painting
That I keep with me
Always
It's one of those little postcard reproduction
I've even made a gold frame for it out of balsa wood
The painting is called
The artist
In his Studio
It's by John Singer Sargent
I brought it with me here to the studio
I have it right here in front of me
Propped up next to the microphone
The painting
It takes a Man painting a picture in his Studio
But this artist studio
Is not an ordinary Studio
It is the artist home
The man has his painting propped up
On the bed and the bureau
There is no easel
You get the idea that
The only things in the room are the bed the bureau
And the chair upon which the name Sid
The man is confined to extremely small quarters
The setting is grim
And it contrasts with the painting that the man is working on
Alliance k
The man is painting a landscape
Horses Meander through a soft Green Meadow
And the trees are Lush and full
The Blue Horizon is dotted with clouds
Most Sergeant commentators dismiss this pain
They consider to be nothing but a silly joke
An artist painting landscape it is cramped doleful bedroom
But I consider this painting
Because it captures the idea that through ART
Man is able
Transcend
Is this MO
Squaw
Surrounded
This painting
Is not a joke
This artist is not painting
A landscape
This artist is painting
A window
Look out this window for a moment
Here let me move out of your way
You'll find The View
It's breathtaking
I spend
My entire life looking for the way
To get to the other side of this window
I've Been Told
Time and time again
That I'm wasting my effort
But I've never given up
Always known that there is a way
The break the glass
In crawl
Over the window sill
Always been certain of it
And I made a vow
That I would never give up
Until I discovered
The secret
Your snickering at me
Well go ahead now
You think I'm crazy for believing that there
On the other side of this window
Well I'm not
The reality
On the other side
Is just as real as the one we stand in right now
Sometimes
I think
It's even more real
But we do not have to go into that now
I have not brought you here to this window
Discuss the metaphysics of reality
Brought you here to this window
Because
I need your help
UC
I believe
Finally
Discover
The secret
So I'm going to go to the other side of the studio now
I need you
Ted Leo down here and in the front
I'm going to count to three
And on three
I'm going to run towards you
And you are going to
Lift me
Into the air
You're going to
How to fold me
Through
The window
Kennewick
With your help
I'm going to break the glass
Everland
On the other side
Stop
On three
Who
Call
That's the introduction to something will happen soon
And episode from Benjamin Walker's Theory of Everything
Radiotopia
39% invisible is a project of kalw 91.7 in San Francisco
Signs of arcsin in architecture and Interiors firm and beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives
Routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
Got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast oh my God
Black podcast
You can find a show and like the show on Facebook and Twitter and Instagram the best way to explore
90% invisible activity that shapes the design of our world into spending as much time as possible
Epi.org
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that.
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an actor
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast. Com