99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options.
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When January 3rd 1979
Two officers from the Los Angeles Police Department went to the home of Eula Mae love
39 year old
African American mother
The officers were there because of a dispute over an unpaid gas bill
We have been called we're home by the gas company because she had hit the utilities bill collector with a shovel
This is Love was overdue with her $69 payment
The officers approached her
In the encounter quickly turned violent
Love allegedly threatened the officers with a knife
They fired 12 times and killed
Her neighbors in Watts
Couldn't believe it
They could have subdued this lady without using the weapons that they used they could have took her alive
Plain and simple
Cuz two cops against one lady with a butcher knife
Neither of the two offices involved with Prosecco
The Killing
That's George lavender
Criminal justice reporter at KCRW in Los
The shooting sparked protests
I'm calls for the resignation of the chief
Police
In the month
Blacks and liberals
The become intensely critical
Love what they charge is excessive use of force
By the Los Angeles Police Department
The American civil liberties union says that in the last 4 years officers here
Have shot over 300 people
Killing nearly half of it
Even though police shootings have been happening for years
And of course
Still happening today
The killing of you love received a lot of media attention
That put pressure on the department to respond
Los Angeles Board of police Commissioners recommended changes to training
And the way shootings by offices where investigate
In The Killing also led the department to research non-lethal weapon
To see if there was some alternative that might reduce the lapd's Reliance on guns
We needed to find a way to
Control people
Was there something that we could do
Before we had to shoot them before they had a knock
Opportunity to attack
Can you get shot that's Greg Maya
He's a retired Captain with the LAPD and in 1979 he was given the job of researching
Non-lethal weapons for the
And what we were looking for
Was something that
Was
Effective
At subduing a person
So that they could be
Be handcuffed
Expeditiously without a big fight
Maya and the LAPD set out to find a new tool
They hoped would help avoid needless deaths
Hand injuries
The police chief at the time Daryl Gates
Told the Los Angeles Times quote what we need is that thing used to see in Buck Rogers
Nothing uses iPhone
Resume
Nothing
Ever since the beginning of policing officers have been looking for tools to subdue people that they consider threatening
When police first started
Patrol the streets of America cities
Mini carrot sticks
In nineteenth-century New York
Cops actually had to stick to choose from
Shortest dick for the day and a longer one for the nighttime
Because it was thought that more dangerous criminals would come out of the dog
That bigger stick became known as the knights deck
It's going by other names too
Billy club
Truncheon baton
By the early nineteen hundreds
Lots of police departments
Across the country what equipping that offices with guns
But nightsticks remind me alternative weapon of choice
In the 1960s that began to change
It was a lot of interest in using new weapons to control large crowds of people
Many of those weapons
Like tear gas
Came straight from the military
But some Police Department started using a new electrical web
The cattle prod
They're designed to move castle by providing a very focused
Pain on the body
That's dries rajabi
He teaches political science at Reed College
As written about the history of electrical weapons and torture
They're usually two electrodes separated by about two in and they provide a sudden sharp
Blaster
A voltage which moves
A person
To comply with commands
Please begin to use cattle
It's against protesters during the Civil Rights Movement
In addition to attack dogs
Sand fire hose
Cattle prods
Emerged in the hands of the Alabama
Police
As early as 19
And by 19
64 they had B
Become
Quite common and also quite
Contentious
Because people objected to being treated like cattle
In 1963 a New York Times article described Alabama highway patrolman using cattle prods on a group of
American Freedom Walker
The Times Reporter
Quote
As one of the Negroes
Splinched and twisted in the grip
Of the four Troopers
An elderly toothless white man shouted from a roadside pasture
Stickum again
Stickman gun
In quote
People were offended
By these stories and images
Proponents of electrical weapons
We thought they were better than bludgeoning people with sticks
Better of huge amounts of electricity
The Knockout blow on the head
That's Richard Doherty
Former deputy Police Commissioner of New York City advocating for electrical prods
On ABC in 1968
What is a knight
It's a club
It's no stick
It makes the cops
Look like ugly Primitives when they use the same
And it makes the people who get hit
As well as the thousand
To watch sex scenes on television
Hate the police more than before
Now why does this happen
Why in this age
Science
And alleged enlighten
Dwyer police
After use a weapon that is right out of
The Stone Age
Is it turned out an inventor named Jack Cobra was thinking about these
Questions to
Instead of a weapon from the Stone Age
He wanted to create one right out of the space
But whether it would be any more enlightened
Is debatable
Covet work as an aerospace scientist
I have been involved with masses
Apollo program
In the late 60s
As images of protest
Police violence
Saturated the Nightly News
Cova came up with an idea
A weapon that would temporarily immobilize a person
At a distance
Using electricity
For several years Cova work to develop this device
And finally he created something net worth
He named his new invention after a science fiction novel from his childhood
It's called
Tom Swift
And his electric rifle
In the book
Tom Swift Electric rifle is a lethal device the five bowls of electricity that can pass through walls and penetrate
Koba's electric rifle on Amazon
Was intended to be non-lethal
Something that could be used to incapacitate a person
Without injuring them
Janine the weapon
Cobra took the initials from Tom Swift Electric rifle
T ser
And then he added an a
To make the word easier to say
Taser
Space-age weapon does not kill
It's called a taser
It looks like a large flashlight
You shine the beam to light up the target pressure switch and it fires
Best way to use the small gunpowder charge
Defy the two metal.
The gunpowder it meant that some of the early tasers
What categorizes
Espira
Which would have to find wires
Broward County 50000 volts the time
When both darts hit a Target
Electricity would flow along the metal wires
What's causing the muscles
To tense up involuntarily
Bible describes hit clothing
And send a charger temporarily paralyzes muscles incapacitating the attacker
Drive right through the clothing they don't have to penetrate
The cattle prods Police Department
Had been using
Delivered painful jolts of electricity to make someone move
The taser on the other hand
Use electricity to immobilize them cover patented his weapon for immobilization and capture in Maine
Thought about approaching police departments across the country
To see if they were interested in buying his invention
But he didn't get much traction
June 1st
It's important to recognize that
In its early days
Police were absolutely not interested in this weapon
They could imagine what would happen if a if
I think I believe the line was
A crazy hippie grab the end of a taser and wrap it around the neck of a policeman with all this electrical
Wire nobody wanted to go near it with a ten-foot pole so, try to find other Baez
Like Yami
But that didn't work out
He then tried the airline industry
He wanted to create a
Light
Device one that could be handled by a female stewardess
Incapacitated with
Butera's
Our hijacker
In those days
But Airlines ended up addressing their hijacking problem with the introduction of metal detectors and x-ray machines that screen passenger
Bears and their belongings before they got on the plane
Kovac at tweaking the design of his taser
And shopping it around to potential customers
But except for a handful of small police departments
You didn't have much
Success
Then finally
In 1979
Found a good man
One of the biggest police departments in the country
The LAPD
As it turned out the taser seem to be exactly what the department have been looking for a device the police could use to quo
Zap em freedom and stop them handcuffed expeditiously
Without a big fight
Since the killing of you love
Greg Meyer at the LAPD have been searching for an effective non-lethal weapon
Respondent looked at things like chemicals braids
Bean bag rounds
Sandra Bullock
They also looked at all kinds of contraptions
Including
Nets
And something called the action control chain that was very complicated
LAPD even spent a day at the Los Angeles Zoo
To see if it might be possible to use
Tranquilizer.
They're not ready then and they're still not ready now for
For him and you
Too dangerous
Too many too many animals die when tranquilizer guns are used
And that's when they
They already know the animals diet
Waiting
Habits came along with his taser the department was intrigued
The first Meijer needed to see how it might work
My job was to figure out okay is it really a good idea does it really
Work in real life on the street not just enough
Testing environment that in
Real police situations out there
So the LAPD took the taser out onto the streets of South Los Angeles and began to test
Actually using it
On people they were trying to subdue and apprehend
A first device didn't do what the police wanted
And so they asked over to increase the power
Which he did
And then they took it out for more testing
And within within just six
10 days
Yeah we knew we had a winner
The LAPD put in an order for several hundred cases
And other police departments would soon follow
Today tasers are a huge business
Almost all tasers used by police in the US are made by one company
Taser International
Kelly by Two Brothers Rick and Tom Smith in the early 90s the company work with covert uak
Expand on an original invention
Over 80% of all law enforcement departments in the US
Now use tasers
When Jack Carver died in 2009
His wife told the New York Times
They believed his invention have saved a hundred thousand lives
Of course the story of tasers is way more complicated than that
One thing it's tough to save tasers have or have not save lives
Data on both police shootings and taser used are notoriously unreliable here in the US
And even if they're not designed to be lethal
Taser still produce an incredible amount of pain
I know that first-hand because it back in the summer of 2015
I volunteered to be tasered
When I get to drive for this Drive Hiram
I met up with two taser instructors who what for the Los Angeles sheriff's department
Deputy Chris aldana and Deputy Ed Clark
Most of them are being tasered
4 and they tell me
The only thing I have to worry about is ruining my shirt
It's going to get blood as getting ahold
Romanticizes used by the LA Sheriff's Department have changed a lot from The Middle
First developed by Jack Kirby
4 *
They look much more like guns
The one clock is holding his hand looks a bit like a pasta
Sex toy gun
Black with yellow stripe on the side
Modern tasers also use Compressed Gas instead of gunpowder to fire
Which means are no longer considered firearms
The basic function has remained the same
When it's fired both darts have to connect with the target to form a circuit
Each teaser cycle typically last
5 Seconds
Thought you'd lay down right so I don't fall and hurt myself they asked me to lie down
As I get onto the floor if I want to be able to
Tap out early
Meaning stop the electric shock before the 5 seconds are up
I think I might tap out then
Then I'm happy to go shorter
Then clock raises the weapon and points it at my back
Taser Taser Taser
I lost it
For about 2 or 3 seconds
For I had to tap out
More than enough time to know that I wanted to do whatever I could
To make it stop
I think what I remember most was just
Nothing else focus on anything except
The feeling
And my back or across my body
Photos
2 seconds
It felt like my entire body with out of my control
It was the most intense pain I've ever experienced
After George had recovered the instructors had to pull the taser barbs out of his skin
Twist and pull
Really the only Medical Care to be rendered is
Abandoned
So it's not a it's not like a
A big hug that's going to tear a hunk of
The Flash
My back was sore for a few days
I took about a week
The puncture wounds to heal
But the memory of the experience
Stayed with me for longer
I kept replaying it over and over in my head
Several weeks
Soft words
And the fact is George had it
Easy
Most people get tasered don't do so voluntarily
They don't have the option of
Tapping out when they got enough
In the real world
Effects of taser
Can be much worse
Texas and now referred to as
Lethal Weapon
Rather than non-lethal
That's an acknowledgement that any weapon can be fatal
Even a blow from A Knight's Tale
Can kill someone
There is no use of force that is completely safe
According to a report by Amnesty International
Medical examiners have listed tasers
Is a cause or contributing factor
And more than 60 deaths in the United States
Between 2001
And a 2014 article in the Journal of the American Heart Association
Completed the taser could cause cardiac arrest
Taser International training materials Walnut its weapons can quote
Cause death
The company's release statement
Stressing that they are quote generally safe
After you will love death in 1979
The LAPD set out to find a new weapon to reduce their Reliance on guns
And improve their relations
With the community
But it's not clear that tasers are
Succeeding
Central Perk
Even in the majority of
This when they don't catch
A person's death
Do use of these weapons really drives a wedge
Between
The police
And the communities that they serve
These weapons
And seeing them deployed
Seems
On its face to be somewhat barbaric
Best Tom Nolan my name is Tom Nolan I'm an associate professor of criminology at Merrimack College in
Massachusetts
27 years I was a city of Boston police officer the teaser didn't solve the problem of excessive use
Sephora store police shootings
Besides some researchers have found that cops are reaching for their taser for too quickly
Leanne too often
Situations
But don't just
The more weapons we have of course the police are going to use them
That mean it's it's becoming the default compliance tool and well information on taser use across the
Apache
In several jurisdictions there's evidence that they're being used disproportionately
On people of color
Juveniles and people with mental health issues
In a 2016 Department of Justice report found in Baltimore Maryland
Police use
Tasers was often quote
Unnecessary
And unreasonable
Additionally the Baltimore Sun found that people were sometimes being tasered for longer than the 15-second limit Taser International
National recommend
In one case a black man named Anthony Howard
Was tasered 9 times for a total of
37 sec
He stopped breathing and died shortly after
Video of the incident shows that when Howard was
Tasered
He was standing still
Holding a child scooter
After he dropped the scooter and fell
Officers continued to shock
Places where it originally sold as a way to respond to dangerous situation
Like the kind where someone had a knife
Without having to resort to using a gun
But Nolan says
That's not how they being used
I think the concern that we should all have is that
Is that the police are using these weapons unnecessarily in situations where
Someone is just in as they say in the police World someone is funky attitude test
The real solution to the issue of police-community relations isn't a tool or technology
The alternative
To this is to
Is to initiate institutional change and cultural subcultural change in police agencies
That's something that is extraordinarily difficult to undertake let alone
Accomplish
Visit change we have tons
Even if it is
Ordinarily difficult
Because there is no match
Take bullet
99percentinvisible was produced this week by George lavender
Delaney Hall Katie mingle and she refused
Recruit Kolstad Avery trufelman Sam Greenspan Emmett Fitzgerald Taryn Mazza and me Roman more
More to the story originally aired on KCRW
So two things did Joe Dominic Matt Stroud and Brendan Baker
It's little things to melodeon and okay akumi
For their music
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexa's talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
Routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook who tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99.
Run Instagram and Tumblr to
Just want all the story The Full Experience of 99 pi
There's only one place to go
99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com