99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
And decodedc
Is a special joint episode between my friend here Roman Mars
It's election season as you know
And I found out we had a lot of the same questions about the political events
That are everywhere right now
Questions like
How much of a debate or a press conference is genuinely spontaneous
And how much is pre-planned
Who designed the theater of politics
Why do speeches in town hall meetings look the way they do
And what message are the campaign's trying to ask
With their design
Answer some of these questions
We tracked them to the most interesting people I've ever talked to
Solitaire
Let me ask them for their secret
Cigar number one
Every campaign has a brand
This is probably not a huge secret that anyone is paying close attention
It's more than just a politician himself as a brand is an abstraction that
Float on top of the human being that's running for office so
Obama in 2008 it was hope
And virami right now
I don't know I can't read
Put my finger on it
Tommy's brand is like a
Competent
This man who can bring back jobs
That is the message that the campaign is selling and every detail is arranged the market that brand
The politicians clothes how he walks what he says where he goes
A sense of humor
His wife
His haircut
His watch
Which brings us to secret number
Every campaign has a
Team of people
Who are in charge of making every event
Fit that brand
The called the advanced
Team
From campaign headquarters
They're giving a location
Update
A type of event
Donnie Fowler is a longtime Advanced guy he worked for Bill Clinton Al Gore John
Scary Barack Obama
Very much Democrat
And Fowler says that for every campaign event there's something you have to have on the stage
But it's a different thing in every place
Whether it's the flag
And I with a hay bale or
Nicole matter standing behind you in Ohio
Orange Beach Florida
The Naval Yard here in Virginia
So you want local color
You want sound of America
Americana
And you won't real people
The keys
She says is making the event look genuine
The politician look more human
Included relating to
Regular mirror
So you rarely are going to see
Even Mitt Romney
In front of a boardroom with a bunch of white guys in blue suits and red ties
His background to his benefit
To his credit
Is from the corporate Barbarian
That's not the kind of images you want to choose when you're when you're running for president
John Seaton a republican Advance guy agrees
Having a bail of hay or corn references
Something like that
Kind of gives
Clear the air
Somewhere awesome
Here in Iowa
Seton work
Republicans like John McCain
Sarah Palin Tim pawlenty
Injustice secret number 3
The advancing to run their campaigns pretty much the same way
Summer better funded than others
But they're all doing the same thing marketing their brand Day by Day event by event
Fowler says the advanced team
Flies into the event location a week or more
Before a speech
Torelli
20-minute event requires several dozen people
Campaign staff
Secret Service
They start from zero and work hundreds and hundreds of hours
Put together what might be that
20 minute campaign stop
The advance team is responsible for the staging of the event from the flowers to the backdrop
To the security and the audience
The first big decision is where to have the event
And that's the Feller can
So easily go wrong
Like in 2004
When John Kerry went to the key primary state of South Carolina to announce his
Candidacy
Pictures of Vietnam war hero and he gave his speech before the USS Yorktown
A massive aircraft carrier did the time seemed like a good idea
It's not fair
The crowd was Tiny
Especially in front of a huge aircraft carrier
And fair
Once and for all
Is a big lesson in this one
The Statler
Don't put the candidates in a situation where he looks diminished
You can't build a crowd
Economic speech this year where he put it in a football stadium
About the economy
I want to take the folks at 3 at Ford Field
After making this a space available for us I guess we had a hard time finding a
Large enough place to meet and this
Certainly is
The Republican Advance guy Seaton
Also talked about that Romney speech and he too says
Choosing a venue that
Two large
Can be disastrous
Immediately
Texas stadium
People tweeting and blogging about how
Support in this County because
Venue is
And then remember those week
The Plaza
The cameras pan of the empty Stadium will be played over
Over
And over again
Romney's campaign couldn't even fill all the chairs
In the audience
Secret number for is a corollary today
Every campaign these days send out
Spies I guess you
You could call them to every one of their opponents
In politics they're called trackers
Sissy
Gentilini motors have trackers from the other campaigns
Here's the half Secret
Advance staff
One candidate
Robin becomes
Friendly with the trackers of their opponent
I mean hey there in the same line of work
If each other
They're like
Well
Better luck next time
Timeout
Oh Sherrie
You can't win them all you know
Thanks
Nice day outside
To be alive
Secret number 5
Everything
Is staged
I cannot
Stress this enough
And the longer in advance an event is planned
The more granular that staging become
Take the debates
The Statler
So here's what you're seeing is not an extemporaneous debate
Between two
Very smart people
No it didn't
Credibly
Finally staged
Theater
Every little detail about that stage how they're standing
Is it
Litigated really
And if you watch carefully Sisseton
You can tell look at how the candidates
Each other what they're doing when the other person's talking
Then there are the convention
Also incredible dramaturgical feet
From the message of the speeches
The timing of the balloon drop
Even the chance of the crowd
The teams so spontaneous
Completely pre-planned
The campaign staff
Seton says each section of the convention floor have a campaign
Who receives instructions
Passed down from a central planner
And the website make sure that their sections are her chanting appropriately
Because left to their own devices a big group can become a big
Stupid mop like at the Republican convention this year when a bunch of people started chanting the USA
Preventing the committeewoman from Puerto Rico from taking money
Which actually brings us to secret number 6
No matter how carefully the Advance Team plan
Campaign events can and do go wrong
The biggest
Screw-ups
Acetin
Are totally self-inflict
I think everyone remembers
Turkey's being
It was supposed to be a pardoning of a Thanksgiving turkey
Palin's attempt to do a
Presidential event
But when she took questions from reporters she stood right in front of a slaughtering table
I was happy to get to be invited to 4
Participate in Miss
Panda
Behind her right now
Man is hoisting live turkeys
Into a cone
So he can slip their neck
Bleed them to death
You see this happening and
And it's just like
IFit overlap
Donnie Fowler remembers a fancy fundraiser for Bill Clinton's 1996 re-election campaign
Harvey Weinstein Paul Newman
Big fundraiser in Connecticut
And I was in charge of telling
Paul Newman Harvey Weinstein
Any my little earpiece
I heard
Where are you in the program
We are on our way
So I went to mr. Weinstein
It's time for you to go into this present into the room
Play Stand Up and they say how happy they are to be there and they say will you please stand up
Welcome
President Clinton's the room the doors in the back of the room open
Spotlight
The doors
Walk energy
He wants to look at me from the stage like what the heck is going on man
Tyler realize the wrong person have been
Talking in his ear piece
Let's get started we're on our way
He thought it was
Clinton's Handler
But it had been
Kenny G's
And that brings us to secret number 7
Everyone traveling with a campaign the advanced team that handlers probably even the candidate ends up loading
The music so do the reporters
We love America pop songs that every candidate has
Pain in the neck
God just makes me ill
Sometimes it's rock and roll sometimes it's country but it's inevitably
Fun upbeat pop songs
But you come to the stage and you leave the stage and workable plan with two
Sometimes got this song Only in America that makes hissing used by
Book party since President Bush in 2004
Patriotic mix
Growler both of them
Serious Political Animals
Told us they do not miss that
We on for years
So Seton Fowler I can't remember who's the Republican and who's the Democrat
Doesn't matter
Putting on
Same show
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Andrea Seabrook Lina misitzis Sam Greenspan Hemi Roman Mars
We are project kalw NAIA San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secret scroll dinner
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Iceland episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcasts and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and your sister
Routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms
Please come back again and again and you don't know why but it may be time to seek help go to oh my God
Got. Info / podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info
Podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us run Twitter Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Putting cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that car
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an actor
The movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com