99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
If you've ever wondered what
Squirrels
We're good for
Besides being adorable
Wonder no longer
These are
Lettering quills
Brushes I was talking about and they generally are squirrel hair that Scott Theisen from New Bohemia signs a world-famous
Hand-painted sign shop
In San Francisco
And have
Pretty long very thin handles
Petroleum
Or Das
Any movie made before 1980
Campaign signs everywhere
Would see like a certain type of an A or a certain type of an S being repeated and all the difference
Signage in certain neighborhoods
The first time for me
I realize there was actually a
Job that was a sign painter
It's not as common a job these days but sign painting is still thriving in According to some of the voices you'll meet today
Even undergoing a kind of Renaissance
But let's start
With a cartoon
Not just any cartoonist one of America's original underground cartoon
Justin Green
My comic book Frankie Brown beats the only Virgin Mary
That's my best known work and I did
Is a young man
I can't seem to shake a little faster
I got to see Justin speak last year at this fancy academic comic book conference in Chicago
And he gave me a book of his sign painting,
Reporting right there is our friend Benjamin Walker
The way Justin Green tells it is one night his wife asked him how he was going to pay the bills
And he said
I'm a cartoonist
And she said I know but
How are we going to pay the bills
But an artist entering the sign painters world
Had to tread
Carefully because to tell you the truth
Oman
Harbin sign colors
The word artist
Is 8
Pejorative
Mechanic is the term they use
Justin came up with an ingenious way to have it both ways
He threw himself into the world of sign painting
Frantically
Reading technical manuals written in the twenties
Work learning
On the job
Gathering tips from the Elder Statesman mechanic
Any documented all of his adventures in a comic strip
Called sign game
But the best thing about these trips is that Justin actually teaches us
How to book
An old hand-painted sign
I literally did that I mean I would stand in front of these old sunburned signs
Leica history Detective
And I would see how good the Craftsman
If someone was a fledgling or
A drunk
UC
Lawsuit
Brush work around the tricky parts
Like an oval
Play old-timer was done in about 4 Strokes amazingly
Although I can use
50 spokes too
Skin the ballpark
But at that point you're
You know you
You can't make a living
So you very quickly you learn
How to coordinate your eye in hand
Is mind-blowing to think about what was done by hand in comparison to let me know how things are done now
That's Faith Levine she just co-directed a movie about sign painters and also wrote a great book with a guy named
Making my name is face reveal
Justin Green to tell a story
About a group of people
Who used to be in charge
How are
Letter forms were
Ideal for a barbershop
And you're not for restaurant
Sometimes I think the most
Design signs are the ones that we don't even notice like a No Parking sign are the street sign that tells how to get away
And so you know we got a lot of really amazing stories about
People getting job lettering all the street signs for an entire city at back in the day
Stand-alone trade-in industry that employed
Thousands of people
That had a direct impact on or hand in
Define commercial landscape
All of the sign painter Sam and Faith introduced us to our unique
But as a group
A consistency to these unique individual
Their characters for like or as
Anyone
In the song for you
It's a little bit nuts
We got some wild stories many of the sign painters use their painting skills to crisscross the country
Bob Dorr says that
He could just show up in a town on a Greyhound bus
Sleep in a field
And the painting a sign
The next day
It seems you can't be a good sign painter
Unless you're also
A good Hustle
You got any business that opens you walk in and I'm going to make people come into your shop
Because I'm going to paint the sign that people are going to walk by stop look at income in the door because it looks so good
At the heart of the sign painter hustle is a promise that whatever you have me put paint on a wall of Sandwich Board
Side of your truck
It's going to make you
Us both
Look good you want to make sure that this truck stops traffic
But the thing is there was never just one guy doing the sign painter Hustle
Sign painting with competitive
It was very very hard to break into the business
It's like you couldn't get hired if you didn't have experience but didn't want to hire someone with experience cuz I didn't want them to take all the jobs
I really had the time to earn your stripes or talking about
A minimum of two years experience to even
Call yourself you know
Cuz I may not even that could be debated need to have the necessary knowledge
How to
Form the letters
Lay out the wording certain kinds of informational signs
Illuminator Foreman
Inappropriate
That knowledge needs to be disliked
So bacon
But you can then apply it hanging off the side of a building
In the winter
Painting class
It really is an arduous training
Physically
Ensign game strip Justin Green tries to help us understand
Why things used to be done a certain way
In one of his Comics he explains why sign painters didn't like to use the color yellow
He require double coating and Faded easily
But in every single one of Justin greens Comics you get a sense
That he is scrambling to document a world that is fading away
I feel compelled
Do the song game as a historical piece because I knew the world around me was
Overnight
Sign painting is by no means the only industry that was
Wiped out by digital technology
But still I can't help but feel extra sorry for these guys because they got their butts
Buy vinyl
Specifically the vinyl plotter
Which looks kind of like a big computer printer
The vinyl plotters are
Machines that would basically Tap Out vinyl letters
You wouldn't program in you know welcome and then it would
Punch out the vinyl letters indeed weed out the vinyl with a razor blade and
Welcome letter is onto the surface
Of your sign
1 vinyl first appeared
No one
And yet for all intensive purposes
It was even better than a hand-painted sign because
It was perfect
It was of the same color
It would weather better than paint
For letting us because Window Washers were enemies
Its deductible
The vinyl plotter with something
Sign painters really like to have
In theory it was considered like
Undermining your brothers in the trade
Slowly the guards
Stubbornly cling to their brushes would call them
The guys who have the machines
When they got the chance
I'm just going to do this one
First hundred words
Before long
Everybody bought into it
By the mid-1980s sign painters
We're no longer in charge
It's a very
Simple
Story
Technology
Lower the bar to entry
You got people that are necessarily the most like visual people sometimes going into like a Kinko's
These are the words
And those words are printed out in the thing they could qualify to sign and that's what goes up
Songs
Girlfriends
But all is not lost for the sign painters
New and old businesses who want to advertise quality and craftsmanship of the items and services inside the store
Wanted sign that embodies that quality and craftsmanship
On the outside
And back in San Francisco at New Bohemia
Scott Theisen says business is booming
Since the past
Three or four years have been a Resurgence of
Especially designers really appreciated hand-painted signage
You know the way the letters flow on the brush
You can
Do slight things to
They just having something that's Hands-On hopefully we'll always be appreciated
The pendulum always swings back
And unlike the Cutthroat days of a Hustle
New Bohemia now teaches sign painting classes that consistent
Play sell out
And we don't view it as Creighton competition reviewing it as
More people
See that
You know what happened at sign looks like
More likely someone's going to want it
Heather Hardison is one of the young painters who took up the craft a couple years ago
And is now a journeyman painter
The New Bohemia
Damon who's the owner always says
It's not perfect it just looks really good and that and that lends to
What makes it beautiful.
That little wobble is
Gorgeous
99% invisible with produced this week by Benjamin Walker
And you know I'm Roman Mars
Talking about
Cities
And sign
How you say
Am I
Deep back
Observation
Blah blah blah
Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars
It's a project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and the American Institute
Dude of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy, go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and like the show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
But we have a signed game comic from Justin Green pictures from New Bohemia and a trailer
For the sign painters movie all at 99% invisible
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com