99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
You know when you notice something for the first time and suddenly it's
Everywhere
My friend Julie Shapiro has a thing for personified teeth
On dentist signs
With a cartoon tooth often as a smile and Teeth of its own
I always notice things now
That an ant more pies pigs were selling themselves as BBQ
That always gives me the creeps
And one day I noticed that sign store scene of the ones that print homemade banners and posters for you always without fail have the
Ugliest collection of signs with a horrible fonts in their front windows
Now I can't pass one on the street without taking a picture to document the ironic tragedy
Lots of things are like this for all of us on staff we can get obsessed with tiny little designs laurentia and this is what
Happened to producer Avery trufelman
It was just a
Shape a basic little shape
It's rendered in concrete on a building by my house
Its pattern in an office doorway down the street
Imagine
A simple stylized
Four leaf clover flattened
With no stem
Very symmetrical
I took a walk and I found this shape in 10 different places
It was embroidered on bedding with plastered on wallpaper
Was patterned in a public garbage can you'll see it anywhere you see
Great
Gothic Revival
The Cathedral of Saint John the Divine in New York
Washington Cathedral
You will also see it
In
Domestic architecture in the
Great as they're called cottages
It's down in Newport Rhode
Here in California it's a Hallmark of mission style homes
Expunge it just sucks up meaning
However
You wanted to be used
This is Christy Anderson
My name is Christy Anderson I'm an architectural historian and I teach at the University of Toronto
Talking about the quatrefoil
Cuz four leaf clover like shape
There's nothing that I can think of like the quatrefoil witch
Appears
In so many different
Forum
Over such a long period of time
It could be endlessly
Reinterpreted
Really understood
Which architectural and art historian
Sometimes referred to
Is iconographical drift
Constantly sort of shift
Depending on where it's used
Who's using at what purpose they're using it
But no matter where it's used
Implies the same thing
Fanciness
In this painting is symbol is very basic
To reiterate
The shape
Is
Like
Four leaf clover
With the in its simplest form
You can pronounce it the French way
If you would like
Meaning for leaves
But the American pronunciation works
It's hard to know for sure why the quatrefoil is the global fancy shape
There aren't that many resources on the subject
You know nobody's really worked on it
But Christy Anderson is a good person to connect the dots
I rummaged around I looked and I just started sort of thinking about it
Questions as weird as it come from
Pure out of now
Christy Anderson says it just by looking at the shape you can see it has roots in Islamic or Moorish architecture
That kind of organic shape
Comes out of a geometric
Forum
Almost
All of them have some kind of Islamic
Origins
Partly because
The great map
Magicians
Working on early Islamic art
And the quadruple made its way to Europe
The other Silk Road
Do small objects
Could be transported
With early carpets
Velvet
Silks
Broad and tiara
As Luxury Auto
When's the quatrefoil made its way to Europe
It was incorporated into tracery
Which is the stone framework for big stained glass windows
Quatrefoil shaped Stone frames were considered beautiful because the quatrefoil
With difficult to make
The fanciness of the shape
Is because it requires a certain amount
Mathematical skill but also craftsmanship
They could have used much simpler forms they could use Simple Diamond forms you're seeing something
Which really shouldn't be made out of
Hard hits
Colts forum
Stone Sour only appeared in places that could afford them like churches
And because it appeared in churches
This simple shape could take on Christian meaning
Just think of anything in the Christian tradition that comes in a set of four
Or a variation on a cross
It's a Greek cross with
Equal arms on all sides
I'm sure people who use the quad
Well now
Will not sit there and
Count to you
The two about this
Islam and metalwork involve all of this
If you Google the image you'll find a lot of modern interior designers talking about the trendiness of the quatrefoil
I was just amazed I found like about 7 interior designer
The quatrefoil is
The shape that I'm using it on my wallpaper at all these
What do they think they're doing
Schlage when they're doing
My name is Brooke Taylor and I am an interior designer at arcsine architecture
You work
Two desks away from me
Wework inside arcsin an Architecture Firm in Oakland
Brooke is designing the interior of a big hotel in Palo Alto
I asked her about the quatrefoil when I saw a picture of a quatrefoil shaped table
On her desk
I believe what you saw was an end table that were using where it's the barbed quatrefoil
And
It's basically the shape of the tabletop
Brooke says quatrefoil which is also a correct pronunciation
Interdesign for the lobby has a lot of quatrefoils in it
Mark Hatcher boils
Here's a rug that were using in the lobby that is literally overlapping patch
Boils and Brooke actually didn't do this intentionally I didn't even realize
Until well basically just now that that cash referral table is going to be on the
Overlapping catch well drug and close by there's also a chair with quatrefoil fabric just happened that way
Oil just has an appeal
It is
At Heart of very
Simple shape
But somehow there's just a formality to it
You can tell that there's a history behind the TV if you don't know what it is
You can tell that it
Out of History somewhere
And so to then take that and reinterpreted into a modern form
I think has a pill for
Four people for the way we see the quatrefoil in modern interior design is not referencing Gothic tracery directly
Surprise price
The quatrefoil shape first came back in style in a big way in the 19th century
During the Gothic Revival. In the Industrial Revolution was in full swing
People were seeking style inspiration from the pre-industrial era
And kind of harkening back
A simpler time
The Gothic Revival movement was also Around The Time Of The Addictive Mania craze
When new archaeological digs were
Popping up all around the world
It was all very new was like oh my God they
Discovered these tombs in Egypt and uncovering
Roman ruins in
Greek ruins
Bring all those influences in and also Reviving some interest in Gothic
Text designers were looking to the Past
And around the globe for inspiration
They travel
Photographing
Sketching
Digging into archives and collecting patterns Motif some shapes that they found inspiring
And they would publish these findings
In so-called
Pattern book
In the second half of the
19th century historian Christy Anderson again
There was
Flourishing
Of Architects and designers
Who created
Pattern book
Books of designs which could be used
By Architects Masons
Craftsman really in any field so didn't matter whether you were doing painting or tile work
These were
Cycling
Tedious of design of which the most famous One
Was the grammar of ornament
Which was published by man named Owen Jones
Owen Jones was an architect
Who took a special interest in ornament and pattern
I mean if you've never seen owen-jones as books they are so
Beautiful
Big book
His book
The grammar of ornament that has pages and pages of pure pattern
The most part
Colorful
Squares of
Pattern from buildings all over the world
India you've got
Chinese you have Moorish
Celtic Turkish tour
Wallpapers
Owen Jones book
So the transformed
The whole way in which design was created because now you had the
Annie's patterns
Which work
Leafly disconnect
From their original funk
They were just forms
Printed on the
Many of the forms across many of the cultures Jones documented
Work watches
Chick-fil-A
It was particularly Owen Jones's work
The grammar of ornament
Where the quatrefoil had
Very important
Place
Part
A number of different pages on
On ornaments
Repeated over and over again
And certainly
Spurred on the interest
And this
Forum
In the later 19
Dinnerly 20%
Designers still use these pattern books for inspiration
Down in the sea
60 yuan
Combat veteran
Renaissance
And it would seem that Jones succeeded in his mission for his butt
He hoped the grammar of ornament
Provide context and background for these patterns
And that they would be a source of inspiration which anyone and everyone could use
But today part of the quatrefoils fancy symbolism comes from the modern luxury brand that have associated with it
Many of which are clamoring to own it
Louis Vuitton had a lawsuit over use of the quatrefoil
Luxury jewelry David Yurman trademark the word quatrefoil
Another Jewelry Company Van Cleef & Arpels is fiercely litigious over its claim to the shape
There is a power about this simple form which is everywhere and it has no steady associations with any specific
The country or movement
This is what separated from other ornamental forms like the fleur-de-lis or even the swastika
The Middle Ages seriously their patterns Middle Ages in here
And you see the barbecue
How can you copyright that the best thing about the grammar of ornament are the pages and pages of beautiful pattern
But Jones is brief introduction is also really interest
Init Jones was 37 propositions for the creation of good decorative design
General principles in the arrangement of
Form and color in architecture and the decorative Arts
Witcher advocated throughout this work
I'm at the most people just skipped right over these and get to the pretty stuff
It's an interesting mix
Of statements
Annies Papas
Proposition for them
Philosophy
Absolutely
True beauty results from that repose
The minefields in the intellect any affections are satisfied from the absence of
If any wants
Extremely philosophical
And then you have something as basic as proposition
26 colors
Black round spider
But I think
Proposition 13
Unlocks the logic
Behind the inherent attractiveness of the quatrefoil
Flowers are other natural objects should not be used as ornaments
A conventional representations founded upon them
Sufficiently suggestive
To convey the intended image to the mind
Without destroying the unity of the object they are employed to decorate
Porta Translate
Baseball
Don't you put a bird on it designs don't necessarily look good
According to Jones the best kind of designs imply nature
Bookkeeping with composition
Ethical constructs
The quatrefoil is both geometrical and natural
But without being too floury
And this just might be what attracts designers to it over and over again
And keeps it forever floating around us
And iconographical drip
My boys were born and quatrefoil say building in Chicago the Prentice Women's Hospital at Northwestern
The whole building is in the shape of a quatrefoil as seen from above who's cool looking but according to the people at Northwestern
It was a pretty impractical shape from Modern Research Hospital
So it's been demolished
A lot of people including myself or sad to see it go
A safe princess group trying to get that building Landmark status
Petitions were circulated
The effort ultimately fail
But I think it's safe to say that no one would have cared at all
The building was not shaved
Like a quatrefoil
99% invisible was pretty sweet by Avery trufelman with Katie mingle same Greenspan and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And produce are the offices of arcsin a brilliant Architecture Firm in beautiful Downtown Oakland California
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology to make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
Family ghosts
Is a podcast
Explores all the unexpected ways are family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled a new Wii
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Fox podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us her on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go
299 pi
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com