99percentinvisible is brought to you by
By Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a
Explores all the unexpected ways are family
Structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's
Haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you go
The podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Tomorrow night 15000 ceiling fan for Pac-Man
How to prepare Garden in New York City the witness a giant basketball
You're not cheering crowd sitting in row C seat 11
Will be a mother
77 year old man
He made possible the game
Miguel going to beat him now
That tape is from an old New York radio show called We the People
The guest is James Naismith
125 years ago
Massachusetts
When a particularly bad snow storm struck
4 days the students couldn't go Outdoors
Show the begin rough housing in the hall
We tried everything to keep them quiet
Something had to be done
One day I had an idea
Call the boys to the gym
Divided them up into teams of nine and gave him a new soccer ball
I showed them to Peach basket side nailed up at each end of the gym
I told them the idea
Into the opposing team speech path
Eleven Sports don't have such a definitive
But this one.
I blew a whistle
The first game of basketball begin
That day in 1891 James Naismith
Invented basketball
And what role did you have for your new game
Dr. Naismith
Well I didn't have enough
That's where I made my big mistake
The boys began text
Kicking it
Punching in the country
They ended up in a free-for-all in the middle of the gym floor
In subsequent weeks Naismith would go on to make more rules for the game
Some of those are still around today like the one that says players can't run while holding the ball
They have to dribble a
Rule but it design decision that he made back in 1891
That continues to define the way the game is played
He had to decide how high
To hang the peach basket
That's Cari Champion she's an anchor at ESPN and host of the be honest podcast and she's going to help us tell
Story today Naismith chose to hang the peach basket at 10 feet above the porch floor
There was a running track that went around the court at that level but otherwise the decision was pretty random
And just a little higher or a little lower
And everything would be different
That arbitrary decision
To put the basket at 10 ft
Cause the game of basketball to take shape around the tallest players
But it happened gradually
In fact in the beginning the game was played by shorter less imposing players
In the very early days of the game
People didn't really have a conception of
Height having really
Any importance
Mets writer and journalist Andrew High School
It's a lot of the other hiscores
Very early days guys were like six foot tall
It was not until
A few decades in
That
Team started recruiting
Really tall guy
Send at the time they were sort of
Refer to often is goon
Nowadays if you play a little rough or dirty you might be called a goon
Back then big men were sometimes called goons just because they were big
The first so-called going to have a major impact on the game was a big white dude named George Mikan who played for the mini
Fabolous Lakers
From 1948 to 1956
He was a 6-foot 10 monster who wore big round spectacles when he played
Notice the comparative size of referee Ackman
Mike and towered over his opponents
Ambrose scoring records with his strength and accuracy
Mike and with such a force they actually had to change some rules in the game to offset his advantage
For example the rule against goaltending came about because it might
Goaltending is the active catching or batting away another player shot as the ball is on a downward passport
Basket
Mike and was so tall he could just stand under the basket and SWAT away Shots by the other team
Goaltending was banned in 1945
But rule changes didn't stop George Mikan or his fellow big man from dominating defensively and offensive
You start to sing people saying like it's too easy to score like they actually were really sort of disgusting
They thought this should be a Triumph
To get the ball in the hoop not something that happen
The ease with which these super-tall players could put the ball in the basket was alarming people
The traditionalist didn't like the way the game was going
But they had no idea
What was about to hit them
Bad dog
Sometimes called the slam dunk
The first one in organized game happened in 1936 but donkey didn't really get going in basketball
Until the 1960s
Amanda traditional is
They hated the duck
But not just because it was a new unconventional way to put the ball in the basket
The dump became political
The chi year
Is 1966
That's Matt Andrew
My name is Matt Andrews I teach American history of UNC Chapel Hill and I have a particular Focus
Champs Sport and Society
So it was in 1966
In the NCAA champ
Texas west
With an all-black starting five
Easily defeat Adolph Rupp
All white
This win by Texas Western against Kentucky was a big deal in the college basketball world
Kentucky was one of the last major college teams in the country
It still didn't have any black players
The coach of Kentucky for the guy named Adolph Rupp
Mini
Butte him as a racist
According to the sports correspondent Frank Deford who is in the Kentucky locker room that night
The language rap use against the Texas Western players
Send a chill down his spine
And there was this moment
Right at the beginning of the game
Where Texas Western David Lattin gets the ball
And makes a move toward the hoop
The defender in front of him is Pat Riley
He going to win nine NBA titles as a player coach and executive
In Latin
Flies over him
While he's like six foot for stockli belt
In Latin just
Rises above him and slams The Ball
Texas's Victory and Latins dunk were seen as Direct
Challenges to the establishment
After all this was 1966
There was a lot going on in America
Black Panthers have become invisible force
In Oakland the Panthers had armed and organized themselves to protect their communities from brutal racist police
How many white Americans were worried a Revolution was about to take place
Black Power
Was this new evocative free
So that the failure to pass the Civil Rights bill
Racism because of black power
Isn't because of the students
What's so interesting about this phrase is it's
Lack of specificity no one is exactly sure what black power
Adidas contact
Comes the duck and it seems to be black power manifest on the basketball court
The dunk
Is
Physical
Donk is
Forceful you know when you lay the ball in your laying the ball in but when you dunk
You're doing it too
Someone and at a time when so many white Americans
AR
Uneasy with the Specter of black
Violence
The dunk
Becomes
Suspect
Been to scare people like a tall frap even more comes a player called Lew Alcindor
You later changed his name to Kareem Abdul-Jabbar and become one of the most exciting and famous players in the history of the game
But in 1967 he was a young man
7 feet 2 inches tall
And already tearing up the college game with his vicious dunks in fast movement
Alcindor surrounded by white shirt
Unstoppable
So the NCAA
Betsy National Collegiate Athletic Association made a decision the only way to stop this guy with to get rid of the thing
Being heated best
The slam dunk
In 1967
They banned the dunk
And for 10 years
There's no dunking in college basketball
Lew Alcindor AKA Kareem Abdul-Jabbar who's not happy about this
In fact he explicitly said that the only reason for the band was because they were scared that black guys like him we're going to take over the
The game although he was much stronger words
Regardless
The slam dunk was done
In college basketball was sent back in time for 10 years
Basketball was in a bad place
The NCAA administrators had made an arguably racist decision to ban the slam dunk
Meanwhile in the professional League the NBA
Players can still dunk but fans were losing interest
Here's Andrew heysel again
This is
For the NBA
Considered like V
Low point
Of the week
They're all of these pieces written about how
The game is dying and nobody wants to watch in this all these
Questions about why
Naismith original accidental design decision
To put the basket at 10:50
I didn't Berkeley given us this beautiful and exciting slam dunk
But it also caused the professional game to revolve too much around these super tall players
The game just got jammed up around the net
People weren't passing as much
They just hand the ball to the giant guy and he'd stand under the basket
Trying to put it in
This had the effect of slowing down the play
And that slowness was draining the game of its excitement basketball
People suggested a lot of fixing
No backbone
Contacts backup
A smaller basket a bigger ball
A smaller ball I know scoring Zone around the basket
And even a hike app
Another group of coaches called for the hoop to be raised to 12 ft
None of those changes caught on
And then
This guy comes along
We feel that those people who are not
Under contractual
Navigation to
To remember George Mike the original NBA goon 6 foot 10 inches tall
Big round specs
Will a 1967 he was working as a travel agent in Minnesota or used to play
When you get a call from a couple of guys asking if you want to head up a new professional basketball league that would compete
With the NBA
What was old NBA friends have to say about his new job
Good luck
I mean it really was just started making up that you go on
It was
Simply what
Get an idea
And let's see what we can do here
That's Terry Pluto who wrote a book about the founding of this new league
They called it the Ada
The American Basketball Association
And George Mikan became its first commissioner
They were trying everything to get fans we engaged in a game
Sometimes they featured Cow Milking contest for entertainment
And1 half time show in Indiana
About the wrestling bear called Victor
Beautiful Brown
There looks to be
That he weighs at least five
Most of their ideas didn't stack
A lot of times good ideas are like that they're one of 12 things at
People suck
To the wall in and out of the 12-1 became really good
One helped a little bit and the other 10 are almost embarrassing
In this case one of the ideas was really good
In fact it's the design solution that arguably saved basketball
In the secret star of the story that were telling right now
The three
Point
Shot
So all you Sports
Smithfield we're all worth 2 points
But the aviators Innovation which they actually borrowed from an earlier defunct we
We should draw an arch line
About 22 feet away from the basket
In any shot made from behind that line
Was now worth
Three points
The ABA was trying to please the fan
Fans get excited when they see a 3-pointer
But they can also go and practice the shot at home
It's more egalitarian that's Ramona Shelburne senior writer for espn.com
If I practice hard enough
Don't have to be the most athletic guy in the car
I don't have to be
An incredible dunker it's it's something that when fans watch it they think I can do that too
In 1976 the NBA merged with the ABA and three years later they brought in
At first it was about pleasing the fan
But they slowly came to realize something about the three-point shot
When you study if you shoot
35% on 3-pointers
And you shoot
45% on 2 point
Just break it down
It makes so much more sense to
Build a team around 3-point shooting because
You're going to score more points and that's them
Point of the game
And now some teams have decided that the way to win
Is to concentrate
On three point shot
When NBA first introduce the 3-point shot
Games featured
Only a couple of 3-point attempts
This season
It's more than 10 times bad
And if there's any team that's demonstrating the value of the 3 point shot right now
It's the Golden State Warriors from California
And Mister Steph Curry
Hurry
You don't know who Steph Curry as he's about six foot three so he's short by NBA standards but this hasn't stopped him from being the
Star of the team end of the whole NBA
I think every kid growing up an American I was trying to be Steph Curry
He is
Skinny and
Doesn't seem to have anything physically dominant about him
And yet when you watch him play He's Alive
Curry can hit 3-pointers for Golden State
From really anywhere he likes which makes it hard to defend against them and balances the influence of the big men
Because of their guys like her who can score from
Anywhere
Then the 7-foot guys have to move away from the basket
Weather most useful
Could have been
And once you allow players to score an extra point from shooting further out the game spreads out
You got a whole new game
The game has changed for the better
Is no doubt about it
That's former Indiana Pacer Jerry Harkness
Harkness was a player in the NBA and the ABA
Because the game is exciting
The game
Is running shoe
Quickness
Defense
Opening the game up
Making it more grass
But even though the 3-point shot has had a balancing influence some traditionalists
Still don't like it
Penile leakage basketball
And like a circus sort of thing you know when we have a 5 point shot
7 point shot
Stop doing that sort of thing. Just old school that San Antonio Spurs coach Gregg Popovich
Speaking to ESPN about Steph Curry's Golden State Warriors last year
What Popovich is saying kind of Echoes what people said about the dump 50 years ago
That it's a trick
A departure from the fundamentals of basketball
And I kind of agree with Coach pop
But even Popovich seems to think that the 3-point shot is here to stay
Do certain degree you better embrace it you going to lose and every time we want to Championship 3-point shot was a big part of it
Instead of Designing the beautiful powerful dunk out of the game we designed a counterbalance
The 3 point shot
And now the game is more inclusive than it's ever been
You got these little guys I can shoot bombs from anywhere on the court
And there's still room for the big guys close in
The three pointer and the dunk and become the yin and yang
A basketball
All of this has sort of him by Acts
The 10-foot tall basket to dunk
The 3 point shot
But then again the game wasn't
Carefully designed in the first place
Really it came about because all James Naismith wanted
What's to stop some rowdy kids
I'm getting into too much trouble
And the whole thing
Started with a couple of peach baskets I put up in The Little Gym
48 years ago
I guess it just goes to show
What you can do if you have
Yep
Nope
Did it happen in one day
Yep never know what kind of
Yep
That's 99% invisible for this week this episode was a collaboration with our friends at ESPN in his part of a podcast
Launching later this spring called donkey Ventry's it's a collection of stories all related to basketballs
I am dog feed is live right now so you can subscribe to it on the ESPN mobile app for on iTunes or wherever you get your pain
Comcast on Twitter
At duncombe entries for more info
Joe Sykes reported and produced this story with us for ESPN with help from Ryan until in the Morgenstern
Determine Joe Fuentes and Kevin Wild
Thanks to Jody avirgan for Okinawa
Also check out Cari Champion's podcast be honest where she gets candid conversations with some of the biggest names in sports music in there
High School Story in Vice inspired the idea for the store you can find a link on a website
On the 99 Pi team Katie mingle did the heavy lifting on this one
What's in Greenspan Avery Elementary Kolstad Delaney Hall Sharif Youssef and me Roman Mars
We are production of 99% invisible ink on a project of kalw San Francisco
Use of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California
The one and only home
Of the Warriors
If you want to learn about another little game design Innovation that's the game of basketball
What's up number 77 of this program is called game changer
About the shot clock
Like it
Between the beat
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm
Listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and
Voice technology talk
To us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Npip
We need to talk about
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad
You take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
Ikebana show and like the show on Facebook all of us on Twitter Tumblr Instagram and Spotify but to find out more about
This story including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible you must go to 9
NPI
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really
We jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
On the truth podcast
Dot-com