99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that
Fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family Guy
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family cult
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stock
Love letters
Moon episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family Ford
25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The only time you should really rob a bank
Is on a Friday afternoon
. they're still needed to be a way to steal something and get it out of there
The Guiding principles you do not want to get caught
When I go into a bank
Especially effective stand in line waiting to make a deposit
My mind wanders
One of the first places that wonder is 2 in is how I would Rob the place
I look at the exits and entrances the layout of the building how could it be done
Most of the time
Buildings are our friends
It's fun to recast the building as the enemy
The obstacle we have to overcome
I guess it's a good thing we made our last Kickstarter goal the puzzle of how to get the money
Out of the bank is one that our culture has been obsessed with for a long time
The first recorded bank robbery took place in the 1860s and basically ever since we've been sued
Seduced by the idea of ice
People
I do them today will meet three people who all tried in their own way to beat
The back
With designs that go from a spectacularly complicated
Did the deceptively simple
Oh and one of them
Actually pull that off
Several times
Iced one
Mastermind
Los Angeles
So I'm alone agena number designer noticed I'm based in London my work
Relates to the idea that design could be a plot
And I think while I'm fascinated
Bye
Is a fact that it never has to happen so you have absolute freedom to find size about whatever you want
And with this in mind Gainer set out to make her Heist
Is big and calm
Cheated as
A sort of go-big-or-go-home style
And she was interested in the interplay
Hollywood movies about heists
In real life
This is really weird feedback loops that happened in Hollywood Hollywood being the intrinsic pool on everything
Thing that relates
To the iconography of a heist
So of course her highest had to take
Cake place in LA
There were years mostly in the 70s 80s and 90s
When La was accurately dubs the bank robbery capital
The world
A particularly bad years there were as many as
2600 bank robbery
That's roughly one robbery every 45 minutes
I've been working
People of conjecture about why this is
Inner thinks it may be the pull of Hollywood
Or the physical layout
Ballet
Is constructed due to the opposite of the highways
It's actually very easy to get away
As long as you're not trying to get away during rush hour
To be fair to La their bank robbery stats are way less jaw-dropping now
According to the FBI there were only 212 reported bank robberies in 2013
But let's get to gainers
Chapter one school the distraction at one Wilshire
Panoramic Kickstarter last year to fund her work this is from the video
Plane takes off from Los Angeles International Airport on Tuesday morning at precisely 9:46 a.m.
It's assignment to deliver a full-scale replica of a 747 commercial jet to a fill
Somerset
Lost flying over downtown LA the cables holding the replica snap
Dropping the plane 10000 ft
Crashing into the government building one Wilshire
One Wilshire is a 28 story building in Downtown LA most of it is filled with computer servers in Telecommunications
Equipment is the goal of is to draw crowds of pulses buying preoccupied police from what's real
Really going on
And what's really going on is that wall every emergency responder in La is busy with
The destruction at one Wilshire
5 different banks in the surrounding area are being robbed
Beginners plan involves stealing the actual safe
Because that's where the big money is
It's become La loan now that they're only allowed to hold $2,000 at 1 so if they there
For example there were 10 total
Behind each cubicle you need 10 people in the OD amount that you ever get is a is a limit of $2,000 in
Each of those cubicles
Gaynor's plan was to drill large concentric circles
Into the bags
Fallout the vault
And then load them on a truck we could call circles that get smaller in size as you reach the vault
Anasazi pool
Pull the goods backwards it rips the building and pause so that the building could collapse on its own weight after you
Leaving no traces or trying to diminish the amount of evidence possible
Gaynor did a ton of research trying to figure out the size of the vaults the layout of the building
She was working with a group of students from the Art Center College of design in LA
And we have them ask questions in the buildings
Kind of playfully where architecture students who want to find out
Powerful How deep the building goes and so on
As of now she knows the sizes of all the vaults
But one V one was still trying to work out weave Comfort to the cleaner that has worked in one of the bank
Entering the Vault tolls is very difficult
Not all of the research
Has been
Like watching Lots
And lots
The only thing the one you want to have insane ironically is Inside Man and people keep telling me to watch it and I keep
Meaning to
And it's one I'd like to save up because I'm told it's very good
Mastermind Russell to work
Location New York City
New York
Hello my name is Russell gewirtz on the right or the
Inside Man
Starring Jodie Foster Clive Owen and Denzel Washington
In the early 2000s gewirtz was living in New York City
He wasn't a screenwriter he had nothing to do with Hollywood
I hadn't
Going to film school I hadn't
Read a book on screenwriting or anything
He was just a guy working in real estate that like me and apparently a lot of other people
Like thinking about the best way to rob a bank
Part of my daily commute
Was that I walk for my Apartments my car a few blocks
Walk past an empty bank
Every day when I was walking past this bank that's what we're talking
My head so it was sort of like this
It was just a few minutes of my day every morning and every evening where I would end up
Working on this snow soda fantasizing about this story in my mind
In fact for about 3 Years chords constructed the
Heist in his mind
Before he ever wrote down a word
For most of that time I don't think I ever really intended
To write a movie
It was just
You know just
The date
He knew he wanted his house to take place in Manhattan
But it took him awhile to
To figure out what kind of Bank
It would be
You think about it
The story
Is
Dependent upon me
The architecture ever if you will or this
Structure as I was writing it I had to have a sense of
Okay is this a modern banquette
Glasgow
Going to come see everything
What's going on or is it old
Just have smaller Windows into me
You know sometimes we know can I only see a little
Because that was going to determine how you know a lot of the action
In the film
So the fun of it the great part is that
As I'm writing it I really get to build the bank however I want it to be
The bank that gorgeous in that building cuz they classic old one high ceilings marble floors
Elegant and uncomfortable in a way that big city banks used to be and it has no windows in front of the police
He's a very little idea about what's going on inside with all the bank robbers and hostages
CBS 2 News outside Manhattan Trust Bank where we have just been told by investigators
The bank has been robbed
An okay spoiler alerts ahead but the house that he designs is really clever
A group of masked robbers
Enters the bank and takes everyone all of the customers and all the bank employees hostage
Everybody that the robbers make all of the hostages take off their
Clothes and put on the same outfit
Update Robert
Are also wearing
I kind of blue jumpsuit
Like a painter would wear
I need all of you to put on one of these suits
Chinese mask
So you can't tell
Who's the hostage
The robber
Even the hostages lose track of Who's Who
Toward the end of the movie
The hostages and robbers all come out with their hands up
But because they're dressed exactly the same
The police have no idea
Who was the hostage
Who were the robber
They questioned everyone but they still can't figure it out
And eventually they have to let them all go
Anna Bruen
But there was still one problem
It became clear to me that
As clever as it was to tie them in a dress themselves up like the hostages
They're they're still needed to be a way to steal something and get it out of
You know I couldn't I couldn't sneak it out
Indiana with the house
Messages
So
In the end I decided one of them had to stay behind
And
From there it became well if he stays behind he's got he has to be hiding and if he's going to be hiding
It's got to be really clever and it has to be something that is hinted at
Throughout the entire movie while the robbers are in the back
They're doing something in the back room
Building something
Digging something
It's unclear what's going on
You think that maybe they're digging a tunnel
But they're actually building is a room a tiny cell with a false wall hidden behind some shelves
In the basement
At the bank
They use the building itself
As an unwitting accomplice
One of the robbers the one who actually has the stolen goods
Has to stay behind until all the police are gone
Until they're done Gathering evidence at the bank
He has to stay in this little room
Burn entire week
You know it's it's
It's funny it's hard for me to know exactly how much
My intention actually
True but when they're
When they're hacking through the concrete floor
They're building a toilet
Because of your hiding in a tiny cell for a week
Well you're going to have to go
Somewhere
And that's the thing about this high
It feels pretty believable
There no black box
And you know if you're watching a movie
And a bunch of crooks get to the unit get to the safe
Somebody just pulled out a piece of equipment from the backpack and sticks it on the lock and the villain a lock open
It's called the black box
Those don't exist in the real world they only exist
But even without black boxes a highly orchestrated highest with multiple players and lots of moving Parts like the
1 in Inside Man
Is really different
From the reality of how most bank robberies take place
According to the FBI's own status
Sex most Bank
Properties are done by just a single person
Who presents a note to the teller
And walks out
Without a lot of fur
Which is a fundamental principle of design
If you want something to work and work well
Keep it
Symbol
Mastermind
Tom Justice
Location
California
Illinois
So all of the other people I'm I'm talking to you for the show
Designs
Bank robberies or bank heist
Kind of a creative exercise but that's not the case with you
Now that's correct
I have unfortunately been convicted of 26 bank robberies in three different states
A my case they called me the choir boy robber
The FBI gave him the same because during the robberies he would stand with his hands folded on the counter and his
Head bowed
When I can't see someone's hands
That makes me very nervous
So in order to serve make myself calm and
Bank teller calm
Your hands full but nicely
Put them right there but everybody IDs
Tom always worked alone
And he always used a note
The noise
This is a bank robbery
Put all your money in the bag
Thank you and you have to be prepared
The teller to think the note is a joke
It's interesting it breaks your stride a little bit because
You should have in this Zone
And then the teller
She looks at me like
Are you serious
Yes serious
Because if you've never experienced his butt
Before and who has
You think it's
You think it's a joke
And like Alone Again
The artist that we are
Heard from earlier
Tom Davis
Is research
Especially at the
Probably took
3-4 months of
Over Surge and a lot of observation
The Guiding principles you do not want to get caught
And as such
You want to sort of
Envision all sorts of different scenarios
Someone might engage you in the bank
A bank employee
A bank
Customer
What will you do
When you if you reach an altercation what is your Escape Route
Is it might be different from your
Sandrock
Everything has to be highly thought out
Tom getaway vehicle was his bicycle
So the first thing you do is figure out where he was going to leave the bike park
Well I was inside robbing the bank
From there
I actually
Physically
Walked through in terms of the steps
I'll actually count the steps
I would count the moves
I would practice
Literally
Hundreds of times
A small notebook
And which I wrote on every single
Would you leave Footprints police patterns
Possibilities
High pedestrian traffic areas
Come spend a lot of time observing people
Patterns and completely unintuitively
Came to believe
Banks closest to
Popsations
Make for the softest Target
Tom thinks this is because when cops go out on duty they tend to drive out a ways
The station
Which means it takes them longer to get to the
He never called back
Robbery
Any tended to rob banks in Middle to upper-class neighborhoods
So that it would look at
Black with support somebody
Riding away on a bicycle if you were in it to be in a really tough area
I really working class area
That would stand out
No I did not lock up my bike
Honestly I was only away from
That site
223 minutes
Over the course of four years Tom stole close to $130,000
Plus about $5,000 for robbery
He never used the gun
And no one was ever physically hurt
For the end of his bank-robbing career Tom got careless
Stop putting as much time in planning
Did all of the standard steps of
What is the Escape Route what is the alternate Escape Route
But I did not really
Pay attention to like
Police and I will hang out and watch police patterns
I just got a cocky
Tom Justice was eventually caught and spent nine years
In prison
Design matters
You want to know what else matters
What
Cheat
We want our know what we have in the bank money not your money your money is insured by the federal government not going to lose a dime
The 1995 movie
Heat from director Michael Mann
Set in La of course it influenced
All three of our Heist masterminds
I kind of a scene
Lots over the years my favorite being Heats Michael Mann's Heat
In prison
Heat is the number one movie
Amongst convicts
Whenever say we're all
Hanging out on a Saturday in heat comes on
TNT and it's on that at all time
Whatever it is you're doing
You you should have sat down
I'm going to watch at least an hour of
Craft projects
Jenkins
You put it all aside
Repeat
And the heist designers in our story aren't the only ones influence by heat
There was a real heist in LA in 1997.
The North Hollywood shootout
You can actually watch and listen
Parts of it online
It's a robbery on a Bank of America gone awry
And it all unfolds in a way that is suspiciously similar
To the plot
That's really weird feedback loops that happened in Hollywood
It seems when it comes the heist
Life often imitates art
And all these plans are only good at Art I cannot stress this enough people crime doesn't pay
Baby must embark on a life of crime
Don't let yourself get attached to anything you're not willing to walk out on in 30 seconds flat
If you feel the heat around the corner
99% invisible was Bruce's sweet by Katie mingle with Sam Greenspan Avery trufelman and me Roman Mars
We are project of 91.7 local public radio kalw in San Francisco and produced are the offices of Arc
In beautiful Downtown Oakland California around the corner from the chase
Which has
Wall of in
Thick lucite between you and the tellers
So you ain't getting in there
Don't even think about
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
MPI fade
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad to take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Dot and Bo
You can follow along with this show and all the people make the show
On Facebook
And Twitter and Tumblr but I think your mission this week is to describe
You're perfect heist in great detail in the comments
999 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast