99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Americans have always had an uneasy relationship
Gambling
Does circumvent anti-gambling laws in the US
Early slot machines masqueraded as vending machine for a trade machine
Machine Head to obscure its true intent
Cherries and lemons and oranges
On the reals and they would offer prizes like chewing gum or other treats
That you would then have to redeem for
Cache Lake tickets
Chuck-E-Cheese
So it was almost like laundering it back
Into money
Many slot machines have retained the fruit symbols to this day in the UK there actual
Call fruit machines because of this
What is a carryover from that era the new Universal bar symbol
What's I always thought represented stacks of bars of gold
Has a similar origin
The bar symbol is actually based on the logo of the Bell fruitgum company
I'm talking with the Tasha doll show
My name is no
Natasha. Shull
And I'm
Associate professor at MIT
And the title of my book
Is addiction by Design machine gambling in Las Vegas
You can probably picture of slot machine pretty easily
The image we have
That we carry around in our minds
The slot machine
It's pretty much the same machine that came out in 1895
3 reels
Mechanical reels
Spin
You
Are playing two light up symbols across one line
The one bar
And to get the machine
Play you're putting in coins
And then you're reaching up with your arm and
Pulling this
Lever
So it's a very mechanical interaction
This is the
The famous one-armed band
Today if you walk into a casino you may still see those levers
But they have a new name
Legacy
Is there basically just there
To invoke that bygone
Mission mechanical
Machine
Attract us over we recognize it
Pull the lever but we very quickly realize after sitting down at it's a lot faster and more efficient
Ultimately less fatigue
For sitting there for a while
Depressed
The buttons or in some cases to
To touch the screen a classic skeuomorph
The physical machine the hardware that you're interacting with
Has really shifted
Skill morphs are design elements that are retained as an ornament
Past the point where they serve any meaningful function
Slot machines
Yuan morphic
Champion
Is there lousy with design elements that make you feel like you're interacting
Play trustworthy mechanical objects
It's not just the Legacy love
It's also the screen you're looking at
So this is
Typically now a video screen
Rather than
Mechanical
3 wheel setup
Some of these video machines however
Try to
Make us
We're playing
Mechanical machine
Analog to Ching Ching to them
Military
A visual
Mapping technology is
Is used it's like this three-layer plasma screen
There are actual real spinning their blank and what's happening is there's a video projection onto them
So it's not like they're marked
Actual symbol
The symbol that appear can just be changed up there's lots of little tricks
Which designers try to get us to
Field we are still playing
An analog mechanical device
According to CBS News Americans now spend more money on slot machines than movies
Baseball and theme parks
Combine
But this wasn't always
Insta case
These were seen as
Really just
Frivolous little devices
That were there tok
Skip I
The wives
Of the real gamblers or occupied people in
Transitional
This is why they were waiting on line
Hallways are around the fringes of the main
Gambling
Pit
So they didn't tend to have stools much less the precise ergonomic seating that they have today
They weren't destination
They were really
Transitional device
But not anymore
And then there is this historical Association in this car
Between women
Particularly older women nowadays
Any slot
So in every way these machines are thought of as
Light a light for me
Gambling in the real irony there is that
These machines that anyone can a very approachable you don't have to know the rules you have to be wearing this
Suits
Or interact with other people and some intimidating way the irony is that
They are the most
Potent if you want to
Use that word
In terms of
How addicting they are
It's been shown that
You got problematically
Involved with these devices
Three to four times
Who's faster than
Then you would
At the racetrack
Playing card game
Problematically involved is my new favorite you
Despite the slot machines very familiar appearance
This is a device that has evolved dramatically
One goal in mind
The keep you playing that machine
Especially people who don't play these machines
Assumption
People must be playing these machines especially the people who play them a lot
Because they want to win
Caesar
Poor people who don't understand
How probability work
They're not rational if only they could
Educated they make these proper
Consumer decision
But in fact if you talk to a lot of these gamblers they are incredibly Savvy they're not dupes
They know they're not going to win
I know that they say doing a jackpot
That means they'll just sit there longer
Play it off
So it's not really about winning
It's about getting into
Vizio
Everything else Falls away a sense of
Monetary value X
Space
Even a sense of
Self
Is annihilated
Stream
Forum
That you enter there was one moment in trolls research for the whole concept of the Zone really sunk in for her
She was talking with a gambler
She said you know I
Sometimes I have to say that again
The sense of frustration irritation when I win a jack
Pot because it just
Freezes at my
Wow I just want to continue playing
I witness this in a casino in the player wins and as the credits are accruing Thing ending meaning
They're just
Continuing the
Phone that's been button they just can't wait to hit it again
So there's this design imperative to overcome the
Problem of interrupt
Can I design imperative to overcome
The players
Problem
With winning
And you know the gambling industry
How did own way of
Freezing moo
They're aware
Of this Zone
Sometimes they call it a Zone
They also have a term that they played when players
Spore jackpot players
And then there's
Play to win to play play
Otherwise known as time on device players
It shows book tracks this
Sea change in the gambling in this
Straight away from jackpot
And towards
Time on device play
So this is not play where you go in and you're excited
And you're out to get this
Forex
Thrill from Big Win
Or from the industry side you're not out
To certify
Fleece someone and take all their money right away and then
Get them off the machine so you can
Take someone else's money
This is more about profit
From volume ideas that
Gamblers want to sit there longer
And the industry has realized
Prophet really isn't about the
The price of play
It's about the volume
Play
Once you understand that
It begins to make a lot more sense why Penny machines machines played
With a denomination
$0.01
Are generating higher profit
Then any other machine today
It asked industry
A decade ago
What's going to become a penny machines they would have laughed
Is it that stage
Nickel machines
Considered they were really mock
Daz games you'd only find in
Grindr
But if we look
Closely at
Some technological advances
That certain makers
Hit upon
You started to realize
Aha
If we
Take the bet
And we break it down
Into pennies
Find ways with
Computer algorithm
Inside the machine
Stand betting over a longer period we can ultimately make
More money
To the lights in the soundtrack to you
The casino atmospherics draw you in
Hiragana exceed
Keep you comfortable
The max bet and spin buttons
Don't even require you to move your hand from its resting position
The reset screen
Pulls you into your own private world
And you enter
The zone
But what's going to keep you playing
Is the math
And that's really the revolution
Video slots
And the math
And that's the term industry uses
Has gotten very
Complicate
If you imagine
Our friend the old one arm bandit
You had these
3 reels with symbols on them
And you were betting on lining up
One single line
Symbols across
Now even on mechanical machines
Designers
Quickly found creative ways
Is to add another line
Play so usually when you see the real you can serve see the line above in the line.
The Genius of showing extra lines above and below the winning line
Is that it introduces
The near-miss phenomenon
It's that feeling that you
Almost one
When you see that winning symbol
So close on that adjacent line
But the extra lines are also available for placing extra bets
So the idea was
Let's let people bet on three lines
Instead of
Yeah1 token they can buy
M-43
So you did see these early multicoin game
There was limits to them because there isn't there's really a limit when you're talking about
Mechanical reels to how many
Symbols you can fit
On the screen but then video technology came along and slot machines
Could do whatever the designer one
So you started seeing this progression
From not just lying
You had even your
Your two diagonals from the corners of the sea
Screen.
Then you started seeing
What's a Dexter Real let's add 5 6 7 reels
The cross
And let's add
Zig zags
You know weird directions
So it's difficult today to see
25th
100 line games
And it gets so complicated it begins to get really hard to tell if you even one or not the on-screen Graphics have to draw
All the lines for you
Some machines have even gone so far as to do away with lining up altogether
They have what's called scatter play
So it's really quite random you're no longer playing to line up that one
Line of symbols across
Which is insane
That's all going on what's going on here
What's significant about that
Is this you're playing on a penny machine
You decide that you're going to bet
Penny per line
So that's that would be 100 pennies
The dollar
In fact
You can Max it out and bat
3 pennies
Pro-Line
So in fact you're making $3 a bat that's quite
You know when quarter players started disappearing
1 videos
Came out
Researchers were sent on to
1600 floors to find out what quarter players going are they migrating $2 as we thought they would
No they were kind of regressing back to nickel machines
But in the end they were actually
They were betting more per hand
Then they had
Quarter machine
So the question is why would a gambler do that the slots are more appealing because they take more coins
Here's the real trick
When your bedding 300 pennies
100 line
You're going to win back
A portion of those
For the first time in history
You're not betting a token and then losing it all
Ore doubling at AAA
That's a really volatile set up
This is much less volatile you're spreading your bed across a hundred lines
It's really a lot safer if you want to see it that way
Because chances are you're going to win back something on some of those lines
And it just so happens that these machines are designed
When you win back
Something
To give you all the winning stimuli that comes along with a real win
One researcher has aptly called this
A false twin
Or losses disguised as wins
Quote-unquote winning 9
That's a pretty radical
Net loss
But yet
There's little videos that are being played
It's virtually no difference
Then when you really do
Another key factor in making Penny machines possible
And all their little micro bats
Are updates and how the player feeds money into the machine
Yeah this is a huge
Part of it
Alongside the ergonomics of the chairs and the
Changes in the
Responsibilities of the buttons and how they're placed
The financial access
Knology
If you think about the past
If you ran out of money and you wanted to continue to play at a machine
There was a lot of steps you had to you really had to work for it
You had to leave your machine maybe wouldn't be there when you got back
Someone to hold it
Search
Get some cash had to search out a cashier's cage or
A roving chained attendance
Buy these coins return to a machine open the coins and put them in one by one that was very low
Labor intense
And then imagine feeding in 300 pennies
What would take
22 credit play bill acceptors
Are you got these little digital monitors where
It wasn't exactly telling you how much money was in the machine it was telling you how many credit
So already there with Bill acceptors you saw it kind of turned toward
Credit play with
Really dematerialize the money
Made it less real somehow and allowed you to
Get in that zone disconnected you again from
The everyday world is a lot of machine gambling uses these player reward card
Mature essentially
Credit cards
The casino sets up for you where you store credit
Casino and see people that their seemingly
Connected to these machines almost like life support with
Plastic bungee cords
That are attached to their car so they won't forget them and lose them there so you look down a whole line and everyone
Attached
Rote
But ticket in ticket out technology where you're playing with these barcoded tickets
And player cards
We're really necessary piece of the technological puzzle
4 pennies
To come on the scene
With multi-line
And this design evolution is the reason why slot machines are the most profitable form of gambling even though there is no
What's going bald
And the player
Doesn't even know the odds of winning for any given machine
Machine technician understand more about the
Machine that I thought it would be
A good part of my recovery from the addiction because I thought if I understand how these machines work
The spell will be broken
And she said he don't even after I was
Putting machines together and designing
Work
On my lunch break
I would just go down the street
Play the exact
Because that is how addiction works
99% invisible in Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars where project of 91.7
Local public radio kalw in San Francisco
And the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
If your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why then it may be time
Nancy, go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God
Black podcast
You can find the show and like to show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars that we'll have more info about Schewels
Really great book addiction by Design
And her film about all you can eat Vegas buffets oh my God
At our website 99percentinvisible. Org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com