99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Ready open on Roman open
When I'm not making radio I listen to a lot of radio more than
Set a clock for 4:30 please my earbuds are constantly lost in my ears
So that I can press play and listen to radio at any moment that doesn't require me to talk
Or listen to an actual human being in the real world
Riverside by Troy malattia
Produced by speaking into microphones
Julia walking on cement stairs
Or doing the dishes open or driving the car they are but you're somewhere else too
Create driveway moments
TM
Story so good
That listeners can't leave their car until they're over part of what makes a driveway moment is the end of that moment
When you realize what time it is
You could have been staring at a clock all along but for a while
For once
It had no power of you
That time Distortion field is one of public radio Secret
Awesome powers
Which is why it is such a shock
When those of us go from being radio listeners
Do radio producers
Like me and my friend Julia Barton here
The audience is hearing this it's hard to believe he's not nervous
But this is what radio sounds like on the inside and 32 seconds
Short of what I'm
Supposed to have
So what I'll do is I'll just take 15 seconds of this song
And then why would they be 60 Seconds
You will
I visited NPR's headquarters in Washington DC
And sat in on the live roll of All Things Considered
Their Flagship Afternoon News Maga
Show their clocks all over the studios
Big Red digital clock
Huge round analog clocks
Special software and calculator
Time calculator
What's 60 + 60 equals 200
Hi
Bring one of the only two play 15 seconds but you're wrapped up 45 seconds earlier so now I have to pay a long time is it okay
Yeah I mean
Choice really
We have enough to Detroit
I don't think so
Monica is Stevia directs all things considered 4 days a week
To me it's the scariest job in the world is built into the design of a program like all things considered
It's the show
The show has a set
The clock is a template
From which it almost never varies
Every show that broadcast
Soar aspires to broadcast in the public radio system
Has a clock
Basically it looks like a pi it's round
And sliced and lots of weird ways
Some of the spices are very thin there's 59 seconds fit program opening we call that the billboard
14 seconds for the funding credits
Ephedra slices 5 minutes
For the news
The biggest slices are lettered a b c and d
And they are the psychic
That's where the stories and interviews live
And they have to fit together
1 minute to close
I remember I was very
Meteors
Figure it out
The clock is your master for the two hours the show rolls out
Everything has to be ready
Segments can't run long by even a second
Because most of the local stations are automated
To cut off the national
Program where the clock says they can
These times are called post
You have to
Nothing
Can go wrong
Of course things go wrong everyday someone reads too long and interview runs too short
You might hear the dreaded
Dead air
Or someone rushing at the post and listeners can hear the clock
He who can't be named in public radio
And then the spell is broken when you look at this document
You see something
Very regimented and we talked about how it is very rich
In terms of
Things happening
Goal is
For people not really
No it's there
That's great Dixon who also directs all things
Considered
But like Michelle directors he never actually looks at the diagram of
The program clock
This visual representation was hard for me
To reference
Have
I had a piece of pie
Why is my cheat sheet
I brought it into the studio every
And according to Greg Dixon he brought it in much longer than he actually needed it
Until it was in tatters
What does crib sheets and you will find them everywhere in broadcast
Are Abridged the place where the clock actual
But you can wake up
Wake us up in the middle of the night and we can be like
59 528 1228
128 like 7:48 we know we can go down
But the entire hour
Without ever stopping because we know it we know it by heart
And some
And of course they had dreams about it
NPR they're called directors dreams
You lose control
You cannot regain that control and to have lost sense of how much time is left in the segment how much
How much time is left
The feast and usually is
It's like the worst
Bannock
And you wake up and yours
Wedding
You can't believe you just
I've had those where I'm on the board
Announcing the Morning Edition on kalw and the sliders
I don't do anything in the Buns just don't look right
Enter rather than try anything I'm just paralyzed with fear
Oh yeah in my dream I'm doing a newscast with no copy and I just have the talk
And talk and talk and talk
And talk like an idiot until the clock goes
I haven't even seen it down clock in ages
Note podcast there is no time scarcity no interlocking gears
Of local and National broadcast
And that changes everything
But we also make a version of the show that fits inside the NPR clock
The c-segment of Morning Edition to be exact
4 minutes and 30 seconds exactly
Over by 143
Figure out a way to take all these ideas or at least some
Fraction of these ideas
Brandon
Into a show that less than 5 minutes
Sometimes
That really really sucks
But you'd be surprised how often I actually really like the radio version
The first time I really internalized the difference between doing radio and doing podcast
When people would tell me
But they wanted my stories tubing longer
In the entire decade of radio I produce
Tired of this podcast
No editor has ever asked me to go longer and I can vouch for that
You're so mean to me is so mean for 30 soccer
What podcasts have no constraints you can be any length
The only constraint is the content
And people always tell me they wish this podcast was longer but I think the show would suffer if it went on too long
Until maybe there's a need for a clock
Even if the clock isn't strictly required
Constraint
Or maybe
Restraint in this case
Makes for better art
When I started thinking about the broadcast clock
As a piece of design I wondered
How it all got started in public radio
NPR came together in the late sixties in the early 70s
When Network news with
And those broadcast shows of course
How to clock
But public radio news wanted to be something
Because of this guy
I'm Bill Sebring and I was the first director of programming for NPR
Still simmering
He came up with the whole idea of All Things Considered
Which of course everyone in the business now refers to as a
In the original mission statement
Did you see was
Called
Did he identify with
But you decided that wouldn't be a good name for the show
Right-wing was among the earliest designers of the public radio Sound
That sound included lots of audio and voices from the world outside the studio
It called for a documentary-style approach
Even the same day news
For that
Bill designed a very open clock
We didn't have a lot of breaks
Throughout it
And it was so
This frustrated some people because they thought
They wanted a very fix clock
There was a clock but it was
Not that
I believe it was time for a we had
Join
Stations but otherwise
And
I think that's
What are things that made it
Interesting to listen to because it wasn't predict
That way
And you let the
The stories
Stories were leaving
I like the
The peace the old ATC clock only had a few slices in a lot of open space
In there one story might be 2 minutes followed by another that was 20 minutes
It was
Open it was kind of like a podcast
But it still was saying there
Not everyone appreciate
Did that there was a conference two weeks after ATC rolled out in the station managers just
Call Bill Sebring today
Carpet for hits
Fluffy loose sounding program
And it was something else that they really didn't like in this is a digression here but this is a punk ass so we get to have digression
And of course I got this criticism from something about
Women's watch
All that stuff
That
On FM women's voices have the high frequencies and
You should see the meter
Building
Let me go
Just come on
Really they said women's voices were too high for FM
Did some voices
Peakmeter
Oh my God
We have Sean build seeming was out of NBR a year-and-a-half later followed
Began a long process of becoming more subdivide
The women he hired like Linda wertheimer and Susan Sandberg
Are well-known
Semen on to help turn Fresh Air with Terry Gross into a national program
Annie's the
Kind of the patron saint of creative open style public radio including this program right here
But you know being loose and open
Can also be its own form of
People
Often mentioned to me. The boy
Those were the Halcyon Days of all things considered and I was there no they weren't that's Neal Conan who's done everything
NPR including until
Recently hosting the two-hour live call-in program Talk of the Nation
New Conan loves
The clock for him it's an art form until
Itself
There's these little things that
If you've never done it or impossible if you've done it forever you don't even think about doing them
How long is 5 Seconds
You can ID 3DS and say goodbye in French
So it's not surprising that would Neal Conan took over Talk of the Nation
More posts
Because it turns out you said
Pretty much all you
Need to say about
Medical marijuana
By the 40 in
You still coming to something else unfortunately Neal Conan is doing something else now
NPR recently cancelled Talk of the Nation after 21 years
And he resigned
Neal Conan says artificial constraints make us better
And I noticed that the person who edits audio story
We was perspective when we're inside the
The story just trying to make sense of all a report
We can't tell what's important anymore
If we don't have any constraints we can make boring and confusing
Wingstop
The constraint doesn't have to be a time limit but at least the clock forces
To have a perm
Perspective
It says
Stop right there
And figure out what really matters
Of course the clock and also limit what you say as well have to do in the broadcast version of this piece
We're can create nonsense we Samantha Phil time you didn't expect to fill
So there was a day long ago when Neal Conan
Was not mad
Picture of the clock
When he first started at NPR in the late 70s
He had to direct this new show called weekend also
Considered
I think briefed on the clock
By the event director of weekend All Things Considered Deborah Amos is
Turn on December 9th as a reporter
And
And my question to her was
You mean exactly the time
And I think we ended that for sure that I produced
About four minutes earlier I was so terrified
A blowing the post
So a while ago I went to hear Deborah Amos
And afterwards I asked her if this story was
True
That Neal Conan ended his first live NPR Show 4 minutes
Early
And she said they did
And that they had to grab the longest film music they could find in the studio
Which was some kind of whale song
No super design subdivided format is telling us when the stop the story we're just kind of winging it
Radio
Are always kind of winging it whether you're in a studio
Set like mine where I don't even think I have a clock in this room
Or you're in the broadcast
Palace in DC
The clocks everywhere
I know so you have the line
We just hope someone out there is listening
OKC disaster avoided
Yeah she finished
45 seconds
Earlier
You're not listening hard enough to hear the clock monster
And Hans the dreams of anyone who's look
Into its Dark Soul
Do you have to stand by
Ready
Open
The crowd
Ready
Hedrick
Let me take a Julia but hold Roman open settings and go 99% invisible
This week by Julia Barton
Sam Greenspan and me Roman Mars we are product of 91.7 local public radio kalw
In the American Institute of Architects in San Francisco
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Another word for all hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Mix
For a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
Family ghosts in the podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of
The world each episode of Family ghosts
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called an episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled and annuity
We discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for
For 25 years and more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
You find a show in like a show on Facebook I tweet at Roman Mars
Sam Greenspan
Even though he doesn't website
Diagrams of broadcast clocks
So you can save your friends things like
Heard that during the block of Morning Edition
Knowledge awaits
A99ii
Let's go home
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com