99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness
Tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Reply
This is 99% invisible
Let's go back to the Soviet Union in the 1950s
It was a terrible hunger for any sings it came from breast
This is Alexander genis Russian writer and broadcaster
For example light
Didn't even mention
How important was
American life that it was like
Trailer for the lighter is just a lighter
During the Cold War were expressions of creativity in art
Much of which
Came from the West
They wanted western music
There was of course
American Festival music
Bethel Music
Incredible importance
They were crazy
Crazy about jazz and rock and roll
Cousin
Express
And it was extremely hard to smuggle and vinyl records that were made in the West
Enterprise album did make it in ordinary Russians couldn't make copies to sell or trade to their fellow,
That's because vinyl the material itself
Was impossibly expensive
And scares so we didn't have any record
Syphilis
I didn't even see Rec
My wife
Wisdom
Gosip
The Angelus
Soviet censorship was endless
So was Russian ingenuity
That's davia Nelson she and Nikki Silva are the kitchen sisters the neighbor dudes the radiotopia podcast fugitive waves
So the dissident music counterculture produce bootleg records on anything they could get their hands on
Before the tape recorder
Be used X-ray film of your bones
But used used X-ray film of your bones
This is Sergei Khrushchev
And they table this the music from Unite
Stacy from Europe
So it was
Musica
Liquor store
Music of the bones
Music on the bone rock on Rib Crib
Skeleton music
Phone
Yes
Baton Rouge
My father was Nikita Khrushchev show the head of the Soviet Union from 1953 to
The beginning of all this America music then
Just released rock and roll
They didn't broadcast it
From the official radio
The kitchen sisters first learn to build music records when they interviewed Sergei Khrushchev about the distant activity taking place in
In people's tiny kitchens and the new Khrushchev apartments that is father had built in the 1960s
These private kitchens became the hotspots of the culture
The place to gather for the free expression of ideas
With the KGB looking almost everywhere and nearly every phone line bug
These individual kitchens made it possible
All four friends together privately and
Their mind
Vodka flowing and pickles and Herring piled high on the tables
These dissident kitchen
Became unofficial lecture Halls
Nightclub
Art galleries bars dating service
The place where politic
Debated forbidden music was
Play an underground art
And literature search
Calculated it was amazing the lengths people went to to share uncensored culture and Paula
The risks
They took to see if forbidden painting
Read a Banned Book
Orilissa
Into a song
Music on Bones is the legal production of Records unexposed x-ray film
This is eczema video Leyva to the visiting professor at Columbia and the department of history and theory of architecture
And it was a dissident pract
Chess in the USSR
Primarily during the Cold War
The first
Studio
Which produce records
Beliefs
Was it golden
Book
Named in tribute to Nipper
RCA Victor's famous dog logo
Book the golden dog gay
Bruce Las Vegas Los Campos engineer gutted idea to use old
X-ray
Google slavsky reverse-engineered a record duplication machine that a friend of his and brought from the west and put it to work
Roll vinyl plastic and other durable materials to make records was basically non-existent
Caboose lost keep trying to use whatever was available to scratch out copies of the records that were smuggled in
Coated paper was the most common source material on which to print copies but those records
Only lasted a few plays on a turntable
Bootlegs can only make a big impact in the black market if they were more durable and then hire Fidelity that's when he thought of
Using discarded x-ray
Taken from the hospital trash and medical archives in order to make a kind of photographic record
The copying of a western vinyl record
Really do them Justice
The Ghostly
Beautiful
Hunting
Transparent
Just ever-so-slightly
X-ray plates thicker than the ones we grew up
Ribs
Feet
Tarsals metatarsals
Femurs
Tumors
Kidneys
All with a slight itching of circles of sound scratched onto the
You can see the rough edges of the graph which reflects the level of hardship that would being overcome
Baseball records
Kmart
What are cells called
Total shortages of absolutely everything
It would take an x-ray
They would
Got a trim in the shape of a record
I'm looking on the
Ralph
Circle
X-ray
Uchealth
Even the cat
Because it's made
Caesars
And you can see
Simply Blues
Through
Record you can see it
X-ray of
Call
It's like from, today
These records where
TouchWiz manicure
Caesars
Is that was a cigarette they would burn the middle out
Could actually play it
These strange Homemade Creations were eventually put on the market
The black market
It was Shadow industry like
Any singing for my brother
Ketosis
Excellent record
Already
Love Me Tender
There's a single life
This Record was very very expensive you have to pay like weekly
Sounds like
C Michelson was commander
Dwight Yoakam participle of sink
I wrestled in underground Bethesda under the table
Could never
Chip with you by
Give you something as a promise that it is Elvis Presley
Right and you can complain
I remember the first one I heard was Chubby Checker's
That's Gregory free professor emeritus of Slavic languages and literature at Stanford
When I
Became a teenager myself
I used to go and shop for them
The black market was opposite the official Soviet record store melodia
It was a courtyard where they were young men's long overcoats
Woke up to them and you ask them what they have them they would
Open Little Cottonwood say that this is Chubby Checkers and this is Elvis Presley and this is Twist
They have the whole catalog the whole
Display cases on the inside of the elbow called
It's pretty easy to look back on this practice and find it to be lights Amber so fun
But this was serious business
That wasn't official music Patrol initiated
It's by the KGB
The track
The production of this
Auntie USSR activity
Punishments
Kobe extreme
People making and buying bone records were always looking over their shoulder
In the 50s
The owners of this recording studio got arrested for spreading Western propaganda
Moscow
T i a Russian vice squad
Uncovered
Clandestine
Vast Underground
The report said
Official shutdown
Operation
Arrest records
The Golden Dawn
You could get 3 to 5 years for illegally copying
Music
The X-ray innovator himself Ruslan boguslawski was sentenced to 5 years prison in Siberia
But cracking down on the Pirates copying the disc wasn't the only way the state was combating the scourge of Odin
The pirated
The Pirates
It's to flab the market of bone records by creating
Play Bolero Cocina effort
They would even make records
Musically mask
Or is it would include recording in the middle of the music saying things like
You like rock and roll
Taiyuan
Toilet slime
This is cheek to cheek
She cracks
Is it Russian translation
You can easily identify them
Because I want No Label so you say okay this is a non-drowsy
And the News Elvis
And this is Tina dads
Brain tumor and that means
Duke Ellington
These exposed x-rays became when you form of secret and precious information
Porta-Johns Interiors of citizens
Bone music is a collaboration between the kitchen sisters and 99% invisible
Did you hear more about Bone music
And the X-ray records that Jack White and Gibby Haynes made for Third Man Records on the kitchen sisters podcast it's called Feud
Subscribe today the kitchen sisters are Nikki Silva and Davey Nelson without from Brandy Howell Andrew Roth
Jason Dalton
99percentinvisible exam Greenspan Katie mingle Avery Trucking and Kurt Kolstad and me Roman Mars we are
Project 91.7 kalw San Francisco and produced of the offices of arcsin
In architecture and Interiors firm
In beautiful downtown
Oakland California
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here on the 99 pit
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secret scroll in the newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Eastman episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
The proud family goes to wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is free
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God.
Open find the show and like to show on Facebook all of us on Twitter and Instagram and Spotify but they find out more about this story
Including cool pictures and links and listen to all the episodes of 99% invisible
You must go to 99 pi
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com