99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
When I dunk it in you'll see like I'll just try to make minimal splashes
Artist and curator the case of breast men free SEMO
John put on sunglasses
The thing then yeah
We're in our backyard in Oakland making an indigo bat
Which is to say we are making a natural blue dye using powder from the indigo plant
Kind of complicated
This is actually our second time trying to make indigo
Because the first time we didn't get the ratio right
It's Tricky
YouTube
By stirring the Indigo powder and the other ingredients
Together in this bag of hot water very slowly because
It's a strict kind of lovingly and slowly
And then if you actually do it right and all goes according to plan
It's amazing
I want it to do the Indigo mixture seems to come alive in the
Water it starts listening
Shimmery bubbly chunks are swirling around and water it's like we were mixing a cauldron
Swirling purple potion
And then when we dumped in some white t-shirts
They came out deep green
And then if we let the shirts dry in the Sun
Patches of blue gradually emerge
And slowly spread over the cloth
Like we have conjured it
It's pretty cool you like a magical process
It's also just like
Make the real
Color if I feel like
Nobody
Nobody doesn't like indigo blue
Or at least I can't imagine anyone hating it
It's so ubiquitous
Have you like
Someone hating water
Indigo is everywhere
Because indigo
Is what put the blue
In blue jeans
Articles of Interest
A show about what we wear and so maybe the ideas about clothing
To a piece of cloth
Annie falcon
Where's clothes
But if you ain't got the attitude installed a carrot off
Man U District closed.
What's great about blue jeans
We like to say that
We pioneered the
And we claim thing the inventor of them this is
Is Tracy panic
The corporate historian at Levi Strauss & Company
They touch on
The roots of blue collar workers they became a
Canvas 4
Self-expression
1960s so in many ways
They hit on
Key cultural moment
Across
Our society
This is a difference
Between denim
And jeans
Denim is a fabric that can be used in jackets shirts dresses tablecloths
Upholstery
You name it
Blue jeans
Are a very specific
Kind of
Pants
And they have a couple Hallmark
For the most part
They are blue
And they are worn in
They basically look
Like this
This
But you're looking at is the oldest pair of blue jeans in the world
It dates to about 1879
And
This is
The blueprint for all blue jeans today
World's oldest pair of blue jeans
They looked
Classic
Meaning they really don't look very different from the kinds of genes you find in a thrift store today
They held up well
Yes they were patched in a little stained but if I wanted to I could have totally put them on right there and walked out of the
The archive wearing them
And the security guard would have even noticed because they're still
Jeans
The differences
Are subtle
This one only has one pocket
In the back
We didn't add the second pocket onto the back until 1901 and here's a really cool thing about
But most of our clothes we try to keep them pretty pristine and avoid spills and rips and tears
Denim so hard wearing and hardworking I just kind of a mess as more and more signs of wear
You can just text a pair of old jeans like an archaeologist
You can actually see how someone walked
You'll see all of this where this honeycombing as we call it
That's simply wear and tear from
Keep all the men who were wearing it
And we think
That there were as many as three men who wore this
This particular
You can tell by looking at the Impressions on the knees
Anthony marks
Go up and down is several
Places
Because they are in several
Locations
We know the sea
People wore them and that was common with you
They get passed around they were sturdy enough that you could do that
Which is kind of romantic writer
Because this is
Oh how we like to think of our blue jeans today
Broken endurobol
Something to be worn and reward and passed around
Just like these original jeans
But the jeans you and I wear today may look like those original Levi's
How the maven say Levi's on them
They are not the same kind of pants
In between 1879 and today
Everything that makes blue jeans blue jeans
How they're made to what they're made of two where they end up
Change
Because
Blue jeans reveal our wear pattern
R-value
They show the movements we make
Over and over again
They show
Are true color
Sew denim with around
Levi Strauss
And blue denim trousers were around before Levi Strauss
But here is what Levi Strauss did
That made the blue jean
He patented the rivet
On the pocket
The innovation of the rivets is that you could take at a little tiny piece of metal atom to the pockets
And they became much stronger so if you're putting your hands in your pockets
They're not going to chair
The rivets were the big selling point
Not necessarily the denim
And when they use denim it wasn't always necessarily blue
It doesn't have to be
Blue is just tradition
Denim can be any color
Lynn Downey is a biographer of Levi Strauss and the former Levi's corporate historian
Before Tracy
Over the years the company did make blue and gold denim products
Red and white
But
It was indigo
Indigo blue
Dyed thread
That was
Easiest
That seems seem to last the longest and people just gravitate
It's hard to explain why humans are so attracted to Indigo
Historically the dye had massive power
Indigo used to be very rare and expensive
Especially since that process of dying is so special and magical
Blue was a symbol of status and or wealth all over the world
Indigo has its roots in India and its name and variance grow in Vietnam in West Africa
Anywhere where it's humid
Humidity
The same conditions as rice
So Indigo was also able to
The drive
In South Carolina
Indigo had first been cultivated
In the United States and
1740s by a woman oh by the way Eliza Pinckney
Really a girl
She was 16 years old born in Antigua
And her family then had plantations in South Carolina and she and her family moved there
And her father has sent her some Indigo Seas
From the Caribbean and she thought
Let's try this
She was able to cultivate enough Indigo to make it a cash crop
American Indigo have kind of a cool feminist success story
But
When Indigo became a cash crop
If you can master
Produced
And so that labor-intensive magical process of making indigo
Scaled-up
With slave labor
And I can just imagine the slaves and
The women especially or are stirring these Indigo Vats they were processing this die
And their hands are blue before the American Revolution before cotton became king
Indigo was the second largest cash crop in the colonies after rice
Indigo plantations all across the South and some of them lasted well into the Civil War
Virginia South Carolina for sure the story takes place in Georgia this is an Mass Eye and she has this amazing
Using story about her grandfather's grandfather
Who was born as a slave on an Indigo Plantation his name is John John Henry
And it was very common for them to swaddle the babies in the blue cloth so when baby John was born
His parents decided to escape
Play wrapped baby John and indigo and headed north
They crept through the underbrush
Creeping their way up about an hour after they set out
Their dogs barking in the distance and the screaming of the voices if they recognized was the overseer so they ran
They found a place to hide the secret of themselves and baby John started to whipper and fuss
Somebody came over and it was investigating this noise was the overseer he
Look down just as the moon came out
And the baby John jump them screamed out and suddenly the overseer ran away like
Yankees are the union Army's uniforms
Girl get out the blues are here
He saw a baby John swaddled in the blue cloth
The Indigo cloth
And the overseer thought that that was a Yankee and his blue car
Hiding and they are going to be
Ambushing this
And they got out
This story that Anne has is a rare one passed from generation to generation
And
Hearing about an Indigo Plantation nestled in the Land of Cotton
Plantations
Centos add ready-made symbolism
Because cotton and indigo
Go really well together
Cotton gloves
The cotton reel
Loved soaking up
And this
According to Lynn Downey is part of why jeans are blue
Not only was Indigo a beautiful color that humans have always been attracted to
It was the color that could cling to fabric best
And it was a color that was very present in the United States
And it was relatively easy to
Procure the time
There was a system in place
For textile manufacturers to get their indigo
And this is where our idea of blue jean kind of got
Frozen in Time
Need to last forever
100% cotton
100% indigo
Are jeans still made with
Actual natural indigo
Not
Really big lines of them know
Indigo's magic concoction is
Too fickle and expensive and complicated for a massive industrial-scale most
Synthetic Indigo synthetic indigo is not without its own kind of Cruelty
It's often made with petroleum mixed with heavy metals and other chemicals
I got the chemicals that is used
Processing of this fabric
Positive
Too Human this is Aida Khan
The toxic manager at Greenpeace East Asia
She says the textile industry discharges the third most Wastewater in China
And it's runoff chemical water gets disposed of in the rivers and basically poisons them
The thing is that the waters might be Juiced
For the
Local farmers for irrigation
Play my problem growing their crops
Lots of dye colors have harmful chemicals
It's not just synthetic indigo
But
Here is the other thing that makes denim especially noteworthy in terms of production
GM fuse app
A lot
Of water
They're actually all washed in China map multiple times
And all this washing Wastewater discharge to
3 bus
Multiple times
That's the special thing about that
Yes
Speck jeans to be blue
We also expect jeans to come soft
And Warren in
No other
Textile on Mass
Is being purposefully broken down in this way
Before it even goes on a Shelf
This is Emma McClendon associate curator costume at the Fashion in
Attitude of Technology
And she says after the genes are died
They are washed
And maybe washed again
May be washed again
They are being broken down
Being made softer
And given that touch of white that emerges
The top layer of blue cotton is worn away
To get that worn in look
Manufacturers actually poor bags of Rock
Into industrial washing machines to Pamela jeans while they spin
This
Is Stone washing
Literally washing jeans
Several Cycles after the made into jeans
Washing them in
Giant industrial washers
With varying sizes of stone
Thomas you know this volcanic
Stone
Now I know
I know you might be thinking no no no
I don't
Pre distressed jeans
I just wear simple sturdy well made jeans and I hate all those artificial holes all over the place
Well
Here's the thing
You probably do every distress jeans
If you have bought genes within the last four decades
They've been processed
When people bring up Stone washing most people think it's a
Something very 80s
And it's just not the case every
Jean on the market today that is not
Raw denim jean husband Stonewall
Really
Denim raw denim is in
Ratably
Steph
Cute filters
It's really heavy
A hard heart
That's not
Necessarily something
Do you want to put on your body
This is old Simpson
A designer and owner of the small independent denim brand the end short for ubiquitous Industries
He is showing me the raw unprocessed denim fabric
Which is very thick and heavy and it's just a uniform dark dark dark
Navy blue
It has no stretch
What's the weather
No GIF
Jeans like that first pair of Levi's from 1879 started off as raw just like this
All old jeans did
The only got soft
Because the men or the three men who owns them wore them down
A lot of people don't
Today Ulrich is one of the few patient people
Who actually wear
Raw
Unprocessed
Datum I'm sure I've been chased
But this is just part of the
Just like anyone
Breaking in a pair of shoes
I don't know it kind of seems a little more extreme than that to me
Breaking in denim means you have to wear these thick
Heavy scratchy jeans
For like
6 months
Without washing them if you get something on it you maybe try to vacuum or brush it off
And after all
After all those many many weeks of chasing you finally wash those jeans
The first time
And that first wash
Oroville
All the marks you've made
I like wrinkles around your hips when you sit
The imprint of your iPhone in your back pocket
And then
It will finally have that soft worn in feeling that we all associate with Dunham
But this is so much work
Only real denim has bothered a break in their own jeans
It's the baby
3% that will actually wait and go through that process
Get it
She didn't feel like this
And this is the one that's been artificially
Denim makers artificially
Processed cheese
To break them down for you
So that
Yeah you don't have to
Go through the
Breakdown
. could look like that
And stone washing is one method for
But they're also manufactures will break the jeans down by hand
Can you sand it down
Physically handsome
Val Hansen
All of this process
Define
Sandpaper
Workers will sandpaper each individual pair of jeans to make them look like they've been worn in
To create marks
Even flight ones
Denim has that authentic
Worn in look and feel of those archetypal 1879 jeans
Morning by three different men over the course of decades
In Mass Pursuit
Comfort Inn
Authenticity
Blue jeans have become a completely different
Garment
Colors are different there
Synthetic and stretch elements in them with
What is this even mean what does it even mean to call
Denim the labor of breaking in and wearing down the genes have been transferred from the customer
To the manufacturer
The blue is not indigo
And the cotton
Is not exactly cotton
I mean
Denim
As stretch what do you think stretch
Increasingly
Synthetic fibers in it denim is not caught
Lycra nylon polyester
It goes by many names
But let's call it what it is
It's plastic
This is as much applicable to Denim as any other part of the industry
McClendon says we are at an unprecedented
Enphase
Concluding hist
We've never had so many clothes available with so much
Plastic
And no one knows what
Leggings and sweater
Wicking jacket
Super stretchy jeans are going to look like
30 years from now
Plastic Stone Age well
And we don't see it because we throw it out before we see it at that
In the future our genes
Which is down to Such Great Lengths to make a Pierre loved and worn in
Probably not age
Like those jeans in the Levi's archive
This is what people need to realize plastic
Sometimes age in such a way that they are attempting to go back
To a gas
Or they want to go back to a liquid
So that means that if you feel your sneaker sold
Time for a really long time begins to stick to the floor
You should get
Rid of it because it is
What we would call
Weeping other terminology it's going back to its liquid state
It's toxic you don't want to touch it
Same with something if you keep
Aplastic
Barrette
Or a tupperware container you never know in
Airtight
Drawer so you don't open it for years
And then you open it and you find shark
It means it explode
It literally combusted at some point and you will smell it
These things are giving off noxious.
And again we don't tend to see this because we see plastic is disposable but that's what this stuff is doing in
These landfill
And the vast majority of clothes do end up in landfills
Even if you donate your clothes
You're mostly only delaying the inevitable
And again
This is not just
Jeans
There are Plastics and harmful dies and damaging process he's in a lot of our clothes
Denim isn't even the worst culprit
No I mean not more than necessary any other plate like leather
Industry with a whole lot of problems
Denims just one because you know you can isolate it so easily
Denim is easily isolated from the rest
Of the clothing industry
Because
It is
So
God damn popular on any given day over half the population is
Of the world is wearing
So when you have numbers
Consumption numbers like that coming from one faction of the industry
That's when this kind of
Environment
Impact starts to become so
The average American own 7 pairs of jeans
Wear these jeans are going to end up
What it took to
Create them
Is just staggering
I feel so dizzy and because
In examining genes
You realize that it's nearly impossible to create a morally perfect
Piece of clothing
At least one that's affordable
Redo
Let's take jeans for
Say okay
Will buying organic jeans and then you add
Petroleum-based
Indigo
Do denim makers have to pick and choose their priorities
What are those priorities are local labor some people are all about local
Are natural fibers not using pesticides or chemicals or comfort
Affordability
Or trendiness obviously did list
Sustainable that we're all buying organic local whatever but
The reality out there in the world
That's very difficult or nearly in
Impossible
So I think what people should do
Who are listening is that they should
Pick what's most important to them
And your dollar is the vote UK
Are contact Greenpeace says companies directly respond to our buying habits
Tim Riggins has the most actually have power on the brands
And the brands that have powers to in
When's the factory supplies in China
And this is what happened happening
Clothing manufacturers have been hearing a real consumer demand for sustainability
Well we're very excited
Tracy Panic at Levis says the company is working on this technology where the genes will be worn in with laser
Rather than
Stone washing and sanding
Using lasers to work on those finishes to cut down the time and all the chemicals that are used
We have been working on ways to reduce the amount of water needed to create a pair of blue jeans
And we've not only done that in our processing the weekly manufacturer saving water but also in share
The message
That you don't have to wash your blue jeans as much
And it's true you don't have to wash your jeans as much
Really you can wash them every fifth where or so
And you can catch them and stay in them
And wear them and tear them more than you can with other clothes
On the user end
Within our closet
High quality jeans are a very sad
Temple garment
As long as we don't
Throw them away
What everybody should
Just do is
Stop by
The Crux of the issue is that we should learn how to
T Bar clothing
Think of clothing as something to
Have
And to mend
Don't automatically get rid of something
And if you do
Keep them around
And really let them walk
For your life with
Your genes will start to occur
Express how you move through the world
Are pants in our clothing
Will continue to tell
Aspects about ourselves
Arguably blue jeans should be a thing of the past
But in modern times
Without real cotton or real indigo
A real years of hard labor wearing them in
We still want our genes to look the same as they did in 1879
Turn all these hidden ways
Genes have changed in accordance with Society
Anyways mermaid
Heather Warren
They will continue to evolve
Even if they continue
Toki are unchanged
Words
Portrait
Painted on
Articles of interest is made by myself
Avery truffelman with editing from Emmett Fitzgerald and Joe Rosenberg
Music by Ray Royal intro and outro themes by Sami Ashworth
Fact check by Graham Haisha mix by Kelly coin
And Roman Mars
Is the ethical manufacturer of this whole series
Special thanks to Aaron Newport Broadband in Taylor Hamilton Morgan Brown Sally Fox
And Elaine Hamblin as well as Katie mingle with Delaney Hall Vivien Leigh Sean real Sharif Youssef Kirk Halsted and the whole
99 Pi team
Between the beeps bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered world
Handmade sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife is
Call hearing. Voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound make
For a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th right here and then
Npip
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad
Take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating but doesn't have to Define you
Constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why and it may be time
Nancy kulp go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms
Oh my God. Info podcast oh my God. Info
Flask podcast
The fashion industry is
Very terrible for the environment
The textile industry now accounts for more greenhouse gas emissions
Then all international flights and Maritime shipping combined
So you might be thinking
Okay wow fashion is the worst we are all slaves to desire and capitalism and the endless cycle Trends and it's over
Spain and time-consuming and killing a planet
So
I'm just going to get one
High quality uniform and wear it every single day forever
Just like Steve Jobs or Mark Zuckerberg
For the weekends I figure you're going to have some fun so actually have
The same shirt
In other colors and I wear those on the weekend
This is kind of essential question of it all
Like
Why bother
Why bother dressing up or dressing differently
Article of Interest
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked
Play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I
I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th bendall five-part
Arts on the truth podcast. Com