This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
It was a little bonus episode of 99% invisible and one of the big things we did this year
Was
Released a brand new show inside of a show
Created
And hosted in conceived and reported
By Avery Johnson when he was here with me in the studio
And what I want to talk to you about is
This was
A phenomenon it was called the fourth best podcast of the Year according to the New Yorker
So I wanted to
Talk to you a little bit
About the making of it
And
What you learned in the in the process of it
Both in terms of
The production of it as a as a show is
A piece of entertainment and information but also like
Personally I would
Affected your view of clothing your beautiful smile on everything
The first
What was it like
Like to have the show within a show and how did it feel
To be out there
As the host
We don't like how it's so scary I don't know your voice
Especially in this round what I didn't know anything about it
And yeah there's a
So much to
Synthesizing
Working on it for so long
I learned
So much
And it's really changed
The way I dress
And the way I shop
Hireling it's amazing so what do you mean by that
The funny thing is I think going into the series
I was like I am a close purse
I am a person who loves
After reporting a series
I am a person
Who hates Claire and I am a person
I'm a person who loves
Style and I love fashion
But
Lowe's
Ricky
Json
Explain the nuance
As we learned in episode number 5 of Articles of interest about denim
The process
Making clothes
Any kind of clothes is really wasteful
And we live in a world where it is
So easy to just buy new clothes
And that's what I used to do all the time not even thinking about it I think a lot of people who don't consider
Big shoppers
Just you know it here and there occasionally just impulsively buy things from the internet from us
Store
And maybe sometimes it fits in sometimes
It's your style and sometimes it's not
Whatever then you donated to the Goodwill and that's good for the Goodwill and that is totally how I live
From the consumerism because you know you're going to donate it and clothes are these
And that lead
Donatable object
But that's
Not enough
It's no no because it
Really
Most clothes end up in landfill
Anyway
And
Goodwill and Salvation Army these amazing organizations provide this like a virtuous outlet for us to just continue getting rid of clothes
Buy new stuff
All the time
And when the cycle of Life by donut by donut by donut by donut
Which you know it's good to donate your clothes
But
It's not
The solution for overconsumption
And
Close
Distribute
To 8%
All CO2 emissions in the world
Huge
Huge output
And we are just consuming too many new things until every designer I talked
Thinking about this
Concerned about this worried about this
And
So many people are just like you need to stop buying
Yeah
Even the people who make the clothes Vivienne Westwood
Herself has this whole campaign she has your shirts what they buy less on them I don't know if she's selling them or not but
Honor Twitter does a video where she's like
I'm making this new collection
But you
Because
I don't buy clothes
That's the tricky thing as someone who loves fashion and lifestyle
It's extremely hard to be like stop
Bayern because
It's a really important for myself
Expression
And as you grow and as you change
And as your
Entire body completely regenerate on a cellular level every 14 years you need to find new ways to express
Brace yourself and the world around you is changing the weather is changing like
You can't not
WEAR news
Yeah
So how did you stay
The cycle of
I'm buying them
Ironically
My cell really pared-down in the course of reporting
Frau that's because I was traveling so much
I lived off of backpack and I had a uniform I wore
Is black overalls and a blue shirt every day and it was extremely embarrassing cuz I was interviewing these
Fashion designers Consultants you know and I was the
Unshowered mess in these clothes that I've been wearing over and over again and
I recommend everyone do this it was like going on a fast
Yeah I just have this one outfit and then I got
Back
Oakland
And
Suddenly look at my now in Norma Seaman closet
I guess I was just
So overwhelmed by the number of clothes I had him if I go to the Wonderland and I can
Play in this forever
Oh so you're saying that like it actually helped you not consumer buying you clothes as they were new to you
Totally
And actually owe this amazing producer Eleanor Kagan
Has this great little game she likes to play call the Pantone challenge see about a book of Pantone color wheels
And try to pick out outfits based on color wheel combinations just a helper like rifle around and dig out new thing
Are all these ways of like
Appreciating what you already have
But you know
But doesn't that you're never
You will check your body changes you change attitudes change and style is a thing
I used to have this idea
I used to think I was immune to fashion and I used to think that fashion people
Like get Vogue magazine
And a bit like it's the Bible and when Vogue says
Polka dots are in like you go out and you buy polka dots and you throw out your stripes and that's not how fashion works we all
Pay attention to Fashion
But the way it manifests is not from this
Ruling that comes down from on high it's just when you
Look in your closet and you think I have nothing to wear
Or when you see someone
Wearing something new and you like that one
What's kind of Interest
Hawaiian shirts episode they were talking about how the cuts
Hawaiian shirts have changed how to call her
We're pointed in the seventies and
Now you know they were like kind of box here in the nineties in there a little tighter know like Fashions change they just do
All
Obey them
But the thing is
It's so easy to just scratch that itch right now to like seeing new style and be like I'm going to go online and just get it
And you can really easily
And this was a trap that I had
Falling into over and over again
And the person who changed my life
In this regard I went to a panel about sustainability just to do some research
This
Fashion consultant named Andy going through my name is Annie going through Dan die in fashion industry
I do like you know look
People say stop buying it's really hard to just quit
Set up to shame someone be like
Stop buying don't even buy
Awaited
Circumvent that
I guess I'd addiction or that poll is to buy something
That's used
There is this whole new
Market out there
A second-hand clothes the research is saying that we decide
Card
Before a year
Is that we buy and then before a year is up
Discard it
There's a
World of like
New looking clothes
It's a barely-used
I don't smell like mothballs they don't have stand on them and
Are these websites that you can go to
Thredup
Poshmark is another one
The real real is another one
You can shop on them like
As though they are new clothes you search for your size you can look for your color you can look for the price range
And
You can just
Kind of scratch that itch that need to like scroll and look and see what's out there find the brands at you
Typically by just
When I see something that I like I just checked want to be second hand stores
They have it instead
And this is not a way of buying less but it is a way
Of not buying any new material and it's also way really interrogating what I buy and some Justin
Constantly clicking it just helps we go wait a minute and it helps you realize do I really want it
If I do let's
Look
It's not even like digging through
Bins at the Goodwill it's not that involved it's one you know one or two searches
And it's helping me kind of wean myself off the habit
I'm just in possibly buying you things
So you can begin to pair down your consumption by buying second-hand
And then you can also donate
Second hand and then that's right
Create
A little bit more time
Between a thing being made
Intuit landfill
Totally
If you were not
Going to spend all your money on new clothes
What would you spend your money on Avery truffelman
What I always spend my money on Roman Mars
Podcast
Do the podcast
After you love the most
I also do the podcast that I work I actually done it to the podcast that I work for
Best radiotopia is the best
Totally
And also you know like if you were going to
You go out in the world
And
Consume thoughtfully
I thought you should know things and that's a lot of what we do here not just an articles of Interest
That's what we do at night
Invisible
And it's a
The thing that is
Quite virtuous it doesn't use a lot of
Carbon resources I don't know what the carbon footprint of podcasts are
Percent
So whatever you would spend
The next time you're on
Some
Site
For buying piece of clothing
Temperature right now
Take that amount of money
Philodendron bitter radiotopia. FM
Donate button
Feeling that amount
That's a great idea and then
Save the world a little bit
Go ahead more Beauty and
Sure and cool things in the world
And also know that when we do things
The reason why we can do experiments
And why were you able to grow and create new shows
Articles of Interest
Why we can experiment is we have this Baseline UPS
From our listeners
So if you want to be a part of that
Radiotopia. FM
And what donut
Yes
Answer
Nice
I think that's
Great thanks