We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet
But thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek out go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
When the country's leading providers of Auto in
With progressives name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
I was actually like Loki
Pretty good
Sarah Berger up in Hawaii
Just outside of Honolulu
When I was in
High School I visited New York for the first time
And noticed that a lot of
Vintage shops had all these
Tacky Hawaiian
Shirts
And that it was Fisk
Skinny jeans
This is a good thing right yeah that was totally a thing and it's still kind of a thing now
These days high end designers are making versions of Hawaiian shirts
Hawaiian shirts are in style
Most hilarious
Trapped
Why it just
So
Like where L L Hawaiian
Well first of all they wouldn't call them Hawaiian shirts
No one would say Hawaiian
In Hawaii that just sounds
In Hawaii there Aloha shirt
Are slightly different
The Aloha shirt is a very common thing
To where and why everyone has
It doesn't look
The same as a Hawaiian shirt
I don't know about you but I think of Hawaiian shirts as having like
Tiki heads in bikini ladies on them
Aloha shirts
A little more professional
Aloha shirts I like
Down you know like
Like really taste
Floral print
If you're going out to
You would wear a antelope
Really
Yeah
It's a very calm
But it's definitely
Still
A product of
You know what I mean like it's not like
Back in the day
Native
Aloha
Articles of Interest a show about what we wear and so maybe their ideas about clothing
Ideas about to a piece of cloth
But if you ain't got the attitude install the car at all
Manuel District closed
Markers
Which are the jigsaw pieces of the shirt that is the sound of an Aloha shirt maker wielding a giant and
Industrial blade
And he is cutting through about 50 layers of
Brightly patterned fabric
Stacked in a pile
Cutting all of the puzzle pieces out together like a perfectly plan
Jigsaw puzzle
And so this
Stack of 50 fabric squares will create 50 Aloha shirt
Is the back of the shirt
Placket
That's the front panels
Sa Yo there's a collars in the pocket over there
Jason Morgan but general manager of Kahala sportswear
Show me around kahala's Factory & Design Studio on Oahu
Kahala mix Aloha shirt
It's actually one of the earliest companies to do so it's been around since 1936
And is Jason and I watch this worker definitely cut out the puzzle pieces in the stacks
You can see that all the different parts are strategically placed along the pattern of the fabric
So json informs me with pride so we always match
And so that
Is why that pocket is specifically placed right there
When json does match the pocket
He means at the breast pocket of the shirt
Doesn't disrupt
The overall pattern
Like the breast pocket will be a continuation of the design
So that it Blends in it for Splash you don't even notice it
Looks like it's a lot of extra effort
It's a lot of extra effort it signifies a higher quality garment just more attention to detail
There are a few ways to tell if you're looking at a real authentic
High quality Aloha shirt
If the pocket matches the pattern that's a good sign but it's not the be-all end-all
Much of the understanding of an Aloha shirt is about
Paying attention to what is on the shirt itself
If it tells a story and it has real references that are specific to Hawaii
We know what fish that is and that it you can find it out here in the waters around
You know we're not going to slap something on a shirt just to do it cuz it looks cool
Visionland it's about a real place all the animals all the fruit all the landmarks
We'll all be real and significant to Hawaii or to the many cultures that have melted into it
How would you describe this classic
Simple one color ground one color print
Since the sixties it's white flowers on a solid color background this part
Saturn features breadfruit flowers because breadfruit was a primary staple a lot of Polynesian cultures
What they call the new plants which were the plants at the Polynesians took with them as they explored Polynesia
Has explored Polynesian Sailors discovered Hawaii and migrated there in significant numbers these kind
Find the specific cultural references or rather specific Multicultural references
Makes the difference between aloha
And Resort where is more informed by
What makes Hawaii unique it's something that you'll Bankers wear in downtown Honolulu
Bankers are in aloha shirts in downtown Honolulu everybody is leaving wear them for funeral
And part of the logic of Aloha tire is of course that's it's too hot in Hawaii to wear a suit
That does explain why the shirts are so colorful and patterned and fun they could have just as well worn plain white shirt
Hypothetically truly understand the origins of the shirt
One must understand the origins of the state
I don't have a copy hotfoot
Got to pronounce it correctly
Aloha kakahiaka that's good morning in Hawaiian this is data capture
The historian of Iolani Palace
Iolani Palace is the last official residence of the monarchs
Who wrote Hawaii is it combines Kingdom for 100 years
And its predecessors will here for over a thousand years prior to that
You only Palace is the only actual Bonafide Palace
On United States soil
Turn on Ballroom reception room
Formal receptions here
Receptions in the Blue Room would have included food Beverages and entertainment
You want a palace is
Truly elegant
With Sumptuous wooden staircases and crystal glassware
And what was then cutting-edge technology
They had electricity in 1887
4 years
For the White House in Washington DC
The king also installed a telephone oh yeah by 1889 home little probably had more phones for free
Person than any other city of it same size anywhere else in the world
This is all just to say
Hawaii as an independent constitutional monarchy
Transcended it's tiny geography
The kingdom was technologically advanced and known diplomatically all over the world
Queen liliuokalani
Our last Monarch is in the portrait on the wall over here
In this portrait she is wearing the Gown that was
Created to be worn at Queen Victoria's golden jubilee in London
Liliuokalani became queen of hawaii in 1891
And choose a musician as well he was a musician she composed over a hundred fifty different songs
Including Aloha toy
It's a really famous song
The highway is actually a love song
Aloha means goodbye to you
It was written
In 1878
She saw
A woman and a man saying goodbye to each other
And it was such a touching scene as she was coming home
She's humming and writing in her head
She had a wonderful ability to write songs
So we're talking about Billy okalani because she's a major character in the story of how Hawaii became a territory
And then part of the United States
Which led to the rise of the Aloha
And in many ways
This all starts
With sugar
Sugar became a minor industry until the Civil War
When is sugar planters
In the United States
Could no longer grow back
Because they were fighting the war
To the sugar industry Skywalker
An influence and in
Income
Most of the sugar plantations were owned by
Americans and Europeans
Many of the Hawaiians may not have had the money
To be able to buy the property
Some of the immigrants
Fortunately does it have family that had money
European and American sugar magnets who had been setting up plantations all over the Hawaiian Islands work their way in
Into the legislature of Hawaii
Give themselves better deals on the shipping and tariffs
They impose a constitution
That dramatically reduce the power of the monarchy
Any more of a figurehead
The Constitution also allowed non-hawaiians citizens to vote
Allowed non-citizen residence
Are American and European ancestry basically it was those
Who could read or write English or some other European language
2 Bolt
So disenfranchised were native Hawaiians
Left out the huge Chinese community
Sugaring European so why can't we
This allowed American and European business interests him Medellin Hawaiian government even more
Estelle
With what little power she had
Wheely okalani tried to get that imposed Constitution repealed
Pretends to put into effect a new constitution
Cuz your group of 13 local residents of American and European ancestry
To create the Committee of Public Safety
To protect their own in
That's a group that opposed Lido kehlani
The long and short of it
Is that well-connected businessmen used the US military as backing for a coup
In 1893 the monarchy was overthrown and a provisional government was established
McQueen was accused
Treason in America video kehlani
They brought her here to this room
This is called the imprisonment room this is where she was held under house arrest
Very sparsely furnished
And initially no writing material
For eight months
Emilio Kalani was Prisoner in this front room of Iolani Palace
Edison lights
Screams in hot
For lack of writing materials
Video kehlani and her one permitted companion
Sewed
She made a quilt
From brocaded silk fabrics and ribbons from her own wardrobe
And she stitch them with the names of her friends and supporters
Embroidered are the words
Imprisoned at Iolani Palace
And that's as we began this quilt
There
Which means they completed it elsewhere
The quilt was probably completed after liliuokalani moved to her private residence down the
Street where she continued her life as a
The private citizen
Until she died in 1917 she was considered until her death
As Queen of
Hawaii
And respected as such
And the queen quilt
Would not be the last time
Story of Hawaii would be told and cloth
From overthrow to statehood Hawaii was in sort of limbo as a territory
The sugar industry had changed
Everything
From the Constitution to the configuration of the government
Actual makeup of the population of the Hawaiian Islands
The Hawaiian Islands from the late 1800s
What's a 1924
Were the scene of many different immigrants coming into work in the sugar industry
The sugar plantation owners were mostly white Americans and European
Recruited field workers from China Korea the Philippines and Portugal
Japan this is just sort of brown the historian at the Bishop Museum in Honolulu
And
The federal government of the United States ended
Asian immigration in 90
24 but by that time
The population of Hawaii was about
40% ethnically Japanese
Excluding Japanese
Fabric
The Japanese fabric
Was
A witch
Which was made specifically for kimonos
Just the Japanese Nash
Costume
And there was one particular company
In downtown Honolulu that
Call Worcestershire Worcestershire sauce Japanese fabric
And you can go in and choose the fabric you like and they would make a shirt for you
You could buy a western-style collared shirt
Made out of kimono fabric
Became a fun special thing to buy especially for the Youth
Buy about 1936-37 local manufacturers then begin to
Have
Fabric
Custom made
With tropical or Pacific or Hawaiian motif
In addition to the Japanese mochi
Which were already available
Kahala
The company you heard cutting the pile of shirts
Established in 1936
And it was one of the first to mass produce aloha
Because these shirts sold like hotcakes as souvenirs
Americans first started coming to Hawaii on map
A soldier's
And as Taurus
It was always intended to be like souvenir shirt
DIYs
Where is the desire to have
Something as a reminder a token the souvenir of
Of the experience
And then one day
Went back home after World War II and all that
But aloha shirts were still nice
People didn't wear them around in a real way
Even on the territory of Hawaii
Look like the Westin one
Everyone was dressed like they lived in an American Metropolis
Prior to
2 it wouldn't be unusual
Everybody in downtown
Suit tie
90 degrees outside
Humidity and everyone's walking
Is ridiculous this is Josh Feldman
CEO of
Tori Richard
Which is a Resort Wear company and the parent company of Kahala
The Aloha wear manufacturer
Josh's father
Mort Feldman
Was the founder of the
And even he
The founder of a Resort Wear company
Used to wear
Suit and tie to work
Everyday
My father and I
He's wearing
Coppola Mad Men suiting
Dapper looking guy
But
It's kind of farcical
Write that
On a tropical island
Josh's father joined forces with some other Aloha a tire manufacturers
And they formed a lobbying group
Called the Hawaiian fashion Guild
In 1962
They began a campaign
Called
Operation liberation
It's all started with operation liberation
Which was to get mint
Where are the hotter in the summer months
In operation Liberation the Hawaiian fashion Guild gave each
State representative and senator
To Aloha shirt
And then
They took it a step further
They decided let's Lobby
And get this
State Legislature
Justice League
On Fridays
Who are products
Hawaiian attack
They got a resolution pass
Cast in 19
C7
Formally creating Aloha Friday
Formally creating a Friday that were
Acquired
State Legislature
Where this product
That meant every Friday members of the State Legislature
Wore Aloha shirt
And then that spread to the business
The way to
Support
Factors in the people wants
They started doing that
Hey this is a heck of a lot more
And wearing a suit
And that went on for a number of years in pretty much every day B
Became a lot
On any given day of the week in downtown Honolulu you can see people in Aloha shirt
Not the Jimmy Buffett vacation kind of way
A workplace casual kind of way
And to this day
This especially ramps up on Friday
And if you live in the mainland United States this notion of a casual Friday
Might sound Vaguely Familiar to you
Casual Friday
And casual
Would go on to affect how we all dress at work
Not just in Hawaii all over the United States
The Casual Friday cam
Evelyn credits Dockers
Dockers in a company that makes khaki
And they are owned by Levi Strauss jeans
Babe
Fully acknowledged
They do
We're here on the West Coast
Aloha and the prince once aloha shirts at the scene Levi's started manufacturing them
Aloha shirt since the thirties I hear at Levi Strauss
Company this is Tracy Penick
Historian at Levi Strauss & Company
But you needed a companion
Peace and we introduced in the early in the 90s
We introduced the idea that human resources department said that you could let your workers come to work
Rest one day a week
In something a little bit more
Casual.
Curse Princeton's in with Dockers
Levi's really created the concept
The business casual wear
Which they then sold to businesses we took the idea to Human Resources departments in fact
We created a kit
How to put casual business wear to work
And we sent thousands around 2 HR department
And in it and included a guide to what was
Appropriate wear and in this guy that we're looking at here is
A man dressed in his Dockers slacks and a collared shirt and other
Clothing that he could wear Aloha Friday came from Hawaii
Casual Friday
Came from Levi Strauss & Company
We are credited Levi Strauss & Company for creating
Business casual Fridays
This business casual movement in now
It's not just one day a week
A business casual for many
Workplace environments is okay all through the week
This might be one of the largest seismic ship
In recent fashion history
Turn to casual
Goodbye silk ties and garters and stockings
And knowing how to use an iron
Hello
Two CEOs in sweatshirt
And it's not that Casual Friday invented casual wear that is a much
Target phenomenon
It has its roots in the rise of Leisure Time
And the rise of sportswear and the influx of college students dressing more practically to Trippers campuses
What Casual Friday gave us
With a foot in the door
Casual wear
Spread into public life
Where does casual break
It hurts up
When does it start to B12 churches
Regional specific
This is Deirdre Clemente historian of 20th century clothing and fashion and author of the book dress casual
And she says business casual was the Tipping Point
Because
The office was kind of The Last Vestige of everyday Formal Wear
The office
What's the last place to break which I think because it's such a public
Runt the places where people had more interaction with clients like maybe Banksy or somebody
Sales rep who had to go into attic
And yet many bankers and politicians still wear suits
But for Life Industries now where workers sit in front of a computer they don't need to change into heels or iron a jacket
I think casual dress
Speaks to America
Desire to be
Comfortable it speaks to our desire
To create in many ways
Classless society
Or at least the appearance of a classless society
America as a nation where everybody considers themselves middle-class matter who you ask
70% of Americans
Poor or wealthy
Call themselves middle class
Casual dress really speaks to everyone sooner wanting to dress more towards
Socio-economic middle
Send the edges it's almost uncool
To dress up
Watch now
Dressing up with
Call too much attention to yourself
And that way
The Aloha shirt is a beautiful aberration
When I think
Aloha shirts I think of my dad because my dad wears almost
Solely aloha
She has probably
Aloha shirts
Because he wears one
Obsessed with buying different ones
Where he'll get really into the pattern I really like this
Textile or whatever
Aloha shirt is bright
Aloha shirts
Colorful and bold that tells a story
Yes about a fish or bird or plants
Also
Quietly
About the whole history of a little chain of islands
I left an outsize imprint on the world
Pieces
Words from yes
Portrait
Painted on the things we love
Articles of interest is made by myself
Avery trufelman
Edited by Joel Rosenberg
Music by Royal intro and outro themes by Sony Ashworth
Back Jack by Graham Haisha mix by Kelly Coyne and Roman Mars
Is the Big Kahuna
This whole series
Thank you to Delhi
When are the Bradley Nick Wong in the Alcatraz Islanders
Quick career and michelia gems world
As well as Katie mingle Vivien Leigh Delaney Hall Kirk Olmstead Street Yousef Chun real Fitzgerald and the whole nine
99 p i t
Mahalo
Make yourself and make it stand out with Squarespace create a beautiful website to promote your business publish content sell Prada
And much much more
High Moon Squarespace sites Roman mars.com to Showcase my work
As links to my TED talk into radiotopia even has a sign-up form for the 99percentinvisible Weekly Newsletter
It was really easy to make a man of myself
Which is how I know that you'll have no problem making a Squarespace site to
Christmas Bayside, invisible for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Easy offer code invisible for
For 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
You
You inspired Xfinity to create internet that puts you in charge
Bob Ross
Your movie marathons are better
When you can stream them all night
Video chats for Grandpa's birthday it should be possible from anywhere in your house
And when you can pause wifi before bedtime
Putting your kids to sleep gets a little bit easier
So Xfinity reimagined Wi-Fi in created Xfinity X5 because for the best Wi-Fi XP
Prince mini speed coverage and control
This is beyond Wi-Fi this is X5
Visit xfinity.com
To learn more
The rise of casual wear
In many ways
Has been the rise of synthetic
You start to see America's really accepting synthetic fibers
Acrylic fiber
Spurs going into sweaters Dacron all that kind of stuff you know the name brand
DuPont
Sponsored
Ifiber
Going into sweaters Men's Wear huge mentor
Synthetic fiber
Breaking kit
For good reason
We are sick
Trying to fit into our clothes
We want our clothes to fit us
We won't stretch
What a little gif
Flexibility
Which comes at a price
Your next article of Interest
Is denim
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com