We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
Yes. EDU
This is not 99percentinvisible
But I am Roman Mars
So I created a secret
Side project podcast
Sex with a friend of mine
The goal was to take some of my anxiety
About the political news
And turn it into something
Destructive
And fun and interesting and share with me
Hope you like it
I hope you subscribe
Hope you tell all your friends
Let's send it to the top of the charts that would be nice
I want to take all of this energy
And do something good
Like learning the US Constitution
So here's the introductory at
The whole idea for the series
Just came from a tweet
It was by Elizabeth Joe she's a professor at the UC Davis School of Law
And I know her personally because our kids go to the same Elementary
Elizabeth tweet red and I'm paraphrasing a little bit so it sounds better when I read it out loud
Teaching constitutional law in 2017 mean
Glancing at Twitter every 5 minutes before class
First I laugh
Then I retweeted
And then I wondered
What is that mean exactly
I mean I kind of have an idea what constitutional law is
It's a class that sometimes called the structural aspect of the Constitution mention law professor Alyssa
How so I talk about things like
A separation of powers what are the different powers of the president vs. Congress
I also talked about federalism
So how much
Power Congress has as opposed to state
It's nothing about that usually require me
If you're going to be a lawyer
It's a class I love teaching a lot
I admit that not every student loves it
And I can see why
For example the very first case I assign on the first day of class
Every year
Is a case that was written in 1803
It's called Marbury versus Madison it's a big deal and we'll talk about it at some point
You need to know right now is
Is it the first sentence of that case
Is 60 words long and the verb comes in the middle
So it's pretty dry
This year's been a little bit different
This is what Trump can teach us about con law
An ongoing series of indefinite length
Where we take the extreme actions of the chief executive of the United States
In channel that chaos
Little Learning our constitution
Like we never have before
I'm your fellow students and host
Roman Mars
Coming up
We're going to law school
But in a fun way and it's meant for everybody
Converse
We got to pay some bills
I'm still can be cheaper in Moscow
Support for Trump con law comes from Squarespace
As you can tell from the existence of this side project podcast of mine I like to take on new creative projects just because
I can't help myself
If you're about to embark on a new project you should announce it to the world with a cool website from Squarespace
Their award-winning templates are the simplest and most beautiful way to present your ideas online even someone like me who
There's No Business coding at all
Can create a beautiful website with Squarespace is all-in-one platform there's nothing to install patch or upgrade
Ever After free trial in 10% off
Your first purchase visit squarespace.com
Con law
It's all one word
Squarespace.com
Con law
So the bread-and-butter of law professors
Are hypothetical
Professors love
Crazy things that happened that they serve
Think about in their minds what if
What could happen
And so it's the sort of thing that is not realistic always but it's a way to get law students to think about
What are the limits of the law
Here's a crazy hypothetical former president sue a sitting president for libel for making
False statements synonym
Possible but it is possible in this new reality that's not a crazy hypothetical
President Trump tweeted
That President Obama had illegally tattoos phones during the election process
He said it was at the level of Watergate
And he called him a bad or sick
Guy
Doesn't appear to have any proof but that's what he tweet
And this new window into the mind of
Trump has changed the way Professor Joe prepares for class
Before this year when I
Prepared to teach
Each day's class
Constitutional law
Typically I would
Read what I had assigned
Look through my notes from the previous year
Go teach class
Her procedure
A little bit different this year
This year I had a little ongoing note to myself
Do not go to class until I have checked whether the president has tweeted
If the president has tweeted
Screenshot the tweet
And discuss
Swift class
Roman when you brought up the idea of having some basic explanations about,
I thought what a terrific idea
There are so many constitutional issues
This presidency has brought up
Whether you're testing mathematical models were automobile crash
Cuz I think you can learn a lot about something
By testing the extreme
So I like this idea that maybe we have a president just kind of stress testing the concert
Really giving us in a sense of
What are the limits of each of the different Provisions that
He seems to be
Challenging in the car
And that's
It's really important because it turns out
It's forcing us to think about things
And wonder well do we have answers to some of these questions
For example
When can Trump treat the presidency like The Apprentice
And declare you're fired when can the administration declare it's going to cut off funds to Sanctuary cities
When the president
Talks about
So-called courts
Should we be worried about that
Should be worried that the salad yet
But we'll do an episode about it nonetheless
Is that going to happen
I think it's actually practically pretty unlikely
But Everybody's Talkin
And wondering about this portion of the Constitution
So it's important to understand what it's about
Maybe even more interesting is that we're dusting off part of the Constitution that people hardly even considered
A hundred years
For example
President Trump just went
Overseas
He got a gold medal in Saudi Arabia
Can you keep that shiny gold medal
Is that the kind of thing that's barred by the emoluments Clause of the Constitution
What about owning the Trump Hotel or property in other countries
Plus there's this hardly considered part of the Constitution that Liberals are salivating over
Could a president be declared unfit to serve and then removed from office
That's the 25th
These questions don't generally make it into the basic constitutional law textbook
Because really no one has cared about them before
They're not relevant that's the basic answer
It's kind of relevant now
So this is a real opportunity
I think
When it comes to the Constitution this should be a moment to care a lot about the concert
And it's not an onerous task
It's short
It's less than 5000 words
You know we're both Californians here so I'll give you an example to California
The California Constitution is 100 pages long it's one of the longest in the world
So by contrast the Federal Constitution
You can read in one sitting
Freezing
It's also remarkably stable.
The Federal Constitution has only been changed or amended
27 *
I'm really only 17 times since the first
Can the Bill of Rights were ratified very shortly after the original
California Constitution we love changing stuff we get tired of
We've actually change their state constitution over 500
California
So what's my confusion here it turns out that in 2017 I've decided
That Trump
Can teach you a lot
,
So we're going to learn the Constitution together
Because of trump
Because I need something to hold onto
The Constitution
Is the life raft
Our forefathers gave us
Dammit
I'm going to learn how it work
A preview of what's coming up this season on Trump con law
Are you hiring are you the president invoking Article 2 Section 2 Clause 2 of the US Constitution
Well with ZipRecruiter you can post your job
To 100 + job sites with one click then they're powerful technology efficiently matches the right people
Do your job
Better than anyone else find out today why ZipRecruiter has been used by businesses of all sizes to find the most
Qualified job candidates with immediate result
And right now my listeners residents and non-residents alike
Can post jobs on ZipRecruiter for free
Go to ziprecruiter.com
Vet ziprecruiter.com
This season
On what Trump can teach us about con law
Refers to the Judiciary as so-called
He really raises a question about
Judicial legitimacy
It's going to take us back in time to Youngstown Ohio President Truman and the Korean War
President Trump has threatened Sanctuary cities
Why is that even an issue for the federal government to talk about that's because of the spending clause
Trump wants to build a border wall and we're still not sure who's going to pay for it but one thing that's absolutely clear
Is it if you're going to build a physical wall along the Southern United
States
You have to take people's private
And that involved the takings clause
We are probably going to get a lot stricter with the Border
In all kinds of places not just
List the physical border of the United
But also at International Air
And many more people are raising concerns that their cell phones and laptops are
We're getting looked at
Buy border
What happens when you are asked to provide the
The contents of your cell phone or lap
Why can that happen
Can it happen that has to do with the Fourth Amendment so-called border.
So every week I'm inviting you and Elizabeth Joe over to my house
The teachers these topics in so so many moron
What Trump
Can teachers
About con law
It's going to be fun and you're going to get smarter and be a better City
Bring the kids
They're going to like it too
Subscribe now in apple podcasts radiopublic or wherever you get your body
First full episode is already there waiting for
Go to trumpconlaw.com
This show is produced by Elizabeth Joe and me Roman Mars
AllMusic and Trump con law is provided by Doomtree records
The Midwest hip hop Collective
The two big takeaway lessons from the show
AR
Learn the Constitution
And
By Doomtree record
Because both will make your life 100% better
Attractions week were from Sims
Desa and laserbeak
We are proud member of radiotopia
From pra
Find out more
A radio talk
Radio 2