99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of Auto insurer
Progressive Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price and coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high quality leads website traffic
And higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title
Company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
Roman Mars
When you crank the gear of the music
You make the tune go as fast
Or as slowly as you want
As you spend the little handle around and around
The music is read from the series of little bumps like Braille
Producer Avery trufelman
These little bumps stick up and they hit a series of time
Which creative song
It's a form of storage this is dag Spicer
Senior curator at the Computer History Museum
Program which is the music
You think of that as software even though you
Think of it as that
That's really what it is it software
In this method of data storage series of bumps or series of holes
Was also used in player pianos
It's also the mechanism behind computer Punch Cards
Ask your grandfather
Throughout most of the twentieth century Punch Cards were the dominant form of data processing
Input and output
Form paper punch card technology
Precursor to electronic computing
Was the way that data was stored and tabulated
Decades back when computer is would take up a whole room
Best technology
Bumps and holes
Is also
Why you wearing
What you wearing
Write well one of the things you may not know is that an early
Automated weaving machine actually has a role to play in the history of computing
When he says a weaving machine
Dag is talking about a loom
Illume is gigantic
Well there are lots of different kinds of looms in different sizes but
Yes
European industrial Looms in the 1700s
We're really
Big
About 30 feet high in some cases and maybe 30 ft long and
It's an enormous enormous piece of
The design in the fabric is determined by how many threads the Weaver goes over or under
Which one's come to the top
Which ones are submerged in the Wii
These patterns were so complicated and intricate industrial Weaver's needed to hire
Little delicate fingers to pull the threads and keep track of them
It's on the 17th century this was a job for the draw boy
An actual boy
So your draw boy
Would go and say well we need to have the white showing through here
So I pull this one
This one needs to
Go all the way through but this one needs to be skipped and on and on until he's pulling these thread this is Chris Garcia
Also a curator
The Computer History Museum
It must have been
Murder on fingers
Well they were tools created to help the draw boys
Forks and leavers in harnesses
It wasn't all done with bare hands
But
It was a lot of work to do
You could imagine if you have significantly large item you might have
Friends that have to be pulled
At the beginning of the eighteenth century
Clothes imported from China became All the Rage in France
And a fashion developed for beautiful tiny
Ornate weaving
Making closer little bit finer a little bit
More interesting to look at
You can use a check card
Patterns sophistic
The Jacquard Loom was the device invented by Joseph Marie Jacquard
In 1804
This is me and you can attach it to the power loom
Nothing it's like
An added feature
People with the word private clubs you can produce
Each new fabric design was encoded in thick
Cardboard
Each whole position of the whole represents
A hook on the loom
A hole in the card told the loom yes
Lift This Thread is raised or lowered
Depends on whether there's a hole or not a hole
Indeed Jakarta
Cool cards tied together into a loop
Said automatically
Into the loom
In one card represented just one pass of thread
But there'll be lots of cards so together
And loop of cards went around and around and around
Create a repeating pattern
Just like the music
Encoded in the music box
Didn't mean the machine was weaving the cloth automatic
It still required a master Weaver and a pattern designer and
But it did mean
The draw boys
We're out of a job
Once you have a Jacquard mechanism
You don't need the driveway
Half of your
Workforce
Can be eliminated
Manufacturers who wanted to make
The most beautiful the most intricate patterns
It was increasingly more important than labor
Was intellectual property
The designs
In Jacquard Stein people stole these control cards
Because they represented patterns
If they
Patterns for popular could be very lucrative
Fashion goes in Styles and everybody comes out with the same stuff every each other almost
The same trends
So I like to think of this is the first instance of software piracy
The people are stealing these
Jacquard Loom cards
And the Jacquard Loom cards would lead to the development of an entire new industry
I would change the world
In 1890 a German American
Invention in Sherman Hall
Devised a solution to the United States Census Bureau has problem of counting all the new
Prince to the country and citizens
Tabulating the census used to take about 10 years
So they mean by the time the sentence with finished
Start taking the next one
How old is came up with a sister
Where is each individual's information
Punch on cards
It could be process more quickly
Herman Hollerith
Specifically quoted the Jacquard Loom
As his influence
His influence for coming up with computer Punch Cards
Once you have
Patterns of holes in the card it's now machine-readable
And that's how the census was done in 3 years instead of
The 1890 census was a huge advance in the history of computing
Now just to wrap up the story
Hollaras punch-card patents were actually the foundation for a small company you may have heard of called international business machine
Or IBM
Which in some ways owes its existence
To the Moon
And to that Rising demand for beautiful ornate pattern
Pictures of fashion
Because of fashion
Fashion is just another word for the constant inevitable shifts in popular taste
Garments
Just like buildings and cars and movies
Reflect the circumstances of Our Moment in history
That's what fashion is
Another way of telling time
Back
And back and forth
Around and around
Tulum inspired as the computer
Computer changed the way we think about clothes
Clothing and culture
Impact each other
We need to dedicate some serious time
The talking about what we wear
So that's what we're going to do
The past eight years we've asked you to start noticing elements in architecture and design because architecture
Is the art we live in
The medium in which we move
Influencing us
In a thousand invisible waves
The next three weeks we're going to ask you to do the same
With another Universal art that we all live in
Clothing
It's our first spin-off show hosted by Avery
Cold articles of Interest
I'll be right here
Twice a week
For the next 3 weeks in your 99.
We'll have the first episode after this break
About what happened to working children
Like those draw boys
And how their clothing change
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
Routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define if you're constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flash podcast
So what are you wearing right now
LG
So what I'm wearing now
This is a
Black shirt from like American Apparel and
It's like
God fabric
Can't explain it
My friend and colleague Joe Rosenberg is a really good dresser
He just had this Rich understanding of
Styles and cuts
And you can just tell and all these subtle ways
Hello that is
Seven For All Mankind jeans
B good
Kids size
What I wear
Joe shops in kids sizes
I'm forfeiting
I guess you could say I'm a
But
I don't think myself
I'm just the size
10 year old
Joe doesn't have the typical dimensions of someone with dwarfism
Just called
Pronunciation
I'm spondylo
Dysplasia
It's a mutation
To demonstrate out Rarity
My entire life
Only have one occasion to meet someone
Who was my height and was short in the way I was short
Harding College
And we talked about
Articles of Interest a show about what we wear and so maybe the ideas about clothes
Ideas about craft modular home to a piece of cloth
But if you ain't got the attitude install the car at all
Manuel District closed.
Close our records of the bodies we've lived in
Think of an old
What are you used to have that's
Just not your style anymore
Or jeans with us aren't your size anymore
We are like snakes to shed our skins
And grow new ones as we age
And it all starts
In the kids.
Oh wow Joe and I went to J.Crew together
He was pretty much ready to give up as soon as we walked in a vignette
Kids section was
One row
And everything in it was very loud
This shirt glows in the dark
Has many
Tie-dye bicycles on it
So many stripes that maybe it almost were
The color palette of the children's Department tends to be really bright and way over decorated as Joanne died
Debriefed in his car
Short person having shop for kids clothes
Is that your life is just
Desales game
I've liked
Ripped jeans and deliberate patches and fun slogans and crazy zippers
Bold colors and prints and the idea that you're
Slim
Jeans
Enough
Subtle
Hugh
Dark wash
It just doesn't matter
It almost makes no sense
You'd think that we would also
Start as young blank canvases
Dressed in shades of white and gray
Slowly acquiring more and more colors
Moore graphics
More signifiers of we are as we age and solidify into ourselves
Finally retire in jeans that we've ripped and distressed and patched ourselves
Paired with graphic t-shirts that list all the bands TV shows we've watched
Cities we've visited throughout our lives
But no
All that decoration and phony self-expression
Is put in a blender with birthday cake in sequence and then
Put in a hanger on a rack
That's the kids section
It's really bad
And actually even if I'm just
Slightly
So how did we get here
Where did the style we call children's clothes come from
Children's clothes haven't always been a thing
And historically especially in the United States
Childhood itself
Was a luxury
Cuz you have working children
Parents Sue
Are not slaves
But have to work
Can the children
Are slaves
But have to work
And maybe.
Have a childhood much
Billy at all
This is Erin lgo
She's the curator at the lacis Museum of lace and tie
Textiles in Berkeley
Some children always clean and some children always
That's class
What are some of the slave
Free The Children who are not considered
Clean or precious
Didn't get
Children's clothes
I'm sure you seen pictures of children that are working
And they do book my
Mobile.
As they're standing in the
Cotton mill
Boys at the down and work in the mines
Basically poor children were given what was around
Well upper-class children had the privilege of being deliberately dressed
And although fancy children were also sometimes dressed like little adults
Underneath their clothes
A lot of them were wearing corsets
Parents want to raise you Crackle
They would put you
Boys and girls in cursive
There's a whole idea that children had to be cultivated
Like a dog in a harness
Or flower on a trellis
Nova courses for not as intense
As older women wore
But yes please
Who's considered
That you would be in
And although it happened slowly
The demise of the child corset is thanks to philosophers
Jean-Jacques Rousseau
A concept of childhood that we have now
Was really formed
In 1762
Rousseau wrote
Hold childhood in reverence
I do not be in any hurry to judge it for good or for ill
Give nature time to work
Before you take over her business
Less you interfere with her dealings the time childhood is
In the 18th century
Close
Just for child
And they look different than adult clothes
Annies close
Children are dressed up
For the occasion of their youth
This amazing time free from cares
Separate from the rest of their lives
When we look at them today we can't believe anyone
They may have been easier to move in then a corset
But these clothes are still really formal
Like embroidered dresses for girls and boxy little suits
For boys
But it just looks like a little suit I guess
I know it is it is adorable actually
Two children are wearing these adorable mini me get up
It's almost like a parody of adulthood
Stuff meant to look like adult clothes
That adults would never actually wear
Which is what we see now in the kids Department
It has everything to do with our evolving concepts of childhood
And how much
Freedom and protection we think children ought to have
Because although their corsets are long gone
Children are still bound
By legal requirements
What what is this thing you gave me
This is from the NRA no not that NRA National Association of
Australia
My friend Morgan is not Australian
See the technical designer for a big children's clothing company
She'd rather not say which one one of the major children's clothing retailers
In the United States
Her company has many many many rules about what can and cannot be until it's closed
But those rules are top secret
Don't Morgan brought me that Australian safety guy
Because it's kind of similar and it gives you a rough idea
Pages
Long
And thorough
And it goes through at the beginning
The way you assess risk
Which is high to low based on
A kid could die from it
You don't want choking hazards no sharp edges and no drawstrings
Injuries and deaths occur in would not tacos or cord ends to come snatch your cotton to moving parts or closing doors
Naruto dress that you can't have
A car that's longer than three inches and that goes all the way up to
12 years in the United States sometimes in the kids section you can see drawstrings on hoodies or sweatpants
But those are actually function there just decorative
It's basically so that kids can look like little adults
Without running the risks of adult dressing
To the clothing companies don't get in trouble you can get sued for sure if you could kill kids you know
You're not doing it just for the sense of morality
These guidelines are the cobbled-together aftermath of a series of disasters
Every time an item is recalled or clothing company gets sued for endangering a child the guidelines get revised
Or Titan
I'm one of the biggest legal differences
Between children and adult clothes
Is flammability
Flame retardant
Everything has to be flame retardant if they're sleeping
If a child is going to sleep in it
The fabric
Has to be flame retard
And the Garment has to
Fit tight
They are concerned about
Candles Night Lights
Fires in house
Whatever could happen if
Their kid is wearing loose-fitting clothing and it's hanging this from YouTube
How about an ox
Give you a bunch of third-degree Burns
Anything that could potentially be sleepwear
How to renew your skin tighten a city climbers
Distance of that
And this
Starts to get at our question about why kids clothes look the way they do
Because note how Morgan said anything that could
Potentially be sleepwear
Probability rules don't just apply to clothes labeled as pajamas
They could apply to Any Garment apparel
Put the kids to sleep in for that a kid decides that they want to sleep in it
So anything that is comfortable or soft
Which means that kids clothing if it's not sleepwear
Have to go through great pains to prove that it's not sleepwear
So that they don't have to meet all those flammability in size requirements
So let's say you're trying to design kid clothes that are not for sleeping
They can't have pictures of anything that could be interpreted as
Weepy like what is
Pictured on it is it sleeping animals is it a sleepy scene that make you feel sleepy if it makes you feel sleepy
Knit sleepwear
Sono images of the moon no images of stars
And no clouds
Your legal department at your company like you can't do that cuz that makes me feel like sleep
And then
Certain animals
Like I will
Same with other nocturnal creatures like bat
Unless you're designing a Halloween line and you really really really want to have a shirt with a bat on it
But enough is on Halloween in that had enough like sequins on it or something maybe you can get away with it
Sequence of good way to show garment is not for sleeping same with glitter and Action Graphics and bright colors in order
You could bring it enough out of sleepwear.
The kid would never want to sleep on
A jacket or something like that
It's decoration as a form of protection
Sending kids from fire and also protecting the companies from liability
Sometimes behind the glitter and garishness
It illegal subjects
Sometimes
Not all the time I would say that that they believe that they're giving you something more special
Something more marketable
By putting tchotchkes
On the Garmin
This is Lana Hogue the industry expert has been working in garment development and production for over 30 years
And the sequence
Are usually to appeal
To the child
Pets groups in focus
You know I think they should more I have not seen that anywhere really I worked
Manufacturers will ask
Parents what they're looking for in terms of styles
But not the kids themselves
Probably the closest they've come to focus groups and test groups
Where the photo shoots well and fit sessions we want to see how something fits but if they're kind of
And they want out of it
Then you know that that's probably just a special occasion
Cancel
A garment because
Kid didn't like it personally they don't
Estelle
The loudness of a kid's department has to do with safety rules
But not entirely
So it's not because of flammability it's because of what kids want but we don't ask kids what they want
Exactly now I think you're right
But if you took a child into the store
And you're walking around
A lot of them are drunk
To the the silly things hanging off a Garmin
But only up until a certain age and I think that kids go through a really awkward. Where they're trying to figure
Route
What school again cuz they don't trust their
There
Previous
Chase
Hello
This is true for anyone at any age
We move out of one face
And into the next
Unless you are trapped
In the children's section
And forever relegated
Phyllis bright
Loud
Strange way of dressing
The piece of paper
Words from yes
Portrait
Painted on the things we love
Articles of Interest was made by myself Avery truffelman edited by Joe Rosenberg
Music by Ray Royal intro and outro themes by Sami Ashworth fact-check by Graham Haisha mix by
Kelly coin and Roman Myers is the adult supervision of this whole series a very special thanks to
Kassia st. Clair Susie fur Juliet highly Andrew Solomon and the smitten Mitten audio collective in Detroit
As well as Katie mingle Emmett Fitzgerald Sharif Youssef Vivian Lee Delaney Hall Kurt Kolstad and the whole 99 PA
A-Team
When you think of old timey little kids
What's the main costumes that come to mind
Is the Steelers
Like Donald Duck
Illume Naval costume
A cute little future man
You're being part of this type of
Putting your kids into kind of something they might one day grow up and become
It's rather perverse but maybe
He says that in the United Kingdom the equivalent of the Sailor suit
With a little plaid Kilt
With a suit jacket over it
Because
This was once the uniform of the Catholic soldiers in Scotland
But they found me to dress your kids in
The little plaid Kilt with common for upper-class boys and then this uniforms red the girls
When they were also able to attend school
Your next article of Interest
Is plaid
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com