99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional net
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
I couldn't figure it out
Sitting on Olive Street
This is a Napoleon
She's a writer
And when she moved from Chicago to San Francisco
She didn't know who to hit on anymore
Midwestern career culture is extremely different
Agriculture
And one of the things that
Was most noted
Supposed to mean what
Fashion
Some of the queer signals for the Midwest
Didn't quite hold
Like plaid flannel shirts
In the Midwest
Or so I think
If you are part of a group
There are things you can wear or ways you can style your hair
Show that you are part of that group
Final is one of my eye to signify
I exist
But you can't really stop other people from wearing these signals and So eventually the power of that signal gets diluted
If you see someone wearing plaid now
Thank you
Well I might
First Bank are you on by
And then the next thing you know you can't even tell what clothing is signaling what anymore
Redbox
Bye
Best Straight lady
And I got
Obsessive that at
Outside bendik
About hipsters
Working class culture motifs
And
Flannel
Like lesbians are appropriating
Working class wear
So that's an interesting I don't know who actually owns
Phone
Articles of Interest a show about what
We wear until maybe the ideas about quotes about class
Piece of cloth
Where's clothes
But if you ain't got the attitude install the carried off
Manual defect clothes.
Lumberjacks wear plaid
Punks were plaid mini skirts
The Beach Boys
I kid you not
Used to be called the pendletones
Applied with their surfboards
So many different groups have adopted plaid
So it almost doesn't mean anything anymore
Really
Why are we all wearing this
This particular pattern
Which Once Upon a Time was mostly concentrated in the upper corner of this one Island
Off the coast of Europe
Set me for Coughlin distress
Precious thing
Identifies people in Scotland address as well
This is Peter McDonald historian at the
Scottish tartans Authority
They call this pattern tartan
Not
Plaid
We don't use that word
For patents
In this country
Platies a goblin
The Scotsman who lived in the highlands
The northern hilly part of the country
Used to wrap themselves in a cloth
Almost like a blanket
Kind of like an Indian sari
So if you like it's a top and sorry will be the nearest equivalent
Was called a plaid
It had a Tartan pattern
On it got into the US
And that way they become synonymous with the patent
It's not like
Back Then There Were Tartan shirts and Tartan scarves
No Tartan was on
These traditional plaids
Overcoats
And on the traditional pants
Which were called Truth
Tripping out tries it cuz it's the types include the feet
So that more like
Ladies tights
She knows what kind of this parochial little pattern but Scotsman in the country used to where it was pretty
Pretty much only used on these obscure traditional Highlands garments that I had never heard of before
And then something happened
Something that would
End up turning Tartan loose on the world
These obscure traditional Highland close
Warband
The ACT
Band
Are kilts
Plants and other elements of Highland dress and outdoor coats in top nekot where is well
Donald is talking about is the dress Act of 1740
Scotland was being taken over by the head of Aryan Empire
How many of the Scots
Subaru Outback
We're from the Highlands
And so they wore Tartan coats
And Kilts and plaids
21 Pilots
They would be seen as terrorists
Open fights depending on which side you wrong
But that's the reason
Forbade
It was a way to suppress the resistance
By limiting what they wore
Then we're not allowed to wear Highland clothes for 35 years in Scotland
But here's the thing
Just like banned books become the cool thing to read
When Scottish close or band
They became the cool thing to wear
This is Jonathan Ferris author of the book
Tartan
He says what the band did
Was that it made Highland closed
Trendy outside of Scotland
Suddenly
Tartan was also being worn in England
Meytal in the fashionable time break it was no longer a sign all indigenous Highlanders
Linda's all English people with special sympathy started the way
But Scottish man had an option
If they wanted to keep wearing their traditional clothes during the band
There was a loophole
They can go fight for the British Empire the band didn't apply to Scotsman who join
It encouraged people if they wanted to continue until
Age of God to join the military
Scotsman wearing tartans were deployed around the world which influence the style and popularity
Similar-looking patterns across the colonies
Like mattress in India
Maasai warriors
The colonialism of the British empire spread these influences around and increased Global demand for tart
And Tartan like Fabrics
The presence of Highland
Regimental soldiers wearing Tottenham son fulmore.
And meanwhile people in England with Scottish sympathies all got together in 1778 and made it kind of
Booster group
The advocate for Scottish culture
Some people the hottest sahib London was formed in order to try and preserve customs and manners
What was called the Highland Revival decline Revival they were responsible for the repeal of the
Site to 1782
Has finally lifted
It was just like
Tartan media the great Island Revival was in full swing
Scottish soldiers were coming home and now they could wear their Tartan and Englishmen were wearing Tartan and people
All over the colonies are wearing tartan
And North American
We're really wearing tartan
Obviously the kind of work shows
That you would
Particularly identify with American Oceanside a kind of plant working shirt
If you got back some of the earliest clothes
What we used full of tomatoes what shows was exported from Scotland
Tartan became a massive export to the United States
Top was a huge exports
To America in the 1700 early 1800
In the United States
Tartan was also a symbol of Heritage and belonging
If you were
Scotsman
Who was made to flee your Homeland
Or if you literally belong
To a Scotsman
Lots of very powerful squishies family is very active in the slave trade
These kinds of records are hard to find
But it said that enslaved people across the colonies
Also wore Tartan pattern cloth
Because
Tartan is bright
Unnoticeable
Slaves would be made to wear a cloth with a particular tartan
Which side who they belong to
You looking malty would be branded by you
Cognos bi or presses
We sprayed shooting
But he said needful those people was very much. Cost of Oppression
Tartan has been in many ways
A cloth of Oppression
But the Scots were being oppressed
Themselves or acting is
And the British Empire
Or perpetuating the global slave trade
And it functions efficiently as a
The clock of Oppression because it is so loud and highly visible
Negating the body
I'm becoming literally just the patent so you are literally Honda
Becoming the brand
Antarctica can be a brand of so many different conflicting things
In the United States
Tartan can be a nod to a rugged Highlander
Who's running around maybe looking out free sheet Monday wearing a kilt
La Monarca colonizer
Frequently used home
I think it is probably
Associated with ideas of colonialism in Empire
And that's aside from its associations with queerness or Lumberjacks or Cowboys are bike Messengers
Quite literally
There's a tartan
For everything
Dee Williams work
The national records of Scotland
In these boxes
Ikea
And she is showing me
The Scottish register of tartans
Which is very much not
Open to the public
How often does someone
Come to
You are the first
She said I was the first journalist to have been in there
Office
We don't say that
People coming in
Anybody can look online by the way they can look up if Peterson online did not register they just need to put in a
Search they just need to put in a name and it will come back
Curtains traditionally have been associated with Scottish names
So if your last name is McClain or McAllen or hannie
You can look up the traditional tartans
Associated with your clan
I had to the clan chief
Talk to David Henrie came in today
And he was looking at these tiny titans
Everyone who lives in Scotland has a long family history with a traditional last name and a family tartan
Scotland people wear Tartan Kilts to weddings
What are you supposed to wear if you're not from a clan
That's where you get out of
People that got Personal Touch
Sentinel Titans for designs
They really want it just for then you've also got organization corporate ones
Lots of military ones being registered lately
No matter who you are or how not Scottish you are
I will bet money but if you peruse the register of tartans
You will eventually find a Tartan for
Something
That you like or can identify with
The Zoo panda
Panda at the Edinburgh Zoo have a tartan
It's still just as tartan
But it's black and white
So these are some hairdos
Kaiser San Francisco
I won the San Francisco Tartan is Sandy and Scarlett like the colors of the 49ers
New Jersey Trenton is a sand and
Blue and
Splendor bits of red states in the US have an official tartan
A lot of countries have won Zimbabwe new Zimbabwe
Kenya
Oh wow this is the Africa folder
Volkswagen American Express and Coca-Cola have tartans
Nike have a couple
And there's a Tartan for the Scottish register of tartans
You too can have your very own official tartan
Death certificate cost 70 lb
And it's $100 if you want it in a wooden frame
But you'll get the tattoo name you'll get the registration number you can design your own Tartan and literally 10 minutes
Because official tartans don't have to be cloth anymore
You can go to any number of online Tartan generators
Business Club
And import the colors you want to use power and the thread count
And tell you the tartan
Saving my tartan
You'll get tan people design Utah
Dog
You know all their dead relative
Drinking why
Our historian friend Peter McDonald is part of the committee that assesses the incoming tartans
Theater on 8th
Proposal
And I wish doesn't make them good or tasteful or meaningful frankly
I mean to do some of these Titans get denied of the new incoming tartans
The majority of them
Arnott from Scotland
Top of my head 70% come from North America
Probably knows from the US by size
Portion from
Cottages Wells
Quite a few from Japan little Japanese school seems like top of the uniforms.
But yeah the majority of income from America
America is really
Into tartan
I mean just go to New York City on April 6th
What's National Tartan day
And they put on this huge parade with bagpipes
Scottish Terriers and Scottish associations from all over the US
Harden is one way that white people can claim some sort of cultural heritage
Because you're young country you all want to play in your heritage and actually a lot of people play me that
Scots-irish ancestry
Because it has
The cultural icons by dent
Which help you belong
And everyone wants to belong
2 something
Somewhere somehow
There's about a 30% increase last year Thomas register
Is it definitely increase
In some ways
If you don't get your Tartan actually woven
The register of tartans might seem like a Cheesy thrill like one of those online services where you can
Pay to register a star
Or buy a plot of land on the Moon
But those authentic Clan tartan
The ones that represent last name
Those were also kind of made of
When you look
Actually I believe
Examples of
Surviving talton's it would not really have been associated with particular families
And there is no way that
This idea of official Clan tartans was part of a great Highland Revival
Gosh
Stop around speaking title
200 years is old
But that's nothing when you compare it to the ages of the Clans themselves
Raise the Macallan
Those are closer to 1000 years old
But basically in the 1800's
Many of the clan leaders just went and picked out tartans they liked
And we named them after themselves
Is it kind of like what's your favorite absolutely
No Campbell Chiefs
Used Blackhawks shopping as a cheese and Kenzie use the 70s.
Atlanta
That's awesome that
Can you tell you've been being sold as Caledonia
Tartan plaid
Whatever you want to call it
How many different meanings and associations
It has been used symbolically
Tonight so many different groups
The people
On the surface
Pattern seems simple
It's a series of overlapping threads
A warp and weft
Really
If you look at it
And get your nose right up close
Notice the number of colors
Stripe with
The variation in the ways the threads overlap
It's quite complex
Etta candy
Particular enough to be specific
In general and I
Be for everyone
I mean just yeah
Cultural recognition
Visibility being able
I want to walk down the street
Do you like oh that's another
Something that plaid.
A piece of paper
Words from yesterday
There's a portrait
We love
Articles of interest is made by myself Avery truffelman edited by Joe Rosenberg
Bagpiping by David Watson other music by Ray Royal an intro and outro themes by Sami Ashworth
Fact check bigram Haisha
Next by Kelly Coyne and Roman Mars
Is the Macho Highlander of this whole series a very special things do crystal Isabel Sloan Rachel White
Ira Goldman Christina Stokes and Ian Ferguson and love Katie mingle Emmett Fitzgerald Sharif Youssef Vivian Lidl
Delaney Hall Kurt Kolstad
NFL 99 git
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing that voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is
Frustrating but doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know
Know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Black Box
Scots are really adamant that killed
Arnott
Skirts
But there's is one important way that Kilts are very similar
To womenswear what are you wearing right now
So I'm wearing my Kilt which is a
McPherson
Ancient tartan
Mike
Choose killbros
And then to top it off career
Jurassic Park
This is David McPherson who I met outside a bar in Edinborough
And when he wears his Kilt
He also has to wear something called a
Warren
So what's up
Oran
Spartan is a big furry purse
The fur and leather purse that sits
Right over the crotch
And it's kind of
Hangs on a chain
Rand your hip
Terrible
Because Kilts don't have any pockets
So
Stop somewhere so right now I've got my
Phone in it
I've got my keys
I got my wallet
How do people I don't know they might
Braveheart on DVD-R
I whisper Focus mean it's not
How to get very much in it
Your next article of Interest
Is Paca
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com