99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
I had never worn a dress
I'm sure it was like slightly graceless test like all the things I did it
Time seemed to offend IMAP hears on our very first
Wheaton College
It must have been
Dave
One or two it was really early to a super PC liberal arts
School and so are freshman mixer
Was a cross-dressing dad
But you're such an outdated term now but whatever that's what it was called I think all he told us was
You should wear clothes of the opposite
Cisgender
They probably said it in a way that slightly more you know literate in the difference
Between gender and biological sex
What I just said
It was a strange way to make First Impressions on each other
Not because we were scared of wearing dresses or backwards baseball caps or whatever we were that night
Is because for many of us we could borrow clothes from the other people in our Hall
With weirdly intimate
Peers and I
Complete strangers
Swapped outfits
You're tall and I'm tall and I think that you're probably the only person
In the Hall of the building she's close with it
I remember I loaned peers
Pink swirly patterned mini dress
From the sixties that I bought from a thrift store
And I have no idea if he would
Take care of it or even return it
Peers tried it on
He went to check himself out in the bathroom down the hall
Here's what happened.
I immediately locked myself out of my room
Oh no my Keisha from my room
Because I did never put them
The dresser
Piers is brand new roommate let him back in
But then he went to sleep
So peers wanted to make sure he didn't make that much
Mistake again
He couldn't lose his keys at the party
We all ended up in the big dance hall where there's really loud music and it was like
Unbearably hot
All the ladies
Eyebrow pencil mustaches were running as their teeth
With sweat and things like that and
I believe I just clutched my keys in my hand and thought about it really hard all night
Which sounds crazy
Articles of Interest a show about what we wear and so maybe the ideas about clothes
Ideas about to a piece of cloth
Wear clothes
But if you ain't got the attitude install the carrot off
Manuel District closed.
Women's wear
Is littered with fake pockets
But don't open
Or shallow pocket
Guess I could hardly hold a paperclip
If there are Pockets at all
They are just smaller
And they sent
Less than men's
It's due
And you have to take my word for it
We are going to the police supply store
I want to find an example of a uniform that had pockets
And compared those made for men and those for women
This is the shop that provides the uniforms for the Oakland Police
When I asked the store manager if I could look at the men's and women's uniforms
This is what he told me
Are you ready for this I'm ready for the the women wear the man
Really because of pocket
Too small
Really that's your eye
But there is a women's
Well I've got some over
Traditionally
They use the men
Because
The pockets are bigger
How to make him put things on him where the women's are smaller which I can show you
Yes
That's fascinating
Now you have something
I'll give you something to blog about
Men's great evolutionary advantage
Is the creation of tools
The problem is we're not marsupials we need to carry them somehow
And this idea of who has access to the tools they need
Who can walk through the world
Comfortably and securely
This is what we are talking about
When we talked about pockets
Pocket
Speak to the
Question of preparedness and your ability to
Why can't I be confident
It's really difficult to get around if you don't have what you need and it's about I think mobility and movement in public
Hannah Carlson lectures at the Rhode Island School of Design where she teaches classes in material culture fashion history in fashion Theory
She's working on a book about pockets
Is the formal question for me is what is it what difference does it make put together what's the difference in a pocket in a bag
And I think the key difference is that the
Pocket
Is internal and
Secret a bag can be stolen
Tea bags can be lost
And then
That's it
You don't have your things anymore
With pocket inside you don't have to think about it
You forget about it
You still have stuff in there
It is
Penises
Territory of your own
That connects you to the object you carry
Those objects
Become part of you
Kissing point
Thomas Jefferson
Jefferson
Was called Walking calculator
For all the miniature tools and devices
Scale drawing instruments of thermometer
Surveying Compass a level of globe
And he was able to jot down his observations
From his daily wanderings
Historically men have been the ones with these tools for public life on their person at all times
In Hannah Carlson's research she found a lot of accounts of women complaining about this
One woman noted that her son was better equipped than she or her daughter
And she concludes that a boy's pockets are history
Tificate of Empire
All through life he will carry the scepter of dominion by the right of the
Great language I loved
I mean it's playful it's
Funny but there's some seriousness
Hear about
What leader costume historians call real social handicap
Pockets are just a
Perfect metaphor for privilege
Not only because they are so easily taken for granted by the people who have them
But also because
Like the categories of race and gender themselves
Pocket disparity
Is a construct
It's made out of
There's no reason for women's Pockets to be so small
Back in the 18th century
Women's pockets
Quite large
She could hold
Quite a lot
Women putting
Hooda net
He later
Writing tools maybe a small diary
Sowing implements
Especially if you had to
This is Clarissa esguerra
Associate curator of
Los Angeles County Museum of
And where are we now
We are in a
A storage area at the Museum Fire Department
Until we have everything laid out
On a table
Currently covered with tissue but I will reveal them when it is
Is it allowed to pick on the radio but indulge me for a
Pockets
Used to be
A completely separate
Garment
They're really more like pouches
Pockets
Send it from the waist has a really long song
Actually it started
For both men and women
In the Medieval era
Are there were suspended from their waste over there
Henan and sometime in the late 17th century
Men started
Having clothes made with
Incorporated they were in their coats
The waistcoat and in their breeches
And women's Pockets remain separate from the rest of clothing
Fanny pack
The pockets
On the inside of your jeans right those
Teardrop-shaped
Couches
They're kind of like that but they were just on their own like separate from pants and they were attached to it
String tied around
And in some cases these patches are really big like the length of your forearm
Andis detachable Pockets Worthen Warren
Under women's dresses
So even a lot of old dresses look like they have pockets
They really just have cuts
What's in them
Women's hats made in the petticoats
Dresses and
Could access our pockets
Spike going through the
You can reach through your dress to get to your detachable pocket
That makes sense
Sherwin
Would like to see them
What should I start with
The more simpler ones and then kind of go to the more complicated
Because they're a really
Functional but also they were an opportunity for
Splendor
I'm actually just going to cut to the complicated expensive fancy pockets
They are indeed very splendid
Oh well
Disease
Very very finely embroidered
This one is a silk pie
Pocket and it's lately quilted and then it is covered with
What is beautiful
Floral
Chain stitch embroidery so these are all tiny tiny little chains
Stitches
Oh my God
It's really fun
Match
And this is something that she just wore
And only she and
The woman who
How to get dressed
Perhaps your lover song
Pockets were almost like lingerie
Especially the beautiful expensive ones
The pockets for the intimate thing
Close to the body
Holding your mouth
Precious items
Safe under the layers of your ginormous fluffy dress
And then came the French Revolution
French Revolution happen
Which
In many ways was a revolution against
Access
These dresses that
Wer
Silk skirt
No longer fashionable in what was fashionable
Sundresses
Cling to the body
So when you get to the 1800 and that empire style wear the waist
Is pretty much gone
Can't think of Jane Austen movies
Do you have the columnar silhouette silhouette like a straight Greek
Column
And some of these columnar dresses have slits for Pockets but a lot of them
R2 body-hugging to accommodate extra bulge
There's no space for pockets and so suddenly women begin to carry little person
And there's lots of ridicule about women having to lose their pockets and having to carry these silly bags
Teeny teeny tiny little drawstring pouches
Elaborately beaded & Decker
Beheld maybe a few
Kucoin
He's but like
That's it
And you could
Hanging Loops of the draw string around your wrist
Which was another reason why it was considered ridiculous
You have to remember to carry it is
Easy to lose people can steal it
That's the
Formal difference
But
It's kind of price you pay for a fashion
The little bags were in style
I mean you can see why if you look at them they're beautiful
That very fancy Beautiful Things shell-shaped 2
Made of silk
Gorgeous paintings
That should be seen
And not particularly capacious
This is dress historian Barbara Berman
The ridicule
Becomes a kind of temporary
Fashionista saying
And so you get jaundice writing in the
First and second Decades of the nineteenth Century about pocket has
The fashion press Made pocket seem like they were for housewives
For women who needed to Lug around sewing kits and bits of food they were saving for later
Empty pockets
We're going out dancing and gambling
They have these peaceful sabbaticals and
Professional I don't need to carry keys and
Bibles
Pennzoil gold is useful things in the
Play much more out and about
Until you have to poke assistant practice papers
Strong alone
In the 19th century fashion magazines were saying it was a liberating thing
For women not to have
To be free from tasks
Reticule would hardly hold anything
We're kind of like long nails but don't let you use your hands as much
What's the Leto heels but don't let you walk as far
There's that luxury in not moving too much
Are doing too much and just
Looking really good
It's always been an ongoing debate if that is empowering or not
What is a reticule completely killed at the tie on pocket
They were still around
A woman who cuts a well
Have a pattern for kids
And what's her excuse when she wants picture
This kind of pocket carry out live spectacle you find mean using the 17th
So what why don't we have these anymore if it wasn't for Columbus LOL
That's me
If you can come up with
Spell difficult
To pinpoint
Safe age for music
Become old fashioned
More dresses. Have integrated for kids
But they're often very small
Shuffle ways but they offer baseball invented
The women wear that had integrated pockets
Tended to be feminized versions of Menswear
It made by Taylor's no dressmaker
Taylor Swift
Putting in
Fit in pocket
Because of using male outfit had an inset pocket
It was a uselessly proportion version of a men's pattern
Pocket is seen to be a monopoly of the male sex
Eventually
Pockets in trousers R1
As women's Fashions changed
Pockets
Camelot
And as men's fashions change Pockets can be gained
And they were again and again and again Pockets were getting added in added an additive
The course of decades
By the early 20th century
It was just getting ridiculous
Copious amounts
The pockets I can't even like you happier
Ticket pocket for the train
Watch pocket
Pocket City have all the pockets in your waistcoat and then in your trousers
Really interesting and women have one purse
Both genders extremes were starting to get terrible
Because pocket
It's a proliferated they had become completely worth
We couldn't find anything you stopped on the street yet to Pat yourself down to remember where you've left your wallet
The average man of 1944 head 24 pocket
Way too many
At least according
To Bernard rudofsky
He was kind of
Enraged
By the way that pocket
Stop popping up
Bernard rudofsky Was An Architect
Modernist
Modernist for really into sleek
Simple buildings that were absolutely functional with no access with his modernist who wanted to make clothing Park
Perfectly rational
And he found it ironic
That all his fellow rational modernist architect
We're all wearing
Suits he wanted to I think shake-up
This confidence that we have about
A suit a suggestion of it is not modern in any way it has all sorts of old ideas and beliefs
And this pocket that was once
Functional is now no longer functional because we have so many
And to prove his point God love him rudofsky
Put on an exhibit at the New York Museum of Modern Art
And it was called
Are clothes modern
?
Are clothes modern with a
Central peace in Rudolph's Keys Moma exhibit
Big multi-layered infographic
It looks like an x-ray
A man's three piece suit
We have color-coded the pockets in his shirt
It is vested is
Coach and over
And you see that's wonderful
Chaotic overlay
The average suit had 24 pockets and 70 buttons
Rudolph he was really passionate about how completely silly and redundant this was
The guy is a wonderful nutball but he was really onto something
Because he wasn't only about abolishing suit
Pizza Hut
At the root of this in
Saying pocket conundrum
With a much larger problem
Which is about
Generally what we consider clothing to be
Clothing hanging on
Hangers to him look like
Peoples
Dead
Skin
He wanted to be blue
You sure that you can travel to a friend's house and they would have clothes for you
Because
Clothing wouldn't be individuals
Body
A universal size mean
Where's the clothing unisex
Universal clothing
According to Rogowski
More like a toga
Or apparel that embrace the nature of cloth itself
Something that would drape and move matcher
You know he hated the idea that
Too close we could
Show ideas about status and gender that were unfair
He hated this
Spanx the waist
So he wanted this
You know really simple cloth
And of course the images that he showed his ideas
For this
New utopian future
Are very simple clothing
That have no pocket
A world with no pockets
At all
And no bags
You might know the perfect world when you arrive there by its
Pocket listing
My college friend appears got really into researching and reading about pockets
Long after his debacle with my dress
There's this whole strain of thought which suggests that
If
The world were perfect
Which society were perfect if we lived in a Utopia of some kind
Where you don't have to worry about your physic
Eagle safety. To worry about somebody robbing your house
You wouldn't need pockets
In order to
Carry money in order to carry keys
And certainly in the course of time
We've come to hold
Fewer and fewer things in our path
All those little devices of Jefferson's are contained in a single phone
That we
Carrie externally on our body
And
Pocket really is this sort of knowledge
Envelope
Compartment
But the phone stays adjacent to us
Remove
Encased in a bag
I tech company of tried to sell us on wearable
An apple watches in Google glasses
Which would take your tools out of your pocket entirely
And maybe bring us a step closer to that
Pocketless Utopia
These products haven't taken off in the way they were supposed
Wearables were foreseen a long time ago and we
We still feel a little anxious about their use
I think there's just
Too much doubt at the moment about whether that
Utopia can never work
And perhaps one day we will have all of our tools and planted in our skull
Or embedded on an accessory with
Everyone will be able to access in the same way
And then when we get there
Pockets will seem just as ancient as rudofsky
He thought them to be
Already it seems so Antiquated that clothes are needlessly gendered in the way they are
Because we should all have access
To the tools we need
Or at least a place to put our hands
The piece of paper
Words from yesterday
Portrait
We love
Articles of interest is made by myself
Avery trufelman
With editing from Katie mingle and Joe Rosenberg
Music by Ray Royal
Intro and outro theme
Tommy Ashworth
Factcheck bigram Haisha
Next bike
Articles of interest is made by myself
Avery trufelman
With editing from Katie mingle and Joe Rosenberg
Music by Ray Royal
Intro and outro themes by Sesame Ashworth
Back Jack by Graham Haisha
Next bikes reviews
And Roman Mars
The Deep Pockets
Nicole Siri
Special thanks to pierce Kelly for telling me about this topic in his podcast Cellar Door
As well as to Delaney Hall Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Kurt Kolstad Sean real and the whole 99 Piti
Gloria Trevi
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
Technology
He talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50%
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
Gemini 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating
Routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
And it may be time to seek help go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more
More about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
The fake pockets on women's where are proof that fashion always takes useful things and makes them ridiculous
Fashionable dress
Spurs the assertion of utility
So utility itself
Like how plaid fell into style once it could be worn in Scotland anymore
Or how high heels developed from riding shoes
Became trendy once we took them off horseback
Who was it and Hollander notes that
Fashion instantly Mox
Sensible inventions in clothing
Subjecting them to unfunctional usage
As soon as they appear
And that's absolutely true of pockets
I mean
You can think of the wonderful
Ornate
Suits of the macaroni
Like when Yankee Doodle stick a feather in his hat he thinks that makes him one of these Dandy macaroni
Who were these British youth
In the 1770s and 80s these young men with big elaborate hairdos and he's tight little coats
And their coats were so narrow and form-fitting.
Once again in the name of fashion
The front pockets became useless
And so now they have this pocket that makes no sense and so Taylor's invented what is the breast pocket
Put it inside the coat of the breast
Clothing is always shifting in and out of practicality
Sometimes
Just because something is useless doesn't mean it's meaningless
Lake with a pocket
Even if it can't hold much
Sometimes it matters that it's there
Sometimes
It matters exactly how its play
Your next article of Interest
Is the Hawaiian shirt
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com