99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
Just a warning
Best episode contains
Mature language
Members 1st
They are got the college
I was in line at the bakery
In the town in the woman pulled me outside
I just want to talk to you because
I'm a Christian woman
And I worry about
People like you
And your relationship with Satan
My boss
Roman Mars
What were you wearing that day
I was
I might think it was
I must have been a band t-shirt in the
Final or something from nothing
Like a band t-shirt one particular shirt
So if you met me
From the age of moon
14219 I was probably wearing
This one hooskerdoo t-shirt
By the time I stopped wearing it
You know went from basically white to gray to almost kind of clear
It's hard to keep it all together
I put little safety pins across the top
To keep it to keep it all together
Other people doing that so I remember
In
High School
There was a
There's very little punk present
You call a skater
If you wore
I will tell her listen to the bands I listen to
This that doesn't sound so weird this quizzical look on your face
It's just put in central Ohio
In the late 80s
There wasn't a concept of what
I like hardcore punk was
It was there was no you I would call a skater and Rock
Autonomy
People throw rocks at you this is
Yad skaters were hated by everybody
So why bother
The standout especially if people are like actively throwing rocks
Are you like why bother
Yeah it's weird
Because
I don't know
I don't know why I want to have that fighting all the time
But
I had to
Articles of Interest a show about what we wear and so maybe their ideas about quote
Ideas about class that I do home to a piece of cloth
But if you ain't got the attitude install the current off
Manual defect clothes.
There is this myth
That's frivolous or unproductive.
Care about how you look
Clothing and fashion get trivialize a lot
But think about who culturally get
Associated with clothing and fashion
Young people
Women
Queers
And people of color
Groups of people who historically haven't been listened to
Express themselves on their body
Tudor style
Their hair their tattoos or piercings
And what they wear
You gota understand
Black working-class get that tool the only way we had to express ourselves so through the music release
Listen to and the clothes we walk this is Dunlap
A legendary DJ and filmmaker
And creator of the documentary
Punk attitude
I've always engage with the Lord
Because you know in Black Culture we've been. Express ourselves in a very punk rock weigh and what is a very white
World
We've only been left
The fringes to operate with
Search for stuff to do
With things like come up with
Reggae
Princeton
Which is actually
Phone by a lack of Technology not because you've got it in a minute
Definition of punk
Hip Hop
Two turntables and a microphone I mean if that ain't a phone with black punk rock what is
Punk rock
In the classic sense
In the way it sounds in the way it looks
Emerged from a place of disenchantment and dissolution
I already was
Black alien
I want you talking specifically London Society
You going to set the scene a little bit
What social crisis economic political jobs accommodation
I'm Financial you know what about three days a week so very concerned about unemployment
Unemployment
And we don't like it
And then I just felt like it was constantly f******
I mean I was lucky I had a soundtrack to ease my pain I had the reggae
What makes not so lucky
Now there are a lot of different opinions as to where punk music came from
And what its roots and influences were
And whether it started in Detroit or New York or whatever
Wide-leg read that punk music
Came from
Somewhere in the United States
Everybody thinks England England invented Punk
The look
A punk
That
Started in London
Which is not to be sniffed at
Is that music install combinations a deadly combination
And the look
A punk
A traditional 70s British Punk is so iconic
Think the green mohawk
Safety pins leather jacket the Plaid mini skirt
And look that iconic
Not specific
I didn't just happen by axe
Someone design.
Hi are you okay
Yeah
On 430 Kings Road in London
There's a little shop
It looks like a little Shack
Tiny
Don Letts remembers the first time he went in there
I found myself wondering up and down the Kings Road Chelsea which back in the day in the early 70s
Which is like the major fashion High Street in the UK and under
And I wandered into the store
Cool.
Xenical too fast to live too young to die or Let It Rock
Cricket changing the name of the store
I walked into what was kind of Aladdin Cave of
Subculture
Mountain was there and Vivian was there in Westwood and Malcolm McLaren
The couple that owned the shop in the 70s
They started out selling records and then moved into clothing
Probably one of the most food
To assist meetings I've ever had
Vivienne Westwood was in her early thirties
Primary school teacher and mother of two who sewed all the clothes in her living room
She had no formal training
But she had grown up sewing her own clothes out of necessity
Malcolm McLaren was in his mid-20s
And lived in this kind of world of ideas
The counterculture
B a Paris Grosvenor Square you know Kent State
Situationist movement in Frosty
The situationists were really important to Vivian and Malcolm
As early as the 1950s
Situation of spirits declared
The artist
And thinkers
Morally obligated to break
Down The Divide between art
And like
Diffuse art with everyday existence
So that art could not be
Cleaved Wade etherized and put into Galleries and Academies
The way to do this
The situation is said
Diffuse art and life
Artist
Activist
The provocateurs
To create dramatic
Outlandish Interruption the everyday
To expose the absurdity of the status quo
Art
I protest review
On the street
What do you know barriers
For everyone
In there
Faces
Whether they wanted it or not
Yeah the whole idea of being subversive
Thinking Out of the Box
Punk
But
The look of punk
Still wasn't quite born yet
In the pursuit of testing limits
Emerging art and life
Vivienne Westwood and Malcolm McLaren we're constantly changing the shop
In the style clothing sold within it
They closed it down Renee Mission reopen it again as long as they were closing the stores down cuz they were failures
They were changing the face of 430 Kings Road
Because they wanted to
And he wants to move on and sit if this is Claire Wilcox
Senior curator at the Victoria and Albert Museum
By the way Vivienne Westwood herself declined to be a part of the story
But Claire Wilcox interview Westwood
Cuz they were failures
They were changing the face of 430 Kings Road
Because they wanted to
Maximum term
And he wants to move on and sit ophidian
This is Claire Wilcox
Senior curator at the Victoria and Albert Museum
By the way Vivienne Westwood herself declined to be a part of the story
But Claire Wilcox interview Westwood and curated and
Credible exhibit of the many faces of her work
This is not avoid without running
The rodents is there always one step ahead
They never arrested on the Lord's Day
Moving changing
Gathering momentum
You're kind of like anthropologist
It really intrigued by certain subculture
And they build the shop around it
430 Kings Road had an iteration where it's sold
Dandy-Walker clothes
Another making more leather biker inspired stuff
And then in 1974
Vivian Malcolm turn 430 Kings Road
Into a shop
Called
Sex it was cold sex one word
All caps what Vision said about being interested in clothing
Used in the sex industry
The latex
She appreciates it fit strength Honda Beauty
The sign
Just Had Sex
A big pink
Plush letters
The clothes inside were leather and rubber and cover.
Straps
Skin tight and androgynous
And she said that you had a Mexican tile coming to the shop when it's cooled sex range from
She said
SunTrust in
These types of governments
Kids off the street just wanting to be fashionable soap
Malcolm and Vivian new had a shock
No one had stuff like there
Snow in the moment
Some of a t-shirt
Sears
I didn't put the talcum powder thing on nobody told me about that s***
A Navy diver
Thing wrapped around my neck trying to get it off
On trips to New York Malcolm and Vivian discovered the burgeoning American punk music scene which was blooming in inter
Trust in NuWave
ISO
Upon his return to London
Malcolm decided that he would like to manage a band of his very own
Ian Didion gathered some kids who worked at and hung out around 4:30 Kings Road
Inform them into a group
Named
The Sex Pistols
But it's not like the Sex Pistols were just like a clever ruse
Sell clothes
No I mean listen to it was a fortuitous combination for the restie
Things to watch together but that wasn't anything weird I mean
Style of
The music in this country
It's so important
There's any shame in that
Malcolm and Vivian wrote some of the lyrics for The Sex Pistols
Which were about
No
Anarchy in the UK in bad-mouthing the queen
It was not your mother's rock and roll
It was
The Andy band
The Andy music
Built
To shock
Kind of her politics but also kind of just to shock people
Like a situation is happening
Although maybe that's getting knocking too much credit I don't know how planned out this
Malcolm
When I scrape Malcolm will
What is endgame was I have no
I think Malcolm
Good makeup looks
La things that kind of
And jumping chaos
She pretended that you orchestrated
What was your question
This new movement
Demanded a new look
A new store
Sew-in 1977 430 King's Road was reincarnated again
This time
It was called
Seditionaries
And this is the iteration of the store in which
Punk fashion
Would truly emerge
Because hair
Female gymnast
Music McLaren's to Humane labs
The chapters of 430 Kings Road all compounded on each other
Elements of Edwardian Dandy and rocker and biker and sex-worker all combined and key
How do eyes work
Hardbass music and political imagery
Top
Union Jack
Put together with safety pins
This is style icon Michael Costa
A longtime neighbor of 430 Kings Road
Over the years Michael and his wife gerlinde about
Somany Westwood clothes
The Collection was
Acquired by Victoria and Albert Museum
Copper trousers
Really yeah they're on this what you said
Big wide belt little bit hipster almost
Michael is showing me a pair of his old bondage trousers
Which look like
Straight jacket for your legs
Are loaded down with zippers and chains and straps hanging off them
And there's even a strap that ties your knees together
Which Michael assures me was
Less limiting than you think
The legs are connected
I need was
Latino Barber to walk
Ultra
What can you do with
With your knees tied together
These bondage trousers of Michaels were black
But they were virgins and plaid and some had killed that you could
Clip on the front and back or little towels and other things that would hang off them
A conversation with Bob Marley argument about the bug that trousers I was wearing
What what did you say about that he didn't like them until they look like Mountaineer Travis
Vivian Close turn people into
Strange sculptures
She played with the human form
Finding the legs together extending sleeves down to the floor and pushing the body into new angles
Only things were so differently you know with won't sleep either
With a neck cold one side Minnesota
Pull the fabric in different ways it was all wrong fabulous
Photorealism movement it was resolved it was
Well-crafted
It's not cheap
It wasn't she wasn't cheap
Halo toys for not cheap
In other words
The code I was closes on
Levittown
Those first punk clothes Warrant dirty grungy sloppy
You are fabulous
Estranged
Vivian's closes they would closes
You could understand.
Always taken great pride in Crossing how close right calf
You got this extraordinary sort of marriage crafts in car
You know damn right outrageousness
So outrageous
Just that other shop started the copy Vivian's designs
Lots of people call Paige as look
Once that you knew about the pothole then
Pumpkins ride with selling
Variations on a theme
Would love to go with you know you got studying and wristbands
L'homme
Ephemera
The people of China
Have a business
Hunk was easy to rip off
Michael showed me some imitation bondage trousers that used to belong to his wife
They were made by another shop
Called boy
These four countries that boycott pedo Vivian's things ended the much cheaper and cheaper
Barbrix System of a Down The King's Road
Which Wich
Kind of cool cuz it gave more people a chance to wear the clothes
Fabulous Heights boy
Shuttle migration
Set my shop on fire cuz they have to do the same
But the other side of the coin was that individuals could imitate these looks very easily as well
Elaborate on them
Dial lexicon that anyone can play around with large featuring yourself
Novak fake
I mean you could go into your own wardrobe right now
And rip stuff up and put it back together
And make it Punk
DIY Park
That Vivian love
MacGyver transfer
The kids with no money to developer do it yourself
Version of God
Vivienne Westwood after all didn't have any training as a seamstress
She just figured out how to do these things
So anyone could and should
Follow her lead
It was part of this
Shad movement of rebellion but these clothes to be adopted in customized and adopted by
Wherever you came from have Rachel pull you all have I told you I would have sex you while you could take these clothes on
Cups you might save up
To buy Paris bondage trousers but you to customize your own t-shirt
Punk became Grassroots
As Vivian herself has said
It wasn't invented from the street
It was the other way around
It turned into a movement
So I think in a way it was cut so joyful
Expiration of
Take possession of your own identity
Before the internet this look was cross-pollinated between New York and London
By touring bands like the sex pistols and the Ramones
It's either started to be this back-and-forth dialogue a little bit
Between the two scenes but they were visually really different
Monica sklar fashion historian and author of the book
Punk Style
She says the New York look
Was based in functionality with New York being
Jeans t-shirts using safety fence for functional purposes but the London look
Thanks to Vivienne Westwood was rooted in art aesthetic
Advanced word and cultures mix
Spheres of influence spread across the US
And then it would
Go around the country
At around the globe are there scenes wood
Come to fruition and take on their own bed of influence
Depending on bands on the weather on the local culture
Hulk became reinterpreted
See whether to Troy London York Minneapolis had a large series of
Bain & Style leaders
And then as those individuals and their stuff
Whether it's been personally traveling around or as their Z makes it around or their music
Dallas gets to the next place
The style ghost
Note
Harmonica score said their Style
Went with them
Not their fashion this goes Way Beyond
Conquer subcultures in the United States
Fashion is associated
With entire groups of people
That are often relegated as
Secondary women queers people of color and Youth
Fashion is the realm of the historically powerless
And so people don't want
To talk about things that are associated with them
But they do have this huge awareness
Style
How important style is
Style according to sociologist Michael break is a combination of
3 elements
Image image
So what are we looking at demeanor
And this concept called Argo
Argo this French concept of
Swang and secret language
Kind of like jargon
Special words or phrases that only insiders in a group would know
And so being able to have image demeanor and Argo is awesome
Is true Punk Style
In other words
It's part of what makes you authentic
Or a poser
You have the right
Dial
Emperor Punk's it was a
Vizslas hunt
To sniff out true Punk Style
Looking for little Clues
Hints of authenticity
Try to figure out
Who was on your side
It was a sell-out
Wisconsin
It was exhausting
That
Only shortly after seditionaries open
In the late 70s
Vivienne Westwood herself
Got tired of it
In hindsight
She said
I got tired of looking at clothes from this point of view of rebellion
I found it exhausting
After a while I wasn't sure if I was right
I'm sure that if there is such a thing as the anti-establishment
It feeds the establishment
If you give something a label in that tool that can be in the whole thing about Punk is it
Ever-evolving
Early definition
Not a man that was just like one
Screaming shout
Through the door
You weren't supposed to get
You know you get on this letter
Smoke to keep climbing
Into the eighties a lot of London punks kept climbing
Members of punk bands killed off to learn how do you actually play their instruments
Experiment with lights
Sympathizers
An interesting about postpone his own people
Honest about what they really like
And Vivienne Westwood taught herself how to
To Taylor
Like give herself a real formal training
Sochi
Bumped on this mission to self educate yourself
Through
Locate 17
18th Century Century dress and this is not DIY these are not garments but anyone could copy
Vivian played with corset tree ball gown suits
Evening clothes
Using nicer materials and toying with elements of History
Even nostalgia
Stuff that was not Punk
Replacing
Two dimensional could be laid flat
Weather when she learns
How to tie a tie
And this is a very difficult process that she told herself
The clothes
Sycamore Mall
Three dimensional
As her views of authority and establishment became multidimensional
Her garments Gaines Dimension as well
You see the development of Pasco running alongside
It's up to her interest in history and also
No projection of poem is at the lowest a part of her but her
I'm moving on
Wei Zhang
Underpants toys
Being insulting some kind of
Conflict
It's cool sartorial conflict with the wild
Yeah
Majority
Are you awake
Earth's gravity
That store on 430 Kings Road
It still belongs to Westwood
Ever since 1980
It's been called World's End
Add a giant clock on the front with its arms spinning backwards
I did go there today
Not really a band of Misfits that hang out there anymore
But there are a lot of Japanese tourists to come to pilgrimage
Vivienne Westwood is one of the most famous clothing designers in the world now
I mean she is huge she doesn't have the time to speak to me for this podcast
But she is the reason why I wanted to talk about clothing
Because in 2009
I heard her say this thing to the New York Times
I haven't been able to stop thinking about it since
The Paradox is that
People sing this if they wear something simple
UNAM
Say it
That somehow
Stunning them beautiful from it
It's not
Truitt Christy Turlington
I don't want to see
Chuggington in a T-shirt and jeans
Chicken why not if you're bored
Somebody
Free calls
Beauty
I think everyone knows that feeling when you're dressed in an outfit you really like
You look good
And you feel good
That is an essential power of clothing
Aside from
You know covering your body or keeping you warm
Has the power to give you confidence
It's why Roman dresses up when he goes to do a life
Performance
I have lots of options and ties and I have lots of options in
Pocket squares and stuff like that in that I have fun with that
Form and actually show respect that I care about these things to an audience
That's what that signals to me
I don't feel like it I think I look up
And the sing Punk did
Was pushed the boundaries of what
Looks good
It's not about looking perfect
McLean
Or Rich
Incorporated people of all ages and bodies and backgrounds and ideas
And gave them that confidence
It pushed our ideas of beauty
And Professor Monica's flower knows this firsthand
Beauty standards were pushed and pushed and pushed
I was fired
From a record store
A record store
Does a use for having an eyebrow piercing and now I'm a professor and curator and vice president of the national
Society of my profession
And I have it
And really this is the power of what fashion designers can do
Something that appears strange or scary or expensive at first can trickle down through the cycle of trends
Maybe
In time
Come to
Expand Notions of what's acceptable
Send more people can feel comfortable expressing their own style
Their own cocktail of image demeanor and argot
However it manifests
Anna Smith
But it's frivolous or unproductive to care about how you look or what you wear
Is completely bunk
I have to think about how you present
Or to assume that you can somehow dress in a way that is neutral
Anon saying
That
Is a massive
Massive
Privilege
Whether we like it or not we are all speaking with our clothes
And we might as well give a good hard think
About what we want to say
The piece of paper
Words for me
Support
Truth
We love
Story
Black and pink
Articles of interest is made by myself
Avery trufelman
But I didn't come Katie mingle and Joe Rosenberg
Music by Rebecca Redmond Shannon the druggie Jenna marks and Maya Seto of the band sore
The theme songs for articles of Interest
Are by the Sami Ashworth
Fact check bigram Haisha mix by Sherif Youssef
I'm Roman Mars
Is the in Micaiah this whole series
Special thanks to science Danville Al original is Brendan Cormier and Online Library Bloomsbury fashion central banks
As well to Mary McCune Delaney Hall Vivien Leigh Sean real Kurt Kolstad and the whole 99 pit
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing.
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself it's not that bad you take laxatives you modify your diet
Does routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
Infowars podcast
Oh my God
Flask podcast
The history of clothing is not a linear one
Circles back around and around on itself
Styles weave in and out through the decades
Each time reincarnated a new material
New associations
The history of clothing
The history of subversion
Whether it's bringing bondage we're into the light of day or jeans in the workplace
Are Pockets into womenswear
It's a dynamic that puts our bodies and conversation with all the many many political societal and
Economic forces that have determined the Fashions before us
As a cycle trends
Goes around
Around and around
And that's it
That concludes articles of interest thank you for listening
By the way this gorgeous music box theme that you're listening to was composed by the great Sean real r
99 Pi staff composer
And we're back to regular 99percentinvisible programming after this and all these episodes will be archived on a separate feed
We're thinking about whether or not we want to do a second season of this
Let me know your thoughts
I'm on Twitter at troubleman 1f and at articles of interest on Instagram
And a final thought we're celebrating this podcast with a big clothing swap
If you've never been to one of these before it's where a bunch of people gather somewhere and everyone brings their clothes that they don't want anymore
And then trade them all up with each other for free
I find it's the most sustainable and most interesting way to dress
Consider throwing a clothing swap with your own sometime
If you have to wear clothes anyway
Right
Radio 2
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com