December 7th 1941
A date which will live
In infamy
Call Chris Duran
Biofreeze
Call Miss time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein Berliner
If we dig deep in our history and our doctor and remember that we are not descended
From fearful men
Hardcore history
The dictionary defines the word
Laconic
As
A form of speech that
Blunt
Kissy
That uses an economy of words to make a point and sometimes two point
Is particularly biting
You're On Target
Mysterious
And I love the word because the word refers
2 way of speaking it was
Popular amongst a picture
Particular group of people
Ancient Greece
People known
Is like an ammonia
Otherwise known
Ispartan
Connex peaches Spartan
That's the way they're supposed
To talk
Imagine
Love child
Clint Eastwood and Batman
And that's the way
Way they spoke
Man's gotta know his limitations
Man's got to know us
Spartans of the kings of the one-liners
Ancient Greek history
And they are
Cinematic and character I mean is not a movie maker out there that wouldn't want
Clint Eastwood during his various
Movirs playing various forms of Spartan
You know from a spaghetti western era in his twenties he can play your average Spartan warrior
He gets into the Dirty Harry films
Enough 72-73 1974 he begins to age a little bit more replays one of those older Spartan Warriors and then you get in
You know after the Dirty Harry's are over and he's an older man and now he's the king
And he talks like he talks and all those other movies combined with Batman and you have
Another way the Spartans are supposed to have spoken laconic
How cool is it
Did the 25 centuries
Those people were
At the height of their Fame and Power
We still know the way they talk
It's famous
Prince famous
Because people wrote
People whose work
We still have
Telling you the way a certain
People spoke
That long ago
Describing
Some of the things that they said
All these sorts of little details help
Bring color to the story they
They help us all relate to these people
A little bit more
Human touches the
Flush out these historical figure
You begin to get the sort of stuff
The sorts of details that you were likely to hear in an oral tradition anywhere in the world before this time.
When you begin to get the stories
Come down to us
You begin to see
Truly cinematic
Pipe creations
Stories that you could take
With very little changes and updating and make movies out of them today and have them be
And it's not just the character development either the themes can be epic
In the store
Take for example the most
Famous story involved
Sparta
At all
The famous incident in 480
BCE
Pass of Thermopylae
Also called hot gay
This may be because of the movies and because of the books
Sleeping written forever
This may be the earliest confirmable
Historical event most Americans know about
The defensive
300 Spartans against a million or so Persian
A battle
It's summer described over the eras
For the
Existence of Western Civilization
By the way if those are the stakes
Who side are you rooting for
What was it the Indian leader Mohandas Gandhi supposedly said when someone asked him
What he thought of Western Civilization did he say something like
I think it would be a good idea
Nonetheless the way this story is framed from the get-go
Is designed to have you affiliate with one side over the other
One side is like the Plucky little Republic
Lakewood Luke Skywalker in Star Wars and their beleaguered and
You know they're good and they're under pressure and they're trying to survive against Darth Vader
And the empire
Devil's snuff out all freedom
Hope and happiness and
You know all those kinds of things
That's the way the ancient
Story is handled
Water called the Greek and Persian
A moment that has sometimes been
Portrayed in
Apocalyptic like terms for what has sometimes been called the West
The part-time christened
So already many in the west are going to feel like
It's a sporting event and where the home team
Why were all homers when it comes to
Greek and Persian Wars unless
Of course
You're more like
We're portrayed as the Persians
Then remember this is not just
An ethnic thing this is a values thing
Narrative
Something called the Grand narrative
Play some
Greece's fighting
The things like
Liberty and freedom and democracy and artistic I mean everything
The evil empire isn't evil empire will snuff it all out and make slaves of air
Coincide
That's right
The story of
Is one of those that is absolute
Dramatic
Beyond anything you get in early
Because you have a master Storyteller in parting the story to you when I started in
News reporting an editor said to me your job
Is to relate
The facts of the story
The true information and do so in the most compelling way you can
If you imagine the Battle of Thermopylae
That's written by say the scribes of Babylonia
It might sound like this
In the fourteenth year the king of lands by the will of Marduk overcame the Spartan Army in a place called the hotkey
297 of the enemy were counted the Spartan King went to his destiny
The Babylonians have been writing that way
Forever
They were great record
Capers
Things were a little dry
Now
North of them were the Assyrians a culture that
Existence of alongside the Babylonians
A lot more aggressive
And big on the propaganda front and didn't mind showing people's nose in their defeats
And they like to maintain shall we call a muscular foreign policy
There's what sound a little bit more
Like Darth Vader's PR firm issuing a press release they would
Describe the Battle of Thermopylae like this
Like a storm I overthrew them
All ice luge
Their King I crucified
Their land I devastated
You may notice
There's not a lot of character development
Fair
Unless making the king of Assyria frightfully terrifying is the development or after
Then the last as I said in this story
Darth Vader's really the only character on the other side that gets flashed out
Very much
Compare
The sample Babylonian and Assyrian approaches to the story
Does something like the description you get from people like Herodotus of halicarnassus
Sometimes called the father of History
Occasionally called the
Lies
Writing is history generation after the events at Thermopylae
He talks about
Are the Spartans blocking this road
Understand
Tail that has developed over the hundreds of years afterwards of an event
The people have been adding a few screenwriting touches to since the very beginning
As the story is often told
There's a bunch of Greeks trying to block
The army of the Persians
I'm coming into Southern Greece
Xerxes the
The crack of Doom named Persian king
The only truly free person in his whole society
The story would have
Rules all of Asia and so many other lands
He is entitled a
King of Kings
All his people of the equivalent of slaves we live or die on his whim and when he orders them to fight the spa
Spartan in this
Stay obey
And are whipped
Buy overseers on to the spa
Ears of the Spartan
The Last Stand is it's called at Thermopylae the greatest last and probably in all human history
Was not supposed to be the kind of lost and turned out to be there were thousands of Greek soldiers at Thermopylae initially
But eventually became apparent
That it was going to be a death
And so the Spartan King
Supposedly sent the other Greeks away and kept a sort of rear guard if you want
Stick with the narrative a rear guard for
Greek and Western freedom
Behind hold off The Purge
They were other Greeks
Who are involved in the so-called Last Stand at their mop
What is the Spartan
To get the most attention about 300
And again you can understand why as characters they were fascinating in their own time
The Spartans are kind of a cultural experiment
A better way to put it is when you think about all human history together
There's enough law of averages stuff working where you can see
All kinds of little human experiments going on in various communities in Sparta
It's whether or not the culture can Infuse
A certain fighting quality
Human beings if they grow up a certain way pressured by the culture in certain
In a facets that just make them more likely to be extremely nasty and combat
Spartan warrior Sparta its do nothing but fight
There is no other job for
Entire culture seems to be designed from much of what
We know now
To reinforce this
Including a code of laws and behavior
Dependent to make the Spartans enough alike so that
Laconic became a term that describes
You know most of them they're not a lot of Chatty Spartans in history that culture didn't
Encouraged
Listen to the color
Come down from this story
The great King Xerxes with his army reported to be a million man so large that it drinks the river is dry
Comes to this road
With this pass that has to be crossed and these
Small group of Greek hoplites guarding it
Xerxes according to Herodotus
Doesn't know what to do
Can't quite believe he would he
Look at the color
Story
According to Herodotus
Xerxes senses Spa
To go up to the Spartan lines and try to figure out what's going on and not
Get caught
Not only does he have
Get caught but according to Herodotus
He reports back to Xerxes and says that the Spartan warriors couldn't have cared less that he was there they were fine with him looking around then care
He said they were doing exercises and combing their hair
Again you have to imagine Clint Eastwood
With long hair and a beard
Right there that be worth
The price of admission right
Tall sinewy guy not a big muscle-bound guy doing bodyweight exercise
Xeno calisthenic
Push ups
Sit ups
Gymnastics
That's how many
In-app wrapped in the coming a long hair was a Spartan
Xerxes cannot get his mind around Herodotus basically says
The idea that these people a couple hundred of them we're going to try to take on his reportedly million man army
Three calls in an advisor that he had
He's got a Spartan King
A guy who fell out of favor
And he hooked up with the Persians thinking that if they Conquer All In
Greece might be good
He's been the advisor to the great king
He had told
The king or earlier about these people and they made fun of him so now Xerxes called him back to report on what the
Spy it said the Spartans were doing
I'll let
Herodotus
This ancient screenwriter
Cannabis store
From their writing 2500 years ago
Quote
Xerxes listen but could not understand
Did the lack of the Mohicans were really preparing to kill or be killed
The fight as much as was in their power
CB him to be the height of folly
The action of fool
So we sent for demerit oh son of Ariston who was in the camp
Amanda Mariposa ride
Xerxes question him about everything he had been told
Trying to understand the meaning behind what the lack of the mornings were doing
Demirtas answered
You heard what I said about these men before
When we were just sitting out against the Greeks
And you made me a laughingstock when you heard my view of how these matters would turn out
But it is my greatest goal to tell the truth in your presence
So hear me now once again
These men have come to fight it for control of the road
And that is really what they are preparing to do
Purchase their tradition that they groom their hair whenever they are about to put their lives in danger
No no this
If you subjugate these men and those who have remained behind in Sparta there is no other race of human beings that will be
Left to raise their hands against you
For you are now attacking the most noble Kingdom of all the
And the best of men
What's a merito said
Toronto test rides
Seemed quite incredible to Xerxes
And he asked for a second time
How big could possibly intend to fight his whole Army
Since There were so few of them
Tamara Torres replied
Sire if things do not turn out just as I claim they will
Treat me like a liar
And quote
July to the
Great king of kings
The achaemenid Persian Empire
Was a capital crime
He was basically saying
If this doesn't turn out exactly like
I told you it will
You can kill me
That's pretty darn colorful
But it gets even better
Breaking the Persians was supposed to a send a message
The Spartan life
King Leonidas and say
Basically join us
Making the overlord degrees you'll have more than you ever had before
A lot of Nations have done that joining the Persian Empire was not a bad idea sometimes he's basically saying we can make a deal here it'll be worth
Worth your while
His father Darius was a great deal maker
Xerxes was coming from a position of negotiation here
And the Spartans basically dressed him down more
Saying something to the effect if you know you have all this land already but you need to bother us
We'd rather die
Freestone anything it was one of those wonderful Spartan moralistic put-downs
Against
Q words
Does possible
And then famously
As recorded by Plutarch 600 years after the event
30 sent another Messenger to the Spartan Lions supposedly
Another message for the king of the Spartans
And says to all the men who can hear him you can all go home
All will be forgiven just put down your arm
And then you get the wonderful
Praise
Alarm
Translated many different ways but it
Just as good pretty much any of
Commentator
Lay down your arms
Come and get it
Having come
Take
You can take them when we're all dead
A lot of the different ways the
Difficult to translate
Greek
Is used it still by the way the model with the Greek
1st Army Corps
It's been used
For many causes all throughout history cuz it's such a great
Dramatic
Colorful spit in the face of death line isn't it Clint Eastwood line
Do you feel lucky punk come and take
How do you not stand up in the theater and cheer
When that moment hits
Every screenwriters dream to have a scenario like that and if it can be true how wonderful is that
The Greek
Chroniclers who wrote about this stuff
Did not skimp on the drama
And it makes it colorful it makes it really make a compelling even 2500 years later
And you give your right arm
To have this kind of stuff
Right out of the mouths of the oral historians from all these places that didn't have them
I look black and white because of
The Persian story must be magical author
We don't have that stuff
And traditionally difficult for us to imagine that we like to hear
From a pro perspective the story of Darth Vader in the Empire
Trout history they weren't always Darth Vader
And some of the
Greatest chroniclers of all time
Have gone to Great Lengths
The show inside
That they may have been on
God
If that turns out to be the case
Whose side are you rooting for them
Of course in this time period the Iron Age
Ancient world
And in this area the Mediterranean and the near East
You'd have to be a heck of a lot more specific when you start talkin about deity
He's been to just say God
The likely response during that era might have been which God
It was a wild and crazy time
The religion in that part of the world and they have a lot of different ones and they ran the gamut from things you might
Understand today too wild and crazy
And everything in between
Most of these
Religious beliefs had a Pantheon of gods a bunch of them
Some of them had a so the dominant leave God but but
Having
You know multiple gods with normal there were groups
Especially one
Known for only having one
And they were the ones that
Put together
With Divine or without Divine help take your pick
A
Home
A combination of
Catalog of events
Stories
An accounts
Perspectives
And
Admonitions and hymns and
It's hard to describe exactly what the old Hebrew Bible is
It's also hard to know when it was written
Are the accounts
From the. Around the time the Persians first appeared on the scene
Legitimate from that.
Biblical A
Experts think they were written light
We use Plutarch 500 years after the fact and so does everyone else so
When the
Old
Hebrew Bible
In multiple places talks about the Persians
We should probably at least
Note the attitude
And the attitude that the writers whomever they may have been of those Works had toured the Persians especially early on
Wasn't just positive
It was divine
Meanie meaning
Tackle
You Farsi
Number
Wait
Division
My favorite part
The old Hebrew Bible
Which is so full of wonderful stuff you know that the Greeks don't have the market totally Corner tan color
There's just not a ton of stuff from the parts of the world
During the time. Represented by the Bible but remember there's a lot of discussion over when various pieces of the Bible
Well written
A lot of this good stuff might have been written in well into the pros. So we've entered into the color era
Because there's so much color on the Book of Daniel has this
Scary story spooky stories not like a horror movie but it's a spooky
And today you have to have a little CGI help to make it work but it's my favorite scene it's
Out of the Book of Daniel it involves a
Ghostly hair
Writing words on a wall meaning meaning
Tackle
You Farson
I have to back up a little bit in the story to set the scene
The king of Babylon
The Bible calls belches
Is having a party
And his body is
What's a concubine
That's the way the
Bible books
Probably have to imagine some loud music
You know there's there's booze I mean there
Drinking in a certain point
The king of Babylon want the really nice
In silverware brought in the Big Top
Gold and silver are the ones they took from
Jerusalem when they sacked
The capital of Judah not that long ago cuz that's what the Babylonians is done
Scattered a bunch of Jews everywhere
Forced a lot of the Premier families and Craftsman's and Artisans to deport all the way back to Babylon
And destroyed Solomon's Temple
When it comes to PR
Is belshazzar guy in the Babylonians are not getting a ton of it
Positive
From the Bible
And while he's drinking out of his big
Innaloo Didcot
Hanging out with the concubines
All of a sudden the ghostly hand with a finger
Piers right under the lamp
It starts writing on a wall
Meanie meanie tekel ufarsin
And everybody free
Freaks out
My King James version of the Bible
Makes it sound like he
Essentially couldn't control his bowels he was so scared
My eye later more colloquial version just
Sticks to the knees
Shaking
Version
Nonetheless
He couldn't figure out what it meant
So the Bible says this
Babylonian leader called in all his Sorcerers and necromancers and astrologers
All these people
Are the Wizards that advised
In the high Babylonian King
And part of what makes Babylonian so freaking Wonder
Is there a combination of like rational logical hard observational Science and Mathematics and all these kinds of things
Divination
You have to imagine a Stephen Hawking type character
But a Ouija board is an integral part of how he goes about his business
But none of these people the Bible says can explain to belshazzar what the writing mean
When someone reminds him that his father use this guy
This
Deportee you from Judah after the Babylonian to destroy Jerusalem there and he was here in Babylon
We could bring him in and see if he knows with that
Mostly writing means belshazzar
Grab the guy and brought him in and it was Daniel
It was indeed
Deportee
Belshazzar gives him the same offer he gave to his soothsayers this and you tell me what this means and in a gold chains and
You'll rule the third of the Kingdom all the cat stuff and Daniel says
You keep your gear
Or give them to somebody
I'll tell you what to do
Writing mean
I have a lot of different versions of the Bible
All the Torah all these things in front of me
And all the versions are good but the King James Bible with it
The wrath of God Style
If sums it up perfectly
Daniel looks at the
Mini mini tickle you Farson then describes the words as meaning
Number number weight division
Define
Dad
As meeting list
From the King James version
Persian quote
This is the interpretation of the thing
God hath numbered thy kingdom and finished it
Tell her to wait in the balance
Found wanting
Thy kingdom is divided
I'm given to the medes and The Purge
And quote
But pretty color.
Isn't it
And in that version
The king of the Persians a guy named Darius conquered Babylon that night and kills belshazzar
Well none of that's true but that's how the Bible
None the less it's clear from
Yeah that perspective
Did the Persians in this story are not going to be the bad guys they're going to be the instrument of God that rectifies things
If God is on anyone's side in that story
He's on the side of the medes and the Persians
Who the heck are these medes and Persians
And if they're so good in this story during the time of the Babylonians how did it go from
That
To the evil the Greek sea
You know two or three rulers later
I'll let remember Darth Vader
Wasn't always evil
And in fact
The guy who will kick off
The
Persians first real appearance on the world stage
Will be a guy that is so beloved by at least the Hebrew God
He will be the only non
2 ever
Proclaimed the Messiah
The person who will get this honor
Is knowing your history
Books by the name of Cyrus II
Horse Iris
The Great
She wanted to make it sound a little bit more like it
Probably Saturday
In Persian you would say
Kourosh
He's probably the greatest conqueror in world history up until the time of Alexander
He's got some of the best historical
Press anybody's likely to get nobody has a bad word to say about the guy
Even the Greeks like him
Xenophon write a whole book
Essentially romanticizing Cyrus is the greatest perfect world leader in wins you like to be like him and here's how you could emulate what he
Cyrus becomes part of a
Greek motif
Western tradition will continue for a long time
It portrays the east
As decadent and saw
Interrupt
But then how do you explain how some of these great Empires got started will the way the Greeks do it is Cyrus's fantastic
And he builds up his entire thing and bequeathed it to the Persians who proceeded to become soft and Rich and lazy and decada
And ruin
What's a great Cyrus gave them so even the Greeks
Trace Cyrus is this
Describe figure
And yet we know so little about the
If you can trust what we know about him and the guy who probably takes the crown from him is greatest conqueror in the world
Up to that point Alexander the Great
It's night and day
Alexander the Great exist
Nepali colorized historical world
A poster rotten
I just world a world where Alexander will bring his own publicist
With him
From place to place so they can record his latest deeds and sayings and doings
Cyrus the Great founds
The last great Empire and maybe what you could
Call the black and white era
In the near East
Panera wear
We know the majority about the people back then because of things like monologue
Statue
Send relief
Carvings
And tomb paintings and architecture and ruins
When you do have writing you get
Business Rec
Records and proclamations and transactions
Some of the best stuff you get from this era are the correspondences the letters between diplomats and governors ruler
But with none of those people are doing is writing
To amuse or entertain anybody
All of the writing from
The black and white. Of human history
Is colder
They all have a purpose Beyond being
Entertain
It might be a religious purpose
Business purpose of governmental purpose
Or even two important officials writing each other about in a matters of state and a few personal things creep in
That's very different than writing something
To be performed in front of a live audience for their entertainment and enjoy me
I read something historian Michael Grant
10 written about harada
Suggesting that the reason Herodotus
The interesting structures
But he does to his histories
Is because it was not meant to be read as much as it was meant to be performed live
Read aloud by Arata
Simself
And that the digressions and the tangents in the work
Represent things that would have worked much better in a live situation with somebody broadcast
Will and orator
As opposed to use somebody
Writing something to be red
By somebody else
Remotely
If that's the case
And you don't really have the first written
Pros history with Hirata tissue of the script for Herodotus is live showing
Which would explain a lot considering that if you want to get drama and color and stories before the. Of Herodotus
You're looking at things like The Iliad
By Homer
Or the Epic of Gilgamesh
Mesopotamia history both of which are believed by the way
Tubing stories told for hundreds of years that were finally
Compiled and written down same thing with like a bat
In Scandinavian
Maybe Herodotus is more like the angel
Storytellers
And first meets the eye
To give him some credit Herodotus was trying to be a chronicler at the same time he was trying to do the same thing I was told to do a news
To relate the facts as best as he understood them in the most compelling way he
He could
So
What you have
I'm here in this ancient story is not so much myth
That wouldn't be fair not just two people like Herodotus
All of the great historians overtime who found all these records
Together like a jigsaw puzzle
Viewing of the past
There's always being redone and improved but
Wooden to be existed there if
How different pieces of the puzzle hadn't brought together
But the same time
Well it's not myth
Reject the truth either
Historians
Who spent their whole lives
Separate the
From The Fixx
And works
Like Herodotus
Actually laughed out loud when I read
Prblms
From Cyrus to Alexander
Rihanna's with the great historians of ancient Persian this book is like
The
I made very detailed very specific it's 1200 pages
Enormous
Comprehensive book
And the very first lines in it
Are as part of the an opening page where he quotes an artist
Who says quote
And even if it is not true
You need to believe in ancient history
And quote
Does anything better
Set up
The dichotomy here
And how wonderful that in the 1200 page book
It is exhausted as all get-out the very first line from the historian is
That may not be true but you have to believe it anyway it's it's wonderful and it sums up the problem with ancient history in that is then
You have the feeling that most of what you're reading here is the truth in these events did happen but there's a lot of fiction mix
Extending it's difficult to know what's what and it's difficult to separate one from the other
Also difficult to know where to begin the story this is a classic problem anybody has trying to explain something right how do you begin a story of
Cyrus II in the Persians when does that start
All history is connected as we know right
It's all a bunch of tumbling dominoes
One event
And series of events leads up to other ones and set it all up where is The Logical starting point
I'm terrible at this by the way
I did a whole series on the decline and fall of the Roman Republic hours and hours and hours cuz I was trying to find the logical place to start a story about
Cleopatra
Never even got practically to Cleopatra was all
Domino's before then
Herodotus starts
With the earliest thing he knows about it it's a miracle he knows about it at all
He begins by talking about the Assyrian
He also talked about having multiple versions of this story to Herodotus being Herodotus
He says listen I've heard a lot of different things
Here are my sources
The Story begins boom
And here's what
Quote
From here our story demands that we inquire further about Cyrus in the Persians
Who was this man who destroyed the Empire of croesus
And how did the Persians become the leaders of Asia
I shall write this account using as my sources certain Persian to do not intend to magnify the Deeds of Cyrus
But rather to tell what really happen
Although I know of three other ways in which the story of Cyrus just told
And quote
Then he begins the story using a phrase that should probably be preceded by a line like
Once Upon a Time
Quote
The Assyrians ruled Inland Asia for 520 years
And the medes were the first to revolt from them
It would seem that they prove themselves to be truly courageous Men by fighting the Assyrians for the cause of freedom
Any succeeded in casting off slavery
And we're liberated
Afterwards the other ethnic groups
Read themselves as the Meathead.
And quote
Well the medes need a little explaining
Just like after the biblical story of belshazzar's feast when he said that the empire was going to be divided between the medes and the Persians
The medes and the Persians are they related peep
The Greeks use the terms interchangeably
They were
You know practically like brothers in the eyes of the Greek
When I was growing up they were just starting to change from the brothers sort of
Interpretation of maybe saying maybe they were more like first cousins
Some of the more recent histories I've been reading maybe you could say we downgrade the relationship even a step further to something like
Second cousins who fought some
Historians differ on Wendy's related people's arrived
In the area where they can now play a role in the history of this
You know when close to a geopolitical world
Babylon and Assyria all these places
Historians
I think they may have always
We've been there you just did
Didn't hear about them
Nevertheless the world upon which they have intruded
Is so old it's
Hard for modern people to get our minds around because
It's hard for us to imagine something 2500 years ago
In a wind Thermopylae is happening now imagine something
From 2500 years before that
And that's how old this world is I love the way in the 1940s
Historian a t Olmstead
Tried it
Give the reader a sense of how old this world was and how the people who lived in it knew it was old
He starts by talking about
Cyrus
2nd are Cyrus the Great person
Battery takes over Babylon
I'm trying to do
Describe how old world is the Babylon represent nieces quote
When Cyrus entered Babylon in 539 BCE
The world was old
More significant the world Nuit antiquity
It's Scholars who compiled long dynastic list
And simple Edition appeared approved the Kings whose monuments were still visible
Head ruled more than four millennium's before
Yet earlier we're other monarchs
Sons of God
Cancel themselves demigod
Who's Reigns covered several generations of present-day short-lived men
Even these were preceded the Egyptians believed
By the gods themselves
Who helps way through long EI
Before the universal flood the Babylonians placed pin Kings
The least of whom ruled 18600 years
The greatest 43200g
Other people's he writes
New this flood and told of monarchs
Nana cast of Iconium for example who reigned in Pre diluvian * meaning of the
Before the biblical
He continues
The secret history of the Jews extended through 4000 years
Modest that's where they're figure is when compared with those of Babylon or Egypt
They recorded that one pre diluvian patriarchy almost reached the Millennium Mark before his death
Greek poet chanted a legendary history which was counted backward to the time
When the genealogies of the heroes ascended to the god
Each people in nation each former city-state boasted of its own creation story
With its own local God is creator
And quote
Avengers on the diagram
That in the 600 and 700 BCE
There were quite a few rulers in quite a few of these old countries that became archaeological bus where they would go back and
Pay for the excavation of earlier rulers that ruled a thousand fifteen hundred years before them
And in Egypt may have dressed
Similarly that's
The continuity of the Egyptian fashion
My favorite
Story that really gives you an idea of the antic
If things and how the peoples of this region understood it and new it in a way
That you don't normally think about
Have to do with an archaeological excavation that
Happened in late 1800s early 1900
In Modern Day Iran
In the city
Through much of the historical period It was called Susie
Sousa is a very old
Ancients
It will be important in the Persian.
After that.
For a very long time of people called the Elam
Resided in Suzhou
And it was in a strata
Where the elamites. Was
Duffy's archaeologist
Began to uncover some of the greatest treasures
And Antiquities in near Eastern history
And they didn't belong there
They found for example the famous
Steel or Steely take your pick of Hammurabi
Something that is
Huge I mean it's a giant 7ft tall or something heavy big thing
And I find it there
What you doing there
That should be in Babylon
Now if you think the stele of Hammurabi is
Circa 1700 BCE or something like that
Archaeologist then find something
It's a good deal older than that
Call the victor
3 stele of narim sin
He was an Acadian
The 2200
BCE
So by the time they were making the stele of Hammurabi
The victory stele of narim sin with half a millennia-old
They were other Antiquities that they found to all of them from Elsa
They were
The spoiler
Balut
Stuff that the elamites took back with them
When they sacked Babylon
And in fact you could tell
Because somehow all this stuff was on display
I'm below the original inscriptions in the original language explaining what this was
Wasn't even might inscription explaining when it was taken from
The Babylonians as Loot and spoil
And is a piece of memorabilia commemorating the great victory
I keep imagining a bunch of trophies
He's in like a
College or university or School trophy case
You know commemorating the victories over the air has over your school rivals
The Oaken Bucket
The apple cup
The stele of Hammurabi
You know that kind of
And by the way it wasn't just
In a cultural artifacts that were taken in the famous Ela might Invasion that happened in the 1100
They took the god The Babylon with them they took maardu
With the statue that represented the guy
And this is one of my favorite things about ancient history is this idea sometimes that these statues that represented the god
Or somehow connected to the god
Him or herself
And sometimes were I mean there were some belief that they were the gods and so you'll see for example the Assyrians
In a lot of their were Stone released when they're showing the conquest of some civilization or City
They've got the god that their soldiers are carrying away along with all of the loot
And it's kind of symbolic when you think about it it's a sign our God stronger than your God after all we've got
Your God
And in a lot of these near Eastern civilizations the historians wrote that you can't reestablish
Some of these cities until the God has returned so another words with Babylon get sacked in the God has taken away
They can't do a big rebuilding thing until the God has brought back
We got your God
I mean talk about rubbing your nose
Any defeat there
I mean I was trying to think about what the equivalent would be in the modern world certainly if somebody took over the United States
If the elamites have done it they would have the Statue of Liberty
In their little Museum there with a little notation underneath
Taking from New York City after we Crush The Americans
I love to eat them
Would love to know more about them than one of those people that just not a lot is known
What you can say for sure is that they are the great long-standing Urban power
In what is now modern-day Iran for thousands of
Here's the big contemporaries and the big Power from that region that rival the Babylons in the series
He is in the Egypt's there's usually a power in the north to North of Assyria but that changes
He could be matani it could be the hittite taking bur to
Nonetheless you have
A relatively stable
Geopolitical balance going on for a long time even through the ups and downs
And then that world
Begins to be consciously
Destroyed
And that opens up the door
To an instability
Where
Anything can happen
A shocking things did
It starts with
The absolute
Skyrocketing
By historical standards
The military dominance of the Assyrian
And you may be thinking we were just talkin about the medes a minute ago and now we've shipped it over to the Assyrians and what does one have to do with the other
But it's their paths
Crossing
DeSoto set up the stage for the next.
In Western Asian history
The medes will turn out to be one of a couple of David's in this story will take down Goliath
In order to understand what a big deal that is
You need to understand
You know how big of a deal Goliath was
In the story the Assyrians are
And they were transformed
In the 700s BCE
From one of the great power sometimes the greatest of the great Powers sometimes not
Into the
Regional superpower
And as far as these people
We're concerned
The region was the entire world
And this quickly growing
Absolutely
Devastating
New Empire in terms of its military
Abilities
Would have been the ones fighting the Greeks
And the Spartans at Thermopylae
Have the means
And their allies not been able to take down this Goliath and I got news for you
I don't think
The Neo Assyrian armies at their height
Would have beaten Alexander the Great and his makedonian I'm not sure but I don't think
But I think they Crush
The ancient Greeks of Athens
Sparta
And so maybe if the pass of Thermopylae in the greco-persian wars really was a war for Western Civilization
We should be thankful that there were people like the medes to take down the people
Oh I think would have been the odds-on favorite in any Vegas betting pool
To take down the ancient Greeks in 480 BCE
They weren't around in 480 BCE in part because of these people to me to
In the 700 when the story really heats up and gets strange
Quora people on the periphery of the known universe at the time
Do the Assyrians the medes
Are sort of the Eastern edge of the known Galaxy
Biondo's midi and tribes with all their petty little
Kinglets
Are groups of half human half monsters
Call The Omen Monday
In the Syrian annals Eagleman Mondo by the way in Old Acadian term
Demeans The Horde from who-knows-where
It's believed
At this refers
2D nomadic
Cultural forebears of the Huns in the Turks and the Mongols and all those people
Infected medes and the Persians were supposed to be able to speak
To the Lumen Monda
Without the use of Translate
How'd you like to be related enough
Two people known as the
Horde from who-knows-where
To be able to understand their language without anybody helping
None the less
It's in this. Right around 7:50 BCE
Where you get a sort of an unusual happening in ancient
History where a lot seems to happen
In a relatively short period
Free time
Because it's ancient history you get these long stretches where it seems like very little changes
In 7:45 BCE
With the arrival of a new Assyrian King a guy named tiglath
Pily's Earth
The 3rd
Syria begins to go on this
Sprint maybe you could call it a historical Sprint
That will last until about 6:15 6:12 BCE
And we'll be like
Maybe you could say the last
Burst of rocket fuel
Historical era of that ancient world
About to give away to the air of the
The Greeks and classical Antiquity and all that kind of stuff
And Rockets it to the heights where the Assyrian army for example
In say 700 BCE
Are the equivalent of like the Roman Empire's armies if they're high
For their error
The Assyrians will
Systemic
Smash
The other great powers
In that area and it's difficult by the way they're powerful they're sophisticated
They have a lot of money some of these places
The Assyrians
Often have to face not single States
Coalition
Estate
Big allies that alive simply to deal with the Assyrians and they lose most of the time anyway
I'll try not to geek out on the Army too much but it's the gold standard for the era
Richard Gabriel and Karen Metz in their book from Sumer to Rome
Describe it in a nutshell in terms of just giving you a mental picture of the capabilities of an army
From this era
End of the so-called biblical era when I was growing up there right quote
The Assyrian army of the 8th Century BCE
What's comprised of at least a hundred and fifty thousand to two hundred thousand men
And was the largest standing military force at the Middle East and witness to this time
An Assyrian combat field Army
Numbered approximately 50000 men
With various mixes of infantry chariots and cavalry
In modern times the size of an Assyrian field Army was equal to 5 modern heavy American Division
Oromo State Soviet field division
Win a raid for battle the Army took up an area of 2500 yards across
And a hundred yards deep
The Assyrian army was also the first Army to be entirely equipped with iron weapons
And quote
Boy doesn't that's so V
Reference date me
Nonetheless
You get an idea that we're talkin about armies that were exponentially larger
Then in the recent past
In the Bronze Age you know now room scene was putting like 6,000 guys into the field and thinking he had a lot of men
The Assyrians have multiple divisions of 50000 each
They will smash the power of the Mountain State of you are too at one point during this
. that's where Modern Armenia is
They will several times have to deal with Babylon
Another one of their great Kings
Sennacherib take care of that
And then they just have to do it again and again Babylon is a thorn in the side perpetually of the Siri
And the elamites always get in trouble with the Assyrians today we support the Babylonians cuz after all
All of them would like to see the Assyrians cut down to size
Eventually the Assyrians will cut
The elamites down to size 2
One of the most
Horrifying of all the Assyrian reliefs
And you know there's a lot of them in historians
Don't always know how to classify them
You can't tell if
You want to say
That these are real scenes that they're showing when you see these carvings which were probably painted at one time or often
Displayed in the waiting room before you got to see the king
What are you looking at while you're cooling your heels waiting to see the Assyrian King the things he did to the people like you
Who may be turned against him
Sometimes historians think
If they're taking a sadistic
Sort of cruel loving this
Sometimes it's meant to be terrifying and they enjoy that Saddam Hussein Style
Sometimes they think of it as a convention
In the same way the Egyptians always seem to show them
Wearing certain kinds of clothing whether or not they did anymore was artistic convention showing people getting their heads lopped off
Is just
You know if you go to Assyria you expect to see BC ringtones
Ted Kennedy
That's who we are
Nonetheless one of my favorite Assyrian relief shows the aftermath
Of the era where the Assyrians finally decided to deal with the ongoing elamites
Problem
It shows the Assyrian King ashurbanipal reclining on one of those wonderful Oriental near Eastern
New kinds of things that they used to lay down on the couch
What do we have somebody feed you grapes or something and he's sitting there drinking wine or eating food
In a luxuriously relaxing soda paste in a garden with little palm trees if I recall it correctly and is a woman
In there with him
And you get the feeling like he in that woman are together
And then right
Over nearby up on the side of a wall or poster pillar
Is a head
The head of the elamites
Pickled
Or otherwise
And that woman who you think maybe is ashurbanipal zwei for maybe
Royal concubine
Some historians think is the wife
Of that elamites
She having to be there with the person who killed him
And have him looking on
Anybody list the whole time the Assyrians just had this wonderful
Historical reputation for something that once again is Cinematic
Now it's not color it's not like Herodotus and all that we don't have it in color
But it's a really
Scary black and white horror film
If you're on the receiving end
I'm a Syrian violin
I should point out that you know focusing so much on geopolitics
And a Syrian foreign policy May Minnesota color the picture in a very negative way because to live in in the syrians
City during this time period might have been awesome
Vitamin the height of civilization and it was it was a society that was in some respects one of the most literate at all
Time. It was wealthy it was cultured
How you been great to live in the Siri you just didn't want to be on the wrong end of Assyrian for Impala
I'm about 7:45 BCE
To about the you know early 600 a lot of people were
And very few people came away doing very well after that they
Systemically batter down the structures of this region now
Battering down the structures of the region were very important if you wanted to kind of make it aminia Bowl 2
Being incorporated into a single political entity like an Empire
Everybody is individualistic nature had to be curtailed somewhat
The problem will come
When the unifying force that did this disappears
To get an idea by the way of how many peoples were talking about
But he has a wonderful way to sort of contradict the earlier way the story was told
Which was focusing on people's ethnicity
You say
You know the Assyrians were submitted
And the
Iranian people's leave medes and the Persians were
Indo-European and all that
Is to realize when you deal with a place that is so filled with different ethnic groups
Intermarrying living together
It doesn't take very long for peoples languages to change which used to be the way
We charged who was whom
It also means that
The job of any unifying force that wants to turn all these different
Freedom-loving groups
Into a single political entity is huge
History will Durant tries to little lay the foundation and then basically says you just so you know
Look at how many people there are in this part of the world and they're all interacting all the time and their intermarrying in them
It's an ethnic Melting Pot
He says quote
Do a distance and yet Discerning Eye
The near East in the days of nebuchadrezzar would have seemed like an ocean
In which vast swarms of human beings moved about in turmoil
Forming and dissolving groups
Enslaving or being enslaved eating or being eaten killing or getting killed endlessly
Behind and around the great Empires
Egypt
Babylonia Assyria and Persia
Flower this medley of half Nomad have settled tribes
Canarians collegians
Cappadocians bithynian
Ashkanian
Messenians
Nyan Nyan
Carrion's like kean's pamplin's pisidian lucky Nyan
Philistines amorites Canaanites edomites ammonites moabites and a hundred other people's Each of which
Spelled itself the center of geography and history and would have marveled at the ignorant Prejudice of his story and who would win
Induce them to a paragraph
And quote
I got a bunch of History to talk about
Difficult the task is to meld all these individual list
Different peoples into
A single political entity Chester star writing in the middle 1960s
Put it this way as he tries to sort of
Counterbalance
This ruthless image the Assyrians have with the job they're trying to do when he writes quote
This ruthless Spirit perhaps
Proves not so much that the Assyrians were inhuman monsters
As it shows the sternness required to break and harness the near East
Assyrian. Was in reality one of the greatest turning point in the Civilized history of the area
And in this fact must be sought the justification
Are the booty in the tribute of Empire
If Empire needs justify
Vacation
Politically such Kings is tiglath-pileser the third took decisive steps towards uniting the fertile
Crescent the next great Empire the Persian reaped the benefit and so could afford to exercise its way
Hey in a more lenient Style
And quote
This is actually key to one of the things we've been talking about
The fact that even though the Greeks portrayed
One of the Persians a suit of Darth Vader and the empire
History outside the Greeks knew them as a comparatively tolerant Empire
Comparatively lenient
Who were they being compared to
The Assyrian
But it may have taken with the Assyrians did
To make an Empire that was docile enough
For the Persians to treat them that way and have it all work out
I should also point out that there are quite a few historians
Suggest
Did the Assyrians have another Legacy
Potentially
Credit them
A much more noble
One by the way despite the horrific
Marketing and the frightful branding
Perhaps you might look at them during this time. Depending on your Viewpoint in more of a Captain America
Style roll
Fending off
The hordes of barbarism
Whomping
The Civilized world with their
You know Murder and robbery
Because in the last years of the 700 BCE
The Omen monitor
Breakthrough
And when they do
It will take the greatest military of that age
To be able to resist and go up against what is a revolutionary military channel
The first peoples in history probably
Who had to try to figure out how you die
Defeated Army
Where everyone in the Army is mounted on horse
Now
Our modern era is so different than
How the Dynamics of
Warfare work for most of human history that it's sometimes
Is it difficult to reintroduce the more obvious thing
Tissot to click a light bulb on in your head and remind you oh yeah we're talking about something this basic for exam
I cannot love these military Revolution.
Can you imagine what it be what it must have been like when the first
Chariot
Attacked the first
In a settled civilizations out there
In the first time in army
It was composed entirely of people walking
Had to deal with something moving at the speed of a horse
And by the way the way that they usually function was that the person inside the Cherry had a very powerful
And shot arrows at people and never really tried to
No contact them at all until they were broken and running away so you couldn't catch him and they move faster than you did
And it changed Warfare
And sometimes it's funny by the way to read some of the
Did the records that have been kept that you have from some of these very early Chariot Society
And you realize how little they know about horses because people who knew anything about horses are these really high paid in
Important individuals and they have this hidden knowledge about
And here's how you take care of the feet of a horse and he fears what you do if they get bloated mean at things that today Brazilians of people know
Acton this was like privileged information Heights
Right
And the Horse Inn
The
Settled societies the Egypt The Babylon and Assyria at first you can see that they that they don't know how to deal with
And there are wonderful little figurines and what
Not showing
In the Egyptian movies like an Egyptian Scout
Out during
Maybe the first two hundred years or something that the Egyptians were really trying to use horses and he's sitting way back over the tale of
The horse like he hasn't even figured out
But that's not the right spot
Decision
But we take it for granted that this is an obvious thing
You might not have been
About 1000 BCE Cavalry first
Appears
And it generally appears
In in in in in a way that once again makes you think that these people are not very comfortable riding and
Remember there are no Saddles there are no Spurs there are no stirrups
I mean there's a lot of
Mac
To knowing what you're doing here
And remember also that riding horses can be
Dangerous and fatal
If you're not used to it right in none of these people are growing up doing a whole lot of horse riding
About 900 BCE you can see carving showing Assyrian Cavalry which is probably
If you think about it
In a cutting-edge for the time. For the subtle civilizations
And they send the Cavalry Riders out in pairs
Because one guy has to hold the reins for The Other Guys horse when the other guy decides he's going to shoot or anything
In other words they don't even feel comfortable enough to shoot and ride
You know
Independently you got to have someone there to hold the horse when you do it another word you can watch the evolution right
It's different when the armies from the Middle East
The ancient near East
First run into the step troops that will make up
One of the dominant important
Tribal areas in world history for
Almost at 4 I mean it's only the last couple hundred years
That the Eurasian steppe
Part of which you would refer to a central Asia today
Kazakhstan Keurig
Yes and those kind of places
Show me the last couple hundred years those places have not been massively relevant to
You know what's going on
I was reading a book not that long ago that was going into all of the things that
China and Russia of the 1700
See he's only a couple hundred years ago
All the things that they had to do to deal with it
Tribes
On the step and it's crazy because
You know when you look at history you become very accustomed to watching
The so-called civilized societies
Just rolling over tribal peoples you know to certain point in history once once the momentum gets going
And you have like Julius Caesar in Roman armies just rolling over Celtic Society
You're already prepared to get to the part where the colonial Europeans going to show up on these Distant Shores and run into people
People with wooden clubs and bows and arrows when you got gun
Conclusion write
But you look at the step
And you see the one place in history where for a number of different reasons the odds are much more equal
Between settled and tribal people
First of all
It's likely that the odds in terms of fighting Power in terms of Manpower was probably pretty close
The settled societies had a lot more people
But a lot of them weren't Fighters the
Tribal societies
Usually had most of their male people
As Fighters
And some females by the way
The weapons technology was
Probably comprable that the bows used by the step people are famously
Some of the best ever made
But it would have been other things that the settled so-called settled societies had in their favor so probably wash their butt imagine
Imagine the Native Americans
With a rough parody in fighting men
And a rough parody and weapons technology what would the Native Americans have done to the settlers then
Who knows but at least it's a fair fight
Add to that
The geographic conditions in the distance right this is a harsh environment the step sometimes if you're not adapted to it
And it's a long way from point A to point B no matter where you're going
And you had a part of the world that was protected by steppe peoples
For millennia
Were they maintained their way of life
And where shall we say relevant relevant is a good non bias in any direction where relevant
To the societies of world powers around them
And we've known them forever right we've seen
Wave after wave of these people come forward from the magyars
The church to the Honda to the Mongols
This is the first. In recorded history where these people break through and then someone's there to
Record
There's always been a historical school of thought the Chariot invasions from Central Asia long before this.
Earlier versions of these kinds of invasions
But this is the first one recorded
Will you get to see
You know the kinds of Step arm usually
Respect for the next
2000 years
Mounted on horseback
With people who are you know as we said about the Spartans that they were sort of a laboratory experiment to see if a culture
Circuitry in a super soldier
The steppe societies are kind of a laboratory Experiment 2
If you put people on Horseback from the time when they are
Toddlers
And put a bow in their hand from not much later
And have them ride all the time and do everything on Horseback and use those bows continually and developed a
Tactics where they never really come into contact with people that don't want to come down
What do you end up with
Then the answer is you end up with a weapon system
That was so effective
The even after guns were developed modern societies were having a tough time pardon the pun corralling me
These people
Even up until relatively modern times
Now when you think about how long that is people trying to contend
With the step people
Think about how much admiration we should have with the first people who had to try
With no track record of experience
The Assyrians would develop a kind of a broad policy of dealing with these
Tribal step people that resembles
What very sophisticated people who dealt with him for a very long time came up with
With the Chinese and the byzantines for example would use a mix of diplomacy intermarriage
Warfare
And
Keeping the tribes divided and fighting amongst themselves
New series did all this stuff do they use some of these people as allies sometimes it have
Mercenaries were
Do people from these tribes the tribes like the canary in the Skippy in the various socotra
Jobs in the mass of GD they have
Tribal
Confederation
M1 is
Scarier than the next and if you're one of those settled Society people
Barbarians in air quotes always scared you mirror just something scary to settle people about
Do people like the Celts for example
Skinny jeans are no different
Coventry steppe peoples are no different there headhunters for example famously will
Drink
From
The skulls of their dead enemies make cups out of them
And if you want it
See how the wonderful continuity of Step culture sometime ago they were doing this in
In ancient times and they were doing this up until relatively in the Mongol type history the drinking cups golfing
A perennial favorite
But it's just a cultural thing
Ride me the Assyrians are hanging enemies heads on walls
So that they can watch their in a wife have
Relations with the Assyrian King who killed them I mean everybody's got their thing
Right
Same time
These people are are scary
They're effective
They
Are entirely mounted which means they have amazing challenges to the militaries of the day cuz remember you move at the speed of your
Slowest person if you have an entire Army mounted
The entire Army moves at the
Speed of a horse
Peter huge challenges in the Assyrians
Managed to ward off the worst of the attacks in the sense
You know you can make a case that they protected this entire
Area of civilization
From marauding
Scary people who were not going to leave it intact and you know this because there were several Invasion that do brakes
There's a horde
Ascidians
It will rape and pillage all the way down to Egypt before the Egyptians either buy them off or militarily turn them back
Can they go bouncing around the region like a snooker ball
The fact that in a lot of these step Army's every single person was mounted
Was also revolutionary and
Huge
In the armies of the day
If you were lucky and 15 or 20% of their
Force mount
Did sometimes
Quite a bit less
You still move at the speed of your slowest troops
If you don't if you break the Cavalry off so you can operate independently you'll have a
Nice small group of cavalry
It gets overwhelmed by an entirely mounted Force
Turn on the lights
A10 army with infantry moves at the speed of inventory these armies that the settled Societies in this geopolitical round and
Sunshine are trying to deal with
Speed of a horse
Strategically on the map
That's a devastating thing to try to counter
The fact that the Assyrians could is a testimony to how great
The greatest military the world has ever seen was
And how well LED
You could see how big the challenge
705 BCE
Sargon II arguably the greatest
King of Syria ever had
Well as an elderly man
Leave the Assyrian army in person
Up to Modern
Southeastern
Turkey near the border
Neo hittite area
Call to ball
And probably fighting in conjunction with some of these
Neo hittite cities
Eurasian steppes
Trips to Marion
And Sargon II
Will disappear
With the army
The body will never be
That is a very rare event when the body is not recover the assumption is that nobody
Because one of the last things you will do is grab the king's body
B&M Spirited Away
It's like saving the flag
* 10
Dubina Gyptian King 2
Famously
Will stay on the battlefield and they they they end up getting it later and mummifying
A body that's been
The mutilated it on the battlefield for a few weeks
Can you can still look at the
Mommy today and see
Oh wow
Didn't get them for a while
Sargon II will never be found I've often thought it's not a coincidence his son's Tanaka read never
Actually
Letter
Forcing person when he was
He left that to the generals is very important things in Nineveh that need taking care of
Newsstand
Anyone who could do that
Two in the Syrian Army at the height of the series Power
Is formidable indeed
Now you know Siri could protect some of this region they couldn't protect
And some of these tribes filtered down to the area where the people were ostensibly talking about here are
The medes the Persians the elamites the Zagros Mountains Iran
The peoples in this region are about
To go through
A one-two punch that will change them for a
The second of these punches will be delivered by the Assyrians
Surprise surprise there throwing punches everywhere why shouldn't this read
Get to
The first will be delivered by these steps
Belize tribes
Sumerians
Skip the end
Who will at a certain point I said filtered I thought that was a nice ambiguous way
When you don't really know what happened but the traditional idea is that the Skippy Inns in the khmerian
Attacked
Broken to assaulted
Dominis
In a giant invasion
There's even a year
Associated with
At 6:53 BCE
Which if you think about it like 50 years after
Sargon II dies
You up into ball right at about 55 60 years since these
Horse people first appeared
And they're still managing to totally disrupt
In a huge areas of this
Geopolitical ecosystem only use that word from now on we all know what I mean right
Filtered is a good word though because it also allows room for Theory
Where Warfare should have doesn't dominate the reasoning behind
Why all of a sudden all these Central Asian tribes moved into this part of the Run
One of the things that's really changed since I first started studying the story is the concept that historians have about who these midi in the world
What kind of state they had
When I was growing up the history is all made it
Sound like
The medes were like the Babylonians
Any Assyrians by this time a centralized state with cities and and governance of bureaucracies and all that
Historians today and you know I'm not one I just read the best
They make it sound much more like the current state of theory is that these means are much more tribal
Then we had previously assumed
And if so might not be that much different than these Skippy and zakim Aryans coming into their area
To be much more like
A tribal relationship would have received the medes and the Persians were second cousins who fought sometimes
Easter peoples are like 3rd cousins who fight a lot
Remember they could allegedly speak to each other
There without the use of a translator
When you are that
Close to another people
What appears to be a conquest from outside might be much more like
Dynastic marriage
Or someone having to change their Alliance status or becoming a vassal of someone else are having to pay tribute
Herodotus might see all of that stuff is a version of slavery
But when he calls it slavery we might be picturing something else entirely
Herodotus says that the
Domination of the medes last
28 years
An interesting little
Tidbit
That might confirm what he says is
During that time. The Assyrians in the Babylonians who keep records and who know and mentioned the medes from time to time
Start calling everyone who lives in that whole region
The Omen Mondo
And Reese's origami among others suggest that this bite
Mean
The entire area has just been sort of overwhelmed
And if you can't tell one tribe from another without
Scorecard
Herodotus if you want to go with this tells one of his really
Fun stories I'll me know if
Like me
About how the medes eventually threw off
The nomadic eoq know if that was
Suppressing them and he tells a story about how
They invited the Skippy and leaders to a banquet
And then got them all drunk
Can the money were also inebriated they could hardly stand they went in and killed them all
I guess you could call that
Your decapitating the enemy leadership literally
Or maybe the tactic is drunken Mass homicide whatever you want to call it
It seems like a motif another one of these recurring sorts of things you see all throughout history in the writing and and one
What are those
One of those aspects of the story that often times professional historians will discount because after all we see this all the time this
Sounds just like blah blah blah and they're almost always right
Here's the weird part though this is something that you actually see in history confirm Ubly
The relationship between using alcohol as some sort of a trap
To ensnare other people who then become vulnerable when we seen this in recorded history like not that long ago
Native American tribes had this treatment done to them
Sometimes multiple times
In other words what might look in this case like a recurring motif
Might actually be a recurring historical occurrence
How would you tell the difference
In any case it'll happen again in this story
Which once again makes you say okay is this just a recurring Motif or is this a tactic that worked last time so we're try
Trying it again
Nonetheless somehow
The medes regain
In a freedom of action from these people who are then thrown out
Leaving behind another
Wonderful ethnic strain of the Central Asian bloodline that will run through around over the ages and that will be added
Do with New Blood
Sometimes tragically from time to time
The guy who is supposedly the king of the medes during this
Period of Domination by The Scorpions
Is a mead name
CV axle
Herodotus
Credit scam with totally reorganizing
The military of the meat
He says
Seahawks series becomes the first Asian leader to in a separate
An army into component parts in archery
Cabaristas before that they all fought together in a chaotic Mass which is not
True at all
But some historians think he's preserving some sort of a memory of this important
Madeon ruler who
Reorganize the military made it much more powerful and considering what he was about to do with it
There seems to be some historical evidence for the Meads all of a sudden becoming very formidable indeed
Right about the same time
When the Great traditionally great power in that region
Gets
Mortally wounded by Assyria
Alluded to this earlier part of the series
Laying waste
To all these
In a competitor
Lyrics for their superpower status I did not going to be anybody that even gets to put up
A little resist
The elamites once again get on the hit list for doing the same thing they always do
Babylon revolt against Assyria
Elong helps Babylon as soon as the Assyrians take care of Babylon they come for
The elamites and this happens under the last
The Great
Assyrian rulers
Ashurbanipal
Hoosier Hoosier very long ruling guy in at the start of his Reign the Empire could not be
Fireplace
By the end of his Reign you know he's writing these woe-is-me Tales what did I do to have the gods turn against me
Everything sucks
You know but I'll die soon at least kinds of
Your writings
Assyria
We'll go from the height of its fortunes to
1945 Berlin fall of the Third Reich devastation
Never to rise again
In a very short period of time
And some have argued
The part of the reason why
Is because of what they did to the people around them
They destroyed the other powers
But might have acted as barriers against New Rising ones with of the new Rising ones are Skippy and sinking Marion from the eurasians
Or whether there
An obscure
Tribal people known as the me to all of a sudden they're really getting powerful and well lad
The weather wise would have been dealing with the elamites
But the elamites get smashed by Usher Bonaparte
In 646 BCE and the devastation is
Arguably immortal
We are ready
Mention two scene from the actor
Elamites
Final Solution when
Ashurbanipal is lying on his
Couch with that woman there
And then this Everett had you know upon the pillar of the wall That's
In a part of the aftermath
Dealing with the elamites this way
Ashurbanipal Leeds
The greatest Syrian Army
All the way it's a long way again to Susa
Devastate coelom as his scribe writing for himself
Recounts
Quote
For a distance of 1 month in 25 days March I devastated the districts of Eli
I spread salt and thornbush there to injure the soil
Sons of the Kings Sisters of the Kings
Members of balaam's royal family young and old
Prefix
Governor's Knights Artisans as many as there were
Inhabitants male and female big and little horses mules asses
Flocks and herds more numerous than a swarm of locusts
I carried them off as booty to Assyria
The dust of Susa of medoc to of how termination of the other cities I carried it off to Assyria
In a month of days I subdued Alam and its whole extent
The voice of man the steps of flocks and herds the happy shouts of Mirth
I put it into them and it's feels which I left for the asses the gazelles
And all manner of wild beasts
Two people
And quote
The Assyrians were
Thorough
They even removed
The bone
Show me old going back to ancient
Elamite rulers from their tombs
Them back
It was Siri with the loot
Historian 80 Homestead says they put them in
Particularly awful spots
So that they would get no rest ever again laying in a foreign land
I'm paying an eternal price for their enmity to Assyria
It may have happened in the Deep Misty
Eras of the past
And we said you earlier that it
The elamites
Conquer the United States they take the Statue of Liberty back as a prize of War to be displayed
Police syrians wouldn't stop at the Statue of Liberty
They steal our constitution they take the Washington Monument
8 snuff out the flame
John F Kennedy's grave and take the bones with them
Assyrians
We're sort of setting the bar for this region people like the Babylonian to come afterwards we'll be just as brutal like they're trying to
Imitate whatever the standard of the day is
But the standard of the day
Is
Even today
Try making a movie out of it it's going to be it's going to be a cable one for sure
In the story Olmstead tells of the parade is that a good word
When is your Bonnet Paul and his army arrived back home in Nineveh
Displaying the loot
And the prisoners and meeting out punishment by the way to all and Sundry
Is
Spiteful
First of all
The head of that Edomite ruler that will be sitting up on Usher bottom pause
Wall or what have you
Was transported from Susa on foot
Around the neck
Of the elamites general
Imagine how
Freaky that with a
2 Live Crew
Who did The Walking Shane supposedly
And then
The various generals are brought out and punished and there's a psychological twist with Siri and Punishment by the way
That is part of kind of what the
Persians will sort of do away with
Here's what
18 Olmstead
Brighten I'm going to try my best at some of the pronunciations of these Mesopotamian names they are wonderful
He writes quote
Ashurbanipal was about to leave Arbella for Nineveh
And the severed head of the elamites ruler was entrusted to his General
Dunoon news neck for transport
As the musicians led the ghastly procession into Nineveh
The terrible sight
Craze how Madara and Nabu dummy
The ambassadors who would receive their commissions from the dead monarch
One tore his beard
The other thrust his girdle sword into his bosom
Aplia son of Nabu Shalom and Grandson of the famous merodach-baladan was extradited from
Mallam Manu keahi Dunn Avenue and Nabu Shalem The Gambler Chieftains had spoken
Blasphemy against the Assyrian gods
And for this crime they had their tongues pulled out by the roots
And we're skinned alive
The horrible scene is represented on one of the reliefs although
Strangely enough Olmstead rights
The names have never been filled in the blanks left for the purpose
The new new was placed on the rack and slaughtered like a lamb
His brother Sam gulou when aplia
We're slain and their flesh distributed among the surrounding land
Nabu not eating bellatier sons of Naboo Schumer
We're forced to crush the bones of their father
And the head of the Edomite King found its final resting place over the gate which led to Usher
And quote Asher being a primary a Syrian City
The forcing the sun's to crush the bones of the father is one of those really
Psychologically
Horrible things and you'll see this in other occasions the Babylonian King for example who supposedly
Once he took Jerusalem took the ruler the king
And forced him to watch the
The slaughtering of his two young sons in front of his eyes and then had his eyes put out so that the last thing he saw
Always.
Extralegal cruelties
That just seemed
Well that just seemed calculated to subdue somebody's will to resist but you could easily
Really see how it might have the opposite effect
You could see how a people coming
After this time
Might be able to make all sorts of political hay
Selling themselves as the alternative to this kind of Cruelty
And you can also see why
I went to Syria
Spell
There were not a lot of Tears cried
What was gone in fact
Even the biblical prophets are rejoicing
As I was trying to come up
Some sort of analogy
To try to do
Define the stakes here
With what's about to happen all I could
Think of in my
On creative
Mine was the idea
Of the United States over the next five or so years
Somehow
End with jaw dropping
Astonishing events
Tell apart
Imploded
Broke into some kind of a Civil War ended up getting involved in maybe a foreign war at the same time I mean
You never know how these things are going to turn remember how you felt if you were old enough to remember
What the 9/11 attacks look like on live television while you watch them
There's almost nothing positive that comes out of something
Like that but one of the few things that was in my mind
Was that you watched it
You were reminded
That the most astonishing things not only
Can happen but we'll have
They're like earthquakes you know there's going to be a big one you just don't know when
You know there's going to be some massive jaw-dropping historical event in the future you just don't know the date
I have time like a 911 but when you watch that happening
That astonishment is how mankind has failed over and over and over
As you look back on it
There's about to be an astonishing moment in this story it's not really a moment
5 to 15 years it just appears astonishing now
But it's akin to the United States imploding
Really I think it's more than the Soviet Union falling but a little less than the modern United States going away
Nonetheless if the United States did go away in the next 5 years
What is the international situation look like
Then
Mean what
World instantly Springs up to replace such an important call and how does that go
This is actually the world
It is going to exist
As soon as this story that must be
You're one of the great events in all human history
But we don't know
Because you don't have a Herodotus there to give it
Even with a bunch of lies and exaggerations and untruths that may have filtered in over the hundreds of years
We don't have his version or anyone like him
To explain it to us
We like the color
By the way promised he was going to tell the story
In one part of his histories and then never did
Or didn't come down to us or something
Futurist Babylonian sources
And that's it in fact the stuff you thought you couldn't count on like as wonderful as Siri and
In a pronouncements by the king of kings
I went in there I planted Thorn bushes I killed everybody
That ends in like 6:39 BCE ominously and mysteriously all of a sudden
What the heck's going on
I love the different ways that historians try to
Describe this 211 history says he was unclear what was happening
Author Mark Healy
Explain the importance though this. Silence cuz he says
Quote and it is in the Silence of those years that is written the fate of the Assyrian Empire
And quote
So the important stuff is happening we just don't know much of what it is
Open to interpretation is how another
Historian put it
Here's what basically goes on
Ashurbanipal zeringue
At the end you start to see things spray
You begin to see places that were under a serious control on the on the margin
Break Free
A lot of historians think that it's rather telling that all of a sudden you can have these Skitty and tribes riding roughshod now in air
Areas with the Assyrians used to keep them out it must mean that they can't
Well no one is really paying alot of attention
The medes are beginning diffuse sort of
And it's unclear how they did this with the elamites civilization
Could have been peaceful could have been War like
Could have been diplomatic marriage
But it's making both
Civilization stronger
Ashurbanipal die
And his sons go to war with
Now
This is not uncommon
In Assyrian royal succession
But this is coming at a particularly bad time
Does all of a sudden the Babylonians
A resurgent
It got a new Dynasty
They got an army that is modeled it's it's it's a not as effective copy of the Assyrians
B series copy the Babylonian civilization not quite as well as the Babylonian original and the Babylonians copy.
The Assyrian military though it's not quite up to the originals standards either
But when you've been fighting
One half of your Army against the other which is what the Assyrians were doing in the Civil War that's why they're so ruinous
Do you have outside power starting to loom over you and what do you do with your army you divide it in half and fight against each other
Worst possible thing that could happen
And then the Babylonians
Starting at about 6:16 start
Sending out an army
Taking some of these border cities between Assyria
Babylon
And then the war heats up a little bit in there fighting back and forth in the Assyrian army seems to be a shadow of its former self but you could see how
How strong it still is
Because they're holding their own against these Babylonians pushing them back sometime chasing them back sometimes
But it's all they can handle
And then like 6:15 BCE
The meter's jumping
Going to East
Anna North
They start taking cities in the east
The next year the medes come forward
Under their King tri-axle Ruiz
And Advance is on
And one of the capitol
Nineveh
I can't take it
Because none of this massively fortified
Probably the most fortified City
West of China
In this whole human history up to this point I mean just
Incredible feet
The human Marvel
And it pushes these me sideways
They just can't deal
Right now
Unfortunately syrians if you can't go out there and defeat that midi in army
They can do whatever they want
So they go Sac a nearby City that's not as well defended to just happens to be a sure
Integrate
And Once Upon a Time Assyrian capitals vital
Connected to their religion and their God and
And morale and everything else
The big deal
At the last minute
The Babylonians run up to be a part of it this is a famous event that
They don't want to allow the medes
To take this important city by themselves be left out of the spoils the reputation everything
But they arrived too late with their army
The means of already sacked the place maybe rushing the attempt
So that they beat the Babylonians there
They treated the way the Assyrians would have treated it and it's a horrific event
The Babylonian
Kane and the
Dianping
Pledge their friendship to each other as
Asher Burns in the background
Chilling continues in the slaves are being dragged off
All of a sudden
A week into Syria
Has Babylon
And the medes
Working together
Advancing on Nineveh
612 BCE
If this wasn't bad enough
At the last minutes allegedly not everybody says this but the standard belief is at the last minute
A horde of Skitty ins
In the rides in the wild Northern Horseman
And joins both the medes
And the Babylonians in this last assault
Upon this
Greatest of
West Asian
Military fortresses
Together they take
Had to fight
Three battles on the plains
Supposedly before they even got a chance to
To get near the wall
Walls with this last old aging damage Lion of Assyria swatting them away
And fighting well
As long as they could
The Babylonians
King
Winter style
And if those people wrote In
Describe what he did to
What he calls the land of subaru
Is there a word for
For Syria
And by the way notice how he's couching this in terms of liberation
From the
You know what Siri iniocc the record say quote
I Slaughter the land of Subaru
I turn the Hostile land into heaps and ruin
The Assyrian who since distant days has ruled over all the peoples and with his heavy yoke
Injury to the people of the land
Is feet from a card I turned back
His yoke I threw off
And quote
And you have a basic problem when when discussing
Events of the past life
If we're discussing something from recent his
3 say
The end of the Third Reich
Get the Second World War
All that emotion is still felt
Right you get a real feel for the kinds of things historians don't want to touch once you get back
A certain distance
Someday they're not going to look at the Nazis
As the kind of evil that we do
They're going to
Somehow say well they were on the far end of the spectrum of what people did that
Which is kind of what a lot of modern ones would say about Assyria
They're not doing anything anybody else isn't doing
They just may be at the far end of the spectrum of
Anaconda
It's all kind of relative right
But you could certainly see
The
Anger
And Vengeance in the people that goes beyond mere
You know the taking of Loot and slaves in the things that have motivated Soldier sometimes In the Heat of battle at all time
This involved
Some Payback
Story Mark Vande Maru
Explains that you can still see
Avengeance today
I mean there's an eternal bit of payback that was done
Erase quote
The Conqueror set out to destroy the cities of Assyria
Taking revenge for the humiliation they had suffered a serious hand
On wall reliefs of Kings
Tanaka read and ashurbanipal in Nineveh for example
They identified the representations of the Kings
With the help of the inscriptions accompanying them and ritually destroyed them
By cutting out the ears and eyes
These were not random acts of Mutilation
In the detail to picture of ashurbanipal to feed of the elamites for example only the face of a soldier cutting
Turn off the head of the king of Elam was similarly destroyed
Probably by the medes
Who saw the elamites as their ancestor
Likewise
The records of loyalty Oaths
The Chinese are head-on had forced Maddie and bodyguards to swear and which has been stored at Cal who
The Palaces were broke down only after the lengthy task of defacing images
And destroying symbols of submission to Assyria had been completed
And quote
If you go to the British museum
Today and look at the Assyrian reliefs
You can see
Are the defacing done by some
Angry vengeful and probably rightfully so
Soldier as they took down Assyria piece-by-piece but stunningly quickly by historical stand
And while there may be no Herodotus
To give color to this story
There is one of the most
Tickets for military
Three fans one of the most colorful sections of the Old Testament
The Bible 2 deals
With the fall of Assyria
And I'm sure Assyrian descendants of people who are
Big Assyrian fans think this is very unfair
Soda propaganda
Again it's just their bad luck to get bad PR sometimes in the Bible
The biblical Prophet Nahum
Was prophet sizing supposedly that you're going to get it
And then once they did get it he was sort of saying see this is what you get
Now what kind of interesting about Nahum unlike some of these other prophecy
There's a decent chance he was a contemporary
A lot of this stuff was put together in the Hellenistic period later
Unifab earlier stories are all kinds of things dealing with that era
Some of this goes back and it's tough to know when the story is argue but it's possible
But this profit damn guy was maybe even a predecessor to some of these events so who knows you know I won't get into
Something like that I just found it interesting
Because when he recounts what happens first of all he gives you the color and tells you
A little bit about the story in it in a religious sort of framers still doesn't sound like Herodotus there's a religious tones
But at the same time it's very colorful
He describes for example
In what the battle is like after proper sizing that you're going to get it for a long time he says quote
He that shatters in pieces
Has come up against the
Guard the wall
Guard the way make Thai strength the utmost
The Shield his Heroes is red
His Warriors are clad in Scarlet
They prepare the Chariots today
The Chariot horses are eager
The Chariots rage in the field
They rushed to and fro in the plaza their appearance is like that of torches
The yard about like lightning
He reads out the list of his Noble
In their eagerness they stumble they hastened to reach the walls the battering ram is made ready
+ 4
10 a.m. describes
The unleashing of the rivers I guess the dams were broken
Or reroute it or they reroute the
The course of the rivers are what have you to help undermine the walls that's not that unusual atactic
But with a big city like this
Not a small engineering feet
And the prophet
Name says quote
The river sluices are open
The palace walls are crumbling the queen is stripped of her clothing they are leading her way capped
Handmaidens moan like doves
Upon their breasts they're beating
Nineveh was a tank of water
From it they are now escaping
Handstands they cry not one of them looks backwards
And then he
Basically tells everybody to take back the stuff that Assyria took from them and that their housing in this
Immensely wealthy City he says quote
Takee the spoil of silver take either spoil of gold
There is no end to the store in abundance of all good lie objects she is empty and void and waste
Hearts melt
Me shake
There is pain in all loins and pale have waxed all the faces
And quote
And he does a little
Trash Talk loading
Maurice's where are The Beano great Lions now and all the people who took all this stuff
And then like again so many of the people during this era
This was seen to involve
You know a little proof that their God was Superior or in the case
Of some of these people by this point
In history the only God
The name says
Quote behold I am against the says Yahweh of hosts
Dilator I will burn with smoke
They're young the sword shall devour I will cut off. I pray from the earth no more be heard by Messengers voice
And he continues to rub it in
And basically blame this on Karma if you will
Woe to the bloody City
Full of lies and robbery
The crack of the whip
And the Thunder of the rumbling wheel
The Prancing horse in the bounding Chariot The Horseman mounting in the flash of stored The Gleam of spirit
Mass of slain a heap of corpses
There is no end to the dead body
For the many in Fidelity's of the well favoured Harlot
The Mistress of incantations Who Sold States for her Wicked Deeds
10 Clans through her incantations behold say if Yahweh of hosts
I am against it
I will strip thee of thy clothing and show their shame to the nation's
Bill I will cast upon the in disgrace the
I will sit V up as a warning
All who see the Shelf leave she'll cry
Desolate Nineveh
Who shall bewail her
And quote
Well listen they may not have a ton of dramatic stuff
From the near East during this time.
That's awesome
I mean the all history aside that's awesome stuff
And it does give you a feel
The emotion of the time. We may think
You know that it's all been drained but that's somebody who is clearly thinking
What is Siri is reaping
What she sowed
Again I pity the poor Assyrian people who have to live with
One piece of horrible PR making it down through the eras
The most widely read book in history and your people get some negative PR
The last Assyrian King is rumored
That's a good way to put it
There's not enough information to know on this is rumored to have
As the enemy was closing in
Heil all of his worldly possessions that were in his Palace around him in the gold and the silver and have family
Play members killed and eunuchs and concubines thrown on in the pile stuff with him and then have it all set up
The light with him sitting in the middle of it
There's a seem like that in The Lord of the Rings to apparently in this time.
It happened a few times probably
Who's the motif they certainly referred back to
For short time
An Assyrian successor State maybe you could call it
If you could call it the last gasp of resistance try to make a stand but by 605 that was
Destroyed to
And the Assyrians will
Turn into a people that never disappeared
But whose destruction was so massive
And so sustained until total
That they seem like they do
You will hear Assyrians trying to tell the world still today we are still here
And try to fight that idea that every last one of them was killed in the in their version of a holocaust you know at the end of that era
What's not true
But you can certainly say that
Within a very short period of time
Those masks
The top of their era
Cities and fortresses
We're almost unrecognizable
In a famous passage the Greek General xenophon
What is 10000 weeks bleeding
A Persian Civil War
Will get chased all the way through
What's now Northern Iraq
He will come upon
These great
Master Sidious
By their standards of the day
Simply no rotting in the dark
Deserted
But the walls are so high
And the workmanship
You on the streets and everything
All modern
That he doesn't understand where it came from
The locals don't know anything about a Siri they think the medes built it
Another word for than 200 years
The cities are lying in Ruins they're still larger than almost anything new being built at that time
And nobody even remembers that they were Assyrian
The account by xenophon
Are these ghosts
Cities by the way
I've spoken about them before it's the ultimate
Statue of Liberty in the sand sort of historical moment
You know what I mean when I say that
The end of the Planet of the Apes with Charlton Heston believes he's been on a
Distant planet the whole time in the very last scene in the movie
He looks and in the distance
You know with the surf crashing against it he sees the Statue of Liberty 3/4 buried
In the sand
If you could take in the Syrian
Individual from 3 for 500 years before xenophon
Lived and bring him forward or her forward in the time machine so that she could hang out there
You know by the ruins of Nineveh
With xenophon
Run through her head what would run through your head if you could go forward in a time machine and see
Our ghost City
Someday
Am I Marvel the size of me 200 years later
Xenophon says and he can't really lies a lot of people who know
It was uniforms talking about here and have seen it and could call him a liar
And he says the base of the fortification he's camping by is 50 ft Broad and 50 feet high
And then has
A brick wall
50 ft Broad and another hundred feet high on top of that
And that the circumference of the fortifications is 18 miles
He says there are some people so they've been a little like refugees and small villages and semi-nomadic group
Groups of people camping by
But that City used to have
Hundreds of thousands maybe a million people
Living there
That's a ghost City
From a
Dead era
Are the X and the funds they are only a couple hundred years later
And when Assyria Falls
It's like that moment we spoke about earlier what would happen if United States disappeared in 5 or 15 years
What's the world
And look like without that you know Center spoke of the Wagon Wheel anymore it's hard even to think for people born
In the last
20-30 years maybe
Does any other sort of reality
Maybe that's the case for the people who lived through and maybe they were blinking and just waking up to a new day it really does have soda
End of the second World War
Sort of feel like everything's been devastated in the whole bunch of people who had Allied together for this
Common interest of taking down the Assyrian Empire
When I was staring over the rubble wondering who gets what
And all of a sudden
Like in 1946
In a year up especially allies were turning into potential adversaries very quickly
There were four
You know if we look at this as a
Encapsulated little micro-world here go politically speaking which is how I look at
Happy stories
Sorry for all
A little bit more
A religion
Nonetheless in the geopolitical setup we really have four great Powers now you go from one
And a hegemonic power Assyria
To Babylon
Picking up a lot of the Syrian territory in this whole deal
By the way
You also have the meats obviously doing the same thing you know moving into
Territory in the north Assyria tone
Irani Egypt always a great power if they can be
But not that long ago you know under Siri and domination like everyone else they start moving
Towards the modern-day area around
And it is real and in there and they are
IPlayer and finally it's at 4th power called Lydia
Lydia
Is the power that's now in modern-day turkey
For the most part
Like everyone else they benefited from the Assyrians going away
They were able to move and expand into other areas
They are
Generally credited with the ones
Inventing metal money
At least in the western world
And you will begin to see at least in the long-term view of things
All sorts of conflicts breaking out now
As all these new powers sort of
Vie with each other
The Egyptians and the Babylonians for example will go at it
And several times trying to figure out you know is anybody going to talk to anybody Where's the border going to be in all that kind of stuff
And a lot of the littler States just get totally screwed
In this deal it's a little like the Cold War
Where some states in the middle try to decide do I side with the Soviets or do I side with the Western and then if you screw up
All kinds of bad things can happen.
Exactly what happened
Chipor Judah
It was sacked by the Babylonian King during
Dussehra
For continually
In a swaying soda between the two powers that were vying for them Babylon on one side and Egypt on the other
And finally exasperating the Babylonian King
Connect to the breaking point
There are
Jews in Iraq today whose ancestors were apart
Of the Babylonian King
You know taking them out of the city of Judah that he was just destroying
That's where by the way
Solomon's Temple was destroyed by the Babylonians again earning them bad PR
In one of the most important PR books of all time
The medes
Will scare the Babylonians to the point where the Babylonians would build something called them to DN wall
To hopefully slow them down
And then upon Saul that to about a hundred and fifty years later
It was a wall that supposedly
Ran across the narrowest part of the division between the Tigris and Euphrates River so you'd have the river on tubes
Poseidon in this wall in the middle
And xenophon says that 200 years later
It was quote
Made of burnt bricks laid in bitumen it was 20 ft thick
100 ft High
And said to be 60 miles long it is quite close to Babylon
And quote
Again if he's lying about that there's a lot of people who would know that he was
You have a reputation for that that would follow him
Unto our own time now
The medes will famously go to war
With the lydians
And this is when some of Herodotus is really just has a little bit of a horror
Story and Alfred Hitchcock e side to him sometimes
Or maybe just the people he talks to happen to
Cuz during this little. Which were really only last like 40 45 years between the fall of the Assyrians in the rise
The Persians
There's going to be incidents that are eerily similar and you start to wonder whether the guy telling you about them or the
People existing in this era have a certain weakness
For that sort of incident
In this case Herodotus says this is how the war with the medes
And the lydian started
There were some skit Ian
Who were hunters for The Medallion King
That guy cxr
Freeze right
And normally they bring back food but one time they show up Herodotus says
Empty-handed
In front of
Who supposedly Herodotus says had this awful temper freaks out and starts abusing including some physical abuse
One must imagine him kicking
Maybe these
Skitty in archers
Dallas Gideons would never known to have particularly
Non
Excitable temperaments shall we put it that way is that fair
And Herodotus says
That they went in in their anger
Chilled one of the boys probably from the Royal Court
The team Indian king had sent
To learn archery
From the same Skippy and while they're great Archer let's send some of the royal boys out there and they can learn how to shoot bows like a
Ancient
Eurasian steppe Archer
And they killed one of these boys are out at this says and cut him up like that game that they normally gives the Maddie and King
Showed up gave him the food watch them eat it hahaha
It's like putting urine in someone's beer before you give it to them
The king finds out
Anna goes after them they run to Lydia
And then the median King says I want those Skitty into cut up that boy and made me eat him
And Herodotus says that the king of Lydia sit down
Cat album
War
That will run into Herodotus telling a similar story with an even
Greater psychological twist very soon after this
Nonetheless
This war with the medes and the lydians are going for like 5 years Herodotus says
And will end
With an we don't have a fact here we can play with something that's real we don't have to say he says she says this historian claims we've heard from
Herodotus
There is a solar eclipse
That happens on May 28th
585 BCE
And at the time that solar eclipse happened
Which by the way Herodotus is a Greek
Predicted
Claiming it was the first time that ever been done
I'm sure the Babylon
Hold off a few of those correctly who knows
Modern astronomers of course have no problem
Going back
With Precision calculating the date
Past
Astronomical event which is why we have a rare confirmable fact
At this point in the story
But when the eclipse happened
The medes
And the lydians happen to be fighting about
Herodotus says as it was warming up as the battle was getting hot
There goes the Sun
Now if you are an ancient
Person
With the religious beliefs you must imagine many of these ancient people had there are few atheist
In the ancient world
And sometimes it can be very superstitious indeed as you might imagine
Now you're involved in a battle man killing man
You know both sides have almost certainly had sacrifices any Omens examined in there looking at the liver
It's a good day to attack and all these kinds of things in the middle of the battle of a song goes
Out
What are you going to say
Well you might imagine
The medes and the lydians stop fighting
In the Heat of the fighting they stop fighting
We're talking about
Tens of thousands of people on each side and everybody just stops
That's the way it's portrayed anyway but think about it this way
If an Eclipse is really going to stop a battle
It's going to happen fast cuz eclipse doesn't last that long
The piece was brokered we are told by another of the great Powers Babylon
And also the collegians involved maybe you would call them a midsize power in that region Regional power
That part of the world
And the deal sealed we are told
In the traditional way although the Greek did a little differently we're not told how
Both rulers slit their skin
And suck the blood from each other
Also you know gave
Daughters and whatnot in marriage that's the part I left out two of the deal
When the Babylonians and the medes
You know sign that agreement
Probably the same way a little vampiric blood sucking to go along with it outside of a sure as they destroy that is Siri
Green City they also married off
Daughters to each other and I mean it was one of these things were all the suddenly families are related
As though that's really going to stop anything given the history nonetheless they did the exact same deal here
Got a few daughters we can spread around got some blood we can suck and and and
Forever Friends
That battles known as the battle of the Halley's River
Or the battle of the eclipse sometime
That one thing
But it's worth pointing out
From this.
Because it's going to matter
In the northwest
And very West
Hearts of
Modern-day turkey
The Anatolia
It was called earlier
AR
Settlements and Villages and cities
Greeks
Nicole ionian
But Greeks of one kind or another
Being you know such a seafaring people around that region head
Colonize that whole area a very long time ago
And they had relationships with the Greeks
You know on the mainland
Places like Athens
You got to imagine trade routes back and forth people going back and forth in fact
The part of the Greek world that was located in modern-day turkey at this time
Was the more sophisticated the more cultured the more learn it
The Greeks in Athens and Sparta might say the more effeminate
The more corrupted the more lazy the more opulent in a connected to all that Eastern opulence as they were
See how that Motif work
Nonetheless
Those Greeks in
Anatolia will become a big part of
You know the problem because
They are the part that links Asia back to the Greek mainland
And the Greek mainland has an interest in how their shall we call them
Cousins
Second cousins
How they're doing
The time the battle of the eclipse
Figures out what's going on between the lydians and the medes
Those Greeks are for the most part subject to the lydian king
That's going to change
Going to change for everybody
What's about to happen in this region that will affect the Greeks and everyone else
Is every bit as shocking
And unexpected as the fall of Assyria was
It's interesting that they will happen within a reasonably historically speaking short. Of time from each other
You have to imagine that
Analogy we have the United States disappearing
In 5 to 15 years and what would the world look like after that
Well what if I told you that Within
You know another 20 or 30 years after that one country that you'd never know some out-of-the-way place
I taken over the entire planet
That's how this analogy works when we start trying to realize that somehow this people call the Persians
Will first get their control over the medes
And how that even happened I mean resource origami the author has a great line when he points out
But you know between the fall of the last great Assyrian monarch
And the rise of Cyrus the Great
There's no mention of these Persian people in any text
In any politically significant way
They are virtual nobody
And within a generation they're running the show for everyone in this part of the world
How did that happen
Judging from the overwhelming
Number of historians from ancient times all the way to the
The latest often contrarian writings
The Lion's Share of the answer seems to have something to do with this incredible leader
Cyrus II
Also called as we said earlier
Cyrus the Great
There are lots of stories by the way and some of them are fantastic
One of Herodotus as best as one of the ones
Details about the rise of Cyrus but you have to remember something
This person Cyrus the Great is to
Persian and Iranian history sort of what George Washington is to American history with King Arthur is
Do British Legend
I mean this is a legendary figure
And because there's so little that talks about him
During his rise to power historians here
In a really thrust into the detective role trying to figure out what it is
It is going on
I like the way his during Peterburg and kind of tries to explain
What sort of assumptions you should maybe build into this and I got a history and so he was writing as a historian trying to explain to a laborer
Person like yours truly left up the layperson understood
But he kind of said
Listen if something appears to happen out of nowhere
But it's unlikely that it could you should assume that there was stuff bubbling up under the surface you know a foundation
Taking place but that's hidden from our eyes through the historical Veil right
So when a Cyrus the Great all the sudden takes over the median Empire that looks like a lightning bolt strikes
It's probably safe to assume
Things have been leading up to this somehow for a while
For a long time one of the things historians like to
Suggest was percolating
You know beneath the scene
But you couldn't see you with something like rot
I guess you could say maybe moral
Rot
This is something that is
Inner part of earlier histories and because it's impossible to quantify I mean we can even ask these questions a day is there any
Truth to the idea and we have by the way
The older Generations in tougher times are tougher than we are today
If there is any truth to that could that have been true in the past how would a historian even measure that
So they don't
Anymore
Writing in 1935 and I love him
But it was written in 1935
Historian will Durant tries to tie
Are the downfall of the medes to their moral degeneration
And the fact that they were sort of
Nouveau riche
He writes quote
The generation was even more rapid than their rise
Osteology who succeeded his father 3 accessories
Proved again that monarchy is a Gamble
In whose royal succession great wits and Madness are nearly alive
He inherited a kingdom with Equanimity and settle down to enjoy it
Under his example the nation for God it's turn morals and stoic ways
Well fed come to suddenly to be wisely used
The upper classes became the slaves of fashion and luxury
The men wore embroidered trousers the women covered themselves with cosmetics and Jewelry
The very horses were off in comparison to gold
These once simple and pastoral people who have been glad to be carried in rude wagons with wheels cut roughly
Out of the trunks of trees
Now Road inexpensive chariots from Feast of Feasts
And quote
The truth is though that what Durand writes there in 1935
Isn't a whole lot different from what the ancient Greeks saw
The ancient Greeks or the saw themselves as Marlboro Man
Compared to these people from the East that were at best
Citic metrosexuals
The Greeks like to point out the use of makeup as part of their idea that these
Easterners were effeminate writing hundreds of years later by the ways in a van talks about
Osteology the last king of the medes and his
Guyliner I guess you would call it today his stencil dies the Rouge on his face and xenophon who would have no
No way of knowing
Says
A wig of fake hair
Now here's the thing though
In the east
These kinds of things were cultural norms it wasn't a sign of effeminacy of the Pharaohs and the Egyptians have been using the
Dark color around the Eyes Forever
Just a different cultural thing that the Greeks Sade is just another sign
Of these Oriental
Effeminate
Opulent
Week
Clever sneaky you know fill in the blank
Easterners
I will leave it to the
Credible historians to decide someday
Whether there's any truth to this Motif about the medes
Sort of
Slouching towards Gomorrah or what-have-you most of the modern stuff I read today look at that as a
As a terribly old-fashioned way to view the situation but as I said how do you quantify something like that anyway
But if you follow that narrative the way of Godlike Herodotus is to
Taking it or guy like will Durant writing in 1935 is taking it
There's an almost opportunity created by the decadence of the meat
The cruelty of the ruler right
And that can be exploited by somebody who has the opposite values
From the people that are busy slouching towards Gomorrah
In other words people that were less corrupted by luxury
We're not as decadent
Who were more shall we say
Possessors of the old-time virtue
And this gets us back to a secondary value that a guy like Herodotus has remember like I said he's like the color are the first
Real screenwriter
You know showrunner and and and you learn two things from a guy
Writing the way he writes in the way a lot of people after him
One you learn about these events he's trying to relate to you
Which may or may not be true and are probably a combination of the two right we learned about
You know the rise of Cyrus at least the story that this guy her
But at the same time
You're having like a Vulcan mind meld
With a 2500 year-old basically alien mine
The one way
Conversation
With a 2500 year-old guy
And when you read Herodotus I
I really wish I could speak
The ancient Greek and read it
And understand the little nuances so I could really hear this guy in his own words that he meant every specific word
But you're getting a chance to see
You know what this guy from a completely different time. Likes
And dislike
Is worldview what he thinks is good and what he thinks is bad
You know his views sort of on the Supernatural and the Gods
His biases and his prejudices
You're learning about
He and his world when you read his stuff
Why do I have to filter it so carefully because just like all of us his world pollutes his worldview so that
You know we don't get as
Non-bias view now
As we might want
But what Herodotus does in the story
Is kind of say that because osteology was the way he was
A Cyrus arises on the scene
Modern-day historians can't decide or argue over whether or not there was some War fought between
The medes and the Persians remember these are for the most part
Semi tribal peoples probably at this time
They used to think they were more like States now no one's sure maybe a combination of some cities
With some pastoral people that were lied to it it it's an interesting sort of hybrid and there might have been a lot of these kinds of us
Societies around back then when you're transitioning from
You know an old tribal world to something more along the lines of a centralized bureaucratic State when you're inside of it a tween
Zone if you will
Twitter war between these medes and Persians were the tribes that they controlled
Or sort of like has one historian describes it
The midi and Empire getting a change in management
With maybe some Maddie & Nobles
Helping to rebel against this osteology person in modern historians have some interesting
Understandable should have common sense reasons why they might want to
The theory is that this osteitis guy is trying to convert them he's into more
Ava typical centralized Mesopotamian government
Where the king is is more autocratic has a lot more Authority it sounds like maybe he has to share
A lot of authority with these different tribal rulers
And as you might imagine it's almost like a law of nature
They're unlikely to like that
This may have led some Modern historians think just sort of an uprising an internal coup if you will
And this Cyrus the second guy might be
The person who gets to lead this now
As the greatest early screenwriter
Herodotus has his own view of sort of what turns the tables on
Now it's one of these stories that again maybe tells us more about
Herodotus and the audience he trying to please
But he must have heard this story somewhere this is a typical tail by the way of Oriental cruelty
But he's setting up
Something that actually seems to happen in the story and trying to give you a reason why it happened
Without having any real way of knowing other than these people he's talking to
He tells one of the most horrific stories
In his writing
But he tells it like
Alfred Hitchcock
Or Wes Craven or someone like that
We alluded to it earlier when we said than earlier story in those Skippy ins
You know kill the boy and served it to the Midian King and he didn't like that
Well in this
Story it's that same thing but with an extra twist I have several different versions of Herodotus
But let me set this up what happens
In the story
Is it concerns this osteology is Guy the son of CX series and nowhere near his
His father in terms of greatness and in kind of a jerk and that's the way he's portraying
And he has a dream
And these dreams you got to love ancient history cuz they're always so wild Herodotus related
The dream has something to do with his daughter
Urinating over the whole world or something
As I said, love the engine history
And he asked the Magi to interpret it and they say very good this daughter is going to give birth
Bertha something or she's the seed of something that maybe going to overthrow you and so
Play it safe
Herodotus and he marries her off to some Persian
You know maybe a great Persian guy but this is a median Empire and and no son of a Persian is going to be ruler
Numidian Empire so that's been taken care of but then about a year later Herodotus says he has another dream
His daughter
Who's about to give birth to her first child in this dream
Ecu's
I think it's it's like vines coming out of her womb and then encompassing the whole earth or something again
Do that
And the Magi come in and interpret that and as you might imagine it's not good
And it scares osteology who thinks that she's his daughter is going to give birth to a person who takes his throne
Show me the story that you see
Another tales in other words
It's a pretty common Motif with Different Twist
Osteology is called in a gym
A guy named Harper
Who seems to be a historical figure
And tells harpagus
To get rid of the baby
The Harper guess Herodotus doesn't want to get rid of the baby
Let me stop for a second
In the story Herodotus is lovingly telling the story he knows what the colorful
Pieces are
And he says Harper guess it doesn't want to get rid of the baby Emily kill a baby
So we give the job to a shepherd
And give the shepherd the babies get rid of the baby
Expose it you know out into the open and let it die
Emma Shepherd doesn't want to get rid of the baby and it just so happens his wife is pregnant
And she gives birth at just this time to a stillborn child
Doesn't sound like a bunch of old Grimm's Fairy Tales at this point
So
As you might imagine they take the stillborn child wrap it in the Royal clothes
Cheap alive when they were supposed to kill a give the stillborn child back to Harper gifts to give to his boss the Kings AC
Fast forward
Like 13 years later or something like that
And a boy is brought before this is the hood rata two-story osteology because he's been whippin
Little boys higher on the social standing scale than he after a bunch of questioning it is determined and again this
Is the wonderfulness of the ancient mind-meld you're having with Herodotus
The basically
Asiatees can tell that this boy is a king
Like in your DNA you can tell the difference between Blue Bloods and now I'm Blue Blood by the way they just handle situations
Sodium bread
Besides that. The ig's notices that
The kid looks like human after all he is his grandfather
He calls in harpagus when he calls in the shepherd He does a little investigation figures the whole story out
And pretends he's not mad
Tell Harper I guess he's often felt
I'm paraphrasing here for productivity Patel's hard because he felt bad about the whole thing afterwards so he's he's secretly relieved
Did the whole thing went the way it did why don't you go home I'll tell your wife we're going to have a banquet to celebrate all this
You can come over and end with Will
Highlight you at the banquet send your son over your thirteen-year-old son so he can keep the new boy you know my grandson company
And you know we'll have a party tonight
And Herodotus says that Harper just goes back home he's relieved cuz he knows he could have gotten in big trouble the wife is happy
And they go to this banquet
And this is where
Alfred Hitchcock Herodotus of halicarnassus takes the story over
And again I keep telling myself I don't think this is making this stuff up
Somebody
Little Kim this story this is what somebody somewhere believe
Now listen to this and try to imagine a story like this
From the Assyrians
Were the Babylonians or the ancient Mesopotamians they just didn't write this way
The rocket has a story has
The 13 year old son of heart because going to the Palace as requested
And then picks up the story and says
This is from my de selincourt translation by the way
Quote
When Harper gets his son arrived at the palace
Osteology had him butchered
Cut up into joints and cooked
Roasting some boiling the rest
And having the whole properly prepared for the table
Dinner time came in the guests Assemble
With heart because among them
Dishes of mutton were placed in front of Osteology is everyone else
The Harper guess was served the Flesh of his son
All of it
Except for the head the hands and feet
What you been put separately on a platter
Covered with a lid
When Harper gets started eating as much as he wanted I see I just asked him if he did enjoy this dinner
He answered that he enjoyed it very much indeed
Whereupon those whose business it was to do so
Brought in the boy's head hands and feet in the covered dish
Stood by har Pegasus chair
And told him to lift the lid and take what he fancied
Harper just remove the cover and saw the fragments of his son's body
Has he kept control of himself and did not lose his head it's a dreadful sight
Osteology asked him if he knew what animal it was whose fleshy and just eating
I know my Lord was Harper gets his reply
And for my part May the Kings will be done
He said no other word but took up what remained of the Flesh and went home
Intending I supposed to bury all of it together
And that was how Harper yes was pun
And quote
If that'd been in the Syrian record it would have said something like
His son I divided the pieces I fed to him I mean it would be a straightforward sort of thing
You wouldn't have anybody setting up the suspense of
You know having him eat and not know what it is and then having the platter brought in having the king asked the question do you know what you
Did you like it and then the platters lifted up I mean those moments where you set up the tension in the drama
It's
A movie
You could do that
Movie and change nothing
Living Color
What's more Herodotus is
Clearly setting up these moments for his audience to do the equivalent of what we would do in a movie theater one
Some great seen on the
Screen happens that we're all really glad to see in you clap or something he's got these moments cuz when you make iced tea ig's out to be such
Jerk
And he gets what's coming to him in the story it's a crowd-pleaser
And in this story of course he does
And while it's tempting to think that the entire thing is just a great tale somebody's brake tail maybe not Herodotus is initially
There are definite facts mixed in and you can see Herodotus trying to explain
The reasons behind the facts
Text today maybe a screenwriter would call it dramatic license
Because Babylonian records indicate
That there was
A general who corresponds to this harpagus guy
And the. General was involved in a Battlefield
Betrayal maybe you could say
In a key battle osteology had
A large part of his army
Desert him on the battlefield and go to the other side
It very well may have been this harpagus person
Who led them to do that
And Herodotus want you to think
Dead Sea
He was a jerk
And now this is what he get
That's an end who would think that you could trust a man whose son you had served him for dinner
With the entire Army in the first place but none the less
The moment when Harper guess and the Meads cross over to Cyrus's side of the battlefield must have been a crowd-pleasing
Satisfying
The audience right
Jerk got what he deserved
In the Babylonian records it's much more Stark as you might imagine
One of the texts
From Babylon as quoted by Pierre Briand
Reeds
Quote
Osteology has mobilized his army and he marched against Cyrus
King of on Shonda conquer
The Army rebelled against osteology and he was taken prisoner
They handed him over to Cyrus
Cyrus March towards ekbatan on the Royal City
And quote
By 550 BCE or thereabouts
Cyrus
And the Persians
We're basically in control of the old elamite territories and now heading heritage
Control of the Madea and Empire
Which was already one of the great empires in this particular World stage
It's kind of possible that the lydian came for example
Wedding
3 years
Cyrus will be at war with
Doesn't even really have a key idea who the Persians are I'm not sure but I mean
Judging from the sources this is
Quite the turnaround
Ground
And as I said in 547
Cyrus and the new Persian Empire
Is fighting those same people that means were fighting when that eclipse
You know caused everyone to think that maybe they shouldn't be fighting
And it's a great story cuz the guy who runs
The lydian Empire now at this time is a gun increases and there's a saying about him you may have heard rich as
Croesus
And that's the stereotype of the lady into this time
As I said they're known
As people who invented metal coinage
It's really true or not but that's their reputation and it's attached to them because they're in a thought to be extremely wealthy
Increases is supposed to have gone to one of the famous oracles maybe the most famous Oracle in
The entire Greek world
The Oracle at Delphi
Which he may have been giving
Money to influence it was a whole big problem during this. We're some questioned the reliability of these oracles
Can you imagine
Because of them taking money to keep operating
People increases with Richie gave money to everybody a little Donald Trump issue maybe you might say
And
Ask the oracle
You know now what would happen if I went to war with the Persian Empire
No
Lucite tray
Maybe only
Worthwhile for the bedding people
Amongst you
But if you went to an advisor
In Las Vegas who gave you betting advice and you said
Will the Green Bay Packers
Win the Superbowl and the answer was
If the Green Bay Packers play in the Super Bowl
They will add to a great legacy
Do you bet
Creases was told by the Oracle at Delphi
They have creases attacks the Persians he will destroy a great Empire
You can take that a number of different ways couldn't you
You can say hey the Green Bay Packers are going to win or you can say listen at the Dallas Cowboys
Beat the Green Bay Packers
They've added to a great
Championship Legacy 2
It's just the Dallas Cowboys championship Legacy
When creases and the lydians
Fight
Cyrus and the Persians
He loses
Who destroys a great Empire
The one that invented metal coinage
I would love to get into the kind of army that Cyrus had and what he used
To accomplish this victory over the libyans butt
The achaemenid military system
Is not well understood anyway it was only in the 1980s that they started putting together realistic reconstruct
Sections of the army
In the days
That are much better known than this. I mean during the Greek and Persian Wars or after
Against Alexander in this. It's all conjecture what the heck
Cyrus was using I mean you can say well you probably use this and it's logical to assume that but nobody knows
When you read Herodotus he's always got some little stratagem
In play the keeps you from having to know
In a really what the Army was doing in one of these big battles against creases
You're the Persians were told will take their baggage camels
And take the baggage off of them and put them in front of the army so that when the lady in horses
Never seen camels ride up to the front will be scared off by the camels I mean are you get a victory the battle just with that
Uno
Much about an army that must have been really really good to do all these things Cyrus was doing with
He does look like a very bold Commander
From the sources I mean one of the things are audited talks about
Is this what we call it a misunderstanding
Between croesus and Cyrus
After this
Big battle that starts off the campaign and
It's bloody and inconclusive in
Winter's coming so creases does with any ancient Commander would have done during that. He went home
Went to the capital that starred at this giant fortified City in
Dismissed his mercenaries and let most of the army go home
And told his allies
You know in four months show up here and we'll deal with this
Emerging Persian threat
Is All Eyez by the way including
The great Powers Babylonia
An Egypt so maybe Cyrus was starting to be seen as
The destabilizing force in that little
Geopolitical ecosystem
In that part of the world nonetheless
Cyrus didn't
Disband
He didn't go home for winter he were told pursued the lydians right on their heels this is bold strategy
Any forced another battle
And we're told it was after creases that already basically sent most of the people home
The person win that battle ain't got the camel battle
Anime faces monsters fortification
At Sardis the capital of Libya that could easily hold out until all those Ally show up in four months you would think
We're told it holds up like 14 days
Again we have another Herodotus story
About a S8 back path to the
Citadel being found by a Persian who spies one of the guards hats falling off helmets falling off in the guard
Retrieving it down some
Unipath again
You wouldn't know about what amazing Siege engine
Maybe Cyrus had because we always have some little story that accounts for
How one of the great fortified cities in this part of the world gets taken in 14 days
Nonetheless we also get
Some accounts now of of of something we spoke in about about how the Persians maybe like Darth Vader to the Greeks
But they have something in and you know you don't know if you want to call this
Propaganda
Or a sincere
And clever and Common Sense and realistic approach to things
So take it away
Shall we call it the tolerance bomb
Which hole
Diodorus siculus especially dimensions
It's Cyrus gave a deal to the lydians before this whole thing started he said listen submit to me
And I'll leave you in charge of this whole area
It's basically the same deal Xerxes offered the
Spartans at Thermopylae come on let's make a deal on those weapons and
Not only will you get to go home
I'll put you in charge of all these people you'll benefit
Submit and profit
Maybe you can call
This combination of
Sort of
Machiavellian thinking
With a sort of Gandhi like ethic that's going too far but I love the
Connection
A realistic hard-headed
Knife in the back sort of diplomacy
With tolerance and mercy and leniency as your weapon
Nike with leniency
And you know you would have to suggest perhaps
That there were two ways this lenient idea could go
Either not work at all
And then you see why the Assyrians had to be as harsh as they were
Or because the Assyrians were as harsh as they were in the Babylonians who followed after them
The area was right
For somebody
Who would offer if everybody was going to be under somebody's control when do you want to go with the tolerance guy
Remember we are grading on a curve here
Let me talk about tolerance
The Persians could be every bit as atrocious
As any other ancient people on occasion
It just seemed like once they took over there were a lot
Fewer of those occasions
Maybe the historians are some of them that I grew up with would say something like
Well that's because the Assyrians already broke all the trouble
Some people to the yolk of Empire
Seems a bit
Far-fetched
Certainly you can say though
That the whole sort of mood and attitude was altered and you don't get anymore
Are those really intimidating reliefs showing things like
You know heads of your enemies staring up at you
Or horrible violence of the flaying of
Live captives and you don't get the the writings where there's a boasting and a propaganda Valley
Are you where you're saying this is what will happen to you
If you rebel against us
Rhesus argami
Quotes
Leave rassam cylinder it's called and it's ashurbanipal the last great king of Assyria boasting of what he did
To Babylon after his brother
Please put on the throne of Babylon rebelled against him
In 6:49 BCE
Firsties
Besiege the people until they were cannibalistic
And then picks up in there it is saying quote
Out of hunger the Flesh of their sons and daughters day 8
Afterwards I ripped out the tongue of those officers whose mouths had blasphemed against Asher
My master and then slaughtered them
Any soldiers found still alive we're flawed in front of the wing it bowls built by Sinatra with my grandfather
I whipped them on sennacherib Tomb
And then tossed their quivering flesh for The Jacka
The birds and the fish to eat
In this way I placated the Wrath of the Gods would become incensed
Spider ignominious bee
Prince argami picks up
The Narrative saying quote
This grisly passage related to events that transpired in Babylon precedes a brief description
Section of the restorative work that I sure banipal undertook in that City
That the Assyrian King was unabashedly about intertwining the account of his brutality
Without of his clemency
Indicates that Mesopotamian royalty did not frown upon the infliction of vicious reprisals against Concord pop
Populations
This attitude enabled the Assyrian and Babylonian Kings
To base their policies largely on terror
During the two centuries preceding Cyrus's rise to power the Assyrians and Babylonians hits act nearly
Every major near Eastern capital
Enter preferred practices of population deportation and kidnapping sacred images
A deeply traumatized the people of the ancient near East
And quote
In other words
If you had ever wanted to find a winning military strategy
This might be the time
Where Mercy
Tolerance and being
The cool conquerors
Really worked in your favor
Cyrus is the one who initiates this idea
That
We're not going to impale everybody
And we're not going to play them and we're not going to force them to convert to our religion
You join us
Pay your taxes
I may have some representatives in a Garrison in your city
But life will be good this Persian deal
Was very seductive
Now
Here's where the Story begins to dovetail with what we've already talked
About earlier
The peoples that we spoke about
These Greeks
Who were in Anatolia
Spoken language that was called ionian so they're often called ionia's but they were
Other types of Greeks there too
Asiatic Greek
Pictures of turn that sometimes used
These people have been paying tribute
Two creases in the lydians and Cyrus had gone to them before the war with creases in the lydians and said listen
How about you revolting
Croesus and they said no
And some of them foreign creases aside so after Cyrus wins all the people in the region are coming to him to kind of say hey boss
I was wanted you to win I'm glad I'm glad you're Victorious and.
In the case of these Greeks they went to him and said can we have the same deal we had with
The lydians
And Cyrus gets mad at me which hole he basically says you could have had that deal if you join me and didn't fight against me now you will
Want a special deal
Over all the other people in this region who didn't fight against me
And got mad
And those Greeks went back home had a big meeting amongst each other
Started rebuilding the walls of their cities which they had knocked down it in as part of their deal with creases
And put the word out
For help
And they sent word to the Spartan
Now
The Spartans had also promised help to croesus when he was
In trouble
Supposedly they were just getting in the boats getting ready to go help when in 14 days the lydian capital Falls
Didn't give him enough time to get there
Now they get
You know in a very short period of time a second call
For helping this time from Greeks
It's about the Persians just like that last all these Persians must be a Troublesome people the Spartans were a little busy
When the message came
But they sent an emissary
To talk to this Persian now every historian I'm reading is assuming that these Persians
Any Spartans do not know each
Did this may be the first time they ever encounter one another
And it seems The Logical considering all the trading and what not going on
But let's understand
Best case scenario it's unusual
Chinese people don't really know each other
Any Spartan Diplomat shows up in front of Cyrus were told him we have one of these wonderful.
We can imagine our
Clint Eastwood type figure showing up
In front of this
King on the rise again I try to imagine in Alexander the Great life
Like figure on the rise
Must have been a pretty good-looking guy cuz we're told that the Persians standards of beauty were modeled on him ever after
Words
This is the way Herodotus
From my purpose translation describes
The Diplomat
Talking to
Peking
Of the Persians was just conquered Lydia
I was just about to put the hammer down on the Greeks of Asia
Herodotus
Quote
And when they arrived at the Kia they sent the most distinguished man with them name Lecrae needs to start is to declare desyrel
In the name of the lack of the mountains that he must not inflict Reckless damage on any of the Greek territory
Since the lack of demonion would not tolerate
Remember liking ammonium is another name for spark
Now this people that Cyrus has never heard of it's just told him not to mess with any of these people he just
Concord
And he basically turns to the Greek advisor next to him and says
Who are these people and how many of them are there
Herodotus is quote
They say that when the herald had delivered this message
Cyrus question the Greeks who were with him
Asking them who were these like a demoney and who would send such a command to him
And how many of them were there
When he heard their response Herodotus says he said to the Spartan Harold quote
I have never yet feared any men who have a place in the center of the city
Set aside for meeting together
Swearing false Oaths and cheating one another
And if I live long enough
Leica demonion will have troubles of their own about which the converse
Rather than those of the ionian
Herodotus then says
Quote Cyrus that insulted the Greeks because of their custom of setting up agoura's which are Market play
Places in their cities for the purpose of buying and selling
Which is unknown among the Persians who do not use markets and indeed have no such place as an Agora in any of
Their cities
And quote
This is worth a little digression for a second just from an interest standpoint first of all
Herodotus would have probably known
What person cities were like
He himself
Was an ionian Greek or lived in an ionian Greek city he would have known this and that's fascinating when you consider that you think of
The Middle East now and you think of the bazaars in the marketplace isn't all that
But the Persians had this really interesting
Cultural
Carrot and stick thing going themselves and we talked about the human laboratory experiment few times in this
Burn like a spark
The Persians had a different one going and it's fascinating to me
Everything you read about them says that you know of the top three things that that Society
Places import on one of them is the truth
And if anything is in our world today we think oh yes sure everybody should tell the truth but what if you made this like a command
Management
The people took Ultra seriously we told you earlier that when the
Spartan told Xerxes about the Persians he said if I'm lying
You treat me like a liar
And and I told you that that's a death penalty the Persians took lying really seriously
We're told that the education of Persian male youth was
To learn to ride to learn to shoot the bow and to learn not to lie
To tell the truth
Isn't it fascinating to imagine a society where this was both
A state and legal requirement for hats and certainly a heavily
Encouraged and incentivised cultural norm thou shalt not lie
You know most becomes like the plot to one of those movies you know where
The main character drink some potion and all of a sudden you know was forced to tell the truth all the time what if you had a society like that
What Cyrus is saying to the Spartans is I can't respect any people who have these places in their cities
Set up where people can specifically go to lie to one another
And by the way without going too deeply into it there's a lot of connection to Persian religious beliefs during this time.
And how that plays into the question of lying
The Persians were
Worshippers of Aqua Mazda was a god named and
The old Mead used to worship a god named Mithra
And if connections between good and evil that some religious experts tie to Christianity in ancient Judaism and who the hell
Techno is all you know is that it's not just a cultural
And legal question it's a religious 1/2
Interesting to speculate
How much people still alive
In a society with that many things favoring the truth it's interesting to think about
Another human laboratory experiment if you will the truthful society and how realistic is that
Nonetheless
We have now set the stage
Problems between the Greeks
And the Persians
From this point on
If you want to call it a clash of civilizations you who have marketplaces in lie and we who don't it's about to happen
Lucky for the Spartans don't get to stay out of it
Waka Cyrus isn't done conquering
Not by a long shot
Historian still
Discuss whether or not
Cyrus
Should be seen as an intentional yunnan conscious conqueror
Paula Alexander the Great or Napoleon
Recreate the old Assyrian Empire
Or somebody that got involved in a bunch of conflict each for their own reason
And you know when you when you take over their territory and and kind of tripped into Empire
I mean obviously that's a little simplistic
But
I think it's indicative of
Howling inserting really key motivational areas
This guy is still a bit of a mystery
He will disappear
Behind the veil of our historical site I guess you could say for several years
After his
Taking over Lydia he will leave a general who maybe this historical harpagus guy
And an army behind
In Western turkey was not modern
De Western turkey
To reduce these Asiatic Greek cities
And he will go
It's assumed
To the eastern part of his realm in the northern part of his realm
And Conquer further and also Shore up his defenses against
The many powerful tribes that sort of ring his territory
Probably a combination of
Fighting some of them showing the flag to some of them
Intermarrying and making diplomatic agreements with some of them
Accepting vassalage for mothers
I mean it was years of work
So this guy is doing the
You know yeoman's work the hard
Slogging
Of creating a stable State and it requires years of constant effort he disappears from the historical record while he's doing this
And then Ian
539 BCE
He reappears again at the head of an army
Heading toward Babylon
Now what Cyrus is going to do to Babylon is
Probably his crowning
And I have to remind myself to his career is already incredible
This is a guy who buy 539 BCE has been a king for about 20 years
And in 20 years he's taking his people
From a virtual
In a Backwater nowheresville
To a point where they've conquered half of the great nation states and their little ecosystem that exist you know after the fall
Fall of Assyria
And he's outside the gates of number 3 of 4 with an army
That's pretty awesome right there for a
King of on Sean
Very soon be referring to himself as
Part of his official Royal titles at the king of the universe
When you go from an Sean to King of the universe that's quite a jump and he's kind of a self-made conqueror
You compare him to someone like Alexander the Great was a course awesome
But Alexander reminds you of sort of a historical
Rich kid who inherits his father's already thriving Corporation with tons of ready cash and does great things with it
No offense
Go to Alex
But Cyrus never had any of those
And look where he is only 20 years ago
Now let me just voice my own opinion that what Cyrus is about to do to Babylon
Is strange
You can't tell with the sources what's really going on in the different histories have different approaches to it and it's been argued about it
And the views have changed and updated over time
There's just not enough hard sources though for anyone to really know
For anyone to conclusively win
I'm certainly not going to take a position on a plane could explain
What are the weirdness of
The first thing you have to ask
Is whether or not Cyrus arriving outside Babylon when he did was a coincidence
Because the timing is awesome
If you're hoping to take over Babel
Is that just because he gets lucky or is that just because of the Babylonian propaganda would say later the end of March
Can seize him and brought him to Babylon
To get rid of the horrible king of Babylon and restore things
Just lucky
Orb did Cyrus and the Persians have advanced information that thinks sucking Babylon right now
You come now
And half the population will be ready to welcome you with open arms was that may be part of the reason he showed up when he did
Orisa
I have argued for years could you make a case to the reason that people were so disaffected in Babylon was in part due
The Persian propaganda that undermine
Retire
Will to resist
And I have to be honest
I did not understand
That part of the story for years growing up
Something has changed in the way historians view it so now makes more sense to me
When I was growing up the attitude was it in 539 BCE this is when the Cyrus arrived
So something happens and occurs in Babylon Falls in sorry takes it over there you go so
This idea that he had this propaganda undermining Babylon made you think about
When
When was that going to happen mean you just everything happened so quickly
The modern way of viewing this almost a lot of historians is that maybe the Persians in the Babylonians have been fighting battles for a couple
What years
And then 539 when Cyrus and his army show up outside of Babylon
That's like the end of the second World War 1 the Russian show up outside of Berlin and you're having your last climactic battle
In a multi battle long War
Again the sources are just not there
To confirm any of this
Are categorical
But it would make a heck of a lot more sense if you were saying that Cyrus and the Persians were undermining the Babylonians with propaganda if you had years to
To do it right
Understanding what Cyrus might have been doing work
Requires talking about Babylon
Like the Assyrian city of Nineveh
This is a great urban center
And it's large enough in complex enough so that you see a lot of the same sorts of Dynamics going on
In Albia through an ancient lens that you would see
In any modern large city today
There are fissures
Is there a division
There are tensions
There are
Are disagreements there are there also
Two things that if someone wanted
To come in they could widen
The disagree
Slowly but surely increase the level of
Anger
Discontent
The number of things to be exploited to
Start with the fact
The king is on Pop
The king of
Babylon during this time. Almost certainly suffers from from
Bad bad historical publicity his name is nabonidus somebody
The time all of this is going down
Nabonidus is about 70
70 years old
World in a world
You know where the lifespan is so much shorter
How many 70 year old people are they
He's like a wizard
Into the population
In terms of this is a guy
Guy
Whose memory goes back to events most people can't get anywhere near
Memory
He may have been the general
Who helped seal the deal
Between those two sides at the Battle of the eclipse remember when they suck each other's blood
Part of a
And sealing the deal this this
This nabonidus guy when he was much younger and more vigorous may have been one of the generals on site
Now he's old
And it's really hard to get your mind around what this guy was really like
He sort of portrayed
As a as a kind of a doting
Antiquarian
I-70 East
Some people consider him the first official archaeologist I think it's got to be crazy cuz because there were lots of earlier Kings who were into
Digging up
You know earlier versions of their civilization but this guy
Is portrayed as somebody who almost prefers it to being a king he'd rather be out there Indiana jonesing
Some old Babylonian stuff from the previous Kings than
Then dealing with the day-to-day government
He also looks like a guy who doesn't mind getting out of Babylon
I have this image for the movie of some
I want to use like the guy who played The Scientist the doctor in Back to the Future and have him be
Nabonidus and just have him sort of
Finding the hustle and bustle of Babylon too much in those young kids and their loud music and all that stuff
He and the priesthood of Babylon especially the main important
Marduk
Begin to have these disagreements
Now understand something
In the world before modern times
There is really only one reliable counter.
To the power of a
Pharaoh
And at the priesthood
Because the power that that
They have stems from the same source
Right ear your King by divine right it's a God who wanted to be a king
Who was the special relationship with the gods and who helps me know
Placate the gods who does the work of the Gods and who knows what the god really wants while the priesthood
Allegiant
The only other source of legitimate
Empower
In these societies before modern times are often
Other priests in the priests of Marduk don't like this nabonidus guy and part of the reason why
Is he seems to be kind of
Will favoring another God over there
This is what I mean by it's hard to get your mind around nabonidus
Because he may
Be like an Akhenaten type Cara
Do you know the Egyptian pharaoh that may have been a monotheistic may have tried to change Egypt religion
Another similar story right where you have the autocratic ruler opposed by a powerful priesthood
And after Akhenaten died things return back to normal that kind of work carving his face off of all of the old thing trying to forget he ever lived
Nabonidus may have been one of these guys to the wanted to change the religion
His mother was supposedly a priestess
Have a religion
Devoted to a guy named sin
The moon God
And so nabonidus right before this time. Give me the ultimate middle finger
To the priesthood of Marduk
By leaving Babylon and going to some Arabian Oasis
Now historians in modern times I found all sorts of really good logical
Patriotic reasons
Why the king might do that
In Past Times it was much more portrayed like this guy is a mist
Either a Mystic or an old man or a combination of the two
And he just wants to get away from his unworthy people and he appreciates it more in in these Arabian Oasis
It's probably what modern
Historians that he's probably they're doing
Important work
The country but he's missing important work
Time
The Babylonians required their King to be there once a year for a New Year's Festival it was import
He had to physically grasp the hand of the god in front of the
Population once a year to be sure
Success and good things in all these kinds of deals and he stayed away for like a
Decade
When the Babylonian records will say every year the King was not here for the ceremony or what have you
And they're getting pissed
Annies putting more money into it
Creating more of these temples for the other religion denying some money that the people of Marduk expecting and you can just see it
It boiling over right and then the Kings not even there is Sun belshazzar as ruling as a reagent and he's not
Popular either
So the king is part of it
The Babylon is going through
In a tough Economic Times too and that's putting the squeeze on people they're having problems with disease and that's causing unrest
Archaeologist doctor
John Oates
Describes
You know the down-and-dirty parts of a day-to-day suffering and let's remember something babylon's banking system
And financial system was developed enough so that they had great banking houses there that were very powerful and lived on
Long after this. And that's just another one of those dynamics that
Makes us think about modern times these are
Powerful interest that have
Unisom Authority in the state
What happens when things seem to be falling apart and people are losing money in end times are bad and
And you start getting Persian propaganda about this King
It sounds like things are going his way which remember during this time.
Cause a lot of people to figure the gods are smiling on that
Guy
And are Kings not even showing up to shake the guy's hand every New Year's right
Is the weight doctor Joe notes describes the
Situation in Babylon
Considering also remember that this King looks like a guy who's trying to change religious Traditions trying to change a bunch of other things in end.
Clearly nabonidus is religious and administrative reforms
Provoke great resentment
While the wars and extensive building programs of his predecessors had proved a severe burden on the country's res
Large numbers of economic text
Reveal severe inflation
A situation now made worse by the spread of plague
Between 560 BCE and 550 BCE Prices rose by up to 50%
Turn 560 to 485 BCE the total increase amounted to some 200%
And quote
Nitrostat
But again you know take this with a grain of salt at Target about
But there are people inside Babylon
Who might be considered shall we say vulnerable
Two propaganda that
Creative dissent
There are a lot of people in Babylon
For there because they were forcibly taken Once Upon a Time
From where they came from
And some of the propaganda afterwards certainly
Post propaganda but maybe some of the pre propaganda to from Cyrus
Told these people that have the Persian War to take over
They get to go home
Start with
The deportees from Judah
Jewish people today there and there are still
I'm sure still
With all the troubles
Jews in that part of the world today that are descendants
People who were forcibly removed after the Babylonians
Sacked Jerusalem
What is Cyrus was telling those people
If I get
Vicodin power you can go home
And what if he was telling all the other deportees the same thing
When historians refer to Cyrus in the Persians propaganda
The first idea that comes to mind is like negative propaganda like the Nazi stop designed to lie to people and get you to believe
Things that aren't true
But you could make a case that that's since we know
Did Cyrus and the Persians will eventually actually do what they're saying here
Write that they will
For example allow the Jews to go back
To Judah and re-establish their religion
And even eventually you know pay for some of the rebuilding of the second temple
What will be the second temple with with royal funds
When you know that they're actually going to do that maybe you could say that this propaganda is a lot more like dropping leaflets
Over enemy military lines that say something like you no surrender do us we don't hurt prisoners and we'll give you a hot meal
In a few bucks in your pocket some cigarettes over they've done in the old days
Maybe this is like telling
The people inside Babylon do not fear
I may be coming but I'm going to send you home
No
Real experts on this light Pierre Briand caution us against thinking about this the way
That
I just described
But this is a
Conscious policy of Toleration he says the way the marketing really is
Is a lot more like Cyrus's
Assyrian and Babylonian predecessors
Where he's essentially promising continuity
And because continuity means allowing these people to do things the way that they are accustomed to do it
It seems like tile
He points out that it's normal for conquerors in this region even before this time. To come in and promised to restore every
Everything that's wrong
The gods are upset I will fix that
Economy is bad I will fix that you are kept away from your home and your gods are just you know I will fix that
The restore Andre creator of order
The whatever you want to call this
In 539
Cyrus and the Babylonian Army me
I need a battle where there seems to have been a really maybe nasty massacre at the end
The Babylonian Army is defeated
The rest of the troops of the run back to the very
Formidable defenses of the city
I'm within 2 days
Somehow
The gates of the city are opened in Cyrus's General is marching through the streets and triumphant Babylon Falls
Nabonidus fleas eventually captured and supposedly treated well by Cyrus just like all the other kings were
Herodotus of course has to give us a stratagem story of how it happened this time it involves
In a waiting until they can get the river down the flows through the city to a certain length or to a point where they
The troops can go through the marshes or what have you
And capture the city and I think he's one of the ones that say
That the city didn't even know it was being captured because there was some
The revelry going on attached to a
Religious cult in the city so big anyway
Me modern excavation
But the city sizes
Over 2000 Acres
And
The wall circumference at about 11 miles
So it's possible that in one part of the city
But they were partying it up
And then the Persians got in
The natural thing to do would be to throw out a story like that and blame it on typical
You know Greek stereotypes and what not but it should be pointed out
One that often times in these ancient religions there was an awful lot of
Decadence or fun or depends on your point of view I guess stuff that was
Heart of
You know the religious rights and you'll see this in Greece and Roman a ton of other religions the world over especially the ancient.
And these people are immensely religious the Babylonians especially the holy city of Mesopotamia rights are very religious
People to imagine people with the commitment of like a Taliban right the seriousness with which they take
Strident militancy
But you might be commanded to party it's a party for God and if you're not there the
Ramifications could be huge
Right
I'm inclined to think that it's a Greek stereotype of course but there's a
The part of me that wants
To believe
The latter
Can the one thing this
Conquest
If that's even the right word of Babylon is known for
Is the fact that
It's generally
Considered to be blood
You forget that battle we talked about with the nasty potential Mass
At the end
When the city of Babylon
Is taking its taken essentially voluntarily minutes like the Babylonians open up the door in Cyrus's General comes in
17 or so Days Later Cyrus himself comes in and we're told that the population
You don't get in front of his Chariot and lays down
Palm fronds
Stopwatch some historians in the old days used to be
Sure was a sign of how much people wanted in there
More modern-day historians point out that that's generally how you get treated when you come into a city that's trying to show that there
No threat at all and please don't hurt us
That's perhaps what
The Persian takeover of Babylon is most known for
Cyrus didn't hurt anybody
And as I said earlier nabonidus is life is spared
Which supposedly
Is the same fate that Cyrus has meted out to all the king's he's faced which by the way is not only unusual
But it's not even maybe true who knows they're always a little hint somewhere that maybe Cyrus killed these kings in the in the propaganda covered it up
Nonetheless historically and traditionally he supposed to have spared and given good lives all these other things he did
Biaggi's
Priests of the palladians now banaitis of the Babylonians
What is the message Cyrus is trying to send here I mean that's what I find
You want to know a little bit about the guy
Himself and maybe what he was trying to do what the message when he does that because the Assyrian King
Who last conquered Babylon brags about how he tied the
King of Babylon up like a pig
And displayed him in the center of Nineveh
So this is not standard operating procedure
It's one of the things by the way that fascinates me about Cyrus
Because the Occam's razor approach to history which is the right way to go me what else you going to do
Is to assume the most logical thing you don't assume Elijah
The Assumption always is
Someone likes irises playing at
Hardcore
Cynical propaganda game
Again Audrey probably is most people would be
But occasionally you're going to get some different kind of human being because we see them exist
It's just if you're using the Occam's razor approach to try to determine
You know what a Gandhi was really like a thousand years from now
You might be looking at listen Gandhi was really up
You know this was a cynical attempt to figure out a way to gain power level I mean could figure out all these real logical reasons why a guy might do this
Sometimes people who are doing things for Mystic reasons
Or morality reasons or humanistic reasons or any of these things sometimes those people slip through the cracks because it's just so
Easy to assume
They had a more real-world terrafirma reason for doing things
Is it possible
It's Cyrus was kind of a humanist
Maybe
You know this is how he's portrayed by the way by his real fans on the
Why do people back in the rain
Is the guy who invented human rights
Sort of at least as a
The ruler is
Concerned and Babylon is one of the number one pieces of evidence
Another gets trotted out in defense of this idea
But this isn't just some sort of policy
A tolerance for expediency sake
But this is how Cyrus really believes you can govern
And it should be pointed out that the
Not only has Babylon kind of surrender without a fight there's another Babylonian City or two
The kind of opens their doors to Cyrus
And it's interesting because he knows reasons argami has an interesting take on something that the Babylonian King did is part of the
The fighting with Cyrus for Babylon
Supposedly in this is
Way to look at nabonidus showing that maybe he was just really responsible king after all before Cyrus get the Babylon
Nabonidus goes around all the surrounding towns and it takes their God
Takes all their little the statues in the representations of their God
And take some to Babylon
And traditionally this is considered to be an actor
The safekeeping right
You know that you don't want your Statue of Liberty falling into the hands of the elamites and ending up in their trophy case rescue take all these
Village guide back to Babylon for safekeeping
Risa zarghami that has an interesting take
In his book discovering Cyrus
You did a great job reminding us of the interesting belief systems of the people who have these guys
And then how maybe you could see what nabonidus is doing is the equivalent of 4/2
Kidnap
The gods of these towns and holding them hostage for good behavior
Right
Stay loyal to Babylon or your God gets it in the neck
Something like that here's what's origami rights
And remember this only makes sense
If nabonidus is seriously worried that some of these towns are just going to go over to Cyrus because of the propaganda
Or whatever he writes quote
Faced with a very real prospect that is cities would open up their gates to the Conqueror
Nabonidus settled upon a drastic policy
He decided to hold hostage the sacred Idols of Babylonians outline City to ensure the Loyalty of their
Inhabitants
So when Cyrus and his army resume their March in the late summer of 539 BCE
A series of Caravans Laden with Divine Images and other religious artifacts
Made its way to Babylon
Living today we can hardly grasp the full psychological impact nabonidus as action
The idol was the centerpiece of the ancient Mesopotamian a cult
And the most important symbol of the community
The inanimate statues were treated like royalty
Bathe
Perfumed
Groomed and even fed lavish Meals by an Entourage of domestic servants
Priests and personal attendants
Ancient Mesopotamian culture geographically centralized
And the god Powers territorially Limited
That is why Cyrus could not receive the Divine approval he desired with the gods concentrated in Babylon
He then continues but nabonidus was playing a dangerous game by emptying the cities of their idols
Proximity to the cult statue meant everything to the superstitious masses
Who believed that the sacred images of their gods could perform miracles
Cure illness
And most importantly protect their settlements
Cities lost Divine protection when their gods left
And quote
One of the first things that Cyrus will brag about doing
When he takes over Babylon
Is returning all those
God's to the outlying communities
And those people freaking out
And you know having their gods back
Once again is Pierre Breann says Cyrus is portraying himself as the restorer of order of things that they should
Should be
Is beginning to tie himself
To the ancient
Assyrian tradition
Some historians suggest consciously
He'll talk about repairing something in the city and coming across
Some Proclamation by ashurbanipal the Assyrian king of tie himself to Assyria
And it's ancient
The Royal tradition
We start calling himself king of
King of the universe
These are old a Syrian and even
Acadian terms
But if Cyrus was starting to use these ancient titles for himself
You can see why he thought he might
Deserve it
Because 80 or 90 years after
You're the ancient Kingdom of Assyria fell
Cyrus and put Humpty Dumpty back together again
What sort of a different form
Different marketing
I'm Different branding
But all of a sudden once again just as had existed during
Later Assyrian times
One power had hegemony
In that part of the world now
Trying to rule
Immensely different people
People from
And everything from from deeply Urban environments and places like Babylon
Two Phoenician cities
Two tribes that existed off in the edges of the Eurasian steppe and incorporate all these different
People
Into one Empire
Much is made of the different
Strategies that the
The Persians use over the Assyrians instead of trying to shoot everybody into one
Intercultural Style
Convert everybody to your religion
Make good Assyrians of these conquered people
The Persians used a much lighter touch
That the idea of Toleration really was to allow
Local Customs to continue
The Assyrians wounded tolerated that the fact that the Persians didn't try to change all that whether it was a question of religion
Or language or anything else in fact
When the Persian Empire gets up and running
Persians will be putting all the most important positions
The Purge it will not be the language of the Empire there will always be only a tiny minority of people actually speaking Persian
All of the official in a proclamation will be multilingual so the different people can read them
All the local gods are respected and supported
Now again is this some sort of
Humanitarian gesture on Cyrus's park or is it a guy who is a humanitarian and thanks listen I'm just now
Tell me this is the best way to treat people and it will work out that's another where the guy who believes his own humanitarian beliefs and morals
Dovetail into good outcomes
Or is it somebody who's cynically looked at this and just as listen to just telling you if we do it this way we'll have less revolting to be much better
Assyrians
Who knows
It's tempting to think of Cyrus as brilliant and visionary
Regardless of which one of those things is true
He organizes this Empire restarts creating things that are called satrap since at trapeze
Which are
Administrative
Units that will be built upon by his successors
And then the next major thing we hear about Cyrus it's almost let you know when these people live that far back you get the highlights of their life
Why is right by letting everyone know conquest of Madea highlight number to conquest of Lydia hi Lite number 3 Conquest
Babylon highlight number 4
The
Expedition against a queen
One of the most powerful tribal coalition
In Central Asia
Now the fact that there is a queen involved in the story should tip you off to the idea that it's going to be a good
Herodotus by-the-way knows that he's eager to get to the story and he's going to spend a ton of time on a fusion setting it up
He knows his audience is ready
He's got a little moral Twisted may or may not have anything to do with reality
But you get a look at that 25
Hundred-year-old mind that your mind melding with
One way at this point the story
But if it comes the time where Herodotus is at his least reliable to
He jumps from highlight number 3 to highlight number 4 in Cyrus's life
In one second if you look at the actual dates and Volvo you'll see that
There is like 9 years between highlight number 3 and highlight number 4 and 9 years when Cyrus is
Well to use
Marketing and branding King of the universe
What the heck was this guy doing for 9 years
While he was putting out some propaganda we know
Something called the Cyrus cylinder is
Famous
And it's this piece where first Cyrus has the Babylonian God saying I was with him the whole way
And then he introduces himself is this good guy
Again propaganda makes it easier to rule the subject people if you make it feel like it was your God that wanted me
I came because he took my hand right to figure legitimizing your rule and tying you into the
Did the angel power structure basically saying that King you defeated was the real weirdo that the guy didn't want I am
Restoring
You know the kingship to the people that Marduk wants to have it
You can see that the same is true
In a lot of the other religions that Cyrus is involved with this is why a lot of people think this whole propaganda tolerance thing was much more.
Political move
Because look at how it helps him politically
In a way that by the way he could not have foreseen
It made him immortal
This is from Pierre Briones book
From Cyrus
2 Alexander
What's the translation from the Bible that he use
In the same way that the Cyrus cylinder says the Babylonian God Marduk took Cyrus handle swept away all the opposition
This is what the Israeli God Yahweh did according to the Bible
Quote
Thus says Yahweh to his appointed
Bucyrus
Whom he has taken by his right hand to subdue Nations before him
And strip the loins of Kings
Divorce gateways beforehand that their Gates be closed no more
I will go before you leveling the heights
I will shatter the bronze gateways
Smash the iron bars
I will give you the Hidden Treasures
The secret hoard
That you may know that I am Yahweh
And quote
The once again Cyrus has these Gods on his side why are they on the side when he's always helping isn't he
He's always doing what the priesthood of Marduk would like engine
It's interesting how Marduk follows along he likes you
Treat his priests well
In the case of Yahweh
Well according to the Bible again and Peter Brianna skeptical of the details but says in the bigger picture at least it was
Consistent with what actually happened
The Bible says that in the reign of a king
2 Chainz
After 2 official Kings after Cyrus they found the actual order
That would have made Yahweh pleased with investing shall we say
In the Cyrus conquests
According to the Bible in Pierre breons description of it
This is from Ezra by the way
Out of the royal archives of Fatima
The order said quote
In the first year of Cyrus the king
King Cyrus decreed temple of God in Jerusalem
The temple will be rebuilt as a place at which sacrifices are offered by which offerings are brought to be burnt
It's height is Tubi 60 cubits
It's with
60 cubed
There were to be three thicknesses of stone blocks
And one of what
The expenses to be met by the king's household
Furthermore the vessels of gold and silver from the temple of God which Nebuchadnezzar took from the sanctuary
Jerusalem and brought to Babylon going to be restored
So that everything may be restored to the sanctuary in Jerusalem and put back in the temple of God
And quote
Dr. nicely with that story of the ghostly hand doesn't it because what that guy belshazzar
Was drinking out of that made
In a y'all way so mad to begin with her all these sacred vessels from the old Temple in Jerusalem Solomon's Temple
Cyrus One
The cream that you rebuild
Solomon's Temple
And you pay for it out of the
King's treasure
Can you bring back all these things that are still around
And restock the temple with them
And then you send the people
Who has been deported to your back home
Now here's the thing
This reconstituted
You know area
It will become a satrap by the way does not have its political freedom
They're not going to be the way they were
You know when the Babylonians and Egyptians were arguing over them
But you got to see that they're pretty darn far ahead they went from a people that might have died out
Religiously
Defective book I have the places Cyrus has one of the top
Most 100 influential people of all time says that that's one of the things maybe you credit him with
The fact that if he doesn't do this
There's a chance Judaism
Doesn't continue over the Long Haul
In this case he builds what's known as the second temple
And if you want to see continuity
The wall that is still one of the holiest did not be holy ass I get the Temple Mount would be Holier but but it's
Part of the Temple mount
It is the famous in the Western Wall
The Western Wall
Is a Roman era Edition
To the second temple
Which Cyrus
Allegedly according to the Bible
Paid for an authorized
So interesting isn't it
Considerate
How connected the stories of the ancient at Ronnies ancient Persians are
To the ancient Jewish
Especially considering the current
Antagonism between them
As late as the 1970s the Shah of Iran was was
Touting this ancient closeness
Between the peoples in their relationship
If not for the ancient Persians and Iranians there's a chance there wouldn't be Judaism today
And depending on when it died out there's a very good chance you wouldn't have had their religions
That
Sprouted off that Branch you into had Christianity you probably wouldn't that Islam in other words
Is Cyrus the Great actually did do this
And he had never lived to do it
What would the world look like today
Another thing of session that
100 most influential people of all time that I thought was interesting is that
Many of the people that get credited as being very important
And dynamic and
Instrumental
Human beings in terms of their effect on history
It's something that would have been done anyway
I got a big-time or that way
But a lot of this stuff would have happened someone else would've discovered the light bulb probably
The author Thoreau
Likely
That if Cyrus the Great that never live
None of this stuff
He was a
Unique individual
Even though you can't get your mind around the specifics of how he was a unique individual
You can sort of look at what buildup
Even appear Brianna's right and you have to assume that there was a lot of foundation bubbling up under the surface for Cyrus to work with
Is it still a pretty incredible
Human being
I think you could probably say
With a decent
Chance of being right
But he is
In the 5:30 is BCE the greatest
Geopolitical figure
Who's ever lived
Which makes
The next thing I'm going to say
Is it hard to believe
You know why should I say
How about
Letting
Historian 80 homes
Getting a book published in 1940
Say it
And again
Is there any more of a telling
Example that
These people live at the very tail end
Black and white era of recording of human history has how can this guy be as big as he is
And yet this next line be true
Homestead said
Quote
Here we must leave Cyrus
For suddenly and without warning
Our information comes to an end
And quote
200 years after
We will know Alexander the Great's symptoms
To such a degree the doctor's today try to diagnose what he may have died up and they still don't know I'm not saying everything's
But you know where when the house the wise
How can you not know
How does guy die
I like number for in his life as portrayed by Herodotus
Is Herodotus a story of how he dies and I love the fact that Herodotus goes to
You know the trouble to point out that he's heard several different versions of the story but the one he's going to give you as the one he thinks his MO
Most likely
And maybe it's just a coincidence
That the story that Herodotus thinks is most likely
Is the one with the most exotic
Interesting
Movie like elements to it you can imagine I can't imagine he left a better
Version on the table somewhere say nope you know I just don't be
Because the one he used is so awesome
Now is it believable
That's the problem here nobody knows what to believe
Off the top of my head if you ask me what percentage
Bought into the general idea of Herodotus a story I think it's like 80
Most of them don't believe any of the details but the broad idea that in 5:30 BCE Cyrus the Great died so
Somewhere out in this step area as Herodotus said details probably
Unknown
About 20% I'd say of the historians don't think he died a completely different way
Something against different tribes in Herodotus says different areas others that he didn't die that way at all xenophon writing a couples
Afterwards he died in bed
Peacefully
So there's a mystery to buy that you hit it wrong it's a generally I think a higher percentage of historians think he didn't die the way Herodotus
Says
You could understand why
You be a little skeptical it's just too darn interesting the way erotica
You can see
You're the admonition that I got when I was starting in journalism the one that said
Natal what really happened
In the most interesting way possible
What happens to an admonition like that
If there's no way you could possibly know what really hot
But you have to tell it anyway
What are your standards then you pretty much left with the most interesting way you can at that point right
Drop the story as Herodotus tells it
Involves this
Little twist you're going to end up leaving his theatrical presentation with a deeper message
Again the deeper message may or may not be true Herodotus couches the story now into the idea of ovary
Maybe the idea of absolute power corrupting absolutely
And before we write this off
As many historians do right away because it's just such an obvious moral message remember you can make that
Case about Hitler
You know what the absolute power
Turning you mad after a while with Alexander you can make that case I mean I guess there are historical figures
Where this is both of motif cuz it's this recurring theme you see all the time
But it also happens to be true
Maybe
After years of being King of the universe
Cyrus got a little full of himself who knows but that's the way this is portrayed right is going to be the object lesson here
And the person that is going to stick it
To Cyrus and teach him this lesson is going to be a queen
Yeah but you have to think of it like an Amazonian Queen this isn't some woman who's walking around in velvet
You don't want a throne being fan I mean this is a person who probably Once Upon a Time was killing men
In hand-to-hand combat
Got it this woman really exist
Who the heck knows there's no historical confirmation that I've ever seen
It says that they found anything that proves
This queen is named by the way I used to call it to Mira's when I was growing up but I've seen
Timorous timorous
Number different pronunciation
I think Shakespeare might have used her as a character
His place
None the less you can say couple of things one
It wouldn't have been outrageous to think of her is a Female warrior because these tribes actually had them
It may have been the actual root of the
Idea of
Amazon's inside of a mythology
So she could have actually been
A killer Warrior
And also the tribes he was supposed to have led
Was real
All too real to some people
They were called the mastic Italian the message tie
Dangerous
Powerful numeracy
Tribal
Coalition
That
Urologist in his writings he have to set it up and tell you what he knows which isn't much he says I hear there was Skippy and Peep
But we kind of were
You have to think of
Mangol type
Culture
But with people who were probably predominantly light-skinned
And
Ranging on the scale of looks from like a turkey
It's kind of look
All the way up to people with blond and red hair
Blue and green eyes tall
Is a little Viking site
A little bit of the Viking ethos
Bella Thorne worshipping
And things like that supposedly once a year
These people would have a
Scaffold erected they put a sword on top of
The scaffold and then they would mark underneath the scaffold one out of every 100 prisoners that they captured over the year and execute them
Sacrificed
Sky Go
God the son God
Miss right
These are colorful
Scary people just what you wanted a story like this
Herodotus is already talked about their head hunting
The fact that they make
You know drinking cups out of skulls and the really nasty Warriors are the ones with the most
Cups
He talks about their cannabis you so again this is the Exotic Barbarian you want to hear what they do
He says they found this
Fruit that they can burn
And then they sit around the fire burning the fruit and it gets them intoxicated like wine gets Greeks and talks
Educated
So another little bit
Barbarian color to throw in
He also points out according to him
They're very promiscuous you might call them free-love types or swingers Maybe
Anybody can sleep with anybody else's wife he just
Had to put his bow
You know alongside their 10 to let him know
You're interested I guess
So
Weed smoking
Headhunting
Blood drinking white sharing bike
Who would not want that in a good story if you don't know anything you just trying to make the best story make sure you include these
Herodotus says that Cyrus leads an army
Up to this Queen's territory
And then basically proposes marriage to
So would be like a diplomatic Alliance
Herodotus says that
She sees through this ruse immediately saying
He just wants to conquer her people by marrying her
So then when she says no
He begins to try
To set up what we would call today in amphibious
River Crossing
Is a big river
The divide the territory he's coming from
From the territory of these
Central Asian horse Nomads up in places like
Like you know
Kha'zix
Any places like that today
And as Cyrus and the Persians were told her building these boats
Some of which have like Towers
Fighting Towers on them
She sends him a message
Remember she's going to be like the voice of avenging Karma here
In teaching Cyrus a lesson
So her voice in the words that Herodotus puts in her mouth from a screenwriter showrunners point of view
Are designed to naset this idea up right
You should know but you don't you know you're going to get what's coming to you here's what Herodotus says
This is the de selincourt
Quote
King of the medes
I advise you to abandon this Enterprise
But you cannot know if in the end it will do you any good
Rule your own peep
And try to Bear the sight of me ruling mine
But of course you will refuse my advice as the last thing you wish for us to live in peace
Listen that
If you are so bent upon trying your strength against domestic a tie
Give up the laborious task of building that bridge
And let my Army withdraw three days March from the river
And then you come over yourself
Or if you prefer red retire the same distance yourself
And let us meet you on your side of the river
And quote
This
Barbarian Warrior Queen
Is basically saying to a guy whose title includes king of kings and King of the universe
To come and get it
Or I'll come over and take it from you
That's a pretty strong female character isn't
I was thinking that it makes Herodotus a X look a little pro-feminist right like you like he's been looking for a good strong fee
Female character
Doesn't know the reason maybe that would play well
Maybe some of the people in his audience are women
And it would be good to have a character that they could both relate to in cheer for
Finally it might just be a dig
@the manliness of the Persian
It's right I mean
Here's the greatest King that Asia has ever produced
And he's about to be beaten and killed by a woman
Nonetheless in the story when she says you know do you want it over here do you want it over there
Cyrus and his
In a general and whatnot sit down have a conference about this what do we do Which choice do we take in all his advisers they let her come to our side of
One adviser though says None of my go over to her side
That advisor
Is our Old Friend the King of Lydia croesus
Instead of being killed Herodotus has
You know going in the stories of acting is advisor to Cyrus all the way through
Increase his advice is totally different
Personal he says you can't
Let her come over here and get branded front of her it's a woman it would look terrible so
Is that other little dig
He says go over to her side
And then he says
And how about we do
A little trick
Any precedes to tell
Cyrus
Did they should have essentially do the same thing
To these people that the medes did to
Either these people or their cousins a generation before in a store you may recall
Get them all drunk and kill them
Midas ellincourt translation
As croesus telling Cyrus
To do it this way
Quote
Here then is my advice
Cross the river
Advance to the limit of the enemy's withdrawal
And then get the better of them by a piece of strategy
I have heard that these people have no experience of such luxuries as the Persians enjoy
I know nothing about the pleasures of life
What is take advantage of this fact
And set out of bank
Narcan
On the most generous scale
With a great many sheep slaughtered and dressed
All sorts of other dishes
And bowls of strong wine in Liberal quantities
Then when the banquet is all prepared
He says
Let us March back to the river
Leaving only a Detachment of inferior troops behind
Unless I'm very much mistaken
When our enemies see all those good things
They will set to work upon them
And that will be our chance to distinguish ourselves by a bold stroke
And quote
Again is that a recurring Motif or is that just a
Tactic that seems to work quite a bit who knows
But in the story we're told
That the author
Of the army
Chose up
Chills the inferior troops
Cease all the food in the wine precedes to get
In a very full and very drunk and then the Persians come in kill a bunch of them and capture some others about a third of the army
According to Herodotus
Included amongst the prisoners
A general
Who also happens to be this Barbarian Queen's son
So now in this scenario Herodotus is playing with his movies turned into a little bit of a thriller with a little chess match and all the
Sunday Cyrus's side is captured a major
Peace
Son of the queen
Sochi issues one of these
I'll let you go now if
Give me back my son
Kinds of spy
From the Purvis translation
Went to Mira's learned what had happened to her Army and her son
You sent a Herald to Cyrus with this message
Bloodthirsty Cyrus
Do not gloat over what has happened here
You Persians indulge yourself with the fruit of the vine to the point of Madness
So that the wind descends into your body
Ugly words flow up and out of you by such means you have tricked me
Are you taking my son prisoner
But not by shoepremacy in battle
Well then
I heard you to follow this advice
Return my son to me
And despite the damage you have cunningly wreaked upon a third part of the army of the message that I
You may leave this land on our
If you do not do this
I swear by the Sun the lord.of.the masakit I
Did I will satisfy your thirst for blood
Insatiable As You Are
And quote
So was Cyrus going to do
With this interesting
Powerful
Chest piece
He doesn't get the chance to decide
Because we're told that as soon as the Queen's Sons sobers up
Finds himself
You know hands tied or bound
He beseeches Cyrus to undo his hands
Somehow Cyrus's
Convinced and
I like the way my Rawlinson translation puts it
The minute his hands were free rawlinson's
Herodotus says he destroyed
3 committed suicide
Now all of a sudden
Cyrus just lost his pay
And this is when we're told the Battle app
This from the desellum
Translation quote
The queen on hearing that Cyrus ignored her terms engaged him in the field with all the forces she possess
The battle which followed I judge you have been more violent than any other fought between foreign Nations
According to the information that I have
The engagement began with the two armies coming to a halt within range of each other and exchanging shots with bows and
Narrows until their arrows were used up
After which there was a long period of close fighting
With Spears and daggers
Neither side being willing to retreat
Finally however the masakit I got the upper hand
The greater part of the Persian army was destroyed where it stood
And Cyrus himself was killed
He'd been on the throne for 29 years
And quote
Of course
That doesn't quite
Twist the knife enough
Have you leaving the performance really thinking
Thinking about some of the greater things in life
Socarrat is from my
Purvis translation
Add the code
The story
Price quote
Queen Tamara Stanfield a wineskin with human blood
And search for the corpse of Cyrus amongst the Persian dead
When she found him
He thrusts his head into the wineskin
Unless she does abused the Corp
She declared to it
I am alive
Concord Yuan battle
But you have ruined Me by taking my son through dial
Well then just as I threatened
I will slake your thirst for blood
And quote
So if
As the
Recurring Greek Motif will later show that the Persians are serial over Reacher's
I'm sure her audit is his attitude here's that they should have learned their lesson with Cyrus
By the time Cyrus exits
The scene though
Built an Empire
Stretches from
The modern-day Pakistan all the way to the Mediterranean
I've been to Turkey down by the Red Sea to the borders of Egypt
Can out to the Central Asian steppe
He's taken
Your efforts in and spent years organizing it
Putting it in a form
Word has a chance to live on after he's gone
None the less you cannot lose
Person
Of that magnitude you cannot lose in Alexander you cannot lose in upholding you cannot lose and have these people from
Such lofty Heights removed from the scene without there being this huge vacuum
A couple hundred years
After this time.
One of the people who will fill a vac
Play a similar role
And maybe eclipse this
Person
Visit his tomb
Alexander the Great
Along with some influential colleagues
We'll go to the spa
Not in the building that is assumed
To be the tomb of Cyrus
That tomb is still standing
The way in Modern Day Iran
Interesting to think
Climbing up the
In a fully colorized historical era now by the way bringing with him people who will write about it afterwards we actually have
Through another guy the writings of someone who's with Alexander and kind of describes what the tune look like
Lot of clothing lot of souvenirs lot of things that just sort of helped the guy into the Afterlife sort of deal
And then a body
It was preserved in
Wax
This was this was kind of a Persian custom to
This might just be me but I had to
Is feeling better
Queen of the message either the message Atty
I have taken his head or something
That's a
Mutilation that they would have
Probably told us a
It's probable that the body look pretty darn good cuz no one talked about it
Working any other way
We told that there was a man
On the tune out some historians think it must have been
In front of the team cuz it's missing but they were a couple of different
Descriptions
Some people who supposedly saw
Summer more flowery than other
One that I like this
Says
Quote
Mortal
I am Cyrus son of cambyses
Who founded the Persian Empire and was king of Asia
Grudge me not then my money
But there are other
Tradition
Also from eyewitness accounts of region
The record of very
Sodapoppin
Some of the historians I like
Much more
Traditional Iranian to it's much more pissed
Right to the point
The Persians when they were leading the Empire could
Put on the airs as well as any Mesopotamian Dynasty ever did they could
He Ballin all the traditional titles
Queen Victoria as the Empress of India
The kings of this area had King of the universe
King of the four corners of the earth king of lands
The Persians could do that
Sometimes when they were just recording
For eternity
Which is what a tomb inscription like
This is
They adopted if
Different style
The tomb inscription
Supposedly from an eyewitness
That's what I like the most likely to use services
Pershing Pre-K
Forum
The name Cora
It says
Here I lie
CoolROM
The Persians grew up
Can you quit Melinda potop neighbor
The show you just heard involved a lot of
Student worried
Discuss the background
Where they
Sprung from
Because this does a bunch of things one it makes their achievements all the more sound
I mean they arose in this world with all these
Amazing competitors and managed to
Neclimbs
Top of the Heap anyway
It also helps us set of Baseline for
Harrison when we say things like the Persians are
Tolerant or lenient
You want to immediately say compared to what
You just heard gives us some idea
What they might be compared to
Finally it's a fantastic story the story that usually relegated to dead are between two other stories right
Somewhere between the fall of Assyria and the rise of Persia
Is the
Your latter part of the 600
And the high 580-590-5585 what's going on during that era
Normally it sort of just a transition point
Between
The two chapters in a book
Where is all by itself
Twisted in fastener
I love the idea of the great power like the US and the Soviet Union
Collapsing in the rest of the world sort of looking at each other over the
In a smoking ruin trying to figure out
Who gets what and what do things look like that
I love that
The key to this whole story this point is
You know what it took such a singular figure to put this improbable
Event together
What happens when that figure exits the scene
What are the odds of getting to Cyrus the Great in the same family one right after another
Remember this is the largest Empire in world history the distance from one part to another is Dante
You have all these different people people that are very independent-minded and fractious and who gave the aesir
Syrians
All the time
So many different religion so many different languages how is
In one
Small minority of people going to rule this giant entity especially without the specially gifted guy who bill
Built the whole thing
In the next episode will examine how
Can buy
Son of Cyrus manages all
And it will be Coos and they will potentially be armies disappearing and sandstorms
There will be far too many Greeks probably for what the story really warrants
But you have to understand while we all know instinctively there important things going on
In the east in the North in the other parts of the Persian Empire that don't touch Greek lands
The only people writing about it in any sort of extended
Colorful way
Are the Greek so just like everyone else will
Talk about the Greek and Persian Wars will get some context of that Battle of Thermopylae
Movie scene with a Spartan say come and take them
And then we'll deal
The guy
The next guy really in the story whose personal talents are such that
He's a game-changer all by himself
The natural successor to Cyrus the Great and
The person who finally put
Stake in the heart
The black and white world
The son of Philip of Macedon
All that
Amor
The next episode
Kings of Kings
If you think the show you this hurt is worth a dollar
Dan and Ben
Would love to have it
Abacus show it's all we ask
Go to dancarlin.com for information
Turn on how to donate
To the show
Do you want to help the podcast
Just buy your amazon.com products through the Amazon search window
On dancarlin.com
And Dan and Ben will get a percentage of what you spend it doesn't cost you a penny more
And it helps these guys out because they are nice
Young fellows