What you're about to hear is part 2 of a multi-party
Series on the achaemenid Persian
Empire and especially its dealings with the
I suggest getting part 1 and listening to that first before you dive into this but listen I'm not here to tell you how to live
Live your life you do anything
I would like to point out that
This is the Dan Carlin version of this story which is always what you get
With me
Which may or may not correspond
To the traditional way these things are told
So please
Please listen at your own risk
And if it Sparks a an interest in the subject
I'll be very happy
Nonetheless without further Ado and with proper warnings in play
This is
Kings of Kings
Part 2
December 7th 1941
A date which will live in infamy
Call Nick time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein
Belina
Weather now
Remember that we are not descended from fearful men
Hardcore history
How many people out of 100
That you could name either people that you knew or people that you heard of or read about
How many people out of a hundred do you think could handle
Absolute power
Without totally losing their mind
And
If you could handle it initially if you could find that well-balanced person to the deal with it initially
What about dealing with it for the Long Haul
Because history shows that there are a lot of people
Another Power gets to you over time it eats at you slowly I mean if you could have lots of power and
Initially could you handle it for 10 years
Or 20 years or 30 years
Those of us in
Democratic systems tend to assume because it's kind of built into the thinking of our political systems
But nobody can handle absolute power
Or did it certainly an unbelievably small number right absolute power corrupts absolutely
How long we all heard that term end
We assume it's a truism I know I do
And yet I can prove myself wrong pretty easily
By looking back at the past and realizing that
By that sort of rationale shouldn't every
Emperor and King throughout history that had either close to or
De facto absolute power should they all be crazy and they all lose their minds
And while you can certainly say most of them probably lost perspective
For example what life was like for normal people
The vast majority of them didn't go crazy which might be more interesting
And assuming the opposite
Although we all know of the high-profile examples don't we
I mean all use the classic ones when I go right to Godwin Plumbing look at Hitler
You could say maybe it was
Form of Parkinson's disease or maybe the doctor feel good drugs he was being shot up with
At the same time by the end of his rule he is exhibiting
The classic
Symptoms of megalomania and paranoia
They come with the absolute power
Some stereotype
Look at a guy like Alexander the Great, he's almost another kind of Godwin's law in the especially with this program
By his early thirties he's a paranoid
Andaz megalomaniacal is Hitler
And again maybe some of that connected to what a lot of historians be called rampant
And terminal maybe at the point he was at alcoholism who knows it's difficult to separate
Alexander seem to be able to handle power initially and then somewhere along the line he couldn't
And the sources at the time by the way right about this growing
Megalomania and paranoia
Not very fair sources maybe to Let's acknowledge that
Wendy
Near legendary an enormous historical figures Cyrus the Great
We talked about in the first part of the story
When he died
Was killed in 5:30 or 5:29 BCE
He bequeathed to his son
The most dangerous inheritance I can imagine
He leaves in the Empire
But yeah just one
And by doing so
He both
Create an immense challenge for his son to overcome
Absolute power or something very close to it and what that can do to him
But also we hands his son something that is
So valuable
Immediately
Other entities are going to be tempted by it
It's like leaving him
You know
Ineffective really did leave him
And then sending them out at 2 in the morning to walk down the most crime-ridden Street in town
You're always going to be looking over your shoulder
And there may be other people very tempted by what you have
Cyrus the Great oldest son what name can be
Officially it's Campisi's the SEC
That's part of what made Cyrus such a Visionary ruler
He paid a lot of attention before his death to making sure that there would be a smooth transition of power from him
To his
Designated successor
This is an era in human history
Where this was a very precarious Affair a lot of the time I mean we take for granted
In our Democratic systems today
The transfer of power will be relatively smooth
And we consider it a really big deal in a constitutional crisis if
And we can't name the winner at the end of the day
You don't want an election day and it has to go to a cord and if there's challenges to
In a ballot in the state of that say that's a huge deal
In the ancient near East and West Asia and the fury were talking about here
All kinds of nightmares happened at any king or ruler would have known about them
It would be Revolutions in Coos and assassinations and Sons would would kill their parents and go to war with each other
My favorite story about
These kinds of Affairs and it's a classic case I guess you could say that
Rule proving classic case is the Assyrian King sennacherib
Who famously destroyed Babylon
And then lost his life supposedly while praying
At the hands of at least one and maybe two of his sons
And then one tradition by the way killed with a statue that represented Babylon so you get that wonderful
You know ancient history tie-in that the authors from ancient times all like
Where are you now there's a certain karmic Justice here you destroyed Babylon in the Madonna Babylon get back at you and then his sons
Go to war with each other the tail tell them at 3rd son maybe comes in
Defeat both of them
And then takes over
The throne
Jump reverse but not that unusual in a guy like Cyrus the Great would have understood
You know the pitfalls
Right is going to be a ton of entities out there
Want the power that you just created remember Cyrus is a guy who in the space of a single rain
Admittedly long rain
Took his people from a geographical Backwater on the world stage
And made them the masters of the greatest Empire the world has ever seen
A guy whose initial title when he came to the throne with king of on Sean
Whose titles when he died where things like
King of the world King of the four corners of the earth king of the universe
As we said in the first part of the show
That's a heck of a promotion in one lifetime
While it's hard enough for the self-made individual that makes that progress in the space of a lifetime
How much harder might it be for people
Who simply have that handed
2nd generation or the 3rd Generation begins to live a lifestyle
That's different than expect these sorts of things
You can see Cyrus training his son
4 years before his demise
To make him
Essentially on-the-job-training he's going to hand over the family business
His son gets to be the Viceroy Babylon for a while to hang out with the Army for a while do this do that he's learning how to be
The king of kings
I wonder if that somehow
Increases your chances that you can do so without losing your mind and your perspective
Cyrus also
Brokers an important deal because he has more than one son
And if you look back at even recent history a guy like Cyrus would have been able to notice how much of a problem you have when you have
Have more than one possible inherited the throne
Cyrus
In addition to his oldest son came by sea has another one
Known by multiple names
The most common probably be mispronounced by yours truly is bardia
Is the younger son
And according to the ancient sources take this for what it's worth
When Cyrus is crafting essentially his will his inheritance the deal
It makes Campisi's the next king of kings but he gives out of a consolation prize to the younger bro
Right you lose out on the
On the fruits of Empire but here is your runner-up
Gift
He gives him a large territory
In Central Asia to govern
And apparently says that unlike all the other territories that are being governed
In the Name of the King you can keep the taxes in the tribute
You know from your places
You still are beholding to your older brother but
You have a nice little in a place to call your own sort of and keep the money
Initially this thing to work rather welcome Cyrus dies
Transition to his chosen successor
Seems to be relatively scene
And then
Things begin to get
Corrupted
So corrupted in fact
But you actually have to look
At the end
Afghan by Caesar's rain
And then work backward
To the beginning
Because what happens at the end
Changes kurupts and altars
All that we know about the rain
And by she's the second rain is going to be like a
Game of Clue
Did you ever play that game where
And yet to figure out the murder mystery in the weapon and what room it happened and it was Colonel Mustard in the library with the candlestick
Trying to figure out
The reign of Campisi's and who this guy was
Is a little like trying to figure out the who done it
The game of Clue
Because something happens to Camp by sea
And it might be
The he goes insane
Because he can't handle the amount of absolute power he has that's what the ancient sources
Indicate writes erotic just basically says
He's lost his mind
A lot of modern historians don't buy that at all
AC cover
Conspiracy
Something that
Would not be
Unfamiliar to people who read
You know things about the John F Kennedy assassination conspiracy tales about that because
If something about the demise of
Can Pisces that looks a lot like one of those John F Kennedy assassination conspiracy books or several of them
More
The people that may have
Gotten
The King of Kings the founder of the Persian Empire son out of the way
May have been the ones who got it then decide how the history about him
Was written
And that has
Colored everything we know about
Second ruler
The achaemenid Persian Empire
A guy who had the very
Unenviable task of trying to follow a legend
Who could follow Alexander the Great
Well nobody they ripped his Empire apart
And started fighting over it rather quickly
Who could follow Adolf Hitler if his dreams of a
Thousand-Year Reich even partially came true
Imagine it can you Hitler's personality and DNA
Was
Entwined all throughout the idea of the Third Reich you can't even imagine anyone succeeding him in any of the realistic way
My ride is opposed
Admiral Donuts who succeeds in for a couple days to sign the peace agreement
Who could
Napoleon
Can buy she's the second is in the
Unenviable position
But if modern historians are to be believed and I shouldn't see why they shouldn't be
He did a pretty good job
For the time he had available to him
Was he insane
That's much harder ones
Figure out
Depends on who you believe
But if he was
Sure wouldn't be
Hard to imagine why how many people that you know out of a hundred could handle app
Absolute power
The idea that can be seized was insane
And that he did all these crazy things
Was one that took hold way back in ancient time
I persisted up until really like the 1960s or 1970s
Will Durant in 1935 a great historian writing an outdated history
Did a wonderful job and by the way taking it at face value
Giving you the traditional cambece story
And it's a Litany of Horrors but it's fascinating as heck I mean if your Herodotus and we describe the ancient Greek
Historian as an ancient screenwriter or scriptrunner
If your product is
Don't you want a nice half-mad Persian king to play around with because
Think about the possibilities inherent in that right
Here's the way will Durant describes this in 1935 again taking the entire story at face value but essentially giving
You the story as it was understood and believed to have happened
For thousands of years he writes
Starting to talk about Cyrus can buy sees his father and contrasting and comparing the pieces quote
1 great defect had sullied is character
Meeting Cyrus's Carey
Occasional and incalculable cruelty
It was inherited on mixed with Cyrus's generosity by his half-mad son
Can Pisces Begin by putting to death his brother
And rifle
It means bardia he says smartest
I told you the guy that a lot of names
By putting to death his brother and Rivals Meredith
Then lured by the accumulated wealth of Egypt he set forth to extend the Persian Empire to the
He succeeded
But apparently at the cost of the sanity
Memphis was captured easily
But an army of 50,000 Persians sent to Annex the Oasis of Amun perished in the desert
Any expedition to Carthage failed because the Phoenician Cruise of the Persian Fleet refuse to attack of Phoenicia
10 colonies
Can Pisces lost his head
And abandon the why is clemency intolerance of his father
He publicly scoffed at the Egyptian religion and plunge this dagger derisively into the bull revered by the
Egyptians as the god apus
Exhumed mummies and pride in the Royal tombs regardless of ancient curses
The profaned the temples and ordered their Idol to be burnt
He thought in this way to cure the Egyptians of superstition
But when he was stricken with an illness apparently epileptic convulsions
The Egyptians were certain that their gods have punished him and that the theology was now confirmed Beyond dispute
As if again to illustrate the inconveniences of monarchy Durant rights
Can Pisces with the Napoleonic kick in the stomach
Kill his sister and wife Roxana
Slew his son for Zaxby's with an arrow
Barry 12 Noble Persians alive
Freezes to death
Repented Rejoice to learn that the sentence had not been carried out
And then punish the officers who delayed in executing it
Tony's way back to Persia he learned that the usurper had seized the throne and was being supported by widespread Revolution
From that moment he disappears from history
Tradition has it that he killed himself
And quote
If you're the ancient screenwriter that is Herodotus
You love this guy is a story of
But is it true
Trying to investigate
You know what happened to your like
Going into a crime scene and being an investigator
I've often thought that history is like a crime scene
I'm not a historian I meant admirer from afar but I love those moments where historians are put into the
So the Joe Friday the sergeant Joe Friday weather
As I said Colombo mode and go into the game of Clue and start investigating what happened
And the guys from Durant Sarah an earlier they're sort of like old-timer investigator that go out there the interview the witnesses
Try to figure out what happened they give you the stories they understand it
But they don't have modern-day techniques right it's like
Investigating the Kennedy assassination
In a with techniques from the early 1960s or being able to have it happen today and investigated
With DNA evidence in modern-day ballistics in an audio sample in cameras
I mean the difference is
Astonishing and when modern-day historians go back and examine this case they break it down to the same sorts of things you would if you were start
Joe Friday going into the scene
It start looking at the physical evidence right the blood spatter
And the fingerprints that's the archaeological stuff
Can you start comparing that
Do the stories you got from the witnesses and the different people around
You know the neighborhood there are the
In a written source is in the stuff that's come down to us
You start compiling sort of a
It'll come positive what the person the victim was like
Maybe you send investigators down to the city hall and you start looking at the paper trail see if there's any
In a records on this person arrest records real estate transactions anything like that
Those are the
Ancient sources like the Babylonian tablets that they found
Can you try to compile some sort of a
Semblance of what happened based on
You know the total view of the evidence
The story that can be seized is insane comes from some of the
In a Witnesses at the crime scene
And they may have been giving you the information secondhand
And it may have come from biosources
If you're investigating
Crime scene you'll start with
Just the facts
Sergeant Joe Friday might have said
The facts of cambyses II rain that you can say
With certainty
Is that he
The rules for about eight years from about 5:30 BC each about 5:22 BCE
He was the king
That first really gave the Persian Empire a naval capability and it may not sound like a big deal
Really made them the first of the powers that were based in Mesopotamia in that area of the world
Have any sort of significant Naval capability ever
People like the Assyrians might have had the tribute on the
The nominal allegiance of some of these coastal cities on the Mediterranean may have even been able to operate some Coastal forces
Forces in freshwater areas
But the Persians become the first of these people to have a fleet which is significant on the Mediterranean Naval worldstage
And it should be
They take over the one that was probably the best in the Mediterranean
Up until that time
They start absorbing Phoenician cities with the fabulous Phoenician navies
And the way the Persians govern days and create their own Navy or they didn't take the Phoenicians in and make them as a base to start their own
They simply went in there as soda subcontracted inside will listen what you have to offer the Empire militarily speaking is
New York have a fleet so when we need to Fleet your Fleet is our Fleet and you'll run it and
You know what you're doing and they'll be a bonus in it for you if you do well
Assyrians would have said something like you perform well or else
The Persians probably said something like a knight perform well in
We little something extra at the end of the year
Pisces is the guy that does that
And that makes a huge difference in the story that's about to happen
Because if the Persians don't have any Naval power
Well a lot of things
It'll occur in the rest of their history cat
Example
The other thing came by ceases absolutely known for in this a physical fact and that's the
He's the king of kings
Takes over Egypt
Something that requires by the way this Navy in order to do
And a complete the conquest of his father
Remember his father
You know we first started off conquering things they were for kind of superpowers in the world at that time or their version
Another world
Cyrus conquered conquered the
Remaining one
An Egypt was a great state pretty much always
They were no pushover
Although not a lot is known about
You know the fighting in the battles and all that sort of stuff
There were some decent stories
One of the more perverse that one of the ancient sources wrote
You know probably totally false but
Said that
Persians took advantage of the ancient Egyptians reverence for cats
Strapped cats to their Shields
So that the Egyptian archers would be
You are unsure of how to react to that
That would be exactly the kind of
An image that Herodotus type character would love to share with an audience at the colorful anecdote isn't it
But Herodotus himself says he actually saw
Bonfield
In Egypt from some of these battles
And that would have been
In a 75 years
After the fact or something so
Will be very interesting it's not like Herodotus to lie about what he actually sees or what he actually talks to somebody about seeing
Herodotus tells a story from the fighting
It says that the Persians at one point and it should be very like them by the way cuz then we talked about in the last program that they essentially did this
Is with the Greeks
And with other people's they sent an invoice to the Egyptian Defenders at one point probably try to offer them a typical Persian
You give up this fight will all benefit probably be great to know
And it must have been
A sizable delegation because Herodotus says that the Egyptians
These the delegation and tore them limb from limb
Pretty much any time in history just about anywhere you go
And boys and and ambassadors and whatnot are
Untouchable
Are there are usually very strong
Reasons to not
Abused the envoy's of another country in the
Persians are no example in his we said the last of the persons are very lenient Empire sort of graded on a curve
But they could be just as nasty as their predecessors in the region
It when they decided they wanted to send a message
And the Persians were very good at knowing who to send it to
Herodotus tells a story who knows if it's true or not
About what the Egyptian punishment was
When they lost the war and someone had to pay for
The treatment of those invoices were so horribly abused
Herodotus has
Can Pisces right after he captures Egypt
Summoning the Egyptian Elite to the capital of Memphis
To watch a demonstration of what happens to
People
To break the law
And I keep trying to imagine what a saying like this is like it must have been
Intense enough with an oral historian like Herodotus
Talking about it to an audience
I can imagine what the
Extreme modern day
Blockbuster movie would be like
But here's what Herodotus says when you try to imagine
And what the sound
2000 parents watching the children being executed
Is like
Product assist quote
9 days after Campisi's at taking control over Memphis
Deseeded
Centos
King of Egypt
Would Rain 6 months
Egyptians in front of the entrance to the town as an insult
How do you tested the spirit of 70 toast in this way
He had the daughter of the former King dress like a slave
Instant out carrying a jug to get water
Along with other girls
Selected Daughters of the most eminent men
All dressed in the same way as the daughter of 70 toes
As the girls walk past their fathers they cried out and wept
And all the other fathers seeing their children so degraded answered their cries and wept with their own
Vignetos after seeing and recognizing his daughter only bent down and silence to the ground
Herodotus continues
Quote
After the girls are gone by with their water
Can I see sent out the Son of Sam anitos with 2,000 other Egyptians the same age
Bound with ropes around their necks and bits in their mouth
They were being let in this matter in order to pay the penalties for the Egyptians destruction of the middle Indians
Memphis M4 the decision of the royal judges
Was that for each member of the ship's crew
Eminent Egyptian should be put to death in return
San Benito saw them passing by
And realize that his son was being led to his death
But while the other Egyptian seated around him were crying and openly expressing their anguish he behaved just as he had in
In the case of his daughter
And quote
I try to imagine that scene
The parents watching
Their children put to death into slavery thing
Might not hit home until you think about it
These girls were probably dressed extremely scantalides or formerly the noblewomen you know of the realm
And they're dressed
In a way that would be provocative to
Let's just say the male population looking for slaves for more than just menial labor
We tend to forget that element of slavery over time
But it's undoubtable that sex was an integral part of the attraction of having someone
That you owned available at any time and if you're the parent watching your daughter in that situation
The anguish and then did watch your son being executed in front of you and then seeing you know the other people in your situations were right now
Text You In This Crowd I mean
What's that sound like
What is this allegation true
Are you begin to ask questions
That are part of investigating
Crime scene
True
It's not hard to imagine
The Campisi's might have made a few enemies in Egyptian society and might not have the greatest reputation in Egypt which is where you
You can start the investigative process
Herodotus is very open about where he was giving
Is information about these events which happened
About seventy-five years before
And he's writing
He says he got information from Persians and Egyptians
Will the Egyptians might not have been too happy
With can buy cease to begin with
And by the time Herodotus is talking to them
They're having problems with Persian they're not very happy and they had some revolts and
Is every reason to believe that this Egyptian sources that he use
What particularly anti Persian but secretly anti-cant Pisces
The first and sources were too which is a much harder question to answer
And why
Is the son of Cyrus
Not more highly thought of almost his own people
It's a lot of allegations against cam Pices
Use the legal terms right alleged as though the lawyers piling up the historical charges against
Alleged to have
You killed the children of those prominent Egyptians he's alleged to have lost an entire 40 or 50
1000 man army in the desert
On the way to conquer an oasis
And supposedly a sandstorm blows up berries the whole Army and they're still there
Protist organism articles I've read do not believe they're still there but it's an intriguing enough thing to
Capture the hearts of archaeologists about every 10 or so years who set out
For expeditions or start talking about the
In all likelihood of finding the lost Army of cambyses
Then supposedly
Is range and paste
He supposed to have
Attacked the people to the south of Egypt
The vile Kush the Egyptians called them once upon a time
The black African Egyptians
If you will
When people think of
The dark sub-Saharan African pharaohs
The thinking of the cushites in the cushites dominated Egypt
Cancel timeshare example around the Assyrian time. You literally had Black Pharaohs
And the culture of this area down south of Egypt with Egyptian also
Pisces didn't prepare for this and general told him you had to have him supplies he didn't care in the army star
Starving in the field
And they draw Lots the ancient sources
And you pick a lot in the guy who gets the short end of the straw one out of 10 of the Persian soldiers has to sacrifice themselves for the
Into the pot they go
I'm bringing his
Cannibalistic
Decimated Army back up to Egypt get there and see the Egyptian celebrating
Assumes that the celebration is
A celebration of his Misfortune and he starts getting crazy and
Killing priests in interrogating them
And then he does the thing that is the most sacrilegious in the
Tradition that he
Picked up a daiquiri stabbed the apis bull
If that's true there's very little
It would have upset the Egyptians more than that
The apis bull is a sacred Egyptian symbol
They are venerated
Treated with a huge amount of care and respect
It's overcame Pisces to deliberately injure or hurt it
Would have been
A huge religious transgression and shocking to the people
Love Egypt
Once Upon a Time the early investigators of this historical crime scene accepted
Can buy seeds kill the apis bull in a lot of other things falling from that not hard to see
But he's got bad press and is portrayed as insane
Prodigious
The killing of the apis bull is one of the best pieces of evidence to prove it
But the modern-day investigator the Colombo the Joe Fridays
Have more
Tools at their disposal in more information at hand than the early investigators did they might have had to rely on
Eyewitness testimony back in the day of will Durant in 1935
The Bible the 1960's and 1970's
The records were becoming available in modern-day historians could look at the equivalent of fingerprints in the blood spatter evidence and they found
Out
Through
Egyptian records
The therapist bull didn't die
Because it was chilled
Not only did it die a normal death
And was interred with the other apus Bulls from previous times
But the Persian king of kings can't Pisces
High Sparrow
Conducted all the normal sorts of religious rights in sacrament you would have expected in native-born pharaoh
To do
He behaved
Exactly as you would have expected him to if he was keeping
A continuous policy
You know the sort his father used to employee of Tolerance
And having the Persian king
Assume the legitimate mantle of the religious beliefs in the Garment of all these countries
This is part of what began
To make modern-day historians suspicious of the official story
So who was propagating the official story
Is this all based on
You know Greek writers like Herodotus
Who are all sorts of undercurrents of other things he was writing about including
You know the idea of the growth of Persian decadence and house from the greatness of Cyrus they were already beginning to
Downhill from there
2 themes of Oriental weakness and decadence an Indulgence to have continued up until the present day
Daddy
So you take everything he says with a grain of salt
But there is an influential Persian
It sort of takes a swipe at Campisi's
And adds fuel to the conspiracy fire
He says he's killed his brother
Kept it a secret
Quote
Campisi's had a brother
Bardia by name
Of the same mother in the same father is Camp by Seas
Afterwards Campisi's killed bardia
When can babies have killed bardia it did not become known to the people that party I've been killed
And quote
Those ancient allegations are more than 2500 years old
They were carved into the Rock
Face of a sacred Mountain Side
Along which the old heavily-traveled Royal Road used to run
I've always thought of it as
Kind of one of the most
Successful example
Roadside billboard ad ever
Although I don't think it was very easy
They put a garden around it and stop maybe more like a rest stop and it contained a carving showing this
Being involving human figures
And then in three different languages and their raishan
The narration is the story
Of how one of the greatest kings in the achaemenid Persian Empire probably number two
On most people
Top 10 list behind Cyrus the Great
It's hard to
Not the founder of the
Empire
Off the top job usually
But this other guy named Reyes
Or Darius the great I use both pronunciations interchangeably and for that I apologize
Hopeless sometimes
Unless this is the story of how he gets the job of King of Kings
As Told
By Darius the great himself it's an autobiography of sorts
That reason it's a little self-serving
This is the guy who by the way
Seem to have every quality you want
Interperspective
Great
Can you change except for one thing
Legitimacy
And a story that he tells on the Mountainside amongst other places
Seems to be a quest to explain to you the reader
And why he should have and deserve the top job including the normal
Soca qualifications that the God wants him to have it
Furama Mazda
Stop being the god in this
Set up a change in emphasis in religion of the Persian Empire much too complicated for me to understand
Ahura Mazda
Find them and give them all these great gifts and make some The King and I
Marching down the job
Goes into his lineage and all the blue blood that's in his veins these are standard
Justifications anyone
But then his story views
Into the weird
Weird and wonderful and conspiratorial in fantastic
What's funny about this is this is the official story
And the official story is Twisted
Thrice the great is an interesting person to get this information
Because Jiraiya's the great in our historical crime scene
Is like Colonel Mustard in the game Clue
Is a potential suspect
Because somehow
This guy who is not directly connected to the Royal Line will end up in the top job how does that happen What
What's an interesting story
And the rice the Great Cars along side of mountain to explain it to you when it starts off
With Cam by she's killing his brother and keeping it a secret
And the reason this is important
It's because apparently can't buy she's had no heirs
So what happens if the
Son of Cyrus the King of Kings were to die
Who's the only other person
Logically that you give that job to
All the other son of Cyrus right bharti
The son who got the consolation prize of Empire
You've heard that
Line services
Sons were the air Campisi's
And the spare
RTI something happens to Camp by seat return to the spare don't you
So how did Urias have the job why didn't the spare get the job will funny you should ask
Can braces kill the spare
And then he didn't tell anybody about it
And then he led the Army to conquer Egypt and Darius the Great
Serving as his Lance Bearer
Or spear-bearer which is a
An official position think Ibaka
Personal the general staff for something like 28 years old
Part of that increasing
Nasty veteran Persian army that conquered Egypt
And according to the rise while they're away
Or while they're on their way home one of the other
They get the word
That the throne has been seized by a usurper
A usurper claiming to be body
But according to Jiraiya's body it was dead
Problem of course is by not telling anyone as he says Campisi's didn't
The people didn't know the party wasn't alive anymore
Jiraiya says that the name of the Imposter on the throne
Was galmada
Origami
Annie identifies him as a majus
One of the Magi
Our modern word magician
Is related to that
And I didn't realize this until Tom Holland the historian pointed it out in this book Persian fire
But there may be a connection to the fact that this is a really sort of hard to believe story
But now it has someone who could
Be considered to have potential Supernatural powers
Involve which explains away all kinds of story holes doesn't it when you have a problem you just say listen the guy that matches
You don't know what those people can do on yeah that explains it
But after this
Dalmata seizes the throne
The Empire starts to come over to him
It's on his rock carving that
The people began to go over to this false party
You seem to be popular by the way to
I compare it to the line that's well-known among football fans that the backup quarterback is the most popular player on the team
Because you know you can invest all your hopes in that you don't know how that person would play
But you know you're not so happy with the starting quarterback and Pisces is the starting quarterback
And there were a lot of
Historians thinking that there were policies that Campisi's was apart of
For example in Egyptian priesthood
You know eliminating or reducing the power of Clan leaders in local Noble so that they could consolidated
In the central government all these sorts of pink tax policy
He may not have been too popular with a lot of people wear at this party a guy well
Who's the backup quarterback I think he played better if you just gave him the job
Sundry says he was getting a lot of support about becoming a big problem
And he's with Campisi's at the time
Erotic just tells this wonderful story again another movie scene
Where he has the representative from the new king showing up
You know in front of the army
And can't buy seeds while they're out in the field
And proclaiming in front of the army that there's a new King on the throne and that they should no longer you know he'd the orders of the very King
King who's with them
Visible
Those are great stories
And then somehow in this story in 522 BCE
Can Pisces die
And a bunch of historians will set you know suspiciously it's suspicious that we don't know
What happened to Kim Pisces
According to De Reyes on his rock carving he says he died his own death
For a while that was also translated his by his own hand which made us all think of suicide a while back but
Modern historians have pointed out
But that's probably not the right translation and that even if you use the way the Greek writer say he died
You could interpret that as by his own hand and not have it be a suicide question for example Herodotus
Says can buy Seas will die
After he jumps on his horse
And stabs himself with his sword because the tip of the Scabbard to come off
Entity
Leg wound will get infected
And he will die several days later and by the way because Herodotus has to tie the story up in a wonderful bow he says he's
Stabbed himself right at the spot on his thigh where he stabbed the apis bull in Egypt see once again
Karma this is a big, guy loud the ancient writers are they just don't call it that but you get your Just Desserts
It's right
In another Greek authors
Kale which is you know strangely similar in its own way he says Campisi's was wiggling a piece of wood with his sword
And he slipped and he cut himself on the thigh and same thing infected dies a few days later
So he died by his own hand but that's not suicidal
Don't let no one knows how he died
And there's a decent number maybe I took 20% of the historians you read
You think that the guy probably was a victim
Of assassination by his underlings one of them was
Darius the great and suspiciously the one who becomes the next
In a big chain
If you're at the Historical crime scene mr. Ryan the great guy is the one is going to get all the stuff of the murder victim
Please Colonel Mustard
He's a potential suspect here
So this whole story has to be taken with a grain of salt
Because of what happens next
According to the riots after 10 Pisces dies
He organizes what maybe you could call
The hit team
Earnest assassination Squad an oligarchy
But he will set out
To chill
This person who is impersonating the Dead Brother of cambyses
Right cuz if you believe the riots is official story
When he in his six
Assassination cohorts go out to do this deed
Both of the sons of Cyrus or dead
Tell the story as told by
Psoriasis on the Mountainside at be his phone or bisitun that's what the inscriptions called
Is in its own way dramatic enough although it's pretty bare-bones once Herodotus the screenwriter / historian gets hit
His hands on it
If it comes this wonderful Tale
Fully modern and probably the precursor to several repetitive Movie themes we've all seen a hundred times
But if that's the case Herodotus is the guy who started this
In his hands this assassination
Movies like a force 10 from Navarone type movie
And we have the Assassins the Commandos
Other working for the good guys
And can I go to this heavily-armed
Nazi Island
Take out the head of the Gestapo or something for all these guard with lots of explosions and all these things
That's a little like what the story sounded like
Herodotus says that the riot and his compatriots
Go to a fortress where they false King
The mattress is
Stang and that they get past the guards because of their lofty status in the regime right these
Pillars of the regime the aristocracy this is the oligarchy walking in
Surely there's nothing to stop at the gates and fear
Herodotus portrays the story
Force 10 from Navarone group get past the first level of Defense
And Herodotus has them
Encountering
Royal eunuchs in the courtyard these Royal Messengers he says
The Persians like a lot of the regimes in that area had a lot of eunuchs
And have a lot of debate over whether or not
They were sort of really castrated males taken is as young boys to provide
A governmental class for the Persians or weather
Castration had actually sold become symbolic by that point and it was more of a
Title it's hard to know probably the former though I tend to believe the weirdness when I can
Annie's eunuchs
Recognize that these
7 aristocratic
Knoebels are there for no good and challenge them and then a knife fighting shoes making a lot of noise in the
The courtyard and again when you're reading Herodotus at A Moment Like This try to remember
The one in history is think he was performing this live for Nadia's and if that's the case this isn't her rotten actions
It's all that's missing really are the explosions
Andaluca sound of the big score in the popcorn
And you can hear the courtyard sound effects of there's a lot of noise and Herodotus basically says that the Magi
Giant he's got two of them because why I only have one super villain in the story when you can double up
So instead of just having the Joker
In this movie he's got into the Riddler to
Two of the Magi
And they look down in the courtyard they can hear the commotion so they arm themselves
And then after the force 10 from Navarone Commandos get rid of the eunuchs
Are the running towards the stairs and you can imagine the music right right
They run up there and there's a swashbuckling fight with the two Magi and the force 10 from Navarone Commando guys
Fungi gets stabbed people directly and then again in a million times
The one principle matches the one who is the false party of the one has been sitting on the throne dressed of the king
Takes off out of the room
To be followed by a guy named Gabriel
And the soon-to-be down the road king of kings to write they take off you know after the one guy
Down the hallway through the door
Into the darkened room imagine the music
Go for your popcorn here right
And then the brightest and the false king of wrestling in the darkroom
And ariya sitting there was a sore but he's afraid to stab because he's afraid of hitting his friend and your Brian says to him parotid says
Why are you hesitating because I don't want to hit you when he's established both are you crazy
Runs in through
It only gets the bad guy
Has in his rock carving is a little bit more Bare Bones than Herodotus is about what happened
After pointing out
That the
The fake King had letter Reign of Terror
In Persia because he was wiping out anyone that could recognize that he was a faker
Do anybody know what the real body look like
He was getting rid of so he could consolidate his position and not be called out a fraud
So after explaining that the reign of terror was going on to Raya says
On his Mountain Side quote
No one dared say anything about dalmata the mattress until I came
Afterwards I pray to ahura-mazda ahura-mazda brought me Aid
In the month of Baguio dish 10 days have passed and then I with a few man slew Kalamata the
The magic and the men who were his four most followers
A fortress
Chick Alla Bosch by name and a district necio by name and Madea there I slew him
I took the kingship from him
By the favor of ahura-mazda I became king
Ahura-mazda bestowed the kingship upon me
And quote
As several historians have said
In this entire account it does look a little bit like the riots don't protest too much doesn't it
The story of how he goes from Simply being one of the Assassins to the one that actually gets the top job
Involves a horse and it's not very
Good to talk about it breakfast and it's a it's a weird story
And it makes no sense at all and there's no way anybody ever got picked to be a king that way
So it all becomes a little bit weird how the riot ends up with the throne
Here's the problem he faces
If you don't believe
The camp Isis killed his brother
Look at how this entire story changes if you the crime scene investigator when you approach it from that way
Willis historian Peter Breann says
The entire structure collapses like a house of cards
Because of Campisi's didn't kill his brother bardia what happened to Barty
This is where we get back to the game of Clue where you're examining possibilities scenarios motives
Things like that for example
Scenario number one
Is that maybe bardia
Letter Rebellion
The very thing that Cyrus the Great was so worried about when he divided his Empire worry so much about
Giving body the consolation prize to Empire and avoiding that terrible thing that happens so often in the ancient world will maybe it happened anyway
There are hints that the brothers may not have gotten along so well
Body isn't very popular at that
In a backup quarterback thing going for him
Maybe he led a rebellion in which case if cannabites he's did kill him
That wouldn't have been some slam on his historical reputation it would have been a pretty standard thing for a ruler to do
Doing probably justifiable
I think by leaving out the specifics of a Campisi's is motive
Biosource Landers him for all eternity by letting your imagination or Herodotus is Imagination fill in the blanks
Why did Campisi's kill his brother
Cuz he's insane
You know what I mean
Unless the idea that body and may have led a rebellion
With local Elites and people trying to preserve their power pushing it a different approach for the empire
Although that's very possible in which case bharatiya may have died as a usurper
In a kilobyte can buy CDs
Another possibility has to do with
No question of timing
When is bardia character took the throne right
Still alive and well
Well then that's a usurpation right he's a rebel basic
But what if he takes it after Campisi's who died
We cut ourselves we died ten days later from gangrene
Who did The Empire go to
But can't buy she's really had no errors the way the ancient author said
The Empire should go to bharatiya shouldn't it
And things get really strange when you start asking the question about
You know if this was the real body because if
Body wasn't killed by Campisi's who is it
That dries and his hit team take out
When they go
You know we kill the majus
Another false party and y'all not
Well if it's not the false party
It's the real bar
When I think of the various scenarios out there I think of our historical crime scene investigator
The showing back up at headquarters and telling their
Superior officer you know the old grey-haired
Cynical
Veteran lieutenant
The official story that they got from the crime scene that this dries character tell them yes I stab this guy dressed as the king
Do you have a name tag on it said I am bar together
Son of Cyrus but he wasn't party and I stayed the nation by killing this imposter
And the lieutenant the grizzled veteran looking at them like they're out of their mind and going
You don't really believe that crap to you let me tell you what probably happened
This derives guy killed Campisi's his King and then went and killed his brother the guy who should have been the next
King Shannon took the throne for himself case closed
Now that might have happened to
Historians just can't know there's not enough information would tell you so much about what was going on to know the facts
But it's like the ultimate Cold Case file of all time isn't it
I like the way
Historian
Marc Vandermeer kind of sums up the situation and gives you the the sense that
That it's suspicious but we don't know what happened and there's a lot of possibilities he writes quote
Our main source of information about events is the description by the final Victor
Urias
Who was not a legitimate successor to the throne
Is a count was carved in three languages
On a rock facade
Gaston
Minnesott Grouse Mountain Valley connecting babilonia and Aron
It was also spread throughout the empire
In Aramaic translation on papyrus
Impossibly Herodotus used one of these
As the basis for the story he told in his history
We have the say severely biased description
Buy a usurper
Who justifies his actions in the text
And it is not easy to determine what really happened
And quote
But because it's so important all these historians who don't like the Stray very far from the data
But because they're so little data are forced to
He gives you his best guess here
Quote
Can Pisces his prolonged stay in Egypt
Gauges brother bardia a chance to claim kingship at home
The latter abolished taxes in military levies for 3 years in order to gain popular support
Can Pisces return from Egypt
What was probably assassinated
Either by bardia or by Jiraiya
Ojai military commander who subsequently killed bardia
And quote
There are other theories
As well
Actrices zarghami in his book discovering Cyrus
Says we shouldn't be so quick to throw out the official story
He's not specifically lining up with it but he says listen if you look at a certain number of facts history has been weirder than this
Maybe there was a galmada trip maybe he was impersonating
The
Have your son of Cyrus and maybe came by she said killed
Equita final possibilities that it's probably true they can't buy seeds
Anybody about that
But eventually
The oligarchy is confronted with a king of kings who's not in his right mind
You can't exactly impeach one of those
So what's the logical alternative in the system
Going to do away with an absolute ruler at the absolute ruler has lost his mind
Maybe in this case
Psoriasis
Send
You know the rest of the aristocracy was simply doing
The Logical Common Sense thing in that situation who knows
To those historians who suggests that what we may have here when derailleurs comes to power some sort of an olive
Oligarchy coup
He writes
In the inscription on the side of the mountain
Quote
Dries the Kings
These are the men who at that time were there when I slew galmada the magic who called himself
Bardia
At that time these men cooperated as my followers
And he goes on to name
Specifically
F-fix co-conspirators the other members of the assassination hit team one by one
And then he says
Quote
You who shall be king hereafter
Protect well The Offspring of these men
And quote
How many descendants
Over a hundred years let's just say although the Persian Empire existed closer to 200
How many people can be The Offspring of those six original conspiratorial Force 10 from Navarone
Comrades
Descendants of
The Assassins may have ended up being
Like an oligarchy in the Persian Empire or maybe a better way to phrase it is like an oligarchy on top of
Of the already-existing oligarchy
Creme Dela creme
The descendants of the hit team
In Greek literature they will usually be referred to as the 7
One of the seven may have been the equivalent
Of having your
Place in Persian Society literally
He carved into stone
That one of the greatest
The Persian Empire ever produce
I've always seen
The 7in adario sin his six co-conspirators
A little like the initial investors
In a
Fascination related startup company
In this case a startup company devoted to
Assassinating a ruler
Taking the throne /
If that's the case and it really did put those people into apartment a different class well
That's a heck of a long-term dividend return
Paid off
Until
Basically the end of the Empire not a bad deal
Historian Peter Briand
Is one of some of the newer ones who question the entire idea behind the special class by the way
Some of the newer historians suggest that these
6 Persians that were the co-conspirators that that number might have been chosen for religious reasons
But they may be one six or more than 6 or less than 6
Also that it just so happens that these people may simply represent the powerful
Noble clans of Persia anyway
So the people that already were kind of the oligarchy in Persia
Just get their status reaffirmed
Doesn't matter which one of these
Scenarios now that explains
This weird. Between the end of Campisi's is rain at the beginning of a rain of a guy who doesn't seem to have any connection to the Royal
Family Jiraiya
Doesn't matter which one of those scenarios are true and by the way we only scratched the surface on the mini that are out there
They're all pretty darn wild and wooly all of them would make a good film
Personally I think the best one
Is this Advanced version of like the Warren Commission report the official Narrative of the riot makes the best movie
Get Herodotus to do the screenplay Oliver Stone to direct it
Make sure there's some Lucas sound I mean in
It's stuff like this that make this may be the best coup d'etat / assassination / regime-change conspiracy store
Doesn't matter which one of them turns out to be true though
By 521 BCE the end result of this guy dries is on the throne
And he's got maybe you could say a legitimacy deficit
Maybe the only thing he's like
And it causes him problems right away he's very open about this in this autobiographical account
You carved into the Mountainside
A list of all the places that rebelled against his rule
If ID says 19 battles
Year-and-a-half to three years to quell
All of the uprisings in
These places in Persia that are rebelling are some of its most
Important provinces large places right Egypt freeze at
And they're not rebelling
So that they can band together and support some sort of rival claimant to the throne because his story think there might have been a bunch of
People in the Empire the thought they had as much of a connection to the throne is this the right guy
It looks instead like they're all kind of going rogue at the same time
Like they want their independence back
They all seem to have kings that Sprout from nowhere
Better claiming royal descent from the last independent line all these places had right
And in the same way that the riots on the Mountainside inscription says that gal motto
About being bharti remember the Persians have this thing about law
Basically number one on their cultural naughty list
List at this point
It's a when he says they lied that's pretty bad
But then he goes on to say that all of these Kings and all of these provinces that have rebelled that are claiming descent
From the old royal family that used to exist there before the person showed up
Caroline
Historians refer to all these Kings at the liar King
Jiraiya's would have to go from place to place to place biting battle after battle after battle he would send his generals to go fight some of these battles
Had to conquer Babylon more than once
You'll love this one of the liar kings that pops up
Also claims to be bardiya so this would be the second bardia that shows up on the scene the zombie
Now other son of Cyrus that cannot be killed
I love the way
By The Wager is on the Mountainside inscription gives the orders to his forces to go quail these Rebellion
He says the same thing every time which probably means it
It's ritualizing somewhat but
But it's still wonderful
You know old school ancient staff
Terminology
Jesus quote
Goforth
And defeat the rebellious Army which will not call itself mine
And quote
And then is he captures these
In a rebel leader the ones who tie themselves to the old
In a royal family from long ago
He treats them all pretty darn badly sometimes they only show up in pieces the elamites
When they find out he's basically on the way they kill their own independent King themselves and send body parts to
Psoriasis
That's like saying we're sorry
But when he gets his hands on the hole
Liar King one at a time
He treats them like this this involves
One that rebelled in the DNA manfre Ortiz which is a
Greek version of a name that's famous
In MIDI in history so
Rooted in the old royal family and then
Dries got his hands on
He writes on the bisitun inscription on the Mountainside quote
Dries the king says afterwards priorities fled with a few Horseman
There is a district in Madea
Rockabye name
After that I sent an Army in Pursuit
Freddy Ortiz was seized and led to me
I cut off his nose ears and tongue
And I put out one of his eyes
At my gate he was kept bound
And all the people looked at
After that I impaled him at Fatima
And in the Fortress attic patinar I hanged the man who were his four most followers
I executed is Noble
A total of 47
I hung their heads inside it bad enough from the battlements of the 4th
And quote
He said the Persians were more tolerant
Then a lot of the early rimfires in the region
But that's graded on a curve
This is still the ancient. Where the sorts of
Treatments
Prisoners and captives and people on the other side of justice for example
More resembles the stuff that the very worst of the terrorist in our world today do
That's often part of the legal codes of these early societies
Yunnan fascinated by the
Streams of The Human Experience
When you go far back in time you see them everywhere
I mean I was reading for example
The process by which impalement as an execution is carried out in some places and sometimes
I think in our heads we just think there's a sharpened stake sticking out of the ground you throw the victim up
They land on the steak impalement. No muss no fuss well
Basically
But instead I'm reading about
You know a whole thing with a
They use a razor blade in advance and some of these places they would then put something on to stop the bleeding
Fix you up a little bit so it went the way they wanted
Greasing the the
Steak and mean things that just you
Doesn't make any sense to the modern mind you think about the people who did this
And you think that they almost sound like a different species don't they
But they're not
The little newborn baby out of a modern hospital
40 minute time machine
Send them back to
Ancient Persia hand them off to a childless couple there and
Go back in 20 years to check on how the modern kids doing being raised in the world
And it'd probably be able to explain to you the logical common-sense moral rationale behind impaling people
They might even explain to you that they enjoy watching it
Times change of course but
We human beings are an interesting species aren't we
None-the-less is horrifying as all that sounds
When you grade the Persians on a curve
They still come out as a rather lenient people by the standards of the place and time
The way that dries handles
The many revolts and uprisings in the need to placate whole areas and put in new structures
Choosing to keep fires from breaking out again
Is a foreshadowing of what's to come
It comes to the ability
I'm disfigured araya's who will eventually be
Be called the Great
Is gifts though
Our little bit unusual
The kings of Kings heads-of-state especially
If in the Persian tradition where they're always thought to be like Warriors like Cyrus the Great these
Little leaders on Horseback continually pushing the Empire the head of their troops
Dries is a little bit more
Like a
A white-collar worker like a desk job.
Herodotus says the Persians
Had a saying
And he said that Cyrus was the father
Can Pisces the tire
Andreas
The shop
Which if you believe what people like Herodotus of written about
The Persians and a lot of aristocratic people have felt this way over time
They sort of disdain
Des
Rather
A lower class by their standards things like mercantilism getting your hands dirty with money business,
Of course
In the modern United States in much of the world
Well that's maybe the most
It highly thought of profession and in a way shopkeeper
Which sounds a little like a
Master ayaz
If you think about the size of the shop to riots was running he was running Walmart
And we don't call those people shopkeepers we call them CEOs
And when you look at the riot that's what he looks like
A modern CEO
Which does make you wonder
Again about how we get the job because he seemed so suited to it
You can't help but think he's some sort of process of natural selection in which part of his cast mean we were only choose
Oozing from the aristocracy
But that's a heck of a bigger talent pool than trying to choose from
Two sons of Cyrus
Isn't that always the problem with monarchy right
Such a small talent pool to pick from in some countries you have to pick the oldest son and then there's no chance at all that's just a roll of the dice
The rise may have been the most capable amongst
You know the
Nobility of Persia because he seems
Exactly what the Empire needs this time
He is overly concerned with money is sort of The Stereotype he thinks about profit
And loss and he's an administrator
And a person who organizes today we would think of him as a consultant who comes in and streamlines operations
I mean he's credited for example with starting the sad traps in the satrapi's which probably isn't true
Probably didn't start it
Organized
The Empire instead of a lasting way
He would handle things
Sometimes in a very cut-throat manner sometimes in a very Innovative manner
And another way Jenna in a very Deft manner with his options
Clever is what they would say about him in some of the histories I've read when they wanted to be nice
But that could swing over into conniving you know what when the pendulum move too far
Different directions
You think about a guy like Steve Jobs Maybe
Or some of those CEOs not the ones you just go collect a paycheck of the ones who get paid 123 million in
Cotton house since I've been here
You think about the people who really
You have something to them Hugo okay I mean I like this guy or I may love this guy
But you can see that there's some genius there and sometimes the genius is in things
The maybe some kind of Monday Monday you know I mean
Strait of 1
But when they're working their wonder sometimes
The benefits are incredible and when you look at Jiraiya's and how he
Took the Persian Empire essential you could call it a startup company at the beginning
This is when it goes public and arises when it gets its first really high-level CEO
Who takes it to the next level there's a lot that have to be done to make that happen
A lot of people in the Empire might not have liked it very much
Which is another reason you have
19 battles you have to fight sometimes to Quail all the fires that are springing up
But the difference between the empire
When this guy takes over
And how he leaves it is profound
There's a reason a guy comes out of nowhere in terms of his Royal lineage
Ends up probably number two
On the greatest
Achaemenid Persian kings of all time
Is a highly energetic highly competent
Long-ruling
Figure
Who becomes important
In the story as far as westerners have been concerned for more than 2000 years
Because he is the one that starts mixing it up with the Greeks
And supposedly when I was growing up Western Civilization considered the Greeks the home team
This story is kind of a
Chance to highlight things
From the visiting team's point of view in the battle for Western Civilization
Of course as we point out early
That's pretty hard to do when you were working mostly with the equivalent of the home team's newspapers
And the way we structured the story is to just do
Every King in the achaemenid Empire one after another in order a sort of the structure of the show but
So far we've been dealing with kings that are so important
And the sources
Especially the hometown newspapers
Western Civilization are so
You're full of
Things involving them that we've been able to go into the mid loving detail there will be whole kings that we will almost fast forward
And it isn't because they didn't do anything is because if they didn't do anything to wear with the Greeks we don't know a lot about them
You do have is mostly with archaeological evidence can show you and things like that so they will be kings that might have done a bunch of things
Interesting over off in India are up in modern-day Afghanistan
Theory around southern Egypt today who knows
If the Greek sources didn't write about it sometimes we don't know about it then which case
Some of these things are going to get short shrift indeed
Cyrus can buy cedar isvs are some of the heavyweights in the achaemenid
Empire and like a lot of Empires
Their leadership is soda front-loaded
Which is why it does so well for a while if you can tie
Competent
Oar inspired
Leadership to in the Good Fortune of an Empire well at this point the Persian Empires on the upswing
And Leadership is a large part of it
And the rice is
Perhaps in terms of a total competency overall maybe The Best Day Ever Had
He concerns himself with the boring
Side of government
Things like a monetary policy
He's very famous for example for instituting
Maybe the first
Metal coinage in the region outside of
Lydia which is famous for having started metal coinage
Certainly in that region
The gold coins will be called Derek's after him
Shackles will be the silver coin
And the Persian
Gold and mm the wealth of the Empire will become an absolutely
Hallmark Elementary
They're known for having a lot of money
And they use it
And of course there's nothing using bribes and money is a foreign policy tool and all that sort of stuff nothing
That that goes back
Time immemorial
And during the. We're talking about here maybe only the Chinese though
Are doing it on a comparable level
To what the achaemenid Persian Empire is doing
And some of this plays into this CEO style of dries two things
Truly weight on a profit-and-loss
Criteria and if
In a weekend
Solve this military problem without having to fight a war let's do it that way
He's concerned for exam you can tell he's considering like all Persian kings with the status of the office and protecting the reputation
And all those kinds of things
But you know I mean if there's something that comes up where we can talk about some sort of
I totally closed minded their Empires that have come around
Have much more of a machismo to them where we don't know
What do you mean deal do what I say or else where is the Persians are kind of perennial
Open for business
If you will
I like and let's be honest there could be some ritual ization to this what I like
What dries himself has card
On his
He's buried on Mountainside eventually he'll have a carving so they've been know what he decided he wanted on his tomb
Any emphasize food of the
The thinking man's approach to running an Empire
Psoriasis says quote
I am not hot-tempered
What things develop in my anger I hold firmly under control by my thinking power
I am firmly ruled over my own impulses
I have a strong body
As a soldier I'm a good soldier
I see who will rebell and who will not
First I will think
Then I will I
And quote
There's an ancient line that money is the sinew of War
And the Persians were not dominant militarily at everything and in the areas where they lack something
The ability to come up with a ton of cash as needed
Could compensate for a lot of those shortcomings and believe me a guy like the Rye has understood that better than anyone
Historian Pierre brillant runs down
Psoriasis qualities a bit and then
Point out how
How much of a change to. It's getting nausea rates in Persian history is
He says in a chapter subheading entitled a new foundation for the empire
Quote
The ways and means adario secession to power
To the extent that we can reconstruct them
Our Testimony to the new Kings energy indecisiveness
Urias was undeniably an exceptional personality
But he also proved to have organizational ability
During the same time that he was reorganizing the entire tribute system
Other projects were carried out in various regions
Construction of new capital
The conquest of Samos
Expeditions from the Indus to the Nile
In the year 518 he also commissioned the satrap ariani's to gather Egyptian sages tackle
Like the quote and quote Egyptian laws
Other measures affecting Jerusalem were affected at the same time
What is striking he writes
Is the care with which the king plan for the long-term
And quote
And discussing the era that he inaugurates
Do do his
Energetic efforts to
Create a support system long-term for something
Brianna rights quote
Without in the least deprecating the work accomplished by his predecessors
We made us a certain that the Advent of dries marks the foundation of a new Diagnostic and Imperial order
In this regard the first years of his Reign definitely represented decisive. In history
And quote
One of the revisions to the
Structure of things that dries works out
Is the succession
We tried to create the conditions so that
The way he came to power will never happen again
One of the first things he did this is a traditional thing by the way to do after a coup
For toppling middle of regime in the Middle East you want to marry into the previous royal family cuz remember this is all about some genetic
Blue blood
Even if it came as a bad guy or the regime is is is over throwable and it would be a good thing doesn't mean you don't
Don't want that blue blood in your lineage you can go back to like
You know pulling the sword out of the stone Type legendary beginning you want to have that in your bloodline
Tareas takes care to marry two daughters of Cyrus the Great and his granddaughter
Some of these the previous wives of Camp by Seas by the way
So anyway I think it's like the Ford Motor Corporation and Henry Ford the big founder maybe he's like Cyrus the Great
And then
You know Henry Ford's son takes over the company
Heaven by hooker by crook Colonel Mustard May intervene who knows
All of a sudden you have this guy who wasn't in the family tree not the direct one anyway maybe a second cousin or something and
He's running the Ford company and then all the sudden he marries
You know the daughters and granddaughter of Henry Ford
Maybe one of these was married to Henry Ford son who knows but eventually
You know some guy from outside the direct line of the Ford family is running Ford Motor Company
Here's the thing though
He may not be a member of the Ford family
But his kids will be
So that's how you tie yourself back in the
Early Royal Line statues
No hide your tracks a little bit too in your building project historians
I'm starting to think that they seem more and more
That the entire lineage of Darius connecting him to the great Cyrus of old
May have been sort of forged in Reverse reverse legitimacy as we called it earlier
Once again smart
Jiraiya's becomes the king
That expands Persian Authority more to the east of the Empire which is
Which is territory that because the Greeks didn't know much about
You don't hear much about you know that it happens though because soon you'll have set traps in the East that are
Indian
Essentially what what's now modern-day Pakistan is the part of India that the Persians conquered one way or another
And as far as the ancient Greeks were concerned that was like the end of the known world I didn't know about anything maybe that existed past that that could
Baby dragons unicorns
Or no hostile barbarians as far as the eye could see maybe the Persians do but they weren't
Telling Herodotus
Dries will do some more conquests
You know in northeastern
Africa Empire goes from these
Amazingness
You know healthy growth rate with the Empire's expanding nicely thank you very much but not so fast that we can incorporate everything nice
And absorb everything
Appears to be the inevitable long-term outcome of things if you're looking at a map of this region
Yunnan 515-514-5513 BCE
Because the Persian Empire looks like
You know the 1950s horror movie blob
Slowly
You know advancing in all directions and spreading out and just you know naturally absorbing everything on the fringes
And while there are certainly natural limitations and Empire could run into
Might reach the limits of communication for example
Or run into climate
And environmental things you can't deal with I mean I'm sure the Persian army this. Can defeat the Indian army in the Interiors of
India but can you deal with the jungles in these snakes in the weather and all that
Ask Alexander in a couple of hundred years how much of an impediment going to be
Can you deal with Transportation questions
Of course revolts are always a threat especially the larger you get
But who's going to act as any kind of a military counterforce
To the great king
And the Persians as things stand
You know around 5:15 5:14 BCE
Look at the map who's there
There's no one to have World War 3 with
The Chinese
Play me a fun fantasy matchup with their on the other side of the world in their own little civilizational bubble
If at all aware of the Persians simply probably through
You know some traders who actually make the long journey but who knows
So those armies aren't fighting
So who is going to stop the blob from taking over literally everything until they reach their natural limits
Well that's what makes this story so compelling
That's what sets it up
For the movie The Rocket is going to give you
When he explains to you how
You know this David will beat this Goliath
How someone will stop the blob
And by the way there by save everyone
Like so many other people
Who been interested in the Persian army
Open this.
I became interested in them because I was interested in the Greeks
And the Persians are the Uber adversary the arch-nemesis right of the Greeks from the in a class
Classical era
After while
Can you become a little curious about these people that
You know the classical authors mostly portray but you know you even get this up until the modern time
As soon as zombies Orcs
The only are formidable because of their numbers but their numbers are so huge that they're massively formidable
Regions of them
The drink Rivers dry there are so many of them
Can you become
Kind of curious about these people
You know once you get past these numbers after a while and once you get into it
The Persians become so fascinating
Because they're the final installment
Of the ancient military system of the near East
The final development
And it doesn't really mean the Apex of its development because it's possible that that happened during the Syrian times
But the last of the armies fielded
On principles that were developed in Sumeria
And nurtured by people like the Assyrians the Babylonians
Fordham
Characters to a 2500 year-old military tradition
What historian Nigel tala says
And once you get rid of the very large numbers at the classical authors give you turning them into Orcs
You realize how good they must have been at what they did
I mean if there weren't millions of them
Look how nasty the smaller numbers of the more
Look what they did look what they conquered
If you believe the ancient authors here thinking well of course they conquered all of them there were millions of them swarmed over the Defenders
If they weren't millions of them if they were
Roughly equal numbers
Then all of a sudden the fighting quality of these Persian armies which it always assumed to be relatively low
It's increased
Buy a lot and in the quality begins to look like the kind of quality you would have to have to win an Empire like this
And hold it
I told you in the first part of the story when we were talking about Cyrus the Great
He was doing all these Conquest with his army we kept talking about his army but we couldn't really discuss what that Army was like
Is it a really no
The shame to cos that's an army worth knowing about right look what that did
The by the time of Urias the Greatsword of the Mist
Heart a little bit
And give you a look into the military organization and the equipment and whatnot
Of the achaemenid Persian Empire and I don't know if you could say it's the height of military development but they're still fighting it
Very high level
They are a veteran Army that fight a lot
So they have a lot of actual practical real-world experience
And the Army is relatively unbeaten they have set back here or there sometimes but by and large
Are the places they want to conquer they come
Good luck they'll getting any agreement among the modern-day historians concerning
Exactly how they did this
Because just because they've
You know done away with those crazy numbers from the ancient source is the 2 million men type things
Doesn't mean that they figured out any better ones automatically that everyone agrees upon
The numbers that the Persian armies brought to the battlefield not the entire number available to the Empire thing
Mustard everybody but these battles that are famous that involved the Persian army how many men were there
Will you see that it ranges from a low
I would like 12 to 15,000 men
And a high of like 250 or 300 thousand men
You begin to see what huge difference
Any of these different peoples have on how this Army operated just to give you one example
It's well-known
The dacor you would call them maybe guard
Today existed in this Army
10 to 12 thousand men strong
Corporate the extra super Royal Guards
And at these troops were Superior in general to most of the other troops on the body
They were what you would call today regular
They may have Benadryl
Write the best troops in the army
If your army is three hundred thousand men
And 10 to 12 thousand of them are these guys
Well you might not even be able to call them the tip of the spear in an army that large they may just be the king
If on the other hand these armies are closer to twenty-five or thirty thousand men strong in reality
Well then a guard of 10 to 12,000 regular drilled troops
Is 1/3 to 1/2 your entire Army that's a huge difference in a much better Army
So right there that would impact
You know the impression of how these armies did what they did
I will say
That is a fan of the Persian army it's been wonderful over the last
20-25 years
To really see
A more modern view of how the Army fought in was organized
Crystallize
Very exciting and this could change by the way down the road I mean this is just the
Latest interpretation of the evidence
It should also be pointed out that when I talk about the Persian army
This is an Empire that stretched over 200 years the Army will change and evolve
And and become different
You know from the start of the Empire to the end of the empire
We are freeze framing a moment in time here but it's a moment that according
To the Greek source is pretty much determined whether or not Western Civilization would continue
So what's worth focusing on
It's also worth focusing on because
The majority of historians for more than 2000 years
Pinpoint the reason that history went the way it did
Down to a question of Weapons Systems
On the battlefield and how they interacted
Estranged is that sound by Nova
Because we normally think of
The things that impact history is being either massive soda forces like
Industrialization mixing with colonization mixing with a newly unified a very nationalistic
I want to see if you got the Boom
Your history changing right
Maybe it's the
Extraordinary individual comes along at just the right time and we going to catch a few breaks here there
Lumia djingis Khan or Julius Caesar
Oliver Cromwell
Tecumseh
And most of the time obviously it's a combination of things
Extraordinary individual showing up just at the time the colonization you know is going away is going in Germany needs its Place in the Sun
Write all those things working together booty of historical moment
Put another one of those areas
We're history can turn
She's almost banal by comparison but he can come down to the simple question of
Weapons system
It's on the battlefield
Remember in this era were talking about
The battlefield is like
In a 2500 yard long maybe just on average
And the decision Point happens in a couple of hours or an afternoon
And it can be determined by something
You know if you go back to weld the majority of historians even now probably but certainly the way Herodotus ought to a question
Something like
Whether or not you're armed with a spear
Horrible
Or whether or not your weapon system includes a lot of body armor
Or doesn't
And if you think that's a little kooky
Well if you think about
One side having
Firearms
And the other side not
You can see what a difference a weapon system differential could make to an outcome of a battle
I don't have to convince you do I let the way battles and Wars turn out
You have a huge impact on the way history goes right imagine if you lost the Second World War
Some great many historians
For more than 2000 years have boiled down to why things happen the way they happened
2 question of how armies
Interacting with each other Greek armies in Persian army so you have to understand the Persian army that's going to go into these conflicts with the Greek.
Understand what happened
If those historians are right
The first thing to understand is that the Persian army
In a 2-2 we ancient history wargamers and I know you're out there
To watch this is the Army you get when you like a lot of Beaufort
I mean like machine gun level both
Buddy of mine once said that you could just directly justify giving every single person in the army during this time. Of Bowie
If you want to
But how many arrows does it take
To blot out the Sun
During his
Story of The Last Stand of the 300 Spartan
Remember those Clint Eastwood types in bronze
Herodotus tells a story of a local person who goes up to one of the Spartans and says
You know that the Persian archers are so numerous that when they shoot their arrows they hide the Sun
Famous One
Liner to comes back another bravado from the shore to die Spartan was something to the effect of
To be great be
Because then we can fight in the shade
But it's indicative of what this
Persian army was known for archery
I need it hyperbole to suggest that they could blot out the sun with it
Don't you wish you had video
I wanted these ancient battle to get some idea
What we're talking about here in the capabilities
I've said many times that if I ever get that time machine I want to be
Transported into a hot air balloon floating about a hundred feet over one of these ancient Battlefield so I can see
You know what's going on I'll answer 100 questions in about a minute-and-a-half as soon as I can just visualize there's no video
It'd be very gory and awful if there were
But I look at it just to try to get a picture of what we're talking about here
We haven't done this in so long nobody knows what it was like
The same thing when I was studying
Western sword fighting type
Nobody knows that either everybody trying to recreate
How people did Medieval sword fighting with a long story based on still
Two-dimensional images from books
Because no one kept alive the artform say the way the Japanese did with their sword fighting techniques right that the
Alive and well
But nobody knows for sure
Even with some pretty darn good Recreations out there
A western sword fighting did you don't do something for a while
You don't have video of it yet
You lose the ability to understand it totally
Same thing with these ancient battles right
Often times these ancient authors that you would use as your
Your best pieces of evidence to explain and color eyes would it all look like
Leave out the most important parts of the story cuz to them it's just known stop right
Explain the most basic stuff to you everybody understands what happens when for example two blocks of human being
Thousand
Oh no I don't know what happened there and either do historians and if I was in my hot air balloon a hundred feet over the battlefield I would finally be able
Answer the question
Do those blocks are human beings actually run into each other
And go face-to-face tooth to tooth toe-to-toe in a claustrophobic horrible scrum
You know where people are so cramped together they can hardly use their weapons in the people in the front row
Are being squished to death by the people in the back and then pushed to their adversaries is that how it goes
Or is it more like other historians have theorized
We're at the last second there's something
Inherent in human beings were they want for themselves on the weapons of their enemies and they stopped with a 4 and 8
Gap
Between the two blocks of human beings are no man's land
If you will
Were there stabbing and throwing stuff across the Gap in Champions
Running out from each side and challenging each other in the no-man's-land in
Other brave people are running across to the other side and grabbing somebody out of the ranks and pulling them back to their side is that how it was
There's other historians who split the difference
And say that the units run into each other for a second and then you know over the first minute and a half or two minutes or whatever slowly pulled
Back from each other creating
Dead space in the middle
But nobody knows nobody knows if Cavalry will charge infantry or under what conditions
I mean it's just stuff
It's still debated by the experts because how would we know
You could do some mathematics though if you're not terrible at math and I'm
Not that good but I was able to handle
Round numbers like this
To try to get an idea certain capability
One of the wonderful things
About Ancient Warfare is that even if you can't know what it was like
You can understand
That there are certain realities to a physical laws if you will let's call it the physics of the battlefield in
Pre gunpowder times
There are limited by
In a certain Bedrock elements that don't change
Human beings for example
Horses other flesh-and-blood creatures like camels and elephants that are often used in battle
There's a limit to human endurance there's a limit to human morale there's a limit to muscle power
And those sorts of
Constraints
We're operating
In the armies of the Pharaoh in ancient Egypt
All the way to the armies of Richard II the lionheart you know in the holy land during the Crusades
There's something about
In a battle over the air is until gunpowder takes over
We're commanders from different eras could have commanded armies
From other areas and not been
2 deep out of the water
For them to understand
You know what they were dealing with custard and elements didn't change
When you're talking about
The sorts of armies that these great States through against each other they generally included
You know close-order infantry as a sort of the rock around which you built your arm
The battle line you would say in some.
A good estimate for a
Traditional set-piece battle with a Persian army might be a 2500 or 3000 yard or meter
Think about unicorn T5 or 30 football fields long
And
A solid line of man across a ton of that space
The battle line was generally makeup maybe if you wanted to just get it off the top of your head estimate a 7275
Avi charmi side is made up of these
Phalanx has
Units of men patch shoulder-to-shoulder next to each other
And keeping that pack nature things staying together and then multiple ranks behind
The rank death changed and if you had four ranks behind you that's pretty shallow formation
In the Hellenistic period
You'll get some Hellenistic Phalanx is little go 72 Mandeep
The armies of this periods near East tended to be organized a simile
So the smallest unit would be 10 men
Turn up to a hundred and a thousand were told the Persians had 10,000 man units
The Tweak that the Persians are supposed to have made Modern historians think to the age-old formations of the Assyrians in the Bible
Have to do with how many ranks of archers they have versus how many ranks of Spearman
Story Nigel chalice is one of many who points out that the Assyrians thought and the Babylonians
Copied them
That you needed to have half of your
Units ready for hand-to-hand combat
And the other half could be armed with missile weapon
That's what they would do is pack the front half of the unit with the Spearman
It was a big spear heavy
Big Shield
How many if you could an armored if you could
And so if you had a formation that was
8-ranked deep the first four in the Syrian Army would use to get a hand-to-hand combat guys the rear for The Archers
And The Archers would shoot over the head of the Spearman
Pretty very flexible formation
Any enemy that won't come to grips with you you can strike from a distance
Any enemy you want to advance on and close with you can weaken before your spearmint have to engage in hand-to-hand combat
Anyone who just sits there you can shoot for a while
And anyone who comes at your unit
You can kill on the way in making an easier job for your spearmint when they finally get to you
Historians think that the Persians tweaked that formation by taking out most of the ranks of close-order Infantry
Spearman
And replacing them with archers often archers with little or no armor
I know she'll
Most of these Persian units
Are going to have a front rank of Speer armed
Shielded
Often armor but not always
Infantry that protect the archers behind them
They have a shield that's made of wicker but that looks like a boogie board for you Americans of almost a man size
Size tall wicker plant
Hot Square
And it looks like when all the front rank decided to close together those things are going to fit together like a perfect wall
Imagine in a 70 to 75% of your 2500 to 3000 yard front
Has a wall of wicker
Shields in front of it protecting
New your archers from any missile fire back
But your Rogers AR shooting over the heads of the troop and just blowing people away so I did some calculations
Assuming loan numbers
And every step
Imagine of 50,000 man Persian army which would be alone number believe it or not
Imagine that
In that battle line that the Persians have probably increased the Firepower over Syrian versions by
In a 20 or 30% more
Imagine that twenty thousand archers are in that main battle line
Each Archer fires about Five Arrows a minute
And their Quivers carry 120 but just for the sake of argument will say that they're not
I will give them all a hundred arrows each
That means that across that battle line
When these troops were sitting behind the wall of wicker Shields are shooting
If shooting a hundred
Thousand arrows a minute
From the main battle line
Distance of about
200 yards in front of the
Army beyond that they can shoot
But effective range is 175 to 200 yards
They can keep up this fire
For as long as their muscles will hold out or
Until their arrows run out which at that rate would be after about 20 minutes of shooting
And after 20 minutes of shooting they would have fired
2 million arrows
Now
Infantry with armor
Might be able to withstand that
But if you run a horse in front of that crowd
Your dad
Pure driving a chariot
You're gone you don't get anywhere near the battle line right you're blowing away at a distance
That's a great sort of military change that they made over the Assyrians if you're fighting the kind of enemies
Improve those Assyrian formations
Unless of course enemy
Hand to hand combat troops
Finally get to you
Here's the way historian Nigel Talent talks about
You know this change the Persians did the Tweet the traditional Assyrian formation quote
It is likely that the battle array of this kind would be highly effective when facing the large mounted forces no
At least the second millennium BC
The horse is a large and vulnerable Target for archery
Well equipped infantry is less vulnerable
As the Persians worded discover
It is probable that achaemenid formations follow the elamites tradition of maximizing the number of archers in the in
Infantry units
Unlike the Assyrians who seem to have maintained a 50/50 ratio of archers to shielded Spearman
And quote
I know it's tempting to think of all this as minutiae right war game
But if the majority of historians are more than two Millennia are right
This is the kind of minutiae that determines why these battles were about to go the way they do
Now
Whereas the majority of the Persians in this time. Or going to be in that battle line we just talked about
You're also going to have some Cavalry in the Persian take brake caliper
I've often thought of the Persian army in this period
As a moor
For lack of a better word
Barbara raised version of the Assyrian army at its height
They often compared to like ancient Rome if you look at the Roman Empire at their height
It's so tempting to see them almost as like
The Nazi Germany are aware they're all marching in almost lockstep goose-step formation with intricate precision
Immaculate drill
You know everybody's sleeping in the barracks everyone professional in the whole thing
And then I think of the Roman Empire a couple hundred years later where the Army is lost
Some of that
Spit in Polish
And instead of having everybody or the majority of troops you know what the top being Roman you have
You know some
Barbarian
Call them tribal peoples more
Aristocratic I mean hands delbrook calls the Persians
From this. The calvary Knights
So imagine
You are more barbarize version of the Roman Empire's Army
With Norman's
And maybe that's a little like what the Persians are I think the Persians could give the Assyrians a run for their money but they're
There's not as much spit in Polish
And there is more
Aristocratic tribal nobility
But the Cavalry can fight like hell and there's a lot of them
They fight a little bit like these Gideon's in the Huns in the Mongols and those people that shoot you
In a from a distance in small units with bows
Generally thought that the big unit of Cavalry would go over
2 near where it wants to attack
Stay at a distance and then send out subunits smaller Squadron
Food then go up to where they want to attack unleash all their javelins and arrows until they're out
Right back to the main body and then another smaller Squadron comes and repeat the process until
The unit that they're firing at begins to get all disorganized
Or their morale brakes
Or they become so weekend
That there
Easy prey for the
Persian infantry once they run out of their 2000000 missiles or however many it is to come in mop-up
And of course once an army broke
Starting to run away
All that Persian Cavalry becomes absolutely leaf
They do nothing better
Cow breathing running down fleeing
Rotting fruit
How does Calvary was one of the most feared elements
Of the Persian army and it worked in conjunction with the Infantry in fact
It's tempting to make a case that the Persians might have rationalized
Getting rid of all those close combat troops and replacing them with archers by suggesting that
Their overwhelming calorie could make up for the difference and their battle system required
Combining what's a Cavalry was probably doing on the flash with what the Infantry was doing in front and close cooperation with created
Lethal combined-arms
Reproach
Wentworth
The Persians also had those guard units we talked about they were called The Immortals
Also called the attendance of the attendees
Probably armored
May have fought in a similar way to the rest of the normal troops but just at a higher quality level
Also the Persians use mercenaries and hired them more and more by the way as the Empire went on
And lastly
The Empire could Levy
Troops from its own Empire which is what it did with the main Force the main forces are Persian and Madeon and elamites
And the troops from the center of the Empire but they had all these provinces stretching from
Modern-day Pakistan
Two modern-day Libya up all the way to Afghanistan and down all the way to like practically Saudi Arabia
The huge territory naked Levy troops or the entire thing
And when you read your Herodotus by the way
He says that at least nominal units from all those different people
And Herodotus runs down more than 40 of them you know when he runs down the Persian army
Seattle these people we just talked about then you have all the Exotic people from the periphery of the Persian Empire
Herodotus
Talked about the Indian troops that are in the army
He talks about the troops or Africa who will paint half their body white and have their body red and tip their Spears with antelope
P*** black troops are modern-day
Sudan
You talk about what he calls the black Ethiopians from India which modern historians think you're probably dravidians because they are
They're dark but they have straight hair and horsehair helmets
I mean it's a wonderful exotic list and historians think
Depart of what the Persians were doing
Is showing the flag a little bit to these people that they were fighting basically saying
Look at the rec
And scope of the people we can draw from this is how big our Empire is that we Encompass all these groups in your singing just a small
Small number of them imagine how many are back at home that we could call on
If we needed them
Historians are unsure
How much does
Troops played a role in a typical set-piece battle
But it just kind of shows the
Width and breadth of the
Persian
King of Kings ability to call on troops
And sometimes because of your specific skill you know I need this done call of the Ethiopians
Mean for example.
In a Persian get the greatest Navy in the world like overnight
When they take over the Phoenician cities
They're on the coast
They essentially I would say subcontract but there's no
Choice in the deal it's like
You know the CEO Darius of Persia core announces the acquisition of The Phoenician Navy
And now the Phoenician Navy is a division of Persian War
Something like that
But that's how they are with everything right we take over the local institutions
And we let you do things your way as much as possible I mean part of the fun of of running a Persian Army in ancient
Was it all these troops got to fight
In their own local Style again that was sort of a subsidiary
Of the Persians letting you do things your way it kind of go up to you
According to the way we used to think anyway and say
What is it to do while while we're very good at spear-throwing okay why don't you do that for us
You'll be just like the Phoenicians maybe they're really good on the water
According to
History of lies and b-list the Persian army is real strong point and they're also it Above the Tie
He lists intelligence as something they do wonderfully you know reconnaissant sending out diplomats and spies
And Merchants who report back and they usually know quite a bit about the territories around them
Besides diplomatic Warfare as his number two thing that he says the Persians have a huge advantage in
As we've been saying that kind of always ready to make a deal measure the profit loss and all that kind of thing
And if you weren't so willing to make a deal
You know when the Persian army was a long way way they send diplomats with the army so that
They just check back with you to make sure you're sure on that deal decision
You know when they have 3050 a hundred thousand men with them armed
Abilene
Ivan B says meticulous planning was one of your strong suits in a you would think that is inheritors of the whole mess
Tradition
Greatest record-keepers in the Ancient World ride the Babylonians and Sumerians and all those people
You think that you inherited the ability that
Can handle that sort of thing will keep your records keep your books and
Be organized
But that actually played into how far away from the Homeland you could move your armies
Because if you weren't a meticulous planner those armies starve when they get a certain distance away
Every Army is constrained by sort of a range of motion by how well you can supply it
And this year fact that what we call the greek and Persian Wars will happen in Greece
Shows you in a how good the person planning was
Make a projector power along way
And finally laughing B says that they had an engineering expertise that he says was quote of a high order and
Basically
The Greeks were
Blown Away by the Persian ability to bridge rivers to dig canals
To knock down walls in this is really cute when you think about it we've been comparing the Persian
You know approach and conquest of territory and expansion to The Blob
Lava
They just kind of you know when they have to reconquer territories they just so to go in there
And one after another slowly but surely knocked down reliably knock down the walls of the city take it
Yuan to the next city
It is a very business-like approach to the whole thing
And if you weren't good at that
You would've been able to do with the Persians did too many cities had walls and that was such a huge part of
Conquest
As I said before I would love to see what this all
Look like actually in battle actually go watch by the way
You know some of the worst riots you've ever seen that are on the internet and everything because you'll see often times police
Who have big field that are like the Romans
And it kind of packed into formations and you'll see the Riders on the other side and flinging things and
An attacking sometimes and sometimes Cavalry comes into what you think yourself okay
It is not really apples and apples at all but they're certain we get back to the physics of the battlefield element
It make me think okay maybe this is a little what it's like look at how those two bodies of people move when they get close to each other what happens when a horse
Cinders the picture
I mean maybe you can just get the tiniest taste of what the physics
A bottle
Did everybody up until the time. The gunpowder took over would have known instinctively
What's your experience
Worship leader common knowledge
According to ancient Greek authors the Greeks had especially before
You know the big tangle happened
A healthy respect a very healthy respect
For the great Kings armies and capabilities
As we said
Up until this time this is an army that basically win
But then sometime between 5:15 and 5:10 BCE
Jiraiya's decides to give this Army one of those tests
That are so difficult it would be a surprise if they didn't fail
Many great armies over history of fail a similar test by the way
He decides to go invade
The land
Occupied
Are the Central Asian nomads
And becomes just another one of those
Little leaders over time
Who found out the people who live on the wide-open expenses of the steppe weather in ancient time
Or
20th century versions of them
Have the option of Simply retreating into the interior
And then you have to follow them
Ask Napoleon how well that can work
And that was in an era by the way Napoleon's time when there were cities and things that could be burned down and taken
The secret weapon of these people to rise tries to conquer
Is it there's nothing to conquer
The Nomad there are no cities there are no Urban centers and how do you with your fantastic Army deal with them
Is there strategy to deal with you
It's just simply retreat in front of you and keep going and going and going while your supply lines get longer and longer and longer
Cuz guess what
You aren't
Central Asian tribal nomadic horse archers
And you can't just apply a huge Army whatever that means with lots of infantry and horses and camels and all sorts of
The things endlessly
On a wild goose chase or in this case
Awhile Centaur Chase
Now there are two reasons why this gets a ton of historical attention because dries it actually had to quell a revolt against
Central Asian people right when he came to power
Biscuits a ton of attention though
Herodotus makes it a key scene
In his narrative so when he's giving his performance
And another opportunity to emphasize the wonderful
Colorful nature of the Skitty into one of his favorite subjects and let's be honest one of mine too
Cuz if you're trying to entertain people these people are the color brilliant historical color and fearsome
Full of all sorts of exotic customs
They play the same role
His story that Native Americans play in the old dime novel westerns right
And there's a similar feel by the way mean Americans would recognize a lot of the same things
Because tribal people share certain qualities in the same way for example
That tribes would band together in the confederations in the Americas and we've always considered them fairly or otherwise to be
The next level in state development when you go from Individual tribes confederacy's banding together into Super tribe
I would like the Iroquois Confederation
Well they did this in
This entire world of the Central Asian Nomads and so the tribes that we actually know the names of our infect confederations of
Many tribes
And it's a hard enough Army to try to deal with
When the Central Asian the Barbarian nomadic people from the step that's the traditional
We would say today probably racist
A culturally need is Centerfield they can move the million name to describe how the Herodotus is views of The Barbarians are
But it's one thing to try to deal with them when they break into your territory that's hard enough
Trying to deal with them in their territory
Let's put it this way won't be too long
You're down in the history where makedonian armies from the. Of Alexander the Great or leaving their bones
You know on these desolate steps trying to chase down these armies of
Horse Snowman
In Herodotus a story there a wonderful scene
Your course makes it a personal thing you put dialogue in people's mouth
Ascidians you know
Play the djingis Khan role in this story they are
A combination of merciless and menacing
And by the way now if you look at a map showing
You know the route that dries Tookie crosses that little strip of water that separates
Europe from Asia yunnan modern-day turkey
Becoming an Invader now from the ancient near East
Stepping foot on European soil
And it moves through
You know the area east of modern-day Romania and up into the southern Ukrainian area
I mean it's an enormously long Rock Co
Whatever there might be
In an attempt to somehow bring these people to battle
But they won't stop running
Herodotus in his account rights quote
Does there seem to be no end of this Pursuit which is going on for a long time
Source
King of the Skippy and would this message
You extraordinary man why do you keep Fleet when you could certainly do otherwise
If you think you were able to challenge my power then stop your wandering and stand to fight it out
Or if you acknowledge that you are too weak for that course then you should stop running away bring gifts of Earth and
Water to your master
And enter into negotiations
And
Sounds like a civilized kingly approach right
Let's settle this here in now
But that's not how they did business on the Central Asian steppes
Andronicus
As the reply
From the very scary
In a barbarian
Central Asian tribal leader
Direct quote
To this I didn't king of this Gideon's responded
This is my situation Persian
I've never get blood from anyone out of fear before
And I'm not fleeing from you now
What I have been doing is in fact no different from what I'm accustomed to do in times of peace
I'll tell you why I do not engage you now
It is because we have no other towns nor cultivated land to worry about being captured or raised
Which might induce us to engage you in battle sooner
But if you really must come to battle without further delay know that we do have ancestral Graves
So come on
Find them and try to destroy them
And you will know whether or not we shall fight for the grave
But before that
We shall not engage you in battle if we see fit to do so
Ethan says quote
Instead of gifts of earth and water I shall send you the kind of tokens you really married
And in response to your claim to be my master
I tell you
Wheat
That is your answer from the Skitty in
And quote
Week
That's a great scene in a movie isn't it
So is this one that's recalled by
Historian made Ave
Quote
The security and risk a decisive
They therefore resorting to their beloved scorched-earth tact
They retreated
Taking with them their livestock burning the grass and feeling in the waterpik
In addition
To get the in Cavalry repeatedly attacked and destroyed small Persian hunting parties
The Persians were worn out by their protracted pursuit of the Skippy in the deep into their own territory
When the riots was looking for a way out of this predicament
The Skippy and leaders in response to his demand that they would either come out for an open bottle
Or submit voluntarily
Send a messenger to the Persian camp
Subsequently if Herodotus is to be believed
Urias was presented by the messenger
With a bird a mouse
A frog and Five Arrows
Jiraiya thought that the Scorpions dust announce their submission
Cabrillas however
One of the seven conspirators against murder
Bardia
Gave a completely different explanation
If a person could not fly in the sky like birds
Could not burrow into the ground
Or jump into the Lakes like frogs
Then they should expect to die by Arrow
And quote
There's a lot of different ways to interpret this generally it's always been considered to be some kind of a
Lost in the Persians come struggling back to Asia lucky to make it over
The bridge of boats held by Greeks
The modern-day historians look at this number different ways one of which is
These leaders
People who are descended from steppe tribes themselves dealt with them all the time
Knew that you couldn't
Capture them or force them into battle and so in effect what they were doing was something like what the Chinese did
For Millennia to try to control the people on their border sometimes you have to just punch it.
Just launched a raid essentially with a huge Army
Go smack them around sometimes you can depose their leaders and put in
A client King cuz is
Condemning your points out you can't actually in a put a Persian ruler like a sad trap to rule over the
Tribal people they won't they have to have a tribal Chieftain or something like that but you can
Pam pick that.
So another words might have just punched these tribes exactly how he wanted to
Historians point out in which case you almost have to look at this as a victory that when King derailleurs comes home
Supposedly struggling with this Gideon's close on his heels
He leaves a general
In frase
Traces in the modern-day Balkan
And this General's orders
Are they continue the conquest
And subject that entire area
Entire area
Is Europe north of Greece
The northern part of the Black Sea
A place where
Cities like Athens depend on grain shipments that all of a sudden
Are threatened by an army
Whose capital is located in modern-day Iran
But these Persians are in
The Balkans
This is the setup
For what's about to happen
And what's about to happen
Kicks off of the revolt
In cities that are
In modern-day turkey
Greek City
But cities that were under Persian domination at this time
Many of these cities
You know we're going to province of Nina what's now modern-day turkey Asia Minor called Ionia so they're called I own
In Greek
And this Revolt is called the ionian revolt
A logo for like
499 to like 490
3 BCE
The Greeks were great colonizers ahead cities all over the Mediterranean
The coast of turkey on the Aegean like these cities
And they had
Many of the islands in that whole region were Greek
They had colonies on the North African Coast they had
One outside of Egypt they had
Mini on Sicily they had some in Italy
These are great
Can you colonize
And so they have cousins all over the Mediterranean
And it is to the mainland Greece at the ionians go for help after they were ballon realized
And we're screwed
If we don't get some help here
When terrible terrible trouble is one of the leaders of this revolt
Back to Mainland Greece to essentially make a pitch like a business proposition
I know this whole show as a sort of
Corporate business feel but this is the way Herodotus portrays it
He actually has this guy going here would like a PowerPoint
Presentation first of the Spartans
And has him acting as a clever businessman to try to sell
Sparta
On Intervention in their revolt against the Persians
When is Mardi gra parts of Herodotus
Where
Essentially he has the story of aristagoras first going to
King cleomenes
Spartans remember the Spartans had two of them
In this case
Aristagoras goes in there with his
Bronze tablet so you think of Uriel laptop PowerPoint presentation
And he sits down with the Spartan King and he starts giving them the rundown of all the good things you'll get
If you invest in this
You know ionian Revolt idea
That I have here for you today
This is for my Purvis translation
He translate that he should buy the
Greek
As Helene's
So when we say Helens we mean when we say like a demonias we mean Spartan
Misquote
According to the account of a lack of daemonium
What do you want to talk with cleomenes aristagoras had with him a bronze tablet
How much a map of the entire world was engraved
Including all rivers in every sea
To begin the discussion aristagoras dead
Cleomenes do not be surprised at my urgency in coming here for this is how matters stand
That the sons of the ionian their slaves instead of free men is a disgrace
And the most painful language
But also to you
Especially of all the others and as much as you were the leaders of Hellas
So now by the gods of the hellions
They were the same blood as you after all
This will be easy for you to accomplish
Since the barbarians are not valid
Why you've attained the highest degree of excellence in war
They fight with bows and short Spears wearing trousers and turbans on their head
Easily subdued
Further the inhabitants of that continent possess more good things that all the other people of the world put together
To begin with they have gold as well as silver
Colorful clothing
Beast of Burden enslave all of which could be yours if you really desire them
And quote
He then runs down every territory that the Persians have at least the ones Herodotus knows about
And with each one he says what it has
This one had a lot of gold and silver
This one has a lot of cattle in this one have a lot of slaves in other words
And he's running down the benefits right of this
Business proposition of his
Leader of Sparta says
All right go away let me think about this for a couple of days I'll come back and give you my answer okay
He comes back
And he asks a simple question of this aristagoras guy
He's just so how far is it
From where we are now
To where this king is wants to know how far it is to the Persian Capital how far do I have to go to win this war that you're trying to sell me on
Says at this point
This business proposition ghost our when aristagoras makes a mistake
When he takes the opportunity to not
Lie to the Spartans at this point
This is how to write a test for my de selincourt translation puts it
You know right before
They're supposed to meet again
For the Spartans to give the answer
As to how they feel about investing in this ionian revolt
Quote
That was as far as they got at the moment
Open the day came on which cleomenes had agreed to give his decision and they met at the appointed place
He asked aristagoras how far off Sousa was Susan the Persian capital
How many days it took to reach it from the ionian coast
Up to this aristagoras have been clever
Headland cleomenes on with great success
Answering this question he made a bad mistake
If you wanted to induce the Spartans to invade Asia he never ought to have told them the truth
But he did
And he said it took three months
And quote
Herodotus writing 2500 years ago I mean think this is a great scene right there
You must think about him as the sort of this sleazy
In a Salesman type comes in here and tries to saw to put one over on the Spartan King and then all of a sudden falls into the Trap and says 3
How long it's going to take to get to the Persian capital
I mean he's basically said get the hell out of here
He says be out of Sparta by sundown
Are you crazy
And she would have instantly understand that this whole time and he's been late on that Herodotus says that in a plane
Please go back home in the sales guy follows him
Tries to start bribing him to do the deal, I'll give you $50 if you do it I'll give you $100 if you do it
Neurologist is a little Spartan boy one of the sons of Pekingese was in the room
And said something like Daddy better get out of here cuz this man's going to corrupt you if things keep going the way they're going it's another one of those stories about the
Interruptible Spartan
Now
Because he fails with the Spartans this aristagoras character then goes to the Athenian
Being a democracy Now
Pretend 15-20 years and it's a short
New kind of system are running with their
And it's not like a democracy you were I would recognize
But as Herodotus points out
Instead of having to convince a king or two in Sparta to invest in your idea
Here you have to kind of convince the majority of whomever it is that makes the decisions here that they shouldn't be
Other words voters
Remember the heck that might be in an ancient democracy
This also from The Descendant or translation
Quote
He was at this moment when the Athenians have made their decision and we're already on bad terms with Persia that Arista Gore
Mulitas
We've been turned out a Sparta by cleomenes
Arrived
He knew that Athens at this time was the next most powerful state in Greece
Accordingly
He appeared before the people and made a speech
And when she repeated the arguments he previously used it Sparta
About all the good things to be found in Asia
And the Persian methods of warfare
How to use neither Shield nor Spears and easy to beat
In addition to this he pointed out that mulitas have been founded by Athenian settlers
So it was only natural that the Athenians power should help
Indeed so anxious was he to get Athenian Aid that he promised everything that came into his head until at last he succeed
Apparently it's easier to impose upon a crowd then upon an individual
Aristagoras would fail to impose upon
Succeeded with thirty thousand Athenians
Once persuaded to ac2 aristagoras is a peel
The Athenians passed a decree for the dispatch of 20 ships to Ionia
How did the command of a distinguished Athenian
Erotic Justin says
The sailing of this fleet was the beginning of trouble not only for Greece but for other people's
And quote
Dutch translation of that line differs book to book of translation to translation
But that's the that's the moment when
The Athenians decide
To do something that's a little bit crazy because they essentially giving in and Herodotus
Putin blames democracy for this
That one spot and came to see the flaw in this dude's proposal from the get-go right spotted the flaw like the Shark Tank
Investor
Venture capitalist should get the heck out of here don't you try to cheat me but 30,000 Athenian
Voter is part of the electorate there
They could have the wool pulled over their eyes by a clever salesman right
Any Athenian send
20 ship
To go help the ionian Revolt the 20 ships is not enough to do anything except
Get you in trouble
These Athenian ships will join with other ships they will
Disembarking join rebellious ionian troops who will
Among other things burn the provincial capital at Sardis maybe accidentally
And then that Army will get
By one of the provincial Persian armies
And crushed with heavy casualties
At this point
The Athenians who's
Support for this ionian Revolt is kind of like
Not a little more than symbolic but quite a bit less than useful
Be kind of pull back and go I am going to win
Anymore
We can kind of see echoes in a
In an inconsistent policy where public opinion just sort of changes right this there's no King
Public wasn't sure anyway
And all of a sudden maybe these Persians didn't look like the pushover is that the
Salesman for the ionian Revolt said they'd be yeah we're out
And hopefully
We'll just forget that this ever happen
Of course Herodotus makes a point
To say that
Dries of course it's not going to forget that it happened one of Herodotus is great stories revolves around
Notoriety
Trying to make sure that he didn't forget most all his problems
Yuan his Empire
Those people
The Athenians
Herodotus a story talked about after the burning sardeson
Dries gets the news about that
Quote
It is said that when the riots first heard this report
He disregarded the ionian
She knew that they at least would not Escape punishment for their revolts
Inquired as to who the Athenians were
And after he's been told he asked for a bow
He took the bow and arrow on the string and shot the arrow towards the heavens
And is it flew High into the air he said
Zeus
Let it be granted to me to punish the Athenians
After saying that he appointed one of his attendance
Repeat to him three times whenever his dinner was served
My Lord
Remember the Athenians
And quote
That's how they did things back in the analogue era no word on whether the attendance name was Siri
Probably either just totally false her
You know another way to look at it is that this Athenian problem of daraya this was so small he had to have someone
Remind him everyday three times a dinner otherwise he forget about it with all the things he had to deal
To show you what a low priority this whole Revolt is for the Persian Empire
The great king himself doesn't even worry about the ionian Revolt delegate to an underling and the Persians like slow-mo
Moving lava methodically reduce these rebellious cities
In Asia Minor and off the coast
And it's often
Awful
The retribution of these Empires
Meat out too rebellious it is but let's understand that's that's something that in much of the world is still treated rather harshly
And this time. Standard operating procedure what an extreme experience
For example the home city of aristagoras
The PowerPoint presenter
Of Herodotus he gets his City level
Maletis
Is the name of it
And the men are for the most part killed but the boys were told are castrated
Instant back
To Persia to be eunuchs
The girls and women sold into slavery
And so if you don't look at aristagoras two-way Herodotus
Like some clever manipulator
And instead look at him
As someone who one way or another gets involved in this Revolt but once you're in
The stakes are everything you see what happened to his home City when it got
Cannery taken by the person he knows what the stakes are
If you're thinking every man dies every boy gets castrated every woman and girl gets
Sold into slavery in your cities leveled
Wouldn't you do anything
When you by hooker by crook tell the Athenians anything that they needed to hear to get public opinion on your side enough to send help
And even though Herodotus ordered makes this
Aristagoras in his movie version of events out to be a little like
Professor Harold Hill in The Music Man
I'm in inter-cell River City on the idea of a boy's band with instruments that'll never show up
And the people of Athens released a sizable percentage of their electorate is easily Hoodwinked by Professor Hill
It's clear that
At least some Athenians
This issue of ionian freedom
Greeks in Asia Minor
Is big and passionate and import
Historian Peter Green
Tells a story of a play
The aired in Athens
Right after the ionian Revolt collapse
He says it may have been the first time that recent historical events
As opposed to miss
I've been represented in the Athenian theater
Any rights quote
In the early spring of 493 the dramatist Fran I guess put on a play called the capture of Meletis
Vividly depicting the collapse of the ionian revolt
The effect was remarkable
Copernicus saw his audience weep tears of grief and patriotic shame
Strong into Swift action the pro Persian Lobby got the play band
When in doubt green rights
Fall back on censorship
Tinnitus himself was fined a thousand drachmas
Almost three years pay for the average working man
But the idea of subservience to Jiraiya's however reasonable it might be
Now rapidly lost Brown
And quote
How modern does that sound
Public opinion
Altered by a popular portrayal of events
Wild
Historian Peter Green
Writing in 1970
You know she has an attitude that we probably would share today living when and where we do
The censorship is not a good thing censorship of the arch is not a good thing in that public opinion
Should matter
Democracy or Republic remember Athens is in what you could call the testing phase Maybe
How this whole democracy thing is going to work
There certainly must have been other Democratic experiments the world over to Athens is credited with
Quote and quote first democracy
And they probably are given the scale you know
First major attempt
Experiment that is democracy only 10 or 20 years old at this point
And if you're watching from the sidelines and you're a member of the conservative former but still powerful ruling class
And you're looking at how public opinion is doing so far
I trying to
You know Governor things intelligently
They've already done something the Spartan King refused to do and got involved in a Revolt that tweets the nose of the gray
Great King of Persia
But never had a chance of achieving anything really meaningful with the small amount of people they sent
Was just enough to get you into trouble
You already did that
And now this playwright is writing plays that get them all
Fired up about confronting Persia cuz of all the injustice
Darth Vader on the evil star Empire
If this is the same thing as like remember the Maine was the newspaper campaign the fired-up Americans in the Spanish
Going to go to war with Spain
It's a little bit different because in that conflict
You could argue about historical Justice and all that kind of stuff with the United States
So propaganda that got public opinion to support the idea of chicken Spain's rear end
Is something that is not
2 detrimental
To the country
This is much more like the people in Latvia
Being encouraged war fever
In order to confront the Russians
Or the Mexicans
You know having the propaganda and the entertainment in public opinion and everything pushing towards
Going back and reconquering those States they lost to the United States a century-and-a-half ago
That's something that in that case
Is public opinion leading you toward National Suicide
Already shown a propensity to get you into trouble that's why you're on the
In a great change naughty list already
It's no wonder that guy was fined
Just stoking those kinds of emotions at this time at this place
Existential threat
Athens at this point
It is interesting the ability to portray the Persians in such an evil light
I thought because if you actually look
How the Persians dealt with it afterwards
They actually did so in a way that was just typical of their Style
They punished the rebellious City's horribly as we said
But then winning in trying to figure out why the ionians kept revolting
Lower taxes in places change some trade deals in others
Try to alleviate the problem at its core
And ironically enough
Because some of these cities that have revolted didn't like the tyrants that were ruling them
This newfangled thing called democracy they wanted a piece of that too
The Persians let them have it
Remember they were known for allowing local customs
You have to stay in place as long as things still worked out for them and if the local custom was going to be to collect your own leaders in your own City
Directions were fine with that
As long as the city stayed loyal to Persia
So once again the Persians kind of look like the place we all like to live if we had to live back in those days
In a absolute monarchy right
On the ancient monarchy scale you know they score very highly
Leniency tolerance compassion
Common sense
But if you're Greek you're not going to
Look at it that way at least not if you're Athenian
The last thing you want to do is have a
You have a democracy Now
And if your Spartan
You want a king but you want a spark
Can laughing you want to some Barbarian King so
No people ever in the path of being conquered by any other people
Could see the upsides can you blame them
But you know I've always thought that if you were another city-state in Greece remember
Greece is not unified place
It's a bunch of competing
Often warring in some cases
Bitter enemy
City state
What is a city-state
Athens is a bunch of places
Argos
What do you think in democracy did by sending those 20 ships to Aid the ionian revolt
Is take the great king of kings the most powerful figure in the world
Turn it into your direction and he doesn't just seatins he's everything over there
What is the people in Argos do to deserve that
They might have eventually been absorbed by The Blob who knows
Athenians essentially declare war on Persia
What lives in the neighborhood that the Persians couldn't help but trampled on on their way to punishing the Athenians
And this is partly why the story has magnified in terms of importance
For the people in Greece
This is life-or-death
To the Persians this is a frontier disturb
Historian ATMs that has a chapter I love the title it
Problems on the Greek Frontier
Storing George cockwell
Entitled his whole book The Greek Wars instead of the Persian Wars because
The Persian Wars makes it sound
In a like the Greeks are talking about it because they're them that's what this was but to the rest of the
In a world that was centered around Mesopotamia these were the Greek Wars something over on the frontier something that didn't
No way you could ever imagine
Could threaten the empire
The Athenians
Whatever we're doing
And I knew it was coming
Soldiery traditionally there's a lot of focus on Athenian internal politics in the war
In what the Athenians sometimes called collaborate
They had a word for it based on you it was the Persians in the medes
So they called it me dies
Can you or me doubting you were talking about collaborating or giving in to the great king
They had these different factions that buy different powerful families in Minnesota
Sparring and fighting it out in meanwhile
Are the existential threat in 492 BCE gets going
Led by a son of one of the assassination hit squad members
Who also happened to Mary
Into the royal family so you know you can see how this test you with all this assassination hit-squad thing is starting to be
His name is mardonius he's fascinating I wish we knew more about him he's an interesting
In a Persian General
And he takes an army and a fleet
Working together in a way we would call Lancey operations today
And leaves Asia crosses the Dardanelles in 2 years
Nobody Knows the size of this Army Herodotus says it was 300 ships take that with a grain of salt but it doesn't
Matter if it's half that big this is a mammoth operation
For navies in the ancient world
The Persians of course did not create their own Navy
They took over the best one in the world and then they test it with things that never could have been tasked with the for like
Okay we want you to support
A 20 or 30 or 40 thousand man army with your Navy
That's a new level of sophistication and operations and what the Persians are doing
In his conquest of Greece which is something that they might have done in Egypt to
Earlier but this is where you really get a chance to see it on display
Is a precursor to
Delancey operations today involving
In a Marine Amphibious Landings everything
Please please can be used
To spit offshore and follow an army that's marching along the coast
And feed it
Extending operations nobody knows how many troops mardonius have buddy lands in this area
Controlled by
Thracian
The entire region around the Balkans during this time. In this particular area of courses up in
And sort of by where Modern North
Eastern tip of Greece's you up in that area
All a bunch of stration tribes Herodotus labeled them the second most populous nation in the world after the Indians
And
Extremely warlike he said that they would have conquered the world if they didn't love fighting each other too much
And they are
I know you don't want to be so stereotypical about barbarians because all these people had wonderful
Cultures and values
Religious beliefs in puberty right to mean it's all a part of it but you can't help but look at it
Inspiration and think there's your Hollywood casting directors idea of a barbarian
They look a lot like a Skitty in without the horse
They got the warpaint they got the tattoos they like to cook
Carry severed heads around with them when they're trying to intimidate their enemies
And they're tough
Any like ambushes
And it like to kill prisoners I mean they scare people
And this area had submitted to derive this whole area when he came along chasing those kittens while back
But you know the Persian army then goes home and they kind of
You'll get a little locks and yeah we haven't heard from him in a while and whatever
And then the Army comes back and says you know what we just going to tighten that relationship a little bit more
And made all of those areas that have been formally sort of just yeah we're your vassals kind of deal
Into official provinces
Run bike governors
Appointed by the Persian king
One of these provinces
Is the is the is the next little
Kingdom I guess you could say on the way to greasy go from Thrace to
Makedonia
If the name rings a bell the king at the time will
The Ringgit even harder Alexander Alexander the first
A makedonija
You know what he does when the Persian army under mardonius shows up
He submits
Tecumseh Governor under the control of the Persians
And
Some historians in a wonderful ironic Twist of History say
But if not for the stability and centralization and State Building
Climate that
Persian control in a gave makedonija during this. They may never have coalesced into a strong centralized state
It would eventually evolve into something
That could destroy the very people who made that centralized State possible
Oh and just for the fun of it do it under a king with the same name
Don't you just love history
Nonetheless
Thracian tribe do get one good Sucker Punch in
I'll mardonius before they get crushed brutally
A tribe of them will Ambush the Persian army at night
And create great Havoc including wounding mardonius
Right around the same time
This Fleet
It is accompanying the Persian army will try to round
A point called Mount Athos
Herodotus says as soon as like going around the tip of Florida
I think about it that way
And as soon as the fleet hits the tip it gets hit by
When
Strong winds according to Herodotus and he says 300 ship sank
In 20000 men died
Is what my perviz translation of Herodotus
It says
Quote
From fastest to Fleet crossover and sale close to the shore of the Mainland
From which they set out and then attempt around Mount Athos
But if they were sailing around a strong North Wind came up on them
Which was so impossible to deal with it and battered them badly in rectum any of their ships against the shore of Mount Athos
In fact it is said that about 300 of their ships were destroyed
With more than 20000 men
And since this city is full of savage creatures
Some were snatched up and killed by them
While others were dashed against the sharp Rock
Some men perished because they did not know how to swim
And still others died from the cold
So that is what happened to the fleet
Indica
I'm sorry my head right now I just think to myself
What do God look like
300 ships
Twenty thousand men
Somewhere between 13 and 14 Titanic
It's going down in terms of
Live Loft if eroticism numbers are anywhere near correct
Even more from a visual standpoint
Is the ID of 300 ships wrecked
All
I mean what are they all bunched together in one place or are they scattered around in the entire coastline
Usually doing the movie who doing the cinematography on that
How much do we have to use
Is CGI computer Graphics because there's no way otherwise to
In the show that see how much would it cost to do that
1950s Elizabeth Taylor Richard Burton style right
Analog
How to get
300 fake ships and I mean think about
The visuals just
All the people in the water I mean everything that people find so horrifying about going down to the Titanic you have happening
You know route Mount Athos
I know what you think about
The precariousness of Maritime traveling bad storms will sink ships today
We all know
Well the farther back you go in history in general
Away from the coach Dreamer
Standard operating procedure was to beach the ships at night
And then in the morning push them back out and get their big ships but you still beat them
140 guys at red
It took two
Essentially lift a trireme
On to the shore at night
I wonder how much it took to actually give these these weeds trouble but the idea of 300 vessels going down
When they rounded the cape a it just boggles the mind
Have to be the Kamikaze right
The divine wind
When Japan was saved
You know from the Mongol horde because the storm came up and battered the fleet
Saint Paul uShip
The Invasion right
Maybe this was
Grease his own version of a kamikaze
The one thing
Did the Greeks knew
Is that this was not going to say that
This Kamikaze was not
Deliverer
It was a double layer
Ending a nier
2 years
The riots will have
Is next Invasion Force ready
Irish dancing
We will stop most ancient empires in their tracks
Persians methodically just put together another one
In 490 it's ready to go and it is bigger
It is nastier
It is going to be handled
Better and we're going to take into account everything we learn from the failures of the last Expedition
And this time it is going to be right
The heart
Avastin
And it's tempting to see the CEO role
As already seen that the odds are
I mean in the celestial Casino in the sky
The battle between Athens and the Persians is off the books are not taking bets on that there are no odd there is no
Champs
And the rice is still trying to
Get a little edge here or there
Leave no stone unturned planning White
In the year between you know the first expedition that Founders off the rocks
Bose
And the one coming up
Ethan zohn voice degrees
They go to all these Greek States and Greek Islands and they asked for earth and water
Remember earlier we said that was the traditional token of submission
Most of these places give it to
Vast majority of the islands a bunch of Creek State
Two notable holdouts though
Athens who either throws their Persian Envoy into a pit that they usually have four convicts win
Execution or throws them off a cliff take your pick
Which one of the famous movies of all time although some historians doubt it ever happened
Supposedly throw the Persian Envoy into a well when he asked for or some water and tell them he can get both of them down there
That killed the Persian Envoy
And puts both the Spartans and the Athenians if they really did that
Onto The Ledger of
Misdemeanors and high crimes at the Persians are keeping track of remember what happened to the Egyptians
When they kill
Persian on boys
Can Pisces got to sit there and watch a thousand or 2,000 other kids executed and sold into slavery
A bunch of Greek city-states and Highland
Chose what you probably have to see you the only realistic answer
And submitted
Earthen water to the Persians as ass
And instantly becoming not just
Neutral
In the struggle that Athens is about to engage in
But adversary
Other city-states in Greece all of a sudden were subjects of the great king
That's like a slow-moving lava on the other side of the Emoji and all of a sudden launches Embers into the sky
Sky the drop-down on city-states in Greece near Athens
The great king is going to Levy troops from these other
Greek cities to use against the Athenians
If you're already we're going to crush poor
Little Greece
With your Persian forces
Well now he's isolated the Athenians for the most part the Spartans with them
So now he's just going to crush that little part agrees
Now he's going to add Greek city-states to his side and their armies to his
I mean this is a guy who really likes to load the dice right
When you hear
The scale
Of this attack
And what it takes to logic gives you a an absolutely new appreciation for the capabilities of ancient
And you really do think you're so cool we do this today
If we had no computers and none of the modern stuff we normally use I mean
You try to take
Let's just say it 50000
Stadium size
Crowd of people
And transported over water and land
A long way
And not have it be a catastrophe
Historian Tom Holland
You know how both of the generals of this Expedition one guy's name is artha Franny's and he's related to the Royal
Family
The others called datus and he's a Mead and they come in this Expedition and from their eyes
He has them see the preparations that were so large and massive and went on for a whole year and there's no doubt the Athenians
This was going on Holland rights quote
Every Day's Journey Westward brought them fresh evidence of the barely believable scale the great Kings
Resources
The labor gangs toiling to maintain the roads
Whole population sometimes
Transplanted from the farthest reaches of the Earth
The guard station beside every bridge
Every flotilla of pontoon Every Mountain Pass
The troops in their own rear
Not merely Persians and medes but Levi is drawn from further
Bactrian
Sean Diaz
An axe-wielding soccer
What was Athens the people such as B
Not even a name
Get on they marked
Directed by the will of their far-off All-Seeing King
And every evening no matter where they halted
These men from the steppes
From the mountains from The Villages of a Ron
They would be provisioned out of monstrous depots
Supplied punctually with jugs of wine and loaves of bread and barley for their horses
And when it last
Having passed through the Syrian Gates and descended into the plains of culicchia on the Southeastern coast of modern-day turkey
Turkey they found there waiting for them
Sun Builders weapons of war
Others as horse trainer
And quote
In the history of Naval Warfare what the Persians are about to do here
It's hard to find an earlier version it's hard to imagine that anyone moved
Tens of thousands
Of troops across the water
And landed the minute like an amphibious assault situation with the Persians are doing here
Is breathtaking and remember
2 years ago you would have to go two years ago they lost three hundred ships and 20,000 men doing something
Like this
So they know what might happen
This Time by the way they're going to go much more direct route none of this going around the long way and supplying
In the Army we're going to transport the Army on the ships and we're going to Island
Across the Aegean from Turkey to Greece
Take the islands on the way
If you are in Greece
Especially if you are in Athens
It's hard to imagine those folks feeling a whole lot different than the British
In the second world war after France fell
And they knew they just knew
Okay brace yourself
Storm is Coming
Athenians
In 490
The storm breaks
In the summer of 490 BCE
Persian X
Expedition gets underway
Herodotus says
It consists
Hungary ship
Now modern-day historians have done a great job
Poking holes in the ancient authors numbers where they were talking ships are men
But they have no real agreement over what numbers to plug in for them
I miss broad disagreement in fact historians are not even sure what the goal of this mission is
Is this a mission just to punish
Athens and some of their in a small island friends and whatnot
Well if so we require
A1 size Force
If on the other hand this is an expedition
With the intention to punish Athens and conquer the rest of Greece you need another size
Even trying to figure out
You know your numbers requires you to make certain assumptions and historians differ
I mentioned earlier that this operation is really a different sort of operation than what you saw before this.
The Persians as we said may have done this already
Generation before when conquering Egypt
Earlier. You always had Warfare but it was something more like a glorified version of what the
Vikings did than this
What the Persians are doing is really the precursor
You know they will eventually evolved into say the D-Day Landings in June
Because when
The Trojan Wars happen for example and the Mike Indians come over from another area that's now Greece in the NBA
Meaning of the Trojan War they come over on ships to
But they don't bring sophisticated Horse Transport
And food carrying ships do nothing but bring the supplies to keep everybody fed and watered
That's a modern-day operation
I'm going to see people's came to Egypt in ancient times they didn't bring Horse Transport in everything they needed to supply in
An army with them by sea
In 1944 when the Allies cross the English Channel they did
And they did here too
By going island-hopping when these islands in the Aegean are relatively close to each other the Persians can avoid having to
Cross like a large stretch of Open Water
Think of a place to place to place
You know most of the time probably just Beach their ships at night
Some cities get
Destruction treatment the first when they go to is one called nexos and they owed some payback to that one
And so even though the population fled up into the mountains places got burned
Your bad things happened
But then they arrive at another Island
One that is supposedly the birthplace of the god Apollo
And the population runs away they're all scared and the Persians stop and they tell them to come back you have nothing to fear
Because that Island didn't do anything they submitted
Then the Persian
General goes up today
To the altar of Apollo and burns and out
Frankincense
Massively over tipping the God is a kind of a
A way to say listening
This guy is going to get even more than he's used to you know when you were taking care of
The characteristic approached at the Persians
Then they go to another city
And they ripped
Shreds
The city's name was Eritrea
It was one of the two cities
In a long without them but really supported the ionian Revolt so it's on the hit list for the Persians
And they
Take advantage of the divisions that seem to be in almost all these Greek cities
Steven Sparta
Using their gold
Their promises
And this carrot and stick approach of theirs to essentially
You note are the Greek
Up from within 2 exploit divisions that already exists
The Greeks art
But it's not just a division between the city-state Argos does not get along the Sparta
Divisions within the city-state
Example of how MA Den Daniel describes
What happens when the Persians lost this expedition to the islands
And begin to punish people
Quote
The Persians disembarked on naxos which was still independent
They conquered the island and pillaged it
The majority of the people of the island fled to the mountains
Thereupon the Persian army sailed to the town of eretria on euboea
At that time Eritrea suffered from the strong antagonism
Between two political parties
The aristocrats wanted to defend their town
The Eritrean has offered resistance against the Persians for 6 days
On the seventh day
The Democrats surrendered their City
I hope that the Persians would give them the power over Eritrea
The Persians however burnt and destroyed the city and its Temple
Into captivity
They were deported to suzhou
In modern-day Iraq
And thereupon by orders of daraya settled in the village about jurica in the ELA my district of Kiss ER
And quote
Supposedly the great King's orders to his generals have been to reduce
Eritrea and Athens to slavery
And then to bring the slaves to him
I have always assumed that to be rhetorical you need doesn't mean really likes all the people in the city state
Put them on the ship
Send the ships back to the Asian mainland in March than 3 months to him and chains and Suzette does e
And then I remember that
If people have been moving whole populations of other people since time began
He wanted to come to look at history through a lens of population movement and start by determining that there's two basic kinds
Voluntary population movement and involuntary population movement
Movie the people who want to go elsewhere
And the movement of peoples that somebody else wants to go elsewhere
Joseph Stalin was doing this kind of stuff in the 1950s
So maybe not that hard to believe
And certainly if you were the Athenians
You get worried about this Eritrean disaster
And you get an idea if you know what you're very near future
Probably looks like
Can you have divisions within your city every bit as contentious as those that brought down Eritrea
And
You can't help but notice once again.
In a very modern move the Persians are
Taking advantage of this
With them leading them guiding them and helping them
On this Expedition towards Athens is a guy that used to run the place
They're bringing back an old Tyrant And I stress the word old cuz that's what a Rattata
Chastise
This is a guy who ruled the place before democracy broke out in the Persians are bringing him back there interested
We would say today in regime change
And they're bringing a foreign army to back it
But the assumption is that there's going to be a bunch of people in Athens who welcomed this
From the other
Party if you will
Supposedly there are high signs and all kinds of other things
Conspirators and those who want to revert back to the
In old days meaning
The city divisions in Athens are clear they're open they're talked about by the primary sources in the Persians appear
Designing their strategy to take advantage of this
It seems just like them. And then you know how we going to rule this fractious very political place will it bring somebody back in your nose delay
Faction in Athens is opposed by some of the most famous people in this story if you're looking at it from the
Traditional Greek point of view
Guys like
Temistocles
A lot of historians compared to
Churchill figure in the story and
Another one name
Yuletide at ease with
Play a key General role in this upcoming
Your face off that we're about to happen
According to Herodotus it is the former Athenian tyrant in between wheezing and coughing fits that's a
Supposedly tells the Persians the best place to land for their amphibious operation
A plane called
Marathon
About 25 miles outside the city of Athens
You could call it a staging point for your amphibious operation right unload everything
I get yourself all put together and then you can march on the city or
You can just act as the incentive
For Athens to
Interchange public opinion favor and more these people who are saying it would be great to have the old Tyrant back
And at the same time will be realistic about cutting our losses against the great king
Who now has an army 25 miles from here by the way
Did I mention that
In a war party Themistocles
What you going to do about that
Of course this leads
To a famous encounter first of all
The Athenians do the smart thing
And they send a runner
Which boggles the mind when you think about how this is a
Life-or-death issue
Do we send a Horseman know there had to be a reason why and I don't know what it is
We'll leave it to a story to explain why somebody would run
To Sparta
But that's what they do because they need help and you know who you going to call most of Greece is already working that with the Persians
And besides the Spartans could kick all their rear ends in combat anyway send to the Spartans
And begin to put your own
House in order and get your soldiers together
And this is where the story once again you to focus a bit on the soldiers
We describe the Persian army early
We pointed out at that time that
There's a real importance to things happening on the battlefield level
Tactical questions that impact the rest of human history
Because
Remember this is a
Encounter that should be off the books at the wedding
Casino the celestial Casino mean this is the great Persian Empire encompassing most of Asia
At least a part of Asia that anybody knows about all the way to India
And Athens
What is going to make
Resistance anything other than completely futile
Maybe the weapon system
It's kind of crazy to think of
When you realize how long military history has been happening in places like
Innovative Middle East right or or
China or any of those places they've already got thousands of years of military history under their belt
Button
490 reading this dussehra right they were talking about BCE
This is the emergence the beginning
The entrance on the
In historical stage
European
Military history
Obviously there's
As much European military history there is anything else if you can
Enough we had the tribal record
All the peoples
That existed on what's now the European
Continents going back to 10000 BCE
But we don't
Historians can try to reconstruct
In some sort of Dark Age or heroic. Of Greek history in a during the time of the Trojan Wars
I am large
You know the first record we have of European armies armies armies were talking about right now in Greece
The vast majority of them
Made up of average everyday folks
Dressed and equipped and fighting as heavy infant
That because this is the earliest form of of Western military history you you will have whole schools
Historical thought
And they were dominant for the last twenty-five hundred years most of the time that will assert that there are qualities in the
These Greeks
Either what makes them fight or how they fight or their theories behind how you should fight
That have influenced maybe even made
Military
For the last 2500 years
Reciting a phrase you might hear from someone from the Victor Davis Hanson School of
Yuan historical thought on these questions for example
The idea that the Greeks
Were people who believe in decisive battle
And that we ourselves are the inheritors in the modern world of that same idea as a whole
Easy to get lost in the rabbit hole and I will leave it to the
Mainstream historians Hanson's of provocative character but he gets a lot of pushback and there's a lot of great arguments repeat
Like yours truly
The part of what makes the Ancient. Warfare so fun for a guy like me
Is that you get to see
The most
Variation between cultures and peoples and societies
And their influence on warfare than you see in any other.
They were very standardized
If you look at a military
From say modern-day South America
I compare it to one from modern-day Asia
They're going to be dressed the same they're going to be using the same equipment they're going to be using very similar tactics
I mean the difference between the two will be minimal
But the farther back in time you go especially to the ancient.
All of these cultures are in their most exuberant shall we say flamboyant Maybe
And distinctive sort of cultural incarnations for lack of a better phrase
They all look very
Like their culture they fight in ways that are connected to their culture their organization everything
The contract is part of what I love about the. When the Persians and the Greeks
First meet in this. They were talking about right now
This is a clash of cultures literally
And that's part of what makes this such a rabbit hole of stereotypes and motifs and everything like that to go down because
It's been this west-east Dynamic ever since
But you can't help but notice
The wonderful distinctiveness for example the Persians are a combined arms Army
When we talked about them you have all these different
Things to talk about first you talk about the Cavalry then you talk about the light
When you talk about the line Infantry
The Greeks don't have much of that during this time.
They have heavy Infantry
Hoplite
You are wargamer it's part of what makes Greek armies from this. Kind of boring
Everything you get it is a hoplite basically
The hoplite is the quintessentially Greek heavy Infantry
And they're one of the examples that historians often look
To to try to answer another man's horrible but fascinating question
Especially from the pre gunpowder in a period of military history as to why some people
In a developed weapons types and Weapons Systems and soldiery the others can't imitate of me why are there
In Japan why can't the Chinese emperor just decide one day
Those Samurai are really badass I want some samurais I'm going to get a disgruntled Samurai bring him over here let him train
My guys I'll give him the same weapons and armor
We can't do that can you there's something cultural right the cultural carrots and sticks that are reinforced by the Japanese
Feudal society that you can't create
Samurai
Just cuz you want them
In history when the Roman legionaries were reigning Supreme during the Roman Empire. Other commanders tried to imitate that
Is imitation legionaries by the
Couple centurions
By the same armor weapons and I'll have
Legionaries too but they never quite measured up
Decant
Do that there have to be some of the cultural
Aspects that are very hard to reproduce
Same thing with hopper
Historian Victor Davis Hanson
Gives a remarkable
Statistic in his writing he says quote
For nearly 300 years
From 6:50 to 3:50 BC
No foreign army despite any numerical superiority
Withstood the charge of a Greek phalanx
The battles of marathon and potato
Relatively small numbers of well LED heavily-armed Greeks
Had little difficulty in Breaking right through the hordes of their more lightly equipped
Unless cohesively rank adversaries from the East
And
Why
This is a fascinating question to ponder and it goes down unquantifiable
Unmeasurable
You know when you start getting into questions of things like toughness
How on Earth does one measure toughness and how is toughness infused
You know if you could take all the children from a
So cold
How civilization and transfer them to the parents from a so-called weak civilization whatever time
I take the children for the week civilization and give them all to the parent of the tough generation a generation from then do you change the
Power relationships at all
Does the week civilization stay week or does it get tough and vice-versa and then why
What is toughness anyway
What the heck is this
Dominance that these hoplites have something that simply based on
You know the way they fight between their formations and their weapons and stuff like that
This is the stuff that historians argue about
Victor Davis Hanson probably is the
In a leading proponent of what maybe you could call the traditionalist approach to thinking about hoplites as
Did he call them at one point in one of his books I love the way he phrased it
He called them heavily armed and armored farmer
And each city-state
Is a little like a sports team
And they all have personalities even if you think of the Pittsburgh Steelers is tough blue collar
You know guys and that's reflected in the way that they play in the toughness of their teams
I would like to know you have fever to the city-state of rustic farmers and they're always out there
But they're a little rustic I mean every every city-state had its own kind of reputation
And record versus traditional opponent
How are the Spartans doing against the argyle
And some of these city-states were considered to be tougher than others
But according to the traditional approach
Most hoplite armies are militias
Are the citizens of the city state
Usually just a percentage of them but
Hanson point.
About 80% of most of these city-states were made up of farmers are people who made money in farming
Athens and Sparta are always kind of exceptions to the city-state ruled by the way
Athens is kind of a New York City or the Paris or the London
Of ancient Greece a little bit more chic
Little bit more gossiping with more gossamer into the theater in the latest trends and very glib politi
Ethically speaking
Talented
Funny humorous wonderful entertainers
And the Spartans are a laboratory experiment I love these things where you use human beings
You can create a soldier
You know this extra special of all the societal carrots and sticks are arranged
When I was growing up there was a ton of admiration for Sparta and their system and everything
Nowadays even conservative historians are much more hard on the Spartan system than they used to be
Victor Davis Hanson
Himself
Will say about Sparta quote
Are disclosed militaristic Society
Produced an army of professional
Immune from pressing economic a rather peacetime obligations
They were free to threaten the Farms of others
The fight year-round if need be
Secure in the knowledge
But in their nightmare a system of Apartheid
Servants were busy with their own Harvey
There's all kinds of debate and discussion and disagreement among historians about a lot of things that mean you have Victor Davis Hanson in one quart
You got a guy like hands band
And he wrote a fascinating book
Greek Warfare myths and realities
But I'm still trying to get my mind around cuz it's so challenging to traditional beliefs doesn't make it true doesn't make hands and true
As One reviewer I read said maybe it's more like something in between the two is true
Says that everything we know about hoplite Warfare comes from a later.
5075 years after
And that the armies were talking about here
Are much more rustic even than the ones
Nina from Classical Greece
It's called this is still archaic
He says they're only reason that the Spartans are considered dangerous at all is because they're the only Greek city-state
The prepares for war at all
What's that line in a world where we went blind the one-eyed man is King
Maybe the Spartans aren't so badass
Compared to anybody who actually trains for war
That seems heretical
His point is that if
Most of these city-states are simply getting all their people together you know the ones who fight the 30 or 4
40% of the male population out there free male population actually fights
When you get them out there if they're not trained to move as a group
You know to follow commands and do drills
What are they going to do
Out there
And fun ways is pointed at the Spartans actually did do that drilling which made them seem almost otherworldly to these arms
Men's Wear
You know guys just got together one day when we needed for war imagine you know you have a spear and some armor that's
It's over
You know your fireplace and has needed once or twice a year or maybe once every two years
You down the armored you meet up with everybody in your neighborhood that you normally fight within your go out there for the day
And you try to beat the neighboring city-state on a in a nice wonderfully labeled flat
Field of battle with some certain rules probably
So we've been believe that these freaking rules.
You're not too many of us are going to use bows or anything like that right this is a man on man contest right
In terms of weaponry
The Greek hoplite was a Spearman
Wielding a 789 foot long sometimes we even hear longer long spear
But that spear was only about an inch thick
Had an iron spear head
And a bronze butt Spike on the end
Historian said that was called the lizard
Whatever that means it sounds awful
And that these
Troops would form up injury close formation shoulder-to-shoulder essentially
With their shield in front
And their Spears
You know ahead of them now this means that the spears for about three or four ranks behind the front rank
Protrude
Beyond the front of the formation so you have a pincushion here
Usually the ones behind that week
Keep your Spears up
Hoplite formation is called
Phalanx
We now know as we didn't maybe 50 years ago or sixty years ago that
The Phalanx is a formation that has been used ever since very very ancient times Mesopotamian cities were using
A long time ago
But the Greeks may have formed even closer than the norm it's debated and debatable
The one thing that these formations had a real problem with his any sort of difficult to rain in fact
Maybe even just a little uneven ground
Because if you were trying to stay
Shoulder to shoulder with the person next to you in front of you and behind you the last thing you want to do is run into for example
Your formation
Victor Davis Hanson approach to thinking about how this Phalanx spot
Would make it seem something like a very very very pointy
Irresistible Steamroller
And usually they would put
The best man in front and an often times the best man in the rear file to
And put the least
Trustworthy Brave experienced what-have-you man in the middle of the formation because the news really no way
Out
And many of the people who write about
The Greek hoplite
Phalanx
Will point out that it doesn't require a ton of weapons drill
You don't have to really learn how to do much in the way of
Another great warrior out there with sword player using the spear like that
Like a Shaolin monk not that kind of think you're more of a part of a machine
In the phalanx
And the Greek authors and the modern-day historians often say that what seems to be strapped in the sources this much more what we were call today
Physical fitness
Endurance
Strengths that kind of thing
And it partially explains why you can have old people
Fighting in the skylights is why everyone doesn't have to be 25
Liking today is Milla
Call Terry what part of it is it's a militia right you're supposed to get
A cross-section of the public but also because Ena formation like that
Older people aren't required to be so nimble
The arthritis
You could be more control me you just go to stay and do your job standing die or you know conquer
And move forward but all is apart of this math working together in fact the older people
Added both experience
Add
In a veteran status and they could help
Stiff and some of the younger
We were soldiers in the formation
And some of this is believed by some people to try to explain maybe why these hoplite to do so well
When they face non hoplites are they kicking ass you know who knows
Is the armored wolf other people have
Is it the long Spears will anybody can put long Spears in the hands of their troops
What makes them
Do what they do what makes Samurai so good what makes it so good what makes Mongo
What makes Apache so good
That's always also have another idea about armor and such
And he points out that well
What am I let him
Explain how
He sees the development of armor is different from everything we've always learn
Quote
A Scholars have traditionally reconstructed the history of hoplite equipment
It follows in a perfect Arc
Beginning in the late 18th century we witnessed a gradual introduction of hoplite armor
Culminating in the Universal adoption of the full hoplite panoply in the middle of the 7th century
From the middle of the 6th Century onwards parts of the panoply begin to be discarded by the end of the fifth century
We reach the rather lightly equip hoplite already described
This tidy picture needs a modification
And quote
In his opinion
The artwork is kind of
The biggest baddest guy with the coolest looking armor set
Sometimes I verify
Affected the history
Buddy's point is that
And when you actually look at archaeological finds it cost
Fang
And when you throw people of different
Wealth classes into a large body of people and tell them to wear
Their own stuff
This is sort of the Hallmark of all of the
You know city-states except Sparta
Is you buy and bring your own
Kit
Right so everybody's kids kind of different than personalizing sometimes they all go down to the neighborhood market they're selling helmets in there
If you put all these people together on Battlefield
It doesn't look very yunnan
The Forum
And because of this were told
There's even conspicuous display of the rich guys come
Hylan drive up in the BMW is right and they have the
Horsehair crest
It's triple and maybe ostrich feather sticking out too and the really cool bronze armor
The Nimbus 2000 kind of thing
And the poor guy shows up in some leather jerkin or maybe some
You know nothing of Linden they used to think it went from the Barnstormers into the linen or it might have just always been a Cost question
The more wealthy the phalanx
No members were the better the armor look
Well
While the experts May disagree or discuss quite a lot
Questions of what a hoplite was or how they exactly fought
We can say with a pretty good level of certainty can't we
That those are the kind of troops regardless of what they are that Athens is going to have to rely on
If they are going to turn back this
Persian amphibious assault
We mentioned a little while ago
That lands at a place called Marathon about 25 or so miles outside of Athens
It will be a lively debate in this
Wonderfully interesting democracy and Athenian democracy
In some ways remind you a little of the early French Revolution in the sense that
Their Democratic about like all kinds of things like they elect General
And if you believe Herodotus
They liked multiple generals who then have two in a share command somehow Maybe by you know today is my day tomorrow
How was your day I mean
In that sense it's a kind of a
Radical democracy in in in in all kinds of ways
There will be a debate in the city about the best course of action
Dealing with the Purdue given to the Persians at the realism
The fortify the city and stay here with you go out and meet them eventually
Impart led by
A guy named milk as we mentioned earlier
They will put together their hoplites and maybe their attendance
The debate over how much the people that actually held the armor for the hoplite
And then once the hoplites were ready to fight one of those guys do they pick up
Javelins and fight his light infantry lot of debate over that too
But I can to put together 10 or 11,000 he's
Citizen militia soldiers who may be trained every now and then is going on some sort of yearly event or
What not and they certainly would have had experience fighting
But men from different social classes men from different age brackets up to
Little guys in their 40s certainly
And prominent people is a lot of prominent people
Who will forever afterwards remember that they fought in that Phalanx that day
Enable take off for Marathon
Given that famous order something to the effect
Take food with them and March
Grab formations and go
So this citizen militia of Athens
Takes off
Joined by
800 to a thousand hoplites from the small city-state of
Tortilla
And then they go and put themselves
In a blocking position
The chi
The Persians from breaking out of their little beachhead area and expanding out into the country
And then they sit
And hunker down
Within sight of the Persian army
Best face off
Which goes on for a couple of days I try to keep reminding myself
Of the intimidation
If something that tends to diminish over time
But the Persians in this time. Or like the heavyweight champ
Certain aura about them and Herodotus comments
He says that these Athenians camped out there are the first to endure he says
Quote
The site of the medes clothing in the men wearing it
He called the Persians medes
He called the Greeks Helen
Nieces quote
In fact until then even to hear the name
Spoken would strike Terror into Helen
And quote
So there's a
Intimidation Factor here there's also a
Are tactical reality that the Greeks understand
Persian heavy cavalry
And calorie is something that the Greek
Way of fighting
Without
Extra troops around can't deal with a mean
If you're in the formation where the number one thing you have to do is stand shoulder-to-shoulder
With the guys around you and not break formation cuz then you're doomed
How do you deal with Cavalry that you can't catch
They can ride up to you in small squadrons and Pelt you with javelins and then as you move out to deal with them
In a runaway and if you chase them you break your formation
And then your meat
For that saying cavalry
Rewrite the can come in there now that you were all disordered take you apart
The Greeks also don't have archers
The one thing that might keep that Cavalry at arm's length right away to respond at least at the Tactical level they don't have that
Lots of them
So that'll keep you camp down for a while wondering what to do the other reason that historians think it's a logical thing to wonder about
That the Athenians are waiting for here are for spark
They sent a runner to Sparta remember as opposed to a championship Cherry driver
Or Horsemen we don't understand why but he made it in record time so who's going to argue
And this
Person tells the Spartans Unity
Alright now
Can't make it right
Right this second
But as soon as the moon gets into the proper phase were there
Something
Athenians are waiting there for the Spartans didn't you know
Hopefully nothing happens before then
Historians wonder why the Persians are waiting also and
Many theories center around the idea that they're waiting for
You know the coup d'etat to occur in Athens right for the people there to another the realism party which the
War party would call the collaborator party the me dizer
Just waiting for those guys to get the upper hand
Nothing historians think maybe those guys are waiting for the Persians to defeat the Athenian Army
And then throw open the gates everybody kind of wants to hedge their bets right that's natural
But if Athens gates are thrown open the person can just get back in their ships maybe leave a covering force on the beach
And sale around Athens and go take it while the army that should be defending Athens is still waiting for the Spartans
Marathon
And truthfully
This is an enormously compelling story
And always has been
If you look at it
From the Greek side
I mean with much as I'm trying to look at this from the Persian side
And I'm only human and I'm a fan of history and
You know if you forget all that
In a fun we were having with the nonsense of the home team of Western Civilization
There's still a compelling angle that a totally neutral screenwriter would want to exploit here forget Herodotus
You know Greek anyway writing for a Greek audience
I mean if you're a neutral if your perversion screenwriter you might turn the story into a great movie because
Kaminis Athenians have no chance
They're not just the underdogs
But the stakes are everything
Persians lose here and in what are the odds that they almost never lose
No big deal to that
If you think Indians lose
Well there's two ways of looking at it the macro in the micro the micro isn't the Athenians lose they get sold into slavery
Dimaio's probably all die a lot of people died
And they will pay for all they've done to Persia
But on the macro Athens hasn't reached its civilizational Hi-Point yet
Play sit
You know the part of Athens that makes it so influential on the rest of world history
The reason we still think of it as different now
They really haven't come to that point there on the way mean democracy is starting all these things but the high-water Mark is still a ways away
If they get wiped out before that happens
There's a lot of ways you could play that what if game writes on the macro level we all have a stake
And maybe
Athens surviving a little bit longer at least
But there's almost no chance of that right now
The Persian numbers are unknown as always
Ancient sources put him as high as 500,000 Persians there on the beach somehow being fed and everything well that's crazy
I see numbers as low as of 9000 which would make the Greeks outnumber them
That seems unlikely to
Historians usually think it was about it
L321 outnumbering us that's a pretty
Safe number to 25,000 50,000 men seems pretty normal to run into
There's debate over whether or not the whole Army was there on the beach or whether or not some of them are still embarked on ships going elsewhere doing other
Things don't knows
Not only do you have this intimidating Army which Herodotus specifically mentions the intimidation Factor
I purged there on the beach
But they probably outnumber you and they might have number u321
And you don't even have the Spartans with you
But you don't have any Cavalry you going to be archers
So not only is this like a David and Goliath struggle but it's like you go up to David and say I'm by the way give me that's playing in that
Rock to anything else you might be caring and take your shoes off and do this barefoot
How many things can be against these
Something that adds to the compelling nature of the story the odds are just incredible and then they keep getting worse
Earlier we talked about history
As a crime scene
How often historians have to go in there and
Beauty investigator
There have been so many different interpretations on this Battle of Marathon
That is about to happen here and you'd expect that there would be a lot of interest after all
This battle is often infused with almost mythical levels of importance
I think it was John Stuart Mill who said that the Battle of Marathon
Was a more significant event in British history than the Battle of Hastings was
But what kind of crazy is for such an important event
We know so little about it for sure and it leaves a lot of room for the experts to sit there and disagree because there's a ton of
Things that have to be pieced together
Number one on the list is how the heck does that even happen
According to Herodotus who is the mean the one that closest early sources about 70 75 years later he says there's a disagreement
Amongst the commander
These democratically-elected generals Alpha Mill tities is one
Erotica signal tities and four other generals want to attack
And five other generals on the other side don't want to attack and even split
So he says miltiades then goes to the war archon
Who's there who can break the
The deadlock and no tities give him a whole bunch of arguments why he should
The only one that has any bearing on why all of a sudden the Athenians should go on the offensive instead of
Waiting for the Spartans write them you would think they would wait
Heidi has more weight and he says that the people in Athens
You are liable to turn against them to go over the collaboration side to me.
If they don't do something to rot will get worse according to one of my trans
So the longer we sit here the more the chances are
That the tide will turn in the wrong party will get a hold of Athens and they'll open the gates and all of this will be for naught
We can't wait for the Spartans
Later tradition very late tradition probably unreliable tradition suggest
There was a turncoat spy on the Persian side who told the Greeks
The Persian cavalry
Was gone
Horse manure weigh
The reason that that comes up is because nobody can figure out how
The biggest thing that the Greeks were worried about the Persian Cavalry how it's not going to play any
Important role at all
And what's about to happen
And given the fact that Herodotus emphasizes that they had specially built Horse Transport
Anime to convey the horses
And it Marathon was specifically chosen because it would be good for cavalry
Where the heck are the horses
Turn all of a sudden
No tities is able to convince the war Arc onto support
An aggressive attack
Against the Persian live
I should also point out that there are other historians who think that would probably happen to yours that the Persians decided to attack
And the Greeks
Put on their armor
Got already formed up and met them
Another line of thinking is that the Persians finally decided to move
You know that's okay nothing's happening here let's get on our ships and we'll sail to Athens
And it will
To this Army as we leave them on the beach and then we'll beat them back to their home City
Doesn't matter what happen apparently
The Greeks moved out
According to Herodotus
They lined up their troops in a way so that they could match the Persian line which supposedly outnumbered
I'm so in order to match the length of the opposite side they had to make their
Dinner
Herodotus says that on the wings they were normal depth which most historians think was about eight ranks deep
But he says that they were only a few ranks deep in the center
Why historians
I think that's more like 4
So they're taking a chance here
They'll avoid getting out flanked on the left or the right
By matching the length of the Persian line but they're taking a chance by going off of shallow in the center
The center is where the Persians put their best true
According to her on
Persians are
Caught off
Guard
Buy an army of more than 10000 Spearman
Charging them at a run
He writes quote
After the troops were in position and the sacrifice is it proven favorable
When the Athenians were let loose and allowed to advance
They charged at a run toward the Barbary
The space between the two armies was about a mile
And the Persians
Who saw the Athenians advancing towards them on the double
Prepared to meet their attack
They assume that the Athenians were seized by some other least self-destructive Madness
As they observed how few the Athenians were in number
And how they were charging toward them with neither Cavalry nor archers and support
The Barbarian suspected that the Athenians have gone mad
And quote
Stories been tearing apart
Herodotus's account of events ever since but
In many ways
You know we can't expect him to give us the sort of details that we need to Envision what's really going on here but I mean a hundred years ago
Hans delbruck was saying there's no way
Those hoplites ran a mile in armor
And then got to the Persian line where they then had to exert themselves fighting impossible
So the many many books and Papers written out there about what actually happened at Marathon
Will disagree about all the specific
Of course what everyone would love is a little bit more detail from Herodotus me since this great story up and then he doesn't tell us
Anything about the archery of the Cavalry what happening is just
You left a piece of together
It does appear that there was some running involved because the battle would become known as a battle where these hoplites ran into con
Victor Davis Hanson says
You know over the years to follow Veterans of this battle
Tell others
That they fought there simply by saying
We were
And everyone would know what that meant
But it makes sense to do a lot of historians because if you're going to run into one of the great bow fire armies in history
You said earlier like a machine gun
Archery fire
You don't want to
So the move into contact by taking your time are you wanting to get to the line so you can start to fight in knots
Suck up
Any more arrows than you have to do on the way in so it makes sense
Like almost all the ancient writers Herodotus is just a big on all the details we would want
There's a lot of writing about why this isn't going to be too General reasons one the ancient authors thought it maybe not
Up to the style that they like
To go into the Gory details we wonder about in terms of the blood and the guts and everything in
How it was visually for the senses like a
Horror movie
But also so many of the
Physical elements the physics of the battlefield like we talked about earlier that we'd like to understand better was known to them
And Their audience of mostly people who would have occasionally have fought in battles like this would be known to them too
The way
Yohance vanwey
So the points out this well understood problem we have with the sources not telling us things that's obvious to them
But the baffle off
Quote
Exactly how hoplites fought their fearsome battles is not immediately clear from ancient description
All the most explicit evidence relates to the heavy infantry employed
By the makedonian
Guns from Philip II
Alexander the Great
Rather than to the heavy infantry of the Greek cities
Archaic and classical Greek authors assumed that their audiences were familiar with the experience of combat
And apart from recording the occasional striking detail
Describe the battle only in the most general terms
Army's advance
Fight and
In quotation marks
Porsche
Until one side in quotation marks
Break
And run
And quote
So it's sort of left
Two modern-day historians disorder fill in the gaps a little bit
And one of the best accounts if you're going to do this movie you're going to turn Herodotus Astorian
You want a guy like historian Tom Holland
How to do that in a modern-day screenplay because it's cinematic
He turned it into one of these Charge of the Light Brigade type stories
Spirit of the event
And he has the this phalanx
You know advancing into combat and all of a sudden the storm of arrows starts
Pick up account down there in 150 yards are in 100 yard there in 50 yards you to all the way getting closer and closer than he writes quote
Those of the enemy directly in their path had already begun scrambling defenses
If they realize to their horror
At the wall of shields in iron tip Spears
Far from providing easy pickings for their Bowman as they had first imagined
Was not going to be halted
100 yards
Then is the Athenians war cry
A terrifying you ulation
Rose even above the Thundering of their feet upon the dry Earth
The cacophony of clattering metal and the screams of the panic-stricken enemy
The Phalanx crunched into the Persian live
The impact was devastating
The Athenians at home their style of warfare in combat with other faillite
Wooden Shield smashing against wooden Shield
Iron spear tips clattering against breastplates of bronze
Now though Kenny's first terrible seconds of collusion there was nothing but a pulverizing crash of metal into Flash
Flash and bones
The rolling of the Athenian tied over men wearing at most
Quilted Jerkins for protection
And arms
Perhaps with nothing more than bows or slings
The hoplites ash Spears
Rather than shivering is invariably happens when one Phalanx crashed into another
Could instead
And stab again
And those of the enemy who avoided their fearful jabbing might easily be crushed to death beneath the sheer weight of the advancing
And quote
The account by Herodotus leaves out almost all the stuff you'd want to know about him and his official account of the
The battle this most famous
Yunnan military
Charges Against All Odds like I said so
Charge of the Light Brigade kind of thing
He says quote
They fought in the battle at Marathon for a long time
The Barbarians prevailed in the center of the line where the Persians themselves in the secouer deployed and
As The Barbarians were winning here
And chase them inland
But at the same time the simpletons were prevailing on the wing
In their Victory there
The Barbarian troops that they had routed
To flee and then drawing both their wings together they fought those enemy troops would broke
And in this encounter to the Athenians were victorious
And as the Persians fled
The Athenians pursued them and cut them down until they reach the sea
Where they called for fire and started to seize the ships
And quote
One of the things
Crazy about her rod
Screenwriter
That's what we're going to see him
He's here he's trying
How to please an audience
The Greeks
And he goes into loving paragraphs
After paragraph
Detail
You know over something like
Psoriasin is 6 hit team assassin's going after the fall
For one of the greatest battles in world history even recognized at that time as being a huge deal
He gives us like three paragraphs from start to finish
And in those three paragraph she take some time off with some digressions
And the one real
Solid thing you would think you could count on in terms of a fact turned out to be wrong
Almost assuredly
This is a perfect example why so many the history into this
. have to be like crime scene investigators and how little they have to go on and how they all
Ingeniously do things like
Mine
The plays in the drama being performed in the Greek Theater
For example.
Write popular entertainment
Because the playwrights
We're writing these plays were often
10 * veterans
Sometimes veterans at these very complex were talking
The audience members
They make a joke about
The
In a rich guy who shows up at the Phalanx with the super
Nice clothes in the triple horsehair Crest with the ostrich feathers in the Nimbus 2000 armor
And then by the end of the battle
You know it's all brown below the waist because he defecated on himself out of fear
And the audience laughs
It's kind of because those things may have happened
The audience is probably sitting there going I know a guy just like that
Bright
Play well
And historians can go a ha
Piece together that
Information into the puzzle of what it was like
To fight these
Listen full disclosure here there's a small chance that I told you this entire tail
So that I'd have a reason to talk about my
Fascination
With ancient,
I'm fascinated with all comp
Actually
Because they all
In all combat experiences tend to score pretty highly on my list of
Extremes of Human Experience
By that
But the different eras
Each come with their own particularly horrifying variables
Are there certain elements of warfare there unchanged
Since the Stone Age
But there's a ton of different
Where to write what you facing say
The Battle of Verdun
Or the battle of the Somme or something in the first world war different experience from what the ancients
What's your face
The Warfare since it's a little like the difference between a hundred yard dash
You know I'd a
If you'll pardon the
Marathon
Ancient Warfare Sprint
Modern 20th century in a long War warfare that's
Hard
Distance from
The challenges to the front line Soldier
Different
Like the worst game ever
Would you rather
Would you rather be a
In a soldier in the trenches in the first world war or would you rather be
An ancient Persian Warrior at the Battle of Marathon take your choice
The challenges in
The stress on your psyche is different isn't it
Two kinds of situations you think of the modern Soldier
And there's a drip drip drip constant pressure
If you think about it on the psyche of men
Will serve
In a week or two or longer on the front lines in the trenches Under Fire
24/7 risk of death day after day
The Beats on you in a certain way
Warriors facing a different
There lies a relatively fine most of the time outside of battle day but on Battle day
The stress the intensity in
Fear it extreme
So they don't get a drip drip drip on their psyche they get a title wave
It on your psyche that hits over the space of a couple of hours
Equally horrific challenge but death
I think about myself
I think this is our modern by
I think we all have it
In terms of my modern bias as to what I'm going to
The first World War
Which I have described several of the battles of his reminding me
More
But the first world war is unimaginable is some of it is is something I can conceptualize
I think we're conditioned
To understand better things closer to our own time in the way they fought in the first world war something
And we grew up understand
Eating right
Sit there and use the machine guns there be under Fire it's all a part of our understanding of essentially Modern Warfare
And what people go through and soldiers we know and
Ancient Warfare is much more exotic
Can therefore perhaps carry
Adults only exotic because of the time difference
Because they were doing this kind of warfare
Enough from Stone Age times up until a couple hundred years ago
But for modern people watching it it looks
Terrific Lee similar to watching Jack the Ripper at
It is
Butchery in the pure sense of the word
And it's
Close up
You're looking into the eyes of the people you're killing
Maybe I'm just a modern whim
But it's a lot easier for me
To shoot from a cross a
Nice little intervening distance
Somebody moving towards me whose face I can
Just barely make out
Then it is to sit there and hear the ground
Once in the ground in the last
Mouth
And I think most people feel that
One soldier
Corded one of the books I read it
It said that when you know when you're close up and
And you can hear them
It's a b****
When Ancient Warfare most of the time once the arrow fire was done
When he was a b****
Here's what historian has been we strike
Concerning the differences in what a soldier in the modern 20th century Great War
Sample might have faced
And what the
Ancient warriors on the
Battlefield America
Night school
The trauma of ancient Greek battle
Was different from the experiences which leave so many modern soldiers
Shell shocked
Or debilitative I post-traumatic stress disorder
Greek soldiers he writes
Rarely came close to suffering the extremes of physical deprivation
Associated with trench or jungle war
And never saw their friends blown to pieces
On the other hand
Hoplites suffered the devastating experience
Almost unknown in Modern Warfare dominated as it is by long-range fighting with guns artillery and bomb
I'm standing at no more than an arm's length from the enemy
And laying into one man after another with spear
Sword and ultimately bare Hands and Teeth
And quote
See this is where
Ancient combat
Becomes like my little labret
For observing
You knowing
What's innate in US vs what's
Activar culture on our development
We think about yourself
Per second
I think you like me can imagine yourself firing rifle
Some enemy
Can you really imagine yourself
Under almost any conditions on the battlefield
In a holding one end of the spears you drive the other end into the chest or face of another human being
And by the way you're not done yet
Do something like
That again
You can
Or if that doesn't work and you down to your other weapon
In a slicing them
Or stabbing them with a sword
Face to face while they try to do the same to you
I mean some of you can understand that we
We have all kinds
The people but I mean for the majority of you out there
Is this something you could realistic
Stickley imagine yourself
Doing
Under almost
Any circumstance
Because remember most of the people in these Greek city-state
Sparta
Accepted
Are regular people minis are not professional Warrior these are commercial people these are Baker's these are farmers
These are even unit
The politicians of Athens
Would be out there even
Mini people going back to their jobs today
I can't help it
Austin the same situation
I mean if the Great
Simulation player in the sky
I can't help but think about
My Nick Bostrom simulation Theory at a time like this
If he changes the preference on his game
To one that no longer allows us to have any weapons that were invented after the year 1300
Could we go back to fighting
The way they fought back then
I mean to recreate
A
City-state freightlines maybe the Los Angeles ballet
Train it up for a little while send it back in time to take on the average
City-states phalanx
In ancient Greek times
And have them
Not
Defecate
And run away
As soon as the spears of the enemy came close
I mean I'm wondering if you could even trained one of our military units of their way forget the people of Los Angeles
They may be a little
Too thin for the
I need to train a military unit
Career and send it back
I bet you they be better at than the Greek Phalanx at maneuvering
And drill and all that kind of stuff I bet they'd have that down
It's the Rubber meets the road moment does it counts when they
Have to face the spirit had long of a citizen Phalanx of Bakers and Potter's and farmers
You've done this before
From a culture that understands it
Do you think our
Even military unit with
Stand there when the spears start
Jabbing at each other's faces and
Not run away
And here's the
A question that really gets me thinking
If you want stand
Because we just don't do that it's not our culture
And we don't have what they have anymore
How long would it take to get it back
If you decided you know
The great simulator in the sky just took guns away we have to fight like this if we're going to defend ourselves
How long would it take
How long does it take for the culture to rebuild the ability to do
A skill that has not been necessary
Very long time
And the thing is you wouldn't think it would be so difficult theoretically
But it turns out that over the last several hundred years of people have shot at each other more on the battlefield
It's become
Harder and harder to actually
In a walk-up to somebody else and stick them with the pointy object
It's been quite a bit written about
This
It seems to be both
Particularly
Beard as one might expect
But also particularly abhorrent
To the people who have to do the skill ring
Can I run elsewhere this is one of the things
Make some of the
Feigned military units out there like the British gurkhas for example that are known for hand-to-hand combat
You know more particularly intimidating because unlike most people
They're generally okay with the idea of coming
When to close Grill
Most people would rather
I stay away
Because obviously it's nasty stuff
In his book on killing
Lieutenant Colonel Dave Grossman says
It is the proximity to the victor
That determines you know how resistant to killing people tend to be in that
By the time you get to like bayonet rain she says the resistance on the part of human beings both on the receiving end in the
The giving end of the band that is intense
What happens when you're talking about it. And warfare
Well that's not an unusual event that it is in Modern Warfare
It's the way you do business is how you fight
We stick people with pointy things or they stick us with theirs
Welcome To War 4
Well most of human history from the Stone Age until a couple hundred years ago
Nowadays
It's the nastiest thing most soldiers
Condoms
Grossman
Along with a lot of other historians goes on to point out how most historians think
That the idea that there was ever bayonet fighting in a band that's those
Does long nylon the ends of
Rifles
The people used for a long time
I'm in the American Revolution we had them Napoleonic Wars the u.s. Civil War the first world war they still use bayonets or have
For military today
But it seems like almost never
Is anyone killed by one
The Dirty Little Secret apparently according to Grossman another's
Is that one side always run
Before having to get stuck by the other
And usually according to Grossman decided didn't have to stick together so I just kind of glad they didn't have to either
He says when two bayonet lines came together historically he said quote very often neither side could bring itself to
Clothes with the enemy's bayonet
The advanced falters in the two parties begin to fire at one another from ridiculously short-range
And quote
Ethan quote some other stories that say when
Soldiers would come in bayonet range with other soldiers somehow they just managed to turn their guns around or off and using the
The butts of their rifles is clubbing instruments instead
He said quote
We can understand then that the average Soldier has an intense resistance towards bayonet in his fellow man
And that this act is surpassed only by the resistance to being Bayonetta
The horror of being Bayonetta
And quote
Well of course it is so he said that modern people don't want to stick a knife into anybody else and that they don't want a knife stuck into that
Makes perfect sense
But nowadays you can avoid that in most cases this is the goal of ancient battle the very thing he
He says modern people
Would most like to avoid
Your groceries according veterans who are saying that the worst thing that
They ever dealt with was the kind of thing that Greek and Persian soldiers dealt with in every battle
What's mission of course in this whole question is something from the Persian song
To try to get an idea of what it was like for a Persian soul
Soldier fighting in a little bit more than
But at least normal
From the
Persian side of things but there aren't any accounts
Individual soldiers in the ranks
Or generals or anything from the person side
Just come down to West it would give us the equivalent of what the Greeks do which is a tiny little window
One more little tile in the mosaic
Helping the historical investigators
To recreate a little bit about what this combat must have been like
It's sort of historically ironic that what little you can
Divine about what this must have been like for the Persians you get from the Greek sources
Often talking about hoplites who fought differently
Then thereupon
You have to weed out
Things that are
Specifically part of the Greek hoplite experience that would
Why Persian say something
And then noticed the other things maybe we would call them
The physics of the battlefield
That would be present for anybody
In a pre gunpowder battle
But they were talking about the womb
Beer
Persian have to deal with that on their side as much as the Greeks have to deal with it on theirs but we may only have the Greeks version of the events
In order to extrapolate
What's a person experience must have been like
Mention the idea
Times of
A creeping incontinence and then turning and running away
Because of these ancient battles
Beer
Is the key component
In fact one could make it
Kstat the main thing that a general wants to figure out how to do in a battle plan is how to create the
The biggest chance
Scare
The other side
I mean if you think about people is kind of
Like spooked animals I've ever seen a horse heard when they get scared and all of a sudden the fear spreads for the initial point
Contact
Did a little rattlesnake that scare them or whatever
And you know sort of Moves Like A shockwave through the whole herd
That's what people facing danger would choose to do
Allowed to do whatever came naturally
Playwright we see danger we go in the other direction
Part of what military discipline has been
Aiming to do pretty much since ancient Sumeria or before
Is to keep people from giving into that natural urge right that's self-defense
Preservation and evolutionary
Right
Reason fear is a bigger more
Cute problem on an ancient Battlefield in a modern one has to do with the size
And you have an occasion where units
Panic and run
Break route
Whatever term you want to use
In the big modern Wars
That is a small cancer in a big organ
And it can usually be
Isolated and cauterized
Relatively easily without the entire Enterprise along a giant line being too badly affect
Putting the constrained space of these ancient Battlefield
And it was contagious
And you don't know
How many people it takes to run before
Do everybody
Nonetheless when people start to run
It's almost as though the little fin
Piece of your intellect that is key
Keeping you wear your
Supposed to be due to all military discipline and everything else snap
Any further saying last one
Is a rotten egg
Tianjin Battlefield last one is
Would be a better phrase
Because
When a route happen
The people most likely to stand and try to
Stick it out of the ones where the most Brave the least likely to give him the ones that don't want to be cowards and sugars and wanting to run away
But they're also the last to get away
The one who gets speared in the back
First during the pursuit where the majority of casualties are dished out by the way
That's where you died
On an ancient battle historian Richard Gabriel
In every Army there is a mob waiting to escape
And it's motivation is fear
The real killer on the ancient Battlefield Was Fear
Men in combat have their instinctive flight or fight responses
Eldon delicate balance by a thin string of intellect
Continued stress
Increases the probability that someone within the ranks will lose his nerve and run
Sometimes the actions of a single soldier
Are sufficient to Ford's the onset of panic
In an entire unit
Once the Integrity of the formation begin to erode the ancient Soldier was a very great risk of death or injury
And quote
So everybody's kind of
You're trying to stand their ground without wanting to be the last guy to get away if things go badly so and everything
The hell
By such a narrow strand
Of discipline
The Greeks used to talk about the God Phobos
And that's from the
Another route
Phobia
Beer
For the god pan
Panic
Who can sometimes come into these ancient Battlefield and sweep through them in like a herd of horses
You just spook everybody
I mean if you saw someone get around Your Flank
An ancient Battlefield you might run you might spook and if you do the unit next to you might spook also
You see a friendly unit route you might spook and run
And if a bunch of people
In your unit start getting
Torn to Pieces
In a bloody Carnage right near you
You might decide to turn and run two or your psyche might decide
Eliminate all choice for the matter
And Terror blind terramai just take over
And fear is actually
You know something that is exploitable and it's paid attention to I mean you feel like there's almost a Connect
Into the animal kingdom
You're talking about Warfare in the era where you came to grips with your adversary or nearly so
Some of those animals are get up on their
Your hind legs are stand up taller than nickel balls out to make them look bigger
It's a psychological thing right at the
It's a
Intimidation
Part of the reason these Greeks have these giant
Crest on their helmet
Same reason was Napoleonic troops would get those really
Tall Grenadier
Captain makes you look taller give you that little bit of extra intimidation imposing
Factor
On an opponent at least in Greek times you might come face-to-face with
And that's when something like a little extra
Intimidation Factor could be the difference
Between life or death
In fact some
Units were considered to be in some people's and armies were considered to be extra intimidate
There are stories about whole units running before combat sometimes running after they see the
Lambda
On the Spartan Shield
So that they knew
Some people didn't wait around
To see how that was going to turn out
And so to be intimidating was just one extra thing that helped the Spartans when they actually came to battle and they were
Bunches of units
And types of
The troops that had those sorts of intimidating
Reputation
Preceded them
To be intimidating is something that can actually give you an edge in hand-to-hand combat
Even that term hand to hand combat
You know I mean it sounds almost nice. Look like a helping hand
When in reality I keep trying to remind myself that we are talking about
You know what if it happened today
Civilians out of context today would be a face-to-face
Brutal murder
In a lot of food you can watch
Moderately
Conflicts in many places
See someone get killed
And they'll be Manning a gun somewhere moving somewhere and I will send you here crack sometimes from a distance when no one's looking at someone
Fall down and will be this horrifying experience for all
Concern
What is this shock
It's over in 2 seconds in
And you don't even the terrorists would have after the fact
The whole different thing when you get a chance to March up
And see
Your face
You know it marches towards you and you know knowing that one of these not getting out here alive and you both might die
And as you're getting closer to people summing-up you know which person out of that crowd of people you're running towards you're going to
Aim towards
You know what might be aiming towards you what means the thoughts that run through the head the challenge you in different ways in these ancient battles
You again just wonder how people
Who did this
Historians often used
The book The Iliad
Stories of Homer
As a tool to understand kind of how these weapons
In what kind of wounds that they
Inflicted an LP
Reacted
Because
The weapons are the same even if maybe how they used it was different
It's terrifying stuff at 1
Horrific
An outcome after another the spear goes through the eye hole in the brain loses down the shaft
I mean it's stuff like that
Horrible things lots of people get hit in the groin and it's awful and
And you turn around you start to realize
You know maybe the reason that the ancient playwrights in these authors didn't get into the Gory details
You know about all these battles that we want to hear cuz we can't imagine it
Might be because the people in their audience might have been trying to forget song
But it's absolutely
Terrifying
Warfare terrifying anyway
But having to face
This kind of conflict
I need a I need a river at least in terms of the Greek phalanx
A lot of times two people fighting right next to you our relatives
And friends and loved ones
Local politicians and the Butcher and the baker in the people that you know
And that's great in terms of stiffening you and helping your resolving and fostering sort of a camaraderie from people
You know who are training together all the
All the time you have the camaraderie naturally cuz you're related
And you know each other
And you grew up together and what have you
But when those people start dying
It's the double edged sword of that affecting all of a sudden you in the ranks trying to keep it together and not run or watching
Know your loved ones people you know get speared in the face and having the brain
Run through the I hold down the
Shaft of the spear
Is there I mean it's just it's terrifying on a Visa you don't even know how people control themselves forget about having
Any sort of conscious sense of fear
The Greeks were terrified to all those people have been
Let's just say very
Respect
Full of the power of combat forever
Stories abound
Besides the involuntary loss of
The incontinence Joey say of the of the rancors
Are there stories of trembling in the ranks their stories
Teeth chattering
It was so loud and widespread
I think we're supposed to have drowned out the sound of a speaker
People understood what they faced
And there was involuntary responses to that that are just human
How to be soldiers deal with
Lithosphere
Well how would you deal with it
How is soldiers dealt with it forever there been widespread
Conversations shall we say most historians were very long time
Over how much you should or should not assume the presence of alcohol in a lot of these
These bottles or other drugs
There are all kinds of problems trying to figure this out I mean for example in a lot of these cultures they drank a lot anyway
How do you separate what was the normal wine ration for a breakfast
For some of these soldiers
You know from the extra amount they drank because they were going to in the face of wall of Spears that they had to run into head on that day
Hard to figure
One historian when asked to
Theorize about the
Likelihood
Of hoplites going into battle drunk
He said that the likelihood was that they were
Almost
Drunk
So take that for what
It's worth bunny who would be surprised
One part of me wonders how people
Give themselves up to do this with the other part of me wonders how they live with it afterward
We do things haunt
How would you react
If you killed someone by her
And what if you killed 8 people
With a knife
Over your lifetime
Would that change you
I would that change
Would you still be normal
What is Norm
What if you done this in the service of your country
He killed eight people with a knife
Your hero
Are you unaffected and if you're affected how are you
And if that's not normal
Especially in our society today and that person is unusual
You know when compared to the normal
In a rank-and-file of the population have an unusual experience
What about the ancient world were in some of these places
You can reasonably expect a decent percentage of the
Are people in these societies to kill people in hand-to-hand combat sometimes multiple
So in other words what might be very
Abnormal in the society
HBA
Person has killed multiple people with an edged weapon might be a
Relatively normal expiry
How does that change the society
I mean when people could say
My husband is
My dad did
That my grandfather did that until 16th
And I hope my son will grow up someday and do that
I'm human.
Are the carrots and sticks in the expectation levels in society
How does that alter the equation
And this whole question about culture and environment and nature nurture I guess you could say it even goes back to
Really manifests when you
When you read some of the debates between the experts
I'm weather in talking to people
Suffered from what we would call today post-traumatic stress disorder
Because of their involvement in this kind of murderous cons
Historian Richard Gabriel suggested there must have been thousands of psychological casualties after these
Terrible ancient battles
But there's a whole school of thought that suggests
That that's not true
And by the way it's been wonderful to see the addition
To the traditional historians in classicist to been dealing with this kind of question forever
Neuroscientist
Evolutionary biologists biochemists and people who
In the focus so much on how the brain functions because
Some of this stuff that these people go through can be impacted by the way they were raised but some of the stuff is just how your brain is why
Hard to figure out where one ends and the other begins and the debate is fantastic
For example
If we went back in
Are there mythical encounter between the Los Angeles Phalanx in the
City-state of themes
Do you think if you could go interview the survivors of the Los Angeles Phalanx 40 years later
Can we be expecting some psychological PTSD hangover type casualties some effects
I imagine we would all expect there to be
Let's just say haunting memories at the very least
The question over with of the Ancients actually suffered from this that was interest
As you might imagine
You know historians and others comb through the original material in fact at the Battle of Marathon
Rattata says
There was a case that modern day
Researchers often point to is an example of
It'll PTSD Herodotus says there's a story of a soldier who went blind
Get the bottle
But who's totally unhinged
The story is that he saw Warrior huge warrior with
The huge beard coming to strike him
And instead the warrior struck the man next to him
And the site instantly disappeared from this man
And he never got it back and a lot of is I said modern-day researchers pointed that is an example of what in the first World War II
Hysterical blindness
Are these guys are with reading Khalid
Convergence disorder or something like that it's above my paygrade to understand
But the point was just a suggested in twentieth-century combat it would not be an unexpected thing to have happen
Anthropologist Alan Young for exam
Apple says
That what we call PTSD today is not timeless
Or uniform
He says that the idea of traumatic memory is
Quote
And quote something that originated in nineteenth-century thought
Nieces quote
Before that time there is unhappiness
Despair and disturbing recollections
But no traumatic memory in the sense that we know it today
Inshort the person
Quotes and letters
Reading from says it's a culturally conditioned response to trauma
And quote
The person I'm quoting from those historian Lawrence
Trindle
Who is suggesting that do
Neuroscience now becoming involved
It's starting to look more and more like the responses that modern-day soldiers have just some of their combat experience
Aziz time listen
As a sort of a universal Soldier
Call it a spec
With the kind of thing
Where modern day soldiers would be able to commiserate with these hoplites
With these Persians at Marathon and talk about some similar things may
I brought your mother rejecting things that suggest that the Greeks for example maybe the Persians to
Wind of had any bad thoughts about the people that killed they would have been haunted by ghosts and stuff like that because
All the societal carrots and sticks reward that
You know they would have been Norwich notches on the story about the
The family honor would have gone up nothing no societies really discourage the killing of
You know enemies to the people or the state or your local District or what-have-you so there would have been a ton
Vim support
The idea of the great things have been done things worth bragging about as opposed to
You're fretting about
At the same time
Anybody's liable to go through these experiences that just haunt your nightmares and you wake up in cold sweats
From later I forget about you killing somebody else how about you narrowly being killed yourself
We're watching your body have that spear shoved through his face or whatever it might be
The Panic of the moment
Isn't it just human to expect that that might come and find you later
In your dreams
Or elsewhere
Or does your culture insulate you somehow from that
Article I read suggested
Maybe a case could be made that enough of these societies were enough of those people had experienced incidents like that
Could be called a traumatized Society
And does that explain thing
That it
It wouldn't go through and did I mean
Does it take a traumatized Society to fight him one of these battle that would traumatize us today cuz they're insulated from it
I don't know the answer to any
I find them all fascinating I find the laboratory
It helps us to
Do experiments with these kinds of questions is ancient battle
Door opens up the door I told you I'm totally fascinated by
What does can tell us about
People and culture and stuff like that
And when we think about cultural differences for a minute
Let's remember what people grew up watching
We need more people that in a lot of these areas enjoy going to executions
For the entertainment value
Right select remember that a little bit
Victor Davis Hanson tells a story in trying to give us an idea about how terrifyingly horrible
The battlefield
For the day after the battle was over in any of these ancient battles
And he says
That's sites
Would go to the battle but sometimes if the rulers would one these battles would actually in a fairy the sightseers over
Sometimes couldn't even keep up with the demand
Just for entertainment value. Let me say something here I know we're sick bunch
And I know that if you put this stuff up on YouTube a lot of you out there would go and watch it
Many of you out there
Would click on the website video that showed you one
These battlefields aft
You know which is really indicative of how nasty these battles are
Because unlike Modern Warfare
This all happens in a confined
Space and it is the confined space to create the uniquely horrific slaughterhouse that is an ancient Battlefield
By the way
Is a historically
Nobody will ever see this again and nobody has seen it for like 400 years
This kind of Slaughter in a combined space
Would you go on the tour I said I want to be in that hot air balloon
Which by the way I read another book someone else said so I'm obviously ripped it off on consciously
But I've often said I want to be up there in the hot air balloon
Looking down and answering all of my questions about
Hardest formation
No drill actually move on the battlefield
Totally forgetting that going on a hundred feet below me is app
Salute
People absolutely scared out of their mind cutting each other up at the I mean
Madness
And there's no way
I'm going on the foot tour
Afterwards I had somebody I knew once you said that you know
You can kind of say that
Modern Warfare is like a bunch of jumbo jet
Crashing
Over a relatively wide are
Antibodies are off
Burned or corn nuts considered to be an extra bad thing if you're the first Rewards
The torna bodies are
Destabilizing to your mind it's awful
And the smell is like
You know of
Explosives
Fuel
But if you go to an ancient battle
Oil field
It looks a lot more like a
Bunch of individual murder
Basic basically made it sound like you
Kind of walk the battlefield
And recreate what you were seeing this guy stabbed that guy these two people kill each other but both died I mean
You're watching a lot of different
Individual stories when you walk those Battlefield
And you're getting your shoes
Extremely dirty
Victor Davis Hanson reconstruct
And with one of these fields must have look like and remember he's talking about the onlookers who would go afterwards
To experience
That's what it was like
At one of these
Battlefield the day afterward by the way Herodotus is like 6400 Persians
Diet marathon in about 200 degrees
Which shows you
At one side of ancient battle could be if those numbers are correct
Imagine going to the battlefield the day out
After that he was a handsome
Describes
The reality of this
Historically extinct thing
It must have been very familiar to
Are human beings for tens of thousands of years
Your rights quote
Besides the sheer concentration of bodies
The most common site to these onlookers
Would have been the quantity of spilled blood and gore
And some of the larger battles between hoplites
Deleon leuctra
Template AI
Thousands of corpses lay with huge gaping wounds from the spear and sword
Since the flash was never incinerated
As it came to be in modern battles
By the explosion of bomb and she'll head because the entry and exit wounds created by double-edged irons
Beerheads
Tends to be larger than those caused by Small Arms fire
The bodies would have drained much of their bodily fluids upon the ground
Walking among the pile of corpses
Entailed treading everywhere over stained Earth
And pools of blood
Olivia says that after Zama the battlefield was so thick with bloody corpses that it was nearly impossible to advance
Dance over the ground
Would suggest
That many had attempted to do just that
In his famous description of cornea
Xenophon recalls that the very Earth had turned red
A phrase that was probably no exaggeration
And in Sicily at the final Slaughter of the Athenians in 413
The bodies of the Dead lay piled on top of each other in the water
Their spilled blood turning the very current read
Plutarch recorded a similar picture
After the death of some 25000 makedonian pipeman impedance
The entire playing there he says
Was filled with Corpses
And the river lukose ran red with their blood
Again this seems likely
If each of the following men lost a mere third of his 6 quarts of blood
Either during the final moments of death
Or after the corpse lay in the dust
There could have been more than 10000 gallons to stoke the feel
10000 gallons of blood soaking a field that
20 football fields long
Tumi
Simply walking that feel the next day would be one of the extremes of Human Experience
I can't imagine being one of the people who had to create that
Or
To be honest
Anyone want to try to clean it up
The mess at Marathon afterwards
Could not have been tidied
Too quickly
Because one of the things
Of course being very different man than yours truly
That we are told that the Spartans
Wanted to do as soon as the Moon's phase
You know turn correct and they were able to show up
Too late to fight in the battle
But apparently
Not too late to see the bodies and they wanted to go look at the dead Persians in the battle
Field
R2 on the way
Different times
The aftermath
After the Battle of Marathon
Is frustrating from a military history standpoint because didn't you say earlier that
This is an occasion where
Tactical weapon systems actually impact
History all the way up to the really big trends and forces level
But there's not enough information about how this battle went the way it did for you to discern anything
I mean you want to know how the cavalry's going to face off against the hoplites and how that weird weapons system anomaly is going to play
Play out but he doesn't even mention the cavalry
Which is why everyone wonders where it is
When you wonder about the archery and is the machine gun archery just going to mow these hoplites down
Piranhas it doesn't mention anything about the archery either
The only thing you mentioned with any certitude
Is he said
That the Victorious wings of the Greek army turned around and surrounded
End of the Persian Center in other words a double envelopment which
I can't find historian to think yes that's likely
Inna. We're Greeks were better trained and better drilled in the Hellenistic era
You still rarely could have a single envelopment
Historians suggest
It's a little strange to think that these citizen hoplites for
From Athens
We're able to achieve a double
Especially
Planning to and then carry
Doubt
So the one thing around it
Just tells you changed
How to not be true
History
Enable play with ideas
The Greeks were victorious that they had a lot more to fight for which is certainly true
But all speculation and it doesn't tell you anything and you feel like you waited
You threw a whole thing for a cliffhanger episode
And then the Cliffhanger episode of the show you're watching has a cliffhanger episode at the end
Is the heavyweight fight that ends on a foul
Although let's not take anything away from the Greek Victory it's huge
That's right
Nathaniel take such pride in
Their Victory Marathon that they will continually be reminding Greeks of it for a very long time
Famous playwrights will have it put
On there
Or the equivalent of their Tombstone instead of any reference to there
It'll work in the theater
I want you to know I fought at Marathon
The medes know it
That kind of thing
So becomes
Apart of Mythology
And not just Greek mythology but as we said at the beginning
In a western traditional mythology
Ever since but from the Persian point of view
A marathon may have even just been a single setback
On an expedition that had tons of positives
Pierre brillant suggest that this whole affair
Was a
Punitive Expedition you know we burned
Eritrea we
Had most
Of the area submit earth and water to the great Kings of before we
Left those places work beholden to us now they are
So you have one step back at Marathon
Troops we can easily replace money we have more than we need
And by the way
They don't really look like a beaten Army when they leave Marathon we're told that the Battle of Marathon ends when the Persian to get on their ships and
But where did they go
They don't go home like tail between their legs straggling hoping that they're not chase down
You don't run down to the ground they go to Athens
They take another stab at getting into the city at the Army's not there we just lost the only reason why not sale around take advantage
Image of our extra mobility and capture Athens while they're gone and again
Are rumors of
Fifth columnists inside the city saying how now and field flashing on the top of mountain sides you know
Who knows
And you have another part of the story which is
Is famous again from the Greek point of view
Troops at Marathon
Go to 25 miles on foot at high speed faster than you can even expect them by the time the Persian Fleet pulls into the harbor
What happens if they see the army they just lost to
Waiting there for the
So now they compare the profit-and-loss column and especially if breandan others are right in this is more of a Expedition it's on
Achieve the major goals
So now they go home
And while the Greeks and especially the Athenians are justifiably proud of defeating the Persians at Marathon and they
Should be what are the odds of that
You can't help
But think there was
What's happened here now
Is the Dave managed to go from
Anet
It was a minor annoyance
What's on a dragon or a giant and they were absent-mindedly swatting at them with their hand
Just something the bit hard enough to get their full attention
And find themselves now in the cross
Harris
I'm a man who's not just a king of
But he's been on the throne for more than 30 years
Is uberconference
What is people according to Herodotus
You don't think of him as a shop
Or hoxter we thought of it more like a CEO he reminds me of like a
A Steve Jobs type character
You're somebody who's
In a whole sort of being
Is infused in the corporate structure
I mean after 30 years of world
The Persian Empire has
Psoriasis all over it
And now
He decides
If he's going to lead a bigger
Better prepared
Expedition
To Greece
Can self
If you want something done right
Sometimes you just have
If you think to show you this hurt is worth a dollar
Dan and Ben would love to have it
Abacus show it's all we ask
Go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
Can you have drama without the drama
It's something like
Myself
Look ahead
Head to the neck
Next part of the story
Because if you believe the ancient sources they always make it sound as though
The mainland Greek life Ethiopians in the Spartan
Really had little or no Kane
With the Persian
Until.the. We just talk
But once that. Happens
The Greeks and the Persians you can just see there
Fates become like
Unbreakable linked with each other
And it influences the story dramatically because the dramatic people who are writing about it
Take the dry facts that you might be able to glean
From the Babylonian record
Uniform toddler
And make them laugh
They reject the coloring
Into the situation
If you talk about big political type things like I tended you in the shows
Those are dramatized
My people like
The Persian Empires doing things in other corners of the rim
Things that you can sometimes find out about her green
From things like Babylonian cuneiform tablet
But that doesn't mean they're dramatic and sometimes there's very little to talk about
Other than to say
We can tell that the Persians were
Operating in the North
Used to their empire
During these years
If a rata tesoura Greek tells that story
There's probably a love affair involved
For some wonderful Oracle has spoken
Or somebody's doing some stuff that he's getting some karmic payback for
So even though we want to look at the story more from the Persian side
Pain is normal we're going to be hamstrung like everyone else and we are going to
Have to
And you know let's be honest
It's hard to not lovingly Embrace some of these
Persian and Greek
Kabuki dances that they do with each
Try to look at
Depression side as much as
We can
But as always you're getting the Dan Carlin version of the story and I find
You just like a filmmaker would be give me as much of latitude please as you can give Oliver Stone
To take the part of the story out to just blow my mind and string them together I always figured you can get
The traditional telling of the story
From some more credible Source than yours truly
But you can't get my incredible telling of the story from any credible source
I don't know if that's a compliment or not but
In the next episode of this program
We're going to start out pretty darn soon
At the beginning
Which war
And it's one of the most famous Wars ever
I'm going to be followed by
Some similar conflicts after that
If this
Little
Intertwined Destiny between the Greek and the Persian
Little People's it's a little like I was thinking it's a little like a man and a woman that just can't stay away from each other but they had this poisonous relay
Relationship
And maybe at some point the man representing the Persian Empire who's the CEO of
Amigos back
And finally breaks away and
And the toxic relationship has ended and then somehow some way
The Greek Spitfire woman shows up
With a new abusive boyfriend to punch him in the nose
Oh did I just give the rest of the show away
Well probably in the next episode but I've learned to make no promises
That
And a whole bunch more
As we continue this
Maybe endless
Sakai
With Kings of
Part 3