It's hardcore history
If I asked you to get a piece of paper
Something right
Onto
Make a numerical list
Of all the things
But you would be willing to
To die for
How long is
Amazon
This is kind of an egg
Exercise and you run into these the
I'm sure as soon as
Clarify your
Exercise
Another one I've heard is
Don't write your own obituary now
And you can see how that might
Help you get a sense of
Oh Jesus
To be Sunday and here's how
Brian from that now
Help you figure out
How you doing
The what would you be willing to die for question is a priority
Helps you solidify
Figure out what are the most
Things to me
And if you think about
Bliss like that I mean I think we probably all have pretty similar things at least it
The top of the list when we met wouldn't loved ones
Be on that list right near the top
I would be willing to die
For my wife and she
I have to believe
That's pretty common
In any era in his
And then
Likely something on that list near the top would be possession
Things of one kind or another
Land
Come to mind right
Off the top of my head
As far as been in my family for three generations I would give my life
Number of conflicts
That we're land ownership based
Since time immemorial is uncountable isn't it
Common
Other kinds of possession you might think of his like money
How long down on your list though does it
Go before you get two things
Better little harder to get your hands on
Tangibly
I mean we're something like freedom
It's funny because if you go and look
All throughout human history
Slogans like New Hampshire state motto
Which is Live Free or Die
You going when you look at my
Like revolutionary France
And all these other movements throughout history and some form of Give me liberty or give me death Live Free or Die is on the
List of people willing to give their own lives
Based on the idea than an unfree life isn't worth living
So willing to die for a concept for the concept that means everything when you talked about your day-to-day life and we should play
Point out that freedom is always meant different things to do
Different people
And it's been different things in different
Eras
The two big definitions you run into is the obvious
1 freedom is
My right to personal
Control in autonomy and sovereignty
The other one that was a political sword
Freedom
That says as long
Has no outside people or power or state or entity is controlling
My Pitt
Then we're free we may live in
Dictatorship
That kind of thing
So Freedom involves
Freedom from outside control
Tell me change the
Parameters Varla
Question them
What If instead of giving your
And what you would be willing to die
The new list is
What would you be willing
Toulouse
Everything
And by everything I certainly mean your life
That's a given
The lines of all your loved ones one way or another either
Throughout right death
Having them sold into a life of slavery your little kids sold into a life of slavery
And all your possessions
Taking in all your stuff stolen in you community devastated in your culture
Mortally wound
That's pretty much everything isn't it
What's the worst that
Some of the greatest human tragedies
Open a personal
And on the society-wide love
Bible throughout history
5 happened
Some of the things on the list that you'd be willing to die
Become the cost of preserving
Other thing
And you see this all the
What time in the twentieth century look at how many people
In order to
Protect their societies freedom
Sent their own children off to die
So this is part of the human condition
Unless you've lived through
Near genocidal condition
Most of us
To deal
With the kind of
Threat
Fat people
Throughout history have had to deal with
To everything
That General Okoye New Hampshire state motto Live Free or Die
When the Revolutionary War
For example
He wrote that phrase decades after the war
And in total freedom and
Safety
Now I have no doubt he would have been willing
To give his life
In the service of what was
The brand new country
During the Revolutionary War
But you can also take some comfort in the idea
That he wasn't going to have to give much more than
I mean the
British were not going to come in today
Country and after they hanged him
Execute his teenage Sons
And rape his wife and his children and send them off to slavery burn down his house destroy his town and stamp out his
Church
They're not going to do that
It's a different kind
That's genocide
And people still deal with that
Even if I'm speaking right now somewhere in
Obviously genocides come in many different shades
Colors
Variations
Answer comes
And take the
Jews and the Gypsies in the second
The world war during the holiday
Json example where
The people
We're being victimized had absolutely no choice and no
No one said to them
Either do this
Or
We're going to kill you all
Choice was never offer
Sometimes
It is
Choice a is
You do this
Choice be
Is we
We committed genocide Rainier genocide or an absolute crime against humanity by modern-day standards against
Paying for most of human history
That's the choice that cities have
When enemy armies
Show up outside their walls
Surrender before
The Siege weapons start being used
And you can maybe go free maybe carry some
Of your personal possessions with you maybe not but the deal is is that is
Soon as the siege starts
Most of these cases
They could do whatever they wanted to
Sometimes they might still like
Sometimes they might have a negotiation 3 weeks from now so we could you want stopping now we'll make a deal
But often times the deal
Was in pussy
Historic Hanson we says
That this isn't this the standard understanding
Throughout most of
Pre gunpowder history and even into gunpowder
Are history
That if
You don't surrender when called upon in the city Goes Under Siege
That you could have an absolute genocide
At least on a Citywide level afterward
And everyone will understand that
That's just how it goes
They were doing that
Civilizational equals
Much by the 18th century
Which of course.
The British would have considered the colonists who five minutes ago I've been
Subjects of the same King as the
British
But when you were dealing for example with Savages were barbarians
Whistler terms
All bets were off
In the history of the laws of
Term for
Latin
Bellum romanum
Basically means war the way the ROM
Total War
Legal definition I got from one place in
Bellum romanum is all out War without restraint
As the Romans practiced it against groups they considered to be barbaric
And let's understand that the British crown
In 1775 we're dealing with Native Americans
Might have been very different situation all of a sudden
You can treat them the way
Rome treated Barbarian
Often times with what we would call today
Genocide
But
Often time
With choices unlike the Jews and the Gypsies in the second world war Holocaust
Often times the choice was
Surrender
And accept
Subjugation
Without Rebellion
And live
Or do any of those other things
And see everyone
Either killed or sold into slavery
What passes for a city in your culture destroyed
And maybe your culture itself
Taken apart piece by piece
There's something very strange Maybe
About me
But I see A Certain Romance
Doom sort of Rome
The same sort of thing you see with the Native Americans sometimes will you watch this story that is a calamity
And it times
Behavior of the human beings in it make a tear roll down your cheek
Touch something deep in your soul
Those were willing to say
Yes we know
But you'll kill all of us or
Destroy our civilization if we don't
Subjugate ourselves to you
But we're going to
Take the chance here and try to Live Free or Die
The only one that sees the obvious
Entertainment
The compelling nature
Green situation
A choice like that
Put human beings into because it's a Hollywood
Cliche isn't it
Storytelling
A recurring theme
I mean it would be very easy to tell this to
Story and turn it into Brave
I'll try very hard not to do that
But it's an old theme and it's easy to become
Soda
In Norwich
2x overtime
So numb
The other problem
These situations that were talking about the reality of them is actually so intense and so extreme
Any portrayal or discussion of them can't help but somehow minimize or trivialize or height
In a different way for entertainment.
But the people were actually going through
I always try to think of myself
Imagine if that list that we mentioned a minute ago
Genocide list
Imagine if only one of those things was going to happen to me
In my cushy life here
Where I'm in no danger or say having my culture wiped out
Can't even imagine what they
That would mean
Blue jeans illegal
No more iPhones and they start destroying the Christian religion I mean I'm not quite sure in the modern sense in the United States where I live
I mean you can't even get your mind.
Maybe in some weird
Emotionally voyeuristic
That's what
The kind of intriguing
As I've always said
You can't imagine dealing
With yourself
The story that I would like to use to highlight that has a very familiar ring
Because we've seen this movie historically speaking before
Over and over
Again
Broadly speaking
It's the story of a European power
Using it
Technological and civilizational advantages
To dominate
Take over
And colonize the land
Of a tribe
Less sophisticated politically speaking tribal people
Into
Destroy
Broad elements of their culture is part of doing so
Obviously over the last 500 or so years
We've seen this movie play out in the Americas
Would European colonization and Conquest
We saw play on an Africa to same thing
The difference here
Is it the people the tribal people
On the receiving end of European conquest and colonization are themselves European
And this didn't happen a couple hundred years ago
This happened more than 2000
And the reason I wanted to talk about this story as opposed to any of the others with similar themes
Because this is one of the times where you
Look at the
Odds
And you say there's a halfway decent chance here
Of the people on the receiving end
Of the European colonization
To fight back
And when
The Native Americans for example never had a chance never a chance ever
If for no other reason and there's a lot of other ones just a disease alone
If you're about to have it
A hemispheric civilizational
Conflict in a between the New World in the old world
You don't want to lose
Maybe I mean I saw an estimate that's at 98% I think that's got to be high but let's just say 85
5% of the entire population of the hemisphere to disease right off the bat
There are bunch of experts who
Try to explain what the situation must have been liking these tribes in the center of the Americas you know there were still Untouched by
What European
Contact
What the disease is managed to find them
And we're just like shell shocked
Traumatized
Remnants by the time Europeans got to the interior
Diseases like a magic imagine the Bubonic plague in Europe but worse from the Middle Ages
I see numbers that say that in the end say 1800 they were estimating what the
Tribal population of North America was
No not the North America that constituted the United States in that area back that because that was just a sliver compared to today
But the native population throughout
In from the Pacific to the Atlantic
And what's now the United States
Some estimates are as low as 600000 people
That's a pretty unfair fight right there isn't it
Not just that as we all know
That's not
600000 people
Smooshed into one state right next to the 13 colonies when the United States becomes a state right it's not like the US
Play Saturday with 600,000 native next door they're spread out in small groups
You know the width and breadth of the territory
Able to be picked off
Divided and conquered one by one over time which is what happened
I mean it still blows my mind to realize
How small the number of Native American warriors there are
Fighting
Against the encroachment of manifest destiny at any time
And how well they did based on how small they were would you know if you get 1500 North American Native American
Warriors
In one place at one time that's a sizable Force
The highest estimates I've ever seen for the largest Native American Force of Warriors Everest
Is between 4 and 5000 people
A Little Bighorn why do people think that's the biggest battle that's
The largest numbers I've ever seen or just under 5000
When the Spanish
Conquistadors found the Aztec empire the Aztecs could raise tens of thousands maybe hundreds of thousands of War
Warriors
Obviously there's a different state organizational system which plays into the store
Dory
At the same time it's also
First Contact basically in the disease had not had time to take hold
And then fast forward a couple hundred years
And all of a sudden you go from
Hundreds of thousands of Warriors Maybe
To 1500 being a sizable Force
And look how long it took the US to deal with that
And to be fair
It wasn't like United States had a hundred thousand people against 1500 native
The forces of the European
Powers fighting in the new world were very small also
Can 1500
And US forces fighting these Native American tribes half of which might be local militia that was not uncommon either
Even in the big Wars like the American Revolution the numbers are smaller than you would think I mean again
25000 would be a ton in America
So you wonder how the US
Or before then the British and French explorers would have fared
If they were exploring the interior say of North America and They Came Upon some
People that had not been impacted by the disease I mean what if the Aztec empire instead of being in the middle of Mexico
Was on the opposite side of the Mississippi to be running to buy the Europeans at some point
Or better yet
Let's make it an interesting combat
Let's put ancient Gaul
On the western side of the Mississippi
Is regardless what the Romans called an area about the size of Texas
In the ancient world
The comprised
Well most of Northwestern Europe modern-day France a lot of Belgium Western strip of Germany's of a Switzerland in
During one part of this.
Northern Italy
Estimate of the ancient population range from 3 to 7 million people
I'm a kind of armies that they could put in the field
Well let's just say I'd imagine they're pretty close to the kind of numbers that the Aztecs probably could put
The field
An army of forty or fifty thousand
Garlic
Peoples
5 or 10000 of which might be mounted
It's Not Unusual
Imagine imagine those armies
Better used to brushing aside $1,500 maybe on a really bad day 2508 is having two.
Chat with 40 or 50 thousand
Of them instead
No I have no doubt
Given the technological
Advantages and more importantly these State organizational advantages of a place like the early United States
Before than the British in the fight I have no doubt they would conquer this
Latter-Day version of gall at some point
But I wonder if they are
Concrete as quickly as Caesar did
In the real thing
2000 years before
And if they couldn't
What does that say
Rather than
Attributed to any
Failings or shortcomings
Of the
European or American forces in North America
Maybe it says how
Incredibly awesome Julius Caesar
Bellossom doesn't mean good
And
Up until relatively recently
What she did
Golf
Will celebrate
And in fact going back
100 or 200 years and they are aware
The great Powers especially the great powers of Europe are celebrating the idea of doing exactly what Julius Caesar
When the Romans were doing to the tribal peoples north of them in their own era
They tended to see Caesar as the good guy
Story I want to talk about today
Is narrated by Julius Caesar
It's a little like hearing the Star Wars saga
As Told by
Darth Vader
And it is designed
To have the audience
Cheer
When the Plucky little republics are crushed
And a hundred years ago
All people dead
The beginning to my recent translation
Caesar's War commentaries
From his commanding goal
The Carolyn Hammond translation
Feel the need at the beginning of the work to explain why yet another translation of Caesar's account
Of his
I had one professor in school in the 80s
Call today
Celtic Holocaust
Why a new translation is needed in Hammond points up because the views of the audience are different
Then they used to be she right
Quote
A new translation of the garlic War does call for some explanation not least because the number of version
Regions are already available
Yet each generation needs its own translation of any classic text
The culture and mores of the translator Zone time are bound to leave their mark
Besides
The subject matter of the garlic War
Is potentially distasteful
Even immoral for the modern reader
The drive to increase territorial Holdings
By civilian as well as military casualties
And the predominance of economic motives for organized aggression
All these belong to an accepted Norm of international activity in the ancient world
And hence
Need careful introduction explanation
As well as up-to-date translation
And quote
Of course what she's basically saying
Is it once upon a time this was written for an audience
Who was expected to cheer
What was going on
Nowadays
We look at things so differently and can't help but notice
But in the process of achieving these glorious an almost
Impossible military victories
Julius Caesar
Is killing
Reportedly
A million
Are the inhabitants of Gaul
Enslaving another million
As
Celtic expert
Archaeologist Barry cunliffe says
If you take the low numbers of the entire population of Gaul that means Caesar killed 1/3 of the population in slay
Find another third
Is that genocide
America's
The disease did most of the damage in terms of
The overall death rate
In Gaul
In the 50s BCE
Caesars
Even if I say that I can hear something in the back of my head
The screaming
Objections of the ancient Roman lawyers
From the grave
Of the way that I'm framing this whole thing
Comparing
Roman efforts against the Celtic peoples north of them to the Holocaust in the second world war would be in
An insult to Roman honor
Although there were some who complained about
Cato
None the less they would say that to suggest
That doing what Caesar did to the Gauls is the same as what
Happened to the Jews and the Gypsies in the Jehovah's Witnesses in the gay folks and all the other people persecuted
In the Holocaust Roman Catholic priests
Familystrokes
Those are like lamb
Innocent
Led to the slaughter
Caesar did
He did to a people that were like
Lion
Dangerously
Lions that had attacked before and might do so again
If you are forced
As a state or people or what have you
To commit genocide in order to protect yourself
That's one of a get-out-of-jail-free card
Any sort of
Jenna Seidel Court situation that mean in a judgment call would you say Willis and you know they had to do with anybody
He would have done it
The same time of course
What Caesar was suggesting and we'll get to that in a minute was that they needed a preemptive War
Because he Lions could attack at any time so it gets murky quickly
But there's no denying
These Celtic peoples
All over you are more dangerous
They are
Vikings a thousand years before there are Vikings and I don't mean in the in the pirate like sense I mean
In the European Barbarian stereotype sense
And the Vikings are like version 3.4 something because that the Celts are the Alpha version of the Europe
Northern European Barbarian type
They exhibit all the typical traits
They get crazy and battle supposedly in a fight with enormous amounts of like ferocity
The geographer strabo said that they are warm at
The ancient sources also point out that the Celts are Headhunters
Which is always a
Little bit unnerving
Ancient peoples are always more comfortable with head shopping than we are in the modern world
But in the more settled societies when it was done it was sort of
They didn't enjoy it they didn't Revel in it they didn't take pride in it it wasn't something you showed off to visitors
But in the Celtic world according to the ancient sources that were not Celtic
This was something that was done it only says he's visiting Celtic homes and they want to bring out the heads of slain
Enemies you know that they've kept in a chest you know soaked in cedar oil so everything stays nice and pristine and you can still recognize
Nice the features
And they have found by the way the archaeology has shown that there are these for example pillars
I think they find with little cubby holes
With skulls still in some of them by the way in little hangers to
Do a fix the skull to the back of these things I mean
This may be a religious thing but to the settled people cutting the heads off people keeping them in and adorning your temples and
What not with headset that's just freaky
And was even then by the waypost Adonia says he would get used to it after a while but never quite got comfortable
With people treating human heads the way some people treat
Yeah the antlers of the deer they shot last fall
Put up on the wall mounted with a name tag underneath
To talk to it
Always give that great story about that you killed this dude
I should also point out that
Besides the religious significance of the head
Caesar says that the the Gauls believed in the theory of reincarnation soda maybe you could call it was simple
A major philosophical group in Greece always believed that the Gauls kind of believe that when you die in this world
You just born into the other one then we done the other one you just born back into this one
A correctly
Caesar says that this is part of the reason why they're so Fearless in battle
Because instead of being worried about having your existence not doubting you just you know in Oblivion
You just going to be born in the next world
Just to avoid confusion by the way
Because it can be very confusing
The terms
Gaul and celt
Are used by the ancient sources in a way where it's impossible not to get everything
Archaeologist John Collins has a whole rundown of the various ways you can interpret this the most common ways we were going to do it
We're going to assume that when we say Celtic Women Celtic people across
The width and breadth of areas
That have Celtic language and culture if we say Galls we specifically mean the Celts in
Ancient Gaul modern-day France except
Tetra
They are like all these Northwestern European Barbarian types
White they are strong they are tall especially to all the people riding in the Mediterranean they always look taller
They might have only been like 6 feet if we could go back in a time machine
But if that's five or six inches taller than your average Mediterranean type
Still like fighting giants and battle isn't it
And that's what made fighting the Celtic peoples
You know scary to it's not just their enormous numbers according to the ancient authors
Listen if you were in a 21st century Army and I tell you listen we're going to go to battle going to fight another 21st century Army
An old by the way everyone in that Army is six inches taller than all of us
You might think to yourself
Dang it doesn't sound so good I don't like the sound of that
At the same time you don't you realize
7 foot tall people or whatever they are go down from bullets and she'll fire and bombs just like shorter people do
You're so it's not that big of a deal
But in the ancient world when you say you're going to fight an army people that is on average five inches taller and proportionately stronger doll
All the rest of us when you're doing that in a hand-to-hand sense
It can make a huge difference
The Celtic people were scary
When they had scared Rome before
And
All the modern historians point out that this was somehow a scar
Ran through the Roman psyche
So that even after the Celts really weren't that dangerous to the Romans anymore
They still felt the memory of
Lion attacks a long time ago
I never quite got over them
You know if you look at Roman history there are a couple of Famous Tate
One of them is 410 AD right the famous fall of Rome to the Germanic barbarians
Why do people like to make that.
Exclamation point at the end of the Western Roman Empire
Always debatable of course
But the reason it's such a big deal is basically wrong with being on a huge winning streak to Joe DiMaggio hitting streak
You know ancient
Runs in the sense that Rome hadn't been sacked by a foreign conqueror in almost a thousand years right
That's a pretty big deal in the ancient world
The last time though that they were stacked
It was these Celtic people that did it
Roman never forgot it and is a famous phrase that sort of
Sums up the whole. And I've always wondered if the ancient author writing when the Roman Empire was around take
Taking everybody's but didn't have a Sly reason for putting it in there
Pointing out that
And if the Cavs can say that back then we can live by those same rules the line was
5 victus
Or why we
The translation usually
Youjizz
Woe to the
Because that's what happened to the Romans famously
I had a Forever After remembered as an inauspicious day in Rome
July 18th
The first Celtic Army
That the Romans had ever encountered supposedly in their history
Bore down on the city itself and we're coming at speed
Jerome completely unprepared to meet them
Bunch of different ancient historians who written an account of what happened here
Livi is of course the most famous most romantic and goes into the most detail about
This
Interesting battle where
And I love ancient battles and then when you try to recreate what happened it's kind of impossible any people do their best but the physics
Which of the whole thing or just not understood
And
Ideas and Concepts go in and out of fashion as to what really happened
But there are elements
Humanity on an individual level
Things like
Beer
And intimidation
And very hard to quantify
Sides of a human beings that
A part of when you take those things collectively right what is fear do when you magnify it
Yuan to a whole group of people as opposed to one individual
This is the part of human history that make history hard to turn into any kind of hard science
How do you quantify things like that
How do you say that one side in a battle
What's more scared
Then another side in the battle and that's what made the diff
Or that one side was tougher
And that's what made the difference
Is clearly
The ancient writers and let's be honest historians writing
Even 1500 years ago had no problem saying this
But when you need evidence to prove it
There are certain parts of humanity infused into history that you just can't quantify
I mean the most logical way if you want to follow the sources anyway especially Livy
To view this battle that's about to happen when the Romans in the
Celtic armies first Clash
Supposedly
Is to say that the Romans were terrified
And then 2300 plus years later it actually seeps through
You know can you imagine
That you can walk up to one of them things they listen as a friend as you are it'll be it'll be recorded in people
Thousands of years from now will know how scared you are of this alien people coming down
North
Aliens are keyword to see you add the fact that these are
Obviously big people
But the entire look and feel of them had an alien quality that just is scary and understand Barberry
Are always scary
To settled societies
Not just scary sometimes a little sexy
You can see styles that catch on
Like in Rome the start wearing those tight German pants
But the barbarians where there's a certain element to then that's a little Clint Eastwood at times
But you know I like to think that there's a barbarian scale
12101 being most barbaric
Can being one step away from being a Roman with a mustache you know
That's what depends on where you are
The really cool barbarians walking around Roman leather jackets you know they're there more like a nine or a 10 on the scale if they get
Drunk to get hurt somebody but otherwise they pretty well-behaved
You take one or two and put them in there and they're going to be like a bull in a china shop
And that in 390 or 387 BCE
Is what the Romans are facing on the opposite side of the battlefield and by the time they get there
According to Levy the battlefields already swarming with these people so you don't even have time to get your lines all straightened everything all figure
You're not in a Felix brace ourselves
You are essentially having an encounter bottle with it with a Celtic Army heading down toward Rome and it's about
7 miles away from the city
In all fairness
This is not the Roman Empire or even the
Romans of the Julius Caesar are that we normally think of those terrible badasses that are absolutely frightful
This is a militia Army
And at this battle it's also about half of it is just a
Citizen
Citizen DeSoto
Raising so you have your militia Farmers you do all your fighting for you anyway and then you have
Townsfolk and other people
But it's an emergency and it happened so quickly there was no time
They resist rmb hastily
Rome at this time is merely a city in Italy probably the predominant
But they just had a
A long conflict
With an arch enemy Etruscan City
That they had just recently defeated and it was only like
Are 10 miles from the city of Rome so you can see the small-scale they're operating on in this era
But this early Roman army of
Militia and
Soul of a citizen
Contingent as well
Meet this Army of huge tall
Extremely scary barbarians
And we are told it takes
Little time
Before they are
Are fleeing
An abject Terror
Libby seems to say pretty openly that he thinks the commander
Of the Romans at this battle was incompetent
He makes the
Celtic command around
To be pretty darn good
No one knows how many people died
The movie called The Battle of the Aaliyah
Where the battle of the Alea River
I know one knows how many people fought there either
There are all kinds of different estimate
The low ones
You're probably right though because in this time. I know it's hard to imagine this but
Rome is a true city-state
Probably only controls
It may be 30 miles around the city somewhere in that area
That means so this is a really small scale very early version of Ron they probably didn't have too many soldiers to defend them
The problem is is regardless of how many of those soldiers there were
They weren't there anymore after that battle
Between Rome is totally
Undefended
Panic sets in the city
People stream out of it in
The
Religious artifacts are evacuated in these terrible choices we are told or made
This reminds you of the list of what you would be prepared to die for
We are told by
Residence Inn the city where the fighting men are going to be separated
From the useless mouths including women and young people in old people
You know to be the one to defend the
Center Citadel of the city I mean if it's the story of impending doom
My favorite piece
I'm living maybe in its entirety though is what happens when the
The Gaul the Celtic people the army
The first Army that the Romans supposedly had encountered of these alien northerner shows up
Outside the gates of Rome
And they're open
The city seems both deserted
And
Simply left unlocked and unguarded
Olivia
Paints
Picture
I was seeing that's like something out of The Twilight Zone
You have these may be superstitious natives like I said they're often portrayed very similarly to how you would see
And the Native Americans are African tribesman
Has somehow extremely superstitious had both
Savage and skittish and unpredictable and childlike and mean
It is interesting stereotype
But here's the story that Libby
Paints and it involves
The great old man of Rome from another time the ancient ones were still around with with longbow
Beards as he says after the fashion of their day
They're neither useless mouths
Nor able to fight in the Citadel so they decide Livy says that they're going to set an example by simply
Sacrificing their lives in the hopes
Did that somehow maybe help things with the
God's or what not he says they
These generals from the Past who celebrated triumphs a long time ago
Any senators in August people who are now the elders and Society put on
They're most elaborate and decorated Robes of higher office
Went to their homes in the parts section of Rome
And sat in their chairs of high office their Ivory chairs
And waited likes
Silent statues for deaf
Find them
There's hardly be described
The Celts coming into the city of Rome and it's like a ghost town with the gates open
And they don't know what to do and they freaked out a little bit and then an incident happen
It's wild
The touch is off the forest fire of garlic impetu ocity
This by the way from the Aubrey de selincourt translation
Here's what living rights quote
A night having passed without action
The gulls found their Lust For Fighting much abated
At no time had they met with any serious resistance
And it was no need now to take the City by assault
When therefore they entered on the following day it was coolly and calmly enough
The colline gate was open
And they made their Way to the Forum
Looking with curiosity at the temples and at the Citadel
The only place to give an impression of a city at War
They left a reasonably strong guard in case of attack from the Fortified Heights
And then dispersed in search of plunder
Finding the streets empty
Crowds of them broke into the first houses they came to others went farther afield
Presuming supposedly that buildings more remote from The Forum would offer richer prizes
But they're the very silence and Solitude made them uneasy
Separated as they were from their companions
And suggested the possibility of a trap
So they soon return
Keeping close together
To The Neighbourhood at The Forum
Here they found the humbler houses locked and barred
What dimensions of the nobility open
The former they were ready to break into
But it was a long time before they could bring themselves to enter the ladder
Something akin to all
Held them back
It what met their gaze
Those figures seated in the open courtyard
The robes and decorations
August Beyond Reckoning
The Majesty expressed in those grave calm eyes like the Majesty of God
They might have been statues in some holy place
And for a while
The garlic Warriors stood entranced
Then on an impulse
One of them touch the beard of a certain Marcus Poppy rhoeas
It was long as was the fashion of those days and the Roman struck him on the head with his Ivory staff
That was the beginning
The Barbarian flamed into Android kill him
And the others were butchered where they sat
From that moment no mercy was shown
Houses were ransacked in the empty shell set on fire
And quote
Whether or not that happen that's a pretty cool and interesting scene and a romantic and Superwoman Patriot like Livy
He probably saw it that way too
None the less who knows what source is he was working from
As The Story Goes On basically
The Gauls sack Rome set fire to a bunch of it and start this seat cuz they can't take the Fortified Citadel
In the middle
Data sources differ
What happens next book
The famous story is
That They seized develops them both sides want to call the sea job they come to an agreement a thousand pounds of gold
Right at the Romans will pay a thousand pounds of gold
The Gauls will leave
And then as they're weighing the gold out one of the Romans famously complains
That the weights have been doctored with
And the Gauls are
Falsifying the weights to their advantage
And the King
Of this tribe
Walks up to the scale takes his big heavy sword throws it on the Gulf side of the scale
And says
Woe to the
Squished
Meaning
What are you going to do if the weights
Are loaded in our favor
You lost
Pay up
I was reading a fantastic book
On early Rome called war and Society in early Rome
By Jeremy Armstrong
Floatin idea that a lot of others are floated to the idea that basically
It's this
Conquering and sacking of the city of Rome
Thousand Years almost before the next time that they will do it
That will create the Rome we all know
What's up line from The Batman series where the Joker said to him you made me
It's the same thing we said with this woe to the vanquished line that Livvy throws and right it's almost like the Romans hundreds of years later
You're saying hey you set the rules
So we're playing by the world of the vanquished this isn't genocide what we're doing in
Celtic land when Julius Caesar conquered all these tribes this is
Playing by the rules that you set up when you first conquered ice you made me
Armstrong points out
But the actual sacking of Rome may not have been too terrible because the archaeological evidence doesn't seem to sir
Support some
You know terrible carthaginian solution type
Burning to the ground already
Anything
Before the Romans that probably wasn't
The problem
Probably a lot more
What a lot of beat writer to write about the Romans
It's quite a bit pointed
How did they have this
Inability to accept defeat and humiliation and where has most people probably would
Write something off and move along with their lives the Romans
Faster and focus on things and remember
Old slides in wounds
And the psychological seeds for that if not planted may have been heavily watered
As a result of Roman experience after losing
Just supposedly this first Celtic army they ever fought at the Battle of the Aaliyah
And then seeing their City sacked by them
By the way I should point out because I think it's
Cool
That the old idea that this is a try
Celtic people that has shown up the sacrum is challenged by a lot of historians and there's people on both sides who said
Just at the evidence shows that this may have been a group of hired mercenary
It has been hired by
A ruler on the modern-day
Island of Sicily to fight with him
And that Rome was just on the way and what the heck will second pick up a couple extra bucks to eat on the way in a while we're doing it
So this idea that what we have here is a try maybe wrong and
It's kind of important because when seizures conquering Gaul hundreds of years later
Don't be talking about yeah that's right over there those are the ones that
Affect our country
340 years ago
Does rhombus have long memories
Unfortunately not just for the Celts before every
And it's worth pointing out that you know in 390 win this battle happens to the Celtic peoples of Europe are very powerful
And they're all over the place
And who they are is a great question
Once upon a time when it was easy to classify these things in ways that sounded easy to understand but now seem totally ridiculous
They were a race
Celts were a race like Anglo-Saxons were a race writing all these
You divide the world into the different racial group
These are the yellow people in these are the black people in these other white pill
I mean a hundred years ago you open up history book and that's how they do it
As the complexities mounted and that whole way of looking at things went out of fashion 50 years ago 40 years ago the counter and
Ethnic group
RPP
That's how I grew up reading
Kelly Michael Grant who
Like everyone else would have insinuated most of the time that these Celtic people were probably all related by blood
Those people that sacked Rome in 390 BCE
Are the ancestors of the people in Ireland
500 years later or today
Nowadays
That's a pretty tough argument to make given the way it scene
Amongst most of the experts and I don't mean to speak for them because they're and then just Celtic studies stuff is
Fascinatingly debatable and the passion with which the experts go out of this fun to watch from the sidelines
But it means you have to be really careful and there are a lot of people out
You are very passionate about their view of who a caliph is
And who is not a celt
I love the way
Barry cunliffe we mentioned earlier
I push it because it gets me out of all kinds of trouble to say it
The way he said it he said account is a person who believes
Him or herself to be Celtic
I thought of a t-shirt that I should Market I'm going to make it green of course
And I'm going to say
Celtic
It's not a nationality it's a way of life
But the point is the same the modern view of a lot of the experts on this and then there were
Archaeologist linguist historian everything all kind of look at this in
Different
Is that what we're looking at here is a culture
Shared culture and similar language Maybe
Like blue jeans
You don't rock and roll and beer drinking I mean
It's something that spread
Sullivan prehistory to a bunch of different peoples
The
Foundation of which might have been in place since the last ice age if you think about it
And then overtime succeeding waves
A people and immigrants an in-memory and all that adds layers of spice to the original but when they do DNA test today
It's hard to not find lots of people who have been there since lots of DNA strands that have been there for a very long time much earlier
Did the Celtic era in history in fact maybe you could look at the entire Celtic.
In ancient history in Europe
As a fashion
Era right it's the era of bell bottoms
Cineeurope I mean this is an era where a certain culture dominated
If you go
3000 years before it's not there
And after Caesar is mortally wounded
Truthfully even if Caesar is the one you could say mortally wounds
The Celtic culture
The Romans have been like Kryptonite
To this culture for a couple hundred years before Caesar
If you look at a map of where
Celtic culture predominates at the time that story happened we just told you the sack of Rome in 390 BCE and
Where it is after Caesar does what Caesar does
It's
Some kind of
Terrible ethnic cleansing
The Celtic culture stretch all the way from Portugal on one side
Well I was going to say to the to the Balkans but truthfully there was a
Treiber a group of tribes that that went all the way into modern-day turkey they were called the Galatians
They're famous because
A couple hundred years after they settle down and go for me
Warner E2 on The Dan Carlin tribal scale
They're up to a nine or a 10 in St Paul will be writing his famous letter to the Galatians
They have found Celtic cultural remains up as far north as like Poland all around the Hungarian Plains
Southern Germany modern Austria all the way into Northern Italy which is a real Celtic country for a while
And of course all of modern day
France and whether or not the British Isles and Ireland should fall into this
Anybody's guess
Why do people argue
And let's remember before you send me an angry letter
Account is a person who believes him or herself to be Celtic right
My get-out-of-jail-free card
I love the way
Diodorus though diodorus siculus describe the Celts
And by the way
Most of these accounts come from the same guy supposed
The eyewitness account
I'm a person who is an expert in many different subjects one of the great figures of the ancient world whose writings have not come down to us
A guy named posidonius
But we don't have his exact work what we have is whatever he wrote down and put into the local libraries everybody else
So we have his eyewitness accounts
As Told through a bunch of other different people for example
Diodorus siculus who says
Of these Celtic people describing an ancient culture something National Geographic today would certainly be
Cataloging all the time
National Geographic Explorer of his day
And through
Diodorus siculus we here supposedly was posted in you saw when he visited Celts
Diodorus rights quote
The Gauls are tall of body
With Rippling muscles and why does skin
And their hair is blond and not only naturally so
But they also make it there practice by artificial means
To increase the distinguishing color which nature is giving it
For they are always washing their hair in lime water
And they pull it back from the forehead to the top of the head and back to the nape of the neck
With the result that their appearance is like that of satyrs
And pans
Since the treatment of their hair makes it so heavy and coarse
But it differs in no respect
From the main of horses
Some of them shave their beard but others let it grow a little
And the noble shave their cheeks
But they let the mustache grow until it covers the mouth
And quote
If you haven't looked at the wonderful art
Pergamene art that includes this figure called the dying Gaul go take a look at it cuz it's beautiful
But it describes sort of maybe a stereotype but maybe not the classic look of these people the Warriors and
Anyway it's just described by diodorus
They look like
Punk rockers first of all with the haircut and you have to imagine the bleach blond hair that he just described there cuz that's what
Put the lime water would have done with bleached it like bleach blonde hair and if you've ever had
Like I have before the bleach blonde hair gets all horse mating like after a while
So this figure in the artist sitting there with like wounds in its side and remember it's statue stone color so you have no color
But you can see the blood dripping down and he's holding his wounds in the broken he gets a broken sword by his side
He's also got a mustache though that's not very Punk of the time
But the punk hair cut the mustache and the build is interesting because
You know what's the difference between the modern weightlifting muscles today
And the life natural muscles but he's muscular
But also sort of sinewy and long and there was actually the ancient sources say that
At least in the. We're talking about
The a lot of these Celtic tribes had rules
And they would fine Warriors if your belly
Drooped over your belt line so they were required soda to be in shape supposedly
This guy is heroic Lee new does it's called
And it's hard to figure out cuz the Romans like portraying barbarians is heroically new but they sometimes by portraying themselves
Ugly nude
It's hard to figure out what to Convention and what's real
And this may have had religious overtones or other things
Going on nonetheless
Some historical evidence to back up the hero within you.
Concept
But there are multiple incidents that
Talk about
Celtic warriors especially
Select the groups of Celtic Warrior stripping off all their clothes
And fighting absolutely nude except for a gold
Torque around the neck which is just like a giant
Armleder anklet or something I guess you would describe it so he's got no clothes on he's got the punk haircut he's got the mustache
He looks about 6ft 5
About 200 pounds of raw muscle and you know
Naked
With the talk around it
I'm sorry visually it's
Striking and Cool Whip and if not naked then you get those wonderful Celtic Fashions right supposedly the stripe
Clothing the check
Clothing
We would call today the Plaid clothing
They are wonderfully colorful
Interesting cool people add to that the women she got the Celtic women
Once again we get absolutely shafted by the fact that
These Celts did not leave a historical written record that we could get their views on things and historian
Scrappin
Try to find any little piece that might
Help us to understand their personality better in their own words as opposed to hearing from people
Often despise them certainly belittled them
But I mean they thought for example in the Mediterranean the Celtic women were beautiful
But I guess you could say maybe the way the
You describe them today or their attitudes were that they were also
Uppity
And somewhat ferocious a memory I think sometimes in the descriptions it reminds me of the old stereotype
And it's an old one now.
Housewife in the henpecked husband in the housewife was kind of Burley and had a rolling pin in her hand would smack the husband upside the head
Sometimes with it
Among some of the people out there that
Are sort of that that people that think of the Countess of a new age kind of thing there there's a
A view out there that women were equal to men in these societies and Barry cunliffe among others
Said that they miss
Perception
Because they're only
More free than women in the Mediterranean are for example Greek and Roman women by comparison
So maybe a bit uppity by Greek and Roman standards but that's kind of points out the husband still has the power of life
Death overs wife
The law in most of these places allows the wife
To be tortured to find out how husband died so
Not exactly equal rights but maybe a bit uppity by
Mediterranean standards
I will say
That the
Ancient sources talk about these women is every bit as tall and strong and athletic at the men
They talked about a society where there's more sexual freedom and these women have more freedom to be what the Greeks and the Romans were
Consider to be promiscuous
Certainly there are
Famous
Celtic women
Warrior is maybe the most famous ever the warrior Queen Boudicca from the
British tribes
Remember
These stories may not be true but they're playing to an audience
And their stereo
So if I told you the story about a particular Celtic Woman
And you heard it and you said something like yep
That sounds like what these Celtic Women are like
Be careful
Don't marry a celt
When are you going
A stereotype
How much is
That is true but that's the image
And by the way
You think of a fiery
Irish redhead today in the stereotypes of mean when I grew up this is Maureen O'Hara in The Quiet Man
Just give her a bow and arrow in an Axial Wraith Maybe
Rolling pin
And stay out of her way
She could probably kick the hell out of you
One of my favorite stories about
Celtic women
Is the one about
Giumarra orquia Mars probe
We closer to the right way to pronounce
She was a
Noblewoman not a queen or anything but a noblewoman of adulation try
And when her try was conquered by the Romans she became a prisoner
And here's the way diadoras tells the story
I'm kiamara and her husband or tigon
End
Well mean the end message is clear right first of all the audience would listen to this and go yep that sounds like a Celtic woman to me
The second one is
They are not to be trifled with obviously
Diodorus rights
Just by the way the CH oldfather translation
Quote
Geomara the wife of or tigon
Was captured along with the other galatian women
When the Romans undergone a s Manlius
Concord the Asiatic Galatians
The century in responsible for her took advantage of his soldierly power
And raped her
This man was an ignorant Beast who loved both pleasure and money
But in the end
His love of money 1 hour
With a large Ransom having been agreed upon he led her to a certain River
Across from Agents of her own people
The Galatians crossed over and gave him the money
But after they did so
Kiomara signal them to strike down the Centurion
As he was making a friendly farewell
One of our countrymen aubade
And cut off his head
She took the head wrapped it in her cloak and went home
When she returned to her husband she threw the head down at his feet
What kind of Dawn was amazed
NSAID
My wife
It is important to deal honorably
Yes she said
But it is more important that only one man who has slept with me should remain alive
And quote
Dang
Does Celtic Woman are fierce
The sack of Rome by the Celtic peoples IS300 more than 300 years before the time.
The best stories about today
Take place in a lot has changed
Many of the Celtic groups in other parts of Europe have been
Pacified might be the way Caesar
Would put it
Brought under Roman control
Their ability to
Break out and cause destruction
The nearby communities curtailed because if you look at the history of the Celts right after that battle of the Aaliyah we're Romans
That's sort of their debut on the historical stage
Like the way HG Wells
But if he says
The
Northern people came down into the light of History
For the first time with the Celts
Peter berresford Ellis
But this raises the Celts were the first European people north of the Alps to merge into recorded history
Okay but that emergency
Comes at the head of armies
And those armies broke into various parts of Europe and cause wide-scale problems
4 century
275 they went down there smashed into Greece and cause all kinds of problems
The Romans with fight them over and over and over again in various places
Winning most losing some
There would be a big battle
The crushed Celtic power in a whole region called The Battle of telamon into 25 BCE
And that one the famous account say that the problem for the Celts was
They got trapped
Between two Roman armies coming from different directions
And the highlight of the battle if you like these sorts of things
Is the Celtic Army supposedly if you believe the ancient sources
Turning back to back
So they could face
Both armies attacking them at the same time
Ferociously falling
Basically you know almost
Wiped out
Then when Hannibal and his carthaginians happened in all these great Wars for survival you're the ancient version of World War II
Breaks out
Those of course being the world-famous Punic Wars of which there were
For 3
The Celtic peoples for the most part but not exclusively
Bitter anywhere near by side with Hannibal and look at it there's a good way to get back at those Romans
Which just makes them seem more dangerous treacherous and unreliable to the Romans
After Hannibal's invasion of Italy is beating back you get a hundred years of Roman conflict with v
Various Celtic
Peoples
Play the lead role but not necessarily the only one
In
Eliminating galatian freedom
In Asia Minor in that area in the Balkans also
Although the Galatians had made a lot of enemies and the
Romans had plenty of help
Most famously from one of the key
Kings
Fighting the Galatians where he invited
The entire galatian leadership supposedly
The story invites the galatian leadership to dinner and then Massacre is the mall while they're eating
That's a good way
Devastate the command-and-control of your enemies
The Celtic peoples of Northern Italy are defeated and absorbed by the Romans
And that area will become so Roman so quickly they'll start calling that toga wearing Gaul
The Romans will
Before it's basically that's how they would
The Conqueror
A nice chunk of the south of France
From the Celtic peoples there
Because it controls Access Road access to Spain and they have to get to Spain now because after the Second Punic War
There left there
With a lot of
Really
Ferocious tribes of several different cultures
Summer Celtic but some aren't
Summer supposedly a mix
What do you get when you cross a
Belt with an Iberia
Canterbury
Raquel to Burien
None the less
The Romans will get involved in a war there that one might compare to a 200 year-long Vietnam
War
Gorillas fighting
Atrocities
Wholesale massacres
And the disillusionment to summon roamed this ongoing
Commitment that they had signed up for that was just raining there
In about the year 1:15 BCE which is about 15 years before Julius Caesar
Just birth
Some tribe
Appear
From the north seemingly out of nowhere
Their Origins are not understood even today
By the way
But their numbers are reportedly
Outrageously large
Once again we
Filter out
All of the exaggerations that have happened at the time and cents and still come to what we must suspect is a lot
Larger than normal numbers
It's one of the main thing
Pointed out
Continually
Arguments persist
On whether or not these people
People should be called
Dramatic
Celtic
Or a mix of the two because
A lot of time
Where
Different
Early European cultures come together there's like a
A cultural SG
Between them where they mix
We already talked about Celtic Marion's art
Bereans
Caldo German
Counter Thracians
Barry, just one of those people
Trying to point out two things about
I'm talking about Celtic people one
They're different all over the place Celtic peoples existing in what's now
You know the modern-day area around the Adriatic or not necessarily going to be very much like the ones
Your modern-day Portugal
They're all kind of Celtic with
Variations
And also the time is elapsed in this idea that barbarians or so-called barbarians
Are stuck in neutral
Troll in terms of civilizational
Or
Political organizational
Development
Is wrong to they're all in different spots on the scale and all evolving and changing at different speeds
Some of it based on how close you are to more sophisticated civilization
In this case
These people that
They come down about
At 1:15 BCE are always sort of portrayed
As a 1 on The Dan Carlin tribal scale
In the most Barbarian of the Barbarian
Types and there's hundreds of thousands of them
Not if you think about this as a national security problem with the Romans is interesting because even today
If you could somehow sneak
Let's just play with two hundred thousand as a round number
200000 hostile people
Right on the border of the United States so that when we wake up one morning there they are
Were there there in a very short period of time
That would still be a major crisis
Today
If that's how many people were talking about
In this earlier era
I don't know how they fed them
But you can certainly see how you would have a situation on your hand with the first thing you thought of
Where do these people come from
The second thing you thought it was what are we going to do about them
And the third thing you thought of his how do we prevent this from happening again if we don't know what to the north of us right with
If we conquered everything next to us. We had a buffer zone
And then these people from the north that we didn't even know about coming and smash right through our buffer zone and threaten Rome itself
Between years 115 and about 100 BCE
Teutons
Gymboree
And related tribes is there
Are called
Destroyed Roman army after Roman army I think the final grand total of something like for Roman armies
They scare the heck out of everybody
They March around seemingly going where they want to go and
Doing what they want to do rating here in there into Roman territory out of Roman Territory go to Spain for a couple of years head on back to it
Italy
Finally in desperation Romans
I put this guy in command we just finished mopping up
Guerrilla warfare problems in what's now North Africa famous person in the entire Roman story named Gaius Marius
Gaius Maro
Andreas by the way
Is the uncle by marriage
Age of Julius Caesar
He's a major player in the final stages of the death throes of the Roman Republic
The begin to accelerate and pick up speed
With his appearance on the scene
One of the things that Mario's famously does before he fights the
People that have already destroyed for Roman armies
Is change the Roman army
One of the benchmarks in Roman military history
Something called the mauryan reform
Now to be fair I've seen some writings out there and some thinking that
How the guy gets way too much credit for this for what he did because of what he did
These people would say
Was simply codify informally institutional
Is practices the Romans have been doing
On an ad-hoc basis
Improvisation Lee four-decade
Feeling neither they came up anyway they could and that Marius was basically
We're doing good
To fill those needs let's just make that how we do it
Turn the last I'd say most people still give
Gaius Marius
The 10 of credit for
Taking the Roman the late Roman Republican Army and let's be honest and call it what it is
Turning it into the Roman the first Roman Imperial
Because it has Imperial Prov
And trying to deal with Imperial problems with the Republican Army has been killing it now for some time
Pan
Damaging Society 2 in
Spin off Waze
Mary's opens up to Legions to everybody
It's no longer based on
How much land you own
Farm your wealth anything like that
And
These people don't go home
Denver fashion
It's a permanent
Now what this does is completely changed the institutional memory of
The force is something most people don't think about
But I mean the thing you lose the most
When you send
The citizen Army back home cuz the war's over is so much of what you learned
And the cohesion that you gain from training together and how much math is your kid forget over the school summer
Write the magnified that
* 1000 I mean
Bye
Keeping an army together all the time
Building experience as units
Drilling continually and not stopping
You are building capability and institutional memory so that 5 years from now
Your cohort
Is it going to be that much better
These Roman armies are a huge leap forward
In terms of effect
Gymnast what they could do on the field and how much they outclassed
The competition
He then took this New Model Army
Out and
Proceeded to butcher
The course of a couple years
Both those tribes
And their subsidiary friends that they brought with them
The Butchery is supposed to be intense after all if you have these massive numbers are people which made these people so
Particularly dangerous to begin with what happens to all of them
If you don't kill them
Bellum romanum right
War the way the Romans did it
Against people they consider to be Barbarian
I read one story and said
Some of the survivors of one of these battles were more than a hundred thousand were supposed to have been left dead on the battlefield
They ran to a nearby Celtic tribal sanctuary and the Romans pursued him and told the kills to turn them over in the Celts turn demo
Over they butchered him on the spot
After one of these battles supposedly
The peace terms for some of the people that were left over where the 300 of their married wives had to be sold to the Romans
Slavery in the famous story
The wiser
Reportedly strangled each other to avoid that
That fate
Now at the time the chi is Marius is destroying these dramatic work
Celtic or Celtic or Germanic
Tribespeople
Caesar's being born
That's the time frame
So there by the time Caesar is an adult
Mature man
Trying to argue about
You know what you do about this problem we have with barbarians north of us he's able as are many other generals and politicians
Directions to make use of this deep-seated fear
Did the Romans have about a potential Invasion from the north one that goes all the way back to the sack of Rome in 390
Here's the way history Nick
Fields
Explained
What the memory of the
Cambrian the two-tone Invasion degeneration
Mint
To somebody trying to exploit
Fears
In the Rome of the 50
He's BCE he writes quote
The vivid memory of the near-disaster remain however
And served as a frightening reminder to Rome that a new Northern Barbarian threat could suddenly emerge
Anytime
Barbarian migrations were the stuff of Roman nightmare
And Caesar made good use of it by playing up the
Quote and quote Germanic Menace in his writing
More to the point
He writes
He also had the wit to revive fears of the Gauls that dated from the sack of Rome in 390 BC
Eazy-E
And advertise them as a race without civilization who are not above Burning Alive their prisoners of
War
And quote
So in effect
The
Near disaster against these
Tribes peoples that were sprung on the Romans unexpectedly
Was to deepen widen and reopen
A scar that maybe you could
Say it been
A piece of the Roman
Psychological reality since at least 390 BC
And
You know as
Early Roman writers kind of said
There's a belief that wrong sort of
Conquered an Empire
In self-defense
I think it was Olivia where we going through that version of that line out there Conquering the world and self
Defense
What is other historians put it on a red one that he got a great lie he pointed out that look at Rome is looking for secure borders and security
And the problem is is that everytime they conquer a new unstable region
And pacify it thinking that okay now we're safe over there
They inadvertently create
A new frontier
Whatever the kingdom they just conquered
And whatever their neighbor was is now Roman neighbor and it's another unstable Frontier so they keep getting sucked
Farther away from the center
As they continually try to make sure that they're safe
Not sure I buy that
There's a whole lot of wealth and money and all kinds of other things involved here
That explain things at least as well as the idea that we're just trying to
U-Save
If I were a super Roman Patriot like Livy
Maybe that's how I would defend the conquest of the world myself we just trying to be safe anybody do it
Patricia Lee the biggest threat to Rome
In the fifties when Caesar is a mature man
Playing his role in the
Decline and fall of the Roman Republic
The biggest danger to Rome is no outside force its inside
It's tearing itself apart and reaching the boiling point in a story that is well-known
Impacts this story only obliquely
But if you believe Caesar and by the way there's some confirmation from Cicero and some other places
Rooms. The only place reaching the political boiling point
Instability looming
Apparently Galls in terrible shape that way as well
It's 63 62 or 61
BCE
A member of one of the more powerful influential garlic tribes a try which by the way is a friend of the Roman people
Diplomatic designations of a kind of like a light
Shows up to inform the Roman senate about something that's been going on deeply in
The heartland of his territory
Because the Romans don't know we know they know what's going on in nearby call but sometimes you get to the
Barbarian Heartland and they find out when people tell them and that's what this guy is there to do
His name is the biggest
Then he is we are to
About to
Closest thing I'm ever going to find in a historical situation
2 King Arthurs
Merlin
We are told
The Deepika shoes
Is a druid
And the Heat
Can see the future
Now wiggle side note here
The Druids are
One of the wonderfully famous
Very compelling sides of the whole Celtic
Culture
It's connected to the religious side
They have been called all sorts of things
Generally thought of to be the priest
The Celtic religion but
So many other titles and
Positions are mentioned on the good side the admirable side the Civilized side you'll hear them called teachers
Supposedly you were not allowed
Write down Druid acknowledged and so it was twenty years of study for
At the light to become a druid
They're a little
Leica philosophers to in the Merrifield
Cicero
I think he calls him a philosopher philosophy there was something is often attributed to the Missus Celtic philosophy
They are also called judges
And if for example if you have a murder trial or something going on you'll take it to a druid for
Adjudication
Most of the modern archaeologists
And people like that that I've read seem to think it's a pretty good bet that The Druids are sort of the intellectual
Will class of golf
If you will
Study things like astronomy
Herblore
They make
BV oral
Traditionalist in historians of their people
Acronym called natural scientist before
And the magic that they're supposed to use if it if indeed magic it is
Is soda
Nature magic
If you will
They're like Gandalf
Or Dumbledore but it's all nature
Magic
Caesar and Cicero on the people who do mention Druids
Seem to have quite a lot of respect for them
There is a
Course also the more lurid
Side of it where it's more
I can to chamonix Medicine Man and maybe even witchdoctors when you get to that stage
They are supposedly the kind of people that if not conducting it or supposed to be there for legal reasons
The human sacrifices that the Celts are supposed to participate in or at least once did unclear
Whether or not by Caesars time they still do much about all those Caesars the one
Dimensions the Wicker man himself
You've heard of that
When haven't you the one where they build
The giant Hollow see-through wicker figure
Imagine something like 20ft 30ft tall
Wicker but with holes in it so you could see inside the Nae fill it with people
Caesar says they prefer criminals and convicts but they're not picky if they run out of those
And then maybe throw in some other live animals
Hey and other combustibles unlike the whole thing on fire
And supposedly The Druids have to be around to witness that
Another thing you'll hear blamed on The Druids or the class right below them
Is of a certain form of divination where you stab somebody
And then you look at the convulsions as they're dying
That explains what's going on
The funny thing about the ancient world
Is that the Romans can sit there and scoff at these Barbarian superstitions and all that kind of stuff
Leslie so-called Superior culture looking down on the
Childlike superstitious natives
But then at the same time make sure to point out that listen if you ever need
A flock of birds analyzed for what
The movements of the flock of birds means and then how that foretells the future the Celts are the best in the business.
Another word showing
Yeah that one person Superstition is another person's magic and vice versa
I remember
Getting a great piece of advice from one of my professors ones and how to see the ancient world differently
Cuz we were talking about something he said what about the impact of magic
And it was long pauses my brain trying to figure out the proper answer to that I said well there's no such thing as magic
He says I know that
And you know that
But the people in the story didn't know that and they believed otherwise
And because they believe these things to be real and true
It impacts reality cuz they act upon those beliefs
Play give me a call at the Tinkerbell effect or something but the idea was similar to because you believe in this as reality ubass
Your moves and how you behave on that
And if that changes real history
Nonetheless this guy dipika shifts
Was there to explain to the Romans that a terrible battle have occurred in the deep dark Barbarian country
There must have been thousands upon thousands of these battles throughout history don't you think these ones that happened
You were great Deeds were performed an amazing things occur but they happened in the Deep darkness of
Prehistory somewhere between tribal people you don't know anything about him unless somehow
They come to light
So there's this battle that you can look up now that exist that's real
Call the Battle of megiddo Borgata
But you know about it because this guy this Druid showed up to explain to the Romans that his people lost that battle
It was against one of their traditional Celtic enemies and again we think of Native American tribes were there were just tribes
That were long-standing enemies of
Each other
Right
Long-standing
Crow
And Lakota
Perfect example
Apache and Comanche when you didn't matter what you did they would Ally with an outside power to go against them rather than
Reunite with their historic enemies in this case
It may have been a war that was over trade rights
I could charge tolls on this area of a river and it's something really been all like that
But in this battle the Celtic tribe
Fighting
The Druid who showed up and Rome's people
Brought in outside help
They had solicited
The assistants on some German
Certainly some of these tribes
Did Caesar called German
Let's be honest the Roman ethnographers are little bit sloppy and sometimes they just have their all
Raquel Studio look the same those barbarians
This is the story
Right there
Germans and they come in and they tipped the scales in favor of this other tribe
Leading to divock ashes tribe getting decimated on the battlefield and if you believe him
The nobility Massacre
Do you lose basically
Your entire aristocratic
Class in the stroke
Of a sort
Or a bunch of swords
Destroying basically is pleading for help from his allies the Romans and pointing out
The entire area is destabilize because these Germans who came in to help
Discounted tribe
Decided that they don't want to leave they like it and go they're going to stay and
That's
Causing a domino effect
As they become the neighbors of all the Celtic people around them
All of a sudden
Call seems extremely d-stabilized & Decker
Proved to be a very dangerous situation in Rome it could also prove to be extremely profitable
And a potential opportunity
In fact
There's a way of looking at the story in a lot of people do
That this is Julius Caesar's account
And what's going on in golf
And making it seem like a destabilize national security threat
Is something that works out in his favor
If he's trying to build a case for why he should go in
Fictional
And as far as theories about Wyatt broken in the first place why are they having all this
Destabilization will Caesar has a theory
And even though it's impossible to
Approve
It's one of those lenses that you can look at this whole thing through this rather interesting but it brings up other question
I'd like to point out
The only reason I'm qualified to discuss this is because I don't have a reputation as a historian to protect
Every now and then
Mopping historian works out in my favor doesn't it
In this case
It allows me to examine
Things that used to be valid theories once upon a time until they required things like
You know supporting evidence for
For valladares Once Upon a Time in Costa Rica to listen to Caesar said this happened
And without
Something that makes me think he's a liar I'm going to believe him if you do that
Here's how you can explain the instability in Gaul
Remember
This guy has a vested interest in convincing you
Gall needs his help
But the way the story is told by Caesar and other earlier historians
Is that the reason
The Celts are having some problems in that that whole area of Gaul most of which is still outside of Roman control the time
Having problems
Is because slowly but surely
Due to the infusion of
In a Roman and Greek and Mediterranean luxuries and culture and whatever
These cats are getting for lack of a better word
Saw
Cesar by the way
2 wine
More than once
Does the
Leading softening agent involved
And actually says that some tribes prohibit the importation of Italian wine for just that reason that
Is known to take the edge off
The Celts were saddled with the same
Reputation as drunkards that you often see
Associated with other tribal peoples Native Americans for example affect the liver
For that stereotype
My forever
Our friend diodorus siculus said this about them
This by the way these CH oldfather translation of the work
Quote
The Gauls are crazy for wine
And consume unwatered amazing amount imported by merchants
Their unrestrained consumption often leads them to fall into a drunken stupor
We're sinking Tim a roast depression
Therefore many italian merchants
Seagal is the land of opportunity for quick riches
These Traders bring the wine by boat on the river
And by wagon through the plane
Immature and they make an amazing profit
Were they receive a slave in return for each jar of wine they deliver
And quote
When I was growing up
There was a widespread belief among Native American
Group themselves
That the importation of alcohol had done damage
2D traditional culture
It would not be surprising at all if that happened
Among the Gauls as well
In the case of wine
Specifically
It designed to take the edge off
People drinking for that reason here's the problem what if that edge
Is required to survive in a world
That is
Basically dog-eat-dog in geopolitical terms
If Only the strongest survive is what if you have your people
Being impacted by your proximity to a
Luxury field culture nearby
Who is weakening you in a way they will eventually cause you to lose everything
To somebody
What if you're taking the edge off
And the Ferocious tribe next to Yuan
In this case those tribes were called by the Romans that you get Hermione
Often translated to German today but whether or not they're related to modern-day Germans is just as contentious
Discussion is whether or not cancer related to modern-day peoples in the regions where
They used to be
These Germans are portrayed
As
Like hyenas
Ready to pounce on any weak animal in the geopolitical heard
Portrayed as rough
They're nasty
And they're interfering in the Celtic World in a way
That threatens if you believe Caesars account and of course his War commentaries are told from the point-of-view of Darth Vader
And this is his
Excuse for getting involved in this whole thing
Is that these Germans are destabilizing the whole region and this is what this Druid comes to Rome to say and he's asking for
For helping in a couple of years
Caesar comes to help
And you want to have that
Star Wars music start playing the ominous kind because
Caesar's going to stop the Warfare in the region
But he's going to do it anyway that you could easily make a case should be called the celt
How to call the cops
Now the idea of any society getting soft is impossible to quantify
Falls into that category we discussed earlier but
What is human qualities
Historians have to steer clear of because you can't make any sort of case if no data
100 years ago
The wonderful professorial military historian hands dalebrook had no problem laying it out you in a way
But he treated this
In scientific
You couldn't say this today
But it sets up this
They're fun idea I want to throw out the RISD foolish
History
A hundred years ago actually back in 1908
Brook Road
About this
Questionable
Civilization versus barbarism in terms of the military Pros
Kanji said quote
When modern peoples
It means the people in his era 1908
Come into conflict with barbarians
The outcome is determined from the start by the differences in weapons technology
In Antiquity this relationship was not so simple
Here we may wonder he writes
In what Manner the Roman military system was really Superior to that of the Barbarian
Visa ve
Civilized people
Barbarians have the advantage of having at their disposal the warlike power of unbridled animal instinct
A basic toughness
Civilization refines the human being he writes
Making him more sensitive
And in doing so it decreases his military worth
Not only his bodily strength
But also his physical courage
These natural shortcomings must be offset in some artificial way
Scharnhorst he writes
What's perhaps the first one to state that the main service of the standing army
Consisted of making civilized people
Through discipline capable of holding their own against the less civilized
If a given group of Romans normally living as Citizens are peasants had been put up against a group of barbaria
Games of the same number
The former would have undoubtedly have been defeated in fact they probably would have taken flight without fighting
It was only the formation of the close-knit Tactical body of the cohort
Equalize the situation
And quote
It's an old idea
Brightest civilization
Allows you to compensate for what you lose when you give up that whole Warrior Society
I remember the military trade-off
For losing this Barbarian Edge
It's supposed to be
You have the ability to control
Troops with officers in
Instill drill
An organization in the logistical ability to concentrate
In a food and supplies and keep armies in the field all those wonderful benefits
But what if you get hit
You know when you've lost the Barbarian Edge part but you haven't quite gained the benefits of civilization yet what if you get hit when your
Korean translation
At the vulnerable
Point between
The two kinds of approaches I mean for example have you ever heard what A BMC is when your ship is being to to the Sea
It means a ship is getting hit broadside with the wave
That's a really dangerous thing that happy you want to have your
Your nose pointed or your Stern pointed
But you don't want to be sideways on the big waves
But if you have to turn around
In the sea
Didn't we that danger point one for a second your side onto the waves I wonder if one could make a case
And some of these
Celtic tribes in Gaul
Heaven
Contacted by the Romans enough to be semi civilized
Which doll their Barbarian Edge against
They're less civilized Neighbors
Without yet providing the benefits
30 more
Centralized urbanized State like systems have
The Celts got caught in a BMC
And to be fair this is not
My ID
Yeah my idea to knock off of the very one seizures proposing here to he's talking about the beam CID
In different terms
The problem is is if you're trying to defend this from a historical Viewpoint how do you do it
And there's no doubt at all that historians are a thousand percent right when they say the teacher classic
Recurring themes in ancient literature that the audience expected
Absolutely correct
But does that mean that you can automatically rule out all of them
Is what Caesar says here so implausible and if so does Caesar know it
Is he deliberately trying to lie to us
Or is he just misconstruing things because of his own biases from his own era
Can any case The BMC idea may not be quite originally mine
I'm just
Academically safe enough cuz I don't have any credentials at all
To be able to suggest that maybe
There's more to it
Pain is often
Acknowledge these days
Caesar in his War commentaries
Explains several times
That certain tribes used to be
More feared and more tough and now weren't
In other words implying that they
Movement on the softness vs. toughness scale
What he doesn't really tell us because maybe it's
Common knowledge
Is how advanced
Some of these garlic tribes were including the one that this Druid if it gets just came from
This is the way history naydra
Goldsworthy's
Explain sort of the system
In Gaul which is hard to describe because it has so many different tribes and all these tribes are in different states of
Development in fact
The most advanced of the maybe shouldn't be called tribes at all
But is gold worthy explains
What do you call him States or tribes neither one of those words is a good translation for the Latin that sees
Pictures of a gold
Tuition after explains
Is Gaul
Is essentially organized
In tribe divided into Clans but
Call someone who states quote
The basic political unit was the Klan
And several of these usually made up a try
I give the Latin word
By the way and then he said that neither English word is entirely appropriate
And some Scholars would prefer state to tribe but no one has really come up with anything better
Ethan says quote
The importance of the tribe seems to have increased markedly in the century before Caesars arrival in golf
And some Scholars would like to see them is comparatively recent inventions
More probably
The changing political and economic climate in Gaul had simply given new importance to loose ties of
The kinship and ritual
They were very long established
Even so he writes
The degree of unity between the clans of One Tribe very considerably
And there were a number of cases during the gallic wars
We need to visual Clans acted independently
Kings appear in some tribes and perhaps also with the clan level but not in others
And the majority meaning of majority
Groups
Seem to have been governed by councils or Senate
With day-to-day running of Affairs being placed in the hands of elected magistrates
Rome's oldest Ally the Eataly
Just wear this
Drew it was from
Add a supreme magistrate called the vertebrate
Who held office for a single year
No man could be elected twice to this post
Nor can any member of his family hold the office during his lifetime
Thus preventing any individual or group from monopolizing power
The similarity of this ideal to the Roman Republic system is striking
And in many ways
The tribes of Gaul resemble the city-states of the Mediterranean world
So perhaps in an earlier stage of development
Ndk
That's a really
Good concise way to explain that situation
And there are books written about seizures book
And more on this in a second cuz that's what we're going to follow and get into
That describes his rationale for arguing about why we have to have this conflict against the Gauls now
White have to be pre-emptive as opposed to waiting until they all attack us
And he says it's because Caesar is making the argument
Did some of these tribes are becoming more like us
And we have to get them before they do cuz they're going to leave then combine
You know the
Warlike
Irrationality that they have now in their spirit
With greater capability
Which by the way is a
Reason that some historians give for why the Germanic peoples
You know fast forward to the fall of Rome will eventually be able to defeat the Roman Legions
But they will learn enough fighting the Romans over time
And develop enough of a state like system
That they could truly be dangerous
Andrew M riggsby in his book Caesar in Gaul and Rome war in words
Points out that Caesar's argument in his book
Is it we have to get the Gauls now before they do precisely that
He says that in Caesars work
And as part of the propaganda
The people he called Gauls and people he called German serve different purposes
Rigby rights quote
In the same way the two Northern groups are dangerous for complementary reason
In the case of the German the problem is their fluidity
The people who do not recognize boundaries
Social Geographic
Cannot be trusted to stay in their own territory and to not make war on the Romans
With the Gauls
The problem is not randomness
But I'm more specific tendency to wage war
They are prone to fighting
Both individually and collectively
Their temerity makes them unable to check violent impulses
Even when that would be the prudent course of action
Whatever the source of danger the Romans will respond preemptively
As chapter 6 discusses he writes
This is an important source of justification for military actions
Furthermore the semi civilized Galls provide a special kind of threat
Their similarity to the Romans grows over the course of the war
If they are not conquered now the threat will only increase
Answer the preemptive strike is required now
The characterization of both peoples he writes
Legitimizes their Conquest
The specific nature of the Gauls
Make them particularly attractive candidates
And quote
Why would Caesar want to conquer them
Oh yes
That gets us to some of the problems that motivate
This story to push it along the add the booster Rockets to the whole thing because
I mean let's be honest
What's the likelihood that is Rome becomes more powerful
It doesn't absorb these tribal areas to their North
That's like saying that you could expect somehow via treaties in good faith and everything else
The 13 u.s. colonies to just stayed over where they were on the Eastern Seaboard and never Advanced into the
Native territory
That's a what if
But you can hardly
Even
Plausibly play with right and what's the likelihood
What's the likelihood
The Romans don't absorb
These tribes to the north and Conquer that territory
Because the money that is available
Inland and let's not forget this cuz it's huge
Slaves
Is so tempting
And Caesars need is so great at this time
That is impossible to imagine that that giant pot of gold but is Gaul
Wouldn't be taken by somebody in the attitude that these Romans had in it
Part of something we discussed in another program
This insane and yet wonderfully
Merit-based system
Will you call your way to the top like it's a mafia crime family and Only the Strong Survive
Head created by this time in Roman history
A three-headed monster that's what the Romans called it
We know what is the first triumvirate today and essentially what it is is a conspiracy
One of the great conspiracies in all world history
It is Caesar and the other two most powerful men in Rome and their
Allies essentially
Against the rest of the Roman governor
And they are so powerful and they control so many people and one of these guys in this 3-headed Monsters the richest man in Rome
He sprayed money everywhere and that makes a huge difference that
By this time. As long as these three men Caesar
Pompey and Crassus agree on something it's going to happen
All three men want something
So all three men support each man getting what they want
What Caesar wants is a chance
To conquer something
He is the least
Grand this time. Of those three people
He doesn't have a whole lot of military conquest to his record or his name yet
And he owes so much money that one point we're told he's not even allowed to leave Rome the creditors basically grab him
Either you're paying up or you're not going anywhere and Crassus one of the members of the three-headed monster the rich guy comes in and
Pays off the debt so seizure can go and do what he needs to do
We just find a way to get the money
To pay off the debts
And also
To spread it around in Rome
To make more friends because these politicians and that's what Caesar is there deadly politicians their politician generals
But spreading money around Rome throwing games and all kinds of other things is how you get your name out there and it's a
Large
Part of the reason why seizures in such great dad
And there's two ways of looking at the garlic situation at the time
One is to say
There's all that land and all those lays there for the taking the gall seem vulnerable and the Germans are coming in
Doing it
And the attitude being a somebody going to get that it's going to be us
The other way of looking at it
Is it this whole idea of a German thread is part of a manufactured
Plot
A reason that provide Caesar with an excuse to go in there
And scoop up
All that wealth
Himself
And to do so right for the glory in defense of Rome
This brings us
To the actual War
Terry's because we're going to have to rely on these
And yet
I'm not sure you could find if you had to be stuck with one main source I'm not sure you could find a better one
It is one of the great works of literature of all time
In military history
There's very few things like
As historian Michael Grant
Setopati
It was the best account of warfare that it ever been written by a Roma
And it retain the Supremacy at least another for centuries
And quote
He also wrote
Did because of seizures I mean Caesar was one of the great writers of all time and so much of the Earth is other
Qualities are overshadowed by
Is military reputation
But the concise surprised that he used and everything
Made his work a staple of
In a first-year Latin course is all throughout the
Western Civilization the world and everybody knew Caesars work Once Upon a Time
Michael Grant also said quote
Caesar's formidable intellect and Lucid concise Latin
Transform these ostensibly modest Works into masterpiece
Is unique inside knowledge carries extraordinary Authority
And quote
It's very rare
To have essentially the war dispatches
Of one of the great commanders of all time I mean you have nothing like this from Alexander the Great
For example or most of the other people in where's Jenkins cons
One of the ones that you can have fun reading today for example
Is if you go read the second world war series as penned by Winston Churchill
You get a similar sort of field because instead of having somebody tell you the story they're basically telling you the story from within the story
There's a lot of I said and then he said to me and then
I mean it's a completely different way to view history you know it's completely biased mean Churchill even said
I know history shall treat me kindly cuz I should be writing that history
Well that's what Caesar doing to
And one of the parts that will screw you up the most if you never read it before is he refers to himself 99% of the time
I'm in the third person
Caesar Caesar did that
It's a little strange but
If you understand and read several books
Just on that book and it's fascinating the way they tear it apart and and look at all the angles cuz Caesars playing three-dimensional chess
Would this work
He's writing it for a contemporary audience and for the future
The little intricacies that you would have to actually not just speak Latin but archaic Latin and have a really good idea
Contact
These experts will point out that
Just based on the way Caesars using the Latin language she may have been writing it may have been political purpose
Because instead of writing Maybe
For the aristocracy of Rome in the power Brokers in the Senate
Caesar was a popular he was one of these people that made his political name supposedly appealing
To the needs of the people as opposed to the wealthy people in Rome
So he may have written this maybe not even to be read maybe read aloud
To the crowds in Rome
In a language that was straightforward that they would understand and pulling themes and ways of approaching the story
For example
Praising the average Roman soldier quite a bit
And something to Curry favor with the crowd
This is a political document
It's a document of personal aggrandizement
It is a piece of propaganda
And it is also the best source
Of military
Conduct that you were going to get to the Byzantine
Maybe the best source you're going to get in the entire ancient world
For a man as Michael Brandt says
Whose authority is absolutely unmatched
Who would you rather if you could only have one account
Would you rather have it from
An unbiased Observer would be nice
But when Caesar tells you
About the intricacies of this war he's telling it to you
United the man who decided on things
She's bias as hell but he's an absolutely
Unbelievable source to be able to hear from the first person sent
Caesar gets the command he wants from the three-headed monster he was looking at a place called Daisha over near the Adriatic
Because maybe a placed it to involve himself at the good place where I can conquer some people make some names and
Secure Rome's borders
But trouble Brews over in Gaul instead
And it flared up
In an indirect way if you believe the source is because of this new German situation
A tribe
That was located her territory number to call and try to get some of these places were really Proto States or States let's understand
Krabs is a bad word but that's goldsworthy says we're kind of stuck with it
But this tribe
Located in what's now modern-day Switzerland Caesar says decided they were going to move
Enlightening neighbors of the Germans and they fell
Too constrained
In this land Hand by mountains and not in the territory they were going to move and they were going to move in a way
Where they were going to cross
Roman territory this Southern
France area that the Romans had to take
Had to take
Take a course to protect this road to Spain
They called it the prophet
Providence
Today I think I'll
Cesar just always called
The province
And this group of Gauls from modern-day Switzerland
Numbering the ancient sources said nxcess of 350 thousand people
In a migration you know men women children the whole thing
Bring your possessions bring your towns
3 years in the makings and leave
350 plus thousand people going to cross Roman territory
And Caesar in the room is basically saying no they're not
Now this is where seizures narrative begins
Before he starts explaining another Golic
Where's the first thing he does is for a paragraph or two he lays out the land for your average Roman
Consumer of his media
We would say
Today
Because one Caesar gets away from the clothes parts
Right toga wearing Gaul
The next short hair golf
Once you head-on into long hair go you are continually moving into less and less well-known territory the farther
Hugo
Caesar becomes a bit ly
Like a
Lewis and Clark
Expedition at some point
In this endeavor a very heavily armed one it must be said
Arizona has to lay out initially the lay of the land for the
People in Romney talks about 3
Big cultural groups
That inhabit this whole area
And the differences between them in one of the more famous passages in all ancient literature
Napoleon all the greats read that
Caesar in the
Doesn't matter which translation you use its it suitably awe inspiring in my opinion
In all of them
I use a Carolyn Hammond translation for this but
And here he is laying out the land for you and by the way
Notice how he's also kind of
Beginning the
Transition idea the softening ideas
Roman luxury softening
And by the way I'm going to say Bell gay
Guy some people
What's a LG
There's an old saying that there's a right way and a wrong way to mispronounce Latin so hopefully we're mispronouncing it the right way in this Pro
Most of the time
Cesar Chavez
That's amazing
The Caesar right
Caesar's writings
It's crazy.
Seizure rights
Quote
The whole of Gaul is divided into three parts
One of which the belgae inhabit
The aquitani another and the third a people who in their own language are called
Helps button hours
Galls
They all different among themselves in respect
2 language
Way of life and laws
The river garron divides the gulls from the aquitani and the Marne and Seine River is separate them
From the belgae
Of these three the belgae are the bravest
Were they are farthest away from the civilization and culture of the prophet
Meaning of Roman
Merchants rarely travel to them or import such Goods as make men's courage week
And womanish
They live moreover
In close proximity to the German
Who inhabit the land across the Rhine
And they are continually at war with them
For this reason the hell VT also exceed the other Galls in bravery
Because they are embroiled in almost daily battles with the germ
Either when they are awarding them off from their own Frontiers
Or when they themselves take the fight into enemy territory
And quote
Historian Andrew M riggsby goes to Great Lengths to point out the
Cesar is actually establishing his own boundaries for his own purposes here
And that these may not have been boundary that were recognized in other
Places necessarily and Caesar is creating boundaries so that he can come to Natural extensions of them and stop
I mean it's all very interesting but the point is is that a procedure says with a grain of salt
As always
But he's basically telling you the lay of the land in Gaul and then right after he does
He starts talking about a conspiracy
The conspiracy
That will legitimize actions in
Galbi on stopping the migration of his tribe
But according to Caesar it's behind the migration of the helvetians
East 350 thousand people or more that Caesar says
Burned their 400 villages
And 12 towns maybe some of which Maven Proto cities
Before setting off so that they would know
The we're not going home right
Same ol thing on the captain of the ship
In the Shipwreck burn the ships so you don't think of going home or going to burn these Villages and then we no going back
And
But Napoleon referred to this part of Caesars being simply in comprehensible
Hans delbrook
Golf that there could be all these
Tribal peoples on the March like this
Walking with the logistical disaster will be
But a couple of modern-day is doing some interesting way of looking at it kind of comparing it to the way you would have compared
People who showed up for the Woodstock
Rock concert in the 60s right
Small groups of people so they're migrating at a time caring most of what they needed on their back or with a single wagon and having them
Migration take a longer period of time
So instead of having like one Army
Moving around you have
Groups of people migrating in and the way Caesar tells the story it sounds more like
Now these are it should be pointed out probably heavily armed migrants so let's not make
A bunch of lions out to be little lambs
Right
But Caesar claims
Did the migration is all part of a plan
And the leader of this tribe of helvetians is trying to become a king
But the tribe doesn't have Kings anymore
They have
Magistrate
An elected official
And
Some sort of aristocratic oligarchic Senate of A Sort and
The punishment for trying to turn the society back to a kingship is to be burned alive Caesars
Now I should point out that this information is delivered to us
By Caesar on like the very beginning
Of his
Commentary
Right after he lays out the way that
Gaul is divided into different groups
He then explains this story
The story involves three garlic
Nobleman
Powerful guys in three different powerful God
What tribes
Ethan describes a scenario that a couple of historians
You don't point out and it's obvious and ironic and there's some code of psychologic
Nothing maybe going on the seizure but he describes
A three-headed garlic first Triumph
If you will in other words
He's explaining that these garlic noblemen are working together
To help each other get what they want in terms of more power
Situation seizures involves hitting
Back in room with those two other guys that make up the
The first triumvirate right
He's a lot more critical
Of their triumvirate the use of his own
He makes it out to be Sinister AC
Just at these three garlic nobleman
Plotting to take over all of Gaul
Which you know again if we're looking at it from the point of view
The Gauls
Isn't that what you'd want them to be doing
And by the way it is already been done by other garlic tribes in other areas that the wrong is that already taken over in Spain by the waves
Common
Is a national hero
Portugal
Consolidated tribes
And the locals and fought the Romans for a long time happened in packaging galatia to happen.
The Balkans to
So it's sort of standard
Panigale point of view these three guys might have been national heroes like Winston Churchill type thing the Romans are coming the Russians are coming
We have to combine at the national security question but Caesar plays it ought to be a raw grab
Power by the three guys
And one of them is the helvetian ruler in the reason he's moving his people is much more Sinister than just
They need more territories part of the plot
The Roman diplomacy
Was at RhymeZone people find out
The involved in this plot
Information about have a big trial
Are they going to bring this guy and he shows up with like ten thousand of his best friends
Annie's retainers and whatnot to the
Court in the court basically have to gulp
And let him go
And then Caesar says
The Civil Wars about to start then mysteriously the dude dies his name was Argueta Rex
But the tribe still going to move
Because it was in the plan
And sold that starts this chain of events that will eventually lead to
Celtic culture in with Now France being mortally wounded
So what's the cause of all this if you're in a war crimes trial
How did this happen a cleansing or whatever come to beat will it all starts with
The rationale here's how Caesar lays it out in my
Sa handford translation quote
The foremost men among the helvetia and rank and wealth
What's organic
In the consulship of Marcus Masala and Marcus piso
He was induced by the hope of obtaining royal power to organize a conspiracy of noblemen
And persuaded his countrymen to emigrate and math
Telling them that they were the best fighters in golf
I could very easily conquer the whole country
And quote
Ethan explains
This organic soda
Leeds
The entire movement to get it together to burn the homes eventually
And migraines and then as part of the process of negotiating with nearby tribes you know that they would have to pass through
Restart make it a couple of important friends each other tribes
They decide to work together
Procedure says quote
Or get Eric's convinced them these other two
Aristocrats
That these schemes were quite easy of achievement by telling them that he intended to usurp the sovereignty of
Arizona State
What you said was beyond question the most powerful in golf
And then he would use his wealth in military strength
To secure them the possession of their Thrones
Is arguments proved effective
The freemen sworn oath of mutual loyalty
Hoping that once they had made themselves Kings
The great power of the warlike people they ruled when they able them to get control of all of Gaul
And quote
If you're looking at this from a pro garlic perspective though
That might be a good idea Cesar portrays it as otherwise but remember in this story it's Darth Vader's account
And we get to have
Celtic X Burberry Conley
Offers
An idea or way to look
Redis where
The people of
Gulf War
Unusually threatened during this
Time. Maybe in
Crisis
In which case t
Migration of the helvetians might have been much more like a
Cherokee Trail of Tears
If you want to compare it
Did something from the Native American terminology
He says that Caesars oft-quoted
Rationalization
The gall would have to be taken over by the Romans if it were not to become Germanic
He says quote may have been an unbiased interpretation of the evidence he had before him
And quote
Cunliffe also points out
That events
Quite a distance from here could be having effect
Ripple effect
For example he talks about the dacian which are a barbarian people that may or may not be dramatic also
Having a huge offensive against another Celtic people in the Hungarian plain which has a domino effect
An accordion effect that in a Caesar ends up being with the end result of
You know how these helvetian start to move cuz tribes to the east of the helvetians are being displaced
So the Celtic peoples of Europe and Galls specifically are threatened from multiple
Directions
I'm different people
Let's try the helvetians would have been on like the bleeding edge
Of what maybe was starting to look like the sick man of Europe for this time.
And they were having
Pieces of their territory beating off from every direction
The Germans from the East that dacian from the southeast and now the Romans from the south
Darn right you be talkin about consolidating your power
Try to resist this if you could
Caesars
Great
Period in his history
Begins when he confronts
This
Person
Column of humanity
If you believe either the numbers the way
They showed up but rum and doors
Over River
With a bridge
That Caesar had just destroyed
Basically
This group of people.
Front end of this tribe is reached Caesar and now they're going to have to ask him for permission to come into the
Providence
Caesar's going to say let me think about it
Go over their camp out while I think about it
Meanwhile while they're doing that he's
Organizing the raising of armies far away
He's got the troops within building a giant 16 mile or something long
Fortification
Winegard Towers at regular intervals No Doubt with some Roman bolt throwers in them
And when the tribe comes back for their answer
You know after they've been how are they eating you know that me and you could have lots of people dying on this
Little Bataan Death March from the Swiss Alps to where Caesar was
And they say okay can we cross now and Caesar now with this giant fortification behind them in more troops with them since now
I'm just curious
If you are in this garlic
Massive PP
And you've been camping out eating at maybe with little of your food is left
And you're waiting for a Roman decision and more people are showing up as
Trailmaster humidity keeps arriving
And you're waiting in your waiting and the Romans are building these fortifications and you show feasible can we please cross now and then they say no
What do you do
Caesar says that small groups of
People
In the night in the daytime try to cross over themselves over the river to get on the other side it doesn't sound like a big
Armed mass of humanity sounds like a bunch of people desperately in like small family groups in the butt not trying to cross over and
Overwhelm the defenses or sneak by
On any given point in the Romans concentrate missile fire they say
And you kill all these people in the water and drive them back
You're so historian Adrian goldsworthy describe
The situation he says quote
When the hell VCI returned for seizures decision
He bluntly informed them
That is procedure now
According to the custom and precedent of the Roman people he could not permit anyone to Journey Through The Province
And that he would stop them if they tried to force their way through
Goldsworthy
The new fortifications were there to demonstrate that he meant what he said
However it was difficult for such a great mass of people suddenly to change direction and purpose
The period of waiting by the river had also probably been very frustrating
And many of the LBC I were determined to keep going
Especially after the years of preparation
And a willing destruction of their old home
Small group began to cross the road
Either using the Fords
We're rigging up rafts to carry themselves or animals in vehicle
It is possible that these were deliberate Pro
Sent by The Chieftains to test the strength of seizures defenses
The more likely they reflected the loose Central Authority and individual Independence it seem to be characteristic
Give many of the tribes of Gaul
They were certainly not full-fledged assault on the lines of fortifications
Most of the crossing took place under the cover of Darkness but a few parties were bold enough to risk the attempt in daylight
None succeeded
Procedures men were able to concentrate and meet each group intern overwhelming many of them with missiles as they struggled across
And quote
It seems to be that goldsworthy to maybe leaving open the possibility that this is more of a humanitarian situation
Interior light on
Eventually
The
Celtic tribe will move away they have a plan B which they tried to avoid because it's a much tougher route and they have to get there
A bunch of different of the tribe
I think start heading away
And Caesar decides
Maybe he can't let them
Migrate
To the other location that they want to do even if they don't have the pastor Roman territory could be a problem anyway
And he says that
One of these conspirators one of the garlic triumvirate the three-headed garlic monster
He's working with
The helvetians to negotiate and you know Passover all these differences between these tribes right smoothing it out maybe
So they can work together more
They organized
Situation with the helvetians promise we won't do anything we will be very nice and we cross your territory we won't do anything bad and then they go through
The territory of these tribes that are allies of Rome and then they start breaking stuff
SD land stop
And devastating the territory and so these garlic tribes that are Allied to Rome say the Caesar or so Caesar says
Alpa
How can you let this happen to your allies right when you have an army right here
And Caesar says I can't let that happen to my allies
She justifies in the book that way then he goes after the helvetians
Caesar will go raise some more armies real quickly
You catch up to the helvetians
Is there migrating a
Across another try
Tribes territory
Caesar will come up
Upon the tribe while they're in the process of crossing a river he's a 3/4 of the driving already crossed
Pizzas in 220 days
Shows you how long
This massive Humanities taking to move whatever the real numbers were talking about here might be
Procedures must be
But it's a lot of people one way or the other and they're hard to feed
And Caesar
Comes upon he says
This tribe wear 3/4 of the tribe CrossFit 1/4 was still on the other side waiting that was the side Caesar was on to Zoe
Attack them
Killed a bunch
This is women children
Wagons
Warriors
A bunch of them ran into the forest
And now
The tribe comes to seizure and basically says you know
What do you want from us
Caesar says
This that and the other thing reparations and oh yeah bunch of hostages now this
Is a moment we should
Just discussed this for a second cuz it's wild also
This practice
Of hostages for good behavior
This is very common in
World but I always
I think to myself what if this happened today
What if that's how we ensure good behavior today what if when we were having problems with Saddam Hussein and you have your first golf
Ford at the end of it he stays in power but in order to stop fighting you demand a couple of his sons
As hostages
Would be an interesting way to handle modern diplomacy
But that's what Caesar said he wants from this tribe and I want hostages and they're always going to be like the Sons and Daughters of the nobility so the people he's negotiating
Give the sons and daughters and they say
Hey hey hey
Don't get cocky just cuz you beat us in the situation where we were
In refugees over River we're basically still undefeated heck we beat you a couple Generations ago
Practice of taking hostages not giving
And so
The meeting broke up
Attributions would not provide hostages go back along
Their merry way continuing their migration the Romans go back to Taylor
Caesar now is looking for a way to strike at them because they haven't accepted his terms
Before he can manage to do it though
It begins to have severe Supply prop
More on that in a minute
Forces him he says
To break off the pursuit
And going in opposite direction towards a friendly Garlic City where he can get supplies
And Caesar says when they change course away from the migrants
The migrants turn around and come after them
Little Caesars stopped he puts
His entire force
On a hill where it's covering the Hillwood legionaries
Reason the traditional three line formation
He's preparing for the battle
Caesar says in a very grandiose move for the folks back home but one that has real world dividends
Sleep aid
Caesar will get off his horse and send it to the rear and take his
Replacing the front line with the soldiers
Sharing their faith
Encouraging them
And remember this
Stage in his career Caesars not the great General that we know
Was Julius Caesar you seen a lot of fighting but this is really his first
True command
And this is where he's making his name and part of making his name
He's showing that he's something special
Napoleon did a bunch of things like this and so did Alexander
Typical General move
But it can work wonders over the Long Haul seizures earning the trust of his army
He says that these gawlik troops these ferocious
Soldiers come
Charging uphill at the Romans so you already sent disaster right
It's not a good move
But the gulls are not known for tactical brilliance
In fact it almost seems like
Inevitable trade-off
In the price you pay for being these
Out-of-control impetuous Warriors that lose your mind in battle lost
Is that your
Inevitably
Less tactically cohesive and less
Concerned about
Things like making sure you save enough energy to be able to fight for a while they traditional book
Play book the opposition handbook on fighting Gauls says
That the initial charge of these people is
While
And hard to hold
But if you can stay strong and hold the initial charge they begin to get tired
And then they begin to get disheartened
And that impetuosity phase and then the lack of the armor that they normally have
The fact that they've totally lost cohesion after all this stuff against to tell if you can sit through
And whether the initial storm
You tend to be okay
Charging up here with a bunch of Roman throwing heavy joblon downhill
Not a good start
Caesar says that the
Roman Pila God
Stuck in the shields of the Gauls
Little narrow weaknecht
Deliberately designed
Tube and so then all of a sudden it's
Dragging down the shields of these Gaul Caesar says they shake their arms for a long time then throw their shield down
You take the people already not
Heavily armored and take away the Shields and then the Romans charge down at them with swords and it begins to be
You know a typical Roman battle against Gauls where they're going to get chopped up pretty good
He says you never see their back they don't run
But they conduct a
Fighting withdrawal up to a nearby Hill and when the Romans pursue them they're hitting the flanked by two other tribes that were nearby
We should point out
Caesar has every interest to exaggerate how dangerous this enemy is
And how difficult the conditions he faced were because
Obviously if he prevails and wins
Well it's that much greater of a victory to cite to the folks back home
Nonetheless
When seizures hit in the flank he says the people that he was pursuing charges him from the front again so he's surrounded
His flight is he that this is a Greek army
Instead of a Roman army
It's done for this point
Because the Romans could do with the Romans could do
Tactical flexibility that was pretty much
Unique in the ancient world
Caesar's able to take one of the three lines of the Roman army the one that's not yet fighting
And
Shift it's facing so it's now facing the enemy
Benefits of Romans in the flank now they're facing Romans from the front
Turn a hard-fought battle now
Caesars troop get the upper hand
The
Warriors will retreat
To a wagon Fortress 2
Taking all the Wagons at there
Migrating with and they put them in a giant Circle
And it's offended by all the noncombatants and whatnot end
The Romans attack it
That's was The Last Stand of the battle
And by the time
The whole thing is over
May have killed 200000
These people
Ayhan
If you believe those numbers
Historian Michael Sage
Says this about the numbers quote
In the aftermath of the battle Caesar claims that tablets were found in the helvetian camp
Written in Greek characters
Containing lists of men of military age women boys in the elderly who joined into migration
They were also
Council the other tribe to accompany the helvetians
For a grand total of 368000 people
Of whom 92000 were capable of bearing arms
Seizure then record the census
Taken when the Gauls returned home
Which totaled 110000
It is difficult to assess the accuracy of these figures and this is the only case in the garlic War we're Caesar worth
First of such list
The Gauls did write Celtic in Greek letters
Numerous inscriptions in Celtic written in Greek characters have been preserved
The figure of 92,000 Warriors is plausible that the total of 368,000 is accepted
In premodern populations about 1/4 of the population consisted of males of military age
The total number for all those migrating is also in the realm of possibility
110000 survivors representing 1/3 of those who set out is more of a problem
The loss of more than two-thirds as possible
But he must have had a number of causes
The migration from beginning to end probably consumed about three months
With the final battle in late May early June
Many especially the sick and the infirm may have perished along the way
And other simply settled along the route of migration
Once the battle casualties are included which Caesar does not give
The figure four losses still seems too high
There's no other evidence and at least it's in the realm of possibility
And quote
How do I say just broke I enjoyed immensely on this
Buddy's point is well taken
We don't know how many people really were there
And you don't know how many people really came back
And it might have been more of a Trail of Tears type situation of Bataan Death March as we said type situation
Where a lot of people died along the way rather than have Caesar stuff out their lives
But you can be sure
It sent the helvetians were one of the great tribes of Gaul that we're talking about a lot of people
You're not just talking about combatants at all
The end stages of this battle with Caesar had the Roman legionaries assaulting
The wagon
Brought up into a great
Notification with all of the stuff that these people owned in the middle of them
The Gauls and the Germans on a bunch of occasions
We're said by ancient sources to have the women staying back by the wagons yelling encouragement to their men
Deriding the
Behavior cowards
Providing first aid and Medicine help to those who staggered back from the battle line wounded
So when the Romans
Unidrive back
Defleaing
Routers after they just decimated their formations and those people run back to the wagon pursued by the Roman army
The Roman army does when they get to the wagons
They kill everybody
When you try to
One of the main things that actually protects lives on the battlefield like this
Is the prospect of Stelling
The people that you can capture
The one thing a person on a battlefield facing the battle lost of other people has in their favor and then they the only thing they can work
Guess I'm I'm worth more alive than dead
And there's no doubt that lots of slaves were sold after this battle and you can hear your mind a cash register
In a ding every time one of those people Soul because one of the reasons seizures there if you recall as he has a horrible death.
Home
One of the ways for a great Roman to pay off these debts as with a successful profitable campaign
And one of the main things you profit off of is the people you sell after
Words
Nonetheless
The reason seizure came
To this entire area to begin with
I just been dealt with
After the battle the helvetians essentially what's left of them come to Caesar and say you know we're in your power
Will do whatever you want to send them home
Send them back to where they came from and he feeds them on the way the Rangers are food and everything
Little Caesar I'll take care of you but
The end result is you lose hundreds of thousands of people to return things to the status quo
So why doesn't Caesar go home now
Wow he's noticed something he says in his works
It's been brewing for a while he's been doing some investigations and he's uncovered a bunch of
Well stuff that the people in room should know about
Stuff that you can Overlook for example
He was already noticing the weird stuff was happening
With the garlic troop the friendly golly troops he was using his army
The Romans for example don't produce cavalry
Anymore they produced legionaries
Heavy Infantry
Men armed with a heavy throwing javelin
Devastatingly nasty sword
The Cavalry is raised from
In a local Friendly peoples in this case a lot of Celtic peoples
Which tribes allied to Rome but there
Doing things on the battlefield it make
Caesar suspicious that maybe
Just maybe
They're not altogether loyal I mean one famous thing that Caesar talks about thousands of these garlic Cavalry and they go up again
Get the few hundred of the enemies and then all of a sudden flee in Terror
Very suspicious thing and started doing some inquiry
Then while he's pursuing the helvetian
Column the helvetian columns
Begin moving away from rivers and stop procedure can get supplies
Shouldn't matter because all these friendly tribe that a seizure and have to come up here and save us from these people that are stealing and destroy
Boiling our land they were supposed to provide the food but the food not coming
He said he keep getting these excuses I should have been here all we're still raising it. It's on the way why you didn't get it I mean that kind of stuff
So he starts investigating that to calling some of these Nobles into his office and saying where the hell the food what's going on here
And all comes to a head after this battle with the helvetians because he says
It all the other with a few exceptions
Big garlic
Leaders come
His location to congratulate him on his victory and all these kinds of stuff and then they say they can can we see you in the back room privately
They called him into the back room privately in the instantly all fall to their feet Vita beseeching HIM Tears in their eyes and they give him he's
This sob story
About please please please you have to save us from this German King who's taking over golf
We told you about this guy right he was the guy who was brought in when these two tribes of Gaul that were historic enemies were looking
Looking for an ad
That's the one tribe. Let's invite these
Germans over and they'll give us the edge we will win the battle which they did and they
You destroyed the nobility of the other side but then the Germans didn't leave as we said
In fact according to this
Group of people that comes to Caesar he's taking all their children hostages and anytime they move the wrong way he tortures them it does bad
Things to him
Caesar's never speaking to a Roman audience and basically saying can you believe what this German King is doing
Judy's poor girls who are allies and Friends of the Roman people
Caesar stand for that of course he can't stand for that
What's more
These cats have been telling Caesar stories
That they've got people in their own tribes were just loyal rug you know the tribes are enemies of Rome are just loyal but these are
People in tribes that are nominally friends wrong they have huge numbers of fifth columnist
They want to work for the garlic cause instead
Now again seizures portraying this as Sinister and bad to Roman audience
It's hard not to see these troublemakers that Caesar talks about those
Anything other than Golic Patriots
If you're looking at it from their point of view I mean the people that are here beseeching Cesar for help these are like the quislings aren't they
The traitors of the garlic cause but
Just like the Native American tribes
Just like the tribes in Africa
These people have
Historic enemies amongst their own kind
With disputes
Memories of Tit for Tat
Revenge cycle killings that go back forever and
These were able to be exploited
In Africa and the New World by European powers in Gaul by the Romans
Exquisitely I mean it is the Romans who invented the phrase that we use today to divide and conquer
That's what they're doing in Gaul and seizures using some tribes against the other than these tribal leaders are telling him
We just want you to know
We have large factions in our own tribe that are working against you
They're the ones that kept the food from coming to you
They were the ones leading your Cavalry when the thousands of your Cavalry turn in flood and Tara from a few hundred of the
The enemy in other words
Caesar's got them all around him
And this becomes an excuse to stay
What's more when Caesar says this German King is a pressing all these people
He basically says
So the Gauls want us to stay I have to stay to defend them and the enemy has just shift
Some garlic people
To a new people now let's understand
Whether or not these new people really were new people is open for debate
Cesar makes them a new people in his writing because it serves the purposes of his right
It's an outside power
Caesar's going to use it
To defend now these people that are closer to home
These people he's just killed a hundred thousand or more people of
He's now the savior of the Gauls
And he stay
Now I should point out that there's no consensus at all
Over Caesars
Decision making
At this point
Everyone seems to agree that it
At some point Caesar decides he's going to take all of garlow
And most seem to think that that was not his initial plan once he
Originally set out to change the course of the helvetian migration
But there's a lot of disagreement over at what point Caesar crystallized this idea that the heck with it I'm taking it off
Many historians Arts
Spoken about this
Andrew Rigsby
This tendency and seizures writing sometimes
To give a hint of the idea
Bengall is maybe kind of doomed anyway
And that it's like a vulnerable
Animal in the geopolitical
Will Hurd and somebody's going to get the Germans
It's the Germans that form this
New CounterPoint in the story when they appear on the scene because
Up until now Cesar hasn't really had an antagon
When you're stopping in migration of a tribal people
Who's the bad guy in that
Right even though Caesar had some bad guys involved
Conspiracy initially by the time he's involved their dad
She never having any sort of a one-to-one
Darth Vader versus another Sith Lord
Confrontation
And of course he's also got that
Conspiracy the shadowy thing going on
Nowhere
It's almost like a guerrilla War now he can't
Trust
Are the Celtic people who are his friends
Your friends are your enemies are they all look the same
But again not a single opponent for Caesar to really measure himself with
Until he comes face-to-face with this German King
Ariovistus
King of the swing
Now let's step back a minute
For the sake of those were huge Julius Caesar
Your fans because how can we ignore
How quickly everything here has happened that's a Hallmark
The moving with speed and determination focusing on
In the core issues in the most decisive points in my naughty mean
This is all happening in the year 58 BCE
The dealing with the helvetian migration is during the same year and let's remember they hardly ever campaign in the winter
But this is really like
8 maybe 9 month campaigning season
And right after he deals with the helvetians and has those
What was a huge bat
You know you know marches to another part of this area where the German King isn't begins to deal
With him
In Caesars narrative this guy is sort of the root cause of everything hear me why
Is Cesar even having to do all of this in Gaul will because the Germans destabilize the whole situation
Came in there with their
120000 Warriors or whatever began settling in Gaul and has set the whole place in motion
So when Caesar confronts REO Vista is he
Confronting the root of the problem if Caesar were a less
Ambitious man this could be
The end of his story this could be the culmination
He goes to the root of the problem and solves it comes home celebrate the triumphant lives happily ever after
I do have to remind myself.
How this has a feel of Caesar kind of being at the end of the Earth we said earlier that he's like a
Heavily armed version of the Lewis and Clark expedition
He feels the need in the narrative to tell the people back at home you know what these
Germans he calls them are like
What are their customs
God's do they believe in what they look
Like how they fight
Supposedly the Romans had dealt with these people militarily before right at the time Caesars born remember the Cambrian the two tones in
Invaders from the north unexpectedly a national security crisis
If you forgotten Cesar will remind you over and over again
In his commentaries
The great way to justify going out to the Germans to remind you
But every now and then they come after us
But other than that not a lot to go on
I'm so Cesar explains to the folks back home
You know that these Germans are essentially like the Gauls on steroids
The Gauls art all the Germans are that much taller
The Gauls are blondes the Germans are blonder
If the Gauls fight in a war mad Berserker crazy Frenzy
The Germans do that more often and their friends he's deeper than
Caesar kind of says
The compared to the Gauls the Germans are primitive
Shuffle using a tribal scale on the Gauls are moving up to like threes and fours and fives the Germans are one
Just you know Caesar would have you believe just graduated from caveman's.
He said they don't even really practice agriculture
None of the modern histories or
Going to stop by archaeologists that I've read
None of them believe that
They all think the Germans practiced
There you go
Caesar says that the Gauls used to be able to stand up to the Germans in battle but they can't anymore
Essentially saying that they're gun-shy that they lost so many battles that they
Lost
The psychological Edge if you will and it becomes another one of those unquantifiable things doesn't it that affects human history
And we talked about intimidation on a personal level
But you know what happens when you get a group of skittish
Scared unpredictable human beings together and then try to
Quantify the impact
Of the mass amount of psychological intimidation I mean if you've lost three battle to the Germans already and you're
You're lining up to fight your fourth
How much does the history of how you done against them recently play into your ability to stand up to them now
Of course if the
Celtic people can't stand
Did the Germans anymore in a dog-eat-dog world what does that mean
Are the long-term ability of gall to remain
Free and independent
So you looking at this from the Roman Viewpoint you can kind of see how they might come to the conclusion
We're going to have all these German people right next to us and Gall soon
So Caesar goes and begins a conversation with this German leader
Were you essentially tell the German leader look at all the stuff has to stop
He said he begins of Correspondence
Send a message
Umi says
Can we please meet halfway between our two locations because give important matters to discuss
This is all in Caesar commenter
By the way
He says that the German king of replied
Essentially if I have something to say to you
I come to you
If you have something to say to me you come to me
And then begins with a line of discussion that's hard to understand
And if you're looking at this from Caesars point of view
Because the German leader begins to question Caesar
About
Maybe you could say
The legality
As they would understand it in the ancient world
All these things he's doing
And sites
Legal arguments that you couldn't use now I mean you have to be
A Nazi to use arguments like right of Conquest today
But that was something that was actually sometimes part of the rules back then
And this German leader will cleverly say over and over again
We're not doing anything you don't
Baidu
Answer why are you interfering
The arguments that ariovistus makes through the pain of Caesar
Are just as compelling as the ones that the helvetians kind of made when they were trying to ask the Romans can we please come through your Terror
It's a humanitarian crisis Maybe
Modern readership
As a whole different feel for it maybe then Caesars Aldean
Kentwood
Because I have this just looks to the modern reader may be to be making some really good points
When Caesar tells him
In the next letter which is much more direct you will do this you will do that we're going to have problems because you're going to release the hostage
Did you ever realize you can stop attacking our allies you going to stop bringing more Germans from Over the Rhine River
Andario Vistas
Straight up answers him Caesar basically says with Defiance but here's the problem
The only information you have about this is from Caesar
And one cent he's the best person in the world to give it to you cuz he met this guy face-to-face and talk to him
On the other hand he's the worst person in the world to tell this to you because
Nobody has more of a vested interest in slanting and his way
Caesarstone
The message that came back
From this Barbarian again but not sounding very much like a barbarian maybe Barbarian lawyers helping him out with the legalese
He says to Caesar
This is from the essay Hanford edition of Caesar quote
In reply all Rio Vista said that he went to recognize custom of War for Victor's to rule the vanquished
In any way they please
And that the Romans acted on this principle by governing their conquered subjects not according to the dictates of any third
Party what is their own discretion
Since you did not dictate to them how they would exercise their rights
You're not to be interfered with any exercise of his
He was because the Eid we
The tribe that's a lie to roam it's because the Eid we had tried the fortune of war and where the
The losers in the fight that they had to pay him tribute
And Caesar was doing him a serious wrong in coming to golf and causing a loss of Revenue
He would not return the hostages to the eat weed but would refrain from making any wanton attack upon them or
Other allies if
They kept their agreement and pay the tributes regularly every year if they did not
The title of Brothers of the Roman people would not save them from the consequences
I am not impressed
He concluded by Caesars threat to punish my in quotes oppression of these people
No one has ever fought me without bringing destruction upon himself
Let him attack whenever he pleases
He will discover with German Valerie's capable of
We have never known defeat
We've had superb training in arms and for 14 years we have never shelter beneath the roof
And quote
It's easier than mine that's basically the equivalent of saying it's on
He starts to send his army toward the German he says the German starts
Send his army towards Caesar there's this strategic town that ends up between the two armies
Lil Ceaser going to basically
Going day and night Jim
Pushing his men to get their first get there first
Like all great
Generals
Understands the value of speed
They locked themselves in the Celtic calendar prepared to defend it
And all looks pretty good for Caesar except that the people that have taken over this town his soldiers start talking to the local goat
Tallest people
And those people start telling
Caesars troops about these German
And what they're like and how they can't even look them in the face
Without
And running away
Can seizures cause all of their gossip
Makes his army scared
And the rumors of what the Germans are like freaking out and he specifically singles out you have to love this
The folks back home in Rome probably did too
Those young men on the make
Son of the Suns
Of the richest senators and whatnot
Cool military experience on a resume before they start their running for Roman officer nothing too scary Wonder
Maybe just a nice person with seizure look good on the resume
And all will be well Caesar says that when they're
Looking at facing these ferocious
Scary
Unknown beasts from the edge of the world that the garlic people who normally scare the Romans a little have said
Acecare Ross
Caesar says these young men on the make all of a sudden they're finding
Good reasons why there urgently needed back in Rome
He says the
Beer spread to the rest of the ranks in people start drawing up their wheels and he says they're breaking into
Tears
You know it's at strange times and they're the moaning their fate and all this kind of stuff which of course look Beyond it now Caesars
Built up his enemy so that when he conquered them he'll be that much greater he's also creating a need in the Army for him
Cuz he's going to go in there and with a combination of shaming people
But also logical arguments
I throw in a little bit of
Theater and you know you can
Caesar says anyway with the Army into shape and let's be honest we seen this with other great generals also
Soften the quality
The people associate with great generals
Write the ability to turn around the morale of your troops and rally them
Caesar says then as soon as the German approaches
That the king of the Germans already Vista says okay now that I'm here we can have this discussion you wanted to have and Caesar has this wonderful moment where they meet
Unlike a hill in the middle of a giant
In a flat area and they weren't allowed to bring their Army's close to each other so their armies are like in the distance and only 10
Guys on Horseback or supposed to accompany each leader and were told they have the conversation in garlic
So
This German King supposedly speaks Golic and Caesar probably had a good friend
Translate forum
Caesars has basically the same thing it said in the note
To the German ruler and the German ruler says something similar to what you said before back
In a questioning Caesars right to do this
Pointing out that we all live by the same rules
You conquer your people and you decide what happens to him afterwards that
Where we live by
And then he says and it's a wonderful line when he questioned seizures motor
And he says I think all this
Is just so much pretense
Or you coming here to crush me
And then he says unless you take your army out of this country right now
You know he's going to finish these
And then he tells him but if you do leave right now I'll be happy to be your muscle man hearing
Germany and in Gaul in anytime you need a favor you wanted to have to lift a finger and I'll do it for you so it's a little bit of a carrot-and-stick soda
Once again if you were a neutral arbitrator
You might say something like hey that's not a bad deal
So let's stop for a minute
That you're really dying at this point in the story for an outsider's Viewpoint anyone else besides Caesar here cuz he's really
At this point why is he putting these sorts of
You know accusatory good arguments into the mouth of one of his characters that he wants
You two want him to conquer
You mentioned earlier there were a couple of Roman writer that came after Caesar
I see Tony is his one and that's not very long after Caesar about a century-and-a-half for two centuries afterwards is a guy named Cassius Dio
Ideal has a much more
Gritty
View of Caesar in his motivations and essentially is one of those guys that falls in the camper
Cc's are doing this
The most basic reasons you can think of
He's involved in this Monumental Gamble
In the politics of Rome where his involvement in this region risking his life and devoting his entire exist
To this cause and gall
Is only because of what benefits he can glean from it
In the politics of Rome
And he desperately in need of things like money and Conquest
And
Honors and he's got to keep
This
Military command going because the the moment that his
Term in office is over
He's prosecutable by his enemies in their licking their chops back in room waiting to get to him
At the same time
You know
At least at this point in history he has to assume that this is not a permanent command so he's on a bit of a Time Clock of Caesar real
Really wants to do these great things he's going to end up doing in golf he's got a limited amount of time to do it
And Cassius Dio as one of the people that says that everything Caesars doing here is the equivalent of
Poking the Germans with a stick
Trying to get them all roused up so you have an excuse
To go in there and kill a bunch of
Deal by-the-way confuses us
Entirely
By saying that all Rio Vista sitting the king of the Germans he's a can of account
That means one of two things either
Cassius Dio is a lazy Roman ethnographer and there were plenty
And doesn't really draw a distinction
But if he's accurate
Then you have to say well why did Caesar call him in German what's the point
A Caesar doing that what does he gain by creating this new group of people
It may have been a generic name
Once Upon a Time only apply to One Tribe in modern-day germ
This from my Herbert
Baldwin Foster Edition by the way
I should point out the
Videos
Pronouns and use of pronouns simatai
I'm confusing. I'm going to
Insert the name of the person he's talking about
Pronounce Odin makes
ScoreSense
Deal rights
No ariovistus was the ruler of those
Celts
Is Dominion has been ratified by actions of the Romans
Any been registered among their friends and allies by Caesar himself
In his console
In comparison however with the glory to be derived from the war
In the power which That Glory would bring the Roman general Caesar
He did none of those considerations
Except as insofar as he wished to get some excuse for the coral from the Barbarian
So that should not be thought that there was any grievance against him
Caesar at the start
Therefore he sent for REO Vista
Pretending that he wanted to hold some conversation with
Ariovistus instead of obeying replied
And this is close to Caesars on description
Is Caesar wishes to tell me anything let him come himself to me
I am not in any way inferior to him and a man who has need of anyone must always go to that person
That's if Caesar showed anger on the grounds that REO Vista said insulted all the Rome
MCS are immediately demanded of REO Vistas the hostages of the allies
And forbade him either to set foot on their land
What are bring against the many auxiliary force from home
This seizure did not do with the idea of scaring him but because he hoped to make him Furious
And by that means
To gain a great and fitting pretext for the war
What was expected took place
The Barbarian and rage that the injunctions made a long and outrageous reply
So that caesar no longer bandied words
And quote
That's a completely different view isn't it
Cassius Dio also
So gives a very different
I'm Caesar rallying his terrified Romans in the gallic town we just discuss
Rather than being one of the few
Non terrifying
People who can then spread his lack of fear to his entire Army
Deal basically has
The troops looking at what they're up against and thinking maybe that they shouldn't even be up against their not so mad at the
Germans they're mad at the guy who put them in a situation where they should be fighting the germ
According to do they are very aware
Of what role they play in this whole thing of the ponds and seizures game to further seizures career
And they also seem to realize politically speaking
That this is outside the boundaries Maybe
I'm with the Romans themselves would consider a legal military venture
Cassius Dio size
It when these Romans are scared
And I call it
Town
It's scared cuz they keep hearing about the Germans and the Germans are
Becoming he says it leaves them deeply did Jack
And then he says quote
Alarmed by the statue of their enemies
By their numbers their boldness and consequent ready threats
They were in such a mood is to feel that they were going to contend
Not against man but against uncanny and Ferocious Beast
And the talk was that they were undertaking a war
Which was none of their business
I did not mean to create
Merely on account of Caesar's personal ambition
And they threatened also to leave him in the Lurch if he should not change his course
And quote
That's not a bunch of scared soldiers who get
Their Fear
Rallied out of them by a charismatic leader this is a bunch of
Troops who fully realize
What's going on here are angry at their leader for putting them
In this position and are threatening
Mutiny if he doesn't change
The course he's on I mean
That's a very different story right there isn't it
I'm not sure it really matters though in terms of
How it reflects on Caesars room
Reputation because either way
It really says something about the
The guy that he was able to
Rally those
Troops
And put them in a position in a state of mind where they could face this German lead
Either a king
Maybe ariovistus
Person elected Worley
Confederation
It's argue
YouTube out
But that's a guy ariovistus who has the entirely central part in in fact you could say most of Gaul
Howard by his
Power and authority
Procedure turns these
Either mutinous or petrified with fear or some combination of the
2 troops
And get them out in the field against this guy
Now the way the battleships up supposedly is it starts with a bunch of maneuvering this is the very unsexy
Decide
A military history
People like yours
Truly like
Cut right to the chase we like our nice
In a well-organized and set up
Filled bottles in a nice
Level Valley where you've had a lot of time for both sides
The setup and then you have
You are super big encounter
But truthfully
In Real History of one of the generals had done his job or her job
You should have the other side beaten by the time you get to that point
And it's sometimes the big maneuvering on the Strategic level that does that but sometimes it's just a little shading here
And the slight Advantage there and they all light up
Generals throughout history
Almost neurotic
Think about figuring out the little elements
How to gain advantage
And there are quite a few different periods in history where because of the military
Technology in the limitations
If both sides didn't actively want to fight a battle sometimes it didn't happen if one side wanted to avoid it
Often times it was easy to do
The seventeenth and eighteenth century
Probably
Like the high-water mark of that a few hundred years ago where
Because of the way things were
Enough once I didn't want to fight a battle that almost never have
Sonus. Caesar and the German Commander
Are both sort of jockeying for position and maneuvering
And one of the things about the Romans
That makes them so
Again another unsexy side of military history but the Roman soldiers are about 1/2
Devastating
Soldier
And about half construction worker
And these people could set up
Fortifications
In real time
In a way that actually effective
The battles
Situation of the maneuvering actually takes
The form of both sides
Trying to March around the other encamp on their lines of supply
Cut them off
When the Germans did it they would take wagons and what not supposedly with them and sort of put them in a circle like
Pioneers in the old west used
Of course they have a lot more wagons were talking about a lot
Your structures
But when the Romans would build a calf even a small sub cap
They would build it like an Old Fort
In the old American West
You know we were talking about what
Timber
Garden Tower
And maybe even artillery in the guard
Towers in the Romans were so good at this
And often did it every night when they were out in the field
They had this down to a science and everybody knew exactly where to go and how to do and what are we going to look out the layout was always the same
So when the Romans
Camped on your line of supply
You wake up the next morning and there would be a fort there where there was Open Country the day before
So then
After the initial maneuverings once the Romans have this sport in too good of a position
The Germans are launching attacks against the fort and those are beating off and there's a bunch of this kind of preliminary but still pretty
Large-scale skirmishing
Before Caesar maybe some historians think is beginning to have Supply problems himself that a lot more
Are the natives around him here
And he seems to be in danger and needing to fight a battle or get out
So he says he
Straws the Army up in battle formation and marches it out toward the germ
On several occasions by
By this time.
The Roman battle formation by the way
Is 3 big lines deep usually
Caesar says that's the way he lines up and just so you know
That means a different thing from Rent
Ranks of the number of troops that are lined up
You the one behind the other
And often times each of these lines is between Genesis not just for Romans for anyone
For to like 16 ranks.
Pike formation maybe 12 or 16 rank the Romans more 4 to 8
But then you'll be a dead zone if maybe 50 yards 30 yards a hundred yards
And it'll be another line of men lined up in
This would be the Roman second-line and then the Romans would often have a third line
This seems like common sense when you think about it today but in the ancient world this is very unusual
The Romans have reserved
And time and again it will save them in these battles because
They will find out if something's going wrong someplace and guess what we have about 20 to 25% of our total Force
Just sitting back there
Throw them into the troubled area and time and again it saves them
In this battle Caesar is
Very cut-and-dry remember this is not a true history he's writing this is supposed to be sort of
In the format of
You know dispatches from the front
And sometimes she'll talk about
You know what's going on in the battle at length but you would think with a really important one like this one he go into great detail and he doesn't
He basically says
When the real Clash of arms comes
This bottle was supposed to have been fought most historians thinking what's now Alsace but no one's sure
Probably on the West Bank of the Rhine somewhere
The Romans probably had in the neighborhood of thirty thousand men
The Germans who knows
Usually Sefa
I'm 50 200,000 although you get the occasional outlier
I love hamster Brooke as you now and he's usually a great
Neutral arbitrator unless there's Germans involved in which case he's got his Homer glasses on
He doesn't see things
As unbiased he thinks the Romans
Outnumbered the Germans
He's unusual so we'll set him aside there and just assume the Romans
We're probably somewhat outnumbered perhaps 2 to 1
In the worst case scenario
Caesar says that the battle takes place so quickly there's no time for the usual exchange of missiles
The Romans love to throw those heavy jollands they do a lot of damage
When you throw them in all at once hundreds of thousands of men throwing these heavy javelins all at once
But the Germans and the Romans end up charging each other too quickly for that and it gets right to a sword slog right away
Caesar says that the flank he's on
Begins to push the German flag opposite them back
But that the other Roman flanked on the far side of the battlefield is being overwhelmed by the German numbers
He then says
That a Roman officer that he names by name
Because he's on Horseback can see the problem from a distance of realize oh somebody better order the third law
It's not doing anything right now in to fix the situation and he does so when he saved the Bible
Cedar by the way name this person as
The son of the richest guy in Rome Crassus who if you recall is one of the
Members of the first triumvirate along with Caesar
And Tom P so you see in a way
Caesar still doesn't forget
You know where his bread is buttered and how to play the wonderful game of
Politics and you scratch my back and I'll scratch yours
Caesar was allegedly not able to leave Rome at one point because his creditors wouldn't let him out of the city
Until crashes pay the bill
Well now all of a sudden here in this battle where Caesar doesn't go into depth about much of anything
He goes out of his way to mention a single individual
The son of the guy who paid the debts for him and oh by the way
He's basically saying without that guy you know we lost that battle against the German
That's a little bit of a
Honor to the family isn't it
So maybe paying back a favor or maybe
Putting crashes in debt for a future one nonetheless Caesars never far from playing the game
In this case the game is deadly as you might imagine
These Germans once again or supposed to have come
With the wagons in the families and the women on the wagons you know where the disheveled hair screaming at the
The Men Please Don't Let Us fall into slavery
The problem with having all these women and wagons on the battlefield is obviously that at some point
The battle moves from where it started
To the wagon
And the people in the wagons and once again we have
A bottle where
It's implied more than laid out for you but that the Romans kill a lot of civilians including
I'm some of the relatives of Arya Vistas who somehow gets away but we don't hear any more from him
The Germans will run
Miles to the Rhine Caesar size
There will be more Germans that are just about to come over and help as soon as they hear about the big defeat of aurea Vista turn around and go home
What's Caesars doing here from a macro perspective though if you think about it isn't there were a bunch of powers
That were the power Brokers in this region before Caesar intervened and that would have been last year so think about how quickly every
Things happening
Caesar has
Essentially neutered one of them the helvetian one of most powerful tribes
Of the count is now a shadow of what it was just months before
Cousin what teacher did do it
And now this
Player from out
Side the Stratego
Or risk
Mat board who come in and intervened and garlic politics is smashed in
Packing back over the Rhine this thing that Caesar portrays is a border
What's crazy to think about
Is that all of this has happened in the year 58 BCE
Because when you think about the ancient world you think about a world that in many cases moves much more slowly than the modern
And yet Caesar has a blitzkrieg
Going on
Mingle
He says and some historians will date three battle some
Some will day two battles depending on whether you consider that
For slaughtering the helvetians
When 1/4 of their number were caught on on the far side of the river to be a bottle or not
But nonetheless in that one
Really six to eight months because they don't campaign most of the time in the winter
Caesar. All this damage and changed
The
The power structure of this reading
If he thought it was destabilize before he got involved in that was the excuse for getting involved he's totally destabilize
Now
But winter is coming
So what is Cesar do
Well he puts his army and winter quarters and he goes back to the area just north of Rome to keep an eye on Roman pal
What you think about his next move
Here's the thing
You could make a case if you wanted to and some have
Did everything Caesar just accomplished was done
You know in a crisis situation in Hot Pursuit
Whether it was the migration of the helvetians which is you know as we said earlier it's like if you woke up this morning and found 200,000 people
You on your border just
Unexpectedly be some sort of a crisis so that's the way Caesar portrays it so if you give him the benefit of the doubt you say will you know he had to react you couldn't go
Ask for votes and Authority
What part of what you do is that
Head of the problems you go in there and you
You roll with the punches so Caesar had to do that and then the Germans and their involvement I mean that was also the same thing mean they were
Coming over the Border was getting worse you had
He was a critical situation
But now you're taking the winter off
We go from a hot blood situation to Cold Blood
Will you can think about what you want to do now
I love the way Tom Holland
As an author he's great
Building a sense of suspense in
And he portrays the Gauls
At this point
In his book Rubicon
A sort of waking up together to the fact
That they're in the process of being conquered it's a strange thing but it's happening so quickly
And because the garlic tribes are
In a separate from each other
If they conquered the tribe next to you does that mean you're being conquered will not necessarily and you might
Might not be too panicked
But if enough of the big tribe near you are being conquered and if you happen to know just a little of the history
A Roman Behavior another Celtic areas
Spain for example or Northern Italy or what's now southern France
You understand that these Romans have a track record
They come in they defeat the Celtic people they begin to settle
And in a generation or to the Celtic people become short-haired Galls in a couple of generations after that they become toga wearing Gaul
And Tom Holland
Present this case where
Once Caesar puts his troops in Winter quarters in the middle of God
It sends a signal to everyone
I hate waiting
Easier to stay
And if we're going to prevent a complete takeover as has happened to other Celtic peoples
It's time to get serious about defending this place Tom Holland right
Quote
That winter of 5857 BC
Rather than withdrawing his Legions back into his province
Caesar left them billeted 100 miles north of the frontier
Jeep in the territory of a supposedly independent tribe
Once again and it legal measure was justified by the proconsul
As an active forward defense
This was an argument that may have satisfied public opinion back in Rome
What did nothing to ease a mounting sense of outrage and Gall itself
The full implications of seizures new policy we're by now starting to hit home
What precisely would satisfy the Romans desire for a defensible frontier
If the Rhine to the east
Then why not the channel to the north
What are you laughing Coast to the West
Across Frozen forest and field
From Village to Village
From Chieftains Hall to Chieftains Hall the same rumor was born
The Romans were aiming to pacify all Gaul
That importation Ma
As Warriors burnished their glittering Jewel Rod Shields
And stripling's eager to prove themselves ready for battle
Forwarded I cheated streams with full armor on their backs
So rival tribe sought to patch up their differences
Free golf prepared itself for war
And quote
I think
A sure sign of the way
Caesar was thinking during this time.
Is his excuse
For going back into Gaul and continuing to fight
Even though these things
Are these crisis moments that had forced him to respond or done with
He says the very Act of these people deciding to work together
Against him
Justified him
Going after them
This is for my Carolyn Hammond translation
When Caesar refers to Caesar he's talking to himself in the third person and when he talks about the belgae
He's talking about this
Kind of Celtic people as he describes it
To the north of the area he's been campaigning the people that actually make up
What was
The population of modern-day Belgium part of the Netherlands
The part of Germany and part of Northeastern France much larger area than modern-day Belgium in some of the Mets
It migrated across the channel to Southeastern Britain to
But it's these tribes of belgae that are
Uniting against Caesar so he
Point out that well obviously it's a conspiracy
Payment translation says quote
As we mentioned above
Caesar was in near Galt
Where he heard a host of rumors
Confirmed by a letter from Lady Ennis
Did all the belgae who make up 1/3 of Gaul as we said before we're hatching a plot
Against the Roman people and exchanging hostages
The reason for this plot or as follows
First
They were afraid that our army would March against them now that all the rest of God have been subdued
Secondly they were being stirred up by a number of the god
Some of whom have been unwilling for the Germans to have any further involvement in Gaul
Equally reluctant for the army of the Roman people to overwinter and become established there
Others were of a volatile and unstable disposition
The sort of man who Delight in changes of rules
Yet another group inside of the belgae to conspire
Because it was common in golfer men who possess some degree of power and the means to hire support to cease re
Regal power
Something which would be more difficult to achieve under our rule
And quote
Now forget this is a neutral arbitrator here
Once again Caesar is essentially in dating these people for doing exactly what they should be doing if you think about this logically
Because Caesars just smashed
One of the most powerful tribes
He's got the support of another he just kicked the dreaded Germans out if you believe
These really were Germans
And he's taken the
Surrender and submission of a bunch of other Golic tribes who are cowed now by what is a comp
And these people to the north all these tribes that Caesar says are
He kind of implies that they're part Celtic and part German
But this is free golf at this point
These are the tribes
That have the ability to raise a lot of troops and still fight Caesar and Caesar says and it's not hard to believe
The Beast fifth columnist from friendly tribes in tribes that have already submitted
Are you secretly whispering in the ear of the belgae to in other words there is an anti Roman
Insurgency in Gaul and seizures talking about here and once again the simple fact that it exists
Legitimizes his involvement in the region to stop it
Allegedly
This tribal Confederation in the North
Belgae tribes will be able to put together almost 300,000 War
Not women children old people and all that but Warrior
Once again you can't help but
Contrast that with what the Native Americans are trying to resist
You know expansion in North America with your 1500 or
Maybe mm on a relief
Good day Warriors and here Caesars trying to figure out how to tackle
With no guns
Right with no Cannon nothing like that
300000 native peoples
Even if that number is high what if it's 200000
One of my favorite stories which kind of in my mind shows how
You know you can do things in different ways to accomplish the same goals when you think of the really bureaucratic ancient States when you think of it
Egypt or China or in the Siri or Rome even
And you think okay when they needed an army how did they mustard how do they put it together how did they raise that you think of a really bureaucratic affair
The only thing missing
Are the iPads for these people MLB paper records of you all kinds of
Stop at the Modern in organizational situation where you raise armies or hide tribes do it
Especially tried to had lots of people while
There's an ancient source that says that the Celtic method
For this was a variation if you will on the idea
The last one in is a rotten egg
It's last one
Who arrives to the monster gets tortured to death in front of the army
Isn't that wickedly
Efficient and yet in a decentralized sort of Tribal Way
We're not going to get to
We're not going to get too specific about this but the last guy who shows up to the muster we kill him
Bystolic torture in front of the whole Army see you soon
I love that I hope that's true just cuz that's
That's wonderfully color
Purple
And yet the problems these tribes have is that they need all these people to resist Roman encroachment but the large
These so-called Barbarian armies get
The harder they are to feed
Just imagine if the 300 thousand will play with a nice smaller number 200000
Well that's
What 2/3
Modern football stadiums
How long can you feed that with Barbarian Logistics
Pastel Brooklyn oh I'd love to focus he's so materialistic and down-to-earth and scoffs at every
He points out that this is where the unsexy advantage of the
Are the so-called civilized bureaucratic States really is
The ability to feed people in the field so that they're there to fight
Doesn't matter how many people your opponent has if they're starving and I could be that good
Dorothy Army have to break up cuz they can't find food
We are not really an army of three hundred thousand people then
Are you
You're a bunch of smaller armies
Spread out over a wider area trying to find enough stuff to keep your troops from starving to death
And that means the enemy can defeat you
Bit by bit we just what Caesar does
Caesar will also have his garlic allies
Attack
Individual tribes that are part of this
Belgae Confederation and keep them busy while he concentrates another one
Once again Caesar says that these people are particularly ferocious and once again he blames it on the fact that they're not
Corrupted by Roman luxury that they're a long way from Rome which keeps him somewhat insulated
A train archaeological works that do say that the
Farther north you go from Rome the smaller the town's get
The less urbanized sort of
Core you have
The more the government's begin to resemble governments that have gone out of fashion
The parts of Gaul closer to Rome like
Aristocracies and kings
So maybe there's some truth to it
Hard to explain
Why these belgae people
We're so much tougher than the surrounding Galls if indeed they were
They don't seem to have been more numerous
Or better LED
They don't have better equipment
Or training they don't have more money
I mean none of none of the things where you might be able to say well there's a legitimate reason
Why these people
Lord it over the garlic Neighbors
Caesar says it's basically cuz they're tougher and more ferocious
I don't accept that
Because that's a stereotypical
Rhetorical
Trope it is
How do you explain it
A friend of mine
That was a military history major I went to
College with
He had the best answer I've ever heard to this
His answer was
He just wasn't buying any of
You wouldn't believe in any of the
List of Caesar
You said in his mind
Any
Question about how tough this tribe
Waze vs. hot tub tribe was his all stuff Caesar throws in there to make Caesar look better
Because you can never know about that kind of stuff so he's going to use
The only
In a fact that you have out there on the table to form a most likely scenario he said the one fact on the table here this
Clear from everything
And it screams through the sources
Is it this Roman army was in comparably better
And the photos that they face
It's not a very good story though if you talk about how
Are you pitted the Roman army maybe the best of the Roman armies arguably the best of the Roman armies that was ever
Fielded
If you say that
Yes our army came it cut through the barbarians like butter it was no competition a child could come into the
The Romans and destroyed the barbarians that's another very good
Way to frame yourself promotional piece
But you're sending back to Rome is
My friend just doesn't buy any of
In his mind the only thing you know for sure
Is it these battles sound like Slaughters
And even though Caesar usually tries to throw in it
Near run Mama Jesse was touch-and-go for a while but then we cry
It doesn't really seem
And the Roman advantages are hard for
Most modern people certainly for me
To really understand because there's something about the way were raised in the
The technological era that we live in
It whenever you talk about vast
Differences between military capabilities we assume it's got to be mostly Technologic
Not easy for us
If you say
One side in this battle had machine guns in the other head bows and arrows
Are modern brain goes oh well that's a sloth
Write the technological differences going to equal a certain outcome
But if you tell us
The two armies
In a 2000 years ago
We're really different in terms of what they could do to each other and how
You're nasty they were but they're very similar in terms of actual weapons technology it's hard for us to
Stand
What it is that makes up the difference is that could account for that
And of course all the experts you really understand and there are few experts on real Ancient Warfare
But they'll tell you this is what drill and discipline.
This is what equipping basically most of your troops
With armor and metal helmets does
And we used an example once of Imagine two NFL teams
Deciding to have a football game at 1 teams not allowed any pads or helmets or anything
And now imagine that
Both sides are actually playing with edged weapons and
And it's a lot more
Nasty even then pro football you could see where that might
Be a big advantage
Also you threw that in
With the drill with I mean if there's a lot that goes into it
But it's not as I said a very good story if you say the Romans came
And destroyed the Barbarian did it with no trouble at all
And in my friend's mind that's why you need to keep
Pumping up this next tribe it's easier than
And you thought that was bad this one's even worse because
It begins to get a little monotonous Caesars not losing any of these battles and he's not even coming close
Really until
You end up with one of these tribes doing
What common sense would dictate a certain point you should do
Which is
Is Caesar's got this in comparably fantastic Army
And if it's eating you alive
On the battlefield stop facing it
You don't have to
Right it's not prescribed
And it's hard for certain culture sometimes because when you get to these Warrior cultures that have a heroic
Certified personal ethos
Where
How you doing battle and bravery and conspicuous bravery right out in front of other people in Fair fights and Duels and
All that is part of your makeup
To talk about
Subterfuge and ambushing and stuff like that
Well it doesn't always match so well
With the Inner Warrior Spirit but believe me necessity is the mother of invention
And when Caesar goes to take on the various tribes
Of the belgae the Bell guy by the way is another way to pronounce it
The first thing that happens is they get these large numbers of people together which they can't feed so Caesar apparently way
Wait them out
They'll be some skirmishing a little bit of this a little bit of that but it looks like Caesar's plan is to just sit there and absorb all the food he can
Resume logistical Services while he watches the enemy around him supposedly in the 300,000
Numerical range
Begin to Star
Of course I have to hold hands down bruker
Cuz he's the logistical guy
Delbrook
Explain Caesar's into Northern Gaul where the belgia corbel get people live in says
The belgae
Also Bell guy
Had a premonition of their impending Danger
United their forces and when Caesar cross their borders moved out against him with a large Allied Army
That civilization has means of warfare that are lacking to Barbary
The belgae were no doubt capable of assembling a large army
But not a holding it together and feeding it
Just as the cimbri and teutones those barbarians from
Caesar's birth.
Had to split up on their campaign into Italy and were defeated individually by Marius
Caesar instead of moving immediately into a decisive battle against an army of the same size as he is her perhaps cancer
Suitably larger
Found the means of splitting up the Allied Army
So that he could then deal with only individual try
In the meantime
Deborah Crites
Caesar head organized two new Legions
Somebody now had a total of 8
Which is auxiliary troops of numidians cretans bow lyrics and garlic cavalry
His army may have well numbered 50000 to combatants
And a grand total of 80 thousand to a hundred thousand Souls
In order to feed such a mess in one place for a rather long time
One must have a very strong and reliable organization
Transport suppliers in finance system
The Romans had such means
Where's the belgae did not
Can any points out that
Wicked ability of the Romans to sort of make
Stationary field fortifications of Battlefield weapon
Deerbrook says quote
But Caesar had still other means at his disposal
He set up a camp on the North Bank of the Seine
River
And his army was so well equipped with tools
And it's Soldier so well disciplined and so well-trained in their techniques
It was in the shortest possible time an impregnable Fortress stood there
And quote
To give you an idea of size
Is in size vary depending on how large the Roman Forest that needed
To be in the camp
Happened to me but
Some of these camps could be well over a hundred acres in size
And they always had a ditch and I always had a rampart in the Roman soldiers carry sharpened Stakes when they marched
Savannah at night they could stick those steaks into the Earth and Rampart so became a
Pincushion around the camp
Guard towers walls and everyday the camp stayed in the same spot and didn't move it became
More sophisticated deeper more defensible more finished
That you were there long enough Roman 10 switch were laid out on a prescribed Roman Road grid system which included a main
Main Street inside
This little Roman town is what it amounted to these tents would turn into cabins at that
Camper there long enough
There be artillery
And they could put it up so fast
Knows every said earlier I believe the Roman soldiers about half soldier in about half construction worker
And a construction worker side
Was more important than you might think
You fans the Romans know already though it's
Something that they brought to the table which was unusual there were other armies that could create
Some more obsessive about creating camps to
Protect themselves for example when on campaign
But the Romans almost use their construction ability in an offensive way it's fabulous
Unless of course you're a call a component in which case
You know how
Disheartening is it to think UK we got a nice relatively open Battlefield here we're going to fight these Roman tomorrow
And then wake up in the morning to find fortifications on
Add artillery
And I should point out when we say artillery we have
Beastly mean Roman and Greek style
Artillery nothing gunpowder e
In this case a lot of it was
What's called torsion
Vices and I've seen these things and I still don't understand the prince of
But it involves Twisted sinews and
Stores that buy lot of energy and when it's released
You can fling
Stones or projectiles at
Look like big heavy arrows were
Beers
From these weapons
And by the way these weapons come in all shapes and sizes and the Very largest of them are rather enormous
But in this case most of the ones were talking about
Lighter weapons
Caesar specifically in one of my translations
Refers to one of the
Artillery pieces involved is a 1 pounder
And had to go look that up a one-pounder means the stone itself that this weapon
Flung
Weighed 1 lb
But I read another source that talked about the fear
That these
Stones flying through the air at high speed in the sound they made
The fear that that generated sometimes if you were on the receiving end of those
Maybe this is how you outclassing opponent
When your weapon systems are not
All that dissimilar I mean
They're both use an edged weapons that are metal they both got Spears they both either use human sinew power for
Your Tactical Battlefield stop at the Roman artillery is pretty awesome
I'm having the logistical and organizational capability to build a fortress overnight
That's pretty important and effective to
Add to that what we've been talking about the ability to feed your Army on campaign
And easily explained how Caesar's campaign against these
Tribes of belgae actually workout
Every said he may be facing 300,000 of these Warrior is up in the north here near the
English Channel but how do you feed
A barbarian Army that large the answer is apparently you don't
Caesar says the tribes come together and have a meeting and say
We got to go home everybody's got to go back to their own home we know we can feed ourselves
Timolol go back to our own homes and when we get there
If Caesar attacks any of us everybody will come to the aid of the attacked right
Historians are divided as to whether or not that is a realistic defense strategy
Samsung compact
Or whether it is a cop out
Sham to cover up
A every man for himself or every try for himself so tough attitude
Panache curious handstyle Brook falls into the latter category
He's tribe decide to break up and go home
Well let's pretend it is three hundred thousand people
When they decide to go home and they've been facing Caesar
How did they even go about this meat is it like then we compare things to Woodstock the Woodstock Rock concert earlier what how
Happens when Woodstock breaks up
Woodlots
The people in large masses just so to go streaming in the opposite direction
So what do you do if your Caesar in your opportunity while you attack don't you
He sent his Cavalry running through
These crowds of people spearing them shooting them
Just running them that killed
Untold number
And all of these
Belgic tribes
Ran back to wherever their tribal Homeland was they seem to have decided that they were going to hold up most of the time in these
Hill forts of theirs which by the way if you've never seen one
Go look at an aerial photo they're awesome
Basically what these people did was find
You know nature is fortification where nature had crafted a wonderful area to defend and then added in a human
Touches
Kimber hear some stone work there
And what have you but if you have a nice
White giant Hill
And you have maybe a nice river that curves around a whole side of it forming a defensive Optical I mean your you got a pretty good start
A lot of these tribes maybe thought they could hold out in these locations and they were wrong
Apparently all Caesar had to do was show up
Just some of these
Nasty scary tribes that he talked about
And the second they saw him they gave up One Tribe big nasty tribe tens of thousands of warriors
Caesar says they saw the Roman Siege weapons and when timeout
If you're going to use those I'm out
So overall by Roman technology there
This is another one of those big nasty tribes
Didn't even get within 5 miles of their Hill for it and they were coming out to say we're done
He says the last of the big tribes
It was opposing him where this tribe called the nervii or the nervi I
Way up in the north right
Scary nor he said that they
Took their people there
Wives and their children and their elderly
Their animals and their baggage and possessions and they took him into the deep dark swamps with a Roman couldn't get them
And we're going to resist self course
Caesar takes the Army into the land of the nervia
He says one day
You know they're deciding where they're going to camp for the night
We talked about that right
A little obsessive about the camps but if you were
As bad at scouting and reconnaissance as the Romans are always joked about being
And one of my friends also said that behavior is bad it's gotten to the Romans are you better have a good camp with big walls and
Towers
In this case Caesar
Has his army arriving in a long column down the road because where we like to talk about field battles all the time with understanding
Most of the time these armies are on the move and when they're on the Move they're stretched out in a long line like a snake
All the way into the distance
Very vulnerable position to be in
And when the head of the snake arrives
At the campsite for the night
Caesar tells those Legions that are their first to start building the cat
The legions at the very
Tale of the snake won't be arriving for some time
Caesar chooses another one of these Hills that if you've been paying attention and likes all throughout his writings
He likes an ice Hill
They can put most of his army on its size-wise he likes a nice gentle slope on one side he loves it if you can have a tray
Rain feature to Garda Flanagan in this case there's a river
At the bottom of the softly sloping Hill he says
Only about three feet deep but it's there
Benny says on the opposite side of the river is a mirror image of his Hill
It slopes up from the river gently he says there's about two hundred paces
So think about a couple of football fields
Obama
Sort of Open Country and then there's a wood
Imma top of the hill
Little Caesar has the
Elite Legion put down their packs
Interpret their military stuff aside get their hammers their nails the timber the shovels and begin making the camp and transform themselves
Into these amazing
Construction worker
Meanwhile he says
And this could be open to
Question by the way. What's about to happen here will learn Caesar some criticism during his own lifetime
Enter military experts ever since
But he says
I put out my Cavalry in my light troops and had them screening this whole operation right to protect the owner
Purple lesions that were
You know under construction at the moment as more and more of my troops arrived
From the column
Eventually Caesar will have
Six Legions they're building the fort
With more on the way
And he says my Cavalry is skirmishing with some of the belgae cavalry
And he says and then my baggage comes into view in the distance so the Roman baggage is in the middle of this long
Columnar comes over the horizon and everyone can see it and he says when that happens
That's the signal for the Ambush to start
He says that there's an army
I've never VI in the woods
On the opposite Hill from suzhou
An army
Is my friend said right
If you're going to be so bad at scouting you miss the army
Of Barbarians in the woods across from where you're building a camp you better have a strong camp
In this case
Right around the time seizures Cavalry gets close enough to the woods maybe to figure out what's in there
What's in their charges out of the woods
Caesar salad at astonishing speed that's by Carolyn Hamm
Carolyn Hammett has the great line astonishing speed
Seizure then goes on to say that they brush aside his Cavalry and light infantry screen like an insect basically and they come
Screaming down the hill
Now
We have no idea
How big does hell is
All we can say is that they scream down that Hill they cross the 3-foot river they start up the next Hill
Lil Ceaser in six Legions are on not ready for this
Now we talked earlier about why we chose this as a subject I said
I was fascinated with a tribal people
In the situation that we seen all throughout history
Trying to resist the encroachment of a more technologically and organizationally Superior
Are more efficient culture
And I chose this one because unlike the Native American example of the African example
These people had a chance to win
Now they were never the betting favorites
And the
Way that they perform so far in battles against the Roman army demonstrates that
The numbers are so much larger than what the North American Native Americans for example could have put together
But you can see why you got to give these people
The corner boxing line the punchers chance
Good luck figuring out how many people there are here if you're going to believe Caesar you're going to get up to number they're like 75
Thousand
Those seem absurd
But there's a lot of Romans there and that's pretty confirmable so it's not going to be too low
If you said 20000
That's going to be
Four times the largest Native American Force I've ever heard of
4 *
And we're talking about a charging Out of the Woods all at once
20000 would also be about how many Zulus were at that famous battle in the late 1800s where they wiped out
A force of 13 or 14
Soldiers from Britain
But the truth is it's probably larger than that so if you said 35,000
35000 man charging out of a Woods
Within running distance from you and that's how long you have to get your act together before they hit you
And try to blow you away like a wave blowing through
A few bathers on the beach
Caesar goes into overdrive
At this point
And you begin to see
You know what makes the guy so special he's not Alexander the Great
Grabbing a spear and leading the Cavalry in charge
Cesar does grab a shield he says
But he begins to go and demonstrate leadership
He also says that these veteran troops
Do a lot for themselves and Caesar had left their officers with him and so all of them would simply throw down there
Work tools grab a weapon that they could find
Caesar says their shields were still in the leather cases their helmets worn off and around and they just ran to the nearest standard
They forgot anything about going to their own unit they're just trying to form
A block of human beings that can resist this on Rush that's coming toward them at full running speed
I'm not understand by tribesmen here
Are participating in a huge gamble because they certainly know
That they are going to be like blown horses by the time they reach the Roman line
They're taking this gamble that there won't be any Roman lines when they get there yet
And if they're going to be able to attack these Romans while they're still divided and in small
Lumps that are unconnected to each other in which case they should be able to just blow them away
But the gamble is if they don't
They're not going to have a whole lot less
If this turns into any kind of a long-term slog they're doomed
Caesar says he grabs a flag he says a couple of words of encouragement to the unit that he's with
Before going to the next unit to talk to them about the time he gets to the next unit they're already engaged
This is a moment here
With these Legions and Caesar with the
Could easily be overrun
And it allows us to play with some counterfactual we haven't really been able to discuss yet the first counterfactual is
What is Caesar loses here
The second counterfactual is
What if Caesar dies here
In the first case
And we had said earlier that
The Roman expansion into
Tribal
Territory the rich tribal territory to the north of them seemed inevitable just like manifest destiny
But maybe the question to ask is how many
Deaths would it take to make something that seemed inevitable
Not inevitable anymore
Because we can see that only about 65 years after
This battle
The Romans will be ambushed by another tribe of people
4 tribes of people this time in Germany modern-day Germany and they're probably what we could call German
They will destroy
This Roman army a famous battle called the teutoburg evolved
In 980 I believe it is
The Roman Commander will commit suicide on the battlefield to avoid falling into the hands
Apus Barbarian opponents
Which if you believe the hype top Roman sources
Is a good thing to do because the Romans conduct is his legendary would be a good way to prevent legendary
Asian a couple years after that
Beaten debacle
To recover what's left of their dead comrades
And they go into the deep dark forest and supposedly they the Allura details of
A Roman skeletons
Is stapled to the trees and piles of skulls and religious
Alters with
You're dead Romans and blood everywhere I mean just this horrible tribal nightmarish
Visitation of all
Shall we say the native frustration at the situation
And you have the famous story of the Roman Emperor at the time who will beat his head against the wall and supposedly yelled the name of the jet
General who killed himself Beres and say there is give me back my Legions
That was only about 15000 Dead Romans
And whatever happened there was one of the main components supposedly
That made the Romans decide you know what we don't need to advance any farther in Germany anymore
That's a good place to just set the border and we'll expand elsewhere
If that really played that large of a role in the Romans decided not to go into Germany any farther
What is
Caesar lost
Twice that many men
At this bar
And what is twice that many men
In the larger scheme of things what you say
Chica the natives have ever done anything to short-circuit manifest destiny
Well I don't know what if they killed
30000 American soldiers in an afternoon
I went and did the math
And you know these numbers are
Debatable
Too but I went to some common sources and I added up all of the combat deaths that the United States has suffer
From the wars of Independence when we got our independence in this country
Up until the first world war start
And then I subtracted the Civil War because those are crazy dance and everybody on both sides dying as in America
Casualty
So
Total us combat deaths excluding the Civil War up to 1917 and it's
Almost certainly under 30000
If you lost
All the people you lost from Independence to the first world war minus the Civil War in an afternoon
Wood that is slowed down Manifest Destiny at all how much
If United States ran into a gawlik
Kingdom on the other side of the western side of the Mississippi early on
And they inflicted a 30,000 death afternoon on the United States
The ramifications of that who knows
But remember the Romans have no guns they have no Cannon
They're on this hill
Trying to deal with these people that are going to smash into them
And seizures running from unit to unit trying to help
It's the most critical point of his career so far
If he dies here which is very very possible
Does the Roman
Republic fall does the empire ever start I mean the Dominos Start Tumbling
If there's no Caesar
In at the end of this afternoon
Remember Caesar is going to maximize his chances of becoming a casualty
I continually
In a running over to whichever part
I'll his battle line if you can even call it something is organized does that whichever part is the most threatened
Right where the 911 call is he's going to go there
When the belgae when the nervi I managed to hit his
Troops
Is troops on the left are able to get off he says a throw of their Pila the heavy javelin
And then charge down the hill
At this one group of
Kalter belgae
They will beat them chase them down the hill chase them over the river
The Warriors will then regroup and charge the Romans again only to be beaten by the left-wing of the Romans again
And that left-wing will start advancing up the hill
George where the Celtic Camp is
Cesar Center will also weather the storm
And managed to do something similar by beating and hand-to-hand combat the Warriors that they run into to their front
And will also advance
Now the problem is is with the left in the center advancing
You end up with an open space
The Roman right-wing no longer has any protection their uncovered on the flank you might say
And Caesar says a giant group
Are these nerves VII tribesmen
With the Commander in like a giant
Hammerhead column
Push through this Gap
And then once they're past the CenterPoint
Some of them turn around
And begin to smash into the flank
Oh Caesars right hand units
Some of them go straight on ahead toward the Roman camp
Thoughts of looting and burning and pillaging
So Caesars right-hand Legions are now in trouble
He runs over to them to try to help
Meanwhile
When the Celtic forces the belgae forces break into Caesar's camp and start looting
The people that see that think the battle is over
Caesar says his Cavalry in
And light troops in
Been brushed aside like insects and beaten so badly when this first
Starts
Are just now we really struggling into Camp they look up and they see
The very people who just beat the hell out of them running rampant through seizures camp and they go that's that and they run away
All of the civilian
And
An average Joe camp followers run in fear we're told even that seizure is very tough supposedly
A Celtic Allied Cavalry season
These belgae running rampant through the Roman
Camping figures they're done to so they turn around and go home and other words
Little Caesars bad situation is getting worse by the moment
So he runs over to the right flank
With these units are in Desperate trouble
And basically
Portrays the situation as dire
And collapse of the right flank as eminent
Usually seizure
Describe the difficulties on
The right flank is from is a Hanford translation
And remember when Caesar writes Caesar he's talking about himself in the third person quote
After addressing the 10th Legion Caesar had gone to the right wing
Where you found the troops and difficult
The cohorts of the 12th Legion were packed together so closely that the men were in one another's way and could not fight
Properly
All the centurions of the fourth cohort as well as the standard Bearer were killed
And a standard was lost
Nearly all the centurions of the other cohorts were either killed or wounded
Including the chief Centurion Publius extjs Bakula
Amanda very great courage
Who was so disabled by a number of severe wounds that he could no longer stand
The man's movements were slow and some in the rear
Feeling themselves abandoned we're retiring from the fight and trying to get out of rain
Meanwhile
The enemy maintained unceasing pressure up the hill in front
And we're also closing in on both flanks
As the situation was critical and no reserves were available
Cesar snack The Shield from a soldier in the rear
He had not his own shield with him
Made his way into the front line address each century and by name and shouted encouragement to the rest
Cast of the troops
Ordering them to push forward and open out their rank so that they could use their swords more easily
He's coming gave them fresh Heart and Hope
Each man wanted to do his best under the eyes of his commander-in-chief
However desperate
Apparel in the enemy's assault was slow down a little
And quote
But the legion next door to that was having even worse trouble so Caesar ran over there
Go to the commanders of that Force 2
Put his soldiers into a square so that they couldn't be out flanking attack from the rear anymore in that stabilize that's
Situation
Historian Adrian goldsworthy writes about this moment saying that
Caesar had stabilized the situation on the right flank but the collapse was still Eminem
Was just a matter of time
The
The Celtic force was battering these Romans down
But two things happen
But ended up having the same effect on this battle
As the Romans having a third reserve line has done in the previous battle remember they don't have a reserve line
They don't have a line
They're not deployed
What ends up happening is those Romans that had
Victorious initially on the left side and gone and capture the Barbarian camp on the opposite Hill or now he
Able to look down and see the problem that Caesar was facing
So they began to come down the hill
To renew the fight themselves Plus
The legions in the very end of the column
The tale of the snake
Have finally
And I've gotten to the top of the hill and look down and see what's going on
And they now enter The Fray
So even though Caesar wasn't able to create the traditional Roman 3rd line reserve line to throw in in
When everything
We're going to hell in a handbasket
The circumstances had an effect created one
An allegiant that came down after capturing the Celtic camp and the ones that came up from the rear of the baggage train
Turn the tide of the battle
And
Remember these
Belgae these nerves VII and related tribes who sold their soul
For that initial charge they were like blown horses as we said
The arrival of fresh troops is the worst thing that could have
But Caesar says they were
Tough
They were ferocious
They would not give in
Even when he had them basically
You know compressed into a disordered mob and he was
He was killing them all with missile weapons that you didn't even have to risk his troops
He said the Warriors stood on top of the corpses of their friends
Cold
The
Spears
Of the enemy out of their Shield or caught them in the air and turned around and threw them back in a yelling defiantly
Need to the Romans even as they know
How the afternoon is going to turn out
A ferocious Warrior enemy
Allowing themselves to be absolutely decimated
Rather than running away once again let's remember Caesar has every interest in portraying the
To be
As incredibly nasty and brave as possible none the less
Maybe they were
Caesar says that after the battle
Families that had taken shelter in the Deep
Darkwood
Swamps came out
Begging
Is clemency with
Which Caesar gives and was known for giving
Plenty of times with point that out in
To be fair to him it was part of his act
Clipart of a stick
Unites Jena se qua sometimes I'll let you live
But he did
He also says though they gave him a rundown of what they suffered in the battle and he says that they told him
Out of 60000 fighting man
They only had five
Country left
Carry arms
Now that doesn't tell you
If those people are
Heralded
Incapacitated from wounds
Likely a combination of both we have no idea what
The breakdown is
And they also point out
The Caesar has
Destroyed their lead
In this battle they say out of 600
The different translations say different things one says senators and others as counselors into this is magistrates but out of 600 of these
These leading figures in the tribe
The survivors tell Caesar only
3r live
So for all intents and purposes he has destroyed
I did it in battle
And that's going to make a crucial difference soon
There's one little bit of leftover business of the Caesar accomplish is right at the end of this battle
One of the tribes that was coming to help the nervi I never made it to the battle
Found out the results turned around and went home
But that doesn't get you out of trouble
With Caesar who follows them back home
He has a very
How confusing incident involving
You know the deals of a surrender that
Maybe were misinterpreted none the less bad things happen so Caesar eventually had to storm the town kill a lot of people
He says he sold 53000
People from the population into slavery
And point out that he sold them all in one lot
Conversion of Storage Wars
Or something
How much for this
Entire city of slaves
Say you got 53000 at a bargain price
And the slaves now let's recall something
This is money
Teaching you sell the slaves
You make money it's one of the
Things that comprise booty
Money
Stuff
You know whatever you can take and sell
Whatever you can take for yourself sometime Caesar wood gift
Slaves
And I want slaves 5 minutes ago that's for that out
Which one get this life
That is a nice
Little
Christmas bonus
If you are Roman soldier or any Soldier
And a couple of historians
Say but no one knows because it's not like we have a financial
Statement on how Caesars doing each year
But you stopped hearing about seizures terrible Financial crunches now and he's
He seemed Distributing money more
He's allegedly paying his troops more than the going rate and he's sharing the winnings with them which is pretty normal but if you're doing
Doing really well
The winnings can be really good
And as a side note
All of you who know the Roman story understand this
There's a process underway here that will play
You know mightily into the destruction of the Roman Republic very soon and that's the
Allegiance of this Army
Not necessarily being 100% entirely to the Senate and people of Rome
But increasingly more and more
To this man
Julius Caesar
And he's far from the only Roman general this is happening to
His
Fellow members of the triumvirate are getting into similar situation
When the allegiance of the truth because
You know how they're doing in life is so dependent on that single figure at the head of their particular Army when they were Legion ship
Gifts from the state to a single individual you can see how the recipe for disaster is just
Will the chain reaction is already started right drums problems go deep into the distance but
That's a key component that has to happen
And what I always tell people
I think they see
Parallels with the United States today
And the Roman Republic is yes there's there are some
But you're missing that key component and it's important
We don't have armies that are beholding the single
Military individuals more than they are the state
Increasingly is this Army and Cesar bond together and share the fruits of their labors they are
So the question of whether Caesars in debt anymore seems to be that he probably isn't and in fact this little business
Adventure
Gall is working out pretty well indeed
So Caesar says after this little battle with the belgae he sends a message to Rome and he says
And let me find out
Not for the last time in his commentary
Gaul is pacified
Now let me stop
Because if you say not for the last time
Is Gaul really pacify because again you have to wonder what Caesars doing here he may have had a whole lot of reason
For going back to Rome at this time.
And telling them pay the war's over and we won
Can see some advisor going to listen to Caesar you have no idea what it's like on the ground in Rome right now we're trying to get
These people elected to the Senate you would really help if the timing we're going you said we won in Gaul right now
I guess what I'm saying is I trust Caesar and his intelligence
Both his
Mental intelligence at his reconnaissance
Enough to think
That I doubt whether he thought Gaul really was pacified because let's look at what just happened to your into campaign season
Less than 2 years
Caesar conquered a place the size of Texas
Ploutarxos
300 tribes
Really
And you expected to stay subdued
Well if he did expect that he was wrong
And if you didn't well there must have been another reason for
Telling the people back in Rome that the war was over
Caesar in a rare obvious Bragg in the commentaries points out that when the Romans heard
The teacher had just wanted ghaul they proclaimed 15 days of Thanksgiving in the capital
Which Caesar points out
Is a longer. Of time than anyone before him at ever had a Thanksgiving declared in their honor
So maybe that
For it right there
Let's remember
Why Caesars in Gaul doing all this
To begin with
Because of how it's looking back home
15 days of Thanksgiving an unprecedented amount
That makes it all worth it right there doesn't depends on what your goals are of course
Now the other thing that needs to be pointed out here is how victory
Heather Way
Forgiving everything
Because
There is an undercurrent in a row my mom
Prominent individuals admittedly prominent individuals that don't like Caesar anyway and would find something to get him with
If they could anywhere
But what seizures doing is grossly illegal on many fronts
He's raised
Legions
Out of his own pocket booking without permission
His opponents in Rome
I pointed out things that he's done during this campaign
That are violations of Roman honor and one or two of them will suggest maybe he should be handed over
To the former Roman enemies as a
Well slippery this way the Romans have done that before
Who are some Roman General on the ground made a deal with
Another city
Came back the Roman senate repudiated the deal
Sent the general back to the former opponents in Chains left him outside of in front of the front gate and said sorry he couldn't make a deal
You like that does against Roman honor but since he did here you can have him do it
And what you want
Never people
You know of the Cato Camp they were maybe suggestion Caesar deserve treatment
Like that but very few people were listening you know why
Cuz the guy just conquered and area
Larger than all of Italy itself
Into campaign season
You can hear the
Crowd going wrong number one I mean come on when in human history
Have the populist not celebrated unbelievable Victor
It's almost weird to imagine
The general public ever doing the opposite
So what it took for is easier to get these victories legal or illegal
Are totally overshadowed by the result
The result may be an illusion now Caesar says that after
He's done here he goes and starts to look at
The next big adventure he's going to do is between illegal to go into Italy around where
You know the modern
Adriatic is he's going to start conference and try to that which had been a plan of his all along but now they call is pacify her
He can put some time into it nieces while he's there
Gall erupts back into war
It happened so fast you can't help but wonder if it was ever pacified at all
And there been some theories floated in a bunch of books I've read lately which I think is facet
I'm going to run past you cuz it would make a lot of sense winded and it's the idea
That may be the reason Gul almost immediately erupts into trouble after Caesar says it
Pacified
Is it maybe they didn't fully understand what they were agreeing to when they said that they were going to submit to Raw
Redwoods Rome is treating them as though they have signed a contract
And if you break the contract
The ramifications are
In a mafia-style in nature so don't break the contract
And maybe like a bunch of Native Americans
For expected to read like a lawyer this treaty and yet they can hardly write their names
In the white man's language
Maybe these Celtic leaders were essentially taken for a ride their Barbarian lawyer is not as good as the Roman ones
And maybe as soon as they started living under the real terms of the deal maybe was a little different than they thought of what he just during the Great lie
He's a beast tribes were accustomed to making themselves clients of other Barbarian people
Very well may have treated them
In a much more laissez-faire hands-off kind of fashion that might have been
Their idea of a client in their world
But now the Romans were coming in and these are going to send the fence surveyors to your property let's see where the property line is your we're going to
Some former Soldier veterans on part of your property to take your son into the army and oh yeah I'll taxes are going up this year we need extra
Weed cuz the army star but I mean whatever it might be
The garlic people are
Chafing at what it's like to be Roman
But now I think we get to the Crux question that we started this talk out with
If you know what would you be willing to sacrifice everything
If you are
Chafing
Another word I just used to get chafing from Roman domination
At what point is the chafing bad enough for you to risk having the Romans come back
Beat you in some sort of field battle
Kill you
It would be sick before kill you kill your son's rape your wife send your daughters off to slavery Destroyer
At what point is chafing bad enough
And then you begin to get into this question of human motivation
What is it that's worth risking that
Kind of
Terrible outcome for
Caesar says it's liberty
And freedom and Independence and that's
Weird
Not because those are weird motivations
Topeka Caesars the guy
Who's going to stamp out these people
And once again he's giving them aspirations
That we can sort of relate to that make them sympathetic characters to us in the same way he's put
You're the voice of an almost war crimes prosecutor in the mouth of his German opponent
Ariovistus
He's going to put
In the words of people like Patrick Henry Give me liberty or give me death and all those kind of people into the mouths of these
Is Golic opponents
Who's Liberty he is smashing
It's fascinating and again it's very complicated I don't fully understand it
I enjoyed Andrew and Rigby's book as I said on the
On the whole analysis
But no consensus exist they just analyze the three-dimensional chess game Caesars playing
And of course the first question we all ask
Friday's
If Caesar says that these people are fighting for Liberty and freedom in when he puts words into their speeches and they talk about
Liberty and freedom what the heck do people Barbarian people
2000 years ago mean when they say that or Caesars putting those words into their mouth and their Caesars words
What does Cesar mean for it to me
According to Andrew Rigsby it's just what you think it means maybe only more so
He writes the word and then gives you the Latin word Caesar actually use he says quote
Freedom libertas wasn't even more politically charged term for the Roman senate is generally today
Prettiest deeply rooted in the pervasive social institution of slavery
Despite the many and varied situations to which it was applied libertas remained a powerful
Slogan because if it's unambiguously positive primary sense
Conversely
Slavery servatis
Recalled the degradation of slaves seen daily in a society which as we have already noted
Personal dignity was a fighting matter
And quote
In other words
You know Caesars basically giving
An excuse for these rebellions
To the Gauls
But he says right away right is it a question of Freedom versus slavery and pliant Romans understand that it would never settle.
To be slaves
And that we today look at and go will I can fully see with the Gulzar about because I'd be on their side to
It's a very interesting document and it says a lot about the tenor of the times in the audience he was writing for the he
He could position the whole story this way
And still expect you to cheer on his victories when he crushes these freedom-loving calls right to pets really
What they were
And just with every
Story of Revolution by the way
For every account you hear of the Gauls trying to preserve their own liberty and freedom in a very high-minded Patrick Henry send
You will read the accounts that get much more greedy
And describe much more
Base values to the people who are doing these things in this particular group run by this Aristocrat wants
More power within his try but Roman domination uniforms his Ambitions so he's wanting Revolution
When the southern tribe who used to collect all the tolls on this River before the Romans took over but now they favor the Rival tribe
And so you know receipts are down from the river tolls so we're going to rebell
The ones who are just playing
Fickle and tired of living under the same set of rules for a significant. Time seizure said that the Gauls all have
A bunch of men who just Delight in the change of government and they get bored easily and so they're easily roused to
Some sort of change just for change the sake of who knows what the actual reasons are
The bottom line though is Cesar barely gets to enjoy
The winter off
Before he's back in Gaul right recently pacified Gaul is exploded into problems
Three or four months after Caesar declares mission accomplished
There's a strain of historian to think this is all part of the plan
CJ doesn't want to give up his command remember he be vulnerable in wrong place there still places to conquer money to be
The major reasons to stay armies to keep
Assembled
And in your hands
But a pattern is going to emerge
Free for the next couple of years and it's a pattern actually that's not that dissimilar
From other Roman
Conquest of Celtic peoples in other parts of Europe
For this time
The pattern is
Charismatic leaders emerge
Who can manage to unite at least local groupings of tribes into larger confederacy's who then
Challenge the Romans by rebelling against them
And the Romans will respond
With extreme violence
It's actually very interesting case study for modern people in
If you're interested in military Affairs in guerrilla warfare
And I
Civil Wars and things like that to watch House Caesar approaches in the rooms during this. Approach
How you quell
Domestic
Resistance you know by a population because when I was growing up
In the wake of the Vietnam War there was so much talk about if you'd only fought the Vietnam War
You know with the gloves off
What's the phrase you
Take away these modern cultural innovations that tell you you know that you can't do this and you can't do that if you go in
When are you really your star ruthless and you'll change the battlefield scene overnight
The Romans are an example of that
In later Roman history they will be very good
You know what the game of the carrot and the stick and they'll learn how to bribe tribes when it's better to spend money than to be
Beat people over the head with a stick
In the Caesar. They're much more in the beat the other people over the head with a stick
Mode
And Caesar will go back
To Gall and spend the next several years
Truly
Pacifying
The methods that Caesar will use the
To quell this resistor
When the first people he'll deal with it.
The Confederacy of peoples on the Atlantic Seaboard in 56 BCE
He will defeat you have to build a fleet to do at the Romans are crazy good that way
Defeats the seafaring people
And because in Caesars mind all of this area is already been pacify we're now dealing with rebellions this isn't a contest
Best of You Know virtues on the battlefield May the best man win and you'll probably get clemency afterwards
This is you are rebelling against the authority of the state
You are setting a bad example for other people we need to keep down so we have to make an example of you
And I'm the main tribe called the Venice High or sometimes daniti
Caesar
Kill their entire leadership beheaded them
Sold the population into slavery
He will
Deal with an German incursion again
Or so he says
In 55 BCE
So he launched is what you might call a
4re
A raid
A punitive Expedition into Germany
Meanwhile manages to have another battle
Against the German tribe
This is the incident by the way they
Some of the Cato crowd back in Rome
Suggested to Caesar maybe should be
Be handed over
German enemies in Chains
Because what he did and he admitted freely in
Is commentaries
Is this
Leadership
This German tribe
Sounds like a large number of people
Showed up to Caesar maybe to negotiate what they thought was a surrender
And instead Caesar grab them
And holds them and sends his army out to attack the now leaderless and unexpected ending
German tribe
And the numbers that died here are crazy unbelievable in crazy I mean
Wait for it
400000 German people died
And Caesar himself in the writing talks about a moment
In the fighting
Where there's just crowds of women and children
And what does he do
He sends his Cavalry to and this is a quote from the
Hammond translation
Hunt them down
So perhaps we're moving from
One potential un war crimes tribunal set of charges when we're talkin about
Free and understood Warfare
And a contest of arms
And something like this
The most amazing things easier does we have to point out the wild Factory don't we
Is that he will build a bridge over the Rhine River right no small river that
He will do it in 10 days and I mean it involves
Cranes and pylons
And Rams to put pillars into the
River Bandits
Incredibly
Tribes common submit to him simply because they've seen him build this
He said he had to build it because both did not seem like a good way to cross the river and he wasn't sure it was
In keeping with Roman dignity he said
So you spend 10 days and you build a Trestle Bridge
The Romans cross the bridge burn lots of villages in a killed quite a bit of people in these raids took 18 days comes back
Back over the Rhine on the bridge they built and then they destroy the bridge
It's generally assumed that Caesar was trying to send a message
The message is at least one is clear
And that's that
We can come over this River anytime we wanted snowberry rittal don't pretend like you're say
The other one was just with some historians have also said
Is it was also Cesar's way of saying
And by the way this is the Border
You come over here expect a response not from these garlic peoples
Home you come to expect you can beat in battle
But against us
Did you just lost yet another battle to
How many dead 400000 Caesar said they were 430,000 people there
He talks about great numbers of them die
Even Michael Grant says the numbers may be exaggerated but maybe not that much what do you do with Caesars
Death Ledger there it just went up by a lot didn't
And if you believe Cato and that segment of the Romans
It wasn't something that had to happen
Caesar prompted at
Maybe wanted it
After this
Defeat of the Germans late in the campaign season right as you're probably pack it in after that big German thing no heat
It takes a fleet
And Crosses
The English Channel goes where no Mediterranean Army has ever gone before
The foggy Misty
Almost legendary in Mediterranean circles island of Britain
Lands there
Talks about the natives being in chariots and painting themselves blue and Caesar has a battle and of course it's no near run
All kinds of problems
Corsi wins
Are the fleet almost gets destroyed by a storm
There are howls of protests about his contemporary political opponents
And let's be honest armchair generals ever since going
What the heck are you doing
What does this have to do with anything how do you justify this
And yet the publicity is outrageously good
Earlier we said he's
Leading the SEC
Expedition like a heavily-armed Lewis and
Clark exploration team
LG Egypt
Landed in Britain and the people back home can't stop talking about it
All those people that keep talking about him exceeding his wartime Authority and what have you
You know I'm can hardly make themselves heard
Above all of them
The positive comments
By the way little side note here
The debate is ongoing whether or not these people in the British Isles
During this period should be classified as
Celtic
Or not
And again we're not talking in terms of ethnicity is much a
Culture
It's a little confusing cuz Caesar says
One of these tribes that lived on the now French side of the English Channel
Did some migrating over
So when Caesar goes to Britain and describes people that sure sound Celtic
They sound a lot like the people we've been talking about in terms of their dress and their Styles in there
Attitudes in the religion War.
You don't know whether or not he's running into that one tribe or whether or not the people all through the rest of it I need the
Y'all have Celtic names I mean again
I'm not qualified the way into this ongoing debate
Apparently Caesar doesn't refer to them specifically as Celts
In the ancient world that used a different name for them and I'm going to use my very kind of get out of jail free card and say that a Celtic
Is anyone who consider themselves to be Celtic I don't know
The Caesars obviously created a problem
Not a hard one to imagine happening either when he takes a
Big chunk of his army
From which now modern-day France and takes it over New Britain because that means it's no longer in what's now modern-day France
You can already feel
Your 2,000 plus years later some of the Rumblings going on right of seizures not actively here
You know The Cauldron starts bubbling again
The next year 54 BC
Caesar launches a much better prepared
And significant
Raid was what the earlier expedition to Britain probably was this is more like
NAA reconnaissance in force reminder invasion
Elaine's their defeats a major British tribe
And here's sort of army if you're following Caesar story and Caesars narrative
Throughout the entire narrative we said there's been this V
Column
Entity in Gaul itself
People who are in these tribes
Certainly in the last friendly tribes but even in Rome's greatest allies you don't like the Roman
Consul Caesar
When he's going to go back to Britain for the second time realizes
But you know he's leaving all these troublemakers back in Gaul so in a very ancient typical Roman thing
He asks for them to come to an honored guest and probably be the way the invitation said but hostages the way
Any you would call it today hostages for good behavior we're going to take the troublemakers with us
There's a whole bunch of famous troublemakers in
Roman Celtic history
These people that are like the geronimo's of Celtic
Resistance and in this case one of them
Not that I expect everyone to remember
You know that magician Gandalf Dumbledore religious leader Druid guy we talked about earlier he was
The reason this whole thing happened though if you believe the official narrative
Duplication
By the way you will also c-diff
Wahkiacus
And give a Chaka
We're going to go with you
Vacations DeSoto
A Roman friend
What he's got a brother thinking like two heads of the same coin
And his brother in this tribe what are Rome's greatest friends in the region
Is anti Roman
And his Druid Brothers been covering for him all this time and Caesar says he's been nice about the whole thing because he
Appreciate this Druid guy and likes him and needs his supporting his tribe is very important
But this is one of the guys
His name is Jim norick
One of the guys Caesar wants to take with him to the British Isles so that he's not causing trouble when Caesar the way
And this do Norwich character decides that this
At least
Caesar Caesar says do nor extinct Caesars going to
Take heed and all the other troublemakers across the English Channel
And kill them there
Away from the prying eyes of his own people
Able to come back and make up any old excuse why they're not with him anymore
And if you Norrix doesn't believe this himself
Cesar said he's going to all these other
Are tribal leaders and saying you don't go it's easier to to Britney's going to kill us there
Cesar then talks about you too many excuses that this do norick making of the sort that you know I get seasick and I can't go with
With you for all these other reasons Caesars has finally when you know Caesar Corners in
The guy bolts
Basically showing his true colors Caesar would basically have you understand he's just uncovered and unmask this conspiracy he sends
Just meant to go bring this guy back Dead or Alive they bringing back dead
And this guy becomes just one of many troublemakers that Caesar begins
To go after now is his way of shutting down this garlic resistant I get rid of the the leaders of the
The resistance
Because you're some of these tribes have large numbers of people that are of a different political opinion than what them
George eventually get them in one of these battles that Caesars facing
He'll face a tribe that has reportedly killed
All their Senators who disagreed with the idea of rebellion so when we were saying what are you willing to die for
What are you willing to lose everything for
There might be disagreement in your community about
That
Caesars is one of these tribes killed all the Senators that had a no vote on Rebellion
And went unified to go meet their fate against the Romans
The Troublemaker that Caesar head
Instructed be brought back to him dead or alive that do Norrix guy
He represents an example of a counter faction in opposition party if you will in his own tribe
He must have been karizmatik
He must have been dangerous in the romanized
And he just becomes the latest victim
In the Roman standard policy of how you deal with these troublemakers everywhere you encounter them
It's a sort of if you will
A very mafia-like approach to the situation but
Hard to argue
About its efficacy
When faced with
Karizmatik
Tribal
Guerrilla leaders if you will kill them when you can
The Romans have done this many times either directly or indirectly
I believe earlier we mentioned one of the
National
Heroes of
People of Portugal now when they were in their ancient version and he's one of these people that
You let a position to roam and they managed to get him assassinated I Believe by his own people
I believe there was a bribe
Paid assassination
In another case
The Romans ran into one of these leaders and this isn't this conflict
That was karizmatik that they wanted to get and
During a Cavalry battle
The Roman this is from Caesar by the way the Roman leader
On this site had instructed his Cavalry remember this is at least hundreds of men against hundreds of men and maybe thousands
Husband against thousands of men
It when you go out there on the field for this large Cavalry battle
Don't pay any attention to any of the other
People
In front of you go right after that one guy
And all I could think about was imagine being
You're that guy you're on the field with your hundreds and hundreds of cohorts thinking we're going to take on their big formation and everyone in their fur
Formation is after you personally
Needless to say
They brought his head back
Can you run command
Mission accomplished
They are
And another influential maybe Irreplaceable
Leader of the Celtic opposition is no more
Right out of the Roman Playboy
I didn't 54 BCE
You get one of the pretty good troublemaker
Baker's right at these are all spark this is a pretty good spot
His name is ambiorix he was one of several important people in a revolt
He's a national hero of Belgium now
Any Fitness template abate
Have a karizmatik Celtic figure who could unite a bunch of tribes together to oppose the Romans
He's a particular Lisa
Successful one of these rebels in the he manages by hooker by crook to kill a bunch of Romans
I get like 15 cohorts like a legion and five cohorts something like that
He gets out there and convinces them to leave the safety of their fort
And then ambushes them
When they're marching through some deep dark woods No Doubt
And the Romans would be in trouble all the time during the winter when they would break up to the various areas they had
Patrolling KeepSafe
Annie's 4th and it becomes like Fort Apache
And any time of rebellion happens you know these
This isolated Legion or two of Romans will find themselves deep in Indian Country surrounded by Angry native
Time and again
This becomes part of the narrative
When Caesar will go back and Rescue all these people or avenge them a lot more of the garlic folks.
Can you again have to ask yourself
You know what's going on here and what do you form in terms of an opinion of
Whether or not it is a good idea
If you are a follower of ambiorix for example
To rebell against the Romans because on one hand how could anybody
So you didn't have a good enough cause when you're talking about your freedom and your Independence right your Liberty your political Liberty
The sovereignty of your own people whatever it is
Those are pretty high-minded
Causes
But if you're in the meeting amongst your peers and your countrymen and you're having this discussion of do we reveal or don't we
I mean are you a coward if you stand up and say listen
We have
Very little chance
Sub actually succeeding here
And if we fail there's a hundred percent chance we're going to lose everything that matters to us
Including the Liberty that you're worried about now maybe we shouldn't do this
Those are the kind of choices
This is the old saying goes
The try men's Souls right
I just to get an example of what it might mean in practice take a look at what happened to this ambiorix
Write this latest Spark
The guy who when he destroyed the
Roman Legions in the D
Deep dark woods on the March
Daniel Caesar made it out to be like a
Custer's Last Stand situation with the officers in the men who were left over commit suicide because they're just there
Trapped by the natives around it I mean it
It's a harrowing terrible story and Caesar lunches
Recriminations at certain commanders I mean
It's a
Staying and so the bad guy
Well probably hero in the Gully guys with the bad guy the Roman story have your ex is going to be pursued as if to the end
End of the Earth
And Caesar has this ongoing
You know what temp to track him down he finally hasn't getting away and riding off into the sunset with like only for
Bodyguardz is the only amount of people he would trust his life to
Of course it's a good end of the movie it mean that the Geronimo figure here from the Roman point-of-view gets away
Lives to ride another day off into the sunset whatever
But unfortunately it's whole tribe can't do that
And Caesar will
Wipe them out of existence
Well that's the way he frames It Anyway historians are not sure if that was really what happened
It's pretty fair to say though that Caesar treats this tribe to tribe the damn your ex was a leading figure in
As harshly or more harshly than any other entity
Cesar punished in his career
And so you might think to yourself okay now that these people have seen
What almost everything is
Is the Romans after this. We'll start going after
Celtic cultural things that they think are
Inciting revolt
Or bringing tribes together we mentioned Druids earlier
There's a pan
Tribal nature to these Druids maybe where they come together from multiple tribes
In meetings to debate things and it
At certain points after this. The Romans will think that the Druids are sold of a hotbed of resistance
And Target then the Romans could be very accommodating to your local Traditions as long as you didn't mess with them
If you cause trouble and they decided that these local Traditions had something to do with it goodbye local traditions
So this is where
Some who will say that maybe we're not talking about
An actual genocide here as much as we're talking about a cultural genocide may have a point there
As we said before
Genocide question is somewhat
Clouded by the fact
That the people in this story have a choice
Unlike those involved in the Second World War
Write the choices submit and stay quiet or die
How does having a choice like that
Make this sort of a holocaust if indeed that's the proper term for the Celtic Holocaust
How does having a choice make it different
Cuz it obviously does
From something like what the victims of the second world war Holocaust went through
I would also be remiss if I didn't at least point out
But this idea of choice may have been in illusion
For most of the
Story
Caesar himself sad and I don't know how well we can believe him
That they were really only three class
Do use a modern term in the garlic
Society
You had the knights
You're basically the aristocracy in the nobility you had The Druids
And then you had everyone else he said everyone else is basically a Slave
This is probably Roman hyperbole in
And misinformation what not archaeologists like Barry cunliffe
And John Collins will point out that there's a lot more
Nuance to something like that than Caesar points out but
His point might be well taken how many people if you give the
Choice of
You know if you just acquiesce to Roman conquest and submit everything will be fine but if you don't you're all going to die
You sold into slavery how many people get to make that choice in that
Garlic Society on that decision
I would submit that it's probably likely and Common Sense
The most of the people in this situation or simply caught up in the gears of History
Like most people in any other piece
.
Sometimes it seems like we're all just along for the historical ride
Does net
In this case Caesar will spend
The entire campaign season 2
53 BCE essentially
Punishing
Punitive
Traditions finishing off
Battles
Small Things is Adrian goldsworthy says he
He campaigns the entire campaign season in Gaul but he doesn't fight a major battle what's he doing
Pacifying
And it's ugly
Brutal business on the ground
And we don't have details but goldsworthy has an interesting line where he says
That the archaeological record has shown
That the quantities of gold and other precious materials found
Insights in this area after Caesar's time in Gaul plummet
Jesus quote
Overall the archaeological record shows a market decline in the quality and quantity of material culture
And suggest that the region did not recover for at least a generation
And quote
So
Swelling
The
Spirit of the population to resist that's an age-old counter surge
Urgency strategy
Don't just go out to the rank-and-file though the people you go after their leadership as we said and seas are determined that this one
It seems highly respected figure it's hard to draw any other conclusion considering what his
Demise
Created in terms of resentment procedure determines that this garlic leader name Echo or Echo
Is in part responsible or was somehow involved in this resistance Maybe
Secretly
Supplying them with something where have you and Caesar decides he must die
So he has him flogged
To death
Which two deaths of the bolt of a bullwhip run electrical cord
Hitting you until you die
Caesar had his head cut off which is an extra
Twist of the knife given the
Religious reverence the garlic people in the Celtic people
Half of the head
And then
Caesar gets
Swept-back
Into the Maelstrom of Roman Palace
Because all of a sudden
You know if it's a Roman ship of state has been foundering for a long time and taking on water
All of a sudden this year the ship just
Go straight down in the bow to the stern of it sticks straight up in the air and all of a
It's teetering
And Caesar course because this entire life of his revolves around Roman politics and how he doing it
Gets drawn back into the situation there's Riot there's killings the Senate houses burn down
And the garlic healthy people
Hear of this
And they think
Maybe Caesars not coming back
At the same time
They are upset about this nobleman being whipped to death
They're upset about the pacification there's a whole bunch of tribes Adrian goldsworthy reminds me
That are some of the most powerful tribes in Gaul
Some of the most sophisticated to the ones who have the most contact with Rome which is why most of them are Roman friends which is why up until this
Time
They haven't really participated
In the defense of Gaul cuz they run the Roman side
But they're starting to realize
Did the Roman side
Is going to control all of them at some point you may be a more favorite tribe under Roman domination
But you're still under Roman domination
Goldsworthy did a great job explaining the situation he writes quote
Caesars understanding and manipulation of tribal politics was generally good
But over the winter of 53-52 BC his policy failed badly
There were a number of reasons for this failure
But it is root with a growing sense of the extent to which his presence had changed things
This was especially true of the Celtic Golic peoples of Central and Southern Golf
One of the three broad groups into which Caesar's commentaries divided
Quote on quote the whole of God
These tribes had not yet fought against Caesar to any meaningful degree
Although it was in their lands
Did the campaigns against the helvetii and ariovistus have been way
Dominating the trade routes with the Roman world
Tribes like to eat sequani
And arverni
We're wealthier and more politically sophisticated than the people to the north
They had Aiden Caesar and he in turn had favored the tribes and leaders most sympathetic to him
And he had thought
Or at least so he claimed on their behalf against the helvetii in REO Vista
Now over the course of the next year
Virtually all of them would turn against him
This was not simply a question of rebellion by those who would not receive the proconsuls favor
I had watched his Rivals were elevated above them the rebels eventually included many Chief into a done rather well Wonder
The Roman domination
That was at the heart of this new mood
The realization that Caesar and his Legions were in Gaul to stay
And would not be returning to the confines of the transalpine province after a few Swift campaign
Rome now expected or power to be acknowledged on a permanent basis throughout golf
DIY have become a conqueror
Without ever facing serious resistance from the Celtic peoples
And quote
Well of course they hadn't faced serious resistance got these are have been practicing the divide-and-conquer strategy on them he
I've been using these powerful tribes that were friendly to Rome
Against the powerful tribes that weren't
And now the ones that are friendly to wrong realize that it doesn't matter
You know which side you would lie with
You're going to be living under Roman control either way
And it makes them
Receptive
To the idea that come forward once it's clear that the political problems in Rome
Make trap Caesar there
While his Legions are wintering in golf
What if
All golf
Could you not
Against Caesar especially while he was away
Think of how crazy the movie idea would be
Screenwriter developed
Treatment based on the idea
Did all the North American tribes
Unite together
In a common
Effort militarily speaking
To defeat
The European colony
Nest on the Eastern Seaboard in
I don't know 16 V
They would have
Of course had to have conducted their own Native American version of the Lewis and Clark expedition so those Eastern tribes
Trekking across North American find out that there's a West Coast
Native living there at some point
Have this big Face-Off between all the native tribes in North America against the relative newcomer Europeans
It's too crazy to imagine though is that you wouldn't be able to suspend disbelief the premise is too far-fetched
That's what happens in golf
That's why it's such a rare moment
The divide-and-conquer strategy
All of a sudden fails
All at once
And these
Tribal people realize their predicament
At the same time and are able to drop their age-old animosities
And decide together that it's now or never
We're going to maintain our freedom even our freedom to fight each other
For tribal soupremacy down the road
We're going to have to unite now
And defeat this threat before it's too late and it might already be too late
This opportunity of Caesar getting roped back in the politics of Rome
Opens up the door
Caesar says that
And there's a lot of other grievances that are coming to a head all at the same time including Caesars execution of that Noble Monaca or a
Graco that he had whipped
To death
And he says that these garlic tribes come together it's makes him sound like the leadership
Ships Come Together in the deep dark woods
Archaeologist Barry cunliffe suggest
It would not be
Strange to think of
The Druids
Being the ones who sort of officiated an event like this both for sacred reasons but also because they're so.
The diplomats
The Penn National
Sanctifier of these tribes I mean they would have been the respected
People to
As the referees and judges and arbitrators in a case like this there are stories by the way of Druids
Stopping marching to the middle of a battlefield between
The lines of two armies about to clash and stopping the conflict of these are people with huge amounts of moral Authority and cuddle
Suggestion
For such a sacred important situation is this
Piracy in the Grove
Caesar portrays it
Would not be
You beyond the pale
In fact considering what these tribes are pledging to do
You would want to have a signed contract in blood you want to have The Druids officiating you want to have a lot of witnesses and if you know
Notary public
Because the challenge here
Is it now everyone is aware with the stakes are
Then everyone knows now
But if they rebelled they're going to get the treatment that these tribes that have had everybody wiped out
Efface
Everyone understands
The two
Fight back now is to wager everything
Once again the Genesis of the story Ground Zero is Caesar himself
I would love to know if it's even true how he found out about it
But he gives an account of this
Tribal meeting in the deep dark woods
My Thomas Holmes translation of Caesar which dates back to the early 1900s and is a
Has some fabulous different words in it then
Most of the more modern ones I mean instead of saying call is pacified over and over
He uses the word tranquilized which gives it a
Feel
He picks up the story where seizures back and Rome dealing with all the political trouble
And the Celtic people in Gaul hear about that political trouble which then prompts this meeting in the woods here
Tell my home translation of Si
Caesar have it
Picking up right after
Procedure talked about all those problems in Rome keeping in there
Quote
The news of these events speedily made its way to transalpine Gaul
The Gauls Amplified and embellished the story is the faxing to war it
Spreading rumors that Caesar was detained by the disturbances in the capitol
And that while these beers conflicts were raging he could not rejoin his army
The opportunity stimulated the Gauls
Stimulated
Stimulated the Gauls they were already smarting
Another good one
They were already smarting under their subjugation to the Roman people and they now began unreservedly in boldly
Deform projects for war
Deleting men of Gaul mutually arranged meetings in secluded Woodland spots
They spoke
Bitterly of the death of a CO
That was a man who's with
Telling their Heroes that the same fate might befall them
In deploring the fortune that oppress the whole country
They made promises
And offered rewards of every kind to induce volunteers to strike the first blow
And risked their lives to restore the liberty of God
And quote
There he goes again Caesar making these people in their cause sound like the one you'd want to get behind right garlic
Liberty
It would oppose that wretched have to be Darth Vader doing pose that what's Caesar doing
As we said earlier
You're the experts disagree
Caesar's writing on multiple planes here
There's lots of speculation some of its fun I'll just give you one of the ideas out there that might
You know again speculation
Might help explain know what he's been doing this whole time we've been making the Celtic
Side out to be somewhat admirable
There's an idea out there that you sort of
Setting the stage
What happens
A generation or two down the road
After they've conquered all the
I mean you have to kind of sell the idea back in Rome a little bit don't you that listen don't worry we'll incorporate
Gall
Into raw but there is simulator bull
You know for sure there are intractable and they're not housebroken in their culture is substandard by Roman
Measure but we can fix that can a couple Generations will turn them into good romance and the way you can tell it's because look at
Same values
I mean
Yeah if you put these
Phrases and Concepts
In the mouths of a Roman character in a Roman stage play
The Roman audiences going to cheer
In other words
And he sort of making the case according to one of these theories are red
Were the Gauls are trainable but the Germans are never
Going to be house
Therefore we can incorporate the Gauls and down the road
You know after we break him to the yolk of Empire
Can teach him up right look at how well those Gauls and short-haired golub been doing now for
For 50 60 70 years
You know we can we can make these people into good romance and you can tell just look at how their spouting phrases that would make
Them good Romans today
It's an interesting idea and it would explain
My Caesar makes
Their cause sympathetic as he's crushing it
It does sound a little bit like he misjudged how serious it was
When he got word of it back in Rome the situation was starting to mellow out a little bit back there he says
And then he hears about these problems but as one historian pointed out
You know he conquered this area what four five six years ago initially
And he's had problems with it every year headaches
Brightsparks the way we describe them all these aren't headaches and he doesn't know yet this is more like a stroke
And all the spark that we talked about
Earlier
Finally fan into a general forest fire
As all of Gaul will go up basically
In Rebellion including the great friendly tribes of Rome
And it starts with one of those moves
That a tribe does
As a way of sort of Dipping their dagger in the assassination victim and saying okay I'm in
Involves tribe it's always been possible for the Romans it is the one that
Steps forward allegedly at this Woodland conspiracy is says will strike the first blow
They go after this hill for town
By the Celtic tribe that
Full of Roman Traders and businessmen
And after they take the town they Massacre all the Roman
So essentially saying you the rest
The tribes okay we agreed to do this we're all in there's no going back for us who's next
And the rhythm of the story is interesting
Because
You will have the tribes
Join the Rebellion
You know usually in Big Shot
But even
You all along the way some big tribal at the last moment change sides and and so slowly but surely the Rebellion games
Steam
The massacre that kicks it off that we mentioned earlier the news about spreads like wildfire in the central
Gauley tribes go up
In Flames except for the ones most loyal to Rome we are the
Are the big tribe that matter
They're the ones
Who initially went to Rome and said we need help cuz this Germans been brought it I mean this is the Ally of Ally
Wise for the Romans
In this region
So they're the ones that they worry about that's where
The Romans get all their supply help
The grain that's where they store their hostages when they take them from other garlic tribit sort of there
Administrative Center in Gaul these are our good allies and we can trust
Well
On paper it may look that way but remember what we said earlier
Is garlic tribes are not United
An even Caesar says there's
With and rifle
Faction
So think Democrats and Republicans Tories and Labour and whatever you want to say write your
Your two sides of the coin and maybe just because a tribe is taking a particular course of action it maybe like 51
Percent of the tribe wants to do it in 49% dozen
So sometimes it doesn't take a whole lot of change
To sort of make the scales tipped the other way
And when the first big tribe
Galls
Commit to this massacre
Romans it's on in the number of these tribes start to get up and eat cuz it's Caesar says that's kind of the garlic character
Anyway writes the excitement happening and want to get on board
And by the time he realizes how bad things are
He's in trouble
Because he's a long way from the action and he's got enemies between him
In Roman
Northern
Italy now
Angle when the armies are so the first
Chapter of this story has Caesar
Doing amazing things let's be honest he's an amazing guy and in the speed of movement that he employs for example
Who is crazy
And his audacity he takes the Great
Calculator
Alexander would have jumped off the cliff in darkness and whatever happens happens
I'm a God right
Caesar took a calculated risk
His audacity in his speed
Is continually on display in so he manages
To get back to his armies
His armies managed to break out of a
I've been ambushed when more of these tribes start going the other way
And while this is going on
A figure emerges on the scene that we only really know of because of Caesar
But he's
Fascinate
And anyway
Could be an example
Of that beam see idea we talked about earlier you know how the Celts might have been caught in the beam CD because they
Transition from
A more ferocious Barbarian way of life to use it
100 years ago
And a more Romans in existence in that they
Play Datsik maybe lost in my court jester silly Theory
The ferociousness of the more Barbarian tribes and not yet gain advantages that comes
Would being able to handle Logistics and supply and and finance an organization and all these Roman thing
This person that will crop up at the last available MoMA
Will try to turn
The Celtic armies into something that can fight
The Romans
Because just because you can make a lot of garlic
Tribe decide to join a rebellion
And maybe grab hold of more Warriors than they've ever been able to put together in one place in golf
You still can't feed them right
We learn that earlier in Caesar's Conquest
These armies can't just get bigger they have to get better
And they have to be able to support
Bigger better arm
So how do you do that
Will enter
This amazing character
You can pronounce his way several different ways and you can have fights over I've always gone
With me I can get erect
But they're saying generates is also popular
He is the Great
Unifier
I've been gawlik p
People in the last possible moment
You know when resistance is possible
He appears on the scene
As a king
By the time Caesar
He came from a tribe
Pretty out of this hole Celtic gallic war thing at this point
That's a try by the way that's one of those developed ones that has more of a senate the Mormon oligarchic sort of
Roman system
And there can get her exes
I'd had apparently been
Executed for trying to become king of these people taking them back to an old way of government by the way
Early in Rome's history when their Republic was new and they had ditched the monarchy
The crime of trying to reinstall the monarchy was was equally harshly punished but in this case remember yours
Supposed to be burned alive
She try to do that so I guess
Without really saying so maybe they're can get erect
His dad was burned alive for trying to become a king
When is whole Rebellion take place as The Story Goes
I can get her ex and his family members including an uncle
Will
Minnesota fight over what to do
There can get erect will
Apparently be wanting to become a king
And maybe take on the Roman of the uncle opposes him so very can get arrested
Thrown out of his City
Caesar says he goes out and using garlic Liberty and freedom as his as his
Rallying cry rally always
Caesar says Desperado
And dead-enders but you could really see them as Maybe
Patriotic young Golic Warriors
Finally ready to rise up I mean
Depends on the way you're viewing
I guess they must have been pretty
Decently intimidating because we'll come back to his home City with all these Desperados and
Dead-enders around him essentially
Launch 8
Who if you will against his home City become the king of those people
And then begin to Rally tribes together
These tribes begin to seed
Authority to him as a war leader which is very unusual in the Celtic world
Historian in class
Closest Michael and Sage
Points out that vert can get erect didn't start this Rebellion against the Romans but he quickly came in and sort of
Took it over
He sent embassies everywhere and formed alliances Sage says many names all these big important rhyme
That we can get our experience to communicate Within
Say listen the time is now remember it's only been a few years since Caesar conquered this place oh
These are all recently
Subdued people
And they sort of understand that this is how it's going to be unless they move at some point
And there can get over to sending embassies to all these tribe saying that point is now
Michael and Sage writes the beer can get erect
It was chosen
The war leader of these tribes
Have began implementing policies
That were very ungodly
In nature
But that a Roman like Caesar could appreciate
Because they're more like Roman Standard
Sage rights quote
There can't get erection was chosen as commander
And quickly set about organizing the rebel Army
In accordance with standard garlic procedure he demanded and received hostages from each of his allies
Is pledges of good faith
And issued orders to them to provide a specific number of soldiers for the Allied Army
Enforces orders with ferocious punishment
That included execution and torture
This was an extraordinary developer
During his campaigns in gaul caesar had faced individual tribes
4 coalitions on the battlefield
Perhaps the largest was that of the belgae in 57 BC
However in these conflicts there is no hint of any Central organization among Allied try
After seizures initial refusal to engage the belgic army
The tribe simply returned home to face these are individually
Beer can get erect represent an entirely New Direction and garlic resistance to the Roman
For the first time their opponent was a centrally organized and directed Army
That represented an alliance of a number of different tribes
Which creation was in part due to the extraordinary personality of your can get erect
And also to the effects of the Roman Conquest
The Gauls repeated failures against Caesar had led to the realization that their traditional military meth
Is were no longer adequate
The Roman army in Gaul was too large to be dealt with without a collective effort
Importantly he provided a model of a highly organized and centralized Army that there can get Alex karev
Rick Lee saw was the only possibility of defeating the Roman
And quote
Sage goes on to point out
That
There can get her riches try was
Friends with the Romans and that
It was not unusual for garlic nobleman a friendly tribes to serve
With the Romans on campaign is Allied Cavalry and it's possible although he points out we have no evidence one way or the other
The Vera can get erection done this once upon a time too and maybe was quite familiar
With the way the Romans fought
Adrian goldsworthy even suggest
Possibility that Caesar and Burger King Garrick's knew each other personally
From years before this.
Completely new Laird
Things wouldn't it
Nonetheless
There are some things that I can get erect now as the
Supreme Commander the warlord of all these tribes in Gaul with the exception of a few who are slowly but surely
Come on board
He can control some things now
With greater Authority than any garlic ruler since Caesar first arrived on the scene
But there's other things you can't change
He can start ordering tribes around now so instead of having to beg
A tribe you normally your enemies with better temporarily fighting with
For supplies and
An nth roots and whatnot you can order it
So you can begin to
Mimic in a may be less efficient way
Things like Roman Supply
And
Working together and telling One Tribe to go over here in another tried to go over there as part of some larger strategy
Which is a huge Improvement
But you're not changing the reality on the Tactical level on the ground
You're not turning your Golic warriors with their swords and their Shields into Roman legionnaire
You're not inventing Centurian
You're not getting Battlefield discipline and drill and organization at that level
So you still can't
Face the legions in the
And you can get Eric seems to know this
Because he's going to be famous for telling
The rest of the Gauls that they have to do something
It runs against their nature in terms of this heroic ether
He tells them they are essentially going to have
A guerrilla war and they're going to have to adopt a scorched-earth strategy and they're going to have to destroy
Their stuff
And where they live
And every
In order to defeat
Cadiz Roman
Now we talk
Earlier about some of the greatest tragedies in human history being
When some of the things on the list that you're willing to die for become the cost of other things on the list that you're willing to die for
And this is the greatest test
In the history of any Golic leader
That we seen
Well maybe anywhere in the house
Swear
You are going to have members of rival tribes making decisions that tell you you have to
To burn down your homes in your city and leave
Tribes listen
And agreed to adopt the strategy of their can get erect this is a sign one of the desperate times
And two of his unrivaled
Authority
For the first time in history
Gall or
Most of it anyways
Acting under the control of sort of one mind
One-wheel
The Nazis would have
Create a situation where
The Gauls are now at least on
Par with Caesar in the ability
To have a United strategy and this has never before been the case
But just because you have more power than any garlic Warlord
You can find in the previous history book doesn't mean you're the one who always get to the side
What to do
We all know right War the game of seizing the initiative and sometimes responding to
The other person
Doing that sometimes you get
Play offense but sometimes the other guy
Right
In this case
There will be games that both Caesar and vercingetorix will play with these cities
Is it sort of ironic
And one of the things they're saying getting rich is known for his telling that
Celtic people have to burn all these cities will where do all the major encounters happen
Outside these gall
Much of this encounter involve sieges any attempt to relieve sieges for various political reasons
Caesar will show up on the scene and go Bam Bam and take a couple of towns realfast remaining the Celtic
People that they cannot
Stand up to Roman Siege
Is very well
Then they will defeat
Some garlic Cavalry in a skirmish sort of reminding the Gauls that they can't face up to Roman
Field tactics and field armies very well either so what do you do then
This is where the straw
She comes into play
Scorched-earth type deal
Also very can get erect according according to Caesar we should emphasize that
Give this big speech where you tell them you're going to have to destroy everything at
It's great it's worth quoting in full and notice at the End by the way
Three throws up one of those
And you'll lose everything
Kinds of pictures to these people right I realize I'm asking you to do a lot and it's a bunch of things you'd be willing to die for maybe
But it's there to preserve other things you be willing to die for remember the steaks
This from the essay Hanford
Addition in this is Cesar
You're putting this into bear can get erect his mouth room
Procedure will mention these other cities that he's now taking already on the way to dealing with this
Rebellion
And they sound like names out of The Lord of the Rings
Don't they
Quote
After this series of reverses
Ed Villano doing them
Incentive them and novio doing them
There can get Eric some and his followers to a council of War
And told them that their plan of campaign must be completely changed
This is
Beer can get a ride
Stalking according to Caesar
Quote
We must strive by every means he said to prevent the Romans from obtaining forage and supplies
This will be easy since we are strong and Cavalry in the season is in our favor
There is no grass to cut so the enemy will be forced to send out party to get hay from the barn
And our Cavalry can go out every day and see that not a single one of the returns alive
What is more when our lives are at stake we must be prepared to sacrifice our private possession
How long the enemy's line of March we must burn all of the villages and Farms within the radius that the foragers can come
We ourselves have plenty of supplies because we can rely upon the resources of the people in whose territory the campaign
Pain is conducted
But the Romans will either succumb to starvation or have to expose themselves to Serious risk
By going far from their camp in search of food
We can either kill them or strip them of their baggage which will be equally effective since without it
They cannot keep the field
We should also burn all the town
Except those that are rendered impregnable by natural and artificial defenses
Otherwise they may serve as refuges for shirkers among our own numbers and give the enemy the chance of looting the stores are
Provisions and other property that they contain
You may think these measures heart
And cruel
But you must admit it would be a still harsher fate to have your wives and children carried off into slavery
Have you killed yourself
Which is what will inevitably befall you if you are Concord
And quote
That is by the way sort of Caesar pointing out I guess you could read it to this yes that's
True that is what I'll do to
Caesar says that most of these tribes
That were working with
They're can get erect complied and he says one of them burned 20 of their Town simultaneously
The smoke in the skies
The One Tribe
Back to the other garlic tries not to make them burn their City down it was the special City they said I mean they were wrapped up
Dumping it was one of the finest doing all the gall please don't make them do that since like please don't make me choose between
One thing on my list that I be willing to die for and some other thing on the list
So you never can get erections softer than he seems in other parts of the story or maybe he didn't have as much Authority
As you suggested
By Caesar but none the less
These people are able to get there
City spared the
This hill
Top town of theirs
Supposedly one of the arguments they made is listen it's impregnable don't worry and
Then Caesar took it
This is the city of
Avarakkai
And traditionally is considered to
Be one of the
The three main encounter
That formed the military side
This Golic Rebellion
But it's worth pointing out that
In the same way that the word pacification
Covers of town of low-level violin
That doesn't quite
You reach the standards of making it into the history
Talking about this garlic rebellion and then boiling it down
2-3 sieges in the violence associated with that
Is a
Minimizer
Also of all the things that we're going on SO2
Under the radar under the historical right
Archaeologist Barry cunliffe points out an interesting sort of ironic facts
You have your king Garrick's you're saying they're going to have to burn the cities of the Romans have
No high value targets and yet here they are
Going after high value targets anyway all of the major Encounters in this Rebellion
Will happen around cities
So what happened there
They should be burned down should they but each one sort of has an excuse for why it's still there
I'm very kind of points out
What sort of ironic is that
It's only in the parts of Gaul
Did it had significant contact with the Roman to become more Roman like
Did you have these sorts of cities
Are the Romans and Julius Caesar to Target to begin with
Why did you go to the less civilized amusing hair
Civilized tribal north of where the nerves VII in the belgae are and everything they don't even have Sundays
You're much more decentralised you going to have to chase the
Tribal people out of their little hearts and Into the Woods
But here you can almost treat these
Garlic States remember that's the way some translators
Translate it now not tribes but States
You can almost treat them the way you treat these states in the Eastern Greece
When the Romans go there they just go to the major population centers and take them
Warzone
Some of these Gauley tribes are becoming more like the Romans or the Romans can fight them more like
Their traditional enemy
They can go after basically the capitals of the states
Administrative Center
The tribal heart if you will
Carlos writes quote
In dealing with the more urbanized tribes of central Gall Caesars tactic was simply to pick off the pop
Population centers one by one
Such an approach would have been impossible
Among the tribes of America and belgica
With this degree of centralization had not yet developed
And quote
It's funny that knock on the Gauls is always been that they weren't able to work
Work together
+ 2
Take things to the next level developmentally speaking
Inform 3
Example more organized state
A John Heywood I think was the author that I read that.
Went the complete hundred 80 degrees on that theory and said that
What would have kept the Kell safer longer wish to be even more decentralized
And his theory if I remember correctly
Was that
And when the Romans faced
Other urbanized centers in other place is Egypt Greece any place like that
They would destroy those States in one or two battles because
The other centralized State brought all of its assets to one place in the Romans destroyed them there
But look how long
Again if I'm remembering
He said it took to defeat the Celts
And the various other people's of the Spanish and Portuguese area right of a
Lusitania and all there because those tribes were so divided and so decentralized you always had to keep
Going after another tribe it's an interesting Theory
But in this case the fact that there were even cities at all
Cesar to Target
Is a facet of
The Gauls becoming more and more like the Romans and by the way this is something seizure now portrays in his
Writings and it becomes a feature
Of what's going on in the longer the Romans are out here now fighting the Gaul Caesar says
The more the Gauls are imitating the wrong
Romans becoming even more dangerous or there's this now
Undercurrent of need
Not only are the Gauls perhaps
Worthy of becoming Romans if we
We just train them up a little bit but
The more contact they have with us the more like
Romans are becoming here in battle so we better hurry
Annovera come Caesar and the Romans will be unable because of
The fact that this
L4 disc
City on a giant Mesa is a good way to put it that's what these Hill forts that
Become
Hill towns that eventually Morphine to Hill City
In these more
Sophisticated garlic states are like right it's it's not a man made fish
Feature
It's something
What was the lines in The Lord of the Rings that has stood here
Since the dawn of time and then man put some fortifications on top of it
Avaricum has Marshall
Is all around
It's all the Romans can't do their normal
Practice of building a giant wall around the whole place be
Because we're going to build in the middle
Swamp
There's only one entrance to the place
So it looks like
If This Were A Golic besieging army they would be stymied but of course this is the Romans
Andover course
Almost 30 days
They build a
Counter Mountain maybe you could say it's hard to understand some of the sources talk about a ramp
Others talk about a mound
But essentially Caesar build something on one
Part of
One side of the fortification to equalize the height
And it takes the legionaries almost a month and it's like
400 ft long
About 80 ft High
And you just marvel at what the Romans are capable of doing and listen a lot of other ancient armies could too
When you have that many people
Involved in laboring for 10 hours a day 7 days a week you can get a lot done
Now the Romans while they're building this or under pressure because
There can get erect his strategy of scorched Earth is working
He's brought his army and he's keeping it 15 or 16 miles away from the Romans were building their Siege engines and
Creating this giant Mound or ramp
And they're picking off Roman stragglers as the Romans look for food and they're looking for food
Already this
Strategy is starting to bite as one of the historians on red footage
The scorched-earth strategy starting to bite
But the siege is working too and at one point Caesar says
The man in the Garrison decide they're going to try to slip out
Get severe can get erect his army live to fight another day
The problem is is that that town contains not just those Warriors
But their families too
And Caesar says their attempt to sneak out
You know without alerting the Romans was foiled when the women started screaming and crying
You know when they realized the men were leaving begging and beseeching them not to leave them to the Fate
A falling into the hands of the Romans
Soda
Screwed up their playing they alerted the enemy because they were so loud and
Warriors had to give up their ideas
You're slipping away
But it's an emotional reminder
Reason of the steaks you can get
Caught up in the
Did this happen
Bananas next year this
Forget that
No we have women and children screaming
Because they think their men are leaving
Because it's better to save at least the Warriors than to have everyone die right
Because that's what's going to happen when less than a month after The Siege started
After
A rainstorm begins and the Gauls
So don't lose their focus on one part of the wall for a second
The Romans take over the wall
Close off the city and you know they kind of point out of you ever been to like one of the old towns and some of these European cities
Stockholm
Examples
When you walk
Truitt you realize
How really narrow in Pence
Small all these old-fashioned
Medieval and ancient streets were in all the little side streets and how clogged they could be
If you like crowds of people trying to oh I don't know
Get away from pursuers at the same time
Caesar points out that every place gets
Choke
People trying to get away
Atlanta population
40000 Caesar says about 8
Survived
Man woman child
Old infirm Devery
And
Goldsworthy another's pulling out that
This might not
Have been part of Caesars plan
He will be very strategic as he sort of puts down this Rebellion who gets clemency and who gets out
Absolutely decimated
The important tribe that used to be friendly to the Roman Caesar tends to be kind of
Light-handed
That's right
Oh we're sorry you left you should come back to the room
But the people that have been
Nasty the whole time at the Romans have nothing too politically game with often are used at the
Examples
In this case though
Cesar is giving up a lot of money
When these people are being killed in the streets of America
And even these soldiers who stood
To get a cut right in my to gotten their own slave but they're busy killing the booty
In these narrow streets of this
Garlic town
In some of the historians goldsworthy's one of them I think
Made the suggestion that this might have been an army that
I was just so angry
For all sorts of reasons including the killing of that
The Roman businessmen in traders to kick-off this Rebellion
But they couldn't be controlled or were mad enough to think to hell with the money to hell with the slave to hell with the booty I'm killing these
And it's another
Tragedy
It goes into
Stomping Down Golf
Like resistance
Normally a disaster like a verican would have heard a war leaders reputation but Caesar
Suggest and it's not hard to believe that it actually helped American getaways
Because he had been one of the people that said
We should be burning this town down
And then when his
Advice wasn't chosen because he's not an absolute ruler in any sense of the word he should have chosen almost like an outside
Contractor if you want to look at it this way by these trying if they don't like his leadership they can Bolt
Singly or in groups
In this case he looks like he was in the right all along
So after their akum
Tagalog Army continues to harass and Shadow Caesars Romans
Remember Caesars Romans are the only Roman army here
So there's no other pincer that can come around and do stuff if Caesar want the
Do something
In two places at the same time he has to split the Army he's got
Which means if the Gauls could keep Caesar's Army set of occupied somewhere
They're free to move around and do things in every other area of the theater for example there can get a rich is continually sending it
His emissaries to all these other tribes that haven't joined the Rebellion yet
There's one in particular
It would transform the situation
If you can get a restricted flip them
It's this
Tried so close to the Roman the easy way
The ones who got us involved in the story to begin with that
So-called ruined efficacious is a
Member of the EU
Do we try bright
The reason that they're so important
Is because that's who's providing Caesars food right now
And regarding his food supply lines also with their Warrior
What would happen
If they flipped
Fast forward to what's going on
Caesar
And this garlic army or soda
Shadowing each other
I can get Eric takes his army
I've been to some hills around this
But call it a very large Hill or a mini Mountain
And it's very top hits
2400 +
What's feet above the ground level
And this is another
Garlick Hill City or Hilltown or fortified
Whatever
Definition you want to use
And once again there's an excuse why it escaped burning this is very can get a rix's
Tribal cap
This is his home
Basically
So maybe it's a do as I say not as I do situation you all burn down your town but I'm not
Mine
Or maybe
This place was so easily.
Offended and so hard to take
Did beer can get a restarting
The place he could pin Caesar down
While he destroyed his Supply
And by getting
This friendly tribe
It was providing seizures food to flip
Caesars in terrible
Trouble camped out in front of this city called your govea
And you're govea
Is normally considered II begin count
One of the bean
As part of these garlic Wars
It's also one
Were you have to take Caesar
But even less face value because this is not the high-water mark of Caesar's generalship
And so for a piece of propaganda like these War commentaries
If you're ever going to shade the truth and try to make yourself look better and spend things this is going to be the play
Place where you do
Normally seizure would look at a place like this and think let's starve it out
But given the supply situation he be more likely with his army to starve
Before the people in your govea did
What's more seizures a little light on troops at this point
Just one of the moves that some have criticized over the
Ciara's butt
We told you earlier Caesar needs to things done simultaneously
In different places he doesn't have another Army in Romy can call on hands to split his own
And before this battle The Siege at your go via he does
And sends out about 40% of his forces
To go handle something involving a couple of other tribes that need a good thrashing
But it means that you're going to be there not
There
So when you start considering
Oh maybe enclosing an entire mini Mountain
With walls and fences and
Things to cut it off from the outside world
And you look at your six Legions you may be thinking to yourself I really don't have
Enough people for that
Second strategy
Right now
A describing sieges is always differ
So I'll just use these these rough ideas but basically when Caesar gets there and sees what he's up against
He starts nibbling
Terrain features nearby that will help
He'll nearby
Where he takes that little Hill that the Gauls haven't really defended it'll be harder for the gulf to get water so becomes his little game
Of nibbling on terrain features
Building camps doing all this other stuff and then while he's doing it he gets word
That the easy we have flipped
And at the baggage in his rear is compromised
And the food may not be arriving so he takes a large
Portion of the legions he's working with a jerk over yet
And goes down to deal with the problem with the supply lines and while he's gone
Supposedly they're can get erection the Warriors come out of the the heights down the hill and attack this Roman
Camp
Roman Camp built for like six Legions but now only defended by two
Would you can see would make it difficult
Caesar gets word of this when he's on his way back
I'm dealing with the supply line problems with like four Legions
And when he gets to the Campisi's that they have managed to beat off the assault with her
Artillery and all kinds of things but they're if they're in a bad way
Procedure devices this strategy
He's going to faint an attack
On one side
Get all the Celtic warriors to go to that side of the top of the Mesa of the Hill Ford
And then Caesar will attack on the on the far side that's now abandon with some more troops
So he set this up
Eventually gets to the point where the Gauls take the bait
They all come to the one side of the Mesa to deal with seizures faint
Caesar sends his Legions around the
Supposedly now undefended other side
They start doing real well they get through the
The main wall they're starting to cut up some of the camp in the women in the children that I mean maybe this is going to win
And then the Celtic warriors that have been drawn off to the other side of the Mesa by The Faint
Come back
And math
There can get a raise himself might have led the cavalry charge
That sent the Romans careening
Back down the hill
Caesar will get together a bunch of Legion that are not involved at the bottom somewhere near the bottom of the hill so that his own
Don't troops can then hide behind them and
His new troops that are uninvolved in the combat can ward off the pursuing
Celts
Cesar Chavez will admit to
Like 700 dead legionaries
Is between 40 and 50 of these people are century
There's been an interesting debate you can read
On whether or not this is the Roman habit of ink
Encouraging
Well conspicuous bravery would be one way of putting it if you wanted to spend it one way reckless endangerment
For personal gain might be another
But Caesar kind of blames that a little bit at the same time
Xi jinping encouraging this kind of audacity
Forever
You know where these legionary in their centurions are rewarded for
Throwing themselves into the breach and being extra tough and extra aggressive
In this case Caesar says that one point these Gauls will be throwing these dead Romans
Over the walls head-first and Caesar will name at least one of these dead Romans being
Thrown over
The wall by the
Celtic warriors who killed him by name
So you know the guy
So you're seeing thrown over the walls dead I mean it
It sounds like it was a nasty situation to some historians have suggested the casualties could be a great deal higher than Caesar was admitting to
The military setback that
Cesar suppers at your govea
Combined with the losing
Of the Eataly tribe to the Rebellion
Begins to flip yet more try
Tampa science how quickly this is happening
Everything were talking about he was happening in 52 BCE
Normally when you think of this. You think of an era of almost glacial
Operation
Army is advancing or sieges rndc just
Years
All of this is happening in 50
B2
Which shows you how
Quickly events are unfolding
And by the way Caesar was not given conventional dates
So you could say that all this stuff happened in this one year but you don't know when sometimes
He'll give you an inkling of a Caesar
Rise you can say what this happen
In the winter or this happened
In the spring or what have you
But most
Armies I can think of from the ancient. Well up
Mean to almost the modern era
Would have a hard time dealing with the speed of something going this fast
I keep trying to imagine
Are European armies from the Middle Ages trying to crush this Revolt this
This quickly
Part of it of course is wrong
But the other part is
And what sort of Bad Karma clock
Did the Gauls have that this happened that they get one of the great generals
In all human history
And a guy at the top of his resume when he's bragging about his god-given qualities is going to put
Speed and decisiveness of movement
As if the Celts already didn't have enough
You're going against them in this deal between the technology and the
Your lack of centralization all the things we've been talking about they got to get this guy at this time to
In fact it's worse than just that
Caesar's political antenna as you might imagine from a guy holding his feels
In the Rome of the late Republic are exquisite
And his ability to read the proper way to respond
Did these tribes in order to play them
As much as he can
In a like it musical instrument is crazy
If some tribe get clemency others get wiped out and you got to know how to play this game to keep most of them in your camper at least
The 49% of the try maybe that wishes they were in your camp but are currently in the minority you think of
About guys coming from
Tiara Caesar was born in Marius and sulla
They might have been equally successful in destroying these garlic armies
But I imagine Caesars going to look like a great being
Softer
When it comes to the genocide of the Holocaust were talking about if it's Marius or sell Edition out the Punisher
Baby everything
When we talk about these
Historical genocides
Crimes against humanity and all these modern terms
Maybe they all need to be graded on
Kirby
None of us at this point in the story
This is about the low water mark
Caesars entire career and most of the generals would be toasted
Remember now
This is an army seizures that was already feeling the bite
Of the scorched-earth policy
He was not doing all that great to begin with
The military setback at your goby is not huge in the military
Since the Romans can suck up those casual
But in a political sentence
Separatist Orion
Roman invincibility more tribes join the Rebellion
But bigger than that
Is the flipping of these we try
For all sorts of reasons but just look at one of them
The E do we control Rome's administrative base in Gaul their storage locker if you will
Where they put all their stuff while they're traipsing around Gall at the city called noviodunum
And when we do we flip
They take noviodunum
With them
Then they Sackett
Almost as if they were conquering their own City
So that they can keep it out of the Romans
What did it have in it
Here's
Historian
Nick Fields talking about noviodunum
And its importance
The Caesar
Quote
Here were to be found all his gaulish hostages
His brain reserved his War chest remounts for his cavalry
And the best part of the army bag
Epor rhetoric
Indira Damaris
Too young Chieftains of the E do we turned on the Roman Garrison at noviodunum and slaughtered them
Together with the Traders gathered there
Release the hostages divided the money and carried as much grain as they could transport and dump the Romaine
Thunder in the river
Hand torch the town
And quote
Fields actually said APA done which is the
Word for garlic town
The point is think about
This from the Golic perspective
This is an Apache raid the successful
And it takes an enemy who's already reeling from jerr govea
And stab them in the back I mean this is a huge moment from a native perspective here
And the potential ramifications that become possible now Caesars defeat in the distance
Well that's a chance that the Native American tribes never had even if they had
Gone after the
You're very early settlements in Virginia and places like that could they have wiped them out forever
Could they have
How do Europeans draw a line and say we're not Crossing this ocean anymore
Because you can't live on the other side the natives will kill you
Same thing with Africa it was just too late in technology since the odds were too one-sided
Look at this here
This is an opportunity for the tribal people to win
Caesars in trouble
Think about what you say
Having the hostages.
For a change in power and authority
Here Caesar had been keeping the
Your sons and daughters of the powerful and important people of all these garlic tribes he hoped to keep under his thumb
And now all of a sudden they fall into the hands of the rebels
The corset
Rebels can do any number of things
Right they could be magnanimous
Give them back to these other goalie tribes and say Seagal stick together and by the way you owe me a favor
Also if they wanted to play hardball say something like
Caesar doesn't have your children anymore we do
So you're joining the Rebellion right
Turn the last now that
The EDI we are on board we are told that beer can get erect at now with big tribal meet
And in this meeting
The EDI we are apart of it they actually make it play for the leadership at their SmackDown
And almost all the other tribes in Gaul
Plutarch says that they were like
300 tribes are states that Caesar subdued I can't believe it's anywhere near that many
Some of these may have been really really small but let's just say it's a hundred 150 Caesar says he's got like two
That still support him
Severe can get erect has this big meeting with all the other tribes the Giant
Pangola Council
And you do Wonder
Is say the Native Americans
Or some of these other people who are victims of colonial Conquest ever were able to get all of their people together in one place
Who are the representatives of them and also to try to unite and speak with one voice
This is an amazing thing when you think about it
All of Gaul
With the exception of
Apple tribes are United against Caesar in Caesars in trouble
This is a historic moment
He's basically cut off
From getting new troops in Italy at this point
And remember the Romans don't use their own Cavalry anymore what do they use while local Allied troops
Who's that lied to the Romans now
So Caesars got an issue where did he get his Cavalry from well this is where we find out
You know those who enjoy
Little teeny tactical things on the battlefield that end up having perhaps
Huge effects on History love this part of the story
But this is where we find out
The seizures been making friends on the other side of the Rhine
What does German people that you can't House break
You can't
You can incorporate you can't assimilate but if you need the Cavalry bad enough you can maybe
Work out a deal
Caesar starts bringing
This
Friendly German Cavalry from some of these tribes Maybe
That were the enemies of the people Caesar was beating up on in Germany
And we hear their appearance and it's
Bedeviled take more games
Most wargaming rules
Twin talking about this German Cavalry in this. Gave it
Special powers
Especially special powers
/ Celtic troops
You know why
Because the Celtic troops were scared of them
These are the same kinds of forces remember that Caesar had noticed
And driven off
Many more times their number in garlic Cavalry earlier
So what's going on you know when we talk about
Intimidation
For all these qualities that are
Hard to quantify
What do you get when you take 400 German Cavalry which is not enough to make a big difference anywhere in these
Size battles
And they dominate
What kind of Superman are we talking about here
And people have wondered ever since now we can go into the unquantifiable things but they are of course
Unquantifiable
You could talk about the fact that these Germans had a way
Of utilizing infantry with the Cavalry so they have
One light infantrymen to go with one Calvary men and they were supposed to operate together
And the light infantrymen supposedly
Hold on to the manes of these horses they rode into battle and it would almost act like a night with his squire
And at this
Combined Arms Mobile infantry formation with
Unique and
Deadly
They're also
Some theories that these Germans weren't just your average German Warrior but this is more like
You know a bunch of German adventurers
And it's like the Magnificent Seven or something but it's the Magnificent 400 or later maybe 600 in there all these
You know badass German Seether
Germans who make other German scare
So you might be that kind of a deal that explains why they're so dominating on the battlefield
Once again it's kind of confusing isn't it why Caesar who's writing this propaganda piece
Please Roman audience blah blah blah
Why is he
Saying such nice things about the Germans and giving them so much credit
Hard to figure out especially for an onyx
Like yours truly
All I can say is that in a number of different encounters
These Germans are going to make all the difference in the world in fact
The reason that we're going to have the climactic battle
This great
Spare pump
Right that's what the German general say this this climactic intense decide the whole War
In a situation in this one city
Is maybe because this German Cavalry turn the tide at a battle
Revere can get erection assembled all the dang Cavalry could get his hands on price
Tell the other tribes he didn't want any infantry he already had 80,000
Many historians will point out 80 thousand is a lot to
Speed already
And at this point in the story and again
You got to love the way these things work
Dirty ghetto resume want that infantry more as a way to hold some of these tribes hostage we got your Warrior
Be good right don't flip back to the Romans
But at this late stage in the garlic
In a military development it's their Cavalry that's everything
And Caesar will end up re hooking up with those forces that he had sent away to do other things before your govea
They will start to March
In a direction that looks like maybe they're leaving
And this is where maybe verican Garrix
Confused
Lot of the different histories
Portray this
As an attempt
Attack the Romans as the Romans March away
There can get erections put 15000 Cavalry were told together
All of whom have pledged to not go home to their wives and children or anything unless they have ridden twice through the ROM
How many column
Attack these Romans on the March
And the German Cavalry working in conjunction with the legionaries once again Saves the Day
And
Sends
There can get her ex and his
Counseling reeling back towards the first place to Rally which is this Garlic City once again remarkably under
Untouched by flames
Call Delicia
Caesar says by the way that he
Pursues Tagalog Army so close
He kills 3000 members
Their rear guard
They try to cover the armies were
Retreat into
Hilltown Tavern
You can say Alicia
Able to
This is a tip
Typical Golic Hilltown in the Sun
Protected by natural features to make it pretty tough
Have to take
Michael and Sage says it is
Plateau
Near Dijon
Right now about
Hi
About one point
2 miles long 600
50 yards wide
On three sides the train is like impossible
All Rivers
Craggy Rocky Terrain
Put on one side on the west
It's a nice gentle
Smoke a couple of miles long
There's another history point
Think of a peninsula
And it's a little like
Severe can get a rich retreats to this city
Then turns around and blocks the entrance to the peninsula with his army
Digs a ditch build a 6ft tall wall made of loose stones
And above him sits this hill Ford City with
The tribe whose home it is
Is there a lot of civilians
He should have weights for Caesar
Caesar shows up
Take a look at this
Slice
And decides
Well this is something you have
How to put under seat
Obvious
But how do you
Put a
Place this large Under Siege this is a huge Endeavor if you really want to go there but
As we've said all along the Romans are
I want a great secret web
Is the fact that there
Legionaries are about half construction worker half Soldier
Astoria Michael M stage rights
Caesar looking at Elysian deciding what to do quote
Since a direct assault was precluded the only alternative was to capture the town by sea
Which required the construction of massive fortification
One of the Striking aspects of the garlic War
Is the engineering skill the Romans displayed in constructing Seas fortifications
This expertise was part of a wider development in the use of fortification by the Romans
They were used extensively not only in Siege is but also on the battlefield
The Romans constructed a continuous Siege wall over 10 miles in length to close off Elysium
And quote
Well that just for starters
But basically once Vera can get a Rick Steves what's going on here and the scope of what Caesars about to do
He launches a Cavalry attack down that one gentle slope of the peninsula of this Plateau is occupying
And gets into a dust-up with both Caesars legionaries
An Caesar's German Cavalry and once again the German Cavalry make the difference
And they pursue along with the Romans
These garlic Calvary members who Caesar says get caught up kind of in their own defenses and they start
Clogging up around the narrow parts and they get just massacred in crowds of people
He just crushed
The death
So Caesar says that this
Tells beer can get a Rex
But he's not going to be able to break this Siege himself
And also as this
Fortification starts to become complete what are you going to do with Calvary anyway
The teacher said he sends his Cavalry away send all the Cavalry back to their home try because this is an army that is a
Consolidation of a bunch of Allied tribes now right almost everyone
So you send the Cavalry back to their own tribe and Cesar said he tells them to bring a relief Army
Put together rising of the tribes and come here and save us we've got Caesar pin down right here
As I can get away to sending this Cavalry all back to their home tribes
Caesar again putting the words in his mouth has him saying
You know don't leave me here don't forget who fought for your Liberty
And then something to the effect of oh yeah and I have 80000 of your countrymen with me you would want to see them die either would you
Would you bring us two numbers here
Here for a second
Because who the hell knows
What else you going to say
About these ancient battles
Sometimes you can reliably come close to something on the Roman sikasil say something like we had this many Legions
You know they're probably understrength you know they probably got
Young part-time combatants were their servants and Camp helpers and all that the other so you don't know but you can estimate better
On the garlic numbers you only have seizure to go from and he's
Outrageous
But as every historian says what are you
Fill the blank with
I like the way
Adrian goldsworthy figures 86 what's about to happen here
You don't know the numbers of Celts involved but you can reliably say it involved more than it ever been assembled a task
Single place
Because this relief Army
The begins to come together is going to be
According to Caesar
Absolutely normal
Now Caesar may have expected the relief Army may not have
Accounts different interpretations differ on that front
But if he didn't expect it at some point he hears it it's coming
So he begins doing
What is battle for the sea just kind of known for
He begins building
Another wall
And another fortify
Vacation facing in the opposite direction from the one he's already mostly completed
So another words
Is besieging
The
Celtic Army in this hill Town while preparing to be besieged himself
From without
The Roman army is going to operate
Within two separate seeds while they're going to Camp there they're going to live there
And they're going to starve out this Celtic Army on the hill
While frustrating the efforts of the relief Army that showing up to rescue it
So for visual purposes if you imagine a
Hill or a plateau completely
Surrounded by fortifications or ring of fortifications and then an even larger ring surrounding that
I read somewhere it's like
14 miles
Circumference
Something
And Visually you'll get the right
A picture
Imagine
Watchtower that had artillery in them I thought I read somewhere 1500 was an estimate somebody to
For the number
Aldo's
I watched hours
This is a place that's going to be able to
House
60 to 80000 Roman soldiers and Friends
Show me think of the sides were talking about here it has multiple camps each campus it is a fort in and of itself
It has 23 things that are like of the Roman word means little castles or little fortresses
It's crazy
The best short description I ever read because they're hard to find because even Caesar
Who's normally very spare with words
Can't help but go On and On by seizure standards
But all these pits
Still with sharpened stakes and I mean all these things that are awaiting
The garlic Warriors
John worry run
The great book online
Warfare
And he described
Defenses
Which is a weird word right there
Defenses in one sense but they're also the
Fortifications besieging the other Army in another
Is how he described the fortifications
Analicia
Quote
The Roman entrenchments LinkedIn encircling chain of camps in Fort
The interdict was 20 ft wide
With sheer size
IE not tapering at the bottom
And the main circunvalacion was constructed 400 Paces behind this ditch
Here there were two trenches
Each 15 feet wide and 8 feet deep
The river was diverted to carry water into the inner trench wherever possible
Behind the trenches was a 12-foot earthwork in Palisade
With antler drawings projecting from
Breastworks in battlements were overlooked by turrets at intervals of 80 ft
Cesar also sold the ground Beyond his fortification
With prongs and pitfalls of various patterns
Illustratively are humorously termed lilies
And
Stingers
A parallel line of fortifications was then provided
As an outer circunvalacion against the inevitable really for
The inner perimeter was 10.1 miles long
The outer 12.9 MI
And quote
So if you wanted these garlic Warriors looking to
Strike a blow maybe a fatal blow in the defense
Or reconquest of garlic Celtic Liberty
And you show up here to do battle with the Romans before you even get
The actual place where the Romans are going to their standing behind their Earth and Timber
Fortifications there
Behind all these defenses you get to get through the gauntlet
And The Gauntlet is worried points out starts with
A huge 20 ft wide
It'll say howdy but the other trenches R8
Diva figure at least eight feet deep
Trench
That'll break up the momentum of a giant
Human wave charge won't
But that's about six football fields he's
Says from the rest of the defense
Is when you run into them you're running into things like a double
Line of trenches 15 ft yd
Deep one of them filled with water
You're also running into an
This is something you can see it and there's almost enjoyment
Citic constructed all these little trap
They sound like the kind of traps when I was growing up
The North Vietnamese the Vietcong always set
You know these these things were they
Put a big sharpener
Unit 3 feet in the ground and then covered up with leaves and wait for someone to walk by but the Romans have like thousands of though
In front of the arrow
Trenches and then they have a
A bunch of other things that are similar
But disguise differently and they mix them all together
So that as you're approaching know you're coming towards
Artillery
The Roman start shooting at you and you're just starting to get your blood up you're not worried about where you're stepping and everything and then all of a sudden you run
Into all these traps
And then right after the Trap there's another more trenches and then you run into the prom
Worry called them
I was reading how they did this the Roman soldiers would go cut all these branches
And then they would cut the ends off the branches and sharp and all the ends and then they would arrange them in a way so that it was like a giant
And hedge
Knife Thorns I guess you could say a giant almost it's almost like ancient barbed wire
And they would either put it at the bottom of one of these trenches or right as you were clamoring out of one of
Clamoring out of this 8-foot Trench
And you know what your human wave attack has been somewhat disrupted and what's at the top of the trench this
Giant Hedge
Braum's
And all this of course is before the garlic Warriors even make it to the Roman Stockade in Earthen
Set of wall
Historian Nick field says
That 6000 trees
Warlock
To create the
They might have been tough for the
Celtic people to overrun without all that stuff in front of the
And let's not forget that Behind These fortification of these very same legionaries that have beaten these garlic Warriors most of the time
Time in the open field without even having the help
Guard towers everywhere as we
Artillery
Daniel Caesar doesn't he
Aldi
Remember
There is a reportedly
ATS
Thousand let's lower that to something more believe
Golic Warriors essentially in his rear
That Army he's besieging
If the Army from outside the ring attacks Caesar the relief Army
And he turns to face it
He's got very can gutter extend that Army in his rear
So they can coordinate their attacks
Well Caesars got a heck of a challenge in front of him
If you are a tribal Army trying to resist
Colonization from one of those you know
Technologically more sophisticated more centralized
Power Rangers Dino throughout history
This is one of the better chances as I said you're going to find it's a gamble this is wagering as we've been saying
Interrupt this talk
Everything
If you are these Celtic peoples and yet at the same time
This is a pretty good wager it might be a bit of a long shot
But this is a chance that you would think for example Native American tribes were
Forgiving everything
To Simply have a chance to maybe win
He said that maybe 80000 Romans are here we don't know how many Celtic
People are coming in the relief Force
But the people inside the besieged
Hilltown don't know that it really forces coming at all
Cesar points out that there can get erection his army up on the Hill Florida cutoff
Germany news and information
They have this due date in their heads when they think there were leaving Army's going to show up but the Army doesn't
Food starts running low and they start having these hardcore debates inside
The hill for the monks the various garlick leaders in
People of note
There's like 46 tribe
I think Caesar right in
Involved in this
This is a pan tribal group of people
They're starting to think that there's no relieving Army coming maybe so what are we going to do
One group wants to surrender
Another wants to charge out there and sort of like a giant Bonsai charge of deathrite make a good
Song at least
And then there's a third group that wants
The holdout cuz they think a relieving Army is coming and seizure put one of these
Fantastic
Speeches into the mouths of one of these is one of the longest I think I read it's the longest speech
Seizure put in anybody's mouth in the whole commentary
And he means it in a bad way he wants you to look at this people and think aren't they disgusting
Because this garlic guy is saying
We need to be prepared to be cattle
We need to just eat
The old people
And useless now this here is a way of holding out
And the speech is worth
Recount
I'm Caesar
Again he's trying to make this guy look
Degraded
By this but there's another way to look at it
Which is
Again this is a committee
What does it mean when you sacrifice were willing to sacrifice everything it means you're willing to go cannibal if that's what it takes
This is from
My Thomas Holmes translation of Caesar
Procedure says that this song
Nobleman's garlic no woman makes the speech when she said should not be passed over he doesn't think another word somebody should say
Disc golf at these horrible things
And so here Caesar
With this goal and he has him saying quote
I do not intend he said
To notice the view of those who dignify the most abject slavery
Buy the title of surrender
Bright hold that they are not to be counted as Citizens
Or admitted to a counselor
I am only concerned with those who are in favor of a sortie
Meaning of Rage
Bonsai tree
Praise You are all agreed
In their council is to be recognized the memory of our ancient Valor
To be unable to bear privation for a short span
That I called weekend
Not manly resolution
It is easier to find a man who will upfront death than men who will patiently endure suffering
And yet I would give my sanction to this View
So highly do I respect the authority of its advocates
If I saw no evil involved in it say the sacrifice of our own live
Informing our plans we must have regard to the whole of Gaul
For we have called upon the whole of Gaul to help us
If 80000 men fall on one field what
Think you will be the feelings of our friends and Kinsmen when they are constrained to fight almost on the very corpses of
The slain
To save you
They have counted their personal danger is nothing
Do not then robbed them of your Aid
Do not
By your folly or righteousness or lack of resolution ruin the whole of Gaul
And subjected to Perpetual slavery
Can it be that
Because they have not arrived
Punctually to the day
You doubt their good faith and resolution
What then
Do you suppose that the Romans are toiling day after day on those outer lines simply to amuse themselves
Is the messengers of your countrymen cannot reassure you because all in versus bard
Except Roman testimony that they're coming is near
Dread of that event
Keeps them busy upon their works Night and Day
And quote
Other words he's saying
If you doubt the relieving Army is on the way tell me why the Romans are going to all this trouble
He then says that they ought to be
Prepared to eat
Each other.
What it takes to regain garlick Liberty
Instead
What one translation here called the Council of War decides to send out the useless mouth
Central long
You know how long the food will last a little more sort of counting on the Romans maybe to take in these women and children and old
Old people and infirm
You know the people who used to live in that town before it became a Battlefield
So they can get erect
Send those people out to the Roman lined and Caesar probably sends them back
It's been explained that maybe Caesar didn't have the food to feed these people those people were besieging Caesar make us slaves and then feed us
Just like slavery just wanted to eat
And Caesar didn't have a ton of food himself obviously but also he thought sending them back might eat up
There can get her riches food supply even faster
The problem is is neither side relented in those people began to die
In between the lines
Eating grass is the way one
Ancient source describe
Deadly Women and Children
The families of some of these Warriors dying in front of you day after day of slow starvation and exposure to the other
Goes on and you have no idea if your friends are coming
And then one day
They do
And they are visible in the distance
Cincinbear can get erection his troops can see them
Operating on an open playing in the distance
In a way that is all but like a Sky Rider saying
Rejoice
In all of Gaul is here you are rescued
And on multiple Hills in the distance the Roman C
What Adrian goldsworthy said is
Almost certainly the largest
All the army ever assembled however many people that might be
Ashley Goldsboro
Only one out of
The largest armies
It's a Jew says
Likely the large
Starmie
Hopelessly outdated but impossibly logical friend
From 100 years ago Hans delbruck who thinks all these numbers are
Crazy
Admits that it might have been possible that this was a larger-than-normal army because even though he's the guy who's always going to say you know how
How are you going to feed them
He says it's possible that these people were never meant to eat
Very long
But this really farmies like a cruise missile
To be launched right at Caesar the Romans and eased
Defenses
And so you don't have to worry about them breaking up like the belgae did you know if they're starving over a month or so
So figure
You have an army here if we talkin about the Native Americans
Having two thousand Warriors and it's a pretty good amount
Were the Zulus having 20000 and it's a large Zulu Army
This Army
Might be
When you combine the numbers inside the Hill Ford with the relief Army
130000 the ancient sources haven't well over 300,000
250000 infantry in the relief Force alone
Those are crazy
But once again
If this is a hundred and twenty
Thousand
Tribal Warriors in one place
Well you know I like that Napoleon
Quality quantity has a quality all its own
That'll make up for a lot of Roman advantages wangjing
Just having so many people
And
You can understand
David brooks idea that maybe these p
People are just meant to be used right away when you see how quickly everything unfolds
Alief Army shows up
Camps out of these Hills about a mile from the Romans
Goes down to this plane which is the only part of the
Mary which is really like a battlefield the one open space that
That Western area the gentle slope of the plateau so all the real fighting especially the wide-open Cavalry stuff happen
There
And they go out and they demonstrate their and that's where they're can get erection all his beleaguered besieged
Starving people who've already seen those people from the town starve him between the two armies you not throw up a cheer season
And let's remember why we say Caesar says
Why we're so reliant on
Vim
He's the only eyewitness from this battle
Do we have any account from
And anyone else's account of this battle off and uses him as a source
So he's both invaluable
And at the same time obviously biased as hell although
Anyone you got
Open this bottle who wrote about his
How to be pretty
In this case there when Caesar plays up the fear a lot of times when seizures playing up the fear of the dangerousness of a situation
You can perhaps suggest that you doing it to magnify his own greatness but this looks legitimately dangerous here
This looks like a moment in history as we said
Where the tribal people kind of have a shot
120000 hundred thirty thousand Warriors gives you a shot
So when they're can get a rich and his people see this relief Army Caesar says they come running down from their positions
Towards that trench that separates them from the Romans and they begin filling it in
In other words preparing to do
Their job in this whole attack which is to attack the Roman from the other side when the big relief Army smashes Against the Wind
At the front
Teacher says he has all those people take up the positions
And then he sends his Cavalry down into this plane to engage the garlic Cavalry that's down there
Now
Who knows about these numbers estimates are Caesar had about six thousand Cavalry wide mixing things
Still have some garlic Calvary
Spanish
Community and we know we had some Germans
The Gauls
Well and Gauls and
They fight and Skirmish all afternoon apparently and the gulls are getting the better of it when Caesar says
All of a sudden and not for the last time these German Cavalry once again turn the tide
Kill a bunch of the Gauls chasing off win the day
And he says that there can get Alex and his people who are
You're standing by having field in the trench waiting to attack dejectedly head back uphill toward the town
After they see that
This relief Army isn't going to be giving them any relief today
So then you get
The next day
And something happens that seemed to validate some of those earlier points we were making
But in the later books of seizures as Ender Rigsby point.
He begins to
Point out that these people are growing and they're changing and they're their prolonged contact and fighting with the Romans
Just making them more dangerous
Maybe said earlier this is the reason sometimes
Used to explain why the Germans will
Sack Rome in 410 AD right prolonged contact with the Romans made them Roman enough so that they could do that
Will seizures kind of alleging is this
No commentary his goes on
Did the Celts are going that way
And they need to be dealt with now before they get any better because they spend
The next day during the day
Calmly and coolly and logically and diligently the Romans might notice cuz they was the
Ounces so lazy
I'm liking to avoid hard labor but they're cutting down trees
And they're making ladders
Play commotion putting together bundles of
Styx
Play when they run toward these Roman trenches they can all throw their bundle into the trench and eventually the bundles Philip the French and you can run
Over them
In the words
They're not rushing at the defense is like a bunch of
War mad
Battle crazed
Barbarians that you can just
You pick off cuz they're so
Stupid
They are calmly and logically
Replanting
For an organized assault
Scarier
And then when the Sun goes down
Things are only lit by Torchlight maybe Moonlight Uno's
The largest army
Probably ever assembled in Gaul
One that is
Infinitely larger than any North American tribal army ever assembled in exponentially large
Throws it
Self against the Roman
Defenses
At night
Caesar writes that after midnight
This Celtic Army
Right just creeps up
Quietly
And then launches its attack all at once making a lot of noise
All at once I mean imagine you're up in the Golic Hill Ford besieged
Wondering what's coming next cuz you're out of touch with these
Forces on the other side of the road
And then the
Stillness of the night is broken by this
Loud roar
And you answered
Delino something's going
Going on down there so they can get her
Blows the trumpet Caesar size
Begins to get his forces together to support the attack on his side meanwhile
This
Celtic force is throwing themselves again
The Roman defenses in the dark
And falling in
And traps
And Spurs and all these things that Caesar so lovingly and devilishly
Described
They're bad enough in daytime but at night
Well you can see how it'd be
A bigger problem he says he's
Galls are falling into the pits in there they're being skewered by these
Steaks
We sharpen pieces of wood
Size of a man's thigh some of them others are
Much smaller meant to go through your foot and disable you meanwhile Roman artillery shooting from the walls
Did you you're trying to get through the trenches you got to deal with these prongs
But Caesar makes it out to be a near run thing and they are beating off this attack
Well like something out of one of those old westerns
Where the Native Americans are
Are attacking the small little fort
And there seems to be an endless supply of them
And you seem to almost be at your last leg Caesar specifically names he's good at this remember
Two of his
One of my translations cause of generals which is not a good
Beijing bohemian senior commanders on the scene
One of them is Mark
Antony Marcus Antonius and of course he'll be
Ancient tabloid fodder later when he hooks up with Cleopatra
But he's one of the people that will run to the aid
Of the beleaguered sectors whenever it's needed
Caesar says that even with all the
Traps and everything they got set up these Gauls are throwing down there
Bundles of sticks and they got their ladders in the end it's a near run thing at several different places and then the dawn breaks
Cindy Golic wave subside
And this melting of the Gauls back to their Camp is portrayed as some historians as the failure of the assault
Call but other historians
Suggested that first battle they fought the
The calvary one that the Germans once again turn the tide at
I made it impossible for these Celtic infantryman to operate in this big field during daylight so
Whatever the reasoning
The relief Army loses its second battle against
Caesar and the first assault that it makes against the fortifications
Of the Romans
Tails as well
And Caesar says
That part of the problem here is that Vera can get a Rick's and the troops
Besieged in the hill Fort never got their act together in time to help
Dead by the time the relief Force melts back toward the camp at morning there can't get a rich hasn't launched his attack yet
So that's a traditional garlic
Coordination problem it's not surprising
Although there can get her to done a pretty good job avoiding those kind of traditional garlic mistake so maybe it's
Surprising in that
Caesar says that the garlic leadership which remember is made up of a ton of different tribes under
Several major WarChiefs from different tribes as a Native American fan I can't help but think of some of
The the Chiefs that I've always thought most highly of working together obviously
Different working together in some giant effort like this
But they have a conference to try to figure out what's going wrong
Cuz we've lost two battles in 2 or 3 days
They were upset about the reconnaissance pointing out maybe the
Yeah we should have lost so many people
Both of those traps
That we didn't know about
And then they interview the locals who are
After all
Garlic themselves
About the local lay of the land is there some weak spot in the Roman forum
Vacations turns out there is
A hill that Cesar couldn't incorporate into his defenses
The Celts find out about it
Caesar says 60,000 of them under one of these WarChiefs you got to love it when 60000 is a detached
Attachment of you
Your forces on whatever the real number might be
60 thousand of them sneak
Over to this week spot
And then when they launched
Their attack there will be corresponding at
Tax launched elsewhere to help
Interesting
To wondering whether the people of the time understood what this is
This is the actual
In a spin of the roulette wheel
Right now I mean this is the encounter that will decide and Caesar will say this he says during the fighting to his men
This is the encounter and they will come down Caesar says to a moment
It will decide the course of the war that he's been fighting for the better part of a decade
And given what we know now
Decide the state of garlic Liberty for the next five centuries
Caesar says that it is about noon
Did the surprise attack
Is launched against
The weak part of the Roman fortification
And they say it's the week part because instead of being able to be situated on top of a hill with a good view all around this one party
Are the camp had to be situated below the crest
But that means you don't know and can't see what's on the
The opposite side of the crest of reverse slope
And in this case if you believe Cesar 60,000 handpicked tribal warriors were
And around noon they come Galloping over that slope
Heading towards a part of the camp
Remember Caesars troops are numerous but they're strung out over the entire length of
This 14 mile circumference or whatever it is
There's about two Legions maybe eight ten thousand people right here close by
With 60,000 sounds crazy so we'll say 30,000 screaming Warriors coming down that hill at them
As we mentioned
This isn't all Caesar have to deal with because of course
They launched a strike
From the main area
This great big plane that all the battles been fought on the main Roman defenses well those Kelly
Come out to play again to
Historians are divided on whether or not this is a real Attack
Intended to produce results of its own
Or whether it's purely a diversion
But you can't just send a bunch of legionaries from there now to go bolster the week area cuz they're busy
And
Because this is the climactic battle you would expect that their can get erect up in the Hill Ford
With his lean
Hungry besiege troops
Would also launch an attack to help to
So they come down off the hill and they do the same and then they begin to concentrate
Right near that same
Weak spot
That the 60,000 pick the guys from outside are concentrating on this is now the Crux of the battle
So seizure goes to a place where he can see really well at his job as he sees it and he emphasizes this instead
Being the heroine commander on the ground wielding a sword and leading his men like King Arthur or Alexander
Caesar's job is to hold on to the precious reserves and Dole them out
To wherever they're needed most and he does this but what's going to happen when he runs out of Reserve
What's going to happen when you have a threatened part of the line
And no more legionary to send there to bolster it cuz you'll do this several times in the Bible
Finally the situation of the weak spot in the fortification is so bad it's in danger of being overrun
Which everyone seems to think would mean the battle
The Caesar has to go in South
The last thing he does before he runs to that spot of the line though
And it turns out to be crucial wouldn't you know
It'll take a few Legions that he scraped together with some Cavalry including our German friends
Put them under the command of someone says ride outside the fortifications and whip around
And try to get behind the enemy that were fighting in that area and see what you can do basically and then seizure
Grab some more Legions
I guess that's the bottom of the barrel
And heads beer in South
Arrived to the threatened part of the line and you instantly have this
Feeling that he's just walked into the Alamo
When it's totally Under Siege annies Davy Crockett
He didn't have to be at a place where he might die and I'm in a few moments but now he's walked into it
Of his own free will
Caesar says that everyone notices the Red Cloak
Which is why you wear the Red Cloak but he
He has the same effect that is super celebrity would have on both sides he says
Celtic and Roman alike
Remember this is not Modern Warfare where because of the projectile weapons everybody stays as far apart from each other as they can
Is Ancient Warfare
We're Wars decided as the Romans always say by hand stroke
So you got to be close and everyone is
And Caesar says that they see him arriving and both sides fight harder because of it
What's more
A lot of this battle is visible from
The battle lines of people who are not involved in the fighting so they're cheering to Caesars of the 1st Cavalry battle in the plane
Both sides are cheering it's like a
Murderous bloody game of quidditch or something
In this case Caesar says because of the way that he'll is slope which made it vulnerable to begin with most of the Gauls
And whatnot in a lot of Romans two can watch this entire fighting are cheering and making noise
And the way seizure narrates this is It's a near run
He says his troops
Throw their Spears
Fight with swords
People are cheering and yelling
I'm Different sides of the battlefield
Shouts are going up he says from the hillsides
And then he describes
This moment
Again you know you can't help but think the Eagles are coming it's one of those
You had to be it's like the people who were at the sinking of the USS Indianapolis
The delivered the nuclear bomb and they're in the water and the sharks are eating them and they've been in there for 5 days and then the
Rescue plane appears and there's that moment where you just
Never happy in your whole life to see anything
Caesar looks
And he sees
Among other things
Is German Allied
Or mercenary Cavalry maybe the Magnificent 400
Of the German people
Behind
The Celtic Force that's about to overrun that part of the fortify
Vacations
And slaughtering suzhou
It's one paragraph from Caesar arriving
At the beleaguered section of the fortifications
To the complete turn of the tide
From the wonderful Hammond translation Caesar talks about arriving
On the scene in his Red Cloak
And no word on whether he
He was doing the little Darth Vader breast
And he did
Caesar says quote
Cesar hurry to join in the fighting
The conspicuous color of the cloak he habitually Warren battle proclaimed his arrival
Because the downward slope swear in Clearview from the heights above the enemy spotted the Cavalry Squad
Quadrant and cohorted order to follow him
Enjoined Baba
A shout went up from both sides
And was answered by another from the rampart and Defense work
Are men through their Spears
Then fought with sword
Suddenly the Cavalry was glimpsed in the rear
More cohorts were advancing
The enemy turn tail
And the cavalry charge them as they fled
Massive Slaughter follow
And quote
Once again Caesar spare with words but you get the
The picture
It was a nightmare
We don't know how many people died in the fighting the
That climactic moment in Celtic history
We don't know how many died afterwards I've seen estimates although Caesars not helping
At the Romans lost more than 10,000 which is a lot by Roman Standard
The counts lost way more
They lost enough
So that when these
Survivors of this
Charge in this attack on this one part of the fortification made it back to their own Camp about a mile away they knew it was over
And they began to break up
And go home
And it's indicative of how hard fought this battle was
Caesar and the Romans didn't just totally destroy them then
Caesars
The pursuit had to be
Postpone for a little bit while they recovered
And of course
Not forget
There can get a ride
Breaks his besiege
Starmie
Is Allied
Army of many tribes
Watch this whole thing
I now know they're due
Along with
Well
Everything
Else
You know I'm always fascinated by the
Dreams of The Human Experience
And the emotional and intellectual
Edge
Involved
And some of the Affairs I mean
Think about if you could take
A photo
Of what it looks like
American Gutter exist
Point of view
And when this battle is over as he looks
Out
At the Panorama laid out
Beforehand
Roman defenses the skyline in the disaster in the foreground
Print Outlook
What are your emotions
As this
All sinks in
What this mean
And once again Caesar makes him out to
To be kind of a noble savage if you will
To bring up one of those literary
Conventions again
And has
I can get erect
Basically saying you know do with me what you will I only did what I did for Golic Liberty
Is it kill me
Or hand me over to the Romans alive whatever you
So Caesar says
He sets up this chair
Are you sitting outside this camp and they're bringing prisoners to a notable figures from inside The Siege is they empty this
Splice out
And then
Caesar makes no big deal about their kengarex surrendering
Which may be closer to the truth some historians say about Adrian goldsworthy says Caesar would never allow himself to be upstaged
In his own commentaries
Maybe he's suggesting you should believe the Cassius Dio or Plutarch accounts which are more romanticized
What sound much more in keeping with
Where can you get a wreck this status as a noble native tribal chief
Kind of
I mean you put an African king
A great Native American Chief or
A Pacific Islander King for example meaning this works in a lot of places
In that same position in the movie
And it works just as well
But the sources saying if you eat
Allow for a little amalgamation of them
There can get a rich will go and put on
Is best armor
Adorn himself with his best weapons
Get on his horse ride down to Caesar who sitting in the chair
Do a circle around him
Get off the horse throw his armor down sit at Caesars feet in.
What's a word
To be led away
The people who were
We'll throw him into the Roman dungeon
To wait his fate which will have to
Intercom after
Caesar's schedule lightens up
Because he's got a whole civil war to fight
And he's going to tear the guts out of the Republic and when he finally gets a chance to settle down and party
You know he'll have 20 days of Thanksgiving proclaimed in his absence when Rome hears about this whole thing
But for him to actually participate and enjoy himself it's going to be a while and and when that happens though
There's lots of different entertainment very Exotics
Stopping the highlight of this the party favor of party favors
Will be there can get away
6 years later paraded in Chains as part of this procession
Can be taken down to one of these
Dungeons
And he will be ritually Strang
So think about the human misery
It emanates
Scrum
The results of this
I like the way
Historian Nick field soda breaks down
The importance of these days I mean remember earlier in this conflict
I mentioned that Cesar Soto breaks it down to like a frantic moment
Practically that the whole battle hinges
Think about what that moment going the other way
Which might lead to that battle going the other way
Would mean over the Long Haul
Story Nick Fields rights
About the
Affect
Of the Alesia Siege quote
Battles are singular moments in history
Productive of strange events
Much may depend upon a small detail
The effects of a detail maybe victory
Any effects of Victory maybe long last
Delizia was such
Bring a very real sense
It's symbolized the extinction of gaulish Liberty
Rebellions would come and go
But never again would have gaulish warlord independent of Rome
Hold sway over the tribes of Gaul
To gain Liberty
Beer can get erect
A strong and popular leader had hazarded everything at Elysium
And loss
And quote
Which begs a more fundamental and difficult
When you look at the cost of losing
Was the fight in the goal worth
The Gauls went from being political slaves to being
Actual
Slaves
Historian Paul gavigan in his
The Cutting Edge
A statement that I thought was so deep it itches it makes you question the entire Paradigm when you think about
Admiring the resistance too hard
Did NeverEnding never-say-die resistance
Which is the thing that makes the
The movie so great as the Native Americans
In the face of Calamity continue to resist against overwhelming odds
Write me out come is known the Doom is upon them and they still fight back
Downtown right
Quote
Unfortunately the Gauls protracted the war meaning the garlic War
49 bloody years
It has been estimated at least 1 million of the natives perished in the process
From another perspective
This was their War of Independence
But they lost
And quote
When you're one of those garlic Warriors looking over the edge of the Hill for to the devastation after
In the Battle of Alesia
You realize now what the downside of
Give me liberty
Give me death choice
Going to look like
And the gavigan quote makes you wonder about
And what's the proper amount of
Resistance to offer in the
Face of
A conqueror who will take everything from you
For resisting
The hard question because one might be willing to sacrifice one's own life
But balk at the idea of sacrifice
Pricing for children
And I mean it
One of those choices as we said
Will your pitting things that you literally would give
You are life
Or against other things that you would give you
The hardest choices
In the human
Experience I think
The resistance of
People that have been called Celtic are lumped in with Celtic
We continue for many generations and Celtic civilization would 2
This conquest of the Gauls in the submission
That this supposedly enforces doesn't mean they're going to stop speaking a Celtic language in these areas for example in their will
In a people talking about this scourge of these Celtic languages that are still tenaciously holding on centuries
After this
Whether or not you classify
The people in the British Isles and Ireland
Celtic I'm using air quotes
But my hands here to
Seems to be a judgment call best left
Stop to experts
But the DNA evidence as we said earlier
May indicate
There are things
That go well
Into the roots of all the p
People in that region
The predate the Celtic.
Quite a bit
If there are similarities in them it might be a combination of
Cross cultural contamination
With some things that are very old indeed
None-the-less maybe those personality
Traits often associated with
People's aren't altogether gone or made up
Much of this by the way as you know
Abilene was rediscovered
Over the last couple hundred years as part of the Awakenings of nation states and their roots
Who they are and who they were
I certainly know that the Irish consider themselves
You know as Celtic as Kelly gets
And I happen to know that at least a few of them haven't given up
The fight
Maybe the Romans think they won
But maybe they just got outlasted I remember when I was a
Kids 7
2 years old
V8
I had an Irish girl who was taking care of us some stereotypically named Maureen
19 years old 20 years old that You Came Upon me one day
With my soldiers all set up having a bad
Romans again
Celts
She said who's going to win
Image of the Romans are going to win did the Romans always beat the couch
She said oh really
What language are they speaking
Concurrently
Pieces bearing mine back at home
We're still speaking the IRA
Corcyra
Gaelic
Is it count
Language
Note
But it ain't dead yet
Go to dancarlin.com