Been a long time since we've done a blitz Edition
And as a friend pointed out to me when I explain that this latest program of ours is going to be a 6 hour long show
That we were going to classify as a blitz Edition
Is it don't take this the wrong way but I'm not sure you know the meaning of the word
And I laughed because he's right
These started off this idea of a blitz show was going to be something to help us get more shows out
And some nice quick ones right another words in addition to these great epics it took forever and
You have killed us and have killed you listen to them
We have things in between and they grew too cuz I'm obviously
I have a problem I'm addicted to contact
Is one of you sad
A firm believer in the past is prologue
And there's no good natural place to start any story right everything's connected it's arbitrary where you decide to begin thing
That's how I
And I show I wanted to do about Cleopatra that stretched into a six-part series on Rome
Because where do you start the Cleopatra story
The reason I chose the topic
The originally chose for today's program has cuz I thought it artificially constrained me it's 2 weeks long
Possibly
Do a really long show
On a two week long event well
6 hours later here we are
And it's also a blitz Edition which now doesn't have anything to do with the length of the show it's turned out through Evolution to be a different kind of show that
Focuses
A different things
Instead of being about
People
Or events
Or error has specifically
Usually they focus on an idea or question
And then
In a weave history around the question somehow
Usually the recipe
As a slightly less drama
Historical epics but slightly more twist does we call those
Musings in
Weird Twilight Zone things that
Should have come with the territory with these programs
For what it's worth this could have been a two-parter
But we didn't want to do that to you so you get one long one instead
And maybe in an experimental
Never here to see what works
And in addition to some feedback we got from you folks we tried
Arbitrarily after-the-fact mind you it wasn't
Put together this way
The separate
The show into sections books book 1 book 2
In places where maybe there are natural breaks
Stopping points or what have you
We'll see based on your feedback whether you like that approach or not
Finally this is a very unusual story to tell
Because unlike most historical Tales which are about things that happened
It's about something that didn't happen
Almost happen
And still could happen
Undertale being told
In the middle of the story
In in
Unfolding series of events that are still ongoing
So why you can feel like you somehow have a bit of a spoiler knowing how this will turn out
In a specific case we're talking about here in this tale today
Because it's an ongoing story
There's no guarantee that you actually do know the end
In that sense
This story is not just
Prologue for the event I originally wanted to talk about which was the Cuban Missile Crisis
It's prologue
For our own future potentially
Strapping
Get ready for a
6 hour Blitz Edition
We call it by the Light
Andheri romantic comedy
Style title
The destroyer of worlds
December 7th 1941
A date which will live its hardcore history
The blitz Edition
Anytime you hear and Analysis
Alaris PC
Explaining
Are strong and are weak points
Why we are where we are today you'll hear someone talk about human adaptability won't you
The fact that we can adapt
This is something that's tied your intelligence obviously for changing circumstances has helped us overcome all sorts of problems
Walls that you might have hit along the way for civilizational growth
To transcend all those boundaries and here we find ourselves in the 21st century today
Alive and thriving
But with several major problems in the distance that have the potential to change that fact
Unless we'd
Adapt
Around them
Now given our past history he would think that we've shown quite the attitude in adopting
But some of these problems
May require adaptation Beyond which we are cape
Do you hit an adaptation wall at some point Beyond which you can no longer
Change as a society as a species as humankind
There are things that we have done from time immemorial
Fill up your history books from start to finish
It would be unimaginable if we did them today
But considering our track record history wise
What are the odds will never do them again
Case in point
We currently live in an era of human history that some have referred to as the long peace
Began in 1945
Obviously
There hasn't been a whole lot of pee since 1945 there's been lots of conflict people get bombed all the time and mean
Human violence is ongoing and continuous
What that refers to is
Conflict between the great powers
The kinds of Wars you've seen
From Mesopotamia onward
The world for 30 Years War
The Hundred Years War
The Punic Wars
Trevor
One of the constants of human history right
Up until about 70 or so years ago
Of course it was 70 or so years ago 1945
For humankind
Continuously improving their weapons technology from the Stone Age forward
Finally reached a point where they had created a weapon system that might be too destructive to be used
And yet if mankind has always used their Innovative technology to create better weapons and always use those better
Weapons
What did this mean
The Norms of human behavior
Mankind simply treated
The things that we discovered at the end of the second world war the way we treated every other weapon we've ever created
What would happen to the world today
What makes you think though that this is a theoretical question
There is no guarantee that the long piece
Last forever
And it's unimaginable to think about what a general War amongst great Powers would even look like with the kind of
Technology we possess today
Humankind is
70 + years into an ongoing and unending experiment
Can we handle our weapons technology
The only way this experiment ever concludes
Is if we find out that we can't
There's a famous quote that may or may not have been said you never know about these things by
The great physicist Albert Einstein
You supposed to send something to the effect that he doesn't know
With what sort of weapons
The third world war will be fought with
The one after that will be fought with sticks and stones
My favorite
Phrases
Pointed a certain point during the long peace
Which was attributed to Air Force General Curtis LeMay but he swears he never said it
When bombing someone back to the Stone Age
Is something like that even possible
What are the odds
That we get to find out
I think what I find so interesting about both those quotes the Einstein one and the Lemay one
Is that they both invoke this idea
Of knocking Humanity back on the civilization scale a few rungs
Below where we are now
As we all know human history
As I described it as kind of like a stock market and you have your UPS when civilization reaches new levels of sophistic
Location and technological capabilities and all that in
And then you have your downs and it's sort of weird for modern people to realize that they were ever people who lived in a Time
Where their forebears were more technologically sophisticated than they were we've been kind of on a long stock market
It runs since about the Renaissance tour
Really the Middle Ages
Haven't had any downturns
You know within
1000 or more years
Start getting pretty fat and happy and comfortable and you forget that they may be are variables out there
They could do to us what
Giant plagues that wiped out
You know what quarter of the population could do back in the old days
Take for example
With both Einstein and Lemay were referring to
Nuclear war
Between the great powers
But we used to call World War 3
Once upon a time when I was growing up even
Seem to be like a gun
Aimed at your head and you walked around with this all the time a Sword of Damocles over your entire Society really
The entire world
Cuz it didn't matter if you were a neutral country
During the Cold War
All-out nuclear exchange happened between
The United States and its allies
And the Soviet Union and its allies
Switzerland wasn't escaping unscathed by just cuz they were neutral
Became the first time in human history where you had the potential
For a single human being we really don't know how these things run
But the potential for a single human being to have the power
To destroy tens of millions maybe hundreds of millions of lives
With a decision window of minutes
By the giving of an order
You think of all of the really scary people in human history from a power standpoint Theory
Your djingis Khan Dior Alexander the Great you name it Dior Hitler's it doesn't matter
None of them had that kind of power
Genghis Khan decided he was going to destroy your civilization
You were in for 10 20 30 years of war maybe especially if you were China
If Richard Nixon in 1969 decide to Nuke China
You destroy a hundred million people in an afternoon
Nobody's ever had that kind of power before
It's a unique new human experience and you don't get many of those
Although the people that were there the 400 450
Special
Human beings
Witness the birth of the atomic / nuclear age
Realise the minute they saw it
Did everything a chain
The successful testing of an atomic bomb was of course the famous Trinity bomb test from July 16th
And Not only was the weapon successful which was not a given
What was more powerful
Then the physicists unexpected
And many of them is not all of them could look into the future and see
This was a weapon that was only going to grow in power as time went on as
Powerful is the test they had just witnessed was
This is scratching the surface
Of what this new era
Will provide in terms of weaponry
J Robert Oppenheimer
Sometimes called the father of the atomic bomb describe the moment
Did the bomb went off
This way in the 1965 interview on a program called the decision to drop the bomb
Quote
We knew the world would not be the same
In the world would not be the same
True people
People crying
People were silent
I remember that
Line from the Hindu scripture the bhagavad-gita
Trying to persuade
You should do is Tuesday
Quinn Preston
Multi-armed form
I am become death
Destroyer of worlds
Now I am become death
The destroyer of worlds
All the old religious texts always have so much power to the language don't they and in this case
It matched what
Oppenheimer and his fellow scientists
Created and saw on witnessing
That day must have been a whole slew of mixed emotions for those people
The famous Manhattan Project was a
Giant Endeavor to build
A super weapon
And some of the greatest Minds in
Physics
And science is related to that from all over the world were brought together massive amounts of
Resources and Manpower and money devoted to the project
And all these people sitting on pins and needles during the test because nobody knew this was going to work or not
There are a lot of reputations on the line all sorts of
Giant amounts of pressure and tension so when the bomb went off
It was a huge sense of relief and Triumph but mixed emotions among some of the physicist
Not all of them by the way
But people like Oppenheimer for sure and the reason for the Mixed Emotions was
If you had already seen
How the last year but would become the last year of the second world war 1945 had gone
Who would have thought
Anyone needed to create a superweapon
It was much of an improvement on the technology as it was being Unleashed that year in the war
Cities were being wiped off the map couple of times a week
Cities
If there's one thing the second world war proved yet again
Is it doesn't matter
How many arms limitation ideas you want to float
You know when you're not in Total War
How much you have these genteel ideas about how
Weapons will be used and when they will and won't be employed
When you are fighting with everything you have against the other great powers in what's called total war
There is nothing in the Arsenal
But you are not prepared to use
People sometimes point out poison gas wasn't used
Any sort of Major Way in the second world war but the reason why is because it wasn't a war winning tool
If it had been
Lady used it
Wasn't worth what would happen in return to you
For something that amounted to essentially a minor irritant in terms of the war effort
Nuclear weapons would have been a different thing
I mean imagine if Hitler
And the Nazis have gotten hold of a nuclear bomb first
That's the thought that motivated
A number of those physicists involved in the Manhattan
Project deny Germany the chance to get nuclear weapons before the allies
Some of the more less enthused once they realize while there's no way that they're going to beat us in this race
Because then all of a sudden
You've worked to create a superweapon
And you put it in the hands
Human being
Therein lies both the problem and the challenge
And the physicists when they thought to themselves about this
New it
When they
Talk about
How we are all going to survival world
Where the Weaponry is is powerful
The modern descendants of those weapons that were originally used at the end of the second World War
The physicists talk about us needing to grow as a species
Or else is sort of what's implied
And I would suggest that in most of these quotes you can hear them
Looking on the bright side or putting the best face on the idea of now that we have the super weapons what does it mean
For mankind Oppenheimer himself said quote
It did not take Atomic weapons to make man want peace but the atomic bomb was the turn of the screw
Screw the atomic bomb made the prospect of future War
Unendurable
You just let us up those last few steps to the mountain pass
I'm beyond there is a different country
And quote
In other words we could never quite
Get that piece thing right till we had the right incentive the fact that we'll all be blown to Kingdom Come is the right incentive
Hail piece
That's putting a good face on an Oppenheimer wasn't always so positive
Arthur Holly Compton also physicist
Bro quote
It is hard to think of fissionable materials when fashioned into bombs
As being a source of happiness
However this may be
It was such destructive weapons mentor to survive
They must grow rapidly in human greatness
A new level of human understanding is needed
The reward for using the Adam's Power toward man's welfare is great and sure
The punishment for its misuse
Would seem to be deaf
And the destruction of the civilization that has been growing for a thousand years
These are the Alternatives that Atomic power
As the steel of Daedalus
Presents to mankind
We are forced to grow into greater manhood
And quote
Is that a nice way of saying adapt or die
When it comes to altering modes of human behavior
That have been a part of the story
Since there's been a story
Of course not all the physicists always look at the bright side on this question
Is a famous quote by Albert Einstein and makes him sound like he's a bit of a pessimist when it comes to the question of
Society's ability to adapt or die in this question he's supposed to have said quote
The Unleashed power of the atom has changed everything
Save our modes of thinking
And thus we drift towards unparalleled catastrophe
A gun aimed at our heads
Sword of Damocles something we were very aware of
When I was a kid we did Duck and Cover drills for atomic bombs dropping nuclear bombs
By then
That kind of still pointed at our heads
We just don't notice it anymore because so many people have grown up in the shadow of that they're used to it
If somebody is pointing a gun at your head all the time
Eventually do you forget about it
If you're born with a gun pointed
Towards your head do you even notice it
In a way I kind of see the ability of people to forget that that gun is aimed at them as an evolution
Married
Success tool
Why should these people be traumatized because of something that happened 70 or so years ago
They had the wrong lives our own problems our own world to deal with
I mean if we all had to
Carry the baggage
Preceding Generations on our backs all the time
What were we be dealing with
I sent it to Healing mechanism but his healing the same as forgetting it seems to me
One of the main things working against the idea of this long piece continuing indefinitely
This we don't remember why it was so important
We never have another great power War to begin with
If the Sword of Damocles has not fallen in a while you forget how sharp it is
Affordable Mexican leave
British philosopher Bertrand
Russell
Once made it sound like the odds of human beings managing
To avoid
Having to be reminded how sharp The Sword of Damocles is going to come to nuclear war seems unlikely he wrote quote
You may reasonably expect a man to walk a tightrope safely for ten minutes
It would be unreasonable to do so without accident for two hundred years
And quote
If you want to be reminded
Of what that Sword of Damocles can do
There's only two real world examples that you can go study
That will tell you
There's a lot of scientists out there and calculations done in testing
But the only thing that really compares
If you want to see not a glimpse into the past of a singular Human Experience it only happened twice to a certain group of human
Individuals in a certain situation
But instead you want to see
20 future nuclear attack
Will look like
You have to look at the only two that there has never been
Atomic bombings of Hiroshima August 6th 1945
And the one right afterwards
2 Days Later
Nagasaki
These days when the atomic bombings are discussed it's often
In the context of discussing the morality of dropping them was it right to use them at all
I find
The problem with these
Discussions and I talked about it at length
In other programs
Is this idea
That the people involved at the time the decision-makers had as much
Free range of options of people today assume they have when they didn't
I mean the idea that President Truman
Could have done something besides drop the bomb
Is a little bit out of Step
With the political realities he was dealing with at the time
Historian Garry Wills who wrote a whole book on the
Power of the atomic bomb to change everything
Had this to say about what would have happened if Truman had decided
Not to use the bombs which would use them in another way
The other person by the way mentioned in this protist General Groves General Groves was the military head of the Manhattan
In his book bomb power is storing Garry Wills rights quote
If it became known that the United States had a knockout weapon it did not use the families of any Americans killed
After the development of the bomb would be furious
The public to press and Congress would turn on the president and his advisers there would have been a cry to impeach president
Truman and court-martial general Groves the administration would be convicted of spending billions of dollars and Dre
Draining massive amounts of bring power and Manpower from other War projects and all for nothing
And quote
In addition to that and this is often overlooked I think by people
Who talked about the morality of dropping a bomb
Wifey Hiroshima and Nagasaki weapons on civilians
And that's what the Japanese civilians were already putting up with on a daily basis
What the Germans had started in places like Rotterdam and 1940 and the Japanese have done in China before the second
World War even officially started
I've been developed
Into the area weapons we saw from 1943 onward
And they were devastating without the nuclear bombs at all
In March 1945 months before the atomic bombs were dropped Tokyo was hit with a fire bombing raid to kill the
100000 people
Vaporized
17 square miles of the capital and by the time the atomic bombs were dropped 50 to 60 square miles of toe
Tokyo gone
And it has been taken off
The top priority targeting list
Some 60 plus other Japanese cities
And had the same fate meted out to them
It was a logical extension a natural progression if you will
Total War
It's a dynamic
That would have been very difficult if not impossible to stop
It's partly the reason why
When we discuss another Total War today
It's so scary
Because the idea that human beings could control what's going on is an illusion
It has a momentum all its own
Now there are some things
We're different about the atomic bombings and that blow me away to this day
One is the instantaneous nature of
It's hard enough you would think to get your mind around the changes that happened to your city
During a massive
Late War bombing raid
I mean if you have five hundred or a thousand heavy bombers flying over your city practically wingtip to win
Dropping incendiary in high explosive bombs on your town
How hard is that to get your mind around
When you crawl out of the bomb shelter
See what used to be your city in Ruins how hard is that to get your mind around
What If instead of happening over 24 to 36 hour time. It happens in the blink of an eye
Well that's what the atomic bombs did
The best relatively short description I've read
Aldi
Effect of the two bombs
Was Panda by author Susan Southard in her book about Nagasaki
He says that within a second of the bomb being dropped
The fireball with 750 ft in diameter
When the temperature
In the fireball was 540000 degrees Fahrenheit
Higher than at the center of the sun she writes
She says
Quote
The bombs vertical blast pressure crushed much of the urakami valley
Horizontal black twins tour through the region a two and a half times the speed of a category 5
Hurricane
Pulverizing building trees
Plants
Animals and thousands of men women and children
In every direction
People were blown out of their shelters houses factories schools and hospital beds
Catapulted against walls or flattened beneath collapsed buildings
Those working in the fields
Riding streetcars and standing in line at City ration stations
We're blown off their feet
Or hit by plummeting to breathe and press to the scalding Earth
An Iron Bridge moved 28in Downstream
Is there buildings began to implode
Patients and Hospital staff jumped out of the windows of Nagasaki Medical College Hospital and mobilized
High school girls leaked from a third-story of shiroyama Elementary School 1/2 mile from the blast
And quote
She then points out that a survivor
Emphasized
That all happened
In an instant
Think of the shock that this engenders
And it seemed to be your two things in quick succession
Will really three first if you saw it you got the light
And if you weren't shielded from the light somehow it burns you
It looked
Kind of like it's been described differently but like a flashbulb going off of an old camera
Facts of a bluish white light
Then it was the blastwave
Which you could level everything depending on how far away from it you were
And then they were the fires
Which seem to break out several minutes after the actual glasses though
Everything we're sort of heated up and it took a minute for
The kindling to
Catch a light but then it did everywhere at once and some of the most heroin stories
Come from family members
Would be trying to get another family member
You know who was stuck in the debris that was all of a sudden everywhere out as the Flames approached and had to leave them
Essentially saying goodbye as they watch their child
Stuck in the rubble is the Flames approaches
It's horrifying stuff in the people who were first on the scene
In both cities
Talk about running into
Are human zombies if you will
Silent People
Burned almost beyond recognition
They were like in a trance
Hiroshima Survivor Hiroshi Shiba Yama
Saw the explosion and ran toward the city center where the bomb and gone off
I said quote
When we are done about one kilometer we were brought to a standstill by a grotesque group of people
The blood pounded in our heads again
I remember that my eyes were drawn and aux ribly to the scene
The people were burned so badly
But it was hard to distinguish feature from feature
And all were blackened is it covered with soot
Their clothes were in rags many were naked
Their hands hung limply in front of them
The skin of their hands and arms dangled from their fingertips
Their faces were not the faces of the living
And quote
He then went on to point out
The heat scene
Quite a few normal Air Raids up close but this was different
Quote
How can I comprehend what I saw before me now
It was not just a group of injured people
Nor was it a procession of the dead or a band of ghosts
No sound came from these figures
They seem to have given up
The pity that they engendered is beyond expression
I continue to stream past in deathly quiet
How can anyone describe them
Their clothes ripped from them by the force of the explosion
Their bodies burned by the intense Heat
Somewhere completely naked
And others had only two shirts stuck to their bodies
The injuries to their faces
We're particularly cruel
Unscathed then with clothes intact
I felt like an intruder
And quote
The general estimates of the
Casualties from the Hiroshima bomb for example are between 70 and 80000 dead
From the fire and explosion
More killed later by radiation
I'm probably an equal number of people injured
The Nagasaki bomb numbers
We're somewhat lower due to all sorts of different reasons
Nonetheless
The tens of thousands of deaths maybe almost a hundred thousand in one city
Cause
Buy a single bomb
Was an exponential growth in the power of the weaponry
After the first bomb was dropped on Hiroshima
US President Harry Truman went on television to try to explain to the American people
The rest of the world
What does new weapon laws
Essentially
Officially
Bring the rest of the world up to speed that an entirely New Era
Heptagon
Atomic age
A short time ago an American airplane
Gospel run bomb on Hiroshima
And destroyed its usefulness to the enemy
That bomb has more power than 20000 tons of TNT
Japanese began the war from the air at Pearl Harbor
They have been repaid manyfold
And the end is not yet
We have now added a new and revolutionary increase
In destruction
The supplement The Growing Power of our Armed Forces
Prison farm
These bombs are now in production
And even more powerful firms are in development
It is an atomic bomb
It is a Honey Singh of the basic power of the universe
What's the sunrise his power has been loosed
I guess those who bus route to the Far East
Astorian Michael S Sherry
Says that there were overlapping feelings on the part of the American public
To finding out that this new reality existed
Your rights quote
A cacophony of reactions to the bombs Advent
A rose swiftly among America
Some stressed pride in American achievement and satisfaction in gaining Vengeance against the Japanese
Truman's announcement that the Japanese quote have been repaid many fold and quote for Pearl Harbor
A minority of Americans wish the war had gone on longer
Some more atomic bombs could have been used against Japan
Others
Especially soldiers who assumed that an invasion of Japan was the only alternative to the bombs use
Welcome to the peace that the bomb head speed
And the bomb itself as a tool for enforcing continued peace
Overlapping those other reactions was another
As in responding to the Holocaust
Many Americans saw the bomb as evidence of the scourge of Modern War
In the face of which the wisdom of American use seen the minor matter
Ali quotes in New York
Herald Tribune article
From the era
Which said quote
One forgets the effect on Japan
As one senses the foundation of One's Own Universe trembling
And cool
Same CBS News correspondent Edward R Murrow
Put it this way
At the time
Quote
Seldom if ever has a war ended leaving the victors with such a sense of uncertainty and fear
With such a realisation that the future is obscure
And it's survival is not assured
Indica
So all Americans could be glad that the bomb
Was in their hands
It was a clear sense and understanding that this would probably not always remain the case
Something like that when you were used to having two oceans
It kept you safe
From anybody doing any major damage to your country of the sort that other countries were very familiar with during the second World War
Could set the foundations of your Universe trembling
And this is where you begin to get this device
This idea on the part of some
And everything has changed and so the human species is going to have to shed themselves of habits they had forever
When people who view themselves anyway as much more
Firmly attached to reality
I think that what we have here is just a natural extension
Of
Technological change
Working in the benefit of
Our side the good side
President Harry Truman call the atomic bomb
The greatest thing in the history of the world
The following year after the bombs were dropped in the war was over
They would be famous meeting where they
Who headed up the Manhattan Project
Meet face-to-face with the president who dropped
Is creation twice
Oppenheimer is a perfect example of the side that feels
As though Pandora's Box
Has been opened
He feels increasingly responsible for picking the lock on it
It sounds like President Truman was caught off guard
Oppenheimer's
Gilt
There are many different
Quotes of this account and they're all different
In their book to win a nuclear war Michio Kaku and Daniel Axelrod
Tell the story
This way
Oppenheimer in the president
And the Secretary of State
Are talking
Quote
In the course of the conversation
Oppenheimer told Truman mr. president I feel I have blood on my hands
Truman then reached into his top pocket removed and neatly folded handkerchief and offered it
Would you like to wipe them
After Oppenheimer left
Truman turn to Dean Acheson the under Secretary of State instructed him not to bring Oppenheimer around anymore
Undeclared
Blood on his hands damn it he hasn't happened much blood on his hands as I have you just don't go around belly aching
In about it
And quote
Amore R-rated version of the story
Is told
In Jean-Jacques Salomon science at politique
Where he said quote
Oppenheimer when he went into Truman's office with Dean Acheson
Said to the ladder wringing His Hands by a blood on my hands
Truman later said to Atchison
Never bring that f****** Cretin in here again he didn't drop the bomb I did that kind of weeping this make me sick
And quote
Truman could dismiss
Oppenheimer but he was far from the only Atomic scientist who was Gravely concerned
Even before the two bombs were used
On Japan in the second world war more than 70 Atomic scientists signed a petition
With a bunch of different things in it but among
Other concerns
Would that the bombs were going to be used against cities and people and they suggested using them
Offshore
Uninhabited areas
Truman as we said had a whole bunch of different pressures working on him that the scientist didn't have working on
Damn
Once the war was over
All of a sudden the Outlook
Could change cuz he could afford to be change your not in hot blood anymore you're in Cold Blood
Now you have in your hands
These new weapons
What do you do with them
How do you control them
Who's in charge of them
And what if either country you get them to
There were in the Years 1945 and 1946 a lot of tug-of-war zand
All sorts of questions being debated I mean the number one
For a while I was who's in charge of atomic weapons
The military seem like a logical choice
Their argument why is it we're going to have to use them we ought to be in control of him and know what we're doing
Truman is supposed to have said something to the effect of I'm not going to let some
Dandy lieutenant-colonel decide he wants to start an atomic war
Eventually that power would be
Rested into the hands of the civilian authorities and the president particularly
He was going to be the one
Who had the power to decide
To push the button as it will be known later
Historian Garry Wills said this is one of the effects the atomic bomb had
It changed the American constitutional system almost quietly
Due to the technological
Necessities
That the weapon required hero quote
Lodging the fate of the world in one man with no constitutional check on his actions
Cause of violent break in our whole governmental system
General Groves had a mirror simulacrum about Authority
And only for a single project
Presidents now have it as part of their permanent assignment
This was in effect
A quiet Revolution
It was accepted under the impression that technology imposed it has a harsh necessity
In case of nuclear attack on the United States
The president would not have time to consult Congress or instruct the public
He must respond instantly
Which means that you must have the whole scientific apparatus for response
On constant alert
Accountable only to him
If on the other hand a danger to our allies or unnecessary assets is posed
Calling for a nuclear initiative on his part
He cannot issue a warning ahead of time without alerting the enemy
Like President Truman who was told he could not forewarn Japan
He must act with a loan Authority
The nature of the presidency he writes
Was irrevocably altered
By this grant of a unique power
And quote
So already the nature of the weapons
Was changing the way we do things
On a national level here in the United States but the question of how this might change things on a human wide level
Was being widely debated as well
In the Years 1945 and 1946 there are some very interesting
Relatively unique ideas
Floated in the world
A public opinion
And governmental proposals
There's intent in those years
An active attempt
To try to put the nuclear Genie back in the bottle
To eliminate Atomic weapons from the face of the Earth
And almost as if to pretend that they had never been discovered at all
There are two things to understand before we get into this the first thing is
All this is occurring when the bodies from the second world war are still warm
And after these terrible
The shattering Wars you often have a hangover. Afterwards were people are understandably
In one of these moods where they say
Never again this can never be allowed to happen again and at the end of the second world war you throw the
Advent of atomic weapons in at the very end there
That the definitive extra! On that never again
That's what this seems
Like a pie-in-the-sky rainbows and unicorns utopian approach to things realize
That they're living
At the last time the Sword of Damocles dropped
And they have a justifiable fear of it
The other thing to take into account and I'm not a historian so you're not going to see me picking the right approach
Is that
This can be a legitimate
Proposal that were talking about here
This could be for public consumption
And behind-the-scenes realpolitik
And geopolitical chess matches and business-as-usual can be going on
In October 1945 which is right after the second world war ends
President Truman gives a speech to Congress
Which kind of begins to
Deal with that question about how are we going to control these nuclear weapons now in this new atomic age
Sunday speeches where he says you know the hope of civilization
Rests on International agreements
Where people renunciate the use and development of atomic weapons
It's pretty big deal and then he
Begins work with the heads of Canada and the United Kingdom a month after that on formulating some sort of
Policy
One of my Nuclear experts I was reading Joseph
To riccione essentially says it's the first nuclear non-proliferation
Agreement ever
They send their
Financier representative a guy named Bernard Baroque to the brand new United Nations
On June 14th 1946 he makes this proposal
He does it with this very dramatic famous language
Noah says we are here to make a choice between the quick
And the dead
That is our business if we fail then we've dammed every man to be the slave of fear it's a great speech
That is supposed to set the
Apocalyptic tone though the world were these weapons out there
Conjures up
And the discussion talks about
I'm taking all the uranium and plutonium everywhere and everything you would need to build these bombs and putting them in a central location.
International Silver
Security
Situation where nobody could get their hands on them and you couldn't have these weapons anymore
Now if you are one of these people that thinks in terms
Maybe that the physicists were using about people growing into greatness maybe you could see this as an example of that
These are human beings treating this with the respect and rationality that it deserves
An issuing all of the normal Power politics one would expect
You know five thousand years of human history
Would lead you to believe
And truthfully from humanitarian Viewpoint the United States offering
To essentially give up their Monopoly on Atomic weapons and he went in the history book to somebody do that
Neenah weather
Superweapon
We've got the only one but we'll give it up for this humanitarian cause
Now here's the
Catch sort of the United States said they would do this as soon as
Everyone else had renounce them in Aldi
Materials have been put into a central location and all of the
Agreements to make sure no one was cheating and building these weapons on the side were in place and then as soon as that was done the US would give up all their way
Weapons to
Well there was a little
Counter proposal made by the people that we're going to begin to be
The other superpower in the world for this next
40 years after this. That we have called in the history books all label
The Cold War
By the way there's a decent number of historians who believe it's a cold war instead of a hot War
Because of the existence of atomic and later thermonuclear weapons
Are former wartime allies but we weren't exactly buddy-buddy with them before the war the Soviet Union
The seeds of the suspicions that will explode
Into
Rabid animosity in just a few years are already apparent
In 1946 in the Soviet counter proposal
Did the United States Britain and Canada saying let's all just renounce the use of development of these weapons in as soon as we can
All done that the United States will throw their is away in the Soviet Union now
Since you're the only one that has any
And then we'll figure out how to keep the world from developing anymore after that
That's exactly the kind of attitude that anybody studying human history forever would expect
Right
Many out there would say that's just rational absolutely don't get Hoodwinked
There was a belief
On the Soviet side that what the United States really wanted to do with this Arms Control agreement if you will is extend the leg
Length of the Monopoly that they had
Atomic weapons list picture no one else can develop any and then
L will have a longer period of time we're the only ones who have them
But it began to sort of lay the groundwork for
What we would see in the future
A three dimensional
Geopolitical chess match
Where the board itself
Is booby trap with nuclear weapons
And no one knows where they are on the board so every time anyone conducts a major move
Move everyone tenses up
Board itself
Was determined by where the armies were when the second world war ended
And there are some notable trouble spot
The number one geopolitical trouble spot on this chess board
Berlin
Former German capital
The end of the war Germany is divided the eastern half is
Under the control of Soviet forces the Western half under control of the United States France and Great Britain
All four of those powers
Sharing jurisdiction in occupation of the former German capital in Berlin
The problem is is that Berlin
Is geographically speaking well within the Soviet zone of control in Eastern Germany
The Soviets control all access to the city
A couple of Roads
That the Soviets watch over carefully is where all the supplies coming from the West
It's an important
Piece on the chessboard
But it is a piece that from the beginning of the game is effectively held hostage
The most important piece the Soviet Union has on the chessboard is the Red Army
The Red Army is constructed differently than armies in the west were it's an army that was meant to slug
I'll get out with German forces with tanks with heavy artillery
It is a hammerhead Sledgehammer of an army
It is full of veterans
And their commanders are well-versed in how to use the
Very large horses that they possess
When the war ends
The other powers like the United States and Great Britain
Quickly start demobilizing their forces
The Soviet demobilize forces to a degree to but the Red Army stays where it is large powerful
Threatening
And the Allied Forces really have nothing on the ground
In terms of
An army
I can stand against it when asked what the Red Army would need to advance into I believe it was Switzerland one
Us Commander said shoes
I mean the belief that it could just advance
All the way to the Atlantic
In 1946
With little to stop it was widespread
The chess pieces on the Westside though
Wer
Compensatory
A balanced out the Red Army to some degree
The West have the grade air forces
And Naval Supremacy
And they also had the atomic bomb
The problem that the United States found itself in in terms of a dilemma
Is the only thing that they had that they knew
Could blunt the red Army's
The march to the sea if it came to that were Atomic weapons
It may have been early on
Too valuable a piece to give up
Of course let's remember the Red Army was not sitting on the edge of Soviet territory
Defending the motherland
They were perched basically along the farthest extent that they had
Taking over in Wartime
And we're occupying unwilling populations of people who before the war were living in their own countries
Places like Poland
And Romania and Hungary in the Baltic states and a lot of other places
We're now occupied
And we're being Incorporated
Slowly but surely into the Communist Bloc this became a bone of contention
And something that would have kept
Good relations from breaking out probably in any case
The other issue that divided the two sides after the war was ideological
And that should come as no surprise I mean the 20th century such an ideological Century anyway
In the 1930s who had three giant different ideological block sort of
Competing with each other fascism communism in
The Democratic
Free market West
The war essentially eliminated the big fascist powers
Leaving a dynamic that is historian Gwynne Dyer points out
Diplomats from hundreds of years ago would have understood
They would have predicted a war between
The Soviet Union and the United States
Based on power politics alone
I have to bear this in mind because
Throwing up when I did the idea of Communism vs. democracy was such a huge part of the equation
That it's hard to rule that out or minimize that
What is dire points out
It's a lot like
The role religion played in the wars of the sixteenth and seventeenth Century it's important and it makes a big difference
But if you took that out of the equation
You probably would have had the same competition anyway
The rights quote
The United States and the Soviet Union have no common border
No claims on each other's territory
No history of national animosity
They're not even serious Rivals for trade and resources
But their postwar confrontation with perfectly predictable and widely predicted
As soon as the probable outcome of World War II became clear around 1943
He said
Quote
Our gravest error in the late 20th century is to overestimate our distance
And are difference from the past
We believe that the present round of competition between the great powers
Is different from all the others in history
But it is invested with special significance because of its ideological dimension
And because of the appalling consequences if it were to lead to war
Has all such other competition to eventually done in the past
And quote
Ethan goes on the list
Did both sides can use to point to the other and say We'll look at all these provocative things you've done
And then he says quote
Each side has an ideologically watertight explanation for why the adversary behaves with sucks
Persistent wickedness and aggression
But none of the post-1945 developments would seem surprising to a 17th century Spanish
Your ottoman diplomat
Neither communism he writes nor liberal democracy would mean anything to him other than is it useful
Label for the players
What he would have no trouble understanding why the Victorious Alliance so quickly fell apart
They almost always do after Victory because the winners are the biggest players left on the board
Hence they automatically become the greatest potential threats
To each other's power
And quote
Now who am I to disagree with Gwen Dyer's excellent point about power politics
Yet at the same time as someone who grew up in that are also
It's hard to discount
What do you dread
And just staying here in the United States for communism
The impact that had overall
Events
There's a
Foreign Affairs Magazine review of Stephen Whitfield book the culture of the Cold War
That I thought was an interesting description that sort of span the width in the breath and then
Of the weirdness as you look back on it now decades later the entire affair
It says about the book quote
A lively and well-documented account
Of how the Cold War both produced
And was sustained by super patriotism
Intolerance and suspicion
And how these pathologies infected all aspects of American life in the 1950s
Entertainment
Churches schools
Older readers will remember and still be amazed
Younger ones will find this a readable introduction to a bizarre aspect of the American past
And quote
You know looking back on it there was something bizarre about it and I didn't even
Exist in the time when it was at its most bizarre
The 50s 1950s
The same time
And I've said this before
I wish that there was this potion or syrup that you can drink
That would allow you for a moment
To feel what the people living in that era felt
About this
Ideology that too many of them seemed little better than what Hitler and the Third Reich was awful
And who's
Desire as they saw it to extinguish Freedom all over the world was about the most evil thing
They could think of
When you are fighting the most evil thing you can think of
There's not a whole lot of things
You're not willing to use to win
Case in point
Atomic weapon
There's another element that's involved in the story that contributes to how bizarre it looks as we look back on it now
It's something that for a great many people was an article of faith
At the time.
Which we know to be false because
Well what they were worried about happening never happen
They don't have that luxury
And every era has
It's conventional wisdoms
That it has to use in factoring out how to make decisions we are as trapped by our own as they were by there
But a great many people and it's hard to quantify exactly how many
But it spanned the entire Spectrum from world leaders and decision-makers
To the intellectuals
Down to the farmers and the maw and PAW operators of hardware stores in Middle America
It was this idea that war with the Soviet Union wasn't just a possibility
But that he wasn't eventual inevitability
And that colors your thinking and ways
But if you don't believe that or if as we do we know that that wasn't what was going to happen it looks in
Insane
Because you consider things
That don't make sense outside of that context for example
If war is going to happen eventually
More than 5000 years of human
Political and military history tells you it's better if it happens
At a time
And at a place of your own choosing
And also when your advantages are maximized
And your adversaries are minimized
Since the end of the second world war no greater disparity in weapons technology has ever existed
The United States had a monopoly on Atomic weapon
Now it should be pointed out that there were those even at the end of the second world war cotton famously and legendary
Currently the American General has suggested that since
You know we already had our stuff all over there everything was mobilize everything was at the height of how we ought to fight that war with the Russians right now
Now
But he was a notoriously gung-ho
The General
But even Stone Cold pacifists will be tempted
By this temporary window of opportunity that exists
If the one
Atomic power
On the planet
Wanted to know kill the other potential one by strangling it in the Cradle
And no one knew how long the window of opportunity was going a lot of expert opinions different
President Truman supposed to vast
J Robert Oppenheimer
How long he thought the Monopoly would like what do you think the Soviets will get the bomb
He supposed to replied
I don't know
To which Truman is supposed to responded I know never
Truman didn't explain his thinking on that whether or not he thought perhaps
The D
In a collective minds of mankind would come to their senses and international agreements wood
Fix this problem
Because he believed World War 3 was imminent
And the Soviet Union would be wiped off the map and your problem would disappear
In a giant mushroom cloud
The military head of the Manhattan Project General gross thought it was going to be two decades
Before the Soviets got the bomb
But concerned scientists and even pacifists
We're worried enough to consider the potential value
Of a preventative nuclear war Bertrand Russell
Was jailed
For opposing the first world war as a pacifist
Rote
In right after the second World War
Quote
Russia is sure to learn how to make it
The atomic bomb
I think Stalin has inherited Hitler's ambition for World dictatorship
One must expect a war between USA and USSR
Which will begin with the total Destruction of London
I think the war will last 30 years and leave a world without civilized people
From which everything will have to be built afresh
A process taking say 500 years
There is one thing and one only which could save the world
And that is a thing which I should not dream of advocating
It is that America should make war on Russia during the next two years
And establish a world Empire by means of the atomic bomb
This will not be done
He writes
Kitten gives a speech
Pretty much right after that time
To the British House of Lords
I'm quoting this by the way from prisoner's dilemma by William Poundstone a wonderful book on one of the
Most famous
Scientist associated with
Atomic power
John Von Neumann
Any quotes Russell is telling the House of Lords
Is Nightmare scenario that would turn a pacifist into somebody that wanted a preventative nuclear war
Ruby started
On his advice
He told the House of Lords quote
As I go about the street and see Saint Paul's the British museum
The houses of Parliament and the other monuments of our civilization
In my mind's eye I see a nightmare vision of those buildings has heaps of rubble with Corpses
Is all around them
And quote
One Russell who's one of the more intelligent people of the century
Theorizes that the next War which he sees his imminent
Will leave people uncivilized and the civilization will have to be rebuilt
A new and it will take 500 years
To get back to where we are now
Think of how apocalyptic that is not humankind I'll be asleep faces these sorts of threats periodically in fact
We still face this one now although we don't think about it much
But I mean everything for example from global warming to some meteor hitting your planet or anything like that
Constitutes
A grave Potential Threat and end the Dynamics of each one is different so our reaction is different climate change for exam
Sample because it needs to be figured out via mostly things like data and observation and science it becomes a
And aren't you in ground for people with vested interest
These people had a different situation going on the Dynamics around Atomic weapons I just been proven
And scene
Basically the attitude was
If you don't want to end up looking like Hiroshima and Nagasaki and Hiroshima pictures by the way if you didn't see it
We have to do something
Doing something
What is a conundrum that these people found themselves a lot more trap to buy
And we would find ourselves
Trapped if we invented Atomic weapons yesterday
Just one of those little vagaries of history is method
A lot of these things happen at a time. Where everyone is still all traumatized and stressed
Not when you really want to hand
The new powerful super weapon over to human beings
Let's let the human beings he a little bit I mean if you discovered atomic
Bombs yesterday in the laboratory and we were talking about it today
Different might our approach to them be
These are tear these could really do some damn we better think about this you know nobody's ready to kill each other we're not sitting
The knife's edge of tension
And Bertrand Russell give that speech
Remember what's going on in this guy's memory banks remember the life experience that he's warming his.
Decision making with
Which is the best line I think a history teacher never gave me said remember what these people have seen
Their life experiences determine how they formulate
You're the best reaction in any given situation or the approach
Bertrand Russell was born in 1872
Into a completely different world and the reason it wasn't the world he was born into anymore the two worst wars in history
Destroyed it twice
The first one was so bad
That they had this entire. Afterwards
Where humankind said never again
Not the first time nor the last time
And build a pole structures and treaties and arrangements and Deals and everything the League of Nations of just one example
This never happened again
That is dead within 20 years it did and it was worse than the first one
But at the end it ended with atomic weaponry
So you're wrestling 1945 a month or two after the war ended
You are suffering from historical post-traumatic stress disorder and so is everyone around you
So when you wonder how atomic bombs might be used
You're thinking you're probably going to be used like the last two things I saw happen within living memory
It's going to be a lot messier than any of that
The other thing that these people have going on that I have to continually remind myself up and it would be again so different if we
Develop these weapons yesterday
Is that the two sides that are the
Can we call them the tip of the spear in the Cold War the USSR the Soviet Union in the United States
Both
Enter the Second World War
As the result
Devastating surprise attack
Barbarossa
The German surprise attack on the Soviet Union in 1941 and then in December 1941 of course Pearl Harbor
Imagine
The next devastating surprise attack happening with atomic or nuclear weapons
And then remember that these people had already seen that movie just a few years ago
The other thing that they were absolutely certain that they had learned
In the second world war in the time leading up to it had to do with appeasement
Tough you had to be on people and
All of these elements
Combined create a dynamic
Where everyone was
On hair-trigger alert
And now they had these weapons that were so dangerous on one side
This was key
In Northern Iran when the Soviet Union did not leave as quickly as they were supposed to President Truman is supposed to have threat
Threatened to use an atomic bomb on them
And then seem pretty darn happy when they got out
Real fast in other words
The idea that when you have the super weapon you can impose your will on other people is really really seductive
Truman Secretary of War Henry Stimson
Explain the advantage that the atomic bomb gave the president and the United States and the West in poker
Opera terms
You said that
When it comes to world power
The atomic bomb was the equivalent of a royal straight flush
That is a hard
Geopolitical hand
To avoid playing isn't it
What would people from earlier eras have done if they had nuclear weapons and a monopoly on them
Julius Caesar Alexander the Great a bunch of Chinese Emperors Japanese daimyo Zora
Egg
Hitler
Here here's fifty atomic bombs but don't use them
Is Oppenheimer in those physicists were talking about human beings having to rise to another kind of
Level of evolution in order to avoid destroying themselves you can see why
Because actually imagining them in the hands of most of History's great figures in the past
What song is the Prelude to a nightmare
It occurs to me maybe that
Question could be phrased a little differently and examined also I mean if
The physicists were talking about a new level of human understanding being necessary to live with this sort of
Analogy
Maybe it's not fair to imagine
Atomic weapons in the hands of some of the most sociopathic leaders in history
How humankind in general
The past dealt with something like this is perhaps a fair comparison
You could go back in my famous time machine a very large version of it
And bring back nuclear weapons and some technicians to set them up in
What button to push in everything
Do you think of people from the Bronze Age
Or the Iron Age
Newk's their adversary
If you give Hannibal nuclear weapons explained what they do set them up for am heading the button and say if you push this wall of Rome will be gone
A walking zombies with their skin hanging off and
All that was dead and all that does he push it or does he say maybe I should think about
Interesting
To wonder
About the development over time of human ethical systems
But also something based on
If you want to suggest the species learning
How about the idea of imagining Hannibal
Would that nuclear weapon
Haven't gotten the chance to already live through things like the first and second world wars
To experience Verdun
And Stalingrad
And gas an atomic bombs used in Warfare
And then handed the weapon and say
Maybe now you understand the mess this Sword of Damocles will leave you still want a new Chrome
I'll tell you what's fascinating to me and again is part of the human condition I'm not sure you could get around it
Is at this moment and maybe this is the kind of stuff the physicists were talking about also
At this moment when
It's all on this like Doomsday Clock knife-edge in in 1947
Scientist will inaugurate the Doomsday Clock because it's
Show me how close we are to destruction because of atomic weaponry.
Doesn't matter how close it is Doda striking midnight
We still playing politics in the world's democracies
Because that's how democracies work
To go back and read
The political pressure
On a guy like Truman
That the opposition party uses against him and the typical political Dynamics are trying to
To peel the rule voters in swing States and it's insane how
It changes a dynamic that you would really wish him and kind of sit in a room
Coldly and dispassionately without 1 oz of concern about the politics of it
And think about this issue that bedevils us right and maybe all humankind maybe all succeeding Generations if you want to take
Take it to the logical nth degree of hyperbole
But no
We're still going to call the president soft on communism because it's going to help us win the congressional election in place like New York and we're darn close
So taking the Senate back
How else can a democracy run
I think and I don't think this is an unusual statement to make it all if you look at us history there are certain
Time. Where the country fundamentally change is theirs
It's almost like a body part breaks and we replace it with something else that's reasonably similar if you want to fool your
Self and dress it up but has been
Altered
Irrevocably and is unrecognizable
To previous generations
The founding of this country in the change from the
Confederation to the Constitution is one of them in my opinion
The Civil War and reconstruction to another one in everybody's opinion
But
If you look at the. And then people would have different dates on this from about 1946 to about 1952
You see the United States government transformed
Historian Garry wills and we described
I'm talking about how the presidency in the power of one person to decide to go to war in MA
Window of minutes change that aspect of Presidential Power but then he goes on the list
Things that people who know American history all know anyway all of the famous
International Security decisions and things like the Marshall Plan in the Truman Doctrine in
All these different things that when taken as a whole and when you look at them on the list it's amazing how many happened in the space of a few years
Create the National Security State
And you should know my own biases before I go farther because I do have them in this case and it's worth
Factoring that into
You were thinking when you hear me
But I talked a lot about politics
And in my opinion the United States
Made the wrong course change during this time. And became a different country
Country much less connected to the 1:00 Americans believe that they have
When they study what I like to call them it's of America
And the Constitution as a lay person would understand it
I think September 11th in the 9/11 attacks is another one of these periods in US history and I think you see a similar Dynamic there
And as well
In neither Case by the way do I hold the decision-makers accountable
For having made the decisions at the time
I think it was inevitable for example that any us Administration given what's going on with the freaked out
And overreacted after 9/11
I think the same is true in this tree were talking about here between 1946 and 1952
It is the later
Generations afterwards that I'm upset with for not fixing it
Problem with historical memories a transgo on long enough
Whole Generations are born never knowing what needs to be fixed because they never lived in the time before the chain
Change occurred
If you wanted to say today
We need to go back and fix the
Things that we did between 1946 and 1952 The Dan Carlin things were over reactions
How the heck do you get back that far
And I'm more critical question for a person like me is what if we like it better this way
So please note my biases at the outset
But this new National Security setup
What developed from about
4690 46 to my 1952 and hit when the CIA was created the NSA
The entire structure of government that we know today that protects secrets
And and spies on the enemy it keeps us safe and yet medium
It's our world now and this is what happened
It seems to run counter
To the very things that some of those scientists were saying you were going to have to do
If we were going to avoid World War 3
Were they called for a new level of human understanding
Whatever that is and I don't pretend to understand exactly what these physicists wanted to set things like this
But you got the opposite with the National Security State
Whereas some of these famous physicists some of the most famous
We're saying in 1945 and 1946
That we should tell the Soviets about the bomb right when we started making it
Or that we should give them the nuclear secrets after the war
Thinking how crazy that sounds to us today
And with our modern mentality we should just give the terrorists all the nuclear bomb secrets
That sounds insane insane do a lot of the military class
After the second world war we executed people
In US history
For turning over nuclear secrets and some of our physicists were suggesting
But that's the sort of level of understanding
They will take us to a new world where we can ease tension so we don't have World War 3
That's a pretty hard evolutionary tool
To have to fight again
Because you have to combat your own fear
And I think I've said before
Fear is one of those evolutionary developments that is probably save more lives in human history than anything else I can think of
Normally it's a very good thing to have right saber tooth tiger comes at you back in caveman times run
Or kill it or whatever you have to do then protect yourself cuz you're afraid from saber tooth tiger attacks and put up fences and
The fear thing is not a bad
Condition
It helps with security
But it's a very things that I've always help with security
Threaten not just your existence but civilization
Can you turn that evolutionary tool off
If that's the only way to survive
As I try to play with counterfactuals you know what if scenarios in this.
Imagining it turning out differently than it did I can't think of any that sound like
They would be rationally imaginable
Take for example the military in this situation
What are they supposed to do
After the second World War
Pretend they don't have a bomb if you're the United States
Or if you're the other side in this
Growing distrust
Neither will turn into the Cold War for the Soviet Union
Do you just pretend the United States doesn't have an atomic bomb how does that work
Like we said
It's for the president of the United States almost
Too good of a hand to resist at least threatening to play
I mean that's just politics right that's just foreign policy the way it's always been handled
And if you look at this from a strictly
Age-old
Power politics Viewpoint historian
Michael Howard does a great job adjust setting up the way the military saw this thing
To them and we're speaking of them as a whole rather than some of the individuals and even perhaps some of the various Services moron
I'm not in a minute
I saw these things because that's what they're paid to do
Howard Road quote
When confrontation developed between the Soviet Union and the West shortly after the ending of the second World War
The military on both sides
Forshaw business-as-usual
The Soviet plan to advance their Western glasses
To the Atlantic
Didn't either the Americans the use of air bases in Western Europe
Volume arrogance hoped at least
To retain bases in the British Isles Spain and the Middle East
From which to bombard the Soviet Union
And then in due course
In quotes here liberate
You're up for a second time
It continues
The peoples of Europe knew nothing of these plans and would have shown little enthusiasm for them if they had
Next time remark at French prime minister who did know about them to his American colleague
You will be liberating a corpse
And quote
The problem you faced in 1946 1947
If you're the United States military or Harry Truman and maybe you've already threatened to
To play that royal straight flush on the Soviets in Northern Iran once
The problem you have
Is you have very few of these bombs
Although no one knows that
And you have no good way to deliver them
The next couple of years
The military and
Harry Truman and the government of the United States will focus on a system to deliver
Armageddon
If that's what's needed
It's official name with the Strategic Air Command
And was part of this brand new branch of the United States military known as the Air Force which used to be a part of the eye
Army and it was part of an entire reorganization that was also a part of this post
Second world war transformative. The change US foreign policy in the hole
Design of government the new Department of Defense the new Pentagon it was all part of this
Strategic Air Command job
If called upon to do it
What to destroy the Soviet Union's major cities with atomic weapon
And in the process
Kill tens of millions of people
The Mind sort of real
When you think of how quickly we went from that
Well to us today it even looks like a rainbows and unicorns place
Trying to crap legislation to rid the world of the scourge of atomic weaponry
To a year-and-a-half two years later
When the president
Has to deal with the approval of Air Force plans
For winning World War 3
That involved as the key part of the strategy something
Commonly referred to as the atomic Blitzkrieg or Atomic Blitz
Trying to explain
All the various things that go into why these decisions were made as complicated
And one of the main reasons why is her recent all this is as we said before
Reality is complicated I don't have to tell you that
Social cultural economic
Individual forces I mean a thousand things working on it and every direction all the time
Well that's pretty much how it's always been
But you can always see it the source is so
When you go back to like ancient Egypt and you look at what historians write about that
They don't have access
To all the information that would flush out the reality of those people the way we feel it now
Consequently history seems much more simple cuz the
Minor strains that are all interwoven around events are not visible back then
But the closer you get to now
The more visible those minor threads
Become and it's impossible to quantify the importance of this the right over that's right for example as I said earlier
You would love to think
In a situation is important potentially is nuclear
In a global nuclear war that we would have philosopher-king sitting in quiet rooms
Discussion with the most intelligent physicist in an ethical people in the world how we deal with this situation
But instead
The normal things that impact human Kinder at work here to despite the stakes we said politics in a day
Democracy
A little while ago
But it's more than just politics
How about
Such
Banal concerns as budgetary questions and
Interservice rivalry
Changes to
For example
I think you could make a pretty good argument and a lot of people have
But the number one reason
That you have an atomic Blitz style strategy
That's the plan to win World War 3 should it come during this time.
Has more to do with budgetary restraint than anything else
And you again wish that you had your philosopher-kings and everything in the back room not worried about anything but know I like politics and budget
What have you but reality intervened which is why this
Whole argument about having to change
Humanity in order to survive in a post Atomic world is so difficult
Einstein said the atom changed everything but our modes of thinking
But it's hard to change your modes of thinking
I mean think about Harry Truman after the war
Harry Truman's got to cut the budget because it's
Spending a fortune cuz it was just in the biggest war in history and it was doing the Lion's Share funding
Cathay those levels right
Can't live at those levels on Harry Truman
How to cut the military by what he think is going to be 70% after the war
While still having to be able to fight World War 3 should it come
And as we said a lot of people thought it was imminent
How do you do that
Remember running business people who you know opened up there
Business books from college that just said listen it's all about prioritization in consolidation
There's no reason for all this redundancy first of all
You just combine all these services and have no air force and no Navy no Army 101 hold military defense structure
You hear this argument all the time in this country and other countries to the service is hate.
Because they all have a lot of pride in their own service and sometimes a little bit of antipathy toward the other ones
What's more
You had
A whole new branch of the service out there the u.s. air force that he just been created
And all of them competing
Or an economic pie
It was going to be cut by 70%
As you might imagine in any country at any time. Ever
Are the knives came out
And the backbiting started in the services had to get up there in a centrally argue for
Why they were relevant and why they matter them why they should get a larger
A piece of the economic defense pie
I was the air force that ended up winning the argument
They went to the president basically said if I can simplify this
There's only one branch of the service that will win World War 3 for you and it's us
Because we're the ones who will send fleets of bombers over to the Soviet Union and bomb them with atomic bombs
This was a very contentious. Us defense history again it's part of that entire area with a big change occur between
46 + 52
But the services in some of these cases were fighting for their very existence
In the second defense secretary guy named Louis A Johnson
Who is totally on board with this let's get rid of a bunch of branches of the service idea
It supposed to have said this quote
There is no reason for having a Navy and Marine Corps
General Bradley tells me
Did amphibious operations are a thing of the past
Will never have any more amphibious operations
That does away with the Marine Corps
And the Air Force can do anything the Navy can do so that does away with the Navy
And quote
Then goes on to cancel this giant supercarrier the Navy was building
And as you might imagine things just go ballistic
It leads to something
That's considered to be one of the more unusual and serious because there hasn't been a lot of them
Revolts by a branch of the service in American history
It's often referred to as a mutiny in some Spirit high is it would be very strange because usually gets the Mutiny is from the the
The lower levels of the Navy to the higher-level this involve the highest levels
Of the Navy
Who came to the defense of the service
By arguing for all sorts of things that you would understand you know they're just trying to make themselves look relevant and of course the Navy can do this in
No one else can
Usual argument that they also brought to the table and they brought it out in Congressional hearings in it
In a way that when you think about it it's just shocking
Was they questioned the US strategy of atomic bombs
On moral grounds
In something known as the Revolt of the Admirals and Congressional testimony
A bunch of war heroes from the second world war in the guys like Chester Nimitz and everything came out
And then arguing essentially that we don't like your plan
To just go
Drop atomic bombs on cities and that's how you're going to win the third world war but at the same time in a defending their own branch of the service
Did you cried the entire idea as an American and a moral
Does Eric Schlosser rights and command-and-control quote
Congressional hearings in October 1949
One high-ranking Admiral after another
Condemned the atomic Blitz
Arguing that the bombing of Soviet cities
Would be not only futile
Money and morals
They advocated Precision tactical bombing of Soviet troops and supply lines
Using planes from American aircraft carriers
Admiral William F Halsey
Compare the Air Force's new bomber to The Siege weapons once used to destroy medieval castles and towns
Quote I don't believe in mass killings of non-combatants and quote
Admiral Arthur W Radford testified quote
A war of annihilation might bring a pyrrhic military victory
But it would be politically and economically senseless and quote
The harshest criticism of the Air Force
Came from rear Admiral Ralph a Asti who would toward the burned-out cities of Japan after the war
He described the atomic Blitz as quote
Random Mass Slaughter of men women and children end quote
The whole idea he said was ruthless and barbaric
And contrary to American values quote
We must ensure that our military techniques do not strip us of self-respect
And quote
Once again hard to quantify
And really know
How much is the Navy's opposition to use of atomic bombs of the war winning
Can you base your strategy on would because their service didn't have any
And how much of it was based on moral grounds
Complaints with P notably muted
When submarines could carry nuclear weapons it should be noted later on
But the Admirals bring up a key moral question that people will wrestle with four decades as a matter fact they still Russell
Is there an ethical way to fight
An atomic or nuclear war
Is there a way to bomb cities and civilians with atomic weapons
And have it still square with
American values in the values of the
Freedom-loving Weston it would have been known back then in general
In there fighting a bad guy is I said that you go read the literature the time it is clear
This might as well be
And the Third Reich again and Joseph Stalin might as well be Hitler
Little known facts here in the United States but the Soviet Union will mellow out a bit after Stalin goes away but this is the
The hardcore era still
He is considered to be a ruthless guy and communism appears to be on the move
But if you kill tens of millions of civilians
Using atomic bomb
In order to thwart the evils of a totalitarian superpower
Watch evil do you get splashed on you in the process
And what if you strike first
At the second thing that came into play even
Gossip is Bertrand Russell for a little while I was thinking that the United States should strike first
To keep the bomb out of the hands of guys like Joseph Stalin
Interesting to think about what our history books would look like today and how it would treat the subject of a preventative nuclear
Your War
Had the United States acted on that kind of premise back in the day when Bertrand Russell was making those peaches
How do I know if he would change his opinion later on this
Unless I can't imagine the history books
Treating it all that nicely today
Try to explain away all those deaths
To keep the Soviet Union from getting an atomic weapon
1 is
Reminded
Friedrich Nietzsche's lying about be careful when fighting monsters
But you yourself do not become a monster
The tough ethical dilemma isn't it
Confirm my own stamp when I find this. Fascinating because
If you think about the ethical dilemma maybe you're putting
A handgun that's loaded into the hands of a five-year-old boy
That's kind of what I feel like this. Is here
Maybe the most dangerous. In atomic history because it's the one we're still trying to figure out
Oppenheimer's right and we have to grow into a new hire
Version of ourselves just survive
This is the. Of like adolescence
Can we do it before
You know we should something
And it's a. Where the tension is mounting at such a pace
Did Michael Sherry the historian says that the drumbeat of crises and initiatives was relentless during this time.
You go look at a timeline in it
One thing after another Bam Bam Bam Bam
And remember those are the things that make it into the history books that totally discounts with the people in that era
Reading their morning newspaper on a day-to-day basis would have had to contend with
All the rumors and lies and
And threaten and Maneuvers and things that might happen but never turned out to be true they sweat that out on a daily basis
What you're talking about these things that sound horrific to us today that anyone would even consider you don't understand
People thought they were facing
The fact that we know that their worst nightmares won't come true
Can't be allowed to Blind us
From the position that they found themselves and remember we have the luxury of knowing how things turn out
It changes everything doesn't at all makes it very difficult to put ourselves back in those shoes and I want that serum
Instantly allows you to go on my God I'm so scared that the Communist are going to take over the world
You know what I was doing at the 1970s
There was something known as the Domino Theory
Communism
This idea that
Spreads from one country to another
And let you know as soon as one Falls it subverts the next one over there
And was supposed to explain this exponential growth
Of a of Communism in the world and why you needed to be concerned about all these little countries
You would say what cares about this little out-of-the-way place that they go Tommy this is not exactly like they're in the
Center of the world you know what why do they matter you say you don't understand
The domino effect
They will submit the country next door and then you can't let me get a foothold
In the seventies when I was growing up you were beginning to think that that was crazy although there were still a lot of proponents
But the reason it looks so out of whack
Is because in the 1970s when I was a kid things that stabilized
It was a theory developed by people that were watching reality unfold
Back in the era we're talking about now
Where did look like dominoes were falling and it looks like they were falling quickly
Couple of different kind
Covert and overt
For example at the beginning of 1948
The Czechoslovakian government is
Overthrown in a coup and they become part of the Communist Bloc one of their
Famous ministers
Found at the bottom
Of a multi-storey apartment dead in an apparent suicide out of his window which many people believe now was
Nothing but Russian agents tossing them over the side of it
That began to give everything so the berry
Spy underhanded clandestine You Know The Enemy Within soda field and communism was different than fighting
Nazism
You didn't have to worry about Nazism is an intellectual contagion very much
Or as communism was something that could appeal to downtrodden peoples everywhere including in your own countries
I want to send you a new enemy to deal with
Potentially some of your own people to change things to as everyone knows
Couple of red scares if nothing else
The McCarthy era and some legitimate problems with
In a people who were spying because they had an intellectual affinity
For the beliefs of the Soviet Union
When I get
What are some communist all the time saying you was between communism and such a terrible light
All we can go on is the examples we have
If they don't match the
Potential
Of the classroom theories well
Can't help. I can only tell you what the Joseph Stalin regime was like
And it wasn't pretty
And if you want to point out the problems that the West has I'm going to agree with you on all of them
But there's still no comparison
In this case the Soviet just were
Ruthless in the United States and others argued that you had to meet that kind of ruthlessness
With a similar sense of resolve
And some of this resolved
Required the ability to push back in places
Couple months into 1948
Joseph Stalin does something
The test the resolve of the West if you will in a way
That is so challenging it's like calling your bluff in that high stakes poker game
Michio Kaku and Daniel Axelrod and their book
How to win a nuclear war say that by this time. Harry Truman has already threatened the Soviets four times
With a nuclear bombing
Maybe blops but
Never came to a head because
The Soviets gave in
On June 24th 1948
A pretty darn good geopolitical chess player himself Joseph Stalin makes a move
The basically calls the entire nuclear block of the West
And shuts down
All the Rail lines
And the land routes
That we're supplying
West Berlin
The place occupied
By the French the British and the Americans
That they shared with the Soviets and it was deeply inside
The rest of Soviet Eastern Germany at the time
Only allowed to exist because Stalin allowed food and everything to go through
On June 24th 1948 he stopped allowing that
And then basically looked at the United States in the rest of the world
And in his own geopolitical way
Send
Check
You may be thinking to yourself that we are over playing
The
Poker and chess analogies a little bit
Because they are things by the way they can always be applied to
Diplomacy in foreign affairs
Realpolitik that you can always compare those things to chess matches and whatnot but nothing so fits
The model
As the Cold War
And in fact
In due time and alternative approach to
Oppenheimer in the physicist idea that we're going to have to grow as a species or we're going to wipe each other out of
Will begin to be developed along the lines of things that we call today Game Theory
And we're already under way in the minds of people like John Von Neumann and others
Developing ways
To see if we could use our intelligence
To not drastically lose the game
If humans had to adapt or die to their new weapons technology
What's the only kind of adaptation that was going to work
An evolutionary one
Where's that was impossible
Did humankind have a back-up plan
Living with a sort of Technology
In this case was Stalin at setting
A foreign-policy sort of terms
Is are you really
Going to start World War 3 over this
All I did was say
You could no longer have access to a city deeply behind
The Border in our territory with at least we're we're
In charge of Defending
R zone
Influence
We haven't attacked anybody you be attacking us first what would World opinions are you going to start World War 3 over this
And
If you do
Not only
Will the war start but will
Start with wiping out all of your forces that are in Berlin now
Appetizer for World War 3 if you will
How do you respond to that and especially in this. Where once again it's hard to get into the minds of these people with everything you read
He talks about how much both sides in this cold war
Thought that they learned
From World War II
And the lead up to that
The whole idea of appeasement is ever present in the discussions right
Hitler proves a point for every
Maniacal
Aggressive
Dictator everywhere right they're all like Hitler so you everything that was applied to Hitler applies to everything else and in the symptom of Joseph Stalin
You cannot show weakness so do you start World War 3 over this well
The wheels are in motion
And
Very soon
A solution the ground apparently by a local Commander
Who started to have food flown into Berlin cuz apparently Stalin wasn't going to shoot down airplanes I guess they saw
Pretty quickly
And very quickly
Harry Truman saw that as the
Life preserver thrown to him
Right where your choices start nuclear war or let Stalin get away with it what about we don't start nuclear war either
We just start supplying the city now what are you going to do you remove
See how this game thing work so well in this situation
Another start nuclear war first
And what will be known as the Berlin Airlift
By the time it's finished and it'll be
An ongoing for more than a year
The United States and the other Western allies
Will fly in 1.5 million tons of coal
Fuel and other necessary products for everyone West Berlin
With nearly two hundred thousand flights into the city
It's an amazing achievement
And was an easy out
Good World War 3
But worth noting
A during the crisis especially in July 1948
Discussions and real discussions were had amongst the United States the president is advisors
About whether or not you start nuclear war over this and they're fascinating to go back and look at
Begin to see the big divide between those who think
The nuclear weapons are the special class of weapon that you left treat totally differently than any weapon that's ever been invented ever
Ever and don't you think it's just a bigger bomb
The purposes of our story here
Which is more about Humanity adapting to its
Weapons capabilities
The 1948-1949 Berlin airlift crisis is key
Because it's the first time
But you get the rubber meets the road practical questions
But hadn't really a reason to this point it's almost like you have to have the crisis before people actually sit down in the room together
And debate
The question that should have come up a long time ago like
What can we really accomplish with these weapons what can you do with them
Not everyone understood that you can threaten with them because they already done this before
By the way it's a
Strategy known as escalation dominance and you don't need a Tomica nuclear weapons for that strategies always been used.
But it's basically the idea that you're willing to take it to the next level
You really want to fight over this with lucu
And the other side doesn't have nuclear weapons well that's the end of that game right
The problem is is that that's a bluff game
And what these people are asking now
Having played the bluff game three or four times already since the second world wars whatever Force to play this hand
Words that mean the really practical realities things like do we have the planes in placed how many bombs do we have
What are we going to Target
Get those places and Destroy them does that get us what we want
These are the kind of things that have been sort of
Compartmentalize and talked about in various branches of government the Berlin airlift crisis brings all these people together with the price
President to have really fundamental discussions of the store that hadn't happened before you could see these broad differences of opinion
The military man by and large are under the impression
It when we go to World War 3 we're just going to use the new weapons to the way we use the old one
And some of the other people for example
Head of the atomic energy commission David lilienthal
He's part of the group of people that are counseling Truman in this
Key moment during the Berlin airlift crisis not to use the nuclear weapons
The July 1948 meeting between Truman
And his various advisors is
Talked about him and she okay KO and that's a rose book and they write quote
In his journal that day
Lilienthal atomic energy commission head
Wrote The Truman quote
Greeted us rather solemnly
You look worn and Grimm
None of the joviality that he sometimes exhibits
I rather think it was one of the most important meetings I've ever attended
And quote
The authors continue quote
At the meeting so I'm like lilienthal expressed reservations about using nuclear weapons secretary
Royal however
Spoke for the hardliners when he said quote
We've been spending 98% of all the money for atomic energy for weapons
Now if we aren't going to use them that doesn't make any sense
Ann Coulter
But even those
Who are trying to figure out maybe that you can just use these weapons as a bluff have a problem themselves
They want to deter with these things in something
Strategy-wise will become known as deterrence their problem is that for that to work
The other side needs to think that you would use the weapons so you can't publicly come out there and say these are the most
Awful things in the world we would never use these weapons because then you can't threaten to use them anymore than they have no utility
If you're one of these people who believes
But you won't
Really use them you won't play the hand but you're threatened with him
Right to work
People have to believe you'll go there
That's one offer I was reading pointed out
He said that the bombs too terrible to use under any circumstances it has no determined value
So even if you're one of those people that would never foresee the use of atomic weapons
You can't say that
Because then they're no good at all
This becomes the main conundrum
Of using the bomb but during this period
There's one main part of the conundrum that we understand today that's missing
Because if World War 3 breaks out in response to some event connected to the Berlin airlift in 1948
Only one side is going to have Atomic Weaponry used on them
If you're the American public and you're sweating out these increasing tensions
You can at least Comfort yourself in the idea than the era of atomic war in 1948
You are still safe for being new
Because your government is the only one that has the weapons
That will change and that will change everything
Part 2
The destroyer of worlds
1949 is a terrible year
In terms of the Cold War the only thing that keeps it from being say the most terrible year in all world history in terms of danger
Our technological limitations
You give 1949 the same technology we had in 1969 and I think it is the worst year ever most dangerous
Why things happened in 49 that make people very edgy
I mean for example
After a long-running civil war with an intermission during the second world war the Chinese Communist finally
Only gained victory in their Civil War over the Nationalist nationalist go over to Taiwan
The Communists declare a communist country
And all of a sudden
Soviet Russia the largest land power in the world in terms of actual Geographic size
Has added to it a country roughly the size of the United States geographically
And with the largest population in the world communism just took in
25% of the world's population and added it to its ranks
That's how
Country like the United States or
UK would have seen the situation
Does zero sum game and all of a sudden communism just took China and we lost it
Be a big political debate in United States for a long time
Which party in the White House lost China
ISO China was ours to lose
1949 is also the year NATO is formed
In attempt to begin to Cobble together a European defense strategy from a whole bunch of country still trying to recover from
The damage of the second world war remember
Only one country came out of the second world war major ones anyway any better off than they went into it
The United States everybody else was recovering
Certain countries like the Soviet Union from really Grievous wounds
And that's partly the reason why
The estimates maybe on how long it would take the Soviets to get their own atomic bomb we're so off
Are they do it so quickly the military head of the Manhattan Project General growth didn't think that the Soviets would get it for 20 years
They got it
16 years sooner than he thought they'd get it
There's no doubt that Espionage played a key role in helping
It doesn't change the fact that it took the Soviets about the same amount of time it took the United States
The UK and the Canadians in the Manhattan Project to build their bomb
On August 29th 1949 in the Central Asian deserts
The first Soviet a bomb test goes off
The United States finds out
From a monitoring plane that was just sort of keeping track of radioactivity
Joseph Stalin not the kind of guy to come out and announce anything about anything
The USA though thought he was going to so after debating whether or not they should tell the people of the world
Did the Soviets were Atomic power now
One of Truman's advisors specifically mentioning the Panic After the War of the Worlds broadcast by Orson Welles
And saying that the whole thing might cause a panic
But in an attempt to sort of get ahead of the Soviets if they were going to announce it and approached the proper spin on it Truman came
Vim forward and basically said
The Soviets have it in this is why it's so important to control these kinds of weapons
The Sands that tiny little. At the beginning of the atomic and nuclear age
Where Atomic power rested in the hands of merely a Singleton
It's somewhat amazing given the state of human affairs
That Williams Monopoly one country didn't use that weapon to dominate the world so maybe one could suggest
But in an ethical sense
It showed human progress
Perhaps Bertrand Russell's line about
How long you can expect a man to walk across that tightrope with a hold on
They haven't had to do this for very long
First round goes to man's ethical and evolutionary growth because we avoided
Bombing the Soviet Union when only one country had the bombs but now two countries have the bomb
Are they going to change the dynamic
What takes the fear level
An exponentially can found it because now all of a sudden the United States have to worry
About having the same thing happened with the places like Belgium and Germany have had to worry about forever
But the US isn't going to get invaded in the old-fashioned sense but what's the difference
Eventually some other power
Can just ignore the fact you have a couple of oceans protecting you and turn your city's into smoking heaps of rubble
The United States hadn't faced anything comparable to this since the British burned the Capitol building in the War of 1812
Psychologically it would affect any power the United States though
With this extra sense of invulnerability it's always had
Was in a unique place in its history
Now the other side becoming a nuclear power does a couple of things first of all
It closes the circle
In terms of
Creating the dynamic that we have lived with ever since
This Dynamic of both sides being able
To do incredible amount of damage to each other at least theoretically
Very different Dynamic than only one side being able to do that
The other thing that happens in a geopolitical sense
Is the era of
The United States having that MasterCard
As the Secretary of Defense and said
The royal straight flush
That's over with
The window of opportunity is another
Advisor had said this. When the US was the only nuclear-powered that's over with two
And predictably
The
Question of how to respond
Ran the gamut
With even sober humanitarian type scientists trying to figure out
If all of a sudden the balance of
Rational thought has swung towards the idea of will now that they are nuclear power
We should nuke tomorrow we can
In his book prisoner dilemma author William Poundstone quotes
Harry Truman science advisor
A guy named William golden
Who penned a letter where he tried to imagine how
A man from Mars Mike view the geopolitical situation in other words somebody didn't have any humans
In the game just from a purely
Dispassionate outside observers Viewpoint and he wrote
About the
Soviets having the bomb now in the way that the US and the rest of the West should respond and he said
Quote
This brings up the matter of immediate use or threat of use of our weapons
Let us not delude ourselves
To bring about a true International control agreement with Russia we would have to use them
The consequences would be Dreadful indeed
Even though I assume that the Russians have so few a bombs now that they could do little or no damage to the USA
Even if it could put them on target
In theory we should issue an ultimatum
And use the bombs against Russia now
From here on WE inevitably lose ground
And this is true no matter what how much greater rate we produce no matter how much more potent weapons for once
Russia is in a position to put a bombs on our City's no matter how inefficient those bombs maybe and how few in number
She's in a position to do with unspeakable injury
That we can retaliate a hundredfold or wipe out every Russian will not repair the damage
So we're good
Low morale case can be made by the disinterested Man From Mars for are shooting at once
And quote
Then goes on to say however we won't do it of course
No matter what the alternative because the public would never support it
The last comment is fascinating again cuz your again tempted to see this some sort of an ethical evolutionary
Change
Mean with the ancient Bronze Age civilizations have hesitated the minute
Don't know
Of course if one wanted to look at it in a more cynical way
Maybe you just say
No one wants to be living on what will turn into a nuclear Battlefield if such a war breaks out
Also when your country talks about starting one
Or being the first to introduce such a weapon I think maybe there's just a survival Instinct kicks in and maybe the p
People from the Bronze Age would have understood that perfectly
But we come to another one of those moments now
A fork in the road a decision
Between maybe what you could call doing things the way we always have for all the right reasons
And acting in a way that would sort of defy your expectations
Giving human history
And it's what are you doing now
Will you do if your the United States and you just had your
Atomic Monopoly destroyed
Human Nature
And all of human history would say you try to go get another Monopoly
Continue work right you develop the next system you regain dominance and superiority in
I feel nobody wants to be the one who's the last person to invent a machine gun or something like that you lose a war that way
The last Nation to get an Air Force right
But if you are already struggling to try to figure out how to handle
You know not having catastrophe strike in the world of atomic weapons
How sort of against the grain
Hermann Einstein and Oppenheimer viewpoint does it sound to talk about making
A super super weapon
The super was actually the nickname for the next
Level in Human Weapon Redevelopment that was already
Theorize and it working already begun on
A weapon that would make
The atomic bombs of Hiroshima and Nagasaki look like
Nothing
Weapons that require.
A bomb like the bomb used at Hiroshima and Nagasaki
As a primer
Moritz main explosion
A guy named Edward Teller is most famous for association with what
Will be
The weapon that makes atomic bombs obsolete
A guy like J Robert Oppenheimer who
One of Truman's aides said was too much of a poet
And not enough of a hardheaded realist but the kind of bomb that a guy like J Robert Oppenheimer would say
Is is
Farther than we should go we should no longer develop more powerful weapons than the ones we have
Think about how much that runs against the grain of human behavior
Could we if faced with Extinction decide to cap
Weapons research and development we will never discover anything more powerful or deadly than this
How do you shut off
Information like that he keep someone else from developing it
Is the Angel problems that Humanities always had to deal with
And right after the Soviets demonstrate that they too are now an atomic power
Harry Truman have to Russell once again with all sorts of forces and uncertainties and he's
He's in a brand new era of human history with no roadmap
This is a guy by the way who had been vice president for like 5 minutes when Franklin Roosevelt died
Edwin cried saying he wasn't up to the job he's dropped two nuclear weapons on Japan ended the
Second world war in the fact
And now he's called upon
Too Faced these kind of pressures it's crazy
One can only
Whether you think he did a good job or not
Have some sympathy
For the
For the haberdasher from Missouri
Which is what this guy was like the artillery captain from the first World War
Truman is not one of the great minds of History one of the Marcus Aurelius type leaders he's just a pretty
Normal human being put in the situation where he literally is making decisions about whether or not we can build stuff to destroy the
And whether or not that's a good decision
After the Soviets
Blow up their first a bomb Truman asks for some help and some
Advisors and he gets the Wiseman together
It's not exactly philosopher-kings but it is the physicists
Who invented the first weapon
Bunch of the mini with led by the guy
Truman's a that was too much of a poet
J Robert Oppenheimer
Obviously folding
Text from the Bhagavad Gita so maybe there's a point there nonetheless put him in a room
In October 1949 says should we develop the next
Level of Weaponry above Atomic weapons and is it possible and if we did it with his helping
Do we need a Manhattan program for the next super weapon
The one that makes our current super weapon obsolete
And the physicist winning a room
Talked about this an issue to report
And the report by the physicist said
Don't build
This weapon
Just went by the way or something today we call a thermonuclear bomb
Or a thermonuclear Warhead
Hydrogen bomb
Thousands of times more powerful than the bombs dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki
And described by nuclear expert Joseph cirrincione
As the equivalent of bringing a literal piece of the sun down onto Earth
There is no upper limit to their power
In the report Oppenheimer & Friends
Essentially now 5 years after the atomic bomb was dropped have a chance to see how Humanity's dealing with it
And they've decided maybe in Reading between the lines here that we haven't evolved
Enough yet
Something like the hydrogen bomb the report says quote
We believe the superbomb should never be produced
Mankind would be far better off
Not to have a demonstration of the feasibility of such a weapon
Until the present climate of world opinion changes
And quote
Is that code for until we evolve more
They also seem to be
Suggesting that this is a chance
To provide an example
On how we can break the patterns of the past because we have to to survive
They write quote
In determining not to proceed to develop the superbomb we see a unique opportunity up
Providing by example some limitations on the totality of War
And that's limiting the fear and arousing the hopes of mankind
And quote
There's that poet
Oppenheimer & is rainbow and unicorns coming out again
The people around Truman might say
The great Enrico Fermi and another physicist
Pandan even more
Apocalyptic respond that they didn't think that the one that I just read you goes far enough
They wrote this and I quote it in its entirety cuz it is shocking
They're basically saying
You are inventing weapons that can now do the equivalent
I'm creating giant natural catastrophes if you could turn on for example the ability to cause
Cause a massive tsunami or something
From me and his colleague right quote
A decision on the proposal that an all-out effort be undertaken for the development of the super
Can our opinion be separated from considerations of broad National policy
A weapon like the super is only an advantage when its energy releases from 100 to 1000
Times greater than that of ordinary atomic bombs
The area of Destruction therefore
Would run from 150 to approximately 1000 square miles or more
Necessarily such a weapon goes far beyond any military objective
And enters the range of very great natural catastrophes
My very nature it cannot be confined to a military objective
Becomes a weapon which impractical effect is almost one of genocide
It is clear that the use of such a weapon cannot be justified on any ethical ground
Which gives a human being a certain individuality and dignity even if he happens to be a resident of an enemy
Country it is evident to us that this would be the view of peoples in other countries
It's used what put the United States in a bad moral position relative to the peoples of the world
Any post-war situation resulting from such a weapon would leave unresolvable and middies for generator
Nations a desirable peace cannot come from such an inhuman application of force
The post-war problems with dwarf the problems which confront us at present
And quote
That's pretty harsh and you can say to yourself well you know some of these physicists live in their own unreal world
But David lilienthal from the atomic energy Commission
One of the people who pushed back against the idea of using atomic bombs during the Berlin Airlift
Running his diary
About the way the government was leaning and it was not in the direction the physicist wanted when he said quote
More and better bombs where will this lead
Is difficult to see
We keep saying we have no other course but we should say is we're not bright enough to see any other car
Course
And quote
So you run into the people that give you the old Machiavellian
Reality which is we've got to build these bomb cuz the other side's going to build them to in the last thing you want to do
Is be the last person to own the next level of weaponry
It makes total sense given our history
What the physicists are telling us is that everything you learned in your history everything's been
Need a paste it onto your DNA from thousands of years of human evolution some cities first cropped up is obsolete
And you can either change that standard template
No by which you gauge what you should do in any given situation
Will you can find yourself a victim
I'm a weapon that makes an atomic bomb
Look like a conventional bomb
Truman as usual had many more pressures Weighing on him
David lilienthal in his diary also record the statement by Senator Brien McMahon
Describe sort of the mood that the American people would have
If they found out that the Russians had an h-bomb but the United States didn't he said quote
Why a president who didn't approve going ahead on the h-bomb all-out would be hanging from a Lamppost if the
The Russian should get it and we hadn't
And quote
Kind of hard to argue with that logic isn't it
Same logic we operate with today
And it's hard not to be struck here
Isn't it
When you consider
Estranged divide between the level of the intelligence of the people
That were put together to create the super weapons
Versus the level of intelligence of the people whose decision it will be whether or not to use them
The political class in these
Democracies and republics for example but let's remember
As that statement by that Senator points out how heavily influenced AR by public opinion
We're living on a knife-edge
How these weapons are used in
How wise we can be about them do you really want that decision devolving down to the average Joe and Jane level
The counter proposal by the way by physicists like Oppenheimer
Over why you don't need to build the super weapon
Is that you've reached a maximum threshold when it comes to the power of these weapons to do anything
They offer the idea
That you can just use atomic bomb
To deter anyone who got any weapon greater cuz you don't need anything bigger than that
They may say we'll drop a hydrogen bomb on your city that's a thousand times more powerful than your puny a bomb yes but the
I'm still basically takes out the city
You trade and cities were cities and what Oppenheimer and those guys were saying is that
Once you lose a city in this deal
What you're trading City for City you have the deterrent value you need to stop somebody else
I'm attacking you with any kind of weapon
This is
The beginning of the ideas of nuclear deterrence
You begin to see the introduction into this debate
Of a civilian class of intellectual
Will become sort of the alternative
To the rainbow and unicorn poets like oppenheimer's approach where they wanted to become different people than we've always been
The other side of that coin these these people
I would say we're not going to change and it's too hard to change you and the system isn't flexible enough even with we wanted to change the
We're going to have to learn how to live with these weapons
Intelligently as we can
And big civilian thinkers started to meet with each other starting about 1945 right after the first day of autumn
4 dropped at the end of the second World War
And he began to coalesce in groups and meetings at Major University Place like Yale for example
These experts would come from a wide range of
Discipline social scientist political scientist physicists of course but also people like
The civilian leaders of agencies. David lilienthal from the atomic energy commission was there
And they would debate these fundamental questions
The simply had to be answered in this new era first of all
Could you use these weapons
If you use them
Did that make ground war and and tanks and armies obsolete what will World War 3 be like
All kinds of fundamental questions down the problem
For these people
Is that all of this stuff
Is part of what you normally considered to be
The responsibility and the prerogative of the military leaders
No tell the general how to use his weapons
That's not your business you tell me where to go and what to do in terms of winning I'll take care of it
Now the weapons were so powerful
The meaning of the big thinkers out there argued
It's simply using them had a huge political implications
Something you could not delegate to a general on the ground who might think he needed Atomic weapons
To blow up the entrenchments on that enemy he'll not realizing that he can lose the entire war of global public
Look at pinion by doing so I'll write another word to the use of this most powerful weapon
Had to be in the hands of the supreme leader whomever that might be
Well in 1950 that's still Harry Truman by the way in January 1950 after reading the report
Work from Oppenheimer and his fellow
Scientist saying don't build a super bomb
Truman decide to build the super bomb
The reasons given
And in the people around him you've given the recent they all revolve around the same thing again
Easily understandable stuff you can't be outdone
Truman even mentioned the psychology of Adam even if you believe the idea that Oppenheimer floated that you can just use a bong
Against their h-bombs
The psychological effect on the American people was unacceptable
It was a standard understandable response they're going to get it so we have to have it
I do know the way you can kind of reliably
Test to see if this is something that you know there was such a thing as collective human DNA means the species of
Hold it it's in there somewhere
Can you imagine humankind
Saying no
To a more powerful weapon system
I mean I'm sure there's groups on the planet is a very peaceful group of people in that part of the world they would say no
What is a hole when you think of the powers at the very height of
Important can you imagine them saying you know
Yes we know that's a much
Bigger and more powerful weapon than we have but we're okay with what we
Currently possess we don't need that
Bigger weapons
Let me get the aliens landed tomorrow
And we found out the biggest weapon they had
Destroy the galaxies in the blink of an eye
What's the x 14
They're going to be people on this planet right away that say we have to have an x 14
The walk all over if we don't have what even if we don't know how to use it even if it might destroy the Galaxy as long as we have one they can't judge
Israel all I have to take it into account
Wrightwood, player
We will not be subject to escalation dominance
Psychologically it's important for those aliens to know we have an x 14 2
Here's the thing though
The Truman administration at the time that he approves going ahead with this hydrogen bomb
Still hasn't figured out how to use the great power of the atomic bomb
You still trying to figure out what you do with that cuz it's so powerful and yet now we're going to move ahead with
Having a hundred times more powerful than that
Truman has taken the pistol out of the hands of that 5 year old was trying to figure out what you do with that
And the Machine Gun instead
He still doesn't know what to do with it but at least it's a lot more power
That's kind of where we are because
In this period between 1945 and 1950
When it's this theoretical. Punctuated by lots of scares and near misses and threatened
And all that
People are trying to figure out what you can really do with these things in Oppenheimer and his folk it said you don't need anything
Think bigger than an atomic bomb
The problem is a during this time. There is no chance to do what will later be called counterforce really
Counterforce means using your nuclear weapons against the enemies military targets
At this stage of development
You are lucky to use them against to anything
Use them against big things cities with people
These are City destroying
Weapons
And that's what you use them for in this.
The question of the Moor political minds are asking during the security does that get us what we want
I mean if the thought is that you're going to kill millions and millions of people
Do you end up with an outcome
In the end
It was better than what you had before
Banana courser really important
Question during the entire period of the cold warning and up to now
Is does the other side really think you do that
Remember they were really
During this. Two kinds of people when it comes to nuclear weapons to kindly things you can use these things to do plan
And the kind you thinks you can't use them
But even those people think
Did they still make up a part of what you can use to threaten other people
Being the best use of this tool
As many theorist during this period
Thought about it anyway
Was it at
Created something where you could tell someone else do that or else or
Don't do that or else you'll get new
Remember Truman did this several times
After the second world war in before 1950
But in April 1950 Truman is presented with a document that will become one of the most important and yet
Very little known actually documents in American history is called nsc-68
And it did a lot of things including
Pushed forward some of the hydrogen bomb development stuff
But what nsc-68 did in
In paragraph after paragraphs is spot the hole
In his entire defense strategy
The fact that you basically were relying on a threat
And if the threat were called
You either had to Nuke the other side and kill millions of people or back down
Other powers could test that
They could try to find a point
Underneath the threshold
Of when you would use these weapons
What if somebody just sort of gobbled up their neighbor a little at a time
When.do.you Newcomb
Allies were worried about this too because they were starting to think that maybe
The United States would be willing to use nuclear weapons for themselves and their own protection but if it was somebody in Europe that they said they
Check baby they don't nuke anyone for that maybe they don't kill millions and millions and millions of Russians
If the Russians invade West Germany
That kind of thing would make the West Germans nervous for example
One of the things nsc-68 side is that the risk that they were running right now with their strategy of
Nuke everything or nothing with quote
The risk was having no better choice
Then to capitulate or precipitate a global war and decoding other words they had no flexibility at all it was new
Nukes or nothing
Nsc-68 becomes the document that Advocates a huge increase
Back
2 spending on Conventional Weapons tanks
Plane naval ships all the other stuff
But doesn't back off the nuclear stuff either
In other words whereas before the budgetary choice was between this or that now it's this and that and everything more
This becomes a document
The Begins the giant military buildup in the US
In the role as sort of the policeman of the Free World
That we still live with today
Now initially Truman looked at this thing and we are told by the history books. This was going to be horribly expensive and true
Intended to be fiscally conservative
Any sort of put it on hold and thought about it a little bit and then in June
On the 25th actually 1950
The North Korean Communists invaded South Korea
And what that man was it all of a sudden
I'm moving very quickly
And hard to get your mind around and react and debate and deliberate
What'd initially seemed like it was too much money to spend for Truman
I'm probably Congress and the American people
I think it was something like a
In Virtual tripling of us defense expenditures
Seems like a no-brainer
Now that all of a sudden
For all intents and purposes as far as anyone could tell with quickly moving events
The fuse for the third world war seemed to have been lit
Korean War as it's come to be known is so fascinating as so many things involved with it that have nothing to do
Do with the great power that would make a wonderful discussion all by itself
And I really resist
Going off into too many tangents and try to stay on
On the focus which is
But it's a completely different sort of challenge
Then trying to live with these amazingly powerful weapon in the Temptation in the fear and the uncertainty that they
Can I bring to the table this new thing
In peacetime
Even with all the
Retsina scares
Entirely different matter to try to deal with the Temptation and fear and uncertainty involving them
In Wartime
And let's also remember the very
Other human elements involved that are operating sort of underneath the scenes here
There are a lot of people
11 vested reputations and viewpoints and all sorts of things into
The efficacy of these weapons and what you can do with them than once of the game changers they are
So now we were going to find out
You know whether they were right
We're all these
Pronouncements and positions taken in peacetime going to play out the way The Advocates and opponents thought they were going to play out
Now that we have a real
Live fire situation going on
If there was ever a conflict that would tempt
May leader to use Atomic weapons
The Korean War seems tailor-made for
Because eventually it will settle down to an almost first world war Style
Very little movement kind of stalemate
But initially it is an absolute bar brawl
Where the momentum swings wildly from side-to-side and there's crazies after crazies and each side gets in
Ended their own trouble
Initially the North Korean Communist forces
With tanks and people that have fought in the Chinese Civil War just swarm down start smashing the South Korea
Reinforces driving them South towards the water
And this is going to be a Dunkirk with no place to go if you catch my meaning
They outnumber them they have our Mormon is a whole bunch of reasons why it happened
Taqueria
Had been just what I'm getting
The idea of Independence down after being occupied by Japan
At the end of the second world war the Soviets
It occupied the top half of the country basically the west of the bottom half of the country they put in governments to
But they were in friendly with a communist one in the North in the non-communist one of the South
And then kind of sort of
Look elsewhere while the whole Berlin thing is playing out in a bigger fish to fry as a matter of fact in the Korean War breaks out there's a
A large contingent of people that thinks that this is just a diversionary faint
Shurhold Joe Stalin
Does a little move in Korea the entire free world in the moves their military forces their we get bogged down and then he
He invades in Europe
My people thought.
The historian John Lewis got it makes a very interesting point
Saying that if this hadn't been a World War II style attack with tanks in the whole thing going over the Border
Basically an open auto Andover challenge
To the post-war idea that wouldn't have collected defensive there's never going to be another Hitler in Nebraska Wars never going to win again
Got it says if this
Attacking been more like the way the Vietnamese were very good at attacking
15 years after this were they were they would send in gorillas and it would be subversive and slow and infiltration and
Will you never know where the decision points are that the Americans probably wouldn't have gotten involved at all but this was a chair
Challenge and somebody
Had to stand up to it or at least that's the way
It look to Truman
Who was just
In the major stages of codifying one of the policy he's most known for instigating something Cost Containment
There were several different views on how you handle the spread of Communism from the domino effect
The one that was eventually part of nsc-68 was called containment don't let it spread any farther
There were other more aggressive ones like rollback or another one that Liberation was with some of the far-right
Hawks wanted
Containment is what sort of became the policy of the United States and that's going to be your policy even if you thought that just meant you were going
Going to give money and Aid and help certain governments
Now you had a situation on your hands were if you didn't act and you didn't act soon
South Korea was going to disappear it was going to be a fait accompli it wasn't going to matter what you said
It wasn't going to be two koreas anymore you weren't going to be able to put Humpty Dumpty back together again
You know in like 3 days the capital of South Korea Falls what are you going to do
We're so many other things we have to remember we're on going at this time
The importance of which has faded in the 70 years since remember this is 5 years after the second World War
These people had
Began to think that they had made War illegal for lack of a better word they had once again built
Old structures
What they thought were new and improved structures over the last World War structures the League of Nations proved
Toothless tigers and that we had a new and improved version of it called the United Nations and this is a real test for the United
Truman involved them
You're basically right away
They start debating what to do and as fate would have it and it never went this way again
The Soviet Union happened to be boycotting the UN at the time so they were not there
Now as we all know today
What we would have expected to happen given our understanding of History
What's a twin this question of what should we all do about this Korean War thing
Came to the UN the Soviet Union as
Friends and backers and fellow communist with the North Koreans would have used their veto which several members
Of the UNR on the security Council permanently and wage
And have a veto that they can use and often do the Soviet Union one of each of the whole thing and everything would have been modeled in there would have
Unified effort
Because they happen to be boycotting at the time they couldn't do that
And the US with a bunch of other nations
Got an agreement together to go in and save South Korea quickly and the US
And other countries
Became really a United Nations Army at least in terms of the marketing and media
Nations Flag that flew on some of these tanks
Never been quite this way again
The implication was that all the sudden you were going to have any
Global World Army that could go in and do things like this
In addition
Truman put in charge one of the heroes of the second World War
Douglas MacArthur right the guy who so famously in the Pacific said I shall return and then eventually comes back and goes I have ra
Returned
I'm he's he's
Eisenhower family studies study Dramatics for years
As a subordinate to
MacArthur
Just put in charge of these forces that rushed over from Japan
These are a bunch of guys have been sitting in Japan enjoying themselves for a few years they're not exactly crack combat troops when they get
Get there and there's not many of them
And the Air Force comes in the Navy gets involved very quickly you find out that that
Defense secretary Louis A Johnson that it will never need another amphibious operation you don't need an AV
Was about as wrong as you could be because when the Korean war broke out and within five days the United States is trying to
Be there on the ground to save South Korea from falling
And they just don't have what they need straight up
When I get in there and now it looks like they're going to get defeated with the South Koreans it's just a terrible situation
Situation becomes the first moment where
You think God you know if you had some
Really good tactical nuclear weapons during this. You can see some places where you just love to use them but they don't have that right now
But over and over again situation will change
Eventually they'll be enough forces build up
The UN forces can start pushing back and creating a larger perimeter and then
MacArthur and maybe the greatest move of his career
Lands End amphibious operation in your face Louis A Johnson
At Incheon behind the North Korean lines Cuts them off
Begins to
Peter push back up now towards North Korea so we've gone from defending South Korea to now moving in
North Korea and there are warnings be careful
You're approaching China
They might not like that
Even though MacArthur is supposedly finding Chinese dead people when he goes over and
Looks at what should be North Korea dead people he tells President Truman don't worry Chinese are going to get involved and secretly
Later on you find out he's not scared of him anyway
So they don't have the logistics and what are they going to do nothing going to happen and he continues to move forces closer to
Airline and then they Whack Him would like 200 300 thousand guys
Boom
The war changes again now the Chinese have entered the conflict
Think of how quickly this escalated
From me
North Korean South Korean affair
2 something where you now have the United States of America and
A multitude of its Western allies the great powers of the West
Facing off against red China on the Asian mainland
Back by the Soviet Union
We started this on June 25th 1950 within a couple of days the u.s. in the western involved
By September you of The inchon Landings in the hole
Complexion of the war changes by late October or early November the Chinese are in it
But not
Officially
And that becomes part of where you begin to see this evolving
Into a very post
Second World War forum
A form that is largely dictated
Existence
And possible use of nuclear weapon
This is when it becomes a parent
That they keep this from becoming World War 3
All the major powers that would be needed to fight World War 3
Are doing their best to create some plausible deniability
But nobody has to admit this is World War 3
In one of the interesting theories out there that if you don't have nuclear weapons in the world during this time.
Maybe there's a decent chance this does turn into World War
Free
But you can watch
Joseph Stalin in the Soviet Union
Maui in red China and Harry Truman all bending over backwards
To be able to tell the world now this is war
Truman's case famously
And when the fighting breaks out and it's the worst since the second world war pretty hard to deny what's going on there
It is war And the reporter says to the president he says President Truman is this war we at War and treatment favor
Usually just right there no
We are not at War
And so the reporter counters with something like so
So what is this is just like a police action in Truman famously said something to the effect of about sums it up
And forever after it's been called the police action
As though
Proper label on this thing
Put a limit on it
It's not just about marketing either
There are real changes I mean the Truman calls this anything besides the war
Does he have to go to Congress and ask them to declare war
This is another thing that
The bunch of modern historians are suggesting
Was seen by the people around Truman is kind of a quaint relic of a pre nuclear age
Is Secretary of State and people like that not huge fans of
Even more people being in on the decision making process and Truman was able to put troops In Harm's Way
Without ever having to ask anyone else's permission I mean
Is there an Gary Wilson the decision to intervene in Korea was made
Amongst Truman and a tiny group of advisers around himself
The reporter asked that question about are we at War because normally you would know there'd be a big declaration Congress would do it
In the country that use everything in their power they demolish the other side they come home but can you do
Is that a nuclear age
The reason the Korean war is germane to this story
Is because well here's a way historian John Lewis Gaddis explains it quote
The outbreak of fighting in Korea in June 1950 provided the first hard evidence
The Korean War demonstrated how awkward it would be to use atomic bombs even in the most desperate military sir
Circumstances from this perspective they proved to be irrelevant to the outcome of that conflict
From another perspective they were critical importance for Korea determined how hot Wars
During the Cold War where did he fought
The rule quickly became that neither the United States nor the Soviet Union would confront the other directly
Or use all available Force
Each would seek instead to confine such confrontation
Within the theaters in which they had originated
This pattern of tacit cooperation amongst bitter antagonists could hardly have been merged headed not
I've been for the Existence on both sides of nuclear weapons
And quote
In order to give them some plausible deniability and basically say we're not at war with United States you don't have a child
Chinese American war going on
Milo and the Chinese labeled
There are hundreds of thousands of Chinese Army troops volunteers
As though you almost don't even know what's happening what did hundreds of thousands of our people in Korea fighting bull who knew
And eventually when the Soviet Union
Who kind of deliberately doesn't get involved I mean I kind of stay away from this instead you got to be careful cuz
The Soviet Union and China have
Signed a pact defense Pact
So if it looks like China is attacked
Automatically the United States at war with the Soviet Union to which the Soviet Union doesn't want
Either
So they're not getting directly involved or staying as far away as they can and will eventually almost cuz they're shamed into it
They have to send Pilots to help
They make the pilots
They paint the planes like they're they're Chinese
Volunteer planes
They give him fake names they tell him if they're captured you know you say you were a Russian living in China they don't don't fly over water cuz you
The whole thing as a disguise now
It's not fooling any of the other countries
This is essentially to be able to say
But this is not the kind of War
Where we need to use nuclear weapons although The Temptations keep coming I mean
Tell me a point for example
Wen 11000
Soldiers most of them American in sub-freezing temperatures are surrounded
Around the Chosin Reservoir
And there are people that will go to President Truman and say
If mr. president we'd like to use atomic bombs
Keep trying to remind myself that Truman is the first human being to ever have that sort of
Question put to him
To have that kind of responsibility dropped in his lap
You can't fake understanding the ramifications cuz he's already done it twice
What the heck of a thing to put on a human being and Truman as I said didn't just cry when he got the job he basically said
I'm not. I'm not a big enough man for it I'm not a big enough man for it and yet he's the first man in human history
Have this kind of responsibility in his lap
It was a 1952 article in Fortune Magazine where are writer I like name Hadley
Donovan
Did something which I think is really cool where he
Zoomed out sort of an imagined
How
Harry Truman power at this stage in world history would have been viewed
And we've been looking at it from 500 years ago or something if we were treating it like
We would treat to the carolingian Empire the Byzantine Empire or something in your history books because we tend to
Pre-modern history
Totally differently look at through totally different lands in Donovan's article
Put this in terms that we could recognize a we were talking about events from a thousand years ago when he writes
Quote
A Californian named Robert Carney Now commands the greatest striking power in the Mediterranean world
The seat of the classic empires of Alexander and Caesar Augustus
Admiral Carney directs all NATO forces in southern Europe
And the US sixth Fleet
In northern and western Europe the old Realms of Charlemagne and Napoleon extraordinary military
Korean political influence is held by a Kansas man
Dwight David Eisenhower
In Korea
The bridge and Battlefield of half-a-dozen Oriental imperialism's the largest Western army ever lodged
The Asiatic Mainland is led by Matthew Ridgway
From Virginia
All of these officers are answerable of course he writes
Do Native of Independence Missouri
If the president of the US were ever tempted to think of himself
As Emperor Harry the first
There is no evidence that he has been
He can look about the world with considerable personal satisfaction
And quote
And yet several times in this war he will be asked
To unleash the sort of hell that none of the people who ran those earlier Empires
Could ever dream of being able to inflict
When it's
Noteworthy
But he turns them down essentially every time
This is kind of a great interesting psychological question to which there is no clear answer but
There a lot of speculations as I said as to why
Truman doesn't drop this bomb
If it's going to help him out of this jam and Jet lot of political pressure tell me why doesn't he do it
Will this becomes another place in history where
It depends on who you believe
That was a fan of History I simply read all of these different ones and I try to pick the ones in my head which I think are the most
In a logical or make the most sense but often times
Yeah they all kind of
Have a good point I mean
How to win a nuclear war Michio Kaku and Daniel Axelrod amongst other people
Suggest that the reason Truman didn't use
Nuclear weapons in Korea was because he didn't have any extras
People who subscribe to that theory the reason isn't moral at all it's simply that the Surplus doesn't exist and if this real
Is a faint in the Soviet Union is just trying to get all our attention over to Asia and then they're going to attack in Europe you're going to want all 300 or
400 atomic bombs in your stockpile so that's one attitude out there
There's another view that they're particularly unsuited to this kind of warfare where you have
These individual Chinese peasant type infantryman carrying
All they need on their backs over the hills and
Scattered numbers of nuclear weapons not really set up for that
Is another school of thought that
Are afraid of using them and having them not be as scary as everyone thinks they might be maybe Hiroshima and Nagasaki
Sake where the best place to demonstrate them in terms of scaring people
The most effective conditions you could use them under maybe anything else might be underwhelming so
Are scarier if you don't use and there's all sorts of theories
I can't help but notice a certain pattern
Not that if you look at the first three US presidents have had to Grapple with this amazing amount of power
They have often had to do so
At
Odds with their military advisors on several occasion
Truman Eisenhower Kennedy they all will have their advisor saying we think you should use these things
And they will all say no
It's fascinating to think about that and
Again one is
Forced to confront our past and ask if
This is how we would have behaved in earlier Generations
Or earlier human eras in the same circumstance or whether or not
This is indicative of some sort of evolution or growth
And if it is growth
Is it ethical growth of these people becoming more ethical than the people of the past or is it intellectual growth
Are we becoming
Intelligent enough to manage these
Unbelievably sophisticated and dangerous weapons
I can't answer that but I can say one thing for sure it's on a collision course and you don't have to be a genius to see that
With the principal way that the experts
Fight wars during this period remember
Truman is trying to adapt to this new
Atomic age
He's got Generals in charge of forces fighting complicated Wars on a nuclear booby-trap geopolitical chessboard
We're born in the 1800s
MacArthur does not want to worry
About which chess pieces he wants to use on this nuclear booby-trap chessboard or what squares he can and can't move to
He's used to having a free hand
And he and Truman Clash over what he can do
Truman is creating something that will be known as limited War whether he knows it or not during this time
.
The general that he personally put in charge of all these forces in the not just American forces there's Australians
Brits I mean it is a multinational un Force
Headed up by this guy Truman put into place and a guy who has famously said and will during this entire crisis anymore
For there is no substitute for victory
When I was a kid it was widely thought that Douglas MacArthur wanted the power to use Atomic weapons himself
Against his adversaries in Korea in the Truman wouldn't let him
But none of the modern history seem to think so
They point out that he didn't want to use nuclear weapons but he did want to be able to fight
The war in Korea the same way he fought every other conventional war with the standards in the
Attitudes towards victory
But he was accustomed to using
The problem was as if he did those things
It would cause the Third World War break out most likely if you're
Truman in your playing this knife-edge dangerous game it's way too much of a Gamble
MacArthur didn't want any rules
Telling him what he couldn't do to fight a war Nguyen
When he said this enough publicly that he disagreed with the president's policy to the media
He had to go
And you know it once again when you think about The Bravery involved here with Truman Truman fan particularly
But
His poll numbers were much lower than Douglas MacArthur
Douglas MacArthur was a hero to a lot of people in there were a lot of people that just plain didn't like Harry Truman
After he fires MacArthur
MacArthur comes home and a half a million people come out to give him a ticker-tape parade
Most of the newspapers come out from a card I mean
If your Harry Truman you just made the biggest negative move
Xavier entire presidency
And it took an amazing amount of God and you paid forever for it
Probably cost you another term
Endure the right decision
You can say in hindsight because if MacArthur had been allowed to do what he wants
A third world war had broken out
Imagine how different our history is today
Emily have to do is look at what the plans were right
What do you sumption what the plans were in some cases
Western military leaders assumed
At the Red Army would simply launch attacks across
Premier bases in Eastern Europe into Western Europe and roll all the way to the Atlantic
Think about the destruction that that entails right there
Us plans involve the use of this most dangerous of all human weapons ever invented
No not the nuclear bomb because remember
That's a component in a weapon system
You still had to be able to deliver the bomb this was the problem the Soviets had during the street they may have had like 10 maybe 12
These bombs
They didn't have an adequate delivery system they had no Strategic Air Force didn't have a way to bomb anybody
Yet they're working on it
It wasn't a real threat the real threat was at the Red Army was just Crush all opposition all the way to the ocean
The US however would unleash Strategic Air Command
Who had a
Bevy of different plans that they hadn't paper and variance of every plant a plant like Shakedown and off tackle mold
These kinds of things but what these plans have in common
Was a massive Atomic Blitz
Using about two-thirds of the atomic weapons in the stockpile right away the same day actually
In most cases
And then keeping about a third in reserve
To go RI bomb places that needed re bombing
During the. We're talking about here it's something like 200 bombs
Maybe 300 bombs
Maybe on 20 30 40 Soviet cities a bunch of these cities to be bombed multiple times
It's millions and millions of people though
Anyway you look at
And you wonder
What the history books would look like today with the photos and accounts of the survivors
Let's just say 35
Russian cities
After they had been bombed
On the same day
In the world's first atomic war
Like Hiroshima
Or Nagasaki on steroids I guess
I've often felt that
Especially my own people Americans but but maybe a lot of other people too
Don't look
Carefully enough
At what these weapons do
Because there are overtones
That people tend to push away because we're human in the United States when you'll talk to people about the atomic bombings of joy
Japan
There's a defensiveness that often comes up because they assume you're trying to keep some sort of guilt on them and they will get defensive in
Point out the things the Japanese did or or many of the other elements involved
And with a conversation about Atomic and nuclear bomb is usually break down towards and it keeps us
I'm examining the most important part of the story though
Last part that can't be changed
But the Future Part
That needs to be understood
When we are talking about doing things that might lead
To the kind of outcomes we've only seen a couple of times before and those outcomes are
So important
I'm struck by the fact that even people who were living through them at the time and trying to survive
Realized
They were essentially guinea pigs up a new age
And tried to write things down
So we could benefit from it today but in order to benefit we have to look at it history makes you look at things
It's a part of me that thinks there be something beneficial to walk in a lot of people around
The death camps
After the second world war where people were exterminated
Just to remind them
History forces you to look at these things realize that this isn't just some weird occurrence one time this is what happens
Periodically
These mistakes beware of them and know what can happen
There's a diary kept by an amazing doctor
Hiroshima
Italian doctor michihiko hachiya
And in his diary first of all he's a survivor of the Hiroshima bomb
But then he goes on to the nearest hospital to begin treating people one of the things that's so terrible about these weapons is because they
I created almost natural disaster
The First Responders and the people that have to help all the damaged people are themselves victims
And if facilities are part of what damaged
So you can pound
A difficult situation
By killing all the doctors and nurses and destroying the hospitals at the same time
Put in a move that just shows how sometimes like in this case it's scientist but there are other
Peoples are professions also
In this case this Japanese scientist realizes as soon as he's not having people literally dying it is
Beatniks like 4 days later or something
Tell the other doctors that we have to start writing stuff down
The dad is going to be really important to people in the future because there haven't been many people
To live through this yet another words
This guy was already thinking beyond the war to posterity and knowing that
Actual
Data on live subjects in real-world conditions
Will be rare and important for the future
He puts that has diarrhea found that amazing
And heartwarming but it doesn't help us
If we don't use it
So you have to look at this stuff straight in the face and then say
When you're talking about nuclear war you're talking about this and you're not talking about it happening to some foreign people you don't know
You simply have to put the phases of your own friends and family
On the victims and imagine that instead
Hiroshima Survivor
Aasimar koshy
Was in the bathroom
When the Hiroshima bomb went off in the bathroom collapsed around her and she finally got out with the help of someone else
I found her sister dreadfully injured
Mostly from the Heat
Of these bombs that's one thing they had to be
Regular conventional bombs didn't they were somewhat The Flash some people describe it like a bluish white like a flash bulb Flash and Woodburn
Like the worst sunburn all the way to the Bone you've ever seen
But funnily enough it was so quick
But if you have clothing on especially light clothing you can be perfectly protected under the clothing
And your skin falling off everywhere else
When this woman describes getting out of this bathroom after collapsed around her
What happened next and remember this could be your wife or your mother or your sister or your daughter
Quote
Looking around for my sister
I saw her lying sprawled in the corridor
The right side of her body covered with terrible Burns
She'd probably been washing her hands with her right hand stretched over the washbasin when caught by the Searing Heat
I put my sister on my back
And fled barefoot
Tajima Park her face was festering from her Burns at her right I was hanging out
I push the eye back into its socket and try to use a gauze mask to hold it into place but her ear
Airhead melted away and there was nothing to attach the Mask 2
Her mouth was twisted to the right
And she could do no more than whimper for water only the first syllable of the word emerging distinctly
I'm reaching his Gianna Park I laid my sister down on the ground and set off to search for my children
The fires were still burning fiercely
In A Streetcar that have been burned bright red surrounded by people already killed by the fire I saw a woman
Still holding onto a strap and calling for help
The intense heat prevented me from approaching her however
It was nothing I could do
To a man sitting on some Stone steps I said
Come on let's get away from here
And pulled him up by the hand
But as I did so the skin came away from his hand and he fell slowly to the ground
I can see his shadow imprinted clearly on the wall behind him where he had been sitting
Many people called out to me for help or water
Unburned because of having been in the laboratory
I can only bring my hands together and apologize to the people I passed as I search for some sign if my children
As it turned out
None of those who left that morning never came home again
Not my five children my grandfather
My sister Michiko or my cousin
Not a bone remain for me to find and treasure
Our house burned down so that I had not even a photograph to remember them by
My sister has Taco Drew her last breath for days later on the evening of August 10th and Agony from her massive in
Injuries I will never forget the expression on her face when I tried to give her a drop of water
I was alone
And quote
It's not meant to be a tearjerker
It's meant to be an example that you * the number of people
Who are involved in these catastrophes if they happen
When you think about what people are afraid of
Understand that this is a science fiction dystopian type of nightmare story
Until it comes true and in this error the possibility of it coming true
A x appears to be about the same chance
You going to get a
Heads or tails when you flip a coin
And you another
Interesting study into the end of The Human Condition can be made if you asked about the kind of people who advocate
This as a viable and useful strategy
Cuz you might say to yourself we know who would do this who would plan for this
Who could sit down and actually say no this is what we're going to do if the imminent third world war happens and it will so this is what
Will do who does that
If it was some kind of
Mass murderer right
What's the kill people
That's not how the people that do these things see it
They have
What two people on the farther side the rainbows and unicorns Oppenheimer poet side thinking is an aura
Current way of viewing things
But there are a lot of people here that are making calculations about relative disasters
You'll see this later on to when you'll get these people
At these think tanks that will say
And if they're trying to reduce the number of dead in a nuclear war from 40 million to 20 million another peep
People think that simply even trying to do that is morally reprehensible
We should be talking about having no Millions died
Right
But if you read the accounts of people like Curtis LeMay the very very famous
Leader of Strategic Air Command the one who will be
Turned into a stock character in the 1960s movies and whatnot dr. Strangelove Fail-Safe they all have a
Curtis LeMay type the cigar-chomping Air Force guy
Amazed attitude was one that you saw amongst a lot of generals and especially these first and second world war people
Who saw the major nasty part of Modern War
As being its length
And it because the casualties mounted everyday like a meat grinder or anything you could do to shut that down and
Limit the length of time the war went on was humanitarian by its very nature
Even if what it took to do that
Was a shocking amount of violence in a very short time to shock everybody into piece
Lemay did not like what was going on in the Korean War
He wanted to unleash his heavy bombers as he had over Japan in the Second World War
He testified afterwards
But it would have been I'm putting words into his mouth the other more humanitarian approach
This is the philosophy of strategic bombers and believe it or not
It's based on humanitarian
Essex
And just to show you how ingrained it is it is not ironic when they name
Nuclear weapons Delivery Systems as they've done more than once
With names like Peacemaker
And Peacekeeper the the new bomber that will carry out these nuclear destruction places like the stove
Soviet Union happened in 1950 and 1951 is a brand-new B-36
Which is nicknamed
The Peacemaker
Lemay said about
The all-out bombing campaign that they didn't do at the beginning of the Korean War quote
So we go on and don't do it and let the war go on
Over a. Of three and a half or four years we did burn down every town in North Korea and every town
South Korea and what
Killed off 20% of the Korean population
What I'm trying to say is
If once you make a decision to use military force to solve your problem
Then you want to use it
And using overwhelming military force
He was too much and deliberately used too much so that you don't make an error on the other side and not quite have enough
And you roll over everything to start with
Can you close it down just like that
Can you save resources you save lives not only your own but the enemies to
End of recovery is quicker and everybody's back to Peaceful existence hopefully in a shorter. Of time
And quote
So when you wonder about the kind of people that could carry out these kinds of
War aims which may sound apocalyptic to you
These are people flying planes called peacemakers
Who firmly believe
But their way of War
Will end up being more beneficial to everybody
In the end
It's a similar point of view to Douglas MacArthur it's the traditional
Modern 20th century military point of view
Total War saves lives
Limited War prolongs the nastiness
Once again American presidents
Heads of the Soviet Union and China the heads of the western NATO countries
They have a lot of things to worry about
Besides this idea of total victory
Take for example the idea that perhaps
A total or even partial defeat
In an atomic war might have been something in the back of their heads
None the less the way
The Korean war ends up as something that
Either side of that total war vs limited war debate could probably use at ammunition in their discussion
The friends Harry Truman might say listen by middle of 1951 both sides are at the Armistice table talk
Walking and working out a deal
To which the friends of Curtis LeMay and Douglas MacArthur my counter by saying yeah but the talks will go on for two years and so
Soldiers will die on both side the entire time
To which the Harry Truman supporters could then reply yet but we didn't get World War 3
You say that
Yes the situation in Korea was a nightmare
Lots of casualties lots of dead lots of civilians
Bad all the way around but it wasn't nuclear war
Presidents are often
Fortune do
Making lesser of two evil choices in this case
Got to be pretty darn bad of an outcome for nuclear war to not be the greater evil
The 1952
The greater evil is getting worse
I think you have to say that
Harry Truman deserves a lot of credit for getting us out of his entire
Terms in office without
Ascending up bombing anyone with nuclear weapons after the second world war ended because I think
It was a flip of a coin whether or not we did that
Remember all he would have had to have done is listened to some of his military advisers and he would have
As Truman's
Turman office wind down you can see that it's easy to say
And if the world is playing a three-dimensional geopolitical game of nuclear chess
They're playing by the rules laid down by Truman and let's be honest the people that he was playing
Will your chest with also Joseph Stalin in the Soviet it was a
Takes two to tango situation
In between the two major sides
Things are hammered out in there. You know him put some Europeans and third world Nations I mean
This is a global effort to Cobble together a way to deal with what is becoming
An ever-increasing threat and a threat that is moving so quickly
But the sheer speed of technological change
Is one of the most destabilizing parts of the entire equation
At what point do you get used to this
I mean we've been pondering the question about whether humans can adapt to their weapons technology
Let's remember that once upon a time people didn't have to adapt this quickly
Throughout most of human history the pace of change was much less quick than it is today if you could take 1950s Atomic technology
Give it to the ancient Egyptians and say this isn't going to change very much for the neck
15 Generations take some time figure it out
Does the extra time they get help them do it or I mean it's just
Thinking of ancient Egyptians with
In a nuclear technology too weird to even contemplate
The point is is that
You know I try to remember who these people are true miniature grandfather
Surrounded by other grandfather
You ever had to help your grandfather with text off
This is a guy
Who is sitting there listening to different nuclear physicist describe the pros and cons of different ideas and pushing different points of view
He has to decide which one he agrees with
Why do I have an image
I've been having to call is Kayden College to come home and help him figure out where to turn the nuclear bomb off I can't find that button
Truman kind of looks like that weiner president
Non-specialist technical error
To the one where you have to referee
Competing arguments between physicists like Oppenheimer & Teller
Requires a different kind of mind different kind of an approach and maybe a different kind of background
As I said I feel kind of lucky we got out of that era intact but when you look at the last year of Truman's presidency
You can see
The tsunami of dangers mounting in the distance and you just
It's hard to have confidence that the haberdasher from Independence Missouri who's already exceeded
Vacations you know his flexibility
Hard to see him flexible enough to deal
With some of the things 1952 brings on MP4 example
Here's a guy who's advisors and administration
Help craft as we said the rules
How you play this
Global chess match
Two-player game
And in October 1952 the United Kingdom explodes their first atomic bomb
Now they're in the nuclear Club
Now it's a more than two person games
Battle changer Dynamics
Especially when
The part that really bothers everybody about the UK test becomes clear which is that they won't be the last power to join the new
Nuclear Club
In a few years are you going to have 10 15 20 Powers with atomic bombs
So in order now for humans to adapt to this new weapon they now have to adapt to more people having it so the Dynamics get much more
Complex
Now you act out the change in the power of the weaponry
Less than a month after the
United Kingdom
Demonstrates there in atomic power
United States demonstrates
They have the technology and it works
To build a super bomb
They actually exploded
Only a couple of days before the US presidential election
In the power of the bomb
Stunning
Truly
Paradigm shift
The test occurs on an island in the Pacific
When it explodes
There's a fireball more than 3 miles wide
Lightning crackling inside it
The craters more than 6000
Feet in diameter the holes more than 150 ft deep
It's somewhere between 4 and 5
A hundred times more powerful
Then either of the bombs that were dropped in the second world war four to five hundred times more power
The most kind of interesting about this. Compared to our own is
How much of this weapons development of psychological
Again to have a psychological Edge in your opponent's be able to use things like deterrence
Effectively
Everyone had to know you had these weapons and so
Today you would imagine government wouldn't even tell anybody about any of this stuff with the United States announce these things
We have this weapon now we have that weapon
Because that was important to its ability to be used
The problem with something
Like the thermonuclear weapons the hydrogen bomb is that they're so powerful now
That they're in effect working
Against the idea that you can use them for deterrent right the bigger they get
The less willing
Your enemy your adversary is to think you'll use it
Joseph Stalin is quoted as saying he thinks
An impromptu he said that the
Public opinion in the peace movement around the world will ring in their government skin
No one's going to use a Megaton
You know powerful weapon
I want us because World opinion won't stand for it
And there's some truth to that
But if you're the military and you want to use these weapons or your the intellectuals in the political Associates of the
President can you want your deterrence to stilbite and work
How do you deal with that Dynamic right that the weapons are so powerful No One Believes you use them
Make smaller versions of them
It's
A decent argument to ask whether the most destabilizing effect
I'm inventions from 1952
You can make an argument for all three is it nuclear proliferation starting
Is the invention of the super the hydrogen bomb
Or is it the
Beginning of the Revolution that we call Dad a tactical nuclear weapons are Battlefield nuclear weapon
And the funny thing about it is it some of the people who worked on limit Oppenheimer got roped into this. He was doing a good thing I'm going
Create smaller weapons because if I create smaller nuclear weapons the military won't be tempted to use the bigger ones
Turn down
He was wrong about that
In a famous quote that when he
Years later tried to explain his thinking and he said to understand where I was then you would have had to have seen
The Air Force's War plan for 1951 census was those goddamn just thing I ever saw
It scared him so much 500
Atomic bombs dropped on Russia
Eddie thought I'll give them something they can use instead of those it turned out as as most thinkers
Assume today the tactical nuclear weapons
Open up the door dangerously to an escalation very quickly to the very big bombs that Oppenheimer hope would never be used
Did you have the smaller bombs instead
Honest mistake though we're in new territory here
Technologically speaking aren't we another reason maybe you don't want Truman running the show
He's about as well as maybe you could help for
The guy who wins the presidency in 1952 is a very interesting choice for the Sarah and I think more more historians or realize
I think now when I was a kid
The kind of a different View
AB General and now
In November 1952 President elect Dwight David Eisenhower
It's interesting I saw a couple of historians I was reading were speculating it's not far off from them decent speculation Maybe
That partly with the United States was going for here in terms of the electric was they had just had a president and a general sort of
Disagreeing about how you fight this war in Korea and all these questions about nuclear weapons in this whole new world and everything what if you just
Just got a person with military experience put them in the top job and then when the general is arguing with the president the president
There are some people who speculate that Dwight Eisenhower with kind of
Feeling like he stepped down
In terms of responsibility when he took the American presidency for a job cuz he was coming down for like commander of
NATO
It was the general of the West is one
Writer I was reading called in the general of the West
Now he's just merely the president of the United States
Eisenhower's an interesting guy his administration by the way will follow a lot of the same Cycles with the Truman one didn't even ask
Castration after him wheel 2
In part because they'll find that they have a lot of the same pressures
And disincentives and incentives working on them that the previous administration also did
And you often try to adopt the obvious solution in those cases which
Each one gets excessively so
As we said the Trump Administration seems to have
Established a pattern that will be followed by
Subsequent Administration
In Eisenhower's case though
A bunch of things happen basically right at the beginning of the Eisenhower Administration that completely upset the geopolitical chessboard
14 ways to give him
Well both opportunities and dangers The Truman never had to face
Start with the fact
It pretty much right after Eisenhower actually takes office January 20th 1953
Joseph Stalin dies
March 5th
1953 and he doesn't die
Like a long slow lingering death where Russia has lots of time to prepare the Soviets and lots of time to prepare for
What you going to do afterwards
He has like a stroke or something so it's it's here today gone tomorrow or here today on my way to going very soon
What the hell happened in the Soviet Union if there's no Joseph Stalin
This guy's been running the show personally so long in that country
That there's a
Logical question that happened and it happens right when Stalin
Debilitated in a mobile and paralyzed from the stroke in urine-soaked pajamas lay on his floor unable to
Communicate his underlings are outside his room
Outside the door talking on here we do
There is no
Logical successor to Joseph Stalin there was no
Organized system that dictated well here's your Vice Premier who takes over
Once Upon a Time all that stuff it been around Stalin
I'd come up in a system with lots of brilliant intellectuals and people from the original Revolution people like Lenin
Great people Stalin killed a lot of those people on his way to power
And for more than 20 years
He can easily say the same thing at Louis XIV
The French King famously said about
You know his relationship to the country Louis XIV said I am the state
The state is ME
End
Joseph Stalin could have been the poster boy
It came up when you Google the phrase Cult of Personality
Merrifield one of his successors will call it just that
And yet the problem is
Is that this guy's personality was completely infused on his country a country by the way as we've pointed out before
Badly traumatized by a surprise attack
In the Second World War
You add to that
The Stalin view of Communism which is also paranoid which again maybe
Just finely-tuned self-defense antenna at work here instead
But that the
Non communist Powers were going to try to take you over add to that that you'd already been surprise attack added that that you're paranoid dictator
Your type anyway
And isn't it interesting that that is all infused
On the player that the historical roll of the dice just manages to give
The Free World
When you have your first ever nuclear chess match will you play Joseph Stalin
Going to be a little Machiavellian right you're not going to be all Peace Love poets and Robert Oppenheimer
When you're playing that guy and by the way
I got quite a few books on the Soviet side of the story and the problem with the Soviet side of the story is he once again it's all
Call Stalin and you can't figure the guy out so you're taking public statements in this nut
What the
Question that was put to several people like Andrei sakharov and others that have been involved in the Soviet nuclear program
Is what if the US
Egg on the hole
You know
Full force Robert Oppenheimer band this stuff route
What would the
Soviets and Joseph Stalin done
And to a man they all say all it would have been seen as weakness installing would have pushed forward with his weapons program
I mean I believed it behind the scenes at all happening anyway
In other words
If the US
And Britain and NATO and all of them had gone
Into a Robert Oppenheimer dream mode
That would not necessarily have had any sort of real reciprocation
From the other side because the other side was Joseph Stalin
And as of
March
6th 1953
For the first time in the nuclear age it's not
Truman never had the opportunity to deal with anyone else
When Stalin dies new things happen the world changes a little bit and
Eisenhower has a chance for example
To come out with a proposal that's known as the Atoms for Peace proposal
Now I have to make up a disclaimer here
Nothing can be trusted from this era
Nothing
Alluded to this earlier
For example
These presidents from Truman dies and they will all have two faces to them
I don't know which one is real
They will have one face
Where they will say you can never use these weapons mean Eisenhower famously said you couldn't have a nuclear war the running of the bulls
Closers to scoop Up the Bodies
In from the streets
You'll have other statements where they will say they do not ever question or willingness to use these weapons
So you have to say it for deterrence to work but did they secretly believe that you couldn't use these weapons or is it the Opera
Did you know some of these depends on how cynical you are as a writer but some of these writers and historians will say none of the plan
Entire time was to Nuke everything but you just can't say that in public so you get up there and have an Atoms for Peace
This program will you talk about working together to ban these terrible weapons
I will say that I can't imagine our leaders today having something like Eisenhower speech to the United Nations where he
In 1953
Made the whole situation out
Now whether this is some sort of cynical geopolitical
You know the public relations toy or whether he's serious and it's hard to know Eisenhower with a deep and interesting and complex character
But everything that we've been talking about in this program is stuff we know now
The people in the time.
Are just as Whiplash by technology is Harry Truman was an in 1953 Eisenhower
But this is right after the hydrogen bomb concept is proven
Lays out the steaks to a bunch of people who maybe didn't realize exactly how threatened they were
I feel impelled to speak today in a language that
Innocent
Is new
One which I
Let's spend so much of my life in the military profession
What are preferred
Never
To you
That's new language
Is the language
Of Atomic Warfare
The atomic age has moved forward at such a pace
That every citizen of the world
Should have some comprehension
At least in comparative terms
Of the expense
Of this development
Of the utmost significance
To everyone
Clearly
If the peoples of the world are to conduct an intelligent search for peace
They must be armed
With a significant facts
Oxidase
Except
My recital of atomic danger and Power
Is necessarily stated
In United States perm
For these are the only incontrovertible fact
That I know
I need hardly point out
Do this assembly however
That's the subject is Google
Not merely National
On July 16th
United States asset off the world
First atomic explosion
Since that day
In 1945
United States of America has conducted 42
Test exposure
Atomic bombs today
Are more than 25 times as power
How's the weather
With which the atomic age dawn
While hydrogen weapons
Aryan the Rangers
Of millions of tons
TNT equivalent
Today
United States stockpile of atomic weapons
Which of course increases daily
Exceeds by many time
The total equivalent
Of the total of all bombs
Ammo sales
That came from every plane
And every gun in every theater war in all of the years of World War II
A single Air Group
Weather afloat
Orlando Pace
Can now deliver to any reachable Target
A destructive cargo
Exceeding in power
Alabama
That fell on Britain
In all of World War II
That's from the famous Atoms for Peace speech
When Eisenhower like Truman before him
Will evoke the Specter of the world's great cities lying in Ruins
The cultural achievements of the past of thousands of years of
I've worked to build up to destroyed mankind having to
Arise From the Ashes of irradiated in destroyed civilization
Just in case you were unaware of the steaks
There are so many different ways you can view people
Right we all understand that in modern history
Postmodern history
Makes it the most apparent because
You can find statements from all these people
Contradicting themselves
Private statements versus public statements
Diaries that they write in that they assume will someday be published
Where's the secret diaries that they never want anyone else to see
What is PR vs. what is behind the scenes
I mean when Harry Truman talks about the Terrible Things he's nuclear weapons can do
He's the same guy that
Gave the go-ahead to make them
When Eisenhower give the speech is about
These existential dangers mankind faces he is at the same time solving a budgetary
Problem
By deciding to rely on
A strategy with nuclear weapons that will be known as massive retaliation
Which Eisenhower do you buy or is it some sort of blend of the two
And listen as we said good luck getting to the core of any of these public figures they're so multi-layered that
To know you actually had what they really believed that be tough to do
In anytime.
Add to that the fact that we all know when history compresses these human beings into one-dimensional figures you lose so much of the new
You want to meet imagine
If you made it into the history books 100 years from now
How much your life would be compressed into a few bullet points
Did that sort of really give the true picture of you
Bonita J Robert Oppenheimer
Dean acheson's too much of a poet
Wasn't always too much of a poet
He was often opposed to nuclear weapons but not always
Sometimes his opposition was moral but sometimes it was technical
And sometimes he
So good applications for nuclear power and weapon
So he's been
Turned into an archetype
My history as well even buy me
So
But they're all that in mind and even with all that said
Eisenhower is unusually confusing and misleading
On purpose
In his book Ike's Bluff
Author Evan Thomas weaves in
Eisenhower's near addiction
Two strategy card games
And
In a drawers that into Eisenhower's conduct of world affairs and how he handled the various car
Cards in his hand if you will a Dell with the uncertainties involved in other people's hands
He was I guess
A huge poker player but an even bigger bridge player and Bridge I guess it's played by
My all sorts of generals and politicians and strategists
They feel that it better represents the
Great geopolitical game
Then Chester because in chess you can see all the pieces openly
Whereas in a card game your hand is known only to you
Adversaries have their hands secret you don't know what's in the deck you have to do a lot of bluffing
And this is where Eisenhower's
You know deliberate
Opaqueness and confusion
And misleading nature and ability to
Bluff his way into various situations seem to correspond to being a master
Bridge player I mean if you're going to have somebody sit in the chair
To represent your side in this historical
Psychological game of strategy and uncertainty for the very highest of stakes
Don't you want a gamer
And it sounds like you're talkin strategy games
Eisenhower was one
And he was good
He's got a new opponent as we said and you got to be breathing a sigh of relief cuz
Facing Joseph Stalin in the Octagon at that game
When he really didn't even have nuclear weapons imagine him during the 1950s when he really did get the ability to just start striking to you
Atwell
Perish the thought he's gone though
Replacing him in the chair is one of his subordinates
And it's a fascinating guy
To be playing against during this era cuz now you have the general of the West finally the West gets in there with one of these heavy
Wake candidates okay bring on your best shot and their best shot is a guy named Nikita Khrushchev
Who I love
Nikita Khrushchev is one of the great success stories you're ever going to find
It's like a
Forget the Abe Lincoln Log Cabin Story I mean it's it's
Nikita Khrushchev was born a peasant
The only reason that he finally is running one of the two great superpowers in this era
Is because of the Soviet Communist Revolution the Bolshevik Revolution the top of the czar
Before the first world war is over and totally up bands that Society
And puts people in power and authority
Who were
You're mocking at the manure out of the barn when they were teenagers
Nikita Khrushchev is a peasant peasant he uses all the terminology he'll be at the big meetings without he's always use
Using these peasant sayings that are supposed to be deeply philosophical no one else in the room has any idea what they mean
To this guy was so
The United States had the haberdasher from Missouri
Running the nuclear are still for a while and trying to adjust
The Soviet Union's about to gain the kind of power where maybe they could begin to actually as opposed to Theory
Ethically
Threaten the United States with atomic weaponry
And that gets given to a guy who was born a peasant and he's just
Fascinator
This is a man who got a huge challenge ahead of him and we certainly in the west never understood this was all going
It's still not well understood including by me
Maybe least of all by me
The crew Chef was
Part of a group that comes to power in the Soviet Union in Canton perhaps you could say
Guiding that state
To a soft Landing from stalinism
This was not some consensus though
And it were powerful entities in that state vying for leadership also
It appeared much more closely to the old Stalin line
Professor David Holloway in his excellent book Stalin
And the bomb
Talks about how
It was really the pressure is caused by the reality of nuclear war
That forced some of these leaders to take it at a different look at
Even their Orthodox Communists in the sense. Bolshevik and very stalinist
View of the entire world reality
Because Professor Holloway says that
It was Stalin's conviction
I was connected to his views on
Marxism and the inevitability of a war between the imperialist in the Communist States that within 10 to 20 years war
World War 3 was coming
And of course is everyone was Awakening to World War 3 was going to be nuclear weapons in devastation
1955 War plan that the USA commission to check out
How many people died
If the US carried out their proposed strikes against the Soviet Union when World War 3 broke out in the number came back to be 60
And a decent number of those people coming from the countries like Poland and Hungary and all those places that were sort of under the thumb of the
Have the Soviets how do you even justify that right
Sorry you were captive person right now but we're going to Nuke you in order to
For you up there eventually you burn down your village in order to save it
But all the way talks about kruschev in his
Group getting
Power and beginning to talk about
Things that are famous in the history books like
Peaceful coexistence
This violated Stalin view Holloway says
The inevitable war that was coming because if the inevitable War this coming is Armageddon will that'll mess up your long-term planning
I want it
Holloway writes this
About true chef and his people trying to
Walk back
Communist ideology
In order to prevent it from inevitably running into global thermonuclear war
Direct quote
My asserting the capitalism and socialism can coexist for a long time
The new leaders of the Soviet Union
We're rejecting Stalin's vision of Another World War within 15 to 20 years of the end of World War II
Peaceful coexistence in quotation marks
What is defined as the alternative to nuclear war
Has the policy that had to be followed if nuclear war was to be avoided
And quote
On the way then tell the story the cruise ship it told about meeting the much more hardliner Mao the leader of China
And now is still talking in terms of the
Assumed to come all out war against the capitalists
And cruise ship already seems to be now
Have moved on from that this is part of what starts to create a schism
Amongst the Communist States
Almost the way you would see religious
Break off's
Two or three or four hundred years before this era
And all of a sudden the change in religious Doctrine
Dogma
Messed up enough people so that we're going to go this way and you're going to go that way
The United States in the west saw the Communist up to this. Is a monolithic block
Who took their orders from Moscow and all of a sudden
Some of these communist countries are beginning to have disagreements with each other some of them are geopolitical
But some of them are ideological
But according to Professor Holloway people like cruise ships see this is
Something that is simply bowing to reality in a nuclear world
He's a quote
Peaceful coexistence did not mean ideological coexistence however
Nor did Intel renunciation of the struggle with imperialism
But that struggle had to be conducted in such a way as to avoid nuclear war
And quote
In other words the new leaders of the Soviet Union are also
Trying to figure out
How you operate
Under the old rules in the world
Where you have neuclear weapons and where they are increasingly getting more and more powerful
The Soviet Union exploded its first Hydrogen weapon
Why you get a disagreement about this August 12th 1953 is a good date for this
Some of the real nitpickers will take
Nonetheless over the next year or two the
Soviets will refine the weapon to appoint when no one will argue anymore that they too or a thermonuclear power
The equation in terms of the global Dynamics will be altered though
Buy the big us test that goes off on March 1st 1954
This is a test by the way that was not supposed to be this large
Instead turns out to be the largest explosion ever set off by the United States
To this day
More than 15 megatons
Aldi
Bravo test
Just I'm the Fireball was like 4 miles wide and everything just gets bigger and larger butt
What made Bravo so
Completely over-the-top in terms of waking up
The public to a level where the alarm buttons really were raised on a wide range of
I've demographics you know where I was before
If you were a European living on a likely nuclear Battlefield you are always aware what might happen to you
If you were a person
Living in India
With not a care in the world of these Cold War events at this particular time.
You would notice what a lot of the rest of the world noticed about the Castle Bravo test
Was a radiological disaster
And because it was so much larger than experts
And I predicted that it's opened up the door to being wrong about some of the stuff there were physicists who had worst case scenario
Dies in their nightmares
You from before that. The thought of you did this wrong the whole atmosphere could catch on fire and all these kinds of things that sound crazy but
I'm not a physicist so I don't even know if that's possible
But this test showed that just because you cordon off what you think is a safe area and you try to make his own where you can see what these weapons can do
Who doesn't make them
Safe
They cordoned off his own and people outside the zone
Got radiologically sick more than a hundred miles away famously
A Japanese fishing boat outside the exclusionary Zone with bombarded with radiation
Immense amounts of fall out whenever the air you know when these
Just happen in these Pacific
Coral reefs and whatnot are
Atomized for lack of a better word and turned into like micro dust particles
And blown up into the mushroom cloud up into the atmosphere all of them irradiated
And when they fall back down to earth
They can make you quote sick and die soon if you're close by but even if you're far away
Gets into your water gets into your milk gets into your food chain starts affecting people
And after the Castle Bravo test
The rest of the world began to watch
The giant geopolitical card game or three-dimensional chess game between the great powers
It's sort of a spectator audience and
In this particular game the audience made a difference
And both sides tried to appeal to the audience
The audience in this case metaphorically speaking
Is global public opinion
Something that really comes of age in this. In part because
The whole understanding that nuclear weapons use even just testing
On the part of a single Global power
Could affect everyone
All the sudden everyone had skin in the game and by the way
The era of colonialism
Was over for the most part and major
Countries like Britain and France and others were shedding their colonies their former colonies in their former possessions
And these places were forming their own governments and had sovereignty of Their Own
Jennifer change in
They kind of sometimes look at the Cold War the way the man from Mars that we talked about earlier would
As Outsiders who were only worried about the idea that listen I don't care what your beef is with each other just don't pollute the
World we all need
And this new power block
Matter
Increasingly so
As communication and mass media allow people to be involved in the conversation
And all of a sudden you had
Groups of people that could be used in this discussion over how we go forward
In terms of how we learn to cope with our weapons technology
The group of scientist the Einstein of the Bertrand Russell's in the Oppenheimer types
Could all of a sudden appeal directly to World opinion and try to harness it
To push more for their Viewpoint of how you
Adapt to these Weapons Systems adapt to these Weapons Systems in their opinion
By getting rid of War not getting rid of the weapons of war cuz it's their opinion
At the weapons are there and we just pledged not to use eventually someone's going to grab one make one whatever you need to do
Especially if they're losing the third world war so that they don't
The scientist are saying
You know it's going to be tough
Going to have to stop this whole policy of war that you've been using your whole civilized
History
The issue something in 1955
Again and directly at Global public opinion
They do it in a press conference how modern is that
Where Bertrand Russell or old friend too
For the Soviets got the bomb
I need nightmares of London lying in Ruins and thought maybe we should nuke the Soviets first
He and Albert Einstein in one of his last gigs
And others would get out there and push something
Known to history as the
Russell Einstein Manifesto
And it starts off with Bertrand Russell telling the media this line
Is a good way to start off a piece
If you want to say basically just so you know we're directing this towards Global public opinion and we're on it
Side
The manifesto began with Russell saying quote
I am bringing the warning pronounced
By the signatories meaning of their Manifesto
To the notice of all powerful governments of the world
Any Earnest hope that they may agree to allow their citizens to survive
And quote
The peace then goes on to talk about the power of nuclear weapons it then goes on to talk about how
They understand that the idea
Getting rid of War sounds pie-in-the-sky
But the power of these weapons has changed everything including the power to pollute
But they've been come on to say as pie-in-the-sky if you will is the abolition of War sounds
You must keep your eyes
On what failure in this round with me
It's very similar
To this idea
Sending people
To go look at the death camps five minutes after The Liberation happen
Manifestos quote
The abolition of War will demand distasteful limitations of national sovereignty
But what perhaps impedes understanding of the situation more than anything else
Is that the term Mankind in quotes
Feels vague and abstract
People scarcely realizing imagination that the dangerous to themselves
And their children and their grandchildren
And I don't lie to a dimly apprehended Humanity
They can scarcely bring themselves to grasp that they individually
And Those whom they love are in imminent danger of perishing agonisingly
And so they hope that perhaps War may be allowed to continue
Provided modern weapons are prohibited
And quote
Beijing guoan
Explain why that's a pipe dream
The point is it that all of a sudden
These scientists can appeal directly to the general public out there and they can position them
I'm as a block of power opposed to the governments of the world are continuing to act the way governments in the world of active
Trevor
The Russell Einstein group of scientists has found
Hrblock of support
And it's International in nature
Now there are other great intellectual thinkers out there
Who will form the Counterpoint to these people would talk about them already people that started
No getting together at major universities to places like Yale and whatnot these other intellectuals who don't buy this idea that we can change
So fundamentally that we could Outlaw War
They begin
Trying to think of how
Once again you live with these weapons in a way that more closely corresponds to how history has shown we're likely to
To behave
And if the worst happens
How do you somehow mitigate the
Worst case scenario
Earlier we had said that Eisenhower was a good strategic card game player if you were going to be involved in this kind of igloo
Mobile game if you will
Didn't you want to have a gamer in that position
But in a country of hundreds of millions of people why would you stop
At one good gamer
If you were playing a chess game for the survival of the world and your side wings you want
All you're intelligent people getting together somewhere and analyzing it
Studying the game if you will
Analyzing every move impossible counter move
Every variable that might crop up I mean if it's a card game him
We're holding atomic bomb cards in our hand
And somebody draws an ace of clubs in a minute you know what we do
Those people began to coalesce after the second world war these amazingly intelligent intellectuals
And will eventually find themselves working together in places like the famous Rand Corporation
But I didn't start that way
They started by essentially asking the kind of questions
That are a function of the time
The sort of higher questions of the store that got Truman in trouble with MacArthur over War aims right
Mean famously
One of these people who are the founding fathers of what today we would call civilian defense intellectuals
Was a guy named Bernard Brody
And Brody will famously get involved
Initially with all this just because they are forced ask him to look at them
World War 2 bombing results and to analyze them
But this eventually led to Brody asking fundamental questions like
Okay well
How big are bombs do we need to do what in order to achieve watching all these deep questions that in general
The military guys weren't thinking about this wasn't part of their gig
In Korea MacArthur job was to win the war not to figure out the political situation afterwards and all this but
All these people are rising the nuclear are these intellectual for pointing out that there is no separation between those things anymore how you feel
Fight the war
Will determine so many other things
For example
One of the big problems that Brody had with the entire War plan that guys like Curtis LeMay had come up with a nuke to Soviet Union
All at one time
Quickly as possible get it over with
What are you lost every bit of Leverage
But you might have Brody argue that the game goes on even when nuclear weapons start falling
And that the way things turn out
You know the difference between maybe a hundred million lives could be how you play the game once the bombs start falling
Here's the thing all these people at the Rand Corporation in these defense intellectuals
AR
Often characterized as a combination of like mr. Spock
And Sheldon Cooper from The Big Bang Theory
People with great mathematics and economics backgrounds were so great at crunching numbers
But often seemed detached from The Real World blood guts reality
You know what they're studying at the worst case scenario happens
Unless it's hard to argue with some of the things they say for example
Nebrodi is famously said early on
That the city's as hostages you know your adversaries cities held hostage is a lot more valuable than having a bunch of car
Corpses made
Lemay's playing freely Corpses
Brody wanted to preserve
Flexibility even after the atomic bomb dropped and he pointed it out this way Fred Kaplan in his 1980's classic
The Wizards of Armageddon
Disgusted that he said quote
Brody reasoned that the final surrender of the Japanese in the Pacific War resulted not from the atom bomb
Just dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki but from the implicit threat of more atom bombs on their way if it
The Japanese did not give up then
Likewise he writes
The Soviets would more likely stop fighting after receiving some destructive blows
Knowing that if they did not stop
Their cities would be the next targets to get hit
If however we blew up their cities at the very outset of the War II bargaining lever would be blown up along with them
Hostages have no value once they are killed
Consequently the Soviets would feel no inhibitions about blowing up American cities in return
Hardly an outcome that would serve the interests of American Security
And quote
It's a combination of coldly dispassionately logical
And at the same time and its own way
Especially when compared to the atomic Blitz plan that the Air Force had in place
Humanitarian
These are the people that will coalesce and Brody is one of them Herman Kahn is another John Von Neumann will be involved in Venoy minutes
Call by some people the most intelligent man who ever lived
I can very debatable but you know if you're anywhere in that conversation
You have an incredible mind and in the 1920s Von Neumann famously in a poker game
Devises the modern version of what you could call the mathematical theory of games because that's what they did call it
Today we just called Game Theory
The standard definition of Game Theory
Is a mathematically precise method
Determining rational strategies in the face of critical uncertain
Sounds like it might be pretty useful
Any game doesn't it
Or a war for that matter
Or a war game
There have been antecedents of course before Von Neumann
Others work on it afterwards and including Von Neumann some more
But by this time these are the kind of people that want to employ those kinds of theories
To analyze
This game
Patagonia running to the same problem
Mm electrical to want to see mankind evolved away from war running into
Speed of the pace of change
Everything keeps evolving so quickly
The minute you may think you have this Atomic poker game figured out
With one deck somebody decides looking elegant play with another deck attitude
Upsets
Your Paradigm on a regular basis
It's arguable that perhaps the biggest destabilizer between 1950 and 1960s the growth of missile technology
Witching at the end of the second world war the Soviets and the West were both
Scouring Germany as they occupied it to grab as many Nazi scientists so you could because
A couple of key areas German scientists were head of the West and the Soviets
Missile technology for example
They've been using at the end of the war missile called the V2
Against places like London
And suspiciously
For about the next 10 years some of these missiles would look like carbon copies of the V2 the United States would grab one of these scientific any burner
Von Braun who would of course be influential in the US Space Program later
The space programs themselves of both the Soviet Union and the United States had
We'll call it Dual Purpose technological applicability
Because when the Soviets launched the first satellite into space Sputnik in 1957
Some people worry that the Soviets are now ahead in space technology but a lot of people understand that if you can put a satellite in space
The tip of a rocket
You can put a bomb on the tip of a rocket and send it to the United States
The Realty change for me reading all this material
Was the modern material makes it clear that even though the time the United States was most frightened of nuclear war hitting them
When they were building bomb shelters in the backyard in Nebraska
The Soviet Union probably had very little chance
I'm launching an attack on the us as we said earlier
First of all any attack during that period would have involved aircraft in the United States had a wonderful defensive Air Force that could have shot down anything
But it's missiles to change that
They also start putting them on submarines which changes everything to
Difference between 1950
1960 in terms of trying to control
And Corral the threat in the growing
Instability
Is Mike Davis
Nuclear
Expert Joseph cirincione points out
After discussing the Atoms for Peace idea that Eisenhower throughout their they're also be a summit 1955 between Eisenhower and Khrushchev
I'm trying to
To break the tension somewhat
Bikini from Chevys and came to the United States in the late fifties and visited
LED around by Vice President Nixon and oppression toe
Swimming to get to know you know size 2
Humanize each other a little bit
For every
Decrease intentions on one hand there was something
On the other hand
To make up for it
And the complexity and increasing power of the weapons just made the job of anyone who wanted to control these things
Darn near impossible listen to Joseph cirincione Rundown
The growth
In weapons technology in the 10 years between 1950 and 1960 hero quote
While Atoms for Peace was promoting nuclear technology for peaceful purposes
The US military was equipping their troops with thousands of nuclear weapons adapting them for use in New
Nuclear depth charges nuclear Torpedoes nuclear mines nuclear artillery and even a nuclear
Your bazooka
This infantry weapon called the Davy Crockett
Would fire a nuclear warhead about half a mile
The United States and the Soviet Union develop strategies to fight and win a nuclear war
Created vast nuclear weapon complexes and began deploying intercontinental ballistic missiles and fly
Lisa ballistic-missile submarines
The effect of Abandonment of international control efforts and the race to build a numerical and then they qualitate
Nuclear advantage
Resulted in the American nuclear Arsenal mushrooming from just under 400 weapons in 1952
/ 20000 by 1960
The Soviet Arsenal likewise
Jump from five Warheads in 1950
2 roughly 1600 in 1960
The United States was ahead
But afraid
And quote
When you think about
The situation that Harry Truman was trying to cope with
From 45 to 52
And what seemed complex at the time
Look at how all of this stuff
Makes that look like a card game with a single deck and by the time Eisenhower leaves office
He's playing multi-level chess or
Atomic poker with 9 decks when I go in at the same time
But he's grown with it
Please learn how to play this game he started and stepped in at a time when it was much less complicated
The Truman Show Them his hand says this is what's in my hand this is what we think is in his hand this is my strategy good luck
And handed his hand of cards over to
And one of the great Gamers the guy you would say if you had to hand pick them might have been uniquely qualified for this time
Time in this place
But he's also the head of a system
It doesn't pick their People based on qualification the person that gets to sit in the chair and play the other side
And with the world as your steaks in the card game of the chess match
Is chosen by the Electoral
Are they can choose anybody
1960 will be Dwight Eisenhower's last year in office
The Constitution mandates that you get no more than two terms his time is up
He's done anyway the presidency wipes people out anyways and health problems
It's time for someone new the problem is is
Who is qualified to take over the game
Reminds an hour
And what if you get someone in there
Who plays
Corley
Voters in the United States have always had a lot of responsibility
But when they were voting se4
President Roosevelt for reelection in 1940 they weren't voting for the most dangerous human being of all time
When they go to the polls in 1960 to vote for someone to replace the retiring Dwight Eisenhower
What exactly what they're voting for
For all his power and authority in the 1930s and 1940s Franklin Delano Roosevelt
Didn't have Atomic weapons
Dequindre taking us to nuclear war like presidents after 1945
What's more he operated in a constitutional framework
Especially for the big Wars
Require the involvement of other people
The Congress for example he couldn't do this by himself
1945 the Advent of atomic weapons changed all that the Truman Administration took that power
To themselves rightly or wrongly they had some good reasons but you can disagree about them
But it's solidified
The power to use these extraordinary weapons in the hands of a single human being
Don't ever had that kind of power
And US presidents
The 1945 on are infinitely more dangerous in the worst case scenario
And they were before then
And we Americans tend not to think of
Our own people as
Scary and dangerous
But you can bet that in other countries
1960 places that
Might be on the receiving end of a worst-case scenario
People for example living in the old Soviet Union
Those people certainly would have recognized the potential Danger
Are the most dangerous figure in world history
A person that will be determined
Bye
The particular Williams
The US electorate
Of course the problem one might ask is if you have issues with that
Who would you rather have pick that person
And think about it carefully because the power that person is getting
More
Scary
All the time
President that succeeds Eisenhower will be the first one to control the US nuclear Arsenal
In an era where a push-button Holocaust
Becomes possible
During Eisenhower's time
A nuclear war broken out the vast majority of it would have been fought with airplanes dropping bombs
The next president of the United States is going to have enough intercontinental ballistic missiles deployed
So that you have the metaphorical cuz he really would just give an order in a code and all that
Are the metaphorical red button is they call it
It becomes a reality during this era think of how dangerous that human being is he the person is going to have to make a nuclear decision potential
Chili
With only minutes
To debate
And decided
Washington being disqualified for that
How much are the qualifications if you could mold your perfect
President and Steward of that kind of power and authority what should a professional or education or purse
Personal background would you want
Would you want someone who was a politician
Controlling the nuclear Arsenal
With your finger on the button or
Maybe you think that's something that you could trust a
Businessperson more someone more tune to the question the prophet Lawson and corporate survivability and maybe there's a
A lot of things you could argue that that would be beneficial
Or maybe
Maybe you want someone who thinks about nothing
But this geopolitical Atomic card game all the time and you want one of those mathematical economist
I'm someplace like the Rand Corporation put them in
The White House
Well maybe you want to go a totally different direction you need someone who's got them or
Big picture
Humanity side of this like the
People at the
Russell Einstein Manifesto set
Remember your Humanity
And forget the rest right you want one of those get maybe you want a philosopher
Or maybe you want someone
Who's very religious maybe you wanted Gandhi type president through the first Buddhist president I realize it's a long shot but
Extraordinary times call for Extraordinary Measures
Or maybe you want to recreate the Eisenhower years and get yourself a general
Although
You get charm after term after term in the White House occupied by a military leader starts to look a little Wiggy in it
Democratic Republic. Net
What's more
What made Eisenhower so particularly I thought suited as I sent for the role
Wasn't that he was a general
And because of that he was a Super Hawk
It's because he carried The credibility of being a general
I was actually less hawkish than his military advisers a lot of the time
Sometimes they would want to be
More whiskey and more muscular and it would be eisenhour that would say no
I had Eisenhower instead been a civilian like Truman maybe these
Incredible World War Two Guys who made up a lot of the military advisors in this era they were big powerful karizmatik figures themselves
During this critical. We were trying to get the formula right the guy who's
Student
In the civilian role and predicted the civilian rule was himself a military guy and could push back against the general
You know you can't
Accuse Eisenhower of not understanding the military situation
But now Eisenhower was leaving
Who was going to have the ability
And the background to stand up if the generals were to push again in a hawkish Direction
Consequences for voters getting this wrong in 1960
Enormous
It's probably at this point if the man from Mars we've been using a part of our discussion here is watching the 19th
60 election
He's not going to be able to figure out we human beings at all
Because of the mind of any
Mr. Spock type character they're going to look at this and logically figure out that the only thing Americans should care about it getting
The Sword of Damocles question right
But that's not how human being songs you need any system where they're allowed to have an opinion
It will be one of the concerns the factors into their decision over who they vote for 4
Most dangerous man in all human history
But it will not be the exclusive thing I mean they're going to care about domestic issues to MIP attacks question
Determine who they vote for
It's probably going to be an issue of what party they are
Where some Americans are going to vote reliably for the Republican candidate together for Democrats
Even the Sword of Damocles can't prevent
In a Party Loyalty from coming into play
Finally and this is the part of the
I would imagine would really confuse the man from Mars
The question of personal Charisma and glamour
And likeability will come into this and you will think to yourself
Of course that's just how these things function
But if you back off and look at it from an outsider's view point
What is that becomes the reason
You vote for the person who plays
A really poor game of atomic poker
Nuclear Bridge
Three-dimensional geopolitical
Nuclear booby trap chess
And of course
Estes International groups like The Bertrand Russell
Albert Einstein group might point out
It's also a heck of a lot of power for American voters to make a decision that impacts the people around the world
You have no say it all in the decision
The people that we were talking about in India do not care about the US tax rate at all
In the 1960 election but they sure as heck hope
But the
Proper person is put in charge of the nuclear Arsenal
Or look at the central Europeans
For right smack-dab in the center of the crosshairs if nuclear war breaks out in Europe
What insurances do they have that the American people are going to vote for president based on
And who's better looking
1960 the better-looking candidate wins
He's also by
Leaps and Bounds the far richer candidate is the less experienced candidate he is the younger cat
Something
Cuz Richard Nixon the Republican
Former vice president under Eisenhower zamir 46 years old which is young but
His opponent wins at John F Kennedy and he's a mere 43 still the youngest man ever elected to the office he's a kid
The seven-year-old Eisenhower and his old people in a walk off the stage and turn over the nuclear
Launch codes
To a kid a Playboy millionaire Playboy father's money estimated I thought I read in Forbes Magazine
300 million dollars of its so much it doesn't matter whether it's adjusted for inflation or not
Dad was an ambassador
Is earlier history of Highway originally made that money a lot more sordid than being an ambassador
The Sun
Was a swinger he played around with guys like Frank Sinatra and those guys
Dated a lot of girls that weren't his wife done by people knew that in the Preston
Talk about that much but had one of these families that was so beautiful and photogenic
Life magazine and Time Magazine and all these things that that gave all
The public exposure to him free of charge helped him out a time all the
Photogenic nature of omit all helped a ton of everybody can understand that that's just politics
But is that something that's outdated by the time we're picking your leaders
Will give them the sort of power that Richard Nixon don't feel bad he'll get to be president to just not in nineteen
Will brag about it 1974 when admittedly
He's got a few more missiles under his belt and Kennedy will have it he'll tell the press in 1974
And they should wake everyone up to the
Disaster you would have if you voted for the wrong person
Cuz they have this power to
Nixon quick to the press that
I could go into my office and pick up my telephone and in 25 minutes
70 million people will be dead
The real danger in the system created to manage nuclear weapons
Is it there is no margin for error it is a 1 strike and you're out situation
How long do you trust the electorate
And the political system in general because after all the electricity can only choose
The candidate to do well in the political system
How long do you trust them
To do this without making
Some sort of a terrible mistake
In the 1960 election
When John F Kennedy becomes the president of the United States there's a significant number of people that think
The lightweight has just been given control
Of the nuclear Arsenal
And unfortunately
For world events upcoming
One of those people going to turn out to be Nikita Khrushchev
It's going to be wrong about that
But that's what sets the stage for disaster it's those kind of miscalculations that the exact word count
Used
The JFK thought
Might lead
To war because
By this. Is becoming apparent that neither side wants that
How do you have a war if neither side wanted it
A mistake a miscalculation
Something unforeseen
In the book inside the kremlin's Cold War by vladislav zubok and Constantine pleshakov
It's interesting to read exactly how much
Khrushchev was hoping
Kennedy would become the president but not because he thought he was weak
But because he thought he might be another Franklin Roosevelt someone who could reach out and could have another relationship
The way Stalin and Roosevelt relationship was seen to be
Cruise ship apparently I didn't know this did everything he could
To help Kennedy get elected told
KGB officers in Washington you know analyze the situation of the sending you can do diplomatically
Forward propaganda to help do it
Call Kennedy his president after he was elected and told him at the first
I2i meeting they ever had you know
I got you elected
Now trying to figure out the motivations of the Soviet leader in this situation is as difficult as it is for
Any of these other politicians in people we've been discussing right though the layers to the core of the onion are impossible to discern
Zubac and pleshakov inside the kremlin's Cold War seemed to indicate
That
Khrushchev was excited about Kennedy
Coming to the presidency not because he was happy to have
Some sort of weakling or lightweight at least compared to Eisenhower was a
Heavyweights heavyweight in office
Because he realistically believed
But his sources told him that Kennedy was a pragmatist but you was not an idea log
Maybe you could deal with a man like that
Shubunkin pleshakov right quote
Cruise ship was prone to optimistic and often wishful thinking and in the early months after Kennedy's election
He had an irresistible temptation to see his
Is an
Quotes new president in the best light
He tried many channel to convey to Kennedy that his presidency could open up a new era in US Soviet relations
And quote
Detractors and hardliners would say it's all part of a plan he's just going to figure out a way to work this kid and that might be true
Go to recent history you can't always tell
But it seem like it was his honeymoon. And the honeymoon. Lasted pretty much up until about
April because in April something happened if cruise ship thought
He was going to get to turn to an absolute Clean Slate new page
After the Eisenhower Administration
Start bleeding really think that because
It would be not taking into account the fact
But nobody gets to start off with a clean slate especially not in the US political system words we said this is a tag team
Game of atomic poker and in the same way Eisenhower had to take over Truman's hand in mid-game
Kennedy has to take over Eisenhower's handed mid-game and Eisenhower has some crappy cards
Let's lay that out there right now
He warns Kennedy about the tooth loss
Going to be some trouble just warning you
Kennedy would find that next door neighbor Vietnam ended up
Taking more of his time and attention
Eisenhower also handled in the one card everybody knew was danger handed into Berlin card
Which was once again hot as hell
Christian would say about Berlin that Berlin was the testicles of the West
Every time I want to make the West scream I squeeze on Berlin
I'm squeezing it in the late 1950s and it became one of the two closest time the Eisenhower Administration came to me
Nuclear war the other was over a couple of
Islands off the coast of China
But you have that card over to
The new Young president
Annie Hanna
Kennedy a new card an unexpected card one that
Has become
The more more important but it's in a weird place it's Cuba
90 miles off US Coast
Normally a place that us would not be looking for trouble
During this era as we said they see the whole Freedom communism battle is a zero-sum game
If communism win some country on the edge of the Earth that's a big deal
So how the heck did ever snuck into Cuba
Well
It's a good story little off the beaten path for us except as it relates to this great game
But in the late 1950s the government
The autocratic
Strongman style government of fulgencio Batista estoppel
Russian revolutionaries led by guy named Fidel Castro and you made
Recalled his lieutenants name Che Guevara
Perdue short period of time
No one knows what these guys are about but then they end up by hooker by crook there's disagreement about this aligning them
Shelves with the Socialist side of the world
This is a huge problem
And as far as the Eisenhower Administration was concerned during their last years in office
It had to be dealt with they had a plan
The CIA plan
Involving Exile from Cuba
We're going to
Hit the beaches at a place called the Bay of Pigs and overthrow that Castro government
Eisenhower was going to leave office before the plan is ready
Dwight Eisenhower handed that card to John F Kennedy
And only a couple months after getting into office the new kid during the learning curve decide to go ahead with the Eisenhower plan cousin
CIA says it's good
The military wants to do it basically so Kennedy does it and it
Fails
Kennedy Took a ton of personal heat for knot
Stepping in an overly helping more when the
CIA badge
Cubans got into trouble
He was trying to preserve
The same sort of figli fiction in Cuba that it was a Cuban on Cuban thing
But the Chinese and Soviets have been trying to reserve in Korea
That
New way you fight
The wars during the Cold War
Most of his biographers though assert
The Kennedy learn something from this data changed him he already had leanings in this direction but it changed in CKD
Was a second world war veteran he was no Eisenhower
He commanded
A little PT boat with like 15 people on it but
While he was commanding a tegar cutting to
A Japanese Destroyer that rammed into it and he lost two men instantly
And had
It was a highly publicized and used for his political gain story but it was essentially true
He rescued his own crew Towing 1 wounded man by his life vest
With the Rope
Attached to the life vest in his teeth as he swam to Islands miles away
He that Harvard swim team
Experience comes in handy
But Kennedy it said that being a lowly lieutenant
Sort of on the ground on the scene taught him how out of touch
The people he called The Brass hats the military leaders back in Washington war with the realities of what the true
Tips for dealing with
And that
Attitude of common soldiers attitude On The Ground by the way
Was reinforced after the Bay of Pigs disaster
When he got advice
From the CIA and his military advisers that he thought
Was expert opinion
In one sense
It was
But that doesn't mean it's right
Kennedy wood
Be shattered
Die
What happened at the Bay of Pigs he was supposed to be crying afterwards he was out of
Shorts for longtime advisor during meetings would catch him staring off into space saying
How could I have been so stupid
Biographer Robert dallek writes quote
How could I have been so stupid was his way of asking why he been so gullible
He puzzled over the fact
. not asked harder questions
I had allowed the so-called Collective wisdom of all these experience National Security officials
Persuade him to go ahead
He had assumed he later told adviser Arthur Schlesinger that quote the military and intelligence people
Both have some secret skill not available to ordinary Mortals
And quote
The Experience taught him quote never to rely on the experts and quote
He told journalists Ben bradlee quote
The first advice I'm going to give my successor
Is the watch the generals and to avoid feeling that just because they were military man their opinions on Military matters
You're worth a damn
And quote
You know it's tempting to say that there was some luck here historically speaking that Kennedy got this lesson reinforce
Forced at such an early time in his career before things really heated up in the states Really Got High
Because only a few months into his career
Kennedy has decided
But you have to be skeptical of expert advice sometime
In this case though
Is acceptance of an Eisenhower type plan
Made him look a lot more like the previous administration
And it's happening right before the meeting with Nikita Khrushchev
Put the whole kibosh on the honeymoon between Kennedy and Khrushchev as though one spouse itchy
Eat it on the other after only a couple of months of marriage and if anybody was likely to do that
Well John F Kennedy
Nonetheless he went into this Summit
Right after the Bay of Pigs Fiasco
To meet
Khrushchev I die
And every book you will ever read on the subject no one can resist
And we won't either obviously
The visual and background comparison of the two guys when they get together could you find two
More unlike people
From their physical differences I mean John F Kennedy's
Could have been he's the glamour president in terms of
Looks and charm and all that kind of thinking
And and he's like the money man he's a propaganda
Stock character if you're doing this for the Soviet
Newsreels me he's the money man from the Monopoly game
And Khrushchev is a peasant but he's one of these peasants who's
Nicki and he's a Survivor he takes great pride in being able to outwit people who should know better than he
He knows he has no real formal education
He has however
A background in life
What is formidable
Zubok and pleshakov describe the two men's first face-to-face meeting
At the Vienna Summit
Starting on June 3rd and ending on June 4th 1961 this way quote
Khrushchev met with Kennedy and Vienna as a prima donna meeting with a first-time Starlet
I heard you were a young and promising man
Kruschev greeted the 43 year old president
The difference in age was almost a quarter of a century
This generation gap grows into an abyss
If one thinks of all the Milestones of Russian history as well as the personal experience that it's shaped Khrushchev
Head of which Kennedy had only a limited understanding
The only two links between the leaders were World War II and the nuclear polarization of the Cold War
And quote
Prussia had already decided after
The Bay of Pigs Fiasco
The Kennedy was weaker than Eisenhower
Something he could have probably assumed
But now he thought he detected something
At the Vienna Summit
He put his theory to the test
At the summit for two days he put the hard press on John Kennedy
And Kennedy stumbled
He came in with a lot of proposals that sounded just like the kind of guy
Cruise ship was looking for
I typically first-year president with all the idealism that comes with it in the
Set of understated implied idea that surely reasonable people can sit down and settle our differences
And ran into a buzzsaw
Kennedy described the experience to James Reston of the New York Times
You said that the summit meeting a quote bin
The roughest thing in my life
He just beat the hell out of me
I've got a terrible problem if you thinks I'm inexperienced and have no guts
Until we remove those ideas we won't get anywhere with him
And quote
Khrushchev said
Kennedy was too intelligent
+ 2 week
Once again when you read the history books on this it's amazing how many of them
Use
Poker or some sort of strategic game to describe the situation because there's so much brinkmanship going on
So much bluffing
And so much
Testing out of your opponent in this case
Khrushchev
Between the Bay of Pigs in the summit has determined now
But he's dealing with a much more immature as one of his aides said
American leader far more immature than Eisenhower
Inside the kremlin's Cold War
They Ride quote
After the first day of talks at the Vienna Summit
Khrushchev's advisers who waited for his return in front of the Soviet Embassy asked him about his impressions of Kennedy
Khrushchev waved his hand dismissively
Kennedy he said was no match for Eisenhower
He lacked the broad Horizon and the statesmanship of the earlier president
And quote
But this changed
Khrushchev's view of the man and what he could get away with and what he might decide to try
Which is exactly what you broken Tasha Cobbs say
Cruise ship told his advisers when some of them said
Maybe we should kind of listen to this and maybe that will
Better relations in cruise ship told them
At the favorable situation must be exploited
Another words crew Chef originally went into this whole thing may be trying to defuse tensions
Saw that he was faced with what he thought was a weak president a weak player on the other side of the table couldn't turn
Down the fabulous opportunity that the role of the historical died seem to have delivered to his side
And so began to play the game the way you would have played it in a pre nuclear era
The way Machiavelli would have told you to play it
But as
Kennedy theorize when neither side wants War
You're likely to have one breakout over some miscalculation
Khrushchev was making a dangerous one
I thinking that Kennedy was weak
Even now going to play his hand
Based on the assumption that that's the kind of man he was competing against
What happens when
That gaming strategy
Run smack-dab into the fact
If you have misjudged your opponent
Perhaps
Apocalyptically saw
Part 3
The destroyer of worlds
The people from the Bertrand Russell side of the evolved
To deal with our weapons technology debate with saying
The problem here is the game itself is too dangerous because it involves brinkmanship that's how it's played that's why I ever
Everyone including me
Compared to a game
The rules were laid out very openly by US Secretary of State John Foster Dulles in the middle 1950s when he said quote
The ability to get to The Verge without getting into the war is the necessary art
If you cannot Master it
You inevitably get into a war
If you try to run away from it
If you are scared to go to the brink you are lost
And quote
The wind the brink is Armageddon
How often can you go to the brink
And no you're not going to Tumble over the edge
Kennedy will come into office
As like the dream candidate for the
Defense intellectuals in places like the Rand Corporation because
He will bring in people that think that the Rand people have it right
Kennedy will bring in people from outside the government structure his defense secretary will
The guy who headed up Ford Motor Company
Are you bringing in some of the business people to take a new look at all this and say we've been doing it this way for a long time is this the way we should do it
And a lot of those people like
Robert McNamara the defense secretary thought those ideas
Did the Rand people were pushing about you know it's like a bunch of different cards and you have to play them strategically sounded logical
Demonstration is famous
For one of the biggest changes in all of nuclear history of something called flexible response traditionally you go for my eyes
And how was massive retaliation
Did Kennedy's flexible response
I used to be a little bit better talking about this
Before I read some of the newer books by people like Francis J Gavin the basically say
Something like flexible response was much more for PR
Then what really was on the ground
The idea that you could tell the people on the nuclear Battlefield in Europe
Hey don't worry we won't go to nuclear weapons at the very first option
At all sorts of benefits whereas
Kennedy and Eisenhower and Truman all kind of thought that if nuclear war breaks out everybody going to use everything they have anyway
This game of being able to
Throw a few bombs out there stop and see what happens sounds good in the classroom but in reality that's probably not what's going to happen
Unless that's what they're known for a new look at the
At the security strategy when it came to using nuclear weapons right at a time
When Kennedy's up against the guy who is every bit as good of a bluffer as Eisenhower was Khrushchev to Fantastic
Card game player 2
History John Lewis Gaddis points out
He uses rhetoric and Bluster and Bluff to cover up for his own side weakness
Because what the United States doesn't know when Kennedy gets into
Office
Talking about a missile Gap with the Soviet Union has more missiles in the United States is that the Soviet Union is woefully unprepared if nuke
Nuclear war came tomorrow
Showing proof chef says they're turning out missiles like sausages in Russia
No choice but to believe him
The way that us has been finding out what little they could about what was going on is with these over flights of Rush
Russian territory with these amazing high-level reconnaissance planes called U-2 planes
But you have to sort of guardian and dart out real quickly the radar shows that you're there but they're flying too high
Pie for the Russians to intercept
But they cause International incidents
And eventually they start getting shot down by missiles
And when those Pilots fall into Russian hands you have real international incident that was happening during the Eisenhower Administration
But a 1961 Kennedy orders
The satellites
Which are relatively new
To take a look at the Soviet Union and tell him what they see in over a. Of several months they look down
And they come back and the experts briefed the president say
They got my for intercontinental ballistic missiles
And they're not even ready to go
They got these nuclear submarines but they're all import
I'm basically they come to the conclusion
But if you wanted to all these nuclear problems with the Soviet Union could go away cuz we could Newcomb now
And stop them dead in their tracks it would be over a preemptive War would solve this
Catastrophe we all have looming were mankind to be bombed back to the Stone Age what a tempting idea
That would be
And the really attractive part
With the potential to
Knock out the other side's weapons before they could use them
Rather than Uber cities another word
You know like this arm in your opponent by shooting the gun out of his hand
That sounds a whole lot better than watching a holocaust to keep yourself safe doesn't it
Daddy also work well with some of the policies that the new Administration
Add about using nuclear weapons
Something that would be known as the counter Force strategy in the no cities policy
And not for the last time something that was intended to make people feel more safe about nuclear
Your weapon use have the opposite effect
Kennedy defense secretary explain the counterforce idea
But now the weapons technology we had would allow the United States
To Target the weapons of the Soviet Union
Instead of their cities
The truth is we would still Target their cities they just wouldn't be the first option
This was supposed to make people in cities think okay with the United States
Is it
Humane country which it is and it would never Target cities if it didn't have to end after all this will return
You know the battle to the battlefield where it belongs and they'll only be using them against the military forces of the other side
There were two problems with this one
People quickly realized that makes them much more usable
As horrible as it sounds
The idea that you would kill millions of innocent men women and children in these cities
Is a deterrent
If you think what we'll just use nuclear weapons against soldiers
What weapons are supposed to be used against
So does that make it a lot easier to start using them and then have a grow out of control will you do use the big weapons on cities
Does it even matter in a bad enough if you just use them in the military capacity
The other problem is Savvy people realize something really quickly
If the point
Of using these weapons and targeting them at the enemies missiles
Is to hit the missile so that those missiles don't hit the United States
You have to shoot them
Before the other side shoots there's
You don't want to hit
A bunch of empty missile locations in launchers and silos after the missiles are gone
But that means you strike first
The dynamic was turning into one like a
Old west gunfight where to gunfighters
Are going to draw on three
And everybody's worried
You're going to get into a situation where what prevents the other side from drawing onto as long as it disables the other person
Or kill them before they kill you or you going to really question the moral issues
Which led to a whole need to develop was called
A second strike capability
Another word something that said
We can kill you even if you kill us after you kill us
Or we can damage you enough so that this whole thing isn't worth another word for deterrence to work
You would eventually have to have something that Robert McNamara Kennedy's in a former head of Ford Motor Corporation
Would develop he called it
Assured destruction today we often call it Mutual assured destruction or mad
For sure
But this was a concept that was fully understood in the 1950s
It was the missiles that turned it into the kind of reality where
People would start talking about the potential advantages of both sides how to doomsday device
And eventually the Soviets would have something called the Dead Hand
With the exact same rationale powering it which is
We really don't want to have to kill you after you killed us but it might prevent you from killing us in the first place if we do have
Something like that
This whole question how you deter the other side of the weirdness of the entire mental construct
Nuclear deterrence
I was going to enter the doctor Strangelove phase of weirdness during this era
Where they will have debates over whether or not
You should ever respond with a nuclear response if deterrence fails
Herman Kahn
It was also associated with the Rand Corporation who will be one of the main Inspirations often cited for the Doctor Strange
Character
And we'll talk about it
The red button
Nuclear launch button the metaphorical one
And he will say that people have real discussions about whether or not that button should actually be connected to anything
Now he says it's important that the other side thinks it's connected to something
But the idea was
The if somehow
Nuclear deterrence fails on the other side launch their nuclear missiles at you the Humane thing to do
We did not respond
Right you've lost the war already
There's no reason to kill them too
Tasha point out Herman Kahn did not feel that way he definitely thought about you should be connected to something
Nonetheless he was sort of showing us
The kinds of conversations that these theorists are having with the sort of
Questions that will come up
Their academic in nature
Theoretical
Until they're not
Attentions begin to spike
After the Vienna Summit
The last line Kennedy will ever say face to face
Did Nikita Khrushchev
Is in response to
Some of the things that were said at that meeting when he walks out and says
It's going to be a cold winter
He's right
The situation in Berlin will get extremely serious at one point there will be
American and NATO tanks facing off against Soviet tanks
Hanover the dividing line between East Berlin and West Berlin and then the Soviets will put up a wall
Destapa flyme it
The whole thing becomes a nightmarish disaster
And
Problems are narrowly averted
The tensions will also increase the point where both sides do away with the
Unofficial moratorium they had on nuclear weapons when everybody started getting worried about Fallout
No they put a little
Temporary damper on testing these things and then boom everybody starts up again
Because if you're going to have tension Skyrocket while you got to make sure
That your nuclear deterrent remains credible in that means testing
At the same time it was a great way to send a message to United States will test 98 nuclear weapons
According to Donovan Webster in a month
In 1962 in a month
About sending a message because if you haven't figured out whether it works or not after the 91st St in the you just playing around
The Soviets
Have their own way of rattling Sabers they like really really big Savers and Khrushchev Chels
Is physicist including Andre soccer off that he wants a hundred Megaton bomb
Remember the United States is
Test it was the radiological that was 15 megatons
Castle Bravo
And
When you
Try to figure out megatons I'm no mathematician but but the
But the power grows exponentially
You can't just say it's 3 megatons instead of 15 so it's twice as powerful it doesn't work like that especially with things like the thermal radio
Ocean Park
Which is highly underrated I just read a whole book on that
It says for the entire time nuclear weapons been around
Everyone is underestimated the most dangerous part of them which is the fires that they start
Because they're hard to measure
You don't study those just starting to blast so as scary as they are that's all based on blast evidence
According to Lynn Eden there probably many times more deadly than that once fires taken into account
Andrei sakharov is supposed to have had with cruise ship and Oppenheimer Truman moment
A moment with a physicist
The real deep thinker who's thinking about the ramifications of his
Creation goes to cruise ship to try to
Tell him
Maybe we shouldn't make a 100 Megaton bomb remember it might take a lot more guts for someone to do it in that system
Didn't say the United States contact because before cruise ship was Stalin and telling Stalin something like this
Could be bad for your health so already you see that it's a much more open situation but soccer off goes to cruise ship and says
Maybe we should explode this bomb
It'll jeopardize future relations in The Test Ban Treaty is that we were unofficially
I'm having work for us and gets told this by
Khrushchev
Quote
Leave politics to wash where the specialist
We have to conduct our policies from a position of strength
Our opponents don't understand any other language
I did jellyfish and not chairman of the Council of ministers if I listen to people like soccer off
And quote
Of course anyone
The grew up in that era
Will note
Automatically. That's exactly the sort of thing
We here in the US would have said about the Soviets
Tempe jellyfish in front of them
In other words
Khrushchev understands the way it's all played
Just as Eisenhower did
Chinese people
Would make Machiavelli's
Honor list
They're good at the game they play but the game is different and soccer off
At least manages to talk kruschev down
From a 100 Megaton bomb to a 50 Megaton one because if all you really are trying to do here is rattle a big say
Sabor 50 megatons is as big as anybody would want even for intimidation purposes
A slightly over 50 megatons might have been
Just about half of Khrushchev wanted
What is John Lewis Gaddis rights quote
Even so it was big enough
The single largest blast human beings had ever detonated or have since on the planet
The Flash was visible 600 miles away
The fireball now quoting somebody who saw it quote
Was powerful and arrogant like Jupiter
It seemed to suck the whole earth into it
And quote and goddess continues the mushroom cloud Rose 40 miles into the stratosphere
The island over which the explosion took place was literally level
Not only of snow
But also of rocks
So that it looked to one Observer like an immense skating rink
The entire spectacle was quote
Fantastic
Unreal
Supernatural end quote
One estimate calculated got his rights on the basis of this test
Date of khrushchev's full 100 Megaton bomb have been used instead the resulting firestorm
Would have been golfing area the size of the state of Maryland
And quote
Surely nobody would ever use a weapon like that
Calculations can go awry
What do you ramping up at attention during the 1961-62.
Khrushchev attempted to do something
If this were really a board game
The kind I always enjoy playing when I was younger a board war game
More complicated version of something like Risk an awesome move
But with the stakes of something like Tsar Bomba and Castle Bravo and all these multi Megaton bombs involve
It's hard to see how people could justify the worst case scenario
But under the pre nuclear rules
Cruise ship makes a move that is so bold that there are quite a few people that think this is the kind of thing that gave him a reputation as a
Gambler that got him in trouble after this.
With the other people in Russian leadership who had some say in the matter
Because it was a recklessness to it
But my goodness if we were really watching the game instead of life you have to admire
The hotspot
When nobody's looking
Khrushchev solves a bunch of problems he's got
In one Fell Swoop
I secretly beginning to put
Nuclear weapons
Onto the island of Cuba
In many ways it's a brilliant idea
But it all hinges on a single very slender Reed you can see why maybe his cohorts thought him again
Reckless because that read was
You got to be able to get the missiles into Cuba and activated ready to go
Before the US knows they're there
Because if the US finds out
The entire plan falls apart
And when the stakes are global thermonuclear war
How are you comfortable
Changing a plan on such a narrow
Slender Reed
And not just that it's not like the US isn't paying attention there's been a conventional arms build-up going on in Cuba now
Now four months so the US is watching it become a political issue
There are midterm elections
In November
Back in September only about a month-and-a-half ago
The Rumblings were so loud about possible nuclear weapons that Kennedy issued a public statement showing strength and resolve
You know typical Cold War
Rhetoric
I drew a line in the sand and told the Soviet they would be the most Ray ramifications if anyone did anything like that and then Kennedy
Publicly and privately to the Soviet Diplomat since you're not putting
Imagine how he felt
You can also imagine how much gasoline has now recruit around this situation
When Kennedy finds out
But he's been lied to
And if his opponent to
Charged him with being naive and saying you're putting a country security risk in the Soviets going to put nuclear weapons on that island
When he finds out
That's exactly what they've done
The reason that this
Crisis begins at such an intense level from the very first minute of that because the stage is set for it
October 16th in the morning
Kennedy's advisors
Brain photographs
The photographs show the construction of missile sites underway in Cuba
The US have been watching
Weird activity involving
The Russian handlers offloading shipping if there was suspicion but these U2 photos
Confirmed everyone's worst fears and that's that
Within a very short period of time Kennedy CIA advisor thought maybe within a week
You were going to have operational missiles
90 miles or so off the US Coast
Diminutive Kennedy realizes the reality of what he's looking at
Dynamic starts
In the back of your head
A mental stopwatch
Should begin ticking
Because the pressures will start to mount instantaneously
Many historians point out that Kennedy was handing out a best-selling book to his subordinates during this. And you probably read it
Barbara tuchman's The Guns of August
The book of course that deals with the run up to the first World War
And it's really about a dynamic
The dynamic of decision-makers were in charge
I'm making moves on the great chessboard and they have some control and they can do things
But that somewhere along the way
All of the forces and elements involved begin to turn
The decision-makers into historical passengers as well
Or just along for the ride and find
The
Range of their possible decisions and moves
So curtailed that a times they appear to have no good options
Kennedy was fascinated by this Dynamic apparently
And thought he saw elements of it coming to play over Berlin already
Now he was about to take part
Something very similar although
From a time constraint
That run up to the first world war to come month and everybody thought they had no time to react
Kennedy was going to have nowhere near a month because the move by Khrushchev to put missiles in Cuba
Makes the next move the United States as if they don't do anything
Whatever Khrushchev is up to
Progresses farther
Do you have to do something and they don't know how long they have to do it
The fog of War will drive this crisis dynamic
Because right away the first thing everyone wants to know
Is are any of these missiles anywhere ready to be fired
And we found those missile sites
But what missile sites haven't we found
Are there Warheads on the island how many is there more stuff on the way
But your company these critical uncertainties is one thing
That US policy makers know for sure
Daddy is
Every moment you wait the situation is getting worse regardless of what it might be now on the ground a Cubix we don't know that
But we know it'll be worse for us tomorrow
That puts
An incredible
Time pressure on all these events
The attitude is the even if you sleep
Things are getting worse
I need to move and do something
Is exerting a huge force on the people who have to make these decisions in a way
Let's solve the problem
Without creating a bigger problem in this case the bigger problem would be World War 3
And if the president will have to remind his advisors
The other side has a hostage
What if they decide to kill their hostage if we do something
To solve our problem in Cuba remember the hostages West Berlin
Annies Kennedy will also point out to his advisors
Training Cuba for West Berlin is not a good trade in the Europeans definitely wouldn't think it was a good trade
Within hours of seeing the photos of the construction sites in Cuba
President Kennedy calls a meeting of what will be known as the x-com
It's really just a group of hand-picked National Security advisers along with some other
Influential voices
The Kennedy wanted to hear from including the attorney-general's who happens to be his younger brother Robert that's his favorite in
I think it was about 13 of them
And it can be in the first meeting
Noon October 16th and they will begin to discuss
How you react
The couch as move right the balls in the US is Court hear what are you do
At one point Kennedy were reminded participants
They were talking about
Potential for strikes on American Urban centers that could create 80 to a hundred million cash
Talking about the destruction of a country
Not to mention any casualties elsewhere in the world
Has there ever been a more important series of conversations
Ever
And if you're in a position
Play John F Kennedy is in the situation
With that kind of responsibility hanging over your head and the Judgment of History
How to deal with wouldn't you want to cover your ass
Somehow
Kennedy
Without telling any of the participants
In the excomm meetings
Tape them
Is brother may have known but no one else did a 10 years later when this all came out and we found out that several presidents found tape
Systems useful
You can see why
It upset some of the participants in the XCOM meeting who felt a little betrayed
At the same time
It's like a gift from the gods for his story
Because you can be a fly on the wall I can literally hearing the
The secondary conversations in the coughing and the people coming and going through the door
As though you're there
When at least one side in this crisis. That will last Almost 2 weeks
Is making the most important decisions in world history
And what's crazy when you listen to it is it the combination of boring monotony that could put you to sleep
And subject matter that makes the hair on the back of your neck stand up
Because it sounds like an office meeting even during the most stressful. Nobody's screaming and yelling it sounds like a
National business meeting in a board of directors
But when you listen to what they're saying
At one point of me talking about
Casualties that are at second world war levels
In afternoon
With Stakes that high
You would love to wish in a perfect world
But that was the only thing decision-makers took into account how do we avoid
The casualties on that scale and destruction
Not apocalyptic but it wasn't the only thing on their minds on either side
It's funny because
And more than 50 years and now looking back on this
We kind of have that man from Mars perspective
Because all of the individual concerns of the era
A faded in importance
Right it's not our day-to-day existence we have our own concern
The only concern from that. That matters to us now
Is that they avoid
World War 3 because imagine how different our time today would be
Are they failed in that
But for them
There's a slew of things acting upon their choices
Very big things
And very small things at least from The Man From Mars perspective I mean some of this is driven by John F Kennedy's
Political reality in the November midterm elections that seems nuts today
If something like that it influenced
Global thermonuclear war history turned out can you imagine
What the verdict of History would be
Nonetheless this is why those people
Like the Albert Einstein's questioned our ability to live with these weapons while still playing the game
Under the old rules
Because you get into situations like this
I want you to do
You can always get out
After a day or two Kennedy's considering for options to deal with the construction sites in Cuba option number one is an airstrike
Strike against them
Option number two is a general series of airstrikes across the island much bigger affair
But it would help you deal with all the unknowns
I would help get rid of the defenses so that when you had to fly over
More times it would be easier
Number three is a blockade of the US Navy's around the island and say
We don't know how many nuclear weapons and missiles are on the island but we're not letting anything more Ian
Phone number for
Is a general invasion of Cuba by the US Military
Now while he's considering these options
Things get worse
This is also part of the crisis Dynamic but
You think you're on top of the current situation where you have these medium-range nuclear weapons
Into because they measure the size of the
Launching pad areas they figured out these are for medium range weapons
And all the sudden they find more
Missile construction sites
As they fly over with more U-2 reconnaissance planes
And these are built for bigger muscles are going to be winter called intermediate-range
Ballistic missiles now on the island to which will reach
Almost all of the United States
The Soviets don't have a ton of the missiles that can go from Russian territory to American territory
But they have a ton of the medium-range. That's been threatening Europe for a decade now
That's what they're moving into Cuba as one military advisor will say giving them a Quantum Leap in terms
Is their ability to Nuke the United States
Kennedy will point out that this is a temporary thing they're building these missiles
You know every day that can reach from Russia to the United States owe in the matter of time
Does it really matter if the missile destroys Washington DC started in Moscow or Habana
Play Ratchet up the pressure even more
Eventually Kennedy decides
American dolls
A limited action for a limited purpose
He's going to put a blockade around Cuba so that it doesn't get any worse
He's essentially going to
Throw the car down and tell Cruise Ship it's his plane
The problem is such a move
Is that it does nothing
To deal with the missiles that are already on the island in the
Everyone's faking this crushing time problem
And pressure with because no one knows when they're going to be operational
We do about those
Kennedy wanted to take them out we can't figure out how to do it
Without
Potentially prompting World War 3 I mean there's Russian working on those weapons would he kill them to how many Russians can you kill him
Airstrike
And not prompt
World War 3
Just the taking of Berlin which would do the same thing
October 19th Kennedy goes into a meeting with the Joint Chiefs of Staff is Big military advisors the heads of the
Army in the Air Force in the Marines and the Navy
And tell them his plan
To do a blockade with no air strikes
And all of a sudden
It's apparent
But you have a huge problem on your hand because the military disagree
And I don't think
You know we're going too far out on a limb to say that it looks a little like
What you were seeing at the end of the Truman Administration with the strains they had with the military over who controls this stuff
Where the lines of demarcation between civilian and Military control our
Seems like things took a hiatus
But two terms of Eisenhower the general president
And now with the kid who screwed up the Bay of Pigs and screwed up the Vienna Summit I mean the weakling this is how the
Military looked at this guy this
One Admiral on The Joint Chiefs of Staff I think said he was a skipper for a small Patrol boat I mean
They didn't respect him and he was starting to not respect them very much and when they heard his plan was a blockade with
No strikes against the missile bases that were already under construction
They push back hard
The pushback was led by Air Force General Curtis LeMay
And as many of Kennedy's biographers indicate
Kennedy seemed to be intimidated by Lemay but who wouldn't be
Author Michael Dobbs write Salome quote
Anecdotes about Lemay became the stuff of Airforce Legend
Crude and petulant
He used to show his contempt for his colleagues on The Joint Chiefs of Staff
I belching loudly and leaving the door open when he visited their private toilet
When a crew chief asked him to extinguish his ever-present cigar to avoid igniting an explosion on board a
Fully fueled bomber Lemay growled it wouldn't dare
Ask for a policy recommendation on Cuba he replied simply
Try it
And quote
This is what it's like
To be a fly on the wall
Curtis LeMay
Tells President Kennedy that he needs to be invading Cuba right now
That's a shot right there by the man everyone in the room would have known it was President Kennedy's dad was often tarred
Feathered associated with the British
Even policy of Hitler and dappled Lemmings accusing Kennedy of right there
Contentious 45-minute meeting the president leaves the room
And the military advisors begin talking about him bad-mouthing him
Not knowing
The Kennedys been taping the meeting and the tape hasn't stopped
And that's all on Tape 2
This is the way strange Sheldon and Stern put a talking about
Defense secretary
Add another person leaving leaving the military heads quote
McNamara and Taylor Departed
Leaving Lama schupan wheeler behind to talk if the door closed
A way they believe from prying ears the remaining Chiefs voiced their disdain for civilian control of
The military
And left little doubt who they thought should be in charge of military decision-making
The hidden tape recorder of course
Continue to turn
And quote
In their defense
These people have two things to worry about one is keeping the United States safe
The other is making sure that if the worst case scenario happens when President Kennedy calls the final failure nuclear war
The job of these generals and military leaders is just beginning they have to win the nuclear war
So everybody's trying to do the same thing
The president is pretty sure that if he follows the advice of his military leaders
He's going to get you in World War 3 the military leaders are pretty convinced that if President Kennedy
Continue on the course he's on
You going to have World War 3 anyway and the u.s. is going to be at a disadvantage when fighting it
Storing Sheldon Dempster and said quote
After the meeting the president told his a Dave powers that he was stunned by lemay's Kaki certainty
The cruise ship would do nothing if the US bombed the missile sites and killed a lot of Russians
Quote these brass hats have one great advantage in their favor JFK fumed
If we listen to them and do what they want us to do
None of us will be alive later to tell them that they were wrong
And quote
All the modern historians will say that the XCOM tapes have changed the way this crisis have been viewed
It's amazingly clear though
The John F Kennedy like Eisenhower and Truman beforehand but from a much more difficult position Maybe
Push back against
In this case unanimous
Military opposition
The Joint Chiefs of Staff were unanimous that Kennedy's idea of a blockade with no air strikes was bad
Is XCOM advisors his civilian advisor to fluctuated in their views and changed
We're mostly
Sure then Kennedy was being far too weak
And when he finally informed a few members of Congress to the biggest bigwigs in his own Democratic party essentially said are you crazy
Can't just do that and wanted to do
Nothing's more along the lines of what the military want to do this 45 year old guy
Define Olive
Every time I start thinking
Individual don't matter in history I remind myself that there are examples like this where
The odds-on favorite thing to do would be to have a president follow the advice of his military advisers
All it might have taken for things to go sideways is for somebody to have merely done that
It's a little hard to believe isn't it
Now at this point in the story when things are getting very scary the world is unaware of this
The Russians themselves are not completely sure what's going on in the United States
Kennedy
Has one of his people handed note
To the Russian ambassador
Explaining what's about to happen and then goes on National Television to tell the world
The United States has found nuclear missiles in Cuba
And this is a big problem
The Soviets have gotten word a couple of hours before
Kennedy speech
David major that I was going to have to do with Cuba
And at that point
The Soviet leadership got together
Andaz diplomat bacilli
Kuznetsov
Pointed out quote
Khrushchev should his pants
Because all of a sudden it was clear that that slender little read upon which he had built this audacious Reckless gambler
What is
The part about the United States not finding out about the missile till they were operational
Get it slender Reed broke
And as Alexander fursenko and Timothy naftali right
Quote
Khrushchev let the frustration of the moment show to the men in front of him most of whom have experienced the Russian Civil War
War and all of whom headed toward the second world war an survive Stalin Khrushchev bared his soul
It is tragic he said
Did come so close to having a deterrent force in Cuba so close to making this kind of a nightmare unimaginable
Now Not only was a US invasion of Cuba possible
What's up with the new clearxchange involving the Soviet Union
Nevertheless Khrushchev was determined to show resolve quote
They can attack us he said and we shall respond
Articulating what was on everyone's mind in the hall he added this man ended a big war
And quote
Kennedy told the world in his speech about the weapons in Cuba
Said he was going to launch a blockade which they called a quarantine cuz the blockade is an act of War
A quarantine a Future Weapons
And then ask Khrushchev in a global forum
As the world was now Awakening to the fact they were in the middle of a potential thermonuclear crisis
To step back from the brink
And try to work
For the future
To avoid Armageddon
I call upon chairman Khrushchev
The hall and eliminate
This clandestine Reckless and provocative threat to World Peace
And to stable relations between our two Nations
I call upon Him further to abandon this course of world domination
Energon and his Star Cafe
When the perilous arms race
Edit transform the history of man
He has an opportunity now
The move the world back
Show me a picture of Destruction
By returning to his government own words
But it had no need to station missiles outside its own territory
And withdrawing these weapons from Cuba
Refraining from any action
Which will widen or deepen the present crisis
And then by participating in a search
Peaceful and primitive Solutions
Before Kennedy is even done speaking
Strategic Air Command will have moved up hits
Alert status to Defcon 3
Animals have
Bombers in the air which they kind of do all the time anyway to a degree but
Everything begins to go on heightened alert ships begin moving
Into the Caribbean there's already Maneuvers underway with the very suspicious code name of
Well it's Castro spelled backwards I wonder how many people got fooled
And the mechanisms of war that Barbara tuchman would have recognized
As beginning to shift into gear in 1914 as the wheels begin to ground toward that
Particular blueprint for Armageddon
Things began to follow a parallel path
On October 22nd 1962
Kennedy speech to the world
Did two things
Pretty much instantaneously
The first thing it did was confirm with the Soviets were already suspecting
And that's at the US and found their missiles
The second thing to speech dude
Was in one Fell Swoop
Inform the world that there might be a nuclear war in the very near future
I'm fascinated by this
I tried to figure out some sort of analogy for
Something that might be as disruptive you know every single day if you pile on the pressure to our
Civilization of framework
Keep Society
Together
As a
Nuclear war during the Kennedy administration
I thought what would you the same thing
Will the same thing we do the same thing
You found out this week there might be a nuclear war be very similar
Test case scenario I would think
The only other thing I could think of maybe that would compare in terms of
Potentially shaking the foundations upon which we
Don't run out in the street and smash each other in the head with a bottle
If the aliens showed up right at the like in all those movies the Giant
Multi football field size
Spacecraft Park themselves over our city I think the same sort of shaking
Us
To our civilizational foundational Roots would happen
Nonetheless if you thought you might not wake up tomorrow
And most other people around you were having the same sort of thought
Does that change things on the ground in you are
Little world
Does that impact the water cooler discussions at work the next day
How does that
Change your
Travel plans for the near future I mean
There are plans for example even for the most important in the society take the president
Or his family to get out of Dodge in case nuclear war happened and Jackie Kennedy was famously she didn't want to be
And if it was going to happen she wanted to die with the children in Washington with the president
Now there were even plans and once again this shows you how real this is
What to do to get the president out of the White House if he's in the white house when the White House is new
I'm going there apparently would like
You know a saline torches and get him out then bundled him into a radiation suit real quick Michael Dobbs says and then
Hoffman meindl helicopter for evacuation
But it gives you an idea of the steaks here
And what people are forced to contemplate like Bertrand Russell and those other scientist it said imagine your family
Dying in front of you agonizingly while you yourself do it everyone you know in your community
These are thought the people almost never have
I would also suggest that there's a huge difference between
When people worry about a a true nuclear war versus our main worry today in the 24
First century
When it comes to nuclear war
A loan
Attack by a terrorist groups of a single bomb goes off in a single City and that would be a nightmarish disaster don't get me wrong
Shake the foundations of the society because the entire Society will then turn
And help that place deal
But what if it's
12 cities
At once
They get nuked
In the case of the nuclear war plan right now we 1962 Moscow is slated
For like a hundred nuclear weapons on that city alone
Do you wonder how long it is before Society turns into one of those
In a set of a dog-eat-dog everybody starts being pulling out their stored ammunition in their canned goods and and people
Start thinking there's no you know nothing to live for so I'm not going into work tomorrow then when does it start to break down under the pressure
In the u.s. lots of army unit I think I read it with the biggest
In the country
Amassing of troupe since the second world war begins to move down to Florida in case they're needed for a Cuban invasion
All the food and all the canned goods start sweeping off the shelves I mean
In a lot of people quoted
Remember this time. As
The will we be alive next week time.
Bob Dylan famously said he was going to
Work quickly on the song he was riding at the time cuz he was worried you wouldn't be able to finish it or they get as much down on paper before tomorrow
Maybe the most poignant
Line I've ever heard in the
Missile Crisis as it's called
What Secretary of State dean rusk when his aide dropped him off
And said see you in the morning
This according to Sheldon M Stern by the way
And then Roscoe's this really you know unflappable sort of
Emotionally stable guy said I hope so
See you in the morning I hope so
Nehi didn't think about it at the time but he's just contemplating it later
For that guy he said and I'm quoting here that was the emotional equivalent of screaming
First major crisis moment appears
Right after the u.s. establishes this quarantine with their ships and the first of the Soviet ships approach it
It's like two dozen of them
And the world is now glued to this in real time
Not sure there's ever been anything like this in the coverage of news
Where
Be there waiting on street corners for the next edition of newspaper to be delivered back in the day there be several daily editions of nightly Edition
They're waiting outside places like Times Square and reading the electronic
Lit up crawl on the side of the building
And they're watching all three us broadcast networks give this the 1962 equivalent to wall-to-wall coverage
Coquille Maps behind Walter Cronkite
A little paper ship Carter's occasionally being moved closer and closer
Outline of
Quarantine
Even the president and his people were watching this coverage to everybody sort of holding their breath
It seems to me this is quite a bit different than something like Edward armor has famous live radio broadcast
From London is the bombs are dropping on the city during the blitz Because unless you lived in London
This didn't have a direct impact on your life
Whereas
You could be in the heartland of the United States or for that matter the heartland of the Soviet Union over that matter Central Europe just about anywhere
And what you're watching here in real-time May determine whether or not
You wake up
Some morning this week what are your children grow up and have a future
I mean
This is the stakes are hard to imagine aminos
HW Brands points out of he's writing a book about soda political Theory
Point out how this changes the entire equation from anything we ever had in previous history right quote
When people had labored toward distant goals in the Premier nuclear era
They could console themselves with the knowledge that though they might not live to see their objectives realized
Their children or grandchildren might
If the goals were Beyond human grasp
Each succeeding generation could at least approach a bit closer than the one before
The invention of nuclear weapons change the situation entirely
Now he writes there existed a real possibility
But the whole human experiment would be cancelled Midway
In that event not even future Generations because there wouldn't be any would know how things turned out
Under the nuclear Cloud the meaning of human existence through murkier than ever
Quote
If we were still trying to today
Reach the standards of living that they had back then because we were still working our way back up
From the rubble of World War 3
Would any of the concerns
But these people had
It's more important
Seem worth it
This is something that exposes a bunch of things where you could if you were grading humankind on how
How well they were doing adapting to their weapons technology you can give him an ass
Because they've overlooked basic fundamentals for example as this crisis unfolding you just want to scream to the participants.
Something
They can't even communicate
In real time
One on one
John Kennedy can't talk to krisha
When you think about
All the time they had in the 1950s in the stairs and the threat level rising
Don't you think one of these people theorizing about nuclear war be like them or whatever you move be like
Don't you think somebody would have said we have to have a hotline
We're going to want to talk to the opposite number if a crisis Dynamic starts
Didn't
Averanow we could expect world leaders who were
Ratcheting up the tension to a nuclear war to be able to text each other
Khrushchev and Kennedy are communicating
Via letters
Diplomatic equivalent to snail mail
Take half a day from the time
One side writes the letter
Gets it hand-delivered to the other side after cabling it has to be translated in Than Ready is half a day
A lot can happen in a
Real-time prices in half a day
As the Soviet ships approach the quarantine line for this big face off the US Strategic Air Command
Alert level is raised
To Defcon 2
The first time ever and it public assurances are to be believed
The only time since
Defcon 1 is all-out nuclear war by the way
Soviet
Strategic arms expert Steven zaloga says that
At the same time Soviet forces strategic forces were
Dialogue for the first time ever as well so now you have
In many theaters around the globe
These two militaries the two most powerful militaries in all world history and their allies
Rubbing up against each other militarily
Bring in the Arctic in Europe in its is everywhere Asia over Japan
The potential for something bad to happen unintentionally skyrockets
So do all the variables by the way as well I mean think about how much easier this whole thing must have been
Forgot like Kennedy before the world knew about it
Now every press outlet and every big city and small town in America not to mention the rest of the world
Has a headline related to the decisions you're currently considering right now
You weren't feeling the pressure before
The media combined with public opinion combined with
The political realities in democracies all over the Western world
Can criticize you an offer Alternatives and cause all kinds of problems
The stress level becomes so acute it would be hard I think to find a moment
In human history were human beings
On such a wide
Platform it mean not one place at one time but everywhere have been under this kind of pressure
Just my opinion but
We normally localized it if you're about to be taken over by the Mongols in your city you feel every bit as worried but it's
Just in your city
This is everybody holding their Collective breath
I mean you want a variable that would have been hard to model at the Rand Corporation 10 years before this time how do you
Represent with a letter like X somebody like Fidel Castro
A fervent revolutionary who fully seems ready to die for the cause here if necessary
He's pretty gung-ho when he puts pressure on cruise ship like the Allies on the west of putting pressure on Kennedy
He's a hard guy to account for seeing if this was really a show about the Cuban Missile Crisis we be talkin
A lot more about the Cubans
But it's more about controlling your weapons technology and
Khrushchev apparently have to tell Castro something very similar to what he told Mal years before which is we don't we didn't get into
Did the struggle against imperialism just to die
As the line of Soviet ships apparently keeps moving toward the quarantine
The media has
The countdown going I mean that's how tense this is everybody's
And biting your nails including Kennedy and his advisors in the White House is being shipped approach to Line2
What's going to happen confrontation see how quickly could get out of control everybody really worried
In his book An Unfinished Life
About John F Kennedy
Presidential biographer Robert dallek
Quotes
Robert Kennedy the president brother who was in the room with them and they're all sitting there waiting for this
In a crisis moment to occur
As the countdown continues
And Alec quoting Robert Kennedy
Rights
Quote
The president's tension was reflected in his appearance and physical movements
This was the moment which we hope would never come
Bobby wrote later
Quote the danger in concern that we all felt
Hung like a cloud over us all
These few minutes with the time of Greatest Warrior by the president
His hand went up to his face and covered his mouth
Any clothes just Fists
His eyes were tents almost Gray
And we just stared at each other across the table
Was the world on the brink of a holocaust and we done something wrong
I felt we were on the edge of a precipice
And it was as if there was no way off
+ 4
And then
Kennedy gets a couple of messages and relatively quick succession that appear something's happening on
The season
Maybe these ships are slowing down there not sure but maybe and then maybe they're stopping
And maybe some of them are even turning around
This is the moment where
The air goes out of the room like a balloon and then Secretary of State Dean Rusk is supposed to have said you know we had a gay
Game when I was growing up in Georgia where two people have a staring contest in
Eventually you lose when somebody have to Blink and goes well the other guy just blinked
This moment will go down in history of the time the other guy just blinked
Kennedy faced down Khrushchev in this
In a contest of Wills in at the last second
Cruise ship turn this ship around
That we now know that that's not what happened
But the people at the time didn't know that
Has Michael Dobbs Punch-Out in a great line he said kruschev did indeed blank but he blinked 30 hours before
And it took that long for Washington to see it
Khrushchev it actually made the decision not to challenge the quarantine with any ships carrying
Nuclear missiles or weapons pretty darn soon after Kennedy announced the quarantine
But he didn't make that public knowledge
Egypt
Rattling Sabers and threatening to run the blockade in
Push the envelope the entire time
All the while knowing he had no intention of running that particular
Risk
Historians have long differed on how you should see
This move by crucial not to openly challenge The Blockheads
You'll still go through with ships that don't carry band material in the US in
And his ships will play us one of us
Consensual dance of
Convenience to avoid
Now that they've gotten off the crisis hook temporarily having things get out of control again
But a lot of historians will say that this is a crushing humiliation
The cruise ship that have to back down like this especially after he said publicly and the Kennedy and letters I'm not backing down
And apparently
Khrushchev's military advisers are coming to see him similarly to how JFK's military advisors he Kennedy
Not a lot of respect on all sides
That's playing into this but there are other historians that will portray this more like a
Counter-move very similar to the ones Kennedy has been making the ones that say I'm not going to be the one to start a nuclear war
But so many of my active choices would do so I'm going to do more of a passive choice
Right I'm not going to invade Cuba I'm not going to launch attacks against the Cuban Missile sites I'm just going to throw the quarantine
Your move mr. Khrushchev
Khrushchev says I'm not going to challenge the blockade I'm going to pull those shipped back
But I'm going to continue to work on actually redouble my efforts
To speed up the work
All the nuclear weapons and missiles that are already in Cuba
Your turn mr. Kennedy
Now we get to this point in the story where I can't help but think about the unquantifiable variable that is the human element
Again little things that would be so hard to model
You know when the old game theories
Things like sleep
How do you quantify
Lack of sleep these people are putting in 20-hour days now
Everyday
You're not eating well and John F Kennedy's bad back is supposed to problem so much at the Vienna Summit that it may have info
Things went
Okay we're not talking about one person now
In this situation we're talkin about the collective
Frazzled this of everyone
On all sides
Khrushchev isn't leaving his office he's sleeping on his couch and is closed day after day after day
Think about the little things to the you wouldn't even consider
Unless you were in that situation all these people that have not a single spare men in their day
Still have to wonder about how am I getting my family out of this area if nuclear war happens if my wife has 10,000 problem she's calling me back at you
I can't figure out how to get evacuated I mean these people have all these worries that if it was just a single individual even if it was
The leader of a country you would think well
That's a variable the system can work around
But it's happening to everyone all at once all at the same time
And you can't quantify you can't say the factory things 20% more towards bad decisions because how would you know
But you can reliably say that if you compare the performance of the system all the individual together working
You don't want a One
To how their operating collectively by day 10 that we're going to see a diminishment
How long can people in this situation go before you're starting to make really poor decisions
More for fatigue and stress overload reasons and anything else again
If you're the Rand Corporation trying to model how things are going to go in a real-world situation
You know what's the value you plug in Forex for that
And then there's the ultimate variable
In this equation the one everyone recognizes cuz it's so obvious
The two human beings
Who have the power and authority to unleash nuclear war in fact
Things go wrong in the near future have the responsibility to unleash it
Kennedy and Khrushchev
I'd like to be in their shoes
I mean a sociopath might like the idea of having nuclear weapons and
All that that entails
But that's not the kind of thing most people look forward to having to use
It creates a huge amount of stress as you might imagine
Anyone running for high office especially the place like the United States
As a sort of implied promise that they can get the job done and understanding that the job of being the president is going
Going to require decisions on your part that will get people killed
It's unavoidable
I'm killing bad guys for example of terrorists and those sorts of things there's a lot of people that could sleep very well at night
It without and their resume so no problem there becomes a different situation when you're thinking that maybe in the next week you're going to have to
Issue orders that would fry millions and millions of non-combatants and women and children and old people
And even animals and poison the earth I mean there's a lot into these decisions
A lot for one human being to have for the society to handle
Because we discussed earlier
This is not a power that was seen to be something
The because of the way that technology worked could be in groupthink decision
Was something that had to be made by a single individual
Who can handle that power
And I don't even mean in a non trustworthy since we're going to Nuke people like some
Terrible tyrant devold
The more the stress level
And if you get lucky
With the people that you have there at any particular time
What makes you think that over the Long Haul you're going to continue to be lucky
This is Bertrand Russell's comment about Walking the Tightrope for a couple hundred years
Truman did Eisenhower did it for two terms and now in 1962 at the end of the year
It is starting to look like
The person walking across that tightrope
Is going to fall
How do you like to be the person that had to push the button
Is that happen
And there's a part of me that likes to imagine that this is like the ultimate Fail-Safe mechanism in the system
Those last human beings who actually have to do the equivalent of pushing the button
Maybe the last minute thing rebell
And they say I won't do it I won't destroy humankind and it becomes the wonderful end of the movie where everyone go see
She'd probably couldn't handle that but the humanity one out
A human version of that
Red button not connected to anything
Herman Kahn mentioned
Problem is
Most of these situations by the time they get as far as
You would have to get before people were thinking about pushing the button
Are out of people's controls by that time that's what the Barbara tuchman World War 1 book is about
And that's what begins to happen
In The Story 2
Because after cruise ship pulls the
Chips back in the quarantine continues work on those mistletoe that are already on the island
They start writing letters to each other Khrushchev and Kennedy it actually starts on the 23rd but they continue on and they're fascinating
We can watch the tone change with the ebb and flow of the crisis
And at the stress level
An alert statuses
And progress toward an invasion of Cuba Maybe
Ratchets up
You begin to see both these politicians
Trying to find a way out
Both of them are seen
Their option constrained now the door to getting out of this mess is closing
And their ability to control the situation
Slipping out of their hands
By October 25th
The day after the
Non face off at the quarantine line
Cruise ship is getting all sorts of information that makes him think an invasion of Cuba is imminent
The president of the United States have this clock going off cuz the missiles are continually being worked on in the pressure caused by that
Khrushchev got his own clock and invasion of Cuba is imminent what you going to do about that
He know something
But not only does Kennedy not know but no one in the west knew until the Soviet Union fell
And it's record could be made available to historians in the early 1990s
Khrushchev knew that they were Battlefield nuclear weapons operational
On Cuba
Put in place to destroy any Landing
Imagine like the D-Day Landings of the second world war if the Defenders had nukes
That are small each one about the size I read 60% of the power of the Hiroshima bomb or something like that
But they have several of them
Imagine the Carnage
Something like that would have created
And how do you back out of that problem and avoid World War 3 if it goes that route
The Persian Kennedy begin
The. In the Cuban Missile Crisis I like to call
The haggling holding a hand grenade.
Cuz both of these guys have to get a deal together
Before the forces driving them toward nuclear war
Become Unstoppable
On October 26th
Kennedy receives a note from cruise ship
The Sims 2 propose
A way out of this crisis
Some historians have suggested this was a desperate note
RIT nervously
But not everyone agrees with
It's clear though
The true Chef thinks today Invasion cube is coming
He worries that the military has taken over
From JFK
And so he offers a compromise on Cuba
It makes the case that the only reason the weapons were put in Cuba in the first place
Used to deter us invasion
Is it you've already invaded once
That was the Bay of Pigs
He says your CIA is constantly harassing
And causing problems over there that's called operation Mongoose and he's right about that
He says if you would publicly Proclaim that you won't support any more of that you won't invade the item will take the missiles out
Then you write about the blockade in the ongoing crisis
He says to Kennedy in famous language quote
If you have done this is the first step toward unleashing War well then evidently nothing remains for us to Dubai
But you accept this challenge of yours
What if you've not lost command of yourself
I realize clearly what this could lead to then mr. president
You and I should not now pull on the ends of the Rope
And what you have tied the knot of War
Because the harder you when I pull the tighter than that will become
And a time may come when it's not as tied so tight
That the person who tied it is no longer capable of untying
And then the knot will have to be cut
What that would mean I need not explain to you
Because you yourself understand perfectly what dread forces are two countries possess
Therefore
He writes
If there is no intention of tightening this not
Thereby dooming the world to the catastrophe of thermonuclear war
Let us not only relax the forces straining on the ends of the Rope
Let us take measures for untying the knot
We are agreeable
This
And quote
So in the early evening of October 26th 1960
C2
The first
Ray of Hope appears
Right before time Runs Out
Chinese military advisors
Do not trust kruschev they think this is a ploy to gain more time to get his missiles operational
I must remember the Kennedy has misjudged
The Soviets in the past and these other people have been right so if you're Kennedy
You must think to yourself maybe I'm wrong again
At the same time
If we look at it in a certain way Kennedy had just received
A personal letter
An emotional letter some people describe it
I'm the only other person who is actually in the same position he's in
You can be the closest advisor
To the person
Who actually has to push the button and it's not the same thing
Cruise ship understand through Kennedy's dealing with and vice versa
Neither man it looks like wanted to have to do this
The only way to stop this is by going to the other person who also doesn't want to do this and say
And what if I do this can we can we call this off
It must have been a certain mental sense of relief where Kennedy saw this is heaven. Maybe not time that's the problem and you seen the X
Come take the Kennedys trying to get this done with move it along with
On the morning of October 27th 1962 Saturday October 27 1962
Kennedy and his advisers will get together to discuss
That
Letter in the ramifications it can we get this deal done where we say we want to talk to you by and they get the missiles out these missiles that they haven't
But even publicly acknowledge your there
And then everything begins to go wrong
Which is why they call this day
Black Saturday
Black Saturday starts
With a press report that added to Kennedy in the morning as he
Discussing last night's letter from Khrushchev
This is a public statement by cruise ship like on the radio kind of thing
Renounces to the world
The way out of the Cuban Missile Crisis and instead of acts like The olive-branch Peacemaker type
But the way out is not the same deal he offered Kennedy the night before
Is way out is a much more difficult deal for Kennedy to do
Cruise ship tell the world
It will take those
I don't think you said missiles cuz they still haven't publicly knowledge but he basically says problem with will be removed from
Cuba if they pledged not to invade Cuba and if they get their own missiles out of turkey with your as close to us as Cuba
What is the United States
Boom
There's no better example of that old
Add eggs at the light
At the end of the tunnel was instead an oncoming train
Get the bottom drops out of everything here is Kennedy can't do that he certainly can't do that
Before the timeline for airstrikes or Invasion Runs Out
The reasons why he can't do it though
Are the sorts of things that those people
Like those scientist we talk about now that we have nuclear weapons we have to have a one world government so you don't have multiple
Governments
Interacting with each other in these Dynamics
This is what they're talking about because
Cannabis
Fine
With Cruces public proposal
He wanted to get these missiles that Khrushchev says You must remove these missiles from Turkey he wanted them out before this crisis even app
Obsolete
They just cause trouble to get he wanted them out
But now that Russia has made it part of the deal
Kennedy can't accept it
Without looking weak
Without looking like he's kind of willing to sell out the security of his European allies
To buy him some security in the Americas
Looking like he is rewarding
This move by Khrushchev to place missiles 90 miles off the US Coast and movies been vilified
Find the United Nations for more than a week
He's trapped by geopolitical Dynamics
Pharaohs of Egypt would have understood
The game is the same game it's always been
But the consequences
I'm making a wrong move in the game now
Are exponentially greater than anyone's ever dealt with before
And that's what's changed everything
Kennedy's Trapt
Because he's playing a new game
By the old rules
But what is that keeps you from being able to stop thermonuclear war from breaking out
And once again every time you think you can't get any more pressure right how much can the people at the center the story handle
All day long you going to get more
On the first three things in the morning at the CIA telling the president we think those are medium-range Ali some of the missile
Sites are now operational on Cuba boom
Have you waited too long
There's another piece of ammunition for the military Hawks to use against you in arguments
And then
The military's and both sides having rubbed up against each other all over the world on high alert for days now
Spark start flying
A situation as combustible and explosive is the one you're already dealing with
It would appear to be fatal
There are naval incident involving Soviet submarines at the US Navy's chasing around Cuba they don't know that those submarines
Have nuclear Torpedoes by the way
There's a U-2 reconnaissance plane up in the North Pole in the Arctic that gets off course and Strays over Soviet airspace
Soviet send fighters to deal with it
United States up in
That territory up there since fighter to deal with them with
Missiles armed
With nuclear weapons
Over to buy there will be a low-level reconnaissance flight of planes that is hit with anti-aircraft gun fire
More ominously a U2 flying over Cuba to keep tabs on those missiles that the US absolutely has to do
Do
Is shot down by a surface-to-air missile us and bat
And the pylons kill
Now you have blood in the situation
Not just that
In order to sort of
Keep the military Hawks at Bay several days ago Kennedy
We will act don't worry
And one of the lines in the sand why did they shoot down a U-2 plane with a surface-to-air missile we will go take out those
Surface-to-air missiles
Now the military said guess what just happened what are you going to do about it
The president's brother Robert was at these meetings and with him in private talks all during this time with right that at this moment
Crisis was at this stage he felt
That quote
The Noose was tightening
On all of us
Non-americans on mankind
And at the bridges to escape were crumbling
And quote
The bridges to escape
Crumbling
Kennedy would say
A couple of days
But at this point
There was a
Schedule for Cuba
To start with bombing raids hundreds of them
Set for Monday or Tuesday
Remember it's Saturday
His own advisers can't make up their mind what to do in the current situation
Joe Kennedy will famously send his brother Robert
As a back-channel negotiator
Without telling anyone
Robert will go
In Washington DC to the Soviet ambassador
You gone to the Soviet Ambassador few days before during this crisis but was his normal combative feisty self
This time
The Soviet Ambassador says an entirely different man
What's in front of him
Basically trying to explain the plight his brother was in
And
I'm not sure plea it's fair to say pleading
But there was a desperation in all this
There are many descriptions from different people and Views none of them
Quite exactly the same
I like the one you should take with the most salt cuz it's from khrushchev's own Memoirs quoting his ambassador to Brennan
Who's having this conversation with Kennedy
Intrusive rights quote
Robert Kennedy looked exhausted
One could see from his eyes that he had not slept for days
DM self said that he had not been home for 6 days and nights
The president is in the grave situation Robert Kennedy said they say he said
He does not know how to get out of it
We are under very severe stress
Impact under pressure from our military to use Force against Cuba
Probably at this very moment the president just sitting down to write a message to Chairman Khrushchev
We want to ask you
Mr. Brennan
The past President Kennedy's message to Chairman Khrushchev through unofficial channels
President Kennedy implores chairman Khrushchev to accept his offer
Had to take into consideration
The peculiarities of the American system
Even though the president himself is very much against starting a war over Cuba and irreversible chain of events could occur again
His will
That is why the president is appealing directly to Chairman Khrushchev for his help
A liquidating this conflict
If the situation continues much longer the president is not sure that the military will not overthrow him and see
Seize power
The American Army could get out of control
The publisher of my 1970 copy printed in Boston
Add a footnote inserted right there to point out that this was obviously a misunderstanding that the Soviet leader had about the American system without
But truthfully you wouldn't have had to have like a military takeover of the government to achieve
Basically with the Joint Chiefs wanted which they were unanimously opposed
To the president's approach on this in order to get their way if they had gone
To the president's opposition in Congress are example and told them that they were unanimous that he was
Absolutely taking into the country to existential danger in Daily debt to the US media it would be like a giant veto over
The president's policy public opinion would have
Fortune
Into a different route
And if they had gone that route
It would have been simply because
They the experts unanimously talking amongst themselves who decided that the president
I'd literally put the country in terrible Danger
And by the way while most histories portray Kennedy is this wise
Sage guy that save the world in the situation by pushing back against at times unanimous counter opinion
There are other views I mean historian Garry Wills
Savages him essentially accusing him
Of being the one who was responsible for this Timebomb situation to begin with
The fact that he got you out of it means little since he's the one who set the bomb and
Wills Point South if you want to give anybody credit for this give it to crucia
Is the guy willing to suck up the humiliation here
So that we don't have nuclear war and go home with his tail between his legs and not tell anybody that he actually got the missiles out of church
Turkey that were threatening my citizens he can't even claim
Credit for that
More hard-headed
Other historians will use that same right now by saying what you really mean to say is Khrushchev was completely outgunned in
By this time the US military would have crushed him especially in that part of the world choice but to back down
Regardless it's hard not to look at the two individuals in this crisis
Khrushchev and Kennedy and think regardless of the role they may have played in getting us to here
Once they did
They took the most cautious route
Out
One of the historians I was reading a great way
A framing ahead said
If this was a gaming scenario and you could run it a hundred times
How many times would it turn out that you would have nuclear war how many times would it turn out that maybe we forget about
This is Kennedy and listen to his military advisers
Cruise ship with a back down and invasion of Cuba somehow would have happened
And the Cubans been freed and Castro
A bunch of scenarios where it can go
But if you are going to the casino to put your bets on something
And the best case scenario is you could win a fortune the worst case scenario is if that little ball on the roulette wheel and
The wrong spot my goons take you out the back and shoot you in the head do you even play that game
Or do you just play as cautiously as you can so I can listen I know this is not a strategy that's going to get me win per se but the worst case scenario
So bad I'll be happy if I can just avoid
That
Increase Shakira's from his ambassador
Basically that the u.s. government will get those missiles out of turkey but they'll do it quietly but that you can have a deal he's all over
Because he was thinking he wasn't going to get a deal that good anyway
He's a little bit worried about letting Kennedy know he accept the deal before this Cuban Invasion happens that's how close we are
So instead of spending a half day getting letter to him
Eagles right on Radio Moscow on four planes were in accepting the deal and
He keeps quiet
Part 2
You needed to be kept quiet right through the system that we have here of interaction between nation-states work
Choirs that certain things
Be done in ways that help people save face
And preserve their political
Opportunities and whatnot
Khrushchev understands this
Accept the terms
And from this moment on
The tension begins to draw
And Kennedy said just a couple of days later he feels like a new man I mean I had a airstrikes ready to begin Tuesday mean
They know how narrowly
They dodged a bullet here
And
Worth noting
And when he went a few days later that's according to a biographer Robert dallek
To congratulate and thank
The Joint Chiefs of Staff the heads of all the military
Entities in the country on on their help during the crisis
They were mad
Admiral Anderson said to him that we've been had
The essential point was that this too is a stalling thing who who the heck thinks the Soviets were going to get the missiles out of there even
Now
General Lemay for the Air Force called at the worst defeat in the country's history
And said we should still invade Cuba
Defense secretary Robert McNamara says
This reaction on the part of the Joint Chiefs of Staff left Kennedy quote
Absolutely shocked
And quote and quote
Stuttering in reply
And quote
In 13 months
Kennedy will be dad
And
The vast majority of theories
Concerning his death including the
Traditional dongzhimen Theory
All have very close connections to the island of Cuba
Khrushchev's loss of power that will be coming
Will also be connected to Cuba in this whole affair
Traditionally the idea
Was it his
Counterpart in the Soviet leadership considered him to be a reckless gambler but it's more complicated than that
Unless the only person
I would stick around despite hundreds of assassination attempts for decades
He just died recently
Fidel Castro
The histories are to be believed
Out of the
National leaders making decisions during the Cuban Missile Crisis
He was the most in favor
Of using nuclear weapon
Castro's views with mellow
With time
With the acquisition more Insider information about what was going on behind the scenes
But this
Cuban Missile Crisis
Is the best case study
That we've ever had
But what it's like when the Sword of Damocles
Begins to drop
17 years after the debut of nuclear weapons
It was a nuclear near Miss
There's a lot you can learn from that
American story Martin J Sherwin calls it
The biggest
Non-event
Of the 20th century
Which is interesting that we normally think of history in positive terms this was done
Happened
Sometimes the most important things
Are the things you avoid he right
Quote
In a century replete with unspeakable disasters
The Cuban Missile Crisis of October 1962
Came terrifyingly close to producing the greatest disaster of them all
Nuclear war
The final failure
The irony of this non-event
Is it a birding it was the most important event of the 20th century
So it is necessary both to learn how
And why
The United States and the Soviet Union nudged each other to the edge of the nuclear Abyss
And understand how a suicidal plunge over it was avoided
And quote
The lessons of the Cuban Missile Crisis are
Controversial
And argued about an often depend on one's political Viewpoint or what country you come
Definitely scared
The leaders of these countries I mean Kennedy and Khrushchev will both change their tune in a number of different ways
Kennedy will revive some
Ideas from the Eisenhower Administration that never had a real kick in the pants to be
Implemented you know what stock to get passed a whole lot of other problems well
A nuclear scare can all of a sudden
You move mountains in front of you and Kennedy and Khrushchev will start the process
A creation of a nuclear framework
Maybe you could call humankind's attempt
To adapt to their weapons technology
The Frameworks for limitations on testing
Safeguards put in place
To help ease the next crisis situation a hotline for example
And the beginnings of an understanding
That if you can
You should begin to put controls on these weapons so that they don't spread to everyone
Then you can begin talking about how to reduce the numbers of weapons
The two biggest
Holders
Having their stockpiles United States in the Soviet Union on that last front it will be a failure for quite some time
Time
And that also
Is as a result of the Cuban Missile Crisis famously a Soviet Diplomat will
Sado in American
You got away with it this time
But you'll never get away with it again
The Soviets will race to produce
Enough intercontinental ballistic missiles
So that they are never on the short end of
That numerical disadvantage again
By the middle 1980s the Soviet Union will have more than 40
Nuclear weapon
In the United States somewhere
/ 30000
70000 + nuclear weapons
And that's just the two biggest power
And while adding
A hotline
It's going to help the next time there's a crisis situation
The one big safeguard
But nobody can figure out how to implement
It's still a glaring problem
The fact the responsibility for you still revolves around a single human being
Ronald Reagan Road
After his presidency that that was the big realization that really hit him right when he became president
That he and he alone
Control these weapons
And the amount of time he had to talk over decisions with people about using them
Was minuscule hero quote
The decision to launch the weapons was mine alone to make
We had many contingency plans for responding to a nuclear attack but everything would happen so fast
But I wonder how much planning a reason could be applied in such a crisis
The Russian sometimes kept submarines
Offer East Coast
Would nuclear missiles that could turn the White House into a pile of radioactive Rubble within 6 to 8 minutes
6 minutes
To decide how to respond to a blip on a radar scope
And decide whether to unleash Armageddon
How could anyone apply reason at a time like that
And quote
Reagan along with every other American president since Eisenhower
That's had a man
Following him
But she went from place to place
The man carries a briefcase
Inside the briefcase is something
Nicknamed the football
It's the nuclear codes for launching a nuclear attack
In fact
I've read that the person with the football
Is downstairs from the president while the president sleeps
And they time him routinely and regularly
To see how long it takes him
To get from the bottom of the stairs up into the Presidents Room so he can launch a nuclear attack
If necessary
The number of nuclear accidents
Is in the dozens
Those are called broken Arrow's by the United States
The number of false alarms and near-misses is
Scary
Since the Cuban Missile Crisis there been a couple particularly scary ones
Perhaps the scariest
Since the Cuban Missile Crisis but that's an opinion question
Is something known as the Norwegian rocket incident
What happened in 1995 that's 4 years after the Soviet Union fell
When a rocket launch, the Soviet Union off guard
And their higher-ups
Put
In front of Boris Yeltsin the leader of Russia at the time
Their version of the football opened it up
And ask him about the nuclear launch codes
Are those who remember Boris Yeltsin remember that he was known to enjoy happy hour from time to time
So maybe we can consider ourselves fortunate
That either he hadn't enjoyed it
Yet
Friendly with this decision
Or maybe
But he decided not to respond
Prompting the unusual thought in my mind
Did Boris Yeltsin just save the world in 1995
Followed by the scarier thought
How the hell is the world in Boris Yeltsin hands at all
Too many people
Alive today
Boris Yeltsin in that era is an age ago
People don't think about
Nuclear war between the great Powers very much anymore in fact they don't think about war between the great Powers much anymore
And your history would seem to indicate
It's the key danger we should worry about
The only thing that could really kill
A hundred or a hundred fifty million people
In the next couple of years is an asteroid hitting the planet
Or nuclear war between the great Powers what's more likely
Well it depends
A lot of people who argue
The nuclear weapons have kept
Peace
Since the second world war that the reason we didn't have World War 3
Is the fact that everybody realize what would happen if we did
There's a lot of argument about that and I'm not going to go
Into that subject but I would like to point out
But there are trip wires everywhere
And this idea
That a nuclear war between the great Powers as sort of a thing of the past ignores the fact that on the geopolitical three dimension
Chess board
That is currently in use by the great Powers nuclear weapons are everywhere
In fact just to name one potential Flashpoint in this doesn't involve any of it
Many other countries now that have nuclear weapons
But the United States is pledged to defend with nuclear weapons
More than 25 Nations
Any one of whom if they're attacked
Could lead to the same sort of dynamic
And the crisis situation and the pressure and the lack of options
The John F Kennedy
Nikita Khrushchev face in the Cuban Missile Crisis history did not teach you what the Right Moves In those circumstances RB
Because the variables always change
But it does teach you
But you will have far less control over the situation
And it appears that you will when you're looking at it
In a detached theoretical way
That's why they call it a crisis
Right
As I said human beings are 70 + years
Into an ongoing experiment
To see if they can adapt or evolve to handle their weapons technology
So far
So good
But let's
Remember
That we are a long way from the edge of this tightrope
These may not even be
The most powerful weapons
We are creative enough to invent
And the systems we have in place
Still have
Human beings involved
Which is one of those variables that makes it tough to think
That we can go
Whole another hundred
30 or so years
And have the human story and
With the words
And they lived happily
Ever After
For Hardcore History t-shirts or other merchandise to go to dancarlin.com
If you think the show you just heard is worth a dollar Dan and Ben would love to have it