Today Show is sponsored by Squarespace
The easiest way to create a beautiful website
Or online store go to squarespace.com offer code hardcore at checkout
How to get 10% off
I'm a notoriously bad
Topic
And I traditionally pick something that I think I can do much more quickly than
Can
And then when I get into the middle of it I feel compelled to do the topic Justice
And we end up traditionally with a very long series of
Shows
What you're about to hear
Is the equivalent of like a double album
Buy a music band or something
We are essentially giving you Parts 3 and 4
I would probably should have been realistically speaking a four-part series
Achaemenid Persian Empire
With an obvious focus on their Wars
The Greeks in the makedonia
If you missed part one and two you probably want to catch those before you catch this one but there's so much military history in this way
Because I knew I'd be crucified if we didn't go into loving detail
About what
To several of the best battles in ancient
Military history
So we do that
Imma give you what
Is probably twice the length of what a good
Hardcore History show should be
Let it last
And hopefully
It doesn't become like one of those double albums I grew up with what you listen to it you think that they could have cut half that thing you just put up one really good single album
The way I look at it
This is one of the Great
It's a small world history
And if anything it probably merited more attention that I gave it but as I told you I'm a terrible topic
And I'm always trying to recover
After I make my poor choice
So without further ado
Part 3 and really part
For also
Final
Summer series on the great Kings of the ancient achaemenid Persian Empire
Kings of Kings
December 7th 1941
A date which will live in infamy
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein
Spirulina
Whether or not their president
Remember that we are not descended from fearful men
Hardcore history
Earlier we had posed
The question
About whether or not absolute
Power corrupt and absolute
In
Kind of world
Most of us come from
It's sort of taken as a given that you don't want to trust app
Depression
Power Brokers
History right
But look at history
In the story of the
Achaemenid Persian Empire
If you look at all the different key
Which is what we're doing
There are a number of them that almost certainly had
What amounted to Absolute
Power
And several of them
To at least it didn't just not abused it
Seem to
Can almost be
The Prototype
That you would want
Can an absolute
Monarch
Really two different kinds of product
Have to because
Founder of the achaemenid Persian Empire Cyrus the Great was like the warrior king
His version
Is Empires version of a kind of an Alexander the Great and probably the greatest conqueror before Alexander the Great social
The Prototype right King Arthur
But then
Did you get
Psoriasis
A king or two later and dries is like the gifted
Administrator person who's a genius
Maybe at
Organization and
Structure and
Handling things you know from a cost-benefit ratio I mean the Greek writer said his own people called him a shopkeeper
Huckster is another name given sometimes
Basically a shopkeeper as we said in the last
For the program
At the shop is Walmart you have a shopkeeper your CEO and you said dries was like the CEO of Persia core because
Persia kind of seemed to almost have like a subcontractor relationship
Aura
Subsidiary
Lysa subsidiary
3 person car with their various attributes and provinces
Absolute power corrupts absolutely one would think that
You wouldn't have a Cyrus the Great
So you wouldn't have a dries and they wouldn't have done so well so
Obviously there are exceptions to the rule
But those kind of people don't come along every day in any society
I mean often times
The great Empires throughout history of managed to sustain themselves
You know with occasional great leadership how many great leaders
You must you have show up
Overture e 250 or 200 years to keep the empire in good Stead
Supposed to
Pens
On the variables write the outgoing conditions
Things are pretty stable you can have a Caligula
Nero no problem but if the barbarians have been smashing up the
In the borders of the Empire now for twenty or thirty years you better have
A Diocletian and Hadrian
While the Persian Empire gets off to a really strong start
Cyrus the Great
His son came by sea was probably better than the sources describe
That weird maybe sort of Magi King lasted for 5 seconds and then to Rice a grain to make
Buy a bunch of other Nobles
When something weird happened to his predecessor to take over the gig based on competency cuz he was competent as heck
But then about four or five years
After the Battle of Marathon
We just talked about
When the Persian
Amphibious Landing forces expelled from Europe
Athenian with some
Do you need help
Herodotus give this passage where he says that dries is mad and now he will punish the Greeks and personally
But this guy's in his sixties
Remember
Yeah they say that
30 is the new 20 or whatever it is will back then
In a 60 is the current 70 or older and he's in his sixties and he's been on the throne for more than 30 years
Competently an awesomely
Reorganizing the Empire and making the structure so strong and interesting the he's a fabulous fabulous character and if your Grease
You better not Overlook what he can do to you
When he leaves the Army in person which seems to be the plan but then he dies which was not part of the
What's more
The army that he was putting together to go punish the Greeks now
Which were told
Involve like all of Asia in the hole
Area of the near East
How do you side with them like a bunch of bugs
But then
You know he faces
The big problem for most Empires throughout history
There's really only two big problems that they face one is that something will Swampert destroy them from without an enemy force or another
Nation state
For that you will
Collapse from within due to revolt and Rebellion
A lot of times the two of them work together
Assyrians had to deal with this all the time
The Persians did too even though the Persians are supposed to be sort of the
Kinder gentler near Eastern
Ancient nation state
But remember we're grading them on a curve
And the curve was set by a bunch of people who if you were bolted against them
They would cut your skin off you while you're still alive and you can go to the British Museum today
Stroll over to their ancient Assyria section
And you will see
Stone released at the Assyrian government paid for commission
Horse Soldiers
Skinning alive that person was the governor of that City who rebelled against us
For the benefit of anyone
Who views YouTube didn't have to be there at the time
For the next 3000 years
You could see why all of these ancient empires were so draconian
Two Rebels and traitors because that was such a huge threat to them how do you keep
You know people in line
When you give them a city to go ruling and you take the Army and go back home
What to keep them from just saying haha fooled you I'm going to side with the Egyptians now or I'm going totally free or whatever
Well we will do the most horrific things to you if you do that
Go to any premodern society
And you want to see the nastiest things they can do to people
They pull out the really
Awful
Executions and tortures when they're dealing with Rebels and traitors
You go back to
In England for example in the Middle Ages had one
Where
The first thing that they would do to you
Is rip out your intestines and barbecue them in front of you
Are you are alive while all this is happening which makes this a three-dimensional experience you are feeling smelling
Seeing the whole nine yards
And if they're doing this
Particular execution
Go to the nth degree than they will hang you but they will cut you down
Let you down before you die revive you
Do it a few more time
Enable tie
Each of your limbs to a separate horse
And those four horses will pull your four limbs in four different directions
That is called being drawn and quartered
Usually reserved
Rebels and traitors
Assyrians
Had all sorts of things that they did and
Collective punishment was the rule of the day
So if you were entrusted with in the Syrian City and your job was to keep it
In a loyal and all that and you
Stab the king of Assyria in the back
He wasn't just going to cut your skin off you were going to get to watch
People you love die in front of you mean there's a reason they call some of those punishments biblical
Cuz if those are is right
Kill your family in front of you then I will blind you so that was the last thing you see wow
Was Sarah Wright in the Assyrians were
Amongst the roughest practitioners
But they held together
A big Empire for a long time that
Persians have always been sort of
Portrayed
As an attempt to see if you can get away
With leniency what do we say knife in you with leniency
At least compared to the way the Assyrians ran the show
And see if that made people more willing
To live under the rule right of the Assyrian artwork was so horrific
Some of the experts think because they're trying to tell people this is what will happen to you
If you were about to try to get out of the Empire if you look at the Persian stuff that has survived
There is no artwork like you Siri and stuff
The Persians do not have any artwork or or lease or stone carving showing them torturing anyone
They actually have Persian officials holding the hands of people that are recognizable before you can date them you can go
Oh look they're holding the hand of a carry in there
Older holding up assideans had that is by Design the Persian propaganda
As opposed to be a Syrian propaganda
Is that the people who are in their empire
Like that
But they enjoy being in the Empire that is mutually beneficial that it's an Empire by choice
Keeping you here you want to be in the Persian Empire it's good for everybody
As we said the earlier show the person who dolphin sell that too
Donations before they went to war to do we really have to
To do this
It'll listen you join us and everybody will be better off I mean that's the way they sold the empire
In terms of its propaganda it's it's carved in stone propaganda
And they generally compared to the in a curve of that era and that area were generally pretty lenient unless of course
You rebelled against them
Who told that story and story and maybe
From Herodotus describing what happened to the Egyptians
20 earlier Persian king took over the Egyptians
An Egyptian had to be punished for mistreating some diplomats
Erotica sez
And this would be very person to do that all the nobles were gathered for the aristocracy of Egypt
Not the poor people who had nothing to do with the decision making
Upper-crust brought them in and then brought their children in in front of them
And executed the boys 2000 of them
Including
Is the king of Egypt kid
And sold an equal number of girls into slavery
We have wondered
That sounded
Remember that still a scene in my head what's the movie scene like that how do you recreate that for the film
Nonetheless that kind of collective punishment Was Not Unusual at all
Which makes you wonder
You know if if that's what faces you
Let's just say you're the governor your name is borrow
And you run a Syrian City that's about the Persians have taken over and they've come in there
Find a bunch of documents with you and you maybe prick your finger with blood in you
Put at the bottom of the. Yes I will be loyal to the Persian Empire and then for some reason my dad a good reason who knows
Uribel
And the person come back because what are the odds
But that rebellious city is going to manage to
Avoid being recaptured
And the Persians do something horrible to you and your family when you know you let your imagination run wild the Persians have punished
I called the boats for example are sometimes called the ordeal of the boats
Which is
Top three always on my top three worst execution methods of all time
Along with
Also the death by a Thousand Cuts of the Chinese that wasn't
Diabolic
I was thinking Myself by the way you know what this Persian
Penalty somebody had to come up with this
Somebody invented this
Wonder if they'd be proud to find Alison
2500 years later we're still talking about
But the message supposedly again this comes from Greek author so who knows
But the method was to get a couple of boats like canoes or flat bottom boats or whatever you no small affair
But that fit together to put one upside down on the other one you have like a perfect little
And it would stick the person to be executed in the bottom boat
Then they would
Put the top coat on top of the but they would leave the head the hands in the feet out
According to the authors
And then they would feed the person in the boat a lot of milk and honey and then smear it all over their face
And then you leave them in the Sun
Or set the boat adrift on a calm lake in the Sun
And sources differ on what was worse but apparently your face would get covered with insects attracted by the milk and honey
But also of course you're stuck in that boat so
You do what nature requires you to do
And the worms and the bugs and everything basically
Eat You Alive
According to the ancient Greek author Plutarch writing
It took one guy 17 days to die
That's
Who came up with that idea
But if that's what you know faces you if your city rebelles
Why on Earth would you ever do that
So I think about our ancestors I can't decide if they're just unbelievably badass
Or if maybe
You know our whole concept of what's horrible has been changed by softening * I mean
Are the countries that still execute people consider the
Penalty to be the deprivation of life right one
When you're executed United States a lot of stay still just put you to sleep
And you're being punished by losing the rest of the years that you otherwise would have had
In the ancient world of the Middle Ages
Death is not the punishment
That is the byproduct the punishment is the pain you suffer on the way to dying
Just getting your head cut off in some of these places if you were Rebel is cheating Justice
So maybe we who put
Are executed criminals to sleep maybe to us the ordeal of the boats is unbelievable but maybe to the people of the time
I need to go
I'll take it over being flayed alive
Braiding everything on a car
Right
Nonetheless the whole reason that the Greeks are fighting right that they get drawn into war with Persia to begin with
Have to do with revolts that happened
In Greek cities
On the coast of modern-day turkey
The ionian
So you have that did well you know but it must not happen too often
No in the next
Do years right after the Battle of Marathon maybe and maybe even tied to the outcome of mean the Persian get asset
Look back at Marathon all the sudden Egypt revolts
And whereas the Greeks and that whole Greek World in Europe
Is like the fringes of the backwaters of nowhere
Right
Egypt has been described by a bunch of historians as the crown jewel
Of the achaemenid Persian
And like there
Cultural equals in Babylonia
Next to impossible to rule successfully
Egyptians and the Babylonians are notoriously difficult
Kadabra
Part of it is because these are popular societies are Urban societies with crowds and
And I mean in Egypt for example right after this are there will be a lot of documentation about how
If you don't pay enough attention to the general public on the ground they Riot and they start burning and destroying stuff tomorrow I've been places
Lake Alexandria
Which doesn't exist yet of course but
Legendary
Sending the Babylonia mean that there's so many people in such a small area
You got to watch the crowd control a little bit
Loss of both those places have unbelievably high levels of
Cultural achievement and they're aware of
Their heritage
Egypt
In a lot of places you have to do nothing but look toward the horizon
And see
Pyramids
There are 2000 years old
In this era
When they're almost as old to the achaemenid Persians
As he commanded Persians are to watch now
And if you're Egyptian
You're thinking to yourself who are these barbarians who just appeared on the scene look at my ancestors were building
In mythical time
Can you imagine what a person in for
90 BCE thought about something
2018 conceptualize something two thousand years before that we have to leave in
I don't even think they could get their mind around the whole
The pyramids
Both the Babylonians Egyptians very well-developed
Religious hierarchies with tons of different priesthood religion that they were very powerful and influential
Anytime you can speak for God
That's some credibility you can use against
Anyone
Which of all these places difficult to control
And when Egypt for bells
Herodotus says
The driest essentially finds out about it right around the same time he finds out
About what happened
At Marathon in Greece and here's the way the ancient screenwriter
Showrunner
Herodotus colorizing history
Really for the first time ever with personalities and dialogue
And you know significant plot development
This is what Herodotus writes about it and this comes from my
Purvis Edition and by the way it says hello
What he means grease or Athenians
The Wright School
Weather report of the Battle of Marathon reached Jiraiya's
Some of his bass fish
Would already been thoroughly exasperated by the Athenians attack on Sardis
Hina reacted with a much more intense Fury
And became even more determined
To make war on have less than he had been before
At once he began to issue commands and to send Messengers throughout the cities of the empire
With instructions to each of them
To provide a great deal more than they have provided previously
Including horses
Warships
And transport boats the announcement of these orders through Asia into commotion for 3 years
Have the best man were enlisted to serve in the Army had to make preparations for war against hella
Then in the fourth year the Egyptians have been enslaved by Campisi's
Revolted from the Persian
Which only increased psoriasis desire to go to war but now against both people
And quote
As we said though before he can do those things
This ruler who would be in charge of the Persian Empire in Uber competent way
For more than 30 years
Dies
Generally considered to be around
64 years old
Keeping with the mysterious nature of the early achaemenid Persian kings
History doesn't record how to rise die
That's pretty common by the way I mean the founder of the Empire that was the greatest figures in all world history
The Great
Tony knows how he died you might have died in bed
Unnatural death
Of course
The traditional story is
He was killed
Is body found on the battlefield
The head chopped off and shoved into a wine skin filled with human blood by a vengeful homicidal
Central Asian Queen
What you don't know right
His son can buy sees a guy who gets the first
You know absolute power corrupts absolutely
Treatment on the part of the Greek writers
He could have stabbed himself with a sword tip accidentally gotten gangrene died
Or could have been something more nefarious you don't know
The next Persian king is the one who was either
Cyrus's other Sunday
Heir-to-the-throne or some usurper some Magi from outside the
Royal Line
We know how that one died because the person who killed him by hand
Bragged about it for the rest of his known
That is that guy just
Died after ruling version for 36 years
His name was derived
The Great
Psoriasis
As a guy who came from outside the direct Royal Line himself
Seem to have done a pretty good job trying to make sure
That the right son got the job and it was all understood who was going to get it
Although the ancient altar of allude to
Some potential problems
Cuz these Persian kings first of all like a lot of ancient Kings don't just have one wife they have several legitimate why
And then they often have a ton of concubines
Some of these Persian kings will have more than a hundred children
Find that funny when they talk about
You know often the Persian kings will put close family members in charge of important things
They had a lot of them
In this case
Steve
In a potential pool
Successors seem to have only included those of the legitimate wives
And then it seemed to boil down to two boys
The first one was
Psoriasis oldest son
The second one was derives his oldest son born
After he became king this is something that's important I guess
If you're worried about something to do with the
Mythical Blue Blood nature in the religious conception again
You're a different guy after you become king and the child you sire after that point might have something
That the one you sired before you work
Didn't have any this is kind of the way a logical
Debate on the subject ghost 2500 years ago at least
That's the way Herodotus would have explained
So the guy who gets
The gig
Is the oldest son born
After Jiraiya's becomes king
His name in Persian
Will sound something like
Tasha yes sir
Remember of course that's an approximation I am
Multilingual
In my ability to mispronounce
Names for mini lights
Which is
Severe that in mind of course he's known to history by different name and he's probably
The most well-known and famous King of the achaemenid Persian
Dynasty
By the name of Xerxes
He also happens to be
Grandson
Of Cyrus the Great the founder of the Empire this King Arthur like figure
Remember
Durant ISD
Perhaps usurper himself with smartweed said he kind of like a married into Henry Ford's family vanilla
He was running the Ford auto company
Well this would be like Henry Ford's grandson
Psoriasis was careful to marry Cyrus the Great daughter
When he became
The leader of Persia
This kid's mom this is his mom is Cyrus the Great's daughter
The Royal bloodline of this Uber competent guy may be chosen strictly on Merit for me
Select pool of aristocratic oyster is the grade
Cyrus the Great a a mythical figure already
In Persian Society were told
That they based
Their views on male handsomeness
Based on Cyrus's sort of design whenever he look like that's the uberman and anybody who's got that kind of knows and that kind of harem
Like Cyrus you look the more perfect you are
So this is an amazing characters of the Beast Cyrus's grandson
Let's just say there's a lot of Promise in this kid a lot of hype and high expectations
Are you going to live up to that
Xerxes is also hindered historically speaking by the fact that
The portrayal of him fits nicely into into a couple of different narrative
Which of the way this story has always been told one involve the idea of decline
The other involves the idea
Of a life cycle where decline is the last day
Only recently have historians really
Thrown out or mostly thrown out this idea that there
There's a life cycle of Empires if you will
The idea that once upon a time you have people who are poor and their poverty makes them sort of tough in the
Toughness of their poverty in the values and the discipline in the Spartan lifestyle
Create the kind of people who can conquer or amass territory to create an empire
Which brings in lots of money in affluence and then eventually
You know you hit the sweet spot
Will you have the best mixture of the old rocking discipline values
Did you had when you were poor
But also the cultural advancements and what not to come
With some affluence in some leisure time and all that
And then eventually you know the the life cycle of Empires
Culminates with the downhill slope with Voltaire called the silk slippers wooden shoes going upstairs
Slippers going downstairs
The luxury in the affluent bringing on decadence in the decadent Springs on softness of luxuriant weakness
And then in this hobbesian survival of the fittest kind of
World that you get taken over by the new poor people on the Block
Find the values your ancestors used to possess
Xerxes is often seen and often portrayed
Is the beginning of sort of the rich kid
Era of Persian kings of the ones who
Didn't have to earn in Empire they grew up in that right I grew up as a king son
And it's just a little
Right sure they taught me how to ride I had to throw the spear and they they made me run five miles and and do all these things that prove.
I was taught but I'm still the rich kid son
Richest man in the world son
Any idea
Xerxes his failings are
Multitude of things by the way but the classic
Stereotype of Xerxes is the guy who couldn't stay out of the harem
Love the women hung out in the Harem all the time and like to drink his wine who is drinking a lot of wine hanging out with a lot of chicks
And dissipating as they would have said
Amongst the old boxing trainers
Dissipating
Week
The beginning of the downhill slide in the Persian Empire
The decline if you will
Begins you know
The Pierre breandan others will all point out the list of the high-water mark of the empire for using the old line way of measuring this
Is it expanding in territory or is it contracted in territory
Well the height of territorial expansion is right around the time Xerxes takes over
And it never will be that big Again by the time it works he leaves so who do you blame for all that was historically speaking at
Hard not to look for a carport
Where does the buck stop in
Absolute monarchy well
Whether or not its advisors or generals were really calling the shots
The buck usually stops with the absolute monarch in this case that Xerxes
Once again
The poor guy deserved or not get stuck with the bill
And blamed for being the first of the Persian kings to rule
As the Empire has crossed the
You know peak of its performance in his beginning the downhill slide up the first of the kings use voltaire's analogy to behead
Heading down the stairs of civilization
Height in silk slippers is
Traditionally
Xerxes
Is Rehabilitation
Has been going on for almost
Well just say 50 years with Peter Green in 1970 I remember reading that book
But even before that
Right after the second world war with writing his history the Persians and Xerxes was called misunderstood in Moline
Find figure
But here's how green put it
In 1970 the book it's pretty long in the tooth now when you realize how many things
They discovered about ancient Persia but even back then
Trying to recapture Xerxes historical reputation
From
2400 years of media where he become a stock character basically
Green rights quote
Are traditional picture of Xerxes is a caricature
Put together from hostile and finklea contemptuous Greek propaganda
We see him as a small blubbering effeminate Oriental
A cowardly desperate ruled by his women and his eunuchs
Cruel and Victory
Spineless in defeat
Persian sources
No doubt he writes equally Prejudice in the opposite direction
Reveals a very different man
Tall
Regal and handsome he stands in the persepolis release
And his Proclamation have a ringing dignity which Echoes down Through the Ages
I was quoting the proclamation by Xerxes quote
A great God is Ahura Mazda
Who created this Earth
Who created man
Who created peace for man
And who made Xerxes King
One king of many
One Lord of many
I am Xerxes the great king King of Kings King of lands containing many men
King in this great Earth far and wide
Son of Darius the king
Aniki meaning
A Persian
Son of a Persian
An Aryan of Aryan seed
Winter why is my father passed away
Buy the wheel of a horror Mazda
I became king
And quote
You know it's easy to say
Did all this stuff you have from these Greek writers for example is all movie making and it's all falsify to me where different
Herodotus of dialogue come from after all he think he was working for transcripts
So it's easy to say all that stuff should be thrown out because all these people in the story rather than being historical figures are more like
Characters
But if you do that what do you replace it with
Tina Brown says that many times in his book if you get rid of Herodotus cuz he's so inaccurate what do you replace it with
The only time you appreciate the guys when you lose them cuz
He will after 479 BCE and then
There's not even Herodotus anymore
So it's
It's part of what makes the job of a historian fascinating to think of those people that historians having to tease out
The facts in the haystack of fiction
You know that are these stories and these plays and what not to try to figure out could this be true could that be true and then can they check it summer
Or else again some other evidence they may have
I mean it's a detective story as we said in the earlier part of this Tale
Mean take for example
The fact
That you begin to see some significant for Trails of women
In the story in the Persian Empire
Are witches great cuz everyone knows
Women get the short end of the stick in so much historical writing
But you have to ask yourself as a detective don't you if you're a historian which I'm not
Is why all of a sudden
Do you see women when you didn't see as many of them before
Are they there because there's a legitimate reason to have them cuz they're always is right we all understand it's half the population there was 30
Some Authority somewhere
Were they there because
The Storyteller requires them as a tool to do something else
In this case it's very easy to see how sometimes
These Persian women who sometimes are shown as like Dragon Lady
Wright motor really scary
I mean on the level of Alexander the Great's mother Olympia's who is another wonderful carry
But she's all real
As far as I can tell but I mean these murderous dragon ladies are they there because they really were these murderous Dragon Lady
Court women were like
Were they there because they play Into The Stereotype of the Harem in the women beginning to dominate the men and these Persian men are
Sitting there drinking and drunk and they don't even care what's going on in the women are needing them for their man
Wonder Woman Herodotus has doing that though
Is somebody that there's nothing you could do to color
Her greatness any other color but magnificent
This is one of the greatest figures
Certainly maybe the greatest female figure in the history of the Persian Empire
At only the barest facts of her are known but the barest facts by themselves are testimony to in
Amazing life
The person who specialist shines through
When all you really have are few names and dates and facts
Her name
What's a Tulsa
Or at least that's what the Greeks called
She was Xerxes as mother
Herodotus basically says
The main reason Xerxes was chosen over anyone else's because of the influence of Batwoman
But that she would have that influence should surprise nobody listen to the fact that comprises woman's life
And look at how it shows
A woman who was at like
The sauron's eye level of the historical
Focusing Vortex I mean
She's Cyrus the Great's daughter
That's like being Napoleon's daughter chinggis Khan daughter Julius Caesar's daughter
You name it
And she's there when the Empire's being one informed and or I mean
That's the vortex of history in that part of the world to me as we said he's probably the greatest conqueror in world history up to that point and this is
This is girl
And she's there Wallet app
She will then marry his successor
Cyrus's successor
Embassy
Not only will she then be married to her brother
But when can buy cease dies
Remember we had that very weird situation where Maybe Can't Buy sees his brother look the legitimate Heir takes over or maybe
Seizes the throne either way whoever it is that gets on the throne
He marries a Tulsa to
So she either marry her real brother again
She married the
Fake usurper
Whose blood shouldn't have contaminated her super royal blue blood at all
And the guy who may be killed
Her brother
She been married
Darius the great when he takes over
And remember
When he takes over he either did so by killing
The real heir to the throne brother husband
The Magi guy who seized the throne in which case he saved her from that
In a low level
Person who should never have been anywhere near the kingship
No matter which of those stories are true that's an amazing life right there
I look at it this way
This is a woman was either the daughter the mother or the wife
Of the first
5 Kings of the achaemenid Persian Empire which by the way includes their greatest Kings
Wouldn't surprise anyone if she had a little influence at court would it
We can tell by reading about her
The little bit that seep through the she's not like some shrinking violet Prize or something it just gets passed around you can
Tell that she's valuable
For what she knows that she's raised in this environment as I said you know when you're in the center of that vortex
All this history being made
Mitsubishi sounds like a political animal like someone who knows how to move the levers of power and influence
Rule through husbands and Sons and he's a fascinating character she's probably
The most famous powerful character
The female character in achaemenid Persian Empire history
The fact that so little is still known about her
Just shows you
How much does Sarah is still sort of covered in a gray mist
With only the most bright and luminary characters
You know dimly appearing from the other side but a Tulsa is one of them
Atosa Sun
Xerxes will sort of have the opposite problem of his mother whereas
We have some facts and not enough color to flesh it out with her
With Xerxes whatever facts you have are so overwhelmed by the color
It's difficult to figure out who the guy you're dealing with really is
Way back in the early 1960s historians like a r burn
Pointed out that
There are some good qualities of Xerxes that even creep into the original sources like Herodotus
Monroe quotes
Xerxes lives in the Greek tradition is the arch enemy
Presented naturally in an unfavorable light
Herodotus more generous to the enemy than later writers alone presenting in the round
Is Xerxes has a Persian love of natural beauty
He enjoys being munificent on a princely scale
He can forgive surrendered enemies
Even though surrendered in atonement for a war crime
He weeps for compassion over the mortality of mankind
He is easily roused rage by opposition
He is cruel when crossed even those lately favored
He has uncontrolled in Lost in it hard a coward
It is a well-conceived literary portrait
The character of an oriental Prince
Born of good stock
Brought up to rule but not to tolerate opposition or Endura setback
There may be much truth in
And quote
You're my favorite erotica stories about
Xerxes is the one where
He tells the Spartan of the Spartans trying to reconstruct their damaged, I guess you could say for lack of a better
Edward we told the story a while back that when the Persians in the Spartans first got together
The Persian symptom diplomats in the After Earth and water which is the traditional token of submission in the Spartans
So you can get yours and water down there which of course kills them
But this is like a violation of the ancient world's version of international law
The gods frown upon treating diplomats like that
And supposedly the Oracle start giving the Spartans all these bad
Pronouncements for a while and they try to figure out okay how are we going to
Repair this karma for lack of a better word and basically they come up with this idea
But if they send a couple of Spartans
To the king of the Persians and he can do with
Them what you want
Presumably he's going to kill them and we're going to even the score here
Did the Spartans ask for volunteers and some older
Wealthy Spartans maybe looking to
Find one last thing they can do you no further duty to the state volunteer to go be the sacrificial victim to show up
Xerxes court and say they're there to repair the karma and pay the karmic bill
For the death of the Persian diplomats and Xerxes says go home
Because you think I'm going to violate international law
A little like your parents saying two wrongs don't make a right that's kind of the way Xerxes it portrayed which is a pretty cool way to be all
Although there's perhaps a more intelligent way to look at it maybe Xerxes is thinking to himself
Wait a minute
So they kill diplomats and get Bad Karma and now they want me to do the same thing no thank you I'd rather keep my
Karma untainted thank you very much go home this morning
That's a good portrait of Xerxes cuz otherwise he's mostly Voldemort
Or Darth Vader in the story
Other part of the fun is
He's like Darth Vader Who besides his black ominous getup happens to be wearing
Voltaire silk slippers at the same time so it's a little bit.
Little bit of a softer version perhaps in
And maybe something a little bit more luxurious
And wealthy and maybe just a hint of decadence um
More than the earlier Kings who came before him
Wechat the way it's always portrayed
I'm sure the Egyptians would not have thought that the Persians were any softer than they had been when Xerxes takes the Army his father
There was gathering to go punish the Greeks
And uses it against the Egyptians wood recently revolted
The literary Traditions have Xerxes being the first of the uncool Persian kings cuz if we said
Cedar reputation for soda coming in there and saying so you can keep doing business the way you want to keep your religion keep your way of doing things
Are there any new Boston town to order a hands-off all of a sudden Xerxes by the
In the writings of the Greek starts to look like the jerk
Goes into Egypt and start saying no more of this you don't get through this your way any more taxes room take more people for
Building projects in
Egyptians are mad
But in a way you can kind of see the Persians point-of-view if they've been lenient with Egyptians all this time and Egyptians are still a pain in the
At what point does the pressure ratchet up to finally get tough on these people
Looking it up in the Persian point of view
Maybe you would say you're selfish and we tried to leave me in the Pro for these people time and time again
And they keep rebelling
Or maybe the whole thing is made up and it's all Greek propaganda and Xerxes ever did any of this
Would you know he crushed the Rebellion I don't need your PIN stay good for
A short period of time
The Judean this way also have revolted during this. The Babylonians Revolt twice
When you think yourself what
Revolting
Punishments are going to happen to all these people who Revolt you would think the revolts would be fewer and farther between but they're not
And it should be pointed out that this is just the stuff we know about in Persia's West trying to
Divine history Persians like trying to Divine the history of the Moon
There's a light Side of the Moon that you can see and that's the side of Persia that faced Greece in the written about extensively
And it was near Babylon and Egypt in the other societies that kept Good Records
And then there's the Dark Side of the Moon which is everything
To the east of Persia which is a huge expanse of territory going up into modern-day Afghanistan and Pakistan
Just like that
That's almost
Completely invisible
In terms of the historical record
The Persians may have had amazing battle and dealt with monstrous revolts over there we just don't know
Xerxes crushes efficiently the Revolt in these very important places in the Persian Empire
Egypt and Babylonia
My favorite story and Babylonians perhaps what you might call
The final solution to the Babylonian problem but it's not what you might think
They found during archaeological digs I guess a receipt
Maybe you could call it
For a
Statue taken from Babylon
When the Revolt is crushed
By Xerxes the statue is the famous statue of the Babylonian God Marduk
Supposed to be solid gold
13 ft tall somewhere between 800 and 1300 lb
And this is the statue that anyone who wanted to be the ruler of Babylonia had to grasp the hands of
That was called grasping the hands of Marduk
Very important religious ceremony
When the Persians took that statue and apparently melted it down
They eliminated the ability of Marduk to grasp anybody's hands ever again
Hahaha we got your God
Isn't that what we said in the last version of the tale
The politics of dealing with the gods of local communities is fascinating fascinating aspect
Annie's early societies
And now what were the Babylonians going to do if they wanted a new local ruler
Mardels hands have been melted forever
I suppose if you're Babylonian that
Is a pretty big black mark next to Xerxes name forever in your book isn't it
What he hates God understand
After crushing these revolts
Xerxes will turn his attention now to finishing a job his father began
The job of conquering this Troublesome people
Who inhabit
The European mainland
People that after the Battle of Marathon have had a good 10 years to prepare
For the return of the Persians remember
You might think of the Battle of Marathon is an Athenian or a Greek Victory but really all that they had done there is Perry
Persian blow
The Persian second blow should have come a lot sooner but they have the death of a king who's been on the throne for 36 years that'll throw off your
Game a little bit
Then the succession then the crushing of multiple revolts not Ten Years After the Battle of Marathon
The Persians are ready for blow number two and blow number two is going to make Blow number one look like a cat
The preparations for this next Invasion will take
Years
And will be visible to all the Greeks could not have been surprised
Some of the things that the Persians were doing just
The way for the next time they showed up
In a war hard to hide me for example
The last time the Persians were there
They had problems crossing the peninsula around a certain Mountain
Your feet have been wrecked
Right at the tip of the point of the peninsula
So this time
It's been three or four years ahead of time
Digging a canal more than a mile long right through the
The neck of the peninsula right at the base
Even have to go around the next time
Ancient author said two triremes can pass side-by-side
In the canalon apparently they can find remnants of it today
But that's the kind of thing that takes thousands and thousands of people and years and
The Greeks would have no
In addition unlike the last assault
In which culminated at the Battle of Marathon which was essentially an amphibious Landing
Which is kind of cool for this. When you think about the capabilities I mean moving Army
Shippan landing and supporting them and all that that's really cool but this time
They were going to go with more the old-fashioned route which leads a lot more historians cuz there's no agreement on this
To think that the second time the Persian come around this time LED in person by Xerxes the great king of
Kings
This time it's a full invasion this is not a punitive Expedition
This is not something to
In a scare the locals all although history NPR Breon points out that this also would have been something
That the new King Xerxes would have used as a way to show the flag
And it's all the peoples your March the Army through their territory on the way to some other goal
And it has the subsidiary effective
Reminding the locals
You know who their King is
Dissuade any attempt to change that situation
Nonetheless if they're going to invade by land this time so they can take what is reported to be the largest army that
Did ever invaded anywhere in the world up until this time although let's remember these people did not know anything about the Chinese so
Take that out of your equation who knows how those numbers would have stacked up
Unless you can't move in army that
Over the sea
So you going to move it over the lad you going to attack Europe from Asia there's only one problem as you probably divined
There's water that separates Europe from Asia it's not very much and it's a strip but it's famous
The Dardanelles
The Greeks called it
Palace Spa
Wide enough and with a strong enough current though to give anybody fits
Can't build a solid Bridge wouldn't last
Got to figure out a way around the problem
Diversion start doing that too
They begin to build floating Bridges across
At least two spots
The divide Europe from Asia
I think the narrow is like 1700
Yards around there but I think there's one that's like two miles long
The first bridge is destroyed
By the current in the storm so Xerxes has the
Men Who Built it the other ones in charge
Beheaded
Within told
In a wonderful piece of her autistic that is a lot of color and that may have been true but who knows what the reason is
We're told the Xerxes orders
The water itself to be punished
For such activity
He has his men
Wade into the water this is from Herodotus though take it with a grain of salt this Monday just been a great movie scene who knows
But he says that Xerxes has been with the water with whips brand the water with Hot Irons
Throwing Federation like handcuffs into the water
And skull the water all the time while doing it for essentially being naughty
This is what Herodotus write
Xerxes did after finding out his first attempt
To build the bridge have been thwarted by a storm
Herodotus quotes
Xerxes was infuriated when he learned of this
He ordered that the hellespont was to receive 300 lashes under the whip
Another pair of shackles was to be dropped into the sea
And I've also heard that he sent others to Brand the hellespont
In any case he instructed his men to say Barbarian an insolent things as they were striking the hellespont
I was quoting what the men were saying is they with the water
Quote
Bitter water
Your master is imposing this penalty upon you for wronging him
Even though you had suffered no Injustice from him
And King Xerxes will crush you whether you like it or not
You just for just cause after all didn't know human offers you sacrifice
You are a turbid and Briny River
And quoting a neurologist says
Dusty order that the sea was to be punished
And also that the supervisors of the bridge over the hellespont where to be beheaded
Change quotes
Xerxes look like a bit of a nutjob there don't you
And maybe he was absolute power corrupts absolutely sometimes rides are cheese may have thought that made a difference on the other
And I always try to think of
These people is cynical just to see if there's a cynical answer for some of the stuff and I mean
Theoretically look at how
Bad it looks for the King of Kings is bridge to be destroyed by something that would appear to be an act of God to the logo
Almost certainly turned out to watch everything
Maybe the way you pacify the Rubes
And you
In a quell any worries that somehow
Maybe God's not happy with the King
Is the blame it on the water
And punish it
Parsley
Maybe this was a public relations stunt
Make the people know that the water was acting out of turn
And it won't do it again
Xerxes gets to work on the bridge again and they end up
Building at least one maybe two across the water using boats
We're told what they do is they put these boats
Side by side by side with the bow facing the current and then they last them all together they were
Boats strings of boats together
Then they lay planks
Across the boats and then they put sides up
Product assist to keep the animals from looking over the side and seeing the water and getting spooked
Then they put dirt down and pack it down
And all of a sudden you have a floating Bridge something they can handle the current because it can move up and down and be flexible
All of a sudden there's a bridge
Between Asia and Europe that a giant
Nasty
Persian Army in Cross
With all its Cavalry and baggage and supplies and everything
These are the kind of engineering feats
That the Persians and the entire
Part of the world whose Heritage they were the inheritors of
Could do so well
Military engineering
And the Greeks were
Justifiably scared but it's important to point out
The best stories always emphasized there is no grease at this point
And there is no sense of national Greek
Consciousness
The people thought of things more in terms of the city-state they were from
Which is why they had so many problems with each other
A lot of this story that were telling here was actually created after the fact
As part of some historians think of
I'm a literary creation of a past Unity that may or may not have ever existed
But that this
Event which is really to the ancient Greeks the equivalent of like
Their second world war in terms of the
Interest in the fascination and how disruptive and important a thing it was and how how people talk about the long after
How many books and movies and everything we still sell on that event
This in part explains
You know why it's so exaggerated in there so much meth built on top of it so hard to
Tweeze the little facts from the fiction and then throwing all the western civilization stuff come
In a long after that and
Becomes hard to discern what really happy
But you can certainly tell
The Greeks are not foolish and they can see odds
And when they're not even really Greeks but in this case Athenians on one hand
We're spartans on the other hand thebans or are guys or corinthians
In other words
The Persian Empire against Greece is no contest the Persian Empire against some Greek city-states
Is less than Oconto
In fact even seen this
In the traditional sense of Greeks against Persians
Is probably not accurate archaeologist Warwick ball who's trying
Against
All odd cuz of the sources
To look at this more from a Persian point of view
Would point out that in the end
You have more Greeks
Fighting on the side of the Great
King of kings of Persia
Then with his Brethren the Greeks
Supposedly fighting for Greek freedom
So things may be a lot more complicated
Ten thousands of years of historical
Tweaking
Make it appear to be today
One of my favorite part of the story though happens now
When the Greeks do what people in this era did when you're worried about something and you need advice
They went to the Gods
And the Greeks go to the most famous of all the Oracles in this part of the world
Delphi
The speak to the representative of Apollo
Who kind of channels the voice of the god
Threw herself
It's one of the fascinating parts of this this are in human history
I think in when we were talking about Babylonian earlier and we talked about
Magic 8 Balls and Ouija boards and how weird it was to almost have that side
Are the metaphysical be so connected to things like policy decision
Should we invade this country or not
Shake a Magic 8-Ball sources say yes ask again later
Outlook is positive immuno
It is
Crazy soda to the modern mind
But once again there are multiple ways of viewing it
Some of them much more cynical that
Could suggest that some of this stuff
Was only
Metaphysical
To maybe the rank-and-file on the ground maybe the sophisticated people working this
Eric langill
I totally different way for example
The kings of Persia traditionally gave lots of good stuff to all the order
Liam play any favorites and they covered all their bases
Why taking a chance
And the Oracle of Delphi
Channeling the voice of the god of Apollo
Was friends with the Persians that the Persians were friends with the god Apollo and they proved it many times in material ways
The Oracle of Delphi was
Usually Pro Persian
In this case the Athenians go to basically say
Okay we know the great King's coming back and we're trying to work together to figure out some ideas and
You know maybe we should have a Navy maybe we should have an army maybe we should work with the Spartans mean
Let's ask a little advice go to the
Pythia Indigo in this Temple
There's a woman there
Supposedly
They are matronly didn't like 50 years old cuz once they used to be like teen virgin and it didn't work out too well
So they just dressed he's 50 year old women like
Teens
Put them on
A tripod that was in a cauldron Maybe
I don't know exactly but one of those
Accounts of the disc called and had like little air holes
In the bottom
So that the fumes
From a crack in the earth that they were placed over
Could seep up through the cauldron into their nostrils
And allow them to channel the god
This is a fascinating thing you could go into oracle's forever
I love diodorus siculus as a
Account of how they even found this was a crack in the earth he says in it
A sheep from a Shepherd fell into the crack in the shepherd went in to look for the sheep and all of a sudden
You know he could see the past and he could see the future and he was
Well
It's wild stop and historians and scientists ever since I've been trying to figure out
Assuming it's true
What the heck made this woman the pythia she was causing it was associated with snakes by the way so that makes it more exotic and
Interesting and weird
Yeah what she was on what she was taking what she chewing Laurel leaves are Oleander leaves or something or
Was there something to this idea of
Crack in the Earth
That she's sad over and the fumes did it to her told the hair stood on end skin change color they spoke in tongues
Songs
Suspiciously sometimes you couldn't understand a word they said and they have these handlers
You know who kind of interpreted here's what she saying
And sometimes even with the interpretation you had to go back
You know your city and it was like reading a fortune cookie and you had to start a debate with that said that's really how
Helpful they have to do that a lot with an okay here's what she said what the heck does that mean I think it means this woe course you would you want to do that anyway
I think it means that we'll of course you would that your point of view so many things like that sometimes
In this case
When you things basically say you know what we do about the Persians were coming back
The Oracle gives one of its most fire and brimstone and scary
Pronouncements I've ever read
Her giving or unless you want to stay at the Apollo
The Oracle says
Why is it so idle
You poor Wretched Man
To the ends of the land you should flee
Leave your homes leave the heights of your circular Fortress
Bonita the head nor the body remains in it
Place
Ignore the feet underneath
Northern hands northern middle
Is left as it was
Now all
Skewer
Forecasting it down
Aspire
An Aries so sharp on the heels of Assyrian chariot
And he will destroy many cities with Towers
And not yours alone
I need to the devouring fire he will give the temples of Eternal gods
Witching out dripping with sweat
And shaking their fear
As blood gushes Darkly from the top of their roofs
Foreseeing the force of
Compelling disaster
Step out of the shrine
And shroud over your heart
The evil
What's to come
I'd gone to the god Apollo to ask
What they should do in the face of
Persian invasion
When the god Apollo in no uncertain terms told them
Run for their lives
As you might imagine the Athenians are horrified
But that response in imagine if you really took this seriously how horrified you could be by
Somebody just prophesized your doom
They're encouraged to go back
Try to get another
So they may be like a follow-up question in in a roundabout way
And they're given one of those cryptic fortune cookie type responses which they take back to Athens and everybody starts.
Are you over
The bottom line though is
That it results in Athens deciding to build a Navy
Time it comes at the expense of Athens deciding to
Supporting Army was sort of an either-or proposition
But Athens will be known forever afterwards at a great Naval power this is where they develop
Really for the first time and they do it 2
Your take on the great king or at least give them
There's some ability to cope it's
Because not only does the great king have a massive Army
So were told
Give a massive Fleet as well
This time it's a battle Fleet as opposed to maybe an amphibious Landing
Toledo Supply Fleet although some historians think it's
Supplied the army
All the Army was marching
No wonder I was helping the Army was and nobody knows how big the fleet was
Herodotus as
One of the many exaggerated will claim that when all the people and their servants and everyone else is added up
Xerxes Army is more than 5 million men
This fleet has more than
A thousand ships
As we said earlier
Everybody knows those numbers are wrong but nobody knows what numbers are right
Everyone has a way of argue
But even if we play with relatively low Ball numbers and just say
50000 soldiers
Fifty thousand people is your average size
College football stadium is it a pretty good-sized
Football stadium
Xerxes Army
We'll be on the road for a long time
Imagine trying to keep 50000 people
In a stadium
Marching
Hundreds and hundreds of miles alive and well and ready to fight at a distant location and imagine
I'm trying to do that 2500 years ago
Xerxes Army will cross
Hellespont over the bridge
Erotic just says it took
7 days for the whole Army to cross
He runs down famously takes
Images of Herodotus
He runs down every
Contingent in the Army and he says 46 Nations took part
There's a reason they call the Persian king the king of kings
Because he ruled over a bunch of people
Still have their own Kings they just answered to the Persian king
Their kings were sometimes called
Going to put them on or take them off at will
Herodotus says that they all showed up
Enero
Traditional
Local garb
Ready to fight in their traditional ways write the Assyrians the last great military Empire this region would eventually
Turn them all into a serious it would look like Roman legionary they be uniform and they would all fight the same way the Persians
These units fight at whatever they were good at if you had a bunch of croatians
And they were nasty if you met him in the forest in the Hill Country
Will you bring them along and when you have somebody up in the hills giving you trouble you send the Thracians to go deal with them right
I have some Apache Scouts I keep them in case I'm fighting Apache
Herodotus goes down this list
And what strikes you when you read it and he goes into what they're armed with and what their clothing look like and what their facial features and ethnic features look like
Is that the Xerxes is bringing people's from
Three different continents with him to attack Greece
From Europe Asia and Africa
He's got sub-Saharan African troops
Ford roeske says in leopard and lion skins with Antelope horn Spears
Painting half their body white with chalk the other half
Red
I'm carrying six-foot-tall kanebo the supposedly only they could pull back to they were so strong
But with
Stone tipped arrows
I need hose down the list of all these exotic peoples and historians have been wondering ever since
What this mean to be people all get out there and fight
Is it symbolic instead in meant to convince people all along the way in a grease and everybody along the way look at the Majesty of the
The great king look at all these exotic people he has a zoo
And all these people are the animals in the great king is the zookeeper
They're all in their most
You know colorful feathers and look at my Army is In Bloom maybe it's like that
Some historians have suggested
All those people could be hostages
For the good behavior the rest of the Empire right how many revolted they've been dealing with and you're going to take this enormous Army and the
King of kings and take them to Europe
Doesn't encourage everyone to revolt well
What if you have two or three thousand
You know of the sons of the nobility of all those places with you on campaigns that's what the guarantee of good
Behavior
So that's been
Theorize
The core of the army of Persian
And related people's the ones who won the Empire the ones who hold the empire
The very dangerous group
Berserk cease has around him so he may have all these subject people but the people that are going to Bear the brunt of
This thing
Are desperately good fighter even though history in the Greek time is portrayed the Minnesota
Driven Along by the Lash
And nothing more than the slaves of the soap
Slipper wearing Darth Vader
Listen determinant number of people
Gather all through 481 BCE and was now modern-day turkey
In the spring of 480 BCE they will cross from Asia into Europe
Begin
If you're looking at a map to to go around a body of water and now descend on Grease
From above
From the north
Perhaps it is a sign of exactly how disunited the Greeks are
That would the Persian preparations that advanced and the Persian army bearing down on them the Greek still
Will have a hard time
In a crafting together any sort of Unified
Approach to dealing with the Persians rent in fact
And if you tell the story the old-fashioned way
There's a lot of politics going on right now is the Greek try to form this alliance system in what cities are going to stay out what cities are going to go in
Eventually only about 10% will join.
Buy Persian Alliance
But you can understand why I look at how
These city-states would have to bury their even recent
Differences with each other
Take Argos
For instance who just fought a war with Sparta where they lost 6,000 people
Now they're going to join an alliance of going to be General by a Spartan General
A lot of States Argos included will remain neutral against the Persian and a lot of states will join the Persians especially in the North End
Can't blame him because of the north is where the Persians are
Easy to flip the Persians the bird from down south
You know where Sparta is
Little different if you're up in thessaly
With the purge
Persian diplomacy with that much more effective would happen to have the Army there with it
Especially if it was all
Decked out a lot of feathers and warpaint a very exotic looking for
What three continents
This Royal Army is like a loaded gun
Cocked and pointed down
In a towards the mainland
Sometime around this time. The Athenians begin evacuating Athens
A lot of it by seeing
Herodotus
Makes it seem like a desperate effort to get the women and the children and the elderly in the slaves off
The mainland it off to these islands where they can hopefully be safe because the
Understanding uses if the Persians break into Central Greece which is
You're part of War Athens is feed places like that too
A scientist do
Remember the Oracle kind of said they needed to run well
They're taking it seriously they know that
Yeah they're on the Persians
Naughty list and probably the number one
Naughtiest Greek state in the eyes of the Persians and if the Persian get into Central Greece there's nothing there.
Removing right on Athens
So the Greeks end
A force to block the
Now
We get into areas now that are much are you by the experts
And I am not qualified to even have a favorite position
Amongst mm
The problems would have stems from Herodotus you know you were lying on this guy cuz you don't have anyone else
Coloring drama and story he's awesome
But when it comes to real military detail that you can reconstruct and make sense out of afterwards
Not so awesome
Heavily criticized
This and that and the other thing and so
Everything has to be taken with a grain of salt he may not even really
Understood well some of the military real
What is here
His ability to write though what probably amounts to some of the
This this guy is the guy who wrote
The oldest surviving
Battle scenes of the sort that we would know in literature and entertainment
Movies and everything else ever since I mean this
Herodotus histories is chock-full of battle scenes
Buy a screenwriter
An orphan that afro
The one he has for
Thermopylae is part of the reason Thermopylae has become
The greatest military Last Stand in history
Let me think about how many of those there must have been throughout the entire
Length and breadth of human affairs
Thousands and thousands of great Last Stand stories but if no one survived to write the account them
Do they like that proverbial tree falling in the forest does it make a sound if no one's there to hear it
And you also have to get it
By the way
From the sympathetic point of view
What's going to be the Battle of Thermopylae
It's going to sound very different if it's a Persian oral historian describing it to his audience then if Herodotus is describing it to Agra
Week 1
The moment with the Great
Including in his Entourage and exiled Spartan King
Arrived in front of the hot Gates
The blocking position that the Greeks have taken up on land Thermopylae
Cuz you're writing the Persian history of this
You basically say
Within a week
The great king forced
This position outflank turned this position that was the strongest engine
While at the same time killing the Spartan King a bunch of his elite soldiers
1000 or more other Greeks and a bunch of other Greeks ran away
You can add to that
That your Fleet
Thought a Greek blocking pleated place called Art Museum
We're told on like the same day
Both sides were
Roughly handle
Is the way historians like
The great term
But the Greeks ran away
Now they may have gone down to Athens because Athens at this point is evacuate
This is part of what also brings home the stakes of all this and it makes us
Sympathetic forever with the Greek cause on so many levels because all the story elements are in their favor
And when your
Can you get refugees and women and children and old people jumping onto ships to Fleet offshore Islands because they will
Die or be enslaved or something if they stay
Hard not to have some sympathy
When the story is about
You know 6 ft 5 in tall Giant
About to go beat up a four foot tall man
Again
Are natural
Sympathies tend to go to the underdog
The fact that you a lot of us
The Greeks are the home team for Western Civilization as we said earlier
And there are a lot of reasons
To not see the story The Way
The majority of people during this time. Not on the Greek side would have
Which is that the Greeks made what would have seemed like a relatively feeble effort to stop the great king at the pass of Thermopylae and the
Breaking brush them aside
In the ancient sources say he suffered 20000 dead
Look at the out of proportion
Casual
Spartans in there
Allies called
It's before buying remember he puts the Persians it over 5 million men
Do the math that means that they
Turn the strongest defensive positioning Breeze kill the Spartan King is
Guard basically and a bunch of other Greeks
At the cost of less than half a percent of his total Force
Most military commanders would take that any day
Wants to
Persians are through
Thermopylae there in the Central Greece and now the loaded weapon
Is right up against the head
Places like affirm
Thieves
Central Breeze
Now that story is much much better as you might expect
If you're listening to Herodotus tell it
Because we just told
You know the equivalent of the story of the Alamo
From the Mexican side
Which is we got a little delayed at the Alamo they killed a bunch of our guys no big deal but I'm with children last one of them we moved on
From the Greek point of view this is an inspirational account and it starts were told to be inspirational from the get-go
It had an effect on the war effort
But then it's been one of those
Things that have inspired people ever since
Herodotus says he's learn the name of all 300 Spartan
Who fell at the Bible
You could have gone back and told those people we'd still be talking about them
2500 years later I wonder what they react
She would be
Nonetheless
We would be remiss if we suggested they had only been 300 Spartans at this battle in the Persian show up and are blocked
Thermopylae
There are thousands of Greeks
On the other side of the
Now here's the thing to understand this past
Doesn't look the same today
That you go look at it now it doesn't look that
Composing but
If you go look at the Recreations of people have mocked up about where the water used to be
Which is receded
You basically have a narrow strip of beach between the mountains in the water
In some places the Ancient Order said it was so narrow you could hardly fit
A horse-drawn cart through at the normally like a hundred yards I saw one
Mockup suggesting
In any case the point
That makes it useful
Is nullify so many of the person's advantages If there really are more Persians
I can't really use those numbers 10
Can't get around
In the past like that the main person Advantage their Cavalry can't get around that you can basically have a solid line
Kind of armed and armored men
Stretching from the mountains to the Sea
It's a solid body of truth there's nothing you can do but go straight at it and going straight out of his what the Greeks were best
With the Persians
We're beginning to
Trouve
At least one facing Greeks
They weren't pasta
Now
If you have a long memory you will recognize that we have now come full circle
Go to where we actually began this Tale
The story of
In my mind's eye I see all these Spartan troops as
A manifestation of Clint Eastwood somehow
Herodotus has Xerxes and his
Advisor who happens to be an exiled King of Sparta himself as a pretty good advisor if you're looking at Spartans
Going over the finer points
The Spy said he went and looked at the past and saw these
Long haired Warriors combing their hair and doing bodyweight exercises
Xerxes turn to the Spartan king of 50 people the small group of people they're not going to try to contest the past are they and that's when
Yes they are
Kill me if I'm a liar
This dramatic tail
But the resistance of these Greeks dying for any number of themes that have been heaped upon this events
Since
Fidelity to the state
Loyalty to their comrades
Sacrifice for the greater good
Freedom of your PS2 online and all the themes are
Heaped upon one another
Why it's so difficult to see this in the person point of view can from the prison front of you none of these themes are here
The heroism of Davy Crockett means nothing to Santa Anna's Mexican right
Remember it's Plutarch 450 years later or thereabouts who says the response that lie
King of the Spartans remember
That we have two of them
This one maybe
You can call the spare
Official lamb
Is a descendant of Heracles supposedly who is a descendant of Zeus so
This is a Spartan Kings got Zeus's blood in his veins nobigdyl
But supposedly according to Plutarch
The Persians are from the typical Persian deal you guys
And join us we make you the kings of Greece you have more than you ever had before you profit we profit it's all good
Just lay down your arms in the
Answer the wonderful answer you see them blazing done caps today cuz long different causes
Including
Second Amendment Firearms causes here in the United States
Adopted the phrase molon labe
Translated the hundred different ways
Come and take them
Is a
Standard
Lay down your arms
Maybe we can add come and take them from our cold dead hands
But if you're looking at this from the Persian point of view
That's exactly what they do
The chill Clint Eastwood
And the other Clint Eastwood's and all the other Greeks warned Clint Eastwood
And they pry the weapons from your cold dead hands and they move on
And if you're ready Clint Eastwood defender back in the Greek city-state to go yet but they killed
10 Persians for everyone they lost Niger the Persian king Hugo so what
I have lots of
That side of the Persian
Intimidating qualities is not really been brought out here who cares
I will spend 20 lives
To take you down how's it feel
I mean it
If you look at it the right way this is brutally intimidating
And since historians can't agree on what the Greeks strategy was
They can't really determine how big of a deal Thermopylae was in terms of a disaster
But since a lot of historians think it might have been an attempt
2 block
The Persians and keep them out of the rest of grease on land and there was
Happy sad
A corresponding blocking forces
C2 with cape Art Museum
If that force was intended to Halt the Persians like these historians think so that the supplies could begin to run out in The Purge
Army could starve and go straggling back to Persia like Napoleon straggling out of Russia
That's a good strategy by the way
But if that's the strategy
How else but as a horrible failure do you judge
The inability to hold that most defensive position in all of Greece
For a week really only 2 or 3 days or actual fighting
If we're honest with ourselves
Degree skip blown out at Thermopylae
Nephrologist is being honest with us
The Persians to be unusual step of decapitating
You know the
Descendant of Heracles and sticking his head on a stick
As they marched
Out of the mountain passes
And into Central Greece
You can almost hear the background
Juneau Empire music
And the heavy breathing of Darth Vader as you know he he walks through the pass while rides on his chariot
The silk slippers
Don't handle the rocks in the road very well you
Herodotus is version of the fight of Thermopylae which would have been heard by Greek audience members within the living
In memory of those events
Is somewhat more colorful detailed in
More heroic certainly meaning
In Herodotus is tailing it may be true
The Greeks are holding their own in fact they're beating the Persians every time the Persians attack the past their beaten back by Greek
Horses
It's only because some Trader shows up and betrays the Greek cause 4 Gold
Persians are always
Getting people to betray their people for gold imagine that
And the trailer shows
You know the forces of King Xerxes a secret path behind the Greek defenses
Xerxes sends troops behind the Greek rear
And in one of the versions of this Leonidas is able to get the other Greeks to
Head back
In safety
To their cities to fight another day and sort of defends The Retreat to the last man who becomes the rear guard
It's another version of this story
If you don't buy into the idea that this was an attempt to
Hold the Persians until there
Supplies ran out then maybe you buy into the through the dishes of delaying action in which case
The death of the Spartans achieve something they left the rest of the Greeks getaway this is the second world war Dunkirk evacuation
Ancient Greece in a Spartan King
And 300 of his man and a bunch of other Greeks
I don't want to cover the retreat for the rest of the Greek army and that may be true
Administering pointed out if the person Calvary get to the other side of the mountain
And there's a whole bunch of Greek hoplites from miles in front of the retreating they're going to have a field day spearing those people in the back so
Could have saved a lot of lives here
Herodotus's account of course is much more colorful
He has the Persian king
Setting up a
Throne
Maybe you can call it in mobile phone
And he sets it up what he can watch what's going on here
Supposedly like to watch all these encounters on land or sea
Even so degrading
Describe
Phoenicians get a demerit for their performances
Let me know if that kind of thing
And Herodotus says he's sending in
Unit after unit to fight the Greeks and they all get
Beaten back
But they're short Spears can't help with the Greeks
And it finally the king decides to sending his Guard unit The Immortals
But his Immortals run into more than their match when they run into Spartans and
If what
Herodotus says is true
Anyone who's ever been out on a field trying to do Maneuvers with other human beings and having all work together can understand what if
Beat this would be an advantage in combat
After the medes and the kissing hands get destroyed
Badly handled by trying to assault the Greeks in the past years when Herodotus is colorful account
Of The Next Step turns out to be wild Xerxes the great teen watches quote
Since the medes were suffering extremely rough treatment
They now withdrew
And the Persians under the command had Arnie's on the king called The Immortals
Came forth to take their place
It was every expectation that they at least would prevail
Open a joint battle with the Helens the Greeks
They fared no better than the meat
LED they suffered the very same setbacks
The fighting continued to take place in a confined space with the Persians using shorter Spears than those of the
The Helen able to derive any advantage from their Superior numbers
Black Adam onions
Meaning of Spartans
But remarkably well
Proving that they were experts in Battle For Fighting among men who were not
Especially whenever they would turn their backs and Fain flight all together
And The Barbarians seeing this would pursue them
With much clattering shouting
The Barbarians to catch up with them and then suddenly turn around to face them
At which point they would slay countless numbers of
All the Spartans do cells however
Only a few fell bear
Finally the Persians retreated
Since despite all their efforts to attack by regiments or by any other means
They could not gain any ground in the past
It is said that during these assaults
The king who was watching
Left up from his throne three times in fear for his army
Descended the contest that day and on the next two barbarians Didn't Know Better
That's a feel for how Herodotus portrays this and he goes through all the details I mean eventually Leonidas
Killed
It will be a fight restroom over his body to retrieve it
Eventually
Are the Spartans will Retreat up
Choke point with your the wall and they will be down to fighting with their bare hands in their teeth
It's this gripping accounting
It's hard to look at it from the Persian side
And see anything but the bad guys in the story fits the Cowboys and the Indians are the Indians in the 1950
He's right
Are the Zulus I mean you know
Filling the gap
Annie's kind of stories there's always these
Defenders sitting there fighting Doom. Doing it for some greater cause and a whole bunch of ants
This story is Herodotus tells at the Persians are the ants
But the bottom line is no matter how heroic it was
In the summer of 480 the answer and Central Greece
Any burning Athens
This is the real net result
I'm losing the battle
Thermopylae
Set the Persians break into the Open Country of Central Greece
Many of these cities are already going over to the Persians a bunch of other ones due to
Important places like thieves are on the Persian sign all these cities will now provide troops to his army
To use for the rest of this campaign it's starting to look like the war's over isn't it
This is a mapa Bedford isn't it
The cities that don't cooperate
With the Persians
Are destroyed
Potatoes destroy potatoes the city that fought 10 years before this time against this King of Kings
With the Athenians the Battle of Marathon
Long memories
Gone
Thespian
You just lost a bunch of thespian hoplites with the Spartans at Thermopylae destroyed
Daffins
All the homes of the Acropolis the few people who would not evacuated with the rest of the population were killed
We're told Xerxes sins
A message back to his capital in Asia
But she left three months previously remember over that bridge of boats
Essentially telling his people that when it comes to these Athenians
Mission accomplished
How something happen
In the story
That will totally
Change the complexion of everything
But it's hard to figure out exactly how it happens or which stories are true or what-have-you all you can say with any soda
Truax
Persians will get involved in a naval battle with the combined navies of the Greeks were fighting
They may have been tricked into the sink
A bunch of historians think that it's the major mistake Xerxes makes in this whole campaign cuz he didn't even need to fight a naval
You talk for hours about what will become the battle of salla
Historians argue about whether or not it's one of the most important battles of all time
Others will say that this battle of plataea which were going to get to
Is instead the most important so what's up
Tomato tomahto
Historian
I'm here but
The Battle of Salamis involves a character
How much is character actually corresponds to the historical figure named Themistocles
Is anyone's guess but the character is
Fantastic
Annies
Note after the second World War I rent for events in history that were suggesting it after the second world war this entire Greek Persian story
Captains of the second world war analogy and in that
Version of things
Themistocles is Churchill
But what that doesn't capture
Is it there such a wonderfully clever tricky roguish lovable
Does the right thing in the wrong I mean he's Hans Solo rather than Winston Churchill if we're going to stick with our Star Wars
Xerxes is Darth Vader
Themistocles is Han Solo
But he's trying to get in Herodotus a story anyway
The Greek stuff to pull together because this is one of the reasons you know the war is almost over.
Look out for their own interest right
All the Greeks below
Something called the Isthmus of Corinth which is another one of these natural choke point in the geography they're all trying to build a wall
Cross that and defend themselves
Which is great if you live south of that like Sparta and corentin
Are ghosts real
Not so good if you live north of it like Athens.
Cuz the Persians are already there so this is when there's a lot of
Very wonderfully roguish bargaining going on with Themistocles is using the Athenian Fleet as a
Basically saying what half of your Fleet Is Us
If you don't do more to help us when we're leaving
And then where will you be
At the mercy of the Persian Fleet
Bunnelby wonderful jousting going on
You're my favorite
Comeback line to his is when the Admiral from Corinth
Points out that you don't even have any standing
Do we having this conversation is for people about the fate of city-states and you don't have one anymore
Meaning Athens is gone
The Great Wall
A traditionally in the righteous version of the story
Are wonderful Han Solo lovable Rogue who tricks you into doing the right thing supposedly tricks the Greeks
In the fighting
The Battle of Salamis
And if that's true think of how
Wild that is in then according to Herodotus admits to it
Tell him afterwards that's right you're surrounded and I did it so guess what we're fighting hahaha
If you go look at a map this is one of those battles to look at a satellite image
Where it's obvious what happens just by looking at the
You don't have to figure out too much because there's a
An island off the mainland of Greece and then there's a
A body of water but quite small between the island and the mainland that's where the Greek Fleet is
But there's an entrance to that Strait of water on one side and an exit on the other
Themistocles
Tell somebody eventually afterwards I send my slave over to King Xerxes to say
The Greeks are all getting ready to pack up and go home if you attack now they're dead meat
Xerxes
Surrounded the Greeks
Right blocked the channel that they would use for their Retreat and then came at them front Ali
And Themistocles in Herodotus takes credit for this
You didn't want to fight
But now we're surrounded and you're going to get killed so you might as well resist anyway and we're going to win
And they did
That's a pretty great story
And they were writing
Popular entertainment about it
Less than ten years after
Herodotus was still a preteen
Earlier
Greek
Homemakers are screenwriters were winning awards for
Fairport Trails of the Persians
The place is like the bad
Los Alamos
Basculas who's one of the all-time great
Which was a
Veteran of the Battle of Marathon
And may have been a veteran the Battle of Salamis to
Therefore may be an eyewitness
Certainly
Performing his
Plays for an audience of veterans and eyewitnesses
Many times to Athenians who in 472 and right around there when aeschylus was doing this we're still at war with the
Great Kings was very interesting the way this whole thing is portrayed by
The aeschylus has this story by the way of Themistocles
You're sending a false message to the king of the Persians saying that the Greeks are ready to leave to so when
Herodotus is a preteen that's the reason already being performed onstage so who knows interesting character
Winston Churchill slips a message to Hitler
They're all going to be gone you can invade Britain tomorrow no one will be home
If you look at that satellite map
Of the battlefield if you will win this battle occurred
And you think of
Hundreds
And hundreds of ships on each side in that little teeny area
You don't have to be a genius to imagine what happens
And
Play writer is like aeschylus
Mention it
But so does everyone else
It's a place where it's very easy for the ships also to become fouled and disorganized together
The Persians come in apparently expecting a bunch of disorganized and ready to leave greeting instead the Greeks are formed up
Which is interesting if you think about some of these complicated Maneuvers these ancient fleets are supposed to be performed
It must have taken hours and hours of preparation to make sure everyone was lined up just the way you wanted
This is a fascinating. Of
Naval History not necessarily my strong suit by the way
But the big ships on both sides were called trireme
About 40 yards in 40 m long
170 to 200 rowers on board
And where is this thing had a sale for normal travel or is it
Orated
Method for normal travel apparently in Warfare
Didn't use it
So this is a
Human-powered machine
And because of the
Which hold
400 300 500 lb bronze Beach
At the prow of the ship
Ram
But it's like a giant human-powered missile
And so they would Ram each other in this era
They would share they would give a go by really closely and Shear the ORS off one side which you can only imagine
What that must have done to the poor or rich people
And a lot of times they would try to turn it into a seaborne version of a land battle until they get these
Chips all together and use the Marines that were on board essentially your soldiers
The final land battle on board these Wooden Ships
That's Themistocles
To plan we're told see that the
Persian Fleet is superior not just in numbers
But in order they have better rollers they have guys would let more experience because they took over established
Athletes remember they sort of
That's one of a subcontractor or a wholly-owned subsidiary sort of approach to some of these Empires like
Are these cities that are Phoenicians and have such great seafaring Traditions the Phoenicians may have been the greatest seafaring people.
Ball time
So when the Persians get control of these areas
Essentially say okay you're working for us now
You just keep running a great Fleet we like everything about it but we're going to tell it where to go and what to do
The Greeks who just establish their flea recently
Still getting up to speed in terms of okay this is the proper way you
You do this maneuver 8cm mean
I just that developing the muscles you kind of forget that element of it how long could these people you know when you're fighting a battle
Continue to pull the oars before they just exhausted
And what if one side is better at that than the other
Why did you win they're in better shape they've been pulling mowers for 20 years they've got muscles that these opinions haven't even develop
Who knows
Besides Phoenicians the Persians are using Egyptian fleets they're using ionian Greek Fleet it's a bad situation
When you're outnumbered and out skilled
But apparently Themistocles in his
Council of strategist have recognized that if you could pull this giant Persian Fleet
Into that little narrow area you could turn it into a land battle and they were confident that the land battle would go better for them
And it did
But you might imagine from such a confined space where you have hundreds and hundreds of ships
They got very disorganized very quickly in that sort of the mental image you have
In his play Persians
Or the Persians
Aeschylus
Has a messenger
Speaking by the way to that wonderful Persian Queen is directly related or connected to the first five Persian
Kings atossa daughter of Cyrus the Great Chiefs or the main character
This messenger the tells her what happened at salamis is another one
And then I love when they go and they conjure up the ghost of Darius
Obi-Wan Kenobi
Marlon Brando Superman's dad some hologram who comes up to say what's going on now
It's wonderful
Dispersion messenger gives and
How did the Battle of Salamis as seen from the Persian point of view
Of course with words
Put into his mouth
Buy a Greek playwright
Greek playwright who may also have thought in that bottle there for your kind of getting an eyewitness
Count
Weird song
The dramatic way
And it would certainly have been for
Forum for people who have fought in that battle so
Can't fudge too much without the audience catching on
Going to watch this
Persian character describes
In the onset of the Greek Fleet showing up nicely ordered and organized
The trumpets blaring
He says it on the Persian side they can hear this really loud voice but what he really means is he can hear the war-cry of all the Greeks
You know yelling in unison
Lennie describes
An apocalyptic scene and when you think of the hundred
Hundreds of ships on both sides in these narrow Waters
It's not hard to imagine that relatively apocalyptic scene
What color
Is the ocean at this point right
Persian messenger
Maybe
Using adjectives
The mind of a man who actually saw
The battle of Somme
Says quote
And the trumpets shriek blazed
True everything over there signal
Instantly there
We heard the rhythmic rattle slap
It seemed no time till they all stood in sight
We saw them Sharp
First the right-wing clothes drawn strictly ordered let out
And next we saw the whole Fleet bearing down
We heard a huge voice
Sons of Greece go
Free Fatherland free children of our fathers God
Fathers live
Fight for all we have now
Then on our side shouting Persian Rose to a crest
We didn't hold back
That instant
Ship rammed bronze-clad Becon ship
It was a Greek ship started the attack
Shearing off a whole Phoenician Stern
Each Captain steered his craft straight on one other
At first the wave of Persian Fleet roll firm
But next as our ships jammed into the Narrows and no one could help any other
And our own bronze teeth bit into our own strikes
Whole or Banks shattered
Did the Greeks ships
Seizing their chance
Swept encircling instruct and overturned our Halls
And saltwater vanish before our eyes
Shipwrecks build it
And drifting Corpses
Shores and briefs filled up with our debt
And every able ship under purchase command broke order scrambling to escape
We might have been tuna
When they did fish for they kept on spearing and gotten us
Which Splinter doors and bits of wreckage
While moaning and screams drowned out the sea noise
Till the night blackface closed it all in
Losses by thousand
Even if I told the catalog for ten full days I could not complete it for you
But this is sure
Never before in one day have so many thousands died
And quote
Nobody knows how many people died
At the Battle of Salamis nobody even makes a halfway
Serious gas about
Nobody knows how many ships fought there nobody knows how many ships were lost its
All you can figure is somehow the Persians probably were defeated because you could see what happened after
When I was a kid growing up studying the stuff
It was always portrayed as the shadow
Defeat
Unexpected shattering defeated the Persian navy that completely changed the complexion of the war
More modern-day historians of course
Are questioning this isn't that the
Some theme of this whole story
Led by God like George cawkwell in
JF Lazenby Amino question whether or not salamis was anywhere near as big of a defeat as it's portrayed
I do love the story we won't get into it but once again that another Herodotus story that Themistocles tries to send the great king another
Message to cleverly get into do something else he shouldn't do I mean this Han Solo
Discontinued
One of the
Historians reading says you know you can't decide whether the guy is
Wiley
So like clever and Wiley or is he treasonous or some combination of the two and apparently it makes it sound like the Greeks couldn't
Always decide
The traditional portrayal of Xerxes has him sort of running back
To modern-day turkey
Hoping to get
Back there before the Greeks destroy the bridge of boats and trap him in Europe
Weather not text you again
Anyway guests
Lots of arguments
There are some halfway decent
Accounts of why maybe this whole thing makes total sense and it has to do with a change
In Persian policy
The policy is going to be
For sale land battle
Remember up until this point the Greeks really hadn't want to
Land battle against these guys in a straight-up fair fight in the Battle of Marathon have been one of these things were maybe the Greeks attacked while the
Persian getting back on their ships to leave not very representative
All of the various
Clint Eastwood's have been molon labe
At Thermopylae
So maybe a straight-on fight with it
Persian army
Would settle this thing once and for all of the arguments Herodotus has the Persians making to the king
Is listen we didn't get defeated at the Battle of Salamis those Phoenicians ionian Greeks and Egyptians did
The Persians are still undefeated in the field against these Greeks in a straight-up fight
Xerxes moves off to what's now modern-day turkey in Asia Minor
He will leave an army behind
He's the lord of the ants with all these millions of insects that just swamp over
In the small number of Greeks well that are soaked slipper Darth Vader lord of the ants left some ants behind
Definition eating Grease
Under the general mardonius who was a relative of Xerxes remember that this is kind of an incestuous maybe even
Literally sort of
Persian Elite
It's all married with each other and related to each other in this case the guy is mardonius who also has a history cuz 10 years before March
Adonis was one of the generals who invaded Greece the first time his dad right
He'll give mardonius an indeterminate number of ants
Remember all the numbers from the ancient sources are wildly inflated
So there's millions and millions of Persians and he divides this
You have merely hundreds and hundreds of thousands now but really
Most historians going to be pretty comfortable with anything in the 42 60,000 range although this varies
Herodotus says that mardonius was basically allowed
To pick the cream of the army so
You know a way go all the bright feathers and exotic colors and stone tipped arrows in Antelope horn things and you know you keep the amor
Photos in the garden Calvary in
The troops who are
In a Persian related in oef let's not forget the
Skitty and Central Asian horse Archer types
And with
Fifty thousand or so with those guys you should be able to take the Greeks out
Mardonius is going to pursue what kind of a waiting strategy
Going to get the Greeks to fight
Going to find a nice piece of ground that's just perfect for the way the Persians fight
And wait for the Greeks to come to them and if they don't
He's going to damage things until they do
Most notably
Athens
Told it after the Battle of Salamis eventually the Athenians have been evacuated from Athens to save their lives return to their home
Palm City start with building things
Well when the campaigning season resumes
After the winter and we're in 479 BCE now
The Persians from the north of Greece simply swoop down
Take Athens again
Basically the attitude is we just going to keep
Destroying things that are important to you until you come out and fight
I remember lying I'm going to butcher right now but somebody wants to do the only way to stop
50 or 60,000 people working in concert anywhere is with an equally powerful force and the Persians Arkansas
Trolling the whole part of greece with thebes and everything north
Themes being good calorie count
By the way
And traditionally as usual the Greek states are fighting amongst themselves
And once again according to Herodotus it involves whether or not the southern Greeks
Want to go north of that wall that they built at the choke point at the Isthmus of Corinth which looks like a pretty good defensive position
The problem is some of the major Greek States
Are north of it where the Persians are
The Greeks were south of that wall
Once again having this debate about do we really want to go north of the wall to wall such a great defense
North of the wall on the Persian side of things
Having to do crazy bargaining and threatening using the fleet as a bargaining chip in once again Themistocles playing the Han Solo
Parole
At one point
In Appling the big takeaway and maybe even saying we will go and side with the Persians if you don't come up here and fight
And we'll take the fleet let them use our feet against you
If this is to be believed Themistocles in the Athenian several times or even offered that standard Persian
Dealing be good for you it'll be good for us just join the end
Righty the deal according to the Mystic please cuz he's telling the other Greeks look at what the Persians are offering us if you can have your seat
I think you said you can have the government of your choice
Which is the typical Persian offer long as you're
Loyal to the king and pay your taxes I don't care if you have a democracy or monarchy or whatever long as you're quiet
At the Mystic least through Herodotus has been saying also choose one of the territories around you which one would you like the best
Thermal throw that into great for everyone right we all game
So you even at this time
Through the biosources your hearing the Persians trying to make a deal
Must be really fight about
I don't care how much
What harm you've given us
Will give you your city and more land than you ever had and it's the same deal they're supposed to have off at the Spartans at Thermopylae
They may not all be true all the time but you don't get this many mentions of it in history less it kind of was the pot
The Assyrians that previous major Empire coming from that part of the world
Would probably not have offered you a deal of this kind at any time
Certainly not this late in the game
With this many casualties already suffered in this many dead people
Going to have to atone for
And in this case eventually Themistocles and maybe it's part of his genius by hooker by crook
Has by 479 BCE and army of combined
Greek hoplites remember different city states
Heading on up toward the area where Thebes is
To have it out with the spider who sitting up in the web up there just waiting for him
There will be Spartan hoplites there they will be Athenian hoplites there and the eventual encounter will happen
You're kind of a symbolic place when you think about it what happened
At plataea
Tortilla with a city
A little teeny City that help
The Athenians the Battle of Marathon
Kick the Persians out the first time
The TV with the little city that when the Persians arrived in this latest encounter
Didn't submit to them that was destroyed so this is where the battle
It's going to happen
And the parameters for this encounter
Have been in large part determined by the needs and the capabilities of the Persian cat
We're in the Strategic place we are cuz this is the good Cavalry country in Greece that's where the Persians want to fight
What the actual Battlefield
Will be chosen
Why were the Greeks decided to Stan
They choose a spot
Where there
You better protected from that Cavalry they
Appear
From the mountain
Through the mountain passes
Marching up from the south
And when they run into the Persians
They do so from a position High atop these Hills
The Persians are camped on the plane below
Which stretches out in the distance it's wonderful Cavalry country
They are behind River they have a camp built
So they've got a pretty good defensive position they'd love to have the Greeks Advanced on them
The Greeks and picked out a pretty strong defensive position of their own up in the hills and they'd like the person to come up to them
Lost Begins the
Free battle jockeying for position an advantage
And there's a lot of it and it goes on for days
And
You know once again it's a good time to remind you that you're getting the Dan Carlin version of the story because this is so argue about
Autumn Oaks historian to work
Recreating as best they can you know where things happened and so much has changed since in
I'm just going to stake out sort of abroad
View of this for clarity reasons and understand that there's a ton of disagreement about everything
Basically though what happens if the Greeks try to stay in The High Ground and lower the Persians up there
And the Persians
Trying to Skirmish with the Greeks and get them to either break apart go home or come down to fight them
And all through the narrative we have
Herodotus
The ancient screenwriter
Colorizer
And this is his crowning Glory moment
Writes his whole history to talk about any of these events and this is
The climactic battle
It's also my favorite battle
In the entire history of the achaemenid Persian Empire
Because you can color in Herodotus In Living Color
2500 years
Dad but you know what I mean
We have
Really the only
Colorize story of the Persian army at its height
I love this Army
After this. It will change and not be the same in before this.
You really don't have any
In a few for how it operated
In this battle you get to see this Army move
And fight
Is a lot of disagreement to about how the Greeks fought in this battle
In the last
Discussion we had on this I mentioned
In some of the historians like handspan Wiest who suggests that the
Idea that we've always had about how the Greeks fought during this. Is misplaced
And if they don't fight that way till after this.
And the one we're going to now is sort of like
In a while they're in transition from an old style that you know they would have recognized in Homer's Iliad
To the style that will come to be known in the future after this. The region Phalanx style where everybody stays in the rain
Banks under penalty
And you know you move is a body
Because there's so many stories here if they're more than stories where people will spring forward from the ranks and do stuff
Or move backwards fluidly back toward their online which is much more like the fighting
From the heroic Greek era of Homer's time
It would sure explain a lot it been weeks is right about this because
Herodotus describes this all the time he begins to lay out
You know what will become his version of like a Saving Private Ryan type
Battle scene and it's worth pointing out
This is like the first battle scene stuff
But we have to admit will set the stage for all the the movies and plays and books and every
Even afterwards
You start by pointing out that the Greeks and the Persians are trying to
You know maneuver each other out of position and he talks about the skirmishing that's going on
At one point
The Persian Commander mardonius ends cavalry
To go up into the hills and try to mess with the Greeks you don't know what for and historians all disagree
A lot of things though sometimes a general does something just to see what will happen
REITs how will they respond if I go up there and shoot them
Maybe they'll start dying in large numbers which would be good
Or maybe their morale will suffer
Which would also be good or maybe they'll just leave which would be good too
I can't catch my cavalry
Calvary basically dominate this field cuz they're the best Cavalry in Asia just calorie country
But the Greeks have no calories at all
The only Cavalry in Greece
Really worth its salt
Are in places like thieves and thessaly up in the north
And there on the Persian side
There are Greek cavalrymen in this battle they're just fighting
On the Persian side
At one point erotica starts the narrative in
And the
The Greek line which is been put together sometimes
You know sounding like a bunch of
Petulant four-year-olds arguing about who gets to stand on this part of the line in the wicked just stand on this part of the line and its crew
Crazy how
We have to remember in and
History of Eyeglass and bean ever Tire of reminding us that it's accepting the Spartan these Greeks are militia troops
Are farmers for the most part
They fight sometimes in a lot of these guys would have had battle experience when they're not fighting
They're not fighting
They're back on the farm they're living their lives
They are militia
What's more their militia from their own city-states and they consider themselves essentially
To be of that city state as opposed to this larger concept of a Greek idea
And so when the Spartan start giving him orders there likely be a lot of grumbling and it 1 Point
The
Groupon Greeks are called megarians
To end up on the Flank In This Creek formation up in the hills is being
Hammered
By the Persian Cavalry that is shooting them full of arrows
I don't want to be hammered anymore
And they send a message
To the high command essentially sang
If you don't remove us we're leaving
This is the way Herodotus describes
And how really the the
Fighting begins to shape up
He talks about the Greeks he mentions them
And he talks about how the Persian Commander mardonius can't get these Greeks out of the Hills
Quote
Since the hellions refused to come down onto the plane mardonius sent against them his entire Corps of calvary
Under the command how much deseos
On the hellions call Matt Castillo
And it was very prominent among the Persians
He wrote in the sea in the horse with a golden bit
And adorned by many other kinds of beautiful ornaments
The horsemen rode out against the hellions and charge them by regiment
One after another
Doing significant harm to them in insulting them as they did by calling them women
And quote
I remember Peter Greene had a footnote or he said
One wonders if they had asked a Greek
In their own Army
What the word for woman was so that the enemy could understand the taunt
So then Herodotus says
You know that the megarians of the ones getting hammered and by the way
The every said earlier the way that these Persian Cavalry seem to a fault as a lot like Huns and Mongols and stiffens and all these people
Uno Attack you in little teeny packets of horse archers
Hoping to break your
Formation
If you attack them to try to get back at them they just would have drift away from you and your formation breaks up and then they can turn on you and cut you apart
Piecemeal
If you don't you just have to sit there
And take the arrows until you lose so many people you're in trouble
Or until your morale breaks you think no more of this
Maybe a combination of the two affected the megarians
For being Skirmish by this
Persian general of the cavalry
Mustachios and Herodotus rights quote
Now just by chance
The megarians happened to be deployed in the most vulnerable position to be entire Battlefield
And it was they who received the brunt of the cavalry's assault
Because they were so hard-pressed by these attacks
The magarian set the herald to the generals of the Helen
Who conveyed this message to
Quote
Escorting a message now
The megarians have this to tell you
We who are your allies cannot continue to confront the Cavalry of the Persians alone
In this position that we've occupied from the beginning
So far we are resisting by tenacity and Valor
Though we are hard-pressed
But now you should know that we shall abandon this post if you do not send others to replace us there
And quote
So you can already see that
Yes yes yes the Spartan is the commander-in-chief of all of these city-state units are basically keeping their own
Freedom to make choices
To themselves
We're not going to stand here and get killed for all of you we've taken enough casualties of somebody else's turn now
Herodotus says for a long time now I have been wondering if there's some
Favoritism for the Athenians in the upcoming parts of the story cuz all of a sudden Herodotus starts to favor the Athenians
Quite a bit he even makes the Clint Eastwood Spartans
Look a little wimpy next to them at one point saying we'll maybe you should you guys should fight the Persians Avenue View Farm before 10 years ago
We don't even know him
We can fight the thebans were fighting with the person we beating them anytime
You have to be careful it's
Apparently the megarians ask for help in the only people that say yeah we'll go over there and help him or some Athenians
Who also have the only archers
In the whole Greek god
So the
Athenians Somerville
And these archers go over to the flag with a megarians are hard-pressed
And now you get a feel for how chaotic it is
Is there
Herodotus is colorizing is really good he's able to give you a sense now
The danger in the panic in the dust in the
Chaos go look at her video modern video of a riot somewhere that gets really out of hand look at the k
Chaotic element that where the point of contact between the two sides
Athenians with their archers decide to go help the megarians on the flank and he says quote
These were the man who undertook this task and they stationed themselves that you're with right in front of the other Helens were there
Taking along their archers for support
The battle they fought their went on for some time until it ended in the following way
Is the Cavalry was attacking by regiments
The horse of Misty cos remember he's the Persian general of the cavalry
Which stood out in front of the Rat
Was pierced in Its Ribs by an arrow
Heading pain in the horse reared up on its hind legs and through mistc up to the ground
As soon as he fell the Athenians attacked him
They took his horse and killed Mis deseos as he was struggling to defend himself
But at first they were unable to kill him because of the way he was armed
Since he was wearing a breastplate made of golden scale next to his skin
And over the Crimson tunic
The accomplished nothing is they struck against the breastplate
Someone realized the reason for this and jabbed him through the eye
At which point he collapsed and died
And quote
Yuan to real
Feeling there
Of this guy struggling for his life I mean he comes a little too close to the Greek lines
Intersource throws him when he gets hit by an arrow you fall down in this relatively heavy armor that might have hurt him
And when he hit the ground and a bunch of Athenians
Sprint towards you
Have you tried award them all off and then jabbing your chest as hard as they can but they can't see the fish scale style armor
Because you got it under your tunic
Adventure Time One realizes it
Stabbed you through the eye
We're told that
The unit that he was commanding didn't realize that they lost him right away Herodotus is quote
The rest of the Cavalry was it first ignorant of all this
Because if they had turned around and we're riding away in retreat no one had seen how he fell from his horse
And subsequently died fighting
But they immediately missed him after they stopped for no one was there to come in them
Once they realize what happened they cried out and Rally's one another
I've been charged back to retrieve the corpse
And quote
Apparently what happened is dispersion Cowboy that was attacking anyone little dribs and drabs as soon as they realize they lost their General
We're told form into a solid unit and charge the flying to go get the body back
Another giant conflict
Ear drops over the body which is crazy but you see this a lot of Ancient Warfare and no one likes to lose a body of anybody obvious
Remiss.
First of all when you lose these officers it's
Traumatic sometimes it's never good
Ancient Warfare Sometimes the best plane you can have it kill the officer or kill the king
Whole armies have been known to disintegrate
If you kill the leader
In this case if you buy what Herodotus is saying he really gives the impression that these units were kind of left
Unable to know what to do without the commander
So go get the body seems to be the default position
How many people are you willing to lose to
Recover a cadaver
Apparently a lot the Greeks and the Persians by quite a while over this body to greet end up with the body
And then go and put it on display for morale purposes of course around it is right
Quote
Helen's gained much courage from the fact that they had stood up to the attack of the Cavalry had repelled it
The first thing they did was to place the corpse on a wagon
And have it drawn past the armies various units and their assigned positions
They just played it in this way because the body of Misty cos was worth seeing for its size and its beauty
And the men left their ranks in order to see it
And quote
Can you get a real feel for the ancient
Then we're told that after this happens the Greeks decide to advance a Little Closer
Come down
Gina from the real heels into the Foothills and see if maybe something else doesn't begin to happen
Everybody trying to
And see if you can get the other guy to attack in a position of weakness
This again that was where the Persian Cavalry comes in
If it gets to go around the Greek flag
Begins to go after the water supplies in the rear begins to go behind them and start to attack some of the supply column
They're coming through the mountain passes behind the Greek position
Both sides are probably pressed
It'll be a lot of
Depending on which historians who believe the Persians may only have a few days worth of food here
Before they have to retrieve but we don't know they also have Friendly Greek cities right behind them
The Greeks who should have tons of food
Are now having it intercepted by Persian Cavalry in their rear so who knows
You know what the actual needs to attack were
Captain Greeks Advance farther down toward the Foothills we're told that they get into some trouble
I need to change their position so the retreat to a more defensible place
Where the water supply was better defended or what not
And this is where things get Wiggy
Because how the heck
Does Infantry
Retreat
Within visible range of the enemy
Well the Greeks decide to do it
Finite
Which makes more sense if you think about it and they also decide to do it apparently in stages you don't want to give it away right to the Persians
Removing
So the Greeks begin withdrawing backward two more defensible position this is how the story delete betrayed
Dubai morning time when light comes up and you can see what's going on in the Hills above you
The Persian sea that some of the Greeks have gone away
Some of the Greeks are in the process of still leaving
And some of them are still there
But the entire battle line is disrupted
Have you looking at this from the Persian point of view
And you've been in this
Face off with the Greeks for almost 2 weeks in the hot July Sun
And you've been doing damage to each other
True skirmishing and cutting off
Attachment and all kinds of other things
And you're receiving reports of dissension in the ranks and quarreling among the Greeks
Herodotus emphasizes a lot of this
Even the Spartans on the day of the
You're changing location or arguing should we stay or should we go in different people on different sides and mean
The Greeks look like they're a mess and some historians think that's what the Persians were expecting
That eventually
The pressure of all this would dissolve
Rather ad-hoc and not altogether solid Coalition of Greek States
Some of whom
Dislike others
What this means on the battlefield though he's
Nearly two weeks of tactical constipation
Her over in the space of a morning
And everything starts moving again
The Persian Commander mardonius
Is said to have ordered his Persian troops including his own guard Cavalry maybe a thousand strong across the river a dub
Idle speed
To catch these lean Greeks
Herodotus Ben says that all of the
Subject peoples as soon as they see the general in the Persian troops on the double moving forward across the river
They put up their standards and follow along
Rochester shouting jostling maintaining no
Show the formation or discipline of all and why they're running away we're chasing
Would like the animal kingdom feel when you're too
Predators
Facing off at one another and swiping the air and growling at a bank if one of them turns around and moved in the opposite direction
There's almost this primeval need to chase on the part of the other animal
That's what this feels like a little bit
By the way what would the proper response be
In a cold sober situation if you saw the enemy moving off broken in front of you
Pursue right
That's what the Persians do
I can't help once again looking at this like Herodotus is movie and it's sort of a buddy film here and he's got
Three groups
Of Greeks
The Greeks of split into three separate columns and removing in three separate directions
One of the Greek groups and one in the middle is sort of made up of all of the 50 states
Prodigious is not focusing much in the movie extras if you will the big players
But the other two columns
That are retreating in different directions or
Repositioning themselves if you want to put it that way
Are the two stars in this Herodotus buddy picture if you will
In a 1in my mind is a little Michael Caine if I'm sorry a lot of analogies and metaphors today I can't help it.
Athens is the
Guy with the sense of humor in the fun guy in the clever guy and he speaks real well and
Michael kalish
At a younger age
And the Spartans are Clint Eastwood as we said in the two of them together the
The Slick sly
In all the girls love him clever Michael Caine mixed with Clint Eastwood and get them out of trouble with the you know the Magnum at the last minute
Run silent Run Deep End
It's an interesting sort of body film industry said Herodotus maybe a little bit biased towards the Athenians
But he says that when the Spartans realize that they are the principal Target of the Persian Pursuit
Did the king want them
They send the message to the Athenians basically the whole Persian army were coming help you or something like
That we know you'll come and help us are you the great Defenders
And Herodotus the Athenians session
Intercepted
By other Greeks
People who are fighting
For the great speeds is probably the Great
Greek state that sided with the great king Argos is another
Leaders of thessaly also been
But the theban hoplites are great if you're making a top 3 list of great hoplites in Greek history there's only three
City-states that are on it and they switch places all the time
Sparta
Athens
And thieves and sometimes thieves is number one the Athenians get waylaid before they can come to the aid of the Spartans were facing the
Persian
When the theban Phalanx smashes into them
They will conduct their own private battle now and that's what this battle of plataea turns into separate battle
The main one the other one that get the Lion's Share of the screen time
Is when you have the
If I'm acting battle between the Spartans and the Persian part of a Persian army the core including the general March
Is horse fighting in the combat
For a military history not like yours truly it's awesome
And when you read about how it works once against me let me just show you one of the things that
Blow my mind and you can take whichever side you think is more likely in terms of your interpretation and it doesn't matter what
Still amazingly cool whichever side you pick
When the Spartans warm up
You realize it's going to be a fight here
And they're ready for this combat they begin to hold
Religious sacrifices somewhere near the battle line
Right we're already going into who the hell knows
How these troops formed up in a sense of was there an open space in the Middle with a priest could come with the sacrificial animal and do the deed
Forged that happened behind the battle line was it relatively safe Union places on the battle line anyway
We're told throughout this entire almost two weeks both sides are sacrificing
I'm looking at the entrance of animals and basically doing their Magic 8-Ball tests all the time
Is this a good day to cross the river and
Herodotus is the reason that both sides. They're for so long as they both sides were both getting
Almonds that said listen
Decide that will win this battle is the one that stayed on the defensive
Turn Advanced first right
The Spartans are back here
Not just Consulting the Magic 8 Ball
For big decisions right when you go to the Oracle of Delphi
The people of Argos that's a big strategic decision
But the minor tactical ones to quickly kill that go and see if we can charge the Persians that are
100 yards in front of us right now what
Still can't charge him okay we'll sit here
This is what Herodotus says happens
It's fascinating to speculate whether these leaders who are
Beijing and maybe what you could call a prophecy hunt
Here by slaughtering animals and asking for
An interpretation
Please what did the sign say
I mean do they buy into that themselves
What does chicken wonderfully clever manipulation of things like religious but
Going to help them do something that's very
Terrestrial in nature and historians disagree about this forever you go back a hundred years in the very logical very
Most expected monocle is in his eye huntsdale Brooks as a cost
Rubes
There's a lot of other modern-day historians for example the same look at all the evidence
Are other major things that these people refuse to do with the sign seem to be against it
So it might be
A little bit
You're letting our modern lenses look at this and end color the way we see things maybe these really Pius preach in the spa
Spartans
Often considered to be very pious
Maybe they really
Not using this is a tool to achieve aims
Maybe they were really waiting until the entral said it was okay
Courtauld
Did the Persians come running up
Thousands and thousands and thousands of these guys running up the front ranks carrying wicker
Shield this is the modern interpretation with a rock that says by the way I should have
Did the front rank had these almost manhi size but not very heavy cuz they're made of wicker Shield
That they would the front ranks with wood
For Moline and when you put these things on the ground they almost form like a wall all the way up and down the line
And behind them thousands and thousands of archers were running up
And getting into like close formation these more archers that ran in the impact and ran around and and acted like
These were guys who got into basically kind of close order
And lined up behind the shield started
Raining there's no other way to put an arrow down on the great remember there's two things that this person
Which we talked about
The archery
The volume of Persian archery
Is as high as any army in history I mean they basically if you if you have them in your head
Images of what the Battle of Agincourt look like with the English longbows raining arrows down on the French
This is that and more
Which hold it
The Greeks
The meaning the Spartans and they're with their wisdom of the Greeks that are working with them or kind of friendly with him called the tgn
We're told that the Spartans in the standing there
Taking this Arrow fire we just we had talked about earlier if you if you do the math
We are potentially talking about you know the high hundreds of thousands maybe into the millions of arrows in a very short. Of time
What does it take to get people to stand under that kind of Arrow fire
Leaving maybe what would you say a hundred yard who knows no man's land in between
When you're armed with the kind of weapons that are really only useful if you get right up next to somebody
Takes a lot of discipline doesn't it the Spartans are sitting here waiting for the intro to read right
We're told that they are
Friends these two genes in any formation
One would guess right next to them can't wait any longer
Not going to put up with the casualties
Stoically any longer
Which are the story we talked about in the Spartans is Clint Eastwood Clint Eastwood playing Batman
Will these tegean play the role of Robin in the story they can't wait they lose their temper its order portrayed at HR
Charge toward this line of Persians the guys holding the shield
Lancaster charge down there
They're going to get slaughtered aren't they
Robbins going to die
All of a sudden Herodotus dinamita moment of drama has
Spartan leader puffiness in raising his hands to the heaven calling on your local DMV or close by
Shrine or something like that
Please give us a good signs boom they killed the goat down at the Persian line
The following
IGN
Tears away the screenwriter in his own words from the de selincourt translation puts it
Quote
Once more as they were about to engage with mardonius and his men
Meaning of spark
Perform the ritual of sacrifice
The Omens were not favorite
And meanwhile many of their men were killed and many more wounded
For the Persians had made a barricade of their wicker shield and for the protection of it we're shooting arrows in such numbers
Set the Spartan troops were in serious distress
This added to the unfavorable results of the sacrifice at last cause pus Aeneas to turn his eyes
To the Temple of Hera
And I call upon the goddess for her age
Her not to allow the Greek to be robbed of their Hope of Victory
Then why the words were still upon his lips the sacrificial victims promise success
At this the Spartans 2 would laugh move forward against the enemy
Who stopped shooting their arrows and prepared to meet them face-to-face
And quote
Now what this meant is that the Persians are putting aside the weapon
That they're best at
Pulling out hand-to-hand weapons
Weather at a disadvantage
Not just that it seems and this becomes a recurring theme You Hear About Forever afterwards
It seems that the missile weapons of the Persians were singularly ineffective
Against the Greek hop
Did archery fire
Doesn't seem to do very well against close-order troops with big shields who are armored
That's a bit of a mystery cuz Herodotus keep saying that they're suffering but we give the casualty numbers at the end of the battle the Greeks of supper
Historians Like Richard Gabriel
You know I've been involved in test studies were they
Try to figure out who did you mathematical calculations and test studies and penetration surveys and all kinds of things to try to figure out
And how effective things like archery fire would have been and he says against Greek hoplites in close formation
Not very effective
If the arrows won't penetrate the armor of The Shield
For the most part they're looking for a little teeny gaps
And there aren't very many of those
Greek playwrights in the Contemporary during this period will
Continually refer to the victory of the spear over the bow
But usually could have talked about
The advantage of the armor to
I need did Herodotus mention
Think about
If something is subtle
Because there are no weapons involved
As having an NFL game
And mandating that one team can't wear helmets are shoulder pads in this game
What do you think it's going to look like at the end of the game if one team gets to have helmets and shoulder pads
And the other doesn't
How many people die are their deaths in this game
You begin to see the difference
You know an advantage and end from a distance when the Persians are shooting at you which is their Style no big deal
Once the Spartans close.
Gap that no-man's land between the big deal
And this is the sort of moment and I've said this I think
Since I began talking about history
This is one of those moments that just fascinates me where I asked stand there and I try to figure out
You're a Persian
You're in this line you've been shooting at these people for a long time and now they run at you in a giant block of
Men let's just play with a nice round number
And say 10,000 but it seems to have been more than that and Peter Greene says the Spartan line was three-quarters of a mile
Nia Long
So a line of men maybe a track steep
With 10:40 or so Spears you know
7/12
Spears
Charges that you and they're basically shoulder-to-shoulder
And you stand there
By the time is like the Napoleonic wars in the u.s. Civil War and stuff almost nobody will stand there
During a bayonet attack
Big hidden things about the. Of me
The real historians will say nowadays it. Do the evidence seems to show that no one stood around for Bayonetta
Nobody nobody would face Cold Steel yeah but in this. Facing Cold Steel is what it's all about
And even then a lot of people didn't
There are a lot of stories about hole
In almost whole armies running away sometimes before contact
Think about what's involved and think about
You know what you have to have happen to make it all work
Just because you're brave
And just because your friends are Braves standing around you what happens if
The 10000 Spartans in a with their 10ft Spears like a giant pin-cushion start charging at you
And half the people around you run away
What the other half do by the Greeks thought that the god of fear Phobos ruled the battlefield
That before
Because Panic could take over at any time like a herd creature
As the Spartans charge you
How do you stand there
And accept the charge especially if you're not at least arm simile you're going to pull out your little short-sword you're not going to have any
Armor for the standard Persian infantry behind the front line not going to have any helmet
Maybe a quilted jerkin if you're lucky
You're going to get steamrolled
The front rank of these formations as we talked about earlier the current
In a line of thinking
Is that this is a block of men maybe 10 ranks deep but it's the first rank
Actually kind of equipped in a way that might allow them to give a good account of themselves in hand-to-hand combat all those big show
Dealzer carrying are wicker
Shows you the kind of warfare the Persians usually engaged
They're helping to keep their formations safe from missile fire
The Greeks are coming at you with a big old heavy spear head
In a with a
Impetus
That a charge provides behind it all the Spartan sometimes Advanced nice and cool
Uno's
And once that front rank is dead
The Spartans of broken into a formation that is not prepared
This kind of fighting at all it's one NFL team
With helmets and pads and oh yeah big ol Spears facing another NFL team to know how much Notepad
And short swords
Between the prospective you have to
Erotica suggest
Dispersion does he said
We're not inferior in Courage
They were not inferior
In Valor
And let's remember they're fighting not just Greek they're fighting Spark
And they're not just fighting
As we said some Spartans they're fighting Sparta this is the military strength of the Cities
State of Sparta and these Persians are not inferior Robin his Valor
But he said that they liked on
You basically said they're not equipped
This kind of fighting but you get a sense of the desperation the other Greek states are petrified of Spartans
And now the Persians are finding out why
Spartan formation smashes into the Persians remember
D Spears with your only about 2 in wide width there 10 ft long and 2 in wide you can see how
Likely they are to
All the Greek sources talk about breaking Spears all the time even if you go into a nice soft human body with your spear trying
How to get it out of that body like
Break the spears of the Spheres are gone very quickly but yours have Herodotus describes
The moment of impact
From the de selincourt translation
Quote
First there was a struggle at the barricade of Shield
Then the barricade down there was a bitter and protracted fight
Hand-to-hand close by the Temple of Demeter
For the Persians would lay hold of the Spartan Spears and break them
Encouraging strength they were as good as their adversaries
But they were deficient in armor
Untrained greatly inferior in skill
Sometimes tingly sometimes in groups of 10 men perhaps fewer perhaps more
They fell upon the Spartan line and were cut down
They pressed hardest
He writes
At the point where mardonius the general
Farting person
Riding his white charger and surrounded by his thousand Persian troops
Flower of the army
Walmart oneus was a lie they continue to resist and to defend themselves
And struck down many of the lack of pneumonia
But after his death
And the destruction of his personal guard the finest of the Persian troops
The remainder yielded to the lack of ammonia into a flight
The chief cause of their discomfiture
Was their lack of armor
Fighting without it against heavily armed Infantry
And quote
Truthfully
If you read that
Maybe from the Persian point of view
You see that the Persians stood up
To the Spartan
Desperately breaking their Spears
With their bare hands we what would you do what your move
If a 10000 or 15000 hoplites bear down on you
Even do some Jujitsu move or something
Okay soon as the spirit comes forward I'm going to break it I mean you don't even have that opportunity you're facing
15 spearhead pincushion coming at you
What's your plan
I don't even know how you begin to
Process
Okay what am I going to do now they're ten feet away okay what am I going to do away I mean
See how the pressure would have built
You know
It's like the torpedo coming at the shipping to go Utah 60 yards away 50
Human beings are amazing
Anybody could stand
What's interesting is Herodotus said the Persians didn't just stand up to it that they were putting up with the death and destruction
An equalizer of the lack of armor and everything
Until her General was killed mardonius fighting right out there in the thick of things
As we said earlier there's something about these ancient battles where both
There's something expected about that he's he's not there because he's
He's a war lover otherwise I'll be back in a working on the maps in the back room doesn't work like that in this. They're often outfit
And when they die
It's often catastrophic
In this case the story traditionally is a low temperature a long time afterwards
Spartan in the formation
While the combat is going on
Lazenby describes it as what must be
Because in comprehensible chaos
And picks up a rock and throws it at mardonius and fractured skull and kill them
And you know I've been thinking about this if you think about
A formation of men like that
How close could anybody get without tons of stuff being thrown at them I mean very soon there must have been every
Rock that was nearby every stick anything that could have been picked up and thrown at the enemy must have been gone in this case it's not so
So hard to imagine
Are tons of stuff being thrown
If mardonius came too close to the Spartan lines and it sounds like he was fighting in the thick of things
Sakimichan and then we're told
But his thousand man Cavalry bodyguard is erotic just called it the flower of the Army's wiped out to a man
All that together
Collapses the morale
Persian troops fighting the Spartans
Let me begin to route
Now the rest of the army
Remember these are people who might not have chosen to be there if they had any choice but they're not perversions their subject peoples of the
The Persians
What's more there also people who were defeated by these Persians were now running
And the people who defeated them
Are coming your way
What would you do
They turned around and ran to
Headed back to the safety of their fortified camp on the other side of the river
All this is going on the Athenians in a hard-fought battle beat
Beef evens the allies of the Persians
Send them back to Thebes they go running back to Thebes
The Greek army
Led by the Spartans but eventually joined by the Athenians to round
Is fortified camp and eventually break Massacre the Persians in there
Erotic testing the other sources basically say
It wants the walls were basically torn down
The people inside resigned themselves to die in the sounds like they just put up almost no
Resistance up at that point which is interesting
In terms of human psychology to
If you're in that situation with the right move
Have you surrounded a beating you in the battle you're stuck in that
Stockade and then when they break in
You plan to sell your life dearly take out as many of the enemy as you can
Do you just try to figure out the easiest way to get this death over with so that it's not
Terrific
What are you
Entertain fantasies of capturing maybe I'll live through
Think of how many people in human history
Tipping in that situation
Before
The Battle of platea was such a
Monumental Affair in terms of size it had to be so much bigger than anything that the Greeks
Could conceive I mean their battles and infighting was on a much smaller scale than this
Did the Carnage must have been
And no one knows how many Persians were killed because nobody knows how many Persians even fought the bat
Don't know the numbers that fought as hard to
Determine cash
Traditionally the Persians are portrayed as losing a majority of their man in the fighting than losing most of the rest
In the slaughter at the fortification and then losing some more on the way home to some thracian tribesmen that ambushed them
And then finally be starving tattered remnants go stumbling into the
Provincial capital of Sardis
Like Napoleon's Grand Army
Leaving Russia
Thermoball numbers for the Persian forces at
Platia work and then
Unqualified
I put the 10 to 12 thousand men
Of course the high numbers are Herodotus and 300,000 If there really are 300,000 men more than hundreds of thousand
The Pershing corpses litter the battlefield it seems unlikely
But the estimate range
Does anywhere from like 50000 220000 somewhere in there is probably a good number
On the Greek side if the largest army they've ever put together it involves multiple city-states
50080 thousand men is the range that people throw out there
No problem you have with these numbers just so you know and it screws up the casualties to
Is that you have people who are
Temp service
And she lets
Enslaved people whose job it is
The carry the soldiers stop and cook his food and that kind of thing
But on the day of the battle often times especially in Desperate situations they're handed the spear
You know when someone to stick that into
Does that all the sudden make you a fighting man you get the count now in the overall numbers did they
Count
What Herodotus and others do casualty numbers for the Greeks
Fishing ridiculously low
But some historians have pointed out that they might not have been counting some of those other people
Number to Rodger said there were seven Helix for every Spartan
Tens of thousands of people that maybe nobody decided to count
But it came time to adding up the important people who died in this battle
Now what's more they will be another battle that will happen traditionally happens at the exact same time 40 is going on
Probably happened to
A little bit afterwards probably but you know maybe even a little bit before they don't know but they do think it was around the same time
Call the Battle of Nicholas
I'm basically what happens is the remnants of the Greek Fleet
That were victorious in the Battle of Salamis go find the remnants of the Persian Fleet that lost the Battle of Salamis they're going to have this Naval Base
The person who defeated again
If you actually read the rundown of it it sounds very much like the Battle of plataea all over again the hoplites charging tearing down the wall
Olive wicker Shields
And absolutely ripping apart the
Lightly armored archers in the middle of these Archer blocks and a Cavalry once again mysteriously missing
The Persian fighting very well until the officer dies
Basically acts as sort of a last kick in the rear end platea throws the Persians out of European
Greece
And the Battle of miqueli kicks him in the rear end on the way out at the! Basically saying and don't come back
Back
I think it's certainly does though
Is answer the question of the Battle of Marathon
Continue as before this. Did not
Which is
The question of the Tactical
Superiority of the Greeks in these battles and
And things that that involve very high-level stuff either decisions or trends
But sometimes they can boil down
Two things that seem like they should be mine or tactical Battlefield superiority questions and
Sometimes people will think no really
But then you say listen how big of a deal was it
In the age of discovery that one side had firearms and the other didn't
Or machine gun or artillery I mean there are times when
One side superiority on the day of the battle or the year of the war
Determines how everything else goes
These two encounters plataea
And mentally
Show that the Persians can't handle the Greeks for some reason
At least not in these situations and historians ever since I've been trying to
Answer the question you in this great giant upset in history
Without a doubt the greatest
Event in European related military history up until this time right now and maybe for a long time afterward
How did the Greeks do it why did they win how did the Persians lose
There are several theories on this and there is wonderful to watch the historians
You put forward their debating points on why they think it's one of the other and it's possible it could be several of them working together
I'll go over like 4
And some of these theories started with the Greeks themselves and still have their adherence today
The first one is one of those The Speaker versus the bow
The idea that the Greeks had a lot of history and still today
But you look at the equipment differin
Herodotus writes about it to one side had armor the other didn't once I have these long Spears the other one side head
Your heavy Shield the other really didn't
The Greeks also had a subtext to this sometimes it wasn't just
The one side had Spears in the other head bows but the different kinds of men
Are created
You know when you're in Archer versus when you are a close combat infantryman right
And that when it came time to an actual Clash of Spears the Greeks were
Melee fighters in the Persians really weren't
Certainly not
To the degree the Greek for the Greeks can't win without doing that the Persians can you get a different mentality or so
Some people will claim
People disagree with this Theory will point out quite rightly that the problem is if you want to stay at the equipment
Why can't you just make these people when you see how dominant they are at the Persians look at Greek hoplites and say wow they're real
Really affected why don't you just go make their own
Because you can for some reason
Just put a Greek helmet
And Greek armor
And a Greek spear in the Greek shield on a Persian Soldier have them fight like European Greeks
This is a huge question I've always had in my mind why
Jen tried all through history
Famously imitation legionaries during the Imperial Roman period
When Rome is dominating the entire world of the Mediterranean at that point it's only natural
If somebody would say listen I want what they've got going to make me some of those and grab a Roman Centurion
You know pay him some money they equipped or troop like them like Romans but they don't fight like Roman
Why not
Maybe the same reason today that
And some of the great militaries will go give their stuff and training
Two other
Countries militaries in yet when they have to fight
They got the good stuff they've got the top training but they don't fight the same why
We talked in the past about this really hard to quantify and very scary in terms of
They're kind of moves in the areas where you can
You know get into ethnocentrism and bigotry
The kitchen to the question of tok
How do you quantify toughness to how do you research it some people had reputations
For being extra
Nasty and warfare and part of it was just reputational rights intimidating
Herodotus has the Persian General at one point
When he doesn't think the Spartans are performing particularly scary turn of the Greek guy goes maybe you're just afraid of them cuz they're only
Good compared to you
Something like that
But there are people all throughout history
Whose neighbors were terrified of them because of what they could do
The question is why what why why did they do what they did Apache Zulu's Greeks in this.
Some of the original sources will have insane of the everyone knows that Greeks are great Fighters what's a great fighter how do you make a great fighter
What's that a combination of and how much of it is something internal
And what about
Societies like the Spartan one which is supposedly
One where the cultural characteristics are all designed to make somebody
You know more that way
A tough a better fighter whatever
Thing to get your mind around isn't toughness or
Whatever word is a better word for
What makes one side a great warrior in the other not
Some historians will say that this is a cultural question
Some cultures
Have a military tradition designed
Around
Physical contact with the Enemy
Write the Greek culture is designed
To have a military encounter in a you get to history like Victor Davis Hanson who is not without controversy
What you call it a Western Way of War
This decisive battle will you walk right up and slugged the other guy in the mouth in the good part about it is at the end somebody wins and somebody
But then there's the East which has a different military tradition
Much more
San Soo kung fu
And we're going to look for
Open flank and get around you were going to wear you down with missile fire supply lines
The Wharf are you ever going to shoot you from a distance with
In a missile weapon
Wear you down
And what that means is the Persians could win
Against the Greeks on the battlefield as long as they never come in contact with them
Because until they do
There is fighting
Go to their strength
The Greeks can't win
Without coming into contact
With the person but the minute they do
Their armored for it
They're equipped for their train for it they may be hardened by
Generations of people who
Promote the very things it takes to win in hand-to-hand encounter
Another word in Greek may have a culture of melee and once melee fighting happens there in their element
But then is much less controversial and weird and hard to quantify
Reasons that are thrown out for why the Persians may have lost also in the Occam's razor wanted poor decisions
Poor decisions at every level from
The king decided to do things you know
Let's go to war here to the Tactical Battlefield spur-of-the-moment ones made by the General on site and everything
Some historians ijf lies and being run down
In all the ways in which the Persian had this thing one
It was over in the morning you wake up at the Battle of plataea and all those Greeks are moving off in other directions and then
Has broken in the running away it's done
Right at Lazenby makes it sound like
How do you blow that
But they did
A story that comes right after this. He's one of the biggies and one of the Great
He basically says I'm paraphrasing you the Barbarian blew it
Got it
Sapporo decisions is often
In a thrown out there is a reason that the Persians
Fell victim to one of the great military upsets in all time now the next possible theory that was one that could explain to
Some of the poor decisions example Hill talk about Supply brand
The question of trying to supply an army over these distances this must have been the edge of the of the rain
A Persian
Power projection
Trying to keep an army of tens of thousands of people fed supplied
In all their equipment being repaired and everything that it takes for more than a year
Difficult to do
Herodotus tells a story of a king who happens to be a direct ancestor of Alexander the Great
Who supposedly comes to the Greeks before the Battle of plataea and that the person's only have 3 days of food left
If anything like that were true
Think about how that would
Impact
The decisions by the Persian General
If you only have three days left of food you can't wait
So maybe you do something that otherwise would have been considered a poor decision
I must have people who were judging you knew
You know what the supply constraints working on you might have been
Supply is
And extremely light
Certainly impacted every level of the campaign
Finally there's a school of thought in this one goes all the way back to ancient Greece to and still has it
Adherence and a lot of people think certainly even if it wasn't the main reason it played a role in it what about the idea that the Greeks just wanted it
More
Do use of sports phrase
In the Persians are sitting here trying to add a relatively small and poor territory to their already ginormous Empire
How motivated are you
The professionals I mean you know the king reward people who do well images a whole lot of good reason carrots and sticks operating on them
Fighting for their lives
And their freedom
Had to keep their families potentially from being enslaved
People have to live under if you have to live under someone else nonetheless
Why people don't want to do that
And I freedom in or at least the right to be ruled by your own people
Is important to you
You probably feel more strongly about it and adding this poor little territory on the fringes of the Known World here already China
The idea that the Greeks were fighting for more
Certainly Rings true when you look at a lot of other conflicts throughout history where
One side seemingly should steamroll together
And I don't
Carlotta mother
Pact
Dick's has even thrown out there and maybe as we said it's a
Junction of several of these things working together
The bottom line though is that
You know when I was growing up there was a long tradition
And 40 years ago the history that were written
Portraying these victories of shattering
And
Persian history is having this watershed moment in the year 479 right before 479 are on the rise
After 479 are on the decline 479 like the year they're at the top of the ladder right the wooden shoes are going up the ladder the
Silk slippers coming down in there with the top of the ladder in 479
Right before the fall
In the Greek narrative now
And you're going to see the Greeks go on the counteroffensive and take the war to Persia
Golden what's now turkey and the islands in the Aegean and raise the flag of revolt and free all these Greek people from
Persian control
Here's the thing though
This war is only over
If the Persians wanted to be
They have to kind of say okay we're not going to fight anymore because
The Greeks have a problem that the Persians didn't have we said how amazing it was at the Persians could feed and supply
Pisces Army's over these long distance is what
As an example of how amazing it is the breach can't do that
They can't go in
In a launch an attack in sending the Fenian Army into Mesopotamia and feed it and who they just can't
Do that
Ability to destroy the Persian Empire militarily is not in the Greek
Now what they can do theoretically
Is start a rolling chain of Revolt maybe that acts
Like a
Line of dominoes and begins to
Get the Persian Empire just would have seen the shake itself apart Like An Earthquake and there are revolts that happened
There are several historians I would think that
It's logical to assume that Persian losses against the Greeks
Anchorage places like Babylon and Egypt and all the
Usual Suspects to revolt
And that would have been something that they
The Persian king and the generals everybody that that would have concerned the great lie stuff on the peripheries
Little bit more like nibbling
And here's the thing you know if you look at it
Over the Long Haul
You could make a case that and we're trying to look at this from the Persian Viewpoint the Persians will end up winning
This whole thing to declare Victory now
Is a little like declaring victory
It on the second world war in 1942 just going home I mean sure the Persians lost these battle
Because of these tactical advantages of the Greek so what are they going to do
Going to come back and fight
Differently
And when you look at Persian strategy here you can really see some of the advantages that the Persians have
If the creek don't the Greeks had tactical advantages on the battlefield the Persians have
Advantages of a much higher level
They might not be able to raise any inventory that could compete with Greek hoplites head on
But they have a much more powerful and versatile weapon at their disposal
Kohl's
What
And maybe you can't make your own hoplites out of your own people but you sure can higher The Originals
And the Greeks
Begin to play a large role in the Persian military and what's more this is really
An explosion in Hellenism where we begin to see the mixture
At a much higher rate and it always been going on between Greek and the Persian Persian things in degrees because you get these mercenaries at Wilshire
Then come home
The other thing the Persians do with this gold
Is they begin to encourage the Greeks to kill each other
Two things now go away in the story that will change the story greatly
The first thing that goes away
Create cooperation
And the terrible threat of Darth Vader right in Greece
Heading corrida bunch of city-states that weren't that friendly with each other to drop their antagonism some work together when Darth Vader
Relieve the antagonism come right back
Most famous lie between
Sparta and Athens
This begins to be something
The Persian gold we'll figure out a way to exploit and encourage
Persian might not be able to kill Greeks on the battlefield very effectively
If platea and
Nicola Rennie
Laboratory tests but they sure do a good job at killing each other
The Persian Gold Canyon
The other thing that goes away at this point in the story and
You could argue he's the most important person in the story
Is our story teller
This is where Herodotus history and his movies over and
You miss him terribly
Earlier we'd set his during periodic said something to the effect of
Arata's gets all this criticism for not being more factually accurate in yet
He's all you have and you really miss him when he's gone and now he is
And this person that we have used to have color eyes the stories at the very beginning
He's gone a lot of the color goes with him
And we are left with some of the old
Ways of putting a story together the opposite of The Wizard of Oz that went from black and white to color in the middle of the picture we had color the whole
Wayne all of the sudden
It goes back to black and white without Herodotus
That when you're talking about the ancient past black and white generally means the sort of things that archaeologist
Confine
Whether you're talking about
Carvings
Or artwork
Score records
Or letters or what have you
But there was always something missing from the equation when that was all you had
The sort of things that you realize once Herodotus appears on the scene and you get this other side of History this one word
You really get these human parts and dialogue and themes and and drama
When he's gone you miss it
And you're left with wholly inadequate
Replacement with make you appreciate Herodotus even more and they fall into a couple of broad categories
One category I like to call the hard to believe
TCS falls into this category
Was a Greek doctor
Work for the Persian kings
Lived in Persia went to the dinner parties had Persian friends says he saw the Persian historical records himself
Should be the best of the best in terms of helping us understand
The workings the inner workings and then Persia's point of view
In my copy of a TCS which is the Lloyd Llewellyn Jones and James
Robson version
Those two
Write the prologue and this is what they say about
TCS history
Quote
Is history of Persia was completed at a time when the Greeks were fascinated by Persia
And seems on one level
To cater to a contemporary Greek interest in Persian wealth and opulence
Powerful Persian women the institution of the harem
Kings and queens Unix and secret plots
And quote
That's why perhaps a lot of the rest of the history
Of the achaemenid Persian Empire looks like that
Because the people telling you the story are giving you the story that way but
In all fairness to that guy
That's the level he was
Having contact with the Persian Empire that's the level he saw it and if Herodotus is giving you a
Geopolitically focused history you know a film on the Epic Grand scale
I got it she's just giving you more of a John cassavetes film
And it's all going on in one room and it's black and white and dark and really drink a lot of wine and then confessing you know what they really want to do
Each other
History as seen through a very different lens. Both of these
Guys who wrote the TC Spokane reading table
Want to make the case that they think this is a legitimate attempt by TCS to write a Persian history from the inside
Nonetheless this is a guy who you don't let's be honest if he makes it hard to believe he'll write a story for example about how
The events that led up to the Persians taking over Egypt originally couple Kings before this time
Happened because the King of Persia heard that Egyptian women were the best
And having sex
In the world
So he wanted
Yada yada yada ipso facto and all the sudden
In Aldi
Persians are taking over Egypt
You have to take the stuff with a grain of salt right
But sometimes this is all you're left with now different category of people
Then the
Hard to believe
Are the people who are writing about a completely different subject
And they just happened to as part of their story include some facts that are relevant to yours
What are the best historians of the ancient world a guy who starts writing right after Herodotus and thucydides or through Kennedy's
He's one of those guys
He's writing a story about the Greeks fighting with each other
But there's
In a sidebar information about the Persians occasionally so their stories go in there to grab every little nugget
If they try to put it in a semblance of jigsaw puzzle with he's considered a really good historian
Each one of those little foxy throws out there like gold does just not very much of him cuz he's not really
Writing about Persia
The final category also includes some great historical writers
It's those who are writing from a long time later
Take Plutarch for example but there's a bunch of other ones
He's writing from 5 to 600 years after the Persian Wars
And I tend to forget that because you think oh you know ancient Greek writer
Yes but he's writing in the second century BCE of the modern era
Annie's writing about events happening in the 5th Century BCE
It is far enough in his package farther in his past
Then the Europeans discovering the Americas easy an hour
How much did a person in the ancient world somebody
That we would consider having lived a very very very long time ago how much did he know about
His ancient path I'm by Marvel that they knew anything
And that there was some where this guy could go
To read primary sources which is why historians pay attention he was working from the original
Work of blah blah blah blah blah
Really
That original work is still available how many times is that scroll been recopied over the arrow
Ancient people had an ancient history of Their Own
Some method of
Preserving and transmitting it
Wild to me
None-the-less 500 or 600 years is a long time for a story
To get Legends build up around it or Miss
Or shall we use all those wonderful words from Academia we've been throwing out
Motif
Tropes stereotypes
But you know even the motifs in the stereotypes
Literary conventions of those days can tell you something
About the events if the person who's writing them
Is close enough to the one of the great things about Herodotus is
She comes
A generation after the events he is writing about he interviews people who were there
Who have some clothes
Your connection TimeWise to them
And so when he gives you some sort of
Theme for the story
Whether or not the theme is true the way he uses it as one thing
But it tells you something about the people living in that era
And the way they portrayed or thought about or remember these events
Herodotus and his movie
If you will
With a little story
In the story is about
The guy the legendary King Arthur type figure who founded the Persian Empire
And the story is about the Persians coming to him early on and basically saying now that we've won this great Empire we should move
From the poor country that we come from to one of these more luxurious areas with
In a good food and wine and you know
Another word for moving up in the world look straight up to a bigger
Your housing
Property
Virus gives him a moral less
The way this is intended to be conveyed is
The story that Herodotus just told you show you how they went from
An Empire who revered he's kind of values
The one that had forgotten them and paid the price he just related to you
He says in response to this proposal by his people that they trade up to some better proper
Aranas and this movie with this
Quote
Cyrus did not think much of this suggestion
He replied that they might act upon it if they please
But added the warning but if they did so they must prepare themselves to rule no longer
But to be ruled by others
Soft countries he said
Breed soft men
It is not the property of anyone soil to produce fine fruits and good soldiers to
The Persians had to admit Herodotus rights
That this was true
And it's Cyrus was wiser than they so they left him
And chose rather to live in a rugged land and rules
Vented cultivate Rich Plains and be subject to others
And quote
Well by the time Herodotus wrote that
The Persians lived in Aki
Occupied some very rich
Planes indeed
And the theme of a growing Persian decadence
Starts with Xerxes
And becomes one of the most dominant parts of the entire narrative and not just
Decadence but also decline
One of the weirdest metrics I think that's ever develop but it's natural to see how
Nitronic
Is this idea that you could trace the rise and fall of civilizations 2
How they're doing in terms of territorial acquisition and retention
Is the Roman Empire Rising whether they still conquering territory and expanding if so then they're Rising the minute they stop
Expanding start to contract they're falling they're in Decline
Of course.
Ignores the
Empires that
Like a stock market
Expand and contract based on their Fortune
I'm thinking of China
Were the byzantines for example
Going to watch the Persians in that sense to sort of fall of the Roman Empire model
Expand like the blob in the science fiction movie that we talked about earlier to a certain point
And once they stop it's all about trying to hold on to what you have
In the old especially 19th century way of viewing things that's a sign of an Empire in Decline
The idea
That this
Decadence and decline of reached a point where
We no longer have the wooden shoes descending the staircase we're well into the silk slippers going down
You know I thought about that for a minute and contrasted it to this idea that
You know we should be judging Empires on territorial acquisition
If you were living in
Some time. In ancient Persia
Would you rather live in the wooden shoes era or the silk slippers are
But it seems to me we probably live in the sun version anyway the silk slippers
Era in our own civilization lifecycle I would say
And if I asked you if you wanted to go back to one of the wooden shoes are or where things were more Spartan in the food was more
Simple in the
In the rules may be more strict I see two ends of the spectrum either like Viking like to be one level of the
Wooden shoes are aware you're so tough that you're just you know it's like a darwinian nightmare
Day-to-day existence
Or like something like
The Spartans were the Puritans where life is just one long
You know effort in Spartan denial but it's you know
Create stuff people not so much fun maybe live that life especially if you were born and raised in the slipper are alike
We probably were
The funny part about the Persian Empires history coming up is where we talking about it at 8
An Empire that is traditionally thought to be on the downhill slope
But if you live there other than some inflation some high prices baby might not have been a very bad time in fact
There might have been a decent amount of peace and stability and some of these places which is why some of these Kings were coming up or kind of boring
And you can run through 30 or 40 year
Rain
You're pretty quickly
Ironically the first of these Kings to suffer from sort of the darkness that intrudes on the narrative
Herodotus is gone
Is the star antagonist of his movie write the Darth Vader characters
Xerxes without leave the end of Herodotus is movie by darn near 15 years
If you believe the ancient Greek sources like the playwright that they often portray him as sort of like the Broken Man broken by the
Grease You're Never quite the same
There's a lot of building project the archaeologists so they weren't sure what you doing want to building after
Words
You may have conquered
What is general name conquered more territory in the East not really well known
It's pretty certain that the Persians were told a completely different story about the Greek situation than the Greeks would have known
What about
Brianna and Endymion have both quote
A much later account by an ancient historian
Dio chrysostom
And
Freon says quote the official Persian version of the event is probably close to it.
Social reports much later
He's talking about how the Persians probably spun
You know the war that just ended in Greece
DuckTales all the way back to the way we began this conversation
You're much much earlier
We talked about how with the Assyrian to the Babylonians
Everything about
Inable Last Stand of the Spartans at Thermopylae
Well this is an ancient historian Dio chrysostom
Kind of giving one
The everyone thinks might have been the spin that the Persian people were told and maybe the story that after awhile Xerxes told himself
Tianjin Astorian rights
Quote
During his expedition in Greece
Xerxes achieved victory over the lack of demonias at Thermopylae
And killed King Leonidas there
Mini Truckin laid waste to Athens
I wish you sold into slavery all the inhabitants would not succeeded in escaping
And after these successes he imposed tribute on the Greeks and return to Asia
And quote
That sounds like a guy
If that's true that's basically saying
Mission accomplished
Never mind all that
Revolutionary activity does Athenians and their little Alliance are stirring up on my coastline
Also
Both of the principal opponents of Xerxes in those Greek battles temistocles or Han Solo character
Estes Park
Both of them will end up
Either taking Persian gold or in Persian employee or imitating Persians or marrying Persians
Xerxes probably got to see pause Aeneas go all Persian
Witcher something they did the Persians were great cultural imperialistic to you came from a Backwater of ancient Greece like
Seniors did 8 that horrible Spartan gruel
And then go over and see how they're dressed fed
Wined and dined in the use sophisticated Persian women at a lot of people went all Persian
Passing is one of them
Themistocles either showed up in the court of Xerxes or
Kind of a victory for the dad when your Chief opponent shows up there and kind of goes
Can I play on your team now
Open the Persian point of view I mean you might have been able to say what's up
Look we win
All about how you spin it song
Nonetheless
Xerxes historical reputation has had to live with
By the way he's been portrayed for so long the first of the jerk Kings I think we called him
Someone who is less
Lenient than his forebears what episode of a laid-back pek
Policy of Tolerance and whatnot
Probably not true historians say but
Good luck changing that image
Also
Often portrayed as the first of sort of the silver spoon generation of Persian kings the ones
In a raised as rich kids
And not quite of the same metal as their forebears that's kind of what the end of the prodigious movie
Implies
Here's the way I am a den den
Describes
So the image
It's come down to listen to Xerxes quote
In the works of other Greek authors Xerxes is depicted as being surrounded by stupid eunuchs
Plato wrote that Xerxes was excessively spoiled
And it's starting with him
The Persian kings were great name only but not in reality
Contemporary historians often regard Xerxes
In accordance with Greek writers
As a man of week
Character
And a toy in the hands of his unit
The official Persian sources he writes however the pig Xerxes otherwise statement in a try and Warrior
And quote
This idea of Xerxes being the first of the Persian kings to sort of inaugurate
The decadence and decline era in Persian history is long stand
Common until the 1950s
Is at least
And a lot of books even
Call me the time after that
Will Durant way of course love but writing in 1935 when there was a different view of these things
You kept the same sort of an idea going in an extremely satisfying from a Storyteller an old-time his
He writes quote
The Empire of Darius lasted hardly a century
The moral as well as the physical backbone of Persia was broken by Marathon salamis in platea
The emperor's exchanged Mars for Venus
And the nation descended into corruption and apathy
The decline of Persia anticipated almost in detail the decline of Rome
Immorality in the generation among the people accompanied violence and negligence on the throne
The Persians like the medes before them
Pass from stoicism to epicureanism in a few Generations
Eating became the principal occupation of the aristocracy
These men who had once made it a rule to eat but once a day
Now interpreted the rule to allow them one meal prolong from noon tonight
They stock their larders with 1000 Delicacies
And they often served entire animals to their guests
They stuff themselves with Rich rare meat
And spent their genius upon new sauces and desserts
A corrupt and corrupting multitude of menials filled the houses of the wealthy
Well drunkenness became the common Vice of every class
Cyrus and Darius created Persia
Xerxes inherited it
Is successors destroyed
And quote
Is a history fan that's a wonderfully satisfying piece of Storytelling
And there are two things that are wonderful about it one it seems to teach you some wonderful Cosmic lesson doesn't it
About the decay of societies based on civilization
Lesson in wisdom acquired wisdom from the past the other thing that's wonderful is
The Surety of at the certitude
It's a very satisfying piece of writing
Compare that to something like Pierre Briand so much of it especially in the. We're coming up to is comparing
This ancient offered at this ancient authoring basically finding problems with both of what they say
The wonderful irony of this. In history were in now where everything is so much more documented in careful in scientific
We know less than we ever did
Instead of Illuminating a ton of things that were
Dark although there's been quite a bit of that
A ton of what modern history is done to debunk
What we thought we knew in the past
DuckTales right with the way
We mentioned it earlier Pierre Brown started his whole book which is this we know who you haven't heard a thousand Pages or more
Stop talking about this is how it was and you start your entire book off with a phrase that says quote
You Must Believe ancient history even if it's not true
And quote
Because the basic structure is real
The details are completely unknown
Any idea
Going all the way from ancient Greek times to the 1950s at least
But you can see in here part of an of a recurring pattern of civilizations declining and falling because they're people start
Eating Richard food and concentrate their genius on sausage instead of weapons or whatever the implication is there
That's fascinating to because everybody understand how ridiculous it is to blame
You know something like an entire cultures fall on the fact that their people are getting slovenly that they're slouching towards
Master
At the same time
One could perhaps be convinced that something like that has some sort of role in the grand scheme of things but try quantifying
You try
Diagramming the toxics to the brings down the Roman Empire in deciding exactly what percentage of responsibility
Do you tribute to the fact that they're women
Charles Atlas virtuous than they were back when the empire was right and you see what I'm saying
It's possible that that plays a role but when you read these histories and isn't playing a role it is playing V roll
And you look back on it now and you just say okay something like that is patently ridiculous and even if once or twice in history something like
Like that can be said to be what it was
Do use it as some sort of general rule that applies to the rise and fall of civilizations throughout history is
And everybody knows it now
But it's colored the way this story has been told
And so so much about the way to color now is trying to
Look through the weeds that have grown up over 2500 years
Including such things as well Xerxes was hanging out in the Harem drinking too much wine and
You know that's what happened to victim of Harem intrigues
Which brings us to the other problem with all this is going to be great if we could just as I said earlier right all this off
BS
Harriman trees is a wonderful example
Traditionally Xerxes assassinated
In keeping with the rest of this history of Persia we don't know how
Can you have multiple different accounts
The traditional overview they'll say is it's a victim of Harem intrigues of all these women fighting amongst each either on the rivals and and
Quest for power in the Unix and all this stuff in this we said earlier when you get these sources from people like
TCS he may be a little gossipy
Show me the whole history of Persia come down to a princess.
Prince Charles
Love triangle deal
Historian Lloyd Llewellyn Jones who's the one so I'm putting this TCS translation that I have together
He writes a very good defense of the idea of Harem intrigues
It sort of gives a pretty darn good historical justification for something that a lot of historians say this is just a motif
There's no such thing as a Greek
Idea romantic idea of a harem of all the sex in the end the drinking and it's like a Greek fantasy
But here's what
Llewellyn-jones has to say about this and what this does when he defends this idea
Is once more make us realize that when it comes to the history of the ancient Persian Empire and a lot of this ancient stuff we don't know anything for sure
Practically
You can make a case or an argument
For multiple interpretations of most things
Llewellyn-jones rights quote
So what then do we make
Noticias is vignettes of powerful queens and eunuchs
It is clear that the Royal women of achaemenid Persia
Did not live in prayer.
Nor did they inhabit an orientalist world of sultry sensuality
But they did form part of a strict hierarchical Court structure
They moved in close proximity to the king
Is a component of his harem
They followed the peripatetic lifestyle of the great king
The Royal women's importance and their allegiance to the maintenance of dynastic power
The achaemenid dynasty was after all essentially essentially run family business
And at the heart of the operation lay the harem
The king's domestic Inner Circle of women
Offspring siblings and slave
TCS the stories of female power and agency he writes
Always operate
Around the safeguarding of the throne
And the preservation of personal power
Stories of sexual shenanigans
The stuff of orientalist dreams are kept to a minimum
And even when they do appear they serve a bigger picture
Royal women fought over rank in position privilege and when Unix over reach there a lot of positions and names
For the throne
The Queen's act swiftly and punish them
For the women men and eunuchs slaves of the Royal Family
Prestige and access to power lay in their proximity to the king
Kevin says quote
The squabbles rivalries double dealings murders and executions must be seen in the contest
Text to buy Natick politics
Persia was controlled by an absolute ruler
That is not orientalist
Cliche
It is a fact
Absolute monarchies are open to a particular form of political tension which usually focuses on the Royal Family
Turn on the noble families that surround the king
Within such institutions
Women of the dynastic family often rise to positions of political agency
Not sure any formal route to power but by other less qualifiable mean
Cross-cultural and cross temporal comparisons with other court societies
Reveal this to be the truth
And quote
In other words
What llewellyn-jones just did there was take one of the things historians today are most comfortable with blaming on
Greek stereotypes and makes a darn good historical scientific defense of it
And what does that do just muddies the waters even more
This is my excuse now
For moving through
Several of the succeeding Kings quickly
When I decided to deal with each Persian king in succession is my structural framework for the store
I knew I was going to be front loading events because there's so much known and so much written
About the first several Kings
And the created the Empire and then
Do most people tend based on the evidence to scream through the succeeding Kingdom part of the reason why
Don't have as much
To do with the Greeks on a regular basis so there's less written about them
But you'll get whole rain like artaxerxes the first
Screens for like four decades and he's a
Person that normally you see a few events of his life put on a timeline
Listen to the way
That same will Durant writing in 1935
In a paragraph or two sums up the rest of the history of the kings of Persia after Xerxes as time
Quote
Only the records of Rome after Tiberius could rival in bloodiness the Royal annals of Persia
The murder of Xerxes was murdered by artist after a long rain was succeeded
Goodbye Xerxes II
Who was murdered a few weeks later by his half-brother Saudi on us
Who was murdered six months later by Darius II
Who suppress the Revolt of terror attack knees
By having him slain his wife cut into pieces and his mother brothers and sisters buried alive
Darius II was followed by his son
Artaxerxes II
Who won the battle of cunaxa
Had to fight to the death his own brother the younger Cyrus
When the youth tried to seize the royal power
Artaxerxes II enjoy the long rain
Killed his son Darius for conspiracy
And died of a broken heart on finding then another son focus with planning to assassinate him
Ochus rule for 20 years
And was poisoned by his General bag of us
This iron livered Warwick
Play Star versus son of a focus on the throne
Assassinated arcis his brothers
To make our secure then assassinated arsis
And his infant children and gave the scepter
Tokoto mantis
I safely effeminate friend
And quote
In other words
The highlight of most of the reins of the rest of the kings of Persia
Seem to be
The remarkable
Bloody purrific incestual
Assassination leading where they die
But it's worth pointing out
That of all those ends that
Will Durant just gave you
Almost none of them can be confirmed
These are traditions and you have to decide that you're going to buy the sources and sometimes the sources differ for example
Take the death of
The anti-hero in the Herodotus production Xerxes
The sources that are out there have different stories
TC this is the one that usually cited in the TCS version
Xerxes is assassinated by his bodyguard
Which could be a kind of a bodyguard or a general or counselor or busier the position is interesting
This bodyguard person is working with a eunuch
So what else is new
And the two of them are supposed to kill Xerxes
Now later
A fragment of TCS actually talked about how Xerxes died
But it says that he died in the most shameful way a man can die
I having his throat cut
While he sleeps by his son
And then the story gets interesting this is this is when
TCS has the two conspirators The Bodyguard in the eunuch
Going to one of the Xerxes Sons going to be the people who inherit
The throne which may be The Bodyguard wants
And telling the Sun
It is Brothers the one who killed his father
Yeah your dad dead guess you did at your older brother
So that kid we're told goes to his brother's house and accuses him of killing their father
The older brother says I can't kill dad
The younger brother doesn't believe him and killed him
And then there were wild and they could be true but you don't know
Then the conspirators try to get rid of this other son so that maybe the throne clear for them who knows
And the sun figures it out it was told
But he turns the tables and he kills The Bodyguard and the eunuch and the eunuch supposedly by
That wonderful torture method of the boats
And that King
Becomes artaxerxes the first
The artaxerxes the first is a wonderful example
How the rest of the story going to go until the very last king
Of the Persian Empire or maybe the second last depending on how you
Chronicle.
But that's the here's a guy who will rule
From 465 BC
24204 BC it's an enormous rain
For decades floss right
If you look at artaxerxes the first life
It's like a few bullet points on a timeline
That's how all the rest of these things are going to be two up until the last one or two
It's tempting to say maybe that's just because there wasn't a whole lot to record maybe artaxerxes the first is a great
Manager maybe like
You know Darius was a great CEO Persia core and he's so great that you know the Steady Hand on the wheel keeps their from
Norma's flare-ups of things that make great historical stories
I will probably
More connected to the fact that
Woodworking
Other parts of the Persian Empire remember
There's an entire Persian Empire on the other side of the Persian Capital that the Greeks know very little about its like
The Dark Side of the Moon to them
But there's a lot going on there
And a lot of the more modern historians point out that that's probably the more important part of the Empire to the Persians themselves
Who knows what artaxerxes is doing
He's famous though in the Greek story
For being the guy who caught a fisa practice at the Persians were already doing but sort of makes it the foreign policy
Your Persian
When dealing with the Greeks
Artaxerxes is the one
Who decides to make it the policy of Persia to use diplomacy as a weapon
And this is something I think a lot of modern-day people forget
The diplomacy is really good at we think of it as wimpy sometimes best defensive
A lot of the Great
Civilizations in history
Were fabulous at using diplomacy like a sword
Will you can go in and really deconstruct
Your adversaries using
The Persians were so skilled at this that some of the modern historians I was reading
Know that they can't help us a why didn't the Persians do this from the very beginning
I didn't need to fight any of those battle that we just were counted to you they could have just done this cuz look how effective it was
The 490 in the 480s Persia is fighting and mostly losing Land and Sea battles
Against these Greek city-states
100 years later the Persians have essentially emasculated them
I paying for them to emasculate each other
And they're so Machiavellian about it
When one side seems to be doing too well they'll fund the other side and the other side will continually
Change sometimes
The Persians are funding the Spartans to bring down Athenian power
But then for example will be a time where the Spartans will invade modern-day turkey in Asia Minor look like
I'm thinking about marching on Persian cities of the Persians
Front of a bunch of gold back to Greece
Spartan enemies attack Dam
Is there any Chester star said that essentially the
Persian Empire was like
The Puppet Masters of Greece by the end of this time and they had managed to do that simply by
Using money
To prolong and deepen
The natural disagreements that greeted always had with each other
And at the same time
Provide the means to continue fighting until everyone was exhausted at one point in the Peloponnesian War for example one of these
These wars that were spawned
You indirectly
In part by Persian gold
The Spartans will lose a fleet
To the Athenians are most of
Feel like they have to maybe drop out of the washer the Persians are buying another flea
They don't even have to go to the great king sometimes one of the set traps in the local area will pay for
Yeah sure no problem I'll just keep fighting
Now artaxerxes is one of these Kings who may have
Brokered the actual official maybe end of the war peace agreement in
449 but even that is argued about by historians who wonder if there ever was one and if the terms
Come down to us were real so
Who knows but artaxerxes is supposed to have died again we don't know how he died either but he supposed to had a good death Justina song
Breaking Bad or natural or what
Then he's the one who has three of his sons
So declare together that they're going to be king in that doesn't turn on
Atwell
One of them will be killed supposedly drunkenly after 45 days of being proclaimed King
Another one will manage a little longer until
Eventually he gets killed
Bye again close relative these are all Brothers
Black brother will take the name
Darius or dries the second rule from 4:23 BCE to 404 BCE
He has one of the coolest wildest wickedest wives in the world
She will be
Well depends on how you're looking at it
1 top worst mother-in-law's of all time or bastina from my standpoint
Loving the story she's one of the best she can Alexander the Great
You wouldn't want to have them as your mother-in-law but I get the story that come out of it or wonderful
Just so happens of course that just to make matters more Persian and interesting fun
Ancient
Thrice the second wife
What is sister
Your kid is artaxerxes II who's famous because he has a civil war with his little brother
Going to Cyrus the younger
Cyrus the younger as the Persians all through this.
Do hires a ton of Greek mercenaries to fight for him one of them is a guy named xenophon
Who happens to write in whose work has come down to us so it's famous
Cyrus the younger led by his Greek Mercenaries
Triumph at the Battle of cunaxa
Well
To a certain point is a better fight than a van says that the Persians Runaway
Before they even
Cross beers with his degree to pursue them a long distance and it was all going to be one except
Cyrus the younger the
Rebel King they were fighting for manages to get himself killed in the battle in that pretty much ends that you can't really
You know
Fight your brother for the throne if you don't survive the battle so
Story 2
Xenophon tells his famous in Western literature
These
Greek soldiers between 10 and 13000 of them have to manage
To get out of
The Persian Empire all the way back to Greek run territory and do so
You know where the Persian army essentially chasing them in a ratchet in the hallway the long story short of this whole thing is they management
And this has all sorts of overtones including this idea
Vulnerable the Persian Empire must be if they can't wipe out 10 to 13,000 hoplites
In their own territory unsupported
Of course my favorite story and xenophon and I would count it all the time
Is the moment where he and his troops
Camp out near these giant
Ghost cities
Built them and they're bigger than anything they don't know they think maybe
Of course we all know that he's camping out
Near the ruins of the greatest Syrian City
Two or three hundred years before
The Persians are the ones who inherited that old world and they ruled it for a while
And it made the transition from that black-and-white era to the fully colorized era of xenophon and we know he's in the fully colorized
We're reading this stuff aren't we
Versions of the bridge
They sort of explain how we got from the very very old world
To merely the very old world with xenophon asks who built these cities that are
Disintegrating around him
He's looking back to his ancient
Pass and ID
Seems to
And I said there's got to be a very weird
Feeling when you look back on something that is clearly from a long time ago
And some way looks bigger or better
Then what you currently have we don't have that experience right when we look back at the past looks primitive
Imagine coming from one of those time.
Maybe you're living in
5th Century Europe somewhere and you look at things that were built at the height of the Roman Empire you sit there and go
How did they build that and how sophisticated might they have been remembered
Human
Civilizational progress
Has only been straight up
For about the last five hundred or so years since the Renaissance before that time it was more like a stock market
And sometimes you had your high watermarks and sometimes you went down from your high
Xenophon Zera
Is coming up to the highs of the very Heights of the previous era
It won't be long before they are building cities greater and grander than the one disintegrating around xenophon
But when he looks at it
He's looking at something that hasn't
Quite been replicated
In the world he comes from
Going to be interesting feeling when do you think
Right there will if something that great and Grand
Fall
It can happen to any of
Does NF on people
Shortly afterwards
To the kings of Persia 2
But once again after we lose xenophon in terms of you know his story about his Retreat from Persia ends
We don't hear a whole lot about artaxerxes II
But he rules for 46 years
Does that show you how the sources just kind of completely overshadow
The Reigns of these later qinghai rule 46 years and there's not much that
This one incident that happened over one year that one Greek writer wrote about his huge the rest of the guys rain
Practically unknown
He's supposed to have hundreds of wives
Under the kids
One of them will become the next king
In the year 425 BCE and this came traditionally is sort of
The one that takes an already bloody history of the Persian royal family and takes it off into Caligula Ville
He's known as artaxerxes the third
There are a lot of people have gotten the job to but one of the brothers have been
Murdered another one commits suicide another one
Executed and when artaxerxes the third comes to the throne he's taking no chances he starts killing most of the Royal Family
Have you say something like well he killed his brother that sounds terrible when you realize artaxerxes the third had more than a hundred and fifty Brothers probably
You start to realize when wiping of the royal family might mean
When the
In a guy who sired you had 350 wives
MLS
Artaxerxes the Third
Comes to power at a time where Greek Warfare has changed
And once again it's very tempting to get down to the Tactical level and say that there are little teeny tweaks on the battlefield
It will end up involving themselves in contests
The end result of which will change the course of history
In this case
The Persians and the Greeks over the last
Century or so
Advantage to weaken each other greatly
The Persians have funded Athenians fighting Spartans fighting thebans in any strange combination
The year 371 and 1/2 in
Famous battle
Call leuctra
The thebans
Begin the process of demolishing
Spartan military power
And within 10 years I'll have another one of these battles it doesn't and so many Spartans die Spartans never the same
Many different
Innovations in Greek
Warfare
Were displayed in these battles and it's often seen as a step towards
A higher level of military sophistication for the Greek states often tied to
Prolonged contact with sophisticated military fight the Persians writing rubs off on
The thebans especially our are different in Greece because
They are the one major Greek city-state that is always had cavalry
Good Cavalry tradition they come from Cavalry country
And they use this Cavalry in these battles against the Spartans in the use it well
They also incorporate some light troops
Interesting tactics to end something that's been
Growing
An important especially amongst Even Stevens it always kind of
Like to fight in Greater depth
Then the hoplites from other Greek city-states but
They just go to maximizing that
During the reign of their last couple of
Military leaders
And at the Battle of leuctra
The
Even hoplites are fighting 50 ranks deep
And they smash into a
Formation of Spartan hoplites that is lined up
12-ranked Steve now if they had only recently gone to 12-ranked who used to be less than that
So you run a
Formation of
People a block of men that's 50 ranks deep into one that's 12 ranks deep
What happened
Not just that
But the thebans amongst other Greek city-states have begun to have
Professional military
That's Greek Warfare was always such an amateurish Affair and always was taught that way when I was younger
But it's now understood that
A lot of these city-states now I totally professional units
That were maybe like the tip of the spear for the rest of their army which was still Farmers & artisans in those kind of people
In the case of the thebans they had one called The Sacred band
Professional soldiers Maybe
May be homosexual lovers to that's always been thrown in there is something
Involved in the
Interesting
In a Greek city-state
Milieu
MLS
The Spartans great advantage over the other Greeks and the Persians to all the time was that they were the only professional War
Lawyers in Greece
But not anymore
So some of the things that always made Spartans extra-special
AR
Less unique by this time.
So you throw
A force led by 300 professional feed bins
Backed by a Phalanx that
50 Shields deep instead of going after the weak part of the Spartan line goes after the best Spartan troops and Crush
Is as
The theban general epaminondas says
Head of the serpent
And you ruin Sparta
There is somebody
Observing
Is military revolution in Greece
The hostage
Hostage from
Country that for a long time was Holding On by the skin of its teeth
To survival and sometimes not even that
His name
Was Philip
He will be the greatest military
Leader in the most dangerous man that your produces up until his life is over
He's learning
How to fight in the new style
By watching the thebans do it while he's a hostage and feed
Well then go back to his own country and based on a lot of what he learned while observing
Even military innovations
Build
The most
Military the world has ever seen
The Army did Philip bill
Was one that took
All sorts of influences from
Athens
Themes
And took makedonia is natural strength
And combined
Makedonia has great
Feudal cab
Aristocratic cow
Think of them nights and maybe that's not too far wrong
The Greek sources portray though makedonian infantry is being like a barbarian rabble before Philip
Philip turns them into the kind of soldiery
He would have seen it feed
People who stood
Shoulder to shoulder carrying very long Spears and Phillip lengthen them quite a bit since I've had the longest Spears anywhere
And he made their formation
16 ranks deep
Created an entirely new troop type
Information on the battlefield the phalange
With this form in his battle line
Use the Cavalry on the wings of a strike force Incorporated archers and light troops with it to make it flexible
He drilled them relentlessly and he used them almost every year of his reign
To fight somebody
It was an amazingly clever treacherous interesting fantastic guy
Did the old histories always portray as a drunken Barbarian who like boys but like women better
A kind of greekish biking character if you will
And by the time he's in his mid-forties the physical effects of his lifestyle
Are apparent
He lost an eye
He's broken collarbones
He may be fractured his hands and they maybe didn't grow back right that's not
For sure
And his leg is dragging behind him
The result to be there being
Speared
Behind the knee maybe we're having it crushed by a barbarian Club
But Phillips
Physicality on the battlefield
You know which clearly represented in his body the makedonian had a sort of a homeric
Kind of ethos that
The southern Greeks and kind of outgrown by this time there are more like Achilles and
Homer's Heroes ancient Greeks down south of
Become much more cultured
And philosophical and
In a sense you know if you want to get back
That idea of the silk slipper and the wooden shoes life cycle thing
Now it's the Greek
Interrupted by softness and luxury in the contact with the Persians all this time didn't help in now
Now the people with the wooden shoes
Are the ones who have some of the Barbarian virtues of strength and ruthlessness and
Well that's
The makedonian maybe so
From the old history and silk slipper syndrome approach the makedonian they're just the next in line
Florida modern history portrayed Philip as a much more culture
You have often portrayed the Dynamics of the makedonian
Royal family is a kin to a mafia crime family
Without a lot of alcohol and some homosexuality
But you also have to add
Aristotle
When people like that
Philip was
Absolutely
Committed it seems to upgrading the culture level of his court and when
Greek contemporaries met him they talked about a person who was thoroughly Grease
A great speaker
And charming and clever and
Fascinating individual in
Yeah it would be hard to imagine
Makedonia going from nothing
Two great powers
Without him
At the Battle of chaeronea
He will defeat
Utterly
A an alliance of thebans and Athenians to as the old saying goes
And the independence of the Greek city-states
His son Alexander
Leading the cavalry charge that destroys the theban sacred band to a man
Anyone famous story
After one of these battles Philip is portrayed as
Limping around the battlefield amongst the Goron Corpses
Drunkenly
Perhaps making fun of the nickname that they gave him down in the south of cultured so flipper regions of Greece now
Were they called
The Barbarian
You may ask where the Spartans are during this time. Now that Philip has essentially conquered although he put grease into a
Made it look like we were all here
Cuz we want to be and I'm going to call it the Warsaw Pact
To mean something like that
Sparta was like
I'm one of the best stories of the Spartans
I may have mentioned this earlier
Comes out of the
Note that supposedly Phillips ends to the smart
And this by the way has been told multiple ways and translated
But the general gist of it is quote
You are advised to submit without further delay
If I bring my Army on your land I will destroy your Farms slay your people and raise your
Any reply from Sparta
Just said
If
Well
Most historians I read seem to think it wouldn't even be much of a contest between makedonija this. And Sparta
Sparta is way past your Prime and makedonia has way more people in that larger
Economic base in everything
But the makedonian kept their hands off Smart. For what it's worth
All this time it seems clear
As Philip consolidates briefs
These planning on invading
Persia
Philip has a wonderful seeds train he's great at taking cities
He's got good Logistics he's learned
Very well how to fight
And keep armies in the field for long periods of time he doesn't have a bunch of amateur farmers in his army he has a professional military for
For that he can keep in the field
He's taking over gold mines he's got tons of money
If Persia really was that rickety old house that
Some Greeks at the time and some historians afterwards kind of portrayed as
All of a sudden something comes along
They can blow it down
But a year 336 BCE
Philip has established a Bridgehead
On
Asian soil just over the Bosphorus the hellespont
Get an army of 10,000 men there on her makedonian General
The stage is set
And then while walking into an arena
Along the
Column showing
The Greek gods including a statue of himself amongst them supposedly
Walking without his normal bodyguard
To show as a propaganda tool supposedly this is all the tradition
The other Greeks that
He is a
Ruler of Greece
You know by
Consensus if he's a benevolent guy he's not some
Heavy-handed
Tyrant that maintains his
Control by military force I don't need bodyguards I'm loved
And he walks out there alone
Philip
With his terrible leg limping
Garland around his head supposedly a crowd cheering
Alexander the Great in attendance with his wonderful mother olympius who
Peter husband supposedly
And someone from The Bodyguard runs up to the king
And slammed in my
Abs
The assassination is like a
Kennedy assassination in this time. Who done it and why
The Assassin runs autism waiting horses but it killed
By other members of The Bodyguard before you can get there
Alexander the Great's mother supposedly there's a lot of slander that goes on history so take this with a grain of salt
Puts
Emotional remembrances on the Assassins Graves of people have always wondered about Alexander
Because that's who gets the job next
So if we go back to our game of Clue from the earlier part of the story
Alexander's the guy you really benefits from this assassination
But think about it
So do the Persian
A little Persian gold in the right pocket to get rid of an extraordinary man
Especially after that extraordinary man has just landed 10,000 man on your coastline
Who knows who killed Philip II but if you're
One of the higher-ups in Persia you probably have to go give an extra large sacrifice
At the religious Temple
Cuz things just seem to have turned out your way
Alexandra supposed to have fought the Persians behind his father's murder but if it was the case that they were
Kind of looks like a good move if you're looking at this like you're playing some sort of a strategy game right if you're confronted with
An extraordinary individual
Enter causing you a ton of problems what's the easiest way to fix that problem
Maybe just get rid of the extraordinary individual
How many times in history that have
And not just amongst these warlord types of made a lot of enemies and you'd expect them to have people willing to stick a knife in their ribs
But even amongst people
At the other end of the violence Spectrum
Look at Martin Luther King or Gandhi both of whom were assassinated
Both extraordinary
People
And both
Huge D stabilizers
They caused a lot of people a lot of problems and if you're an ordinary person sometimes dealing with Extraordinary People difficult
But you can always get rid of them
Of course you're playing the odds aren't you when you do that the ideas how often do you get extraordinary individuals if I get rid of
Did Philip II is extraordinary European
Certainly
I will end up with someone
Not as good as he is
I'm at the Persians were behind the assassination it would only mirror
What Persian saw happening in their own royal family in assassinations
Always a possibility
Really took Center Stage
The famous Harem intrigues is we said I mean artaxerxes the third the Contemporary of Philip
This guy we mentioned earlier was the one who supposedly took the Royal Family
Caligula bill is real
Nasty ruler
He's going to meet his in the same way Philip. She's got to be stabbed
He's famously going to be poisoned by one of the great poisoners of the ancient world
Now there are some
Cuneiform tablets that seem to suggest that
Artaxerxes the third may have died a natural death and Lord knows he was supposedly in his mid-eighties so that's not out of
The question
But the ancient sources place his death at the hands of his vizier
Where is counselor may be his General
The Greeks always call them eunuchs
Whether they were or not castrated is unknown
This guy's name is Pago us
He's famous
The king that he poisoned supposedly is this one that we were talking about earlier
That is vicious enough so you think of him almost like an Assyrian King rather than a more tolerant lenient Persian king but
When you look at his accomplishments he looks like
The restorer
Of the Persian Empire
Long and absolutely are Jewish career
He is smashing revolts reconquering lost territory and however rickety it may be internally on pay
By the time this guy dies
He is restored Persia
To somewhat of its former luster at least if you look at a map
It's a remarkable achievement this late in the game
It's like an athlete decided they're going to
Compete in the Olympics like they did when they were 20 when they're 50 and they get into great shape and look pretty good they just
Hopefully it's not too hot
But the fun for me if you're a fan of Persia's I am is throughout this time. You're setting up an encounter
Encounter between two extraordinary men Philip II in makedonia
About to lead
The Greek invasion of Persia probably
Certainly after
Artaxerxes the third die but maybe even before and artaxerxes the third
Obviously competent as hell
Going to resist him
For the heavyweight championship of the ancient world right
Who will win the representatives or the representatives of the merely very old world
And then assassination
Removed both of these extraordinary men within two years of each other
And the problem if you're looking at this as a giant championship match
Is it
We get the standings for both the people we just lost
In one corner
We have a guy named Darius the Third
Person that the poisoner
Bagelicious after killing a lot of other people and having a little
Two-year puppet King
In the interim puts on the throne
Maybe mediocre maybe worse than mediocre in terms of replacement
In the other Corner replacing Philip II
Alexander the Great
This is a show about the Persian Empire but Alexander the Great as the instrument of its death
There are some Modern historians would like to think of Alexander is really the last king of Persia
He's the guy who will eventually burn down
The Royal Palace
Tumi
That's where it ends
It's about Alexander the guy who landed
He's a historical arsonist in my book and then that's a term I use for these people who come
In the history periodically
And soda burn down the Deadwood of an old world so a new one can crop up it's a very simplistic historical approach
You see these people all through history
Alexander's the prototypical example
It's almost like they do what they have to do know they play their role on the on the historical World stage and then they die once they are
Job is over
And Alexander falls into one of two categories historical Arsenal seem to fall into
There's the self-made man
Guys like djingis Khan
Cool
Create the instrument first and then go out and kill people with it
That's what Alexander the Great's father Philip
Right he was sort of a historical arsonist in his own way especially if he'd been allowed to continue his career
A self-made guy
Alexander the Great Falls into the other category historical arsonist
Similar to a guy like Frederick the Great
Where he's born
And the father has sort of set the historical table for him
Built the instrument
To go conquer the world with right
Created the weapon and then hands it to the son who doesn't have to spend years of his life
Creating the conditions
Raise brightness he can just go out and hit the ground running
It would be tempting to suggest that Alexander had it made in anybody would have been able to do what he did give
He inherited but here's the thing
Think about the uniqueness to this guy for so understand he probably the most propagandized figure in the ancient world
Especially if you remove religious figures from the equation
Is the Elvis Presley of ancient history he's the king
There is so much
Stop built around him I mean as one historian says the jungle of Alexander myth out there
Has been going forever
We have all the same problems with him that we have with the Persian sources but add to that
Immense propagandizing
And cult-like hero-worship there are even historians who suggested Alexander's
Life story in the sources have been purged and called and clipped over the years
To maintain sort of an image
For all sorts of domestic purposes of the time in a little stalinist a little North Korea like
The point is getting to the real guy here is next to Impossible
There were at least 20
Contemporary accounts of
Alexander stuff written
Including stuff from his generals
All that stuff is gone
Warwick Mall in the in absolutely shattering
Sentence point out that the only actual contemporary thing that exist from Alexander time talking about Alexander
Is a one-sentence dedication on a temple
Everything else is derivative
Which is typical French and history but it does blow your mind when you think of how much stuff there was at one time
Normal after a few things you can say about this guy their mind blowing right away he's not just the son of the most interesting man in your
European history probably up until this point certainly the most powerful geopolitical figure
He's also the son of the most interesting female
Is Mother's fascinating and once again like all women in ancient history she get the combination of rooked
Propagandized
Who knows the truth about this woman the rumors are
She's a Malaysian which who sleeps with snakes and is an acolyte of Dionysus the god of wine
She comes from
A people that the macedonians with the Greeks think are barbarians the makedonian think these people are Barb
The melodians were a powerful tribe that lived in the Wilds of the ancient Kingdom of the Pirus
Located south of
The modern day
Country of Albania
For what it's worth
What you can say about her though
Is this is a woman who is so formidable
That the greatest figure in European geopolitical history Philip II could not handle her
Not only that apparently he couldn't just kill her either
She also proved after Philip was gone
The Phillips generals and Alexander's generals after Alexander couldn't maneuver
Murder dumb
Killed people that got in her way I mean protected the interest of her son she was
Formidable as hell think of the DNA in the sky Park greatest man in European GOP
Political history
With one part most impressive female in European history the malossi in which snake loving follower of Dionysus
Have that
DNA Diamond Polished by
The greatest Shooters of the age including Aristotle
SEPTA
Template design for the guy's life
As one crib from Homer and The Iliad
Aristotle supposedly annotated copy for Alexander who slept with it under his pillow while on campaign
Teach him that he is the descendant of legendary gods and heroes on both sides of his family
Achilles on his mom's side
Heracles and Zeus on his dad's
And then hand him
The keys
Did the ancient world's equivalent of the 1940s German
And he's 20 years old
I keep reminding myself
Even though the world has changed a lot in 20 years old then might have been the new 30 if you will
You're still 20 years old I know guys who are afraid of given a 20 year old son's the keys to the sports car
Because of what they might do
Alexander has the
Most dangerous military in the world
Gassed up and ready to go
Earlier in the story we said that from the Greek point of view
Darius the great and Xerxes are
Invading Greece that they play the role of Darth Vader
To the Greeks
Open the Persian point of view this story
Darth Vader is played by Alexander the Great
Torries warwick mall suggest
The Iranian people thought of him
The demon
There are a lot of Greeks that would
Agree with that characterization
Alexander the Great takes over from his father a bunch of Greek city-states decided to good time to Rebelle
After all
What are the odds of this 20 year old kid
It's going to be able to do to wasps what is extraordinary father did
The answer turned out to be pretty darn good
Alexander spends the initial part of his
Randy first year-and-a-half two years or what have you
Proving the people that he is a chip off the old block
He can use this Army as well as the old man could
And in addition to pounding a bunch of Barbarian tribes that decide to get uppity on his border she destroys thieves
And it is so brutal
I've read several historian to say what Alexander did the thieves was worse than anything the Persians did the Greek cities when they were occupied
Pine grease 150 + years before
But it sends the message in Greece is once again cowed
And as we said earlier you know they're a little like the Warsaw Pact in this deal
They get to go fight this war against Persia they get to provide troops whether or not they want to
There's a lot of Doubt as to how
Excited these Greek forces that will accompany Alexander on his Crusade r
Have a couple has the right to think they might have been
Little more than glorified hostages to keep their people
Down on the farm while Alexander in the main Army argon adult rebelled against me I have 15000 of your citizens
Something like that
In 334 BCE Alexander
Crosses from
Europe to Asia it's a big deal at the time
He brings were told
Historians and geographers and all kinds of people with him
People to Chronicle
Is advanced modern press Corps and propaganda course the way it's often portrayed
Screwed up the sources ever sent to me
It's hard enough to Divine
Fact from fiction in history without having people that are deliberately trying to pull the wool over your eyes for
No short-term military effect
Aunt alexandra was fantastic
Promise you can't tell when you're reading something that's propaganda in something that's true just like all this other source trouble we have Alexander
Used to have
From the water as he crossed from Europe to Asia that short little span
Of liquid
Throwing a spear
Off of his boat
Landing on the beach
Claiming all of Asia by right of Conquest
Stream Peter Breon says that
But this is a novel position
The Persian leadership to find themselves in
Because while Persia had had all sorts of revolts over its history
And certainly tribal Barbarian incursions all over the place
And trouble along the frontier in military Breakaway situations
Interference from foreign powers
They had never had anyone
That had
Both the stated intention
Taking over the whole thing toppling the government in just
Assuming control
And also the means to make that a reality
Kelly Ryan.
Alexander
What Alexander's attempting to do here is much more than an ancient battle he's launching a full-scale
Ancient war
But ancient Wars involve toothache
1 years
Field battles usually
Those are the big battles where everything can be decided in an afternoon
It is between the field battles that the dirty grimy dated a horror of
The ongoing look like slow-moving lava
Have a campaign goes
Taking walled cities for example is famously slow and grinding
So there will be field battles along with a bunch of grinding attritional Siege type
Horror all in between
Alexander's first field battle of hapan
When he is confronted
Soon after
Crossing over into Asia by the local Persian forces
One of our main sources for these events says that
The King of Persia had been given conflicting advice by different
Counselors on what to do about this Alexander problem on their Frontier
There was a
Famous Greek General working for the king of dining memnon of Rhodes and supposedly memnon
That this was the ancient world
What's equivalent to the 1940s German Vermont
Told the king stay away from that
Don't engage that
Burn the crops destroy everything star of that army
Historians think that Supply problems may have doomed
The Persian invasion of Greece 150 years ago turnabout is fair play
Cut off that army
And make it
Straggle home in defeat
And this time
The people from Europe can be like Napoleon soldiers straggly home from Russia
As you might imagine though the governor's the satraps of those places whose farms and everything would have had to have been burned or no
Unenthused by that idea
Cast aspersions on memnon the Greek Heritage may be suggesting that he was working for the other side maybe sympathy wise
Question his manhood sort of and basically said you know we don't
Run from people with the Persian Empire
And so the local forces
Show up to confront
This
Force and here's the thing
At this point for the for the Persians this is not that unusual been dealing with problems caused by the
British people from us 200 years
This is the fringes of their empire even lose battle to these people that happens it's not life or death whatever happens here
As the sword is continually point out
Alexander gets no luxuries here he cannot lose one.
He's in a situation where he if he loses he goes home
The Persians on the other hand are on their home they can afford to lose some especially
Dispersed when we just sort of a throwaway battle to them
They lose no big deal it's just the local forces if they win hahaha
You know makedonian problem solved that the king even having to show up wonderful right you take that gamble every day of the
The week I think
That something happens in the story at this point that is noticeable
And that is it all of a sudden the color that has been missing since our screenwriter Herodotus left the scene
Returned in glorious Technicolor
And it looks like a
1950s Hollywood sword-and-sandal
Jam packed with action is wonderful stuff
2300 years later
Well were using as a source another one of these ancient Greek writers
Who is writing in the Roman Empire 400 years later until
You're tempted to say why pay attention to any of this stuff is just coming out of this guy tomorrow
Earlier that all the Contemporary accounts are Alexander's time. And because of these were huge event a lot of people wrote
My time without
10000 weeks on the bestseller list
But those things are gone now so we don't have any of those
But Roman era writers like Aryan the Greek writer whose account has the best account of Alexander's
Military campaign
He did have access to that stuff
He says he wrote from three main sources
The number one source
Was one of Alexander's best friends one of his companions what is 7 important bodyguards a guy is so close to him he may have
I've been a half brother
And after Alexander's life was over
This guy tore off a chunk of his Empire and started to Dynasty centered in Egypt that rule for 300 years
Not too bad
Primary source right even if your getting a second hand
Also one of Alexander's
Admirals
Combat engineers in the area and basically said she took up with the scientific approach to it and compare the sources to each other
It's about the best you're going to get right
The Aryans the main guy
Arian says
That at the granicus river Alexander's forces ran into the Persian Defenders and that they numbered about 20
Cavalry about 20000 in French
Modern historians think those numbers are high
But Alexander's numbers are pretty darn well close self for the first time in a long time maybe
We have reasonable numbers for at least one side Alexander's forces supposed to have had between 30 and 35000
Instrument and about 5,000 maybe a little more than 5000
So even having one number to fill in for a letter in the algebraic historical equation
Alps
All these battles that are coming up in this
Campaign are argued about endlessly
The exact locations are not even known
So take everything with a grain of salt the one thing you can say though
Is that what about to happen here it's easy to see how this all contributes to the myth of Alexander
And one wonders although I haven't heard anybody say this wasn't true if any of this was true
Theoretically possible that this is all made up about Alexander that he wanted to be portrayed in homeric terms and so
And he's Superman and all the sources
Seems very unlikely though
He seems more on the other end of the Spectrum which is somebody who really enjoyed this
Somebody who would have considered it
A bad thing to have for any reason missed out on The Killing
It wasn't just leading his men cuz it was his duty
If any of this stuff is true about Alexander he got a kick out of it
And the stuff he did is
Frightful
I don't mean in there
Sense of giving frightful order like go kill all the civilians from that City we just captured I mean
On a personal level what he did was frightful
And you can't judge the people in modern cultural
Terms because
Everybody around him was doing similar frightful things that's how you fought right
What's more
The society was built on encouraging the carrots and sticks that made such activities
Cast in the light of
Heroism or Warrior Hood
Or Defending Your people or what-have-you another word
It was completely supported by the culture
Alexander was increasing his
Glory Fame honor
And all those other things
And with all these killing
And having them recorded in
Homeric charms was the sort of stuff
He wanted to read about himself cuz it was the sort of stuff you read about his own hero
Read The Iliad
Is frightful
When you read the accounts
Aryan provides of Alexander's conduct
In
Hand to hand combat at the Battle of the granicus it sounds very similar
Fascinated and everybody is totally confused about how
Ancient combat worked
When you read the sources it's so hard to get Patty to are these literary devices where they have people talking to each other in combat
Were there ways that could actually happen in the demon battle
Aaron's account of Alexander fighting at the granicus
Has that kind of stuff going on
In addition as we said earlier in Ancient Warfare
The officers and the commanders are very important and they're right there In Harm's Way
In the larger battles the commanders might themselves be the head of state
What happens if you take
Them out
Alexander is the head of state
At this battle and he will be fighting in the front ranks
According to Arian
The Persians Mass a bunch of troops together
And just showed up from their side of the battlefield follow Alexander
As he moves in his bright magnificent armor
And with the Trap and you could always tell where these people were because they wanted their own troops to know
And is essentially a unit of Persian Cavalry following Alexander across the battlefield from the other side
Waiting for him to make his move and their job is going to be to take him out
He's the head of the snake as far as they're concerned he's Darth Vader
Darth Vader and the Death Star and the emperor all rolled into one
Tell him and maybe everybody goes home
Alexander's response to that according to Aryan and pretty much everyone else you've ever heard from
Is the charge into the thick of the mess
We mentioned earlier we were talking about the Persian army from 150 years ago that we changed over time
Expect there to be some evolution
Are the criticisms historians
A long time ago in in
All the way up to the time when I was a kid were making about the Persians were
Do they got beaten all these battles against the Greeks and they didn't really even change it any appreciably positive way but modern historians
Answered yes they did
And it was right under your nose is you're always talking about things like Scythe Chariot and all these other things do you think those are
Their attempt to come to grips with their weakness and a great advantage in this case
How do you break up those formations of heavy infantry that fight shoulder-to-shoulder with those long Spears they are a pain
The Persians hired a lot of those Greek mercenary hoplite to fill the gap for them
There's 10 to 20 thousand of them at this battle
They also tried to figure out
Stratagems and ways to break up that Reformation because once those spearmen were no longer huddle shoulder to show
They were vulnerable as hack
That's why this is called the battle of the river granite
Because the Persian forces
We're on the other side of a river
And on the far side of the river was a steep Bank
And on top of that awaited a very long line of Persian cavalry
The thought process seems to be in
Seems pretty sound
We're looking at it
That you're going to have to cross if you were the makedonian foot soldiers that give the Persians historically such a hard time
A body of water
You crossed this body of water
And you scramble up to the other side there's no way you're still maintaining your
Shoulder to shoulder cohesion anymore
And you have Cavalry awaiting you at the top of the rise to charge down on you
That sounds like a pretty good plan if you're looking at it from the person point of view
For some reason they seem to a station there infantry too far back to take any part in the battle I read somewhere I think it's like a mile
Backup meaning
It's a big distance
The last looks like a pretty good plan on paper if we're
Reading Eggs
The other thing that has changed over a hundred fifty years apparently this is all very debated but but it's it's starting to be
Become apparent
The Cavalry has changed
And 150 years since the earlier Greek war with the Persians
Back then if you recall the Persians used to attack
With missile Weapon by Squadron and sort of try to wear you down and they would attack you in hand-to-hand combat if you were like true
Scattered
They were going to slam into your formation probably
150 years later that's exactly what
Alexander's crack heavy Cavalry does
And that's what the heavy Cavalry units on the Persian side due to
Are you study calorie evolution
Is a long
Train of thought going back to the idea that this all started in Central Asia with all those horse tribe that were always innovating and spread
By the time Alexander is attacking the Persian Empire spread indeed and there is melee Cavalry on both sides
And unlike the Greek Wars of a hundred fifty years ago where the Persian Cavalry really had no counterparts on the other side
Here Persian and makedonian Cavalry often faced off against each other often these battles are going to involve infantry in
In the center
Alexandro replaces Phalanx this giant
Block of human beings that took up the main battle line
And then Calvary on the wings where it could do something
It's often opposed by Persian Cavalry on the other side
And a lot of these battles
Involve the Persian and macedonian Cavalry fighting it out in almost nightly fashion
And that's what happens with Alexander
The front of this infantry starts to advance toward the Persians Alexander get to sort of a
A faint underway were you able to get the Persians to move in a different direction then he slams into them in a Cavalry battle in shoes
Games where he almost dies
Here's the way
Historian je London I thought he did a wonderful job synthesizing the Aryan
From the area and he describes what it's like for Alexander the Great
Head of state
And Darth Vader in the Persians eyes
In this battle he sounds like
The guy who he thinks his ancestor Achilles doesn't he
Quote
Alexander lettuce makedonian Cavalry through the riverbed and directly at the position of the sad tracks in the
Persian
When the two lines struck
Alexander broke his Lance in the fighting
He cried to a groom for another
But the Groom Zone Lance was broken and he was defending himself bravely with the broken stump
Ask somebody else
He shouted
When another of his retinue finally surrendered his Lance to the king
Alexander spy mithridatic
A son-in-law advancing
Writing out from his guard the makedonian drove his land straight through the Persians face
Knauer Osakis
Another Persian
Brother of the satrap of Lydia struck Alexander on the head with a sword
The blow wrecked the Kings helmet
Get the helmets Save the King
Clearing Mr Davies asgore off his land
Alexander took Roche keys in the chest
Piercing his queerest
And hurling him to the ground as well
From the melee behind the king the set traps mithridates Wong back to deliver a great blow to avenge
Just Fallen brother
But Alexander's companion Cletus was there first with his own sword
The clove off at the shoulder the arm upraised to fell the king
It was from this point in the fighting
This Cascade of arterial blood that Panic began to spread them on the Persian
Until it carried them fleeing from the field
And quote
That's a famous story in Alexander's life as he's
In the midst of the fighting a Persian from behind is about to strike him maybe take his head off
And is his arm is upraised to bring the blow down on Alexander's head
His friend Cletus
Sears off the Persians arm in a weapon in hand
Think about all that's going on in the midst of how much is that is a good story and how much of its really what happened
It's hard to know
What's hard to know when it's also hard to know if things really went that way some historians believe that there may have been a
Reverse initially at this battle but that Alexander's propaganda which could not afford any
Suggestions of
Reverses
You covered up
But none the less one way or another it seems that at some point Alexander's
Forces Drive the Persian Cavalry off
Greek hoplite infantry in the rest of the Infantry was too far away to impact in the battle
Alexander ends up butchering a bunch of them and then selling the rest of slaves
And the battle of the granicus is over
Remember this was something that involved
Local forces on the scene
Once the Persian see this now it's time to get serious we're going to call in a Royal Army and that's a pain in the
The rear
Remember the Persians treated their empire little like a company with subcontractors and
Their army had a royal core sort of that they could bring to a mustering spot and then they would call
Districts they needed forces from in this case most of them to come and bring troops to the same location to bring you
Your local forces and will pull them all together and then
We'll have this huge Force to deal with Alexander
The call comes out in the
Persian king is going to take the field himself
And meanwhile Alexander goes and does the stuff that you do in a between field battles
He takes the submission of local people
In any area they're saying I was hated the king I'm glad you're here and I'm going to be your friend can I stay in charge of this region I've always run
I'm really good at it I got it down to a science
So there's a lot of that there's also the people who resistant
Hide behind walls and Alexander have to break those places down and he's not nice usually when he does
Alexander comes up with a novel strategy to sort of eliminate the threat from the Persian Fleet
He doesn't have a fleet that can fight the Persian Fleet so he just goes around starts taking all the cities along
The coastline so that there won't be any place for the fleet to
Sika Port me just takes all the port
Combat strategy either
Alexander's consolidating his Conquest
Running his porch strategy the Persians are funneling money to all the states in Greece that want to break away from makedonija
Ironically a bunch of them places that hundred and fifty years ago were fighting for their lives and freedom against the Persians
Hummel all this is going on in the king of kings in Persia
Is mastering the Royal Army which which must have taken a long time
Sebastian Pires getting from one place to another with a lot of troops not easy
So they must have them believe it was in Babylon chords
Modern-day turkey
In the fall of 333 BC
To give you an idea of how rare this is although I think they had fought some major
Battles in Egypt not that long ago
Is going to your brain says that
The
People in that part of the Persian Empire and turkey had not seen a royal Army in a hundred and fifty years since
Jesus time
The Persians don't often have to bring out the big guns
The fact that the king is there with the Army now
Is a sign that they're taking Alexander the Great seriously
Power ancient Greek writer Arian says the Persian king is leading 600,000
Through Syria and up toward turkey to confront Alexander that's pretty darn serious
It's also pretty darn
Incredible
As always with the Persian numbers historians know that
Incredible they just can't agree on what is
Alexander's probably got about 40 thousand guys with him
The low numbers you here for the Persians are equal
2 Alexander
Most often though the numbers you get for the Persians art
Twice as large or two and a half times as large generally it's thought
Did Alexandra significantly outnumber
In this battle and that's not hard to believe
Are you considering that you are in the Persian heart
Land
But I would have to remind myself in again this is the value of a historian from 100 years ago like Hans dalebrook from
Germany
But delbrook reminds us and uses historical example to point out that just because you have a lot of people at a place
Doesn't mean those people are soldiers
We always had this concept that every human being out there was a potential person you could throw into the ranks in his delbrook points out no
Any societies you have people who are warriors
And people who make pottery
And things like that are Farm
And sometimes they can be malicious but he points out
If the Persian army were a lot smaller than you thought it
An Empire that size your produce
There are historical analogies all over the place for why that might
Nonetheless however large this Army is that the Persian king of kings is leading personally
It somehow manages to get behind Alexander the Great's army
Cuts off his
Line of retreat
Blocks his Supply
And
If you believe in stories Arthur Ferrell says Alexander must have been shocked to find this out
How did that happen and historians
Argue over whether or not this was deliberate in a masterstroke by the Persian generals
Or was it sort of an accident and they kind of found themselves
Guess what I'm on Alexander supply line
This fact though is why if you look at the Battle that's about to happen
It looks like the map needs to be turned upside down
The armies appear to be on the wrong side but that's because
The positions got reversed and that's why Alexander is coming north and the Persians are going south and they meet in this Coast
Stop playing so you have the ocean on one side once like is guarded by the sea
Do you have the mountains
Maybe two and a half miles
Any other direction so you got this coastal plain that turns out to be your Battlefield
There will be
Critiques from the ancients
About the Persian decision to fight the spot because they will say that
2 miles or maybe a little bit longer it's not wide enough playing for the Persians to
Really take advantage of their Superior numbers are constrained
Hemmed in by the hills on one side and C on the other
These are the same people that thought they were 600,000 Persians there maybe so
Maybe a little distorted you how it really was
For me though
When you look at what's about to happen you're seen in my opinion but a lot of people feel this way
Alexander's real acid
The first time maybe you could make a good case that he's not living off his dad's funeral
And that everything he done so far
What's something that a lot of people probably could have done having been handed with Alexander was handed I mean my goodness you could add a puppy
Peking
With those generals of
Philips Hue his dad
If they didn't kill you their murderous
Wild guys I mean you know you wouldn't survive in that setting
What do we call it a mafia crime family type dynamic
None the last song in those guys could have run this whole thing probably on autopilot
This to me
Is a battle where you see Alexander stand out of something
Really special
And there are people who will say that even after this battle it still could have been autopilot that's how good this Army was and that's how good
The command structure was I mean it's really
It's really quite a step up
And yet
In this battle
As
The Duke of Wellington supposedly said
About Waterloo
This battles going to be in near run the thing but you don't normally associate with Alexander who got this one of Godlike quality
Impart
Something fans Maybe by his own publicist
And media staff
Where you don't even think he comes close to losing
Body mist bottle
It's a near run thing
Both sides with lineup
On
Opposite sides of a small stream
Manestream gives you a little cover to deploy
Because in one of the little known fun parts about Ancient battle really even up to Napoleonic times and later
If it takes a long time to deploy
Think about it
How many people you're talking about they all have to be in specific position so both sides take hours at this
And in a place like ancient Greece
In a lot of cultures actually they had all these sort of cultural gentlemen's agreement I guess you could call them where we say things like
Don't don't let nobody attacks anybody else is on Drew Brees right right and we'll say go when we go out
Vikings did that
Ancient Greeks did that
But when you're fighting cross-culturally all those gentlemen's agreements got the window
So both sides are on opposite sides of the street and they're all using light infantry and Cavalry to keep the other side from messing with them too much while they get
They're soldiers in just the right spot
Last-minute moves from one side to the other
Countering this encounter in Latin
Basically
The Persians line up a whole bunch of Calvary on their right flank
And they're playing according to you know this is argued about to Bud Arthur Ferrell he's a good military has thrown the following and he goes
Those with a general agreement that the Persians are trying to do a hammer and Anvil tactic and Alexander
They're just doing it on opposite sides of the battlefield
So Alexander going to lead a charge
On his right flank
And try to crush the person Left Flank and then sweep around and go attack the Persian middle from behind and the Persians are going to try to do the
Exact same thing on the opposite side of the battlefield where they've matched almost all their cowboy
Now I can't help but think
How much of a morale boost it has to be to your average Persian Soldier there
You may be facing this demon from guide is Darth Vader character
But all you have to do is look down your own battle line and 100 200 300 yards down the line you see the
Sacred
Chariot of Persia's
King of Kings drawn by the sacred white horses
And surrounded by the royal guard
This guy is not quite a God Like a pharaoh or something
But he's about one tiny half step below that
You have to feel pretty confident
If you're on the Persian side and you look in the King of Kings is right there
What we said earlier Alexander the greatest makedonija is
Head of state fighting in hand-to-hand combat in these battles
This is the first time that the head of state for makedonija
Face is on the opposite side of the battlefield under 200 yards away at the start
The head of state of the Empire he trying to take down
And I love that I mean that
Reminds me of that video when I was a kid
Genesis did one with during the Cold War that had Ronald Reagan in the head of the Soviet Union fighting hand-to-hand in it
Order something
I tried to come up with like a modern analogy
And they're all so ridiculous but they're still fun I mean imagine the Second World War
Where
You're fighting this way and on one side of the battlefield as Winston Churchill in the British forces and they look across
No man's land a hundred two hundred yards across the field and they are surrounded by
You know maybe the mounted SS lifeguard is out of Hitler
See them on the other side and
Depending on
How you conduct yourself if you want to
You can go get them
This is once again we're Alexander looks very homeric in the sense that
She almost comes through on the sources he wants to make this personal
And I'm not sure the king of Persian does
Not wanting to weigh in on the controversy of all the arguments over hubby
Arthur Farrell
Military historian
I'll let him do it
After saying that the
Persians were using
A hammer and Anvil strategy
He goes on to say
That Alexander is to
Pieces quote
Ironically Alexander's plan was essentially the same as his opponents
And we can see clearly in this battle
How the traditions of ancient near Eastern and Greco Macedonian Warfare have been fused
Alexander hope to breakthrough Darius is left Center in a cavalry charge
Andrew Weil around against the rear of the Persian Center in an identical hammer and Anvil operation
Is Alexander near the Persian position
He forced his army to advance of the slow pace
Just as the Persians had done against Cyrus at chew noxa
Finally when the macedonians were well within bowshot probably had about a distance of 100 yards
Alexander ordered an attack on the double
With contingents of Cavalry on his right
Supported by infantry close behind
He charged the river at a gallop
Persian skirmishers in front of their line probably fell back in panic
Creating confusion in the main infantry line on the Persian left fender
And Alexander smash through
And quote
This battle is often portrayed
A Race Against Time
Because Alexander is blowing away the opponents that he and his Cavalry are facing in front of them the problem is
He's having problems
In all the other sectors of the battlefield
In the sentries having problems against the Greek mercenaries hired by the Persians
And his left leg is in real trouble cuz that's where the Persian version
Of the hammer and Anvil tactics are hammering
They put all their Cavalry on their right flank and now the poor makedonian
Calvary really Greek at the sailing Cavalry on their left leg
Is trying to hold their own without collapsing so Alexander has to manage to
Finish this battle
From the
Distant position he has on one flank before his Center in his left leg collapses
The sources say Alexander in keeping with the original plan
Swings his Cavalry to his left
And begins attacking the rear of the Persian line
But is he going to be able to win the battle there before his own Army collapses
And then traditionally
We're told he spots
The alternative
One way to destroy
An ancient army used to destroy the ancient army another way to destroy the ancient army is simply to kill the commander
Doesn't always work course
But if the Commander is the head of state and
A near god-king
Chances are better than normal
Traditionally Alexander spies
Is counter
Not that far away
And in true homeric fashion
Makes right
For him
With a few hundred of his clothes as compared
Historian Peter Green picks up in the
Quote
The moment he located the great King's chariot
Alexander charge straight for it
And every makedonian Warrior that day shared his ambition
The defense was equally heroic
Darius certainly knew how to command loyalty
Among the Iranian barons
Those are threes his brother leading the Royal household Cavalry talk desperately to protect him
Dying men and horses lay piled and wild confusion
Alexander received a wound in the thigh
From Darius himself or so it was claimed if this is true it shows how close he came to attending his objective
The horses of darius's chariot
Covered with wounds and terrified by the corpses line all about them plunged in reared half berserk
For a moment there was a real danger that they might carry the great king headlong through Alexander's lines
Abandoning Royal protocol in this emergency
Grab the reins with his own hands
A second later Cherry was somehow found and brought up
Darius seeing himself in imminent danger of capture
Scrambled into it
And fled the field
And quote
The king of chains
A Persia
Got in his Chariot and in front of all these men whose morale was so heartened by the fact there near god-king was
Was there with them
Sharing the risks and not afraid of the Demon King this Darth Vader
That guy
Was running away
As fast as he could go
Kind of makes you think that all of The Wanderers effect
The magic power of having the god King near god king there
Just what a boomerang
Set a time like this doesn't have been better had the king not even been there at all than to see him turn tail and flee
Is Army
Which has been fighting pretty darn well maybe winning the sender certainly winning
Another Persian right flank against the makedonian other Calvary wing
It doesn't
Not an unusual thing in an ancient battle by the way
Have you told you officers are important generals are really important if you're generally your head of state as well
Well if they run away or die it's not unusual for the Army to sort of Melt Away
In this case
Which hole do you know again if you buy the engine numbers hundreds of thousands of people
Begin a choking Panic retreat
Where the bodies become so thick Alexander supposedly in Pursuit
Of the Persian king of kings can cross rivers on the piles of corpses
Nonetheless that's one of the key battles in ancient history
Because no matter what happens next
This is not a fluke anymore Alexander is in the process of toppling the Persian Empire
And the mood historically speaking seem to change
Now we start getting
Correspondence were toll between the king of kings of Persia
And this
Makedonian warlord sudden controls a nice chunk of what was up until a few months ago The Purge
Empire
Very different tone
Between these two men now
What's more
Some of Alexander's generals people he inherited from his father was starting to think that
What they've conquered to this point looks pretty good
And maybe you might want to walk away from the gambling table at Las Vegas at this point with what you want rather than gamma
Anymore
You know an overreach
But they're not Alexander
And he is
A fact
He continually likes to point out to them
Traditionally at this point in the story
Where the Persians begin
To offer Alexander
Deals
He supposed to get letters or
Envoys the ancient sources say from the Persian king basically offering him territory and other things in exchange for
Deciding you've had enough
I think a little
Peace inside me died
When I read theory on story modern history and he suggested that all these traditional accounts which all the historians I grew up reading
As gospel
Almost certainly nothing but makedonian propaganda from the time. As I said earlier you know it's hard enough to try to figure out what
What's going on with the
Normal Source problems you add the makedonian propaganda
And unfortunately for us some of the best stuff then
Is stuff that Brianna would have us believe is a direct
Fabrication for
More real-world purposes
None the less you know you can actually tell quite a bit about
Other things by
The propaganda
And in this case
And what we used to and not still wishes actually like these official you don't from the desk of Alexander the Great
Type communication between Alexander
And Darius is instead of piece of propaganda
Where the makedonian is trying to give you a feel for a certain relationship in a relationship is this new one
At least in the eyes of King Alexander is he calls himself in this propagandistic note
And the king of kings of the ancient and Grand Persian Empire he refers to merely as
Darius
This is from Arian remember
Supposedly have a source who was there
With Alexander
A describes a response
Tune official note he's supposed to have gotten remember it again maybe I'll pray
Propaganda from the king of kings of Persia saying
And give me back my family which Alexander seized as booty after it says they were there what are you doing bringing your family too
To the battlefield but the King of Kings did Alexander snatch them up
Domantas family back
He's going to make a deal he proposes a deal to Alexander who says you want your family back you want your wife back
The kids back
Arian has the rest of the note back
Sadaria saying quote
Come to me therefore as you would come to the lord of the continent of Asia
Should you fear to suffer any indignity at my hands
And send some of your friends
And I will give them the proper guarantees
Come then
And ask me for your mother
Your wife
And your children
And anything else that you please
For you shall have them
And whatever besides you can persuade me to give you
Any future let any communication you wish to make with me the address to the king of all Asia
Do not write to me yes to an equal
Everything you possess is now mine
So if you should want anything let me know in the proper term
Her I shall take steps to deal with you as a criminal
If on the other hand
You wish to dispute your throne
Stand and fight for it
And do not run away
Wherever you may hide yourself be sure I shall seek you out
And Co
Oh how can you not want that to be true
Right
There's another correspondence is supposed to have happened right before the big climactic battle were leading up to wear another
Margiela supposed to be offered Alexander one that basically give them
Did everything beyond their wildest dreams if they'll just call the war off at that point
Alexander's General parmenio who's a leftover from is more conservative dad
It's supposed to have said that's a great deal I'd take that deal if I were Alexander
And then this great legendary mythical figure Alexander supposed to replied
I would take it to
If I were parmenio
Boom
Write a drop the mic moment right there
But the minute you start getting correspondence like this
Your any king would know
You got to go get another Army
That's a while Alexander deals with a bunch of sieges including a terrible one and Phoenician city called Tire
The King of Persia put together an army mostly based around
Peoples from his Eastern territories and he's got wild nasty Warrior people most of the mounted most of them Archer
Many of them armor from the Eastern territories
Putting all that together
11331 BCE
We're told Alexander soda making towards Babylon
That's something the Persians can't have happened because that's the
Financial capital of it's got all sorts of importance
To the Persian king takes this new Army of his which is supposed to be extremely numerous and extremely calorie-heavy
Finds a spot that Alexander is going to go through although there's some
Tense moments as to where Alexander's actually going to go
But eventually defined as Battlefield were told that the king
Actually levels this battlefield to make sure all the little pieces of brush you're cleared away so it's a nice flat
Place where all of his troops could really operate well and
You know when the sort of a wonderfully ironic
The book ended this whole piece hears this climactic battle
With a representative of where we sat at the very very old world
Of ancient Assyria and the glory of ancient Mesopotamia take on the newcomers here
The guy who's going to murder that old world and where does it happen
Right near the ruins
Of the Glorious Assyrian capital of Nineveh
What is xenophon
I saw his ghost City that we talked about
Statue of Liberty
You have submerged in the surf moment
The perfect spot
To decide who's going to
It take all the marbles here
We're told that the Persian army and the
Hellenic League which is Alexander in
The Greeks the macedonians so they camp
From each other in the traditional story which is part of the fun is that
Alexander
And his troops eaten
Sleep well in the Persians were so afraid of a night attack that they kept their people at Battle Stations all Knights Inn
By the time the battle happens they're all tired
Ancient sources say Alexander intercepts letters from the Persians to his own
Troops
Inciting them to try to assassinate Alexander
And what do you do to level the playing field with maybe you just
Killam
So maybe they were out to do that or maybe that's more makedonian propaganda
It's on the first day of October 331 BCE traditionally that these armies
Deploy against each other
Persian
Army is
Huge
Course
You would expect nothing less from the ancient sources but this time they've
Knocked on themselves Aryan who remember supposedly has a direct line to a guy who is there
And would have known
So the Persians had a million
Infantry lined up on the
Amelia
And 40000 calories
Hans delbruck hundred years ago road if you had twelve thousand Cavalry there they would be impossible to manage
Turn the Lights once again
We have no idea what the real numbers are Alexander
Supposed to had 47000 men
Pretty
Pacific number 7000 those cavalry
It's probably safe to assume he was out number to 321 Maybe
The sources say that the Persian army so numerous
But it's battle line is much much longer than that
Alexander's and overlaps it by
Huge amount of stretches off into the distance it may have been
Almost three miles long
Alexander to account for this just soda plan
Having people available to deal with being surrounded if that happens the angles both his flying soda backwards
So there's somebody does attack from the side directly facing in the right direction
He stationed some troops behind the main battle line with order to go get anybody to give us
And then otherwise he sets up in pretty much standard
Makedonian
Template style he in the
Companion Cavalry on the right flank to act as the lightning bolt hammer
Poor parmenio on the rest of the Cavalry in the Left Flank with
Orders to hold off the enemy attack until Alexander can win the whole thing and then the Anvil
This giant mass of human beings in the middle
16 ranked
Maybe an 18-foot Pike
And stretching themselves
In over a distance of like a half mile or more Miss crazy to think about
What a wonderful platform of maneuver that is
How you do that if you're the Persians isn't this the common
Standard problem they've had all along again
Heavy Greek makedonian style Infantry
Remember the battle of the granicus that used terrain features the river in the
The highbank to break up the cohesion of these troops
On this flat playing you kind of have to bring your own causes a disorder
And the Persians
In contrast to what historians when I was growing up used to say that they didn't learn anything and they could never do any better than
Hire Greeks to fight Greeks
They did have things to break up the Greek formations and they brought them to this battle
Where they were needed
The first of these things that's fascinating from historical standpoint cuz it's probably the first time
Greeks ever saw this ever
And must have been the number one talked about item is these makedonian soldiers looked across the battlefield and saw for the first time
Elephants
Indian
Traditionally about 15 of them
That must have been something to talk to your neighbor about in the ranks as you waited to come into contact
And later evidence was show
Elephants are a wonderful tool against the makedonian Army because they're good against both the hammer and the Anvil Elliman
Against it
Charging heavy Cavalry elephant
Tacticalories usually won't come near them
If they ever do get caught by the elephant's it's awful for
The cavalry
But against the densely packed
Phalanx
They could be murderous
You would think they would be easy to kill but later evidence shows not so easy and you get
Four or five of those things stomping around
And intentionally created crowd of people standing shoulder-to-shoulder and it could be very ugly indeed
If you follow up with form troops
To take advantage of that Carnage that's not a bad strategy
But while breaking up these clothes order troops is definitely a part of the Persian strategy doesn't look like the elephants were what they were relying
Instead they have
Something right out of like a Mad Max film or one of those 1950s Ben-Hur movies
They have saved
Cherry
They have like 200 of them
Stationed all along their Frontline
I've always thought this was an interesting weapon
But nobody knows what they look
Everybody tries to recreate
A visual image of it from the literary sources and everyone's take is a little different
To imagine some combination
Heavy chariot
Cutting blades you're starting to get there though
I usually run into has the equivalent of about 3 foot long swords
1 each
Sticking out
From the end of the wheels of The Chariot and then either
Something projecting forward from the cab of The Chariot like a spear or blades
We're blades facing downward underneath the cab so it's like a giant human lawn mower
There were stories
Earlier in history
Two or three of these things have attacked a Greek Phalanx that was forming up
And created a ton of Carnage and then Persian Cavalry swooped in to take advantage of the chaos and disorder and destroyed the four
Formation
So you can
See how the Persians were thinking I mean the two or three side chariot
Were you able to do that you know 10 20 30 40 50 years ago
What my two hundred of them along our front lines do it's not a bad idea is it
It certainly shows that they were thinking outside the box a little bit contrary to the historical
Your take on the subject when I was growing up
And then they had
There are me essentially deployed into long line
Each line composed of several ranks of Truth
Front
Line was almost entirely cowboy
The line behind it mostly infantry and in seemingly
Slightly useless
Almost like
Cannon Falls
Not the traditional view anyway
And in the midst of it all in the center of the traditional place
Any Secretariat again surrounded by his Royal Guard again
Is the great king of kings of Persia
Pius the 3rd
Still able apparently to command
The Loyalty of enough people to raise an army this big and get it here
Despite the
Events of two years ago
And as I look at this Persian Army on this field
I think to myself you know
Not a bad setup I take that Army if you told me
I had to fight one side of the other
But you know and I'm absolutely using 20/20 hindsight here although I wonder what Alexander the Great was thinking
If you're looking at that
Army
I'm trying to figure out where its weak point is
What if you thought that the weak point might be sitting
In the sacred chariot
What is that Army's weak point
Is the psychology of it
Quasi Divine ruler
Maybe it's a sign that Alexander thinks that this is a dangerous Army and that it is deployed well
3 doesn't just charge into some spot he thinks he can break through that would be
Standard operating procedure if you saw such a spot
In this case he goes to his typical
Plan B
Which is to use tactical maneuvering on the battlefield to see if he can create that spot
I got a fully armored and protected enemy can you get them
To raise up their arm and expose the vulnerable underbelly
As soon as Alexander sees that vulnerable spot he will launch himself like a requiere into the vitals of the
Enemies
Vulnerable underbelly
As he always does
In this bottle that's what a lot of the early Maneuvers are about Alexander starts moving his army were told kind of forward but to the right
To the right would take Alexander's Army into rough ground
Rough ground is where those chariots could not operate them in the king that had that land in front of his chariots levels for real
He can't let Alexandra move the battlefield
So he sends out Cavalry that had been in his front rank
To stop Alexander
Indigo around his flight can you get this
Calorie battle on the right plane to develop with both sides feeding more troops into it
But this is working for Alexander
Because he's planned to have calorie to feed into that where the Persians are taking their ears
From their Frontline denuding a part of their Frontline
And a certain point Alexander with the Exquisite timing that he's known for
Decides that they've denuded enough so that that's a weak spot
And once again you know the Imagine Darth Vader
Or in this case The Demon King at the head of his troops charging an a wedge so it's like that guy
And then two guys behind them and then for guys behind them I mean he's the tip of the spear literally
And the head of state
Charges into the gap
Which is on the left center of the Persian line
Which is right near
The royal guard
And Darius the Third
In the last battle
You sort of had the impression from the sources in The Way It Was Written that maybe
Alexander had never intended to go out
The king that got into the back of it
Ranks it became the quickest way to achieve his goals
In this bottle you get the impression that that was the goal
Maybe he decided
That this guy was
Skittish
What did he say
Benches
Because Alexander goes at him and homeric fashion again
This is where you get into the idea
Of this guy maybe being the weak Link in the armor
At this point
What would one of his predecessors
I've done in a situation that's about to occur
Is the situation that's about to occur
Is that this guy is going to relive
One of the scariest moments
Of his life right now
Dries the third has almost certainly when you imagine he's a human being
Seen this in his dreams before
Alexander and these murderous makedonian
Smashing into the guard that's around him which is like a human wall of people
And beginning to cut
And hack and stab their way
Person by person
Yard by yard
Towards him as he watches in his chariot
There is a
Fragment of a mosaic that they found in Pompeii which is a copy of what was thought to be a near contemporary orig
What's famous and it probably shows the scene from the Battle of issus
But it's the same scene we're seeing a replay
Must have seemed like a reply to the King of Persia 2
And in that scene you see Alexander
On his horse stabbing one of the
Royal Guardsmen in front of the Persian chariot
And the King of Persia with eyes as big as saucers it's like the moment before he takes off at the Battle of issus
And I have to say is I've been trying to look
Pictures from the Persian side the whole way through I have a lot of sympathy
Where
Jiraiya 30 is
This guy wasn't
Really boring Brenda
He's obviously Brave remember he's a guy who killed the rebel leader of the Barbarian leader in single combat
But this is a guy who gets criticized for doing something
I would think all but the most extraordinary people would do
Because for the second
Time in a row
He's going to look at Alexander and the cutting machine
Getting nearer to him as he watches his
Kinsman slaughtered in front of him
And he's going to turn around and run
Even a guy
Who will
Fight and kill a person with edged weapons mano-a-mano
Might be forgiven you would think
When instead of facing a single individual he's facing a crowd of mounted killers were going to roll over him like a
Wave
How many people would stand there in the chariot
And wait patiently as they cut their way towards you especially if you've already been through this once before
It had to be the biggest nightmare this guy that had
Last two years and here it is deja vu all over again as Yogi Berra
I would say
I got me wondering once again about the ability of a single person to impact history
As we all know it's it's usually all kinds of things working together and paying off each other and giant Trends and forces and things like that
What we talked about how extraordinary individuals
Can soda sometimes push the envelope in
And make the difference and pain the meteor off in a different direction and change the impetus and all those kind of things
What's the opposite
Unextraordinary
Did you give somebody in a position
That is less than what you could normally expect to have in Key West
Counting system is based on clawing your way to the top
In a theoretical merit-based system you see this less of the time
But sometimes any inherited systems or systems like this remember this guy got a job for me
Supposed poisoner who put him into
The royal
Position cuz he thought he could control them
What is that guy's just an ordinary person for the most part who ends up in this extraordinary roll
Sometimes you can get away with it after almost monarchies have all sorts of safeguards and
Things in place to keep
Some less than talented Manar from destroying the whole thing right won't let him make a stupid military decision that's why you
You have all those generals and advisors
But in certain keyways
There are no safeguards
Lights for what one single
Below what you could have hoped for individual the opposite of extraordinary what they could do to you
Sometimes history comes down to trends
And forces and big stuff like that
And sometimes it comes down
21 guy
Deciding to run away
For the second straight
Pointing out that
At the moment
The King of Persia
Does the unforgivable again
Things are going that badly for the Persians I would say they're losing but they still have a shot
Just like they still have a shot at the Battle of issus when the king turned tail and ran
Once you turn tail and run
The chances of
You're pulling out that upset go way way down
And why we hear nothing about the elephants in this bottle from the sources and while the
Ferocious looking side
Cherriots turn out to be easily countered by the macedonians
The Persian Cavalry is living up to the hype
Foley
And they have Alexander
In a good deal of difficulty
Sources say that even is Alexander is right on the heels of the Persian king pursuing him
Then he gets a message
That is left blank report parmenio is as usual fighting off
Huge numbers of people in holding his own but starting to fall apart Alexander has to stop the pursuit and come and help
The Persians have also broken through
The middle of the formation in a couple of places where gaps appeared so it is far from
A steamroller have to come back and help him
There's some tough biting in one area and
The bottom line is that for the moment
The person who has the crown that Alexander wants
Has gotten away
The bottom line is
You'll never be able to raise another field Army like
This
To contest the empire
Alexander may not have the crown but for all intents and purposes
Even as the mopping-up of that battle are going on this guy is
Amidst
Some under
Whole numbers of corpses
They continue to pile up
As the fugitives from this bottle or continually run down by pursuing cavalry
Before
What must have been days
It's a holocaust
To the Persian side
And Alexander will spend
Literally years
Quelling all of the hot spots in the Persian Empire
That rise up against him even with all of the wonderful propaganda that's come down to us about Alexander being well
Flowers and roses
Pedals put in front of him and all these kinds of things
Did you got a murderous European warlord coming to your town you be wise to do that too
That doesn't mean
He wasn't better thought of in some cases in the Persians although a lot of the recent history suggests
The Persian rule was more popular than Alexander's
Menstrual
There is a wonderful little
Sort of karmic
Justice in this whole thing if you look at it from the Persian point of view
And the Chinese did this all the time with conquerors
But when you are
The Great
Cultural power of your day
As the Persians were they were in the inheritors of this culture
And the Greeks were The Rustic
Outsiders the makedonian is even more so
Overtime Alexander would be
Become more and more
Persian
Dressing my
Requiring his own people to act more like them
In terms of treating him more like a Persian king there are a lot of historian to consider
To the last
King of Kings in Persia
Is the guy
Who just destroyed the Persian army
At the Battle of gaugamela
I know in my mind
Put an! On this story where
Eventually rides all the way to the Eastern parts of the Empire and captures the great city of persepolis and proceed
Burn
The Royal Palace.
Either intentionally
Symbol
Payback for all those Wars with Xerxes and dries for more than a century ago
Or some
Traditions reported in sort of a drunken mistake
You famous or suggest
That he should not burn down his own stuff
Quite the realization
Poseidon
The Demon King
I've gone native
Alexander's Conquest
Put
European
Dynasty
In charge of these ancient civilizations that had never been under the European heal before
And ruled that in some cases
Sportscentury
When the locals and the natives eventually get native dynasties back and get cash
Control of their own societies
It will be precious little love
Pre alexandrian world
It hadn't been bleached Outlet
Alexander is always considered to be the end of an era in Western tradition is considered to be a good thing he spread
Hellenism
You know to all these parts of the planet that didn't have in creating this wonderful mix
Exploding.
Fantastic culture
But that's the way
The Conqueror
Would see it
Probably not the way
It would be seen
Are the Concord
Geologist Warwick
Ball
Is one of a bunch of
Experts who point out that much of what Alexander gets historical
Credit for
Actually
To be a trip
To the Empire
He brought down
Fall quotes historian
JM Robert
Bert's talking about the
The Persian Empire founded by Cyrus the Great
Couple hundred years
Before Alexander the Great and he says about
Quote
Right across the old world
Persia suddenly pulled people's into a common experience
Indians
Meads
Babylonians
Lydian's
Greeks Jews Phoenicians Egyptians
We're for the first time all administered by one Empire
Who's eclecticism showed how far civilization had already come
The idea of distinct units of history in the near East was over
The base of a future world civilization was in the making
And quote
It's always so strange about hearing this line that Alexander spread Hellenism is it makes it sound like he's bringing enlighten
Cement
To a bunch of
Primitive natives
When in fact the better analogy here
For ancient Persia
Is
The Roman Empire
And the better analogy for Alexander is not the bringer of light
But something much more akin to a visigoth
Or Attila the Hun
The Empire that Alexander is destroying is the greatest the world has ever seen
And the way it's often portrayed in history in the story the stereotypes in The Motif in the home team cheering for Western Civilization
Station
Is it he was somehow
Enforcing a
Law of the Jungle that made sense he's the lion taking out the
In a stick Antelope from the herd it's Nature's Way it strengthens ever
Everything I mean if you get into the wooden shoes and socks slippers
The Persian Empire disappointed like the Roman Empire the N2 they have silk slippers
For their silk slippers
But let's not forget
It was wearing the silk slippers
Last new found out he really like
As we said Alexander
Really went all Persian
Maybe the last Persian king of kings never mind that he may have killed
Dries the third that never stopped at Persian
Being King of Kings
But while he may be a king of kings and while he may actually fit the motif
Xerxes did supposed to fit absolute power corrupting Alexander
Absolutely
Helped Along by
A terminal case of alcoholism probably
His successors would see
No such need
To put on a Persian
Poor local facade they will later
But initially
This is a bunch of Europeans openly ruling
These areas that have never been ruled by Europeans before
And Warwick ball says the next 75 years is going to be one of the
Darkest
Eras
In terms of what life must have been like for the local
Are the people in West Asia up until the time of the Mongol Khan
Goodness they at least got a little Helena
Part of the deal
It's all about trade
And don't forget
Even if it is not true
You need to be
History
I'm on record as saying that I think most of you all to have a website
And if you look at what's standing in your way
Let me suggest that Squarespace might be the answer to your
Squarespace of course the all-in-one platform that makes it
Fast and easy to create your own professional website or
Portfolio or online store could you get a free store with it
Simple and easy with a beautiful design
You can drag-and-drop content
Responsive design
A month
You sign up for the whole year with Amy get a free domain name
At those kinds of prices the risk
To reward ratio
Completely tips in the favor of you should give this a try if you've ever thought about having website I'll tell you what I like about it too and it's
You think alike
Perhaps is the number one thing but if you'd had my personal experience but understand then maybe you have
I spent years going to those websites that are nothing but
Website template
Looking for once I light for my website at thousand and this is the amazing thing I go 3000
And never find one that I really like
And I see very few that look as professional as the stuff
I was seeing out there by big companies
Outlets
Squarespace has a similar attitude
Towards their templates that I have toward this show
Which is quality or quantity they don't have a lot of choices
For your temp
Because they spent their time making really good
Go check them out and see if
That's not one of the better idea to come around in a long time era of choice
I found that it works for me
I kind of like how is working for Squarespace
You can start a trial with no credit card
Required and when you decide to sign up for Squarespace make sure to use the offer code hardcore
I get 10% off your first
Are you awake
My grandmother used to say give fate an opportunity to intervene
Websites right way to do that
Squarespace
Be sure to follow us on Twitter the address
Is at hardcore history
Help the podcast just buy your amazon.com products for the Amazon search window
Carloan.com anymore and it helps these guys out because they are nice young fellows
If you think to show you this hurt is worth a dollar Dan and Ben would love to have it
Abacus show it's all we ask