December 7th 1941
A date which will live in infamy
Call nist time and place
Mr. Gorbachev tear down this wall
I welcome this kind of examination because people have got to know
Weather
Number
It's hardcore history
I remember a conversation I had
Quite a long time ago now
I was an author of A
The author had written a book about how John F Kennedy was assassinated by Lee Harvey Oswald just like the government always
Set it happened
And I've been asking him a bunch of questions about
Conspiracies
This or that aspect of the
Kennedy assassination in only one of his answers
It really stands out of my mind now because it
Teams
In irrelevant on so many different
Confront
And one of the answers on why
It was so hard for some people to accept what this guy with reporting us
Truth
He said was because people are inherently
Very uncomfortable
With the ID
That a single nobody
Can have such an effect on all of our lives
It's more comforting
He said to believe
The powerful
Groups of people or conspiracies are actually running things
Even if you think
Those powerful groups are nefarious
It's somehow comforting to think that
Somebody's in charge
It's not all just random
The mother plane couldn't just drop from the sky and land on your house tomorrow
I thought about this when I was thinking about
Someone if somebody to ask you a question who was the most important
Figure in the past
Hundred years
In terms of
Why the world has gone the way it did
Yeah you would think of all these famous people whose names almost anyone who's a halfway educated would recognize
And it was interesting as you could
Conceivably
You put the name down of somebody who was historically
Speaking
When nobody
Lee Harvey Oswald
On the pages of the history books
Besides the Kennedy assassination is a nobody
Didn't do anything
But that event was huge right if he actually killed John F Kennedy the way the narrative says Lee Harvey Oswald change the world
You change the president instant
Play right I mean how many of us have the
Potential
To change who the president of the United States is
That lone gunmen did if he was indeed the lone gunmen
The person who may be most responsive
For the modern world this entire world including the 9/11 attacks
You know many commentators how they shape the modern world right
We live in an era of terrorism or the age of terrorism you'll hear them say
Without them seem to really understand that the age of terrorism supposedly Spark by the 9/11 attacks in the
Very very very early 21st century
Or themselves
Manifestations
Oven actor
Terrorism
The launch Destin
10 to the 20th
We actually live in an age of terrorism
Some of the people like
Like to say
We've been living in it for more than
I think you could make
Did the most important individual in the last
Century
Is Gabrielle au Prince
And Gabrielle Oprah
Is a name
Very few
Recognize
How can a person
I'm so little achievement you know on the world stage
Be perhaps credited with creating the entire world around us I mean if
If Gavrilo Princip doesn't live is there
A 9/11 attack ever
And if that was all he did when he be important
He's a lot more than that
Every other principle is the reason there was a second
World War
Gabrielle princep
Is the reason it was a fur
And to be fair to princess
If you could have gone to him and shown him the ram of
Vacations of
What that one day
Would you do the world
I think he'd be horrified he wasn't trying
Go to unleash
A global World War
He just became
The latest example
Of someone pulling the trigger
In a giant historical game of Russian Roulette
Trigger that have been pulled several times already with nothing
Who would have thought
At the time that princess
Pulled it that would be the time
Set the
A metaphorical
Revolve
Pointed at the
Skull of the old world
Shot a bullet
Sprain
Perhaps
Princep annies
Pisgah Patriots
Thought that
Sometimes when you're trying to create a new world
Utterly
Destroy the old one
And the people in that old world
We're not naive
If about the potential for
Someone like a prince up to do what they did I mean
Otto von Bismarck one of the greatest
Diplomats of nineteenth-century Europe perhaps the greatest Diplomat Germany ever produced
Famously said that there was going to be some giant
Global
Like it was going to probably break out because of some damn fool event in the Balkans
Gavrilo princip shot
In the city of Sarajevo
Smack
Dab
A place that Otto von Bismarck
Famously said was not worth the bones of a single Pomeranian Grenadier
Cost a hell of a lot
The mat
And prints it becomes yet another exam
Proven to us that
Sometimes when it comes to something like terrorism
In this area by the way when we try desperately
Weapons of mass destruction out of the terrorist hands because we're afraid to be able to kill more people with such weapons
We forget that sometimes
It's not about how many people you kill sometimes it's about
Who they are
And often
It's not the terrorist
Act the changes the world
It's the response of the victim
Teleties
Gavrilo princip
Kill Tupac
He did so in a way
That almost makes you believe
And truthfully
I'm not much of a faith believer
But one of the things I like about histories Howard
Forces me to challenge
Some of my own preconceptions
And I'm certainly make me think about other possibilities
I've always thought for example
History unfolds for chaotic reason
It's somewhat random that millions of people going about their lives in their own ways
With Trends and forces acting upon them and people in important positions making decisions and all this together created
Dynamic is completely unpredictable as I said somewhat chaotic and random
Unfolds into the future
I think my logical side of the brain appreciate
That's what a Viewpoint the problem is is that sometimes
History
Confronts us with events
Where the logical part of at least my brain wants to flip side
And wants to logically defend what I consider to be the moral logical point of view
In this case
The logical part of my brain with sometime shift and try to defend something like
Fate
Destiny
Or predetermination
Those to me are the two ends of the scale Chaos on one side and Randomness on one side
Faith
Can predestination on the other and there's this weird Twilight Zone with a to sort of intersect
And that event that happened in late June 1914
He's one of the best examples you'll find from history where
The Logical side of your brain stand a pretty good chance of flipping and trying to defend the illogical position
But this is somehow
Predestined
I mean look me
Challenge you
With a similar kind of analogy
Take the John F Kennedy assassination
And imagine that in addition to Lee Harvey Oswald up at the Texas School Book Depository
U of A
Another assassin on the grassy knoll it says sometimes been
Suggested
And that
In this JFK assassination attempt Oswald misses
And the bullet strikes
The ground may be injured from passers-by and everybody realizes an assassination attempt is happening
And the Secret Service get on the car and they speed away
Past the grassy knoll past the other assassin who never get the shot
President Kennedy
And President Kennedy's gone
And no one knows what to do no one's quite sure what happens and then
In a later on
All of a sudden
Well the assassin on the grassy Knolls probably trying to just figure out okay maybe what do I do now
The car with the president and his wife
Show up right down the road again passed the Texas School Book Depository right to the grassy knoll
Call work precedes to stall
Unstop
What are the odds of that
Kind of cookie huh history
Can be that way
On June 28 1914
Gabriella princep and from
6 to some sources say 20
Assassins if
If you believe
Some of the people who claimed you taken part in these
Assassination attempts
Show up in Sarajevo with murder on their mind
They want to kill
The
The governing figure in Syria
The person who is sort of the Prince Charles plays the same role Prince Charles plays
In the British Monarchy right now
In the monarchy
Other country that are the overlord
Words in Sarajevo country that doesn't exist anymore
Called Austria-Hungary
And Austria-Hungary is led by really old
Very well-loved guy named franz-josef who's going to die soon because he's very old
And the person who will take over when Franz Joseph dies
Is this guy coming on a visit to Sarajevo
The Prince Charles of his country although unlike Prince Charles whose role is
Completely ceremonial
This guy will actually have some real power when he gets the throne
After some
You're now when you look back on it looks like a stupid reason
This guy whose name is Archduke Franz Ferdinand
And decided to go to Sarajevo on watch military maneuvers
Which happened to coincide with the anniversary of the most emotionally important
Heart-wrenching
The battlefield lost in all serve history
The battle of cowshed
On my way back from
Hundreds of hundreds of years
Before this time
Serb nationalist
And the serbs are very very patriotic even today even more so back in 1914
Look at this as a slap in the face
Too damn Sarajevo is Slavic and should be part of at least a pan-slavic country
Or maybe part of Serbia
Harbin Balkan Wars for the last decade
In a concern with many of these naturalistic questions who should only use areas and it's been in the hands of the Ottoman Turks
The Slavs definitely feel shouldn't have been running the place
And it was transferred to the hands of the austro-hungarian Empire which disturb nationalists
Still don't feel should be running the play
Place
And now if the Archduke
Was coming on the anniversary of this historic defeat
You know from the Serb nationalist Viewpoint to rub their nose in the fact
The Sarajevo is still held by a big non-slavic Empire
They're going to make
Franz Ferdinand
Pay for that
And in a remarkably similar situation to the Kennedy assassination
Ferdinand's
Route for his motorcade is published ahead of time
He's going to be arriving and going down the main boulevards in an open car
With his wife
Sitting next to him
These multiple of sass
Line themselves up at
Various intervals along the parade route
And plan to kill the Archduke as soon as they can
The archduke's car is either going too fast
Or there are too many other serves in the crowd nearby the first few assassins so the first few assassins don't try to make a run at him
Eventually passes one guy
Who runs out from the crowd with a bomb
Really more of a hand
Good way to describe it today
Any flings his hand grenade of the archduke's open car
Very athletic maneuver the Archduke sees it
Ducks behind the door of the car
The hand grenade thing bounces off the car hits the concrete on the street
And the fuse doesn't detonate until the next car in the motorcade
Has passed over it
It explodes
Some 20 people are badly hurt in the blood on the street the whole thing chaos the crowd scatters I mean obviously
Leader of the parade is over
The would-be Assassin shoves a cyanide pill into his mouth
And runs down
Into the side of the
Street and jumps in the river
A cyanide pill is defective and only makes him vomit
And the rivers only about
Is deep so they capture him very quickly
Run him off to be
And basically looks like the whole day's been a failure
The other assassins at least some of them are supposed to have seen the archduke's car speeding off I mean there you go
There goes the day
The motorcade
Goes in a couple of different directions some people are taken to the hospital
The Archduke and his wife
You know go to the town hall to Lodge a complaint
They're going to make a speech anyway but now they have
An earful to give the local officials
Come to your town and this is the reception we get
That kind of thing
And it looks at least
From this point like
End of the heir to the throne of
Austria-Hungary just dodged a bullet literally
There's some Talk Amongst the local officials about maybe figuring out a way to provide some increase security
But it doesn't seem to get very far because within an hour
After the first attack the Archduke and his wife and their small motorcade is
You know off to the hospital
Supposedly
In a following an unplanned route for security reasons
There doesn't seem to be a lot of extra
The police protection up we're told that a
An aristocrat counts France on her Rock was on the running board
Of the archduke's car so maybe a little life
Action
Turns out though that the driver and one of those you know
Strip that affect the entire history of the world turns out the driver of the archduke's car did not realize they were not taking the
Chino parade route
And makes a wrong turn
And ends up nearest street corner
Where one of the Assassins gavrilo princip maybe the guy on the grassy knoll with JFK as station Tim's
Self in the hope that you might get a chance
You know maybe
Just be in the right place when the Archduke
Had to come by again
Perhaps on his way out of town
The Archduke driver makes a wrong turn
He's told by somebody in the motorcade that he's made a wrong turn and he has to backup he stops the car in preparation
Before backing up
Right
Eyewear
Gavrilo princip
Friendship is on that street
Are worthy
Motorcade
Car takes a wrong turn and then stops while backing up
These
Is Target from
Less than an hour before
Near feet
Immobile
I'm slightly below him
In an open car
And he whips out his pistol
And shoots him
And his wife
What are the odds
Happening
It's considered to be
One of the most Wild
Coincidences
In all human history
How many times do assassins in a failed assassination attempt
Get a second chance to go after their target
And we sometimes forget because it's such a Monumental historical moment
But this is still a terrorist.
And it was quite
Upsetting
How to get a witness or Lyft
Part of what makes
These things seem so unreal
Is it we only have grainy black-and-white footage
Even the events before that you can go see movies where you can see the Archduke and his wife
Getting ready to go into the motorcade and you get an idea of what they look like and it's all kind of moving a little too fast the way those old-fashioned movies
You were never look real
But you can go when you can see
See pictures
Because they have saved
The tunic that the Archduke was wearing that day
And you can see In Living Color
Did this was a bright light blue tunic and the
Feathers on the helmet he was wearing a bright green I mean it must have been the most colorful site imaginable but after Prince of fire the most
Colorful side imaginable became a lot more gory
Because there's a tear in the tunic
Where the bullet exited
The archduke's neck
And the tunic is covered in what is unmistakably even a hundred years later blood
And blood has always been one of those things
Where When You See It In Living Color
There's nothing like
I tend to believe human beings are
The program
To react to that specific color
You're always
The difference
Between seeing
Blood in black and white and blood in colors
There's nothing
The person who was closest to the whole thing
Was count von harrach
Who was
On the running board
Not doing that great of a job apparently at security
And he says as soon as the
Shots were fired
They reversed the car
He later testified
This
Quote
Does a car quickly reversed
Athena stream of blood spurted from His Highness his mouth onto my right cheek
As I was pulling out my handkerchief to wipe the blood away from his mouth
The Duchess cried out to him
For God's sake
What has happened to you
I thought she slid off the seat and lay on the floor of the car with her face between his knees
I had no idea that she too was hit
And thought that she had simply fainted with fright
Then I heard his Imperial highness say
Sophie
Sophie don't die
Stay alive for the children
I thought I sees the Archduke by the color of his uniform to stop his head drooping forward
And asked him if he was in great pain
Answer me quite distinctly
It is nothing
His face began to twist somewhat but he went on repeating six or seven times Evermore faintly is he gradually lost,
Consciousness it's nothing
Then came a brief pause followed by a convulsive rattle in his throat caused by the loss of blood
This Feast on arrival at the governor's residence
The two unconscious bodies were carried into the building where their death was soon establish
And quote
And as a way to sort of prove
The old
Old adage that
One man's terrorist
Is another man's freedom
Fighter is true
You have only two notes
That amongst serbs today
Many will consider gavrilo princip
Heroic
Someone who
In a fire the first shots that started the chain of events that
While it will be horrible in both world wars for the Serbian people
Eventually lead to well
Now
A time when those countries exist without
You know having to be
Just simply app
Province and some other major superpowers
Territory
Disturbs
This guy was a hero and to his compatriots
Who are realized they were like
Desperados at the time
They all realized
That they would be immortalized
Natural circumstance
By the way where this plot
Was hatched
Are worthy of a spy novel
And it's hard to believe it hasn't been romanticized to some degree but nevertheless if you ever do
The definitive big-screen dramatization of World War 1 the whole story
I think you want to start your movie off
Without seeing the inside that
Belgrade Cafe
Obscure place kind of run-down
Lead only by candlelight
With a group of 19 and 20 year old guys at a table
I wish I could remind myself how yummy
Not old enough to legally drink alcohol in the United States is how old these people are
And then we're told by people who were there
That what happened is one of their number comes in the door sits down at the table with them and has a package with
And he opens up the package and inside is only one thing
A newspaper
No note
Still not signed by anybody know
Directions just a newspaper clipping in the clipping in ounces
The imminent visit of the Archduke
Franz Ferdinand
Sarajevo
One of the people
Who was at that table and lived
To grow older and write about his experiences after he had time to Indigo from terrorists
2 Patriot a guy named borgio
Junk ditch and if I mispronounce that by the way let's just get used to that
This is going to be perhaps the most
Linguistically an extension Willy challenging show I've ever done and I'm sure to Mango many beautiful
First and foremost
French so my apologies to all of you in advance I'm sorry
I have limitations and you're going to
Tmall
Board subject each wrote years later
This about that moment in history that will turn out to be so very important in a way that you can't imagine anyone at the
Didn't know they were pulling
The trigger again in that Russian roulette game and they certainly didn't know that if they were that was the time they were going to be a bullet in the chain
Jeff tetreault
Can after the fact
Quote
A tiny clipping from a newspaper
Mailed without comment from a secret band of Terror
Christian Zagreb
He capital of Croatia to their comrades in Belgrade was the torch which set the world afire with war
4 in 1914
That bit of paper
Old proud Empires
He gave birth to new Free Nation
I was one of the members of the terrorist band in Belgrade
Which received it and in those days
I and my companions were regarded as desperate criminals
The price was on our head
Today my little band is seen in a different light
Has Pioneer Patriot
It is recognized that our secret plans hatched in an obscure Cafe in the capital of old Serbia
Have led to the independence of the new Yugoslavia the United Nations set free from Austrian domination
Ever since that time
People have been wondering
How connected that group was to outside entities
Now they just a bunch of
In a small little
Self organized Terror groups put together by a bunch of young kids were they working for a larger entity
Today we would ask whether or not they were an example of state-sponsored terrorism
Was there a power
Behind this group arrival power
I mean into understand how big of a deal this could be in a Europe that was already kind of unsteady and stressed
In terms of
Stability
Imagine the United States president
Uno president
Be controversial down the road
Is assassinate
We have all the shock
Anger and desire for Retribution that comes with that
And I'm very shortly after an assassin is captured
We figure out that assassin is working with the intelligence service
Are most antagonistic enemy
You think for a second
How America would have reacted
If Lee Harvey Oswald
I've been a Hitman for Moscow
And that came to light
Which by the way
Is not
That outrageous a thing to consider
When you look at Oswald's ties to the Soviet Union and Cuba
Think about how the American people would have reacted regardless of what the facts were
Were is they thought that was the
McKay's
And it's interesting to note
But that's only a year after the Cuban Missile Crisis a year after World War 3 is potentially dodged
What do you think the leaders of the United States after Kennedy's assassinated
Are worried about in terms of worst-case scenarios
Do you think it might have occurred to them
Men who buy the early 1960s had grown up during
And any immediate years after the first world war do you think they might have been seeing in their Mind's Eye
History repeating itself
A world leader
Killed by a gunman
In an open car
With his wife sitting next to him
In public
Bye
A young person may be working for a foreign government
And then having the world spiral out of control despite what the major players may have one
Do you think the people around Kennedy might have worried a little about how that might have turned out
Because
Those guys in that Cafe very well may have been working for the Serbian intelligence service
There's been a lot written about this
No one knows for sure
They certainly have ties to group that the United States today
Yeah we were ranking groups from 1914 would probably call terrorist
Groups like
Young Bosnia
And another one called the black hand
And these groups had Tae sometime to the Serbian intelligence service so you can believe the historian or the investigator you wanted
I believe it's a hot-button issue
Nonetheless
It isn't so important what really happened just like it isn't so important whether or not Oswald was were
Working for the Soviet Union
What's important is
What are the people on the ground affected by this
Think was happening
The US public thought Oswald was a hitman for Moscow what happens then the austrians thought
The killing of their heir to the throne was in
Act of state-sponsored terrorism
And if it wasn't
They were going to make the case that it was anyway
There's really no doubt that the austro-hungarian empire
Wanted to deal with the Serbian problem that have been bedeviling it for sometime once and for all
And to be honest it's hard to blame
In the serbians and a slob
Will counter with the idea that the austro-hungarian did not possess this territory for very long Bosnia-Herzegovina
And places like Sarajevo had not been austro-hungarian furlong
Time
Nevertheless
You try to think of what nations stayed on the planet
Could put up with the nation over there border fermenting revolution in their country and eventually kill
Are public figures I mean imagine
If you're an American
This happening in the United States
Imagine
Shea Mexico
Creating instability in
Unrest and fomenting subversion and revolution in places like Southern Texas
That's something you mix
And Southern Arizona Southern California and then eventually these
Are revolutionaries that have been egged on by the Mexican intelligence service
Chile major US public figure
How long do you think United States who put up
The reason to become so important though
Is because of all the many controversies in the story
One of the most enduring and important
Is whose fault
Everything that's about to happen is
And if this is a civil lawsuit trying to figure out who's responsible for damages
Is a key part of this story
And the austro-hungarian empire
Is in a position to decide to go or not to go to war that seemed to put them in the driver's seat response
Disability
There are austrians though
Living at the time
Basically say
What choice did they have
Take this Austrian
Writing after the wars a perfect example
He talks about
Archduke Franz Ferdinand is one of the best friends the Slavs ever had and then effect
Ferdinand actually was counseling his government
To treat the Serbian problem or lightly because he was worried about it sparking a general War
When he was killed
It was seen as
An extra perfidious act because the Slavic folks had
Chilled
A person who had been
In one of their better friends in the Austrian government
The Austrian
Try telling you about a second ago after the first world war wrote this
Best quote
When the news of the murder of Archduke Francis Ferdinand arrived in Munich
I happen to be sitting at home
And heard of it only vaguely
I was at first
She's with worried that the bullets may have been shot from the pistols of German stew
Who won of indignation of The Heirs apparent continuous work of slob ization wanted to free the German people
Open this internal enemies
What's a consequence of this would have been was easy to imagine
A new wave of persecution
Which now would have been Justified and explained in the eyes of the whole world
But when soon afterward I heard the name of the supposed assassins
And moreover where did they have been identified as serbs
A light shutter began to run through me at this Vengeance of inscrutable destiny
The greatest friend of the Slavs
Had fallen beneath the bullets of Slavic fanatics
Anyone he says
With constant occasion in the last year's to observe the relation of Austria to Serbia could not for a moment being.
The stone had been set rolling whose course could no longer be arrested
Those who today he writes
Shower the Vietnamese government with reproaches
On the form and content of this Ultimatum It issued
Do it in just
No other power in the world could have acted differently in the same situation and the same position
At herself eastern border austria possessed an inexorable and mortal enemy
Who was shorter and shorter intervals kept challenging the monarchy
And would never have left off until the moment favorable for the shattering of the Empire had a ride
And quote
I actually agree with that
And it makes me uncomfortable
Because the Austrian writing that
Statement
After the first World War
Is the man most responsible for beginning II
I don't fit in
The one line that I think Hitler Aryan though
What is line that this Stone has been set
Rolling nothing could arrest
Because something could have arrested it because somebody had been arresting it there's a reason that the austro-hungarian heading attack the serbs are red
And the reason was that the serbs had a very powerful friend
The Russian
Who consider themselves
The traditional Protectors of the sloth
And the serbs were not alone
Most of the powers of Europe had at least one and usually more
Powerful friends and allies
This was the era in European history
And it's often used
As an example of one of the main reasons this whole story unfolds the way it does this is the era of a very complex way
Alliances
That binds European countries to each other
It's perhaps the most
Enduring work
Of Otto von Bismarck we mentioned earlier the 19th century German diplomat
Is Mark played a very large role in the foundation of modern Germany
But he also played a huge role in creating a system of alliances that both expanded
You know Germany's possibilities
About the same time preserving
A general peace in Europe
There were Wars between Napoleon in the first world war that no doubt about that and some of them were directly the fault
The Bismarck
But there wasn't a general European conf
Involving all the major powers
And let's not
Forget that this is an era
That we would today call a multipolar world
Which is hard for us to understand and then era
One or two superpower
Europe during this time. Had at least
First-rate power state
Britain
France
Germany
Russia
The austro-hungarian empire
Many people throw in turkey and Italy to which would make seven
These states all were bound to each other
With complex Alliance System
And complex is
The way Bismarck wanted
Bismarck had set it up so that
Basically no matter what happened he was in the driver's seat
And this work
Unbelievably well especially for German interest before European interest as a hole for a long time
But by the time 1914 rolls around
This genius who create the system that's so complex only he knew how to run a
I take a whole courses on
Biz Markie and diplomacy from Professor who spent their whole life studying and they don't know why he did some of the things
He did
While he was running it
It was fantastic
By the time 1914 rolls around
He hasn't been running it for sometime
He'd been fired
Buy the leader of Germany
And now this complex machine that the genius of Bismarck had created and run with being run by people
Who couldn't
It'll carry his jock strap is what we
Used to say
It was inevitable that something like that
Breakdown
The reason that
The austro-hungarians
Didn't just March into Serbia
Yeah the minute they found out that the storms were responsible for killing their heir-to-the-throne is it they knew that would mean War
Is Russia
And that is something that the austro-hungarians
We're not prepared
At least not without checking
With their main friend on the world stage
And finding out you know what they would do in that situation
Their main friend on the world stage
What's the German Empire
The German Empires attitude is very interest
The first thing I have to keep reminding myself about the German Empire during this era
Is that at relatively young it's a new country on my
It's only founded in 1871
I like 40 years before this error
It wasn't just a new country
The minute it was proclaimed and that's how it happened you didn't Proclaim England you didn't Proclaim France but your money is a Modern Nation
It was like a day where people signed papers and okay the next day hasn't tomorrow
Germany exist
And the minute existed it was the most powerful land power in Europe
With a larger
Population in France traditionally the greatest land power in Europe
Bucket list time.
And a larger after birth rate
And more industry
And how destabilizing would it be in our world today
If a couple of different nations of moderate power signed a piece of paper tomorrow that United them into one country and that one
On now combined country was the most powerful country in the world
Even if it was just the most powerful land power
Are the most powerful C power you can see how bunch of Nations that really didn't deserve a lot of the perks
That's a super great Nations claim for themselves
Mine all of a sudden do that once they turn themselves into a super Nation
In 1871 with the creation of Germany the kaiserreich
You have
An instant great power on the world stage
It was Prussia
On steroids
With a population like eight times as much and the rest of Germany with demilitarized on the Prussian model with the
Depression King
That's a very destabilizing thing
And when that country begins to demand
Some of the perks at the other great Powers have you know of their own France
Great Britain they got all these colonies all these are the things little Holland to them looks
Like they've got places all over the world what's going on
What are the factor of just having
Been there for a while
You were around during the Age of Exploration and you had a bunch of ships out that you were getting colonies Germany didn't come around until most of the
The good stuff was taken
What's the cause of instability
Germany worried about being encircled
Towers all around them that didn't wish them well
Is there any Niall Ferguson
In anything that I really thought was was quite wonderful because here in the west those of us who fought
The German Empire
Famously said that they had this order paranoia about being encircled are always worried about being encircled will look at them on a map
Airborne in circle during Central you're a big enemy Powers all around the Niall Ferguson said
They weren't
Paranoid about being encircled that were being encircled
They were worried about an upcoming War
And up until
Otto von Bismarck goes away he neutralized Russia that was like one of the main things in his diplomatic Alliance System keep the rush
Washing tapi
He said in a five superpower World make sure your country's 103
Rights was always three against two
Russia was always to be kept on your good side
When he is fat and
Basically the foreign policy begins to be heavily influenced by the German
Kaiser
The emperor Kaiser means Caesar
Imagine
You're calling your emperor Caesar
In 1914
In any case the Kaiser
What a strange guy
He sacks
Bismarck because Bismarck kind of talking down to him and it's kind of running the show when he's an old guy by then and he's much revered and you know how do you agree
Grow into your own man with that guy hanging over your shoulder so he's fired them
And he allows that machine to make vinyl mistakes Bismarck never would have made with that diplomatic machine vital mistake number one
He lost the Russian
He intentionally drove them away basically
Right into the hands of the French
The historic German enemy
The one that they had beaten in the franco-prussian war in 1878 Z71 that allowed them to proclaim the German Empire
Which they did in the French Palace of Versailles
Which is what about
Rub your nose in it
My kind of thing
The Germans and the French
Assume they'd fight each other again someday
Now the French were aligned with the Russians
And now the German fears of encirclement had become a reality
The Germans have been trying to plan for what they're going to do with a war
You know against an enemy
To their West
And another enemy to their East the same time
Write how do you do that
And now the situation in Austria boils over
And the Austrian say to the Germans
If we going to do a war with Serbia Russia is going to attack us if Russia attacks us
Where do you stand
In the Kaiser this is controversial but traditionally the kinds of her supposed to have told the austrians
To go for it
Get Serbia done now
And some historians again this is all very
Controversial everybody has a different opinion
But basically the idea seems to be that the Kaiser believed
If it was done quickly enough
The serbians could be crushed before the situation spiraled out of control in Europe because even as
Moderately intelligent will put will give him some credit that the Kaiser was he knew that Europe was a powder keg
And the key thing that had to be avoided
Was this
Process
Almost a machine
The cranking up of a doomsday device
But everybody who'd actually been present when the thinkers who dealt with the doomsday device explain what the doomsday device did
Understood that once the trigger on this thing was pulled
It was going to be really hard to turn it off
So the austrians to conquer the serbians before the Russians flip the doomsday device
Switch
It would all be okay
Again lot of controversy
That's because this
Is again another one of those places where the war guilt question hinges
Did Germany tell Austria
To go Crush Serbia
And who cares if the Russians attack everybody
But of course the problem wasn't that it would just involve the Russians attacking everybody
Because of that complex web of alliances we talked about earlier
Other countries were going to get dragged into the console
This was something that was well understood by the intelligent heads of Europe
Take for example
The British prime minister during this time. Herbert Asquith
Asquith
Wrote a letter privately
Come down
To the history book
Right after Serbia receive the ultimatum from Austria
It's so important
And
Asquith
It's quote
Austria has sent a bullying and humiliating ultimatum to Serbia
Who cannot possibly comply with
And then demanded an answer within 48 hours
Failing which
She will March
This means almost inevitably that Russia will come to the scene in defense of Serbia
Any Defiance of Austria
And if so
It's difficult for Germany and France to refrain from lending a hand to one side or the other
So that we are in measurable or imaginable distance
I'm a real Armageddon
Happily there seems to be no reason why we should be anything more than spectators
And quote
Let's learn.
Obviously to be wishful thinking on the British prime minister's part
But historians like Niall Ferguson who write revisionist works like the pity of War has suggested that if the British had stayed out we have a better
Better world today
For all sorts of reasons he knocks off
Many of the biggest events of the 20th century the most horrible saying this never happens that never happened that never happens if Britain stays out of the war
Britain can stay out of the work if they don't have a heart Alliance
With anyone they're not caught up in that web of alliances
Not too much to have an understand
An understanding with enough wiggle room
So that there was a lot of talk and Britain about do we or don't we get involved in this whole thing
This whole thing
What's something that hadn't happened in a hundred years in Europe
A general European War
It hadn't happened since Napoleon since Waterloo
And that war was so terrible
Matches that were the entire Napoleonic wars in the wars of the French Revolution era
Mike 1789-1815 so awful in terms of military destruction
That a lesson had been talked
To do in a crowned heads of Europe in the lesson was
War is not as much of a game and he
It's no longer
Are these small private armies that we move around our European chessboard and oh I lost to you so you can have this province in the
Next time I'll beat you and I'll take that Province back you know
Nobody was trying to top
Weather
He was
If anything gentlemanly Warfare
There's never been such a thing
It's been called in the history books
Limited War
Restricted War
It was an Italian historian named Ferraro
Who talked about how
You know that era of warfare was the kind of warfare where
NFL leaders and countries can actually have fun going to war or something you just sort of did like pheasant hunting at least in the
Reminder some of these
Ferrara right quote
Restricted Warfare was one of the loftiest achievements of the 18th century
HIPAA longs to a class of Hothouse plants which can only thrive in an aristocratic and qualitative
Civilization
We are no longer capable of it
It's one of the Fine Things We have lost as a result of the French Revolution
And quote
The French Revolution
Was when
The Warfare God
At least in the minds of the Europeans of this era
You really serious
You want a war then we're going to go to war
The crowned heads of Europe
Attack France after France went all revolutionary
You have to understand how much of a shot
That was historian Gwynne Dyer
As a great way of describing and he says to understand the shock of the crowned heads of Europe
When the most Royal
Of European countries
The French
Were overthrown by leftist revolutionaries
He said you have to imagine if Maui
Toppled the US government today
Now is support being a free hardcore communist group imagine them toppling today's US government and beginning to govern
Because that's how the crowned heads of Europe felt about
The French Revolution and how destabilizing it was seen
Inevitably
The royalty of Europe which is almost all of your classes with this new Republic in France
Coalesces into an alliance and everybody attacks France
They do so with their private mercenary armies
And they run into the entire
French
Population
A people in arms
Because France started by losing you have to imagine a state where the entire underpinnings of the state of being broken down in clue
Hutong especially the army
And then all me Prussia Russia Austria and Great Britain all these powers in Europe attack France at the same time
And you're stuck with
I mean like a bit of your army leftover the artillery stayed with the people so the old French artillery was good
What you've got this mishmash of an army with officers you don't have any authority of crazy
And France is about to be defeated and then as only you know totalitarian type regimes can do
They basically tell the people of France that the war is now everything
Our entire Focus the entire Society exists only
To win this war
The decree of the
The French national Convention
In 1793 said quote
From This Moment until that in which our enemies shall have been driven from the territory of the Republic
All Frenchmen are permanently requisition for service in the army
The young men shall fight
The married man show Forge weapons and transport supplies
The women will make tents and clothes and serving hospitals
The public building shall be turned into barracks
The public squares into munition Factory
All firearms of suitable caliber should be turned over to the Troops
The interior will be police with shotguns
And Cold Steel
All saddle horses Shelby sees for the cavalry
All draft horses not employed in cultivation
Will draw the artillery and Supply wagon
And quote
In other words
The entire Society was mobilized for the war effort this was not something that the other countries did in fact
Most of the royal
The leaders of Europe
Could think of nothing more scary than arming and training your population
Often times that use their professional militaries
To put down Rebellion by their population the last thing they wanted to do was give them guns and train them how to use it right training how to
Cedar Street fire
Wasn't going to happen
The French had a different kind of society one that was supposed to be run by the very
You know lowborn people everybody was in this together
And you combine the willingness to throw human life
You know out there on the battlefield in almost endless numbers you didn't have to pay these people either you can just say I'm sorry
Are you out of work right now you're going to the front end.
Steal some chickens from some Farmer on the way
This was crazy
And all of a sudden the French were able to expand
Live
It was on a scale that was unprecedented and to create armies that were enormous
Mean look
Alexander the Great probably the greatest conqueror in all world history
Alexander conquered
A very large chunk of the known world and a decent-sized chunk of the unknown world at the time
With an army that numbered
Anywhere from 40
290 thousand men
Okay
He was obviously a genius in the way he did it
But imagine if
Alexander could have used a historical xerox machine
Duplicate
That world-conquering arm
So that now he's got to
40 to 90,000 man armies roughly comparable to
Imagine he does it again
And then duplicated again
Did you that enough time to where you got
142 1.3 1.5 million men
Maybe eventually closer to 3 million men
And now you've given Alexander the Great
20th century Army
A twentieth-century army
Is many many armies from the past
The French Revolution is when they really start
When you start
Putting
So many troops into the field
But it doesn't matter that there
Practically incompetent
That their lives are wasted that they're turned into cannon fodder as Napoleon who will inherit this
You know People's Army
That Wilkin script every man they want to come script as long as they need them will say
Troops are born to be killed
When is Napoleon famously said to the Austrian diplomat
Count Metternich
You cannot stop me
I spend thirty thousand lives a month
If any of the major Powers except maybe Russia
In Europe at this time
Lost thirty thousand men in a month would be considered quite a blow
Napoleon lost 30000 men a month as a matter of course
Because he had a new kind of arm
Are people in arms
And in order to beat him
The other countries of Europe had to do the same thing
As the German field Marshal blueshirt old depression
Government
After the prussians have been defeated by Napoleon give me a national Army
Give me what he has
And when he got it
You know which depression aristocracy didn't want to do for the same reason that the European leaders everywhere didn't want to do it and I want to put the people in arms
But when they did they were able to Triple the size of bluchers Army and he took that Army and fought Napoleon
The creation of a nation in arms
What's the first step in creating the Modern War Machine
Because now all of a sudden life was cheap
Not only was wife
Cheap
But the modern nation-state
Was now deep enough
To be able to truly take a punch
This is what sets the modern military is often the modern States off from the ones
In ancient time
In ancient times very few
States
Could take a punch you know to use a boxing term
Many of them could dish it out and you take a state like the achaemenid Persian she was the one who fought the Spartans at Thermopylae and all that
The Persians could dish out really good blows but they couldn't take very many good
Most nations in the past could that's why if you look at a book you know the greatest battles in history
If it's beyond you know about 150 years ago
Sometimes the great battle is the only
The wars are won or lost on one big battle cuz the nation-states couldn't take too many punches they couldn't
Re raise armies the state just couldn't support
Once
France turn the entire nation into the war effort
Nations can take punches better ending in the path of the Mongols and the Chinese could take some punches
The Roman Empire could take punches that's what set those
Nation states in the past
Apart from most of their enemies
Right that they had more staying power they had modern staying power
The French Revolution teaches all these states
To have modern staying power the only problem with modern staying power
Is the killing can go on longer
In boxing
They always feel like in early knockout is more merciful
Been a long match because in a long match you take a lot more punishment
Pulling a funny way if everything could be decided in one big horrific battle you know what the start of a war
That is a lot less costly over time than a four or a
5 year long conf
Like we're both sides
Grind each other down to the nub
The Napoleonic Wars
Created multiple States in Europe capable of fighting
Until they were ground down to the nub
Which meant a lot more damage and destruction before these wars came to walk
The modern nation-state provided the support
That the military
It involved in tire
He pulls in arms needed to keep
The struggle going
You know for long periods of time one half of the equation necessary to create the Modern War Machine
As military historian Gwynne Dyer rights right after he talks about the human cost
The Beast
Along Napoleonic Wars he says quote
Almost as important
Is the fact that European Society did not break down under the strain
There was hardship
But no starvation
And the warring Powers were able to keep at it
And keep your people at
Year after year with no end in sight
Do Europeans pay to develop the wealth
The organizational techniques
And the methods of motivation needed to fight Mass Wars
With a degree of popular participation that no other civilized society had ever even approach
All that was lacking he writes
To transform Mass Warfare into Total War
What's the technology
But the Industrial Revolution was already almost a generation old in 1814
And soon it would begin to fill the last remaining Gap
And quote
What was missing
To make this new deadly machine that the Napoleonic wars in the French Revolution created
What's the technology
To increase the deadliness
By exponential amount
And that was already something that was happened
The 18 hundreds are in error in military history with a killing power of machines Skyrim
And machines have been an important
Part of Battlefield
Since before there were cities in human societies to Field Mass armies at all
Think of the bow and arrow
That's a Neolithic
Stick weapon that's a stone age machine
That made man a more efficient killer
Both in hunting
But on the battle
Field as well
Are the tiny 1800 roll around
The Machine's killing power Skyrim
But
Because there is no major war
Involving all the great powers between Napoleon the first World War
The actual demonstration of how this
Stuff can be used
Is lacking
And the military powers of the world
Try to examine the conflicts that do happen
To see if they can learn any lessons about what the next war is likely to be like
There were European observers for example of the American Civil War
To try to see
You know what you could learn from that
The Korean War breaks out in the 1850s between Russia
And Britain and France
There's a war obviously between the United States
And Spain
Del Valle Cuba in the Philippines
You're right around the turn of the century going into the 99
Probably most importantly there's a war between Japan and Russia in 1905
Where some of the use of these
Any new weapons that win fused together create the modern war machine where some of that was abs
Reservable
The one thing that seems to be
The key element
As far as European planners can figure it out though
Is something
The Harkens back to a phrase
From a confederate general in the US Civil War
Akita dwarf
Westin get their first tooth
With the most
End
The idea now of these Mass Army
That your pen created
Was that you needed to be able to raise them and get them to the battlefield
Before the other side
Beat you to it
The timetable for mobilization
Becomes
Force
But none of the major European powers
Seem to be anything but a slave to
What's the Assassin's bullet
In Sarajevo
Cut down the aisle
Austrian Archduke
When the Archduke is killed by
Princep
He does the equivalent of pulling a pin on a hand grenade
Imagine trying to hold
Negotiations to ward off an explosion with a guy who's already pulled the pin on the grenade right
Limited amount of time
To convince them of anything
Winston Churchill during his life
Famously said
That Jaja
Was better than war war
You need to go see a shins always better than War
But the persons already pulled the pin on the hand grenade you have a very short window of opportunity
To avoid the inevitable end that's where you're at
Finds itself
After the Archduke was murdered
Everybody's worried about the same thing too there's an old
Praise the
Peace movement
Using the lights
1960s early 1970s where they would say
What if they gave a war
And nobody came
The military planners in Europe at this time. Are worried about something a little bit different
War breaks out
Enema days the hostilities commence
Only one side's got their armies
Even if it takes you
30 days to get your
Reservists in uniform to the mustering point to the battlefield before they're ready to fight
How big of a deal is it if it only takes your opponent 15 days
Do the same thing
This puts a huge
Crunch
You're TimeWise on everybody in the story
And constrain the ability to negotiate your way out of the situation everybody feels like
Okay the first person that flips the mobilization switch we all go
Cuz nobody wants to fall behind
The Germans have constrained themselves even more time Lies by the way that they have
Found the solution
To their terrible dilemma of how do you fight a two-front war
And once you violate bismarck's dictum of going to keep the Russians on your side
And then the Russians and the French Ally with each other and War breaks out you're going to be fighting the French in the west and the Russians in the east at the same time
And in the intervening decades
The Fantastic German general staff and figured out a way to not just survive that situation
Win that war
But it involved
Exquisite time
Which further constrained
D-mart negotiation room you had before the grenade went off
The timing involved taking advantage of the fact that everyone thought the Russians were going to take forever to mobile
The Russians were seen as a giant someone
Clumsy Colossus
Less organized than the Germans in the French and people like that
And so by the time the Russians could get their act together and get their monster is armies in the field ready to fight
Germany already would have defeated France
Entire plan for action
Involve throwing almost all their weight against the French immediately and then turning after French
Forces were defeated and throwing those forces against the now ready to fight Russia
The destitute
Things to draw
It meant the Russians could have no Advanced I'm mobilizing you couldn't let them mobilize for
Three or four days while you waited to negotiate putting the pin back in a grenade you know that kind of time
You were going to screw up your entire plan for
Winning the war if you did that
The other thing that it meant
Is it if you went to war with Russia
You had to attack France
You had to assume that the French would come in at some time and the only thing you had a plan to deal with which to attack the French first so if you go
Going to war with Russia you get to it
Cancel part of the bargain
It was even more
What concern than that
It involved
Attacking countries
Besides for
Countries who had no
Disagreement with it all
Neutral country
It just happened to be in the way
The Germans
I come up with a plan
To deal with Aaron Circle
What is involve launching essentially a World War
In their own defense
The other thing that prints up did
What's provide an opportunity for a lot of these leaders who thought war was coming anyway
To decide that now was better than later
And this is another interesting side of the conflict but if
You're part of these many military staff
Absolutely sure war is coming
And you can read accounts from every major military the time.
Numbers of their military planners thought war was inevitable
The question is if it's going to be inevitable
Is it better to fight it now than later
The Germans were under the impression that the Russians were on their way to superpower
Power status which if you look at what happened in the 20th century
Is exactly how it turned out
The Germans felt that by 1917
That was going to be a reality the Russians were completing major military reforms major transportation reforms they were taking advantage of
Huge French bank loans
To do this stop the Germans figured if War comes in three years we're going to be in a much worse situation than we are now
So if it's here we might as well do it now
We have an advantage now we won't have later
The French felt
Similarly about the Germans of the Germans felt about the Russians they were looking at the German birth rate and just going
We're going to be smart
They're looking at the growth in Industry I'm in the Germans were
On a tear
Soft war came in
Five or six or seven years
The French were just going to be worse off
So they figured the same thing as going to come let it come now
And amidst
These interesting
Conflicts of interest in worries about timing and all this stuff
The world
These words heading
And tried to pull back from the brink
But instead of having
You know the greatest Statesman Europe can produce during this time. Some of these countries are saddled with people
Who are like
Millstone's around the neck of peace
People like
Kaiser Wilhelm II
The Emperor of Germany
And Leadership is such an interesting side of this
Conflict
Because
I firmly believe have you had a guy of Otto von bismarck's caliber
Your position of authority in Germany when the first world war is
On the verge of happening
But they could put the pin back in a grenade
Peanut
Gavrilo princip metaphor
People in Sarajevo
And all it would have required
Would have been some real
Diplomatic
Quality
Brilliance would have been great but I don't even think you needed that just some
Some high-quality workmanship what's the Germans who produced time and again
The problem was in this time.
They're stuck with a ruler
Who could not have gotten the job
If married had been one of the requirements
You not having it handed to
Kaiser Wilhelm II
Was not a great leap
He represents the
Elmo's wonderful example you can easily think of
Of what a roll of the dice
Hereditary monarchy
He is
How sometimes you get a great role and you end up with a gifted ruler and then
It almost seems wonderful that they've got so much
Power in their hands right because
If someone really knows what to do with it and does good things with it you kind of stay to yourself
I'm glad they have the power to do this good thing
That's a bit of a roll of the dice isn't it as often as you get one of those people you get somebody who's
Evil or cruel or insane
Some people throughout history of world very badly on the dice
Artemis
But it creates good hardcore history
Tina Frost
The ancient elamites used to roll
Whatever the number is it comes up and you get yet another insane ruler in your
Dynasties
Made for fun
Reading but I wouldn't want to live under it
In Germany
This current leader this current Kaiser Kaiser
Just like Czar in Russia where they have an autocratic
Guy to
Both of those stem from the word Caesar
Which right there in the 20th century sound anachronist
That's part of this old world that existed forever and King and Emperor doesn't sound anachronistic
At any time in history before 1914 going back to like Mesopotamia does it
Just sounds weird in the 20th
Show you how old this world is that is marching into the 20th century
Three of the major powers in this conflict are ruled by Emperors Kings or czars
They don't have total power with Lazaro
I was really
All the Kaiser's had his chipped away
Over couple Generations you have to share some power with a German legislature which has political parties and they
Handle budgets and Taxation with the Kaiser still has a ton of power war and foreign policy and political appointments and all that
He's just as below average guy
The funny part about the Kaiser is that the best thing that ever happened to his reputation was at off Hitler
Because when you look into propaganda and you read
The stuff written about the Kaiser before Hitler comes along
And the Kaiser is treated as this evil character
You know this militaristic want to take over the world blood falling off of the band that you see in the political cartoon
And now the attitude that people have towards him is that he's almost silly
Or that he's full of
I know you just wrapped with inferiority complex and she's almost to be pitied he's
A little mentally doll but there isn't that malevolent evil sort of thing and I think part of the reason why is
When you have Hitler to compare someone to all of a sudden you see that the Kaiser was just sort of a
Are marginally bad role on the monarchy dice
For what it's worth
He was tied into all the other great monarchies in Europe one of the funny twist in the story
And it actually provides
You know something of importance because
In Europe at this time the royal families had relatives
Other royal families in Europe in their families
And his family still communicated with each other which provides like a diplomatic back-channel
Woody's rulers can actually in a sidestep traditional diplomacy and just write the family member that rules
The other country for example
Queen Victoria
I may be the most famous Queen in British
History may be the most important rules for ever
I presided over Britain during the height of Britain's power when she's
Controlling most of the world in the Sun proverbially never set on the British Empire
Queen Victoria's grandchildren
I mean well
Kaiser Wilhelm
He's Queen Victoria's
Grandchild he's the first cousin of the king of England King George
Right
Not just that
What does Czar of Russia
Is married
To another
Queen Victoria's grandchildren
Azhar Azhar son-in-law
It's also wilhelm's
Cousin and when you know he gets upset
We want to talk to the Russians about something people often you'll sit down and pain a quick note to cousin Nikki
That would be Czar Nicholas II
Now
The Czar in Russia is another
Average to low average role on the monarchy
Dice
It's perhaps telling and some historians have made it out to be that you end up with such mediocre leadership in such a power
Powerful countries during this time.
It might account for why
You know these
International incident with the war previously didn't but now are because the leadership sucks
I mean in terms of what you could expect at these people were merit-based leaders
You can say what you want about a Stalin
Or Hitler or even a Mussolini who's been portrayed again in the west like some sort of clown
But all of those people were formidable individuals
Rose through the ranks at some level and same thing with American politicians
How many garlic Franklin Roosevelt you can say what you want about him but that's a formidable human being with qualities that allow them to sort of rice
Rise to the top that requires a merit-based
Something
Being born into the hohenzollern family as the oldest son done require any
That's the luck of the draw
If the job of Kaiser been merit-based
Kaiser Wilhelm II window gotten anywhere near it
And yeah he's the guy
Most responsible for putting the pin back in a grenade Wars going to be avoided here and
He famously said after he sacked Bismarck and then sacked another guy said I'm I am my own chance
Meaning I'm
I'm going to run all this myself
What you do when not only are they subpar and intelligence and Brilliance and all that
Because there's some part that they can't see that there's some part of they don't even take advice well
At one point in the story The Kaiser will ask one of his military leaders to do something that is ridiculous
Stupid lose the war stupid
And the military leader will say it cannot be done in the Kaiser will embarrass him and say something
To the effect of your uncle who was also a field Marshal to give me a different answer
In other words he would have done
What I wanted him to do even if it was
Stupid
The guys are just to show you how it is too so you understand royalty and you remember you had to go yeah that's what royalties like
This a military leader I just called a guy named Von moltke
We'll have to change the way that the German war game system work
For the first World War
And he will have to put his foot down and take a career risky move
Until the Kaiser that no longer can they keep up with the tradition
Whatever side the Kaiser is commanding in the German national war games has to win
Think about that
Per second
Before Field Marshal Von moltke puts his foot down
Whatever side the Kaiser is commanding in these War Games he's National maneuvers
National Security importance
Whatever side the geysers commanding wins
Automatically
Pokestats
Goofy and the Kaiser's a little goofy he's got this one arm that was damaged during his birth
Which was withered and had no strength he couldn't cut his own food for example
Which is so embarrassing to a guy who's already got an inferiority complex
He goes to England to spend time with his cousin and they don't really care for him too much the British royal family is kind of turned off
By William and all William wants his kind of their love and approval and to be like them
What's funny is in this sort of weird
Almost
Like tragic playwright kind of way
The Kaiser sort of embodies the inferiority complex that his country has at this time to there are Newcomb
Country on the stage and they think they're being treated like trash
They're mad they're there
Chauvinistic that's how the British in the French and Dutch people see the images
These upstart
In a push that weight around kind of people
But as many asteroids are pointed out there's no nation in the world that's up and coming it doesn't start to act like
And when they do the Nations that already have it all don't like it I mean how to
How does the United States kind of feel about
China today is sort of elbowing its way into the
You know
Power structure here I mean we all understand they deserve it
You look at their economic look at all the signs they they're their up-and-coming but
Nobody necessarily feels like that person pushing their way in to get their own spaces
Anything other than a bit of an upstart
During this time period the United States placed a similar role
There's some elbow in their way in the world power whether the people that are already there like it or not make some room here we come
That's how the German Empire was there wasn't a feeling of inferiority and Kaiser Wilhelm held that's what
Attitude in Spanish
But if you read this
Stop at the time she portrayed in this military
The term is most often used
German Empire that will be blamed for everything that's happened
Okay military
The entire latter part of the 1800 people focus on militarism
I'm in the building of these amazingly technologically deadly armaments
And the race for power and it just seemed like the world was arming itself to the teeth it was just going to explode and it was these military
Responsible
The people who look at
Nazi Germany and who are I know people who are in thrall
By the very marked in the Precision Marching In the uniforms in this whole sort of militaristic fat
Attitude that the Nazis portrayed and I was trying to tell them that the Nazis didn't invent this
The Nazis were revitalizing
Regular German
Marshall attitude
Set the knights militarism if you don't like it it's Marshal if you do like it
That's what Hitler in his
Tomorrow we're doing
Bringing back
Traditional
Prussian Marshal
Practicing
That goose-stepping robotics
Unbelievably efficient Precision Drilling and all that those are prussians quality to go back to Frederick the Great
And it freaked out a lot of Slavic countries in Europe look at this and they just they look danger they look mean they look
Chauvinistic they look like they wanted to take over your country and then they were building this giant Navy now all of a sudden out of nowhere chair
Challenging Britain
Because the Kaiser had read that same book that Theodore Roosevelt read
Did anybody do more damage than Alfred Thayer Mahan we decided to write a book on nail history cuz
The Kaiser like Roosevelt Reddit was enthralled with it made all his
Admirals read it and then decided he was going to build this Fleet to compete with Britain so that they
It wouldn't take him for granted
Fascinating character
A perfect example of what can happen
With the role of the monarchy
Of course all the governments in Europe
Dead matter
Are not all
Monarchies
Autocratic governments are on the
Famous government of France and Britain for example France is a republic Again by this time
Having tried out royalty again after Napoleon
Decided that they like the Republic
Idea better and there are Republic
Britton might as well be by this time.
They still have the king in the royalty and all that but they don't have any power.
Whether they were during this time. The way the royal family is now
Maybe more gravitas
Maybe more
Able to shift public opinion one way or the other than the more
Cynical generation today looks at
Current royal family
But at the time that's about the extent of their political Authority
Parliament
Legislature of Britain has the power then like they have the power now
But that created dynamic
With a French in the British have to worry about things that
Another country is on the other side of the Ledger or Russian don't have to worry about they have to worry about the political situation
Have to worry about their political opponents
Using the war situation as a in a political issue
He Great Britain there's quite a bit of division over this whole thing
And during this time. Between when the Archduke assassinated
Which happens on June 28th 1914
And when the austro-hungarian government issues that famous ultimatum The List of Demands to Serbia which happens on July
There's a big dead zone in there
Not really a dead zone if you were reading the morning papers every morning in that. There be War scares and comments hearing
There be something new everyday to keep you focused on the crisis
But historically
Not much happens what was going on with behind-the-scenes
Town of diplomacy
I'm one of the main Avenues of diplomacy
Were the French trying to get the British
You know into some sort of hard agreement for what they're going to do if this war breaks out in 5 minutes cuz I don't have a heart agreement
Britishness would have a soft agreement
Instead of a signed on the dotted line contract and a handshake deal and I start to get a little bit worried about the
Deal
I'm getting worried
Even if the government in charge in London right now
Will come through on the handshake deal who's to say they're going to be able to keep political power
Their opponents be used as War issue
Note to topple the government take control of the government then say to Francis we only have a handshake deal I'm sorry the new government will not
Comply
We're not getting involved in this War neutral we have the splendid isolation and the Navy will protect us cuz remember
For folks looking at map of Great Britain
Eva giant moat around their country and the greatest Navy in the world to protect it they have the option of staying out of this thing
If they want to
French don't have that luxury
They're on the invasion list they're on the dinner menu for Imperial Germany
And they're looking for people to provide some help
They got the Russian but the Russians are a long way away
But not being on
The dinner menu for the Imperial German
Military
Mint at the British situation was fundamentally different
They couldn't see
A real positive outcome for them if they get involved in this whole Affair I mean
There are things the French can gain
I got a couple of lost territory they lost to Germany in the war of 1870 1871 they'd like to get those back
In a best-case scenario you know this conflict breaks out they will get them back
The British don't have anything that wonderfully positive to look forward to
Yes they might alleviate the threat of this German Fleet
Dubai 1912
It was already felt that the British had proven that the Germans could not compete with him in the building of ships
Not if they wanted to have a Greatland Army at the same time
And so that's kind of out of the way by this point
So no big game there
And maybe you protect France from falling cuz if France Falls you get the situation you had in the second world
War in 1940 where all the sudden you have the Germans staring across the
In the English Channel from you
And then all of a sudden that mote doesn't look that why does it
But that's not a lot of positive stuff
To go into the first global conflict in a hundred years for
Do the British this looks like a massive disruption of lyrics
Extremely profitable business ventures
They've been snapping up books
Like the great illusion written by Norman angle wherever historian points out how influential this book was
Or angle is trying to explain to the people in that time.
Did this war that continually gets threatened like
The Russian Roulette
Trigger being pulled
Is never going to happen it can't happen
The world has become too interdependent
In that time.
There's too much globalization this is the early. We're all that starts where you at
Telegraph providing instant communication in the railroads of the shipping lines and trade had never been higher wealth and never
Grandeur
And Europe was at the height of its
In a financial power and Britain was at the height of everybody's Financial power
Why would you mess
Would that economic situation guys like angle were saying
That would happen is it was so profitable to Simply do business as usual
That there was nothing worth going to war over
What angle was saying is that anything you would gain by launching a war
Would be dwarfed by what you would lose by destroying the system that was allowing everyone to make so much money
There's an old line
That when Goods don't cross borders
Armies will
Well this is the opposite situation their goods are Crossing Borders like crazy so guys like angle tell you
Filipino because of that formula they believe in that formula you can't have a war
I'm pretty sure starting to find out
You know what is this
Dead Zone. From the end of the archduke's assassination of the ultimatum by Serbia with a pretty sure starting to find out is it
Angle is at least
Partially wrong
He may be right that you will destroy a whole system that's making everybody rich
He seems to be wrong
In thinking
That the powers-that-be will avoid a war because of that
In the British government is having a hard time
Selling their people on the idea that this is good for Britain
July 23rd
Finally
The long-awaited response from the austro-hungarian government to the killing of their heir to the throne
They send an ultimatum
The to the government of sir
The ultimatum is one of those documents you can look at throughout history that is obviously designed to be
The demands would have Bissell
Serbian song
No sovereign state could agree to this
And they're only given 48 hours to respond to all these different points the rejection of any one of which means war
But the day before the 48-hour deadline Runs Out
Disturb government sends a message to the Czar of Russia asking for help
And a rope quote
We cannot defend ourselves
Therefore we pray your majesty to send help as soon as possible
Your majesty is given many proofs of your previous Goodwill and we confidently hope
The disappear will find an echo in your generous love heart
And quote
The serbs
Send a response back to the austro-hungarians
It's not good enough
The austro-hungarian
Declare war on July 28th exactly one month after the assassination
And they're shelling Belgrade in like 5
The Russians
Declaring mobilization
In response
This is the moment when the first
Outside power
Returns on their Doomsday
Easy when the austro-hungarians in the serbians mobile
It doesn't freak anyone else out because they're going to fight a little war against each other and they have to mobilize to do that
It's when the first outside power tied to these Alliance System
Flix On Their doomsday device that everyone else is going to feel the pressure to do the same thing
Germany the most pressure
Because they're the ones
With the very short window of opportunity I think
The designer of the military plans
Couch sleeping had figured out it was about 900 950
Hours
That they had
Just smashed
Potential of France you didn't have to be mopped up but she had to be smashed within 950 or so hours
Before the Russians would start to come in from the East with their armies now mobilized
If you screwed that up they could be in Berlin having coffee and cigarettes and poking the Kaiser with a stick in a can
Age by the time
You know the Germans figured out what was going on
The minute the Russians mobilize
You have this crisis because the Russians have
The flexibility if they want to just sending those people home in the month mobilization doesn't mean War to them
But it does to the German
Because they've got to start their plans and every day they don't that 950 or so our way
Shrinking
This is the point in the story
With the military plans
Begin to take over the political process in a way that makes it impossible
For the politicians in the diplomats to do what they need to do to potentially stop this conflict they need time
Anytime
On the 26th of July the government of Britain cause a peace conference is for the major powers that they can hash this out talk it out
Nobody's got
Once the Russians with the mobilization switch
The Germans are under pressure
The tell the Russians
To stop
The Russians say we're only doing this
Against Austria-Hungary this isn't meant
You know against you doesn't matter the Germans have a problem now and they begin going to everyone else and saying are you in are you in the
Go to the French
The French
Are you in this conflict it's about to come out cuz we're going to go to war with the Russians if they don't demobilize what are you going to do
The Friendship we're going to act in accordance with our interest
On a germicide will listen
If you want to stay out of this war all you have to do is hand us the keys to all your Force
What's on our fortified border
Until the war in the East is over that does a pledge of your good behavior will consider you out of this war
That is impossible for the French government to do as the demands on Serbia War for the serbians to do
French can't do that hand over your National Security keys to your most antagonistic historic enemy
I don't think so
And the Germans must have known that
They knew they couldn't keep France out of this conflict which is why they had these
The Fantastic military plans to defeat two powers
The country they were really hoping to keep out of the conflict with Great Britain
Only kept negotiating with Britain saying
You don't have any deal here we're cousins were both Anglo-Saxons were the same race you know the French are your historic enemies are you really going to work
With them
On the 30th
Of July the British prime minister
Wrote in his diary
Quote
The European situation is at least one degree worse than it was yesterday
And it has not been improved by a rather Shameless attempt on the part of Germany to buy our neutrality during the war
My promises that she will not annexed French territory
Except colonies
Or Holland or Belgium
There's something very crude he writes and childlike about German diplomacy
Meanwhile the French are beginning to press in the opposite sense
Have the Russians have been doing for some time
The city he means London
Which is in a terrible state of depression and paralysis
It's for the time being all against English intervention
I think the prospect very black today
And quote
But something will happen
That will change the mood in Britain
Something that will help to create
A good guy bad guy narrative in this war
You know I told you earlier one of the key issues because this war so important to the rest of the 20th century and 21st century history
Is whose fault at all
And the British were very concerned during this time.
The day be if they intervene
Intervening on the right side
Who's the bad guy it's going to depend on what happen
That's again where the German war plans put them in a situation
We're for the war plan to succeed you have to create strategic problems that are going to cost you the war the biggest thing
The Germans need to do here is keep the British out of this war
But the war plans involve a requirement
That will bring the British into the war
The Germans can't attack
French along their mutual border
The borders full of forts
It's the most
One of those fortified borders throughout world history ever since Roman times
It's the same area but a hundred and twenty mile front
That will become the Maginot Line after this warned before the second World War
During this time. There are fantastically technologically sophisticated forts all through the hundred
20 mile border between Germany and France
With interlocking fields
Fire
Enlarged garrisons
It's not that the Germans can't defeat that they did in 1870 1871 that was the root of invasion back then
The problem is the German can't defeat them
Within that 950 or so our window
By the time the Germans smash their way through those forts
The Russians are in Berlin
Pencil easy and everywhere else right
There's only one thing the Germans can see their way to doing as part of this plan to win the two front war and that's just smash into France in
In the part of France that undefended
But the reason the part of France is undefended or less
Defended than this
Fortified border is left offended is because it isn't on the border with Germany
On the border with a bunch of neutral States
These are going to have
How to be the highway
The German Army uses to get from Germany to France
The only problem is is that those highways neutrality is guaranteed by the British government
And has been for 75 years
What is about to happen as a result of the stipulations of those German war plan
Is potentially
The greatest mistake
Ever met
I mean I put it on my top ten
Greatest mistakes ever made a German I have to believe
I have a hard time figuring out what is a greater mistake
For the entire history of your nation as a unified
Hill Country
Hard time finding something you
You could label
As a greater mistake than this one because so many of the other candidates you might put as your greatest mistake
Only happened because of this mistake before it
The invasion of Belgium is a disaster for Germany on Sony
And that's what we're talking
Originally
And way back in like the
Late 1800 early 1900
Holland had also been on the list
The country to be used as a highway for the German Army but
Since that time in is the war plans were refined it was just narrow down to just Belgium
And the Germans were sort of naively hoping that the belgians would just step aside
Like lying there are me up on both sides of the street and watch the Germans March through
The British and the prussians unihorse were the forefathers of these German
We're two of the signatories of something called the Treaty of London in 1839
The pledged
To defend Belgium neutrality
In a wonderfully tragic ironic sort of connection to by the way
The role Belgium is going to play leading to the first world war is very similar to the role Poland played leading a
Chapter II
In both cases those countries were the reason Britain got dragged into the conflict
Before the second world war Britain had
I tried to
Stop Hitler
Seemingly endless ambition
By putting a roadblock in his way and guaranteeing the independence of Poland
Hitler ignore that guarantee went into Poland and Britain in the war in the first world war the same thing is happening with bells
The German planners can see no way to win this war without violating Belgium's neutrality as we said
This is what makes it the greatest mistake though
Potentially halt German history
Violating Belgium ends up taking a Britain that one historian says
As recently as two days before they declare war on Germany
Is leaning toward neutrality
That's amazing to take my 2 days before they enter the war
The government is leaning toward neutrality what changed that
The invasion of Belgium
The invasion of Belgium does to
Terrible things
Looking at this from Germany
Point of view
The first thing is a changes
British political and public opinion almost overnight
On a dime
As the British prime minister Herbert Asquith
Put it here
Of course wants to get more involved
This looming War
More cuz of the handshake deal with Francie said that the
Ultimatum the Germans give to the belgians
Simplify
All of a sudden the people who are trying to convince the rest of Britain that they have a dog in this Continental War looming up
Have some real ammunition the first thing is assigned
Treaty with the Belgian
That's not a handshake
Deal that's in ink
And it's longstanding
As is the National Security concern the Britain has had for a very long time of keeping the channel ports in Belgium
Out of the hands of some dangerous hostile power
That's right most of Britain's history that dangerous
Hostile power was France
Other calling the Kaiser the new Napoleon
And if he goes into Belgium he's going to have those Channel
Airports
So what have been
A more sort of highbrow
Argument
That didn't really you know
Appeal to the goddess
Is changing because of Belgium
The most important appeal to the gut though the Belgium has is the propaganda
Slash PR site
Belgium is what destroyed
Germany's reputation in terms of global public app
I mean they're always been people who called Germany this evil malevolent militaristic country and what have you
Put on the world stage as soon as the Germans invade Belgium
They participate in the most aggressive act so far by any of the major powers in this cup
Austro-hungarian
Assault against Serbia maybe before this was the most
Egregious but that was seen as having some sort of
Interconnection doivent I mean the Serbian government had maybe been involved in this assassination it was something to do with one another
Elgin was an innocent
I Stan
It looks like a shooting War breaks out between a couple of
Gangsters on the street and the first thing one of the gangsters does it turn to the side and kills an innocent bystander because they're staying
Standing in their way
That's a little like what this is portrayed as by
Italy allied propaganda service
Which make the most use of this Belgium thing you can imagine
So much so that it didn't send
People like
Hitler
Who will write later in mine comp
Nowhere else
Did the Germans
In a fall so far behind the British in the French and later The Americans
Then they did in the in the realm of propaganda
Hitler says the huge mistake of Germany in
Austria-Hungary propaganda was to portray the enemy as comical
And he said that
British in the French the Americans understand
Did the enemy needs to be
Seen as a violent dangerous and bloodthirsty as bad not comical because he said the
Problem portraying them as comical as you run up against them in their tough
And that seemed to shatter all the propaganda it's better to say that these evil
You know the nine Riders of Mordor are approaching he says and then
You know you really get your back into a cause like that
And that's how the allies
Which is what
Britain France
And many other countries the United States later included will be
Call Means War there initially called the triple entendre
The other side the
Alliance with
Germany Austria-Hungary later turkey into other countries will be called the central power
That's what's the triple entendre against the Central Powers
Or the Allies against the Central Powers
In the Central Powers
Will be portrayed just as Hitler said
As these rapers and pillagers and looters
And it will be in Belgium
That the Germans will provide their opponents with the raw materials
Do not have to exaggerate too much at all
To portray them as the modern-day version
Origin of the Han
Now
On August
First
This
Small war between the austro-hungarians
And the serbs
Jets
Bigger
Because that's when
The German ultimatum given to the Russians
Telling them to stop their mobilization or else Runs Out
Historian David Stevenson says
But this is a clear sign that the Russians know what's coming
And they're okay with
They know that if they don't stand down they'll have war with Germany and they don't stand down
So he says
One way or another you have to
Infer that the Russians were ready for this an okay with it
It's on August 1st the Germans declare war
The Russian
That day Italy says they're out
They had a nominal alliance with Germany and Austria-Hungary
But they choose to use an out clause which may or may not be valid depending on who you're talkin
Saying that this appears to be an aggressive war and their Alliance only covers defensible
So they're out
They declare that they are neutral on this
New conflict
It's just starting
The next day
In the West
Germany invades
The new truck
Country of Luxembourg
Tiny little neutral country Luxembourg
And at the same time issues this ultimatum to the belgians
Same listen we just need to use your country to get
To France
Are we mean you no harm I'll just let us March through if we break anything will pay for it later we don't have any designs on your country long-term
In response to this
The belgians have a heroic moment where the king of Belgium
You know I'm in the major officials all get together and basically all agree that they're not going to stand down
The attitude they seem to have his we're screwed either way
We might as well go out of this gloriously and they decide to mobilize their tiny little army and fight in at the same time
Issue the calls to the other guarantors of their neutrality saying
They waited until the moment the Germans by the way stepped in everybody's worried somebody's going to pull a fast
But like the French or were the Germans going to try to fake them into going into Belgium first
Because they think the Germans are coming in the Germans could say we weren't the first people to violate Belgium everybody wants to stay on the goods
Sign in terms of War responsibilities
The French are so worried about falling into a trap like that
They pull the unprecedented move of all time
And on the eve of War
Hold their military forces six miles back
From the border
Remember that's not just
Forward positioning
Those are troops who picked the spots that they were in because there were important strategic spot important passes in River
Crossings and other things that have been built up with fortifications for years
And the French government is so freaked out about
Possibly
Being blamed for starting this in the Germans not being blamed for starting that they pull their forces back
The French generals are not pleased about this
What the move is intended to also make sure that the British
People and the peace
Faction in Britain have no excuse to say well
The French violated Belgian neutrality Forester
Shots were fired by the French first
So the Germans are positioned into this thing where they have a time limit on this deal
They can't sit around and wait around
Belgium have to be violated for the plan to work
They can't get the French or the British to violate Belgium first
They tell the belgians going to let him through the Belgian say no
And on
August 3rd
Germany declares war
Conference
MLG
Not think about that folks
A week ago
Europe was peaceful
Now it's on the
Slide to General War within another week the entire continents going to be flaming out at each other
In a crazy to go from
Tony P's to Total War in less than 2 weeks
HG Wells
Writing a year or two after the conflict and so he's right in the middle of the moment he even says you can't quite
And you can't write about it now
Without the passions in the feelings
You're totally
Screwing up your impression thing
What he does talk about how weird the mood was
Because all this was happening so fast he was talking about the British public cuz that's where he lived
And how there was almost this disconnect between the fact
The entire world has changed
But it's happening so fast we haven't changed with it yet
Any rights quote
All Europe still remembers the strange atmosphere those eventful Sunny August days
The end of the Armed peace
For nearly half a century the Western world have been trained
And it seems safe
Only a few middle-aged and aging people in France and had any practical experience of warfare
The newspaper spoke of a world catastrophe
But that conveyed very little meaning to those For Whom the world that always seem secure or indeed
Almost incapable of thinking of it as anything otherwise than secure
In Britain particularly for some weeks the peacetime routine continued in a slightly dazed fashion
He was like a man still walking about the world unaware that he is contracted a fatal disease
Which will alter every routine and Habit in his life
People went on with their summer holiday
Shops reassure their customers with the announcement
Business as usual
There was much talk and excitement in the newspapers came
What is the talking excitement of spectators
You have no Vivid sense of participation in the catastrophe
It was presently to involve the mall
And quote
It's easy to understand to
Why the British public really weren't ready for this in fact
None of the British
Really red
I hadn't been mentally prep
For the idea that this was coming
For all sorts of political reasons the British government
Couldn't
Declare itself out
To draw a line in the sand and tell the Germans Wilson if you invade Belgium at all
No ifs ands or buts
The British prime minister didn't have that power for all he knew the peace faction in this government would topple is government it
A statement like that were made in
Both the French
And the Germans for a very long time
Before this conflict breaks out but especially in the fever
In the last month
Are trying to get some sort of word from Great Britain what the policy is what are you going to do with the last minute of French or sure the British are going to
Abandon them
The French foreign minister will
Sit down and discussed at one point and say they're going to Desert us
When someone in the British media ask him what he's doing cuz I'm going to wait to see if Britain still has any honor
The British are waiting
For something to happen in Belgium
And somewhere the Belgium
They don't want to do anything until their actual neutrality is violated so they wait until the Germans arrive
When the advance
Cavalry Patrol
Actually some guys on bikes
Patelin de Belgium
And give notices to the locals
We're sorry that we
Do this
And everything be fine just don't cause any trouble don't blow up any Bridges
Don't sabotaging railways
Don't.
Destroy any tunnels anything we might need to get from here to there
Leave all that in place or those will be considered hostile Acts
As soon as it becomes apparent that Germans are on Belgian soil
The king of Belgium basically ordered that all those things be done
Let me contact the other guarantors of Belgian neutrality and says
The Germans are here
We need your help
That's when the British draw up the official sort of
Ultimatum which
People have criticized them for me they say if you'd only given that ultimatum before the Germans had gone into Belgium
Might have had more options once they're in Belgium for them to
Get out of Belgium cuz the British told them he was really like a tail between their legs kind of situation in this is happened in history many time
In other situations where people have said if you had just said
What you were going to do before the enemy did what they did might have been a different outcome
In this case once the Germans are in Belgium
The British
Ambassador to Germany guy name
Sir edward goschen
Delivers the British ultimatum
To Germany he delivers it into the hands of the German Minister a guy named Gottlieb on llego
And the German Chancellor gained Theobald Von bethmann-hollweg
And Goshen knew that this was a historic meeting
And you wrote down what happened and he said the Germans when they received this ultimatum from him
Freak
Out
You wrote that the meeting was
Fraught with Menace
Quote
I found the chancellor very agitated
His Excellency at once began her Reign which lasted for about 20 minutes
He said that the step taken by
The British government was terrible to a degree
Just forward
Neutrality
A word which in Wartime it so often been disregarded
Just for a scrap of paper
Great Britain was going to make war on a kindred Nation who desire nothing better than to be friends with her
All his efforts in that direction have been rendered useless by this last terrible step
And the policy
To which as I knew he had devoted himself since his accession to office had tumbled down like a house of cards
What we had done was unthinkable
In the minds of the German
It was like striking a man from behind while he was fighting for his life against to assailant
Heal Great Britain responsible for all the terrible events that might happen
I protested strongly against that stay
And said that in the same way that he and everybody a go with me to understand
Did for strategical reasons it was a matter of life and death to Germany to advance through Belgium
And violate the ladder neutrality
So I would wish him to understand that it was so to speak
A matter of life and death for the honor of Great Britain
But you should keep her solemn engagements to do our utmost to defend Belgium's neutrality if attacked
That's all them compact simply had to be kept
Or what confidence could anyone have an engagement given by Great Britain in the future
The chancellor said
But at what price will that compact have been kept
Has the British government thought of that
And quote
And this is an interesting key point
Because
I've often wondered if you could take
The principals who were the decision makers in this in a conflict
Into the future
I show them some history books and show them what happened even the winners
Do you think they would have found a way to avert
And what ended up happening because
It was more horrible than any of
Vision
The German field Marshal
In charge of the military Affairs this time van mulkay famously said that
This was the struggle that would decide the course of history for the next
Hundred years
Absolutely right
But he known that this would mean
The Germany would be on the losing end of two world wars in the 20th century
When you think he would have done to me look at
The situation now and imagine Germany without
Having lost those two world wars and how different they might be today
German historian
Who consider this roll of the iron dice
Is going to war here is often referred to
As one of the great irresponsible Gamble's in all German history
And maybe the key element in the whole affair
Was Britain's decision to involve itself in the conflict
Because one can make a very good case that if Britain stands aside
Germany wins
How to start
Instead
They have perhaps
The greatest
Overall superpower
In the early 20th century world
Lining up on the
Other side
To be truthful the Germans weren't really afraid of
The British army
And that's a small
Colonial force that by German standards is relatively insignificant or so they think
I mean Bismarck and famously said when an adviser had warned him
If you go to war with Britain they could use that wonderful Naval power tool and their entire Army on our coastline
And Bismarck famously said if they do that
I shall have them
And he just send the police force
How to Corral the British army that's how
Worried they were about this tiny little forced
Their army dwarf
But they were
Keenly aware
If Britain had the greatest Navy
By far
In the world
They were the greatest Financial power
Power in the world
They controlled a huge
Chunk of the world
Britain and France together
Owned about 70% of the world at this time. When you talk about other colonies and everything else and that's all
Stop that they can draw on
How to fight the war
What's more that wonderful Navy of Great Britain's can shut down German shipping
You know in a moment to the stroke of a pen
Prince p*** sex
Secretary
Sir Edward Grey
On August 3rd 1914 when tensions have reached
A knife-edge
Fever pitch moment
Will look out the window
And see the
Lamplighters of London lighting the lamps for the evening as was customary at the time
Any turn to someone else at the window and famously said
The lamps are going out all over you
We shall not see them lit
The Germans are given the famous ultimatum
And
It's set to expire
At midnight
On August 4th
German time
Which is 11 p.m.
British time
Lloyd George one of the ministers
Says that they were sitting around a table
Just before
Had a stroke of eleven watching the clock tick away
And he said that is Big Ben's chime start chiming
The 11-hour signifying that the deadline is about to expire
He says every ring of the Bells
Sounded like
June
And then when it expires Britain declares war
Germany
That's worth asking it this
What the people who ingest
You entered upon this course of action thought was going to happen
Human Lloyd George
Here's the Chimes of Big Ben sounding and thinks they sound like Doom
What is Lloyd George mean when he says Doom
This is a
Conflict
I'm the sort that your pad not had for a hundred years and a lot of changed in the Hundred Year this is like a jump
Off of a cliff
In the dark for Europe and no one knows how long the drop is going to be
I need been exposed to a lot of thinking out there by guys like Norman angle we mentioned earlier
We're saying no one's going to jump
Jumping would be suicidal everybody died the Golden Goose will be killed globalization be destroyed no one will do it and now
We had just done it
What did people think that meant
Well as we said earlier
The first world war has so much written about
You can cherry-pick
This or that source and create any sort of impression you want
What it really looks like though if you some up you know I've read a bunch of stuff on this and into me what it looks like
Is that there was a small View
Amongst some people
Then understood the real
And they turn out to be the Cassandra's in the story of the ones who actually prophesize
Accurately what's going to happen
Most of these people didn't have a clue I think Lloyd George when he hears Big Ben sound in Doom
Is worried about Britain's financial sector
And he had every reason to be by the way because
A few days before when Austria-Hungary declares war on Serbia the markets around the world
You know go crazy
And in London the financial capital of the world Lloyd George's hearing from all the bankers and all the investors and all these people that this is
Loquacious
It will destroy Britain physically which sounds like the worst thing in the world
Until you fast-forward the time machine for years and see what's really going to happen
Where you would have paid good money to only have the financial system
Here's the thing though
There were people who turned out to be right
About how momentous
The sleep off this cliff and how long the drop was going to be
Who turned out to be right
And we're kind of hoping for
Take for example
The guy who along with Karl Marx helped create modern communism
Friedrich Engels who in 1887
Wrote about this coming conflict and how terrible it was going to be
Of course
You know in his mind hoping for an overthrow of all the existing regime to be replaced by communism
That was sort of the silver lining in this coming Armageddon
Angles Road quote
I see a World War
I've never before seen extension and intensity
If the system of mutual outbidding in Armament carry to the extreme finally Bears its natural fruits
8 to 10 million soldiers will Slaughter each other
And strip your bear is no swarm of locusts has ever done before
The devastations of the Thirty Years War condensed into three or four years
And spread all over the continent
Epidemic
General barbarization of armies and masses provoked by sheer desperation
Utter chaos in our trade
Industry and commerce ending in general bankrupt
Collapse of the old states and their traditional wisdom in such a way that the Crown's role in the gut
Better by the Dozen then they'll be nobody to pick them up
Absolute impossibility differ see how all this will end and who will be the victors in that struggle
Only one result absolutely certain
General exhaustion and a creation of circumstances for the final victory of the working
And quote
Something is your silver lining if you happen to be a communist revolutionary and you want to see the overthrow of government
I didn't want Zentangles will get what he wants at least
In one country
But he's not the only person that receives this
Some of the best military minds of the time see at 2
We told you about the field Marshal in charge of Germany's war effort
The Man known as Von moltke
But he is a
Pale
Shadow of his uncle
The Man known as the Elder Von moltke
Who commanded Prussian forces in the franco-prussian war of 1870 1871
By this time. He's retired and he's on the speaking circuit
In 1906 he speaks to the German legislature and he warns them
What are modern Wars going to be like
Quote
The age of cabinet war is behind us
All we have now is people's War
Gentleman if the war that has been hanging over our heads now for more than 10 years like the Sword of Damocles
If this war breaks out
Fenestration and it's and will be unforeseeable
The greatest powers of Europe oranges never before will be going into battle with each other
Not one of them can be crushed so completely in one or two campaigns that he will admit defeat
But it will be compelled to conclude peace under hard terms
And it will not come back even if it is a year later to renew the struggle
Gentleman
It may be a war 7 years or 30 years duration
And woe to him who sets Europe alight
Who first put the fuse to the powder keg
And quote
This long drop in the dark
Is going to set up the first
If you want to use the boxing analogy
The first heavyweight championship
Fight the world has seen since Napoleon's day a hundred years before
Indians room you had a lot of
In a one-sided Khan
Casino a champion like Muhammad Ali or Mike Tyson fighting
A person you've never heard
Or you'll have something like
The wars between the United States and Spain
Over Cuba in the Philippines which is a rising soon-to-be first-class power against a declining soon-to-be third-class power
Ortiz great Colonial conflicts were
A nation like Britain will go in and crush the dervishes
It's worth a Zulu
With the occasional setback
Back of course
Anyone use Proto machine guns against these natives armed with Spears
One of these Proto machine guns really a Gatling gun with call the Maxim gun and there was a famous
Colonial era poem
It said whatever happens we have got
The Maxim gun
And they have not
In this upcoming War
Both sides
Will have the Maxim gun in fact much more deadly modern versions of the Maxim gun that we call machine guns today
No one had ever seen a war where both sides had machine guns
The franco-prussian war saw the French trying to use these Gatling guns these early
Machine guns as best they could but no one really had any clue what to do with them
That all changed by 1914
We were seeing the most professional armies
Perhaps of the world that ever seen and certainly the largest that the world has ever seen
Getting ready to Clash
In a conflict that was going to be like jumping off a cliff
Open the dark nobody could foresee
The end of this
One thing was for sure
The Army for Germany
That is about to enter Belgium
He's probably
The greatest army
That the world had seen
Up until that
And I say that with everyone knowing what a big
Big fan I am
Demongo
Military
Science and History
3 in their army
They're wonderful
But they get worse
Black people understand how
Incredibly dominant the manga
The army of Germany during this time. The kaiserreich
This is like the Rodney
They don't get any respect
And yet they are maybe I mean you create your top 10 list of the greatest army throughout all history
Map of the kaiserreich
I'm not sure I put the German armed
Part of the reason we don't know more about that first world war German armies because the second world war German Army like so many things
In that second
Conflict overshadowing
In many ways
TV remote
In the second world war is flashing
Then the first world
German army
You know once again to get
The Box insurance
Richard the veermok
Is a big heavy hitter knockout
Best and they go around and it's gym boom it's over in one round sometimes and you stand up and it's thrilling an incredible but you know what
Someone hit them back and or or beats them up a little it's a different game
I want you start wearing them down
Play you can continue to wear them. Because they're not strong fundamentally at the core
They have a great punch
But the rest
Sort of an uneven Foundation
That was really
Where the strength
The first World War
It may not have been as flashy with those giant Knockouts and all that but they
Had a better chin and they
Were they rested on firm foundations it was a fantastic Army
And no one remembers it
Today and what's funny is
Once again it just becomes
Another thing that Adolf Hitler
I was wrong about
When he wrote
Quote
Thousands of years may pass
But never will it be possible to speak of heroism
Without mentioning the German army in the world war
Then from the veil of the past
The iron front of the gray steel helmet will emerge
Unwavering and unflinching
Ramada Monument as long as there are Germans alive
They will remember that these men were sons of their Nation
It's a fantastic
And
Part of what makes it so great
Is this natural efficiency that is stereotypically German
Is applied to military science during a time. We're military science really does become so
Has become
The age of the Bean Counter
Efficiency
When it comes to
Putting an Army in the field that's what the Napoleonic era create
Will you get this first part of the war machine ability to create these Mass armies
Imagine a guy like
Alexander the Great who I love to mention all the time
Imagine Julius Caesar 2
Guys who probably never commanded more than 80
And who staffs you know we're capable and they could deal with it and they were very efficient logistically and everything for their time.
But they were dealing with
80000 men
In this era
You're dealing with
12 to 15 times that
What would Alexander the Great of done trying to
In a control one and a half million men
It's an exercise in
Hiremath
To try to do that
And when you hear
About how the Germans have
Paired minutely for this day that
For so long have been called the day they are taught
I'm this attack into Belgium and 2/1 friends and everything
You get an idea of
How much actual bean-counting in planning is involve now
In order to maintain these armies it would have been impossible
150 years
Before because
This capability didn't exist if it's a function of modern civilization
And the era of the 20th century
How to get an idea of size you have to think about the division
Do the basic
In a unit that these military's kind of Opera
Goes back to Napoleonic time two divisions are still use of course in military today and if you want to think about 15,000
Man in the division as a kind of a rough side
Actually fluctuates
Put Justin 15000mah
A 15000 man division
He's probably more troops
The night of the Normans or the Saxons at the Battle of Hastings
The pivotal 1060
Six battle that decided the fate of
Time in England
The time
Each division is is equivalent to a rather nice sized
Early medieval Army
The German Army at the beginning of the war has more than AT&T
Imagine trying to control 80 Norman Army
And it's not just about getting each division where it needs to go it's about sinking what they do together
And when you start
Organizing divisions into Coors and Coors in the army
Chinese armies have to support each other they have to travel on different roads and then converge at certain points
And you have to think of the incredible math is involved in these March, then it's hard to get your mind around
These units are so large and these roads so narrow that when the head of the column starts walking
They've gone like 29 miles
Before the end of the column can start walking
Trying to plan to have food ready for these guys when they stop marching I mean it's
The logistics of this is incredible
And it's the main reason why you couldn't do this
You know ages and ages ago you just couldn't support
In addition all these armies are fabulously trained
The Germans are incredibly trained in terms of having even their reservist
On the
Practice field in Germany
Doing live-fire exercises preparing for this day
Is Barbara tuchman writes about
And it starts with mobilization and you get an idea of how
Play endeavor
Every step is in the German army
Quote
Once the mobilization button was pushed
The whole vast machinery for calling up equipping and transporting 2 million men began turning
Reservists went to their designated depots
We should uniforms equipment NR
Formed into company
Can companies in a battalion
We're joined by cavalry
Cyclist
Artillery
Medical unit
Cookware
Blacksmith wagon
Stephen postlewait
Moved according to prepared Railway timetables to concentration points near the frontier
Where they would be formed into division
Divisions in decor
Concours into Army
He's ready to advance in fight
1 Army Corps alone she writes
Out of the total of 40 in the German forces
Required 170 Railway cars for officers
For Infantry
2964 cavalry
Artillery and Supply wagons
6010 in all group in 140 trains
And an equal number again for their supplies
From the moment the order was given she writes
Everything was to move it fixed
* according to a schedule precise down to the number of
Train axles that would pass over a given Bridge within a given time
And quote
When you realize how minutely plan
And how you know punctual this whole thing must
Be in order to function you can see why delay is of even a few hours will throw your whole time table off
You're right before this whole conflict breaks out and I mentioned it earlier the Kaiser will turn to Von moltke and he's panicking at the last minute
The great Supreme War leaders not so tough when
It all looks like it's coming down unfortunately for him
Or fortunately for him the staff that works under him are tough-as-nails again another thing is German Army this.
Route to the table
Which to be honest the second one did most of the time 2
It's fantastic leadership
Anna Kaiser one-point things to war with Britain has offices great we can turn the armies around you know just send him to Russia instead of
I'm worrying about France and England it all and then most gas to stop and say you do not improvise
The deployment of Millions
I think the exact language
The deployment of millions cannot be improvised but you get the point
This was a
An efficient plan
To deploy the largest number of people that have never been sent
In a single area
For a single purpose probably in all human history
You think about
Napoleon's greatest
Outrageous gamble right to invade Russia
Utilizing an army composed of many many many different European people
And he had to scrape
Germany in every place out to get enough people to send into Russia with something that was called the Grand Army
You know in the early 1800s
This is crazy in debrecen maybe
750000 men into Russia
The Germans were going to invade Belgium with more than twice that in and out
Flanking maneuver
That's not even the Army that's holding the front that's just a big wide swinging gate that's going to smash on top of the head of France
How do you control
That many people how do you even get them from one place to another we kind of seem to think in our head that they can just
Marcia Cross
You know mountainsides and country lanes and through fields and pastures and sometimes they do
But most of the time
They get two places the same way most of us do
They utilize the road system
Think about what the road system in Belgium
Tiny little
Mostly rural Belgium is going to be like with this massive
Greatest
Sized Army probably ever put together
Trying to March through it all in a short period of time
There were Witnesses
Of course to this actually happening
One of the fun ones
To read for me
Is Richard Harding Davis
Because Davis is one of those guys he's in America
He also is basically the war correspondent
One of the main ones of his era and he wrote about the deployment of
American forces in Cuba you know what the turn of the century and all this kind of stuff and he's he's really Aurora Americana
Kind of guy you know America is the best at everything
And that's what a feeling
But he was there in Belgium
As the German Army comes through
And you can I mean I'm going to read you this extensively because you can hear in his writing his jaw is on
On the floor
And here's someone who doesn't think anybody does anything better than America
And he's getting a lesson
And what the best army in the world looks
Remember
This kind of
Force at this kind of level in potency hasn't been on display in anyone's living memory
You're getting a view of a Nation at War like you would in Napoleonic times
But marked and equipped and organized and supported by a modern 20th century State this was
Why you would be
Beginning to see
Tiny little glimmer
I'm with a leap in the dark
What's going to entail
Is going to entail fighting Army
Like this one
Richard Harding Davis
The entrance of the German Army into Brussels
Has lost a human koala
It was lost as soon as the three soldiers who led the army
Bicycle into the boulevard do Regen
And ask the way to the Gare Du Nord
When they passed
The human note passed with
What came after them
And 24 hours later is still coming is not men marching but a force of nature
Like a tidal wave
Annapolis
4 River flooding its back
At this minute it is rolling through Brussels have a swollen Waters of the coming of valleys went through Johnstown
At the site of the first few regiments of the enemy he writes
We were thrilled with interest
After 3 hours they had passed in one on Broken Steel grey column we were bored
But when our after hour pass
And it was no halt
No breathing time
No Open Spaces in the ranks
The thing became uncanny
Inhuman
You return to watch it fascinated
It held the mystery and Menace of fog rolling towards you across the sea
And quote
He then goes on to describe the uniform
Which
Pretty much the same color the second world war German unit
Feldgrau
Proper way to pronounce it but basically it's just a gray
But during this time.
Most Nations had only relatively recently gone away from Gaudi colorful clothing
You know bright red Scarlet for British troops is only recently given away to khaki
And the French army still war stop that look like they belong in Napoleon's Army
Right they're going to wear red pants
And Blue Jackets
And they're going to carry Savers near Calvary going to have Brent plates and horsehair helmet I mean it spooky stuff most military's remove
Moving away from me
The Germans
Use of gray Harding thinks is the most
Fantastic use of camouflage she's ever seen
The British khaki is often compared
To a canary that's gotten Dusty
Davis goes on and on about how the minute these
German soldiers get a hundred yards from you can't see him anymore
He said he was watching some German Cavalry ride by he could see the horses but he couldn't see the guys on them because they just sort of blend with
The fog and the Mist in the Twilight
In the early morning hours in that color that goes on and on about how great that is it how scientific
He goes on
Yesterday Major General von jarotski the German military governor of Brussels
Ushered Burgermaster Max
Set the German Army would not occupy the city
But would pass through it
It is still past
I have followed in campaigns six armies
But accepting not even our own the Japanese or the British
I have not seen one so thoroughly equipped
I'm not speaking of the fighting qualities of ner
Only of the equipment in organization
The German Army moved into this city as smoothly and it's compact Lee headed the Empire State Express
There were no halts no open places no stragglers
This Army he writes has been on active service for 3 weeks
And so far there is not apparently a chin strap or a horseshoe missing
It came in with the smoke pouring from cook stoves on wheels
N&n our had set up post office wagon from Witch Mountain Messengers galloped
How long the line of columns Distributing letters
Which soldiers posted picture postcard
The Infantry he writes came in files of 5
200 men to each company
The Lancers in Columns of 4
With no dependents missing the quick firing guns and field pieces were one hour at a time in passing
Each gun with that ammunition wagon taking 20 seconds in which to pass
The men of the Infantry saying Fatherland my Fatherland
Between each line of song they took three steps
At times two thousand men were singing together in absolute Rhythm and beat
When the melody gave way the silence was broken only by the stamp of iron-shod boots
And then again the song Rose
When the singing ceased
The bands played marches
They were followed by the rumble of Siege guns
The creaking of Wheels
End of chains clanking against the cobblestones on the sharp bell-like voices of the bugle
For 7 hours the Army path in such solid columns that not want Smita taxi cab or trolley car pass
Through the city
Like a river of steelhead float
Gray and ghostlike
Then as dusk
Caymanas thousands of horses hooves and thousands of iron boots
Continued to Trend forward
Tiny spark from the cobblestone
But the horses in men who beat out the Sparks were invisible
@midnight pack wagons and seeds guns were still passing
At 7 this morning I was awakened by the Tramp of men in bands playing jauntily
Whether they marched all night or not I do not know but now for 26 hours to gray army has rumbled by
With the mystery of fog
In the pertinacity of a steamroller
And quote
That was a long quote
But that's
That's
The German army
The kaiserreich
Campaign the German Army in the Second World War
Is that country's best attempt
To recreate
Matt
No I've always believed
That the very ferocity in the
Scariness of this kaiserreich German army
Work against it at the beginning of the war in a way that heard it
Throughout the entire
History of the war and I think long afterwards helped establish this German reputation
As sort of the bad guys
Because this Army was so intimidating so scary everything from the Precision drill to the
Equipment to how well-organized they were to the logistics
To the leadership
To the intimidating elements built into it I mean they had a wonderful
A unit called the deaths
Head massage
What you goes back to
Napoleonic Wars
Earlier actually
And they wear the old-fashioned huszar's for helmets in 1914
1810 the fur helmet of the Stars
And on the fur helmet is a skull
Reminds you a little bit of ESS forces in the second world war but it shows you that all of this
Predated
You know what the Nazi did the Nazis were just updating a lot of classic German traditions in a lot of cases perverting them and staining them
Blackness and everything but the death head hussar famous
An intimidating as they're meant to be
But then you take that
Nasty ferocious intimidating Army
It looks like I could take on anyone in the world and the first time you see him in action they're taking on
God bless him
The belgians
A tiny little neutral Nation that's less than a hundred years old and has never fought a war
In fact
Is so small
Surrounded by great powers that they rationally figured out a long time ago
It doesn't matter how much effort they put into defense
They can't win
Are the belgians totally unprepared for Warfare lose only a little bit faster than the belgians obsessively
Prepared for Warfare
They put their trust in these International agreement they had with people who were going to guarantee their security which is how this whole things happening anyway
What right
But they did build some defense
Maybe as a
Sign that
You know we can't kill you but we can hurt you
And the defenses are really cool
Because it's really right in that. And in human history where fortification
Sports
Reach
Sort of their high water
And we still billed for today but it's nothing like it was
Pretty much from the beginning of
In human history until
What about the time we're talking about here
Because then you could base an entire defense strategy
Nowadays
We have these special positions where you guard them with a fork but if anybody
Decided they're going to start launching missiles in
Bombs and I mean it doesn't matter
That's something we learn
Very soon in this story
2018 ATS when these Belgian forts are built
This is the. Where it looks like modern tech is going to make these things like space hate Star Wars
When was planetary defenses
They build these wonderful
Subterranean fort
Barbara tuchman said like castles
Sonic Underground
And will do as you I'm reminded of the old
Godzilla films in the Monster Zero films where you have some planet
Anybody have a gun that would just Rise Up from the planet's surface shoot and then go back down underground and
That's what happened in these boards
I have to remind myself
How cool that is this is like steampunk stuff because
When they're building Esports for Belgium
It's the same time that the United States and Mexico are trying to Corral Geronimo and a bunch of Apaches in the American South
Well that's going on the belgians are building underground forts
When you can see some of the stuff on video if you look at the Maginot Line which comes of generation after this obviously
What is the same kind of thing
You know you look at it from above ground you can barely tell there's a fort there
When in fact underground in a massive concrete and in a little railroads underneath moving guns and ammunition
Cool stuff in the way the Belgian
Designer who was one of the best in the world
Built this system he took advantage of the natural River and a slight rise in the hill and everything in there he built
Six big forts
With six small fortune between and they all cover each other's
Fields of fire with your gun so
You know what Ford a
Can reach with their guns Fort be can reach where there's two so they overlap so there's never a place
In the distance anyway
Where the guns can't reach the enemy
Any between Esports the belgians have it so that they're going to put guys in trenches
Between every four
Are people they're supported by the guns at this wonderful system and then you throw more troops out
You know 500 yards a thousand yards ahead to keep enemy artillery away when you have this
System where maybe you can't win a war against someone like the Germans
But you can
Give him a bloody nose and maybe say see you if you really don't want to do this
The Germans aren't sure about that when they come into Belgium
That kind of thinking the Belgian Army is either just going to stand aside like I said earlier
Or maybe you know a few shots up in the air we protected our honor now we're going to stand aside
And the first sign that the Germans are wrong about this is that the bridges are blown up
The tunnels
Are blonde
The railroads
Are blown up
That Madden's the Germans cuz they're on this tight schedule right
So now they have to deal
With at least Transportation nightmare
On this road system it was already going to be clogged terribly and there's your first nightmare in the German straight across
Some of these rivers on the frontier in pontoons
And the Belgian start shooting at them
So the Germans
Put into action
A
Group that they have designed specifically to take these 14 this is the part of the story where we are
When war is declared you have a 72 hours with everybody trying to get their heads around this idea
And at the same time
They flipped all these switches for mobilization the doomsday device I called it work they're calling up all these forces and everybody
Stop here and everybody's are scrambling and what they assume is a race to the front lines which they don't want to lose
Remember what they gave award only
One side game
Gene Wilder
While everybody is concentrating its called their forces
The Germans have like 30000 guys
It was set up in advance to go out basically in the pregame
First World War I guess you could say
And take out the sport if they have to because these forts are blocking the roads
You cannot get to that Belgian Road system that you need to get from Germany to France if you don't take the forts around a place like
Leah Ashe
Renee Moore
And so 30,000 men have been training for years for just this job like I said earlier the day was called deer tag the day
This has been planned for for a long time and the Germans have essentially a special unit of $30,000
Kaiser job it is to take out the sports at the belgians don't stand aside and surrender them
The belgians don't stand aside and
And in fact
The belgians are going to
First
Great lesson
Of the war
About what
Change
Since the last time
Outer space.
How much
Bee killing power
That machines afforded mankind on the battlefield how much that had changed
The angel
Equation of War
Machines been taken over for a long time becoming more and more important
This is the war where
They take over
Completely
And man Supremacy on the battlefield even though the other ones who run the machines
Will always be now
Secondary
Compared to the killing power
And mechanization
They can be brought to bear
You know by modern society
Technology
Was devastating when used against
Bulls and
Nations that couldn't compete militarily
The belgians are going to show what a tiny little army of
Chocolate Soldier
But the Germans
Thought they were going to face
What time is it alarm your chocolate soldiers can do to the greatest army in the world
Because of the
Deadliness
So the weapons at hand
I want the interestings with sub themes of this whole upcoming conflict
Is how long it takes
Some people to absorb the lessons that are being taught in this conflict
Lesson number one is how deadly the weapons are and how you have to account for that
Some of the generals military thinkers understood this going into the
Because they paid close attention to that 1905 War I told you about the russo-japanese war
Which by the way
American president Teddy Roosevelt won a Nobel Prize
For helping to broker the peace
That
But that taught lessons about what happens when two sides armed with machine guns and two sides are on with modern art
All that face off
But the lessons were not the kind of lesson some people wanted to learn I mean if you were a Cavalry
Commander
Example
Your arm of the military is already not looked upon as Berry Survivor
The Warriors all since Napoleon have kind of shown that listen
Calories dies on the
The only thing the Cavalry commander still have going in their favor is there aren't really automobiles yet there will be by the time this war is over
But there are novelty still be used in strange Innovative situations what militaries of the world don't have tons of automobiles
You know running is not mechanize like the second world war everybody's using horses
Even if they die on the battlefield
You like sheaves of wheat being sized down you have nothing to replace that Mobility with
Spanish Cavalry commander don't want to hear that it's even worse than it used to be wow wait till the modern artillery and machine guns get ahold of your cat
I don't want to hear that so they talk about the results as being
On representative
Commanders were very mm
Involved in the idea of
Power of the band that's in the charge in the offensive
For example the entire French outlook on war right now is connected to this idea that you attack
I'm going to go check with the band
Doesn't really mean you're going to
Maybe get into hand-to-hand combat with an aggressive style of warfare is what you want
If you've been preaching that not your country's doctor in your entire military is organized around the culture of the offencive
And cran which is the French word I guess for like guts and skin it's all about guts
Nobody wants to hear that machine guns just rip guts out that the only thing they carried
God damn it doesn't work to have
Bayonet charges in
Ridiculous offenses well
The French would say
Yeah so what doesn't work
Are the Russians of the Japanese
Will work for the fraction that's why we have a great military
I mean there's all kinds of ways to rationalize but you don't want to learn
Many of the militaries of the world are organized like Napoleonic time
They don't want to hear
That is a completely wrong way to be organized
French
Calvary heading off to War as I said earlier but you have to Imagine This
If you want to see what Napoleon's soldiers look like go look at pictures of the French Cavalry 1914.
Going off to war with
Metal breastplates and horsehair helmets and you would have to be an expert to look at a picture of them in 1940
And a picture of Napoleon's Cavalry in 1814 and find the differences
The officers are going to go to war and white gloves
They're going to have swords
They're going to stand up and troops are going to March into combat
In like billiard
Ball formations or
In a bowling pin formations drill formations from the battlefield
None of the people who consider this to be an integral part of military culture want to learn that the rules have changed
A1905 they got one lesson
In 1914 everybody get another
And the Germans get theirs when they try to take these for
On August 5th 1914
The Germans attack
Of these Belgian for
Now
Between the Fords the Belgian to put the put some infantry and there are a couple of machine guns around and whatnot of the Germans
You know they're in a bit of a rush here they don't have time to sit there and starve things out this 30,000 man forth with artillery have to go in there and
Power this through so
The armies behind them
Continue there in a few just salt through Belgium on France
A charge
These
Yuan transfer
The Belgian Slaughter
Slaughter them
Mounds of bodies
And the belgians can't figure out
The best way to deal with it because the Mounds of bodies
Because the mountains of bodies become places German troops can hide behind and shoot from behind and launch attacks from behind
And the belgians are trying to figure out if Kate do we shoot through these bodies and create can you can you create a hole through bodies if you
Shoot through the machine gun long neck
What do we send out people to risk their lives to create holes in the body that we can shoot through
Barbara tuchman
As a passage in her before she quotes
The commander of the Belgian forces that were resisting the German assault
By general von emmich and his
Special brigades
Top gun rights quote
On August 5th Emmitsburg AIDS open the attack on the four easternmost Sports of the edge
With a cannonade by field artillery followed by an infantry assault
The light shelves made no impression on the phone
And the Belgian guns poured a hail of fire on the German troops
Slaughtering their front rack
Company after company came on making for the spaces in between the forks where the Belgian entrenchment had not been
Completed
At some point where they broke through the German
Stormed up the slopes where the guns could not be depressed to reach them
And were mowed down by the forts machine gun
The dead piled up in ridges a yard High
Afford Marshawn belgians seeing the German lines waiver
Charged with the bayonet and threw them back
Again and again the Germans return to the assault
Spending live like bullet
What's in the knowledge of printable Reserve to make up for the losses
A quote to Belgian
Officer who was there
Quote they made no attempt at deploying a Belgian officer described it later
But came on line after line almost shoulder-to-shoulder
Until we shot them down
The Fallen were heaped on top of each other than awful barricade of dead and wounded that threatened to match Target
And causes trouble
So how did the barricade become that we didn't know whether to fire through it
Where to go out in clear openings with our hands but would you believe it
This veritable wall of dead and dying enabled those wonderful Germans
To creep closer
And actually charged up the embankment
They got no farther than halfway though because our machine guns and rifles swept them back
Of course we had our losses but they were slight compared to the Carnage we inflicted on our enemies
And quote
It's interesting to note isn't
That Belgian officers respect for those wonderful Germans is he
He called them
Exhibiting
The military virtues of Valor that were so celebrated during this period where
The romance of warfare
You know what you'd always been strong and human culture was probably at a
Tight
The
19th century the romance was incredible
This is the era where that romance runs into reality in a way that you just can't pretend
I mean guys like
In William Tecumseh Sherman the Civil War General for the US famously said that war is hell
And it's glory is all moonshine
I didn't really see into the mass of the population is one is Dory have pointed out
They weren't publishing a whole lot of combat photos and really nasty terrible stuff for the folks back home
Anytime during these.
So there wasn't a lot of stuff to really
Counteract the Romantic ideas of War
This is the conflict where you can't hide it any
And even though
This Belgian officer looks at this German assault on his food is something akin to The Charge of the Light Brigade
The famous
Doom charge of that British Cavalry during the Korean War
But here's the thing that this war is going to teach
If you watch The Charge of the Light Brigade you think it's magnificent and brave a doomed sort of attack
On the part of incredibly
In courageous men
What happens if after the charge fails
They send another one
And the same results.
And then they send another one in the same
And then I do it again and again
At what point does this wonderful
Doomed romantic
In a celebration of the courage of the military
Heart
Become something obscene
This war is going to take us
And it's going to pound the point home
So you're sick of
After the failure of that German attack on the Belgian Defence
The Germans regroup to attack again that same night
August 5th
And waiting for the sun to go down
And Witnesses who were with the troops describe them as nervous
And anxious and gloomy about the prospects of assaulting
In these defenses again
What's more doing it at night
Throughout most of human history night assault
If you were lucky
Had Torchlight illumination it was always a huge gamble very disorienting you couldn't see anything
That was going to change
War
And it was going to be a facet of 20th century Warfare that we may never see repeated again now that night vision have become about
Battlefield staple
There's no reason to light up
The battlefield
Infected one side like Vision in the other doesn't you don't want it live
In this.
These Germans were going to go into conflict
Where the nighttime Darkness could be banished by technology
You at search lights in these forts Inuit Searchlight
German side sometimes you had
Shell that you can shoot up into the air that would illuminate the night sky and you have to imagine Bunches of those shelves going off
You know it's at separate intervals when they overlap so they're getting brighter and darker and
You know the look of it reminds you of like a
Flashbulb
Flashlights with strobe light fluorescent lumination
And it just cats a go sleep all over the whole Battlefield so that every time you get that burst of light you see
People like ants moving along the battlefield
And you have artillery going off and I'm just think about how weird and disorienting being in the middle of a modern battle
Battlefield would be in the daytime
And I'll take away the light
Freaky
And that's where the German soldiers are about to face and they're understandably nervous they expected some sort of romantic
Kind of War even if it was dangerous you had a chance for heroism
And a chance to die for your country I mean this is it
Generation that is absolutely confused with the ideas of nationalism in the
Dying for your country is a huge glorious thing that you should look forward to
And now they're saying wait a minute
How glorious is it to be one of many people mowed down by machine guns
You just sort of
Randomly
They don't want to go on the assault again
And this attack starts to bog down after it starts
Now there's an officer
Who is roaming around the battlefield who normally is in Berlin with the high general staff of the drum
Military
The Germans encourage their staff members
To get out in the field sometimes and see what's going on in this guy had a particular interest in this battle because he was one of the people who play
I have it
For years he's been planning this bottle he took his vacations from Germany to Belgium just to look around where the battle
I was going to be fought
And now
Cynthia had a vested interest in
Hoping his plans were carried out correctly he's wandering around the battlefield at night looking for what the holdup is and find
Doubt that the general commanding a certain part of the attack is dead killed by Machine Gun fire
So this guy this stop officer
Who
Historians have described as absolutely
Devoid of fear
Big man
Grabs the unit
Of the Dead General
Five or six thousand men
In the dark
And start leading them toward the objective
Now you got all these Sports
More than 400 guns from the four two than the guns on the German side it just got to be this unbelievable chaotic mess in the
The dark and this one General has grab this unit in his
And is heading toward
The city
Aaliyah it's which is protected by the circle of forthright with men in between all the 4th
He finds a spot that undefended leave this unit pasta for
Into the city
On this Gamble
Maybe the city won't be defended or maybe if I walk in there with 6000 guys will just lay down their weapon
Now the Germans don't have a lot to celebrate
In their military history in the second world war because the cause was so nasty
Doesn't matter
You know how many good things their troops did in terms of military history the military side of the causes so corrupted tanks everything
The Germans can take some justifiable Pride
In the adventure story of this guy because
First ewoks in the city
And everybody just want to surrender to him there and then he goes up to the Citadel the main defense in the center of the city
With his sword hilt he pounds on the door demanding the surrender
And they open up the door
And they surrender
Yikes
Talk about boldness
Talk about gambling
This is a basically unknown
German officer
Who because of the name he's making for himself will be in a position that some historians will call
The military dictator of Germany
Within 4 years
Name is Eric looten
Ludendorff actions that night remind us once again that even though is I've sent several times the machines are kind of taken over the dominant
Role in warfighting
Artillery
All the thinking machines
You can't discount the humidifier
In fact the human factors probably the dominant Factor
Amongst
Adversaries that are somewhat evenly matched
Me know about a military genius is going to save Belgium
From Germany
Differences between the potential of the two sides
Just too great
Between
Relatively equal there only moderately unequal Powers leadership could be the determining Factor
And the boldness shown by ludendorff that night is a precursor to what we can expect from him later on and what the rush
Actions can expect from him very very soon
Now ludendorff
Dario dacious capture the city of the eyes doesn't solve the problems the Germans have because all those sports are still a
Taking the city I'm taking the forts
And they're still there
Ready to shoot up German March columns if those if they're not taken before the big March starts
So ludendorff calls for his
No Ace in the Hole
As I said the Germans have been planning for this attack for a very long time
They knew that the belgians might resist
And they knew what they did they had to have
A weapon that was greater than anything the people who built these forts ever envision
In the 1880s although
Some of these for today to the 1890s
In that era
The forts were basically guaranteed to the Belgian government
To be invulnerable to any Canon then known in the world
What's the Cannons that were then known in the world are no longer the maximum size cannons available in the world
Those belong to the
German
And no one even knew it
Until they first showed up on the scene
And they become an even better demonstration
Then the machine gun fire mowing down those boards Germans charging the Belgian defenses
That the Weaponry was simply
Doomsday device like
If you imagine it magnified
Thousands
The times
The weapons that are on the way from
Germany
To Belch
Reduce these
Are the best example I can think
To show how much is chain
Since the last time the great Powers fought each
Nowhere
Is that moron displaying evident than in artillery
Which a hundred years ago during Napoleon's time was already what Napoleon thought decided by
And he was a guy who made his bones
Any artillery he rose through the ranks as an artillery officer he's known for its use on the battlefield here's a guy that
That could shock people with the killing power of well-used artillery
And his big guns
We're firing
12 lb Cannonball
Compound key
The gun itself way in about
1200 lb
The same gun
Essentially in one case.
Both sides of the US Civil War
1200 lb Cannon
The largest of the guns that are on the way from Berlin
To Belgium
The largest of them ways
1200 lb
The shells that Napoleon's 12 Pounders fired
Or between
9 + 12
The shell that the largest of these guns
A 420 mm motor fires
That she'll weighs 2000
The Napoleonic Cannon it was so deadly at the time that it was shocking
Add an effective range of about 2000 yards
The largest of these guns on the way from Berlin
Which aren't even designed some of them for range at all
The largest of these is a Siege Cannon so it doesn't even have to Firebird
Far
Has seven times the rain
That French Cannon
The was designed in
Far
This is an entirely new kind
And the people who actually see this gun after it's assembled
Are slackjaw
And assembled it must be
Because think about how hard it would be trying to transport
Any of these large guns especially the largest of them now
Now turn the clock back
21914 style technology where automobiles aren't even very old there are
Relatively new product
Tractors are even newer
Railways don't go everywhere you need them to and these guns weigh a ton
Guns that are this large usually can only be put on ships that's how you get them replaced
Two places are essentially Naval guns in size
We're talking about a gun that is just over a 16-inch gun that's traditionally a naval gun later on you'll have real guns that are
That large to same problem though how do you get them from place to place they're so big they're so heavy
The largest Battleship guns
You never deployed were the Yamato Japanese super battleships and there's were 18.1
Inches
The famous American battleships
The last
Defective ones we built the Iowa class in Missouri
They had 16-inch guns
Imagine those guns
Trying to be transporting
Opel crossland
Getting him to where you need them to go
The guns on the way
To reduce these forts
Or that kind of size
The largest of them 16-inch guns
Takes forever and it's an amazing engineering feat just to get these guns to where they need to be
And then when they get there
The crew for these largest guns and it's like a couple hundred guys
Have to lay cement the cement have to dry
The gun have to be assembled and put together
Then when they want to fire this thing this gives you an idea of the monsters
You were talking about
The gun crew
How'd it go
Three football fields away 300 yards away
And fire the thing electronically and they were still so close
But they had to put cotton wadding over their eyes their nose and their ears
And they had to fire this thing while their mouth was open
Are they blow out their eardrums and potentially worse than that
Imagine with this weapon.
The shell is fired in a 4000 foot Arc
It takes a full minute
To get from the gun
To the Target. You fire and then there's the 60-second wait
Until the explosion happen
Unlike Napoleon's time we have cool shells that
Can be delayed action fused and armor-piercing so that when you fire meth Esports
They hit the top of the fourth that's the kind of art they had they don't fire flat something they fire we kept in the air and then it drops
It's right on top of the sports
A shoulder
Pierce's armor concrete
And then once it reaches its maximum depth
Benedict play
Wonderful World of Science and Engineering
Is going to take over the battlefields of this upcoming conflict in a way that has never happened before
And this weapon to me most
Symbolizes in this early part of the war
You know your example of here's your wake up
Here's your Darth Vader
Here's what 20th century War
The gun arrives
Along with some cousins were slightly smaller from the also great
Armaments works
Skoda in Australia
Hungarian
Territory then
And the weapons created by Krupp and skoda start selling these Sports and they start going down and start going down
Now
Both of you have listened to many of my shows no I'm not a huge John Keegan fan
But as a historian I think
He's best on his World War 1 and World War 2 history
And he wrote about this guns arrival
Outside the fort
I said quote
After it was emplaced the bombardment began
The crew wearing head padding
Lay prone
300 yards away while the gun was fired electronically
Quoting somebody
To see now quote
60 seconds ticked by the time needed for the shelter Traverse its 4000m trajectory
And everyone listened into the telephone report of our battery Commander
Who had his observation post 1500 M from the bombardment fort and could watch it close range
Column of smoke
Earth and fire that climbed into the heavens
She continues quote
The first of the shells
Delay fuse to explode only after penetration of the 4th protective skin
Fell short
6 minutes later
The next was fired
Then five more each of them walked up towards the target as the elevation was corrected
The Relentless approaching football of the detonations
The paralyzed Defenders of the devastation to come
B8
Struck home
Then the guns fell silent for the night
But the next morning joined by the other which is completed the journey from Essen
The bombardment reopened
The range have been found and soon the 2000 pound shells were quote
Stripping away armor plate
And blocks of concrete
Cracking arches
Sun poisoning the air with heavy brown fumes
And quote and
Keegan then goes on to say
And I'm not going to murder the poor French names of these boards but at 12:30
1 Ford is a recce says and is physically incapacitated in surrenders
They've been shipped fire to another fordwich surrenders
5 hours later
1/3
Explode when it's magazine is hit by one of these shells completely destroying the whole thing that will happen to a cup
Couple of these forts by the way and when they find those the Germans were first on the scene say
But they look like quote
A miniature Alpine landscape
With debris strewn about like pebbles in a mountain stream
Heavy artillery and ammunition have been thrown everywhere
A Cuba Le have been blown from its place
And it falling on its Dome and it now looks like a monster is tortoise lying on its shell
SD Sports began to
The fall
The artillery then closed in on the four that had the general commanding
This whole affair
And he himself
What what it was like to be under Fire
Buy weapons that no one had ever seen the like of it
Human history
Quote
A shell wreck to the arcade under which the general staff were Sheltering
All light was extinguished by the force of the explosion and the officers ran the risk of asphyxiation by the horrible
Gas is emitted from the shell
When the firing ceased
I ventured out on a tour of inspection on the external slopes
Which I found it been reduced to Rubble
A few minutes later
He writes
The bombardment was resume
It seemed as though all the German batteries were firing Salvo
Nobody will ever be able to form an adequate idea of what the reality
I've only learned since
They win the big Siege Motors entered into the action they hurled against us shells weighing 1000 kilos
The explosive force of which surpassed anything known hitherto
Their approach was to be heard
In an acute buzzing
And then they burst with a thunderous Roar raising clouds of missiles stones and dust
After some time passed amid these Horrors I wish to return to my observation tower
But I'd hardly Advanced a few feet into the gallery when a great blast
Passed by and I was thrown violently to the ground
I managed to get up
And continued on my way
Only to be stopped by a choking cloud of poisonous gas he was a mixture of the gas from an explosion and the smoke of a
Fire in the troops quarters
We were driven back
Have suffocated
Looking out of a peephole I saw to my horror that the fort had fallen
Slopes encounter slopes being a chaos of rubbish
About huge tongues of flame we're shooting forth from the throat of the Fortress
My first and last thought he writes
What's the try to save the remnant of the Garrison
I rushed out to give orders that's awesome soldiers whom I mistook for Belgian gendarme
I called them and then fell again
Poisonous gases seem to grip my throat is in a vice
And quote
He woke up to one of his aides and the German officer giving him water
Those
Soldiers he thought
Or Belgian were German
They were the first to enter the 4th
After a shell detonated
In the magazine in the entire fort
The chine explosion
These are enormous
Metal
Seal
Concrete
1/4
These guns were pulverized
Forts that were built to withstand
The Guns of just a generation before and doing so with
That's a demonstration
How much things have changed
Just since the 1880s
And think of how much things have changed from Napoleon's time to the 8th
This was a nineteenth-century world
Discovering the
Horrors
20th century Warfare
And they were going to have
How to learn
How to deal with this new reality
Horrific
Bloody lesson at a time
The lesson of liege
Is it the arrow
Of
Debasing your defenses
1/4
Is over
This is a lesson
That will not be learned and will be taught again
In France
In May
It's also my opinion
That the Germans are being taught a lesson
Even as the story's going down in the guns are pulverizing
The fortune Belgium
The German should be picking up on what
Current events are trying to teach them
They will never
And they will repay
Repeat these mistakes
They're making in Belgium again
In the second
It's safe to say I
Damage Done to
Did the German reputation
Global
Because of what's going on in Belgium
Won't go away till at least the 1950s and I think you could make a very deep
And it involves
German treatment of neutral country
And non-combatants
Wherever they
And you know I should watch this story unfold
It's clear that
In some respect the Germans just don't get it
And you would think they would this is a country that and it's funny now they've lost its reputation
The two world
Are involved in both
But they used to be considered an absolute
Hot day
Of human culture
The Cutting Edge
Art
And science
And literature and
Thought
Philosophy I mean all these things that the Germans really private
Music
Incredible people that
Guys like HG Wells were intimidated
I couldn't help admire them but was intimidated by how
How ahead of
Things they seem to be Asian to be in all these areas
How
Strangely ironic
People that are so advanced in those areas
Could have so many blind spots in areas that one would think are related to the higher cultural
Do the people
For producing such cutting-edge hire culture
How did they miss
Something that's likely to be as damaging
To your International reputation
Asthma history now calls the rape of Belgium
The rape of Belgium I should point out a little bit
Is a propagandist
Fantasy
I mean it made it into crack
Give me a movie the rape of
Belgium
Go see the Rape of Nanking
Your history books and then you will see something
The propagandists
Did not need to magnify at all
To create a world-class historical
Atrocity killing fish
Belgium want that
But it was something
And that something would
Would come back to haunt the Germans in ways that they almost seem ignorant
Begin recording Hitler earlier
Propaganda
Hitler sees it after the war
Did the Germans were just
Blind Side
Buy 20th century
Global Communications in the ability to manipulate World opinion
By taking things that were real facts
And blowing them up two levels that just
Incensed whole society including neutral countries
The Germans don't understand that the way they are conducting themselves in Belgium
Is affecting public opinion
In places like the United States
Which have large German American populations by the way with your cheering
You know the the Feats of arms and how the German military shown themselves to be so dominant American papers are not 100%
Against the Germans at this point in some places American papers are in regions that are
Dominated by German American
They can't explain away what
Happening
In Belgium
And what starts the day the invasion of Belgium happen
German start killing Belgian citizen
When they do so
As part of what is now understood to be
A
Policy of frightful
I'm not sure that's the
Perfect translation
Another term
But the Germans intended to
Instead example
Of people
The did things that the Germans have said you shouldn't do
They said you shouldn't blow up Bridges if they find you blowing up Bridges
They're going to punish you and I do not give probation
They will hang you they will shoot you if they catch you trying to blow up a bridge
The Germans take that
Even farther though
If you're near a village where a bridge gets blown up
The Village might pay the price the Germans believed in Collective punishment
They also believed in taking hostages for good behavior
And when people did stopped anyway they kill the hostages
This has been one of the most
Contentious
Hearts of
You know new scholarship all the time on the question of
Atrocities in Belgium
Because
You know during the war it is this huge
And those of you by the way you've lived long enough to have seen
The same Dynamic at work wear
Real atrocities happened I remember the first Gulf War the stories of
You Know It Rocky soldiers taking Kuwaiti babies out of incubators and throwing them on the floor then stealing the incubator
All these stories are normal because real atrocities are going on but then they're magnified because the man
Magnification Works to the benefit of the enemies of the people the propagandas working against
The Germans went in and did a bunch of things
In Belgium that make him look bad
Because they were bad and then the foreign media like the British were fantastic at this get ahold of those stories
And turn them into the worst things you can ever think of
The Germans
Only began to get this
You know a few people at a time I mean later on much later on
Dekeyser son at gyno NASDAQ
Crown Prince
Would say that Belgium is when the Germans
Lost
First great battle of the war
But they didn't
Lose it
On the battlefield they crushed the Belgian
They lost it
In the realm of global
Pinyin
Because of their behavior
Behavior that the Germans will use all throughout this war and again in the Second World War
This tendency to ignore neutral
As we said earlier
The German diplomat
You told you going to go to war over
Piece of paper neutrality is often violated in war
That's kind of how they thought
They also thought
You treat non-combat
Harshly
Soften that a little it's worth noting that
The Germans treat their own people this
They are a Stern
Rather strict
Some would say severe Society especially
You know depression has elements of it
And they expect in obedience and discipline
Conformity to the rules and that's what they expected their own people and then they go into Belgium and when people violate the rules
They get treated harshly
Your message has failed to foresee maybe with cultural blinders
The people that come from much less
Severe traditions
Would maybe
In a play
That quality up
As something uniquely German
And nasty
Not just that it should be pointed out that a lot of different people
You know in the world at this time we're having problems dealing with your regular fighting
This was a big deal at the time
Irregular fighting
Of course is when
In a regular people take up arms and start shooting at your soldier like gorillas
Vietnam the US fought
Viet Cong Guerrilla
Very difficult
Causes all kinds of props atrocity
Tend to happen
Are the British and just dealt with this not altogether successfully in South Africa were at Ross
Issues happened
French were dealing with it in Asia North Africa the Russians were dealing with in Central Asia the Japanese were dealing with in China and
Korea
This is a problem a lot of countries were having
The Germans were very worried about what we're called free shooters
Today we would call them snipers
Because in the war of 1870 they had a lot of Prague
Who's winning the Belgium
Any place
Thought snipers were there people paid the price left right and Center
The Whole Town's would be
Executed if a sniper was
And here's the worst part
Snipers may not have even been loose some historians say these are a bunch of
Gun-shy soldiers who've never faced
You live fire
Where someone was shooting at them
They may hear some German soldiers gun go off from the other side of town and start killing civilians
It's a very controversial issue
Some historians
Still foam at the mouth about a John Keegan strikes me as somebody who's
Who feels this absolute need to defend this idea
German
You know
Demolitionist
I have a couple of
Pieces I like the author Lynn McDonald
Wrote about this I thought you did a very balanced job
And so did Niall Ferguson and Ferguson
What I love about Ferguson says that he goes and finds like the original thing that happened and then how it got blown out
Portion
But nonetheless
All these people emphasize the same thing
Visa process
Japanese people died the German
Practice Collective punishment
And all these awful things that most
Most of us
Revival today
And then they paid an extra price for it by providing the basic seeds
It would grow into enemy propaganda that would turn the Germans into jangus Khan basic
Which is exactly what Lynn McDonald's
Compared to when she writes quote
In the United Kingdom Germany zahner had already been tried
And found guilty
Germany's name was mud
And now that she had condemned herself out of her own mouth no rumor of beastial outrage was too vile to be blue
They emanated mainly from the refugees
Who would flood have terrified out of their wits
From the towns and Villages of Belgium
They were the first hand accounts from people who had escaped
From the Flames of and then we're two hundred hostages
Gunshot wounds where 400 were gunned down in Bayonetta 2
And from the inhabitants of did not
Who would arouse the ire of the Germans by destroying the vital Bridge
The Germans Revenge was to round up more than 600 men women and children and shoot them In Cold Blood
The youngest age
Three weeks died in his mother's arms
These stories were true and the Germans made no attempt to keep them secret they were after all intended to war
Inevitably as they traveled they spawned fictions in their way
Of rape
McCobb chilling
Mutilation
Abreast in hands sliced off by Sabres
Crucifixion
A baby's dipped into boiling water or Swan for sport against brick walls
There were even Whispers of cannibalism
Springs of Truth swelled and grew into a crop of rumors
How about a speakable billineys unsurpassed since the hordes of djingis Khan had rampaged and pillaged across
Asia
In France and Britain the newspapers were full of
Public opinion Hardin
It was no longer merely a just War
It was positively righteous and people were out for blood
And quote
I don't think the Germans have recovered from that image
Even now have they
You talk about
A mist
What is the Germans had treated
Neutral countries
And non-combatants with more respect
How different might their reputation be today
What if they learn from Belgium in 1914 in reacted differently
In 1939
One thing's for sure this whole idea of frightfulness in order to cow you know the people that you had just subjected to
To the boots of your soldier taking workout
Bad policy
Foundations
And the underpinnings of that idea
You just didn't work in the people in charge it we're guys like fun Monica
Who said
Into his Austrian counterpart
Yeah you know it's brutal are advancing to Belgium's brutal
But what are you going to do you know we're fighting to save our lives basic
This is life-or-death
Going to be a little brutal for a while and guys like fun molta
He was one of these logical Insanity Guys somebody asked him once
What the most humane way to carry out War
And he famously said
Make it quick
Brutal as you want make it quick it's a robotic analogy Von moltke was basically saying knock them out
Quick Knockouts that the nicest you can be even if it's horribly brutal to make The Knockout as quick as it is
Sabon milk in this case is basically saying yeah.
It's terrible but
And in the end this is going to save lives
Can I use you hang a few of these saboteurs you shoot a few of these people that
Snipe at your troops and then they stopped doing it you don't have to burn whole Villages down see how that works
Niall Ferguson when he addresses the
This issue
Is basically sword
Telling us to not be so naive
We've all lived through and where the 21st century now we had a long time to absorb the ideas of 20th Cent
Century propaganda and how it's a legitimate aspect of warm one of the things you do
Is perhaps paint your adversary in the worst possible
You can again
Something that the Germans weren't
White getting when the 20th century was brand new
Did they would get much better in the second one
Ferguson and his book tells a story
Where he talks about
You know the ways in which this propaganda were used when he talks about how the British newspapers
Would take photos sometimes from stories and had nothing to do with this war in one case
Stories
With the head photos from Russian pogroms against Jews
What happened before the war and then just
You know captioning the photo with something
Says it's from this warm and no one had any idea show a bunch of dead civilians and say this is what the Germans are doing
Ferguson riots quote
But pre-war photographs of Russian pogroms genuinely were reprinted to
In quotes
Illustrate
Stories of German behavior in Belgium
The Sunday Chronicle he writes was one of many British paper
With your leg
But the Germans had cut off the hands of Belgian children while the former scaremonger William liqueur
Related with eldest guys relish the quote wild orgies in Blood and debauchery and
Quote in which the Germans allegedly indulge
Including the quote
Ruthless violation in killing of defenseless women
Girls and children of tender age and quote
Ferguson continued quote
Other writers had great fun imagining 16 year old girls being quote forced to drink
And quote and then quote violated successively and quote on the lawn before having their breasts
Quote pierced with bayonet
And quote
The Bayonetta baby Ferguson says was another favorite image
J h Morgan even threw in the charge of
Quote sodomy of little children and quote
But even Ferguson is forced to deal with the reality
The situation
That this stuff wasn't manufactured out of whole cloth
And it being a Belgium
In the in a line of German Advance during this time.
What's a very dangerous position to perhaps find yourself in and perhaps of no fault of your own
Ferguson riots quote
All the on Tom's press wildly exaggerated what went on in Belgium there is no question that the German army
Did commit atrocities there in 1914
According to evidence from the Diaries of German soldiers and other reliable sources
All the advancing German armies executed civilian
Including women and priest
Altogether about 5,500 Belgian civilians were deliberately killed by the German Army most of them in the leg
11 Day. From the 18th to the 28th of August 1914 and at least another five hundred in France
The Germans also use civilians as human Shields
And raised numerous villages to the ground
In one case an 18 year old girl was Bayonetta 2 death
There were also numerous rapes in occupied France
And
John Keegan
Who obviously
Feels very strongly about
About this goes out of his way to point out
That these are not
Minnesota
Ramshackle affairs
That these involve lots of troops sometimes that these
Executioner not done by special execution squads as will be the case in the second world war sometimes
But by regular units of the German Army he writes quote
The victims included children and women as well as men and the killings were systemic
Etta means the hostages were masked in the Square shut down by execution Squad and survivors bayonet
The execution squads were not
As worthy action groups of Hitler's Holocaust
Specially recruited Killers but ordinary German soldiers
Indeed those who murdered at and then we're the reservists of the most distinguished regiments of the Prussian Army
The guard regiment resume.
And quote
And the belgians would have
Every right you would think
When you to wonder as their living through this
Weather protectors
And they signed these agreements
It said
That their independence was guaranteed by the greatest powers of the age where are those people right now
Now when the belgians need them all days to hear the German Army marching through and burning things and perhaps shooting people you know
The answer is there on the way
The British
Are in the process right as we are in the story Landing troops on the continent
To Aid
The French War
Finishing the last
Bits of the necessary ingredients so they can launch an offensive
The Russians are shocking Everybody by putting together enough units to at least
Attack
Eastern Germany and remind the German that you
Eastern border undefended
Everything again
We're still here
And the austro-hungarian
Are about to find out
Exactly why the serbs have such a
Ferocious military reputation
All this is going to happen
Pretty much simultaneously
And it's going to be the first
Real
Consequential experiment
To test a hypothesis a sort of celestial if you want or Cosmic hypothesis
Concerning the question of whether or not
And if you do it in
You can beat the violin
Out of a
Society
Culture
People work
Given the
Globalization
And at this time.
Alsace-lorraine maybe world
And the answer is
But it depends on how hard you beat them
No one's been beating very hard yet in this
Story The belgians are
But an appetizer
What modern warfare is going to be like
Modern Warfare between the Great
Hours on the planet
At the first experiment in this
Hypothesis of beating the violence out of societies
Is on the way
If war is an addiction to the human species
What's about to happen is the first
Dos
Of shock therapy
To see if we can beat
Be sure to follow us on Twitter
The address
Is at hardcore
Do you want to help the podcasts we really appreciated here's how it works it's very simple just by your amazon.com products
Through the Amazon search window on dancarlin.com and Dan and Ben will get a percentage of what you spend
And it helps these guys out because they are nice young fellows
If you think the show you this hurt is worth a dollar Dan and Ben would love to have it
About to show it's all we ask
Go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
Get there firstest
With the most
I think that's
The phrase that made me cringe
During the editing process listening to the show you just heard
Because I could almost here
510 15001 how many average Civil War box American Civil War box we have listening
But that's going to be a sore point with them and I can tell when I listen to a during everything I'm just going to do I really want
All those emails
I didn't attribute that quote
2NE1
I just sent a Confederate Cavalry commander but it was
Supposedly allegedly legendarily said by a guy named Nathan bed
A controversial figure even today but that's not unusual among Confederate generals and it's not
Even unheard of among
Union Northern Jet
Forces may be in a Class by Himself
But he's not controversial when it comes to acknowledging his military genius he's one of the best American Jenner
Emerald in this hole.
In US history and he's an Innovative Calvary
He knows and is already absorbed the lesson
The most European Cavalry commanders even in the first world war when it breaks out that they haven't
Forest realizes that you can't use Cavalry the way it's traditionally been used
In a through its entire history
Free up until that point it's just
Do vulnerable now the weapons have destroyed
A lot of what Cavalry could do
The forest
Strip down
The job of Cavalry to the bare minimum what is it do that nothing else can do and
Moves people
Faster than anything else can do
So we used it for that
Essentially had an elite
Unit of mounted Infantry
And he would transport these people to vulnerable and important spots
Tactically important areas
Dismount amusem is infant breathing
Use horses to skedaddle out of there before Superior Force could
Catch you
The three modern way to use Cavalry and really the only way
Did he could survive on a modern battlefield of course the battlefield
Did Nathan Bedford Forrest was trying to keep his Cavalry live on
Nowhere near as deadly for anyone horses especially
At the battlefields would be in 9
Those battlefields are on the way the appetizers over the main course is about to
Begin
This greatest army in the world
Is about to run into what is probably the second greatest army in the world
Frances and
The
Probably in terms of
Bang for their buck
Most elite military force
Furious military force in the world all these Germans marching on France great
Train troops who never been in combat except against belgians
They going to run into a British colonial Force that's tiny
But that has
So much experience that there's almost no room for any more
Unit owners
Freddy's
Units cuz they fought in so many parts of the world so long and so often
They're not coming to this war
You have to learn on the job
They've already done this job many times they're going to be the only truly really experienced troops in this convo
Which will make them
To get back to our boxing metaphors
Able to punch above their weight
They're going to give a lot better than their small numbers
Probably indicate they would
But can anything stop this German Steamroller
You know
I've often been asked by people how large
The army that
Defended Imperial Rome was
And at its height
High number you usually see 750000 men
The entire Roman Empire that's not one army with the entire Roman Empire
Your total number of soldiers throughout the entire
Borders and interior the places
Maybe 750,000 guys
750000 guys is also the upper limit number as we said in the show that Napoleon
May have used in his famous
And
Forlorn invasion of Russia
So that's okay
Pretty big number
Just understand what's bearing down on the small British forces landed on the continent
And this French Force
Who's waiting to find out what modern warfare is really like
The low number is 750000 German
Just simply marching through Belgium
The high numbers one point
5 mil
And that doesn't even count the troops facing
The French along the traditional fortified hundred and twenty mile border that's normally The Invasion
You have the equivalent
Of the entire
Armed power
Of the Roman Empire
Attitude
Height
Using the Belgian Road system
The fall on Northeastern France
That's an amazing blog
What happens when
The irresistible Force
Anna runs into the immovable object
We'll find out if either one of those
Title
Turned out to be true
Impart to
A blueprint for Armageddon
Okay one last note
Added much later by the way
To let you know
Did the program you just heard is not identical to the version we originally
We did something with this program we've never done before cuz it's crazy hard for
What to do
And went back and actually sacrificed work on the next Hardcore History show to get into this one in and clear up one thing and
And fix another
To improve Clarity and accuracy actually
And hopefully
We have a better program out of it new and improved version 2.0 whatever you want to say
I wish I could do that with every program although as has been pointed out to me I'd still be working on show number 1 to get it quite right
If you folks if they would let me
Nonetheless always seeking to improve and hopefully with the update to this show
In a small way
We have
Thanks for