Today Show is sponsored by Audible
Get your first audiobook free when you start a 30-day trial just visit audible.com Carlin
Or text Carlin to 500 500 to get started
And listen for a change
What you're about to hear is part 2 of a multi-part series on the wars in Asia and the Pacific involve
The Imperial Japanese empire
And many other countries and Powers
If you enjoy contacts
And don't want to get too frustrated with me referring back to things we talked about earlier
Please feel free to listen to part 1 and catch up
You don't care about those things of course or if you've already heard
Part 1
Well please feel free to continue
And hopefully enjoy part 2
A supernova in the east
East
Its history
It's hardcore history
Why is Adolf Hitler and the Nazi
Broadcast
News
And updates
Of what they were doing
As part of the final solution while it was going on
Why didn't they announce to the world
Go to the Joseph Goebbels propaganda Ministry
We set up these industrial killing facilities but we'll work people to death first
If they're strong
Unexplained listen last month we killed a hundred thousand more these people and we won't stop till they're all gone
Why did they do that
Why didn't
Stalin
Get up there
Yelling shake his finger and threatened
The gulags and then explain what the gulag archipelago the whole system was
Starving to death working to death
Are they really education campaign
All you have to do is leave the country and come back for us to be suspicious enough that you've been corrupted to send you away I mean why did he get
Thursday this is what's going to happen to you if you don't stay in line
No one admitted it right
Why didn't the
Khmer Rouge take photographs as they wiped out the intellectual class of Cambodia
Because they thought people with glasses
Were intellectuals in the intellectuals were
Threat to their
New world that they were
We're creating where he was going to go live back on the landing
Why are there photos of that go check out
Killing Fields you know what you'll find
Artwork
Why didn't they
Take photos full color block them up and put them all around the town and send some to the foreign media out
What's 2
That's what an Assyrian king would have done back in the Iron Age
A guy likes inaka rib
Going to level a place like Babylon and then he's going to make sure everyone knows about it in detail
A good historian of that era will point out that a lot of what the Assyrians card
Into stone
Including another version of photos right artwork with comment
Terry and statement by the king
A lot of that stuff was
A quart
Style after
Another words it was
Whatever one would expect
Why you still see Egyptian fashions in the New Kingdom that look
You really familiar like
Egyptian fashion from the Old Kingdom
There's a style that becomes the style you use
But what does it say about you if V style you use
Is to announce the atrocities that you commit
And
As close as possible replicate them on the walls of your waiting room
In the embassies
While people wait to talk to the Assyrian ruler having senaka rib destroyed Babylon and wrote about it here is
The scribes record
The words of Sinatra being
Again this is a court style also
What a style
Sennacherib said of his leveling of one of the great cities maybe the greatest city of all time
If you started a top 100 list
Babylon
And he leveled Babylon
Pain in the six
Hundred
BCE by the way
Quote
Like the oncoming of a storm I broke loose and overwhelmed Like a Hurricane
With their corpses I filled the city Square
The city and its houses from its foundations to it stop
I destroyed
I devastated I burned with fire
The wall and outer wall temples and gods
Temple towers of brick in earth as many as there were
I raised and dump them into the garage shoe canal
Through the midst of that City I dug canals
I flooded it site with water and the Very foundations thereof I destroy
I made its destruction more complete than that by a flood
But in days to come on the side of that City and its temples in its Gods might not be remembered I completely blotted
Send it out with floods of water and made it like a meadow
And quote
All those later Kings
Probably trying to emulate
Badass of the mall I should Nasser Paul II
From Del couple centuries before that time
Turn the Lights you got to appreciate the Assyrians for owning it
And using it their foreign policy was based on scaring the hell out of
People
They want you to rebellon the best way to do that was to punish anyone who did Ravel
Horrible
Now that was more the style of the times in the Iron Age though one could see that not play
Find particularly well in the twentieth century but then let's ask why
If you were to make a list of all the
Genocides in attempted genocides atrocities war crimes and all these things
Fall broadly under that heading and involve enough people
How to make a list
Of the 20th and 21st centuries
How many of the
Let's just call them
Accused perpetrators of these acts
Admit to it
Own it
And if they do how many of them do so in an unqualified way because sometimes the evidence
Just so overwhelming
But even in denial is can't
Figure out how to wiggle out of
Of the facts
So they start rational
Say what the numbers are inflated
Or there's mitigating circumstance
Does or what have you
And here's what makes life so complicated
Sometimes they're right
If you look at the history of the twentieth century you will know that we start off relatively quickly with
Some of them were
Famous
Genocides are attempted genocide or alleged attempted genocide in history and we keep going from there
We have spent
More than a hundred years now is a global Society trying to
Codify rules and laws and courts of adjudication and systems in organizations
To help
Create
Rules about
Atrocities in war and genocide in killings
Crimes against humanity
You could create a timeline
Good start you start before the Hague convention some things like that but
What you go all the way through you know V the League of Nations creation you can get to the
United Nations creation you can get to the
Nuremberg and Tokyo trials there's there's all these sorts of things and now we have this
Xtensive body and many of these Global organizations created
In large part in reaction to horrible atrocities and genocides in things that must never happen again
And yet let me ask you what you think would happen
If it happened again
Indeed
Spent an enormous amount of time and human effort on a fantastic cause right
Let's never have a final solution for example happen again
What happened tomorrow
Of course if this is going to be some sort of analogy
We have to imagine it happens
Powerful state
Cabins in Albania
They'll be no problem the bombing will start the oil soon afterwards in the bean in Beijing
If it involves if this
Crime against humanity involves an important ethnic group that's in many countries are that many countries have an interest in this
Jewish jokes are an example of that then it's going to be different kind of situation if we're talking about a people that almost nobody
You really knows about in some Faraway place
And they're being persecuted by a powerful State the ramifications of confronting and it would not be like Albania
Be committing to some major stuff
Do you think we do anything different today if Holocaust number to start tomorrow
If it's China or Russia apologies to both those Nations but in their league
Powerful choices if I'm not going to choose my own state
Did they start killing a million or two million of some unpopular minority there that most of us in the rest of the world don't know a lot about
I don't have a whole lot of dog in that fight
How well are all these wonderful organization
We have created over
More than a hundred years
How well is this mechanism going to click into place and function to stop something like that
The people at the time get quite a bit of blame for not doing more to stop
Holocaust or
Atrocities that happened all throughout the second world war on
Many major fronts
But I think we sometimes forget how
How hard it is to do that we have many more mechanism
And
Tools at our disposal created
In many cases specifically for this purpose that I still think and remember I'm not a
I'm not cautiously optimistic personality-wise I'm cautiously pessimistic and that all hardcore cynical and pessimistic
But I'm mildly both
I think if the state is powerful enough
We could have
You know the weaker version of the final solution happen over the next year
And the world kind of sit around and look at each other most of the time going you know that's awesome sanctions maybe I mean what should we do
I bring that up because we're coming to a part in the story
Where it's let's call it a milestone or a potential Milestone on that time line that begins maybe you could
In the twentieth century keep going to now
Concerning these kinds of events and I mean look at your newspaper today
We still haven't figured out how to deal with this we just had some problems in the Middle East where everybody was going and how do we influence this humanitarian
Crisis
We had it when the former Yugoslavia broke up you had a genocide in Rwanda going on and everybody looking at each other thinking to themselves
What do we need to do here
Meanwhile you know the killings are everyday
And everybody sort of deliberating and everybody's got to
Considerate of Their Own
Personal country strategic interest and no realpolitik questions at all understandable
But it boils down to the same thing
If this is 1943 and this is how we're behaving
More Jewish people than Gypsies and homosexuals in Polish people and Priests are dying everyday
And yet what
A responsible speed
And what's a responsible level of fourth we can expect nation-states to employees situations like this
So as we
Ask ourselves that question and realize that the people in the in the pre Second World War era had less in the way of
Have tools and less in the way of structure
And probably less in the way of Leverage I mean we talked a nuclear weapons now which changed the game completely
And they're confronted with a similar sort of situation and by the way this is one we still deal with today and it is still
Controversial
And that's why I brought up the point about
Denial
Or minimization or rationalization when it comes to questions of
Atrocity
When last we spoke we were talking about the Battle of Shanghai
A little-known battle by the way in the west but it's participants like to point out
By the time it's done and it went on like 3 months something like that
You have as many dead on the Chinese side as either side kind of a little less I think but but
The Battle of Verdun in the first world war a historically nasty battle that went on longer
The strategy of the battle of Shanghai was influenced by global public opinion or a desire to influence
Global public
Opinion
Chiang Kai-shek in the Chinese wanted to prove that the Chinese to put up a fight against the Japanese and they wanted to
Send a message to the world
It were here we can resist if you want to help us it's a worthwhile investment and it's awful and you should help us
There were photographs making it to the global media stories accounts from Westin Shanghai head
Quite a lot of westerners in it
And so the
Chinese through in all their best unit
Stuff that they had
Stockpile for a long time in other words they were going to shoot off
All of their fireworks at once to make the biggest thing they could make and see if they could attract Global attention while they did so
The upside of this is they did the downside of this is when it's gone it's gone
I want the Japanese after several months of fighting
Launch an amphibious Invasion and open up another front on the city of Shanghai
That's the store
In terms of resist
Chinese resistance
Collapses they suffered a Brazilian casualties
They're out of stuff and they
Stream box
Sort of routing and trying to get their act together towards the capitol At Nanking
The Japanese are closed
On their heels
And as they chase them
An atrocity begins to occur now let me back up here be
Because
I was fascinated and yet I got pulled down the rabbit hole reading about the various
Interview on what history calls
Some people called the Rape of Nanking other people called the name King incident the Dan king of prosody
And the reason there are all these different
Name is because
Diversity of in fact
It's about as controversial as all those other genocides war crimes and atrocities
But you will see on your list if you made a timeline as I said from the start of the 20th century
Go to the people accused of the crime
Admit it
Branson to talk about
You'll find a percentage always at will
But most people reflexively get defensive
Let's understand this is a human thing
And let's understand just how widespread it is
Every now and then regularly
You will see a news story
Involving the Japanese
Education system
The story is always the same
The Japanese textbooks
Specifically the history textbook
Arnott
Are whitewashing is the way someone will be
Whitewashing downplaying
Covering up
Japanese atrocities during
Its aggressive. In the second world war pre Second World War era
Often times these complaints will come from people who suffered at the hands of Japanese aggression
China
The Philippines
The entire area around Malaysia I mean there's a bunch of places that were in the Japanese orbit for a
And those are often the people that get angry
When
Japanese atrocities are downplayed
The people that are sometimes the most angry
AR
The Americans who fought in that War veterans from
Australia
Canada
Great Britain
All these people want the Japanese to confront what they did
Here's the way I want to portrayed in human terms
We have similar
Textbook issues here in the United States and many other countries do to and they often revolve around history
For middle schoolers
Junior High School in high schoolers
The arguments are over how your own countries
Bad periods are portrayed
And in the United States we often have these
Controversies because
The
Nasty things that happened in the past are downplayed or sometimes exercise altogether
And the more patriotic good things are played up now the Japanese will often
Come back with a similar sort of response
How to make a political by both of the right-wing
Extra Patriot size of both countries actually have similar views about what they want portrayed in their textbooks
They want their people portrayed
Positively
Creating a sense of citizenship pride in your heritage
All that kind of stuff in appreciation for the things that make you happy
People special
And yet I do find it so ironic that if you went to the people in my country
You feel that way and ask them about Japanese textbooks
They would definitely want the Japanese in most cases to have to confront
Are these sorts of things right with the
Real Patriots in the United States are pretty
Aware of of Japanese conduct in the second world war against our troops and others and they want that shown
But if you then tried to put the shoe on the other foot and say okay in our own history books when we talkin about the Vietnam War
How much
Full color photography
And eyewitness account should we devote to something like the me Lai massacre
Most of you don't know about the me Lai massacre
Shame
1968 Vietnam War
American soldiers went into a
Hamlet or Village
And when they came out
302 550
The villagers men women and chill
Children were dead
The rapes occurred amoebas
Very very nasty
Very disillusioning
Infratech icon
Speak from experience from
In the end
Ten years after his Americans confronted the fact
That we were actually just like
Everyone else
We were not this special Lone Ranger coming to save the world in a couple of world wars rebuild it afterwards with the marsh
Plan defended during the Cold War I mean we were all those things too
But if you had said to American
People in the 30s or 40s that Americans would do a melee type thing
Anything we find it hard to believe I think with men in combat
Although you know I've only read it so
So take this one
But I think what they would say is
That in certain situations
Things can become very unpredictable
And when there is a lack
Strong leadership in those situations
They can become deadly
I'd like to draw a distinction between two kinds
Atrocities
You saw both kinds in the second world war by the
The way
And trying to link the two of them
Not only Twisted some of the post-war war crimes trials into knots
But affects us even today
The difference between a top-down atrocity
Of the sort for example that Hitler and the Nazis were doing with the final solution
The kind in Assyrian King
Would do for a Babylonian Final Solution a top-down order
And if you're the guy in the ground you're killing people and executing people and committing an atrocity because you ordered two
Or the kind that happens
Of the sort for example that the
Ancient Roman / Latin historian
Tacitus says happened during a Roman Civil War the city called cremona
This was a scandal so he wrote about it and he's almost eight
Contemporary
And the story basically goes
It is a story about troops
When they get their blood loss
Stop
And it reminds us that
You know people can be venal to enlarge group that can come out even
In a more pronounced the way what made from Moana so terrible
Is it's a stacking of the city which is what the destruction of Babylon was and what the destruction of the city of Nanjing is
Going to be
That would be named King
Back in the second World War
The sacking of a city
And tacitus says
That these soldiers
Wanted to sack the city
Did they were worried that the city would surrender and if it surrendered to their Commander the Roman general will then he
Got The Spoils of the army
Tacitus says
And he was a veteran
By the way
Really wanted the city to not surrender so they could loot it
The city did Sir
It was a Roman city by the way and the citizens in it
Where Roman
The Roman army outside the city still wanted to loot the city
So they did
For several days
The account is one of the really wicked
Accounts in the ancient world
And it's funny though
Because
If you took out the
Particulars
It would probably work
As a
Reasonable description of
Sackings of cities
In human history
Tacitus wrote
Destruction of cremona
A Roman city by Roman soldiers after surrendering
He just quote
40000 armed men forced their way into the city
Neither rank nor years
Save the victims from an indiscriminate orgy
In which rape alternated with murder and murder with rape
Greybeards and frail old women who had no value is loot wear dragged off to raise a laugh
But any full grown girl are good-looking lad who cross their path
Was pulled this way and that in a violent tug of war between the would-be captors
A single Lueder trailing a horde of money or Temple offerings of massive gold was often cut to Pieces by others
Stronger
In their hands they held firebrands which ones they got their spoil away they wantonly flung into empty houses and
Rifle temples
There was a diversity of wild desires different conceptions of what was lawful and nothing bard
Kimono last
4 days
And quote
We would be mistaken
Thinking that this is something particularly Roman or particularly ancient
There's something that goes on
In certain situations and you can reliably see it again and again
In
December
You see it in Nanking
Nanking though is so much
Much harder
To deal with
Then something like
Gate from Moana
Or the Iron Age destruction of Babylon because
It's still a white-hot it's incandescence
In terms of
How passionate and upset and how
Visceral the argument over
Can get people get death threats
Regularly
What are the books like
For the subject
Post all of the research
On the website for the shows
Encourage you to buy these
If you like this stuff some of the Nanking stuff is positively Kennedy assassination asked
In terms of the minutiae.
Detail a big Point spinoff and revolver
A lot of people love that stuff in and reading it
I one of them grapes
Nanking atrocity 1937-38
Complicating the picture
Has different Scholars writing each chapter from a wide
Arranger people and one of the things that the Japanese editor of the book said in the introduction is that several of the contributors
It had their lives threat
Some of them face-to-face for
Their writings research
Teaching and lectures
Don't have a whole lot of people
Threatening to bash your head in
Reviews on rimowa
Do you know
I'll give you an example of
Problem
History fan faces trying to talk about this
If you wanted to make a graph of
Of opinions on what the death toll is in Nanjing in December
And onward for months
On one side of the spectrum you have the Japanese people who fall into the
Plastic
Are known as the
Deniers
To consider everything
We're going to talk about here.
To be an illusion
Caused by
Combination of
Contemporary wartime propaganda
And a lot of marxist stuff especially by leftist Japanese marks his teachers were
Polluting the minds of their own children I mean
It's a super Patriot Point of View with a tinge of conspiracy that would probably resonate in a budget
Countries
With the same group
They're probably all
Actually
We said in
The earlier conversation that like
The Jewish folks that this
Phrase was originally applied to
The Japanese really intense there like everybody else
Only more so we're just like anybody
And I think you see it in the passions here to when people get subs
Upset about
You know besmirching the reputation of the Imperial Japanese Army and the country
Patriots will do especially if they don't think it's deserted the people
On one side of the spectrum here
Will claim that
Maybe 45 people
Died
In this Nanking thing in those may have been Justified one way or
Now on the far opposite end of the scale in the Spectrum
You have Chinese history
Chinese official government lie
They've actually cargain number their number
Into a rock
I saw a picture of
It's a little like you know proverbially
Carving it into stone
And the attempts to create it's pretty clear
A number that has the same sort of intellectual residents with
The global population that the six
Million number has for the
Holocaust
Everybody knows 6000000 okay where you come up with that number
Nobody knows
What you come up with a nice round number and eventually people go yellow Holocaust
The Chinese are trying to do
This
With the Nanking at Ross
And the number that they settled on his 300 thousand
Dad
And there are Chinese historians and let's acknowledge your maybe not operating with
Complete freedom in terms of
Historical
Whatever it takes
But there a Chinese history as it will bump that number up
Considerably
The 350000 range is not on her
Kuykendahl
If you want to go to Crazy Town
Find the very end of the spectrum with the largest number you've ever seen my fiance enlarge
$500
So happy
Not credible but that
45 is not credible either on the other
On that scale
Are a bunch of different
Gradients of people
And their views on this subject that's why it's really difficult to talk about because
It's not just an it didn't happen yes it did thing it's
Will Surety but it only happened here or yes it did but it only happen to these people it's just the lawyer Lee break
Down over the geographical boundary
Where someone who dies in this
No quadrant
How to say
Nanking atrocity casualty
As someone who dies outside that quadrant doesn't mean it gets silly light
God the Chinese historians point out
And supposedly this is why China didn't make a huge deal
Specifically over the Nanking situation in the first few decades after
The war
Was because this was more par for the course then not
And part of the way you get some of these really large number account
Is the Chinese historian sometimes include
These soldiers from the Battle of Shanghai who died
In part because the Japanese troops who took their surrender or who captured them or who found them
Wounded on the battlefield
Executed them there
This is another part of the
Gradient in the
Discussion right who do you count
If you were talking about Soldier
Do they count in the atrocity
Will what if you kill them after they surrendered as I said
A bunch of different people have different
Opinions along the Spectre
Now if you're looking for a mid-range to try to
Get sort of a little ballast on this question
A lot of the mainstream
Historians will range from like a hundred thousand to 250,000 dead and that is a huge number
No matter which it is
The other question that always comes up in a case like this in this is connected
To the Nazi situation in Europe
Buddy's
Who's response
Where does the responsibility lie
Because
You will often hear these situations and sometimes it's valid
Compared to the sacking of cremona where you have troops
Your loss of institutional control maybe on the part of the leaders
Or
Callous disregard for the plight of people you know that your lower level troops were just spoiling whatever it might be
Some people make the case that all of this
Is premeditated might as well have been naughty stuff
And once again we could divide it into
Separating soul
Civilians
But there's an interesting little bridge between the two
And that's
Soldiers who dress up
Acivill
Now before we get into this
Entitled to know
How I come to my thinking
King and if anything might on
Tumi
My normal approach is to put myself in other people's viewpoints
To try to see their perspective
But trying to see the perspective
Of the side that thinks there's 45 or a hundred or two hundred deaths here in there
Explain away a bullet
Feels like trying to
Ba
Defender of a holocaust
Denier it's a really did
For me to put myself
I think you should point it out if I had to have a very hard time
Putting myself even
If you were in debating class me so you have to take this person
Forgiven Defender
I am usually
Open-minded enough
Keep a lot of Doubt open though depending on the other circumstances involved for example
If this was a very unusual inside
In the second sino-japanese war or the second World War I think I'd be inclined to say listen wartime propaganda I mean those
People might have a point
The problem is
Is that
The Japanese Army and Navy to a degree with the Army certainly
Is a repeat offender
In this war
But this I know
Japanese 1 and II world
The Second World War
Depend a lot of people when I was a kid I always started it with the invasion of Poland
But since then there's a lot of opinion has shifted in such a really 1937 this
The Japanese are in the world
World War II
The other
Powers just
Armenia
Chinese and Japanese
Starting the Second World War
And in this case
The Japanese will behave toward the Chinese
Atrociously
And you have to really write off a ton of avid
Including your own
Soldiers and commanders Diaries
If you want to explain it away
You also have to deal
With the
Your remembrances of combat veterans
From pretty much every Power
That fought the Japanese in the Second World War
Where atrocious Behavior
And a certain brutal level of conduct
Was always remark
And that's after you factor out racism and hatred of the enemy who killed your buddies and all that other stuff
There's a ton of evidence
And the questions over wide what's going on here been ongoing
Any sort of
In a smaller way parallel the ones going on after the second world war with the Nazis where you have things like the Milgram experiment
These are the things where people were trying to figure out listen
How do you get people to turn off their moral
We all be naughty
Trying to figure out
Motivations and how you do that I mean in the
Second world war in afterwards and let's remember
The Japanese public new
Very little
Love this stuff
Although some of the stuff that they did know and sort of celebrate is once again a little weird by Western standards for example
There's a famous incident Nanking where two soldiers
We're having supposedly this is in the Japanese news media
Contest
A Chinese head chopping contest
And the
Talley was being kept score regularly in the newspaper you know this this guy is up to 75 now
He heads today by the other guy he takes the lead
And it was always used as evidence of
You know you're looking for a sign that this brutality happen will my good if they were celebrating in Japan's newspapers
Turns out most
Mange
Excuse me but you know what I mean
Historians of Ivan reading suggests that that
Never happen
And that it was a figment
Of the presses desire to whip up an interesting story that got people reading which
Did
It does of course beg the question
About an audience who thought that that was worth
But there have been
Speculations
Forever and the early ones during the war we're always going to racist in culture with this is how the Japanese are
Since then there's been a lot of interesting ones including one from Japan and just to give you an idea one of them will talk about the brutality
In the Japanese Army wear of
Apparently
Being punched in the face
Hard with a closed fist by your Superior was not uncommon
And there's plenty of
Reports about
People having
To commit executions
Woody
Killing of pows as part of a sort of blood in you
What's a very old-fashioned idea
Once again a lot of the things that Japanese were going to be in trouble for in the Second World War
Are things that people didn't even
Bat an eyelash
500 years ago
500 years ago they would have known that ever happened outside of a very close geographical area
That's another thing that's different about Nan
There's telegraph's there
There's embassies there's westerners
There is
Us and British
Boats
Chips
In the Yangtze River
The real world outside this area
Is going to hear about what's happening inside Nanking and they're going to hear about it while it's going on
It's a Thoroughly Modern situation
That we have seen over and over
Senseware
There will be some terrible atrocity
Crisis
Humanitarian disaster genocide
War crime going on somewhere in the world and unfolding in real time
And all the great powers are kind of under the gun at that point
When everybody says my goodness something has to be done or more people will die
But the world global geopolitical Powers rarely react
At speed on these kind of things
But it's been a little bit of an unsolvable problem
You see it in Nanjing for sure because what's going to happen there will unfold over a
A period of weeks
The world will be put into a moral quandary
3 / what to do
So picking up the story after the battle of Shanghai
The Chinese forces Retreat toward the cap
Nanjing
Nanking
840 hundred fifty miles west of Shanghai
And during the retreat the Japanese lead elements are trying to surround the Chinese
This is a
A flight with the Japanese in Hot Pursuit
There are also civilians along the path there are aircraft
Strafing and bombing the roads
You get this sense of
Chaos and Bedlam and claustrophobia and panic and
You know I've seen them
You seen war footage since that time that you really get a sense
And the camera gives you a very good sense
A combination of things that must have been working on these people to
The fluidity of the situation right everything is moving quickly
And you're in the middle of it
And also a complete lack of knowledge about what's going on outside your field of vision or whatever the person next to
You can say
The combination of those two things
Is panic inducing
So imagine the sort of a bedlam
Aziz
Is this line of humanity pursued by the Japanese
Runs toward Nanking
The Japanese arrived close on their heels and mostly surround the city and on December 9th
They're outside this walled city of Nanking it looks like a sort of a European medieval
Evil city
Demanding it surrender
There is a Chinese General in command of a hastily thrown together but relatively you know it's China large
Number of soldiers
Are some of them green
Some of them old and reservists
Some of them from the battle that just was over in Shanghai and there
Not fair they don't have their weapons there may be defeatist I mean it's a it's a
It's a bit of a Motley Crew but they're going to defend the city
Seoul for 4 days
They hold out before that general orders a retreat
He leaves the government
Leaves and you have now a city
With hundreds of thousands of people including refugees that's being bombed
And no governmental services or anyone in charge of the Japanese have yet to take over
And it's one of the great stories by the way
Of this
Cities
Plight and that's that there were a group of westerners
In the city most most of the western ran away as soon as the Japanese Army came
But a bunch of different people businessmen and others humanitarias doctors
Stayed
And they weren't
There to take care of all these people but when that
Fell into their lap
They stepped up to do it
There's a little ironic
Twist to the story two and they recently made a movie
Out of basically I almost playing on that
Twist and it's that the guy that was sort of elected by this you add hot group
To be the leader
What's a Nazi
An Ardent Nazi is the sources described him a businessman John rabe
And part of the reason he gets the gig is because the Japanese government and the Nazi German government have been moving closer together
And maybe he has a little bit more pole with the Japanese are just about to take over the city then maybe a British
For American or
I give her the Danish guy maybe they don't have as much pulso this guy gets the gig
And the movie I saw the tagline you know
Of the preview and I think it said something like you can be saved 250,000 live
And you see scenes of him
With huddle Chinese refugees and he hides them from aircraft under a giant swastika flag so they're sort of that
That playing with the idea that here you have the evil Nazis and yet there's a good person mixed in
Juxtaposition
You can hang whole movie
Iman
I don't know about 250000 lives in terms of the number
I do know that this is 20 or 30 people there's women in the group
Eye doctors ministers business men
And they save it
Enough people
And it's in large part
Because of the documents that they sent
Or the information that they kept track of
Do we have a lot of these account
And when I wanted to spend 3 hours on it I was going to go through all of the letters let me encourage you to
You get another book if
You're interested in one of the few I've ever read
This should be dry as a bone but it's actually in its own way terrifying because it's it's
Chronological
Primary source
The cables in the telegram and the letters and the
Please from these people John Robin all these people who make up
The Nanking International safety zone
Pope says it's called and you can read everyday
These letters getting more
Beseeching more terrified more outraged
As the situation descends into
Monsters chaos
On December 13th the Japanese and turn and
There's a letter from John Rabe saying thank you so much for not
Selling our little International safety zone that we created which by the way is nothing more than a part of the city blocked off
And on the sides of the streets were the borders they put international Flags
I think it was December 1st at the Nanking mayor before fleeing the city tells all the civilians to run into the safety zone
You'll be safe there
Which allows the Japanese to then say that anybody who's not in the safety zone is
Ipso facto a bad guy
And what begins to happen right away
Is the Japanese start searching for Chinese soldiers
Because there is as we said a lot of
Another part of the atrocity here is if you are a Defender basically
The Japanese Army in this
Case do you count the killing of Chinese soldiers as a war crime in officially there's no question but
That allows some people to divert you and say what we admit that these people who died Were Soldiers
But I denied the civilian side
In this case what happens is there's a river with the Yangtze that runs behind
Nanking if you look at it it's it it
In order for Chinese troops to get out of Nanking and get away from the oncoming Japanese they would have to cross the river
Going to go over to the more Chinese side and keep going
Normally not a problem but of course you know they were trying to create a defensive Zone before the Japanese invaded blowing up
The bridges and everything that would allow
The Chinese to get away too and now they have to so there are these heroin stories
Of Chinese troops just
At the riverbank waiting a thousands and thousands of people waiting for one little boat that can carry three people look like a canoe
Across the river
And the Japanese are on the way and if there's one group of people that knows
That the Japanese are not taking Chinese prisoners of Chinese soldiers
So distance of
Panic is
Palpable
And I'll let me turn to some of the sources now
And I have a wide mix
Of them
And my apologies I said I'd like to do three hours and
I'd like to just read the document
To you because there are several there like police blotter reports where they're trying to tell the Japanese Commander at this hour
This woman was raped over here and the Japanese soldier spilled her sugar I mean it's literally like police reports but it's it's
All I can think of what I was reading it
Is how unusual it was to have something like this
And if you could have had a similar document it would apply equally well to the sack of Carthage by the Romans you know it ain't
I mean
This is a modern day
Account
Of something you just don't get a whole lot of but that's happened a lot of times in history
Seems woefully out of
Place in time though
Here's the way
Fujiwara Acura contributor to
The Nanking atrocity complicating the picture
Said that the attack on Nanking was out of control from the start
With all sorts of units that were
Glory hungry and wanted to be the first inside the city and
There's a sense of out-of-control troops such as the Battle of cremona would that psychology going on
So here we get another gradient
In the
Responsibility spectrum that we've been talkin
Do you blame
Japan for what's about to happen here no it was a bunch of out-of-control troops in some ways it was
Akira rights
About
The Japanese units finding out
On December 13th that the Chinese were retreating and leaving and trying to get away
Japanese units learned of this Retreat on the morning of the 13th
Skirmishes broke out in many areas of small groups of Chinese troops outside the city
Now lacking a chain of command
Desperately try to slip past advancing Japanese forces
Then the surrendering big
Most of the Chinese troops still inside Nanking rushed to escape Helter Skelter
Through the pot chain gate
Which led to the shock Juan Warfare
I'm shocked when they hope to cross the Yangtze by boat
Buy raft we're by clinging desperately to scraps of lumber
Play madly ran up and down the river Bay
Only to encounter Japanese forces sent to cut them off
Huge numbers of Chinese troops became prisoners of War on the 13th and 14th that shot Quan
Movie Sean
Change Wingate and Michelle hoggatt
With no Avenue of Escape Chinese soldiers lost all will to fight
Despite trying to surrender in drone
Most were killed in the pell-mell of battle
And quote
Ethan quotes
From the Diaries
From December 13th 1937
Of two Japanese commanders 16th division commander and 30th Brigade Commander
These are primary source.
Lights and
16th division Commander Nakajima
Casacos diary rights
Quote
We see prisoners everywhere
So many that there's no way we can deal with them
The general policy is
Accept no prisoners
So we ended up having to take care of them lot Stock and Barrel
But they came in hordes
And units of thousands or five thousand
So we couldn't even disarm them
Later I heard that the Sasaki unit alone dispose of about 1500
A company Commander guarding typing gate took care of another 1300
Another 7000 8000 clustered at the Chino gate are still surrendering
We need a really huge ditch to handle those 7000 8000
But we can't find one
So someone suggested this plan
Now quoting someone else's plan
Divide them up into groups of a hundred to two hundred and then lured them to some suitable spot for finishing off
And quote
30th Brigade Commander major-general Sasaki
Lychee
Wrote in his diary on the 13th of December quote
The number of abandoned enemy bodies in our area today with 10000 plus thousands more
If we include those Chinese whose Escape rafts for boats on the Yangtze were sunk by fire from our armored car
Cars Plus pows killed by our units
Our Detachment alone must have taken care of over 20,000 we finished the mop up and secured are rear area in about
2 p.m.
What regrouping we advance to the hoping gate
Later the enemy surrendered in the thousand
Frenzy troops rebuffing efforts by superiors to restrain them
Finished off those pows one after another
Even if they aren't soldiers for example Medics are priests
Men would yell
Kill the whole damn lot
After recalling the past 10 days of bloody fighting image so many buddies that shed so much blood
And quote
So right there you see
Another one of those lines but some people take which is
The
Superior tried to restrain them but their buddies were killed and they were
Understandably upset enough to commit atrocities
There's also a ton of evidence.
That there was a take-no-prisoners policy
Historian Herbert P Bix
In his book on Hirohito is
Pulitzer prize-winning book on Hirohito
Writes this
Quote
There were no orders to rape in quotes
Nanking
Norton Imperial headquarters ever order the total extermination of the enemy as the ultimate goal of the Nanking encirclement cam
Pain
Standing orders to take no prisoners did exist however
And once Nanking fell
Japanese soldiers began to execute and Max
Military prisoners of war and unarmed deserters who had surrendered
They also went on an unprecedented an unplanned Rampage of arson
Pillage murder and rape
The resulting Slaughter continued in the city and it's six of Jason rural Villages for 3 months
And far exceeded earlier atrocities committed during the Battle of Shanghai and along the Escape Routes to Nanking
General Nakajima 16th division in just its first day in the capital killed approximately 30000
Chinese prisoners of war and fleeing soldiers
And quote
There were charges that these orders to kill all prisoners come from the highest up on the scene
Which by the 13th I believe is the Emperor hirohito's uncle
There will be an execution or two after the war
For what goes on in this city but trying to figure out who's responsible for it has been an ongoing
Part of the debate
How high up the food chain do you blame them
What it really seems to be is this combination of two things
A
Ordered War crime from
The Western perspective the killing of surrendering
Or captured pows cuz after all
You go look at the Soviet Union
And the number of prisoners that fell into German hands after the June 1941 Invasion there and you'll never have these giant
Castle Schloss
These cauldron battles and they
Capture 250000 people at a time
Any of these photographs of huge crowds of people are long column stretching off into the distance kicking up tons of Dustin
I'm trying to figure out how do we how do we barbwire these people in a pan and keep them and then how do we feed him
Didn't see any of that
In
This part of the war
Between China and Japan
Cuz they're not taken prisoner
And nobody knows that better than the Chinese
Troops
So
This sense of panic that's going on in the city
I was trying to think of an analogy
It's a little like
You're getting a hundred thousand or more people in the soccer stadium and then having somebody tell you over the public-address speaker
That the doors out have been barred
An armed gunman are coming in to kill all
Hundred or hundred fifty thousand people in the stadium
And what is the mood like that
Well
If it's
Panic-stricken that would be understandable
And this is when
Incidence begin happening in the story
Dipa come
Hinge moment
We were talking about communicable diseases or an epidemic this is when it jumps species
From
Nearly affecting
The soldiers
And now affecting
The civilian
Because in their panic and quite understandably so
A lot of these Chinese troops an undetermined number these Chinese troops
I going to throw off their uniforms and throw their weapons away
Addressing any civilian clothing they can find
They may be added in this by the population because after all
This is a Chinese City
And these are Chinese troops
But the Japanese start
Looking
Chinese troops that have thrown away their uniforms in address to civilians
And they start
Taking people out of crowds
Many of whom are civilians and executing them
And then you have
The part of the story
It just takes this to unbelievable
Crazy levels which is what starts to happen
The civilians and this is where it looks like from Moana
Because
You have and it starts if you read the primary source material it starts on the 13th and you start to get these
These requests can you please put more
Military police officers out on the street because the soldiers are out
How to control
The main thing they're out of control with although there's a lot of looting
Is rape
Bandits
Crazy to read as I said I want to do 3 hours on this and just go
Go from one police blotter account to another because it gives you a real-time anyway sense of what's going on all over
For the Nanking International safety zone
Where they were getting more than a thousand reports of rape tonight as one
Of the
Humanitarians working there said the Japanese have turned the international safety zone into a public house meaning a whorehouse
And they were often
Chilling
The women that they rape kits
It's worth
Giving an account
From the victor
The Chinese sign
And in one of the books that I have nanking 1937 memory and healing
They have a Chinese story who's giving
What is the recognized Chinese view of this thing and he pulls no punches
He wants you to know
How nasty
You.
And a person who says they're only 45 people who died in this whole incident would call the Chinese a liar or their government a bunch of people
Just wanted to hold this over Japan's head but here's
What Chinese historian
Sunshine away
Shed Happens
Quote
In general the massacre itself can be divided into two types of killings
Mass killings and sporadic killing
Incidence of mass killing range for the murder of 10 to 20 to the slaughter of tens of thousands of people
With the greatest number in anyone into the reaching more than 50,000
Sporadic killing included varying numbers of 328 people
Among the mass killings in addition to those who died by the sword and firing squad
Others were burned
Buried alive or drown
Several after being soaked with gasoline we're set on fire by gunshot
Causing the wounded person to lie covered in Flames rolling and writhing on the ground until finally dying a miserable death
Individual sporadic acts of torture and killing included
Gutting
Slicing
Piercing alive
And dog biting
Summer even burned with acid and then left burning all over
Others were tortured to death
Do Japanese Lieutenant amuse themselves by having a killing contest
The first one to reach a hundred killed one the
Game
Then they raise the limit to 150
In addition to killing
The Nanking massacre also involved rape
Arson
Theft and other violent crimes
The Japanese troops to attack Nanking rape tens of thousands of Chinese women
Many of whom were then murdered
And quote
Anytime I find my
Thinking
That those numbers
The Chinese
Historians
Way too large
I recall that according to tacitus the Roman legionaries completely
Picked cremona clean
4 days
Nanjing is going to
Continue
4 months
How much evil
Do
In Italian frame like that
Admittedly
They're not
Ripping Nanking apart with
Quite the efficiency or capacity of the Romans were ripping cremona
Apart
But if you've got months to do it
I imagine
Pretty thorough
Now if you say that
That we have spent
Too much time
Focusing on a single mattress
When we talkin about
I'm fixing to go on to 1945
I would agree with
Except that we're not going to stay
A lot of time
Necessarily on all the atrocities
Between now and the end of the war that deserve
What's more
You look at the raw death
Totals
The Chinese
Between 1937 and 1945 alone
And if you include the indirect
Causes of death because of the war things like family disease your numbers get
To the 15
And 20 million people level
You want to go just with directly
Caused by violence
It gets down to maybe 12 million in a lot of sources 12 million
In 2/3 of which by the way
Are civilian
Where are their stories
Most of those people die
Individual
What suffering
Are killed in small out-of-the-way villages
Hamlet
Who speaks for them
Let's let
The relatively and comparatively well attested to situation in Nanking allegations if you return
Fire but still
Well attested to allegations in the worst case in
Mario let's let those speak for all those other
Spooky stories didn't make
The second reason to focus perhaps
Inordinate
Atrocity
Like Nanking
Is that it's one of a bunch of
Pre-war atrocity
These will continue by the way during the conflict
As well
The scene to set up
Dussehra
Where you have these brutal
Totalitarian type armies
At least the way the Western liberal democracies look at the
Things that seem to be on the March and they seem to be the bad guys in the store
Bad guys isn't interesting
Because in most wars especially all the recent ones
I can get into the
The newspaper accounts
The stuff like that
Pretty common to portray one dad
Dysentery
In almost
Apocalyptically evil
In the first world war the Germans were
Call the Hun
Because hands were about the nastiest thing
British propaganda and others could think of in Terms
Slapping a label on them
And they
Helped out all they could on the German side by
Doing things that have been named the rape of Belgium and stuff
At the time shocking the genteel 19th century Sensibility
Let the record show
How exponential
That can grow
Ona near generation B
Because
The outrage over the
The rape of Belgium
Involved about 6000
People killed directly maybe though
The modern numbers
And we've already
We talked about what
Numbers are
In China
It's worth pointing out
If you take standard numbers for both world wars and
Compare them
Look at the difference in the ratio of
Civilian to
Casualties in the first world war standard number you
4 soldiers kill
10 million feet
About 7 million civilian
Estimated
In the Second World War
More like 20 to 25 million
In military
3 deaths and more like 35
Million civilians
So
Several times more civilian deaths
In the Second World War
Less civilian death
In the first
And that's the part that by the standards of Mo
Was war crimes
Or just individual perception
Makes the second world war so much more atrocious
A lot of
People are willing to
Forgive
All sorts
Nastiness
12 soldiers
Women children old pee
People the infirmed the sick the non-combat
It's much more harrowing in shock
Walking when there
Chilled and here's the problem with the good ending
Do you think
At the Japanese
Teaching their kids
That they were on the
Evil side of
This war the way the Western Democratic textbooks
Can the frame
The Japanese side of this
Obviously the Germans are
Sauron
But the Japanese are
One of the
Powers that work with sore on the rim
The easterners one of those people
One reason is that
Countries like China have problems with Japan's Tech
Focusing their minds they're not confronting this fact it wait a minute
Let's acknowledge you were the evil side of the
This war
Good and evil is a strange thing though is that I had to think about this
For a while
Because
Who says
A particular behavior is evil
You go talk to djingis Khan about Good and Evil in the 13th century
From the Mongol point of view and he may have a point
A different interpretation
Of what constitutes one of the either write this is a perception thing
If the Nazis had somehow won the war
And we were all having our
Concepts of
Good and Evil
Warframe
Under that regime
How different do
On. For example
That the Fairmont
Carried out on Hitler's orders in the East after they invaded the Soviet Union and it was this you know No Holds Barred
All law thrown out the window kind of conflict
How different is that look you think the Germans
Were the Nazis
Cuz it might be a
Pan Nordic
Sort of
Empire
Do you think they frame that and good and evil terms and if they do
You think they're framing their side is evil
Perception thing is hard to get past isn't it
Because
From
The perspective of
Someone who grew up in what
The post-war history books always called the Great liberal democracies
The Western democracies
You have
Concentration camps
They're being used as genocide Factory assembly lines
You pretty much
Buy our value system states that where you are
On the good evil side of the Divide
Pretty clearly
The Japanese had something
It reminds you of some of the Nazi
Medical science
I put that in
Caesar quotes on their Unit 731 it was
Was called in Manchuria in northern China
The conductivity
Experiments on human
Vivisection
You know you infected
Fleas with bubonic plague
Dropped them by air over Chinese cities and recorded the data
Evil stuff like that
From our Western liberal
Enlightenment era
Face value
Are you system
That's unrepentant
Now if you take yourself out of those shoes though I went and read the
Anyone should
That the people who defend other points of view on
Let's make
Usually
If they don't just deny
The information outro
The deniers of the Nanking atrocity or of the Holocaust do
They will say yes but
Yes we did these things and people are terrible but
You did Terrible Things
Things that are often not
Admitted to or accepted
By the liberal Democratic post-enlightenment side of this thing for example
Strategic bombing
You talk to people in
In Japan
Germany
Live
The reality of their cities being bombed by sometimes
Hundreds of aircraft
Sometimes multiple times sometimes with atomic bombs
And they have an interesting perspective on it
I'll never forget one of them saying to me
If the same results had been achieved the old-fashioned way you'd come in here
And done with bayonet
The functional equivalent of what you did with bombs from a distance
How does it look bad
Hard to get over the idea it looks a little like Nanking
Doesn't it
Here's the thing
You go to someone on the British
And two things though that were
On the receiving end of the Blitz the
Luftwaffe was bombing
Of London
And Britain
Instead of saying yes that's how we felt too you'll often hear them say
Pinotage
You started it
What you got back
That was reaping what you sow
And that's an interesting argument in
Kind of understandable in human terms used the problem
There's always been an implication that the people that are being bombed somehow
Deserve it
And I will try to remind myself
Mike Hunt
Country ever got into a war with someone else
And I got bombed by them
Would I somehow think I deserved it because of
The row line
I played
And supporting my country's policies or supporting my country
Or would I think that I was
Person caught in the gears of History
But I had little control over what really high
And there's really no good
Home to fall on me
The other argument
You will sometimes get
Sometimes from other Asian
People sometimes other Asian people who were also victims of the Japanese
Is they will bring it in
The question of colonialism
And they will say something like
Sure the Western democracies were on their good behavior and did relatively well in terms of controlling the troops
Behaving
Well militarily speaking during this conflict
But look at the situation after the conflict and more importantly look at the situation before head with
Centuries of colonialism add up all that stuff and all those evils and put them on the balance scale to Shirley
The Japanese were terrible
But let's not pretend that we're only tok
Talking about the second world war here when we're adding up who's been terrible to home win
This is about walking a mile in the other
Moccasins
It's important to can
It is worth
Pointing out
And many
Be here in the way
Westwood
That the
Terrible things done as part of the effort
For 2
When the Second World War
Comes after these sorts of integer
We're discussing here and maybe our
Necessary
Because of the kind of Internet
Since we're talking about
That's why we spent so much time
Nanking
Atrocity
Because it's hardly the only thing going on
This would be any
Inappropriate
Find a Zumba
Read the story
Keep one part of your peripheral vision always
On China though
Because
The Japanese biggest fear
I'm getting bogged down in an endless war in China is going to come true we compared it to an addiction
They're fully addicted they don't know how to get out
And the more they conquer
The worst their troubles are
When the atomic bombs are dropped at the end of the war
The Japanese are still bogged down in China
I have this weird
Upside down backwards Mirror Image Funhouse sort of
View
Of the
Strategic situation facing the Japanese in China
It's like this weird turn around the United States
Strategic dilemma
In the Vietnam War
Be there you had this giant Continental power the US
Bog down and unable to extricate itself
With any sort of these terms they can live with
In a
Place
You say roughly just being vaguely the size of something I
California
The Japanese
In
The Chinese version of this
They're more like the size of California and they're bogged down in the Guerrilla war and not always a guerrilla War
In a continental landmass the size of the US
The first thing I'm thinking about if I'm in the Japanese leadership is
I don't want any more trouble
With anyone else
I'm busy
And the Japanese will continue to conquer
City after city after City they will
Call the railway lines to connect these cities cities
And the Chinese can just keep moving their Capital as far away as they need to go to be out of the Japanese
In a range of the bombs all the way
They do fall on
The Chinese capital
From time to time
And the countryside is infested with
Nationalist Army is communist Army
Gorillas and surgeons warlord troops Bandits
And there will be
Hundreds of thousands usually close to a million
Japanese troops some of their best forces to
All requiring supplies all the time
In this theater for the entire War
As we said
We have to zoom out
At this point in the story because events elsewhere in the world are going to have more of an effect
On what happens in this part of the
World
Then anything that's happening in this part of the world I mean for example as as the Europeans began to slide.
Toward the second world war the Japanese are watching
And is that war breaks out and gets underway
They're paying attention to the results and reacting accordingly in other words like many powers
They're trying to read the lay of the land
And if the second world war will break out the lay of the land going to change
Quickly
Tough to know
Which horse to bet on when things are so fluid
The 1930s as we should point out and it is important to understand the context
He's a pretty crappy decade for most con
It is in the Great
Depths of the Great Depression
And it is hard to exaggerate what that mean to me people think of
Economic hard times but it opens the door to
All sorts of political instability and problems
On everything
And some people like
Franklin Roosevelt in the United States and leaders everywhere had their hands full trying to pull out of this economically
Nosedive
Nobody was prepared to spend
A lot of money
Or lot of political cap
Or ask the country to give some great sacrifice for some calls around the world
When you hardly can handle the problems
Going to put people
In
Soup line
In your in the streets of your major cities
Here were things really spy
Control although it's not always apparent that that's what happened
Many people have suggested that it would have been very easy to imagine the Second World War
Breaking out in 1938
Me a lot of things happening you have
D'Angelo's
Where Germany annexes Austria you have the huge situation over Czechoslovakia
Dayton wings and all that stuff
You have the peace in our time Munich agreement
And I should point out something because
Try not to get on my soap
Hierba drive me crazy
The Munich agreement of course is where the
The prime minister of Britain
Quit going to a conference with hair Hitler
Comes back gets off a plane and I've seen this unit you can go see it in the Museum's
Britain
Waves this document with his signature and Hitler signature on it
And declare is basically that this is peace in our time
People apply
Chamberlain is a reviled
To most people today
He seen as a
The week of
Teaser
It should have
Confronted Hitler me this isn't a million things we throw its Aldi
He's weak need
Free Second World War
Politically
Totally forgetting to Major things in about a thousand minor
What's going to the tomb
You think the first one is D people had already live
The worst war that they could never
20 years ago before the first world war and nobody really knew what they were getting into
In the 1930s everybody knows with
Ticket in the first world war only worse again
And too many of these people
They thought
They saw their civilization nearly knocked
Out in that war
If you're going to have another
And it's going to be worse
And you're starting it from a
The Great Depression levels of
Economic health
What's the likely are you going to survive this
What's the proper price to pay to avoid.
Now
What about
The Publix
Support for knee pain
This is the other thing
Riley forgot
In a place like the United States
Especially
People who will log for being ahead of the power curve
Guys like Winston Churchill who
4C all this sort of and screaming for confrontation and
And more
Amor Bella Coast policy to ward off all this stuff
Avoid this war
We're tougher now
The guy is
Like
In the political wilderness
In this.
Credence
These
Derided by many is a warmonger
So he's sort of out of steps with the attitude of the time
As we all know this war is going to break out in 1939
A month after it breaks out a month after it breaks out
There's a public opinion poll
Map of America
On the issue of the war
I scolded by Francis Pike in hirohito's where I think it's a Gallup poll but I'm not sure
All the poll taken had 84% of respondents saying that they wanted Britain and France to win
Only 2% one of the
Irwin
95%
Wanted to stay out of the war
First of all this is more roof
The America of the
That time.
Much less interventionist Toronto
Entire history
Now
But when you think of those kind of overwhelming number
In a system where the political leaders are elected
What is it
Responsible to expect them to do
How many people are going to go against that kind of supermajority
What's more in a philosophical sense
In a system where the people are supposed to sort of broadly
Decide the course of the nation if 95% of them wants to take a left turn at the fork in the road
Where's the moral Justice in the political leaders making a right instead
So I think we judge these
People harshly
Assume
You know that they had more ability to
Do what we want them to do than they did
And of course what's remember the most important part whenever you do
Do something like the Monday more
Quarterback
History we know how things turn out
Datong
Mother having been said
Famously
The Munich agreement falls through
Poland is invaded
Member 1st
Old and it been given a guarantee by Britain and France because they
They finally had enough of his
I don't want anymore
Don't worry
And when the
Nazis refused to leave Poland
After it's demanded of them the war is on
Money in Europe and the Japanese are
Now as we know
Poland is overrun
Quickly
The post-war propaganda calls it Blitzkrieg what it really looks like is just the first World War
Texas strategy
And philosophy developed over 20 years
Then there's this
Stop. That sometimes called
The phony War
Or where nothing much is going
And then in April 1940 Germany invades Denmark and Norway and conquers them
Pretty quickly
And then a month later not even a month
I don't think I'm
May 1940
Not necessarily
Winston Churchill
Becomes prime minister
So now we have one of the major players
In this story
Ensconced in power
Decision maker
Famously Pitbull liking his
Bellicosity
And yet at the same time
Seemingly the right man for the job because I mean
If Churchill was a bit of a lemon antagonist in it
And a fighter that was a little bit embarrassing in more peaceful times he's exactly what you need now that the war's going isn't he
But may is also the month
Where are the
Tony war ends on the Western Front the German blow through a couple of neutral countries
And then enter France
We should point out another real
During the time. That's often for
Forgot now
France is widely considered to be the strongest land power in the world
At this time.
Many International
Calculator
Nations are based on this
Assumption
This assumption would prove to be
Quickly
France will be.
Defeated
In a mere six weeks
To put that in perspective
Understand how
Incredibly shocking that is
For this time.
You're talkin about country here
It only 20 years previously
Had spent
More than a million
Of their soldiers lives
Holding off arguably the greatest army of the Aged
The first world war German Army for more than 4 years
And remember not only has France defeated here
But the Dutch are defeated as part of
The Germans blowing through this area
And the British look like they're 5 minutes away from succumbing as well
If you're making calculations based on world events in Japan
All of a sudden all of these valuable areas in your neck of the woods that are controlled by
The Dutch
And the French
And the British
Don't seem so formidably defended anymore
Remember if your Japan you might not even be looking at those places
If you could just hold on to China and Conquer it and use its resources that's all they need
Really couldn't give you everything you wanted but
Miniature pans looking to be a great power and they think they have to suck up China to do it
Everything in their policy is based on being able to maintain that addiction
They only start looking towards some of these other
Tempting areas like
French Indochina modern-day Vietnam Laos
Cambodia
Because some of the more obvious
Avenues towards supplying your War Machine
Are being squeezed
By other powers
If you go look at the
Economic
I'm excited the second world war which is a very popular way to look at it
Lately and I find it very value
In terms of understand some of the deeper motivation
All of the Axis powers
Words were concerned
Self-sufficiency
Autarky
And this is actually playing into the global trade situation involves economics in a way that kind of explains War motivation very
Well but the reason that countries like
Germany
Free sample wanted self-sufficiency was in part because
They've been starved to death in the first world
When their shipping and trade was cut off by the British Navy
These countries wanted the flexibility to
To be relatively immune
To other countries economic pressure
The Japanese wanted to do what they wanted to do in China
And wanted to be able to
Flip the middle finger to countries that told him to stop
Unfortunately
In this time. They depended on other countries too much
Historian James L McClain rights in a modern history of Japan quote
To the regretted mini Japanese economic planners
In the late 1930s
Japan still depended upon the United States for nearly one-third of its Imports
From cotton to scrap iron and oil
And matter seem to be growing worse
Between 1929 and 1932 Japan purchased from the United States
36% of its scrap iron
Used to manufacture steel for Munitions and ships
By 1938 American sources were supplying 74% of Japan
Scrap
Similarly in 1938 Japan received more than 60% of its imported Machine Tools
I nearly all sophisticated Alloys such as vanadium
And molybdenum from the United States
Traditionally self-sufficient in Copper
Japan in 1939 extracted 90000 tons of that metal from its mine
What industry was gobbling up so much for detonators and shell casings that the nation that year had to import a hundred and five
Thousand tons of copper
93% of it from the United States
The situation for oil the most critical of all Commodities in the estimation of military planners
Was extremely desperate
Japan relied on America for almost 80% of its fuel
Emperor special distillates dependent student more than 90%
In the eyes of Economic and military strategists
By the summer of 1940 Western colonies in Southeast Asia had come to represent a treasure Trove of wrong
Materials
Whose possession would allow Japan to Vault into the ranks of the economic have
To recall one of their prime minister's phrases
And duster free itself from dependence
Upon an increasingly hostile West
And quote
You can see why a concept like
National
Self-sufficiency
Attractive
To someone like
Dependent on these outside powers
To sell them what they need especially what they need to keep the war machine running
So what happens
If the people who sell you the stuff you need to keep the war machine running stop selling you the stuff you need
And that becomes
The story
I know many of you are
Ora's fascinate
Adidas I am
I have wars
It started
And there is no temp
They're all different
The variable
The same
But you can see
You know similar patterns and in this particular case you see the
Pattern of a sort of inertia developer
You saw this in the first World War
Described it
Like someone pulling
Hand grenade
But you could also think about it like a
Fuse being lit
It's when events start to move
Towards Collision
And at a certain point it almost becomes easier
To run into each other and have a conflict
Then to break out of
The pattern and in this case
Going to be
A question of eating the Japanese War Machine
Skip this Dynamic going
And I was trying to get into all the tit-for-tat things and it got very complicated because they're so many players
And as we said earlier in
Important to remember
That in the Japanese government just like the Western democracies there is no hive mind
At work
There are lots of different ideas
What's the best foreign policy directions are to go and different factions favoring differ
Fun things and based on events
Some factions are exalted and others are in Decline
So there is no concerted
Foreign policy effort
Cities with outfits and start
Send a certain level of Chaos
In the case of the Japanese
And we talked about this earlier in the story
Their governmental design is already not
Wonderful
In terms of accountability and the lines of command and all these things
When we start getting to a moment where the stress level and the need for efficiency and clear thing
Thinking and clear lines of authority
I'm really important
This government's going to break down in such a way that if you are a Japanese citizen that you have every right to
Accuse them of some kind of criminal negligence
Because look what the Japanese are
You know right around the time
France Falls where they have a major war and commitment going on in China there already rationing luxury goods and fuel
The people are already grumbling
And then what 18 months later
When you add to that burden a war against
The United States Great Britain France
All there
Former Colonial dominions and Commonwealth Nations
Mean
How the hell does that happen
Well in a broad sense it happens
Because of a decision
To stop
The Japanese War Machine
If you look at it objectively that becomes the issue where there's no given this is very controversy because everybody
Are you forever what the cause of the Pacific meet award who's at fault
But if you look at it if it becomes pretty simple that the Japanese priorities
And the Americans and British the Anglo America
You can call them
Priorities
Clash
And the priorities have to do with what it is the Japanese are addicted to
China
The whole reason I like the addiction analogy
It's because of where we're coming to
There's going to be the global equivalent of an intervention here in the Japanese are going to be told
But they have to stop
Inflating themselves on the steroids that are the Chinese resources and land mass and all that
And if they don't
Stop they're going to get the means to that
Cut off the means are things like oil
Now worth pointing out cuz it's interesting from a military history standpoint
The second world war is really the first big war
Where oil is this super important resource
Award-winning or War losing
Resource at a certain point
Guilin
Most War
Have a component of
Resources involves some
Way or another
Now what's interesting is over the air is often
The important resource that you need to have changes
Right during the
Bronze Age having the Monopoly on the making of iron in
And stuff like that at the National Security
Why aren't still important in the 20th century but
I mean it wasn't all that important all Petroleum in the Bronze Age
Is critical
In this area I think about the knee
To have it for your Air Force if nothing else but also
You know since the first World War
Before the first world war they started changing over from coal
2 oil
For the fuel for all of their ships all the major powers
Algae that creates a dependency you didn't have
In countries like Japan which didn't have a lot of oil to begin with let's just say almost none a little in the sakhalin island
But almost none
Are in a bind if the people you normally buy oil from decide to squeeze you
This is an interesting thing to look at
Because
I remember as a kid growing up I lived through something that if you look in your history books now with a known historical
Event with long-term huge ramifications that we still live with today at the time
We just called it the oil crisis when I was a kid in 1973
Long story short
A cartel of oil producing Nations wanted to get the United States and friends to change their foreign policy
Priorities
As they related
To his realtor
The war in the Middle East going on
Decided to squeeze the United States and Friends oil supply
I have to get the price to rise to sort of
Chorus might not be
A strong enough word petrol blackmail is a word they sometimes use
To get the United States to change its foreign policy
The attitude that the US government had was completely understandable unpredictably attitude they have is no great power
Our is going to let anybody dictate what their foreign policy priority should be
Anywhere few people in the Nixon Administration that we're basically talking about
In a listen if you don't sell the oil
At a decent price where to come and take them
You can understand the idea of no great Powers going to let another
Country
Dictate words
We should be
But during this period of time that's exactly what the Anglo American nations are going to do today
Did the Japanese
And in the same way it's hard to imagine the United States knuckling-under
To the demands
Of an oil cartel and changing its foreign policy it's hard to imagine the Japanese
Publicly with their tail between their legs completely altering more than a decade's worth of 4
Foreign policy
And doing what the great power tells them to do otherwise they won't get any oil which they really needed to run the war
War Machine in China which they wouldn't be in anymore
But because it is so obviously something that might lead directly to war
There is always been one side of the debate
In the United States and elsewhere
About how much
We're going to talk about now these economic embargoes and sanctions
And asset freezes and those kinds of things how much that was
A nonviolent way
To express the moral outrage of the public at the Japanese treatment of the Chinese and all this kind of stuff
Versus
A shove in a direction that the people in the know understood would lead directly to war
That's why
We're going to deal with a couple different sides of the debate here because this is not settle stuff
Play very hard
You believe
But there are number different
Ways to look at
There's a place
Where power politics and moral outrage intersect
And power politics in a realpolitik
And
Moral outrage from
Country like United States or Great Britain or any of these Western democracies these things are usually at odds with each other
Mean a lot of times you have people like National Security advisor Henry Kissinger who was Nixon's National Security advisor
Lamented the idea
That he should be constrained by the public so that we be attitudes towards nation-states when he's trying to
In a create treaties that keep nuclear war from breaking out from let's keep our eyes on the prize here in the nation's of Interest
Right
And yet at the same time
How do you expect a public
Who's reading all this terrible stuff coming out of the War in China
And babies being bombed in a people being beheaded and rapes of cities about to happen any minute now in the story
How do you tell that public
That they should just sit idly by and do nothing
What's more what if
Your country is providing the means necessary
For these events even take place where are you
It's certainly understandable.
Flightreacts
In fact
You might worry about it
Trees popular
Malaysian the didn't
In this case
With a nation so against going to war
What are the options that the president has in a situation like
Is right
Well
This begins to become clear
In October 1937 in a famous speech that
The president of the United States Franklin Delano Roosevelt give
This is about a month or two before the Nanking massacre
What happens what it's on the horizon
In the Battle of Shanghai all that's happened
And Roosevelt give this
Speech where he talks about aggressor Nation
He talks about
Their conduct being
Like a contagion like a disease that will spread and he Compares it to what you do
When people have diseases you quarantine them right
He suggesting that that's what you be done today
Aggressor States
Here's a sample
1937 quarantine speech
I present
Franklin Delano
Roosevelt
It seems to be unfortunately true
That the epidemic is spreading
The best well
Where am I
Physical disease
The community approves and joins in
Eggs florentine
Of the patients
In order to protect the health of the community
Against the spread of the disease
It is my determination
Go fast Chevrolet policy
It is my determination to adopt every practicable measure
Do I avoid involvement in law
It ought to be
Inconceivable
That in this
And in the face of experience
Alienation could be so foolish and ruthless
Time to run the risk of fronting the whole world
By invading and violating
In contravention of solemn trailers
The territory of other nations
Set up Dunlop no real home
Sandwich shop 2 weeks
No protect themselves adequately
Just a piece of the world
And the welfare and security
Every Nation including our own
Is today being threatened
Now if this seems like a rather weak speech in terms of specifics and what not you wouldn't be the
The only person that says so Francis Pike seems to indicate that Roosevelt
Kind of weak on all the stuff for a while he said that this speech was just being a Roosevelt Field of testing the waters
We gave some polling information earlier
It gives you an idea about the attitude of the American electorate during this time
If the president of the United States thanks
That there's a very important direction that the country needs to go
But the country doesn't want to go there what should the president of the United States
It's worth examining this enigma
That is President Franklin Delano Roosevelt
For a minute because he's eight
He part of this story
He's unlike any other US president in history
He was elected
2 twice as many terms
Has any other president
The Constitution after he left the scene
But that would never happen again
But it gave him
An unparalleled amount of actual practical hands-on experience with the levers of government
Nobody ever move them any better
Then Franklin Roosevelt did
Roosevelt and unusually
Hard to figure out US president you would think a guy that was on the scene as long as he was would have all sorts of him
Information attached to
Feelings about things but he died in office
Early into the fourth term by the way
Which meant we didn't get the normal run of presidential Memoirs and all that stuff afterwards because even if it's a pack of Lies
My eyes are self-serving justifications historians have a way of using that to really
Flesh things out and compare them to other events and whatnot triangulate
But you don't even get that from Roosevelt
And he was a hard to read guy anyway almost by
It is very nature
He still elicits
Extremely strong emotions in
Mini directions I mean at the time there was a euphemism for him the people who hated his guts
Used
They wouldn't mention his name they call him Batman in the White House
Conservative Americans often saw Roosevelt as damn near socialist
Man who exploded the size of the America
Government
Put it in in all sorts of areas where did never stuck its nose in before
Transferred money
From the wealthier classes
To the poorer classes set up all kinds of
Agencies appear to be doing all kinds of things spending all kinds of money but we're there really any results
Changing America fundamentally
There is a before Franklin Roosevelt and after Franklin Roosevelt
America
He's arguably the most
Transformative president that's ever been
Again
Part of it being
How long he serve but also because
When you serve during such major events of the Great Depression followed by the second world war you're going to be around
When all kinds of things
Transformed
And you're going to be trying to ride the storm
The captain of maybe
Maybe
The most powerful
Will ship in the world
To a lot of Americans liberal certainly but a lot of poor destitute Americans of the Great Depression Roosevelt
Hero
If he wasn't achieving things that wasn't for lack of trying
He was literally doing
You know programs were people
Did all kinds of things that weren't even necessary in the government would hand them out of paycheck although they also did a ton of things
That we still benefit from today
All kinds of milk
Conservation cores in all these things it would put people
To work
Simply to
Put them to work
Try to prime the pump of the American you cannot make engine and get things going again
There were a lot of Americans who had food on the table because of Franklin Roosevelt
That'll make you pretty pop
Might even get you elected
Before Time
Defenders would argue
That if Roosevelt put in a lot of programs that conservatives thought of as socialist things like Social Security
By the way or a Roosevelt a new deal program
He was up against competition from other forms of government
Like
Bolshevism
And fascism
Took over in countries with political instability taken hold
YouTube horrible economic situations in part
Defenders would argue that Roosevelt managed to steer the United States
Away from either one of those extremes and as one of my
Professors put it
Gave the country a little socialism to avoid having them demand a lot
Views on Roosevelt
Run the game
Francis Pike in his
Book about the Pacific War hirohito's war
Talks about Roosevelt and points out that the guy is a hard man
To figure out
Rights quote
At the best of times Franklin Delano Roosevelt was a difficult man to read
Henry Wallace his former vice president said of him
Now wallet
He doesn't know any man
No man knows him even his own family doesn't know anything about him
Now quoting Roosevelt
I am like a cat
He said about himself
I make a stroke and then I relax
Ike says quote
Loved and respected as a leader
Seemingly happiest in the company of women he was an enigma
Detached enigmatic
And ruthless
What flying over Cairo Roosevelt glanced out the window and said
Call my friend the Sphinx
And quote
Former time
Editor-in-chief
Hedley Donovan
We met like seven presidents personally
Newroz valuable Roosevelt was the first of the presidents that he knew and even wrote a book
All the presidents
He said about Roosevelt
Quote
FDR could brilliantly oversimplify
Is best remembered single statement
The only thing we have to fear is fear itself
Is patently absurd
Emma's probably excellent tonic for a country whose banking system collapse
But in the early and middle stages of decision making
Before it was time to simplify and oversimplify Roosevelt could be impenetrable
Rexford tugwell one of the early New Deal Brain Trust jurors wrote
Now coding tugwell
No one could tell what he was thinking
To say nothing of what he was feeling
Donovan continues
He clearly relished being hard to figure out
He likes secrets and had a few
He was often devious for good reason
Could also be devious just for the fun of it
General Douglas MacArthur who despised him
Ted Roosevelt
Coding MacArthur now
We never tell the truth when a lie would serve him just as well
Donovan continue
Quote
This was considerable slander
What FDR unquestionably did enjoy manipulation and maneuver for their own sake
All part of the great game of politics and Power
Benny says
He was also a man of deep convictions a dedication and unquenchable idealism
He was firm and Serene in his religious faith and have a decent sense of privacy about
It is impossible to imagine him at a congressional prayer breakfast
He was impatient with the abstract or theoretical
In no sense profound but spacious in vision
America an ultimately all the nations
He believed if not in the perfectibility of man in a rather spectacular Improvement in man's behave
Saviour worldwide
And quote
This impenetrability
Roosevelt
So has kind of worked against him
In terms of
Is place in history because it leaves a lot of room for people to speculate about his motives
And often times
It gets wrapped up with
People's politics ideologies worldviews and even
Conspiracy theories
Roosevelt
Everything from
A well-meaning
Moral crusader
Desperately trying to avoid war with Japan while still getting them to change their evil ways
Two on the very far side of the other Spectrum off and conspiracy land
Roosevelt is a man who Engineers this War years in advance
Organized is it pushes the Japanese into it
Knows about it in advance and then luckily orders the carriers out of Pearl Harbor just in time
I'm so they don't get hurt
Cuz he's also aware that carriers are going to be
In the new battleships in the
Modern Age Wichita
Quite know yet but nonetheless
Runs again
Who is this Franklin Roosevelt
Hawkeye right
Sneaky
Conniving
Let's remember
He was elected originally way back in 1932
To deal with the depression
The things he did to deal with the depression were really effective at the time at least in making people feel
Feel like somebody was finally doing something
He left behind a lot of legacies that people in the United States argue over everything
From
In a bunch of different
Government departments to things like Social Security
Roosevelt
Looks to me like one of those
People who has
The reality Distortion field ability
That was something Steve Jobs was supposed to have
Up to
Supposedly
A guy like jobs or
Maybe Roosevelt
Could convince you that a job that was really hard to imagine anybody doing anything about was totally possible and where
We're on the way
Baby Elon Musk
Has that ability to
But
I read that Andy hertzfeld was the one who
Said that
The reality Distortion field was a combination of
Charm bravado
Charisma hyperbole marketing appeasement and persistence
And that
Really sounds like
Pretty good description of Roosevelt to me
I wish. One of the best
Examples of
The Factory Roosevelt possessed disability
Was that while never not admitting and being open about
The information
He sort of made the country just forget
That he was paralyzed
Below the waist
You got polio is an adult he was confined to a wheelchair you didn't see pictures of that the pictures usually show him at electr
Turn 4
Seated with other world leaders
Appearing
Completely able-bodied you didn't but he didn't hide it really I mean
There was talk of it everybody knew but she could just make you forget nowadays it would be something that was celebrated
An exalted in used as an example
Right of the possibilities don't let anything hold you back the president himself
Or herself
Uses a wheelchair
Right
Industrious
Roosevelt was it interesting and interesting sort of Steve Jobs age is not a bad description of him
But if you didn't like his policies
The reality Distortion field almost seems nefarious doesn't
Now some of the people who thought
Roosevelt most nefarious
Are the people who wanted to see the United States
Stay clear this new world war that had broken out in Europe you know by 1940s we said you have
The German Army blowing through France and occupying Western Europe and by the way the stories coming out from that one
What a harsh occupation how horrible it is
Something that moves public opinion yet again
It should be pointed out cuz it probably played into it in a major way
The 1940 is a presidential election year in the United States and Roosevelt is running for an unprecedented
Ended third term
I read one history
The prettiest way when they said that Roosevelt and his Republican opponent were vying to outdo each other
With their promises that they would keep the country out of the European War other words there was no opponent running that said that they
They would get them in the war it was a competition to see who could be most passionate about saying they would stay out of it
And when Republican hopeful
Wendell willkie charges that the president is secretly trying to get the us into the war or doing things that would get the US in
In the war Roosevelt issues
Solomon
Play in the Democratic party platform and Roosevelt on the stumps is it over and over again this is from a campaign speech
Not long before the election given in October 1940 we're Roosevelt references all the other times that he said it
He says quote
I have said this before
But I shall say it again and again and again
Your boys are not going to be sent into any Foreign Wars
And quote
Now
Can you write that off as a
Campaign promise if he breaks it
Is this like you know I won't raise your taxes
Lottery wins
There's a problem with this in America
Consistent to
Because there's precious few ways for the
Public to weigh in on foreign policy in the country
The presidents or people who want to be the presidents often make promises about foreign policy
If they break those promises
What does that mean for the ability of the
The population
To influence
The country's foreign policy for example
Some of the people most upset with
Where Roosevelt is going are people that think that they can see through
Is
Why they see the midline is right when he says I'm not trying to get the country into war they're looking at what's actually happening
And Roosevelt is mimicking many of the same things that Democratic President Woodrow Wilson did the year before the you
Who asked God into the first World War
Wilson also promising by the way that he won't get our boys you know
To give their blood in the European War
What is it 5 months after he wins the election there there
And Roosevelt won't be the last person in the 20th century to do it
There was a
Very interesting argument
Though that I read by historian Campbell Craig
And I hope I got
Get it right
The spirit of it anyway but he was talking about
American history Charles Austin beard who had his reputation destroyed when after the second world war he wrote a book
That treated Roosevelt a little like
Criminal in a docket and he was the prosecuting attorney in
What he was trying to prove with that Roosevelt was involved in the conspiracy
To take the country into the European war against the will of the country
Anne Frank
A very interesting argument he said that
Some historians are mad
Charles Austin beard for saying that they were taken
Conspiracies in the US government all the time
Easter the conspiracies not the problem in the reason that beard was discredited
Beard was just credited because Roosevelt turned out to have done
What do you American people afterwards decided they approved
So maybe you could compare him to the way we talked about Churchill
In the era where Churchill was out of power
His bellicose nature was out of touch with the tenor of those times
Could Roosevelt be said to be more far-seeing
The American public they met 95% of them say they don't want to get involved in this European war that maybe Roosevelt knows better
And if I read Campbell Craig correctly he's saying that the public opinion polls
After the war in the approval rating the people have for that in the fact that the guy who didn't want to be in that war Charles Austin beard
The public turning in cuz it's such an unpopular attitude baby the argument is FDR with right
Sometimes you have to lead from the front right at the American public aren't ready yet I'm ahead of the curve they will agree with me when we get
Although
As we said it was an election year and if you want to read the polls a certain way you could argue that Roosevelt was doing exactly what the police
Data scenes you want him to do
Right you have an overwhelming majority that do not want to send our boys over there to fight
But you also have an overwhelming majority that want to see Britain and France prevail
So those are the parameter is what sort of room for manoeuvre do you have
Well many of the same things Woodrow Wilson did in the first World War
Warframe
You can help the allies
That's a bit of a problem when you're portraying yourself as a neutral country which is officially with the US was portraying itself in the first
For whereas to a neutral country
And you get argument again
General
Marine Corps General
Smedley Butler I think he stole the
A whole book
Small book with a whole book
Talking about how we were following the same pattern again
And we're just going to run into the same kind of problems and that the people in power know this already
Charles Austin beard himself eight years before the war predicted it would come from an incident or provocation and then there you go
Well when you have
German submarines
Torpedoing British Merchant ships
5 seconds after they leave the Eastern Seaboard Sports
Maybe with some Americans on them isn't that just
Setting up a provocation
Isn't that exactly like what happened in the first World War I think there's a Life Magazine photograph I think I remember showing
The explosion of a tank or something heading for Britain right off the u.s. shore and you can see the lights of
Like New Jersey's Boardwalk or something in the distance at night
You got to be crazy to think that that's not going to lead
2 something that sucks a country into the war what's more Roosevelts got an Undeclared sort of War going and it's understand
Hannibal why you would
Sending US destroyers out to stalk those German submarines right the neutral country but Roosevelt could argue
A lot of Americans would agree hey hey hey we can't have
In submarine torpedo in people so close to us
An argument can be made that Roosevelt was sort of following
He said he was pushing it to the limits of the law but you can make an argument just like you can that he wanted the country into war
But he every step of the way was doing the next
Logical step in a progression and hoping it didn't go any farther
Certainly you can make a better argument for that in Asia
The Pacific
Roosevelt is quoted in a cup
Pacific because he only has one Navy in the implication is he's going to need it in the Atlantic against the Nazis but
Let's be honest with a guy
I like this that doesn't mean anything he's much more
Nuanced and layered than that
Some of the modern histories I've read on the
Have a very interesting
You point that I hadn't considered which shows you the blind spot of the kind of histories we used to read
The more modern history point out things from the other side that make
Clear
Things that we forgot
And then one of them is
Debating whether or not Roosevelt wanted a war against
Pan-pacific ignore the fact that he already has one
It just doesn't involve us
Mike Franco David macri and others
Essentially refer to the War in China as a proxy war
Not just for the United States
But for Great Britain and the Soviet Union all of whom have an interest in keeping Japan
Ball gown
So all of them are at one time or another
Providing arms
Resources
Supplies
Some of the histories make
The case that this becomes a wonderful
Thing that Japanese commanders who been promising great victories in our failing can blame things on
And you do once again see the similarities in the Vietnam War era we're all of a sudden it all became about the Ho Chi Minh
Men Trail
If we can just shut down that network of
A resupply roads down
The outside powers like China and the Soviet Union were supplying the North Vietnamese will be able to get their stuff to the moon will win
In this case the Japanese
Become obsessed with shutting off the many leaking like a sieve cuz it's about the geographical size of the
Ussv said the many resupply points that the Chinese have
The Soviets
In the North
The British are leaking stuff over from Hong Kong
The Burma Road their stuff coming over from
French Indochina and the US is
In fits and starts doing stuff too and
Sell at below-cost all kinds of things at one point to the Soviets a deliver like 800 planes and the advisors to teach you how to
Fly them
If you are the Japanese
And you need a nice victory in China to free up another
This is a food eating contest in the Japanese sat down to a giant plate
A pancakes
And they're halfway through the pancakes now and they're starting to realize holy cow I'm not going to make it through this mean while
Other people are secretly
The Soviet Union Great Britain the United States piling more Pancakes on the table when you're not looking and every time you turn the
Around it more pancakes you're already almost full
By 1939 the Japanese
App China
It's like they're addicted to it
But they got too much it was an old comic book episode once about
Are you going to steal Superman's power and you want it but then you couldn't you couldn't handle it all and you just overdosed on it well
The Japanese are looking to figure out a way to have their cake and eat it too in China what that means is how do we get out
But leave it in a circumstances where we control it right puppet governments things like that they want to replicate what they did in men
You know now called Manchu quote
Play Japanese puppet state just like Sharia is
A lot harder to do that in a place the size of China
Especially when you haven't defeated China yet
In 1939 the Chinese been a couple of battles against the Japanese boom
They weren't ready for that
What's more the Japanese who always amongst the Army had a huge contingent of officers
It really wanted to attack
The Soviet Union
Got their wish unfortunately
A couple of things that were called incidents were clashes happened between the Red Army
And the Japanese Army up there the kwantung Army and the Japanese got their nose severely
17000 casualties in one of these
Led to some reforms in the Japanese Army by the way
But also blunted the enthusiasm that had been running in Japanese leadership circles for a
Crusade against the Soviet Union which also turn Japanese eyes into other directions were things might be
At less of a cost
This is what's known by the way
At the north-south
Debate during the time. In Japanese politics do we go north against the Soviet Union South against those possessions
Also well-defended
Why the colonial Masters
The Japanese
Sources invariably focus on two things
That we in the west don't focus on this much
China and communism
Saburo and I got years ago was pointing out going to keep your eye on the prize
The Japanese art this is all about China
All these other things that happened including the war with United States and all of this is an attempt to figure out how to solve
Call their China war situation
To their satisfaction
And communism
Is the other thing that they
Focus on inordinately in we in the West
Forget that to that
It's
Fair I think to call Japan
The most fervently large anti-communist country in the world
During this time period that's really saying something you need age where Nazi Germany exist
But the Japanese hate communism in they portray and they tell themselves and they using propaganda with their public and maybe
There's even some truth to it that this war in China is in large part of war against communism
They have their own version of what the West will have 10 or 20 years after this.
With the West will be worried about the domino effect where
Communism spreads one country to another you like dominoes
The Japanese have their same
Attitude here that's going to move through China and Japan so they going to stop it over there before it comes over to the Homeland
You are there telling themselves that they're paying all this money sacrificing all these lives in an effort to
Keep and protect the Chinese people who haven't fallen under communism sway free
And even to roll back communism in free
Chinese people who are the slaves of the
Bolshevik and Lenin the stinkers
You go talk to her
Japanese
Parent who lost a son in that fighting you're likely to hear some sort of rationale like
Like that after all is that what you would like to think your son died for
Other people's freedoms
It's a pretty I might it cause
Lot of people Sons
On all sides in a lot of War
Like that
Now China of course is going to become
Mary said like an intervention
The big sticking point that it's hard to see anyone over
We're coming because
The Japanese in their minds have to get some sort of deal in China just like the US had to get some sort of deal in Vietnam
Where it gets
The boxes ticked off that it needs to get
So we can leave
In Japan's case those boxes really are control of China's resource
This is not something that the Western powers are for
Prepared to let them have
So how do you get around that
Well
We had said that Japan was
Basically being confronted with an intervention
Body Angela Merrick
Can powers
They pull if you want to look at it this way something more like a Kobayashi Maru
From Star Trek
Rock you like a third way you didn't know I had a third option right
I give up the drugs were going to cut off your money so you can't buy drugs will maybe I have
Prince
After the Germans blow through
Western Europe
In 1940
Right around the same time the Japanese sign
An alliance with
Call the tripartite
Late September 1940
Create something called the axis and the Axis powers
Because Italy will join in
Some of their
Fascist leaning countries smaller country to be named later
This is a unification of
Outside
Countries in terms of
The club all these countries want some sort of
Autarky self-sufficiency and unfortunately for all of them none of them have oil
In Romanian
Little help a little
But the Japanese joining the Axis powers
Is one of the Fatal misstep
Epsom and terrible moves
That leads to tragedy
For everyone in Asia
And it's often
Pointed out
That it should have been avoided had you had
A different kind of government
With a different
System of making decisions
You might have avoided
The way things went because if you actually look at
What people felt like including the emperor
There were
Hunza people in the Japanese power structure that wanted nothing to do with a conflict with the United States and Britain
Avoid that at all costs or how do you end up there
Well is a ton of missteps
A miscommunication
And misinterpretation of mistranslations
How about
The mystery that happens when the Japanese foreign minister who signed this deal this access agreement
How about his misread of how the United States would react
This guy's name of the ways matsuoka
And he is probably portrayed in all the history books
Is important an influencer sometimes debated
But this is a guy who owned his resume essentially called himself the American expert
He graduated from the University of Oregon
You work in the United States and goes back to Japan
And he's the guy who thinks signing an agreement with Nazi
Germany is gone
Help give you Leverage
I guess United States that that's how they're going to react
Japan was hoping for someone who would even up the scales a little bit in terms
Of its negotiating
Power against
When you read what they were hoping for including what the Prime Minister was hoping for they felt like they needed
Somebody on their side otherwise you couldn't negotiate with the Americans from any sort of position to parody much less strength
And I think you kind of have to call it about
50% effective
When examining results because
I kind of did Scare
The Americans get there
Retention
And force a response to 50% of the deal that was not
Successful is it wasn't the response to Japanese were thinking they were going to
It didn't make the Americans back off and think maybe they'd better
How to be more cautious here
Because otherwise maybe we'll be fighting the luftwaffe
In the Pacific and the varimax will be defending some of these Japanese defense perimeter islands and
Only the Japanese
I'm certainly hoping that that might be
Be the case and
If you look at some of the promises the Nazis were making to the Japanese when try to convince them to sign this agreement which they tried to do the
Before apparel
They were sort of hinting that that's how it would be right up if you can do a war with United States
Unfortunately for the Japanese
That's a worst-case scenario for the Americans to in a situation that maybe they could have looked the other way for a while and Folk
Focused on Europe when it was just Japan which had a limited amount of ability
To really threaten the United States looked a lot more like something that had to be dealt with
Right away
When it's
The Eastern wing of the axis Alliance in the tentacles are
Now stretching out over the Pacific in the US
The spacing of War on both fronts
You don't
Walk away with you
Your tail between your legs
That's the situation
Malaysian
You take it with
Animoji
Deadly serious
The amount of diplomatic flexibility to Japanese
You're going to have
After signing this agreement
With the Nazis
This is
Severely limited
Dick compared to what it
Before the state they weren't ready for this
Fact that they were going to be lumped in now
With people
Who had some of the worst depression you can get
In the western democracy
The Japanese PR
I wasn't good already we talked about the Life magazine photos of the babies being bombed in China and all these kinds of things
Well now you hook yourselves up in the minds of the American public
With people who are
Diametrically opposed
To the Western value
Dinner trumpeted
Celebrated
You know you can
Flip a coin who's more opposed
Stalinist see in the Soviet Union or the Nazis in Germany
None the less I mean these people
AR book burner
They persecute minorities and have government-sanctioned programs like kristallnacht there against
Freedom of thought freedom of speech freedom of religion they don't have any due process they don't believe in equality under the law
They have a harsh occupation they believe in Collective punishment they pry mean
The list goes on and on
And the Japanese have now
Thrown in their lot in the eyes of The Americans
With that crowd
How much less willing to come to sort of an accommodation
Imperial Japan
Are the American people
Now
And how on Earth did a guy who graduated from the University of Oregon
And work in the United States get that one so wrong
To be fair
Another aspect of this that we in the west don't always think about
Is the fact that the way the second world war looks to us is not necessarily the way it looks
To a bunch of the rest of the world especially place
This is like Asia
In the west we see this as good vs Evil
In Asia
In a lot of these countries that were under Colonial rule at this time
It's a lot more questionable if it's a good guy bad guy thing it might be too bad guys from their point of view
Storing John toland in a book that was written Way Back in 1970 but still has some value
Inside it despite being outdated in other respects
Including what we know
How about the emperor
But I mean he has a whole part admittedly trying to look
Look at this from the Asian perspective
It points out that
You know if you don't see the Western democracies is all that good and a lot of Asia had bought into the promises the high-minded send
Entenmann's from the first world war about self-determination and all these things that we fight for
And people getting to have
You know their own States and having all that stuff was kind of believed in this
Several of the freedom fighters in these countries and pointed out a lot of the locals who died for
Those causes only to find out after the war they didn't apply to that
It was a racial thing and even in this conflict there's going to be exceptions for
Colonial peoples when the high-minded sentiments are trotted out again is the reason why we fight
In this case as
Towing points out there were a lot of people in countries
In Asia
Who were darn happy to see anybody punching their colonial Masters in the face even if they didn't like those
People so much
If you wanted to look at this as a strategic war game
Margot of the way I like to do
These things
And you try to figure out if your Japan
How you ever win
Win the victory conditions for japan-only Italy of the major player seems harder to me
But they hope their wagon to Nazi Germany Japan's a long way away from anybody at the only way they can win
Is turo like a double zero on the percentile dice but it double zero
Is this weird possibility that the
We are calling the greater East Asia co-prosperity sphere
Does that actually works even though a lot of the cynical people behind it
You don't even want it to work
What is in acai imagine if you could somehow free Asia and be sort of the boss
People of it
We'll all the sudden you open up all kinds of possibilities that aren't there otherwise
But this is why throughout this
Situation even when the Japanese are undercutting this message of Asia for the Asians
By raping and pillaging and doing all kinds of horrible things to other Asians
The idea has a lot of appeal
And sometimes you will run into quotes
Some famous people
Dondi
He's one of the Mohandas Gandhi
That make him look like a Nazi sympathizer
Taken out of context
Contacts
It needs to be added back for to make some sense
Is this idea that
Oh yeah the Nazis are bad but we didn't see the colonial oppressor is all that great either
And the really bad guy
Was
Doing something that weekend
Our local bad guy and that was a good thing you know
The enemy of my enemy is my friend
The point is is that there are other ways to look at the
And if you're trying to look at it from a grand strategy point of view it's like what was always said about the great mistake and the inability
Did the Nazis
The capitalized
On some of these
Peoples that they took over
Eventually when War would break out in the Soviet Union
Because they could have come in there as liberators and they were welcomed by the
Locals as liberate
They could have been the Great
3 years of the people under communist domination but because of their racial theories and their harshness and whatnot
They ended up turning a lot of those people against them
The Japanese didn't have those theories theoretically standing in the way
They could have freed Asia and what would that have allowed
Them to do
Their problem of course is that they sort of wanted
Take a shower while freezing it
Burn down the village in order to save it
Cheap China while somehow getting rid of the responsibility of fighting in it
Leasing it
And expand in the other territories even though we are totally tied down in China once again if I
Boggles the mind looking at it
From the perspective of somebody sitting on the sidelines now
What Japan obviously has its hands full and yet the real debate for it
In 1940 is out can we get something else and then we said all the sudden the Soviet Union seems like a little bit
Too steep of a hill to climb right now
So after they Ally with the Nazis are really right around the same time
They're able to arm-twist is a good way to put it lean on is another way
The puppet French government that the Germans are putting
The place after they conquered France
And move militarily into what's now in Northern Vietnam
A piece of French Indochina
This is kind of spark
It starts the dynamic
That lead now
Kind of very clearly
And straightforward
In war
Is a chicken and an egg thing because you'll give Japanese folk who will say two things one
All this is just an attempt to shut down another one of these
Aliki areas where support is coming in for the Chinese and everybody wants us to wind up its War in China what
We can't do that if he supplies
We're just trying to do what you want to do
The other thing though is that if they're going to have
Their raw materials cut off
They're looking for ways to supplement that in one of the ways it's take the ones that are nearby
And unlike
In anything that might be up in the Soviet Union these are hardly
Well defended at all and
Simply by using
Bullying diplomacy the Japanese occupy the northern part of
French Indochina the reaction on the US and
Britain and the Netherlands part is to ratchet up
Sanctions
Now the next big thing that happens
It really influences this story
Is that
Just about little bit over a year from when the world is turned upside down
And the Germans
Take France in Western Europe
The Germans turn the world upside down again
And in an even more shocking fashion
In June 1941
The Axis powers in Europe launched a surprise attack against the Soviet Union
To say that sounds ridiculous
Because when you're launching an attack that is several times
Does the size
Of Napoleon's invasion of Russia in the early 1800s with the Grand Army
Angus 500,000 guys
And the Grand Army multiple Nations
Several times.
And on the front that stretches from like the width of a continent
How the hell does that Stacy
There were plenty of warning
But one way or another
It had the same effect as a surprise attack
And initially and very quickly
The their mouth especially but the axis armies in general
Appear to be having the same kind of success
That the Germans had blowing through France the year before again
And they are surrounding and annihilating
Not Red Army units but Red Army
And once again the rest of the world is looking on in shock and trying to reassess what the heck this mean
This is the last train
A Japanese
Foreign policy
Have to weave into the story be
Because
If you're a conservatively oriented person like I am
And like many of the Japanese leaders were to there looking just like I would be looking
To thinking they have their hands full with China yet there's this impetus
To not miss the bus
As one of the sayings of the time were to miss the bus
A golden opportunity of the way another person put in
That these changes in the global balance of
The power offer
There's a decent case to be made the Japanese foreign policy since they
Rejoin the rest of the world
In the latter part of the nineteenth century
As always had a Keen Eye for opportunity
And you never do any better than they did in the first World War
They gained
So much for almost nothing
But they were very opportunistic they were allied with the British in the Allies remember and they gained mightily
But they're trying to figure out what they are
Opportunistic play is here and have a couple of different competing things going on
Competing thing number one we already mentioned
There's quite a few people in the Japanese power structure that want no trouble at all with
Britain in the United
Traditionally it's the Navy
That is most credited in Churchill often
Sympathetically
The Navy didn't want the Navy was going to have to be the one fighting it
Any new
At the British and the American fleets were the two largest fleets in the world and you be fighting them combined in a war
The Army could
Pop out its chest and make also it's a brave statements all it wanted to if they weren't going to be handling a lot of the shooting a
In the Navy was
But there's also the two other elements that we mentioned earlier
I need to be pointed out are still in play here and it's
Crazy
The first one is the mid-level
Military off
Officers are still having an empath
These criminals and people of these sorts of rank
Who don't have any of the responsibility
You know having to live with the ramifications of the decisions they push
They can just in an aggressive and almost pugnacious manner
Aggressively push forward with their policies and for some reason their superiors
Tend to be a little bit
Lenient
Or lack sword
10 to defer it puts a lot of pressure though
Otherwise be there the other thing of course it's exerting influence in that direction
And it must play into the head of anybody that thinks wait a minute
We need to back down now this is going to be negative direction is the fact the reason Japanese history demonstrates that your life
We to get somebody killing you
If you try move like that didn't you say it was only a few years before
Some historians were describing the Japanese government as a government by assassination
That's still a problem
And if you're too
Well let's just say non super-patriot
You could find yourself shot
Or your head cut or any number of other things that were happy
Audrina spirit and they were
Certainly lost
The threatened and being anything other than a super-patriot at this time. Is to open yourself up
Just suspicion and maybe imprisonment
Let's remember the climate these people are operate
But even the Prime Minister of Japan during the
Time.
He aggressively sometimes make public statements but he does not want a war with Britain and the United States
And France
And the emperor apparently doesn't want that either so how do you get it again
Well this golden opportunity
You just don't miss the bus moment
That this change in the global situation seems to influence now that the Vermont
Cutting through the Western
Regions
Of the Soviet Union
Is to maybe take the rest
French Indochina
And start making a few public statements to the effect
But you know maybe some deals going to have to be reached for
The supplies we need or we might have to you know maybe move South some more
And so right around the time the Germans
Attack
Soviet Union
The Japanese again not quite bloodlessly but mostly blood does listo to move into the rest of French Indochina Laos
Cambodia Viet
And this is the Line in the Sand
Not just because
They have been trying to get the Japanese move in the other direction and it's like a slap in the face when they go the opposite way
But also because it's more modern historians
Deported out
The raw materials that they're actually getting their hands on this area are raw materials that places like the US need as well
So now it's not just about cutting Japan office about Japan cutting the United States off from things they need this is a heavy.
Duty rubber
So this is when the series
Sanctions
And it's funny because
The negotiating position
Originally start somewhere
In the area of you need to get out of French Indochina which is something that's
Kind of possible
But eventually will move into the area of no
You need to tell us when you're getting out
China
Entirely and it's got to be relatively soon
This sounds like a nuanced position but it
It's pretty easy to
To explain once again if you go back to our Vietnam War analogy
And imagine
The together the Soviet Union and China during that. The two other powers at my
Baby great powers
Counterbalance us strength
If they had said to the United States in 1967
You know when the Vietnam war is going
I mean if it's a long long slog towards even defeat at that point
If they'd said listen
Are you got to get out of here
Give us a timetable for when you're getting a
And a timetable can't be like forever
Maybe a year right
If United States leaves Vietnam in 1968 it's the same as saying
You're giving up and losing the war because the war is far from over
The American position on China is
We need a timetable for withdrawal and it's got to be soon
Does it mean 5 minutes
It may be designed to be too soon
For the Japanese to do anything that they would consider to be winning
And then go home
This is the intervention
Get out of China
We're going to cut off your ability
To do what you're doing anymore
This is the fuse being lit now
The Winston Churchill I like to quote Churchill
For the story because
He's a participant in the store he has his own way of viewing things
He's he's not unbiased by any stretch of the imagination
But he's interesting on the job
Meijer there martial culture
And when Churchill was in his formative stages the
British and the Japanese were allies
Also as a colonialist himself as an Empire guy himself he can understand
The desire in the field
The colonies are not inherently evil thing we talked about the Japanese
And of course she dictated or
Recorded into a machine
These histories
Lady wrote about the conference really sound like
They sound like Churchill talking to you
But he sort of
Encapsulate
That's what happens
I will a little Sympathy for the Japanese
Winston Churchill ride
Quote
The DraStic application of economic sanctions in July 1941
Route to head the internal crisis in Japanese politics
Conservative elements were shocked
Henna moderate leaders scared
The domestic Prestige of the Japanese Army is a constitutional factor in shaping Japanese policy was
Already involved
Hitherto the Navy had exerted its restraining Force
But the Embargo is which the United States
Britton head Holland head in forest
Cut off from Japan all supplies of oil
On which the Navy and indeed the whole war power of Japan dependent
The Japanese Navy was at once
Sports 2 live on its oil Reserves
At the outbreak of the Pacific War had in fact consumed 4 out of 18 month supply
It was evident that this was a Stranglehold
Another Choice before them was either for Japan to reach an agreement with the United States
Or go to war
The American requirements involved Japanese withdrawal
Not only from their new aggression in Indochina
But from China itself
Where they had already been fighting and heavy expense for so long
This was
He writes
A rightful but a hard demand
Any circumstances the Navy Associated itself with the Army in the policy of War
If an acceptable diplomatic agreement could not be obtained
And quote
Cheat codes for the old idea by the way
The Navy doesn't want the war
But because of the sanctions in the cutting off a fuel supply slowly but surely will
Maybe not even that
Slowly the Navy begins to move toward the Army position in these things are more hard-line
Anti anglo-american
Imposition
1 Admiral Pointe Dr
The government
That the fleet is burning 400 tons of oil an hour
The overall military need is something like 12000 tons
Today
Another official or Admiral its Des
Disputed
It's supposed to have told the government
That this is like a patient
Who's going to die
Without surgery
And he still made I even with the surgery but if you don't give him the surgery his Death is certain
Some other word
The showing the position that solve the chapel
I think they find themselves in
One of certain death
Unless risky and still no potentially fatal
Countermeasures are taken
I should point out
That while some people say and Frances Pike is pretty vociferous that every one of these Roosevelt
People knew that once you
Put oil
On The Chopping Block that this basically meant
The Japanese were going to go to war
But in his
A modern history Japan has during James McClain says that
Secretary of State Cordell Hull didn't see it that way
He really thought
You could get the Japanese to see reason
Through something like this in other words
If true
This was the peaceful attempt right there between the two World Wars attitude sort of attempt
To get another country to do the right thing and not just the right thing for you but in the long run the right thing for that
McLane says quote
As the situation in China worsened after 1937
Secretary of State Howell became the primary proponent of waging an economic Cold War against
In his view Japan's Reliance on the American market for strategic Goods
Made the smaller Nations particularly vulnerable to economic sanctions
And the systematic application of ever greater amounts of pressure wood
At some point he believe
Bring the Japanese to their senses
The Secretary of State realize that he had to be careful about his calibration
He did not wish to push Japan into a shooting war with the United States
But he did mean to convince the country's leaders
About the Folly of playing a high-stakes game in which the United States could continually up the economic auntie
At some point
Hohhot
Moderates would return to power in Tokyo
Japan with folded hand and peace would be possible
And quote
This is why we had brought up the
The history of Japan
From before this error
Just sort of set up the contact
And let's just call it the national psyche of Japan during this time.
And of course I don't pretend to know about it it's
Something that everybody talks about
The fact that
The Japanese have what we call it
A rain man like
Laundry list of grievances
Places where they
Think they've been shafted by the rest of the International Community
When they feel like they've been treated as second-class in the some of this is racially oriented
And in the minds of a lot of those people
This just looks like the biggest baddest example of the same thing over again
What are you supposed to do about that
And
Certainly
Asking the Japanese to give up more than any of these previous cases because this War in China
Has already cost something like a hundred thousand Japanese lives
Untold amounts of money effort the
Intense work of a generation Japanese Statesman
What's the likelihood in reality
Of Japan choosing anything other than war in this situation that's why so many people have suggested
It's an ultimatum
Time United
What states is talking about
Get out of China
Cutting off your raw materials and oil
The Japanese certainly saw it that way
Mary's B Jensen that was interesting
He pointed out that
It's not true when it's not true because all of the ideas
It made this look like an ultimatum were part of a
The Japanese
Construe
They created this artificial
Time deadline
The put them behind the eight ball if you ignore the time deadline you could have
Months
Maybe even longer to negotiate
But because you want to keep the option of going to war open
There's as much of an artificial deadline limiting the
Time to go Cedars have to solve this problem some other way
If they had in the first world war in the first world war was all about in a mobilization timetables and
War plans that required precise
Your troop movements and people getting on schedule to places otherwise the whole War go down so you know that limited the time people had to do anything
Other than carry out the plans
In this conflict
It's the fact that
The Japanese Fleet is burning for
Tons of oil
An hour
And the fleet isn't the only part of the Japanese military or the larger Japanese society that needs fuel
It's worse than that though and it's easy to forget
Frances Pike describes
Something that sounds
Benign you know we can all understand the oil question but what about that
Financial squeeze
That's involved here and what does that mean
He writes quote
The evening of 25th July 1941
Roosevelt signed executive order number 88320
Which subjected all of Japanese monetary assets held in the United States
To control by license
The White House Press release stated that quote
This measure in effect brings all Financial in Import and Export trade transactions in which Japanese interests are
Are involved under the control of the government
And imposes criminal penalties for violation of the order and quote
The order
Pike right
Extended to Japanese colonies including Manchu call and China
To protect them from looting by Japan's puppet government installed in Nanking
All assets owned 25% or more by Japanese interest
Frozen
When Wall Street open for business on Monday 28th July
The Foreign Exchange Market for Yen the Japanese currency
Simply disappeared
Japanese dollar Bond
Crash 222 30% of their par value
The Yokohama silk Exchange close
The New York commodity exchange suspended silk futures
In effect
The entire Japanese International payment system seized up
Japan's gold held in America became immovable and unusable
In South America
Modest amounts of gold in foreign exchange were similarly immobilized by governments that followed Roosevelt's lead
Cargos destined for America remain stuck on Japanese war
When Great Britain and Holland followed America's lead
The Yen could only be used and traded with in Japan Zone Empire
And quote
Another way to put that
Is catastrophic
The Japanese are also well aware that
Reducing balance
Between the United States and Japan is growing everyday notches because Japan's getting weaker every day
But because the US is getting stronger
1940 the US essentially
Start sits rearmament efforts and starts
Gearing up for war
Initiate
First peacetime draft
In the country's history
Begins tripling budgets and spending all kinds of money that just the year before Congress would
Laughed the idea of
Appropriating
You know what
Germans taking over Western Europe
So dominant as a way of
Shocking
In Congress
YouTube making up for lost time
The American system throughout most of his his
Clarification
Purposes
I've been one that's been somewhat
Suspicious of standing army
And the lesson that the people
Who designed the Constitution
A framework of the US believed
It's standing army stood in opposition to long-term Liberty
And so
While the US Navy has always been something that's
And paid attention to obviously
Battery Giant
Moat surrounding your hemisphere
Beer makes sense
To pay attention to something
But you have to spend some time in advance building you can't just say oh we have a war let's build a Navy
Usually
Time to use it
Buc-ee's
Where is armies in the old
Say Roman legion style of the Republic
You can sort of build from
A hardcore veterans and that's what the US military the Army was traditionally lights
These long service professionals but not very many of them
It whenever war was going to happen all of a sudden you found yourself with all sorts of volunteers and
Davy Crockett types and Rough Riders
French Pirates
The time
Whatever you needed to get the job done
Are always enough Americans looking for a little action that youku
Could raise enough troops without any
A draft or whatever
And of course when the war was over they all went home
Liberty Safe
It should be pointed out
That even though the United
States is industrial capability had been
In the first World War
Do you watch was
Still gearing up by the time the war ended and it was a us that was nowhere near as industrialized
As the second world war us was
When Hitler and his
In a staff people
We're given briefing
Things on what this is
The famous door
Giving briefings on
The industrial capabilities
The USU
Even when it ramped up
The numbers that they were given turned out to be low
But they laughed at them figuring they were fabrication
So
When you put yourself in the other side shoes and you say
You know why the heck do they think they can pull off anything like this but remember that they didn't quite understand and maybe even a mare
Perkins didn't either
The capabilities of the United States once fully mobilized for war
And 1940 is the year the mobilization begins in
Catch up Africa
Because
The US is very far behind
The power is it in Bennett
4 years in the case of Japan remember
This Chinese incident started in 1937
The other shiny zaferes started in 1931 I mean their troops have been on the ground fighting for a long time
And they've developed a lot of practical experience
The US Army is a green force if there are
That's not to say that the US doesn't have some
Advantages in its back
Pocket
Take for example the fact that in many cases the US is reading the Japanese secret messages
They continually
Despite the Japanese belief that this is impossible they continually break Japanese codes
From
In the 1930s all the way into the War years
They don't always have all the codes broke
So it's hard to understand why if they knew about a why didn't they know about be but for example their reading a lot of the Diplomatic codes
During this period
So while the Japanese are negotiating with the Americans
Americans are often able to read the messages the Japanese sent to each other and the ones they send
Germans
Can I give you a little bit of an advantage in the negotiation
By the summer of 1941 negotiations or not
Doing well at all
Position scene
Hardened
And you begin to see this dynamic
We talked about earlier
Sliding
Towards War I always think about it
Car accident
A sheet of ice
In Colorado I was parked
I release the emergency brake
And I watched
Hill
Picking up speed as it were
Until it
Smashed into another parked car
I watched in slow motion but I could do nothing to stop and I was powerless
And some of the histories that's the way it looks like
Even the Japanese leadership
Feel
In this situation
Right there's there's not many Rara people about the possibility of doing this and you wonder to yourself
If there's such a sense of Gloom
And foreboding
Why on Earth are they stopping it
It's one of those questions always comes into play about the emperor we mentioned it earlier
The emperor supposedly has the power
To stop a war like this before it starts me you stopped the war eventually if you can do it then why can't he stop it before it's
Start these weird questions after the war that he was put to
In this case the guy who's the prime minister's perhaps the next best
Person to look at and say why didn't you do more
Well this time.
All the sudden he decides to
And it's a little bit like
Trying to atone for past sins
He's an interesting character who gets a lot of criticism he's a prince
Last name is Canelo and he was the Prime Minister
Weis
Earlier on he's this sabre-rattling pro-nazi guy is
Historian Herbert P big says you know
Quote
After the Manchurian Incident Cano have been precipitously anti anglo-american and pro-german
On January 21st 1941
He declared firmly before a secret session of the diet
The quote
Germany will win and quote
Now he was just as sure that Germany would lose
And also sure that the senior officers are both Services could not promise a Japanese victory
And quote
This guy
All of a sudden seems to have like
A crisis of confidence in this is what brings the human element back into the story
If you see the slow-motion car crash happening
And it's going to kill lots of innocent people
You know when you're the Prime Minister and you have half of a soul here what would you try to do
Japanese historian
Kerry Hotel
Describes a conversation he had with another
Should a member of the aristocracy supposedly the only kind of people he could show his true self to
He creates one of these figures where you kind of feel bad for the guy even though a lot of this is sort of his fault
Can always looking for a way out of this mess and he thinks if he can
Have a one-on-one conversation with President Roosevelt maybe they can solve this maybe they can stop the
Cars slowly sliding into the other Park Vehicles right can you avoid disaster can you repair the damage
As you called
And by the way she's talking about
Several of these Japanese aristocracy
So when I give you some names that's who they are
She writes quote
At that time
Saionji was preoccupied with helping cannoli arrange a meeting with Roosevelt
TIG and many of his blue-blooded friends knew that a war with the West would be unwinnable
Matsumoto chiharu
The yale-educated journalist who was a direct descendant of another illustrious Meiji oligarchy
Shared so young G's concern
Quote I have made a big mistake on Japan's relations with China
And quote kinue confided to him
In a show of vulnerability displayed only to his social equals
The prime minister went on to Lament
Folding canoe
You're the former
Unipro fascist pro-nazi guy quote
I'm so ashamed he cannot face up to my ancestor
I do not want to repeat such a mistake and I want to avoid war with the United States at all cost
If at all possible I want to improve sino-japanese relations as well
I will give it my best shot
So won't you help me
And quote
It's interesting to wonder about a guy
In a position like that
Who's older has a
A moment where
He wants to undo
Stop may be seized
In a Flash or maybe a slowly developing realization
The
Haitians of what
What's involved here
How to describe
A
Japanese
Life insurance
Sail to it
People
Right during this time. As a way to make money right because there
Encircled by all the other powers
And she brings it all home though
He talks about
Well let me have her
Lights quote
Japan's leaders let the Diplomatic crisis Brew
Meanwhile it's people remained ignorant of such development
In a sweeping national campaign to raise money
Citizens were urged to buy National Life Insurance
Image Ally it was announced with great Fanfare that 50 million policies have been sold
Japan's population was about 73
Raising 10 billion yen almost 40% of the country's gross national product for 1941
Most of that money she writes
Went to purchase government bonds to fund Japan's War in China
Little did people know that their lives would become very cheap
Even worthless thanks to the government they so earnestly supported with their hard-earned
Hard save money
And quote
Not just that
But this is where
The Uber patriotism of the Japanese
He's coming to play here as we said earlier like everyone else only more so
I still feel like there was a
And a New York Times
Article
Just before the war broke out
Foraging John toland
The Rising Sun
We're someone over in
Asia is trying to explain to the American public
You not to
Downplay
The Japanese national spirit and what they're willing to do hey it's funny because if you think of many other country
In a situation with their government gets them in an unwinnable War
Where the cost
Will be everything to everyone
They might overthrow that government rather than go to war
The Japanese people
Are different
If you could have shown the leadership a crystal ball
It only showed 5 years into the future that have given up anything you have made any concessions in any sort of dip
Climatic.
The barring that
They could count on the
Support of a p
People
Takes
Patriotism
Can you level
Literally the day before War breaks out they'll be a
Cable sent the New York Times by one of their
People who
Is in Japan and understands the situation they're better than his Auto delicious
And the cable says
That the Japanese people are refusing to believe that they're just about to get into a war
With four nations simultaneous
Think about how many governments would be overthrown by their people if those governments got them in a situation that hopeless
The Japanese are
A different class of folk
And this
Writer is trying to point out to the New York Times readership
Exactly what things look like from the other side and don't underestimate these people
After saying that the Japanese don't believe that they're about to face
4 Nation simultaneously he continues by saying quote
But their instinctive hopes are daily contradicted by the evidence of their senses
They listen to alarming statements by the highest government officials
About the greatest crisis Japan has ever faced in her 2600 year history
We are called to mass meetings to hear denunciations of the enemy
And they read a steady War clamor in the Press
They see are shelters in water reservoirs being built everywhere in preparation for Air Raids
They're being drilled in Air Raid Offense
Especially in fighting fires
The greatest Japanese cities
Finally they see taxes and prices rising
They know that all these things are not done for fun
And that war real war which only a short time ago seems so very far away
Is rapidly stretching out its fiery arms towards nipon land of the Gods
The cable continues quote
The people do not want war
But neither do they want to give up the fruits of the war that they have been fighting which is costume such a lot of blood and treasure
They've been told that this war is a war of self-defense
To obtain Elbow Room for the Japanese people
Crowded into a few small Islands
A few national resources
Deliberate one thousand million of Oriental peoples
Exploitation by the white races
It would be a great mistake
The cable continues
To assume that the Japanese are so war-weary that they would be reluctant to fight if War really came to their land
Or that their War potential is a smaller is straightened at the outward picture might suggest
As members of a Divine family state
In which patriotism and religion merge
They not merely say
My country right or wrong
But they're convinced with all the fervor of religious faith that their country is right
Whatever mistakes in tactics individual states when they take
And quote
By the way it's this fervor
Something that sometimes wrapped up into something the Japanese call the Yamato spirit
That those Optimist were hoping for a positive outcome in any conflict with the West
Are sort of basing their hopes on right
If you look at 20th Century history by the way there is a lot of places that have tried to overcome
Industrial
And material imbalances by saying things like while we're tougher
Or a fighting Spirits better or what have you
And the Japanese have no choice but to put
Their hopes in the same sort of
Rationales after all
If the government gets a meeting right around this time. Where they're told that
The Japanese industrial capabilities
Even with all the steroids of the Chinese raw materials and everything else
R1
Madea
Of the United States has
Abilities and by the way
That number is a low
As well
So the Prime Minister Prince konoye
Puts his feelers forward and wants to have a meeting with Roosevelt in an attempt to it sounds like
You know use this intricate Japanese governmental system in a way where he plays chess with
The military officials and uses the emperor the nuclear bomb piece on the chessboard
To sort of checkmate
This war that's coming
In it he says
He needs
Is the
Agreement
With Roosevelt needs to come back with something so he proposes disagreement with Roosevelt Roosevelt can't come right away cuz he's mean
Meeting secretly with Winston Churchill
On some Naval vessels
In the Atlantic
And he'll come out of it with something that's known to history is the Atlantic Charter
A template for the governance of the post second world war world
Shorthand but
There's a lot of high-minded Woodrow Wilson type stuff in it
Self-determination
People should be able to elect their own governments a bunch of stuff that if you are the Japanese
Looks like it's directed squarely at you we celebrated in the United States in high school textbooks here
This is the kind of high-minded Western Democratic idealistic stuffing
We've lost a lot of human beings fighting Wars for those kind of values
But if you're the Japanese and someone saying that you know we're going to go
Towards shut down Nation who won't let people choose their own governments will what does that say about China
Right there not choosing the Japanese to govern them
So it sounds like it's directed at them what's more
It looks very hypocritical especially to
Peoples in Asia
When the British were on board with
Because the British are one of the great maybe they
The greatest of the colonial
Peoples
And so are you saying that this Atlantic Charter applies to you too are you signing on the dotted line and saying that you're going to let the people in
India
Vote if they want to have the British government have the role the British government has in India
In the 1930s for example
Churchill goes on to clarify
Like a month or two later no no no we're talking about
Pakistan access dominated lands here when I'm talking about
Eunos Singapore
Once again though to the peoples in Asia
This looks a little like okay it's World War 1 all over again these high-minded sediments don't apply to us
And even though the Japanese are raping China as they conquer it
They may not look as bad to Asians
As they do to the people in the western democracies
Roosevelt is apparently open to the idea of a meeting with the Japanese prime minister when he hears about it
But his advisors kind of shut it down
The Japanese have just rejected the latest diplomatic proposals and the
If I just a list of those need to be clarified before we meet
Now as we just discussed though
How long can you put this off
When the fleet burning 400 tons of fuel an hour right so this becomes another one of the problems and I'm not going to get into
All the many things
What happened in the last
It's a great
Era to look at if you are a fan of diplomatic history
The tit-for-tat things that go on but also the Mini Miss assessments misinterpretation
Miss readings
And
Lee mistranslations
What happened I mean in a famous case they'll be some Christian missionaries in the story well-meaning Folk
For trying to help everyone a vertica tastrophe here
Did the Japanese think
Are working you as a back Channel for the US government
But really aren't
And this confuses matters for a while I mean it's one of these occasions where you wish you had
What the Soviet Union in the United States
Add at one point
The Cold War
Set the battle in the red phone the hotline
And you can just call up the emperor the head of the Japanese government
Talk to them directly with instant translation
But you didn't have that
But even if you did
Is there enough room on the core issues to compromise on any of this stuff
One of the compromises that
The Prime Minister had to make to even reach out to Roosevelt
Was a deal apparently with the army
It is the diplomacy didn't work
Heat set a timetable for war
Well the diplomacy didn't work
Apparently Kanye
There is a significant amount of responsibility for getting Japan into this mess
Didn't want to sign off on
The ramifications of it and have his John Hancock any War declarations or anything he didn't see any way out he said the emperor
Basically going over to the other side now
And so what's the point and resign
The emperor replaces him
One of the
Hawkish
Figures out there
The head of the war Ministry former General
In the kwantung army
A man whose nickname was the razor
The name is Hideki
Keto Mojo
And now we haven't placed the entire
Leadership that you're normally dealing with
When you talk about this conflict
Tell Joe in the American war propaganda
Was simply
Turned into the figure that Americans could hate in the same way that they had Hitler and Mussolini
He's the dictator of Japan is the way it's portrayed
And this continued for decades after the war
Because this became part of the propaganda that help
She'll be Emperor from war crimes charges and by the way
Several modern historians think the emperor might have been executed for war crimes
And those charges been allowed to happen
But if you say the emperor is a puppet with no power and you say he's a tool of the militarists
How do you say the general Tojo the head of the militarists will then you just transferred all the
Emperor's wartime responsibility to decide their figure and that's what the American propaganda kind of Dead 2
Told you looks like your typical Japanese hardliner General but not as far as some of those Imperial Wayfair
Faction people
You can't really say he's like a Hitler
For Mussolini or Stalin
Because unlike them
He has a boss
A boss that it's
Likely
But he saw as the living embodiment of a god
That's a very different situation than someone like Stalin or Hitler
Example
It also means
He has to do what he's told
There's a lot of theories on the emperor for all the reasons why
We talked about but one of them is that this move
To put this Army General in control is not what most people think it is most people think this is a sign that they give
Even in there going to go to war if we going to go to war they wanted general in charge
But some people say that no this is actually the emperor is sneaky attempt to avoid war
This is a minority point of view obviously but
Those who push this idea suggests
But it's a
Nixon goes to China, Scituate
Malaysian
The ol Switcheroo the emperor
Appoints one of the really big
Noisy Hawk to this position of prime minister
He has all the respect of the other Hawks and militarists
And then you the emperor someone this person sees potentially as a living God
Orders this Hawk
To make peace
Somehow
Without War
And then he'll cover your rear end with the other military is right cuz he's got total credibility
It's an interesting Theory
One thing is for sure is that the emperor orders Tojo to pursue diplomacy until the last possible minute and he fall
How old is the emperor's orders
But he's working
With the deadline
And it's a deadline that changes a couple of times but eventually becomes a hard deadline where you have all over Asia
Preparations in
In place
Manor on the move
Shipping is being co-opted things are happening and preparations are underway
Unless something intervenes to stop now
This momentum
Things are going to happen
And I will be set
In the future
Automatically
The inertia we've been talking about for a while now
He's becoming almost on the stop
Football in the final deadline
Now for some sort of diplomat
Breakthrough
Is the end of November
There's a lot of different interpretations of
Hideki Tojo
What kind of guy he is
One thing you never read about him though
Is any sort of suggestion
But he was insane
That's
Basically what
Winston Churchill is saying
Did any Japanese government that would allow their country to slip into a war with the Anglo Mary
And at this point
Is crazy suicidal is the way I think
He puts a Churchill rights
And right after the war
Quote
It it seemed impossible that Japan would Court destruction by war with Britain and the United States and probably
Russia in the end
A declaration of war by Japan could not be reconciled with reason
I felt sure she would be ruined for Generation by such a plunge and this proved true
What governments and people do not always take rational decision
Sometimes they take mad decision
For one set of people get control
To compel all others to obey and Aid them in Folly
I have not hesitated to record repeatedly he writes
My disbelief the Japan would go mad
However sincerely we try to put ourselves in another person's position we cannot allow four processes of the human
Imagination
To which reason offers no key
He sums up
By saying
Quote
Madness is however and affliction which in war carries with it the advantage of surprise
And quote
The word surprise
Is italicized in the original
In order to
Get a little back
And on how
Any surprise my
Place
When you're talkin
Powers that are so far away from each other
You got to go back to 1940
1941 late night
1940's part of the demonstrations are resolved in the public displays
The bolster diplomacy and whatnot the Roosevelt administration did a couple of
Big moves one of them was
To reactivate general Douglas MacArthur
Us
General it was acting as Field Marshal the Philippine military
Reactivating in the Philippines and let him sort of publicly start consolidating a
Preparing just in case any message to Japan
The other thing
Was to demonstrate resolve and all that kind of stuff
The Roosevelt administration did was they took the Pacific u.s. Pacific Fleet which is normally based on the west coast of the United States
And moved it to Hawaii
What is still a 6-hour Jet Plane ride towards Asia from the US West Coast
Based in Pearl Harbor
What you know
One man's intimidation move could be another man's
Opportunity
But it takes
A person who's almost a little bit crazy
To see it
Sometimes that's what creative Geniuses are
Sometimes you just
Require somebody willing to gamble
Farther than most
People are willing
Home to go
Enter
Merle isoroku yamamoto
Did the story
The name's familiar he's famous and
He's famous for both being a creative military genius
Crazy gambler
You met him in person you probably
We would not be very intimidated he stood
543 Maybe
Was missing several major fingers
From one
Hand and walk with a limp because an entire chunk of his
Leg been torn off along with those fingers
In probably the most famous Naval
Unify battle.of
Ashima
The
Improbable
Almost near impossible happened when an Asian Fleet defeated
European Fleet and I mean resoundingly
As we had talked about earlier
Japanese
Destroyed the Russian
Pretended
Yamamoto was there as a Young office
Officer and badly wounded and almost love
Lost his life
That is one of the battles that will often be cited as an inspiration for Yamamoto
Idea here
And idea that is so crazy and improbable in so much of a Gamble
It when he presents it to the other Admirals you know on the big decision board
They reject it
And
It's a sign of how brilliant he was and this was recognized by his peers
That when he threatened to resign if they rejected it
They change their mind
They rather accept an idea they thought was crazy
Then Lose the person who came up with it because they acknowledge what I created military genius
He is
He didn't develop these plan by the way alone
He had spent more than a year working with other notice
People people that are famous in the story with my favorite one of them
Is a one historian described him as he's a military guy that he's a Gandhi like
Figure who chain smokes and leaves Trails of Ashes behind him
Seems like a you know a
Einstein
Flash
Archimedes Sheldon Cooper kind of figure
Doesn't bathe
Apparently or doesn't bathe very often locks himself in completely darkened rooms naked
Transpiration in dominicanas writes things down really quickly in a piece of these this fascinating like wild character
Who can come up with an idea that is so crazy
That the other side definitely doesn't see it coming
And is so unusual and unexpected that I find it hard to even blame them
For not seeing it coming
I said about the 9/11 attack
Before
But even though there were warnings about them it just seems so improbable
And seems so dwarfed by other
Potential bad things that you're also getting warnings about that seem much more likely
But it's only with hindsight that you look back
Can go God why weren't we more Vigilant why do we see this coming
Who would have seen
A surprise attack
On US territory
It was coming from a power that was 4000 miles away
Remember this is an era before cruise missile
Before even airplanes that could get
You know without a refueling stop
From Japan
To replace like Hawaii I don't think they could get all the way that certainly can get to the West Coast certainly couldn't go round trip
So if you're in a place like Hawaii how afraid are you
The Japanese are going to strike you especially since you know you don't even have a war in the answer is
Not very afraid
Yamamoto and friend
Are going to come up with an idea
To win a war
But he doesn't believe
Is winnabow
That's an interesting thing to
Task
Somebody with IBS
Yamamoto like a lot of these Japanese
Leaders especially the Navy Yamamoto went to Harvard
For a little while
He has a famous line about you until you see in the factories of Duty
Troy do the oil fields of Texas you know you don't know what you're talkin about
When you want to make war
The Uso
Famously
How it is
Let's just call him extremely realistic like a lot of guys in the Navy which is part of the reason the Navy was
More against
Fighting the Anglo America
We said earlier
They understand they're going to be doing most of the fighting
Historian area Ulta
Has him talking to another app
And basically predicting the way the Warriors going to go
Yamamoto tells Admiral Lugano
Quote
If I might add
It is evident that the US Japanese war is bound to be protractor
The United States will not give up fighting as long as Japan has the upper hand
The war will last for several years
In the meantime Japan's resources will be depleted battleships and weaponry will be damaged replenish
Fishing materials will be impossible
Japan will be impoverished
He didn't famously concluded quote
A war with so little chance of success should not be fought
And quote
But it was his job none of us to come up with a way to
How to do it
The plan has been I mean there's a lot of accounts it's famous some people being a say it's inspired by a famous Samurai by
Got a long time ago
Some people say the Battle of tsushima that
Yamamoto was out of the inspiration
Others point to something much more recent in 1940
A British
Task force in the Mediterranean with a single aircraft
Carrier and British aircraft carrier to not
Cherry Lana
By Pacific Standard
And their airplanes are very outdated by
Tipping standards
Launched an attack against the Italian Fleet
Which was anchored in Port
At night
These outdated biplane
And they were I think between 20 and 30 of them overall but a minute times you had like six of them attacking
Did a large amount of damage and put a bunch of these ships out of commission for quite a while
The Japanese are there was a Japanese
Envoy or advisor
Attache in Berlin who I just came down to look at
Effects at the harbor at Toronto the 19
E-40 battle
It's called and sent that back
To Japan so all of these things were studied in by January 1941
Yamamoto is God
A like mock-up
Of Pearl Harbor in an out-of-the-way place and he's got people sort of just planning for this he's wargaming it
In the challenges by the way are immense
Because the battlefield
What is a man
This conflict which we fought in the Pacific but will instantly sucking all the Asian
Warfare this been going on now for several years already
This is a battlefield so large you could drop whole continent
The room all around the edges
Logistics
You know getting the stuff that the armies and navies need to fight and operate
Where they need to be in the quantities you need to have them is going to be the sort of challenge that overhangs every op
Operation
And will in large part determine the success or failure of them
For this entire conflict that's the overriding
In a military challenge in this theater
Distance
How to get an idea
Of the kind of distance were talking about uniform comparison purposes
At this same time where we are in the story in October November 1941
Wolverine
Well I was going to say you're a butt it's almost
It on the way to Asia
Outside the doors of Moscow the vert mocked is fighting what they hope we're going to be these climactic
Battles with the Soviet Union's capital is going to fall
But they're facing all sorts of logistical trouble right their supply lines are
Famously stretched to the Limit
The Germans are now relearning the lessons you could have asked
Earlier conquerors about Napoleon could have explained the whole problem
While he was trying to
Deal with supply issues
When taking Moscow hats you could go back to
Charles the twelfth of Sweden before Napoleon he could have told you the same story
That when you get that far away from your base of operations it's hard to get the troops at the head of the snake you know as a
It's called what they need to fight
Berlin to Moscow is Like A Thousand Miles about as the crow flies anyway
Longer when you want you
Go on those roads
But for perspective
Tokyo to Oahu which is the first
You're not to downplay anybody but in the first significant u.s. territory closest to Japan
The Guam
Alaskan Island things like that but that's 4000 miles away
4 times the distance from Berlin to Moscow so if they're having problems keeping the
Vermox applied
It over by Moscow think about what it takes
To transport everything you need
To keep an army put together across the Pacific
This is part of the war plans that the Japanese have had now for more than a decade
Everyone knows right that major militaries have War plans in the back of their Dusty files
The cover almost any eventuality you can think of I mean you got to do something
You're not doing anything else and coming up with a plan
The United States to fight Canada the Canadians get all uppity
Well you know that's just covering all your bases and by the way there was a plant
In this case the Japanese plan
For dealing with the United States involved the Philippines
This is sort of
Bait
They were going to take the Philippines
And then when the United States sent the fleet over to contest it
They were going to have a trap set
This trap was going to be aided by they envisioned
Aircraft and submarines that would use Island bases farther out of the Pacific and they could
Sort of like
Gnats
Or mosquitoes weakening the us all along the way
You don't have them in a condition not feeling so excited about fighting and then they walk into a trap
If you look at the way the Japanese Navy is put together
It's designed especially like their newer unit is designed for this trap
Situation
Anyone who is a fan of the Japanese Navy in the second world war knows
That it was constrained by treaties and other things and not allowed to be as big as the British Fleet
What do you ask
Sleet
So what do you do if your the Japanese and you got those kind of constraints will they decided to go quality
Instead
If we can only have so many battleships let's make them really good battleships
Just as Wars about to break out of here the Japanese are finishing up the field trials
Of the most powerful Battleship not just in the world
The most powerful Battleship that will ever be built
It's famous it's the Yamato
The only other ship is powerful is the Yamato that will ever be built
Is it sister ship
The Musashi that's only a little bit behind
The Yamato
And then behind that is another one called the shin I know
All of these
Ships
Will it rain
Their American counterparts
They have
An unbelievable amount of armor they are enormous their guns are 18.1 in
The nearest Naval competitor with 16-inch guns
19.1 inch gun just so you know and the Yamato has nine of them
Can fire a car
In terms of weight
26 miles
The window shells landed the destruction was enormous
The best battleships
Germany
The Bismarck
Tirpitz
The best battleships of the United States in the Iowa-class Missouri type battleships
You write down the specs for the
Side by side with the Yamato class and there's no
Comparison
These super
Battleship
So they're often termed
We're going to be the major hammers that
Would come down on the American Fleet that's across the Pacific
We can buy submarines and aircraft the entire way across
And during the Ambush This Is How They
Going to be destroyed
In this existing long-term job
Japanese war plan
Then what's interesting is the plan from that point on once you gain this big advantage over the American Fleet
Is the hunker down and sort of wait for the armistice
Remind you a little of how the Russo Japanese war and
Right
The mistake in this thinking and it will be
The mistake in the thinking in the Second World War
Is what if the other side refuses to do the Armistice thing
Well Admiral Yamamoto is
Atypical aggressive Commander there very few commanders that like to allow the enemy to seize the initiative
To choose the place of Battle 2
Tacit the time
Of their
These are all standard military sayings and Yamamoto has argument about the whole existing plan of the strap
Is worth the American don't take the bank
What are they don't come across the Pacific
When you want them to what they stay home and build up their Fleet which they're doing already
Supercharged and then come over
What if they go around your trap I mean it's a whole lot of really good argument
Yamamoto has
Sing something
This is the audaciousness
That we spoke about earlier this gambler but at the same time somebody who's a Visionary a Visionary is someone who sees something
Ahead of the crowd
Yamamoto sees what there are other Visionaries who also see by the way
The potential of aircraft carrier
We in the modern world have a hard time not seeing the potential of aircraft carriers do the capital ships of our air
And having one or not having one sort of differentiates first-class Navy's from other class navies
But remember it's going to be the second world war where these lessons are learned
We should also point out there for the first
More than two years of the war there's only one power that's really using aircraft carriers in combat so they're the only one
One's really learning a developing these techniques
And that's the British by the way
The Germans and the Italians their principal opponents during the
Two years before the Japanese Americans are in the war
They don't have any aircraft carrier
Which means the British don't have to get into this
Technological race where they have to respond to the Innovations of the other side in carrier Warfare
Guy doesn't have any carriers
And the British being the quintessential Battleship Navy
They see the use of these carriers as something that
Increases the force multiplier for there
Naval task force
Normally don't put a carrier with a naval task force in them all of a sudden it has Ariel capability which is a
Of course awesome
You can scout way ahead now the range
A visibility now these ships is increased
Once they spotted enemy Naval unit they can harass it
Attacking and hopefully maybe you could cripple it or slow it down so that
When the rest of the fleet catches them
They can destroy the naval units of the enemy with Naval gunfire and 4p
By the way can be aided by spotting from the
Airplanes to Seoul
It's this role where they are
Something that fits into British
Naval Doctrine pretty well
The attack at Toronto by the way is one of those areas where the Fleet air arm as it's called becomes extra
Are useful because the rest of the Navy can't reach the Italian Fleet and do damage with Naval gunfire so what the heck
Low-risk Venture send them in there and see what happens and everybody was
Astonished by how well the results turned out
I like Yamamoto
Is one of those people that allows you to jump several steps in the normal linear technological
Development
Instead of the normal in this is
Pretty typical in military circles you don't want to
Take too many chances if you're doing one thing different than the last time they tried that's considered innovation
A guy like Yamamoto allows you to skip several steps here cuz he looks at the Toronto situation it basically says
If they can do that with one carrier
And 2230 outmoded by planes
What is instead of one carrier you had something like
Aircraft
Carriers
And what if instead of 20 or 30 outmoded biplanes you had more than 400
Of the most modern technologically sophisticated
Aerial attack monoplane
Also attacking by the way another Fleet
Tied up
Import
Yamamoto doesn't see aircraft carriers
As something that aids the Strikeforce Yamamoto sees them as the strike
Force
And instead of
The naval gunfire being the setup to destroy
The enemy ships which was part of the old Japanese trap plan to wasn't it
He sees the planes from the carriers themselves
Sinking the enemy ships
It's hard not to see that is completely obvious with our modern mentality but not only is this a revolution
Missionary and controversial idea
Without the data to really back it up think of what a gamble it is and Yamamoto says something at one point like at this plan fail
We just need to give up
Well that shows you how much of a gamble it is and watching this whole thing take place is like watching a guy play a car
Card game
Where the odds of winning are low
Annie's been his family's lives on the outcome
In a lot of situations where you see big
Audacious Gamble
The store Yamamoto is working with here
It's because people are in relatively hopeless situations and it's better to take a chance
Because what's going to happen if you don't is worse in the case of
Like cities that are under siege armies that are surrounded
Are you just going to die anyway so why not try a gamble here what have you got to lose
In the case of Yamamoto
The Japanese government in the Japanese nation state they have a lot to lose
Their people are
For the most part speaking right now on a relative
Curved
That your crystal ball would make clear if you could see five years in the future
Are safe
Relatively prosperous
You want to talk about worst-case scenarios here it's not what the American sanctions could do to you it's that with the anglo-american
Demands that you
Attract your Empire could do to you it's what losing in this metaphorical card game that Yamamoto is playing
Cuz he's betting with the live
Is peep
People
Let's be honest
Betting is cities
Is the way it's going
Workout
So what does he have to
To do to win
Well
This offensive attack against the US Fleet in Yamamoto spaces designed to do the same thing that the old trap was designed
As we said
Get the fleet out of the way
What's the fleet got to be out of the way for
So the Japan could take over
A huge chunk of Asia and the Pacific
And then hunker down
And beat off any efforts by the anglo-americans to win it back
And within this core
Surrounded by a defense perimeter that is
Yuan the largest Battlefield in human history
Would be the resources that Japan needs
For self-sufficiency
So you grab the resources you need to continue
Being a first-class power
To continue to support the war effort
You create a huge perimeter a long distance around that is defended
And then you make the cost of taking it back higher than you think the other side is
Willing to pay
This is where the Rose Colored Glasses
Start coming in
Things and according to writer
Cebu Road yonaga
He points out that in all the estimations that the military government have to come up with your all the numbers that you're plugging in
For the unknowable the x's in the wise
Are all sort of Rose Colored Glasses best case scenario
How do you beat the anglo-americans will you take over all this territory and then the Yamato Spirit of the Japanese
Warrior
Will Outlast the soft westerners and they won't be willing to pay the price that you have to take to do this
So they will negotiate and we will have some sort of an Armistice in Japan will come out ahead
Especially if you demoralize The Americans
Estimating their Fleet at the outset
And get a
Advantage on the now the Pearl Harbor attacks they're going to come out of this
Americans have a tendency to tunnel vision and I do this myself
And forget
That is simply a means to an end
The elimination of the American Fleet which is the goal of the Pearl Harbor attack is merely meant to cover
The Rising Sun of Japan going supernova
And acquiring this defense perimeter and the raw materials resources and oil within it
The sculpt
Of the plan for this is
Breathtaking
And it's hot
But I keep running out of words to use audacity is the one I keep coming back to
Remember this is a country that is tied down heavily already on the Asian mainland
But here's what historian Ronald H Spector
Describes
As the plans here
Is it going to all kind of take place starting at the same time
He writes quote
The Japanese plan to seize and occupy a vast area
Including all of Southeast Asia they did not already hold
Burma
Siam
Malaya the Philippines and the Dutch East Indies
Japan would occupy the American Island outposts of Guam and wake
She would also destroy here at least neutralize the Pacific Fleet at Pearl Harbor
On the first day of the war the Philippines Himalaya where to be hit by air attacks followed soon after buying
Invasion
Simultaneously he writes
Troops would occupy British Borneo in Hong Kong
What's the Philippines
And the Malay Peninsula with it's important Fortress of Singapore have been taken the conquest of Burma
And the Dutch East Indies would follow
And quote
Now you can't hide
Preparations
4 operations on that
Scale
And the British and the Americans
Figure out the something big is happening they C troop ships moving they
Hear things in the codes that they broke and they're seeing the redeployment of forces it's a big thing and it takes months in month
Ironically though
It's sort of attracts their attention in a way that diverts their attention from what's going on
In the very northernmost islands of Japan with short stretch up towards Siberia and really Frozen
Foggy
In a rainy condition
Is it just sort of
Hi
Big warships
By the latter part of November the job
Annies of quietly in mask
The most powerful aircraft
Carrier Strike Force in world history up until that
Current time in these Northern harbors
6 aircraft carrier
Prayers together
Couple of battle
Bunch of oil
Supplies destroyers in
Support ship
Shrouded in the fog and Mist up there in the North
Not coincidentally right around the same time that that
Time limit
Aspiring
On the diplomacy has to work soon or else timetable
On December 1st
Its or else
Time
And enough famous meeting the Japanese emperor in what some historians refer to as a meaningless ceremony to confirm something
Already done
Others confuse the
Event with
With some decision-making power nonetheless it's the official
If the Japanese were going to have an official public declaration of war this would have been if but it's not public and nobody knows about it if you're not in
Get on it but this is where the decisions made signed off on
And by the time that happens
That Fleet that have been sort of hiding in the Mist
In the northern harbors
With the six carriers
Has already Departed
Out to sea
And is disappearing in the fog Banks of a northern route
Which avoids normal shipping lanes
And at this point
Interestingly enough
American intelligence which monitors were all the Japanese big ships are found this fast
Before the second World War
They already generally know the location
The carriers in the battleships
Oh that's true radio traffic
They lose
Side of them which leads to a famous
Pearl Harbor related quote
With one of the Admiral
On the island. You mean the Japanese League Of You rounding Diamond Head right now and we wouldn't even know it
The Americans knew war was coming so did the British in fact
There's no
Anticipation in terms of will it or won't it happen in the
Couple of weeks before it does
The question is what's going to happen when it breaks out
The Americans are pretty darn sure you're going to see moves to take over those resources we talked
The Japanese are going to strike in Southeast Asia maybe the Dutch East Indies probably the Philippines
What they don't see coming
Isn't attack across 4000 miles of ocean at them
It is very good book on
Pearl Harbor
Call Pearl Harbor
Is author Craig Nelson quotes some of the
Wonderful
Pieces of dialogue
Were extracted after
The fact that
Look either prophetic
Or
Yashow some sort of
Vulnerability to
That was exploited
By the surprise attack and in one of these
This conversation
He has
The various Admirals in military
Leaders in Hawaii right is late November
Talking about sending planes to some of these islands that they're worried about the Japanese hitting
And the Air Force Commander on Hawaii basically says don't send airplanes away we have to defend Hawaii
Which kind of stuns Admiral Kimmel who basically says
Are you worried about Hawaii
Nelson rights quote
The Hawaiian Air Forces Chief of Staff James Mollison return to shorts original point and he saying now
Our mission is to protect Oahu
And shipping out those Army planes will lessen our capability to do so
Kimmel wanted details on his thinking
Why are you so worried about
Do you think we are in danger of attack
When Mollison replied
The Japanese have such a capability the Admiral argued
Capability yes but
Possibility
The author continues quote
Kimmel Ben asked his naval war plans officer rear Admiral Charles McMorris
What do you think about the prospects of a Japanese Air Attack
McMorris said none absolutely not
And quote
So it doesn't matter how often
The American ministration gets a warning that Osama Bin Laden is bent on attacking the United States and is
In a rumor to be thinking about using airplanes to run into buildings
It doesn't seem real amongst all the other information that's out there until it happens and then after happens you can go
Go back and pick out those points
And they stand out like a sore thumb
Just like that
In a do you mean to say they could be
Rounding Diamond Head right now
Well
Here's what we know they don't have to round diamond head because that strike force that is indeed approaching
11 area north
Of Hawaii
As aircraft carrier that can launch planes without ever getting that close to the Hawaiian Islands
And on the morning of December 7th
Early
They begin to do that
By this time in the plans unfolding
The attack on Pearl Harbor you would have to say that they had
I've been very fortunate
Some of the wargaming that they had done prepping for this event
And had the United States discovered them on the way in the Japanese Fleet having to fight its way within range of
Hawaii to make it
Sackbut
They managed to get 220 miles north of a wahoo
Without being detected
The plane start launching in a really rough Sea by the way
At 5:50 a.m. buy like 6:15 6:20 they got the first wave up in the sky and that's a lot
Aircraft by the way and the efficiency is going to be
Notably Japanese
This first wave by the way consists of 43 fighter planes 49 high-level bombers
51 dive bombers and 40
Torpedo plane
At 6:20 it heads towards Oahu
The Japanese begin
Bringing up the next way
2Go follow up
And this
Gamble
This
Huge audacious plan by Admiral Yamamoto and Company is underway
Ironically
The commander of this operation a guy named nagumo
Not at all day shift guy much more so if conservative Commander
Who doesn't
Seems like he's got a whole lot of faith in this point it's interesting that you'd have the
The
Creative thinker who's really the Visionary come up with the idea and then put the implementation of it into the hands of somebody much
Less likely to
Will follow up in an aggressive way because
Is nature butt
None of those planes got off with
Great efficiency in when they're on their way to Hawaii
Hawaii is sleeping
There's a reason why the most famous books ever written about the Pearl Harbor attack
Actress called
At dawn we slept
Because not only is Hawaii
Sleeping it's Sunday morning everybody sort of rousing a little bit late
But it's a peaceful Island and I don't just mean in and
Environmental sense I mean in a diplomatic one
Are these aircraft are approaching
It was going to be there attack Target
The country they're going to attack
Isn't it war with them
Need a lot of controversy that has arisen
Ever since about whether we was supposed to be
There seems little to no doubt that the attacks against British possessions in Asia where to be carried
Don without wanting those were to be surprised
Whether or not that was supposed to be the same situation against the US
There are different points of view
And I'm not qualified to pay
Pokemon
For a long time
The official Japanese point of view from their historians
Basically said it was a screw
On the part of their diplomatic people
In Washington DC you didn't get the material
To the right place the right
And because of that what should have been there early enough to be sort of Advance warning didn't happen that way
There's a Japanese writer couple years ago that is part of a minority school that suggests that that's all the covered it was always a
Intended to be
You know I'm officially late by
Right ;-)
I kind of like author Craig Nelson
Ian is Pearl Harbor book
His point of view on it though because
It really does sound like
What probably happened which was there there was going to be
A very short window
Write a here here's a declaration of war 5 minutes later boom bombs dropped actually 30 minutes
Later seems to be about what they were after he writes quote
Going by the way plan Z means the plan to attack
Pearl Harbor quote
From the beginning
Imperial Japanese army officers plan to invade Singapore without giving prior notice to Britain
But the Imperial Japanese Navy felt very differently about the United States and operations e
After the Imperial conference on December 1st in fact
The emperor told prime minister Hideki Tojo repeatedly
But he was not to attack the United States without warning
Naval attache Duro sahi Matsu explained the sense of Honor that was a Hallmark of
Japanese military history
This is
This officer explaining now
Quote
Japanese warriors never tried to assassinate a person who is sleeping
When they tried to kill him they first kicked the pillow and woke him up and then killed him
The same principle applied to the attack
The required time to wake America up would be approximately 30 minutes
And quote
Now what Nelson says that really makes sense is
The Pepto really fine line to walk 30 minutes it doesn't allow for any kind of script at all and there's a bunch of
Things that have to happen and go well
And it didn't
Regardless of which point of view
You were here too
It's clear that the people in Hawaii didn't know this was coming and the American people didn't know this was coming in because
Is it bad
Their Wrath
For this entire War
Will be
Visceral
It is interesting in one history not read did this he said he didn't want to be interesting to imagine how different the mood might have
Have been
Had the Japanese said one day ahead of time we're at War and then struck
Interesting to speculate isn't it
The same time though
If it's a minor miracle that the Japanese can get a strike force this close to Hawaii
In peacetime
How much of a major Miracle would they have needed
To pull off the same thing in Wartime
You can make a case that
Yamamoto
Plan
Really
Requires in order to be successful.
Kind of
Surprised that you only get in a diplomatic situation where War hasn't broken out yet
You might need that
For this plan to work and remember
The stakes involved here are enormous
So I always try to imagine
I mean what they must have felt like both in Tokyo the leadership the emperor all those people who know that this is
About to happen you're looking at their watch wondering what's happening at this very moment
To the leadership
With the Strikeforce nagumo and his staff I think they're on the ikagi the aircraft
Carrier
To the leadership of the first wave Strike Force itself it's led by a guy named forsheda by the way
And he's been involved in the planning for this for a long time he's fully aware the stakes
He understands that what Yamamoto said
Is true which is if this attack doesn't do what we needed to do we might have to give up the war
And he understands what breaks they have to get to have a chance of the attack working
The first break he needs a surprise we have to achieve the surprise that we're out
There are a couple of famous things that happened on the morning of December 7th
That could have blown the surprise out of the water and ruin the whole thing they famously
We didn't there much investigated as you might imagine
After the events in after the war because they
Schinus failure isn't probably rightly so
The first one was
In the early morning hours like
Play 3 4 a.m.
Before the attack planes even take off
Midget submarine
Are discovered in Pearl Harbor these almost slipped call them suicide missions cuz that's what they turned out to be
Several Japanese midget submarines were part of this operation
A couple were discovered
An alert was sent and destroyers are soda
Agitated now
In the early morning hours there's activity stirred up in Pearl Harbor that
Wouldn't have been stirred up if those midget submarines hadn't been part of the plan Yamamoto was never
Them by the way
And then closer to the actual time of the attack
As the more than a hundred planes are
Making their way towards a wahoo they're picked up on Hawaiian radar
Which is a
The new thing in this.
Had War already been declared it's hard to imagine that this would not have prompted a major response
The fact that war isn't existing yet kind of help
Wings To Go
The Japanese way
Also the fact that Hawaii is like a giant aircraft carrier all by itself with planes incoming and outgoing all the time
Makes it easier for the radar operation people to rationalize
Many many planes they all of a sudden see on their radar
As something else for example to have some b-17s a big heavy bombers do in
Easy to confuse them with that maybe
In hindsight it should have been seen for what it was but it was
Something that makes the Japanese chances
At Pearl Harbor at least now possible
At about 7:40
A.m.
The first wave of the Japanese attack planes break through the clouds over a wahoo
Lacey Pearl Harbor
And they don't see any anti-aircraft fire or anything like that they don't see much activity it's obvious that they have not
Not been discovered in the surprise has been achieved
What they don't see this is the first piece of bad luck in the first bad breakup
Did the Japanese aircraft carriers and Scout playing
Zoomed by here 10 15 20 minutes previously didn't see them either
And
No other Navy on the planet would have understood the potential value
Of an aircraft carrier more than this one obviously
They probably would have traded
A battleship or an aircraft carrier in terms of what they would have rather sunk
But while they may not have any aircraft carriers they have a bunch of battleships just sitting there
Appreciate it types out
I signal device
The famous abolition controversial
About to snap about weather
He was meant to weigh
It sounded in his
Portrayed famously in Italy Tora Tora Tora which means tiger tiger tiger
And this is supposed to be the message not just to the fleet but it's
Picked up all the way miraculously
How the signal in Tokyo to telling everyone who's in the know that this is happening
The surprise has been achieved
Way
It's described in at dawn we slept when you think about the
The unbelievable amount
Attention
Someone like oh I don't know Admiral nagumo with the strike force would have felt
A conservative guy doesn't have much faith in this plant anyway but realizes as everyone does just like Yamamoto hats
Sad and I'm paraphrasing but if this plane doesn't work
We'll have to end the war
This is
The gamble for everything in this is the call moment in the poker game
Here's the way
Author Gordon W praying
Describes it in at dawn we slept quote
Bushido's radio was still clicking when the first wave broke into its component parts
Kushida swung around Barbers Point
And sure beyond all possible doubt that they had indeed achieve maximum strategic surprise at 7:53
3 a.m. he sang out
Tora Tora Tora
Tiger tiger tiger
The code Words which told the entire Japanese Navy that they had caught the Pacific Fleet unaware
Aboard
The aircraft carrier
Ikagi
Kusaka was not in the least ashamed of the tears which coursed down his windburn cheeks
Impassive Zen Buddhist though he was
Admiral nagumo could not have other the word had life and honor depended on it
Incredibly
Miraculously
They had brought off yamamoto's madcap venture
What's island in the stink
Each man stretched out his hand to the other
And in their eyes were all the words they could not
Ndk
All these planes begin to split up
Into their component parts this is all well rehearse stuff everybody knows what they're supposed to do
And many of these planes don't go anywhere near Pearl Harbor
They go to airfields all over the island and they knock out
Not just the airfields but any planes that they find and unfortunately Americans were more concerned
With sabotage during this periods in something like this
They parked all the planes like wingtip to wingtip which just makes it easier to guard
What makes them
An easy to shoot up from the airport Uso
Nagumo and the strike force of carriers the main worry that they have two hundred and some miles north of Hawaii
Is it they're going to get hit with a counter-attack
The only things Hawaii can counter-attack them with our ships
And playing
So the Japanese attack takes both of those into account
And there will be planes
Singing all over the aisle
And in fact in an event Witness by tens of thousands of people in one way or another
There are so many stories about what happens on this day
Some of which are obviously misremembered and exaggerated but none of them are first hand accounts of people who witnessed
Something they never forgot because it was the most momentous thing of their lives
When they watch this attack on the fold
I myself have a friend whose father
As a kid
Was working on a
It was higher up and a Japanese plane flew right past him and he in the pilot
Made eye contact
There's a lot of stories like that by the way
About seeing the gold teeth of the
The pilot for the pilot
Smiling or waving in fact as the planes approach Pearl Harbor
One of the workers at Pearl Harbor says he waved to the Japanese pilot
Because the Japanese pilot was waving to him
And in a remarkable coincidence that
Seems almost to Hollywood movie making style to be even true
These Japanese attack planes swarm down on Pearl Harbor right is the flag raising Sarah
Ramoni that happens in the morning is happening
And the bands like on the Nevada they've got the Nevada band and they're doing the Star-Spangled Banner like out of Apocalypse Now
Explosion starting with the bands playing on and by the way the Nevada band would finish the Stars
Star Spangled Banner
Even though they were being straight
While they were doing it in the flask was full of bullet holes
If you want to talk
How unprepared people were for a war with Japan
Even after the bombs started falling American
Saylor's especially are looking at this and thinking it's just a screw up
There was no US Air Force at this time there was an Army Air corps to Navy Air corps
And the Navy people are looking at this thinking some army guy really screwed up and put real bombs on these plans cuz they've been
Watching Army exercises for a long time in this just looks like a
Huge mistake
Although one of my favorite
Quotes that is in a lot of the history books
Is the one sailor who turns to his body even after the explosions have started
And says quote
This is the best goddamn drill the Army's ever put on
And quote
Don't know soon enough it's not a drill
When you look at the timeline from this encounter
You'll notice that right after it starts the
The torpedo planes are
Honing in on the vulnerable battleships that are on the outside of some of these pairs
The makeup was called Battleship row
If you look at an actual diagram you'll notice that not all the battleships are in pairs but several of them are
The ones that are in pairs means that the that one ship is on sort of the Waterside and the other ship is on the
Dockside
The ship is on the dark side is protected by the outside ship
Those outside ships are going to take the brunt of the
Torpedoes
And the Torpedoes are shipped
They got like 500 pounds of explosives they weigh over a thousand pounds or 17 or 18
Feet long
A single plane will carry a single torpedo slung under it
The plane will fly low reloader the water sometimes below the level of the height of the ship there tour
Peter Wang
Drop the torpedo and then speed off
These Torpedoes by the way have been specially designed for Pearl Harbor because normally
They dive so deep when you drop them
If they would just embed themselves in the mud of a harbor
The problem is once again that the Japanese designers here don't know if they're going to work so the very last major
Gamble the entire operation here
Is due the ship killers
Working this hard because if they don't you're screwed
Annie's book
Target Pearl Harbor
Author Michael slackman
Describe
The opening of this attack and it's pretty clear
The Torpedoes work
Human rights quote
As the attack began at 7:55 a.m.
Unbelieving Americans watched his bombs rain down on Hickam in Ford Island Airfield
What a little flying Kate
Those are planes
Released their Torpedoes against the ships
Unforward Islands Westside Utah an old Battleship was a Target ship now
Moored in the aircraft carrier Enterprises usual place and possibly mistaken for a carrier Buy in any
Experience Japanese pilot torpedoes
Another struct cruiser Raleigh
Morton line ahead
Both ships began to list
And the target ship capsized at 8:12
What Riley's Crusade the cruiser
My heroic damage control efforts
On the opposite shore of Ford Island he writes
Torpedo struck Nevada
Arizona
West Virginia
Oklahoma and California
Tennessee moored in Board of West Virginia
And Maryland in Board of Oklahoma escaped
Torpedo damage as did the fleet Flagship Pennsylvania in drydock 1
And quote
The Oklahoma's going to be hip
A couple of torpedoes right when the attack begins at 7
She's going to be hit with another one 4 minutes later that
Penetrates where the first two already blew up
And she'll start to roll over
To get hit with two more while she's rolling over and within 12 minutes of being struck
You can see her Underside and men are scurrying as she tips over to try not to
Fall into the sea
Those are the lucky ones because at least 400 Sailors are trapped below decks in the Oklahoma
With water pouring in
Shell's giant shells are getting dislodged and crushing men and the lights are going out in these people are trying to get
It out before they drowned
On the West Virginia there hitwe
Something like 6 or 7 torpedo
A couple of bombs on top of that to boot
And it's a nightmare over there
One of the survivors described what it was like to be on the deck of one of these ships when it was hit by a torpedo
And he says the torpedo
Rose up a mountain of water
Tons of liquid
That goes up in the sky higher than the ship is tall but then crashes down on the deck
And making it difficult because the ship's decks are Awash in water for a bit afterwards
To get off a ship that's just been hit by a torpedo and
You know what is
Exploding and burning and all that kind of stuff
Making it
Even more difficult
To deal with what amounts to most of these men on the ships
With something more like a natural disaster or an explosion at Sea that might not have anything
To do with war
Is very little of the combat
Side of this going on
There are heroic Tales of men breaking into locked ammunition
Cabinets because everything is put away
In the gunzer
Sometimes on these planes for example still packed in the oil
So this is more and intentionally cause disaster in the story of all these human beings
Trying to make their way to safety
All sorts of heroism by the way and let's give
Props were there deserved
A US Navy that everyone noticed
Was behaving as well
As you could possibly imagine under
The circumstance
There's not mast
Panic and screaming and yelling
And people are even giving up their lives and dying
In
The Silence of resignation it's
Part of what makes
Everyone get their teeth and get so angry about
About this afterwards
Turn American
Right I mean this is
Such bravery when you want to avenge
People who died in Sao
Terrible surf
Chances of this and make no mistake about it
You look what's going to happen on the Arizona
Because after the torpedo plane
And you're done
Income the high-altitude bombers
The dive-bombers are striking the
Airfields all over the
The place
The fighters and we haven't even talked about this are strafing all these ships with machine-gun bullets in the zero Fighters
Also at 2:20 mm cannons with your very nasty
When I used to war game
Second world war Naval battles
We paid very little attention in the rules
To the effects of strafing but it's
Clear from reading the Survivor
But it was
Massively effective
Sweeping the decks of human beings making it impossible to get stuff done creating chaos
Stopping people from getting off the ships or where they needed to go because what would happen is on these heavily-armored warships there still a bunch
Stop it's breakable
And the bullets
Hit the ships creating tons of Spartan a Ricochet everywhere
And anything that's not nailed down or heavily armored goes flying the captain of I think the West Virginia will have his stomach
Torn out
Buy some of the shrapnel and they will try to get him off the ship into safety Hill die trying
And commanding the ship by the way and telling everybody not to
Not to bother with him another one of those many heroic stories out of Pearl Harbor
These high altitude bombers though come in at eight thousand fourteen thousand feet somewhere in there
And these are not the best plan to attack ships with by the way
He's very hard to hit a ship from that altitude
Obviously these are not moving ships of that helps and on Battleship row where you have the ships
Moored side-by-side next to each other it's almost like you
Double the width of the ship so it makes it any easier Target
Nonetheless the hit ratio is nothing to be necessarily excited about
But when one of these
Bombs from these high altitude bombers and some of them are converted
16 inch Naval shells by the way
When one of them does hit
The amount of damage is overwhelming and one of them
It's the Arizona
And once again this is all happening
Very quickly
When the Arizona gets hit
This shell it is assumed it's difficult to conduct
Any sort of realistic Recreation of the
Wounds to the Arizona because she's so damaged
But it started this thing some people used to take it went down the smokestack but it's thought that it
It goes into the deck of the ship and penetrates and ignites the forward magazine
Where they keep all of the
Michels and ammunition
An explosives
Michael slackman says the Arizona's magazines contain 308
14 inch shells
Those are enormous and extremely heavy by the way
3505 in rounds
Those are
Standard
Land artillery side pieces right there nearly 5000 cans of powder
And more than 100 thousand rounds of machine gun and Small Arms ammunition
When that ignites
Survivors and there aren't many
People on the ships All Around The harbourside
Say it was less of a
Big boom
The more a mighty whoosh
They said
Another person describing slackman
Hope said it was an awful swish Sora sound
A quotes
Seaman artist T Russo the Arizona he says explode
While he was on the nearby Nevada and says
Quote
The ship he said
Steam to jump at least 15 or 20 feet upward in the water and sort of break into
And quote
The explosion was so large
That
It blew out the
Flames on the ship next to the Arizona which was burning like
A concussion would blow out a match
Car engines
On Ford Island stall
From the concussion
But not everyone flat on some of the surrounding ships
And the bomber that released
The balm
Felt the concussion
Shake the aircraft
The amount of debris that shower down on the ships next to the Arizona to Tennessee's right by it and go
Gets hit with so much debris including
Body parts
It suffers more damage one author said from that then from the bombs that actually
He struck her
The fuel oil that instantly goes out everywhere
In all of these ships are gassed up and they carry hundreds of thousands close to half-a-million
Gallons of oil on them some of them more than half
How many gallons oil
Heavy oil types
It's instantly all in the water so it's survivors jump in to try to escape the devastation
In some places this is
6 in
Pic of oil in the water
The aftermath of
The Arizona explosion amid all this other destruction going on simultaneously is
It described by many
Maybe the most visceral account
My bread is Craig Nelson
He starts by quoting a West Virginia sailor
Who described the scene
Quote
Ships on fire ships burning explosion going on all over the place
I saw the Arizona blow up
And she just rained sailors
And of course those were the ones that were fortunate enough to live
The ones that were blown off the ship
Nelson continues
Quote
Burning Arizona crewman ran after into the water thinking they would find relief
Instead they found 6-inch pools of fiery fuel oil covering the sea
Turning them into matchsticks
Clint Westbrook said quote
All the oil tanks on all the battlewagons have been ruptured most of them and you could just about almost get out and
Walk on it was that big
And around those ships that have fire on it
It was on fire as well so a lot of these people jumping off the ship were jumping right into burning oil
We had just loaded the day before cuz we were going back to the States for Christmas
The Admiral
So we had filled the tank Saturday and quote
Nelson quotes another witness who said quote
These people were zombies
They were burned completely White
Their skin was just as white as if you would taking a bucket of whitewash and painted it white
Their hair was burned off their eyebrows were burned off the pitiful remains of their uniforms in their crotch was
Was a charred remnant
Indian soles of their shoes was about the only thing that was left on these bodies
They were moving like robots
Their arms were out held away from their bodies and they were stumping along the decks
And quote
Peter goes another sailor who said that
The decks look like a Boneyard
From all the body
He parts
Author Walter Lord in
Day of infamy describes the remembrances of
Tennessee Survivor
Who explained what it's like to look up and see a bomb coming down right at you
And then what happens after
The words he wrote
Quote
Seaman JP Burkholder looked out a porthole on the bridge
Just as one of the converted 16in shells crash down on number tutoring
A few feet forward
The porthole cover tore loose
Clobbered him on the head and sent him scurrying through the door
Outside he helped a wounded ensign
But couldn't help one of his closest friends
Who was so far gone he only wanted Burkholder to shoot him
Another armor-piercing bomber through number 3 turret
Farther app
Seaman SF Bowen
Stationed there was a powder Carmen
Was just dogging the hatch when the bomb hit
It wasn't a shattering crash at all
Just a ball of Fire
About the size of a basketball appeared overhead and seemed to melt down on everyone
It seemed to run down on his skin and there was no way to stop it
As he crawled out of the deck below he noticed that his shoe strings were still on fire
And quote
The tragedy is immeasurably made worse
When the fuel oil that all these
Sailors struggling in the water against
Catches fire
The combination of sailors being stuck underwater
And sailor is burning
Is
About as nasty as you can get them in there are reports of
Sailors jumping off the Arizona and sizzling when they
Get the water and then of course the water catcher
She's on fire it's a nightmare
Is that worse than the people that are trapped below decks in the many many stories of trying to escape the wall
Water the climbs up
Annie little pockets of air and people will be cut out of these things for weeks afterwards
The very belt Armour
I just supposed to make these ships a protective place for their Crews making it harder to cut into
There will also be people
That don't get
Cut out of the ships and timing are found
Later sometimes much later
Dead
Entombed in their ships with
Calendars off
Open marking each day that they were
Often in total darkness
Trapped under there
To give you an idea of the speed
Heat of these attacks
The bigwigs in the military on the island
Can kind of see the smoke they have these wonderful home sometimes even overlooking the area around Pearl Harbor
General Walter short C's disc
Admiral husband Kimmel sees this
And
Get a chance to watch some of this unfold as it happens
Did a famous story General shorts he's the smoke while he's having Sunday breakfast with his wife
Runs to his Center to ask what's going on
I asked Lieutenant Colonel George Bicknell what's going on out there
And Big Moe says I'm not sure General
But I just saw two battleships sunk
And then
Short streams that's ridiculous
Admiral Kimmel is having a similar experience and you'll get blamed for a lot of this app The Wharf didn't put out the torpedo
All kinds of the one that asked his associate
You know what the probability of a Japanese Air Attack was that the guy said not absolutely none
And now he's watching in disbelief in real time
You know what's going on out there and it's almost heartbreaking unless of course
Are you blaming for the whole thing
Author Craig Nelson in Pearl Harbor from infamy to Greatness rights
Quote
An officer phone Admiral husband Kimmel at home with the news the Japanese planes were attacking his Fleet
The Admiral was still buttoning his white uniform is he ran out of the house
And onto the neighboring lawn of the district's chief of staff
Captain John early
Which had a panoramic view of Battleship row
Miserly said later that Kimmel stood quote
In utter disbelief and completely stunned
His face is white does that uniform he wore
End quote
Now quoting
Kimmel
Quote
The sky was full of the enemy
Kimmel said later
He saw the Arizona quote lift out of the water then sink back down
Way down
And quote
Mrs. early he writes
Start a battleship capsize
Instead looks like they've got the Oklahoman
Yes I can see that they have the Admiral numbly responded
Nelson rights
Other people encountered
Camel ride around the same time
Kimmel and his associates
Send a message to the Pacific Fleet
And back to Washington singing to Pearl Harbor is under attack
He orders that the enemy force be found
And then one officer remembered and is quoted by Nelson
As saying quote
I ran over to my offices and I happen to be standing alongside the commander-in-chief himself
Admiral Kimmel
We were glumly watching the Havoc
The Carnage that was going on
And suddenly he reached up and tore off his four star shoulder boards
Which indicated his Rank and title as commander-in-chief Pacific Fleet
He stepped into his adjacent offices
And realizing he was going to lose command Dawn 2 Star rear Admiral shoulder boards
And quote
And then Nelson relate
His version of a
A famous story that
It's told a number
Different ways
But right around
That exact moment a bullet
Ricochets into the house if they spent 50 caliber shell is what I read somewhere which would probably indicate
Did he was an American Boy
But it was so spent that hit him in the chest and just bounced off and left a mark on his white uniform
And I
He's quoted as saying several things
Nelson has him saying I wish it
Killed me
But the variations are such that it's sort of a rueful
Dark joke
That that would have been better than what he's going to face now being response
For this immense
Carnage
It is visible to
A car needs that is
Describe over and over
And it's unbelievable that some of these people will come up from below decks on these ships that have settled into the mud of pearl
Pearl Harbor have been sunk by the way out at Sea they would have been lost forever
But a bunch of these ships just so to settle their heroic efforts by the
Cruise to counter flood them and save them
There's a lot of people trapped below them
And when they come up and they look around remember the world that they last Saw
Add blue skies and this marvelous glorious us Pacific Fleet
And they come up in the water
And his body is floating everywhere
The ships are all falling apart and smoking and then and you can't even see the sky through all the black smoke is the oil
Burns off the ocean
Their world has been transformed
They've gone
From a Pacific Paradise to a naval version
Dante's Inferno
In a matter of minutes
And all of this Carnage and all this damage at all this destruction
Has been rocked
By the first
Japanese attack way
Remember
There's another attack wave not that far behind them
And not long after the first wave departs
The second one swoops in
A couple of ships
Heroically a couple of Destroyers the battleship Nevada heroically of managed against all laws to start moving
Making it look like you know we're back already and all ready
You have 30 minutes 35 minutes 45 minutes after a surprise attack the American Fleet on the move and it was inspirational.
All who can see it
Those ships
Attracted the specific
The contention of the second wave
Goes after them with bigger than a bad Waka
Beach in the sand to keep from sinking
Within 90 minutes it's all over
Start to finish
The planes fly off
And Pearl Harbor is left
They smoking devastation
Dead and wounded everywhere
More than 2400 people
Die
In this 90 minutes
More than a thousand
Irwindale
Almost 200 planes were destroyed on the ground
More than a hundred and fifty or damaged
And the entire Battleship complement of the US Pacific
Fleet
Is rendered
Useless
4 ships sunk
The others burning and damaged
The Japanese lose less than 30 playing
There's no possible way if you are on the Japanese side to look at this
And not see this as a huge Victory when you measure it
You know from a cost-benefit standpoint right
Less than 30 playing tuba get all that damage
Although
There were Japanese at the time
Who noticed
You know a silver lining from the Americans Viewpoint anyway
And that's that
The battleships may have been destroyed and put out of commission
But the carriers of the US Pacific
Fleet
Which had been at Pearl Harbor not that long ago
Weren't there when the attack happen
And that means that the weapon system
A few Only The Visionaries and seen as the next
Big thing in Naval Warfare that means the right after the battle that just proved conclusively
Did aircraft carriers were the next big thing in Naval Warfare
Didn't get any of the enemies are crap
Carriers
In the United States is carriers that managed to be away from Pearl Harbor on December 7th
Will be instrumental
In avenging what was done there
Knocking out the
Battleship component
The Pacific Fleet
Is a big blow
The human lies are irreplaceable
But let's be honest
These battleships were not even Cutting Edge
Battleship
Most of them dating back to the first World War
Some of them are even older than that
Useful at a bunch of things surely
Fun if you were someone like
Winston Churchill
The most useful thing these battleships
Maybe did
In terms of helping
Win the war
Was exactly what they did do
And he did not see
Pearl Harbor
Strike is a tragedy
A better word might have been
Erowid
A necessary sacrifice
To get the United States to do something that from his point of view they should have already done
It's probably not act
It's probably a misquote
The one of the lines attribute
To Winston Churchill I would
Why is that you could always
Count on the America
Directions to do the right thing
After all the other options have been exhausted
In this case
The attack on Pearl Harbor eliminate
Did any other Rock
It aroused a sleeping giant
To a level of Wrath
That would carry it forward
Through any misfortunes to an ending that a guy like Winston Churchill saw
As inevitable
The United States
It was
Shocked
And sad
Emotionally
Upset by the Pearl Harbor attacks
A guy like Winston Churchill
Was elated
Because to him
December 7th 1941
What the day that the war was decided
And Britain was going to be on The Winning Side
After all
He wrote after the war about his feelings
At this moment
And said quote
No American will think it wrong of me
If I proclaim the to have the United States at our side was to me the greatest joy
I could not foretell the course of events
I do not pretend to have measured accurately the Marshall might of Japan
But now at this very moment I knew the United States was in the war
Up to the neck and into the death
So we had won after all
Yes after Dunkirk
After the fall of France
After the horrible episode of a rhyme
After the threat of invasion when apart from the air in the Navy we were in almost unarmed people
After the deadly struggle of the U-Boat War
The first battle of the Atlantic
Game by a hands breath
Chapter 17 months of lonely fighting and 19 months of my own responsibilities and Dyer stress
We had won the war
England would live
Brenton Wood live
The Commonwealth of nations in the Empire would live
How long the war would last
Remote fashion it would end no man Patel
No did I at this moment care
Once again in our Long Island history
You should emerge however Mulder mutilated
Safe
Victorious
We should not be wiped out
Our history would not come to an end
We might not even have to die as individuals
Hitler's fate was sealed
Mussolini's fate was sealed
As for the Japanese
They would be ground to powder
And quote
We've been telling you about audible on this program for a long time
And there's a reason
Did you hear
Us discuss them as often as we do when it's because this is not a program that relies on advert
Revising
We're listeners
So we can afford to Simply do advertising that
Conforms to the hosts on radical beliefs on certain things
For example
Reading
Time 8
Voraciously
I'm one of the
The things that we benefit from reading
And we all collectively is a
Society
Society benefits from having more readers
And if you look at the strides
Over the amount of time we've been telling you about Audible
The audible is helped
Make reading something that fits into the modern world the digital age in the lives of
How the next generation of Americans you see that this is an advancement
The keeps reading relevant
And the end result is in my route
View a better Society
Me take for example what audible does
I mean this is an app that allows people to not just
You know enjoy the books
Because they're reading them
But to help tempt other people to enjoy books they may not be reading I love this end of this book
Feature
We're with the app you share a book from your library with anyone
And if it's their first time accepting the book through this feature they can listen for
You can share audio excerpts and clips
From your favorite parts of your books
2NE1
And I love that but you can also listen to different speeds so if the host talks a lot slower than I do and you like my my style you can speed them up or
Conversely ifmy celebrates on you you can slow down
Audible help
Create the modern world
Kunming to audio books that have the largest selection
And they have a
Great deal going on now you get a free audiobook with a 30-day trial
And if you just enjoy the show you just heard we use a couple of
I called him audio footnotes
From the book Pearl Harbor from infamy to greatness that Craig Nelson did
If you're looking for a modern up-to-date
Discussion about Pearl Harbor that
It's a great read the guy it's always in the way that you swim put the story together Nelson does a great job
And I am bringing these characters of back to life
And giving you a real sense and feel for it if it's interesting to you it's available on
Audible right now
If you go there and just
Repeat the code to go to audible.com Carlin
Or text Carlin to 500 500 and listen for a change
You'll get your
Free trial started you can pick up Pearl Harbor
And you can go into I know it's hard to believe after a four hour podcast that you can go into even more depth on some of this stuff
Granular is I like to say
Andrea Lee
In a Flash out this story it's a big story there's lots of wonderful little Eddie's
Or horrible little Eddie's for you to travel down Pearl Harbor is one of them pregnant since book is great
And audibles a fantastic place to
Go to audible.com Carlin
Or text Carlin to 500 500 and listen for a change
Don't forget that all the older Hardcore History shows are available for purchase
From iTunes or dancarlin.com
If you think the show you just heard is worth a dollar Dan and Ben would love to have it
Go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
For the latest news information and thoughts from Dan make sure to follow his history feed on Twitter
The address is
Add hardcore history
Coming up
Call the Pearl Harbor attacks are going on pretty much simultaneously
A Japanese
Blitzkrieg is occurring in Asia and the Pacific the largest Battlefield in human history
That will succeed
In part because of the West's underestimation of Japanese capabilities and
For all sorts of reasons including racial ones
Some of these Colonial
Powers do not believe
And maybe a lot of Americans don't either that an Asian they would have said Oriental at the time people work 8
Capable of something like what the Japanese are about to pull off
But there's a reason we called this series Supernova in the East and this is where we see the Japanese rice
Rising Sun
Explode in conquered territories over a wide area
And the United States
Angered roused
But groggy
Is in no position to do anything about it right away
For those of you who've been missing the combat element of this story
And let's remember for a long time the histories of the story in the American history books started with Pearl Harbor
8 hours into this series let the record show this in contacts
But this is the part of combat operations that most Pacific War aficionados are familiar with and that's coming up
Along with all the other
Other stuff of course all that and more as we like to say
Imparts free
A supernova in the east
Due out in about 10 years given our current schedule.
We try
Thanks for all the support