Today Show sponsored by Audible
Go to audible.com hardcore history
Ortex
Hardcore History to 500 500 to get started Amazon Prime members can get Audible for 495
The month for the first three months
If I get in 3 months for the price of one 1495 a month
And this offer ends July 31st 2018 so move on that fast
If it sounds good to you
December 7th 19
Its history
A date which will live
In infamy
Call Steph Curry
Barclays Premier League events
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein Berliner
Instagram
The Deep question
Time of examination
And remember that we are not descended
From fearful man eats hardcore history
1940s
When the second world war is
Raging
Especially in the Pacific especially around the Philippine
Young Japanese solo
Dinosaur early twenties
Is dropped off
I'm going to be in numeral
Heavily jungled Philippine Islands
And is told to do what he can to hamper Allied activities in the air
Continue fighting until he hears orders to the contrary by the commanding off
Officer who sent him on a mission
This Soldier
Kiro
Oh no doll
Asian convention with switch that around that he'd be on the other hero
Will follow his orders until his commanding officer tells him he can lay down his weapon
He will eventually
Come out of the Jungle into a clearing
Hand over his sword
Standard attention while the guy who ordered him into that jungle in the first place formally dismisses him with honor
And this happened
On the 9th of March
29 years out
After the second world
This guy had
Fighting
Shooting at being shot at
Killing and injuring the locals
30 years
29 to be exact
20 came out of the jungle
It came out with hundreds of rounds of ammunition
A well-maintained working rifle and Hand Grenades
The guy who
Dismissed him his commanding officer
I'm 29 years previously had to be flown in by the Japanese government
He was apparently a Bookseller or something in civilian life now imagine his surprise
When a government official shows up at his office isn't as yeah you know one of those soldiers you ordered into the Philippines 29 years ago
Yeah he's still in there and he won't come out unless you come and tell him it's okay
He was found
Officially by like a kid hippie kid is with the soldier called him or no to call him a hippie kid
Who said he was looking for a red summer city was looking for
Wild pandas meaning the existence of pandas in the wild
The Abominable Snowman
And lieutenant
Onoda
Lest you think
That this is a once-in-a-lifetime Robinson Crusoe shipwrecked kind of
Anomaly
Gyro on Northern
Is not the only Japanese World War II soldier that surrenders in 1974
There's another one
In 1972
There was one
There were two in the 1960s there were a bunch in the 1950s
And in the 1940s after the war ended sometimes whole units were still fighting
I believe it was almost three years after the war ended the unit of a couple of hundred of these Japanese soldiers
With their heavy weapons finally surrendered
What the hell is that
Accounts for that
And it's not just the Philippines I mean it was happening on places like Guam for example
Saipan I mean there were people still running around the caves after the war and he will Jima
I mean it was
Fascinating
That what you saw here didn't happen in the other theaters of War because the other theaters of war did not in
Into the Japanese
One of the most
Fascinating
Interesting cultures on the planet
And what Japanese expert R Taggart Murphy calls
Unquestionably the most distinctive of all modern industrial societies culture-wise
I need is a fascinating example
Are we human beings can be molded and stretched and
Trimmed and shaped like a bonsai tree
Are the cultural influences into many different
Diverse versions of hours
Ourselves
Anyone who's a fan of National Geographic
Example
Seize the many different colorful cultures and subcultures all over the world write the extreme
Differences of humankind
And how wonderfully pliable we are
The cultural influences
Determine
How we like to dress what we think is attractive little marks of status all kinds of thing
Now magnify that
Buy all the eras humankind's ever been around right so not just a diversity of exotic different places all over the world
When was this place is all throughout history and you can see that we've
Well probably tried just about everything is this
BC's wouldn't you thinking and we seen all kinds of different extreme versions of what we can become a man take the physical version
I'm a fan of the people of the Eurasian steppe in those tribes as many of you know
Some of those tribes from time-to-time used to like to practice
Something on his head vine
It's one of the Counterpoint
Foot binding
China
Which was popular in some circle
Sometimes
To keep the feet small and to have them developed a certain way
Will same thing with head
You see this in other parts of the world to and sometimes cradles for example certain Native American tribes had cradles that we
Shape the head
A certain way to the point is is that when the skull is pliable when the person is Young you can shape that
And so like a bonsai tree if you will
And the Romans used to complain that the Huns look monstrous today
I remember growing up thinking while these Romans are really sensitive
Used to seeing some people who may be at
Slightly Asian feature
You're thinking about monsters
Well now we have skulls that have come out of the ground some of these tombs some of these kurgans were they buried some of these hands
And some of these ions have
Skulls
It look like they are
Taken right out of an alien movie
Big elongated skulls that go way far to the back you wonder what they must have look like with hair and skin
The point is is if you were a Roman looking at them you might have thought that they look
Monster
However if you were a young
Calmly Huntik noblewoman
You might have thought that guy looked hot so it's all a question right of
Are the cultural carrots
Dixon White
Sometimes it's not things
There are so visible on the outs
Side
I think we are ready
The vast majority of our makeup
In terms of our attitudes
And the way we think and the way we organize reality is probably going to be culturally
Determined
I am a fan of
Extreme situations in history
In the country
Mapreduce guys like hiroo onoda
Workstream
And the cultural carrots and sticks were designed
To take many
Of the
In a Civic attitudes that most societies considered to be positive
And
Turn them up
To such a high level on the dial of intensity
That they took a bunch of things
Might be considered good
In another context and made them dangerous
How can your culture
Impact things
Like
Duty
And honor
Patriots
And willingness
Sacrificing lay down
One life
For the greater good mean these are all things that most societies
You know what figure out
All sorts of cultural ways to encourage
How about just
Recognize
And take for example
A metal
Ceremony
It might happen in the United States written award citation
Somebody was extra Brave or extra heroic or did something out of the ordinary and maybe you get a medal and when you get the metal
The person giving the award will say something like you know for
Heroism or bravery or sacrifice above and beyond the Call of Duty
Above and beyond the Call of Duty
That right there was a recognition right that there are limits
To what normal people can be asked to do in normal times right
And if you exceed those expectations
Go above and beyond the Call of Duty you get a medal
What is the cultural heritage
Sticks in a given Society
Have evolved in such a way
So that there's almost
Nothing
That is above and beyond
Call of Duty
Where the culture expects
Encourages
And only approves
A level of sacrifice on the part of every man woman and child in that Society
The most other cultures Reserve
For their most elite military unit
Welcome to the world that famed Japanese holdout
Hiroo onoda was raised in
When another got back to Japan in 1974
Ghost written book of his
Remembrances
Was created
It's called No Surrender my thirty-year war and energy describes
The Japan he was raised in he says quote
At that time if a soldier who had been taken prisoner
Later managed to return to Japan he was subject to a court-martial in a possible death penalty
Even if a penalty was not carried out
He was so thoroughly ostracized by others
Then you might as well have been dead
Soldiers were supposed to give their lives for the cause
Not groveling enemy prison camps
General Hideki tojo's instructions for the military CID explicitly
He's not quoting
The instructions quote
He who would not disgrace himself must be strong
You must remember always the honor of his family and his community
Animas dry fervently to live up to their trust in him
Do not live in shame as a prisoner
Die and leave no ignominious crime behind you
And quote
When he leaves to go off to war one of the things he takes with him as a family dagger that his mother says
If your capture use this to kill yourself with
And I tried to think of any other
Mother
Sending her son off to war in any other major power in the Second World War
With that kind of advice
Interesting is a very distinctive different culture
Got some might have a counter on
I meant to this point
That the reason these Japanese holdouts were continuing to hold out was her duty honor country the emperor that sort of thing by pointing out
A bunch of these people said they didn't know the war was over
So maybe it's more of a sense of being isolated and not getting the news
But the counter argument to that has to do
With the fact that
These people were often told explicitly in many different ways that the war was over
And he chose not to believe it and they chose not to believe it because it clot with their
Elemental indoctrination into all this I mean for example
Hiroo onoda
He had family members flown in at high expense to the Japanese government because
Hiro Nakamura still chilling
In the Philippines
After the war right he's not just sitting up there in the mountains by himself not bothering anybody killed 20 to 30 Filipinos
So that makes you want to tell this
This person in no uncertain terms and spend a little money to make it happen
Hey you're killing people in the war is over
Believe that they left the newspapers here's how he puts it
In the book written
With him
Quote
The search party Left Behind newspapers and magazines
Most of them were recent and a lot of them contained articles
About the crown Prince's marriage
The newspapers which covered a period of about four months
Made a stack nearly 2 feet high
We we need to two other holdouts with him
We thought they were reprints of real Japanese newspapers doctored up by the American Secret Service
In such a way as to eliminate any news that the Americans did not want us to
Sissy
This was all we could think so long as we believe
The greater East Asia war was still going on
And in the way he writes
The newspaper has confirmed that the war was still going on
Because they told a lot about life in Japan
If Japan is really lost the war there should not be any life in Japan
Everybody should be dead
When I arrived in the Philippines in 1944 the war was going badly for Japan he writes
And in the Homeland the phrase 100 million Souls dying for Honor was on everybody
These lips this phrase meant literally
That the population of Japan would die to a man before surrendering
I took this at face value and I am sure many other young Japanese men my age did
He says I sincerely believed that Japan would not surrender so long as anyone Japanese remained alive
Conversely if one Japanese were left alive
Japan would not have surrendered
He continues
After all this is what we Japanese at all vowed to each other
We had sworn that we would resist the American and English Devil's until the last single one of us was dead
If necessary the women and children would resist with bamboo sticks
Trying to kill as many enemy troops as they could before being killed themselves
The wartime newspapers all played this idea up in the strongest possible language
According some of the slogan
One was
Another was
The Empire must be protected at any cost
Another one was
100 million dying for the cause
He says quote
I was virtually brought up on this kind of talk
And quote
When another got back to Japan
Some of the things that I read in some of his later actions indicate
But he was less than happy
With
What had become of Japan after the war was over in terms of their National values their intensity level in what
Now I can
Speaker experience but in the 1970s
The rest of the world thought the Japan
Was still a very distinctive culture
And very committed to
Shall we call it the above and beyond the Call of Duty ethics
They seem very intense about that always
Something that they took very seriously they were known for in fact
Other people really
Like things like Japanese products because you knew that they were going to be intense about
You're getting it done right but to a guy raised by the standards of all known Azera
This was not good at they lost something and let me tell you what they probably lost and the rest of the world would consider this to be a good thing and I think
Modern Japanese wood for the most part 2
They weren't all prepared
Every man woman and child
To sacrifice themselves anymore to the level of your the world's greatest
Military units right
Act like Spartan hoplite die on command of the emperor like Spartan hoplites these people in the
Modern Japanese war were much more sensible
But in here all notice world
There's a level of insanity the
It's starting to happen in it
It's really complicated but it kind of explains why
The Japanese are this very distinctive different major power in the SEC
The world war
And why they're certain unique elements to the Pacific War against Japan that just wasn't present in the other theaters
Because I reset the Japanese word
Quick little run-down mighty
Explain some important things and by the way
Japanese cult
Culture is much debated as you would expect extremely complicated and definitely a place to be left
But let's just say
It was some pretty obvious things that we should take note of
That might help explain how you get such a
Distinctive
People and let me use the word here that I like I like the wording.
I will point out my stepfather's generation and he fought in the Second World War
He believed that this regime and this
Government in the society that turned out a guy like he wrote on Lota with turning out fanatic
Another word that was much used amongst
They are
Automatize near robot
And I should point out that
Wartime propaganda played into this but
Americans kind of had this image of both the
German opponent in the second world war and the Japanese opponent as robot
But different kind of robot
The German robot was like
The vision in The Avengers
Cold robotic mathematical deficient precise and deadly because
There's a coldness in a logical nature there
The Japanese is the other side of the robot specs
They're like foaming at the mouth crazy robot
They don't stop you have to
Did Littlefinger will come after you if you leave that alone and ready to die for the emperor excited to die for the emperor
Dora cartoon character that's extremely dangerous
The word fanatic is a wonderful way
To avoid having to look beneath the surface at any of the human motivations that might be bald red fanatic is just an A to B
Sony jerk
In terms of
You know the depth that they need to be examined
Real people
That might be extremely motivated or
Feel extreme pressure in societal and cultural coercion to do something for example fly
An aircraft piloted by then suicidally into an enemy ship
Those people might have
Some really interesting motivations to see
Interesting
Points of view
Where they think they're doing
What sort of a range of options and choices do they think they have
This becomes a much more human story when we realize two things one
Any of us could have been born there
Is a certain randomness
Even if you believe
In Uno a DD selecting everything about you they could have selected that you end up in Japan in the 1920s
Go to school with Heroin OD
Besides that
There's a certain understanding
At what happened in Japan
Can happen again it will happen differently it never looks the same
But look at the elements involved
And wonder if you can't imagine them being filtered instead of three Japanese cultural filter the cultural filter of
Of your Society
But use the same way and turn to the same kind of uses
And maybe turning out the same kind of
Intensity
Did the Japanese really seem to exude all throughout the story telling me point out there's a wonderful phrase
That was used by a rabbi to describe
The Jewish people
Once but I love it
Because I think it's a wonderful shorthand phrase that applies to a bunch of different very distinctive people on the planet and the shopping
These are certainly one of those
Substitute the word
Choose
Would Japanese
The rabbi said
The Japanese are like anyone else
Only more so
Don't know if I got the exact wording correct with its but the line is perfect because it did notes
A level of intensity right they have all the same human qualities as you do they just have them at a higher intensity
You think you are a good Gardener and your garden looks down when you're done in a raking and taking care of it will go look at a Japanese
He's guarding you feel like you didn't do anything
Intensity with which state
They pay attention even to the little lines in the dirt I mean
What happens if you take this in
Density too far
Dial it up to high
Even if we're talking about being intense about are things that you normally
Considered to be positive today
Unless intense level mean your patriotism you got Duty. Love of country sacrifice for the Statham
All these things that so many people today we consider positives
How high do you have to
Turn the dial up on the intensity level though
I know we already have
I Want superhero run
They should have just happened in it but I got another one only cuz
The Japanese holdouts to me
Isn't that sort of like a Japanese version of the Captain America backstory
Right he goes he's a second world war person from the 40s gets put to sleep essentially get awakened
In the modern world and is continually contrasting in the last thing he should have remembered what in his mind
Like last week he was in the forties with the whirly finds now in the values and all these modern different thing
All these holdouts were like gone for decades aren't they all like Captain Japan's in that sense
I need the Japan of the 1970s.
Despite the rock music
The blue jeans in the longer hair
It would have been
On display for this Japanese war veteran
But the Japanese of the 1970s were still
Like everyone else only more so
But in the eyes of someone like oh nah that seems his attitude was not more so enough
Boston College a few things right away the first thing is it's one of the oldest
Tropes
In history
The people look back in
And pine away for golden age that they missed the really never existed and old people do this anyway
She probably got some of that go
Going on
Let me also say that I know from personal experience cuz it's the era I grew up in
But in 1974 there were a lot of World War II veterans from the United States of America that didn't look too fondly of
The direction American culture was going
Or think
The intensity level of Devotion to ideals like Duty and honor and patriotism self-sacrifice
Was strong enough in the American culture of those days
So in a funny way
These bitter opponents in the second world war the Japanese Imperial Army
And the US
In the military
We had something in common if they were reminiscing about the kids today
Give me the early
Timmy 1970s
And you're on the surface there does seem to be a little something different
Doesn't there
From the Japanese to the Allied perspective if you're pining away for the Golden Age
On the Allied side
You're pining away for the things that brought you victory
Right at the kids today
Mi amor
Honor patriotism Love & Country let you know what we could do great things remember we did in the war we won the war but the Japanese didn't win the war
The war was a tragedy for them on so many levels
So why would you look back on the values
The kind of made you the kind of country you were that you can fight a war like that
If that's what it led to
Well perhaps the devil's
Counter argument here
Is it yes while
These specific values and the intensity of the era on a scale of one to ten ten being most intense the
I need during the era hero another growing up in our a1011 and yes that got them into trouble eventually and led to
Japan's downfall is a great power
The counter argument that can be made is Japan never would have been a great
Had it not been for
The very specific
Active nature of the Japanese and let's understand
This is a people
Not quite unique but darn near unique in the.
Of colonial Domination by the colonial powers of the western world
It managed to avoid that
They did not avoid it because anybody was going soft on anyone else or because Japan wasn't day
Tempting targets
Snap up
They avoided it because they created the kind of society and Military
It made it impossible for somebody to snap
And they did this
Well coming from way behind in the technological race
You know most Miracle like fashion that I think and remember you are getting my little toe
For good or ill
The intensity of the Japanese character
Is in large part I think
A factor in this
You start talking about like National characteristics it gets very easily bleeds are usually in a weird
Racism
Stop but it's not
A Japanese
Racial thing that accounts for the way they are to cultural
Carrots and sticks but by the way full disclaimer here
It's going to be a lot of Race 2
Not because it matters to me or because I think it's important
Because it matters to the people in this story and they think it's important
The late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries one of the high water
What's College Global racism
And the pseudoscience
Stop it and it will impact this story to give you just one example without going to depleted when they will be cases where
I will just take
White
Western Society don't use the terms that are popular with the time. Because that's going to keep
We use the terms of use
Contemporaneously
But they will be white
Military powers
That will get
Badly hurt
From Miss judging the capabilities of a non-white power simply because in racial terms they considered them
Kind of subhuman we don't have to worry about
About those people because
I mean listen we're White
In there
I think the word that you
Used for monkeys
And the payback for that car make lie
Is to get your rear end
Handed to you by a bunch of people
And we that you underrated because of some weird
Construct
A racial superiority
It warm
Your perception of reality
Of course you know what perception of real
Eventually
Meets the real reality in
There was some payback there more on that in a little bit
My point is we'll get to the racism thing and we'll talk about race cuz it matters in the story
It's very multi-racial
In an era that's very race
In this case though
How do you
Figure out you know who the Japanese are and why they are the way they are well first of all this is a subject for expert job
Obviously Japanese culture has been much debated even in the United
State
I remember the kid when they started
I'm selling a so much on cars
A fascination with this Japanese
Corporate culture in the way they did things
This is a much-talked-about thing
Per person like yours truly
I can only hit the big boys there are some obvious things that you can look at and go wow that must have effect
Did the story
I don't know how I don't know to what degree I don't know what mixes with the other factors but boy you can't ignore
Is a couple of those I want to get into
You're going to help explain how we get to where we are
Every society in the world right is a blend
I'm old and new
In the case of Japan
The proportion of old to new includes a lot more old than most places
This is by Design
And their history kind of consciously shows not just
Ave
Preserve this distinctive way of life
But how trying to preserve their distinctive
Culture
Can get them in trouble where they then need those qualities of intensity and everything we were talking about before 2.
Dig them out of a hole of their own creation is this interesting dynamic between
Are the Japanese wanted to remain distinctive that that causes problems that then their distinct tivity
Require them to help them get out of
Without going too depleted
Let me explain
A little of
The background
Big events
Raven
Reading
Japan for dummies
Hope you understand first of all we all get the idea
The geographically speaking
Japan has the opportunity to be different just because
There an island nation or in
Series about
Having that
Little bit of water that cuts you off from the mainland allows you at times sometimes depending on the situation
In a long time to keep
The Ebbs and flows and tides and sometimes the storms raging on the big continent away from your shirt
Now the fact that you are an island does not
Determine
In any way shape and form how you develop their lots of different ways you could go for lots of different reason to me take a look at something on a map
Theoretically should be pretty simple
Take a look at Japan on the map of them take a look at the British Isles
Theoretically these places should be somewhat
Now I guess your name
And yet
The Japanese will have
Periods in their history where they as much as possible try to limit contact with the outside world.
That's just the way they wanted to go for reasons that are
Understandable once we get in
And the
English and British
In a larger sense or just the opposite I would going country might be a good way to put it so outgoing
Dubai the time
And we're setting up the story we're getting into now
They directly or indirectly control a huge chunk of the globe
The Japanese culture is a
Of course ancient
Dates back to
Really early time
And the relationship
That probably has meant the most
In Japanese history to the development of that island nation is the one that they've had long-term
With China
Jupiter
Review stage if you ask a Chinese person they might say it's the Sun
Not a necessarily impossible to justify point of view either if you think about
In a China basically being the superpower of East Asia
Throughout most of human history except for
Certain period of time when it
Reaches certain low
Boynton power when does the civilization stock market dips for the Chinese stock
But most of the time in China
Of the world is at least as powerful as today's modern day China is
Things so stable
I had a Chinese history professor
Sad
But if you wanted to make an argue
You could perhaps a
The entire
Second world war and the Dupree second world war in Asia
Is a result of China's historic weakness
During that time
And it's interesting because if you think about
Modern-day China
Find a plugged into that era
You can't imagine any of that happening at all
Instead
The normal Powerhouse of the region the Jupiter is eclipsed in the time. Leading up to the Second World War
Which creates a vacuum
It like my professor said if you wanted to you could probably get a Beat
House on the paper where you try to
Tie that together with
The reason everything was happening
Right you have a vacuum in China
Very well
Territory that seems to be available
An era where the great powers of the world probably could be compared to a
Bunch of ravenous shark
Text looking to snap up an increasingly small and dwindling supply of yummy territories
Dark Horse
Later on in our story
In the case of the
Japanese
And a relationship to China
I had a buddy that compared it once
To a big brother little brother relationship
Which I thought was kind of compelling and he was just thinking he said
That China courses big brother in there for most of their early relationship little brother tags along
Learning from Big Brother pretending to be Big Brother emulating Big Brother
What are the certain point along the way they both
Mature
There Comes A Time in their relationship where little brother can reliably kick Big Brother's ass
And that changes the nature of the relationship somewhat
If you're looking at this though
To the wide-angle Longview length I think you have to save the relationship despite the occasional sibling spats
And pirate activity
Lesbian peaceful
A mutually beneficial especially beneficial if you're looking at this from the Japanese point of view
Because like all of China's neighbors they will benefit
It continually
Ending an ongoing fashion over the centuries from Chinese Innovations
Turn off the top of my head of me think about writing
That the Japanese taking convert to Japanese style but it's from China originally
Town of philosophical ideas
Governmental organizational chart template
Religious Concepts till the cows come home my goodness how about the most Japanese as I think about it insta
Tatoosh of all the emperor itself might be in Innovation taken from China may be as far back as like
7th Century ad
It's funny that was like all foreign Innovations the Japanese managed to take these things and turn them Japanese somehow
And waited instead of changing Japan's distinctive culture somehow is just
Woven into it
That would have been opportunities in history we shall call them historical close calls
In Japan could have fallen victim
To the same
Outcome that many wonderful distinctive cultures all over you raise your fell to it one time or another
Occasionally you get these great
Historical blending opportunities
Sometimes that occur against
The will of the people being Blended
And this will take those wonderful distinctive cultures and sort of homogenized
Anthem
Are you talkin about whiskey it's a blended sort of thing where the place like Japan is a wonderful
Distinctive single malt
Most of the times
A little bit of water separating Japan as we said earlier from being part of these great blending opportunities
But in the late 1200 you have a
Couple of close calls
The
Mongol conquest
Are going on in their blending
Cultures all over your razor with each other
Against their will
They will run out of room to conquer anymore in East Asia they run up against water eventually but you know the Mongo manifest
Best Destiny being what it is
By the time chinggis Khan's grandson the great Kublai Khan is on the throne of China
The launch to amphibious
Assault
Over the waves
On Japanese Islands
Personal imagine that
Permanent light 1200
Tens of thousands of troops over the way then you don't just have to get him there he have to supply them the whole time they are
Are there
And for a significant amount of time and we were talking
Many weeks
The Japanese will fight these armies to a standstill with an absolutely ferocious defense
Now in the defense of Mongolia
Admire is everywhere this is not a Mongol Army as you would normally think of it most of it is
A bunch of Korean and Chinese auxiliary's were
Unscripted don't want to be there because after all their countries have been conquered by the same Mongols nonetheless
A ferocious defense to provides time
From Mother Nature to intervene
Twice
Let me tell you what your military history nut
Looking at this battle shaping up I'm like a boxing fan who's bought the pay-per-view and it's very excited about this
Conflict only to have it
End in a Japanese Victory by disqualification due to kamikaze
Twice
The Kamikaze 4th famous divine wind wind of the Gods
Is wind that comes up and so badly damaged is this Mongo Chinese Fleet
Twice
Will have to call off the engagement go back home
When you think about what would have happened to this distinctive
Japanese culture and how it would have been strangled in the Cradle
Are the Mongols conquered Japan and homogenized and governed it with officials that might be from
45 different peoples I mean bringing a good old Russian governor
Took control Japan for a while to see what happens to that distinctive Japanese single malt whiskey
You know when you start adding all these other elements
So that's why it's an important historic
Does kamikazes of course the deciding factor
But if the Japanese military can't hold off these mongeau forces as long as they did they never have time
Time for the weather to intervene
The key to the whole thing at Ground Zero
What's the Japanese organization in military
It was a cultural system one might call it
What inorganic system
That was
Similar and is often compared to the
Broad contemporary system in Europe
The Japanese during the Mongol Chinese invasion
At the same time when Europe was in a feudal stage
It's a really dicey subject I mean
A lot of people complain about
Trying to fit the square peg Japanese
Culture into the round hole of the European historic
Circle template Amin
The context
Two things like Knights and feudalism in European context
The problem is it's the best analogy for Europeans understand the situation in shorthand even with all the problems attached to
You could say both Europe and Japan
Starting to explore the early ideas
Statehood in that kind of thing
Both cultures
With a hereditary warrior class that made up
An aristocracy
That had a bunch of Fighters who has individuals
Compete for the title of most
Dangerous Warrior of all time
Right
If you are military historian buff where would you place
Samurai
For the Japanese Army
For hundreds of years
Cutting Edge the same way that Knights were in Europe
Hard to not play Samurai in the top 10
Lot of people make an argument
The top five
I think you have to put
Samurai on the top 10 list based on a real alone
I don't think he's ever been in army
It's had higher morale than what Samurai bring to the table me even Knights who I love
And who will fight to the death mean happens all the time
But not usually
Usually when you kill enough nights they route
That's an unusual thing to happen to Samurai
They are more willing to die
Then perhaps
Any other troop type you can think of
And if you find truth that are as willing to die usually it's a small group of special Elite
Run usual fanatical people in the beserker is over in the old Scandinavian armies or what have you
This is a huge chunk of any Japanese Army
Now one of the best comparisons I think
The Dust
Fat when you start saying okay what's similar about Knights and Samurai
Is that the real
Thing 1
Comes to these kind of warriors
Where's the real deal as they were in history
Is
Different
Then the way
They were romanticise later and we all get this I mean think about King Arthur for a min
And courtly love
Ingesting and the Holy Grail I'm in think of that kind of The Sword in the Stone think of the romanticizing
What was certainly I mean if you're comparing the Knights of the Round Table
You don't even in the
Late 19th century Works to something like
Real Knights
Will think about how much the reality differs from the
Romantic
The samurai had the same situation going in the 1400 and 1500
This is the Golden Age of Samurai War
Not the Golden Age of Samurai
The Golden Age of the real thing Warfare
The greedy
Bloody
Grimy
Horrible
And what lies Beyond it
Venal sometimes
Warfare that is the real thing
Can you have Samurai who fight all the time during this. Because there's a lot of War sometimes you're
Fighting the Chinese like we said but most of the war with other Japanese
Armies and with other Samurai
There were hundreds of thousands of these guys
And they fought a lot
The late 1500s there will be a lot of
Japan is in the process of some very big Wars
It will lead up to a big bottle
Famous II
ARA battle
In 1600
I think it was like a hundred
70000 people supposed to be there
And when one side beat the other
It it was the big pushover capsize moment when Japan
Kind of gets yunnan
That's a very quick sounding process the way I said it
But that battle tips things over to a point where you get a new government that
Unites Japan
The government is called
Tokugawa shogunate
Sometimes referred to as the
Bakufu
Hope I mispronounce that name properly I'm leaving
I did
Not as the name implies the
Country is nominally run by something called a Shogun
Translate it off and then when generalissimo
Military dictator a hereditary usually
Military dictator
Japan's history look at a timeline
Glittered with the shogunate
And when the Shogun is running the show The Emperor as a figurehead
Now
Dictionary may say that the
Shogun runs things but in reality he's dealing with a bunch of local Lords people called I'm Yours
Japan during this time.
What happened
About roughly two hundred separate little areas
And eat one of these areas has its local Lord and they raise their own taxes they raise their own military forces they owe Allegiance
To the central government but they have broad ranges of power
Deal with everything in their own domain the wrong way
You can see why maybe people can be forgiven
For applying the feudalism tag to that because on a Surface my blood kind of looks that way doesn't it
The entire. Is sometimes known as the Edo.
Heat up in the old name for Tokyo
And that are relaxed nearly 1600 still like
SM 250 years
Going to leave a mark
Culturally speaking wouldn't you think
And the fact that it's going to go on until the time
Of Hebrew on noda's parents or grandparents means it's going to leave a mark
It persists
Even on the soldiers fighting
For Japan in second world war influential.
I'm part of the reason so influential is it's a Time
Where the cultural head binding is
Particularly tight
And the
Edo period Is known
As I would suggest a double-edged sword a good and bad kind of thing
On the good side in the early 1600 I'm not sure there's a cleaner place to live than Ito Japan
Entering mild germaphobe like myself
Probably the only place I could go back to in the time machine if I had to run away from the present and take refuge in the past
Or wouldn't be totally freaked out
Pretty safe
Very safe
Compared to most other cities of its size around the world at that time.
Pretty darn literate
Very artistic population flourishing
But it also has a level of cultural repression
That it would be difficult for modern people living in the Free World anyway
To put up with
In one story and I was reading
I said that
Edo Japan has
Most of the features in embryo
Of a totalitarian type state
Can we nearly 1,600 including things like thought police
One of the things they cracked down on his people who
Aren't particularly happy staying in their place they will lock in a system that keeps people in their place
They're all about the status quo
And if you violate that
The repression can be particularly harsh they will
Innocence weed-out malcontents
People that cause trouble and particularly
Nonconformist types
I should point out
If we are comparing early Tokugawa Japan
Two other countries in a free sample go to the west and see what they're doing
Are totally up in your intellectual business day or two
Heresy trial and you don't have freedom of speech, freedom of thought
So not that different
Nearly 1600 but
Over the entire course of the Tokugawa shogunate
Things are going to change on the other side of the world
And by Design
They're not going to change anywhere near as much in Japan
Now the reason that this. Is particularly harsh on internal dissent and free thought and all that
Have to do with the priorities of the bakufu
Because they are less concerned about some foreign Invasion coming from Eurasia like a bunch of Mongols or something
Then they are about somebody domestically overthrowing them
They're kind of afraid of the Common People
You're getting weird foreign ideas in their head that make them uppity
They're also afraid of people like themselves other
Samurai because history shows that they're the most dangerous
Class 2
Fear if you are the ruling Elite
And your own people at the most likely to kill you
Some peaceful Society with no outside threat
Patoka gallons are worried about something happening domestic
The Japanese are worried
About dangerous for an ID is undermining their society interrupting their population
Meaning of astray
Might be the way they would put it
And they're answer to this
Is to close Japan to the rest of the world
That's what the Tokugawa
Are famous for
Of course
That's not really what they did but when I was growing up that's the way the history books put it in
Astoria Mary's B Jensen points out that
It's a sign of the
UF ethnocentricity of that error
But you would think that closing trade with the West is the equivalent of cutting yourself off in the entire world
Did the Japanese still most of the time trade with China and Korean places like that but in an attempt
To keep Japanese Society
I'm being polluted with these outside intellectual contagions
They will shut down trade with most of the rest of Europe
Overtime
Image should be pointed out
But nonetheless that's how they're going to try to address some of their
Worried about
Population getting uppity in agitated
The other thing the Tokugawa have to get a handle on and that they're known for
Is solving the samurai problem that they inherit
After all
If you are famous is the Tokugawa are for bringing peace to Japan maybe for the first time in a sustained way
In hundreds of years
What do you do with all the professional Warriors
Better part of the hereditary aristocratic warrior class whose entire
Role in society
Is to be the fighters
You know any time of widespread sustained
Peace
It's actually a big problem
And there's a lot of economic
Points that are brought into the
Say something like
Well this is an economic class now that have nothing to do but they suck up an enormous amount of resources
Blah blah blah
Are Jack Murphy had the best thing I ever saw
When he was discussing
Let's call it the Human Side
You think about you
I can totally see that
It's the problem of having a bunch of people
To grow up
Emulating the great warrior Deeds of their Samurai ancestors
Who trained for war all the time
Whose whole point in the society is as a warrior
Never get to use their skills
Anybody who spent
5 minutes
In a martial art knows the feeling
I'm wondering as you sit there and practice even the most basic rudimentary moves
I wonder what this would be like
Real situation
Imagine what these young
Murphy doesn't use the term but it's implied
Testosterone-fueled
Ambitious
Young Japanese people
Only want to achieve what their ancestors have achieved
Their ancestors lived in a wartime environment they live in a peacetime environment
Imagine how well the idea of
Idle Hands Are The Devil's tools works for them
So they had to have and one of my history had a great way of putting it
They had had their energies
Redirect
Into another part of society what were you going to do with all these Samurai how are you going to justify the cost to society get them another job
And the tokugawa's take this warrior class
Any put them in the bureaucracy
And they start having them do management job they become the
So the organs of the state
And the part is kind of interesting to our story is
They kind of do it in a way
The implies or mandates I don't know what the right term is
Did they take their Samurai values
With them into their new job
Weirder than that though because
It's during this. Now that the samurai don't
Fight anymore
Did they actually kind of double down on the ethical standard they get more concerned
Moron
More militaristic
Part of it is because they're romanticizing the early
Yourpassnow
They actually think that these Samurai they Admire from the warrior. Had higher ethical standards and they really did
And I'm going to try to live up to those
Qatar tiger Murphy
He says about
That Paradox in the fact that Hey listen
The warrior at the
That worked well on the battlefield will work well in the bureaucracy
He writes in his book
Japan and the shackles of the past
There was in fact
Hardly any occasion for Samurai to put their martial training into practice
Are the actual experience of battle receded Into The Mists of History
The ethos of the Samurai became paradoxically Evermore rigida militaristic
With stress on absolute loyalty to the superior
Preparedness to carry out any order even at the risk of death
And it just staying for softness and physical comfort
And quote
He continues
Later quote
But it was not just the austerity the whole Samurai ethic
The disciplined unquestioning response to any order
The personal rectitude in contempt for moral or physical laxity
Just as well to shape a compliant bureaucracy as it had originally done to form of vigorous military
And quote
Obviously
There's an incongruity here though over the stakes involved in different environment
And if you're right. Opting an intensity level that seemed apropos to
A battlefield environment situation where people could die
Is life-or-death here if you don't follow your honour duty loyal traditional
Stop
And now expect those same kinds of standards of intensity to apply to a situation that is not life or death
You can recreate a little
Incongruity there
And if those were never even really the standards in the days that you were admiring anyway
That makes it even more unreal
Doesn't it
Are we sending the 14th
The Golden Age of Samurai
Fighting
But the 1600 in the 1700 of the golden age of creating the
Fleshed-out
Samurai
Eye of mythal
He's not just a warrior he's a
Confucian scholar
Literate ethical judge of the rest of the Common People
He's a poet
A flower arranger a calligraphy
And many other things
If you want to look at this from
Class perspective Mary's B
Jensen has an interesting line suggesting that some of the non Samurai people living in Japan
Might have seen them more like an
Occupying
Army
Let's stay generation after generation
Counterweight look at it
Is worth pointing out the other
The samurai had many different grade
Ranks
And at the top ranks these are the guys were like running the country the big Power
Samurai
We're never going to have to worry
Society
What is the Bottom Rung of Samurai
Those people can be practically
Or just keeping their head above water now you put them into the Japanese version of the DMV job
And
Life is tough with these people
Squeezing them and it doesn't feel so special to some of them to be samurai anymore they certainly off and don't remember
Too much how to fight I read a quote from somebody
Writing in the yard
18 out of 10 the samurai Aurora's wicked women now they just sit around and do nothing
Internal martial training at all
The expectation level on conduct could be
Life or death
Are you one of the things that we maybe should do with real quickly here is the
The Japanese
Propensity and you'll see it on display in the Second World War
All the time
For suicide
This also can probably
Be traced back in large
Hard especially the military version of this to the samurai
Where a battlefield ethic might
Acquire you
To do something. Extreme in some situations
It gets looking a little fanatical wanted
It's applied to situations
Nowhere near that extreme
What started as a ritual sounds to me more like an alternative
If you happen to be a samurai to having a much more terrible
An execution carried out on you cuz you broke some big rule
So you could kill yourself instead what started out like that
Overtime blended into more and more the society especially the military but even civilians Society
How intense is that
As we said here or not his mother
When he takes us
A dagger
I promised houses
Kill yourself
With this if you can
Get captured
How extreme is that
How does that
Factoring the society
Are tiger Murphy points out that for a lot of the history of
Japan
The average Japanese farmers were thought that was nuts
It's a samurai thing weird nuts
Somehow it goes from
That place where it's only Samurai who do this to a place in the second world war where you see it quite a bit
Seppuku is the official
I think name of the ritual
Harry Caray
Vulgar
Stomach sleeve
Oh that's what the Allied
You'll see this in the Second World War
Commonly enough
That it once again remind you okay
This Japanese great power anime in the second world war is different
From all the other
In combat
Who else does this
Regularly
Now in terms of what the Tokugawa unsworth
Afraid of
From other countries cuz they ever said will be known
Closing
They don't really close that they begin to choke off
Trade with the
Eventually they will get to the point
Weather down to trading with one Western power the Dutch
And it got the Dutch isolated in one port Nagasaki
And eventually they build a little man made Island right off the coast
And it connected to the mainland with a little ramp and a samurai guarding the ramp it's basically you have to show your papers if you want to enter
Raku Japanese
On the mainland
Any kind of thing but like the number one intellectual contagion the Tokugawa rulers are worried about his Christianity
And there will be a big
Purge
Christians
Really bloody
That will go on early on in the Tokugawa era
The problem with the Japanese had with Christianity
Is the same problem that a lot of other
Places of had with it I mean look at how
The problem with it free sample before Rome went Christian
It says just like Judaism
By the way that there is a
Lord that is Supreme Over the
Earthly Authority
Certain kinds of Emperors have problems with that right
In Japan
Problem that the Tokugawa and saw his listen your loyalty is to your daimyo your lord
Or to the Shogun or your parents Army there's a whole confusion hierarchy here people
They're going to be part of the
List of people you all your
Allegiance to and your loyalty to and your Devotion to
And there's no place for some Christian God at the top of the food chain here so it's a threat
It's hardly the only one but it's the most visibly obvious one and it's something that bothers
The Shogun and his
Can Patriots about the Europeans entirely
You think they would get confused too they would ask a lot of questions about Protestants and Catholics and try to understand the enemy just eventually they were so
Usually just basically said a pox on both your houses you're all out
But think of all the stuff Japan misses
Because it's not
Not engaging fully with the rest of the world in the European powers
I mean just off the top of my head there missing the enlightenment
The
French and American Revolutions Industrial Revolution Napoleon the Revolutions of 1848 Marx all this stuff
And remember
These things are tsunami
In places like
Social Revolution up Keeble's Big War
The only thing you can say
For the way the people experience them at the time that they happened
Is that at least they got them one at a time usually
And in the right order
So sometimes you have time to recover from one tsunami bomb
For the next one hits you
Time disorder
Incorporating absorb the lessons or what have you from that era
But when Japan eventually will have to join the rest of the world
They're going to get all that stuff at once
Out of order
And they're not going to have build up
Any intellectual immunity or resist is there going to be like the
People in the Americas it first Contact were with actual contagions
But was intellectual ones at least that's how the Tokugawa bakufu
Would see it
This is a theoretical problem the Japanese writers and what not erect
Talking about
In the 1800's
As the bakufu in the Shogun night gets a little rickety it's getting to be a kind of an old system of government it's not really doing the greatest
Job a lot of people maybe think
But in the middle 1850s would have been theoretical happen
Western Fleet
Shows up in
Japan's Harbours and basically says
You don't get to stay
Closed anymore
Stories by the way like
Call Vista policies.
Occlusion
Because it doesn't really mean close but basically to the people who showed up in Japan in the 1850s this is an American Fleet
By the way
Commodore Matthew
Q Perry
And as far as he's concerned they're closed
And it's going to stop
So they will be
Two visits by Matthew Perry over like a year or two
During this time Japan will be open to the so-called they were never really close so they can never really be open but those are the terms
How many of us grew up with
And this is a an act that is sometimes thrown into the gunboat diplomacy
By the way to Japan didn't necessarily want to do
Do this
Just as an aside one of my favorite historical Twilight Zone moments
Is the one that military storing windeyer
Your paints
When he talks about you know
Matthew Perry's Fleet from
What is just a few years before the US Civil War showing up in finding
A completely medieval kind of people and Military awaiting him sort of on the shoreline
Dyer says there were no guns
Mary's B Jensen says they were guns but makes it sound like they were
It taken out of a museum
And so when Perry shows up
He sees a society where they all have like swords and Spears and body armor in that kind of
That's a pretty cool contrast right
Unless of course you're looking at it from the Japanese
Decide because when
The rest of the world west shows up in forcibly opens Japan
Open linear quote
Japan finds out how
Outgunned it is
So outgunned
But it can't stop these I mean if your japanese's foreign barbarians from imposing their will on Japan
And they will quickly it won't you be the United States everybody kind of comes in.
I didn't realize you Pam was open for business. Let's throw some unequal treaties their way of the same kind
Recently foisted on China
And I think it's safe to say that by
You see in Japan that is
Potentially on the road to being
A colonial victim
This inability to resist one of the great powers
Great power during this time
Call Emma
Aceq higher second-tier power
Find this time.
The inability of Japan to resist
That was almost like the straw that breaks the
The camel's back
For the show tonight
They were already kind of rickety certainly
Finding it tough to evolve its 200
50 year old
I'm basically if
An old human being
And so not being able to defend Japan's interests with sooner
Over a period of years the end of the line for them
The next government in Japanese history
Is never going to forget the job one is make sure you can defend Japan's territory and entry
Stan culture
What happens after the Tokugawa shogunate are in Japanese history is known as the Meiji restoration
Meiji by the way the name of the emperor during this time.
Restoration refers to the way this whole thing is going to be build
It's a
In a story that is akin to Tokens The Return of the King but this is the return of the emperor
In effect
Acknowledging the fact that under this military dictatorship the emperor really hasn't been in charge
This explains why everything's going to hell
Handbasket so we will return things to the way that they're supposed to be in harmony with the universe back to the gold
The emperor runs things again which the emperor may not have
I've ever done
And certainly
During the trees with the emperor didn't do this they were
Unusual in in the distant past but nonetheless sounds good to everybody right put the emperor in charge
How much the emperor's actually running things versus how much these new
Mostly Samurai class oligarchs are running things is unclear
But they were powerful dynamic
Individual
Who are part of this new wave of Japanese reformers who take over the government
And try to
Do a crash course
In modernization
In order to survive
And this is part of
The miracle side of
He went to
Hiroo onoda
Instead
Why would you want
To bring back
The values
And intensity
From the time. That led to such a disastrous
And result as the end of the second World War
He might come back with the line
That's a sure but if we don't have those values in that intensity we never get to Meiji restoration
Are the really great
Clear-eyed
Long range
Visions of you
These people who will
Take control of Japan in the Meiji restoration is the fact that they clearly understand
This adapt or die dilemma that Japan is in
I would make the case that
The same dilemma
Most
Victims of colonial ization have faced at one time or another
Weather
Because what ends up happening is
When the
Potential colonizers show up
And meet you
Is a clock tick
At some point
You have to be able to resist encroachment
Or you will get taken over
During this time. In Japanese by the way when they wake up for the rest of the world This Is How They view it
But this is a total doggy dog world
There are predators and their prey
And they desperately need to move from the
Pray
Situation that they find themselves in
To the Predator one quickly
And you don't know how long you have
Most of these countries that turned out to be Colonial victims art Murphy said there were only
Three places that avoided
Sounds like a pretty low estimate to me but even if I added
If you do the lip
It's instructive he said the only three places that
Avoided direct or indirect western or European colonialism
Ethiopia
Siam
Thailand now
In Japan
And the reason why
Is because
This adapt or die dilemma
Is almost impossible to over
Most of these countries that fell to Colonial powers
Could have overcome them given time but you don't have time
Because you have stuff you have to do to wrap yourself up to a level so that you could compete and resist these kinds of great powers
Takes too long
Because you know that easy to forget this
In the later part of the 19th century
In order to maintain a first-class military
By the great power standards of the time
Your entire Society has to be devoted
An organized in a way
To gerd it as a foundation I mean it doesn't seem like
But that's the way it is
And so when you find out way we got to catch up real fast or somebody's going to eat I forgot to be able to resist anybody that would land on
That takes longer than most places have
The Meiji restoration rulers
Clearly see
But they've got the
Is clock ticking
And so they need a mammoth amount of change
And they needed as quickly as possible
That's what makes this whole thing mirror
The Meiji
Government which is usually called
The Meiji oligarchs
Later that we called a
Cabal
Working in conjunction with the emperor by the way we've not spoken much about the emperor but we
We will in a minute
They're trying to ride the tiger here in terms
Of about
Yeah they understand that I said the adapt or die
Situation
The only want to adopt
As much as they have to
To not die
They still want to preserve Japanese culture as much as they can
Right so they're not the Tokugawa ones with the cultural head binding to that level
But they still are
The oligarch
Mikey and
Even though they want to promote more minute marriage
And they feel like that necessary they don't want to get crazy here and they're a little afraid of the masses if you look at their writing
Until they want to go as far as they have to to compete but no farther
But what happens when you have the society now
It's modernizing with you the Meiji restoration rulers will accomplish so much
They're basically governmental decisions
That are hard enough to imagine I'm going to imagine my country doing any of the top five
Considering the amount of resistance
There would have been to the ideas
But forget that
It's one thing to with the stroke of a pen or a calligraphy brush say we're going to start doing this now
It's another thing
Have
A culture and not just a culture a traditional culture and not just a traditional culture
A culture that the government has
Encouraging even more unnaturally
Traditional
Element to it
And saying okay guess what we're modernizing
Now and we're doing it
Quickly
For our own Survival
There's an account from a British Observer
That lived in Japan during the period where this transformation have
The Meiji restoration
In addition to all the governmental changes he talks about what it's like to just see
See how Japan
Changed in charge of its culture in like a decade
Any talks about the samurai
Guy who taught him the Japanese language
And he says the guy had a sword
Anna ponytail
And I mean that's what your plan was like when he when he first got there he says I distinctly remember
This is his words the Middle Ages
Azle
Chamberlain
Does Ultra
Because I distinctly remember the Middle Ages
And then he says you no less than 10 years later he says now they all look like Europeans they speak with pretty fluent English
And all the talking and it's all modern stuff in the late 19th century is of
Bicycles
Bacilli and spheres of influence
Think about what that does to a culture
Because you can transform a society
Inwood New constitutions which the Meiji
Provide
With a parliament which the Meiji provide
With new court
Deutsche Bank
And finances to let me this is amazing stuff right they will they will intentionally launch an industrial revolution
All that
Stop
Is hard on any society
Think about how hard it was on the ones that got to have all these historical moments happen to them
One of the time
In the right order
The Japanese
Extra traditional culture
Get to have all this stuff happened
In my ten years
This isn't a story about the Meiji restoration which is good because I be over my head
Already
But
We should point out that if it's such an amazing time. There are very sober historians
Compare some of these Meiji oligarchy
Some of these really dynamic
People
Two figures like George Washington
Or the
Roll that The Young Turks
Played in the ottoman state that laid the foundation for the modern Turkish state
This is a big deal on these people are August figures
There are formidable and some of them will live on
Azan
Advisors is an Advisory Group
It will be built into this new governor
These guys will still be in advising Japan on the course of action is
Take into the 1930
Which puts
Squarely on course
Indigo right into our story
Think about
How they would handle their task though if it were you or tasks
So if I said to you listen
You're in an adapter die situation you have to modernize your Society
Fastest possible
What's Job 1
What do you do first
What the Japanese did in smart when you think about it
Is they looked around and they sent out
Observer
People to go all of the Tokugawa regime has been very insolent this is like a hundred eighty degree turn cuz they have to
The new government sends out observers of students all over the world
And they haven't come back and report on what all the different countries do well
Write this country does industrial production while this other one does agriculture well
Military stop while whatever it might be
And the Japanese copy of them
As I said smart right
They'll do the same thing
With their government meaning in the way the Japanese are looking at this Murphy makes this clear what's that other writers
Did a predator or prey law of the Jungle thing going on in the later 19th century
And the job the Japanese see for themselves is to convert themselves from
Something that has potential prey into something that scene is obvious predator
So the Japanese want to be taken seriously by the other great powers
They have to also copy
In some form of government that the great Powers had what what is the template that they're going to build this new modern Japanese government
Conscious effort to create a modern state
And you have lots of choices if you're looking at
European examples don't you
And they should have run the gamut
The entire Spectrum jingle all the way over to one side
You have like a British or French system got forbidden America
Rights of Man a parliament
Representative to some degree government all these kinds of
Or in the case of the Japanese who were
In the process can we say that the Meiji restoration rulers were
We're giving Japan's of the soft
Landing 4
Feudalism if you will that's one of the things they're known for
Probably a little too new
To maybe go off
Paul Frandsen
Britton so maybe you go to something with a little bit more
Military muscle built into the
The Constitutional design
This is the. We're Prussia is active but will soon become United German
This this is a transition period for them but either way
Military involved
Mint in terms of
The way the state is or
Kaiser will be called the Supreme Warlord
That's the kind of thing
Autocratic temper is like a lot
Or you can just go in and turn the dial all the way to the other side and Go full Czar on things if you want to
The Czar of Russia of course during this.
An autocrat
He's an old-fashioned throwback
The divine right of
Kings
Disposition
Is divinely ordained in the social hierarchy by God
This is not a person who is
Fearful of Christianity
Like the Japanese were in the Tokugawa regime this is a person who is wrapped up in a Christian
Bow
And presented to his people
As one step below a deity
The czar's regime is also
Notably hostile to all this talk of democracy and all the social agitation that bothers the Japanese
As much as it bothers the Russian ones
So the Japanese will form a system
That actually takes the whole idea of the Czar wrapped up is the
Chosen man of God one step farther in
Create an emperor that is a guy
Creative
How about
Warps
Can you use the word
Rent a historian talking about how this new government
Will take
The Shinto
Why the Japanese religion
And War
It for State purposes
But they're going to do this with a lot of thing
Going to Warp
Bushido they're going to Warp
The samurai path they're going to Warp
Shintoism
Going to Warp
Pass
By the way
Just like everyone else
Only more so
Go look at that
Late 19th century early 20th century
Text books for kids
You know maybe something along the line
11 year old
For 12 year-old what they would read in school
It doesn't matter what great power in air
Country you go to
The books could all be entitled
Not have your flag on it and the title could say something
Here's what's so great about us
Cuz that's what they kind of sound
And if you open them up I want to remind America cuz I grew up with just the
Fumes
That if you open up those
Those books and looking for example
How they portrayed George Washington
You would not call him a deity
But he was portrayed and I mean people believe this at this time as a guy who never lie
Archetype
Figure I mean well
I guess we can all understand very romanticizing
There were no
And he was portrayed as almost super cute
Human
It's pretty interesting guy I'm not saying but you know what I mean
This is part of this is part of your National mythology that was so important during this era
And Japan took this and turn it up to 11
How did the Tsar
Who's only chosen by God
And they wrapped the emperor into a warped version of Shintoism that got more warped
OurTime
And turned him into a guy
Full disclaimer here
Are you done a public sampling of Japanese opinion 100 years ago
And ask the people on the street whether or not the emperor was a god
I'm going to guess here that you get somewhere in the 85% range that says yes
Anyway
I don't know that that's
Truitt although
But the point is is that
This was an existing thing
That the government for its own State purposes like most governments anywhere
Took and you
And I used it by wrapping the entire organization of this modern State around the emperor
Now in terms of the power of the emperor figure all I can say about that is good luck
The determining that
And it's such a key point in the story to because
It's so many points you want to know
Who's responsible for this or that decision that has deadly horrible consequences you want to be able to
Play where does the buck stop in this system and you're not going to be able to put your finger on
I seem to be several
Your layers availed
The cover-up the way the Japanese government work some of it put in there deliberately at the time it was formed
Some of it to insulate
The Royal Court from the muddiness of traditional in a day-to-day politics and say the parliament
When I was a kid that history is taught that the emperor during the second world war was like a figurehead sort of to a military
Cherry dictatorship not unlike a 20th century version
Of the Shogun
Nowadays there are
Pulitzer prize-winning history by historians like Herbert
Suggest that's not true
And maybe what was a conspiracy theory when I was growing
Isn't such a conspiracy theory the idea that the emperor had his reputation laundered
The way
Engineers and scientist who had to work for the Nazis died in Operation Paperclip
So maybe the way you make the emperor and okay figure to be a post-war
Figure on the
Global
Geopolitical Cold War chess board is to launder
Is passed by saying Hey listen to music
Tool of the military dictatorship didn't have any power but maybe he did
By the way the system is designed this major restoration system the emperor supposed to be like the top of the Apex in the
Japanese social hierarchy
And theoretically he controls everything and he has the power to reach down through layers of the bureaucracy
Create Justice and solve problems and cut through red tape
What's the likelihood of single figures going to be able to do all that as they say when one person is in charge of everything nobody's really in charge of
Anything
You can see how this gift the entire
Nation-state into trouble for example
When you look at the relationship in this system the Meiji restoration constitutional system of the emperor
To the Armed Forces
The Army and the Navy of Japan don't owe their allegiance
The nation
State of Japan
The other allegiance to the emperor
Personally
In fact
They're kind of taken out of the realm of politics altogether
And put into
You know his hands for his uses as he sees fit but what if he doesn't ever get involved in the situation
What it really means
Is that the political leaders have no control over the middle
Military the military can say hey we're answerable only to the emperor in the emperor's stays in his room doesn't bother any
It's a little like that
Can I look at the difference. Between
The potential power of the emperor versus
The reality of the situation I can't help
But see him as a figure like
The Incredible Hulk
Superhero reference
My apologies to those who hate that kind of stuff but you seem so perfect in this situation
Because when the guy wants to do and this seems to be almost like
The role of the emperor going way back into ancient time
They have all this
Layton
Power
But they don't use it very often it's the Hulk but they don't turn into the whole very often
Maddeningly inconsistent
But when they do they can move Mountain to me one of the things that the war crime
Investigations after the war
Storing Herbert P big size
But they wanted to know from the Japanese emperor
Is they were trying to figure out if the guy has the power to stop the war you know all he has to do is turn into the Incredible Hulk
The war within now in the War and why didn't he ended it the beginning before millions of people that died
Right it's very frustrating for
The people in the west look at the society and try to figure out where the lines of Power are we're very comfortable
With a couple of different things right there where we used to
I mean if you say you have a ruler
And you have like a Magna Carta
Reconstitution
That dictates what they could do which hardly get that right bring in the
Magnifying glass and the lawyers
Now you can then read the text so we can't do this
You can do that and this other stuff that smirk in the middle we can argue about we get that with a lot of that
Unfortunately we also have a lot of the other extremely get that too
You know that one that's the
Pharaoh God Julius Caesar Joseph Stalin Adolf Hitler djingis Khan thing we have nothing written down because there's nothing you can't do
Total power
The Japanese emperor is neither one of those
Those things
But seem to be
Bound by what historian Herbert pubix
Called
You know an ethos
A restraint
In the use of his
Write something that's Bound by things that are not written
Things that are very difficult for Outsiders to proceed cuz for a bunch of the stuff you have to have
In agricultural antenna
Set to the Japanese setting you can really only get that most of the time
True amazing Decades of study or being Japanese
What's The Outsiders difficult for us to understand but maybe to the Japanese emperor
And this court protocol
The tradition and a bunch of other considerations may be as binding to him
As a Magna Carta or a constitution would be to some other
Trying to figure out how
The emperor
Interact
The military how they all interact
The prime minister
The parliament
Privy Council the genro in all these other elements in that Society will drive you crazy I looks like
Understood it
I couldn't even figure out a shorthand way to describe it so one of the rare times I went to look for somebody else a shorthand way to describe it
And I ended up on Wikipedia which may be the first time we're using something
From there but it was
Perfect
They describe this government remember with adaptations and evolution this is going to be the government that goes into the sea
Where the lines of power
Well the Wikipedia piece described it
As a quote
Form of mixed
Constitutional - absolute monarchy
A form of mixed constitutional absolute monarchy what do you think that the term absolute monarch
So that makes the rest of that phrase moot
He was a wild party
That is what it is
That's a good description of it
But that's out of the scripture that really makes any sense or helps you figure out who's in charge of the
Twice
One thing you can say though
Is that by
Injecting
Add or a religious level
Fervor and belief
Into this state and this culture at this time. Deliberately is as for State purposes
These rulers
Ratchet up the intensity level yet again because I mean after all
When do you normally inject religion and deities in the things people don't get more serious and passionate about it
Probably never end in this case
That was not a bug that was a feature
And I don't mean to say cuz I think most of these Meiji oligarchs
We're True Believer
Example motion and probably believed in the Divinity of the emperor
Imagine for a minute that instead of them being true believers they were
Much more cynical
Power mongers who were just looking at the tools they could use to keep the people under their boot
What an amazing tool this idea
That the emperor is divine is
Looking out if you buy into the state will call State propaganda
Look at how it completely changes your logical calculations
By the parameters
It turns your your mind against you your rational mind for example if you buy the two
Tuileries in this system is going to be drilled into the heads increasingly Japanese students as they grow up
But the emperor is responsible for all the decisions
Littermaid in terms of charting the course of the nation
Ana policies
And also that the emperor is basically
Superhuman
What is The Logical choice to make
In terms of
Accepting
The government's point of view on things
Or the course of the nation or anything else I mean doesn't become illogical if you buy those parameters to think that
Did you have any business
Even questioning the authority
I mean this is basically a god they see things from a higher perspective you're an idiot to send it from your position
You should be questioning that level of authority
If you buy that level of authority
Could have been a class
If you ruin daughter
I believe was born in 90
P22
When he's in
Don't he's in the Early Education levels in his Jeep and that's the most intensive
To Panic or started the public school system
Copying the great powers
They thought it might have been some of the secret sauce
What made those great Powers dominant
But they also needed a literate population to man all those Industries and all those other things that we're going to support their modern military
So it was a no-brainer
But you know
There's an old saying I think the
Nobody ever really object to children
Learning to read the questions always comes
To the forest what are they reading
And this case
As in every country it is pretty propagandize State stuff and then the Japanese case more intense than most
And in the same way that we have people in the United States may have had a little bit of a hero-worship
Over George Washington in Japan they had a little bit of a worship worship
Over the Japanese emperor
You think about how
This can
I'm just thinking about differences in how long a country has to inject a national mythology
Into a popular
Japanese school children
Increasingly
If you boil it down to the subject matter they're all learning things that we would think are good things to Teach Me Senpai treats
Love of country
Sacrifice
Honor your parents
Respect authority minis are all values
Are all the school systems the Japanese were
Imitating we're teaching
And the Japanese parents at the time probably would have approved
There's no doubt it'll brainwash you if you're buying what they're selling
And if you're going to walk a mile and a guy like
Hero another's moccasins let's understand
That is logical calculations
That's simply doing what the emperor told him to do
Is the smart choice to make
And if you are a cynical wielder of the levers of
The power
True realpolitik
Dictator type
He gives you a right onto have that kind of
Belief system on the party
Your population
Dallas remember the number one goal of this new government.
They have to deal with him in all this other stuff is kind of a means to an end if you can't defend yourself from an outside power wants to take you over
None of this matters
Meiji restoration have to build a modern Army and they do
And they do it the same
General way they've been doing all these other things they look at who's doing it well and they copy them and they get their help and they buy stuff from them
Once again this is smart isn't it
On land
Right around
1870 or what not there
If dealing initially with the French military they will eventually though ditch them for the Germans
And in a move that many countries do the United States and the Soviet Union
All the time in the Cold War
The Germans will send advisors over there who will bring
You know equipment
Uniforms
Tactics
Doctrine training leadership bring some of their key officers back to learn things in Germany then send them back to teacher
Everyone out this relationship free classic
But it's sort of creates
A
A forever German stamp in the early DNA of the modern Imperial Japanese Army
Might be a good way to put it
I think we all know history has been a pretty good
Demonstrator that just because you give a whole bunch of the best stuff to some other military doesn't mean they're going to fight well
Because there were two sides
The equation
And one side sort of easy to fill the other side's a lot harder
1 sides quantifier
Right you can spend a certain amount of money
To get this job done we can provide this many rifles we can provide this buddy uniforms this many hours of training this much support
We all that stuff can soda be figured out to the end
Decimal
But the other side of what's going to make us
Successful military
Is something as bedrock in terms of values
As whether or not your people are going to be willing to die
And whether they will fight on the battlefield long enough to make that investment in the stuff that they carry
Worth it
You get two armies and they line up on a battlefield across from each other and one has the best needed
Coolest most
Devastating new stuff in the others armed with sticks
But the side with the devastating stuff doesn't want to fight or they're afraid or they don't have any interest
Destiny just leave
Fat lot of good all that investment did you
How do you inject or create or artificially stimulate a warrior ethos in a brand new
Military
But what if you had a shortcut
Mobile to you
What if you already had
An indigenous
Long-standing
Warrior ethos and tradition of your own just sitting there not doing anything
Could you
Reanimated repurposing clone it
Could you customize it so that it meets the needs of a late 19th century early 20th century regime
Even if I told you
The state was pushing
These values what would you think
Values like
Courage
Benevolence
Politeness
Selflessness
Sincerity
Honor
Loyalty
Self control
A strong sense of justice
That's all like benishan inventing the Way of the Samurai describing
The various virtues that have sometimes been described
2 Bushido
The ethical Way of the Samurai
Your kids were learning those kinds of things in school you probably
We think that that was a good thing
What the government of Japan would do during this time.
Is they will pick and choose when we had said earlier that they warp all these things
Preexisting in Japan Bushido goes way way back although the term itself may only date from the lake
Late 19th century
But this will be another traditional Japanese thing that the modern state will take in warp for its own purposes
And according to Venice if I understand correctly he's basically saying that amongst the wide-ranging inteligencija debating
In the various aspects of Bushido you can find almost every opinion out there you want
But the state would pick the ones that most
In corresponding
With things that would help it for example finally settling on one of the most
Influential they're called Bushido theorist
Out there
Who is boiled Bushido down to just simply really two things and you can see why the state would like a guy like this
Validate his viewpoint on Bushido cuz he boils it down to love of the emperor
And patriotism
That's not a bad thing
From the state's point of view to infuse into your public schools and your children
And then to continue doing so too much more intense level when the male children from that public school
Grow up and become part of the military
The father of the second world war prime minister
Hideki Tojo
Told a gathering of Educators in the 1890s
They should totally familiarize themselves with how the Army does everything because the Army is the real finishing school
And all these educators are doing the public school is preparing the kids to join the Army so get used to how we do things and teach the kids that way
Now we should add that in addition to
Just wonderful high-minded philosophical Warrior ethos
I think there's much more grounded understandable reasons why Japanese soldiers might be reluctant to surrender
Or flee
If things like the commands by Japanese General sometimes that said
That we will execute anyone who does This real-world concerns to but
Why not lots of other armies in history
Chilled deserters
And well
People still route
So there's some combination of elements going on here
Ends up creating a Japanese military that from the very beginning the Imperial Japanese Army will
Will have morale that's probably equal to the other
Best armies out
And it will only get higher as time goes on remember this military only exist for like the light
The 1870s and 1880s it really has built
And course in 1945 it all comes to a halt
But in that time.
You will go from instantly higher than should be expected morale
2 unbelievable fanatical levels of morale
For comparison purposes because we all know that
The German Army II
What's a very good army
But in the book implacable foe as historians Waldo Hendricks and Mark colicchio
Compare the two in this
Morale regard
They point out the
The Japanese situation was often just
Going to be a question
Victory or death they write quote
Surrender was unthinkable
In Tunisia when the German Afrika korps surrendered in 1943
The British captured more than 120000 German soldiers
Including a colonel General and his staff 12 generals and all
The Allied liberation of France in the summer of 1944 they write 200 thousand
As the war progressed the Allies captured so many German officers that the British set up a special residence for them in the English
Countryside
During the final weeks of the war in Europe more than 1500000 German surrender to the Western allies
In contrast
They right
No
Organized unit of the Imperial Japanese army surrender during the entire Pacific War
Until they were ordered to do so by the emperor After Japan had formally agreed to capitulate
This that right
Was a record unprecedented in the annals of Modern Warfare
And quote
And as we've already pointed out there were a bunch of Japanese soldiers
But just because the war ended didn't see
Youfit reason to
Surrender
This is pretty high level of morale
You can't say that this whole Bushido injection which some people compared to an ideology others to more like a religion
You can't say that this is the reason why
But you can stay the
The state was definitely using the idea for those purposes
The morale of the Imperial Japanese Navy will also be really high in some of these Bushido ideas will be injected
You can do that as well
They may have flirted with another
Advisor for a minute on land but
In terms of
Who to look to As You Are
Mentor for building a great Navy in the 19th century late 19th century there's only one choice
What the best the best is the Royal Navy
The Sun never sets on the British Empire was said
What is the Royal Navy
Text that the Japanese begin a long-standing connection with the British Navy
Same thing is on land tactics.
When strategy leadership
A long-term serving of Japanese officers on Royal Navy ships and then going back in the traditions of the Imperial Japanese Navy
Japanese leaving buy some of their
Bigger tickets
Items from the British until they can build their own so the relationship is designed
To make up for lost time
And quickly ASAP right
Create
And adaptation of Japan
That as a heart attack at Murphy point that is at least
A reasonable imitation of an imperialist power
Course if you are trying to present yourself as a reasonable imitation of Imperial
Nation state
That's probably going to require
A little imperialism when you think
Problem with a little
Imperial
Resume is it's one of those things that when a political state
You start down that road it's time to stop sometimes I mean it's like that potato chip commercial you can't just
Eat one
A little like that with other countries and territories to once you get one of them
Start sit
Feel kind of good
Well that's funny because if you and again I'm unless qualified to talk about anything addiction
Specialist
History
But doesn't it sort of look if you look at
Nation-states
And imagine the most people
Doesn't look like your pants about
How to get hooked
Here and that their rise and fall
Is going to parallel something like
Enter your classic
Drug addict
Cycle of addiction
I think you can make it
Vacation at the wonderful hinge mower
MTG Japanese history may be horrible in
Only because they go from
Simply trying to make sure they don't get
In these
Shark infested Colonial Waters
Looking around
Themselves
And well
Like potato chips
Sometimes you can develop an appetite for those things once you start it looks like Japan in this era
Dangerously hooked on imperialism
And it's not hard to see how it happened I mean after all
All the countries Japan wanted to be liked and emulate the club that they wanted to join of the great Powers all those
Guys are up to it already
Even little Belgium
Got a problem
Shake it for
Long time
Even the holier-than-thou United States
Which denounces other people's imperialist Adventures
Boss wearing the
Milan transfers of territory with Mexico seizures of Hawaii and whatnot are not indicative of a growing problem
Will begin having a larger more public problem
In the Spanish-American War when Guam the Philippines Cuba and other places will just sort of
The fall into its lap I guess
William McKinley the president of the time going or should I
He was a junkie of some kind might have been adrenaline
Might have been something else
Not Teddy Roosevelt does not strike me as the
Intoxicating substances the mind-altering substances kind of guy
But if you told me he had an addiction or might be likely to develop one
Uno gym muscle growth steroids
Well shoot I wouldn't be too surprised about that in fact
As I look at
You know what all analogies have a little bit of a silly side but that's kind of what we enjoy sometimes right
Look at this analogy of these countries and imperialism it kind of looks like steroids to me
I mean take Japan for example
Choose a country that in their mind
Should be stacked up with all the great part we can hang with anybody but then they take a 250 year
Seclusion break from the gym
When they next encounter all these other great Powers get huge
We look at how they must have seen Britain
On a map
Lot of comparison to be made a couple of violent Nations you know interesting and distinctive people all these kind of stuff
But that's where the comparison ends
Japan comes out of
Seclusion
Britain controls a huge chunk of the world are obviously juicing on something India Maybe
But Japan
Goes on a crash course to catch up
Number to understand when we say getting addicted
To imperialism when were using those phrases for countries
What are you get addicted to is a country well let's just really go over this quickly cuz I think we all get it but
How about raw materials
How long have people been invading and conquering places
To get somebody else's stuff
In this modern era you also have these
Unequal trade agreements which can lock
A colony into
You're turning over a large chunks of their raw materials and well that reduced
Or
Nonexistent rate of exchange
Prestige in this era
Is huge will have a bunch of countries
Are latecomers to the Colonial party who will take the few leftover places
Just so that they have another place another notch on their belt the reason those places were taken by great power that
Nothing anybody wanted
The last thing they have is a dad to your prestige you I now have $6
Use the last time you saw me
I only had 5 I'm moving up in the world
Those are the things
That attract you to these countries in the first place right with what's the first reason you start using the steroid
Dabbling I want to be a little bigger
Injury I need the raw materials to trade position and LoPresti I want to be big like the other guys it's all understandable
But when you get involved in it
Then you kind of committed and you get sucked into something deeper this is why I like this analogy
And the
Thing that sucks countries into the colonial
Lifestyle
Are things like the capital Investments
But you begin to make it a country or your company's do or your company's in conjunction with a country do
Putting in railroads
Mining
Development in all these local places you begin to have steak
A state that if people start saying listen though they change in foreign affairs dictates it would be best for us to leave this area now
Now I'm turn it back over to the locals
You can have a lot of powerful rich
People were going to say wait a minute
What about our investment
And that's of course just money
What about lie
The lies it takes
Conquer these places in the lies it takes to keep them conquered I mean for example
The Japanese will get their hands on Taiwan at a certain point
I'll buy some sort of treaty deal but the people in Taiwan word after the Japanese will lose quite a few people trying to pacify that
An area that supposedly on a piece of paper they were just hand it over
This becomes not just a cost you have to pay to play this game right an entry fee into the colonial games
Tekashi have to keep paying
Stay in the game and it provides another investment
It keeps you from having the flexibility
Is the X
Dictate that it'd be better to give up this policy of
Colonialism or steroid use
Somebody's going to say wait a minute my son died conquering that territory are you going to make his sacrifices
Meaning what are you going to undo
Everything his life bottom you see how that
To see how that sucks you in
By the country
Remember to the Japanese are seeing these European powers
Suit up at the height of the good time
While they're riding high in the addiction and they're lifting weights and they're taking steroids they're going to the tanning salon and then cover themselves with baby oil
They're getting their hair bleached and I look great
Right there not seeing
These countries down the road
You know on the downside of this addiction when they're in the in old folks home prematurely with all the healthcare Pro
Problems in the steroids are gone in the muscles are shriveled and they look and feel awful
When the
Japanese look at the
French in what's called Indochina for example modern-day Vietnam
They see the French sitting there having the Vietnamese serve them food and restaurants are wonderful Colonial existence while of course the French pay them
Back by giving them French culture in everything except
Traditional colonial trade off
The Japanese will not see the French 90 years from this time.
When the 1950s there fighting a vicious Insurgency by the vietminh trying to kick the French out of via
Vietnam
Going to go talk to then but of course by that time
In the 1950s the Japanese are in full recovery mode
After a global intervention
Pulling into its
Steroid addiction
It's half-century long steroid addiction
If it wanted to go back
And Trace
And the roots of how it began
That initial taste
It seemed so consequence-free that got you hooked and Led You Down
And that terrible path rise and fall of Japan's
Imperialism addiction
Starts with Korea
Just just sitting there wasn't it
Like a dagger
And the Heart of Japan is the German advisor from Bismarck told the Japanese government
The Japanese had already
Treated urea very shortly after it was opened up against its will by the Western powers to that exact same
Pain treatment
And then foisted the same sort of unequal treaties on Korea that the West had foisted on Japan so you can learn
Quickly
They were ripe for trying out
What the Western Powers were
Your building their muscles off of with
And the first hit free happened in Korea
In the 1870s and 1880s the Japanese involve themselves more more in internal Korean politics and Dynamics
Korea is generally in the sphere of influence of the great Jupiter of the region China but increase
Recently is the Russians have advanced all the way to the Pacific they have more of an impact to in that area
Which of the Japanese this is a Kia mean if this were a game of Risk or something where there were no morals or ethics are
Anything involves Reich of the Korean people will suffer terribly
You know into this time. We're getting into but let's imagine people don't matter in a risk
Games
If you're playing Japan you want to take Korea
During this time. The Chinese and the Russians are in a much better position than you are so what do you do
Well in 1894
Somehow Japan ends up in a war over
The sphere of influence control of Korea
With China
1894-s called the first
Sino-japanese War
And it is really the first time that this new Army of Japan since they opened up leaves Japan to fight somebody else
Not counting
In Ireland insurrections and whatnot
Japan's ghost
Someone will say what you forgot
Anything here
First major one
Other way outside Observers
For the most part believe that China will crush Japan
Both China and Japan have been undergoing military modernization for kind of the same reason both of them fighting themselves.
Dangerously vulnerable
To Western Technologies are working to catch up
The stated opinion out there by most people where's the China had done a better job including having a fleet
I love the way again this is the time. We're race and all that stuff is over they had the most powerful
Asian please
In Asia it was thought
Anime stunning absolutely stunning
Campaign the Japanese just roll the chine
On land and its see and it's much more shocking probably if you read The Observer that see
Where they destroy the Chinese Fleet
So terribly that story Mary Jensen says China won't have another Blue Water Navy for a hundred years
The Chinese Admiral commits suicide
On land
It's interesting
The Japanese are so dominant they are dishing out
Casualties at 10 to 1 ratio 15 to 1 ratio
And you can't label any single advantages being dominant because
Energy sword delve into it a little bit the Japanese scene dominance with across-the-board
Chinese and Japanese military to modernize but the Japanese had done it
In a lot better of a way they made better choices the Chinese had gone with the banner system it just it didn't work
It's a coming out party on the world stage in Addis shocking to westerners
Don't have a lot of respect for orientals to begin with but if they have respect for any of them it's
China even though they're biting off pieces of China
And what not to do them China still represents one of the wisdom of the East
Confucian ideas in this great culture theoretically
Is Japanese or nothing but upstart Sandy Japanese go into this war with
China
And end up winning it
While losing less usually the numbers UCR less than 1500 men killed in combat
Less than 1500 men killed in combat
Astounding
Chinese numbers are
You're ten times that or something
The idea that you could win a war
China
And lose less than 1500 men killed
What was the downside of imperialism seemingly that small anybody could get hooked
Good night
The first thing that the Japanese got out of this war which state
Clearly wanted from the emperor down to the
You know average
Japanese person on the street
Was respect
And prestige on the international World stage the other great powers
Sat up and took notice
Nation 95 the year the war ended Lord Charles Beresford was quoted in the times of London this saying quote
Japan has within 40 years gone through the various administrative phases that occupied English
Blind about 800 years
And roll about 600
And I am loath to say that anything is impossible with her
And quote
It was a lot of admiration but it was still tempered by this idea that yes they're pretty amazing for Oreo
Bochum University
It was an almost died
Racialist view of things while they have moved themselves up to the the top of the food chain
Amongst their people in that part of the world I mean that was the progressive way of looking at
There were people around the Russian tsar and begin pardon is a new sound like racism both but we're talking about one of the most
Racist periods in world history and impact decision-making
The people around the Russian czar
Thought of the Japanese up there was one quart of there just yellow monkey
Okay well what happens to you
If it's your job to deal with yellow monkeys
And you're trying to figure out okay how many troops do we need on the border with those people I mean when you're trying to make
Conscious decisions about how you should behave
What your view of reality is so tainted by your racism that you can't possibly imagine these people doing anything that would hurt you
And that's what a lot of the other people said the Japanese were able to do this for the Chinese cuz obviously the Chinese week is heck
They never be able to do what your white Nation
Will the end of Japan's war with China here
Opens up the door to them having a problem with their first European nation
Because Japan
Gets a peace treaty extracted from China that is like hitting the jackpot in Las Vegas for the Japanese
First of all
Did the terms are that they get a ton of money
It's like the equivalent of 4 years of Japan's total budget handed over to them
They also get the island of Taiwan which is huge and the surrounding smaller Islands
Right to use Japan's first colony
They also get
A an agreement that they will sort of have the sphere of influence control of Korea
And in order to make that work they have to get this peninsula
Which is strategically very important so it's all part of the deal
Japan
A sort of had this coming out party during the Great Powers now and then all of a sudden I love the way our Taggart Murphy disc
Scribe that he says it's the equivalent of having three old seasoned lions come in
And steal the first kill of a young leopard who's just learning how to hunt and just you know thinks he's hit the jackpot
No no no no no we're going to alter the terms of the deal said the Three Lions metaphorically named
France Germany and Russia
In a move known as the triple intervention
Those three powers come in until Japan that they can't extract the tri-d from China that they want to
For the sake of the Peace of Asia they said but in reality Japan
Figured that all three of those countries had their own ideas about things in China that they wanted
And so they told the Japanese no uncertain terms giving them no choice by the way
I will have China pay you more money than the original deal called for but you don't get to have that important strategic but
Angela that has that Port named
Port Arthur on it
Now I should point out
Something about Port Arthur before we go any farther
Because it's Jermaine to the story
Port Arthur
Was the site of a terrible Massacre
In the sino-japanese war that just ended
Init
The Japanese Army went in
And killed men women and children between 1000 is the lowest number you see
And the high-end
Possible number is 20000
That's a huge gap obviously but there are other people that take that number
Much much much much higher than that
But they really aren't that many people in that region of the not really that credible but just know that
The incredible numbers go much higher than 20000
The reasons important though
Is because you will see on display
Things that both look
Medieval to Modern people in the late 19th century
And things that are going to be reminiscent
Of incidents we will see over and over in the Second World War
The Japanese going to Port Arthur
And the three
Rationales just so you know that you'll get for this
You'll get for the other basically situations like in the Second World War
You got them at the time you will get them today from ultra-nationalist there's three one is that these incidents happened when
Atrocities were committed against Japanese troops
The soldiers kind of lose their minds for a while
A suggestion is that this is understandable
Troops in combat
And that it's not something that the Army itself condone but it's understandable right so you got the atrocity thing
The second thing you'll often hear is
That the Press is reporting that these are civilians but they're really enemy soldiers were trying to hide from our troops and live to see
Might put them in everything from behind buildings
Dressed as civilians all these people that look like civilians really enemy soldiers and the last thing you will hear
Reliably
Is that the numbers are inflated
Now there is some potential truth to the numbers are inflated thing because in the same way you have
Ultra-nationalist
All around the planet now trying to revamp
The way the World Views perhaps we'll call them negative chapters in the history of their military that they're right
Flea proud of but every nation has them
I mean the Chinese for example have an interest in magnifying Japanese crimes against
Chinese citizens and the Japanese if your patriotic have interest in seeing the numbers in the best possible light it's all
All understandable
But I'm going to let historians argue that sort of stuff I'm just going to try to stick to the facts and I'm going to try to give
Multiple sides
But here's what an eyewitness
And there were several westerners
In Port Arthur when the massacre happened
Here's how he described it and just so you know
You could take this description out of this time. In this event
Substituted for any number of incidents that happened in the second world war and you wouldn't know
It wasn't written down because they have a tragically familiar
Ring to them
Just author who witnessed
The events
At the massacre Port Arthur in the first sino-japanese war described it this way
Quote
Thursday Friday Saturday and Sunday we're spent by the soldiery in murder and pillage from dawn
Wanted dark
Emulation
In every conceivable kind of name was atrocity
Until the town became a ghastly Inferno
To be remembered with a fearsome shutter until one's dying day
I saw corpses of women and children
Three or four in the street
More in the water
Bodies of menstrual the streets in hundreds perhaps thousands for we could not count
Some with not a limb on the Severn
Some with their heads hat
Cross cut and split lengthwise
Some ripped open
Not by chance but with careful Precision down and across
Disemboweled and dismembered
But occasionally a dagger bayonet
Trust in the private
I saw groups of prisoners tied together in a bunch
With their hands behind their backs
Riddled with bullets for 5 minutes and then human two pieces
I saw a junk stranded on the beach build with fugitives of either sex and of all ages
Struck-by volley after volley
Until I can say no more
And quote
What's going through a few thoughts
The first one is that there's nothing unusual about an event like this is their your history books are
Are littered with this stuff going back to the beginning of time project
Italy
Go read the Assyrian animals sometimes it's
Seems like it's nothing but that
Start to finish
But things are starting to change in this. We're coming in to write early 20th century
And you can't necessarily get away with things that people got away with forever nation-states free
Example Army
Ours kingdoms
Warlords whatever you want to say mean if your
If you don't settle philosophical experiment if a tree falls in the forest and there's no one there to hear it either really make a sound
We'll have some
Terrible Massacre occurs if some out-of-the-way people in a remote region in no one ever hears about it outside the little okay
Cavity
Does it really matter
Well
In this time.
And when you're coming into the 20th century here now we have telegraphs and communication on that level
Well it's starting to really matter
First of all
Good luck trying to keep it a secret that account we just read you slipped out didn't it it wasn't the only one
Would that have happened
500 years before this time
The second important point is when it slips out at people in other countries hear of it
They have the ability if there's enough of them and they're angry enough
To make you
Beautiful earrings
And this will be a key part in The Story 2 when public opinion in other countries
Begins to try to make you conform to their standards
20th century
Another standard is changing
Is the outright idea
Is the right of one country to count to another and take it over
And it's been pretty well-established and understood in the 20th century starts becoming on fool
Especially amongst the more
Cool Powers mini old-fashioned ones like
The Germans and the Russians of course not the Japanese may still think you can go in there and take other people over but we more sophisticated power than your
Is it morally wrong
Meanwhile they'll go in establishing
Protectorate over someone
Which is a tree about
Agreement we have with them to safeguard their needs and help them development of an easy what I'm saying mean
It will require many more layers of diplomatic cover
To conquer or control areas in the 20th century
In the old days you could just take them over while they were still powers that live by the old rules
And it will be a public opinion price for doing that
I should also point out
The training of the Japanese military
Was unlike the training of any other
Great power military inside
It's hard for me to find any organized military in the late 19th or 20th century
The train their soldiers the way the Japanese were trained
I mean here in the US for example for a long time I don't know if they do this anymore but Marines for example used to have combat with each other
Bootcamp
In basically that use weapons that are sticks
With tatted at
So you're fighting
Even had a hand combat like that
The Japanese in the second world war before I don't know if it comes into this. I have to be very honest with you
I tried to find research I don't know if it goes back into this.
But in the second world war in the 1930s
Japanese troops will often be trained
On live people
There are photos and they're horrible that you can go and see online
Japanese soldiers bayoneting
In training exercises with the other recruits who's turn is not now watching
Bayoneting
Chinese prisoners just hands are tied
Is multiple photos of of Japanese
Captives were what not tied to stakes and have bayonet practice and sword
I mean
There's an account by Japanese officer who talks about
His training involving
Having to slice the head off somebody
And if you look
At
Paintings of the sino-japanese war made by Japanese artist there's some that
Show the
Mass beheadings of Chinese captives with samurai sword
Japan's victory over China had big ramifications because it was the equivalent
Of throwing blood and Chum
Into the shark-infested colonial Waters and and telling the rest of the world
That the recent victories by Britain in the Opium Wars and what not
What is the sign of temporary Chinese inability to deal with Western military technology
It was the beginning of the end of maybe this Chinese Imperial Dynasty there was obviously some sort of a rotting house
Apparent after the Japanese kick the door down
And that
Lead to something called the Boxer Rebellion where western territories ended up bringing in troops Eight Powers only one of them
Asian one guess who it was
Yes in Japanese
And they sent as many troops as everyone else put together
Basically you know throwing are Laden with the club you belong in the club where here you know
Looking at a map they probably had more of a right to be there than anyone else
The next big foreign-policy milestone on the way to work story here involves
A war that the Japanese get involved with in 1904
Against the Russians
The Russians were one of the Three Lions and said for the Peace of Asia you can't have this Port Arthur area just not right
And forced the Japanese to give in the Japanese always thought that Russia really wanted it for themselves
Within three years the Washington taken its confirming the Japanese suspicions and they started fortifying Port Arthur in the whole thing
Sony 1904
When the Japanese had decided to know for all sorts of reasons
That they still needed
To control this area
They launched let's just
Holiday
Free aircraft version of a Pearl Harbor
On the Russian Far Eastern Fleet
Having torpedo boats go in there and attack Russian ships
About 3 hours before war was officially declared
In short order
The Japanese will
Destroy the Russian Far Eastern Fleet
The Russian leaders around the Tsar or so caught off guard by this they didn't think the Japanese would attack them or didn't have it in
Talking white power
Send the fleet that they have in the Baltic the Baltic Fleet from up near Finland
All the way to Japan to teach these oriental people a lesson
Takes months to get there and when they get there the Japanese beat that to
In stunning fashion is not like a close fight at all
On land it's more of a harder slog
4 simple reasons I mean we're
Like a decade away from the first World War
And all of those lessons they are going to learn
In the first year of the first world war like in the you can't charge machine guns frontally
The impact of the defense I mean all the stuff you're going to learn the Japanese get to learn against the Russians on land
And there are horrible photo showing
I mean like
Walls of Japanese soldiers dead in front of these fortified positions because
You often led by an officer with the samurai sword they blindly in phonetically charged
Are you don't have to
To think of yourselves as Samurai to do that because we all know the European powers will do that in less than 10 years
Turn the last what you see here
Is the Japanese finding out
At the cost of this path on which they have embarked
To emulate the colonial powers
He's not going to come as easy as
That War in China you're not going to lose 1500 or less dead
You know down the road here it's a commitment and against the Russians in the russo-japanese war the Japanese lose some
Something more like 40000 dead
Directions to by the way it's nasty
World War 1 fighting
Before World War 1
And it's all the early War stuff when everybody you know has to learn the terrible lessons
You know about charging into artillery fungus it
Nasty and horrible and then there's disease to as all these wars during this time. Have a terrible problem with
It also and this is another lesson of modern war the other great Powers will learn very soon
It takes
A horrible toll Modern War does on your economy and the Russian economy in the Japanese economy will instantly
Start to feel the pinch and then the stretch and it gets to the point with the Japanese secretly go to American president
Teddy Roosevelt and ask if he can get both countries out of this mess and broke or some kind of a deal
What she does
And wins the Nobel Peace Prize for by the way
But a decent number of people in Japan think that the American president in his peace deal
Rip the Japanese off
The thing eventually won this war
I didn't come out of it with a treaty that
It looked anything like
Hitting the jackpot did
In the first sino-japanese war
This is more like a treaty
Denver countries that
How to tie rather than one at least where the Japanese people reading a bias press that magnify their victories
I think that they had dominated
Lose all these lives
All this money
Beat the Russians in all these battles
And not get significant territory or a big Financial indemnity
And the terms of the agreement ending the russo-japanese war are made public
There will be violent riots in Japan the people will die
The population there pretty much every history book you want to point out
The people there take it as another grievance
The Japanese are holding onto grievances like the rain man character did
In the movie of the same name and they remember vividly that we call it the triple intervention screwjob
That ended the sino-japanese war where a bunch of Western Powers who never would have settled for someone else doing that to them
Treated the Japanese in a way that the Japanese took personally
They saw his changing the rules of the game and the Japanese start winning
And they often sought in racial terms
And maybe not incorrectly
Well now it was happening again
Not only was it happening again
Body was happening despite the fact that the Japanese had taken proactive measures to see that it didn't again in 1902
They signed an alliance with Britain
Part of the reason he did it was they were hoping that if you have a great power on your side bunch of other great Powers won't come in like they did last
Best time and try to steal your kill
And yet here with the agreement ending the russo-japanese war
It looks like it made no difference and your kill got stolen again
Goes on the list of grievances
But it's very possible that the Japanese citizenry
Ed unrealistic expectations
This is the way our Taggart Murphy describes what Japan had one for itself in a decade including two Wars here
And it is far from
Auntie rights quote
Japan's victory in the russo-japanese war was if anything even more striking than its
Triumph 10 years earlier over the Ching Chinese
For the first time since the fall of Constantinople a non-Christian non-western power defeated the forces
Is it a Christian Nation
Both the Japanese Navy and army
Acquitted themselves brilliantly
With the Navy sinking much of the Russian Fleet off the coast of Korea while the armies battles on the Korean peninsula
Culminating in the siege of Port Arthur led to Japanese Mastery on land
Some of the consequences of the two wars were similar he writes
Like the chain
The tsarist regime never recovered its prestige
It defeats at the stage of the 1917 Revolution
Meanwhile
Just as Tokyo had picked up Taiwan as a spoil of the earlier War so the 1905 settlement final
Lilliput Korea into its orbit
Tokyo had to use an ugly trick
He says
Divorce the abdication of careers
King Cole Jung in order to legally convert Korea into an outright colony
But that Ricky says with probably no worse
Done with the United States in 1893 to overthrow Queen let me know akane
And incorporate Hawaii into the American Empire
Japan he says we're behaving pretty much according to the standards of the time
More to the point in fewer than 40 years he rides
The country has transformed itself from a week
Tottering polity into the preeminent nation-state of Asia and the first non-western country and centuries
That the great Powers had to admit into their ranks
But the bill for that transformation had not yet been paid in full
It turned out to be far higher than anyone at the time could have imagined
And quote
The reaction to Japan's victory over the Russians a historian Andrew Gordon says runs the gamut from outrage
To admiration
Big guys like the emperor
Germany dekeyser
Who is a believer in something he called the yellow peril
That all these
Innumerable Asian people like ants will join together someday
Swamp Christendom
You believe that
I like that it looks like the Japanese have emerged just the tip of the spear that will lead
The Asians to swamp Christendom
Would you have a lot of other European
States that all of a sudden have become admirers
Some of them head turned
In a become fans of the Japanese after the victory over China but after the victory over Russia a bunch more people
Will show up in
In Japan you know when
The historians say that they kind of join the great power Club it's more official than you think they actually change
You know the level of the ambassadors that are sent to your country all of a sudden you know when people are debating things like in the United States
Will be debated at the Japanese are taking over Korea or not no be
People who write back even experts and diplomats were going absolutely know what they're doing over there the same thing we're doing in the Philippines another
You really do get special consideration
As a member of the
In a predator Club as opposed to the parade
Club
Another Viewpoint that you can look at
Hits from the colonial victim
Viewpoint of
People like the Korean
Weather history they will suffer
Terribly
So from their viewpoint
Decision day
In a good thing this is a tragedy and once again
It keeps them from Rolling themselves
They will be seeing by
The Japanese government the same way that Colonial victims were often seen by the mother country
Sometimes especially if the
Colonial victims are of a different skin color they will be seen as less than human
We're certainly less than Japanese
Second-class citizens from the get-go
But finally
There's another interesting group
The people whose reaction here
Is important
The other non-white
Victims
Colonialism
Oh I'm just seeing something that in
Spires
They've seen a non-white power punch the great powers in the nose in a way they could only dream of and
It gives them an opportunity to dream of
Potential of maybe even with Japanese help doing that down the road
This idea maybe the
The Japanese emergence in Asia
Is the beginning of
The reality of a bunch of ideas that are sometimes called pan-Asian is
The idea of
It's basically the Kaisers worst nightmare come true
In a way that helps a bunch of people
It would love to gain their freedom from non-asian powers
Victory Andrew Gordon rights
Quote
In places as distant as turkey Iran and India
Over the several years following the war
Japan's victory over Russia was invoked by modernizers and Anti-Imperialist activists
An inspiring harbinger of their own possibilities for nation building and independence from the West
And quote
The reason this is going to get weird though
Is this is a real thing the idea of how this might be a useful
In a way for
Colonial victims to throw off the Yoke of their oppressors with the help of powerful
People in their region maybe even with the same skin color let's look at it from a racial standpoint
An opportunity to be seized maybe right and there are Japanese intellectuals and an entire
In a political history in Japan of people arguing that this should be what your pan does
Free the region lead the region become the economic Powerhouse The Diplomatic superpower in all these think it's a way Japan could have
Gone
The missed opportunity
Tragedy
If you're looking at it from people like
Saborearte in August
Viewpoint he wrote a book called The Pacific War
I may have said this in the late 1960s
And the point of the book
Is to try to figure out whether the Japanese public
Could have avoided
You know the terrible descent
Into war
Well this is the time. Where that up
Trinity best presents itself
And one of the ways because of Japanese probably just so you know they're almost entirely. Entirely almost entirely
Supportive of the idea of
Japan having this real huge superpower role in the region
But how that roll manifest
Peaceful leadership versus you know some sort of military Colonial domination will that's what's being discussed
Samuro INR
Seems to Lament The Lost opportunity when he writes quote
Is Japan a been a champion of Asian nationalism and really desired Independence and progress for it
Which neighbor and had joined with China to liberate Asia from Western imperialism
The subsequent history of the region would have been vastly
Japan would have identified with Chinese nationalism
Help to end foreign domination and made a real effort to create enduring good relations with the new China
Unfortunately.
Japanese leaders chose the opposite
The course of action
They competed with the West for a place at the imperialist table
The slice of the Chinese melon
And quote
Don't have to say
Pan-Asian ism is intox
Educating is an idea even to me is for the
Alternative history possibilities
We can you imagine with all of the
An independence movement in underground Rebel things that we're going on in all these different
In a colonial victims in Asia during this time. If somebody had
In a single swoop coming informed an organization and Alliance System framework in just that everyone can join
Right now
What's more than missing ingredient for all of those
You know people that were under the colonial thumb is some sort of military that could
In a fight off a military from the great Powers will
All of a sudden that's what you have in Japan
The possibilities if it took off could make the fall of the Soviet Union look like a blip on the historical map
But there were a lot of things sort of
It working against that may be the number one thing being that the Japanese were not about to let historians point this out
Japanese were not about to
Submerged themself in some sort of grand
Beijing United Nations where they were just one of
A bunch of different flowers
The Japanese were in a place where they were thinking of themselves
I just wanted to let you write It To The Head and Shoulders of the world but
The Japanese are starting to get some of the
I would say by products
Maybe you look at it that way and you have a right to
Others might say necessary precursors
Colonialism you know in for a penny in for a pound
The Japanese are exhibiting the same sorts of racial superiority
Tendencies
But all the other Colonial powers
Their colonizing Asia due to
Like we said about Shintoism and Bushido and
Concepts like that the Japanese state
Will Warp
This idea of Pan Asian ISM for its own purposes
In the Second World War
Play something called
Concept
Call the greater East Asia co-prosperity sphere yes
It's a mouthful
But that's the official name
This is
One of my
History professors back
Hocking College
This is the marketing
Front
The Japan uses to disguise their War aims
But that's a very simplistic Allied way of looking at it because truthfully a lot of people bought into this idea weather
Whether or not the government did and some of the people in the government certainly did
Problem with the idea of creating
A giant
Asia for Asians
Renee
Hemisphere
Freed
By the
Sacrifice of Japanese soldiers willingly giving up their lives for the greater good
Write up something every mother
And father can get behind when they send their son off to the Imperial Japanese Army
Katakana live up to that
On the ground
Trijicon
Cloak yourself in the robe of
Asian liberation
And then treat the people
But you liberated worse than the people that you liberated them from
The 1910 Japan
Officially annexes Korea
They had
Acquire the sphere of influence rights officially in a treaty when the Japanese
Is Russia ended
Five years later boom they just take it out right it's the first real colony of Japan
Of course they had Taiwan for a while now too
So Japan goes from a country writing about joining the colonial great powers
To one of them
And they don't act a whole lot differently
Then the countries that they wanted to be like
The Korean economy becomes a subsidiary of the Japanese economy for the purposes of the Japanese economy
And the people in Korea
Are treated like second-class citizens
And sometimes they're treated like
Chattel
The brutalities
Sometimes are horrible
The Koreans would sometimes have the gall to get out and
Demand their rights and they would be shot down at protest mean
This is not
The kind of thing that goes on the greater East Asia co-prosperity sphere marketing brochure
In a Windows come out
Office of Boracay Onaga discusses this period in Japanese history and mentioned something else
I'll be in the marketing
Materials
Jesus quote
The wars for control of Korea exceeded their objective and escalated into a general Advance into China
Policies towards Taiwan and Korea became more ruthless as pressure increased on China
Resistance to annexation in both areas was mercilessly crushed
I discovered he writes a vivid example of that cruelty among the papers of a military man assigned
Into Taiwan immediately after the island was ceded to Japan
It was a photograph he writes
I'm Japanese troops beheading to pigtail Taiwanese Rebels
Apparently have been captured in the skirmish
The horrible scene foreshadow the atrocities committed in every area touched by Japanese forces during the
Pacific War
And quote
Now the Japanese
Certainly
Atrocities
On a wide scale
But we should make some cultural allowances I think shouldn't we
Four different
Example
Let's take something that bothered
The Allied soldiers and awful lot and it wouldn't bother me to
The idea of cutting people's heads
I find this particularly hard
Myself
Let me tell you what I mean
In 1944 there was a photo
I believe was taken off of it
Body of a
Dead Japanese soldier
And the photo was forwarded
To come later
Press Outlet I think of United States
Life Pablo
And life was huge there's no way to describe how big Life Magazine was in that Society
Time
I need a publicist
I think you could call this photo arguably
Top
3 most upsetting photos for the Allied populations
In terms of stirring them to a white-hot anger
The photo depicted
An Australian Commando
Believe
Triggered
On the island of New Guinea
By natives
I think incent
To the Japanese on the island the Japanese
Interrogated him
Took him to a beach
Put them on the sand
The photo shows a blindfold on I think it's like a
Sticky blindfold I don't think it's actually wrapped around his head so it looks kind of particularly modern
For some reason
He's got his arms pinion with a rope
There was a semicircle of Japanese soldiers around watching
And the
Australian is in the process of having his head coach
There's a Japanese officer standing above him
And he's swinging the samurai sword down and leave
Photographer caught in mid stroke
Now let me point out
There's going to be some cultural elements that I have to deal with and you might too
When you look at
This is the same sort of cultural elements that the Allied populations had to deal with that the Allied soldiers had to deal with
Cutting people's heads off with medieval
Straight up
It's barbaric it looks seduced
It looks like something
That European countries for example having done
Set the 1600 when Japan
And it was last
Opened before the recent.
They froze their develop
Maybe
Some might think
But let's remember this is a cultural
In places like China they were still pretty comfortable cutting people's heads off to
And if we're getting into this on a
In what type of debate about cutting people's heads off in the rightness OR wrongness of that theoretically
If they had just taken this for Australian Commando
And did what most countries would have done to
Spies and let's be honest
One man's Commando can easily be another man's by especially since everyone
I want to make you a spy when they process
If they can
If they had just shot this poor guy
You would have heard much about it
It was the cutting off of his head
The freak everybody out but you know the other side might not have seen it anything like this
And in fact the people from other countries where beheading was still something
And it wasn't thought of demonically might not have had as much of a problem with either
It's a weird thing though because theoretically all we should care about
The suffering
Right I mean if you shoot somebody
Or if you cut their heads off it's probably pretty close if they hang them we should probably
You feel more simple
Apathy
But people got hung on
All the time and you didn't see any
Particularly
Top 10 photos from the Second World War
Depicted that
Here's the part though that might be more interest
That photo exists
Apparently if my research is correct
Because the guy who was doing the execution the
Japanese officer swinging that sword down on that
Captive
Ask somebody
To take the photo
Because he wanted the photo
I mean
Let me ask you this
If you had to kill somebody in your life you know sometimes people have to do that
How'd you like to have
A photo
Of you in the process of doing it to save for later
In the west we would think of that is something a serial killer some weirdo you write a book about in psychologist
Does Annalise do
So it's not the beheading
Shows a particularly cruel Nature by the Methodist
Itself
Wanting to be
Photograph doing it
Well by the time the 20th century rolls around for a
Great tower
That looks a little bit weird
It may be a sign of something that we could
Suggested
And everything we talked about so far
All these cultural elements layered on top of each other and working together in these human beings and some unquantifiable way
Would help explain all this
At the same time we can
Suggest
The man cutting off the Australian Commandos head in the photograph is a
In a run-of-the-mill routine general-purpose 8s
You get those everywhere don't you
Any more time
They tend to come out of the woodwork for understandable reasons
But it's stuff like this
That will make Allied armies think
Differently about the Japanese in terms of their level of hatred and intensity
But even the German
The Allied powers do not like the driver they really did not
Like Nazis but it's different
And things like this played in
And get you know if you look at the story in 1905 1906 at the end of the russo-japanese war
And realize that the Allied
Armies fighting the Japanese
Is only like 35 years away
You try to figure out
What the heck's going to happen what do they even have to disagree about
Bright
Well this is where I little steroid in
He kind of comes back
Play because it
If Japan's taking of Taiwan and Korea
Is like taking soda softcore steroid
The ones that will make you bigger
But then I'm going to turn you into a Great Britain or anyting mammoth
Like that
But on the upside you're not going to kill you either you can absorb both of them and still be okay
The Japanese are going to get like a little sample
Free little taste a little
Tiny piece of something that has the potential were they to expand and go deeper into it
To make them as
Big a country is they want to be in terms of
Resources
And well
And territory
And whatnot
The downside of course like any sort of more hard
Record
More effective steroids is they also have the potential
To kill you
Japan's
Empires cause of death
Is now visible in the story
As part of the settlement the end of the russo-japanese war a little teeny railroad something will be called the South Manchuria
Green Railway
A little kitty mining concession just you know in a little area
That at the time
Will be called Manchuria it's a controversial name actually now because
Custom Bose
But this is part of Japanese propaganda to legitimize their view of things in the region
We'll call it Manchuria without understanding a lot of history books use quotes now around the term
It's name supposedly for the Manchu people who are one of the many
Northern East Chinese or establish people who take over China from time to time
Traditionally though the area falls into sort of the general Chinese sphere of influence
But the Russians have sort of supplanted them in the lot
20 or 30 years as part of this General disillusion of China or its inability to
You keep great powers and biting off chunks of it
The area is huge by the way I read it
The size of my Texas Louisiana and Alabama put
Together
Lots of coal
Lots of iron
A potentially huge amounts of wheat like I'm were talking United States breadbasket type
Amounts of weed
The entire area of which the Japanese only have a little tiny little piece of South Manchuria this company in tire
Terraria borders several different countries and several different cultures and
You looking at it in the
Terms that. We use several different ethnic groups or races
It's mostly Chinese by the way
But this Manchurian area touches Korea
It touches China it touches Siberia touches Mongolia
It's a huge area
Big enough to give you
And whatever you wanted in terms of
Raw materials
Or
Food
Space
Or
Customers in emerging market
But also large enough if it sucks you in
The kill you
And the potential to draw you deeper into the affair
Is ever-present
Panera people working on
And making sure that happens in several different places in the story at the same time it's like a wild west with spies if I
Berlin used to be when I was a kid were all the spies in the world supposedly hung out
In that one little area that's what this area around the South Manchurian Railway the Japan
And is developing it becomes a little like that and there's people in there
Who work for the corporation to a developing things that people who work for
Have some shadowy groups in there just trying to see what the opportunities are
Yuan to expand a little bit
Nonetheless
Initially it's not much of a problem cuz it's just that little area and the Japanese apparently have the right to develop along the railway line
You know in a narrow sort of way we can develop hotels along the whistle stops
And eventually that becomes to support the hotels and eventually becomes homes with people that work at the hotels and it's cool
Rules for the people who work the hotel's kids and
Slowly but surely these Japanese companies in conjunction with the Japanese government by the way in a way
It does remind when a little bit of the way the British
Colonize India with corporate Affair initially eventually transferring to government sort of thing
Similar pattern in Japan
But the development in this region is
Phenomenal
It happens at a time when China starts to fall upon
Can we talk about pieces of it being ripped off in various areas earlier in the story this is the error which is frag
And the country's in pieces and Warlords are running the show and
Some parts of it at times can be almost a little wild west
It work where governments and power that you Weeks Later another government in power than every now and then the Old Government comes back it's why
Wild
Are the Japanese have every right
It might be worth having someone to defend Japanese citizens and Japanese
Investments and all that
Stuff in the area so they send a Division I
I think
Ava group that will eventually be called
Towanda narmi
These people are going to play
A key role in the
Story and they're going
To be part of the unveiling
Oven giant
Hidden Track
In the Japanese governmental system
It provides the
You know the opening of the door to the disaster here in this story but no one knows this right now
Wait a couple more landmarks to hit on the way to our destination though
One of them happens in 1912
In 1912 the emperor that the Meiji restoration is named after
Dies
He's replaced by his son
The emperor
Taisho Emperor his name is yoshiki.
I believe though
And the taisho emperor
. is really important Japanese history and part of the reason why is because there's something wrong with
Now
Exactly what was wrong with him is not something that the
Royal Court was really publicizing remember this is an era where they're trying to
Publicize the emperor is sort of a god
The idea that you would have
All these human imperfections is not exactly something that matches with the marketing material
I've read accounts
Suggest me the emperor
Cerebral meningitis maybe when he was a little boy and never
Fully recovered
But some people just say he just
Wasn't up to the task
Here's what Herbert P mixes to my helper
Kiipix writes about it in his
Hirohito Hirohito course was the World War 2 emperor in this is his father
Your chiquito
Pics right
Hirohito's father Crown Prince yoshihito
Made Emperor 33 was unable to continue Mages Legacy
Physically weak
Indolent and incapable of making political decisions
He was utterly lacking in knowledge of military matters even though he was now the commander and chief
Less than one month after yoshihito succession to the throne
At the start of the new taisho era
The Press reported the appointment of extra doctor's to the court
In December 1912
Admiral Yamamoto I believe it's going to be I
Told General matsukata Metal that when it came to recommending a successor prime minister
Emperor yoshihito quote
Is not of the same caliber as the previous emperor
In my view it is loyal not to obey the taisho emperor is word if we deem it to be disadvantageous to the state
Discontinuous quote
Those without any institutional change having occurred
The Ascension in 1912 of hirohito's father
Became an important turning point in the state of affairs
And quote
They say nature abhors a vacuum and power does
All of a sudden we get to a very interesting
Question which is in the system where if you
You said you know who's got the power
Everyone answered
It. Where
The emperor is not up to
Using that premiere
Who is your
Default Choice when the emperor is not up to the task that's not been
Really defined in this vague system
Ends of the 1920s will be a. For example
When different elements in the system will be trying to sort of jockey for
A larger position of power in the state now that
There's a vacuum sort of where the emperor's rule the supposed to be
More on that
After the brief interlude that is known as World War
First world war breaks out in 1940
Teen
And in
Asia
It is a very different
Sullivan animal than it is in Europe
Obviously in Europe
Pastor feed is a Charnel house is a night
Mara
In Asia it's not that bad at all
In fact
The Japanese get into the war they have an alliance with Britain anywhere but they get into the war
On the Allied side interested to know the book Italians and the Japanese will fight
With the Allies against the Germans in the first world war and then switch sides in the second but in this case
The Japanese this is a wonderful opportunity
Opportunities at like hit the jackpot in the way they haven't hit it
Since that first War in China right the first sign of
Japanese war
In this case
The Germans don't have a lot
In
Asia but what they do have is almost done.
And so you can argue
And who came out of the first world war the best
And I think the two candidates
The most logical choices here is it the United States or is it
Japan
The United States came out of it much much stronger than
And what they were like when they went into it
And he did much better than Japan did but they paid a much larger pricing doing it
And I really short.
Combat operations United States lost a lot of people
Comparatively
Japanese lost virtually nobody
In a winning is good but
If you look at a map
Look up with the Japanese acquire as a result of taking over German possessions in Asia
What are the Germans have will they have a little piece of china basically like everyone else.
Chunk of China
The Japanese take over the German chunk of that
And then they take over
Some Island chains of the German that they have the Marshall I'll
Eva Mariana
And they have the Carolina
If you know your second world war history
You'll note that these are some of the most important battlefields of the Pacific
Stick War
And if you look at a map of Japan and its
Possessions before the first World War
And the same map
Afterwards you will notice that they basically gain their Pacific island Empire which Japan would later considered to be
Pacific defense perimeter
As a result of taking over the German possessions in the first World War
In 1915 sort of when no one's looking cuz everybody's
Killing each other so horribly on the Western Front
Japanese go to China and issue a bunch of demand
The Chinese are falling apart during this time. The government's very weak and you can see the Japanese almost have a chance to say
What do we get away with here
The demands include some
That was basically the history that was reading so basically turned China into the
Beginnings of a colony of Japan
This freaks the Chinese out
There's no position to resist the Japanese themselves but they appeal to the great powers
The Japanese are forced to back off on the most outrageous of these demands
But it begins to set up
Conflict
With the Allies we're before this time. There hasn't been much of a reason
For disagreement
In 1917 we all know what happens to Russia then and right
They have a revolution
You going to provisional government that can almost go maybe in a democratic way for 5 seconds but then collapses into the Bolshevik
Revolution
Which collapses into the Russian Civil War which ends up with the Communist Victory and this freaks everybody out
Japan more than just about anyone else
Now let me stop for a minute
Point two things one there is no way
For us to understand how much
The Bolshevik Revolution
Scared and freaked people out during the
Era radar are attitudes toward this now are so much calmer
And people back then
And the more traditional and conservative your Society
The more threatened you were likely to be
By What was seen at the time. As a utopian
And by the way one that some people
We're very interested in some of the
Do some countries like their people in Britain and Ireland in the United States for example
Western Europe that looked at the Bolshevik Revolution is something potentially positive
What are the Japanese communism was extremely scary and
One of the things that was not emphasized in the histories when I was growing up
Either woodcutting about the Nazis or talking about
The Japanese was how much at least
They believe in their people believe you how much the materials that they used as propaganda for their own populations
You sold this idea
That they were these anti-communist Warrior
And so much of what they did
Was based on fighting communism nowadays the histories are very clear that
And read the materials right what are they writing about what are they talking about
About what is communism stuff scared them so much
The one of the arguments made for why Japan has to begin to maybe
Take over more of Manchuria
Is to move up into this territory along the border with what used to be rushing but now it's some weird place called the Soviet Union
Case we have to fend off
Communist hordes
Fear of Communism plays into the rest of the Imperial Japanese history
And they will never get over this fear and it's worth knowing
The largest army Japan will deploy in the Second World War
Far
Will be the one
It is standing by just in case
The Soviet Union attacks
In 1918 in November
The first World War
In Japan like a bunch of other powers will get involve
In an effort
You know to try to
Play a role in the Russian
Civil War
But basically when the war ends Japan gets to go to the peace conference
Really moving up in the world but at the same time when they propose
Hey sort of a racial equality kind of clause are really tepid ones
History describes what the Western powers and garlic Woodrow Wilson
That's no surprise shoot that down
The Japanese take this as a sort of a
Argument against
Aldi certified mind
You talk their hearing because there's a lot of wilsonianism going
I'm here that comes from right this high-minded
The first world war had rocked
The countries of the world
And even more than at the end of the second world war there was this attitude that this must never happen again
There was a lot of
Remember to create the early version of the United Nations the League of Nations
Countries talking to each other again
What's more
And this shows you the pie-in-the-sky level but I mean there was a lot of thinking that we have to have a language
That we all speak
We can't have all these foreign tongues anymore that make us
Impossible to understand each other so let's all learn Esperanto
But there was also a real sense that one of the main reasons
You know that
The world got sucked into those Wars with competition over colonies and things like that the very
Crocodile in the water that played such an important role in the story was seen to be an important role in why the first World War
So
One might think
This would change people's attitudes in terms of having or not having
What it really seems to have done
Is change the way you have to speak about them talk about them and refer to them
Can't really
We talked about
Dominating a people but you can talk about a protector
Creating the conditions where a stable government
We can take whole universe
For the safety of the meaning of its
It's a different way of cervix
I need other people
Why you have things like veto power over the
In a foreign policy of another country
The Japanese are watching all this stuff to sort of
I'll see what this new wilsonian world's going to be like
And what it kind of does for the mood of the age of strengthen
That group of people in Japan who think we should be working with China we should be the leader of Asia
Enough
Economic sense meaning
That group is sort of exalted all throughout the 1920s in the 1920s or this really sort of exciting here
In Japanese history where if you're looking at it
In terms of some of the stages that one would expect
A true democracy to go through
True when they're going from where Japan was to where
True democracy would go you would expect the stage that Japan has in the 1940s to happen it's a crucial stage it's the stage though
We're all those bench Electric contagions
Brought over in Pandora's Box by that American Fleet that opened Japan
In the 1850s
It's when they've all had a chance to go to
Take seed and mature and grow up and Bloom and bear fruit even the 1920s is a wild time
Japan
The oligarchs
That were controlling.
Country
Start to lose control
The country
And it goes back to the fact that the emperor is not evil
Multiply his normal role
But the Japanese are
Embracing
Besides of democracy that are a little bit sometimes messy
They are rioting regularly after the russo-japanese war
They are protesting this Parliament which was supposed to just be a rubber stamp Organization for the emperor in the
The Clique that rules the country
Is instead really contentious
Political parties start developing
And you begin to see
An interesting development which is that the Japanese really tight to political parties a lot of them and really get into the
The ebb and flow of the of the confrontation in the ideological battle in the discussions and all that stuff but there's a chunk of Japanese
Society that is just so turned off
Buy a couple
The political wrangling and how vinyl it is and how it seems to
You know put party over country
I also don't like
Some of the other things that they see infecting us deciding which they also kind of
Attached to this new Democratic sort of system
They don't like the
Materialism
I see where are these almost religious
Values of the Samurai and frugality what makes us great loyalty to the emperor these are what we would consider to be if
Flashy look at their beliefs
And you know their place in Japanese Society
Super Patriots
Chinese people that look like the country was
I'm coming apart at the traditional scene
These are the sorts of people want to be
We talked about a nation getting the equivalent of decompression sickness as we said coming up from deep water too fast to get the bag
These are the people that get left behind
The society Maybe
It's moving forward too quickly
And they're not just going to possibly
Accepted
And
Do they have working in their favor the fact that
Yeah they may differ in many ways with the leadership of
The country the old cabal style leadership there are some things that they agree upon
One of the things they agree upon is
That the country is
Dangerously flirting with radicalism
Traditional brain power
Where in the world is
Not the most traditional you are
Definition of radish
You know might be a little bit different than most
Here's what historian
James McClean write to his a modern history of Japan quote
Feisty tenants and disgruntled labor
Intrepid feminists and radical students
Seething minorities and outcasts
Moga and mobo anarchists and communists
Too many within the governing establishment
It appeared that the country was coming apart at the seams
In the 1920s
The disruptive consequences of modernization
The competing attractions of New Visions
The dish locations in Harrington industrialization
The tensions associated with new modes of living
And the stresses that accompanied imperialism we're imploding on one another
The tumult of the 20s
Alarm too many bureaucrats and members of the mainstream parties
Who sought ways to restrain the more extreme forms of radicalism that seemed at times to threaten the very existence
The state
Ndk
The Japanese state will always be more paranoid
And more repressive against any perceived threat coming from the left side of the political Spectrum
In Japan that that includes like bomb-throwing Bolsheviks
And Anarchist to Liberal writers who questioned the Divinity of the Emperor or militarism or women
Men's rights activists get the broad group of people
It sometimes gets thrown into a similar
Bread.
I mean there will be
1/8 what police force of thought police inaugurated during this. It will go after
Likely more writers and thinkers who will be jailed and sometimes torture to death in prison
It's a tough time to be questioning the status quo from that
Political Side Of The Ledger
In the 1920's 1930's early 1940s up till 1945 Japan
The other side's
Extremist
Didn't have that kind of
Problem
In part because
Some of them were
In government already and in the power structure especially when you got down to like the junior officer level of things
Military Circle
They weren't really Outsiders they were kind of Insiders
The other reason why is every time the Government tried to deal with one of those
Super Patriot type
Societies or groups
Those groups
Wooden basically wrap themselves in the Imperial flag
You know you couldn't use a they don't love the emperor
Excuse on them that would get a lot of the public behind you because their response is know we love the emperor we love the emperor
More than you love the Airport Extreme
Sincere in our willingness to lay it all on the line for the emperor proves that we love him more than you do I mean
Mean
That's a tough one
And you will see Allah
Lot of the
The things that are done by these ultra-nationalist group that will get off would like sometimes
Little hand slap
These groups by the way have some of the greatest names you will ever run into these
Patriotic
Start office
It's kind of like pseudo secret societies but more more
You come out in the open
When is one called the black
Dragon Society
Is another one called the dark
Ocean Society
And they have one called
The cherry blossom society which sounds beautiful but those
Members of that cherry blossom Society kill people
The Robey assassinations in Japan a rising amount starting at least
In the late nineteen teens
They have a prime minister and like
19th Avenue
21 who's assassinated they have another one assassinated in 1932
If I had a major
Corporation assassinated
And these groups are killing these people as a way one
To get them out of positions of power and sometimes they do it'll change the course of the way things go by taken out of key person
Other times they do it as a way to send a message
There's the other people out there it's
And intimidation move and an American Diplomat I think it's an American
At will call
The government of Japan during with the late 20s early 30s as a government by assassination
And often times the Assassins are members of these groups
What are these groups
Want
They want to go back to a golden age that never existed
These groups are generally although there are differences among them but they're generally
Strongly anti-communist
They are strongly pro-military and they think that Japan's been
Giving in to the Western powers on arms limitations and all that too much
They are usually pan-Asian
We believe in
Japan leading an Asian Revolution against in a western Supremacy
The superior nature
The Japanese race
Json people
Spirit
Melo's
Parliamentary democracy in olives
Vile politicians who are corrupt but they also have a big problem
With the business and corporate interest of the time the zaibatsu
The people that
The corporations in the government that are partnering together for developmental purpose
These people see them as a western infection
That is destroying the traditional nature Japanese societies and ripping off the populist right in
Taxing them to death and
Squeezing them to death
Passing clot in there will be a lot of
Members of these groups or sympathizers who will come
You know that from idealistic peasant you who to see what's happening
And their little Villages and whatnot
And are outraged
You join a group like this because one of the things they want to do is make it all better and the only way to do that is to
To put the emperor back in power
Like he was in the good old days that never existed
And he'll fix everything Justice wise and if we just
In a bring back the old Samurai virtues
It never existed either
Life will be grand again it's a
Utopian sort of movement and it a couple of figures it if you are so revered
And held in such Awe by their subordinates that there's almost a demigod like element to a couple of
Big thinkers
Pushing these ideas
I think it what they want
There's going to be an expansion of Japanese power in Manchuria and a confrontation with the Soviet Union at the very least
So with all these different
Players in the Japanese
Political sphere
It's a kind of a vibrant
The possibly explosives to hear maybe the beginnings of a vibrant early rough-and-tumble democracy maybe something the
Fall off the cliff in a bad Direction
There will be several major
Historical wild cards that get played on Japan in the 1920s that would have made it tough for
Democracy to flourish anyway I mean in 1923 there's a horrible earthquake
And it affects a couple of major cities more than the rest of the country but it's like a hundred and fifty thousand dead people
Tsunami
Massive economic damage
A 1924
The USA decides they going to pass them
Immigration Act with the Japanese sea is particularly discriminating against them
The United States is almost oblivious to the fact that it bothers the Japanese to the Japanese it's another sign that they're not being
Taking his equals
Was right on the Rain Man
Greetings list
In 1927 there will be a financial crisis
Economic turmoil
And the two years later everybody gets hit by the Great Depression
That's a hard sort of soil to try to nurture the seed of democracy and
And isn't it
We should point out that
The emperor
Yoshihito
Who has not been seen in public very much since like 1920 his son Hirohito is sort of taking over the duties
Is Crown Prince well
In December 1926 yoshihito dies
Hirohito takes over
We now have the World War 2 emperor
You know here in Tower and theoretically perhaps more capable of playing
In some sort of activist role in the system unit should he want to
Japan display app
Are in several major between the two World Wars Arms Control agreement specifically ones limiting Naval
Shipping
This absolutely infuriates the ultra-nationalist rytas as you might imagine
And there will be more assassinations
I think it's a little ironic that some of the people that get bumped off
In this interwar period R
People trying to address
The Fatal flaw in the Japanese concert
Two-channel system the one that prevents the political leaders from actually controlling the military pretty basic when you think about it
If you're going to have a real representative cyst
I'm right
Store in Mark rpd's describing
How this created a confused
Situation with Japan
China
And he writes about the
What's called the right of supreme command
And the fact that the
Army and the Navy are only answerable
The emperor not to elected
Bureaucrats
He describes its effect on on Chinese policy
Price quote
To begin with structural and political weaknesses with in Japan confused the development of a clear-cut
Policy
First among these abilities
What's a lethal flaw in the modern Japanese constitutional system
It's centered on the link
Between the theoretical Supreme Imperial throne
Supposedly the source of all political legitimacy and Authority
Ill-defined locus of political responsibility
It meant that any institution in the Japanese State could if it had sufficient practical power
Pretend to act in the name of an inviolable emperor and that's assumed a supreme decision-making row
With one critical exception however he writes
No institution could claim an actual constitutional right to do so
The exception was the armed services
Right of supreme command
Which made the service is directly responsible to the emperor
Engine no civil Authority
It. Gave the Army and Navy the legal authority to act and speak in the name of the Imperial
Real throne
As the throne was not constitutionally responsible to any other institution within the Japanese state
The services could theoretically act as they please without check for interference from the civil government
And quote
If only it was that simple though
Because then it would just make
The Japanese division of power in the system like a lot of other states right we have an army on one side and elected officials
On the other hand they kind of
Don't necessarily see eye-to-eye but there they are two camps
The Japanese military
Isn't unified at all
Start at the top where the services don't get along with each other
Let me point out that inter-service rivalry between things like
The Army and the Navy in most militaries is pretty common
But the Japanese once again or like everyone else
Only more so in this regard
And the service is
Really don't like
Each other
And really don't see eye-to-eye and can only UniFi sometimes when they're talking about
You know their right to control events or their right to receive piles of money when it comes to specific things they
A total disagreement in the Navy sees the next war in the Pacific against the United States
The Army seized the next War
Has an expansion eventually eventually to confront this new Soviet Union no longer a border where there Japan controls again
Higher Manchurian area right the Texas
Alabama Louisiana state full size
In this system no two services are equal
And they're totally out of the control of the civilian government of who referees disputes between them
Maybe a more complex
The question is
Who referees disputes
Within them
Because neither the Army Northern AVR even unified as a service there faction-ridden
The Army famous
He has a faction and these are unofficial things by the way although
Certain officers become associated with it
So it's not a good comparison but I mean imagine political parties
You just know you're not officially one way or the other but you know General yamaguchi's a republic
In my kind of thing
In this case one of the factions is called
Or known as the Imperial Way faction
Call Doha
Is the Japanese
Mispronounced term certainly
And these people are
The ones who buy into like the super paint
The cherry blossom Society sort of thinking it's almost religious
And it wants to go back to a golden age want to get rid of
In all the materialism all the liberal democracies the politicians and the corruption and just go right back Joshua restoration
The return of the emperor of the total power
The same theme again
Riley comes up in Japanese history
A utopian kind of way of looking at things
And normally you would say to yourself or who the heck cares
You know what a bunch of maybe mid-level officers in the Japanese military think right who cares if they're Democrats repeal
Who cares if they're
Imperial manufacturing people
For the other faction which is
Instill expansion is sticking still doesn't love politicians and
All that kind of stuff but they're more conservative been more opportunistic
The Imperial Way faction wants to take Manchuria and move on up to the Soviet Union from there
Again who cares
Bunch of Colonels and Lieutenant Colonels majors and captains were they going to do
In a normal military not much shut their mouth and follow orders
We run into and it's key to the story
Another one of those
Little Wonder
Full
In a distinctive things about Japan that goes back to an earlier era
And it provides an opportunity for a bunch of Junior officers to hijack policy here
In a way that
Would be impossible in most grade
Powers not impossible ever
Impossible in most braids
Unless things were going down a dark road with your
Of course as we know things are
There's a Japanese
Concept called gecko gecko
And it's difficult understand it's another one of those things where you kind of have to have the
Cultural antenna set to Japanese
It's all so controversial
Because you will hear historians wonder how much of a role this really played in the story versus how much it was a wonderful
Use exploited by
You know higher-ups is a way to say
Oh well we didn't do it some capped
Did acting alone did it
But the concept is not exactly unknown
In Western Societies or Western militaries for example the Japanese just take it to it
You know extremes again in the western military for example the concept might be something like
You're the rule that
It says that if
American soldiers
Irene combat somewhere and some higher up orders them
To commit some sort of
Atrocity
They have a responsibility to be insubordinate in that situation right it's
Natalie forgiven it's kind of required
Will the Japanese take that
To the next level Summit
They will have
And this concept that goes back
Century
Trees that essentially says
The lower-ranking people in some circumstances have a right
Maybe a responsibility
To act insubordinate and sometimes that can mean extreme sort of behavior like killing people
But some of the things I read almost portrayed as like a societal safety valve
Albright in a system in a shaped like a pyramid in terms of its power structure how did the people at the bottom ever have
Callaway
To register
You know their displeasure with something for example maybe this is one of those ways
The key to the whole thing though
Is she going to be doing it for the right reasons why your heart has to be in the right place
Sure they committed in Outrageous Acts
What's a Manuel
This is why something like a cocucho probably doesn't work as well for your
In a communist assassin
Wants to kill the prime minister
And sees that as part of his
Doing it for a good cause
But the public can be really sympathetic to Japanese probably to these people who do it for patriotic
Reasons right
But clearly they loved the emperor sure they were misguided but they meant well
And again you will see these people
Get off easy sometimes in these cases and maybe that's a reason if you're more conspiratorial
And if your general that doesn't want to face a firing
Squad for treason
And you can just have some captain or Colonel do it and then say
David Coker Johnny Manuel
But let them off easy
Maybe the upside of a policy of letting them off
Easy is that you don't create Martyrs out of them
But the obvious downside is it's
Not much of a deterrent either
Example perhaps of this
Gecko Cujo
Enochian action
Happens on June 3rd 1928
When a railway car
Full of officials
From a
Provence
A warlord province in
Manchuria in there quotes
Get shredded by a bomb
The bomb killed several people including the governor one of these provinces
It also kills the warlord himself will die few hours later
Is Warlord had been a friend of Japan
Up until that very
Explosion
But a couple of Japanese mid-level Junior officers including
Maybe as low as a lieutenant involvement but
Kernel and
Captain Maybe
Took it upon themselves we are told
To plant this bomb in order to create an incident that required a response that triggered
A policy change
These officers.
Was the smart move here right that would have triggered
Something that may have led to the Takeover of Manchuria
If you wanted to craft an analogy here you have to start playing with things like
In a u.s. Central Command forces in the Middle East having some mid-level officers there
Can independently decide we're going to spark a war with
The place like a Ron
Because we think it's in the long-term
You know good interest of the United States to do so right to be better to fight them now than later mean everyone would thank me if they knew what I knew
I mean it's it's a little inconceivable to think about that
It has happened throughout history is not
That didn't conceive
But amongst the great Powers usually there's more
No control over that mid-level of command
In this case is very possible that
What you have here
Is a tail wagging the dog
Where people at the at a low level
Are able to
Air control policy perhaps that's one interpretation the other is that they're just Stooges acting for
Much more powerful generals for corporate interest you know you by the interpretation you like
Nevertheless this 1928
Train bombing assassination
Which goes by several different names by the way my favorite
Is The Shining solin explosion death incident
It sounds like a Tom
Wolf
Novel title to me
Nonetheless it didn't achieve almost certainly what the people who did it wanted
And did in fact prompt significant blow back across a number different from front number one
Is global public opinion
1928 before the Great Depression start to most of the world but you're already starting to see
In Europe
And over here in the Pacific a little subtle change in the weather if you will from that
Your twenties
Post first world war rainbows and unicorns thing all of a sudden the realpolitik return to normalcy sort of clouds rest
Starting to appear and this is one of those incidents
The forecast
DePaul a little bit on things
In the United States especially
This assassination stuff just looks sinister
But the real significant blow back
Is that this is as my great aunt would have called it a come-to-jesus moment
In the Japanese governmental system
Because initially
The Japanese government is not sure who does this
And it's
Supposed to be a bunch of local to me one history of red said it was
Opium addicts
The Japanese blame this on some Chinese opium addicts another one said it was
Blamed officially with a communique on elements of a northern Chinese nationalist Army
Moron that later
But almost no one outside Japan was buying it
And when the opposition party in Japan finds out that it's a lie all heck breaks loose in Japan
The Prime Minister himself
During this. A general named Tanaka
Survive
Politically this scandal
And the problem with 20/20 hindsight totally clear as you look back on
It's a moment where the military essentially pushes back against
The political leadership
And they get away with it
Because
The prime minister is
Told by get this
The Emperor Hirohito in one of these
Few times and it's an early young indiscretion he says will turn into the Hulk when something goes
Arai in this whole investigation but he will tell
The prime minister to get the bottom of this the Prime Minister says I will if there any army men involved you can be sure we'll take care of this
And he goes back to his army Folk
Look at him now is a totally political fired General he's not there, read anymore
It might as well be a politician and they don't cooperate with him
Emily says we have to look into this thing essentially say no we have to cover it up
They gave him a whole bunch of good reasons why I should be covered up in a
Affect International standing it will affect our troops in Manchuria blah blah blah
But the bottom line is he doesn't have the power and it's made a parent during this incident
To tell them no I don't want you were approached I'm the boss were going to do it my way he essentially has to go back with his tail between his
When the emperor finds out he didn't do anything the emperor turns into the Hulk and blames
Him
With the famous line the emperor
Said
Hindi
Post-war conversations to Allied investigators the emperor says he told the Prime Minister don't you think you should resign
Boom
I mean that nice
Banal little comment there is more powerful to a Japanese person especially a general like to not.
Then anything a mustachioed spitting fascist dictator type getting in your face and threatening to
Dismember you nine ways to Sunday could achieve and Tanaka will not only
Fall from Government Hill died soon afterward
Don't make the emperor happy
Leave
By the way
It's worth pointing out that according to Hirohito he learned from this
Youthful indiscretion
In a virtual sense killed this poor prime minister by turning into the Hulk and he would learn not to do it again
So this very intimate does one the reasons
Allegedly
You don't see the emperor involving himself more in these sort of matters
When after the war you keep looking at these things going why the heck in the emperor involve himself more of these matters
The real bottom-line though if you look at it
And according to Hirohito himself is there were higher-ups who might have been implicated in all this
At a real investigation and maybe some interrogation under torture of the
Mid-level officers who carried out this stuff
Hirohito says that the mid-level officer in question threatening to squeal about everything so you know things get covered up
No investigation in
Nothing to see here we move on and get a 1928 you've established this with a line in the sand that says
Bennett the political leaders in the military leaders disagree there's not much the political
To do about that
Unless the emperor gets involved
What she says you learn from this incident you shouldn't do
Let the 1928 train bombing what do we call it the chain Solin
Explosion death incident
The timing of that
Is not coincidental
It comes at a time when there is a lot of rising anxiety in the South Manchurian area
About
Events happening in China events that
Have the potential to go a certain way maybe
To cut off the supply of Manchuria
At some point in the future
And there are people who begin to make the argument that that can't happen
We're already hello
And it's worth asking the question
Who is Hawk
Are these corporate / government interest in the South Manchurian area
Are they home
Where's the government hook to the revenues coming in which
Unfortunately off and get turn right back around into new military expenditures because he's new areas require
In Greater amounts of troops
Your Navy all these other things and it comes with the cost right security protection
What are the people who
Well it's during this time period that an open
Propaganda pushes made to convince the Japanese people that darn right we're hooked and not just us you are hooked
We have this thing a lifeline
In Manchuria the connections to the Eurasian population in
Houston's raw materials and goods
Stop back to Japan that keeps us all alive
Well
The question about whether or not Japan really needs Manchuria is an interesting one
Astorian Sandra Wilson in her book
The Manchurian Crisis and Japanese Society 1931 to 1933
Point out that the whole idea of Manchuria is this vital lifeline
Is part of the propaganda of the Japanese state
The stuff is using to justify whatever is required to keep using Manchuria
Using the equivalent of the idea that
We're hooked
She writes quote
The principle that Japan was dependent upon access to the resources of Manchuria
First survival is a nation
Was part of an attempt to create a narrative
Justifying Japan's claim to the region
Emma's closely linked
With the assertion that man sure you're rightfully belong to the Japanese
Spike China's technical sovereignty over it
And quote
She then goes on to describe this phrase that was in use
And she points out that it had
I should have diplomatic Tony it referred to
So did the idea of what Japan has already paid in Blood and sacrifice an investment for this
What we talked about earlier
And certain things keep you there
She writes quote
Far from being a dry diplomatic term
Kenny G in the early 1930s was rather asmira, he only has pointed out
A vivid word
Suggesting sacrifice in the shedding of blood
And it relied for its effect Upon A Certain view of History
In which the sino-japanese and russo-japanese War has figured prominently
Manchuria
She writes
Was frequently referred to as the place where the spirits of 200,000 Japanese war heroes slept
The importance of the South Manchurian Railway and a large amount of Japanese public money which it contributed through
Through the railway to the development of Manchuria
We're also invoked
As evidence of Japan's right
Freely to exploit The Manchurian resources
And quote
Citing the sacrifices of
200000 mortgage
Would be I would think a pretty effective
Tactic in most countries even today
In the Uber patriotic Arrow we're talking about even more effective in the Uber patriotic
Japan even more effective than that
But if you happen to be an investor for example in in the South Manchurian Railway
You have every reason right around the same time. That this warlord's done away with to worry about your in
Vestments because
Events in China are starting to get to a point where it's conceivable to see somebody unifying
In the not-too-distant future
And what's going to happen
If that occurs
Remember everybody's been taking advantage
China during the
Proceeding. Here because it's been down
But what if it gets up
This is the sleeping giant of the world the largest population on the planet when it's all put together it's a land mass
Size of the United States
The Japanese have been taking advantage of this
In a situation while the Chinese are weak they currently occupy places the Chinese consider their
What's going to happen if all of a sudden somebody put Humpty Dumpty back together again here
They'll have half a billion people
The Japanese have 70 million
How does a long-term trends hair look
I mean you can see a positive possible outcome if you are the
People
You know who want to keep this
Lifeline to Japan open you want to keep this
You know addiction
You can make it work but it means you got to either keep China perpetually divided or split it up permanently
Will you got to take it over
Or you got to control it in such a way that you will never lose control of it but you get to tell it what to do
You can't have a powerful independent China though
Because obviously that's going to get messy when they want their stuff back
The other of course policy
Approach you could take is the one that those
More liberal people in Japan
Let's have this Cooperative Asian relationship with China or Japan and China Uno with their population increase
Resources
And our high-tech
You know nose to the grindstone
Fanatical work ethic I mean we can do anyting
Maybe you go the route those people want because it's the only way to deal with China wants their back on their feet start negotiating now
When they're still weak so that they don't hate you later because the Japanese
R not in good graces with the Chinese population during this period
Sleeping giant has already awoken on the ground
The Chinese people are pissed off
And a lot of historians blame the 1950s in the middle of the
First world war when everybody's attention was on Western Europe the Japanese try to slip one of these treaties on a very weak in China that would have made them
Total colony and I freaked out the Chinese
But the people freaked out it wasn't a governmental thing I mean the people started boycotting
Japanese Goods riots with a rubber they kill Japanese officials in in a Chinese I mean it was anger
It was the same
Kind of nationalist Awakening to Japan and had
You know when Commodore Perry at America's black Fleet you know came and opened them up
You get this Awakening in the case of
China they were mad at everybody for what has happened when they were weak being taken advantage of
The Japanese more and more
Wer
You're getting the focus
Specifically of their ire
And so if you want to forestall this if you don't want the sleeping giant to be mad at you when it's fully awake and now might be the time to
Start
Catching up Old Wounds
Fixing things and by the way
567 years before this.
You know when will Sonia nism rainbows and unicorns were totally and play the Japanese were giving territory back to China
Kind of this peninsula Tina when they were trying it was
Policy for a minute
But the people in Tokyo are necessarily in control of policy as we said
This is where the tail wagging the dog comes into play
Or a bunch of people who are on the ground
Can create situations
That the
Military and even the government behind them
Simply have no option but to respond to
Once again if you're conspiratorial
You don't believe any of this is like this you believe
It emanated from Ground Zero
And has been
You know what Scarlett responsibility laundered the hallway but the the traditional story is we have elements that are out of
Control
You in Asia
Better able to prompt event
But everyone else has no choice but to respond to for example
In 1931
There will be another
Explosion on a railway track are you sensing a pattern here
Also carried out supposedly by mid-level
Japanese officers
Here's the way
Historian James Allen McLain in a modern history of Japan describes it
Quote
Captain calimoto Su amore
Lay the 42 yellow packages and Blasting powder with care
Shortly after 10 p.m. on September 8th 1931
He detonated the
Just placing a portion of the tracks of the South Manchuria Railway line
Is it past the northern outskirts of Moncton
How a motor when his co-conspirators intended to derail the Dairy Inn Express
Do just minutes later
And blame the act on the local Chinese Warlord
Zhang julong
Incredibly when the train reached the damaged section of track
It's weighed only slightly and passed on safely
Unruffled
Calimoto relayed a pre-arranged message to his home base
This is the famous prearranged message quote
Engaged in action with the Chinese forces who set off explosion along Railroad
And quote
The author continues
Quote
Ostensibly in response to that quote-unquote unprovoked aggression
Units of Japan's kwantung Army immediately attacked the barracks of James soldiers in Moncton
Enchantress
Within 48 Hours Japanese troops occupied the two cities
And do it hurricane g a colonel in the Guangdong Army
Name himself
They had an emergency committee to govern moved in
Effectively detaching that provincial capital from Chinese control
And quote
This event by the way is known by a couple different names most famously it's called The Manchurian Incident
History Andrew Gordon says that engine
Japan this is generally considered to be the start of a
They call the 15-year War which is essentially II
This is an explosive moment
In some people's view of the
Entire subject we going
You talk about here
And it is the result of
How much James Bond Undercover
You look like the Star Wars bar with all the
Gun-slinging
Yuno Bootleggers from that time. I mean here's how
Historian Mary
Jensen described
And he's a pretty sober historian so when he uses a word like
Hardy
Understand
You know how much like a novel
This is but these are the people
Engineering these events on the ground in a place like
Like Manchuria
Jensen rights quote
Waters had better success in Manchuria
In the days preceding the explosion that triggered the Manchurian Incident
An unsavory group in Japanese and collected in Guangdong Army headquarters
Ethan Goes On by the way the name these people
The first one is a guy who murdered
You know you left leaning
Tickets a writer
And he was there
Sentences with money sent by Japanese rightists
But he says even better Finance was this colonel
You know the guy who would actually blown up
The warlord in the train he's there too
And Jensen says quote arrogance
Abaris and dishonesty found shelter under the claims of crisis
Kwantung army officers were in touch
With Associated figures in the Tokyo general staff
But those man
Doubting the timing though personally favoring the KU dispatch tachikawa you'll shoot Seger
Freshly disappointed that March
To the scene to urge caution and delay
Taunton Army plotters aware of talking cat was mission
Deflected him when he arrived with a round of partying
The delayed his appearance at headquarters
When he was ready to resume his mission the next morning a bomb had already gone off on the south Manchurian tracks
And quote
So the government not necessarily against the idea of this Manchurian deal
But doubting that it's a good time send somebody to say don't do it now he's deflected by a bunch of people to take him out drink
Working so we can't deliver the message right away by the time he's sobered up and ready to deliver the message the events already happened
That's like a movie isn't it
But this isn't like the 1928 incident where everybody seemed caught off-guard there's a bunch of people who know this is going to happen and there's a
A lot more people
Who knew that at some point you know in the distant future this was likely to happen
And when it does
The civilian government
Is exposed as powerless now
As an aside we should point out that the prime minister in Powers often
Lambasted this week
So maybe he is
But he wrote an emergency note to one of the
Minnesota of Old Guard
A wise man that are built into the Japanese system to General who work less and less powerful than they used to be back in the major
Restoration days but this guy's obviously desperate
And this note comes only hours after the
Explosion happens where the government is finding out about this stuff from the newspaper
There are me the Japanese Army over there not telling him anything
The prime minister's name by the way is wakatsuki
And his
Appeal to the
General for assistance says quote
I am not being kept informed by either the foreign Ministry or the Army Ministry
I have just warned them through Chief cabinet secretary Kawasaki
The Chinese forces in Manchuria in Mongolia number more than 200,000
Well we have at least some ten thousand
I asked the Army minister
What are you going to do if by chance your challenge
Causes something you haven't anticipated
Something that giving you are so outnumbered
You can't stop
Army Minister told me
Will sending troops from Korea indeed they may have already gone in
I rebuked him
How can you allow dispatch of soldiers from Korea
Without government authorization
He said
Well the fact is that during the Tanaka cabinet troops were dispatched without Imperial sanction
I gather he had not foreseen any problem at all
Under these circumstances I'm quite powerless to restrain the military
How can his Majesty's military Act without his sanction
What can I do
Maybe I should not be talking to you like this but
Can you do anything
I'm in serious trouble
And quote
Who's the Prime Minister sounds
Panic there it's not just my vocal interpretation
This is the way Mary's B Jensen describes the situation
It was all this is coming to life in the hours after the incident
Quote
Within hours the Guantanamo Army achieved its initial military objectives
Against the fengtian army
What's the forces were engaged
Reuse of military necessity were used as justification for additional move
Giving the lie to promises from the Tokyo civilian government
But these were steps taken to preserve order
And that no further expansion was contemplate
Those in positions of responsibility we're anxious to limit the incident and regain control of events
Why the field and Junior grade officers that people the general staff and army Ministry
Or jubilant
Manchuria Mongolia quote and quote problem was finally being address
In Tokyo he writes the atmosphere was electric with rumors of plots
To take on the home government
A nervous government did its best to hush things up
To avoid destabilizing the situation
But this had the effect of magnifying rumors
The reality he writes was bad enough
And quote
So what was that reality
Well some of the ultra-nationalist looked at this as
The coming out party
Jensen continues quote
A few weeks after violence broke out in Manchuria lieutenant-colonel Hashimoto kangaroo II division
General staff
Install Words of the cherry blossom Society
Conceived a bizarre plan to wipe out the entire government by aerial bombardment of a cabinet meeting
A crowd of rightists
Within surround the war Ministry in general staff headquarters
Adam and the creation of a military government
For this
October incident as it was called which never took place
Hashimoto received 20 days confinement from superiors
Who did their best to deny that anything untoward had taken place
And quote
This guy's got a plot
To destroy the government by bombing it while it's in session and he gets 20 days confinement from superiors
What's going to happen here though
Is going to get Japan in all kinds of trouble because of
As over the months go on and the kwantung Army just keeps
Rounding out their conquest and looking to create it says buffer zones to keep
Are Bandits and whatnot farther away
Their conquering Manchuria
And the people in Japan that were worried and were against this
Start coming around I mean for the first two weeks
Stuff I've been reading since the Japanese populist wasn't sure what to think about this but after
You know incessant propaganda and talk about how this is the life line
And stories and films of Japanese going to Victory the public comes around and they support this big
So you're the politician kind of worried the same we need to get control of the situation and no more expansion
But every time the Army expands the public loves it
What do you do
Well if there were no consequences maybe you just go along with it but there are consequences in their huge
Haley directly to war
And let's remember in this war
A bunch of these patriotic civilians
Supporting the troops
I'm going to die
In their home
Burn to death
I had conversations
A lot
Over the years with
People
About what's called strategic bombing the bombing of
Civilians in cities
The prevalent in the second world war and there are so many side issues and moral quandaries and things to examine but the one
That often gets brought up and it
Well it's
At this point in the story where it's relevant if it's relevant at all
Has to do with responsibility on the part of your average Japanese person
They're getting bombed in the Second World War
Is that something that's the equivalent of getting their just desserts
Historical sort of
The warning maybe lessons are
Not real in here
History but is it sort of something that reminds you that these sorts of things have consequences because there people that will blame the Japanese
Public
For supporting
End of this road to war that they're going down but cannot support it seems a little counterintuitive I mean How likely is
Is it to imagine
This Japanese public conditions the way we've talked about with all the carrots and sticks and cultural head binding and and punished
For people who
You didn't owe the line and all these other thing
How likely is it to have imagined that they would do anything other
And support their troops
When the troops are victorious in the field
Right when it's their own son's out there fighting
Of course you got the government pushing the super propaganda button all the time
How likely is it
That you're going to see anything other than what you did see
What's more
Forget all the
Cultural head binding stuff I've been throwing out there and just think about your own people
How hard is it to imagine
You know most of them not coming out and so
Supporting
The troops
It's something that can be reliably counted
I'm so if that's the case
Can you really hold people accountable and say they had any
Real options as a group right and sometimes individuals
Surprise at the end
Was there really another road for the Japanese
Patriotic civilians to go down once their truth
Fighting in the
Field
It's an interesting question as I said but
I guess the way I look at it
Is I look at it and think got that.
Happen to anybody
If that means we can all be bombed and deserve it well
That's a scary thought
God isn't it
In case of it
Uber patriotic Japanese during this period
It's extra scary cuz this is like a blank
Check
For whatever this kwangtung armies going to do
Control from the central Authority is tenuous
At best
And over the next several months
This
Quantum Lori's going to destroy
Japanese diplomatic
Credibility with the rest of the world because over and over the Japanese government and even the top military officials are going to say
We're not going to advance any farther everything's going to stay the way it is and then they
Almost there saying
The Army in the field would have bats
At one point the army
It stopped one tonight because we are not going to promise we will not Advance on the city and they do
So the starting point not only is the rest of the world not believing anything the Japanese government is saying
But it's making them extra angry
I read one history tomato point of listen
This is a really bad time for the world in the Great Depression and all this everybody's got their own problems every country on the
Worldstage would love to be able to say I'm just going to ignore this until
The long way away
But looking like you're being played for fools
Over and over by the Japanese government
Instigates
Push back that might not otherwise have been there
In defense of the Japanese government they may have believed it every time they said we're not going to move any farther
And then think about the weird position it puts the government in
When the Army does move farther
Against orders has great victories conquerors more territory the media show the newsreels and plays it up
The public is cheering
What are you supposed to do with denounce them
And remember
Nobody in the foreign
World out there at all knows that you don't control your own Army
You don't want to admit that to them so you kind of have to own these things now
It's a bizarre situation it gets even more weird time to because
And you can't tell again if there's a
A forced feeling to this if you feel like you have to do it if they really want to
But I mean the emperor has to have
The general of the Guangdong Army over 40
Private meeting in the
Talisman normous on Earth
He's being honored for all these conquests in Manchuria
But he went against orders to do
In what sort of message are you sending here it's Bazaar
I should point out there have always been some historians and writers out there that's
Suggest that is possible
Did you could look at this entire situation with this
Kwantung Army acting on its own
As a case
Gecko Cujo on a mass scale Army wide level
Entire Army
Being insubordinate for high-minded more
Reasons
Do you say their heart
Was in the right place and maybe because of that you forgive them
Especially since they keep winning
See how that goes
But if it's true
Did this Army really did all this
On its own
And for super patriotic reasons
Is right well then they just managed to do in the very country
And deified emperor that they
Worship
Because
They've gotten
Japan into a cycle now
But it's not going to be able
Get out of
The best example I came up with is unfortunately am limited practical value cuz unless you gone out to deep in the ocean
You know what the breakers crashing on you you're not going to know what I mean
But in my head it seems like
Analogy and if you've ever done it you know what I mean when you get trapped in that no man's land
Between the breaking surf in the shore
Too far away from the shore to get to safety before the next Giant Wave crushes you
There's only one option
You have to go out deeper into the surf so you can dive under that giant way before it starts crashing
The problem is we all know
Is that when you come up
Sputtering from that
You have another giant breaker bearing down on you and you're even farther away from the shore
So you have to go out even deeper
And I'm under that one
Of course you
You can't keep this up forever eventually
You drown
Following that strategy
And the Japanese are going to drown in China
And if you believe the
Army Defenders out there who try to explain what they were doing
They're going to drown in China simply trying to find a defensible place
To stop advancing
The Army claims it's got
Bandits to deal with
For example these Bandits are probably
Really Chinese Guerrilla Fighters and at one point they'll be like 350
Thousand of them
That's a lot of Bandits by the way
There will be a constant
Drumbeat of things that are
Called incidence when Japanese troops and bandits or Japanese troops and Chinese troops
Japanese troops and Warlords troops
Will have some sort of you know
Gunfighter something and all that can break loose for a while that the Japanese take another city in response to that and they'll settle down and then another incident
If you string all these incidents together from
1931 to about 1937
You get
I mean they were like
50 in a really short. How do you get a lot of incidents and some historians like to refer to that hole. Is an error
Undeclared war
Between Japan and China
Neither side by the way wanted to declare war for different reasons
The Japanese are trying to make it look like nothing's really going on here
Nothing to see here great Powers it's not a war we have lunch in
What is going on
And the Chinese have their own problems more on that
Titan II
These incidents
Can get very large
There will be an incident in late January in Shanghai
Which will go on in
March
19th
Shanghai by the way I believe
The second largest city in Asia after
Tokyo itself
Between 3 and 4 million people
In a giant city that is an urban environment
So you can only imagine what it's like
To have fighting going on in the street
Streets of Shanghai
You will have it one point
It starts off with Japanese Marines but
They get into trouble because there's very stiff Chinese resistance
Street fighting
So the Japanese government sending more troops at one point you'll have a hundred thousand Japanese ground troops
Several hundred planes
Like 75 or so ships
Incident doesn't really do it justice
In fact the high numbers when you start adding up civilian and Military deaths
For this incident
Run somewhere between ten and twenty thousand killed that's quite a few people
In something
It sounds
The smallest an incident
Now we've been talking a lot about the Japanese here we've been pointing out that they've been fighting in a quote
And quote Chinese but who are the Chinese during this. It's worth
Examining
You know the resistance here
For a minute
The resistance used to be in 10 years before this time a bunch of
Fragmented
Statesville
Disunited States of China perhaps you could have called it
Buddy in the intervening like
8 years there's been quite a bit of consolidation
The number one consolidator is a guy
Name change
It was a fascinating character
Japanese
Protege Maybe
It almost call it a Chinese
He's a guy who went to military schools and whatnot in Japan learned a lot from the
Japanese came back participated in the overthrow of the imperial system in the emperor
Was a key
In a protege of the guy who started the
The first Chinese Republic
Annie's been fighting ever since to maintain sort of
It away put together China
He's a different
Because he seems to be willing to do
Whatever it takes
Achieve his goals as goals are both to create this
Great China that he sees your rising from the ashes of this terrible low point in Chinese history
At the same time
A China may be run by him maybe perpetually he's got this military dictator side to him that is
Critics
Uhart Bonzo
Bear that in
Remind
But he's a relatively remarkable person to mean think about somebody trying to put the United States back together again
Broke up into its component States against the will of those states by the way
And you get an idea of the tasks were talking about here
Chiang Kai-shek is
Heart and is the leader
Most of the time of a governing / political party called
Daquan Antonio
We used to call it the kuomintang
When I was a kid
I slip into
Your bad habits don't know why
But
That leader and that
RDR sort of the big dog in this Chinese reunification thing going on during the 1920s
He's the major threat that these Japanese people
Manchuria seeming this Chiang Kai-shek Geico
Put china back together again and then where are we
His main competition
In order to achieve this though
Are communist
People getting help for example from the new Soviet Union Chain by the way getting help in the Soviet Union to but he
You'll take help from anybody who will give it to him
All he wants to do is Achieve his goals the Communists are working with the Tommy
But there may be the second great power in China during this
Era
And
They and Chang will have this
Terrible struggle with each other sometimes.
Kiss and make up long enough to fight the common enemy
But Chiang Kai-shek
Point most of the time is that he wants to unify China first destroy his internal enemies
And then turn on the Japanese
So when during this. The Chinese pewter really like not be fighting back too much and deliberately so
Taking the
The easy Road backing up making the Heisman it's all because Chiang kai-shek's got his eyes elsewhere he's try
Trying to defeat the Communists in his country
And by the way
As I said when this guy is taken
In a money and arms and organization from the Soviet Union the Western press is portraying him as a communist stood he's the
Red General
Go to them
But later on he's going to turn on the Communists and he maybe this is arguable it's off the top of my head
He may hold the record
Foremost
Communist
Or suspected Communists killed
You kill like three hundred thousand of them in one
He may have killed Millions
And many of the may not have been communist at all he's famous for phrase he may or may not have said
Just let me
If you got disclaimer right here
But the phrase was something like you're a rather kill a thousand
Innocent people than let one communist get through
It's a little twist of the old American
Idea
Is it better
100 guilty should go free than one innocent man be prosecuted
In any case
Chiang Kai-shek
Seems to be pretty focused on China
And conquering it first and then turning its enormous weight on the Japanese invader
Afterwards is his policy
And not allow this undeclared war to continue longer than maybe a lot of the other leaders in China
Chang's underlings want it
Meanwhile though Chiang Kai-shek in the Chinese
Complain
To the only body out there that's available to do that
The League of Nations
Steve prototype as we said earlier for the United Nations
This will become a product
Pickle test
Are the rainbows and unicorns organization that is
Supposed to prevent
Aggressive War
Because the Chinese are asserting that that's what you have here
And not only that
The Japanese are the signatories to a number of treaties during these so-called interwar years
Design to make war
If not uncommon and maybe even totally illegal one of these is called The kellogg-briand Pact
For example
And sometimes that's the way it's supporters sort of touted
We're going to make war illegal
Because people signed the treaty
So you can see how that goes
None the less the Chinese make the complaint
The League of Nations has to respond to it they send investigators in 1932 early to look at
Train tracks that were blown up and examine everything talk to all sides
While they're doing this the Japanese military's
Creating a puppet state
They're going to call Manju quote
And the reason you create a puppet
You're trying to conquer indirectly like you would in the old days it because you just don't do that anymore it's just not done great powers
Caruthers
You create a sort of a
Wilsonian
Sorta
Colony
Where you call it the return
Of the Manchu people to control your own destiny
The Japanese brought in the last emperor of China a Manchu put them on the throne made it look like hey we've restored the
Manchurians to their rightful place
We Asians are all in this together is going to have this pan-Asian flavor to it
The Japanese Army's going to defend it it's going to send
And economically anything Japan wants back to Japan and the Japanese
Ctrl Alt
Major decisions it's a puppet state
But the rest of the world is going to say
You can't keep
The United
States will be the most
Vociferous
By the way the u.s. it has is operating on many levels Room 1 level there's a moral level two
The Americans have a lot of Christian missionaries for example in China and they get to watch a lot of this stuff unfold
And it's horrible on the ground so they're complaining for moral reasons
The Americans have huge economic stakes in this region something called the open door policy that they want to keep open
I don't want anything that would threaten
The good thing that they have going trade-wise with China and if Japan starts taking all these areas are making
Treaties that interlock China up for themselves with that cuts out us interest so there's a lot of reasons Americans are
I'm so happy about
Invoke something called
From this. Call the Stimson Doctrine which basically says the u.s. is not going to acknowledge
Support countenance or anything any territories that are in a
Created through aggression
Whether or not it's aggression
Up to the League of Nations
They do their investigation they come back with a report that is actually
So even-handed
You have a feeling that the great Powers didn't want anything where they had to confront anybody cuz I said earlier they all have their
Merona shoes they rather look the other way
But the Japanese required light
You know a real accept
They'll be allowed to keep Manchuria they did not get that
So when forced to make a choice
Between
The steroid that could make the maybe as big as they want
Or
You staying in the good guy calling me to offbeat Global International naughty list
They chose keeping
The Manchurian
Addiction
And this will be disastrous in the lawn
In a practical sense what it means is when the Japanese don't get what they want from the League of Nations they walk out of the League of Nations
Trendsetters in that regard because Germany and Italy will eventually join them
But do people like the Americans and the British in the French this looks like
Choosing the dark side in an Ever increasingly dark
In the world is the storm clouds on the horizon International Horizon
Deepen and darken
And threatened
The Japanese decided you know in terms of this International Community idea is rainbows and unicorns thing of the past it's just
The plot by the great powers to keep the status quo or out
But when you think of
In what options they actually had in this regard
And what kind of Japanese really do
Walk a mile in the moccasins
The Japanese government
And here we have to ask what real choices they had in the same way
You know we were
Wondering about the responsibility level of your
Average Japanese patriotic Japanese citizen well
In this case
And sometimes I think we pretend like
There's a fork in the road here for these governments
And we hold them accountable for making the wrong directional choice
You know at the fork in the road when maybe there was no Fork there at all
And this is a wondering but I mean in this case
Look at what
Was being a
Cast of this Japanese guy
You're being asked to give up this territory that many great
Great thinkers have been out
Chinese writing and whatnot
And many of the Promenade
San Japan has to have
In order to survive and
Protect themselves in part from these very great powers
Who banded together in this
League of Nations are telling them they have to give it back in
You can't have these steroids to get as big as we are
Japanese is
I had this long laundry list
Rain Man like
Grievances some of which are real
You also have that
Wonderful Alimentum play that we talked about the
Number of people now that
Died
Conquer this place
People that have died to protect the investment in money
It's in a been invested to create this wonderful
Bavarian China by the south entry and Railway me just goes on and on so if you're a political leader
It's going to
See this as a way to avoid having a showdown with the other great powers in the world and your choices you have to give
Give this back
Could you relist
We do that
I mean I would think that
The Moth
Ace
On the world stage in of the embarrassment of having
You listen to what everyone saying go with your tail between your legs
I mean I think that alone would Doom
A politician
In a with the voters in an electoral system
When you
But what about
You know a real dude
Supposed to
Electoral.
Because this is the. Where
If you realistically sing
Suggested giving Manchuria back
The great Powers were telling you to
You might not live to see the next month
Because we talked earlier about something one American I think
Government by assassination in Japanese history this is the. Where that Skyrocket
The high-water mark
Between 1931 and 90
And you will see a number of major figures not just political figures
Also corporate ones gun down
How about the one in 1932
We're 11 Naval Cadets
From a faction in the Navy
It wants a military dictatorship in a return to the emperor in the Golden Age and all that
Storm into the building where the prime minister is in the 11 of them killing
And is even a conversation that's recorded that happens
In a while it's going on where the Prime Minister says something to the effect even if I can only talk to you you would understand
And the person is about to kill him says dialogue is useless
Spoon
The people who kill
The Prime Minister release a man
Manifesto
One that historian James album
McLane Reaper
Shows the depth of emotional anger
Experienced by these people who want to put the emperor back on the throne to fix all the Injustice has
The
Manifesto says
Quote
Look straight at the present state of your Fatherland Japan where we dare ask can you find the
Genuine manifestation of the godliness of the Imperial country of Japan
Political parties are blind in their pursuit of power and egoistic game
Large Enterprises are firmly in collusion with politicians
They suck the sweat and blood of the Common People
Bureaucrats and police are busy defending the corrupt
Politico industrial complex
Diplomacy is weakness
Education is rotten to the Core
Now is the time to carry out drastic revolutionary change
Rise and take action now
And quote
Playing in his book
Japan a modern history
These kinds of
Coos
Along with
The stuff
The challenges posed by Manchuria
That
Dooms everything he writes quote
The Manchurian Incident and the violence from the right in 1931 and 1932
Mark the copernican turn in Japan's foreign relations and domestic policy
On the continent the conception of the new state
Card from Chinese territory and dominated by a wing of the Japanese military
Soured sino-japanese relations Beyond Redemption
Began the isolation of Japan from
Furiated West
Which view Japanese actions is naked aggression
And propelled the island nation along a path
It would lead it to even more dangerous for an confrontation
At home
The assassinations and attempted to choose
Expose The Fragile structure of Japanese Paula
Contributed to a snowball in loss of confidence in party politicians
And encouraged the idea log
Who romanticize the country's Imperial past
And sought to forge a new National Paula
And quote
The 1932 killing of the Prime Minister
Is a perfect example how so many of these
A coup attempts and assassinations
What happened between like
31 + 9
Cuz they'll put these young Naval guys the Assassins on trial and they're all like 20 years old
Their kids
And they'll
Wrap themselves in the ultra patriotism stuff
And the public
Will be very sympathetic I think they get a petition the court does
Signed in the blood of hundreds of thousands of Japanese citizens pleading for leniency
People offer to die in the place of the
Young naval officers I mean it's
It's a level of fanaticism on the part of one segment of Japanese society that makes it difficult to just Crush these people
Anti-government terrorist
And by the way
For killing the prime minister
These guys get a pretty lenient sentence
Jail time be out maybe in not too long
What the hell is that
Several of these
Events
In the 1930s culminating in the very famous won the February 26th
Incident that happened on February
Next Imagine That
In this when you get some of these Imperial Way
Faction
Junior officers who lead like 1500 soldiers
Against the other War Ministry and some other major buildings they take them over they kill a bunch of officials to former Prime
Ministers
A very dramatic actually and once again there's sometimes talking between the assassins in the end the Wonder movie
We killed it very dramatic
But
If you believe the emperor's post-war comments he basically says he turns into the Hulk again at this moment
Ordered the the Imperial Guard across the whole thing
Awesome people commit suicide the rebels give up
And this time there's a Crackdown after
This is the bridge too far for the ultra-nationalist right
In Japan the Koto half action
And they get crushed
Several people I think my 18 to 20 people will go to the
Firing squad
Be hooked up to the old
Steak and shot
A bunch of generals will be purged from the Army I think it's more than 1/2
Which shows you
Deeply embedded this Imperial Way facts
Why is
Other influential officers that are not
Set of ostracize will be pushed off to
Coming in for they can't cause the kind of trouble that somebody also for example
In charge of the guantan army can cause
And the military will once again soon strengthen its hold over the government
You know they'll say to protected from these kinds of things happening
This of course is a period of growing global
Anxieties we all know right the middle 1930s tough time
In the late twenties
TV fashion
Come to power
Italy
The 1930 to 1933 time. Have the Nazis coming to power in Germany
Both of those ideologies of course make it over to Japan in the Pandora's Box intellectual contagion update
Tina version 3.0
517 with a patch
But while most people don't think of the Japanese during this period as Nazis
Fascism is sometimes debated and people laugh well if we know where the Japanese of this
Fascist
You didn't ask for it but my own opinion is to me it looks more like
Yeah this era provide some frosting on the top of it
Very
Call multi-layer Japanese cultural cake
Each piece of which we've been lovingly talking about in the story
So
Not
Not see you stick or fishes take the both of those ideologies making impact and they seep into some of this
During this period the influence
Of course as I was saying my own no next
Opinion the experts on this from multiple countries
Have different views
By the way on
Will be
Copper closet
Location of the Java
Second world war government
Where the second world war government
Now if you wanted to just sort of look at the Optics though and try to make it
Judgment based on that while the Japanese are not doing themselves any favors because they may not
Officially be fascist at least in my mind
But they sure do
Play nicely with
In November 1936 the Japanese and Nazi Germany will sign
Something called The anti-comintern Pact
Which is supposed to be sort of directed at global
Communist efforts to undermine the world the Italians will eventually sign at the
Spanish will eventually find it so these are basically the fascist states of Europe if you're not a fascist you're sure
Signing the same treaties and
The Japanese were already were not getting wonderful press in places like the United States
See
It just get worse
Now we should point out a new GOP
Political reality that's very important now in the scene here that now that the Japanese have this puppet state of Manchu cool
Wall where Manchuria used to be
It means they now have the same neighbors Manchuria used to have
Which means Japan now has a giant or excuse me
Play the puppet state of Maine
Now has a giant border with the Soviet Union and another giant border with Mongolia
Which is a puppet of the Soviet Union
So now the idea maybe getting involved in any sort of meaningful
Combat with China that would take
Any significant amount of effort
Looks like it might
Take troops away from this giant border that looks
Horribly open to
And maybe a giant tank attack
Maybe infiltration by communist hordes
In 1937 the Japanese do not want
A general war with China
The problem that they're going to
Have his this is exactly the time. Where the Chinese are thinking maybe that is what they want
And of course for the longest time in the store you haven't even been able to say what China wanted because they were multiple choice
Warlord
Multiple different states and I mean
Could hardly keep track of it
For so long
But in light 1936 something happens that
Oil change
The entire Earth
Airfare and will do so sort of against the will
Chiang Kai-shek he's going to be kidnapped
Buy some of his suborn
I'm going to whisk him away to a location where
For two weeks
They try to convince him
But he has to
Stop waging his civil war against the Communists and turn against the Japanese
This meeting has the
Feeling
I would like a mafia so to get together where it's going to put a gun on the table and say either you change your part
I was here you're not leaving this meeting
It gets even scarier for Chiang Kai-shek when the Communists show up they've been invited
Instead of some sort of
Explosion amongst Arch enemies
Baby Chang had no choice of course
Do you actually get this
Patriotic moment
Chinese history worthies
Bitter enemies decide to work
For the common cause
They're going to fight the Japanese and stop fighting each other now
Let's just
Play the syndical card for a minute
Chang will eventually execute one of these guys that lured into this
Detainment in 1949 something like that
And there are
More than a couple of books
It will suggest that the goal of the Communist here rather than some high-minded
International Unity thing involved
Another positives for them getting the Nationalist Chinese enemies of theirs and the Japanese enemies of the Earth
Define each other
Kill as many of each other as they can and then
Eventually maybe easier to take over down the road so you can always go there if you want to
But on the surface this looks like a pretty patriotic heroic
In a moment in Chinese history and you can certainly see it in the writings of the common soldiers saying things like
For the first time in my life I get to fight
Italy to United effort against an outsider
The Japanese are unaware Bass
Sick leave any of this
Show in July 1937 when another one of the incidents breaks out in Beijing which is of course the modern
Hyundai capital of China
Everyone thinks it's the same old same old
By the way there's Japanese troops in small numbers all over China for various reasons going back to
Treatise
Decades ago
In this case though the ones in Beijing open fire against Chinese troops vice-versa they fight for a little while
The truce get started and the
Japanese can't get the Chinese
To agree to the normal kind of almost
Embarrassing terms that they agree to routinely
That doesn't happen this time
Instead
Taking a public
Proclamation
From Chiang Kai-shek is really like in front of the global stage throwing down the gauntlet saying we're not going to take it anymore
And he says quote
If we allow one more inch of our territory to be lost
Or Sovereign rights to be encroached upon
Then we should be guilty of committing an unpardonable crime against our Chinese race
China's Sovereign rights cannot be sacrificed
Even at the expense of War
And once War has begun there is no looking back
And quote
This Proclamation is meant for several days
Different audiences it's obviously
Chinese people
Who are
In large part really excited about the chance to
Define lie
Strike
Get the outside enemies we said
But it's also meant for the Japanese public
And they will be
Furiate
For the most part by it in the editorial in the newspapers
Play it up in general
And bureaucrats rules
Call for China to be chastised here and punished
Are there a country
Chiang Kai-shek
Typically
Not looking very good in the mall
All of a sudden they kind of like him when he was fighting Communists now when he's Allied to communist don't like him very much
Much anymore
But this Proclamation is also meant
Unifour
Global public opinion
To tell the peoples in the great Powers listen how much of the rainbow and unicorn fumes are still left I mean
The politicians in all these countries like
France and Britain the United States when these people are all talk and really good games deal with a high-minded moral sentiments
And Chang's
Message is kind of another way of saying maybe put your money where your mouth is
And answering a key question a lot of people who are wondering about
Supporting China have which is will they be around 5 minutes after real fighting started it worth my investment
Will there even be a Chinese Army still around by the time the rifles that I buy for them get there
Legitimate question
People that are probably in the best position to
To answer this question although they're probably biased you would think though
Would be the Japanese military after all they've been fighting the Chinese now for years in this undeclared war
And they're apparently telling the emperor
But they can get a handle on this Chinese problem just give him three much
So not exactly the highest
Pinyin of Chinese military
Capabilities but let's remember they've not seen a United
Did China
Nor have they seen a very defiant
Chill now
They're getting but with
Time
But in an attempt to sort of answer these questions for
You know the global audience out there Chiang Kai-shek and his generals choose a strategy and it's got a lot of reasons why
But there's a lot of downsides to
That will put everything that's going to happen
You know as much as China has an opportunity to do this anyway on the other side of the world from most
Power is going to put all these events
Front and center in front of the people whose
Opinion matters in this case the people that can make loans
Gendarmes
Maybe even
Launch embargoes on Japan or maybe even bring in troops I mean the possibilities are endless if you can just get them interested
And what if you
Expand the war to an area where they're already really interested
About taking the water Shanghai
I wear all those great powers
Have a lot of money invested have commercial interest have
In most cases thousands in some cases tens of thousands of their citizens living there is expatriate
Or workers
How about you just bring the war
To Shanghai where the entire Global media will be there too
Witness at 2
And what did he throw in a ton of your strength
If you know that you've built up over the years and
And soda safeguarded and kept
For just such an occasion so that you can give a huge display of your capability to fight the Japanese when you want
So what you do all that
And
Not if you trapped these
Technologically Superior
Better trained better coordinated better Supply better LED more experienced in many cases Japanese troops
If you trap them in the narrow Alleyways of a city in Shanghai in it
GHIN score like a modern European
Keystone
Brick building I mean
You trap somebody there it could be
And this is a book
Title that I use
For this by Author Peter harmsen
Stalingrad on the Yangtze
Things like
Street fighting that all falls into
Nicole questions obvious
If you zoom out here though
And look at this from this
Strategic point of view look at with china's done here
And as I said it's a double-edged sword
But he's essentially
Soul calling Japan
Block in terms I would say of being
A true great power
Because there are several
Great powers that
Don't have the land mass
Or raw material
Rose Foundation
You have to put them in the very top classic gray powers and living in Germany for example conduit
They tried to live in the ground
Something once before
But they make up for it with a lot of other things like the Japanese do
But the Chinese are legitimately huge
We're talking about land masses that New Year Soviet Union type size things although that was
Someone bigger
But United States I'd sizes it gives them a luxury most places.
Don't have
Gives them the luxury of space
If you are a battle
Field General
Space is
Just say it's huge might be an understatement might be a determining Factor
Think like a Russian general
The Chinese will sometimes
Space force
What time and what are the times
Will be here
Look at what they've done
I mean if you look at a map
The Japanese are up in the north fighting in above Beijing and
Shanghai is more than 600 miles
The South with intervening Chinese territory the whole way
The only way the Japanese are going to be able to fight is by using the Japanese Navy to Ferry troops
Continually from other areas
And land them in amphibious operations around Shanghai
They're going to have to
Create an ocean-going
Logistical supply line all the way back to Japan that's more complicated and expensive than doing it
Railways and supply lines on land
Are you getting idea of the distance here
In the book on the battle for China which
Each chapter
By different expert
Historians edwidge Adrian hands Vandeven
Try to put it in US terms
And they say that if you locate
Beijing what used to be called Peking back in this Arab if you locate Beijing up at Michigan
Upper Peninsula
That would put Shanghai over by Washington DC
Canton
Down by New Orleans
Wuhan they write would be worse St Louis is approximately
And Chongqing would be in Southwestern Kansas
Imagine somebody landing on the East Coast
And trying to conquer everything to the Mississippi
Now imagine it's a small island nation with about 70 to 80 million people
That less than what 75 years ago was living under a military Shogun
And was closed to the Western world
China's going to call Japan's Bluff here right how large are you you want to play this game you're beating us in single Deck Poker how about
We throw at five decks and see if you can still play
Of course not forget the downsides
A fighting in a place like Shanghai I mean if your Chinese Shanghai is your commercial Capital to
If New York is your commercial Capital how much are you going to appreciate having
A couple of mid-twentieth-century Army's number in the hundreds of thousands
Fighting it out anywhere in your city
What's that going to do
Do your industrial out
It's even
Stranger than that then there's a certain Dynamic when you get
Modern battles in
Big big cities and that's that you can have fighting raging in one part
And your total peace and another part so imagine New York City has
This fighting raging in a place like queens or a burro like Brooklyn
But it's peaceful enough in Manhattan for you to take a date up to a skyscraper have martinis and watch over the balcony of the puffs of smoke
Smoke in the distance
Fighting is Raging
That'll happen in Shanghai to
We're people will come out to watch and don't kid me New Yorkers you have a lot of people coming out to watch
That's the other problem with deciding to have a battle in Shanghai the people
If you have a city of three to four million people and they're going to start to fight a modern bottle in the middle of it what happen
Them
Wella Mass Exodus
Begins right as the fighting
Starts in Shanghai
It will be the largest in the city's history
And at times will reach Stampede light
Levels of panic
And you have to imagine them in all the books try to
Convey this
The Sea of humanity in the city at this time it's already a crowded City and you have all these War refugees and also
Supporting
It is jam-packed
The Sea of humanity
Author Peter harmsen in Shanghai 1937 Stalingrad on the Yangtze
Recalls One account from somebody was caught on a bridge
The bunch of civilians trying to get
Get from one
Perceived unsafe District in the city to a Prestige Safe 1
Thomson rights quote
For the foreigners are Shanghai visitors and residents alike
The war was a rather violent diversion but nothing truly dangerous
Or so they thought
Are the Chinese life was falling apart
As the fighting intensified around the Japanese District
Thousands of refugees
LED through the streets
Heading for Suzhou Creek in the garden bridge
Which was the only link to the international settlement that remained open
It was a mad and merciless Stampy with week had little chance
Recording primary source
Quote my feet were slipping in Blood and flesh
Recalled Rhodes farmer a journalist for the new China Daily News who found himself in a sea of people struggling to
Engku
Quote
Half a dozen times I knew I was walking on the bodies of children or old people sucked under by the torrent
Trampled flat by countless feet
And quote
Thomson continues quotes
Near the creek
The mass of sweating and panting Humanity was almost beyond control
As it funnel towards the bridge
Which was a mere 55 ft wide
Two Japanese centuries were nearly overwhelmed by the crowd then reacted the way that they had been taught
Weed immediate reflexive brutality
One of them he writes
Bayonetta 2 in Old Man and through the lifeless body into the filthy Creek below
This did not deter any of the other refugees who kept pushing toward the bridge and what they believed to be the safety of the
No settlement
They could not know it
But they were now moving in the wrong direction
Toward the most horrific Slaughter of innocent civilians of the entire Shanghai campaign
And quote
These refugees are trying desperately to get to the area they think is going to be the safes
Because they know that neither Army wants
To kill foreigners from great powers
And they know those foreigners stay in place
Just like the French concession
Part of the city where the international settlement part of
The city so they're trying to get there
It's an already-crowded very nice
Part of town
And so are these refugees pouring they're going to swell the numbers even more
Now they're running away from the first real Combat which gets going August 13th 1937
But it's more the Strategic taking of
Places in preparation for the big attack the big attack will come the next day almost at exactly the same time Murphy's
Law comes into play
Murphy's Law
Urban Warfare in dense population centers
And in an attempt
To bomb Japanese warships in the river
Running through Shanghai
Twice in 15 minutes
Chinese planes will instead release their bombs
In places to kill lots of other people
Innocent
People from their own country
If you had wanted to design Annex
Experiment
Maybe you're an arms manufacturer looking for data
And you wanted to
Give the maximum number of
People
In a one bomb in a given situation could kill you could not design probably a better
Testing ground
Positive results as you would see them in that situation
Then choosing this part of Shanghai
At this time
I mean in urban center with
Concrete everywhere buildings on both sides and people absolutely
They're extra jam-packed
Here as well because they're watching
There are thousands upon thousands of people lined up on the boulevard
Watching these Chinese planes and cheering them on as they try to hit these Japanese ships in the river
So when these bombs go arrive
3000 people watching
Actually I mean there's account actually see them coming down
At them they had a
Split Second to think about what was just about to happen
Edgewood Peter harmsen right
Quote
The two bombs released by the Chinese airplane hits truck at exactly 4:27 p.m.
The attacks
Stop the arms of a clock at the entrance of Cathay Hotel
Freezing in time the moment of the twin blasts
The shockwaves and the debris had both taken a toll on the mass of people who have been crammed into the street
To Percy Finch a foreign correspondent it was as if a giant mower had pushed through the crowd
Chewing it to bits
According to foreign correspondent quote
Here was a headless man
They are a baby's foot wearing his little red silk shoe embroidered with Fierce dragons
He wrote
One body that have a young boy was flattened High against the wall
Twisted clown with ghastly adhesion
And quote
Now harmsen continues quote
A sickening stench of burnt flesh filled the air
As the wounded came to they started moaning
Summer screaming
Part of the facade of the Palace Hotel have been blown away
On the 4th floor a man clung desperately to the remains of the wall with one hand waiting for help
It came too late to me eventually let go
Crashing through the glass awning of the hotel's entrance
Before hitting the pavement
Others attempted to crawl to safety scrambling with fumbling limbs over mangled bodies and slipping in the blood
Who covered the sidewalk
And quote
Now let's understand why we know in such
Graphic detail this kind of stuff
All the guys at the Modern author just quoted was a foreign correspondent who was in the street when the event
Happened
The Press is there and it makes a big difference
You want to know how you really get foreign countries interested in events
Far away
In overseas places
Have their own citizens died there
The pay attention
Channel reporter I can tell you the practice is known as localizing a story
Easier to get people
How to relate to something that seems like
Closer to their lives and something far away the
How to get your mind around
In this case
The Author Peter harmsen
Accounts the situation involving 66 year old Christian Missionary Reverend Frank Rollins
He's been in China
After a long time
On this particular day he's driving his car with his wife
Passenger seat 13 year old daughter with him
Down Avenue Edward the seventh which inventor British king selection show YouTube
Not in the
Chinese part of town per se
I can hear
About a billion Chinese people screaming in the back of my head saying it's all Chinese but anyway
Avenue Edward the seventh
Reverend Frank Rawlinson
About to
Run people over with his car it's so packed in the street that is wife says you'll get a better view he's trying to see some of the
In a bombing in the river going on like everyone else
If he gets out of his car gets out of his car
And he gets a hole blown open it is chess
And story in his wife gets out
Caesar husband bleeding out in front of her the 13 year old daughter gets out of the car and seizes for riffic
Traumatizing site and in a weird way because we are human beings and is how we function
To be able to recount that event back to the folks back home will make more of a difference than
Explaining
And the other people
That that bomb killed because that bomb that killed this Reverend
On
Avenue Edward the seventh will also hit
I guess the best description I can describe is it as a
6 story shopping mall but much less structurally sound called the Great World amusement Center
And it's normally packed with thousands of Chinese people right now it's packed with thousands of Chinese people who happen to be most
Refugees
I'm more than normal even on site getting a race
In a food handout
And the bomb hits
There
And the bodies are stacked
5 feet high
You're so Author Peter harmsen
Describes a quote
The mood was excited once more at about 4:45 p.m. when two Chinese aircraft seemed about to make a
Another run on the Japanese positions
Cheers and Applause Rose from the street
Then sharp-eyed individuals notice to small dark dots drop from one of the plane
The same bombs that
Another guy here earlier spoke
Coconut Head scene
They fell with deadly Haze
Hitting the busy street before anyone had time to react let alone Escape
One left a huge crater near the traffic control tower in the middle of the road
The other exploded a few feet above the ground causing shrapnel the fly over a large area
Explosions were so powerful that they killed a servant at the building of the YMCA nearly 700 feet down
A subsidiary Road
The casualties included several foreigners
Arms and rights
On Avenue Edward the seventh Reverend Rawlinson Lay Dying in his wife's arms
What is teenage daughter was watching
Just yards away two other Americans who were konigsberg and his wife were killed in their car
It was the same type of Carnitas in the name Jean Road earlier
Just larger
Death on the most massive scale
What's at the entrance of the great World amusement Center
Where the fatalities were piled five feet high
The victims men women and children have been throwing up against the walls of the building
Many were stripped completely naked after the intent of gas pressure from the bombs at turn off the
The clothes
And quote
Eventual death toll from the great world and surrounding areas will be more than
Do people
Men women and children
The death toll from both of these accidental bombings put together more than 1,200 people and what
Seriously
When did seven foreigners among the Dead
Author Peter harmsen calls
All these American deaths
Tyrannies bombing
First
American casual
Duties of the second word
World War
They matter more than they should theoretically
In terms of public opinion because
After all
People are people they should all count
But there's something about a young American Christian Missionary and his daughter watching him die on the roadside and all this stuff that
The tracks mirror
Attention once again
And even though these are Chinese bombs that accidentally did this
Talk to the IRS directly to Japan
And after all one can ask the obvious question
What the heck are they doing in Shanghai anyway Chinese City so understandable
But it's just part of the drum beat
Atrocity
To make its way into
The foreign media
Manna picture
Just worth a thousand words
There's going to be a weird
Perverse
Incendium Loop
It happens
With these terrible disaster
The suffering the Chinese people
Because the more the Chinese people suffer
Anna Moritz publicized
The more International sympathy and sometimes eventually Aid
That brings them
So for example
In a month or two from this time. The Japanese will bomb a railway
Station in Shanghai in
A photographer will be there again
What time here
We'll catch a photo snap a photo of this destroyed railway station with bodies
Lying around
Anna baby
I'm guessing
Six-month-old seven-month-old sitting there
Covered
Burnt but crying
And
He sent this image back
To the
Emigrate press Outlet it.
That's one of the most moving
And emotionally
Demanding
Photos of the war
It's this kind of thing that plays into a
Change in mood especially once again in the United States a photo like that is a if you
If you're a reporter and you're trying to move public opinion in somebody hands
Photo
Gold how weird is that
The deaf person suffering
That little baby suffering on that Railway platform after the bombing
Is in a weird way serving the interests to Chinese nationalism and patriotism
Bye
You helping to publicize the mass Chinese suffering going on in the way that moves people in a way that you can say yes to
2000 Chinese people died the other day and you go out while you show the baby on the platform to go on my God
It's weird isn't it
Nets
La teacher reporter for example in the news business I mean if it bleeds it leads
And please localize your story so people
Care
This is an example of both of those
Are almost exact same time that those bombs are going awry and killing all the
People on the water
The amusement
Center
The Chinese launched their big attack against the Japanese the one by the way that was suggested them by a German general because they
The Germans are
Training the Chinese in this is very weird if you know the
The story because
Like 5 minutes from now the Germans and the Japanese are going to be allies
But in this battle which some Japanese refer to
And the German war
The Germans are helping the Chinese they've equipped the Chinese elite units
The German helmets in German stick grenade that mean they look like
The Afrika Corps Asian Edition right wearing khaki Asian features but otherwise looking like germ
Soldiers
They have advisors at the officer level that sometimes as advisor sometime
Elite units in the combat
The Chinese amongst a number of other troop there pouring troops into the Japanese are starting to as well
Have these two units the 87th and 88th division both of which I think you could reasonably classify as a liter
The best units in the army
They also have
Stuff the Chinese do that they've lovingly built up
Over the years
Tank force
An Airforce small obsolete but they've got one
Armored Cars me but it's all been took forever to build
And I saved it up and they're gonna throw it all into this
Attack and they're going to do it with
Fanaticism it's going to be interesting for you military history majors
They're going to fight the Japanese the same way the Japanese will fight the Allied powers in the Second World War
War from a position of being the one who has to have sacrificial suicide attacks to make up for material
Differences stories
Chinese troops in throwing themselves under Japanese tanks blowing themselves up to stop a tank column in a shades of what
The Japanese will do in the Second World War
The officer
Casualties on this first day for China will be Irreplaceable and shocking
What is one author pointed out
You are literally fighting in rubble in streets with
Buildings in your having people shooting at you from behind other it's crazy kind of Stalingrad type fighting
But in the first day
The Chinese
Stouffer
Irreplaceable
Author Peter Thompson rights quote
First and foremost however the massive fatality rates among officers and to an even larger extent the rank
Can file
Were the results of Chinese forces employing frontal attacks against the well-armed entrenched enemy
The Man Who as a result we're dying by the hundreds
What's China's elite soldiers
The product of years of effort to build up a modern military
They formed the nation's best hope to be able to resist Japan in the protracted War
Nevertheless on the first day of battle they were being squandered at an alarming unsustainable rate
And quote
By not sweeping away the Japanese.
German general had advised here
They
Allow things to stay in place everybody to reinforce in this thing to go on 4th
3 months
Now I suppose looking on the bright side it's a kind of a victory for the Chinese forces cuz the Japanese thought they'd take Shanghai in 3 days
ISO 3 months
A lot harder than the Japanese
Thought
The other thing that's a lot harder than the Japanese thought was how many people they would have to
Lose as casualties in order to do this numbers are
Sketchy here so taken with a grain of salt
Japanese supper about 40000 casualty
Dentistry month.
Number casualties are killed wounded captured missing
They will by the way and this entire affair with a Stalingrad like
Almost
Uno Attack around the city on both sides and they're getting ready to close it off the Chinese forces have to withdraw so that they don't get too you know.
Dunkirk
The China is going to suffer something more on the lines of 200
50 Cent
Mountain casual
In 3 months
2000 cash
Is it hard to get your mind around
It may be a good way to look at it
This if you take
Those numbers I just gave you Japanese and Chinese cassia
Can you put them together
In three months of fighting you have almost as many people
Darn near
As the United States
It's lost in its entire involvement in mediately Shore
More than a year
In the first World War
By the way Chinese numbers always look like somebody did the math wrong it always looks like somebody X some strangely law
Large number or something but
It's part of what makes Chinese history so overwhelmingly all inspired
You can
How to get your mind around the number sometime
Yeah we had said earlier sort of with the Japanese you get an extra dose of intensity with the Chinese you get an extra dose of
Number
Now when the Chinese forces are
Should have required to withdraw from Shanghai now you begin to see maybe the downside
Another downside of expanding the war this area because if you lose shine
Now you have the Victorious Japanese
Any new theater War now they're in central China and they're winning and they're pursuing the Chinese forces on the road
Back-to-the not very far from Shanghai Chinese capital of Nanjing
A chemist called Nanking
The Chinese
Expended an enormous amount of effort
They are in no position necessarily to stop and halt the Japanese Advance here
What are the Japanese going to do when they get to the Chinese capital
The well-known
Show controversy
Story
But a shorthand way to describe the traditional way of looking at it
It looks like a Mongol
Sacking of a city
Arguably the most horrific
Atrocity they will
Cur
In 15 years of war in the Pacific and Asian theater
Will occur when the Japanese get to this Chinese City
That's coming up next
Just strap yourselves in at the
Beginning of the neck
Max program cuz it's
Get nasty
I have a confession to make
I did not like
The idea of the Harry Potter book
When I first encountered the
Understand I am a fantasy snob I'm Lord of the Rings
Snob
I'm the kind of guy that likes my fantasy to go so deep that we could have legitimate conversations over the proper use of
Pronouns in the wood
Language to talk about the high I'll talk about the southern mirkwood dialect mean that's how I like it I'm a big long poems in a
Language some guy invented in his head
So I scoffed when my kids wanted me to read
Harry Potter
And then I started getting into them
And more and more it's finally almost start like a book written for like a 7 to 10 year old and then I think the next one came out like about 2 years
Later it's almost like that book is for the same kid that read the first one but now two years later and they get
Increasingly more
Dalton dark
I just remember one day waking up to the realization at 4:45 in the morning that for six straight hours I've been saying just one
One more page while I read
The Order of the Phoenix
I had to work
That's what I'm going to have a problem
A lot of people
Read to them and
A good narrator
So much to us
I like the guy
Edibles got doing the whole Harry
Potter series
Right now
Jim Dale
Become a few samples of him to see if he doesn't
Just have one of those voices
The first one
Do anyway
But second it's just
Sounds like a person that should be reading Harry Potter book to you
Amazon Prime members right now through July 31st
2018 can get Audible for a mirror for 95 a month
For three months and it goes up
The regular only 49
A month
Audible members just so you know get a credit every month
That's good for any audiobook in their store regardless of price
And the unused credits roll over to the next month if you don't like an audiobook you can exchange it with no hassle
Plus your audiobooks are yours.
To keep forever even if you cancel I love that
Part
If you're somebody that ever gets to go out and enjoy anal summer activities and whatnot audiobook Sarah course a gray
Great thing to enjoy while you
You're doing it you could be in the dark Harry Potter World while you are tanning on the beach
Maybe that's the best way to
Do it
Audible by the way has the largest selection of audiobooks on the planet
Which let you feel your summer
With things like
Well this Harry Potter series are you could go all you know would L Fish and go
And get the Lord of the Rings 2
It sounds like a good deal to you want to go to audible.com hardcore history
You could also text Hardcore History all one word all lowercase letters to 500 500 to get started
Once again at audible.com hardcore history or just text hardcore history of 505
Get started
Wrath of the Khan
Punic nightmares
Apache tears
And of course
Ghosts of the ostfront
Just a few of the classic Hardcore History titles available from dancarlin.com
Every true fan is hurt these favorite
Hey they make great gifts to
If you think the show Utah
Where is worth a dollar
Abacus show
Oh yeah
Dancarlin.com