What you're about to hear is part
4 of a multi-part series on the first world
If you like your stories to have some sort of cohesive
Linear narrative flow although I'm not promising
But if that's what you like we're
Probably better off suggesting you go check out
Episode number one and work your way to here
You don't care about that kind of stuff at all you just don't trust me to
To deliver a cohesive linear narrative flowing
Blame you
Well then by all means start he
Kira part 4
And check out this series that we're calling blueprint
Armageddon
December 7th 1941
A date which will live
In infamy
The events
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words ich bin ein Berliner
I welcome this kind of examination
Weather now
We are not descended from fearful men
Hardcore history
How do you Market
War
How do you sell combat
To the people who are actually going to have to engage
Hypothetical question
Any military
That requires volunteers to decide they want to join the service has to think about how you actually
Sell the idea to the people who
You'll have to take part in it
An idea that carries with it the potential for
Some very nasty outcomes in the very worst of circumstances done that the difficult
Job perhaps to Market
Combat
Easier to do in peacetime though right if you have to sell
Suntan oil to people in Alaska
You might be able to pull that off in the summer
In December it's a really tough sell
The first world war breaks out
If you're trying to Market
Recruitment into the British army
You can sell the same sort of talking points the same soda angles that have worked
For governments and monarchies and tribes going back to the beginning of civilization the military's long hair
Certain selling points
I think we're all familiar
With them
Add regular pay thrown into that as well
Heroism
The adventure
The status and meaning of this a lot of things
Some people just like to fight I mean you never know
The problem is is that
That's a pre 1914
In a talking point when it comes to what happens when the first world war breaks out
And how that just totally messes with your marketing strategy
Unless you're marketing
Hell
As a travel destination
You can't
No matter how much press censorship you have in the British had plenty in the first world war just like everyone else
You can't mask
Those kind of casual
Now you can mask the reality the sort of stuff that
These newspaper reporters who were sent there during the war after the war
You know they would write books telling you the real story what really happened
Tell you to never imagined it was all censored by the Press
Even with the censorship
You can't
Haida
Death and destruction and dismemberment and you see the people returning to your hometown with a horrible wounds you hear some of the rumors whilst
Stories
You know it's not going to be fun
All of a sudden the marketers
In
Great Britain's recruitment
Operation
To play hardball
No more just throwing out carrots they're going to use some sticks to
In the US we have a twenty-first-century
Volunteer army ourselves in the US uses
Just carrots to
Encourage people to join up
Will pay you more will pay you for college
You'll make something of your life I mean there's all these different things that they used to motivate
People but they're not
Very many sticks
In the USSR
Once the first couple of weeks of the first world war happen
And everybody together
Find out how enormous this is going to be in in an absolutely stunning group wake up call where the light goes on over everyone's head
And they're going
Oh my gosh you don't have enough
Resources
Oh my gosh you don't have enough money for a war like this and oh my gosh we don't have enough people
And even some of these larger States who you think yourself off you know people shouldn't be a problem look at how many people are coming up every generation
Remember
Manpower in the old
You are quotes means Manpower across-the-board not just the people fighting on the front line but the people that can still be
Miners to extract
The material you need to carry on the war
Or people working in arms manufacturing plant so that they can build the bombs you need to fight the war
In other words if you take too much
Jethro on the fighting line
You won't have enough people back home making the stuff that the people on the fighting line need to win
Manpower becomes a very big deal
All these other countries in the war Germany France Russia no problem they've spent
Decades working out of conscription operation where they draft people
Yeah yeah come of age you do a couple years in the service and then you become Parts the reserves then you become part 2 the other Reserve
Heavier than older reserve and
You know after a while they got a whole revolving self-perpetuating system in place where they every generation comes up
They're cranking out new soldiers
Except for Great Britain
The last
Volunteer service
Involved in this conflict when it breaks out it puts unique pressures on them
The first thing they do is simply
Ask people to join I remember 1914 you didn't quite know what you were in for you could still sell the old
Selling point uniform
Wonderful in the women
You look dashing and is just War Adventure
Kill the boss you know all the good methods of King needs a new king and country all the things that have always work and still work
A lot of cases
Special in peacetime
Work and more
Stokes and Britain and Scotland
Canada Australian all these places signed up than they even could handle
I'm looking for a couple hundred thousand got a lot more than that
But that's before the casualties
Start happening
Unpatriotic Britain sign up
But you don't know how many patriotic britons unit you're going to need and not just
In one big lump but every month to replace the troops you lose
In late 1915 the British just lose
At Gallipoli
And they walk away after a couple of months with 250000 casualties
You don't just replace those
By playing nice and easy and saying come and Fight For King and Country using more Hardball method
And one of the ones that I've always thought was just indicative of something that you imagined it in modern times it boggles the Mind using up a strata
How'd you like this today but it's an absolute genius
Shows exactly
The most vulnerable point
In a young man's
Your psyche in the place where you're a marketer you're looking for
In what motivates people how you can touch these
These elements of influence in
The order
I'm the feather the white feather movement
Is absolutely brilliant in that regard I mean it's almost devious you try to imagine our government doing something like this today
Modern 21st century technology
Basically
You know when August or early September 1914 rolls around
There's an admiral in the British admiralty who's working like everyone else to think about it when I come in Courage more people
To sign up for this horrible War
And comes up with
You know in an attack on a motivational marketing strategy
He's going to enlist patriotic young British women
To walk the streets of all these towns in Britain their Hometown in over their people they know
And if they see
Men
Not in uniform who look like they could be or should be
They're going to go up
Surround this person and start
Saying the most horrible thing you are powered and all these terrible things to them
Pretty women
In public dressing you down if you're 18 years old
That's a pretty
Good marketing
You're changing someone's armor to exploit
Not just that
You're probably and usually were on the street of your hometown
Where the passers-by know you or your family
This is April
Soundly embarrassing moment
You know everyone around you everyone connected with you
God forbid you have a girlfriend she's going to think this looks pretty bad for her to I mean that the affected was was huge
And then before this little group of women
We're done with you
They would put
A white feather
Signifying power death
On your lapel or somewhere very visible
Yuan you
This was not
An unusual occurrence there are accounts for people that say they were afraid to go outside the house sometimes
Because
These
Patriotic and zealous women who were really just trying to help that's the funny part this is the society motivating paper
Small bee sting
All the right virtues
But I've got an account from a 16 year old boy
Had to go through this
And then he signed up for the service cuz he was so definitely embarrassed and Afraid in an inch and ashamed and the service
This person laughed him out of the room but then said he looks so downtrodden exaggerated this height exaggerated is 8 in
Exaggerated
Wait and he was in
At 16-under 110 lb
On the Western Front
It's absolutely
Deviously clever one
Could backfire
He's created marketing
Recruitment ideas
Free cable the government felt the need to put out symbol that people could wear
To an already done their service overseas and have been wounded and honorably discharged
Or work for some really important armaments or war-related Industries couldn't be spared because apparently enough of those
Those people were being mistakenly
Given the order of the white feather treatment
To make that an important thing for the government to do
There were other Creative Marketing plans not
Sticks but carrots in one of them
Another brilliant woman you think about it on the surface
Involved the British government explaining to recruit that if you sign up with your pals your buddies
You could all serve together
Other people joined up
On the same street where the same Pub or the same Community or the same fraternity or the same profession
And they all served together they had Wonderful Name ZJ like military unit names that they're still known by I mean they were the Liverpool
Pool pal
Where the Grimsby Chums
I need friends all went to the service you figure if you got a Certain Magical do it with your friends
Can you get to watch your friends die
Heart we didn't really consider when we signed up and it sounded kind of fun
Not just that
When these units would get decimated in some of these terrible encounter for example you can be walking down a road
With your pals in the open and all of a sudden get caught by artillery fire
Supper 80% casualties and then
Instead of the losses and the suffering
And the grief being spread out so diluted across the width and breadth of the entire British Isles for
British Empire for that matter
Some local community
Or some fraternity
Or some profession just gets pounded
And there are Villages and towns in Britain now that
Had these terrible days just happened to the whole community
I'm pretty much everybody suffers a major lost one way or the other
At the downside of that
Clever marketing plan
By 1916
There's nothing clever enough to get enough people in you
The losses are so high
At the British finally do what
The British really don't do
And they started can scripting RPG
It's hard to blame the
List two for starting the same soda draft
That the Continental great Powers use
All you have to do is we said the casualties are so high look at them by the end of 1915 the British have suffered half-a-million casual
200000 of those are dead by the way
For a traditionally Naval power who has traditionally a rather small army by Continental standards
Huge numbers
Now you want to see what Continental standard look like
Look at the British Ally
The French
Who had a huge Army in the meat grinder since the first minute of this whole Affair and by the end of 1915 there cash
Casualties are over 2 million
More than 700 thousand of those order
And all these great powers are looking at the
Principal enemies and trying to figure out
How close they are to the throwing in the towel moment
The Germans are looking at the French and all the casualties they've suffered and they looking in their thinking
They must be
Be close to the end of their rope
The Germans have suffered more cash
By the end of 1915 the French
But they're fighting on more front
Right there fighting the French and the British in the West
Gigantic Russian forces
In the Eastern are involved in the Balkans a lot in 1915
Their casualties by the end of 1915 or over two-and-a-half million
About 750 thousand of those are dead
Hard to know the Germans list 250000
Missing
In this war people got blown to bits they got covered up by
Giant mountains of Earth that shells have blown up in the air falling back on the ground lot of missing people
Probably between 750 and 8
Dad
Funny German
This point in the war
The Russians have suffered Titanic
Losses
From minute one
They lost a huge battle in 1915 called
Gorlice tarnow
Alisa Turner
And
That battle all by itself
They lost a hundred and fifty thousand.
Almost seven hundred thousand wounded
And basically a million
Titanic losses
Maybe it's easier to understand their monthly burn
By October 1915 the Russians are losing 235000 men
How sustainable is that you again you got to be looking at the Russians thinking
They're almost done and the German High command kind of is
Now the Germans can't be too happy though because they are main Ally
The austro-hungarians
Are suffering casualties that are every bit as momentous as the Russians but they don't have the manpower to back them
Meaning 1 4 month. In 1951 four month. The Austrian suffer
50000 cash
Boom
That's in addition
To the already astounding casualties they took in the
Few months
Right after the war started
The German several times will have to prop up the austrians just to keep them able to continue in the cons
The austrians are a pain in the rear
Germany
A lot of the time
Meaning for Eric Von falkenhayn the German commander in charge in January 1916 he can't stand them
They're always getting into some sort of disaster
That they then go to falkenhayn and ask for help getting out of
And to make matters worse it's usually a disaster than from falkenhayn warn them about an advance don't do that
It'll be a disaster and then they do it
Against his wishes and then coming after we bailed out multiple times
They can always play their
Their trump card though against Von falkenhayn
Legitimately considering the huge casualties they suffered
They can kind of go there and say we'll listen I mean you know if you don't help us
We're not that far from dropping out of the war I don't know I can't guarantee we'll be here in a few know you have to help them or it
Strategic disaster if the austro-hungarians drop out of the war
Right
The pom falkenhayn doesn't want to pay any attention to any.
Don't worry about the Russians
There are German generals and what not to keep saying the Russians that's how we win the war
Falcon I didn't hear about that
Doesn't want to focus in the Balkans although in 1915
They destroyed
Serbia
Get that out of the way
Pokemon doesn't want to hear about the Middle East in the turkey doesn't want to talk about Austrian her problem didn't want to know what it'll he's doing
He wants to focus on this
Maybe
War winning or War losing gordian knot that is the puzzle that must be solved if you are a j
General task with winning this war
It's the Western Front
How you deal with that and it kind of does unprecedented problem
Yeah there's a famous German saying that may or may not have happened but it's it's infused this whole.
Where one German general supposed to commented about how amazingly the British troops
Thought and he said they're lying
And the sub-commander with him
Is supposed to have said something to the effect of yes lucky for us they're led by donkeys
1915 Western Front battles
Are with a donkey's first
Get label
With that
Education
The same time
When you realize that they have no metrics for what they're doing in 90
This has never been done before nobody's ever had this
Kind of Firepower nobody's ever put these kind of defenses up I mean
We're playing with all sorts of new military toys
And I've never been tested in a situation like this
How much slack
Do you cut the generals
And give them what is some time to call by historians in this case a learning curve
You're playing with p
People's lives
How slowly are you allowed to figure things out
We can go into any of the 1915 battle
Winston Churchill is just one of many people who objects to the whole idea of calling those battles
In the 1915
Ear or 1916 year or 1917 year battle
He says it's a disservice to what the name means she said there were battles in 1914 at the start of the war
Inner battles in 1918 at the end of the war but that stuff in the middle was a c
Price quote
These sanguinary prodigious struggle
Extending over many months are often Loosely described
As bottle
Judging by the number of men who took their turn in the fighting at different times
By the immense quantities of guns and shells employed
Am I the Hideous casualty total
They certainly rank
Taken as a whole
Among the largest events in military history
But we must not be misled by terminology
You have to call them battle
Was merely a method of presenting a general view of an otherwise confusing picture
It might well pass unchallenged
What are the temperatures been made by military commander
Am I a whole school of writers
To represent the
Prolonged operations
Has it been comparable to the decisive battles of the past
Only larger and more important
To yield to the specious argument
Is to be drawn into a holy wrong impression
Both of military science
And of what actually took place in the Great War
And quote
These
Battles on the Western Front
For a full three years in the conf
Look pretty much like this
As described
The historian
Hold your hair back
Quote
The fighting on the Western Front had taken on a deadly regularity
Attackers stormed enemy trenches in waves
Only to be mowed down by hostile machine gun fire when artillery as they tried to cut the wire in tank
That protected the earth works
And quote
There's a repetitive
To the fighting on the web
It's a repetitiveness that actually
Is associated
With World War 1 and the Western Front specifically
It's part of the tragedy
It adds
To the pain
Because after all
If you seen the same
Event over and over and over again
Doesn't it
Become a different kind of tragic
If you watch the first wave of those young soldiers
Leave the safety of their trench go over-the-top at the
In a whistle of their officer get mowed down by Machine Gun fire
Before they've even gone 10ft
That's tragic
Another level of tragedy when the next wave gets up right behind them
To follow in their footsteps
Having already seen what
And to them
That's what we wanted to capture
In
Are discussions of the western
Because it became an issue
Early on how we're going to deal with all these battles that were roughly the same
Equally tragic
And for the soldiers on the ground
Eerily similar
When trying to figure out
What we wanted to highlight
A Shakespeare quote kept popping into my head when I was working on this
It was just lying that all the world's a stage
And all the people merely
Players
I thought to myself well that's what we have here
We have
One of the most extreme stages
In human history
We've created
With these Western Front battles in 1915 19
16 - 17
A hell like environment
And then
We forced millions of
People
Acton
Some of the most extreme situations
People have been put into ever
In his
And watching how they endure
Is sometimes
Soul crushing
Put another X
It's absolutely life-enhancing
Yeah sometimes you can
Benefit quite a bit
From the suffering
As we sat down
When we started this series and tried to figure out a creative approach to dealing with all these battles
One thing becomes very clear
We did some creative experiments
You quickly find out
Set the battles
In an emotional sense
Reach a point of diminishing returns very quick
You just become
Vietnam
The mall
All the scale the intensity the sheer horrific repetitive pounding
Eventually makes you stop feeling
It's a rather than go from
Indecisive and
Horrific battle to the next indecisive in horrific battle
We thought we would focus on a few
What we would consider to be almost signature battles if you will but
They provide a very similar backdrop for the poor individuals who have to live
In that environment
And allow us to sort of examine at a human level what's going on here a little bit as best we can
And to explore some of the questions that are very intriguing about the story and not just about the human suffering what about
Command Decisions
And some of the technology and some other things
Hopefully interspersed with a little bit of
In a comment about what's going on in the rest of the world while this is half
And part of what makes 1916 so difficult is there a lot of overlapping stuff
So if you tell it in the he said that she said that he said fashion
It becomes very confusing very quickly
The first thing to understand
Is that 1916 comes about
Obviously because of plans made in late 1950
Weed said you earlier
But this was a real question for the general
But how you solve this gordian knot that is the Western Front
Will in late 1950 in the Allied commands got together in a place called Chantilly in France
To deal with this question
Their plan
Was going to be to continue to pound
And pound harder
But the new aspect was
They were going to make sure that everybody
All the different allied powers
How did the
Central Powers Germany and Friends
At the same time
They were going to coordinate the rapper
This was going to
Nullify
What the Germans have been doing so far the Germans have a great Army but they can't be everywhere at once
Luckily for them
Up until 1916 they weren't attacked everywhere at 1
They would use something called
Interior lines it's a little like taking the center
Square in a game of tic-tac-toe
The Germans were able to use their wonderful
Railway system
To transfer troops from less threatened sectors to more hotspots
And thereby frustrate Allied efforts of the Allied plan for knocking down German fortifications to 1960s if they're all go
Attack it basically the same time
Frustrating the Germans ability to move troops to hotspot
The Germans had a different plan entirely
You see the people that Chantilly
1952 get together and decide to attack the Germans from multiple
In allocations at the same time
Are still for the most part envisioning the classic
Military in
To this war
They see the chances increased by attacking multiple locations that you're going to crack the German summer
When you crack them you're going to send your forces through the breach and you're going to send the calvary through and now the Germans are going to break in there going to be
Berlin and you know that's how these things and the minds of people who have a very
Especially old-fashioned View
Of War
There are additional
Dance to this idea who say even on the Allied side you got it all wrong it's not going to happen that way the technology
The specific circumstances the fact there are no flags on the Western Front
You're dreaming
Because you're dreaming your plans are going to work
On the German side the people who have this attitude
That that old-fashioned Viewpoint is just that
Old fashioned
Happened to be in positions of higher authority than the dissident generals on the other side
They looked at the way the war is going and figured out that the casualties
AR
The Difference Maker
And it all these countries are suffering because of the numbers of people that are dying
You need to increase the numbers of people who are dying
Not only does it become hard to replace them
Huge stresses and strains on the society they're losing you
Their families their governments
Some of these societies are fragile enough to Simply
You know fall apart like a house of cards
Others could have the entire population turned on the government and say we've had enough
That becomes the best
To end the war in the minds of some of these
A guy like the leader in Germany Erich von falkenhayn
Is looking at what these 1950
Gamebattles taught him
And they taught him that Modern Warfare on the Western Front
Turns into a meat grinder
No matter what you do
He comes up with the brilliant idea again most of story
Still think
Some people say it's
Shooting an arrow on painting a bullseye around it afterwards
He comes up with a brilliant idea that these meet Brian orser
Happening no matter what you design the Battle of me like what if you designed the battle to be like a meat grinder
What you create
Amy grinder
And then entice the enemy to come into it
If that's what's so effective on the battlefield
What if you plan
To grind meat
Instead of having it be a by-product of other activities and play
Valkenhayn late 1915 determines that the French
Are already in or near their breaking point in terms of the casualties they suffer
And he goes to the rest of the military command he starts talking about
What do you like to do in 1916 to try to win the war
He wants to set
Trap
The French army
The idea is to
Create
One of these
In a modern 20th century
Patricia hampl
Wendy's meat grinder
And then lure the French army into
For that you need
Bait
And the determination on where this off
Happen
Is dependent on what site can be chosen
That would best
Play the role of bait
And I should point out that historians from different countries disagree on this Americans and British historians often point out that this site
Chosen has no real military value at all
It was solely chosen cousins
The perfect emotional bait
To lure the French army into the meat grinder
German and
French historians though often assert that this site did have military
Importance and that that
You did create a real military need to do
What's a French ended up doing
Nonetheless
The German plan
Is to use all this artillery first
Pulverized the defenses
Around this important site
Did the French
You have an emotional
Political and everything else attached
Blow the French off of these Hills
Austin overlook
The city
The city called for John
And then fortify the hills bring your guns up there start shooting at the city of Verdun
And wait for the
French army to show up
Open try to knock you off those Hills
And knowing the superiority of
Prepare defenses
The French are just going to bash themselves up against your barbed wire you
You're trying to use your machine guns
Your Cannon and everything else in a place that was specifically designed to be a killing field
Thoroughly
Attritional
Bloody 20th century way to conduct Warfare
But it's not a bad idea
It also should be no surprise
The battle that was designed to act like a meat grinder
Turns into one of the most horrible battles of
Ball time
Even the name when I hear it
Verdun
It's like Stalingrad
It really is at one of those names that just conjures up a
Specific Imaging in and level of Horror
That puts it in a special place
In military history
Sort of like if you said you know where is the worst place in the world ever be in military history like a tie
Between a million different spots right
Mankind had a long enough past
Is that there are recurring examples of horror riffic places
To end up on any given day we like to site
The famous
Battle between the Romans and carthaginians thousands of years ago
We're all those Romans were
Surrounded in trapped and killed over the whole long day and it's terrible
Probably about as bad as a lot of other terrible situation
There's a few
Or you just go okay that's as bad
As the Battle of cannae sort of
But at artillery
Madonna's like nothing
That has ever happened
Really on a large-scale and I'm sure again
Mankind's a long history everything's kind of tried nothing new Under the Sun as they say
The vagina special for John is so special in fact and so different and so outside the box for the
Thinking of the time.
When fogging hind comes up with the idea that he's going to bleed France
White
His words
It's so runs against the grain of the nineteenth-century sort of morality of warfare remember we started this
Warren Muir
Year-and-a-half ago wearing white gloves with people who dualed when they were in school together
And who thought of this in almost especially on the Western Front
Gallant kind of sense right we exchange swords when we surrender and all the stuff
And now we have generals thinking okay how can I lower millions of men into a confined space
And just pound them into marmalade
To quote one French soldiers
Way of explaining what happened
One of the things I love by the way about this. Just like I love it about the Second World War
Is that we have a lot of the actual words of the generals themselves
They all wrote Memoirs as we said after the war most of the time trying to defend their reputation against their critics
Cuz after this war everyone's pointing fingers at everybody
You know because it was so terrible and people were so angry and and so
Mad at General's amongst other people that they were looking to blame that all these General right pieces defending
The right here
We have Falken Hinesville ludendorff we have all these guys Memoirs now you can't take him you know what face value remember there
Trying to
Stakeout of historical position here in defense of Their Own
Historical
Reputation none-the-less falkenhayn you don't need your love falkenheiner hate me has his fans and he has his detractors
I'm one of his van but I like the way his mind works in the way he writes in his book where he
Written right after the war where he's trying to explain his thinking on this he runs down and logical fashion you where he seized
The war in 1915
And it's not that bad for the Central Powers you'll be a lot of people that will say after the Germans failed
With an initial knockout blow in 1914 it was all a hard slog downhill for them
Necessarily
1950 model year for the Central Powers still have some other attempts were there almost win the war later in the war so this is like
Set all along the heavyweight fight
And there were times when both sides have the other side in trouble
Quick look at Falcon Hines Memoir showed that he thinks France is in trouble that it's not that far from the breaking point
Is wood falkenhayn writes about his
Thinking leading up to his planning for this
Battle that
He's most known for it
Verdun
Falkenhayn right
Quote
As I've already insisted The Strain on France is almost reached the breaking point
Certainly born with the most remarkable devotion
If we succeeded in opening the eyes of her people
To the fact that in the military since they have nothing more to hope for
That breaking point would be reached and England's best sword knocked out of her hand
To achieve that object the uncertain method of amass breakthrough in any case beyond our means
Is unnecessary
We can probably do enough for our purposes with limited resources
Within our reach
Behind the French sector of the Western Front there are objectives for the retention of which the French general staff
Would be compelled to throw in every man they have
If they do so
The forces of France will bleed to death
And there can be no question of a voluntary withdrawal whether we reach our goal or not
And quote
British military historian
John King
Put it this way
Quote
Duncan Hines plan was brutally simple
The French forced to fight in a crucial but narrowly constricted corner of the Western Front
Would be compelled to feed reinforcements into a battle of attrition with a material circumstances so
No favored the Germans
The defeat was inevitable
Did the French gave up the struggle they would lose Verdun
If they persisted they would lose their army
And quote
Displaying falkenhayn
Was giving the Sinister sounding name of operation Gary
Which I've seen translated multiple different ways usually it's
Called operation judge
Which implies
So the finality
Is the High Hope of fall behind going into this campaign right maybe this way
Decide the war
Another translation you sometimes run into
Is court of justice
Central idea
Decision point
The 3rd
Translation of the jewel sometimes run into
Is more indicative
Aldi
Tactics
An approach
The Fall Guy is going to take the win this bad
It's operation
Place of execution
And
Wow
The Kaiser and falkenhayn and all these generals are coming up with this plan in late 1915 the Allies Beyond tan forces are doing
Doing the same thing
I mean I want is a little bit
Lackadaisical about the whole thing. The Russians not the people in the Balkans they've been feeling German attacks over the
The last year
But the British and the French
To haven't seen the German Army on the offensive since way back in 1914
They're kind of leisurely planning what they think will probably be there war winning giant offensive
Slated for late spring or early summer
1916 / on the river Somme
An enormous joint British and French effort with months of planning and and just
Sweeping everything in front of them that kind of
In a Rosy Outlook
And the Germans instead in late February 1916
Go on the
Offensive on the Western Front of the first time in more than a year and catch everyone off guard
It's ridiculous that they could
The amount
Of effort that was
Required to put together a modern offensive or something
We modern people take for granted
But when you hear how much
Planning
And stock
Piling end
Engineering Feats are required to pull off something like the Battle of Verdun
You begin to see why was so different than anything these people have ever known
As we said a hundred years before a Napoleonic battle was considered extraordinary if it went on for 3 days
Throughout most of human history battles take hours
These battles that these
Allied
And Central Power
Planners are
Conducting
Require months of preparation
They don't go on for months to how do you get enough stuff there to make sure your soldiers don't
Starve or run out of ammunition
Well
For the Battle of Verdun
It was more than seven weeks of actual unloading of supply
Is the way writer GJ Meyer describes
Be planning
I'm stockpiling
For the February 19th 6
Battle quote
The Germans meanwhile were accomplishing prodigious feats
And getting everything in place
Helped by The Hillywood in Countryside and the Cloudy winter weather of the Verdun region
They were doing an astonishingly good job of keeping the French from learning what they intended to do or when or
Exactly where
No fewer than five new railway lines were constructed across the German held portion of the plateau
Immediately to the east of the Verdun Hills
In a seven week period
Between late December and early February 1300 train
Not Railway cars but entire train
Holding 2.5 million shell
Earth moving equipment
Construction machinery and everything required to prepare the offencive and support 300 thousand troops in win
Winter came rolling up to Verdun
The guns were positioned in the woods and covered with camouflage
A new development in Warfare made necessary by aerial reconnaissance
Underground Chambers capable of holding as many as 500 men each were excavated opposite the French lines
And lined with steel and conquer
In the sky above all this
What's the greatest concentration of aircraft get seen on any front
150 aircraft
A German umbrella so impenetrable that even on there are days when visibility was good
The French Pilots weren't able to get a close look at what was happening
By the second week of February
Everything was in place for an offensive with the potential to change the course of the war
And quote
The German plan
Wisconsin
Complicated because
This was one of the great defensive spots in French history
We're done watching just a fortress it was a fortress Zone
Multiple Fortress is all working together
Ground that have been fought over
Since the days of Julius Caesar and the Romans
Fortifications that have been upgraded even as recently
As 1914 when the lessons of what happened to those Belgian forts were Incorporated
And then when the war started
The French High command decided to fortresses were old-fashioned
Do do do
The limits of new technology or rather the lack of limit
They decided that those Belgian forts being pounded by that artillery signaled that these Sports were nothing but a death trap
It would be better to take
The weapons on them in the truth that man them
And put them to where the hot spots were in the fighting after all if
Frances in a life-or-death struggle what are we putting
A hundred thousand more troops in the Verdun region to man a bunch of fortresses that are just going to trap them and getting killed by artillery
Let's put them where they're needed oh yeah I make sure they bring the guns in the ammunition and every
Everything else
So they did
Pradhan was a relatively rare
Quiet sector in 1916 before the big German build up
Nonetheless You Can't Hide preparation zzyzx
As the German preparations
Forever
The French become aware of it a couple of weeks before the Germans launch their attack how quickly trying to make up for lost ground and get stuff
You know to these areas because they can sense a buildup in the Germans are launching
Distracting a packs elsewhere this would have been a confused a french-owned where everything's coming from
And on February 21st after a couple of postponements due to bad weather
The storm break
Kicked off by a giant nail gun
Whose nickname by the way as long Max
Just like naming swords
The guns 2
Apparently and long Max fires a shell
The travels
Somewhere between 15 and 20 mile these are in Norman
And that becomes the first shell to drop
As part of the Giant
Why
The kicks off the bottle
Verdun
And right after long Max's barrage kicks off
All these enormous weapons
Open up C
It's not just between 1200 to 1500 guns
It said half of them are cute
You're all those guns that pounded the fortune Belgium's of giant 420 mm Gama Motors you have that 300
80 mm skeleton pieces from Austria and you have more of each of them
Uneven
Enormous number of 210 mm in and 170 is 155 and I mean my goodness
And they open up
All at once and begin pounding this relatively small area of the front
What makes this so incredibly damaging is you have
The fuge weapons
Pounding this
Relatively tiny area on a map
And you fire an enormous number of shells by any standard the first World War
In a short period of time
If you're on the ground at some of those 1915 battles in their firing 1.7 million shells but they're doing it over to
You were three or four weeks
The intensity on the ground very different
Can you play firing 2 million shells
In six days
Poor tiny everyone little wood on the battlefield
1000 yards by 500 yards to
Thousand shells
In the first week
What is that look
There's no human reference for this
When I try to picture I close my eyes I try to picture
Forest
Disappearing in front of my eyes
This is heavily wooded and forested hilly Terrain in Verdun
And right after the bombardment need a 24-hour digital Forest laugh
I've watched Forrest
Elaw
Over weeks in months and it's still appalling to wake up in more Forest is gone
What if you got to watch the entire thing turned up in front of you in a matter of hours like a giant
Celestial weed wacker
The chewing up grass
There are accounts
It say that the shelling is so intense that a giant tree would get blown up in the air before it lands on the ground again another shell
Hitting balls right back up in the air
Veteran
Said that the battlefield quickly looked like an asparagus Farm
Giant shoots
Shooting up all over the soil everywhere which of the tree stump
And wood everywhere
We're needless to say
Tumi
This is something I would have to have some sort of video
I want to imagine
When I was a kid I used to wonder what a tsunami looks
And
Now quick we have video.
It was unimaginable
When I was young now it's something anyone who wants to see it
Can go look up on YouTube
Something that was a very rare sight natural phenomenon or man-made phenomenon for people to see
Shelling is the same way and by the way
There's a lot
You were account
Then you might imagine of the
The first day shelling
At
The battle of
Ferdinand
That's in English
I'm sure there must be more
German and French but
It's important to point out that there aren't a lot of people
It probably survived the war intact after those battles
And the ones who did were probably not all that
Excited
To relieve the itch
Experience
We do have something
Even though it's 40 years old Alistair Horne's the price
Glory has
Some of the best
Accounts in English
Of what it was like on the ground when the shelling started he tells one story of a corporal
Who is with his
Body isn't there just grinding some coffee
When the first she'll start dropping
He writes quote
Suddenly the whole world seemed to disintegrate around him
With the conditioned alacrity of old Soldiers the two men with the coffee grinder disappeared below-ground cursing and
Printable French
Why couldn't the bastards wait till I finish my coffee
The air in the body car a
That little for that area
They are seem solid with whirling material
The Corporal stephayne it was as if it were swept by a quote storm
A hurricane
Attempt is growing ever stronger where it was raining nothing but Paving Stone
And quote
On continue
Quote
Upon the terrible dean of the explosions we're superimpose the splintering crashes of rending wood
The great 210 mm shells locked off branches or uprooted the trees themselves
Barely had the tree trunks fall and then they were spewed up into the air again by fresh eruptions
From his own position still relatively immune to the shelling
Tiffany watches mechanical progress with a certain Macabre fascination
He was like a garden hose
He thought
And quote
And then he described
How
The shells would move like a wave
From one location to another pounding everything in between
And then methodically go back in the direction of just came from his though it's continually mowing the same piece of Grey
Round over and over again
It shows you
What the plan had been before the shelling started to
Make sure every inch of ground was covered
German aircraft
After flying over the battle
Having knocked the French Air Force out of the sky
Enter spotting for their guns
And keeping the French planes from locating the German gun so the French guns could shoot at them
This leads to a very one-sided initial encounter
Historian Paul Jankowski
Compares the initial bombardment here to the 1915 Battle of champagne
Which at the time seemed momentously Titanic
That was a year ago
Now a year later
It seems like
Chump change
Compared to what
The first day of Verdun is so appreciate
Jankowski rights
Quote
It was partly because of such air cover
Partly because it enjoyed such free rein that morning
That the German shelling could exceed in intensity
Anything the French or anyone else had ever endured
This was the Battle of champagne multiplied ten times over
What were the difference in kind as well
The German artillerist were blanketing entire zones with their shells
They directed their fire not merely on to positions they wish to take we're on two lines they wish to a blitter
Put into all that nature had grown
And that man had a record as well
Making up in density for what they lacked in precision
That day they saturated successive zones within a 25 mile Arc between abicor on the Left Bank
Entertain on the right Bank of the muse
With a million high explosive shells of the heaviest caliber known to man
280 305
Even 420 mm wide
And with lesser shells bearing toxic gases as well
Method rather than red
The system of the power hammer rather than the obstinacy of the battering ram drove the destruction
The Morbid calculus presaged the carpet bombing of later Wars
That would raise entire city
And ignite the entire landscape
But for now the thought was purely Tactical
To devastate
So that the Infantry could import
Ndk
Now. Jankowski says the difference in this artillery barrage is not just in the amount of stuff but the way they do it
They are employing every little trick that they've learned in the last year year-and-a-half of warfare
Including
One that
They probably think was a clever enhancement I'm sure the British in the French Mastiff
Another example.
Deviousness only
German Park
But the Germans start this artillery barrage in a little after 7 in the morning
And they pound these French positions all morning and into the lunchtime hour and then they stopped at midday they
Stop on queue all at once
Not even
To the punch drunk French survivors
On the receiving end of the worst artillery barrage in human history know what this means
It always means the same thing it means the German ground troops are coming
In an offensive that's why you stopped shooting so that you don't blow your own men up now that they're on the way right
So the French run up to their positions they man
Defensive spots
They uncover any guns they've got hit and they get ready to push back the German assault now that it's coming except it isn't coming
It's a trick
And all of a sudden all the guns open up again
And start smashing the now exposed French survivors who showed those planes up in the air I'm another observe
Oh yeah that guy survival there's a machine gun that we didn't see
It was an intermission
To get the French to expose themselves
And this feeling goes for the rest of the day until the late afternoon so
Go from 7 something in the morning to 4 something in the afternoon
And then the French survivors
See the first signs of Germany
Country activity
The approaching
What they say
Looks like something out of
Time machine
From the head Larry
Gone
Iconic
Pickelhaube
Mother pointed helmets that the German troops wear that harken back
To the greatness of Prussia and Europe at the height of its 19th century Zona Colonial dominant it
It's symbolic and it's been replaced with something that looks like a minor should wear
Thoroughly working class
Nothing romantic gentlemanly officer or aristocratic
Hobbit
These
Tip of the spear
Troops here are wearing
The German stahlhelm
Which with a minor modification or two is the exact same helmet
The German troops will wear
In the second world
Bees
Stormtroopers as they're called
I've been known to his
Look like the verme
And they're carrying flamethrower
Among other nasty surprises for anyone they might run into they got machine guns with
They got
Men who are wearing clothes
Foods that have
Big bags one of us part of the where they can stuff hand-grenades cuz you just can't carry enough hands
They've even gotten this
You know shows you what they think they're up against
Mei-li wah
Nfamus all these Stormtroopers
If units are famous for the clubs they carry or the hatchets or the Long Knives or
Even things like brass knuckles and stuff these are people who expect to get into physical combat a very close
Strange
They are using
What at the time seemed like very newfangled very modern
Techniques on the battlefield are known as infiltration tactics they pretty much are the same small unit tactics every millet
Terry the world uses today
They've been in development for a while to it's a mister
Suggested the first time anybody sees them is with the storm troops but the storm troops are the first to integrate everything
Into their system
Not only are they going to use these infiltration tactics but look at the weapons that they burned themselves within they train with all this another where they've integrated all the
All the various ideas and theories from all the militaries around the world the last 15 years
And are the first to put these troops out in the field whose job it is
To look for weak spot
And they call him the field
I'm going to run into in a significant opposition they stop or move around it and places where everyone's been killed by
The artillery barrage
Punch right through there
Their goal
Capture
Bait
Remember
This is a trap
The cheese in the Trap has to be captured by the Germans
Before I can play the role
All the cheese
That's what this is all about
That is if you believe
Either the standard historical approaches quite a few historians who believe this whole idea of let's create this meat grinder
Is BS
Propaganda at the time
And
Mia culpa avoidance later on right
If you believe that they're not trying to capture beta try to capture Verdun
Either way the point of this
Initial attack
Is to get the height
The problem is the Germans find out to degree exactly with the French and the British and found out the whole year before
Which is that no matter how good the artillery barrage
There are just units that survived
And then when they strike back at you
It's amazing
And the casualties Mount up
Unbelievably fast
On the very first day
As the German troops pour into an area
And begin to
Cowlicks in front of Master innocent in a specific area
French artillery opens up on them
And this is an account by French staff off
With the artillery
Who first describes what the German artillery attack on his position
Is like
And then describes responding in kind
His was one of the few batteries that did by the way
He writes quote
Thousands of projectiles are flying in all directions some whistling others howling others moaning low
When all uniting into one infernal Roar
From time to time an aerial torpedo passes
Making a noise like a giant motor car
With a tremendous thud a giant shell bursts
Quite close to our observation post
Breaking the telephone wire and interrupting all communication with our batteries
A man gets out at once for repairs
Crawling along his stomach through all this place of bursting minds and shells
It seems quite impossible he writes
Addition escape the rain of shells
Which exceeds anything imaginable
There has never been such a bombardment in war
Our man seems to be enveloped in explosion
And shelters himself from time to time in the Shell craters which honeycomb the ground
Finally he reaches a less stormy spot
Men's his wires
And then as it would be Madness to try to return
Settles down in a big crater and wait for the storm to pass
Now he looks up
Nce
The German assault
Approaching
Quote
Beyond in the valley dark masses are moving over the snow-covered ground
It is German infantry advancing impact formation
Along the valley to the attack
They look like a big gray carpet being unrolled over the country
We telephone through to the batteries
And the ball begin
The site is hellish in the distance in the valley and upon the slopes regiment spread out
And if they deploy fresh troops come pouring in
There's a whistle over our heads it's our first shell
It falls right in the middle of the enemy Infantry
We telephone through telling our batteries are there hit
And a deluge of heavy shells is poured on the enemy
Deposition becomes critical
True glasses we can see men Madden
Men covered with hair or thin blood falling one upon the other
When the first wave of the assault is decimated
The ground is dotted with heaps of corpses but the second wave is already pressing on
Once more are shells Carvalho for gaps in their ranks
Nevertheless like an army of rats the bushes continue to advance in spite of our marmite
I turn the French
Are there shells
He says quote
Then our Heavy Artillery burst forth in Fury
The whole valley is turned into a volcano
And it said you to stop by the barrier of the slain
And quote
That's a foretaste of what's to come
Right there
The Germans have to be on the offensive for a little while in this battle
A battle that is probably built upon the
Presumption that the defense has a huge advantage on the office
This artillery was meant to make up for some of that
But the Germans are taking higher than expected loss
From minute one
This is a problem to cuz remember
Regardless of which historical School you would hear to on the point of this battle it was always part of the plan.
Lose as few people as possible
So the Germans are concerned with losses and part of the reason they're suffering so many is the French or resisting
Heroically
On these first few days
Their units that surrender their units that are just
Gone
From the artillery barrage
But there are units including Elite ones but also
Rather pedestrian one sitting there and dying to the last man to delay
This German Advance these infiltration troops are looking for places to push through they find a couple
But they find a bunch with these
Decimated Defenders resisting heroically
By the country time to get
Fresh troops reinforcing that area
To that area ever done is actually supplied on the French Side by one little Kenny Road
The German to build multiple Railway
The nearsighted Supply the battlefield
Right so as French reinforcements are coming up these heroic Defenders are holding the Germans off as long as they can
There are more big bombardments
The Germans push more troops in with more tenacity
On
February 25th
The Germans in an almost Indiana like Jones movie kind of drama
Capture the big Ford in this region the sort of overlooks the whole battle
We told you that the French High command
Kind of
Lost interest in fourth after the Germans to match the ones in Belgium smash the early ones in France
But they still had people in them and they were still guns in them in slowly but surely they were starting to realize that sometimes and in some places they were
We're worth having didn't matter these troops were in this
Ford which is mostly below ground when a German soldier gets blown into it somehow
Due to a shell exploding nearby
Lansdowne on the ground has a pistol with him and eventually will let in some friends but by and large is walking
Around this underground giant Ford
And as he opens doors into rooms there's a couple of French soldiers playing cards or whatever any capture them and lock them in a room and you
He does this over and over and over again
Finally has everybody kind of captured
Nobody dies on either side
And this major feature in the early part of the battle Falls
To the German
It's one of those situations that sort of rocks
The French morale
And they start
To follow
Part
They've been through a ton
And now
There's this crisis moment we're all of a sudden it looks like the Germans are going to break through in the French were just going to fall apart before any reason for
Porsche Macan stiffen the line
This is where things get really Wiggly in this battle by the way
He gets right down to what the hell the point of it is
If you're falkenhayn
And historians who think he tried to create a meat grinder all that's true
You don't want a breakthrough
You don't want Verdun it's not really what you want
It's the cheese in your trap
If you take it then you're just going to get counter-attack you're going to lose a lot of troops again and that been that's 1915 all over again
What are we do differently right
If you're from the other school of thought though
The idea of breaking through to Verdun at this point is to nearly achieved what the whole bottle
What design to do unexpectedly quickly the Crown Prince was commanding this Army's really excited in there
All sorts of messages where they say hi I will take it I mean it expected this fast but we'll take it and then
They get within 2 miles of the city at one point
And then the French put a new commander in charge
A guy who will be famous by the way in both world wars for different reasons
A guy named Peyton
And pathan becomes you know it's so hard to
To separate the myth from the man went went with his connection to Verdun
But at the narrative is
The pathan gets in there
And changes the French morale
By himself pract
There's all these and you know General
Travel with her on press Corps so there's going to be this guy is going to have a bunch of people helping to to pump up the myth
What is famous for coming to the battlefield and you know any situations where the French just look desperate in a looking
Troops and going now we have them right where we want them that kind of thing and you know
Maybe it's the 19th century mentality but that seems to work
The famously says or somebody says for him and then he stands behind it
They shall not pass
And this becomes too big Narrative of Verdun and it turns into like a French Thermopylae
What the french aren't going to die 2 the last man they're going to win in the end right again part of this this
Overriding narrative
Now morale is kind of a hard to quantify sort of thing hard to measure heart
Look back in history prove anything
You don't have to prove the real world terrafirma things that
Attended
Tanzanite jewelry guy
He's a defensive specialist
And the first thing he does
Is bringing his own artillery and consolidate it and ask for more and slowly but surely begins to build up
His own meat grinder
Two can play at that game
And pathan start stocking up the French side with artillery to
And all this artillery
Turns this entire area
Into the Moon
But weirder
Seashell holes in your head you think of something Symmetra
Trickle like a meteorite crater
But it doesn't happen that way because you get
Seashell holes which can be 30 ft deep with absolutely straight up and down edges
But then they get hit with another shell
Some weird angle Orleans imagine then they get hit with another one and another one and another one and it turns it into
Super weird formation
It still looks weird today if you go look at modern pictures of Verdun Battlefield
It looks
Totally
And it creates a battlefield is a painting by a Frenchman lularoe I think is his name called hell
And it shows a couple of French soldiers
In one of these craters
And a dead body near them and they're wearing gas masks
And the garage is going on a giant Timbers are part of this enormous crater and craters everywhere in the distance is
Far as you look
We said this is like making War worse
These craters are the grossest thing
You can imagine I mean really just
Awful
They fill with water very quickly everyone of them practically with a dead body or two in them
If there was water there's tons of trash tons of stuff
I'm all kinds of I mean they're mostly uses latrines if it's close enough we can get to them
The water is
Bedded
And
Horrible and greasy from the bloated bodies that float in it
Interesting in a poisonous
Because the gas that used on the battlefield I know it
Tempting to think of it as vapor
But it's really almost a solid
Where when a gas shell explodes it covers
An entire area would like a pollen like
Coding and that pollen like coating
Is deadly
So it's like putting insecticide on a given area to keep you out of it for a while and eventually the rain will come and dissolve that
But the dissolve runoff just goes into all these gel holes
That are filled with water and makes them just poison
There will be
Riders will talk about how at first in in the spring the Verdun Battlefield will try to recover a little of its life and they will see little girl
Green shoots
Pop up for a minute before
The poisonous air and Soil and Water and everything just kill them right away
It's a giant
Burnt out
Insecticide Zone
That's what Verdun is an Invicta landscape itself
Is horrifying to a degree that's hard to describe unless you want to say
This is Mordor
This is JRR tolkien's conception
Of the dark light
He was in the first World War
Maybe got it from
The match is perfect. I mean once this artillery has been going for not even that long at this levels of intensity
You have around you on this battlefield and we talked about stage
And all the
People merely players will look at the stage these people are playing on
You know very shortly into the battle it's a lunar landscape it's the Moon
Okay
And these trenches are places where people meet there and very often.
Lots of stories about soldiers with big heavy packs in the night losing their way falling into one of these
Terrible
Craters & just drowning
The worst story are these people who
But you hear stories about people drinking kneeling down and drinking out of these green colored poisonous Waters with bodies float
Coding in it
Because the water isn't making it up to the front
The people whose job it is to bring food and water to the people on the front edge of the meat grinder are getting killed trying to bring it up
Is a terrible.
It's the battles of 1915
Taken to the next level which is what this war is going to be about every time the world thinks
They come to the limits of their interest surely this is the worst battle there will ever be
The standard gets up
Again
And this happens continually
It's a
Pressure cooker
Who's going to break first
And you know you thought last year was bad welcome to next year
I'm on next year's deadlier
I'm on the scale is more and perhaps unsustainably Titanic
The pattern is
Unfortunately for the troops on the ground
Horrific Lee
Familiar
About a week into the assault
The German attack
Jordan Staal
Just like
All these other
Battles we've seen in
A lot more we will
The initial assault is the most
Tense nail-biting up in the air kind of time
Once it stopped there may be abs and flows and scary moments
By and large
We have descended into what Churchill called did you say
Prolonged operations are extended operations
We're now into combat
And for the troops on the ground
It's the most horrifying environment when we want to study the idea
Human beings
Can do
It seems to me you want to see them in some of the most if you want to see if
Just like a product
Test did you want
To put it under the most extreme stress and see how behave
Look at what we're done but
Over the next many months
Do I have to live
How do they induce
And
When you hear the stories
East from this place I mean
Start with the approach
The French
As we said
And a lot of trouble to rotate their troops in and out of this battle cuz they get worn down like a
Pencil in a pencil sharp
Do you have to
And rotate them
When the soldiers approached Verdun they can see it a long way away
I mean the guns of the opening barrage were said to be audible a hundred miles away
So when they're approaching Verdun it looks like a giant
Forest fire
Fire in the distance
One French soldier on the way to it said
Reminded him quote
I'm a gigantic Ford
Neither day or night
And quote
The fires of Mordor
Like I said
The air becomes Smoky and hazy
And you don't see the sun clearly anymore and all the vegetation disappears one artist said the only color in the landscape
After a while cuz it's just overturned
And bodies and debris and everything turned up concrete
It's a hellish environment but there is a smear of red here are there with the horses have just been splattered by artillery
I mentioned that it sounds like hell yet
We mentioned earlier how hard it was to get food and water to
The troops fighting
The front line
But it was hard to get anything
To the Troops
Fighting at the front line for example
To get new troops to the front line
Could kill off half your troops
In his book
The price of Glory Alistair Horne
Takes a couple of different accounts
And put them together and quotes a few
People who were there
About what it was like simply trying to get to the front of the meat drying
Edward on imagine suffering a 40 or 50% casualties trying to get to the moon
Reminder here's what he writes
Quote
A mile or two from the Frontline
Troops entered the First Communication trenches
Go to call them this was generally both an exaggeration
And an anachronism
Parapets gradually grew lower and lower
Until the trench became little deeper than a roadside ditch
Chills now began to fall with increasing regularity among closely packed men
In the Darkness
He says for obvious reasons approach marches were usually made at night
The Columns trampled over the howling wounded lay under foot
Suddenly the trench became nothing more than a track
Harley traced out amid the shell holes
In the mud
Which the shelling had now turned to a consistency of sticky butter
Troop stumbled and fell repeatedly
Cursing in low undertones as if fearful of being overheard by the enemy
Relentlessly pursued them with a shells at every step
Sometimes there were duckboards around the lips of the huge shell crater
But more often there were not
And heavily Laden men falling into the water filled holes remain there until they drown
Unable to crawl up the greasy side
If a comrade pause to lend a hand he writes
It often meant it to Wood round instead of one
In the chaos of the battlefield where all reference pointed long since been obliterated relieving detachments
Stopped and got lost
And wondered hopelessly all night
Only to be massacred by an enemy machine gunner is Dawn betrayed them
It was not unusual for relief
To reach the front line with only half the numbers that set out
Nor for this nightmare approach march to last 10 hours or longer
And quote
Seems to me
Maybe I can speak for some of my generation
If I just spent 10 hours struggling through that
And lost half our people while doing so
Just so I got to take my turn on the front lines
I'm going to be
Severely
Destabilize
Let's put it that
Why is that a good way to describe it
And even though these
French units will be rotated maybe only spend five or six or seven days up at
At the front
I mean that was designed to keep them from just being decimated and being shattered
But judging from some of the witness accounts
It didn't work
British historian John Keegan the late John Keegan
All right
It's that time I French
Officer named Augustine coaching
Spend from the 9th to the 14th of April
On one of these important Hill
And Keegan writes
Coding this
Officer
Quote
The last two days
Soaked in icy mud under terrible bombardment
Without any shelter other than the narrowness of the trench
The boss did not attack natural
It would have been too stupid
Result
I arrived there with 175 men
I returned with 34
Several half mast
Not replying anymore when I smoke
And quote
French Lieutenant describe watching a unit his own unit
Actually
Coming down and back from Verdun after being relieved and he says
Quote
First came the skeletons of company
Occasionally let by wounded officer leaning on a stick
All marched or rather advanced
In small steps
Zigzagging as if intoxicated
It was hard to tell the color of their faces from that of their tunics
Mudhead covered everything
Dried off
And then another layer had been reapplied
They said nothing
They even lost the strength to complain
It seemed as if he's mute faces were crying something terrible
The Unbelievable horror of their martyrdom
Some territorial two were standing near me but came pensive
They had that air of sadness that comes over one when a funeral passes by
And I overheard one say
It's no longer in army
Those are Corpses
Two of the territorials wept in silence
Like women
And quote
So what's going on to those guys
That they go in
One way
And they come out so shattered and sometimes it only takes a couple of days to go from one reality to the other
That's where
At least first hand accounts from these people
Barstow
Moving
Principal from the perspective of these men on the ground everything seems so pointless
Because
They only know this little world of this big Battlefield they're operating on
And a perfect example is how
These generals were now fighting over the same
Terrain features over and over and over month after month after month they take him and then they're retaking them they take them again in the Raw
All fighting over the same Carnage stand ground over and over again
And they develop names
I want these Hills Hill 304
The famous hill with a lot of people paying with their lives to take it and retake it again
There's another one known as the Deadman
Or dead man's heels another way to translate it
And that's another one of these Hills I mean they've had the tops blast-it-all Often by both sides artillery
They're smoking like volcanoes pretty much at all times
We're told some of the Dual amount
Doom if we want to keep arm
Mordor analogy going
And when our unit retake supposition on for example one of those long fought over terrain features
Then you have that around you
I mean for example
Fantastic
Has several quotes where he talks about
Soldiers
Having to retake this ground
That are nothing more than
Open
Cemeteries combined with butcher shop
He writes quote
On the ground
Soldier and writer Jack Mayer describes the real frightfulness when he noted
Quote
Everywhere there were distended bodies that your feet sink into
The stench of death hung over the jumble of decaying corpses like some hellish perfume
And quote
Passing him continues quotes
When the Germans captured Hill 304 in May one of the first demands of the assault troops
Was there a double ration of tobacco
Damask the overwhelming reeked of corpses
Riding around them
Like Jacques Mayer a fellow French soldier Road at this time that
Quote
According to strength Soldier now
We all had on us the stench of dead bodies
The bread we ate the stagnant water we drank everything we touched had a rotten smell
Owing to the fact that the Earth around this was literally stopped with Corpses
And quote
How do you not lose your mind
Barrel maker and Corporal louis barthas
Arrives at the famous Hill 304 at one point in the spa
And looks up
And contemplates
This piece of ground
It is cost so many people on both sides
Their Earthly exist
Your rights quote
I looked out upon this famous nameless Hill
Are trench lay at the foot of it
For several months the hill has been disputed as if it had diamond mines on its slopes
Alas
All it contain now with thousands of shredded pulverized Corpses
Nothing distinguished it from neighboring Hills it seem to even partly wooded at one time but no trace of vegetation room
The convulsed
Overturned Earth offered nothing but a spectacle of devastation
And quote
Now eventually in for reasons that will get into in a minute the situation changes
At ferdon in the Germans go
From essentially a sort of an offensive position to a defensive one as they transfer Forces 2
To another part of their front
For something else
What's going on taking their attention
And so the French use this as an opportunity to retake ground
And now we get the same kind of battles we had when the Germans were moving forward in this now that the French are now the
Germans have taken a bunch of their artillery wasting out of French have the artillery dominance
And now the Germans get to experience what the french experience on the other side
And you know 9 or 10 months into this battle
We have human beings living on the edge
I'm watching and beans can tolerate there's an extended
Apparel quotes from the same guy
A German soldier
Who is
In one of these
Any sports are all over this area this is a fortified Zone that several forts covering one another in a lot of the most terrible bad
Battles happen over these Sports
And their battered down to that they're just shells of what they were but they could still hold hundreds of man and protect them from Shrek
Often times you had tons of men in these underground blown up
Fort with blood everywhere and everything else
And here's the way the environment is described
By this German
Quote
His name is private William Harmon's by the way of the 67th Infantry Regiment and I get this from Peter Hart
The Great Wall
He said quote
The entrance was a mere hole in the scarred Battlefield
And the Silhouettes Of cowering men constantly crawling in around look like huge ants in the dark
I just ended an iron ladder some 40 ft into the concrete Cavern
It was an enormous place
Crowded with many hundreds of soldiers
Some lay on bunk sleeping
Snoring and moaning
Some quarter the passages between the bunks
Chatting writing letters
Are there sat or nelton corners
Packing or unpacking their belongings
Hero flashlight there a candle match or cigarette. In the dark
With flickering islands of light
Continually shifting and brightness
From this Subterranean stronghold
A small patch of Sky to be seen when one stood close to the iron ladder
We're look through the shaft which contain the ventilator fans
The current of warm stale air from 40 feet beneath brought to my nostril the sickening smell of first aid Med
Medications
Every one of the chicken-wire births were filled with mutilated muddy torn in the following uniform
A dismal site
There was a man with closed eyes
A blood-soaked bandage around his head
Another beside him like twisting in pain
I saw some lice ridden Man Who Would scratch their bandages off to ease the itching
The passages Between the Buns were crowded
There must have been a thousand men there
Summit been relieved
Could not withdraw to the rear
And something would come to relieve the others could not proceed to the front lines
All were imprisoned deep within the concrete and rock and roll
And quote
Now that's a senior up till that point could have happened in a lot of War
What happens
Next in that Underground
Environment that soldiers writing from
Is something
It on a large scale
Between great powers
Only happened in this war
He says quote
I heard the cry
Poison gas
And I saw people around me put it on their gas masks
I adjusted mine which still hung over my shoulder
There it was
A yellowish gas glimmering near the iron ladder
A gas bomb must have been thrown into the entrance show
The cry
Gas masks on electrified the whole shelter
Soldiers ran to get their Maps
Which they had hung on the walls and in the corners or lay down their pack
Many who have lost theirs on the battlefield began to cough
The wounded in the Bronx tried to climb into the upper berths
Well beneath the gas crept forward along its way
Extinguishing one candle after another
Soon many were dying
And the bunks and Floors were filled with bodies over which the living stepped and stumbled in search of air
The alarm surge like a wave from bunk to bunk
Before long it would reach the farthest man hundred yards away
The Panic was so great
Did I saw a badly wounded men throw themselves onto the floor as though they wanted to drink in the gas
While others tore their masks from the neighbors faces
Some had a reddish foam oozing from their mouth
And quote
I always try to remind myself
When we're talking about these big
Praying
Battles
That what this really is is a million stories like
The pain of that incident magnified over the entire scope of the war
And while I'm sure there's some people who are harder than I am in terms of
That's life that's what history is filled with all those kinds of things
It's hard not to sit there
And feel a sense of all
For the people who
Facebook
This
I'm not out of any sort of patriotic in a glorification of War anything else
And I said just sort of the
Unexpectedly strong limits of human endurance
How did they sustain the Safra
How did they win told they had to advance into this or just not run away at top speed
How did they do it
Let's acknowledge not all of them dead
There were a lot of people shot in this war
For running away
But the large majority of them did not and you sit there and go how did they not Rebelle how did they not revolt
What would we do today
Is a great quote for Mom
F Scott Fitzgerald novel
It's fictional
But he puts words into the mouth
Of a man who showing one of these 19:16 battlefields
To his compatriots the touring the battlefield and he has a discussion with
Plain to them
The almost
Soup
It was required
Bring up a generation of people who
Do this
In other words
It's not just yours truly wondering how
People sustain this effort
Even right after the war people were trying to figure out how
People could do this
Here's the section from the esca
Scott Fitzgerald
Fitzgerald's character
Explains
Whitney Point in the distance
To a little body of water
Does quote
See that little stream
We can walk to it in 2 minutes
It took the British a month to walk
A whole empire walking very slowly
Dying in front
And pushing forward behind
And another Empire walked very slowly backward
A few inches a day
Leaving the dead like a million bloody rugs
No Europeans will ever do that again in this Jenner
Any other character
Why they've only just quit
Over in Turkey
And in Morocco
The response
Quote
That's different
This Western Front business couldn't be done again
Not for a long time
The young men think they could do it but they couldn't
They can fight the first Marne again
But not this
This took religion
And years of plenty
And tremendous sureties
Any exact relation that existed between the classes
The Russians and Italians weren't good on this front
You had to have a whole-souled Sentimental equipment going back further than you could remember
You have to remember Christmas
Send postcards of the Crown Prince and his fiance
A little cafes in balance
And Beer Garden
Unter Den Linden and weddings at the Murray
I'm going to the derby
And your grandfather's whiskers
General Grant invented this kind of Battle of Petersburg 1865
Came the reply meaning General Grant in the Civil War in 80
The main character says quote no he didn't he just invented Mass Butchery
This kind of battle was invented by Lewis Carroll
And Jules Verne
And whoever wrote ondine
And Country Deacons
Bowling
And Marianne's in Marseille
And girls seduced in the back Lanes of wurtemburg invest failure
Why
This was a love battle
It was a century of middle-class love
Time spent here
A Century of middle-class love
Spent here
That is
Found and that's how the generation that lived through this Warsaw
So basically Fitzgerald
That question
And how did these people endure
Is that you had to have grown up the way they did
The same cultural influences and expectations including societal and class-based ones
Either had you seen the world the way they did had
Similar concepts of
You know Duty and expectations and
Even manhood
When you have to have in some ways
The same allusions to
Because in
Certain circumstances
Having illusions
Could help you carry out
Military
Operations
People who are more cynical and realistic
Would never do
I mean when you think about the endurance to I mean it's so normal to focus on the horrific War side of this
What's a simple
Your life part of this is sometimes what pushes people over the edge you know you'll hear stories sometimes wear
They will say when they were able to adapt
To the shelling they just couldn't handle the rats or something
Something gets them sometimes
Above and beyond what you might think
The perfect example
He start looking at what day-to-day life was like for these people
Any of us would think we're focused on staying alive but sometimes it got down to an even more
Base level than that
Louis Bartos
Fighting in the Verdun Inferno
Writes about
At night being in one of these trenches when the rain just comes pouring down he says quote
We were crouching down so as not to catch a stray bullet or shell fragment passing by
And if this weren't bad enough
A heavy rain started to fall
It didn't take long for the water to fill in the ditch and to submerge our shoes
Our helmets were transformed into drain spouts
Little waterfalls ran down our packs onto our hips off our shoulders in a long are arm
We didn't know what
Or hang you were waiting for
The night was Pitch Black
Were they just going to leave us stuck in the sewer
And quote
Sewer is such an app name to besides the body is
And the poison and the Decay and the lice and the rat is not even dealt with them they're both
Absolutely
Beyond imagination living with the lights living with the rat
You also have
The problems of men fighting in an inferno we're getting out of your trench men too pretty good chance of.
When you have to go to the bathroom when we parked us rights
Quote
And to make it worse cuz I've already described all of us
One after the other suffered from an epidemic of intestinal disorders
The resulting diarrhea sure cleaned us out
Opportunity
As soon as one of us got over his next door neighbor was afflicted with it and had the bad luck to have to climb out of the trench
And head for the shell hole which served as our latrine
Of course we did this only in The Last Resort
At the last moment of agony
Stretching our guts until they were about to burst
One of us was surprised in the lottery and buy one of these sudden fusillade
And collapsed into his own excrement
It was not to expose oneself to similar incidents some used sardine or monkey meat
Kansas chamber pot
It was not to have to leave one's hole in the ground
One even sacrificed his cast iron dinner plate
And quote
How do you keep your sanity
It's a risk your life
Did I mean the whole thing again and lean-to Battlefield there might have been one horrible day where if you're under
Lucky enough to have dysentery that day it's a horrible day in the ranks it isn't the day after day after day thing you people are putting up
With a pounding on their cycle
But understanding what they went through
Is in large part what makes this story so incredibly compelling
The extremes of Human Experience right I talk about it all the time
Is wonderful
Paragraph
By historian Eric
Thorne Bros
Who tries to describe
Why this isn't gratuitous to talk about this why it's
Part of
Being astounded by your ancestor
Here's what
Bro says
Quote
Most historians today depart from the traditional practice of omitting casualty figure
What was once left out for respect of the Dead
And to avoid any indecent hint of criticizing or questioning the sacrifices they made
Is now included
In order to illuminate the magnitude of the horror man face
By citing numbers in other words historians begin the process of turning back toward describing what war was real
I really like and I do this
Despite the understandable loathing of the veterans themselves
To remember we speak about traumatic experiences they have tried
Usually unsuccessfully
To suppress
The problems historians encounter with casualty figures however
Especially the astronomical numbers of dead and wounded in 20th century Wars
Is it numbers have a numbing quality to them
Although shocking to read initially
I quickly lose descriptive Effectiveness as mines failed to grasp or in the abstract
In order to do historical Justice to combat on the ground there for
It is necessary to go beyond the numbers
To the gruesome eyewitness account
Shaking off criticism that to go there is gratuity
The Great War can only be fully understood if all its aspects are exposed
Dimensions of the front experience that not only affected soldiers morale
And eventually
The outcome of the war
But also home fronts and they're critically important willingness to continue shoulder in the war effort
All wars are horrible
Brothers Wright
Tragedies for the Dead
Their relatives and Friends
Hobbling sometimes disfiguring injuries for others
Turning wives children and parents into Caregivers for life
And psychological minefields for veterans who may have escaped death and injury
But not the terrible memories with which loved ones two are then forced to live
The Great War was especially hellacious however
Because it was the first to unleash the full mechanized Fury
A sophisticated industrial technology
And quote
Men had never
To endure
Anythink why
Some of these French soldiers had to go back to Verdun more than one time
What is that Duty right I read somewhere where one of them said the first time you can kind of handle cuz you don't know what you're in for it's particularly hard when you're going back to
Mordor after you've been
Mordor
So happy to have survived
And now you get to take your chances all over again
To the majority the French army get the chance to rotate through this area at least once and they never get over it
Pathan himself
Essay about
The Verdun experience to the French army quote
The constant visions of death that penetrated the French soldier with a resignation that bordered on fatalism
And quote
The fighting went in for 10
About half that time the Germans were on the attack the other half the time the French were on the attack and by the time it was over
This is disputed but about a million total casual
Outside data.
Give or take 2
At the end of the war
It will be mandated in the treaty
That when this battlefield is cleared and it will take
Decades just to get the bodies off of it the shells are still there and many of these areas are cordoned off
Until well probably good hundred two hundred years from now
Recirculated win French bodies were dug up and buried they needed to be buried singularly
And with white crosses
Purity
The Germans
Didn't have to be
Can a single grape
Even their graves were to carry
Black crosses
Signifying
Shame
The depth of emotion
That Verdun
Created in the immediate post-war generation but even in France today
Is unlike
Quite any other
Military
Endeavor
French arms
Participated
And the miss making about this
Crazy battle
Start before the fighting's even done
And there's a hole
Group of revisionist historians who been trying ever since the battle happen to
Poke holes in the myths
That obscure the reality of Verdun
It's got such a sacred hold on both France and Germany it's hard
To separate
The facts from the fiction
There's a huge amount of heroism in Sacra
Device connected
It's understandable that you would get
You know some is making
And the revisionist historians often portray falkenhayn the German
Commander in the one behind this plan is an idiot
Dumb plan executed incompetently and after the war when people went to Falcon Hines or what were you thinking
I was trying to kill a lot of people
My goal
Mission accomplished
One of these revisionist historians
Paul Jankowski is a perfect example will say something like
To make Verdun out to be any worse than any number of terrible World War 1 battles is to play into the myth and he says it
If being in a trench
With the rain falling on you with your feet up to your knees in mud under shellfire and sniper fire.
Day after day
Is terrible will there's plenty of First World War battles where's a soldier you would have found yourself in that say
Situation with bodies all around me that's not that abnormal the first World War
They're right about that too but
You know maybe it's
Bearer to say that there are several
Really unbelievably horrible an unprecedented battles in the first World War
That are equally hellacious and you would not want to be at any
They each have their own
Awful unique
Clay virtue
That makes them different
And nothing smells quite like Verdun
And if you said to me you have to be at one of these horrible Battlefield
Verdun is the lowest on my
Verdun is the last
Place out of all
If you ask what Verdun achieve
Again
There's a wide variety of opinions on this
The most popular is that it achieve nothing
On the broad symbols
The general waste
This war
About a million people
Either are
Killed or wounded
Or
You have never returned from that Battlefield
And nothing
Of huge importance was gained because of that
One thing that certainly did happen as it moved up the timetable
For several other bat
How's that we're going to happen the little bit later but when the French got pressed by the Germans at Verdun they said the British and they said to the Russians
You know those battles you were planning on starting
Could you move up the timetable and starting sooner we could use the help
Prayer
I'm finally
The one thing in 1916 you're beginning to see if we've eluded
Did this before
Is that these people have put up already
With a lot more pounding than we would
Only put up with today
But there's a breaking point for all human beings
In my mind
The breaking point that's coming
Was Quicken
But experience
Ever done
And we mentioned that the French had a policy of rotating troops during the battle to keep them
What that meant was
Virtually the entire
Higher French army
Timer another
Was rotated through that
Sector
Verdun
Took the French
And Ratchet it up
The discontent levels in Waze
It will probably out of proportion to what you could have expected
A problem or normal
It got you closer to the break
The idea of
Pushing your adversary to the point where their society literally implodes
Is a Thoroughly Modern idea
By 1916
Most of the military leaders in this conflict
See that as the endgame in this conflict
The reason it's a Thoroughly Modern concept isn't because people of the past didn't understand it
It was because
They could never take enough damage to get to that point
I reset the route this series
Nations in the past for the most part couldn't take a punch
The ones who could stand out like sore thumbs the Roman Republic for example what makes it so unusual in the
Terry history sent
They could sustain
Defeat
After defeat
And not capitulate
They could lose a battle of cannae they can lose a battle of lake trasimene in the same War
And keep coming back for more very unusual
You know what generation before those defeats
Alexander the Great defeats the massive
And the greatest Empire the world has ever seen the achaemenid Persian Empire with a couple of big shots
There's never enough time
For the society to implode
A society
Collapsing at the foundation's requires that they be able to stand there and exchange enough punches to go
Get to that point
R19 16
The grinding down of Nations is well underway
As author David fromkin says the real war
Can become an economic
And social survival Khan
And the generals are beginning to organize their strategies
To Quicken and hasten this outcome
Example win
Falkenhayn talks about
You know the idea of using attrition
To bleed the French White
Explains that you don't have to worry about the Russians anymore
Because they're well on their way to having their entire Society collapse Jesus quote
According to all reports
The domestic difficulties of the giant Empire
Are multiplying rapidly
Even if we cannot perhaps
Expect a revolution in the grand Style
We're entitled to believe that Russia's internal troubles
Will compel her to give in within a relatively short period
In this connection it may be taken for granted that she will not revive her military reputation meanwhile
We need not be anxious about that
On the contrary
It is probable he writes
Did any such attempt in the law says it must involve would only hasten the process of disintegration
And quote
I should also point out that
In the nineteenth Century for example that kind of disintegration
Not only wasn't the goal
It would have been seen as a negative by Prada
In the era where
A military defeat meant that one General gave his sword to the other General in exchange some provinces or something
Colonies are what nut
The goal wasn't for the society to collapse
It was now
Military leaders
Began to employ strategies
Designed to make that outcome a reality
Spriggs amp
When the war starts
The British use their Navy
To clamp down a blockade on Germany
Now the French
Don't look at that as a very useful strategy because after all
Something like that going to take a long time and no one win this war starts you know a very small minority who turned out the
Because sand
Prophetic no one thinks the wars going to go long enough for something like a blockade
To actually take effect
Dubai 1916
Everyone is starting to understand that those long-term Anaconda like strangling strategies
Are very viable
And the British are not the only ones
Who can do this
German Shepherd
This is the point in the story where it becomes worth talking about it
Easy
This German fleet was a
Key reason
The tensions especially with Britain increased in the pre-war
Call the anglo-german naval
What is considered to be worth it by a Kaiser
And a government that thought it was important to be able to hold your own at CSO
These ships were built and they cost
An amazing amount of money
A huge amount of industrial capacity of sucked up into this every said you you turn them
Basically friendly Britain into an enemy
And
Now that you got what you wanted
It's sitting in pork
Continually
I hear you got your country straining every fiber
You know to sacrifice for the war effort kept the civilians are starting to cut back on their caloric intake and here's this Fleet
So expensive to build and
Every month sucking up resources and sitting in Port
This is the time in the story
We're because the Germans get a new Admiral
Things start to happen on the surface naval front for really the only time in this war
And if you are
Not for this. Like I am I like to call it the battleship era
Somewhere between 8
1898 Chevy 1940 is about 50 years
The arrow will you get these armored Leviathan
Just to me they're fascinating
Write an intersection credible vehicles
That you may have to fast forward the show when I start going off on some detail tangent
In only I find interesting
But I think these vehicles are incredible
And there is so little
Evidence of them actually being used
Did on the few occasions know where it happens I tend to look at them rather deeply there's only one occasion and
I don't think I count the
Russo-japanese War pre-dreadnought think only one occasion in history where
These armored ships from this era
50 years
Actually fought the way these Admirals had envisioned they would
In long lines miles long lines
Stretching off to the Horizon you know
Lord Nelson style Pirates of the Caribbean style
And facing a fleet similarly arrayed in shooting you know when the distance between them that only happened once
In this whole 50-year Battleship era
And only happened once in this war obviously
It's a battle in 19
Call the Battle of Jutland
Coop's Like Yours Truly this is a fantastically interesting encounter
When we were thinking about organizing the story
I know you try to carve out
Places to take a little
Direction change the momentum you go from the Carnage of Verdun and those of you who know the story Noah
What's coming up in the future of it
And you take a little interlude to talk about other elements not just
The navel
Inside of this but also the fact that the Navy really is a wonderful
Canvas on which to represent the technology of this era
How big of a deal that is to the people here
Perpetual problem isn't it
I'm going back in time and seeing
What looks to be ancient technology to us looking at it the way
The people back there looking at it to whom it's cutting-edge stuff
Give me first of all
I was trying to think about the best way to sort of explain
Create an analogy for how these people see the fleet
They having the fleets in the Navy
Along with this new thing these are crap
Are the real cutting-edge technology out there
And
The reason why is because it's just death to be
Too far behind
As I said the best Navy from 1900 would lose to several navies from 1914
That's me you're 14 years I don't think those 1914 Navy lose a ship
That's how quickly
Things are changing
Robert Massey in his book Dreadnought have a great life
He says in 1900
Nothing you're 14 years before the first world war breaks out
Every single British Admiral commanding a British battleship
Have been
Train
When they came up in the Navy in the age of sail
So that's an example of how cutting-edge this is
If you want a mental image think of the Titanic the ship that struck the iceberg and went down and everything that's from this
It's sort of a steampunk e
Sherlock Holmes a kind of feel
I always think about it as I mean if you eat if you are up in the command center Wendy's battleships
It's like Star Trek meets
In a Sherlock Holmes are steampunk and instead of having a digital display you'd have one of those in a round dial
Nails with one of those
Arrows that looks like the elevator arrow in a nice New York hotel that goes around on a gold background of me
You know very
Very beautiful accident ships were beautiful
Polish would the whole thing they were just gorgeous
And they were The Cutting Edge technology of their day
And I had to
Resist
Comparing them to spaceship
As a way to try to have us feel like the people back then felt cushion of me that would be just be so amazing
Like a Starship
But it's a little like one but not enough for the compare
Right as I thought to myself I thought you know
Those people saw battleships has really cutting it but not as much as we would spaceships with an equal number of men
Crew members on board
That would be bigger deal but then I remembered
The submarine
For the people again hard for us to get all wild about them but to the people back then that is science fiction
The very definition of the word right out of Jules Verne's 20000 Leagues Under the Sea
And all of a sudden we have ships that go underwater
Like they have cloaking devices they become
Invisible
And worse
If you're you know an able official back then
Is it they now carry
New weapons
The threatened everything you have
This is what really
Accounts for the cautious nature
Of Naval Warfare in this. Why didn't the ship just all come out blazing and everything
Well there's all these uncertainties
Part of this. Attraction is that you begin to see a showdown
In Naval Warfare when you haven't had any test of any of the technology long time no one knows what's going to happen
When you get whole fleets out here blazing away with this modern technology it hasn't happened before
One of the things everyone kind of scared about is
The Torpedoes for exam
He's mines you know these floating mines that
It lay in the water and then the ship runs into the man bun they explode
Because these weapons are very very cheap
Right you can make a lot of them
And they can sink
These
Massively expensive
You know ships that take years to build
And whose loss is catastrophic
I can sync those
That's a huge change because it most and Naval Warfare
General
There are exceptions but when you want to sink a massive expensive
First class
Ship you generally need either another massive
First class ship or a lot of other one
They have huge survivals
Write a stick and justify their cost in the investment
Now all of a sudden
Free simple Churchill talked about the British admiralty just being
Petrified
That you would turn around one day and these great huge expensive ships that took forever to build and that you only have a limited number of we're just
Disappearing in the blink of an eye boom quick explosion
Mothership gone
When the war starts
Am I the first couple of months that happen
They lose a super dreadnought
Creme Dela Creme of the British
Battleship forces
All the HMS audacious trikes of mine
Like in a month or two after the war starts in that
Pretty brand-new ship almost
And boom goes down 191 battleship
Wow
Again if you're in the admiralty you're going okay what is this mean
And then
A submarine like since a couple of old British cruises boom boom boom Lemme one right after another
And all of a sudden
Yeah these people who got these big expensive ships are kind of petrified about using them
Military strike Martin Van creveld have spoken about this we just have this
Strange dichotomy with you
Spend so much money on these vessels cuz they're very important but that because you spend so much money on them you don't want to risk them and so
So you have the German Navy in the British Navy
Dealing with each other as maybe two snipers hunting each other would deal with
Each other
Waiting for
The other side to make a mistake and then when they do pouncing
The problem is is that
When the war starts the British
Clampdown that blockade
And that's all they need to do
The pressures on the Germans to do something about
And every said Winston Churchill who was the civilian
Head of the Navy for a while in the conflict wrote down that
Really well they would have been a lot of advantages that sending the you know numerically Superior British Fleet to go in there and
Is Kik German
Tail
The downside if you failed to do that
Was so bad it wasn't worth it he said yeah you know we can get all these good things if we
Decisively defeated the Germans because but if we lost
Remember
This is all untried technology and Naval Combat weird and unpredictable anyway you could bring the superior
If lead in there and somehow
Lose or just lose enough
So that you don't have the numerical Advantage anymore you got parody with the Enemy and that was unthinkable
And Churchill said the chances of that happening
Might not be great but if it happens it could cost us the whole War
I remember reading that and thinking to myself I don't know if I buy it
But a whole lot of interesting thoughts come to mind
If you believe what Churchill says
About it
Basically having the potential
To end the war
Now here's how we explained it in this book he said if the German Navy were even to have a nice victory
Against the British cut down the numerical superiority so that they both have the same number of big ships
Then the German Navy would be able to interdict
Just off heading for Britain and Churchill says that that would result
Quote
The trade and food supply of the British Isles
Would have been paralyzed
Our armies on the continent would have been cut off from their Base by Superior Naval Force
All the transportation of the Allies would have been jeopardized in Hanford
The United States could not have intervened in the war
Starvation an invasion would have descended upon the British people
Ruin
Otterbein final would have overwhelmed the Allied cause
He says the great disparity of the results
Stake in the battle between the British and German navies
Can never be excluded from our thoughts
And quote
So if you buy Churchill's theory that means instead of being
The most secure of the Great
Powers that I think most of us assume Britney is after all your talking about an island nation
Country with a motor
Right and then you add the greatest Navy in the world looks pretty secure to me
Churchill's idea here is that
Yeah but we are one lucky punch
Away from that situation changing
To stay with our boxing and
Analogy
And if that's true
The Germans
Maybe are justified in keeping that Fleet safe in Port in case you need a lucky punch maybe you're losing the war
Or else wrong you decide
You'll send your in a ship's on a death run and take your chances maybe you get lucky right maybe you get a knockout blow
If again you buy into what Churchill saying means that the Germans will
As long as they still have a fleet somewhere
Maintain the ability to win the war with a lucky punch at any time
Find it fast
Don't know if I believe it that's fine too fast
Now the only time in this war
That the attempt at a lucky punch happened it wasn't thrown that way
But the only time that this decisive encounter that could be potentially horrifying if it totally went the wrong way
For Britain the only time this happens
Is in this part of the story where are they now
And happens because of that Admiral we mentioned earlier his name is Reinhard Scheer
He takes over in early 1916
And he feels about the German Fleet
Pretty much the same way everyone else
It's time to earn your keep and let's start acting more aggressively with it
Apple Hill start
Trying to
The best way to put in a trap the British
The British have more big ships in the German so sheers ideas will let's see if we can ambush
Small numbers of those big ships
Overwhelm them and slowly but surely Whittle down the advantage in numbers that the British have
And it's one of these
Attempted traps
That result in this
Really only time for enthusiast like yours truly
To see what these
Fleets could do in an all-out encounter
Play Both Sides
Curling steal the horizon
And with all these weapons that you know from a spectator standpoint
You're just dying to see what the heck they can do
I mean let's start with the guns
The guns on these ships are the same kind of guns you saw leveling the Belgian forts in that the Germans were using it
We're done those are the big Naval guns being used on land
Well why didn't they call him Naval guns right
These new battleships I mean for example the britisher
Bring it in for 5
Brand new ones that will fight in the Second World War II that have 15 inch guns
And multiple that me like 8 to 12 15 inch guns
That's incredible 13in of armor they wear like 30 thousand tons
The new Queen Elizabeth plaster called they can do like 25 knots if they're really smoking
These are incredible incredible modern worship
And when you realize that they can hurl a shell
The size of a small Volkswagen
18 miles across the Horizon at a Target that's a hundred ft wide
While both shooter and Target are moving
And hope to hit it reasonably well
That's shocking I mean the Spanish American War
I'll less than 20 years before this time. They would fire hundreds of shots
Add about
Just Less Than 3 miles distance
And every now and then they'd score hit you know hundreds to get a few
In the
Russo-japanese War they broke all records when they open fire at each other at 8 Miles distance
That's 11 years
Before the Battle of java
8 Miles breaking all record
Battle of Jutland has ship that can fire 18 mile
How do you even hit anything on the horizon will both sides British and German are incorporating against like steampunk techno
Media rudimentary
Fire Control computer you might call it
And both sides have different versions of the Germans have Superior Optics and so they'll score
The early hits in it when in this encounter that happens
In large part
Because the British are reading
The naval Communications of the German
Tell of the battle of Jutland
For a couple of reasons not just because it's the battleship encounter
Of the war but also because it's a rubber meets the road MoMA
Put up or shut up historical
Test
Where
All of the military theories in the debates in the
The philosophical differences amongst experts over the proper way to build the ships and what Naval battles going to be like
Like in the next war and all that stuff
Leaves the realm of the theoretical and gets
A laboratory tested on the naval Battlefield
The land Powers already saw this happen to them right at the start of the war
Their military lands their reason all that the people have speculated about for decades
Got their acid test in the first month
Places like the battles of the Frontiers where
Those sort of high-minded academic debates
Military war colleges about whether or not
Charging Cavalry will have any sort of a role on a modern Battlefield with machine guns and everything I mean that kind of stuff gets test
In the first month of the war and the results are of course
Bloody and decisive even if they won't be absorbed writer
The naval side of this war hasn't had this kind of nasty
Little encounter one of the Falkland Islands another one
Dogger Bank between a few Cruisers here in a battle cruiser
To there
But nothing like what's going to happen
And when you realize how
Careful these animals are being
Because of the nature Naval Combat I mean
You could provide an opportunity for someone to get a lucky punch if you're not careful so none of these Admirals wants to go out
Unless they have in it
Unless they have an advantage on their side favorable conditions
The British don't have to do anything
Cuz they got this blockade going so worst case scenario if things just stay as they are there wearing the Germans down
They're going to create
Disintegration
August 8th just like we told you
Nina was the goal now of these leader
You know if the Germans begin to starve at home
And the caloric intake is already being reduced for their civilians you will see revolution in the street so this Brie
Free strategy blockade will eventually bring Germany
So it's incumbent upon the Germans to do something
That situation when they get their new album reinhart's year in 1916 who wants to be more aggressive
He decides to create his own at
Weather conditions
For his own advantage
John the naval battle
Reset the traps
In late May
1960 Nissan S14 what he hopes will be a Detachment of big British warships
Five or six
Battle Cruisers
And entice them past your submarines are into your mind field
Or into an area where they think they can Feast on some of your light forces and then pounce on them with your big fat
But that's what sheer plan
Things to do
Three sets out all these forces
Appears this little ambush
And what he doesn't know
Is it the British as we said
Are reading all these Naval communication
Are the British the greatest cryptographers on the planet
Or is that just the 20th century sort of
Coloring my view
Because boy with a great the 20 Century in the second world war they will famously be reading all the German Enigma traffic among other things
In this war in the first couple of months of German Naval codes fall into their hands
And while they may not be
Deciphering every single message
Winning Tire
German high seas Fleet as it's called hundred ships about
Decides to weigh anchor and go out in a looking to play in the North Sea
The British know about that Dobby big Communications bikes and everything
So when she decides to sit this ambush
The British reading the naval codes tell the fleet guess what the Germans are out there
And they don't know that we know they're out there and so the British Grand Fleet things okay now we have the advantage we will
Crap
The Trappers
And so the British Grand Fleet which is like 28
You know super dreadnoughts and dreadknots I mean it's the biggest Fleet in the world it's the most powerful Fleet in world history up to this
West Point
And in terms of size and tonnage it may be the biggest feet ever
It weighs anchor it starts making its way to where this Ambush point is
And it leaves so early by the way because it's got all this Advanced information
But it totally screws up a lot of Admiral shares Ambush cuz his forces and who had these submarines that were going to be
Outside the British ports and they could shoot at the
British ships as they left the harbor none of that stuff ready
And so the the British ships make their way to the Rendezvous point where the with the Germans
And you're setting up another Trafalgar he I mean if the British
Emerges
Interview and catches the German Fleet there you could sink half of it before they get away
And then
Murphy's Law
Joins the battle movies not take Center Stage
In this encounter by the way which would have made a great dress rehearsal
Early 20th century Naval Warfare
Unfortunately it's opening night
And you know
You have troubles on opening night with all of the Loose Ends that haven't been fixed yet imagine instead of opening night you're doing the dress rehearsal
And yet you have 250 ships in about 15 square miles when these things come together mean
Things that can go wrong and do go wrong effect this battle mightily and it's a good argument for why these apples
Those are so cautious they know this
Murphy's Law intervenes while the British
Are about to pounce on the German because of British send a message back to their intelligence service one of the confirmation of this or that
Any intelligent people reading the German Naval codes tell them that they made a mistake earlier
They said oh yeah the German fleets not at Sea like we thought they're still safely in Port don't worry about it
So now these Admirals who 5 minutes ago knew where the German fleet was and we're ready to pounce on it
Don't know they're there anymore
But of course
They are
And so now we have both main fleets
Close to each other in the North Sea
None of them aware of the other's existence
So the rhythm of this battle of Jutland
Is wonderful starts off as a trap
Flips into a counter trap and now it is serendipitously morphed into
An encounter battle
And that's how it get started
German light forces on one side of the horizon
British light forces on the other side of the horizon
Spot a civilian
Trawler
Between the two of them they can't see each other cuz they're so far away the curvature of the earth limit their site but they can both see the trawler
Bud light units
Unit conversion the trolley to investigate it discover each other start shooting and send messages back to the main Fleet saying guess what
I found over here on the other side of the horizon
The enemy Fleet right
This creates like a war Vortex were all these
Naval forces start converging on this area
Ships that arrived first
Are the battle
This is an interesting side of the story because the battlecruisers
Are experiencing a test right now
And it's the test of whether or not the Admiral that backed this entire
Design
In the decades before this.
What correct about it
This is a theoretical argument until there's data
There hasn't been a chance to have any data now we're going to have data
Are these ships viable
But first of all you need to know what they are and battlecruiser is a hybrid design
It's supposed to combine
The punching power of a battleship
With the speed of a cruiser
So if a battleship is like some
Giant
Lion
For exam
Or tiger
These battle Cruisers are more like panthers
Now this is going to be confusing because they are all named after like giant cats and so
The flagship of this battle cruiser Squadron on the British side of the lion so don't get confused if I start talking about
About the lion
But that describes him pretty well
The hypothetical problem here though
Is that you had to give up
To get the speed of a cruiser
You had to give up the armor of the battleship
So what we have here is a
Ship with all the Striking power of a battleship
But one that can't take
A punch by a battle
Or
Its counterparts
Another battle cruiser
When this was pointed out before the war the Admirals who liked the battlecruiser concept
Waived off this worry by saying don't worry
Speed will be their armor
And that's where the argument is because nobody knows if speed will be there armor
Bees battlecruisers approach this battle at 26 or 27 not
Which is
Amazingly fast worship their size there are six of them on the British side
Five of them on the German side and when they meet
They begin to open fire
And only about like eight miles which is short
The British have the longer-range guns by the way
But don't open fire first this becomes the first of many things
That the British Admiral of these battle cruiser the guy named 80 will be critiqued about
You know after this battle
The battle opens up in about
3:45 in the afternoon
Visually
It is hard to see
The ships
If you actually see a picture of them at Full Tilt are smoking like they're on fire and when you have a bunch of them there
Putting tons of this dark suit into the air
Add to that the fact that were over by Denmark
In the North Sea
There's fog
They're squalls there's mist
There's rain is all kinds of things that inhibit
The ability to see very well
And sometimes one Fleet
Will be in a position where they see the other Fleet really well but the other Fleet doesn't see them and vice versa so the
Part of being a good animal is trying to arrange your Fleet
So that the other Fleet is highlighted against the horizon or in some way that makes them an easier Target and your Fleet is kind of a
Sheraton hard to hit
But ships had not tried to shoot at each other and some of the ranges they're going to try to shoot at each other here
Boonies battlecruiser start shooting at about 3:45
The British
Cute long
Initially over the heads of the German ships the German ships are disconcertingly accurate
They strike the battlecruiser Tiger
Like 6 times in quick succession with 11 inch shells
Anaphora
They strike the flagship
The lion with Admiral baby on board
The shells penetrate
The terror
Which is the
Sort of armored bubbled
That contains the big guns
The turret either explodes or catches on fire and there are photographs by the way
Moments in the Battle of Jutland are not great and I always imagined them
Zoomed in and colorized
But you can see the lion burning
And it looks bad
And Admiral Beatty didn't realize at the time how closely he came
To being blown to Kingdom Come
To find out later
That
A guy who was dying and who lost both his legs
On the line
Save the ship by flooding the magazine the last order he gave was to
Flood the whole area
Where the
Explosives
To keep them from
Blowing the ship
Now if Beatty was wondering what it would be like to see one of these
Modern
Amazing ships
Explode
He only had to wait about two minutes
You actually look at the
Moment-by-moment rundown of this battle and that's part of the fun of naval battle
All these ships kept
Very
Descriptive and detailed logs about their movement Moment by Moment by moment they've reconstructed this entire battle
From almost each individual ships viewpoint
And the part that strikes you when you read a rundown as how quickly everything is happening to
Baby suffers this hit on his own turret like for 2 minutes later
Thms in the figurative
A somewhere in the 20000 tonnes
A battle cruiser
Explode
Just explode in the moment
It's Churchill in the admiralty is nightmare come true
In a blink of an eye
You have a towering Cloud reaching up like 1500 ft Witnesses say you could see
Pinotage
Tunnels in guns and everything shooting up
Into the horizon
And both sides German and British watch this happen together
Out of the more than 1000 Sailors aboard the independable to
Survive
It's hard not to include an account by one of them
I did not include an account of the Survivor
I'm a ship whose magazine gets penetrated
And explode with him on it I guess he was way up high in the top observational are these still call that a crow's nest he said
180 ft High
His name is
Foamer
And here's how he described the explosion of the HMS indefatigable
While he was on board
Quote
There was a terrific explosion aboard the ship
The Magazine's went
I saw the guns go up in the air just like matchsticks
12-inch guns
Bodies and everything
She was beginning to settle down
Within half a minute the ship turned right over and she was gone
I was 180 feet up and I was thrown well clear of the ship otherwise I would have been sucked under
I was practically unconscious
Turning over really
At Last I came on top of the water
When I came up there was another fellow named Jimmy Green
And we got a piece of wood
He was on one end and I was on the other end
A couple of minutes afterwards some shells came over
And Jim was minus his head
So I was left on my lonesome
And quote
Now
About 20 minutes after that
The HMS Queen Mary another one of these battlecruiser
Explode
Same way I mean a little bit different minute she gets hit and then there's this pause and
Sailors are jumping into the water and then she explodes
We're accounts from Sailors who were in the water who said the sky was all of a sudden just filled with all this massively heavy debris
It was now falling down on them in the water
They're all diving into the water trying to
Escape giant funnels and big metal objects falling on them
And probably a lot of them didn't this guy
Again more than a thousand
I'll be Sailors on board a small handful
Rescued after
Less than less than 25
And at one point
Admiral Beatty turns to a subordinate said there seemed to be something wrong with our bloody ships today
Detroit
They're not passing
The acid test the hypothesis
That you know was the philosophical underpinnings of this entire class of Warships at least on the British side it
Proven to be
Floss
They don't have enough
Armor
Speed is not turning out to be there armor
And when their Armor gets pierced
Yeah the way they're handling this ammunition and the lack of flash protectors and some other things means
The magazine is catching on fire exploding way too easily
And you can tell that it's happened too easily become a German side it's not happen
They sacrificed
In some other areas
If their guns are smaller
They're a little slower
In order to
Slap some more armor over some of these vulnerable point and are not blowing up
Again these Germans build ships like
Mercedes and they're taking a pounding
While they are run
Away
That's what you have to notice and what's happening at these battling of these ships are not stationary they're not anchored and staying in the same spot there
All movie
And they're all moving in a specific Direction the
British are chasing the Germans and the Germans are moving away
Now if you were the British Admiral this makes perfect sense to you you've got the bigger ships right and then till they start explode
Going around you you have more of them
Besides that you have a bunch of big brand new the newest
Most awesome battleships in the world are Queen Elizabeth class
I've already mentioned
Warspite Malaya Valiant all these famous ships that will all fight in the Second World War
They're Fresh Off The Docks 15 inch guns 30,000 tons 13 inch of armor end
Baby's got them with him
So you darn right these Germans are going to run away never mind that
You know I tried to communicate with those battleships using
Flags
Let me talk about Murphy's Law
Interposing its will on this battle
Part of it has to do with things that just looks so silly
Ships have radio
Sometimes these animals are not that cool about using
Sometimes it have problems by the way so sometimes they're blameless
But a lot of times these animals are like the old
Guy trying to use the computer
And there's so much more comfortable with the way they were brought up in and the things that they did in the Maneuvers in peace
One of the ways these the ships communicate
Is by running the orders of the Admiral up on a flagpole they have all these different flags and each one means something different so many ads
I don't want to communicate
You know to the fleet his order they run a flag up the flagpole on his ship the flagship
And then every other ship is supposed to as they see it run up the same one and you get the message across
But this is a method that was used a hundred years before
And Lord Nelson's time when they're fighting Napoleon
It ranges
That are exponentially shorter does that make sense exponentially shorter than the distances in this battle
Went out to smoke and all these other things
In the peacetime training it seemed to work fine
In the rigors of combat
It's not working fine
And the big battleships don't see the flag change
When Beatty tells him to do things and they're not here
When this
Battle first half as they've been playing catch-up the whole bottle but now you know they're arriving on the scene and their shells are falling soda by the germ
Herman's now
The British think they've got these German battlecruisers pin down even if you know you're losing a few of your battle Cruisers while you
Chase them
But what they don't know is the throwing battlecruisers
Are leading them into the mall
The entire German Navy which is coming up from about 40 miles away moving towards them
What started off
As the German trap
Slipped into the British counter trap
Evolved and morphed into the encounter battle
As now
By almost
Improvisational lock
Become a German
Ambush
If successful
The German Fleet could wipe out
Four or five battlecruisers
And four of the newest ships
In the British Navy
It would be I'm sure Winston Churchill would say after I could speak for him here
Catastrophe
And the Germans are on the verge of making it happen
And then
A light Cruiser
Scouting For the British
See the entire German Fleet
On the horizon
And radios the message back to Admiral Beatty in the grand Fleet under Admiral jellicoe farther away
And baby sees those Germans very quickly to with the naked eye
The first thing he does when he realizes he's been baited into this trap is turn his battlecruisers 108
80 degrees in the other direction and start
Booking out of there
Once again
Annie's law
Say that many times in this battle if I
Go to deeply into it once again he runs up the flag sang turn around and the big battleships the brand new ones.
I don't see it and they will end up exposed out there to the entire German Fleet for a while taking a pounding and dishing
One out to it should be pointed out
Nonetheless
What Admiral Beatty has done by turning 180 degrees away
Is
Turn himself into bait
And the Germans are following
And baby is running back towards his big
Fleetwood just coming up from also about 40 miles away so now he's flipped the Ambush once again
And now the Germans are heading toward the only Fleet that is still invisible on this Naval Base
Battlefield to anyone
The Germans don't know that
Does the British Grand Fleet
But now the British Grand Fleet nose
But the Germans are
An admiral Jellico
In-N-Out in a very brave move them he's operating without enough information once again I'm real baby gets blamed for not
Giving him your good positional information or what not
A lot of This falls into the category of
It's a dress rehearsal of these guys a lot of their errors are the kind of things they would have corrected
If they had a chance to practice it in
Combat situations
Unfortunately these are a lot of you know you wouldn't call them rookie mistake but but you would correct these before the next battle nonetheless
Jellico takes a chance
Deploys
The entire British Grand Fleet with chinos
More than a hundred ships over
1520 square miles of ocean
It takes 15 to 20 min
That's how well-trained this weed is
He deploys the whole thing
And he's waiting for the Germans to arrive in the Germans are now in the Mist
Write this battlefields marry Misty and you will you run through fog Banks you won't see things for a while
And the Germans can't see what's going on
And famously Admiral hipper who's the German Admiral in charge of the battlecruiser
Radios
Admiral Scheer the head of the entire German Navy who's with the German Fleet here
And he famously looks off in the Mist until sheer
Something lurks in that soup
We would do well not to thrust into it too deeply
Too late
The first thing that happens is
Is the German start taking some fire and they don't know from where big guns
And then all of a sudden the Mist parts for a second
And it's a another British battlecruiser
The invincibles
And as soon as the Mist Parts in the Invincible becomes clear
It doesn't take 90 seconds before big German guns
Are opening fire the shells pouring down on the Invincible and like the other two battlecruisers the
Vincible explode
So if anybody has forgotten in the intervening
You know an hour or two since the earlier battlecruisers exploded that this design is proving to be someone
What flawed
The explosion of the Invincible before the two main fleets Collide is a
Historical reminder
Nonetheless it's only
Soon after that the Germans emerge from the Mist
Defined
The entire deployed British Fleet
Waiting
For the men like a crescent around the Horizon and Shear says
The minute that they can see what's happening the entire Horizon erupts in a sheet of flame
The Bishops are long way from each other almost invisible to the naked eye smudges up against the horizon
You see like the smoke of all the ships
And then you see like the flash of the guns and just like lightning and thunder where you see the lightning and then there's this.
Play in the Thunder ride
Same thing you see this Flash and it's
Silent
And then boom the boom hit you after the shells of already passed over
You know there are destroyers in these battle giving the talk about all the light ships running around you know sooner parrying and like
A bunch of little gnats
Between the battle Fleet
And these destroyers sometimes describe what it's like when he's giant shells
Pass over their heads and they say they sound like a locomotive
When they Screech over your little ships head
But when they fall in front of your little ship you're like your little Destroyer
They raised geysers of water
Sometimes 500 sometimes 200 feet up into the air and it's composed of
Tons of liquid
Which then falls back down to earth in these destroyers these little ships
Are sometimes beaten up pretty severely by all this water
Smashing back down into them some people are
Splashed overboard and all these kinds of
Nonetheless
Admiral jellicoe has performed a famous Naval maneuver that you never want to be on the receiving end of Paul Crossing
The tea where he's formed
The top crossbar the tea and poor Sheeran the Germans form
In a vertical line of the T in every one of the British ships
Can fire on the German ships individually is they
Come to the front of the line it's a disaster
Very quickly she ever gets hit with more than 22 heavy shells fast and within 10 minutes she or has
Quite
Tactically
Adroitly by the way turned his Fleet around and disappeared back into the Mist
And once again without radar and all that kind of stuff
A hard to you know where he is at that point he sends out a bunch of light units in destroyers and what not to cover his Escape so the
The British can't just run after the midnight run into a bunch of torpedoes in mines and stuff
An inexplicably not to
How long after the she arrives back into visual range and Little People fire again
Ashera escapes again cuz he got his T crossed for a second time in one battle which is almost unheard of it shows your jellicoe
Cuz pretty darn good Abril
And then there's a little night action between the light units
What about this time Admiral shares had enough
You get your T crossed twice in one day
It's time to call it a battle
Ed Sheeran the Germans manage
To limp home
When all is said and done the British lose three battle Cruisers
Three armored Cruisers
N8 Destroyers
While one German battle cruiser
1 pre Dreadnought Battleship for light Cruisers in 5 destroyers are sent to the body
The casualties at Jutland
Are not significant they don't hurt either Navy badly
The British learn their lesson about the battlecruiser design
But the Germans are humbled
You know they don't come out again in strength mean if it'll be a little encounter here in a little try there but but this is it
They gave it an attempt
And
They seemed permanently shaking
The German service
Will not perform another militarily significant
Move
In the war
The only part of the German Navy that's going to be relevant
For the rest of the war
Is the party
That uses TWRP
Peatos
To go out
You're not military Target
But economic
By 1960
The economic side of this war
Is coming to
The four
We begin to see
What
War on this scale is like when it becomes
Heart of the normal life of all of these countries you know
This isn't a new phenomenon anymore by 1916
By the middle of 1916 we've been doing this for 2 years
And it's been sucking up more and more of the energy of these
Nation states are involved in the conflict
It's very unlike the way most wars
By these Powers have been fought where the civilian population might not even know what war is happening
If it was happening they certainly weren't directly
Or importantly impacted
This war is different
First of all it's life or death
The stakes are so high that everybody's involved in the armies
Are requiring such an immense amount
Stop
Have the Germans call this material slot
The Wharf
Material
Set the entire civilian population in the production capacity of all these countries
Gets warped trying to provide it
As historian
Gwynne Dyer says
Quote
It is significant that the phrase
Homefront
Came into use during World War 1
When the role of Munitions workers in the civilian production more generally
Was becoming as important to Victory of the soldiers in the trenches
Without a constant flow of supplies
Equal to the vast consumption at the front
The soldiers would soon be helpless
And since the mobilization of so huge and number of men left vast gaps in the normal Workforce
Lansing put 20% of its entire population in the uniform Germany 18% and the other major power
There's not much less
The remaining adults civilians
Had to be directed by government into whatever jobs were needed to keep production going
In effect
Disability in economy he writes
Was conscripted to
The governments of Europe quickly took control over labor and raw material
Imposed rationing on all scarce goods and created true War economy
Women flooded into factories to replace the men at the front and most production beyond the basic needs of subsystem
Was diverted into the war effort
And quote
Dyer is also the
The one
It said by this time quote
Battles had become an industrial operation in reverse
In which the rates of Destruction at the front
Match the rates of production in the industries at home
And quote
I think if guys like
The British military leader
Hey
Or even the German military leader
General Erich von falkenhayn
And I think about all these skills
That they required to have now
Above and beyond what you would think of is a normal generals
Skills
And you saw this in earlier Wars as famous stories of General Sherman
In the Civil War in the United States being
Extra qualified for Modern Warfare because of all these failed
Jobs in Private Industry he'd had the taught him all these lessons that no one knew a general would need in modern
Things about logistics
Stuff like that
But by 1916
A guy like Hague
A Cavalry commander looks like he would be
Totally out of his element
Dealing with the modern
Production needs of warfare as indeed he was
Duncan Hines a bit more scientific of a guy
And he's trying to think if I were General fault
World war game
You know what played a lot of those in my time
And I got assigned
Because I don't think I would take Germany if I had a choice of
On which side of the war game Germany I command play Germany in this war game and I'm fall
Valkenhayn
You know the estimates are especially during this time. If you include the colonial subjects of the of the power
Hours in Europe during this time.
My enemies in this war if I'm falkenhayn have 750 million people
They can call on
You know for their value in their effort and
In some cases their lives
My side of the alliance has about a hundred and fifty
50 million
My enemies have the greatest Fleet in the world and I just learned at the Battle of Jutland that my Navy can't come anywhere near touching them
And they shut down all of my overseas trade
So fine General falkenhayn already I'm sitting here going
Wow
Now you look at the lineup in terms of the kind of countries in each Alliance which of the British and the French in the Russian
Can just a three big guys
In the
Allied entendre
Alliance theatre all first-rate powers Bessie power best land power
Biggest power all three together
Wow and then a bunch of other countries like Italy and and smaller powers
That's a very powerful force who do I have on my side
Austria Hungary Bulgaria and turkey
Steve bacic
None of those powers are first
At least the turkey
Start asking me for help all the time
Vulcan 900
They're putting on a pretty brave fight they've managed to
Kick the British French
South African Indians
New zealanders and Australian out of Gallipoli
In January 1916
Not unexpected
They managed to beat the British forces mostly Indian troops in a place called coot in modern-day Iraq
Trap them in a fortress they are forced into surrender
And
Took them on a Death March but it really
Doesn't impact falkenhayn very much one way or the other
It's just nice for him to know that the Turks are winning as opposed to losing because they are losing against the Russians but it's a mixed bag
Remember the Turks are tough
But they are
Not quite a twentieth-century army so those are all gravy
Valkenhayn
The bigger problem if your falkenhayn is your
Close allies the austro-hungarian
Pain in the rear
They don't listen to you to begin with your having fights with their main military leader
And then they go do what they want anyway and then they screw up cuz they didn't follow your advice and then they come to you and so will you be able to
Without your falkenhayn there pain in the rear
He's continually having to take
Scarce troop from places like Verdun
And instead
Taking the train sending them over Easton
Saving the austro-hungarians bacon
Can't really blame them though they're in big trouble
Anyway they may not have been a country in 1920 even if there hadn't been a first World War
Are made up of 11 major ethnic groups in that state
Some of them don't want to be there
And their army is a microcosm of their state
And you got troops who don't even want to be in your Empire at times
On the front line that you're asking to die
For your Empire
It's not a good situation they're constantly getting into trouble in his
1 German Diplomat famously says about Germany's situation
With Austria-Hungary
We are fettered to occur
What tie do a dead guy
And that's the austro-hungarian force now in your favor if you're falkenhayn
You probably have the best army in the world
The 1916
German Army is
It's a combination
Of the best aspects of the 1914 force that Germany went to war with
But battleheart
Buy Xperia
You're the way writer in passing
Describes it quote
It is true that the German Army on the Western Front by early 1916 was more skilled and better equipped
For trench warfare the neither the British or the French
This is not too surprising he says
And the British expeditionary force it only just expanded its Army from around 250,000
In 1914 to just over a million largely inexperienced men
And the Frenchie right had always been uncomfortable with the notion of defensive operations rather than the offense
Two spirit
Ethan says
Quote many of the German Veterans of the inconclusive though bitter fighting at Ypres
New Hampshire Powell Artois champagne and Lewis in 1915 have survived
And stiffened in army that have been well let at the sharp end
And remain Resolute against Allied efforts in the West
He didn't come close to beating the Russian armies on the Eastern front in that year also
He's short as John terrain has noted it must never be forgotten that the German army of that. Was very
And quote
So that's what you were
To the table
Is that enough
Is having the best army in the world enough
By the way that's something you traditionally
Think of when you think of the French
But it's safe to say I think that since about 1870
The Germans have the best army in the world
Will that compensate for all the downsides of the Central Powers have
Hard to know
One of the worst is the fact that the left hand and the right hand don't know what each other were doing in the Central Powers
The austrians go off the reservation all the time don't tell anybody but they're doing don't get any approval don't work together with anyone
And it's a handicap
Especially when
The Allies / aunt and forces are pretty darn good at this
They have an agreement that they made in 1915 to come to the aid of each other when hard-pressed
When the Germans launch Verdun
Within a month
The Russians come riding to the rescue in Lithuania trying to help
They launched an offensive that they are clearly not ready for and how could you be that would be very
Short time in this period to a planned
Stocked up for carried out an offensive
March 1916 the Russians throw human wave attacks at the Germans
And predictably get mowed down
The Germans
You're looking at the corpses thought these people totally untrained can infer
As though the Russians were willing to throw tons
Human meat
At the Germans simply to scare them enough so that they would pull some units out of her down and take some pressure off the French
It was so inept
That some of the casualties of Russian soldiers suffered were because of
Being shelled by their own sides artillery which is always a tree
And
12000 Russian soldiers froze
In one night
Lolis were wounded
Bought a bunch of people that just you know where out there in the cold without the proper stuff I mean the Russian Logistics are
Traditionally pretty horrible especially in this.
It shows you the nature
Of
An operation
The Russians are not
Generally thought of his handling these sorts of things well
And
In
March 1916
They don't handle it well again
The worst part probably from the Russian respect
That way they went to all that trouble and it didn't take any pressure off the
Ever done
The
Follow-up effort though by the Russians
On June 4th 1916
Will be handled
Much better surprisingly well if you're a guy like falkenhayn
And you've written off with a lot of your other generals any
Chance the Russians have doing anything significant 219
On June 4th 1916 the Russians do something very significant
Led by their unquestionably best General in the first World War
A guy named
Brusilov
Weed mentioned in an earlier episode that the Russians
Simply couldn't.
I mean they weren't they were okay sometimes on the defense but they couldn't attack
The problem
Is always the same they just have
Such an old-fashioned not up to date
Logistics system that the farther
You moved away from where you started the harder it was to get the supplies necessary for a modern Army to run
But where she loved
Is the most modern Commander the Russians have
He's been learning from fighting the best army in the world the Germans all this time
And even that was a Cavalry
Commander and they have a reputation for always being sort of old-fashioned
We're still out and braces
The new systems out there in the new technology for example
He does something almost no Russian army ever does in the first world war he uses aircraft
To help as spotters in to locate positions behind the lines in for reconnaissance
Right there
He's acting in a much more Modern Way than Russian armies do remember we talkin about an army
That for the entire length of the first World War
Will still be wearing cloth cap they never get
Metal helmet
During the duration the first world war is a very old-fashioned fashioned Army
Takes what he can do that's modern and uses it
The launch is his famous offensive named after him
On June 4th and he does so with a very modern artillery barrage intense but short
He's used also to camouflage to
Hide his intentions even as far as
Painting
Fake trenches on the ground
Behind his lines to confuse
The Germans in the austro-hungarians on the other side
And when he launches his attack
He does so along
An enormous front
The Eastern Front different than the Western Front
Disturbing this really constrained
Small area which they can build a wall from side-to-side really easily it's a huge error
So it's much more thinly defended in leprosy love does
Is he attacks across this giant front with a half million men
Intending to break upon the defenses of the central powers like a wave breaks on a Breakwater
And knowing that in many places his forces will get pushed backwards
But where he meets weakness they should burst through here's the way
Writer GJ Meyer explains
What happens
On June 5th
When
Hours after the artillery bombardment starts
The half-million Russian forces step out of their trenches and move toward the
Mostly austro-hungarian line but they were German troops to
Quote
Is infantry when it attacked on June 5th found the austrians in confusion
Hit advanced
Stunned them with its scope extending as a did along a line of more than 250 miles
She loves the idea was that by attacking everywhere
He was sure to find holes somewhere
And he had moved his reserves scant though they were
Close enough to the front so that they can exploit opportunities as soon as any appeared
And quote
He continues
Quote
And the result was from the first hour
That's accessible most incredible magnitude
The austro-hungarian 4th Army disintegrated when hit
71000 of its men more than half the Army were killed wounded or captured
The seventh was wrecked even more completely
Losing 133000 men
He was the same almost everywhere
After three days
Priscilla found himself in possession of three hundred thousand prisoners
Before the end of the week
More than half of the Austrian Defenders have become casual
And quote
Priscilla
Chatter
The Austrian
And then he ran into the typical problem
Any Russian Commander runs into
The inability of the Russian army and government
To get him enough stuff fast enough for him to not slow down and have his offensive Peter out
But this maneuver
Add a domino like effect
On the war
Because at Verdun
Falkenhayn now had a crisis on his hands in the east
Where he was going to have to pull troops out of Verdun
To go save the austro-hungarian Army which was to centigrade
And let's understand
The austro-hungarian forces we told you about those
Those troops
Who were a microcosm of the
Empire is a whole who didn't want to be there you had whole units and I mean battalions regimen
I'm slob
Throw down their weapons and surrender to the Russians who by the way are slobs
To let us not forget
That this War began when a Slavic National assassinated the austro-hungarian air.
The throne right and now we're asking slobs to fight for that
Empire
Many of them threw down their weapons they didn't want to die and they certainly do more die fighting with an Empire and they certainly didn't want to die
Fighting for the empire
Against their Slavic brethren
In fact some of these units
Are said to have jumped into the trenches with the Russians turned around and trained their guns back on the side they had J
Defected
The Germans will manage to contain with their wonderful Army the Russian threat
And they will
Halt murcielagos advance and even deal with defeat
To the Russians
But already the single-minded focus
Falkenhayn on Verdun has been shattered
The Russians who put in such a wonderful effort in the brusilov offensive in did such terrible damage to the austrians
Suffered immensely though while doing so
Well over a million cash
You suffered in the brusilov offensive
Which once again takes the Russians
And begins to ratchet up the level of dissatisfaction getting them closer and closer
To the breaking point you can almost feel it in the air in 1916 a couple of these major powers are
Are within one good punch of going down
In the spring of nineteen
French
Military leader Joseph Shaffer tells his British counterpart
The prince
Is one of those
Within a good shot
Remember
Yeah by this time they've had a month or two at Verdun the French of suffered like 200,000 casualty
And at least this early.
2 months
Into 10 but no
Nobody knows it yet
At the Battle of Verdun it looks like the German leader Falcon Heinz plant
Lead the French army white is working
Why you can't take your eyes off
The first world war there like to Prizefighter
I just when you think one guys taking over the fight the other guy went a good shot in somebody's knees buckle
And spring of 1916 dropper tails
Sir Douglas Haig
The current command
British forces
It's ran Sweeney's
The urges Hague
Just start that summer offensive that he's been planning for a long time on the River Song
Early
And if you don't start early
The French army will cease to exist
Exist
Get so worked up
We're told
He can only be
Consoled and calm down with
Lots
1840 Bland
The year 18
Jafra
Nonetheless
Taig speeds up the
Big offensive
Plan for the sunroof
1916 discussed with all the other allies in late 1915 this is a
Long-term plan and he's going to launch it early
This long-term plan
Results in the most controversial piece
From the British standpoint
Of this whole War maybe of
British military history innocent
Priority
First of all
Douglas Haig you have to
Field Marshal
Choppers talking to is the new guy
Just like most of the great powers
In the first world war by 1916 they've fired
The person that got them into
That's right
Dewar's terrible
Everybody's
Your predictions were wrong nobody's fighting it well so one by one all these countries are sacking the people
They got them into this
The Russians dropped there at the Germans have falkenhayn cuz they got rid of on mold count while the war was in its early phases
The French still have Joffrey
Crazily enough
But
You know about reputation of the miracle of the Marne in 1914 only
Carry you so far I didn't have long
To go either
And the British in late 1950s actor John friends like we told you the last episode
The guy who gets his gig is a guy named Douglas Haig
If you feel Marshall he's another one of these Cavalry Commanders
It's always weird we have a war Cavalry become something you keep off to the side and don't use cuz it just gets killed
And the horses are more important to move
Stop
Is crazily enough
And we haven't talked enough about this and will get to it
Horses are everywhere there's
Millions of them in this war
And your casualties too by the way
But all these Cavalry commanders French Hague all these guys have these visions that we're going to
Break the German line somewhere in the Cavalry going to go rushing in the hole we create
I'm going to the back and it's
It's D
Free
Univera macht
Armor Blitz
Krieg
Version of that
That's a strategy that's been used throughout his
Go back to
Dupree Alexander trying to smash the Cavalry into the hole in roll up the line
It was great before you have motor vehicles and that's what these Cavalry commanders are still dreaming of
2 years into the war that puts the final nail into the coffin to the idea that this Cavalry has any
Offencive rolled
All you have to remember
It still is the fastest moving thing on the battlefield in large numbers you're starting to get motor vehicles but
The top of the motor vehicles to handle to rain in the very unreliable horses are still the fastest Mobility you have so their value
Table just for that
Tortelloni very vulnerable
Stories of
Dead horses
Is in the suffering
Five animals
In the story
Is under
Disgust
Douglas Haig the new British
Cavalry commander
Has at his disposal some of the largest really the largest armies
Did Britain has ever had ready to go to war
Because those volunteers
It started joining when
Lord Horatio Kitchener you remember the British military leader from the beginning of war the guy who when you see his picture
Scream
19th century
Man
I mean it was a giant mustache from another are you can almost see him in a British Redcoat
And he's the big face in the recruiting poster telling Britain's patriotic Britain's to sign up for king and country and a shilling
Kitchener's another one of these prewar
Early war generals military leader who's been tarred by
You know their conduct in the war they don't they don't end up looking so genius like when the first world war gets done
Body right
So is kitchener's reputation to starting to wane he still
Got
And one real feather in his cap and that's
Those armies that he helped recruit in 1914 and 1915 and that he is
Protected like a
Proud parent
Don't send it to Gallipoli don't send her the Western Front early don't throw them in the meat grinder like everything else save them and real
Really make use of their patriotic contribution did people want to win the war let's put them in a position where they can do that
He done an admirable job of that in about three weeks before
Those
Soldiers known sometimes as the Kitchener armies are the Kitchener divisions after him
Are going to lose the guy
That was probably most responsible for seeing that they weren't used up already in the first place
Kitchener dies about 3 weeks before his Legions
Arthro Ninja
Frye
It's a crazy story
I'm told that it is the same
Has any one of those big modern deaths
So the same as a
Princess Lady Diana dying
Or Winston Churchill dying or JFK died in the United States you said yourself you remember when that happened in Britain's of the.
Remember where they were when they heard
Lord Horatio Kitchener British military leader in almost
Demigod
At the beginning of the war
Has gone down at sea
Warship on the way to Russia
On some military mission
And the boat goes down at night
In a force nine Gale
After hitting a mine
And there are
Survivors who say take this with
Did they saw
Kitchener on the deck as the ship went down impassively sort of accepting his fate
And you're standing on the deck of the ship goes
In a beneath the waves
That really work
19th century military
Mutation doesn't it
Nonetheless there have been conspiracy theories ever since about
Believe it or not
It's one of the great conspiracy
The fountainheads to come out of the first world war nonetheless it meant the three weeks later when kitchener's you know
Parentally preserved armies are finally
Thrown into The Fray
He's not there to have any saying
The guy who is
Is Douglas Haig the new guy
Now known to some in history as
The butcher
So that should give you an idea of what we're about to get into here on a wide variety
The fronts
This battle is won the Sir Douglas Haig has been preparing for since the year before
When the French told him
They were in danger of disintegrating he's moving up something he's been working on for a while now at everyone
Nose it
The big 1916 offensive
Is no secret haakenson newspapers basic
Remix that we find out all the ways that everybody knew this was coming
It makes you wonder right again how intelligent it is to be launching something that everybody knows it's coming but
It couldn't really be helped if you're going to fight
At this spot on the Somme River with a British
And the French
Horses meat
On the Western Front with with a British line ends in the French line begins
That's where they're going to hold this joint defensive maybe for the sole reason that that's where both armies
That would be a really silly reason
2 attack
The greatest defenses on the Western Front which of the greatest defenses ever in the world
Right now these are defenses that make the old Roman
Uline
And that you would cross Europe with these giant wall I mean
Minor
There's never been defense
That the Germans are at the point now
Where they're building Creature Comforts into their
Fortified line I mean they're putting wallpaper on and they've got electric lights and ventilation and then running water
I mean it's crazy that the trenches are in some cases all line with wood boards
Done with about as much Theron this is the Germans are known for
These are huge modern fortifications in some sense in these Germans on the other side of this line with the French and the British were thinking
King about launching this big 1916 offensive
Have bunkers that are 30 and 40 feet underground
Cut into the chalk of these Hills
Did the Germans occupy
They're looking down
4 months
As the British load up all the stuff you now need for a modern offense of all that stuff we said that the Germans needed at Verdun
The British needed the song right the French to buy the
David laid five railroad line
The new tracks to the battlefield
Cuz that's how often and how many trains are going to be running
Just unloading stuff
4 months
3 million shells
Millions of tons of food
I mean crazy my engineering course that are building thing
Gino full on permanent structures
While the germ
Watch the whole thing and plant board and train for
They're having drills everyday
How quickly can we get up from our underground bunker and get up to the transit man the machine guns before the British soldiers were on top of us
Everybody knows this is coming
And everybody knows how it's
The British take these armies with
Many many many green troops that have never been in a battle
What time in the trenches opposite these German lines
Again
A position so strong
Winston Churchill says
It was quote undoubtedly the strongest and most perfectly defended position in the world
And start
Bombarding it with art
Start June 20
A lot of Art
As a matter of fact the song becomes one of about four or five First World War battle
They compete for like the Guinness Book of World Records
For the biggest largest worst more intense most numerous you know
Picture category artillery bombardment of the war
Serafino's a history geek I would be arguing it with other history
It's always about criteria right are we talkin about the
The largest number
Rochelle's Foxboro
Battle
4060 million at Verdun Maybe
Who are we talking about the most number of shells used in the initial part of the bat
Or the most number of she'll drop in the shortest. Of time or the smallest space I mean
There's literally a measurement of how many tons of shells fell on each square meter of these battle
By the way if you use that
As You Are
Perdon
Nonetheless the fact that
The song is in this argument
Show you the level of artillery were talking about here
And when it opens up on the 24th
It's it's incredible
When it's volume but the Germans laugh a lot
Compartment
But the Germans are mostly underground Undercover
And most of them are bent is once again
Shrapnel shell
Sounds like a little teeny point doesn't it for about a battle to turn on
But had those shells been high explosive instead or maybe even gas
This battle may go another Direction and every story and brings up
Shrapnel
Pretty much pointless
It's remember it's like a giant hand grenade or shotgun shell exploding in the air and all these little pellets
It's a ground devastating to infantry out in the open but the Germans are in the open
In addition
The artillery is meant to do more than just kill German
The artillery has to clear
The battlefield
All the stuff that
There is defenses
So let the troops on the British I can actually get to the German Trench
It's full of barbed wire
No man's land
Another train
Another no man's land in another Trench
The Trenches are all going uphill and these no man's land areas besides being filled with concrete bunkers and
Everything you told me about
Before The Killing Zone
They have yards barbed wire
Sticking your finger
Metaphysical empath
It has to be overcome by The General
The generals have figured out in their minds that an artillery barrage of this
You know caliber the amounts were talking about here in barbed wire will just explode into
It will not be an impediment when the artillery barrage is over
Except the shrapnel shell dontrel
There was a benefit
Artillery
Recorded before Napoleon has the
The great lion
Comes in handy all the time
Quantity has a quality all its own
And the sheer intensity this barrage
Life began to have an effect on the Germans even though they were physically protected from being
Do injured
I began to play on them
First of all
They know they got something really nasty awaiting them
In their future
You try to put yourself in their shoes
Okay
They know that when this artillery barrage is over
The British are going to be on them they've been training for this moment for months right run up the stairs how quickly can you get
Find the machine gun
In time to stop the British from taking over your Trench
So they're going to either
Be killed
Be grievously wounded
See your friend killed or wounded or happy
The kill someone and they're going to have a really nasty day and they're very near future
In the meantime
You going to have one of the greatest artillery barrage in history going on
Around you
Ernst Junger
Who will be at this battlefield in about a month and can artillery barrage that is not as bad as this one
He will compare it to the Roar of the ocean
He will say that there are no individual sound
He says he will it will achieve at times and last 4 hours A demented intense
And he says when it eventually calmed down
Calm down to Mere drumfire
Which is you know the sound of
Of a drum roll
What's how fast your children shelter dropping he says even when it's the drumroll you can't
Pick out any individual explosion
It's just one big loud sound
But the demented Fury did it reaches sometimes
Blows that away litter
Early and that's
The kind of intensity these soldiers are living with knowing that they've got this horrible moment in their future
And it goes on for days
We're told that
The German soldiers who were kind of laugh
At the fact that the British were using like 70% shrapnel shells on them
Aren't laughing at
They're getting tired
Prince trasimeno
Put yourself in
The position just not sleeping for 5 days
And now
You know ad
All the other thing
On top of that
So there is an effect that distorts Hillary's having in the Germans all right about
The British
Commander this part of the controversy
We're told that there were lots of people saying that this artillery barrage was going to make this a cake
And you've heard that before right
Don't all these battles begin to sound like isn't there repetitiveness to the story
If there is
You're getting the right feeling on
Because that's how
It's always been played and it seems like the people at the time fell to oh no not again haven't we seen this movie
Before the general seem to always
Just want more
Give us more artillery give us more men give us deeper defense
It will fix the situation
So here's the biggest artillery barrage the British have ever launched
They shoot off 2 million shells in node
Different comparison purposes
A hundred years
Battle of Waterloo
Napoleon is estimated to had about 20000
Cannonballs
With the French army
So you're two million shells in a week or two thousand
Crazy the level of artillery we're going to see here
A little bit Lowe's good commanders into this sense that it's going to accomplish so much more than it does
It's the soldiers on the ground though
That produce
The historical reminders
The most of them were too realistic and to Savion too cynical to buy into any of that Rosie
The generals could afford to be Rosie
The guys on the ground going in for example the first wave
Of this assault that the Germans have been waiting for you for months they know better
And you can tell because there are absolutely
Heartbreaking
Last letters home
Animated into the history
Peter Hart wonderful
Has one of these letters
From a captain Charles May
Who fights in the 22nd Manchester
He's writing to his wife
Right before he goes over the top in this battle
Nnn
Again imagine
Imagine
How would it be
That's you
To be in the position of writing a letter
That's a permanent scar on your soul even if you get
The proverbial reprieve from the governor
Right
Captain Charles May
22nd Manchester regiment
Who's about to go over the top on the first day of the song
And writes his wife
Quote
I must not allow myself to dwell on the personal
There's no room for it
Also it is demoralizing
But I do not want
Not that I mind for myself
If it be that I am to go I'm ready
But the thought that I may never see you
Or our darling baby again
Turns my bowels to water
I cannot think of it would even the semblance of equanimity
My one consolation is a happiness it's been hours
Also
My conscience is clear that I've always tried to make life a joy to you
I know at least
But if I go you will not want
That is something
What it is the thought that we may be cut off from one another which is so terrible
And there are babe May grow up without my knowing her
And without her knowing me
It's difficult to face
And I know your life without me would be a dull black
Get you must never let it become holy so
Pretty you will be left the greatest charge in all the world
The upbringing of our baby
God bless that child she's the hope of life to me
My darling au revoir
It may be that you will only have to read these lines
As ones of passing interest
On the other hand
They may well be my last message
To you
If they are
Notes for all your life that I loved you and baby with all my heart and soul
At U2 sweet things
We're just all the world to me
I pray God I made you my duty
For I know that whatever that may entail
You would not have it otherwise
Peter Hart
Remarkable
Sensitivity
Add the post
Princess quote
Charles May the loving husband of Bessie Mae and father to his baby Pauline
Wouldn T be killed the next day
He's buried in the dantzig alley british cemetery
Small-scale tragedies litter the history of War
Sad reminders that the necessities of War ruin the lives of Millions
And quote
She said
All this pain from this war
Are like pebbles dropped in water and the ripples outward
Affect the rest of these societies me Millions
The people impacted like this
The ripple effect affect
Ends or maybe even hundreds of millions of
For a while
The song becomes one of these
Pebbles
It's like Ground Zero for a huge
Ripple of
The Willows
Britain
To this day
I try to think about what mental state I would be in
After writing a
And when you think about millions of people
Young p
People mostly
Being in situation
Weather writing Al
How does that change you
When they are going to be noticeable
Changes
In this generation
In the four years during the special where I've been comparing this. To historical sgo
Right where
One generation and another Generations would have mingled
The old world and the new world
But maybe it's more of a wormhole
All Through Time
And when this nineteenth-century group of people
No transitions through the 20th century
It's not going to make it intact it's going to suffer
Damage on the way through it's like a birthing process to the modern era
And that can be bloody and painful and potentially fatal to
The British
Thought
Throughout this war
That they taken large casual
The Battle of 1915 places like Gallipoli
Those are large casual
The British which are a traditionally Naval power
An employee relatively by Continental standard
Small armies
This is the first time that
Had a large
To suffer the kind of casualties that some
Nations like the
The French or the Germans or the Russians have been suffering this whole time
On July 1st
The shelling subsides
The whistles blow
And these troops in the morning or told to get out of their trenches
I had a cross into no man's land
And continued
To take the German defense
This is where they find out
That the assumptions made in the planning stages of this conflict
Haven't come to pass the way the military
Sports assumed they would
And because of that
British forces
On the very first day
Of the battle of the Somme
Supper six
3000 cash
There's never been a day like
In British history
And now all of a sudden
They can understand how the French belt
On that August day in 1914 when they suffered 22,000 dead in an afternoon
These are Thoroughly Modern casualties in
Two people not accustomed to them they are stunning
On the finger start pointing media
What the heck happened
Generation of people who
Felt this viscerally
Have kept this debate going and it continues between historians even today
What the hell
Who's responsible
What happened to the Troops will they got out of the trenches only to find that in most areas
The assumption that this artillery would Smash Up The Wire
Wasn't true when the wire was there
It was a physical in Panama
In no-man's-land trapping troops in the open so they could be raped
By Machine Gun fire archery fire too but mainly machine-gun fire
From those Germans who were not as badly affected by the artillery either
As the planners had assumed they would be
Tens of thousands of British soldiers are being mowed down
All the time one German
On the other side
Of this human trash
I love the song on the first date
Is quoted Indian passing his book all the Kaiser's men
And he said quote
Deleting wave
A British troops
Was now halfway across no-man's-land
Get ready was passed along our front
And heads appeared over each shell crater edge of final positions were taken up with the best view
And machine guns mounted firmly in place
A moment later when the first British line was within a hundred yards
The rattle of Machine Gun and Rifle fire broke out along our whole line of shell hole
Followed soon after by deadly accurate shellfire
The advanced rapidly crumpled under this Halo shells and bullets
All along the line meant to be singing throwing up their arms and collapsing never to move again
The extended line the badly shaken with many gaps
Now came on all the faster
Instead of a leisurely walk they covered the ground in short rushes at the Double and within a few minutes the leading troops at Advance
Two within a stone's throw of our front Trench
Again and again the extended lines of British infantry broke against the German defense like waves against the cliff
Only to be beaten back
It was an amazing spectacle of unexampled gallantry courage and Bulldog determination on both sides
And quote
Now those are the troops who made it through the wire
There were places where gaps have been blown in The Wire
The problem was that the troops would congregate at those gaps cuz they're the only way to the other side
And then get stuck in giant backup this as a small stream of troops made it through the corridor
And those those backups in those Globs of soldiers just waiting for their chance to get through the corridor the wire would be mowed down
I shall fire and machine gun
This day
Has so affected the British in fact it's their version of Verdun what would Verdun is to the French sole
The song is to the British one
And it has divided historians ever since
And you can see normally calm and sedate
Rather cold sometimes British historians lose their head over this subject
John Keegan who I've said is not my favorite
But the two World Wars I think are his strong point
And you can tell he's a guy who's hung out
With some of the enlisted troops
That were trapped that day at the song because
There
Continued anger and
Incredulously about this whole thing has rubbed off on him and by the way
If you were trapped there like a Sitting Duck
On
You don't open playing in No Man's Land watching your body's get blown to bits
And you're freaking out you would be thinking to who the hell put me here
Who's responsible for this if I ever get out of this Heads Will Roll
Of course most of these
British troops at this battle or not of a
The class in British Society
Made much of a
Fast but they've got
Loyal Defenders
The will when this is over
Keegan's one of them by the way
You can you can just
Feel the anger
When he writes quote
In all the British had lost about 60000
IHome 21000 have been killed
Most in the first hour of the attack perhaps the first minutes
The Trenches wrote Robert key 50 years later now he's quoting Robert key quote
Where the concentration camps of the first World War
Kyle Keegan talks again
And though the analogy is what an academic reviewer would call unhistorical
There is something Treblinka like
About almost all accounts of the 1st of July
How about these long docile lines of young men
Shoddily uniformed
Heavily burdened
Numbered about their necks
To identify
After they were killed
Plotting forward across a featureless landscape to their own extermination inside the barbed wire
Accounts of the song he writes
Producing readers and audiences much the same range of emotions
As do descriptions of the running of Auschwitz
Guilty Fascination incredulity horror disgust
Pity and anger
And quote
Amigos
I want to say that this is not just from
The
Peaceniks
Tenderhearted out there
Not just from the military historians will you get it from either but he was but from the professional troops to
He says quote
Anger is the response which the story of the song most commonly evokes among professionals meeting soldiers
Why did the commanders not do something about it
Why do they let the attack go on
Why do they not stop one battalion following the wake of another to join it in Death
And quote
Getting goes on to say that some Italians were stop
But that's one of the things that so many people got angry about is that
Once you saw for example
That the wire was still there
Why did you let more lines of troops get up out of the trenches and follow the people who just got destroyed in from
This is how someone like Hague
Gets a reputation
Butcher
Not going out of my way in this
21915 copies General Slack
Because they're learning right this is all new stuffing
Until you experiment Louis don't know how to use
You don't know
And what it can do
When can you start holding these people accountable
Or not learning
It was a great line from
The civilian
Political leader Germany
A guy named bethmann-hollweg
He was telling the Kaiser by the end of 1916 he's talking about Falken I
Are the German millet
But it could equally apply to a lot of
Military leaders
In this war especially at the
This time
Do you have to Kaiser quote
Where does incompetency end
And criminality begin
And quote
How many lies are you allowed to lose experimenting before you learn your lesson
But there are a great many military historians today
Who are trying once again if they listen that's what they're doing
We're still holding them to too high a standard too much
Hindsight going on here
Edward Peter heart rate
Lights quote
For many people
The song in the equally ugly Verdun have come to symbolize the Great War
Futile battles fought with other people's lives by incompetent and uncaring Generals
In particular for the British she says
The disaster of the 1st of July on the song has become the sole prism through which the conduct of the whole of the Great
There is no light and shade here
Just a dark despair the numbing horror of the teeming casual
Explanations of what went wrong and why are thrust aside indeed
In the past
Subdued references to a quote and quote learning curve for the generals have been seen as an insult
How to the Dead
There remains a widespread belief he write that there must have been a better way
Something else could or should have been done someone must be blamed
Much of this appropriate has fallen on the head of Douglas Haig
Who has a Time been revealed as a mass murderer
Yet this was inevitable price of engaging in Continental Warfare on the main field of battle
Against the primary enemy
France was well accustomed to the pain of Continental Warfare
It was a new experience
Germany had no exposed flanks
Just the imposing fortifications of the Western Front defending their 1914 games rested from free
France and Belgium
Unfortunately for all their tactical Improvement and Technical Innovations
The British were just simply not able to breach those defenses
Or kill sufficient German
Even in concert with the French
Ever done
To bring Germany to its knees
And quote
It also makes you wonder
A little about the quality of the human being
Who are commanding these Endeavors were making these plans and who are watching
All these people
Die and be wounded because of these
How bad does the general feel the next day
Well it's not something you can easily figure out again John Keegan seems to be so angry
At the field Marshal here
I'm still
Brothers conflict
The heat keep you rights
An answer to that question
What kind of man do you have to be to start for those kind of casualties in the next day think about continuing
Peking writes quote
Haig who his contemporaries found difficult to know
Has become today in enigma
The successful generals of the first world war those who did not crack out right
Or decline gradually into pessimism we're a hard lot
As they had to be with the casualty figures accumulating on their desk
Some nonetheless managed to combine toughness of mind with some striking human characteristic
Jafra he says imperturbability
Hindenburg
Gravity
Fire
Camaro certainty
Hey
He says
In whose public manner in private Diaries no concern for human suffering was
Or is discernible
Compensated for his aloofness
With nothing whatsoever of the common touch he seemed to move through the horrors of the first world war as if
Guided by some inner voice
Speaking of a higher purpose in a personal destiny
That we now know he says
Was not just appearance
Egg was a devotee both of spiritualist practices and a fundamentalist religion
As a young officer
Do you take into attending seances
Where the medium put him in touch with Napoleon
As commander-in-chief he fell under the influence of a presbyterian chaplain whose sermons confirmed him in his
Believe that he was in direct communication with God
And had a major part to play in a divine plan for the world
Is own simple religion Keegan says he was convinced
Was shared by his soldiers
Who were inspired there by to Bear the dangers and sufferings
Which were there part of the war he was direct
And quote
Wow
Welcome to the controversy and the
Heat
The battle of the Somme
Has generated amongst those who write about it but justifiably so I think
And truthfully I think they were military
Who are certainly willing to
Forgive
Douglas Haig
Suffering 6
Mm casual
He's on the first date
All of the song
If he's inflicted something like 60000 on the Germans
Instead
The British suffer those kind of casualties in the German casualties may have been this low
Six
What is the high number used sometimes see split
Take 60 give 8 you get your face
Not exactly the position you want
Your brand new general the new blood the person is going to bring a new
Centos
Stashed
To the war on the Western Front
All the sudden Douglas Haig been look a whole lot better than the people who care
Came before him
Pek John French could have had you suffered six
2000 cash
On the first day of the song right
Previous
Now
To put those numbers
In perspective cuz I was to do this from
60000 amorphous number
What what is that compared to
If there's damage
British 401 years by the battle of the Somme time
I've been talking about a horrible day they'd suffered
You know finishing off Napoleon at Waterloo
Fluoride in 1815
All Napoleon killed 8400
British soldier
Compared to 20
Glock 21 or 19
Huge difference right
How about the Second World War
Are you always think of the second world war being worse
On the 1st
Winnie
British and Americans landed
On the beaches of Normandy on June 6th 1944 for the famous D-Day Landings and then pushed in LA
And a not enough
Attention paid to
Key part of that whole thing in a widening at the bridge at
It was hard combat was historically hard combat
Artichoke
The British and America combined
20 -
To reach
20000 casual
Who took in 20 days
Combined British and American
To reach one third the amount of casualties
The British alarm set for
On the first day of
That's why
Wet sounds
Like Brianna doesn't it those numbers start to sound like what the french are suffering that horrible
In a battle to bleed their army White
Well David fromkin in his book a peace to end all peace quotes normanstone
About
How large these
Battles were compared to what the people in Europe were used
When he says quote
It has been estimated
The total
Of military and civilian casualties in all of Europe domestic and international
National conflicts
In the Hundred Years between 1815
+ 1915
Was no greater than a single day's combat losses
In any of the great battles of 1916
And quote
Credible statistic when you think of all of the battles that Europeans fought in Europe in in colonies and I wasn't
All of it put together
And all the European countries
400 years
Doesn't equal one of the bad days
Effort.
Or the song
The society
Could handle these
Kind of casualty
Will remark
But they took their toll as you might imagine
The time 5 months of the Somme
Is over
You have another million casual
In 5 months
So we're done gives you roughly about a million
And the song gives you roughly about a million
All at the same time
The burn rate on the west
Horrified
And remember all of these battles
Are like a lot of littler battles
Sort of lump together
Being at the song for example the Germans will Counterattack
In that 5 month. More than 300 times
A ton of those counter-attacks in ancient times would have been a battle all by itself right
Part of the reason why it's so hard to follow
The nature of these battle
Churchill has an overall description
That is just horrifying
Of
A conceptual view of this that makes you understand what was really going on
If you could view it sort of from space
And he writes about both the Somme and Verdun
Quote
The anatomy of the battles of Verdun and the Somme was the same
A battlefield have been selected
Around this battlefield walls were built
Double triple quadruple of enormous Cannon
Behind These
Railways were constructed to feed them
And mountains of shells were built up
All this was the work of months
Does the battlefield was completely encircle
Thousands of Guns of all sizes and a wide oval space prepared in their mitts
Through this awful Arena all the divisions of each Army
Battered ceaselessly by the enveloping artillery were made to pass in succession
As if they were in the teeth of interlocking cogwheels grinding each other
4 month after month
He writes
The ceaseless cannonade continued
Edits utmost intensity
10 month after month the gallon divisions of heroic human beings
We're Torn to Pieces in this terrible rotation
Then came the winter
Pouring down rain from the sky to clog the feet of men
And drawing veils of mist
Before the Hawkeyes of their artillery
The arena has used to happen in the Colosseum in those miniature Roman days
Was flooded with water
Steven sang with mud churned by thousands of vehicles
By hundreds of thousands of men and millions of shells replaced the Blasted us
Still the struggle continued
Still the remorseless Wheels revolve
Still the auditorium of artillery roared
At last
The legs of men could no longer move
They wallowed and floundered helplessly in the slime
Their food and ammunition lag behind them along the smashed and choked roadway
And quote
I keep quoting Churchill because wasn't that
Positively
Tolkien-esque
By the way there are people who
USA the tokens experiences with the first World War
Influence
His way of writing
Inthinking
But if it did he would have been just wanted millions of others
People that had their Outlook transform
How could you not
As we said
You imagine writing that last letter home where is essentially a goodbye letter
Can change you can did I known a lot of people who've had
Terminal illnesses
Had months to know the death was in their near future
It often changes
It often
Creates this introspective mood where all of a sudden they're focusing
On subjects that people don't usually spend
Hour after hour day after day focusing on but it's right in front of the right if you have terminal
Cancer
It's going to be on your mind
And the thinking about it changes you
What if you had a terminal disease
And all of a sudden at the last minute the doctors figured out a way to cure you when you were dragged back from the brink
But you'd spent a couple of months thinking intensely
About life
And death and the meaning of things and what you would have done differently in all these really heavy-duty thoughts
But most people can only stand to
Think about in short little burst juice
There are except
Now imagine
Millions
Doing this 90
14 1980
.
Who would have found themselves in a similar sort of a situation
Pretty much sure they were going to die in the near future will be horribly disfigured thinking about the heaviest of subject
Writing letters home to loved one saying
You know I'm going to miss not knowing my baby daughter and then
Some of them
Getting a reprieve
I'm getting a chance to live this life they were all but writing off
During the worst of these War XP
That is a searing
Personal experience that millions of individual persons
Went through
How does that not change
The society when they go home
And you know
One of the things about battles
Specialty's First World War battles is there so dark are they in there so Industrial
And they're so
Unbelievably horrifying the Charnel house Zombie graveyard
Feel of the battlefield in the first World War
Make that
Particularly
Remind me
You'll see a lot of Art
Around the first world war that shows corpse
Ducane
And it's not so you feel sympathy with the Dead
Figure it's so that you understand what it was like for those people living amongst
All those decaying corpses to deal with that reality
Mind-bending battles mind-bending enough right you at all the incredible artillery which is
Disorienting as as all get-out and then throw in
Bodies in pieces of bodies everywhere when you're living as we've said
It's a unique
Experience
It's a form of hell
And yet
Does someone like yours truly
That creates
The circumstance
Where
Human
Brotherly love
Appears so like a light in the dark
Part of why battles are interesting to study is B
Because it's you
Probably figured out you can see the worst
Human behavior and man's inhumanity to man in them
But you can also see these
Pieces of humanity
Slip through and when they do they are all the more bright
And noticeable because they're happening in hell as opposed to asking something that happens in your neighborhood
A little piece of humanity not that surprising in your neighborhood
Probably makes your day a little brighter
A piece of humanity in the
Alabi's Battlefield
Has a rejuvenating
Effect for once feel about
Man
Take for exam
These
No man
In between the fighting lines of
The two sides of the West
Created something that the battles of had forever I'm in the second world war you have these Crossroads
Set up a sudden
You know he was death to cross this Crossroad put the Western Front
Is hundreds of miles
Rules of
Trench line
All of them with this dead zone in between and on the really big front swirl out what's happening
There was tons of
Drama in those dead zone
Things would happen that
We challenged men's
Morality
And what you're willing to do a perfect example
Is in the battle of the Somme
When the 60,000 casualties and a lot of other casualties over the course of that battle or happening
The Germans are often taking pity on their fellow human being
And the British write about it
I mean when
These British
Attacks would break against the German defense isn't in the wounded would start back toward the safety of their own trenches grabbing
Even worse wounded people with them and trying to under machine gun and artillery fire get back to their own
Trenches lot of times these Germans would just stop shoot
On the first terrible day there were often times where the machine Gunners in the officers were just a stye
Letting it be
The human thing to do
Right
On the other hand if they had just machine-gun them
That window surprised anybody
Either
What are you doing now
About those people
Who are stuck out there in no man's land
After the attack is over
There are all sorts of stories about
People who will
Simply
If they can drive themselves to the nearest Shell hole wrap themselves up in the tarp they keep to keep the rain out
Open up a Bible in just died in
Shell hole
When they don't
Taken off and have it
A terrible affair
Fact on the men in the trenches on both sides
Apaches in the American southwest
Used to be able to make such good use
Of pasta
And if you threaten to torture hostile you did towards her hostage you could get all kinds of
Concessions from the other side
Well they were hostages
Hate is holding in the middle of those no man's land areas
And what do you do
When one of them starts asking for help and they're basically calling to you
And your body
Terminal Man
If you want to see their heroism
And the sacrifice
Human beings can show
And in these hellish
Situations
Read the accounts over and over about
How men dealt with
Scream
For help
From No Man's
A perfect example
Of the kind of moral dilemmas and self-sacrifice that these situations
In a create
Is the story that Robert Graves tell
Bealls in goodbye all that
He was serving at the Somme on the Western Front
And a soldier named Samson
Gets hit
In the wave before Graves is wave goes over the tops of graves is just getting ready for this intense experience himself
I'm going over the top of the trench
With other human beings right into the teeth of machine-gun Fire
And all of a sudden you hear the sound of somebody from the last attack
From No Man's Land you know where it's death to stand up and move around
Asking
For help were screaming out and here's what Graves
Is Right remember he's he's in the state himself
I'm thinking okay I got it
Walking machine gun fire
And I'm just seeing all these other people die in front of me quote
My mouth was dry
My eyes out of focus in my legs quaking under me
I found a water bottle full of rum and drank about half a pint
It quieted me and my head remained clear
Samson leg groaning about 20 yd beyond the front Trench
Several attempts were made to rescue
And he been very badly hit
Three men got killed in those attempts
Two officers in two men wounded
Andy and his own orderly managed to crawl out to him
Samson waved and back
Say he was riddled through and not worth rescuing
He sent his apologies to the company for making such a noise
And quote
Other words just guys out there screaming
And it's so driving his own comrade crazy that they keep
Running out there to do something
And everybody runs out there to do something gets killed
At what point if you're the wounded
Do you try to just
Stop making noise so that they don't keep trying to help you out of sympathy
When you probably are dying anyway and now you lost three people or more
Simply trying to
Prevent the inevitable you're going through
So
At night
When we're told the no man's land area comes to life
And in a word
Appears deserted during the daytime at night the trench patrols go out
The people who
In a fix the barbed wire the intelligence folks
The people conducting trench raids I mean supposedly there's a lot of
Activity in the dark even though star shells Light Up the Sky all
All the time
At dark
Graves in his unit
Movies out to go
Cleared any wounded in front of their trenches and he writes quotes
At dusk we all went out to get the wounded
Leaving only centuries in the line
The first dead body I Came Upon was Samson
Hidden 17th Place
I found that he forced his knuckles into his mouth to stop himself crying out and attracting anymore men to their death
And quote
This poor man out there hit 17 times
Suffering horribly unable to Keep from Crying Out
Can't stand the thought of attracting anymore in men
To rescue him
And dies with his
Hand in his mouth
To keep from crying I mean it is it
It's it's the beauty
Finds Its way into the horrific Ness of this war
If you're that person
Parent there's nothing there
Really better than a human being
You look at that and say
There's something about
Not that man sex
Now Grace tells another story
Which not only shows the heroism and the beauty of one of his compatriot
But the same sort of an attitude on the part of
The people the British start with a bad guy
The Germans that we said the Germans have been holding their fire quite a bit
You're doing this bottle and you see it
On the French side of the British side to I mean this is not abnormal
It's
A little bit like that Christmas Truce we talked about in the 1914
Error of this war we're spontaneously
Troops got up and
Should have gave each other a
Little Christmas love in between the shellings right
You see this Humanity appear even in this hell
Graves talks about
Another soldier in no man's
Wakes up
Seemingly dead and then all of a sudden
Is crying for help
And when this happens every man in his trench
Feels like he's going through
I'm sort of a moral test
And one man has it
With flying colors
Raised right
On the morning of the 27th
Briar Rose from no man's land
A wounded soldier of the Middlesex unit have recovered Consciousness after 2 days
Delite close to the German wire
Are men heard it and looked at each other
We had a tender-hearted lance corporal name Baxter
He was the man to boil up a special Dixie for the centuries of his section when they came off duty made him a little
Super T
As soon as he heard
The wounded Middlesex man he ran along the trench calling for a volunteer to help fetch him in
Of course no one would go
It was death to put one's head over the
The parapet
When he came running to ask me
I excused myself as being the only officer in the company
I would come out with him at dusk
I said
Not now
So he went alone
Jump quickly over the parapet
And then strolled across no-man's-land waving a handkerchief
The Germans fire to frighten him but since he persisted they let him come close
Baxter continue tour
And when he got to the Middlesex man
Stop
And pointed to show the Germans what he was at
What he was up to
Venidress the man's wounds
Gave him a drink of rum and some biscuit that he had with him and promised to be back again at nightfall
He didn't come back grades right
With a stretcher party and a man eventually recovered
I recommended Baxter for the Victoria Cross being the only officer who would witness the action
But the authorities started worth no more than a distinguished Conduct Medal
And quote
Sounds worthy of a Victoria Cross
And that's one of those incidents where you see
The opposite of man's inhumanity to man
In an environment designed to Foster the former
It stands out all the more doesn't it
The Baxter could have easily been mowed down and if you don't think it happens remember three people were mowed down trying to say
That wounded Samson character in the first
I can't help
Wonder
How am I generation would handle what these B
People Workforce
What to do
You think of the first day on the battle of the Somme
Think of yourself in the second
Wave
Or the Third Way
And you hear all this stuff from the officers about all them
Killer will destroy everybody that nobody be Left Alive
And then the first wave in front of you units that you know go over the top
And don't even get near their objective before their cuts a ribbon
It's an absolute catastrophe
And screw up and everybody can see it happen
And then they turn to the next wave
If maybe that's not you maybe you're in the third
And tell them to go do the same thing and they doing the same thing happens right it's suicide
Now they turn to you
Let me say okay it's your units turn
What you do
Forget cowardice for a second
Because there are people who simply ran away
Aarhus nerves failed them or whatever
This is not a question of
You know
What could you
Physically
This is a question of what
Would you
See I think
A lot of us
We think to ourselves
There's no way I'm surviving
Going out onto that battle
But if this officer wasn't here telling me to do this and my buddies and I just sort of
Decided all together we're not doing this
Maybe something would change you know
One of the first war novel
What's come out of the first world war actually came out during the
Frenchman name
Henry Barber
And he wrote
Something
Where he as a soldier had served our
Already he was a disabled veteran he wrote this piece while the war was still going on and it's surprisingly anti-war
For the government to put up with it during the conflict
And he implied that the soldiers on both sides the common soldiers
To just agree with each other
Vinegar fighting
And what if they gave a war and no one came right what if the soldiers on both sides of the government can tell it to 5
And Barbara said that in the book that
Truthfully the only people who really understood
What the French soldier and a British soldier were going through in these hellish conditions
Were the German soldiers on the other side of the nomad
Plant living under the exact
Same hellish condition
When the Germans don't fire on the British were getting their wounded
A lot of times it's because there's an Unwritten deal that says
I'm going to leave you alone right
How to get your wounded
People are there in the hopes that when it's my wounded
Did people in no man's land and I'm trying to get them out of there
You'll let me
One of the real phenomenons of this war
Is the fact that when left alone a lot of soldiers on both sides
Decided to adopt what's what's
Officially known as a live-and-let-live attitude
In this war and it was it was common everywhere but the Western Front more than any other
Where for example
Soldiers would be required and they hated this job
To go out at night
And put more barbed wire
Stop in the middle of nowhere
Once you sneak out cuz it's dark
And you bring wire with you and wire cutters and all these thinking of to go hang new wire
Extremely dangerous job in both sides hated
Right
It's a lot of time.
They just wouldn't shoot
At the other pee
People who were putting wire officers hated this
And one of the big
Scandals was after the Christmas Truce
The so-called Christmas Truce of 1914 both sides with fractions
The officers had to make all these arrangements so that next Christmas nothing like this happened again in a minute
Preserved a proper fighting spirit
I could be the way
Most elite military
What phrase about the troops off and found a lot more
To like about each other than their own office
Corporate Louis Vuitton
In the French army
Write about this incident
Where a flood occurs
And all of a sudden
The Trenches on both sides of no-man's-land have to clear and how you have one of those moments where you just look at your
And I mean he looks at you and you realize
The suck
Who put us into this mess and why are we doing this and he almost right to know as a social
It was like a lot of these troops in the trenches are
So he has a worldview that kind of seas
The upper classes the corporate groups and all that is the problem
And that the average soldiers in the trenches we're all just kind of common workers being exploited by the man
He writes about the
This famous
Flood
That he experiences
And what it does
Freaks out
You know his mind is the upper classes in the officer Corps
But all of a sudden
Taobao
Sides in this combat are starting to have some sympathy for each other
Any rights quote
One night when the rain came down in Torrance
The tide invaded our dugout
I'm cascaded down both sets of steps
At the height of the storm some of the men had to devote all their efforts to building a dam
Which the water then broke through it
Three or four places
We spent the rest of the night battling the flood waters
The next day December 10th at many places along the Frontline the soldiers had to come out of their trenches so is
Not to drown
The Germans had to do the same
We therefore had the singular spectacle of the two enemy armies facing each other without firing a shot
Our common sufferings brought our hearts together
Melted the hatred
Nurtured sympathy between strangers and adversaries
Those who deny it are ignoring human psychology
Frenchman in German seawright
Looked at each other and saw that they were all men
No different from one another
They smiled exchanged comment
And reached out in grass
We shared tobacco
A canteen of coffee or wine if only we spoke the same language
One day he writes
A huge devil of a German stood up on a mound and gave a speech
Which only the Germans could understand word for word
But everyone knew what it meant
Because he smashed his rifle on a tree stump
Breaking it into in a gesture of anger
Applause broke out on both sides
Ally Internationale was sung
Pizza
National
The Socialist cause
He says quote
Well if only you'd been there mad King's bloody generals fanatical ministers
Jingoistic journalist
Rear Echelon Patriots to contemplate this Sublime spectacle
But it wasn't enough
He says
Did the soldiers refuse to fight one another
What was needed was for them to turn back on the monsters you were pushing them
One against the other
And it cut them down like wild beasts
For not having done so how much longer would the killing go on
Meanwhile he says
Are big shot leaders were in a furor
What in the lord's name would happen if the soldiers refuse to kill each other
Our artillery men received orders to fire on any Assemblies of men which were pointed out to them
Animo down in discriminately both Frenchmen and German
Just like when an ancient circuses
They slaughtered wild beasts 2 were too intelligent to tear each other's throats out and devour each other
Furthermore he says
Once the front line was established again for better or worse
It was forbidden under penalty of death to leave the trench
Any Act of familiarity with the Germans had to cease
It was over
What was really needed was a second biblical flood
Are Universal Deluge to stop the war
To appease all the anger in the bloody Madness of our leaders
Who knows he says
Maybe one day in this corner of Artois they were raised a monument
To commemorate the spirit of fraternity among men who shared a horror of war and who were forced to kill each
Each other against their will
And quote
There are
Multiple accounts from socialist soldiers that sound like that
But it's more complex than then
Phillip Gibbs tries to make this statement
And now it can be told
We talked about this
Horrible life before soldiers are forced to endure
In about the complexity involved in trying to make some statement that the soldiers are all of One mind or viewpoint
Or anything
We told you weren't Junger the German go through all this
Terrible stuff
I'm kind of finds it
Uplifting
Gibbs write these horror stories and then says this about the song
And the soldiers there
Quote
But however deep
The knowledge of tragedy
A man would be a liar
If you refuse to admit to heroin
The gallantry of Youth
Even the gaiety of men in these infernal months
Psychology on the song was not simple and straightforward
Men were afraid
But fear was not there dominating emotion except in the worst hour
Men hated this fighting
Profound excitement
Often exaltation
Sometimes
An intense stimulus of all their senses and Passions
Before reaction exhaust
Men became gibbering idiots with Shellshock
If I saw some of the
But others
Rejoiced when they saw our shells plowing into the enemy's earthwork
Laughed at their own narrow Escape
Integral test
Comicality this monster is devil tree
The officers he writes were proud of their men
Eager for their honor an achievement
The men themselves were in rivalries with other bodies of troops and proud of their own prowess
They were scornful of all that the enemy might do to them
Getting knowledge discouraged and Power
They were quick to kill him
And yet also quick to give him a chance of Life by surrender
And after that were 9 times out of 10 chivalrous and kindly
But incredibly brutal on the rare occasions
When passion overcame them it's some tale of treachery
They had the pride of a skilled laborer he writes
In his own crap
As machine gunners
Bombers
Raider
Trench mortar
Men
And we're all Keen to show their skill whatever the risks
They were healthy animals
With animal courage as well as animal fear
And they had some of them a spiritual and moral fervor which bathed them risk death to save a camera
How to save a position
40 killed fear that tried to feather them
4 lead men with greater fear than there
They live from hour to hour
And forgot
The Peril or the misery that had passed
I did not forestall the future by apprehension
Unless they were sensitive mind
With the worst quality men might have in Modern Warfare
Imagination
And quote
Well
Imagination I can see being a downside if you are in the trenches Under Fire
And looking at your watch as some of these troops in the trenches did saying I have 15 minutes left to live
Now I have 10 minutes left
Now I have 5 minutes left to live in
Is the countdown to going over the top
Yes I can see how
You crazy
The other hand
We're getting to the part of the war where the really
Imaginative Minds can begin to
Start to have an impact on these brand-new 20th century problems
It only became apparent about 2 years ago when this War started
Some of the solutions to the problems the first World War
Anna brings into play
Debut during the battle of
The song and they look once again this is going to maybe be a sub team of this show on intentionally
They look like something out of Science Fiction in this case
HG Wells
Or if you want to believe some
People go all the way back to Leonardo DaVinci
People who first
Come up with the concept of if you will
A land ship
Churchill and the Navy called the land battleship
We know them by the term
And tank is supposedly simply something that caught on
It was supposed to be a cover work
So that no one knew
What was being worked on in secret in the in the Laboratories of the allies
They would suggest
Statistic Giant
Armored
Tractor
Was intended to bring up Supply water
Her to the Frontline troops
Under-fire so attack
He will water toy
Battle one of these little battles that make up all these giant battles a part of the battle of the Somme on September
AR-15
Offensive
To take a particular part of the battlefield is launched
And debuting are a bunch of these
Chanel
30 or 40 something like that a bunch of them broke down on the way
You can instantly see
You know that this is the solution to the problem right if you go to your engineers when the war starts and say listen we got this bar
McGuire machine gun artillery situation with no man's land in these big trenches you got to get past
Put your mind to it come back with a design
They did they got a giant track
And it's so long that he can
Most of these
Trenches
So
It can go in and not get trapped most of the time it only goes about the speed of a walking human being but the
The point isn't to
In a drive around real fast everywhere the point is to not get killed
While you're Crossing no-man's-land
And not get held up by barbed wire these things are designed to Simply run over barbed wire
Machine gun bullets won't
Hurt them shrapnel won't hurt them and they'll get to the other side and I'll wipe out strong points and when they debut nobody has any
Any idea what that's going to be like
Another one of those moments where you had bite your nails in that you watch the new technology
In this case
Not stuff developed in the last hundred years that never had a chance to be tested in this case stop develop
Specifically in response to problems the first World War
Gina brings up like
No man's land
And
They perform
Astoundingly well
Now they break down a lot
And other terribly uncomfortable today
People inside these are large to there like 15 people in these
I mean you're like
Almost a boss
And they don't have a turret
They have either machine gun that come out of the side or a couple of 6-pounder guns with your about 57 mm
And yet
The Germans don't know what they're dealing with here and we
Have stories of them surrendering to tanks and
How the reaction on the part of the British troops is either really
Excited and happy or
They almost laughing cuz it looks kind of comical
But in a sense
This is what we talked about earlier this is the Star Wars steampunk
Imperial Walker thing for real
Churchill and the people who would back this idea from the time trench warfare got started that's when the the fur
First plans were drawn up in the ideas brainstormed for something like this in the French were working on the two by the way
Churchill was mad and forever afterwards yelled and screamed that
This concept could have really done a ton if they had just waited till there were enough of these land battleships
To unleash and have pad make a difference
The counter-argument which we also understand right is that
What if they don't work what if we don't know how they work how do we do this if we don't have a
Dress rehearsal
Before opening night so Churchill in the people on his side or saying no you wasted it should have been one big opening night that
Broke the Western Front
The other side saying are you kidding me there is an open invitation to Murphy's Law
But if you were looking to try to decide how you like your land battleship
Concept in practice
After it was debuted at the Battle of the Somme well all you have to know is Cavalry commander Douglas Haig
Radioed back to
Your corporate headquarters at the British Army and said that
We want more of those tanks
Now
Other things happen
Because of the battle of
The song two in one was
It was just yet
For poor Erich von Falk
Can find the head of the German military remember he took over after they sacked Von moltke the guy who they started the war with
And now
Like a bunch of leaders who owned a football team and continually like
To change couches Vulcan Hines going to lose his gig
He's got Verdun on his scorecard now he's got the song and then there's a
Brusilov offensive and then the last straw
Is everybody's Whispering that Romania is going to get in the war which doesn't sound like a big deal to watch now
But if you actually look at the literature especially German austro-hungarian the stuff from that side of your toe they're really like biting their nails
About the song
Romania to get in the war half-million bayonets oh my goodness
Everybody's really worried and apparently Kaiser Wilhelm II German Emperor is really worried in Falcon Heights and now don't worry about it
They're not going to come in anytime soon maybe later but no but no time soon and then boom almost
Right after he issues
Did I won't be coming in they come in
August 27th
And that's it falkenhayn get sacked
The last card by the way I love how he knows his Emperor William and William's little quirks about power
And Falcon Heights last car that he plays is
You know if you replace me
With the people everyone knew they were
Replacing with have you replaced me with Hindenburg and ludendorff that's it they're not going to listen to you
I'm the last chance you have of having an influence
My word
But that's basically what you said to the Kaiser you won't have any role in this at all
You better stick with me cuz if you put Hindenburg and ludendorff in charge they going to tell you to go play with your toys in the corner
Apparently the Kaiser felt like he had no choice
Saks
Von falkenhayn
Who asks
Spore a military command
Is giving some people think almost as an insult
The command to go attack Romania
Which he didn't foresee them coming into the war
He takes over a military command and
Conducts a brilliant campaign against Romania
Conquering them quick
Which makes you turn around go now why won't you so scared of those Romanian bayonets
La Terranea
Think about
How that's like a minor league team jumping into the middle of a game against the
Perhaps best army
In the 20th centuries of Romania so unequipped for this
Without a ramp up. And they just got
Smashed
And the worst part about the whole thing from the Allied standpoint again the Allies work so hard to get Romania in the conflict is it
Germany takes over Romania they're going to loot that country of every bit of weed
And oil in anything they can take to offset
The damage that the British blockade is doing so in the sentence like they come upon this Romanian store room and they Luther
The whole thing
So it
So the backfires
On the Allied cause
Nonetheless
Hindenburg and ludendorff this new command team the people who have been in charge on the Eastern front for so long and so
Being the armchair quarterbacks from over there telling
The rest of the German command what they were doing wrong on the Western Front right now in charge of among other things
The Western Front
And they're going to bring A New Perspective in a different way of looking at
And
They will
Essential
Command this German Army for the rest
The war
Now how long the rest of the wars going to be able to
Is an open question
As 1960 begins to wonder if you begin to see the discontent
Cramping up everywhere
How many different fur
When you begin to see for example hunger relief
You'll be a winter
The famous winter of 1916 in Germany
It's called the turnip
Which tells you right there what's go
And all the all the exports from Romania you can get aren't going to
Will make up for the
Overseas
Import needs of Germany
The Russians
Are in terrible trouble remember this is a a regime that almost got overthrown
10 years before this time.
They didn't have exactly the
The greatest most
Solid foundation anyway
These million casualties they suffer 1916 at the brusilov offensive among other things are taking its toll
French soldiers
Our beginning
To bleat
Like sheep
When they pass by their officers these Replacements will come up
Marching by
Camille just here bleeding sound
Sheep and lamb being led to
To the slaughter a sort of his one author puts it
Way that the
The troops
Silently
Protest what they
Mayfield being done to them
Homefront
You can
Now the tragedy is beginning to really see pin as more and more people
I personally effect
It for life
By this confidence
Obviously well this isn't
The
Text book example I don't think most people find themselves in
The same situation
At this German couple
There's a story from the time period from
A British observer in Germany
During the war who was describing a train trip
She saw a couple
Man and a woman
On the train
And the story is absolutely
Heartbreaking but in so many ways shows where we are
By the end of night
16 in the sky
The Observer says
Quote
A poor woman the other day on the train was holding up her hand
I'm counting the fingers on it slowly
Over and over again
The passengers gradually began to smile at her
Until at last the man sitting next to her said simply don't laugh at my wife ladies and gentlemen
I'm taking her to the asylum
Hurwitz Argon
She's lost her 5 Sons
All killed in action
And quote
Can you really examine what's already happen
Since August 9th
You Come Away with
The feeling that if you had bet
On a short war
Like so many did
You are amazed at the staying power
Ribaldis state
Many of whom didn't look that
Particularly stable when the war broke out
Nonetheless as we've been saying throughout this whole program
There's a limit
The endurance
Of anyone
And we're about to enter the point
And Brake
And in the not-too-distant
Get knocked out
If you think the show you this hurt is worth a dollar Dan and Ben would love to have it
About to show it's all we ask
Go to dancarlin.com for information on how to donate to the show
One of the justifiable criticism
You Can level at the show we just
Was it a focuses inordinately
On the western
I did that on purpose
Because to me when you're talkin about the extremes of human
Experienced person that comes to my mind when I
Situation of the West
In front in the trench war and all that
And in that sense I'm not that different than most British French and German historian to a focus inordinately
On the Western Front
But I think we all know
But there's a lot of other things going on in this conflict in a bunch of other theaters
And in the same way
I was able to avoid talking about those other theaters for awhile my good at the jumping around we would do
If we try to get everything in there would be more confusing than what we're already giving you which is more
Confusing the night
Already
None the less you could ignore
Just like most people in Britain France or heck even in New York city in United States when you open up a newspaper in the far corner
Like page 8 is a little blurb about maybe some
Obscure Arab
Tribe Uprising in
In some out-of-the-way ottoman
District
Or something doesn't mean that much
How much do you're not thinking that much about it after all the Western Front is grinding up a whole generation of Europeans
And then in 1917
Events
In Faraway peripheral places
Is the way a lot of people in the west might see them
Rise up and demand to be
Taken seriously
Whether it's the Middle East in 1917 and events
We are still shaking out to this day that are in your headlines daily
Whether it's the collapse
Of an ancient European regime
Which opens the door
The 20th century
Most
Radical regime taking over in a major country
It's also in 1917 that the vortex of the first World War
Manages to sucking
An outside major power
That for almost a hundred and fifty years
Has managed to stay out of direct
Involvement in European Affairs as one of their early
President that said
The United States of America doesn't go abroad in search of foreign monsters to slay
In 1970
Well maybe just this one
You know
To make the world
Safe for democracy
Yes indeed
Many of our modern
Situation
Add the seeds for the implant
In 19
I will get to
All that
And more
Imparfait
Blueprint