How much time do you put into a
The development
Gap
The perfect example
All of the sort of question they've been devil.
In this
Episode
Which covers by the way a ridiculously
A short span of time
But one of the most important
Let's just say month or so
In human history
It represents
The greatest mass
Pouring of organized violence that the world had ever seen
I don't think there's ever been anything quite like
In the second world war begins
With the German attack on Poland and fighting between Germany and Poland it's over rather quickly and it's like 8 months
Before the major Powers actually come to blows
This war starts with all the major Powers coming to blows head on
Instantly on multiple fronts with casualties that no one had ever even seen
In a while
Streams
The same time
At speed
And I started to realize that
The program
You know what's happening.
You can't
Get into the minds of the people in the human stories in the drama in the story
Without getting into the military Affairs and its is
Day-to-day progression because that's the driving force
That's what sets
The timeline that's what determines the turn in fortune
And that's what creates
Human impact on the ground
You know when we quote
A reporter talking about what it looks like in the hospitals in France
There's a reason that the hospitals are full of hurt people in that
Because the events on the ground continue to dictate what's going on
But the military Affairs are complex as all get-out
How much time do you spend
On a gaap
In the battle of the Marne write the famous
Miracle on the Marne is determined by this Gap in the enemy line
How much time do you spend on in a wider the Gap I mean if that really is
A war losing
Situation to have developed you get into that will if you get into that you're starting to follow a line of detail that just
I'll take you off into the weed
The difficult story to decide when to go off into the weeds
And went to stay put on the main road
This is our attempt
And explaining
This most
Complex
And yet
Filled with human drama and great events
And larger-than-life figures
And
Really a changing
Of the Guard
In terms of
In one century to another
Asbestos we can do with the Dan Carlin approach to the
Called
Blueprint
For Armageddon
Vanessa's party
December 7th
A date which will live
In infamy
Its history
The event
Call nist time and place I take pride in the words
Ich bin ein Berliner
Instagram
I welcome this kind of examination because people have got to know
Whether or not their presidential question
If we dig deep in our history and our Doctrine and remember that we are not descended
From fearful men
It's hardcore history
What year
Did humankind
Acquire the capability
Asteroids
If it's an interesting idea isn't the idea that
Every civilization in the universe if it continues to progress technologically down the road
Orisha.
When it can kill it
Either on purpose or accidentally
This fits into something
Some physicists
Theories
On What's called the Fermi paradox
And this idea of reaching a danger point in your civilization
Is called
The great filter
The Fermi paradox
Famous
Paradox that was
Initially talked about supposedly by a bunch of the great physicists in the world on their lunch break
Where they had done the math
Trying to figure out the possibilities
Intelligent life being elsewhere in the universe in the math is so overwhelmingly in favor of the idea that there
Must be
Why there's hundreds of billions of stars in our galaxy
Hundreds of billions of galaxies in the universe it just seems like a slam dunk
Right
So then
Enrico Fermi famously one of the Great
Physicist ever famously than sister the group so where is everybody
That's affirmative
Set the masses they should be there but they're not there
What's the reason they're not there
And that's where the great filter comes
Because some of these people who study this stuff
Have suggested that there might be a point in every
Intelligent civilizations development where they acquire this ability to destroy themselves
Have to get through the.
Where they have that capability and get to the point where they
Figure out how not to do that
And it's kind of like a pass-fail test
For intelligent civilisational growth everywhere in the universe
And soda
By its very nature most civilizations
Don't pass
That's what maybe that's the reason they're not all out there
And guys like Nick Bostrom study
Global catastrophic risk and stuff like that
You know what if a comet hit the planet what is nanotechnology goes out of control means looks at all these issues
He suggests that the Earth entered the civilizational phase this great filter. In our own history
In 1945
When the atomic bombs were
Now I think about this
In terms of
The first world war because
I think that's when people first realized
The human beings had acquired a military capability
That was frightening not frightening because your enemy had it frightening because human beings had it
You can go back and look at history there are lots of times when people
We're afraid of the deadliness of weapons but they were afraid of the deadliness of weapons either because they were afraid themselves of get
Getting killed for their country of getting taken over whatever they weren't afraid for the species
They Wonder frayed
First civilization as a whole in the closest you'll see
You know with that Cummings you have like a Mongolian Beijing or Invasion from the step in it it it it strikes the subtle
Nations a bit like a wave and it washes up a certain amount
You know civilization up on the beach but it doesn't destroy everything
In the 19th century
That's the first time. We're
You can read writings from people who are certain that maybe what they're developing Battlefield capability wise
Can destroy
Now their version of everything is a little bit different than our
When we talk about things like existential risk
We're talking about the survival of life
On the planet
That's a post-atomic
You no idea what existential risk means we understand that you have a nuclear war amongst all the great powers and
You can kiss life on Earth goodbye
Or
Certainly our level of civilization
You've heard that phrase bomb someone back to the Stone Age
Only modern people have the capability to do that right
But it was in the 19th century
The definite the idea that that's what a major war between the major Powers might amount to that
Actually that idea takes hold
Those people are worried about
Definition number two
Of existential threat
You guys like Nick Bostrom have two definitions one is the one we think about
Wiped out life on Earth
But the other
Definition of what an existential threat is
Is being knocked
Back down a few rungs
On your level of civilization
And then never finding your way back to your
Weakness
You know to have
A Statue of Liberty in the sand moment doesn't like
To call it where you look up and you see the Statue of Liberty like in the Planet of the Apes
Coming out of the sand and you instantly realize in a blinding flash of light
That you're living in an era that is off the civilizational highs
And that's what the people rioting in the late 19th
Early 20th century
Especially in places like Great Britain in the United States where everything seems just great why don't have to screw it up with the war
And really nothing to gain and everything to lose those people are writing about
Living in a golden age
Did they believe is fragile
And that these giant war machines
That are equally deadly in terms of their abilities to kill people on the battlefield
But also their ability to Simply
Bankrupt the societies that have to maintain them
Is causing consternation at end of the very weapon systems themselves and the arms race is that there
You're having
Create more opportunities for some sort of violent
Outbreak of War
The women see these things employee
The funny thing about human history who study military history
Is the up until about 200 years ago
You can imagine armies
From a very long time ago
Fighting and beating
Armies from not that long ago
Alexander the Great's army I think
Beats the carolingian army of Charlemagne which is
You know a first-rate army up thousand years later
I don't think they must the macedonians must have hair
And their books like arther ferrill the origins of War
Wechat
You don't say that credible historian can't help but play with the Battle of Waterloo inserting Alexander and his Mack
Sidonians from the 330 BCE
In the place of Napoleon and his French sending the macedonians up against the
Duke of Wellington and his British and their Coalition allies and having
Alexander in the makedonian do at least as well as Napoleon
So what is that show you
What shows you how all of human military history changes
At about the time
The Napoleonic Wars because all of a sudden
A new law of historical nature takes over
Which does the earlier armies
Do not beat later on
In the rules changed
Thousand percent first of all think about today
Speech at the US Army from today had it fight a battle against
In the US Army of 1945
Today's US Army destroys that
Second World War army mid-twentieth-century army and maybe doesn't lose a man when they do it
But that 1945 US Army
We defeat easily
Any army from the first
Any army from the first world war the major Powers would easily defeat
Do United States in the US Civil War
And the Civil War armies
If they went back to Waterloo
Nobita Nepali
So that's sort of the rule
Of the law of technological Battlefield development for the last 200 years
And that's what the people in this story have had to try to suck up and understand
In 1700 some ruler can decide on a new musket design and not change it for a hundred years
He still probably okay
In nineteenth-century if you miss 15 years of development in Rifle technology
You might lose a war cuz of that
You think about
Something like the naval arms race
Places and how this just destroyed everybody's treasuries and everything else
But at the beginning of the 1800s
You are using ship-of-the-line type stuff I mean
You know the same Naval technology of giant Wooden Ships with cannons all in the side that's been the way things are
I've been done for a couple centuries
And when you build a ship and spend all that money and all that time it's good for a long time if it doesn't get destroyed in battle that ship cancer
Serve you for
20-30 years and then just be fine great invest
Pay off overtime if you amortize the cost out over the decades
Tacos way
At the end of
The 19th century
And yet
The cost explodes
You look at a battleship from 1900
And it doesn't look like anything
From Napoleon's
It looks like a Thoroughly Modern Battleship the problem is is technology is changing so fast now
That in the time it takes you to design that new battleship
The Torso years it takes to build and launch and finish it
It may be outdated by the time it's ready to be used
You take a first-class first-rate
No Fleet from a global power in 1914
And you pitted in battle against the First Rate top-of-the-line Fleet from a mere 14 years ago
And the one from 1914 destroys the one from 1900 and maybe doesn't lose a major surf
This vessel while doing so
That is mind-boggling
The people who lived back then because
That means if you can't keep up technologically with what your neighbor is doing at Great expense
You can negate all the money you spent on that Fleet in the first place better to not have that Fleet from 19
If you're just going to lose the whole thing and not even think one of your enemy ships
The need to keep up with the killing power of everyone else
Was impacting the treasuries of these countries in Waze
They created just as big of a threat to their continued existence
As the threat of all these dangerous armies did
It was a catch-22 for them
Take the role
Dirty
Russian czar
Found himself in in 1898 guy named Nicholas.
II may be the single most powerful person on the planet
He's
Got a shaky regime
It's a lot of Revolution there's a lot of discontent in a lot of it is exacerbated by the cost
Trying to
You keep up a modern military
And even with all these cost
He's falling behind
Rushes
To illiterate
It's Industries are too small
It's Society still need so much modernization for can keep up with places like Germany in
France Great Britain and even the United States
The problem is
Is that the czar's power is all in the country size in the population
And that's becoming
Less and less important
Technology begins to determine who wins and who loses battle
And that's being demonstrated all through the 19th century at these small Colonial armies from the
Technologically sophisticated powers
Destroy sometimes
Giant army
Tribal natives
All over the world
I mean that line
Famous one that says whatever happens we have got the Maxim gun
And they have not
Is about using machine guns
On
Tribal people
The Russian Czar is looking ahead and seeing that
If he can't
Keep up with this technological arms race that seems to be never-ending an endlessly expensive
The Russians are just going to be the new tribal
And yet he has to have this modern military machine
Because of his adversaries have it and he doesn't
He's going to lose any War he
Gets into
He loses his dynasty potentially either way
How do you get out of a mess light
In 1898
The Russian Czar thinks he finds a way
Money issues
Public invitation
Two representatives from the other great Powers who are
One degree or another in the same boat he's in
No one knows what the next major war will look like
But everybody's had a chance to see some minor wars in the meantime and if you sort of extrapolate what what they were
They were telling you
The next Wars going to be horrifying and Nicholas II was actually reading
The guy who turned out to be one of the most accurate
Prognosticators what the next door we can be like we talked about in the last show
Ivan block
Nicholas II is reading Ivan Block in blocks
Predictions are horrific
So those are wants out he wants he wants to figure out a way to stop this dangerous cycle that the modern world seems to be for
Forcing all the great Powers into
And I think it's a wonderful
Sort of commentary on the attitude of the times that these guys thought that they could do this it looks like rainbows and unicorns
We modern people but to then they must have thought
Reasonable people can sit down over cigars and whiskey
See this Dynamic that we've got ourselves caught up in realize that it's in no one's interest and reasonable people
Can figure a way out of this
And in 1898
These are of Russia proposed something that will be called the hate
France to deal with this
There are many ways
At the 1899 Hague
Going to be another one in 1907
And truthfully it looks like an early version of Arms Control agreement you will see throughout the
20th century
Which you can also View
Multiple lenses
The first one is you can take it at face value
The ways are sold at
If you want to
Use modern terms desires PR people
When he issues this invitation to the rest of the world leaders
Your couch is this whole thing is a common-sense effort
At a high-minded idea
Is the goal of this conference he wants to put together with quote
Seeking to make the great idea of universal peace
Triumph over the elements of trouble and Discord
And quote
We might sell an arms-control conference today like that
This is the era where you really see for the first time in human history
The growth of what today we would call the International Peace movement
It had many conferences before the Hague conference
To promote these ideas and there was a general feeling
A progress on these issues and sodas are made been playing into that although
Desert was kind of interesting dude
Very much a similar role on the monarchy dice
As the Germans got with Kaiser Wilhelm a very mediocre sort of guy not the sort of person you could imagine ever getting the
This job if it were merit-based
He's the same Czar the last czar
By the way
Who will fall victim in under sort of the sway of
The person that ours is sometimes called The Mad Monk grigory Rasputin although he's more interesting than that probably deserves more credit than that
What kind of again shows you
Bizarre is a kind of an idealistic romantic
I mean he might have bought into this stuff it might be legitimate on the czar's part
But like most Arms Control agreements
There's a
Realpolitik side to this thing
The Czar knows that his armies are falling behind in this technological race the old line about arms controller
Bereavement is if you're losing an arms race it's a good time to have an arms control agreement
And when the powers that are invited to this Hague conference asked for clarification of what's on the agenda
The Czar and his people give them eight or nine points that are going to be goals of the conference
Any 8 or 9 points to a 21st century mind
Are fascinate
Because it really shows you what the Czar wants to come out of this conference
The czar's
Number to gold for example that the agenda give to the rest of the participants says quote
To prohibit the use in the armies and fleets
Have any new kind of firearms whatever
End of new explosive
Were any powders more powerful than those now in use
Either for rifles or Cannon
And quote
Now
This is a staple to some degree of Arms Control agreements ever since I mean
The US and the Soviet Union were having an arms control agreement on anti-ballistic Missile agreement or whatever they may have
Rules on technological progress
But they aren't trying to stop
All technological progress
What does r wants to do
Is freeze thing
Where they are
He doesn't want anymore
Research to increase the killing power
That already exists in military
He doesn't want any more deployment
If you accidentally discover that new Battleship gun that will shoot twice as far as your current one you can't deploy it
He wants the size of armies Frozen and then reduced he wants to size of military budgets Frozen and then reduced
This is a person who clearly shows
His main issue with the way things are
Is the pace of change
And he wants this conference to address it
Nothing modern people who will often freak out
If the promised phone upgrade that's supposed to be released today is late in the internet will blow up with angry people
I've had their pace of change sabotage
The people in the late 19th century can probably be forgiven for thinking something we would assume is impossible
Is possible
The first time I ever encountered this idea by the way was in James Burks
Wonderful TV series from the 1980s the day the universe changed
We asked the question
Is humankind looks in a down the road
Where a particular branch of knowledge seems to be taking them
Can they decide if they don't like the destination to just
Not learn that branch of knowledge at all or the wall it off so that no one learns it
To Modern people that sounds impossible
Two people in the late 19th century they would have been able to show you multiple historical examples where that have been done
The Catholic church was very good out of the medieval times for example
Durban Chinese Emperors who could do it well
The idea of creating 4biddenknowledge and then preventing people from having it or using it
Was Not Unusual in this time.
That's what the Czar wants
He wants to slow
Or retard
The pace of change
And I always try to remind myself
How whipsawed all these people were in This Time. By the pace of change to
That's really what the 19th century is
The are aware at all speeds up
If you could for example
Graph
Human technological progress the way you would a stock market performance graph
Starting at the beginning of human history ending yesterday
You don't having your ups and downs all throughout history
You noticed a couple of things right off the bat
The first thing you notice that there are UPS
And downs
One thing the modern mind seems
Define incomprehensible
Is the progress that removes backward
The people who lived in 1904 example
Reading history books that made that sound like a historical law of nature
They had every reason to believe
The Tiara they were living in might be the last of a golden age before a fall because after all
That's what it happened to every other golden age that they look back on
The first thing the modern mine
Sees when it looks at the Historical
Stock performance chart showing human technological progress that there's a bunnyhop sort of dynamic going
Two steps forward
One step
You might get a big upturn
You know when the New Kingdom Egyptians come on the scene
Maybe another uptick when the Han Chinese arrived another uptick when the Roman Empire arrived but after your Roman Empire High as you get you
Roman Empire bubble dump
And a couple hundred years later when it's gone you have Germanic barbarians and formerly Roman territory looking
Crumbling Aqueduct and wondering what sort of giants once roamed the Earth
I could build stuff like that
The first thing you're going to notice as a modern person
Is a technology doesn't always move forward
The second thing you're going to notice
Is the throughout most of human history
Weather it's going up
We're going down it's moving at a glacially slow pace
The amount of change from the beginning of time to about the Renaissance is nowhere near what you would expect if we were anywhere
We're near the pace of change we have now
Very little overall growth
Until you hit the Renaissance Mac little up
And I'm the century after that little bit more and then about 1810 1820
The graph becomes almost vertical overnight
Shoots up instead of ever plateauing as we all know it goes Evermore vertical everyday
Now we're used to this because it's been going that way for a while
Does our generation yeah that's century
That's the first time it really takes off and those people are looking at that isn't
Extremely destabilizing Force
Bizarre things perhaps
An arms control agreement will help Russia from falling too far behind their more technologically sophisticated neighbor
Now as you might expect they're more technologically sophisticated neighbors see this as an artificial constraint on
On the fact that they're winning
Take the Germans as a perfect
Examples of people who are trying very hard to make up for what they see as the rest of the powers treating them like dirt
They're the ones building more ships than anybody and trying to catch up to Britain the other ones modernizing their military every day they're the
The ones who instead of being Panic by the pace of change are taking advantage of it
To them this looks like an agreement that will lock in their inferiority
And by the way
That's a situation that will repeat many times after this. In Arms Control negotiations
Trying to gain
An edge on your opponent if you were losing the arms race as I said
Good time to have an arms-control agree
Finally there's an interesting group of people
And they really don't exist anymore not opened
They're on the opposite side of the Ledger from save the
International Peace movement
In ramping up during this era
The people who think that war is a good thing
Forget about International
You don't golzar realpolitik people that literally believe that humankind thrives on war and it without War
We will drown in materialism
The only thing that keeps us focused on the higher things
That's an idea that is sort of Gone by the wayside
In Western culture
Today is
Peace activist to argue against
You know realpolitik people
In the 1880s for example you have guys like the Elder helmuth Von moltke who tries to explain to people why Pisa
She's not even a good idea
You're deluded he said quote
Perpetual peace is a dream
And not even a beautiful dream
And here is an integral part of God's ordering of the universe
In war man's noblest virtues come into play
Courage and renunciation Fidelity to duty and a Readiness for sacrifice that does not stop at giving up life
Life itself
Without War the world would be swamped in materialism
And quote
Others will point out
But if you decide to try to make war
You know what thing of the past what happens to all those people that are in situations
Where
You are struggling against foreign oppression for example you going to tell someone they can't free themselves
I'm a horrible pressure because you
Violence
Is bad
But finally
You also have the people that the modern peace activist would recognize very well
Those who adhere
2A
Belief system
That is difficult to argue with
In terms of new historical proof
You going to use history as your guide
You're going to argue that the best way to keep the
The piece is to be so strong
Adidas almost suicidal
Fight with you
Best exemplified perhaps
British Admiral
Sir John Fisher who try to explain
To a friend of his
That when he sounds
Horrific
He's really an advocate of peace
And he said quote
I am not for War I am for peace that is why I am Pursuit cream Navy
Writing your autograph book at the Hague the supremacy of the British Navy is the best security for the Peace of the world
My sole object is
What you call my truculence is all for peace
If you rub it in
Both at home and abroad
But you are ready for instant war with every unit of your strength in the first line
And waiting to be first in
And hit your enemy in the belly
Kick him when he's down
Boil your prisoners in oil if you take any
And torture his women and children
Then people will steer clear review
And quote
Well as harsh as that is it has a certain amount of
Historical evidence to back it up doesn't
When asked
How to make war more humane
The nephew of
Helmuth Von moltke the Elder that would be Helmuth Von moltke the younger
The field Marshal in charge of Germany's war effort at the start of the first world war famously said the only way to make war humane
Is to make it short
Hence
The Schlieffen
We talked about this
So-called Schlieffen Plan in the last episode
Almost
Mythological pre-war plan for how Germany was going to deal with this terrible two front problem
My analogy is like a bar fight
Is there a
A meme online that I saw
Comparing World War 1 to a bar fight
But it's a little like
You know that Germany knows it's going to have a bar fight
With France and Russia
But they know that France is going to be there five minutes before Russia so they get to the bar right on time knock France out in 5 minutes later
When Russia shows up late
Stick it to fight the Germans one-on-one that's the war plan
In a nutshell
But the questions surrounding this war plan
Have become maybe the number one most controversial issue that historians argue with each other and froth at the mouth over
And yours truly you know I don't have a dog in this fight I'm just going to sit back
Eat popcorn and watch the very entertaining discussion
On the sleeping so-called Schlieffen Plan
Because it's not just a
This or that
It's like a Kennedy assassination thing where I mean every different Theory you can think of is out there
There was a sleeping pill
It wasn't Schlieffen Plan but it was modified
X x x x
The people often on multiple sides of this issue are very credible
So I'm not getting it
Waiting on a discussion with scientist you just have to store watch some
How to take a position on the so-called Schlieffen Plan and we'll call it the Schlieffen Plan because that's what everybody knows it by
But suffice it to say that
Sleep is retired for quite a long time before the first world war breaks out
So whatever plan the Germans were going to use are in the hands
A helmuth Von moltke the younger the guy who's leading this whole
Early
War on the Germans part and he's been the one designed his plan for a long time after the first world war is over
You will get a bunch of German generals writing memoirs
Sort of castigating this Malta guy
For deviating from schlieffen's amazingly brilliant plan
It's the way we're supposed to hear you just stayed with the plan the way it was supposed to be
You know that we win the war
It's worth talking about the plan a little bit
From a military history standpoint
The Schlieffen Plan
And again I have to say as it's normally understood
Because somebody out there's going to have a very good
Piece of evidence showing it
Totally different that I'm saying right now
What is it as it's commonly understood the Schlieffen Plan
Is a fantastic military camp
Involved
Taking trips
From basically everywhere else you might have to fight
And taking as many of them as you can and sticking them on that one part that's going to be the sledgehammer
Ahead of the slideshow
End
Your superiority in numbers at the head of that Sledgehammer going to be so overwhelming it's going to crush everything
And then you can swing it around
And trap all the French armies that are sitting on the French border in a waiting to fight the Germans on the other side of the German border
But the head of the Hammers coming through Belgium
A neutral country
Going to swing from above
And then it's going to collapse down on all those French armies facing the Germans
And trapped them in the rear
But it's a huge Gamble
What if you screw up
What if the Russians mobilized faster than you think they are going to
Well they'll be mowing down your tiny little forces left there to stop them and they're not that far
From Berlin and the first territory they're going to take over happens
To be the ancestral home
A precious nobility
Including
Kaiser Wilhelm
So nobody wants to see the Russians anywhere near Prussia
But they happen to be cut in air pressure anyway
So that's a problem
Also
Everyone knows the French are going to want to retake those territories that the Germans took a generation before
Which is down at the franco-german border which means the French were going to attack there was a lot of forces you pull too many people away from there
The French to be breaking through into Southern Germany while the head of your
Sledgehammer still working its way
You around French like a terrible gamble cuz if you screw it up you could lose the war
Remember two things
Schlieffen is writing the war plan and he supposedly came up with this idea
The conditions are differ
The German Army is different in size
So is the French army
The Russians have almost seen a complete collapse in 1905 of their hold Dynasty when they're falling apart they just lost the war
War against Japan
They're nowhere near as formidable as they'll be
10 years later write 9 years later
But that's when most casted
And the situations are different and he has to recalculate things and
The second part of that whole equation is it sleeping
Could afford to be a gambler
Because he doesn't actually have to do it
Sleeping is a gambler
On paper
Multi is a guy like to make this work in real time
And not have the downside happen
And live through it
Annie's more to pass
Maybe you would say more of a realist
And he won't
Put
As many troops
What's in the sledgehammer part of the attack
As sleeping would have dictated you should
He walked into the other front
2 is greater degree and leave them
That wide open
But he can't
Assume that the war will be won so automatically
But you can just know that Germany will be safe and won't be broken true in all these areas you denuded in other words
Most of the more conservative guy
But if this plan is true I'm going to keep saying that disclaimer so don't get in trouble if this plan is true
It puts Malta in a position of accepting a gamble of a plan
Forgot he's not a gambler
But that's the plan
And in order to understand the sledgehammer side of this plan
You have to have some sort of conception
Of the size of the armies involved
For comparison purposes and again sort of demonstrates how much things have changed
In a military sense and how they've exploded since Napoleonic time
If you look at
Assumptions made by people who study the Roman Empire
One of the favorite
Subject
They will debate
Is how many human beings
We're in the military
Of the Roman Empire at its height
Do police and take care of
That massive ancient state
I don't mean anyone battle I mean the total military
Power of the Roman Empire at its height
And you will get numbers
Anywhere from 450 thousand men at the low end
About 750,000 men
The higher
Now
The numbers of German
They're making their way through Bells
In August 1914 as part of the Sledge hammers head
Is at least
Some numbers put that up to 1.2 million
That means that
Flanking Force the head of the sledgehammers we keep calling at this moving through Belgium to smacked
The French like a door swinging on hinge
Is at least at Large
Is the entire military of the Roman Empire
And if those lower numbers are actually closer to the truth
For the empire
New Total military
Capability
Then you might have a German Army moving through Belgium that's twice the size
The entire world
I totally justifies
All of the worst fears of these
Do people in the 19th century worried about that the kind of folks would call ahead conference in and write about peace and all that kind
And the people who understood what the growth in the military technology was going to do Ivan blocks ideas are about to be
Proven
True in no uncertain fashion
These people were used to Napoleon
Will Napoleon
Giant gamble of invading Russia may have had its highest 750,000 man across the entire front
You know from a giant front Russia
That's what you have moving through the
Tiny little road system in the railroad system of Belgium
Napoleon's Grand Army
Is Your Flank
Wow
I keep trying to remind myself
That what the Germans are trying to do here is not perhaps as much of a of a weird gamblers you might think I'm going also need to remember
That most of the people in the higher leadership positions in the German military
I've done all this before
In fact
They fought friends before it's probably the most important war that happened between Napoleon's times and the
The first world war and most people outside of Europe know nothing about the Franco
Depression War
Of 1870 1871
But essentially forget what it says you know when the history books cuz it makes it look like a nine-month war
Essentially the German smashed the French in a month and a half
It's a fantastically interesting conflict and it's shaped
The perceptions and views of these people in the higher leadership positions because they were Junior officers who fought in that war
Bright
They watched
2 amazing things happen they watch the German armies
Crap
An entire French army I like 8090 thousand men in one of the French fortresses that was there too
You keep the Germans from crossing the border
And then
The actual Emperor Franz himself a guy named Napoleon the third another one of those
Interesting roles of the monarchy dice leads a relief Army going to break the siege right and rescues other Army
Have another 80 or 90 thousand guys
And the Germans managed to surround the whole army with the emperor
And force them to surrender
Which kind of course means that entire Army that's also trap nearby have to surrender to
I mean the French fought on for a long time doggedly
The people of Paris rose up I mean there was a fantastic resistance at
What the war was over in a month and a half
That was the way the Germans wanted to do it again this time
And the people who did it last time
Are the ones in command of a lot of these
In a Coors and armies
And in the general staff
Now
As the Germans try to make their way you know through Belgium and not have this important time schedule screwed up
The French on the other side
Are trying to figure out what the heck's going on
Part of what we modern people have to remember and I was trying to try to put myself in their positions very hard because we're in an era
Where the battlefield especially to Western powers and most especially to the United States the battlefield is totally visible for the
You can hide yourself in Foley and sometimes Maybe
For nearby we're going to have female thermal sensors and stuff
But the battlefield is visible to
We're used to this
Most of human history the fog of War as it's known as huge
Because
It keeps you from seeing what's about to happen until it just is about to happen you don't get a lot of advance notice to plan
That's why aircraft stop
Becoming really important
Because they take the eyes
Of the military
Put them up in the air and it
Extend how far back you can see
If you see
You know Army is moving to another area you can safely assume oh I better move my Army to another area something's going to happen over
During this early part of the battle
No one is sure what's happening on the Allied side the furniture is worried about how they get the British over here to fight
With as many men as they can bring over as they are about where are the Germans coming in and in what sort of strength
You see the French have suspected for a very long time
That the Germans were going to do this outflanking move in Belgium
That was not totally unexpected
The part that may have caught them off-guard
Is what they were thinking you know the French through Belgium with
The guys running the French military this time working on their own War plans assumptions
Simply won't believe that the size
Moving through Belgium is as big as it is and let's remember
Molka will be criticized after the war by other German generals who are mad not bigger
I mean end of the French have
Huge problem
Because they have one of the loosest agreements
I've ever run into in my life
In a military cooperation
Their battle plans call for the British army to guard their entire line we talked about
Align the French military line runs from Switzerland in the south
To Belgium in the North
Millions of men
In multiple arms
And by the way on the other side of the board of the Germans have the same thing
First time in human history
Did you had millions of men squaring off against millions of men
But the French
Left Flank
Is counting on having the British army there to Anchorage
That agreement
Has less paperwork attached to it than you would normally generate when you buy a house
For all intents and purposes as we said it's a handshake
Handshake deal that we will go to war with you if War breaks out and a handshake deal with only one government in a
Country where government can come and go
And we're public opinion isn't Unified
A nation that
You had centuries
Use of antagonistic history with
And only like 5 or 8 years of
Your friendly cooperation
What's more when Britain gets into this war
And then the first thing that the British people here is we're going to send the troops that would defend us if the Germans decide to land on our Coast
Flying to France
A question over how many troops to spare eventually the bef
We'll get two friends
With 70
Thousand men
Five divisions
For Infantry
1 calorie
To give you an idea
I'm with 70000 manner
Five divisions means on this front
The Germans are
Deploying
Like 85 divisions on the Western Front
70000 man seems like nothing that's the tiny little you know it's the army of a sea power isn't it that's the
Tiny little Force
That Bismarck a generation before that iron in blood German Diplomat had famously said when one of his aides and what are they
Lander Army on Arcos he says then I'll have them arrested
This is the army that was so small you can joke
About a resting
But here's the difference unlike all the other major armies of
Participants in this war
The British army or professional
Long
Standing
Regular for
With a lot of people in the
Especially the noncommissioned officer ranks who were life
First and who win this war started immediately called up there reservist
Guys who serve 10 15 20 years before had fought in places like
South Africa in the Boer War and they
Turn of the century
The institutional memory
Of these units
Was deep
Quality Inn
These forces was in
Tents that used to have
Unlimited Marksman practice and get financial rewards for
The Winning Edge
Did actually in a lot of the people in these units fought in actual combat with modern weapons
My favorite Source from this early. Is an Irishman
Who's actually fighting in the bet
Name is John Lucy
And he's one of the few British side
Reporters I guess you could call him he's a soldier who writes from this very early.
Because he was right in the first wave
And he explains
You know the difference between his unit and the rest of the Continental troops and he does so in a very chauvinistic
Very proud fashion
But he claims
Quote
The British Army in 1914 was more used to battle than that of any other Nation
He possessed the highest and bravest Traditions that can be engendered in a fighting force
And it's experience of wars with such
That our own regiment though a young one in the Army had so many battle honors
But they were difficult to memorize
And quote
Bajan lose he's only 20
He didn't have a long service history under his belt but when the reservists arrive
He watches
Men who appear to be just regular folks off the street transform themselves
Into grizzled British veteran
Quote
Are reservists came streaming in to make up our war strength
Cheerful careless fellows of all time
Some in bowler hats and smart suitings
Others in descending scale down to the Garb of tramps
Soon like us
They were uniformed and equipped with field kits
And the change was remarkable
Smart sergeants and corporals in beer ribbon Veterans of the South African War
Hatched out of that crowd of nondescript civilians
And took their place in duties as if they had never left the army
They were an excellent block
But their numbers increased our strength to an uncomfortable extend
And quote
What John was he found to be an uncomfortable
Increasing of
Numbers
When they arrived at the continents seem like a tiny little Trickle
British soldier
But the quality of this Army that came to be known as the old
Contemptibles
Was of the
Higher level
Matching the top German unit
It was ironically
Under the command of a British general
Name French
Cooking very much like the
Sir John French will lead
The bef
The British Expedition
On the continent
Just in time to
Play their historic role
In what Sir Arthur
Conan Doyle
Called
The most terrible August in the history of the world
To be involved
In several battles
That are all called
The battle of the front
There's a bunch of little battles
That are all
Wrapped up into this
One big event called the battle of the
The Frontiers
What really means it is
All the fighting that was going on along this front and there are several
Perry's encounter thrust it go on
I'm going to spend a little bit more time than I normally plan to for the rest of
The series on this battle because this
Battle of the Frontiers is in so many ways
The most interesting
Moment of this war
First of all
It's what we talked about for a episode and a half
Now it's the Rubber meets the road MoMA
The testing moment
For all this military Theory and hypothesis it's been happening
In some cases
Over the last hundred years
You get to see
If people
Assumptions about a distant weapon system would work or that tactic would fare
You get to see you know which of those
Turn out to be correct and which ones don't
And
A lot of the time these armies will go into combat
Hamstrung
By decisions that were made a decade before
Terms of
What's the Army's doctrines going to be
For the tactics or how they're going to be
You know dressed and equipped let me take the French
The French will go into this Modern War and it is almost
Impossible to understand this today cuz if there's a ludicrousness to it
That shows off
Another century
You want to see the 19 century class
With the twentieth century it happens in this battle of the Frontiers in August
The French go into combat with almost the exact same uniform
The Grandfather's war in 80
A blue jacket with tails
WYD
Red
Pants that look like targets
And acted like it too
Their officers would have
White
Hats and white gloves I mean again targets
They will send the Cavalry to go fight
That look like
When you can go look at your history book in 1914 and they often have pictures of his cavalry
I told my friend who was always asking
We know how to love to see a picture of Napoleon's cuirassier
You know his famous Cavalry with the
Breastplates in the horsehair plumed helmets
You know when the Sabres in the whole thing I said you don't have to
Wish for a picture of Napoleon's cuirassier they're going off to war in 1914 they look identical
Armor and all
That's the old world going off to war and you can see it visually
Think of how
The French soldiers hamstrung by that
The British have been using khaki
You know for themselves
Since the colonial wars
In the 1880s
Aren't you going to go into this war
Looking like
Walking
Peacock
Tana French soldiers
The price for that still pay the price for not having much of the way of heavy artillery to again
These were all ideas that you could logically backup
The French decided they wanted to have more mobile Army so we don't need that big heavy cumbersome
Maslow artillery to slow it down by the time that gets anywhere the battles going to be over anyway
Sounds great
In theory
Till you try it
And you find out your soldiers are in terrible trouble on the actual Battlefield
Cuz they don't have any heavy artillery
There's a reputation
Can the French have military in the United States
But it is inordinately influenced by the way the Second World War
I always try to tell people
You misunderstand France's military
Reputation.
Casper hundreds of years
They're considered one of the finest if not the finest land army in the world
A hundred years before this time
A little Corsican guy is using you know especially as the hardcore his armies to conquer the majority
Give the world that mattered at this time
And the one that
Only the rest of the majority of the world is colonies
Did it with French troops
They will often
Heroically
Throw their lives down to try to overcome these deficiencies that they enter war with
I think you could make it
EK sedan all three War
3 over 75 years the French and Germans fought with
1870 to 1945
At the average French soldier on the ground was hamstrung by his leadership
In all three of those cops
In the second world war and historically tragically
But I would
Suggest that the war out of those three
In which French leadership
Perform the best
Was in the first World War
There are a bunch of different General
Think second world war France
Would have given their right arm
Led by
A guy who is icon
I always thought of him is like
The French Churchill
In what Churchill was to Britain in the second world war this guy is to France in the first
And he has all these same stereotypically interesting anecdotes and characteristics The Churchill had been
Instead of them being stereotypically British
Is Churchill's work
Are stereotypically golf
French
You know Churchill had this thing with alcohol that was part of his image and part of the fun
With this guy its food
And that's because it fits perfectly with his physical
Sort of
Image kiss you
In every way
He's tall
He's fat
Got a giant bushy white mustache in a plastic look on his face all the time
Chakra
If I mispronounce that
Again
It's going to be the first of many my apologies
Still
You're the lion of France
A lot of French house
Interesting
You know I've read a significant amount on this person and I'm not sure I understand him any better
The before I started and once more I'm not sure these authors did either
He is like a novel
Desk
He is imperturbable good luck scratching the surface of figuring out what you have there and even is contempt
One thing when you read quotes
The people who knew him say about him is one they they say different
+ 2
Sometimes they didn't know
What this guy was up
2 min
And sometimes you look at something and you wonder if he's just a little doll or slow or receive you know Sly like a fox and just hide
And every time it's it's he's an interesting guy you could produce guy a long time
And I'm still not
Really get a good idea about what you're dealing
The one thing you can say about him
Is
He's got one of those qualities of generalship to
It's just going to be a perfect match for what's needed at the time
And I've always said that
The generalship is absolutely an art and in the same way that art
Tennessee's the manifestation of the artist
Personality so dope Translate
Light it and its own unique waiting in the art form
General ship is like that
Tattoo
You can see all these different
Kinds of generals wall have
These different kinds of personalities
And they come in that
The key is to try to find your strengths and then
In a figure out a way to make those drinks work for you on the battlefield take for example
He's really aggressive
These quick thinking hard pushing dashing sort of guys
Presbyterian the famous
Guy who
Basically created the German
Tank approach in the Second World War
He was that kind of guy
The guy by the way who's commanding
The most important Army on the German side in this
The sledgehammer head Army first Army
The guy just like this too hard driving aggressive
Kind of guy
That sort of approach is perfect in some situations and in some arms but then he needs a bean-counter guy sometimes.
That's what Von moltke is either bean-counter he sits there and plan everything out to the nth degree and make sure all that
T's are crossed and the I's dotted you want of anything I'm those guys are very useful to
The inspirational General like an Alexander the Great who get out there and
Get your troops to perform
Benefits of
Heroism that may be a lesser man or woman couldn't have gotten them
There's all these different kinds of General
Jafra is the kind that doesn't ever go
That's what he brings
He refuses to pay
He's almost
Frightful
In situations
But he's about to experience
That they are not only stressful to the point of panic but the perhaps Panic is the right emotion to have
Are there historians out there
Who suggest that we should not look at that as such a great quality to bring to the table
Because
It might be Jeffers own shortcomings and some of the other Arts of generalship
That made it necessary for there to be a guy who wouldn't panic at the top to begin with wouldn't be
Needing to panic if you'd have been a better player of that blind chess game that we talked about earlier
And maybe Shoppers not that good at that game
Hence the situation becomes
Panic inducing Hensel leader that's very good at stopping Panic is
Just what you needed the time
Anyway
Might be yourself
Reinforcing sort of thing
But I think it's hard to deny
The France would have given up
A right arm and both legs
Used to have this guy in the second row
The reason that this guy is going to be so necessary this imperturbability is going to be so necessary
Is because of how this first round in This heavyweight championship fight that's going to go on for 4 years is going to go
If you going to use a boxing analogy here for this this going to be a boring fight
At the fight goes on you know where things slow down to a dull Roar and everybody looking for tactical opportunities in
But the first round is wild
Massive Haymaker swings misses dropping the other guy for you know an 8-count I mean it's going to be a while
First round
And if you lose your head
You can lose the war
So having jafra at the at the French High command shows that the French are not going to lose their head
I can't
Help but think about the German
Von moltke is a very interesting guy in the sense that he almost looks like a guy
Who doesn't want to be there
You know he is the nephew of one of the greatest heroes in German military history it's almost like he went into the fan
Family business
But whereas those guys thought about nothing but War all the time and remember
Sleeping the legendary writer of the Schlieffen Plan is supposed to have died
Still saying stuff about the Schlieffen Plan the last words on his lips are supposedly make sure to keep the right wings
These are people who have no Hobbies
Other than War
Von moltke the younger is a guy who famously said that art
And I think about this guy
In the most
One of the most stressful positions in all history once this
Breaks out
Remember he has no illusions
About what the stakes are he's the one who famously said
That the war that he's launching
Will decide the course of history for the next hundred years
And it certainly have think of the pressure on that
Think about the fact
That his plan that he's operating with is a terrible Gamble
And then watch how every flip of the coin so far in this conflict
Has gone against them
And if you're judging this fight based on who landed the latest punch
Von moltke and the Germans are losing
Right from the very beginning
I think about the coin flips
Already happened
Think about
The Belgium one
To begin with
I mean you were hoping the
When you invaded Belgium they just sort of stood by the side of the road and let you go through
Maybe would feed you and everything right
You would get that's what that's what your hope would have been a flip of the coin instead the belgians resisted you
They destroyed the communication and transportation system you were hoping to use and then to make matters worse some of them were shooting at
That you allegedly but your troops have been executing belgians which makes you look terrible on the world stage
So that coin flip the wrong way
Can you flip the coin again maybe Britain won't get involved when we violate
The neutrality of Belgium right it's just a scrap of paper is a German Diplomat famously said
Hope that landed on the wrong side of the coin to the British came in you lost that
Another flip happens
Starting on August 15th and the timetable going to get weird now.
Because their stuff happening on multiple fronts that overlap with each other cuz while this is going on
I know the first Maneuvers are going on in the west to but but on the 15th of August if your Von moltke watching how your
Your planned attack is is going and you haven't even gotten your Sledgehammer head through Belgium yet
So you're still a ways away from your attack doing anything but you got things starting to collapse around you
On August 15th
Discern
Remember this is a moderate
Fighting a great power you know some Serbian gunman killed the Austrian Archduke and that's why we're here
Right when the one thing everyone was sure about is that no matter what happens in this conflict Serbia is going to get there but
Cuz they're fighting Austria-Hungary is right next door and their Global power
The austro-hungarian they're camped out
Put him on a hillside by a river on on the 15th of August a hundred eighty thousand storms attack them
The austro-hungarian Army has
1000 people
Headed
It's morale just collapse
We told you before the serbs are one of those people
Historically who in the military sense kind of punch above their weight glass
They're ferocious Fighters
They're aggressive aggressively LED
And the austro-hungarian forces were apparently more riddled with problems than anyone knew
And a lot of them will drown
Routing across this River
Pursued closely by 180000 Serbia
Sentry Army
Think about what this does if you're Von moltke
Got in terms of stress
Because you're hoping that the austro-hungarians can help you keep the Russians off your neck until you're done
In France remember you got to deal with enemies on each side of you you're hoping your ally right there is going to be able to help
And yet they just got their tail kit
I am moderate-sized power what's going to happen when they pay
And then
On the 17th
Of August
The biggest disaster at all
Von moltke
And the Russians arrive
Early
Talk about flipping the coin before the war assuming
You can get all the stuff done before the Russians mobilize
And then they mobilize
Early
So by August 17th
Are mochas has problems
Everywhere
Where an enemy becomes a real question
Whether or not
He's ever going to be able to use his War winning sledgehammer
Because maybe he'll have lost the war everywhere else
Before that even writing you can read from this time. 1914 to think that the war's almost already over
Meanwhile on the 14th of August
Jafra in the French launched an attack of the alsace-lorraine
The first
Realtor
They sent a token force in there on the 7th of August
What you see
Remember 7th of August is 4 days
France Germany
Declare war they send a token force in there
It would messages from the French
Leadership about
Still here we're home you're back in the bosom of France all these wonderful things kisses picnic baskets flowers wine the whole deal
In a welcome with open arms
And then all of a sudden
Little token Force
With the roses and wine and everything has to run back across the French border because
The German Force that's nearby is not a toy
Enforce
On August 14th
The day before the serbs smash that austro-hungarian army
That's so discomforts Von mulka
The French launch two armies
Alsace-lorraine and it's serious
Now it's on
Now we have
Two of the best armies in the world clashing head-on with significant numbers of
Anna French push the Germans back
And the next day
Play pushing back again
And then the next day they pushing
Now
It should be noted
That while the rest of the world thinks this looks like just one more disaster for Germany side
We have all these other problems that Russians are already in East Prussia and now look at the French the first time they launch a significant the tactic Germans are
Backing up
But that's one thing I'm sure Von multa wasn't stressed
Because that retreat by the Germans was all
The Germans of course
For decades new the French wood
Involve
Alsace-lorraine in any war effort and so they put troops there who had orders to
Retire
Did you sort of keep the French engaged
But move backwards as they move forward let them even into Germany
Shoot them as they're pursuing you
Take your
Toll on them if they're pursuing you but retire in good order take
Your guns with you
I just sort of
Pull them away from
All the parts of the war that
UC
When the French figure out about the sledgehammer of also compared it to a door on a hinge
Idiom all these German Army stretching from the Swiss border all the way up to Belgium and most of them are just there to keep
Keep the French occupy
The damage that's going to be done is going to be done by that door
Soda in Belgium and Lux
Convert
Swings closed
On top of the French Nation
The other German Army's job is to keep the French in front of the monkey
They can't turn around
And move in a different direction and do anything
But hammer and those French armies way down south in Alsace and Lorraine with your down by the Swiss border
That you're pursuing German armies back into the interior of Germany
Are just getting
Farther
And farther away
From where they can help
Once the French realize they need every army they can get their hands on
To deal with that
Threat so
Anmol cuz not upset about
This is part of the deal
And that starts on August 14
17th Ave
Continues the Russians are in East Prussia now
The austrians have been defeated on their front
Since the 7th of August but really big on the 11th and 12th of August
The British expeditionary Force has been arrived
Driving on the car
They keep saying they're not going to be ready to fight until maybe the 26th of August
But the French would like them there sooner
One Frenchman in particular
Is desperate
The pretty show up as early as possible
This is the French General who is commanding
The Army on France's Left Flank
Bright
The last
Army
You know it's kind of facing sort of Belgium
Where if you look to your right they've got
Several armies millions of men all the way down to the Swiss border
Totally protected from anybody penetrating our ranks and hitting Us in the flank
What is that 5th Army under General name lanrezac
Looks to the left
Looks North
There's nobody there
Is open land
Is maneuvering room for an enemy to get around his flanks and destroy him and roll the whole French line
Turn up all the way down to switch
So he's got a vested interest
And being aware
How many potential threats out there cuz he's going to take it in the flank
In which one shows up and he perceives even before the war start
She sending messages in July
Did you offer saying we can all signs point to a German Advance through Belgium basic
Which is one reason you knew the high command knew about
That they just nobody knew how big it was
Does General and rezac keep telling them
Every couple of days he's sending messages to the high command going
Uno latest reports are
Oregon huge attacking me basically the way history will vindicate this guy
Is he correctly perceives the power
And destination of this German law
Long before anyone else
And one of the historical what-ifs in this time.
Is one of Jeff read taking what he was saying seriously sooner
Again maybe you don't need
To be such a wonderful
Stability Factor when Panic is all around you if you don't make a mistake like not listening to this General
It would create the Panic inducing situation to begin with
Jafra basically think the guy is panicking
And then he starts saying you know as it becomes apparent that something is moving
Belgium Emil sports are going
Turn down
He starts thinking this is going to be a good thing for the same reason is a good thing for the Germans to have those French go through alsace-lorraine and keep
Advancing away from where the action is going to be
Jeanfreau's ideas listen even if the Germans are going through Belgium with a large Force
All the better
Our plans going to be the cut that large Force off of this is a swinging gate or door
We will hit it at the hinge
And then we will roll up behind it all the way up to the water you know in the
In the North Sea of the English Channel right there and then you're cut off and then this wonderful Luna Sledgehammer blow
Becomes the surrounded
Entrapped cream of your army
So he turned a negative into a positive and basically would tell
When rejected
You have nothing to worry
1 rezac.
Different
I figured his chances would be
Improve
Get that British force would hurry up
And come up on his left
So that even though the British might have an open left blank he wouldn't have one
And
It's at that
Point
Did the Battle of the Frontiers bro
The battle of the Frontiers
Is named that because it's
The time where the general eruption of violence
I'm On the franco-german Border hat
And there are a lot of different encounters that are all
A part of this larger, is essentially there is an umbrella term that covers all the viola
On the franco-german
Almost
And it turns out to be
A really important thing for the German war effort
But it did
Because
You know by about August 19th
The German situation really is bad
You said earlier but things have even gotten worse those Russians in East Prussia
And it showing up sooner than expected had defeated some German forces that went out and try to deal with them
All of a sudden it looks like that flight might be collapsing
It's hard to get real excited about anything if you're molka
Who's nickname
Given to him by the Kaiser was something that translates loosely
Too gloomy Gus
Anyway
Not exactly
Optimus anyway
He couldn't have been feeling too good about the situation
On the 19th or 20
He receives a request from one of his Generals in the feet
It's the guy who is retreating
From all those French forces retiring in good order taking his guns with them instead of drawing them away from the action
He's one of the wonderful German royalty that part of this this isn't often the second where we didn't have
We have all these guys like
Prince Rupert
Avaria
And He commands
The force is retreating
He doesn't like retreating
You don't get a lot of medals for retreating it's not exactly what he was hoping to do with an Army in this war
Wework West
Devon molca can I attack
Now this goes against the idea what he supposed to do right he's the retreat or he
He pulls his French Force away from where the sledgehammers going to hit
What makes a pretty good case
These French or ask
Can for it
They're sitting ducks
They've been sort of like getting more and more disordered and strung out after days of pursuit
Doing nothing we've been shooting them with artillery and weakening them
They're ripe for a Counterattack will crush them
And this is one of several into
It will happen
Literally in the next few days
Did some historians have pointed to four years at the moment when the Germans lost the war
In this case
Some historians say that mold cause response to Crown Prince rupprecht of Bavaria
Lost in the war
He told
Group rate
He could Counterattack the
4 strong out
Disorganized
On August 20
He dies
Now
This is the time
Where you get to see
Perhaps from a soldier's perspective
The thing that had changed battle and warfare the most
Really come into its own
Machine guns made a huge dick
Make no mistake about it and there were a lot of things that seem relatively benign when you look at them that maybe
Huge difference
Just to like barbed wire
What the element the technology in land Warfare had altered the most
In terms of
Something that would change the face of warfare and however
Was fought and experienced by human beings on the ground
Artillery
Had come
Leaps and Bounds
Beyond anything anyone
Unexpected
And it's artillery
Did on August 20th
It's the French
When they're still in
Tie column
Marching
And mustering
And just sitting around I mean later in the war
Ernst Junger
German Soldier will write about
The effect on a shell
One single artillery shell Landing in a group of people that were just
You're sitting around in a town square
Soldier comrade
And you said the one she'll killed 70th
Give them outright
Now imagine if you're in March column right
Gathered around us
A mess
Center or
Taking a
Religious
Service in in the field or whatever when you're closely match with your buddies
And then modern artillery
And remember
Part of this is the technology of the guns the other part of it is the science and engineering that goes into
You're making artillery effective not your shooting a gun up in the air but you should see that the scientific calculator
Soldiers on the grounds of the mathematics they had to do to make sure that everything was found in the right way and everything
And that really differentiated by the way
The good armies from the last good army the Russians had a ton of artillery
Didn't have good engineering people
Shooting it was often inaccurate and not effective
The British and the French and the Germans had
Exceptional
Working their artillery numbers very effective
And the German artillery was bigger
And better than anything that the French had this is where they find out
That idea that light mobile 75 millimeter artillery getting the job done in every situation
Was horribly
Flawed
In fact
It was outraged by the German pieces
The Germans could hit it
When they couldn't get the charm
When the German Army under
From Prince Rupert
It's
The French in accounting
Attack on August 20th
The artillery
As historian
Eric Brouse right
It's quote
The first Furious fighting
Occurred in southern Lorain
Where the French second Army having progressed 35km was hit at morang by the Germans six.
Counterattack with Superior artillery fire
From 105 mm and 150 mm howitzer
The Mirage crushed
Second Army formations that were assembling in tight rank
For the day's March forcing it to flee
And thereby compelling and exposed first Army to retreat as well
And quote
Now what Bros is talking about there is
When the Germans crushed the French second Army
And it has to retreat
It creates a hole in the line
And that's the most dangerous thing for any of these armies they want to maintain maintain an Unbroken
Because if there are places that can be penetrated by enemy forces
Those forces can move into those gaps
And then if they turn right
We're turn left
They're eating another Army in
Terribly vulnerable
Or they could continue to go deeper into the interior and strike at Logistics
And supply
Andrea Reyes
I mean the whole point is don't allow
You know what Gap to open up in your line and do whatever you can
To create
Or exploit
You know your enemy doing something like that with air forces
So when second Army gets
Smashed and Haster Retreat backwards first Army has to go with him
Just to make sure that the line stays unbroken and nobody can get
Indoor interior
Now
There's a lot of different things you might be able to draw conclusion why
What happened
You know in Alsace and Lorraine
Armies were hit by the Germans
Jennifer decided
That this allowed him to see where the Germans were we
As mentioned earlier this is about playing chess without knowing
You know where the other guys pieces are
Part of what Shoppers got to do as a commander has some detective work he has a rough idea how many
Forces the Germans have if he can identify
You know where those forces are he can start to figure out where the rest are
He figures if he's
Getting so hammered
Down in the south on August 20th
And
If he believed that General on his flank V army General that keeps telling in the Germans are making a major effort
Belgium
Where are all those troops coming from
They have to be pulled from somewhere
Hopper figure
The Germans are weak
At that point
He decided that they have been pulled from the German Centre
So they're strong down in alsace-lorraine by Switzerland the strong up in Belgium would have knocked down those Sports in there
They're coming at us like a door on a hinge so they're weak in the middle
Jennifer made a major mistake
And the major mistake was assuming the Germans would treat
The reserve forces the same way the French dip
The reserve forces are those forces that are not as competent not as highly trained as the regular military
French practice with those forces
What's to keep them in the reserve
Keep them back away from the action you use them to support people when you need more troops thrown in
But don't put them anywhere vulnerable you could lose the war with an experience
You're not up to standard troops like that
German
Totally integrate
Did the reserves and their armies any plan for this for a long time
They were using all their Reserves
So they had greater numbers actually involved in all these combat
Then Jeffers estimation
And this will cost him dearly
When he attacks the center of the German line
In a battle of
Frontiers
On August 20
XXII
In the center
Is a weird area because if the left is up by Belgium in the right is down by in alsace-lorraine in Switzerland
The Sinner is the part where the terrain is hard to fight in
You know the
Giant ardenne forest is there and it's hilly terrain with not a lot of Roads difficult country right
The same country that everyone was so shocked when the Germans came through it with tanks
In the second world war cuz it was thought to be impenetrable
In the first World War
That's where he's your friend decides to attack
Cuz he's determined that they must the Germans must be weak
What's more
This is how he's going to deal now with this Sledgehammer issue
If it really exists
He's going to cut it off
He's going to launch his attack at the German center right with that hingepoint is with a door swing
Between the forces of the Germans that move and the forces of the Germans that stay stationary they should be at Gap
Mash Brew there
Get behind them drive all the way up until you hit
You know the North Sea or the English Channel and cut off that Sledgehammer head
It's not a bad idea
You can make it work it's like Judo
He just took that great enemy advantage of so many good troops in one location or like a steamroller
I'm turned it into a negative
I could now you going to cut off
The best part of the enemy Army surrounded in Chile
In one place it's a great idea if you can make it work
The French were totally in cave
Making something like
Because they hadn't learned what kind of War they were in yet
That's what the battle of the Frontiers is going to be this first round of this fight where it where everybody's throwing Haymakers and getting some
Smacked on the job going to teach a lot of lessons to people
Jafra will fire
More generals
In this first month of the war than anybody ever fired in history and a lot of the other military Hulu similar things
Because this is where we find out which generals can really fight in Wartime
And which ones are more peacetime kind of generals
And within a couple of months
You'll have much more competent people
You know at 8 at the helm in a lot of places which makes it a little less pain I mean right now
It's
The wild west out here and you have all kinds of different quality
Do people take the Russian generals
That we're going to deal with in a minute I mean
If there's
Variable Quality Inn
This becomes a real
Live-fire test for a lot of these people
On the 21st
Of August
On the 22nd of August
Jumper launches his big offensive
In the ardenne
He assumes he's running into an inferior number of German forces
Calculations
He's instead walking into a situation where he's facing almost
Equal
Numbers of Truth
Underdog in
I'm waiting for
And this is where
The idea
Bayonet attack
And charging machine guns
And not
Digging in with your red Padme we didn't even mention the fact that none of these are
None of them
Are going into this war with helmets
There are no helmets for
They're wearing caps
Okay you know how many people are going to die because of that mistake
This is all kind of win that
Romance in war
It shot down
Literally
I mean to people live in 19th century sort of
Worldview and
And attitudes about honor and Duty in
And the things that are expected for example officers in the field
This idea
French officers standing up
With a sword
In a white gloves and often the white hat
In a storm
Steel in a move that is absolutely suicidal and those Brave
People must have known it imagine how the soul
Give conflicted annoying
To do your duty
And live up to the standards and expectations of your
Countries in Europe
During this time period
You were expected to stand up there
And
Essentially face
Sure death
When you might survive simply by laying on the ground and throw away that white hat and just
Just kind of the hide behind that tree or whatever it is not permitted
Is a romance
Ansan certain standards
This is a heroic deficit with the Elder Von moltke was talking about
Recorded earlier we talked about how perpetual
Peace was not even a good dream
Because you lose all these wonderful values
Warfare brings out
To him that officer
Those officers those many hundreds of officers dying on these fields and their white gloves
Because they wouldn't take cover
Would you mean something beautiful
An adverb
Remember he said that
Quote
Used
That in war man's noblest virtues come into play
Courage and renunciation
Fidelity to duty
And a Readiness for sacrifice that does not stop at giving up life itself
To him this is like The Charge of the Light Brigade over and over and over again
Modern people look at this
As foolish
To wash it's a waste of that officers life and potential
Use them in a way that will achieve
A useful and we have to give up his wife sell it more dearly than that
Two people
Of the time.
The dens really with this war
There was value in what those officers were doing
Simply by Dying Light
And upholding the
Standards
You know that they were upholding by doing so
A higher
Fidelity to duty in Readiness to sacrifice
Prices on mobile
Cassette
One of the things that
This war changes is that hold of you
The people in 1918 at the end of this war would feel very similar
To the way we do
About
Stupid it is to stand up in a hail storm of Steel and just
Be a sacrifice your life for nothing
The generation that does that in 1914 and most of which doesn't make it
Pictures of War
They have different
Way of looking
An older one
And that's why this war is often seen
As
A separation
Origin history between one world
Another
The
Running into this new world
As part of this attack against
Giant Center of the front through the ardenne forest and everything
Comes off sounding like a dry affair
Historians write about it not that they're dry but
Listen history
Sometimes takes
The emotion in the blood and everything out of it
I mean David Stevenson
Have a great one volume work on the war here's how he died
Defenses by Jaffa
And the French to
In a strike against what is certainly a week German center right
Pieces quote
The result was a multiple disaster
The French forces entering the ardenne we're weaker than the Germans in reconnaissance cavalry
Turn on the morning of 22nd August Mist grounded their aircraft
Groping forward in Echelon along the few roads through the forest
They blundered not in the weaker forces
Put into 21 divisions against their own 20
They're 75 mm field guns were ineffective in the hilly Terrain
And poorly linked by telephone with the Infantry
They were no answer to the German machine guns and field Howitzer switch rehab
What does wreaking havoc mean
Historian Peter hearts
Book on the gray
And hard himself rights
About
The Stumbling into each other
There are these
I was in the middle of
Forested Hills
Quote
Any battles few people at any level of command had much idea of what was happening
And for the troops on the ground
It was all utterly baffling
Pre-war tactics seem to have no impact
Bayonet charges let only the more Slaughter
What calling up artillery support was often doomed to failure
He says
Quote sometimes the Gunners were too far behind
Sometimes to close
Hand caught Under Fire from the longer range German gun
Whatever the reason he writes
The Infantry were often left in Desperate Straits
Funny quotes
A captain
103rd regiment who was caught in
George Strait quote
My company was sustaining heavy losses
Evidently it's action was hampering the enemy
Who concentrated the combined fire of his infantry artillery and machine guns on us
We were surrounded by a heavy cloud
Witcher X completely veiled the battlefield from our eyes
Middleburg Irish Spring up
Shouted Vive La France at the top of his voice and fell dead
Among the men lying on the ground one could no longer distinguish the living from the dead
The first were entirely absolved by their Grim Duty
The others my emotions
The wounded offered a truly impressive sight
The quote continues
Sometimes they would stand up
Bloody and horrible looking
Emmett's burst of gunfire
They ran aimlessly around arm stretching out before them eyes staring at the ground
Turning round and round until hit by fresh bullets they would stop and fall heavily
Heart-rending cries agonizing appeals in horrible grounds were intermingled with the Sinister howling app
Projectiles
Furious contortions
Told him strong youthful bodies refusing to give up life
One man was trying to replace his bloody dangling hand was shattered wrist
Another ran from the line holding the bowels falling out of his belly and threw his tattered clothes
Before long the bullet struck him down
We had no support from our artillery
I know there were guns in our division and in the Army Corps besides those destroyed on the road where were they why didn't they
Arrived we were alone
And quote
Frenchman
Will die on the 22nd of August
Many many more will be badly badly wounded maimed and scarf
Now let's put this in perspective
A hundred years before this time Napoleon used to brag
Opponents
But you cannot stop me
I spend 30000 lives a month
As though that was a big deal and back when Napoleon said that it was
The French had just lost 30000 live
That day
And their contact against the other major Army
That had precipitated all those deaths
Has only been at
About 24 hours
Where is Hmong
What's tomorrow
And the next day
Already troops were dealing with
You know a new phenomenon
Created by this artillery
The bigger heavy guns
The extra ammunition and the fact that battles are going on for a long time now
People stay in place for a while me and the people are staying under artillery barrage
For longer and longer periods of time
This is a frightfully upsetting experience
As you might imagine
And it begins to drive people insane
Right as the war
Starts
A French Sergeant wrote in his diary
Offensives in the yard and on
XXII
A quote
The gun's recoil at each shot
Night is falling and they look like old men sticking out their tongues and Spitting Fire
Heaps of corpses
French and German are lying Every Witch Way rifles in hand
Rain is falling shells are screaming and bursting
Shells all the time
Artillery fire is the worst
I lay all night listening to the wounded Groening
Somewhere German
The cannonading goes on
Whenever it stops we hear the wounded crying from all over the woods
Two or three men go mad everyday
And quote
Man who turned out to be one of France's greatest
Public figures in the twenties
Century
Was that these bottles to
It been indoctrinated like everyone else in the romance
And a heroism the ideas of the bayonet charge
And the offensive and all these military
Ideas from another age
It took him one bottle
To learn the lessons that it would take
Commanders on all sides in this war quite a bit longer to learn
Lieutenant Charles de Gaulle
These battles
I need experience in the
Quote
Suddenly the enemy's fire became precise and concentrate
Second-by-second the hail of bullets in the Thunder the shells grew stronger
Those who survived lay flat on the ground emits the screaming wounded in the humble Corpses
With affected cam
The officers let themselves be killed
Standing upright
Some obstinate platoons stuck their bayonets into their rifles
Bugle sounded to the charge
Isolated Heroes made fantastic leaps
But all to no purpose
In an instant it to become clear
Did not all the courage in the world
Could withstand this fire
And quote
The machines that it always been in Port
On the battlefields of humankind
Had to come
The dominant
What had become a tool
To be used by man was now something
That was so devastating in the hands of each other
That the entire ideas about
Warfare that have been in play
In most societies during most time periods up till this era
Are all of a sudden
No longer viable
The battle of the Frontiers
In just
Couple of days
Manages to completely change the whole complexion of the
What it seemed to be
Leading up to the German defeat
All of a sudden
Looks like maybe the Germans are going to win this war
And quickly
Nobody expects the French to lose in a couple of days more than 75000 men killed
And more than 250 thousand wounded
That
Everyone but the French especially
And you have to understand how many people this is
American Steel
Celebrate
In a morbid sort of way
The famous Civil War Battle of Antietam
Famously called the bloodiest day in American history
Warfare
And partly because it's
Civil War and everybody download
American but don't casually levels for comparison purposes
Are about 6000 little less than 6000 dead I think
A little less than 20000 wounded
6000 - 20000
Compared to more than 75,000 dead and 260,000 wounded in the first couple of days
Of action on the Western Front the French were just stunned
And now if you're the German general put yourself in one most issues remember the stress we talked about
And all of a sudden you are presented with a dilemma
If you just did this to your opponent and you stun them in there on the roads and they look like deer in the headlights for a minute what
Do you do
Do you stick with the original plan and say listen or not supposed to attack here
We have the sledgehammer going stick with the sledgehammer and just let the French recover in front of you because
It's part of the plan
Or do you say
As the uncle of Von moltke so famously did
But no battle plan survives first contact with the Enemy
And look at this as an opportunity of Battlefield opportunity that presents itself
Unmute to have to make some decisions here comes another place in the story which historians have argued ever since whether or not he lost the war
And those who didn't believe you lost it earlier in the story
I don't believe you lost it here a lot of German generals
Writing Memoirs after the war you know
Needle him about this
Savage
Making bad decisions weakening the plan
What we all have to understand about
The plan
Hasn't some
Normally thought of
And some very good modern historians have done a great job of pointing this out
Is it the plan with probably flawed from the get-go
It was probably never meant to be implemented in the way a lot of these German general for traded and even more important than that
Evidence seems to show that members of the general staff maybe Von molta included never thought the plan was going to win the war
Anyway
Which means it becomes your plan for starting the conflict and then once everything is in motion you know you look for opportunities you try to
Create some you try to exploit French mistakes that's
Traditional General
Right
What the french are doing on their side
I'm So Gone Monica make some decisions based on having
Slam the French so hard
He's got
Prince rupprecht of Bavaria down in the south
Screaming that now that he's pushed the French back all the way to the French border why didn't why didn't you just slam them
He could collapse the whole Southern flank and if the whole Southern flank collapses and you still get the northern plant collapsing
Because of your Sledgehammer my gosh you recreated the battle of cannae
Like the Romans and
Hannibal all over again it's Henry generals dream
A double envelopment a total surrounding I mean
Yvonne molta were less of an art
A fanatic and more of a military
In a hobbyist I would think he would find that irresistible who knows maybe he's just looking for opportunities to
Outflank French forces as historian David
Did Stephenson suggest here
Quote
Molcas actions at this juncture
Suggest that he was determined to protect
Germany's territory
Weather in East Prussia or Alsace
But willing to strike wherever the enemy seemed weak
Rather than staking everything on his right flank
And quote
Oldest taking everything on the right flank idea
Is just what you do with no other better opportunities develop and when Crown Prince rupprecht
Suggest attacking the French down in the South again
Mimosa thinks about it and says okay
And agrees to take some forces that would be used
To bolster the sledgehammer head and instead use them on the total other side of the flank down south to help
Rupprecht
In his
Offensive against the
French in the south
The plan is now being diluted
Purest
Annie maybe right I'm not taking side I'm just saying the traditional ideas
Molka screwed up the war here now
And some very good historians are saying not at all this is what you were trying to do
I look for opportunities and exploit them without losing the war elsewhere
Which
Creates a situation though that molka himself even says after the war was a mistake
Involves his attempts to try not to lose the war elsewhere but again if you put yourself in his position
It's hard not to do this molka looks at the Western Front
And it looks like it's going pretty well
In the battle of the Frontiers and the end the battle in alsace-lorraine all these things seem to show that the Germans are better than the front
As I said in the last episode this is
In my opinion with the great armies of all time
And what they just showed is that they dominate another grade Army
You know pretty easily if you're on Multi you could sit there look at that and go okay with all of our calculations about the window maybe we don't need sun
Dominance in numbers
Your quality is such that maybe we could get away with taking
A few troops from here
I'm taking them to the east because the Russians are taking towns in East Prussia
And that's what molt
It did
First he changed the commanders over
Stack the guys he was having problems with
And he puts an old retired guy who is more known for the franco-prussian war services and in fact calls him out of retire
Time is so quickly that he has to put on his old blue uniform cuz he doesn't have one of the newer gray ones
The blue ones take back to the earlier War
It combines this older retired guy whose name is Hindenburg Paul Von Hindenburg
With the hero from the German point of view of that attack against
You know the Belgian city of liege in the Fortress there who banged on the door of the Fortress with the hilt of a sword and took the surrender the city
Can I buy himself sort of
Erich ludendorff
Ludendorff and Hindenburg get this job or sent to the east of figure the situation out and then bun Monica
Sends the Muse troops which you know historians later
I really needed those troops
The Western to send them
Any Shonda Center
But he didn't know that
He said after the war was going to be the biggest mistake he shouldn't to send them because it'll turn out there by the time the troops get
From the West to the east on the trains they're no longer needed
Now you know I'm not a
Historian
Historians
Debate this and argue about it ever since so who knows
Maybe we can all take a position on this
Looking at it
From the sources that I have looking at Von molcas decision here looks like prudence
I'm in the
Russians are taking towns in East Prussia forcing
The little teeny German forces that are there to retreat it looks like they're going to be threatening Berlin while on the
The Western Front
It looks like the force you put there to Simply
Keep the French occupied
While the killing Force Maneuvers around their flank
May have
Defeated the French all by themselves what happens when you beat the French
Before the killing thing even get
And then some one wonders if you can spare a couple of cords for the Eastern Front
Von moltke supposedly even ask
One of the commanders of one of the armies that makes up
This
Sledgehammer
Swinging gate thing
You know that flanking for stats
The size of
End of Napoleon's Grand Army or the size of the Roman Empire's complete military the tide
He asked the Commander II Army Von Bulow can you spare a few core
For the Easton Von Bulow says yeah
You know what he says yeah in part because he just smashed a French army in front of him during the battle of the Frontiers
Which happened to be the poor 5th Army commanded by that one French General who saw the sledgehammer for
Forming even before the war started for General in Glen Rose
Because he argues with the high command to let him just shift his army a little bit to protect it
It's like some historians think he saved Fifth Army
From Total annihilation
He does have to retreat though
Move backwards once again to keep
In line with the rest of the French forces that are retreating sort of all along the line
Meanwhile
Here come the British
Now this is a source of contention and Legend like all this stuff isn't it funny how much of this early war is
But the French have been badgering the British since the beginning of the war to move faster move faster move faster we need someone up here on our left
Critical rights the French territorial
Units together with your liking old man and reservists and stuff and put them out in the flight just so that there's something out there but
Against what's coming
I mean it's not
Until they admit her either British up in the British Rush up and they
Running to Belgium so that they can take the position on the Left Flank and protect
Airport General Glenn rezax Army
And before they even get there unrest is moving the other Direct
Is backing up to stay in line with the French armies
Exposing the British Army's flag
Again you can read the British historians have been mad about that ever since being left in the Lurch by the French
What's so funny is I read all these accounts like
The Irishman to count
Lucy's account
I'm arriving in France and how much the French love them and he's wonderful welcomes and then you read other accounts
Uniform later in the war where the soldier to go and get a fresh don't much like us
We don't like them they don't like us
And the
Leadership in the British army didn't seem particularly Pro French or vice versa
There seems to be a lot of arguing between them
And then some weird order although it's totally understandable by the head of the British military right before the bef goes to France
Complicate every
Lord Horatio Kitchener
British Legend from the colonial war never seen a guy like
By the way I always look at this picture Wonder
What he would look like without that
Victorian era wax mustache thing he has going
But he's a he's a fantastic
Six-figure
Character
In his own right
What he famously tells the British commander who's going over to France
Something to the effect of
Look
This 70,000 men is 90% of all we have
France and Germany date that millions of men in the field
This is our army
Don't lose it
Be careful
The problem is he's in a war where
Men are thrown into meat grinders
In very large numbers
The French
Will lose
The equivalent of the British expeditionary Force often in this war in a short. Of time
So the British are moving up into Belgium
To have their first real contact with modern war they fought in South Africa
Against a bunch of
Boer farmers and Guerrilla Fighters
Got an idea of what the rifle fire and all that stuff to do they haven't moved up against an army that can fight like take
And then outnumbers the many times over
They stumble into this Army
Adam place
Qunar
The battle that shaping up will be a legendary British
It's called The Battle of Mall
And
It will be mythologized in a very similar way to the
Dunkirk
The affair
In the second world war unit without
When Germany smashes France in 1940
The British managed to evacuate their army miraculously every ship that can float comes across in every little rowboat
Comes across the channel take British soldiers away and the luftwaffe is held at Bay and and they can flip the Germans off from across the English Channel say hi
Haha missed us
Technically it's a defeat
But you sort of
I portray to spin it in a way that
Makes it look like a glorious victory that ends up biting
Airbnb in the rear end of a long run
There's some truth to that right you can work with that
Publicist a
The Battle of mons is very similar
One of those things that's technically no matter how you look at it
A defeat but there are
Heroic
Naruto
Come out of it
To me it's like the moment
Where the cloaking device is removed
From the German flanking attack
Cuz up till now there's been this
Uncertainty about
But is it coming and what strength is it coming in and how many men are we talking about here and where exactly is it going all these different kinds of things
The British run into the tip of the spear
They run into the most honored
Of the armies
Involved
Chapter one
It has the the important most important position the one that the great Schlieffen famously said
Are the these guys should brush their sleeves against the English Channel meaning that that's how
Why the flanking maneuver they should make through Belgium
They should make it so wide that they actually almost touch the last man on the right touches his sleeve into the water
Is commanded by one of these great German general
A guy named
Alexander Von kluck
And punk Loop is one of these guys
It's like Heinz guderian I think I said in the second world war he's an aggressive General he's a hard driver
He sees as the initiative he gets you off balance he keeps pushing
And he moved
It's all about speed
And deadliness when he gets to the place where you don't expect him yet
Schematic 320000 men in Germany's first arm
Right next to him is Germany second Army also moving to Belgium also part of this out flanking maneuver
260000 man under Von Bulow
Van Heusen third Army below him as a hundred and eighty thousand men this is the flanking maneuver
The British run into the
German Army on the farthest Right Flight they only run into a part of it
About a hundred and sixty thousand men
Who are surprised to find the British waiting for them behind defensive positions
A long 25 miles of a canal
Which we call it
Defensive Ops
Write this is something that
Magnifies the power of the
Defense cuz now the Germans have to cross this canal under Fire
The British think they're going to face
Accor
Germans
Maybe two
Instead they're facing four plus cores
And they're doing it in this kind of an otherworldly
Setting
Barbara tuchman is good for this kind of stuff is she explains
But you know you might think that this is like the wonderful Belgian Farm Countryside in the canal with blue water going
Through which explains that this is a mining town
And the water that runs through this canal is more of a sludge and it's black and it gives off chemical fumes
And she says amongst the flower gardens and vegetable gardens
Are these slag
He keeps that are pointed and look like tall witches hats all around the the landscape
She says it doesn't look like a bad place for a modern
Battle
It's going down in history
When one narrative and of course as in everything else you're going to get tired of me hearing saying this but is everything else will just where there's a whole nother
Counter-narrative
The original narrative is the Dunkirk one that that
Turn this thing into something
That is so
Legendary
That within a year or two legends
Popular Legends will spring up
That there are angels
On the British side of this battle
What you know
To me I wouldn't push that rumor because even though it makes it look like God might be on your side
If you got the angels on your side and you still end up having to move backwards in Retreat after
The battle that doesn't speak too well about
Define empower
The particular Angels involve
But let's not go
Let's talk about
You know the parts we can confirm about this battle
It's a 25 mi from
30 seventy thousand guys
Most of it behind this canal
Reset
And it's starts with encounter between Calvary
Because remember
You're trying to use these aircraft and then send the Germans are better than most attitude
To look at things
But everytime anything's Misty or foggy they can't see anything
So it's still Cavalry that does this job
And while you're cavalry's out front trying to be the eyes and ears of your army the enemy's Cavalry is out front being the eyes and ears of their arm
And they fight
This is what you normally have your reconnaissance forces get into it
And so the first stuff that goes on here is the British eyes and ears and counted the German eyes and it wasn't there some calories
And
John Lucy are Irishman
In the bef talks about this he says
And we run into our Cavalry there some wounded people but
State they beat the Germans in a little Cabaret engagement but the Germans are coming
And so that the British and his
Unit
I'll get ready they can kind of get scratch them out jig would be too strong of a word scratch themselves out a little depression
In the soil when they wait for the
Germans to arrive and I should point out something
That
Maybe I'm estimating here but I would say between 85 and 90%
Of all the accounts you read
From soldiers going off to war in 1914 and it doesn't matter which army you choose
Most of it is overwhelmingly
Positive in terms of the emotion that these young men feel going off
Tour
There were some Russian accounts especially when people are pulled off the farms and don't want to go do this
But most of the young men going off to war here
Are excited it sounds like an adventure the full Romance of War still in bloom
To them this is excitement remember a lot of these people are pretty Drury lives and now all of a sudden they're caught up in
In world affairs that are huge momentous biggest thing that's ever going to happen to most of these people right and they know in their they're caught up
Any excitement they don't have a lot of negative stories yet that have filled it into the public Realm
In explaining what happened to the guys who came before you cuz there are no guys that came before you
Are Irish British expeditionary Force Soldier
John Lucy is moving up
Torrance Mall
In
The. Right around August 22nd August 23rd
And
Says that when he first
Heard the guns
It was a
Queer
Thrilling sword
The feeling that it brought
But it also worried
But maybe not for the reason we would think of as an adventurous
Young man who finds all this
You know interesting and exciting he had a different reason to be scared
He writes about his unit
Thumbs up
Toward the
Situation
I was like
Quote
We swap news with the nearest men in the ranks and learn that nothing exciting it happened to the Battalion in our absence
Acceptable line of trenches have been dug as a defensive measure about a mile behind and then abandoned on the orders of
Staff officer who wished the Battalion to move forward toward the town of moss
Now visible through the slag heaps of many Minds
On the right front of the marching regiment
This dirty-looking factory town had no particular interest just then for us until suddenly above the sound
How did the tread of our marching feet we heard the booming of field gun
A queer thrilling and menacing sound
About which there were many conjectures
The most popular being that they were French 75
And that they were giving the Germans hell
This notion greatly depressed us
We should really hurry up now otherwise we would miss the battle the French would get all the glory while we with our capacity
34 deadly rifle fire and dash in the attack would miss that crowning moment of Victory culminating in
In a sweeping bayonet charge
Relentless in invincible
The grand assault that would drive the enemy off the field
So we damned the French were not waiting for us
And quote
There's that Romance of War again
The Great Adventure
Going to be fun
We're going to be heroes
And it's funny when he first gets to the line
And his men take up positions and what they call me trenches these shallow little
Kind of holes they're not too happy to not be moving forward and doing something offensive
But they sit down there and then the first shells come by then
And again
They find it more interesting and they kind of
Have fun with it
He says quote
The Salvo of shells passed over our heads and burst about 80 yards in the rear with a terrific Clyde
Iran crash
We were highly interested
More came and still more all going over
The heads of our curious men appeared above the trenches looking back to see the burst
Look they shouted
A black one
Or one only
Or
More whites
Some laughingly imagine themselves
On duty at rifle ranges at home and shouted advice to the German gunners
Washout
Another Miss
And lower your sights
One wag simulating great Terror
Cried send for the police there's going to be a row on here and another in mock despair oh mother why did I do
Desert you
Then the enemy Gunners shortened
And the shells exploded above our trenches and the men already taken in hand for exposing themselves
Crouch low
So it's getting real
Right
But it shows you the attitude that they had at the time they having fun with it
The Great Adventure
And
You read accounts
From every major Army of this. I said the Russians have a little bit more people that were sort of dragged into the kicking and screaming
In the country people always more than the urban people
But the twenty-year-olds were marching off to do this
It's hard to find a count where they're dreading
Yet
Adobe accounts down the road where
You know everyone has a good idea where they're going and there's a lot more
A planning for your own death and worrying about that kind of stuff right now as I said John was she's worried about missing
Define
You don't have to worry cuz the funds coming to him
Field Marshal Alexander Von Kluge
Is aiming the German first Army the tip of the spear
Write Adam
And Alexander Von klook
Is like
The German general that Central casting in the TV Hollywood world would have put together
Scarred face
You know Iron Cross
Carrying a soldier's rifle and a pistol at the same time while he's walking around
Fearsome is a great description of him
Wear a French Observer
You during the early stages of this combat you know right around now
Ends of witnessing the arrival
Avon clock somewhere and said it reminded him of Attila the Hun
And he said quote
An automobile drove up
From it to send it an officer of arrogant and impressive bearing
Destruct forward alone while the officer standing in groups in front of the Villa made way for him
He was tall and Majestic
With a scarred clean-shaven face hard features in a frightening glance
It is right handy carried a soldier's wife
And is left rested on the butt of a revolver he turned around several times
Striking the ground with the butt end of his rifle and then halted in a theatrical pose
No one seemed to dare to approach him
And indeed you are a terrible error
And quote
And as we said earlier he's like the Heinz guderian of this war he's
The hard-driving
You know images is everything commanding 320,000 men commander of the first Army
He's going to have problems with German generals who are not as aggressive and hard-driving as he is
It's his army well about half of it
That we're running to the British
Atmos
And the traditional story is that
But they are in for a shock
Because as we said earlier
The British are good Rifleman but it may even this
Just so you know even this is
Contested
In a second I'll read some stuff about the same battle from
The military historian of Britain's Imperial War Museum
Who will kind of go after every single point that
Traditional in this narrative
What traditionally
Alexander Von kluck's forces
Inside of an encounter battle
Stumble Inn
To the British line
And take it on the chin and are hit by so much rifle fire that is so precisely aimed and so quickly
In a fire that the Germans supposedly think they're under machine gun fire
John Lucy's very proud of this moment
And describes what happens to the Germans dust
Quote
Finally the shelling seeds do we put up our heads to breathe more freely
Then we heard conch like sound
Strange bugle calls
The German infantry
Wechat approached during the shelling was insight
And about to attack
Not a shot had been fired from our trenches up till now
And the only opposition to the Germans have been made by our field gun battery
Which was heavily engaged behind us
And making almost as much clamour is the enemy shelling
To my mind it seem that the whole Battalion must have been wiped out by that Dreadful rain of shells but apparently not
Any answer he writes
To the German bugles or trumpets
Can the cheerful sound of our officers whistle
And The Rifleman
Casting aside the amazement of their strange trial
Spring2action
A great Roar of musketry rent the are varying slightly in intensity from minute to minute that's whole
Company ceased fire and opened again
The satisfactory sharp blasts of the directing whistles show that our Machinery of defense was working like the drill book
Another recent Shelly head cause notice organization
The clatter of our machine guns added to the den
Thrust he writes
The battle took the form of well-ordered Rapid rifle fire at close range
As the field grade human targets appeared or were struck down
The enemy infantry Advanced according to one of our men in Columns of masses
Which withered away under the galling fire of the well-trained and Cooley LED Irishman
Deleting Germans fired standing
From the hip
Let me interrupt him here now that's John Wayne Style
Walking toward the enemy
Shooting from your hip
So they're coming toward the British
Trenches doing that
Deleting Germans
I just said fired standing from the hip as they came on
But they're scattered fire was ineffective and ignored
They crumpled up
Mount down as quickly as I tell it
They're reinforcing waves and sections coming on Bravely and steadily
To fall over as they reach the front line of slain and wounded
Behind the deadline
Speaker converging columns were being blown about by our field guns
He then says
Are rapid fire was appalling even to us
And the worst Marksman could not miss has he had only to fire into the brown of the masses of the unfortunate enemy
Who won the front of two of our companies
We're continually and uselessly reinforced at the short range of 300 yards
Such tactics amazed us
And after the first shock of seeing men slowly and helplessly falling down as they were hit
Gave us a great sense of power and pleasure
It was all so easy
He says the German attack
Be broken off
Quote
The German survivors began to go back here and there from Moline
The attack has been an utter failure
Soon all that remained with the long line of the dead before us
Motionless except for the limb movements of some of the wounded
And quote
As a person interested in military history
This
Era of the conflict is the one most interesting to me because
It later in the war everybody's
Pretty experienced
And with what you're dealing
It's at this point in the war that everybody's learning
The reality of Modern Warfare at the same time through bloody hard experience the British expeditionary Force
And Von kluck's first Army are both kind of getting a real initial taste of what the new Weaponry can
Yuan issue
Heard from John Lucy
The Irish riflemen in the bef
He and his compatriots were actually appalled at how effective and deadly it was it's a whole different thing
In a fiery live people
In a parade ground
But if you happen to emerge unscathed
It almost
Seems to
In a bolster that idea that this is spawn heroic romantic
Lynn McDonald in her book 1914 quotes a bunch of people who were there including Lieutenant Chapman
As the British are dealing with the battle tails
What's going on tour
Compatriot of his and says
About the
Repulsing of the German human wave attacks quote
They came at us over a bank directly in front of us
And as soon as they topped it we let them happen
The range was 70-yard so we were firing at them Point Blank
I've never seen anything like
Legs arms heads they were flying all over the place we absolutely smashed them they simply melt
Getaway
Turn the blighters got to machine guns into action at that distance we were like sitting ducks
So we had to get out of it and by jove it was a close shave
And quote
As though it's a fun story
Right
There was a 16 year old
Trumpeter and that's not unusual going back
A very long time they always have boys
Drummers and trumpeters isn't on ship still have
React to her position in Britain's Navy called first boy second boy
And they are their kids
I'm 16 year old British Trumpeter laws
Describes how he just
Admire what the British were doing it
It can never forgot the fire discipline of these Rifleman
He said he was sitting there watching an officer Countdown the range of this advancing gray human wave
And getting very nervous as it got closer and closer and closer
Saying that the British
Officer
Was holding the rifle fire until the Germans got really close and he was counting down the rain
Trumpeter
Jay Naylor from the third division reports quote
He was saying
At 400
At 3:50
At 300
The rifles Blaze but still the Germans came on they were getting nearer and nearer and for the first time I began to feel rather anxious
Brighton
They weren't an indeterminate Mass anymore
You could actually pick out details
See them as individual man
Coming on and coming on
And the officer still cool as anything
Was saying at 2:50
At200
And then he said
10 Rounds rapid and the chaps opened up
And the Germans just fell down like logs
I've never seen anything like it
The discipline
The fire discipline of these troops
I've never forgotten that I was so impressed
As a boy of 16 I was simply astounding
I thought what a marvelous Army we are
The attack was completely repulsed probably not for long
But it was long enough for us to get the guns away it's saved us
And quote
Now
I probably have more than 20 books sitting around me here
Historians talking about the same event and it is amazing to go from historian historian historian to see the different ways
This is viewed interpreted
A perfect example is Peter heart's a wonderful book He's a
Historian it Britain's Imperial War Museum
And he's one of those contrarian to says all this is a bunch of Nas
And let's understand quickly that it's
It's normal in Wartime for this to happen there's not a single power involved in the conflict that wants to talk
Talk about defeats
Or bad things everybody wants propaganda victories everybody wants stuff that helps
Recruiting
You're looking for stuff that you can play up maybe if Peter Hart suggest
That's what this miracle at malls is
But he shoots down a number of the typical arguments
Pointing out that the Germans handled themselves very well
And in fact that the casualty numbers are what he thinks they are
Probably deserve a victory
At the Battle of maldon fact the French and the Germans both thought the British were defeated there at the time he writes quote
When a monk Lux first Army smashed into Smith Dorian 2nd Corps at 6 a.m. on the 23rd of August
The battle that ensued was the inter British military folklore
The myth is one of a heroic successful defense with well-trained British tommies mowing down hordes of
Germans repeatedly attacking in Mass formation
Finally the British will be forced to retreat
Only because the fickle friend should give it away on their right flank
This view of the battle is a great yarn
He writes but like the angels of mons at its heart it is the product of wishful thinking
And quote
He then goes on to deal with every single reality we've talked about it
Shooting down each one of
Again as best he can
Controversy
But he's a fantastic historian who's qualified to do this
I should like to point out though
But this was no different you know manufacturing a victory or playing up a victory
And and magnifying the very real heroism on both sides
There's nothing wrong with that that's pretty standard behavior for every military and every war you can think of
Imprint sample
Ilse
Quote after the second cour being undefeated
I'm forced to fall back only to conform with the French on their right flank this is pure nonsense
He says the reality is that on many occasions the German seem to have been all too successful in forcing a retreat
And quote
In other words
Probably the best army in the world
He's operating that way in the field
And it's disconcerting if you're on the other side for example he says quote
It is undeniable that several of the British Battalion spot well
But modern scholarship has revealed that the Germans maneuvered skilfully to secure a local superiority against the weak point
Going to the British defenses
Wherever possible they operated against the flanks
Forcing the British to fall back
Or risk being cut off and totally destroyed
Throughout the Germans seem to have handled their artillery and machine guns with a great tactical dexterity
Borne of long practice
Operating them in tandem to dominate the British in the firefight
Effectively rendering rifle fire of secondary importance
The British were turned out of their defensive positions in a matter of a few hours and even failed to destroy several of the Canal Bridge
And quote
He then goes on to take issue with the
The casualties that are often cited one of the things the British use it
Claiming that this isn't a major victories
How many more Germans they killed
Versus the casualties they suffer themselves He suggests that even the interpretation of what those casualties are
Are overblown
Again
This really doesn't matter in the
Grand scheme
Every nation was doing this
For me
What's most interesting is to watch these
Nations and these military
Trying to learn on the Fly while they're being shot at
And Translate
Years of theory
Into practice
By the 24th of August
The French will change their mind about this whole idea
Of you know the offensive at all costs when
It offers forced to say listen we need to go on the defensive
Which is in a like heresy
Amir 5 6 7 8 days before
The reality of the situation on the ground
Is changing everybody's mind about another package we talked before the war we're going to be good yeah in practice not so good
The British
Whether you want to believe that they were forced to retire because the French left him in the lurch
Or whether you want to
In a belief as a heart does that the Germans were just really quite good
Attorney influencing and employing
Combined arms is it called
To get the
British an untenable position is it called it doesn't matter
The British have to retire just like different they have to get out of
The first Art Museum
Leader Von kluck writes in his Memoirs the British fought accidentally
But that if he had been allowed
To sweep
As widely around the flank as he had wanted to and has as he requested the time that the British would have been in no position to fight
He would have outflanked them
Smashed them from the rear
Remember there will be a lot of finger-pointing after the war
Over whose fault all of this stuff is in a lot of the generals were still alive will write things to defend their reputation
The one thing
Pachuca
Actively say is going on here though
Is it neither the British
It was a French
We're able to stop this movement through Belgium it's coming down on them
And they're all retiring at
This is the
The part of this
In the early War
Narrative
It's known as the great retreat
The great Retreat is a wonderful example
Of one of those moments where I try to get in the minds of these people and you know that's a fruitless
Past mean there's no reason to
Play with history and study history if you don't want to try to do that but we all have to recognize how impossible it is
But at the same time you try to put yourself in their shoes
If you are one of the commanders of any of these armies and you're over about the age of 58 59
This entire Affair is beginning to look
Horribly familiar to you
What you're on the German side
Wonderfully familiar to you
It looks like 1870 1871
It looks like 44 years ago
It looks like
You know when the Germans managed to surround to entire French armies and get them to surrender
Sir John French the British commander
Is already making plans to
Get his army to the other side of Paris and then starting to think about
The challenges the logistical challenges of getting the Army the British army out of France altogether is back to the safe
Britain
He's worried about a completely legitimate threat
That the British could end up like two French armies ended up in the last war
Completely surrounded by the enemy
And forced to surrender
Imagine if 90% of britons
Military forces are on the continent and have to give up to the Germans and go into captivity
That's quite a hostage situation you have
Pretty easy to get a pretty good
Armistice agreement wouldn't you think if you're holding 90% of the British army hostage
In French
It's confusing is that the British commander named frenchwood French is not confident
In the French
He hasn't been impressed
You know with his dealings with them so far and he's complained a lot to his Superior who I think we said was the military leader in this
Lord Horatio Kitchener
Who happens to be a field Marshal but in fact
At this time use a Cabinet member the secretary for war
History X will feel the need to discard his bowler hat in his suit and tie and throw on his feet
Field Marshal uniform jump on a destroyer go across the English Channel
And
Give
French a little piece of his mind bolster his confidence a little bit
The French has illegitimate worried
This great Retreat that's going on is an extremely precarious moment because
An organized
Retirement can easily turn into a disorganized
Panic route
And everyone knows that
In fact
Only a couple of days after the battle of Mons
British forces will be required to turn around and beat off
German attacks against that which is wild when you consider
That the Germans are trying to catch people that move away from them at the same maximum speed
Your military history not like I am
The one thing that's interesting to follow
At this point in the war
Is something that
That is very unusual military
Because if you were going to take a class on military history this is the point in the war where they would tell you
If you're the Germans that you need to send out your mobile units now and destroy the enemy
Why you have Cavalry right
Can you go talk to her
Genghis Khan or any medieval or ancient
General in history they're going to tell you go get them
Tanger Cavalry after them harassment disorganized and never give him a Moment's Peace cut off stragglers
If you look at where people die
In premodern warfare but even modern warfare
They died in the pursuit
The job of the battle is
To get the other side to turn and run
And when they turn and run
You crushed
Look at the Iraqi highway of death right
With so many Iraqis died fleeing to wait what would they do when they were fleeing
Throughout most of human history
The Casual human Alexander the Great supposedly only suffered less than a thousand casualties in his entire career
Although I don't know if I believe that
Military store inside and the reason those numbers are soloist cuz
Comparatively few people died in the Battle they died
While being pursued after the battle
And since Alexander never lost a battle his troops never had to face that
This is the moment when the German cavalry
2B Unleashed
And finish the job
The problem is we had this tiny little window in military history
Who are the Cavalry is so vulnerable that even disorganized which the French and the British art by the way but even retreating for
Horses can turn around form of firing line really quickly and destroyed
Had a few Howitzer is in there and it will be Carnage
Now
In the next War
Mechanized forces
Armor and aircraft
Recreate the ability to do what light Cavalry did before this.
But in this weird little interim era
The Cavalry can't pursue and Destroy forces like
So the Germans have to do this same job with infant
The problem is the German infantry
Maximum speed is the speed of a marching man
Which is the exact same speed
Of the people they're trying to catch
And yet nevertheless and even though the Germans have marched along way already they get darn near to catch a
Several times in fact on the 26th of August
The British have to turn around
And try to get a little breathing space
Tommy's German pursuers
My
UniFi you again can we get them to slow down cause them to form up and have to reorganize again and get a little
Distance between
Us and Them
On the 26th of August the British including our friend John Lucy from the bef
Fight another battle
What determines
This time in about 11 hours
The British suffered
Thousand cash
98000 casualties in the war that's about to happen isn't going to seem like that much in my goodness
The French of supper 260000 wounded in the last few days
Which of the British army which is historically small
This is a naval Powers Army
That's a lot
In fact when
Lieutenant General Sir Archibald Murray who's with the general staff behind the lines is informed of the eight thousand casualties a couple hours late
Ecolab
Just paints
I'm going to show you need a hard-bitten military men but it shows you the scratching the tension that these people are under
Can you add to that
The fog of war no one knows what's going on and it's happening so quickly there's a huge amount of stress
A German general shoots himself on August 20th I mean
Aldi's administers the real Supreme tapped it separates the men from the boys as the old saying goes
This is the moment
Of greatest Danger
Winston Churchill who is a high official with the Navy
Write about this. In this retirement this great Retreat says quote
The days of retreat
We saw that the French armies of the right we're holding their own
Call the center and left
Was marching Southward toward Paris as fast as possible
Well I run 5 divisions work for several days
Poem lie in the very jaws of Destruction
He says that the admiralty we received requests
To ship the base of the whole Army from over at the cinemas here and with this complicated business we had to cope
The process of retreat continue day after day
A seemingly irresistible compulsion
Was pressing enforcing backwards the brave Army zafran
Why should it stop would they ever be able to turn if France could not save herself
Nothing could save
And quote
The Germans are
Mentor Paris
And the Allied soon-to-be officially Allied armies are moving back in that direction
Here's the thing though
Remember the war plan
You know that the French military leaders offer has not forgotten the plan even if the Germans get within sight of Paris
You're going to lose the war
If it's the same time that happens
The Russians from the East
Are Marching through the streets of the German capital in Berlin
Jafra and the
Whole Allied higher command realizes
On the way
The war can still be one
Even with allied forces in the west retreating
They just have to prolong this conflict long enough to let the Russians smack the Germans in the east in the war will be over no matter how
Oh well
The Germans in the western tv
Enter
Hindenburg
And ludendorff
Arriving even as all this is going on by train
In the East to take command of that one loan German army that got to hold off the Russian Steamroller as it approached
Now the Russians biggest
Victory at this point is
The fact that there's an army there
Where to fight at all
Remember the entire German pre-war
Plans
Assumed a certain speed
For everyone's mobilization in the Russian Tsar are the slow one
And here they are you know in two weeks
And they're already taking towns in East Prussia
East Prussia by the way this area that was
Concord
In the 14th 15th century by the famous Teutonic Knights
Which included
A large fry
Proportion of Germanic nobility
Eventually will settle down
In those areas and so this is where some of the historic German nobility
You don't have their biggest states and everything the Kaiser himself feel this is
This is historic
German territory Within
Abnormal number of the aristocracy there
Important and it's a gateway to Berlin
And it's not far from Berlin
And the Russians managed
Within like 2 weeks of the war start forget the six weeks that
Guys like sleeping accounted on
Within two weeks
They've got half a million man
Operating in that are
And it got even more down south
Against the austro-hungarian it's one of those things where I mean there's an author there's a professor name
Sean mcmeekin was written
A whole book called The Russian origins of the first World War
Where he says the Russians are the ones who should bear the entire
Lion Share the guilt for starting this war they wanted it they planned for it and part of the reason that they surprised everybody
With your quick
Mobilization is because
They were ready for this war they wanted it
And they put up 2/5 of their army in Poland which
Which is right next to East Prussia ahead of time
So that when the war starts when they have to mobilize people they're not coming from all over Russia there's a ton of them right there
Good units to
It doesn't make any difference
The Russian czar
An absolute
Chaotic
Disaster
And
You know if you look at Russian history Soviet history
You just consider that
A piece of Russian history
That's so traditional it's crazy
The Russians always start these wars as disasters
In the Second World War
They can hardly deal with the fin
Scene Finland
Which is crazy when you think about the disparity and everything
Resources
Is the size of the number 2
Everything
I can hardly do you
With the fins in
In the very early part of the second World War
What's 6 years after the second world war starts their Fielding one of the greatest armies in human history
Very typical
Takes a long time to get started but they can be extremely formidable once they get going
Hindenburg and ludendorff aren't going to
When Hindenburg and ludendorff arrive in the east
Remember these guys are
Probably a little
Orange call jet lag
Train lagged Amin Hindenburg is
66 or something and
Just out of retirement a couple of days
Ludendorff has been on the Western Front since about
The start of the war
Banging on the door of the Asian
Accepting the surrender there
A couple of days ago he's helping
Push lanrezac Army back on the Western Front and now he is in the east
Trying to get acclimated to what's going on there's a lieutenant colonel which is a pretty low rank
For a guy to make the history
Like Max Hoffman did
On the scene though it was an expert
On the Russian army
And of course has been there the whole time so quickly feels ludendorff and Hindenburg in on the situation
Which is this
Is about a half million Russians nearby
In about a hundred and seventy-five thousand Germans to deal with
The Russians are divided into two armies
The first and the second Army
And they're making their way across
A really difficult piece of terrain
It's a series of lakes and forests and marshes and rivers
But just is going to make these two armies have a hard time helping each other out
In a while they're on opposite sides of this big train feature
He also tells Hindenburg and ludendorff
But they have a pretty good idea about what the Russians are trying to do
Because the Russians have been broadcasting radio messages and Telegraph messages to each other without using any code
They also find
A Russian officers body after they kill them and it has the plans on it
In fact
There's so much information that's giving the Russian plans to the Germans
But they start to wonder whether or not it's just a ruse
Maybe the Russians are trying to trap us and they're just broadcasting all this to fool us cuz it's so obvious
Who would make these kind of mistakes
Well
It's not the greatest time in Russian military history I wrote down a list
Mistakes
They were made or or areas that the Russians were having terrible
No problem
It's not only understandable because of the Russian tradition of starting Wars a little chaotically and disorganized
But also because you know even the really best are
Are trying to figure out
You know how to deal with all this new technology in a hundred years of theory turning into fact the British and the French
And the Germans are all dealing with this on the Western Front
Understandable that in army
That's all
Really not up to those standards is dealing with it all
2 in fact even though the numbers on paper say there's half a million Russians here they've been leaving
Guns
And soldiers all along the way to get here
And their actual strength when they get the combats going to be a lot
Less than it looks like
The logistics and supply
Situation is disastrous the troops in some cases already eating
They have Rags instead of shoes on their feet some don't have rifles
The two commanders
A guy named Reynolds run in console command the first Army
II Army's a guy named Samson. They hate each other
Which is going to be a problem because
The plans that the Germans have become aware of
Taralli different methods
Say that the Russians are going to try a pincer movement on them is only one German Army in the region
So this first Army will come from the north
The second Army will come from the south
Surround the German Army and destroyed
What is the Commander's hate each other
Telecommunications
Is
Awful
And they have to pass this terrain feature for 50 or 60 miles that will keep them from working together
Dispenser movements going to be tough
The German reconnaissance
Is
So much better me the Russians aren't even using aircraft the Germans have
Are airplanes and Zeppelin's up there watching what's going on
The Germans have
An advantage with railroads because railroads help armies move fast obviously but the problem is is that
Attacking armies once they leave their railroads
Almost never get the ability to use the railroads in the territory they're going through whereas The Defenders
Territory can this is one of those things that makes
The defensive more powerful than the offensive in this war the Germans are able to use railroads
To reinforce points where they need to be the Russians are past their railroads now they're walking
Finally
The Germans know this
They know the terrain and they know the geography this is an area where sometimes the German Army conducts peacetime maneuvers
So they set a trap
For the Russians and it's a very Napoleonic strategy indeed
They're going to attack these armies
While these armies are separated by this terrain and unable to help each other
And smashed them individual
They're going to nullify
That disadvantage in numbers
And the Russians
You don't make this a lot easier cuz they don't know what's going
They literally are
Clueless as to what they're facing
And the high command isn't helping the situation they're telling General samsonov at II Army
Listen to We don't see any German forces we don't expect an attack
I mean Samson I was taking his time
Blind to what's going on around him
We're at the Germans are moving very fast and seizing areas to the flank and taking up positions and setting a trap
Message stories Michael nyberg and David Jordan
You pick up the narrative
About springing the Trap
On the Russian second Army
They write quote
Nervous intense hours follow does the rest of the Trap was sprung
By the morning hours of the 28th of August the Germans had control of almost all the main roads leading to Sampson Ops forces
Combat began in the North
When a Russian core advancing without support ran into a German course
The Germans who were fully aware of the Russian presence and we're lying in wait for them
Smash the Russian
And sent them reeling back in panic
Surprised at the unanticipated presence of German forces in the area
Samsung off order to General withdrawal that night
The full severity of the situation came slowly to
As he realized that he was completely cut off
Is man began to panic
Throwing down weapons and running East as fast as they could
Only to end up trapped by strong German forces already sitting on their lines of retreat
Confusion and panic rained in the Russian lines
Without supplies and without Communications
Panic spread quickly
Renan comes forces were more than 70 miles away and would obviously not provide any help at all
How much money 9th of August
Samsung off himself gave into the panic
He told a staff officer the Tsar trusted me
How can I face him after such a disaster
He then headed off into the woods
Are you committed suicide rather than face capture by the Germans
He was one of the lucky ones
Samsonov powerful Army of 150,000 men had suffered one of the most lopsided defeats in military
History more than 30000 Russians were killed
And almost a hundred thousand in a prisoner-of-war camp
Where they faced a dismal future forced labor and appallingly bad conditions
The Germans needed 60 trains to move all of the Russian equipment they capture
German cars
Casualties were less
And quote
The Germans had this fantasy of maybe
Emulating the famous battle of cannae Hannibal's victory
Total encirclement over the Romans in the ancient world
But instead they got that in the east
And right after defeating samsonov second Army
Those troops that have been taken maybe a great cost very soon from the Western Front arrive
Not in time for the initial battle Justice ludendorff had told mold get earlier
But in time to take on
The first Army of reading comp which the
Germans then smash
With similar nasty casualty numbers not reading comp will do a better job
I'm pulling his forces back and saving his army from total Destruction he won't get totally surrounded like the battle of cannae
But it doesn't matter the results are the same
All of a sudden in shocking fashion
The Germans have removed the threat of the Russians coming in and taking Berlin
Before the Germans can take Paris
All of a sudden the whole strategy that the French and British were
In a delaying and operating under the assumption of if we can just hold on a little longer the Russians
You'll solve this word problem for us
All of a sudden
The French and the British are going to have to
Managed to be Victorious on the Western Front
If they want to save themselves
That helps not coming through
In the West
As the great Retreat continues
You begin to see
What the level of humans suffer
Spring is going to be in the sky
Have to keep reminding myself
Talk about this you know the old Joseph Stalin line is so true
One death is a tragedy
A million deaths
Esthetician
Annies numbers
We will constantly throw out in this
Conflict which are enormous numbers
They failed to register at
Why you become numb
Take what the last several days on the Western Front
I've done to France
So we said 75000 dead
More than 250 thousand wounded
In a couple of days how would our modern medical establishment deal with
Places like that
Forget what it's like on the ground that's why you need these reports that come from people
Who were there
In one of the most famous books ever written
Now it can be told
A British reporter named Phillip Gibbs
Went over to the continent
Right when this whole conflict breaks out
And he reported from it
You know during the Great retreat
Now what he reported that made it into the media is not what he put in the book cuz what do you put in the bookie can't he couldn't tell
Tell during the war
This is the kind of nasty stuff
That none of the government would allow me
Republished
It was too raw
Yuan to real
That's why Gibbs named his book
Now it can be told cuz after the war he wrote it
He described the conditions during the Great Retreat and the human suffering and he reminds us
You know what
It means to have that level of
Death and destruction and injuries
What kind of injuries were talking about remember this is like having
What 5/8 football stadiums
Were the people in a few days injured and we're not talking about hangnails
And sprained ankles here
Gibbs Road in August 9th
For publication later
Quote
Ramya at night head, French army in retreat
There were dead and wounded on their wagons
Cuirassier stumble did they let their tired horses
Crowds of people with white faces
Like ghosts in the dark
Stared at their men retreating like this through their City
I knew that the enemy was close behind
No sampa do Whisperer the woman and gave a wailing cry
People were fighting their way into railroad trucks at every station for hundreds of miles across northern France
Women were besieging a place for the sake of their baby
There was no food for them on journeys of 19 hours or more
They fainted from
From heat and hunger
An old woman died in her corpse blocked up the laboratory
At night they slept on the pavement in cities invaded by Fugitive
Epernay in Belgium and it Dunkirk on the coast of France there were Columns of ambulance is bringing in an endless
Tide of wounded
They were laid out stretcher by stretcher in station yards
500 at a time
Some of their faces were masks of clotted blood
Some of the bodies were horribly torn
They breathed with a hard snuffle
A foul smell came
Headshot red they were swelling over the station hallwood disinfecting fluid
After getting through with one day's wounded
The French doctor in charge and received a telegram from the director of Medical Services
Make ready for 40000 wounded
It was during the first battle of the Marne
It is impossible
Set a French doctor
400000 people were in flight for man
Into which big shells were falling
As English correspondence flatten themselves against the walls and said God in heaven
250000 people coming across the Shelf in rowing boat sailing crafts and rash invade
Did one Village in Holland
They had no food
Children were mad with fright
Young mothers had no milk in their breast
It was cold at night and there were only a few Canal boats in Fisherman's cottages
Is henan them were crowds of fugitive
The odor of human filth exuded from the
As I smell it now
And it sickens me and remember
And quote
This is a human tragedy
Of monumental
Portions
I have to keep telling myself it's just getting started
The French of lost in a couple of days
What do United States more than the United States lost in terms of killed and wounded in the 10-year involvement they had in the Vietnam War
In a few days
That right there should put the
Lie to the idea that the French are somehow
Nicholle Tom
In what American surrender monkeys
They're not surrendering their standing and dying on French soil
You know for the sake of just buying their comrades a little extra time
Francis showing not only that the French can take a punch
Which I think everyone at this time. Was fully aware
Wanted Modern nation-state
Can
It's a mixed blessing now
In the same way that
Boxer say that
A clean early quick knockout is more merciful than a long punishing fight
There are historians who say
Maybe it would have been better for European
Culture civilization standards their golden age if you will
The Germans who just won this war
You would had sort of a Changing of the Guard of the great Powers the Germans moving into a more prominent position
Remember there are new country only about 44 45 years
In existence and they've been moving up the
In a power chart
Ever since with a bullet as they say in radio but it works here 2
Maybe this just seems like a natural progression of things
And if you could save all the casualties that we know are coming in a multi-year long Carnage fast with
U2 later
And maybe save countries from communism and Nazism maybe prevent a second world war in the cold war after that
Me the Dominos that fall if you talk about this war maybe ending here
Well you can play
Brevard County
You can see
Knowing how bad it's going to get and how bad it already is why some historians have wondered how
Anything
It wouldn't be better
Then what they're going to experience
If you are friends you may say to yourself we would never have wanted to live under the German boot in a victory was all-important
But what if you could
Have all those French
Who died
In the rest of the story by
If you can avoid the Second World War
When does it become worth
Same thing to the Germans I mean
You look back and say what if we could
Could have those p
What if we can have that wealth back
But what if we could have
That time
And where we were in 1900
Call crying over
Historical
Spilled milk
But it doesn't prove
Historians from doing that all the time
And has even less of a
Intubation on people like
Yours Truly who are historians at all
The question of what decision should have happen
Is obviously
Historically moot point
The question of what's going to have
Is about to be determine now
And one of the things that soda makes this battle what it is
Shaping up his battles even the right word for
Is it everybody kind of knows it's coming
It's either coming or the war's over
Basically the Germans are moving forward across almost the entire law
Line and the French and British are moving backwards across almost the entire life
Fine and at some point they got to turn
They got to make a stand
They've got a punch the Germans in the nose
Or there's nothing that's going to stop them in the problem is is it everybody's at the end of their rope
Everybody has been marching and fighting for Daisy's units that weren't missing a buckle
You know in parades across Belgium at the Germans started this war missing a heck of a lot more than that
Hazard the other Allied armies
This is why
It's so important
If you can actually get
Fresh troops into the
The combat
Who don't look the way
In a free example these soldiers that have been in contact now for almost 2 weeks look
At one point during his inspections
Jeffers riding around and he runs into some French soldiers and Barbara tuchman describes
The Experience quote on the same day August 30th jafra visited the front of the third and fourth Army
To look for forces he could have signed to Foss
Another French
Talking content
On the road he passed the retreating columns would fought in the yard in
And on the heights of the muse
Red trousers had faded to the color
Pale brick
Coats were ragged and torn
Shoes caked with mud
Eyes cavernous in faces dulled by exhaustion
And dark with many days growth of beard
20 days campaigning seem to have aged the soldiers as many years
They walked heavily as if ready to drop it every step
Emaciated horses with bone sticking out
And with bleeding harness sores sometimes dropped in the shaft
We're hurriedly on harness by the artillerymen
And dragged off to the side of the road so as not to obstruct away
Guns look old and blistered
With barely a few patches of there once knew gray paint showing through the mud and dirt
And quote
Are Irish friend from the bef John Lucy
Entitles a whole chapter of his book
Sleep marching
He talks about how there were people that we just stopped
At the side of the road
And not care if the Germans were going to capture them they wouldn't move for anything everybody was
Exhausted
And
You know we had talked about how the Russian
Supply and Logistics and all that was falling apart because they weren't one of the best armies out here trying to cope with a new modern reality
Will the Germans probably are the best army trying to cope with a new modern realities
And their Logistics aren't keeping up
Either
I mean perfect example is the number of shells that they're using in the number of bullets they're using is so far greater than anything
Anyone have predicted
They're running out
The rationing
Some of these generals are are limited to a few shells a day for their gun it makes it very difficult to fight the kind of battle
That you know on paper the German pre-war planned
Pencil depended on
This is where the operational plans design before the war whether you want to call in the Schlieffen Plan to sleep in bulk
The plant or just whenever it was the German general thought they were going to do
Doesn't ever take into account enough
The human element in the variables
It's wonderfully planned
And
T's crossed and I's dotted but there are things you just can't know
You can't know how tired people are going to get how quickly
You can't know how many times they can fight battles before they can't fight anymore
And you can't predict when they were going to be things
Like hold up some food
And supplies
Asleep in molka plan or whatever you want to call it
Is falling apart do to the human variable
The number one human variable is
Klook and Von Bulow first and second Army troops cannot March 15
Or 20 miles a day
Every single day
While fighting battles and getting far ahead of their supplies and not eating them in there just
They're worn down by the time they reached this stage in the war these vaunted you know
Tips of the spear
Are worn down to a Dominus in fact
They're almost down to 50% strength
What's more remember they had units pulled from them
Uniform over the last several weeks most took some and put them down south and gave them to Prince Rupert
He sent a couple to the east to help against the Russians
Just when you kind of want some nice fresh troops to throw into this thing they aren't there
The troops you do have though
Are very excited about the prospect of ending this war
And capturing Paris
A member of on klook staff
Talks about how
Getting nearby Paris
Has re-energized exhausted men
Quote
Our soldiers are worn out
For 4 days they've been marching 40 kilometers a day
The ground is difficult
The roads are torn up
Trees felled
The fields pitted by she'll like strainers
The soldiers staggered every step
Their faces are plastered with dust
Their uniforms are in rags
One might call them living rag bag
They march with closed eyes
And singing chorus to keep from falling asleep as they March
The certainty of Victory close at hand
End of their triumphal entry into Paris
Sustains them
And whipped up their enthusiasm
Without the certainty of victory
They would fall exhausted
They would lie down with a r
To sleep at last no matter where no matter how
Had to give their bodies a drunken this like that of their souls
They drink enormously
But this drunkenness also helps to keep them up
Today after an inspection
The general was furiously angry
He wanted to put an end to this Collective debauch
We just persuaded him not to give severe orders
It is better not to be too strict
Otherwise the Army could not go on at all
For this abnormal weariness abnormal stimulants are needed
In Paris we shall remedy all
And quote
Indeed
When they saw signs
Saying that Paris was
2022-23 miles in the distance
It was as though they been giving a B12 shot
1 German officer
On September 3rd
Bro quote
One of our battalions was marching wearily forward
All at once
While passing a Cross Road
They discovered a signpost
On which they read
Paris
37 km
It was the first sign post that had not been a race
I'm seeing at the Battalion was as though shaken up by an electric current
The word
Paris which they have just read drives me crazy
Some of them Embrace The Wretched signpost
Others dance around
Prized yells of enthusiasm accompany these mad actions
This signpost is there evidence that we are near Paris
Without a doubt we shall soon really be there
This notice board has had a miraculous effect
Faces light up
Weariness seems to disappear
The marches resume
Alert
Cadence
In spite of the Abominable ground in the forest
Songs burst forth louder
And quote
One can only imagine the disappointment
Those soldiers must have
I felt and probably a little bit of bewilderment
When on August 31st
They change course
Instead of heading toward Paris.
Make a sort of a left hand turn
So then
They're going to march by Paris
I'm going to see it on there right
And supposedly according to the accounts some of uncooked soldiers were able to see the Eiffel Tower
In the distance
Imagine the
Confusion and disappointment in
That must have been some bewilderment like what are we doing their parents were right there
Believe me the government in
Paris realizes
On September 2nd a flea they had to Bordeaux which is as far away
As you can get from where the Germans are
Without
You're not being in France anymore
Costa Mesa
The Bay of Biscay
So they leave a lot of refugees leave
And the soldiers who think okay the city is basically wide open for us and we're heading in a different direction
This turn
Body soldiers
A different direction will create
A million questions
And a million opportunities
And it will make this story almost impossible to understand if you're even able to
This point
The battle that is shaping up here is the most complicated
I've ever encountered
It takes forever
To really try to understand this and then once you think you got it you can't figure out how to explain it to anyone it doesn't even
Really meet the
Definition of Battle at all
What's understand wife
Possible
Remember we've been comparing this little conflict here
2/8 heavyweight
Fight
And you know they often have three knockdown
Which means you know if you're knocked down three times in any one round the fight over
The French at this point been knocked down twice in the first round
There's nothing seemingly to keep it from happening again
Except
That giant of a man
Who comes into his own now
You're the first World Wars version of the second world war Churchill
But for friends
Joseph
Chakra
This is where he makes his name this is his moment in history
This is his Destiny right here you know his Churchill had said I felt like I had lived
My whole life just for this moment
Jafra is exactly what friends needs now and what they missed in 19
This is when he
Take charge
And performs miracles in his one of his generals later said I don't know what we would
As we said earlier it's possible they're only in this situation because of poor decisions
By the guy earlier during The Blind chess-playing Side of this thing
But now when everyone panicking
And the French government is moving as far away as they can
And the British commander on the scenes pretty sure the war's already over and is worried about how he gets his army out of here
And the Kaiser slapping everybody on the back of his Churchill says is in the Haram mood
And everything looks really good for the Germans at this point
And the French could easily lose hard here
Except
Jafra is taking charge
And starts by firing
Generals that are
Within about a week or ten days
Afires 140 of
2 of 5 army commands
9 core command
38 of 82 divisional General
Who's replacing them
With much
Much better
People he even said
A lot of these guys were great
Professor Snape taught at the Academy well another word good peacetime General
He's replacing them with people who've already demonstrated in this short. Of time that they can get the job done their Phi
Fighting General their names are famous their phone
The pathan
Theguardian
And they're going to help
Turn the tide here
As soon as they get some troops to work
And that's what she offered does next
It gets involved in figuring out ways
To get troops to The crucial points in the Bible
Changes his strategy right after the battle of the Frontiers
You know to have all this offensive operations he has people sit down
And hold off the Germans on the defensive while he figures out a way to get enough troops to the important place to me
Make things happen
And during all of this
The guy is absolutely
Freakishly huh
Which is exactly
What France needs this time remember we said the art of generalship
He's kind of
Bringing
What qualities you bring to the table to bear at the right time and of course there's a little luck involved
In that too
This is Jaffa
First time
And while all the Panic was going on
EJ Meyer
Says
Shaffer was in
Perturbed
Quote in the midst of it all
Jaffa remained impassive
Maddeningly silent
Call
No matter how alarming the situation how terrible the emergency the tall and Rotunda generalissimo
Never seemed Disturbed
He became famous for the care he always took
To have a good lunch
Followed by an app
End the day with a good dinner and always get a full night's
Sleep in bed at 9 back to work at 5
Even when things seem to be at their worst
My rights
He made his staff understand that under no circumstances was his rest to be disturb
Between mealtimes and bedtimes he was steadily on the move
Using a big touring car driven by a Grand Prix racing champion
To make repeated visits to his General
Especially those on the left
Does he was able to keep himself in touch with events and observe his subordinates in action
And quote
And Fire
Obviously
But what this is doing is steadily creating
The better leadership in key positions
Learning from mistakes and taking real-time knowledge knot
Theory and applying it
Taking men
Phuket inspired
Troops
In Hope
The situation
Course Joshua doesn't command all the Jenner
In this war
Decide
He's fighting a coalition battle in
British Army that makes up a part of his battle line
That is
Hesitant
About involving itself
In anything involving combat at the MoMA
Sir John French
The ironically named leader of the
British expeditionary Force
Doesn't trust
He thinks he's already had his flank exposed once and then put in great danger he doesn't see any evidence that the French can be
You trusted to win this war
I mean the Germans and basically thrown
On the Schlieffen Plan
If there ever was one out the window here
An attack along the entire franco-german border which is that area that is so well protected by French for
Did the Germans thought it worth
Violating Belgium's neutrality
I'm bringing the British into the war
Just so they could avoid that area and those forts
Well now you know three weeks into the war they were attacking along that entire front and if they break through
They will completely surround the French and destroyed
The problem is at those forts were originally avoided for a reason they're formidable and all of a sudden the French troops in that
Terraria
Are doing a pretty decent job on the defensive they're still losing lots
The people but all of a sudden they get a chance to find out
That this war that we're going to call the first World War
Is the one where the defense has the temporary dominance over the offense in the French
In the last battle only days ago we're doing bayonet charges in advancing in close order and all those things you're not supposed
How to do standing up during the shrapnel attacks
Now they get a chance to be the one
Behind the machine gun
And behind
The field guns firing behind them into Germans advancing in the open
While the French Gunners beat themselves little holes that are almost
Deep enough to be
He called trenches already
And see what the power of Defense
Means
Enough for that
The good news is they don't get overrun by Germans the bad news is it looks like they can spare a few troops
Which is which offer is doing now this is where the real Miracle comes in
The guy can scrounge troops from everywhere
He pulls them off of the line and all these battles near the French Fortress line with a French need every man they've got shot first
I need them elsewhere
More
He's taking newly returned wounded back he's got in a colonial troops coming on boats he's taking people from
On the Far Western Anthony he's using the rail system
To get them to him important concentration points fast
He creates a new Army he called the sixth and he puts it over by the
The flank of the British expeditionary Force creates another one called the night he puts it over as a reserve kind of by Paris
He doesn't want to have an Army in Paris which is a great Fortress actually
But the government of France makes him have one
So they put
Shoppers old Commander galliani
In charge of it
And put him in Paris and basically everyone thinks you just going to stay there and you know man the walls with his man that's the plan anyway
Day after day more French trains are arriving in more troops
AR
EOD training and moving over to the front over by Paris facing
Another projected direction that the sledgehammer is going to fall
Remember they're losing troops everyday they're down to half their original strength and here's
ShopRite
Everyday bringing in more French troops to face it all the sudden the numerical advantage
Begin to diminish
And then
On August 31st
Aircraft
Yes
Aircraft again starting to make an impact already in this early 20th century War
Aircraft notice
That the Germans have changed Direction
The same thing we told you that those troops must have been bewildered by
All of a sudden they're not heading to
George Harrison
What's going on
And more importantly when they change direction
They present their flanks
To the
In a newly-created force
Especially the one
In Paris
Chance
Brick counter
A chance to turn around
You know the entire great retreat
An attack
Jafra needs to convince Sir John French of the bef
That now is the time the opportunities there we need you
And he gives one of the
These great speeches this is the way he recorded himself and remember
Sir John French doesn't speak French
And
The offer doesn't speak
English
And the translator
Is another British general guy named Wilson who is much more diplomatic
And like the French much more than Sir John French.
There's some
Fun moments there too
Here's what
Shoppers on account of his encounter with French
To try to convince him that now is the time to strike this was harappa
Opportunity flop chant all the cards are on the table
Shows that
There was another side to this man
And he wasn't just the
Impenetrable Obelisk will you couldn't figure out what that plastic look on his face men sometimes
He could be positively churchillian
And this was one of them
He told French a suspicious
And pessimistic French
Quote
I put my whole soul into the effort to convince the field Marshal
I told him that the decisive moment had arrived
And that we must not let it Escape
We must go to battle with every man both of us had and free from all reservations
So far as the French army is concerned I continued
My orders are given
And whatever may happen I intend to throw my last company into the balance to win the Victory and save France
It is in her name that I come to ask you for British assistance
And I are Urgent with all my power I have in me
I cannot believe that the British army will refuse to do it Sharon the Supreme price
History would severely judge your apps
Then as I finished
Carried Away by my convictions in the gravity of the moment
I remember bringing down my fish
Start a table with student my elbow
I'm trying miss you and the Marshal the honor of England is at stake
Up to this point
French and listened imperturbability to the officer was translating what I said
But now his face suddenly red
There ensued a long impressive silence
And then with visible emotion he murmured
I will do all that I possibly can
Not understanding English
I asked Wilson what's your John had said
He merely replied the field Marshal says yes
I had distinctly felt the emotion which team to grip the British commander in chief
Above all Hydra Mark the tone of his voice and I felt
How to get all the witnesses to the scene
But these simple words were equivalent to an agreement signed and sworn to
T which was already prepared
Was that answer
And quote
Barbara tuchman of course relates in a little bit more dramatic
She says
Did it tear welled up in Sir John French's I
And it rolled down his cheek before he said I don't know how to tell him just tell him we'll do everything we can
Tornadoes
Critical dramatic moments
In history when you want that you want the guy who would have been the real bat
First house
Hardcore history
Did Warren HG Wells would have to be Churchill wind it
And in his thumb
Account of the first world war was full of
Churchillian bias all the things that you normally get with him what's fun about it is
Is no one explains it like he does
Even with the biases
And he was there
Churchill's histories are always
A combination of romance
History
And if he's in them
In a personal Memoir 2
I love the way he sort of
Explained
How many things had to line up
Right all along
Another War
For this opportunity to be presented to the general
In Paris
Cease
Fun clocks first Army
Turn their flank to him
Churchill
Quote
Assuredly no human brain had conceived the design nor had human hands set the pieces on the board
Several separate and discrepant series of events had flowed together
First
The man galliani is on the spot
Fixed in his Fortress he could not move toward the battle
So the mighty battle has been made to come to him
Second
The weapon has been placed in his hands
The army of Metairie
He was giving him for one purpose
The defense of Paris
He will use it for another
A decisive maneuver in the field
He was given him against the wishes Opera
It will prove the means of jafra salvation
3rd
The opportunity
Swinging forward in Hot Pursuit Of as he believed the routed British and demoralized French will prison
And his whole right flank and rear as he passes Paris to galliani and minori in his hand
Observe not one of those factors would have counted without the other two
All are interdependent all are here
And all are here now
Galliani realize the position in the Flash
I dare not believe it he explained
She's too good to be true
But it is true
Churchill right
Confirmation rise
Hour-by-hour
He vibrates with enthusiasm
And quote
This is what sets up
The famous battle
The most complicated battle you'll ever find
The battle of the Marne is so hard to understand
For a couple of reasons
The first one is just like the battle of the Frontiers that just recently happened
Beast World War 1 battles
Are modern and scaling
They are so much larger and so much longer than battles in the past worth I mean a hundred years ago Napoleon is being defeat
Seated at Waterloo a giant battle involving three Global powers
And you could drive from one end of the battlefield to the other in no time
You could see one side
From the other
But those little
Telescopes they would just put to their eye
The battle started in the morning and was over at the end of the day I mean
That's a hundred years ago
Now the battles last
4 will this one will last for officially a week
But really last longer than that
The battlefield is at least a hundred miles long depending on who you believe
Or the entire front
You know according to other history
You could legitimately
Have fought
At the Battle of the Marne
And not know it
Turn to a buddy that fought there with you saying that where we at the Marne was it was our fighting officially part of that
Or not
Because really it's a catch-all term for all the fighting that is going on
When was really the Marne is all about happens which is
That the great Retreat ends
And the French and British armies turn around
And launched into contact
Got to be fair there are there parts of the front that have never not been in con
In the south
They've been fighting pretty much since minute one and it's never stopped that's why if you told them that they were in the battle of the Marne
They might not even understand it because they've never not been fighting
Historians like
Eric brose suggest that the battle of the marne is everything it was fought
In this one area
In from the center of
France
He described it this way
White quote
What has come to be known as the battle of the Marne should really be thought of as the Battle of France
4 altogether 56 Allied and 43 and 1/2 German divisions engaged one another in a
Titanic struggle
How long a line stretching from Paris
To the Eastern Frontier
And quote
Innocence would really happen
Is the opportunity that was presented
Buy an open flag
As we said
Fun clocks first Army turns
Chose his flank
To Paris
Paris now has an army
I can hit him in the flank and here we're going to have a battle
But that just becomes the opportunity that everybody was waiting for before they turn these armies around anyway
This had to happen at some point
This is France's last throw
Everybody knows that
This has to occur
The problem is is that the commanders who are actually with the troops not these guys at the General headquarters in the
The highest staff officer the ones were marching with the actual soldiers
Are Apollo
That this is being considered with the exception of a couple notable
Commanders
In one Commander one General supposedly looks like he's been hit in the head with a club
When somebody said that they were going over to the attack
His troops have been retreating for days and days and days
At an amazing Pace their closer in rags there
Weapons hardly fire their shoes are falling off their feet they can't stand cuz they're so sleepy and then you get the word
Did you going to attack
But several of these French generals that
Jafra has Putin Commander
Tough
Hardcore fighting General to mean
Ferdinand Fox's right
During this encounter
Quote attack whatever happened
The Germans are at the extreme limit of their efforts
Victory will come to the side that Outlast the other
And quote
The French General who takes over from
Glenn Resnick at the 5th Army when juffer fires him
Famously comes to the phone like one second after he takes command hears from a commander in the scene that says it's him
Possible his troops are falling down
Why are they can't march and he says March or die
Eyedropper issues his famous
Notice to the armies
When he tells them that the great attack is beginning
And it's a classic stand or die exhortation
This is France leaving it all on the table
Jafra announces
The turnaround in the attack
Really the recommencement of contact along the entire bottle line and we've seen
How deadly on a day-to-day basis contact with the enemy in 20th century Warfare is
Announces it
Tousley
Quote
We are about to engage in a battle
On which the fate of our country depends
And it is important to remind all rank
That the moment has passed for looking to the rear
All our efforts must be directed to attacking and driving back the enemy
Troops that can advance no farther must at any price
Hold onto the ground leave Concord and died on the spot
Rather than give away
Under the circumstances which phase has no active weakness can be tolerated
And quote
Wendy
General in charge of Paris gallieni
And I think I pronounce his name
Every time I've said it
But yeah
Famously is a spy
The general of 6th Army
What their plans are if they're overrun
Noah Paris gets overrun the enemy of the runs and where we going to go
Annie looks again
Says
Nowhere
This is it
Imperial War Museum oral historian Peter Hart describes
The Crux of the battle of the Marne
About it
Well as anyone can in
In the short space in Word
He says quote
What followed was a complex battle that defies easy explanation
By this time the German right-wing was actually outnumbered by the French divisions rushing up from the south
At the German first Army tried to turn to face the assault from the French 6th Army along the line of the river or
A huge Chasm of some Thirty miles opened up between Von cook and the second Army on his Left Flank
Amidst the chaos the men of the bef having dutifully about turned found themselves advancing Allah
Alongside the French 5th Army
Into the gap
Between the German first and second armies
There was no great battle
No huge drama
What's a penetration between their armies
Threatened utter disaster for the Germans
And on the 9th of September vodka order his right-wing to retreat
And quote
Now
Peter Hart
It's a great reputable modernista
And that's about it
As wonderful a passage There Was You
Ever hope to get from one of those folks but seat hit they would jettison some of their wonderful history ocity
And throw a little grandchildren drama maybe little exaggerations and romance in there you could get something like
This from Churchill describes the same thing as only he can
And he says this
About the British army along with the French advancing into this crucial Gap that will change
This whole conflict and turn the battle of the Marne which let's be honest
The French are once again taking it on the chin when they're in full contact with the fabulous German Army this is what will decide the UK
Occasional
And Churchill puts it in churchillian term
Quote no human genius plans that the British army should Advance into this Gap
A series of tumultuous events
Cast them into this position in the line
When they advanced
There was a gap in front of them on the whole front it was the line of least resistance
Along it they bored and punched
And it led into the Strategic vitals of the German right-wing
Hi Destiny blind fate regulated the none too vigorous but nevertheless decisive movements of this pretty
Army
It Marches On
Wondering what has happened to the monster which is pursued it with whip and yell since mods
Von Bulow finds his right-wing being rolled back by V French army
And himself cut off continually for his right hand to comrade fluke by the British advance
Klook just as he's got himself into a fine position
The fight manga read
Find his left
And all the rear of his left
Hopelessly compromised and expose
And quote
It's a crazy moment it reminds one of of of warfare in the 18th century they used to call
Positional Warfare where a lot of the fighting was simply trying to you know March around the flank or get to a point where you
Forester enemy into a place where they had to retreat just because of positioning
By accident
As Churchill
So
Eloquently put it
The British army
At almost accidentally
Probed its way into the German liver
Doesn't get much better than that in terms of
Bhai drama
And it completely obscure is
You know the Soldier's perspective on the ground of which we have very little
More and more
First-hand account especially from the German side will be made available as the war goes on
I keep having to tell myself that a lot of the people fighting in these battles
Will never make it home
To write their memoirs
These are people who don't get to go home until either the war is over or they're so vitally injured they can't fight
Anymore and a lot of the German soldiers on this front who might leave memoirs
Someone Like Yours Truly might be lucky enough to have translated into English
Leave their bones on somebody
Nonetheless
And one thing is clear I remember reading an account once and there's lots of accounts like these and you can specifically find them
In Publications that came out not long after the war
I remember I have one in my house actually in many of you do too it's in a great series of books written just after the war
And you read it and it's an account of this
Unbelievable battle it sounds like something out of the Lord of the Rings or some
Napoleonic thing with charges
10000 Cavalry mowed down by cannons he's amazing heroic moments German heroism free
French heroism
Really thrilling moving stuff
And it turns out that that
That's just one of the little battles
Well I mean comparatively that form something called The Battle of Nancy
The Battle of Nancy is just something that formed apart of
The battle of the Marne
There are individual
Stories
Many battles whose names have been forgotten by almost everyone
The Forum
The whole
The battle of the Marne
Is it
Human tragedy is we said earlier about with the civilians are suffering on a mass scale in the drama and the suffering and the heroism
And the stories that would break our hearts if we knew them
Are going on up and down the line from Switzerland
To the Belgian Border in fact they're going on in the Eastern Front to we haven't even talked about
The simultaneous events that are happening while this is going on
The armies of ludendorff and Hindenburg in the East are wrapping up their conflict are against rent in comps Army after tannenberg
In
Delicia which is over
Kind of weird austro-hungarian Poland and Russian interest meet there a terrible battles going on the austro-hungarians are getting smash
Smashed in a way that they will never recover from and this is all happening at the same time
Part of what makes this conflict
So
Disorienting for everyone who's facing it
How quickly it's all happened when you think about the second world war for example
Realize
That there's no big fighting between the major powers
For about 8 months after
The second world war is declared Hitler goes into Poland Poland
That's all quick and relatively painless
By World War standards
It'll be eight months before the Germans
In a real big contact with French and British armies
This war is 3 weeks old
And all the major participants of class
Head on
There's more than a million people dead
This is the worst nightmare
Of every pre-war prophet
Predicting
And what was going to happen when you combined the mass armies that the Napoleonic era Unleashed on steroid
By the way
With the modern technology and weapons
And systems that were being developed
All through the 1800
This is a great
Filter
When you lose more than a million people in the first blink-of-an-eye
And the Warriors now
Obviously going to last a while
How many people are going to die before this thing reaches a resolution
What is a resume
Again to simplify it what really happens is when the entire
French and British line turns around
And smashes back into the German line
There's one spot where
They just penetrate
There's nothing really in front of them and that's the spotted
The bef
The British expeditionary forces French forces go through
And
She had Von klook
And Von Bulow not already been fighting somebody they could have turned
And crushed these forces that were penetrating into that Gap
But they are fighting other
The people that's known as pinning the enemy
Klook is fighting those forces that are coming at him from Paris Von Bulow fighting other armies so they can't
And if they do turn then the Army's they were fighting or hitting them in the back
They're trapped
The only thing they can do
To alleviate this open flank issue is to pull back
Von moltke
When all this is going on
And if you ask me
Understand
Tolisso
This is a guy who's been under
Tremendous pressure already
And
As he watches this plan
So important that for years and have been known as
Dare Todd bday
When this plan is finally used in a whatever the heck
Plan was really this the day means the day that the Germans launched the war
He's watching it collapsed in front of his eyes
Realizing also
That this
We'll all be blamed on him he's coming apart at the
He writes to his wife
As all of this has been
Becoming clear
Quote
I cannot find words to describe the crushing responsibility that is weight upon my shoulders
During the last few days and still weighs on me today
The appalling difficulties of our present situation hang before my eyes like a dark curtain
Through which I can see nothing
And quote
One of Von moltke staff officers
A colonel named Bauer
Broke quote
Desperate Panic seized severely the entire Army would be more correct the greater part of its leaders
It looked at its worst at the Supreme command
Mocha completely collapse
He sat with a palette face gazing at the map
Dead to all feeling
A Broken Man
And quote
Churchill was
Sympathetic
What he wrote
Quote
Everything now converged upon molt
Who was Molech
He was the shadow of a great name
He was the nephew of the old Field Marshal
And it has a DeCamp
He was an ordinary man
Rather accordion
A man about the palace agreeable to the emperor in the palmy days of peace
The sort of man who does not make too much trouble with the sovereign
Who knows how to surprise his own personality
What there is of it
A good harmless
Respectable ordinary man
And onto this ill-fated being crashes the brutal
Remorseless
Centripetal impingement of tides and impulsions under which the greatest captains of History might have Blanche
Input
Molcajete later written
While he still live
That in the moment
Supreme price
Grown
Quote
Nervous
Lots of sources report
Von moltke
Went to the Kaiser at this point Sid Majesty
We just lost a war
I've never been able
Confirm that.
And truth be told
They didn't lose the war
What's just happened is the chances for an early knockout blow an outright German victory
That's what's been
I'm going to say compromise because
It's an open question whether or not the Germans blew this
Where the French simply rallied
And gained the victory
There are lots of mistakes on the German side that people will point to basically insinuating it without those mistakes
The French go down
And yet look at the
Fact
But they were still there after suffering
Unprecedented
Asian punishment
And forget about
Stop for a minute and understand the condition that those armies are in before they turn around at the Battle of the Marne
They are falling apart dead on their feet
In a wearing rags and unable to keep their eyes open
And that's who
The general from the first Army Von kluck
That's who he singles out when he talks about the part
You know this
War so far this
Surprise him
He wrote quote
That men will let themselves be killed where they stand is a well-known thing
And counted on in every plan of battle
But that men who have retreated for 10 days
Sleeping on the ground and half-dead with fatigue
Should be able to take up their rifles in attack when the bugle sounds
It is a thing upon which we never counted
It was a possibility not studied in our warqaad
And quote
So he was obviously
Impress
There's no way to
Denying endless we don't want to shortchange the British expeditionary Force either they
Prove to be potentially
Crucial to this whole thing and
As Churchill Point outside the providentially at the right place
And at the right time sometime
But this is one of those victories where you just have to
Tip your hat a little bit
The French achieved
This is Monumental stuff
It is truly heroic it's a little like the Alamo for Americans but on an enormous scale
And at the same time
I want to remember the Germans
In all this
To every set earlier
They get a bad rap
From a lot of us because of the second world war and rightly so
But a lot of that is connected to the first world war in a funny way I see them
You don't have to bring up some sort of Science Fiction reference
Show me where did that come from
But they're a little like Anakin Skywalker this
This nation that's new and young and has so much promise and potential
HG Wells have the greatest name for them I've ever heard at this point he called them
The best
And the wickedest nation in the world
You know the militarism that's so scared him and his socialistic sensibilities
Was balanced out by the fact that the Germans were so admirable in so many respects what the Germans called culture
Their music and their and their writings in their sophistication
And
And there's science my gosh in their education Wells is overflowing with all these wonderful things to say about Germans
But they've got this flaw and it's this militarism in there the best in the wicked is people in Europe in
And somewhere along the line Anakin Skywalker turns into Darth Vader in the poor Germans get that to be
They are
Image for the
In 20th century
You wonder again
What's the enormous Stakes of this
German
Really defeat our
If a mole can the Germans have been
Victoria's here
The entire German history in the 20th century
Is different
And perhaps much much much more positive almost certain
Like for Germans
And for everyone else too I think
Very interesting what ifs
And it's important to remember that when you think about these soldiers dying on the ground in these nameless
Awful battle
Whether they be French British
German or
Very soon a lot more people from
Canada
And South Africa and Australia
And Indochina I mean this is going to become an international I-4 soon
All these people
Are good people caught up
Religious people caught up in in in the grand plans
And grinding wheels of
Of nation state
They went into these conflicts for reasons that are
Understandable today
Patriots
Doodie love of country
Take your family all those kind of things
They also went for reasons that were really important still in the 19th century
But there were a little different today
Glory
Heroism Romance
As I said they still exist but not quite like they did
Back
You know from the beginning of History until right around this time
September 1914
A general name Vaughn ball 4
Talk about
The changes that the
Dispersed month
The first World War
In created in that facade of romantic War when he said quote
If war was once a chivalrous duel
It's now a dastardly Slaughter
And quote
The suffering on the ground
Regardless of which side you're on is pitiable
And horrific
You know I always try to make sure and I hope auntie
Successful
It would never exploitive
Of the
Terrible things that are going on today
The people need stories
Tell
The reason that I use them is because for me
These stories intrigue me because I always put myself
And I try to imagine
Handling these things and
As a person who's interested in the extremes of Human Experience
There are almost no exceptions
The stories we talked about in this program I can imagine it
And I just feel like I would Wilt under
The pressures that these people
Live through
I mean
When you talk about
Being interested in the extremes of human nature
And wondering
What I would do in the same situation
I think about
The worst places in the world you can think of a man if there's a
Three or four
45 list out there
One of them on my list is the Western Front
In the first World War
And we're about to get there and it is about the worst
Experiencing
I was joking only Hardcore History Twitter feed
By the way you can follow it at heart
Core history
That it's taking us longer
To get the episode you just heard
Released and to you
By the way thank you
Appreciate it
Then the amount of time it was actually covered in the episode itself
And I think if you were
Crunching the data and projecting outward based on how long
To show you just heard was
You probably figured that it's going to take it about 250 episodes to cover the first world war and God forbid we go afterwards
Where did the 1919 in the trees and all that
Will be doing this the rest of our lives
We're obviously not going to do that
Episode you just heard focused on
To be honest
A series of events the pre-war stuff
And the first 10 opening moves
It's common in almost
All the approaches of the
For war because they set the stage for what comes afterwards for example
Already
You know as the story ends the trenches
Are cropping up
Organically
Along the Western Front
It's the iconic image of the first World War I trenches of always been known fortifications always been known going back
Back to ancient history
But never on this scale
Never this long
Never in positions
Another world as an almost immobile as it never under the source
Two conditions it's going to create an almost unique
Experience
The people who have
Go through it
And again something fascinating when I
I consider
How I
Myself would have
Hayden similar
But it's going to make the battles
Somewhat similar
You know so you'll be able to say
A little bit about
The big ones but not have to go too much into the experience over and over again because it becomes similar
In each of the battle
All the people fighting in the trenches in one battle
Often have similar sorts of day-to-day experiences from people fighting
In the trenches
In another
So we will have the opportunity as the program moves along to zoom in and zoom out as needed
This is going to allow us though
To focus on a bunch of other things including how the generals managed to deal with the fact that they're no longer operate
Meeting with pre-war plans
They have to actually think now learn apply they're thinking
In novel ways we're going to find out how flexible these 19th Century men are
As they try to adjust on the fly in real time to the challenges of 20th century Warfare
Which no one's ever really tried yet
They're going to have to contend with and we are going to deal with questions like changes in the air
Changes at sea
Changes involving
Wmd and things we're still dealing with today
And changes involving the scope of this war
That encompasses
You know the rest of the world basically in one way or another
The first world war is about to go global
And Underground
In the next episode
A blueprint
For Armageddon
We just want to make it clear that we are bought and paid for around here at dancarlin.com thanks again for all your