Stealth technology, the internet, GPS in the palm of your hand on the most operation technology, is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight, in the midst of the cold war, doubt the defence advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology.
Welcome to Voices from DARPA a window onto DARPA's core of program managers.
Their job, to redefine what is possible.
My name is Ivan Amato , and I'm  your DARPA host.
Today, I am pleased to be talking with Dr. Sergey Bratus.
Sergey joined DARPA as a program manager in the agencies'
Information Innovation Office in 2018, he brings into the agency,
what you might think of as a six cents for the suring of a deeply hidden security vulnerabilities
in the oceans of software and the communications practices underlying our civilian and military technologies and systems.
Prior to coming to DARPA,
Sergey had been at Dartmouth College, beginning in 2002 as a post doctoral research associate, and most
recently as research associate professor in the computer science department,
he began his professional career at BBNtechnologies where he worked on natural language processing.
I find that professional element fascinating because the BBN-DARPA connections spanned
back to 1960s when the two work together on some of the foundations of Internet. Back to Sergey,
he received his undergraduate education at the Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology and earn his PhD
in mathematics from Northeastern University.
He has published over one hundred technical papers, and his research has received several awards, including
the 2012 Black Hat Pony Award for most innovative research.
That award, pony award is a prestigious (有声望的) one
that recognizes achievements of security researchers and security community.
Doctor Sergey Bratus, thanks for making some time to talk with me today about your many and very efforts to increase every safety in the paralysis, cyber domains that we are immersed in.
Thank you for being here.
Thank you for having me here, Ivan.
Let's start with the origin story of your interests in computer science and cyber security.
I think one of the things that fascinate the public about scientists and engineers is just where there are sort of in some ways, hybrid specialized interests come from.
[Q] So did you grow up in a geeky household ?
[Q] Did you encounter an engaging professor at the Moscow Instruments of Physics and Technology ?
[Q] Where did you interest come from?
Oh, computers were a miracle.
I grow up on the Soviet Union, and we would get a slow trick of imported technology, which is so wonderfully contrasted with the rest of life.
They were something from the future.
And so even though the technology that was available
to a school student was perhaps decade behind,
it was never less a miracle,
and it had an enormous attraction over the executives myself, we wanted to know how it worked,
and we wanted to be able to program something like those games that we saw on those computer screens.
And so we did, but as I was growing up in the Soviet Union, you could
see the slow progression of technology being important from the rest, and we were left behind by some people listening ten to fifteen years.
There was a bit of luck in that, because in my age, I go to see the very basics of computing, starting with programming micro calculators, where my appears in the west might have seen, might have been already seen IBM PC XT, which was an incredible miracle of technology.
And Sergey, just so that the listeners have a sense of timing here.
You say that you, you really encountered computers for the first time when you're in middle school.
So what years were those actually?
we're talking 197x, late 1970s, early 1980s
Okay, thank you.
So I took you off track, I'll right on that
So making computers do things was a huge time sink, because we're people in california might have had access to storage devices and floppies.
we actually had to retype our Texas Instruments
kind of a clone [...] programs.
Still, it was an incredibly magical experience, but that was my introduction to computers.
My introduction to security came when I was a grad student at Northeastern working on my degree, mathematics and Linux was exploding on the scene.
Everyone wanted to run a Linux server.
The internet was still the wonderful place where you met.
Like minded geeks [..] wasn't anything else.
And so I set up my Linux server.
I followed every bit of, the how-to instructions, and it worked, and I was happy.
And then in about two weeks, that server was compromised and taken over, and I found it serving ...
I don't know ..
Music that I could not quite understand or pieces of a game are probably pirated, that I knew nothing about.
It got, as the saying was at the time, a pond compromise taken over as it happened with many university computers in the 1990s, and I wanted to know how. I did everything by the book.
I thought I could understand
the way programs were written by that time I was already competent(有能力的)
C programmer, I thought, and I thought I understood that environment and those programs.
Turned out I did not, and the hackers did. [Host] right.
So you had a very personal experience with personal violation showing up a right at your own computer station that really got you hooked and concerned about these security issues.
I probably owe who ever did that a beer.
Right, so now you wanna go find out who that person is and shake their hand, because they essentially were central in the rest of the trajactory of your career.
I might say that, and so I went down the rabbit hole of a hacking and computer security, rather than being a mathematician
One of the quick question just cause i'm serious in the timing of in your educational, professional development and world history.
You got to undergraduate degree in Moscow, and then you got your graduate degree in Northeastern
So can you tell me, how is it that you made the transition from the then Soviet Union to United States?
I saw the late Soviet Union.
I grew up with the totalitarian(极权) society that it was, and I wanted out at the time, it was nearly impossible to do in any legal fashion.
But luckily, the soviet power was collapsing.
It collapsed between 1991 and 1993, and so I could, in fact, go out and study abroad, if an American university would take me and several offered.
And so I left. Quite a few people were more enthusiastic about the prospects of poor Soviet Russian and poor Soviet States, unfortunately, they were proven wrong.
All right, well, their losses are our gain.
So happy that you did actually make it out and clearly embrace the opportunities that were here.
Sergey, after getting your degrees where you worked first BBN, then you segwey into academy at Dartmouth where you build the computer science and security program that included the what you have described as a called quote-unquote "hidden curriculum(课程)", this one derived from the mindset and innovations of the hacker community, which is sounds fascinating to bring that into account of a computer science program and necessary.
I think the right thing to do surely.
So please talk about how these professional experiences contributes to your approach now to cyber security, and how they lead to your job at DARPA
starting in the 2018. I am very grateful to Dartmouth for letting me do this for taking me on as a research of shoot on one of their cybersecurity efforts.
I started with a machine learning application of a cyber security.
But by that time, I was already interested in how an exploitation worked, how exploits were written, how vulnerabilities were discovered and being a mathematician by education
I wanted to systematize this.
So I started showing up at the hacker conventions, such as the DefCon, and what I realized very soon was that there was a curriculum(课程) there, which the community came up with.
It was distributed and split up between various minds and groups.
But there were, a consistent sets of things that newcomers learned, and even though they had some interaction with how we took computer science and computer programming in academia(学术界), they were not quite the same.
And in many aspects, ah, they actually, went deeper on how things worked, and so I started systematizing this discipline(学科), which I maintained it has become as of at least late 1990s.
And I tried to extract that hidden curriculum, and I had support from my supervisors of Dartmouth doing that, and I have support to bring in students to the computer hacking conferences and then exposing them to this hidden curriculum.
And it turned out that it translated to impressive undergraded and then graduate dissertations(学位论文), all in all, I find that this work is not done.
Ivan Amato: Right
Well, it of course is not done because of there's innovation going on, both in those were seeking new and more powerful exploits,
and those who are worried about that and trying to to come up with countermeasures(反制措施) and defenses against that and everybody in there has to be brilliant, so it's kind of an amazing dynamic going on.
So now, before we talk about your programs, and I think it's scared of algebra's out of listeners who might not know about some of the hazards and wait and sort of, all the software we use, and perhaps how they are even contributing to some of the hazards, and in practices that they engage in the, info sphere, I really want to talk about the way you think about an engaged cyber space in the info sphere.
We sort of began to get into that a little bit, but you know, as I've looked over your programs and really try to understand where you are coming from, and which you are trying to achieve.
As I looked over your Dartmouth College page, your lab page, a sort of metaphor(隐喻) came to my mind about you, which is, and maybe one way of thinking about it is
All of us.  Most of us are drivers, and when we were out there driving, we're paying attention to the various hazards of the road, you know, very traditional things.
What's happening with the street lights ?
Are we going to be able to make it through that yellow, are their children on the side of the road ?
You know, what's the weather is.  It looks like there's about to be a downpour(倾盆大雨), right?
All of us sort of have a sense of these hazards are their part holes coming in the condition of the road.
you know, I imagine that you are looking at the info sphere, kind of driving through that world with that same kind of heads up view on these kind of obvious hazards.
But more than that, I kind of imagine you having almost the sixth sense in being able to see even what might be hidden hazards
you know, let's say, there's a sink hole, and it's just now, as I'm coming upon it about to open up with my cars gonna to go in there, something that you could not see from the surface, but somehow you can see through the road.
And you see that sink hole about to start, I get the feeling you have that sixth sense in the information technology and the cyber sphere to see what we really need to worry about.
Okay, that's me terribly describing your mind.
You know your mind better than me.
So, talk to me about that cognitive framework that you bring in to this cyber rich world that we live in.
On the ex three vision of vulnerability is a lot to claim.
I certainly do not claim that what I could claim is a lot of trepidation(不安) and reluctant(不情愿) using some technologies that I know are not as dependable or as simple as they could be.
I am the person with no personal smart phone.
I am the person who, before engaging with the website tries to see what the website looks like with all the executable bits, a javascript, disabled, and mostly it looks like nothing, which is too bad.
Because for most of those websites, and for most of those tasks that I want to complete on them, they have no business executing code on my computer and then pulling code from their associates, maybe commercial advertising or analysis associates, and then executing their code on my computer.
And then the code from their associates as well.
So you consider these all to be almost like nested vulnerabilities.
They are indeed.
One of the best examples of this is probably the thing that everyone uses every day, the web based email.
But when I look at the web browser, I see a machine for denying the user the understanding of where those are graphic elements in the email were in the overall pain of the browser up come from or where they eat if you click on them, it is the browser's goal to seamlessly blamed all of the content and hide the possible directions.
But at the same time, it doesn't let me see what my next action would actually bring about.
Now for me, I can second guess this for a typical user of such a webmail.
This is the tool order.
Imagine we make our trust decisions and based on the province of what we hear and see them directly.
And here we were denied any visual cues or any cues at all to that province.
Speaking of a protocol, this is a very slow process, but some people could see that bottle hole ten years ago, it was actually hit. One of my programs documents deals with another search photo are peaceful of electronic documents that we all exchange, and we are to not click on if we can't really verify where it came from.
But then, of course, see the previous point about webmail most of the time you are denied any cues as to where it actually came from.
But of course, it is our job to click on those documents, read them, send them onwards(向前), any ambiguity in the description of these formats is insecurity, and that insecurity will hit us ten years or or five years from now, from all from when it was introduced, people might say, well, it is okay.
We have anti-virus programs.
We can check, and we have firewalls, and we have other devices that could just check for mals.
However, it's typical because of the format, ambiguities for all the readers and interpreters of electronic documents to disagree about what those documents actually contain.
It's been a hacker's sport to make a file like a PDF document appear differently in different viewers.
It will similarly use a little different to the anti-virus or an application firewall.
And so if you can't really agree with all your electronic helpers and applications want what is actually in the document, what better way to hide malaysia ?
And again, this is something that fundamental computer science can tell you that will result at in those.
But as we call the parsing differentials of those data formats and those documents.
I'm glad that you have began to talk about your programs you started with safe documents.
Actually that's one of the easier ones of yours to say one of the other easier ones is assured micro patching or AMP.
I'm actually just gonna read all of the DARPA names because they are so DARPA. And DAPRA is known for its names and acronyms just for listeners to hear them.
And then we're not gonna acceptably really go through each one, because we would be here for quite a long time.
I would love to, but we can't have a five-hour podcast.
We lose everybody, but let me just read them because they are beautifully multisyllabic(多音节的).
And they gave some sense of what you are up to.
So here we go, Artificial Intelligence Mitigations of Emergent Execution, or AIMEE.
verified security and performance enhancement of large legacy software or V-SPELLS
recovery of symbolic mathematics from code or ReMath
hybrid AI to protect integrity of open source code.
And we've already mentioned SafeDocs and Assured Micro Patching(AMP), and there is even one more,  I think this is the newest one that got approval is
is called, HARDEN and that's short for hardening development toolchains against emergent execution engines.
What a mouthful that is, it sounds like quite an ambitious set of programs to decrease our vulnerabilities, as we been talking about, but since we can't really go into any depth with these, certainly not all of that. Maybe you can pick and choose and sort of walk through your programs you spend, you know, as little or as much times you want on this one or that one, it just to give us a sense of what, in fact, you are worried about.
And what kinds of problems you're trying to solve, all the interests of increasing security for our war fighters are also for all the civilians out there.
Certainly, and I would borrow a phrase from one of the famous security researchers, who said, the point of our profession, is making computers that we could finally trust.
Which, of course, hurricanes to the fact that we cannot trust computers as we make them now.
But, and who, who said that, who is that famous person ?
It is Felix Linder, a researcher from berlin.
Now we cannot trust computers we built today, and we can not trust software we built today.
And part of the reason is, even if we build them exactly to the specification.
And even if there is no ambiguity, but all the morsel, if there raised some ambiguity(含糊) in that a specific issue, we end up building what we intend, and something else. That something else turns to be a lot friendlier to the attackers, to the exploiters.
Then we've ever intended to be.
It's as if packaged with your shiny work station or your server is the kit for exploiting that server.
And this is what I refer to as emergent execution uh, emergent properties of computing systems, properties that we never met them to have needed the hardware and other software, not the combination there are of
But yet they allow the adversary to reprogramme computers, reuse existing, well-debugged pieces of software before attack purposes.
And this is the aspect of the computers that I would like to reduce, mitigate and eliminate where possible.
Right, so maybe I can ask you to take that another level further.
We have given us kind of the helicopter view.
And then your programs.
I imagine are designed to go after a specific categories of vulnerabilities.
So maybe just talk about two of the ones that may be our particular interest in reports.
So here is, a are likely to find save dogs or save documents.
Looks at the information interchange formats, the formats in which data arrives at our computers and arrives at our software, and will also sometimes exploit them.
Now, how do we build code that can safely intake a data that might be hostile or might have been manipulated ?
How do we make software that agrees on what is in the message between the various computing components that are involved in the the flow of our email of our documents ?
How do we, as we say, parse the data securely, or how do we intake data securely?
This is a SafeDocs, and then, of course, now, that we found some vulnerabilities or ambiguities, we want to fix those vulnerabilities in the date intake, and very typically, those vulnerabilities are like a single check on the input data that was assumed was done, but was actually never done by the actual software doing the data and take the passer.
So how do we patch those vulnerabilities usually is a simple check, but the problem with a simple change to any binary software is that you have to make sure that you are not destroying something else. You are not
damaging the baseline functionality of your device and the methods and tools for insuring it is AMP.
I just have to say, so, what's fascinating about that description to me is that there is a parallel in genetic engineering.
We're, if you're going to make a change, even a varies tiny point change, changing one omenos at a protein, or or just one DNA nuclear tide, sometimes that will have effects on, other proteins that you never thought would be involved, given your initial intention.
So it's kind of the same way, right, a patch going into legacy software.
You'll, you're after, you know, it fixes and try to increase security, but you don't know.
Maybe there is another set of changes that are deleterious(有害的) that you would would regret.
That's right, well, each and every one of us, we are computing devices [laugh] besides other the things.
So this is a very valid analogy(类比).
And then, of course, you might want to check how you could add components or add features to a system without disrupting it.
And this is the V-SPELL program.
So let me just go to one that gets back to your.
I would say earlier interest, you know, your interests as a mathematician is the recovery of symbolic mathematics from code.
So this is sort of working backwards.
It sounds like from the software, to mathematical formulations that maybe were at the heart of what the programmer was trying to do.
Now, why is this an important ability?
It is extremely important when you encounter legacy software as you rely more, as we all rely more and more on algorithms controlling our power, power, medical devices and or even our cards, you want to make sure that the intended algorithm are with the engineer planned to put in that device is actually what the device does.
So connecting back the binary form of software to the symbolic form of mathematics that the software and codes, it is an extremely important step in making sure that our devices are trust worthy.
Very often, you don't have the source code in legacy software, the company that may, the thing the device went out of business, or it might not have gone out of business, but it actually lost the source code.
This has happened to companies begin small.
What would like to do is still be answer the question of does this books do, what it what was intended to do, and what was it in control engineering terms?
Interesting question comes to mind now that as you work backwards from software to, sort of, the original mathematical formulations and algorithms, does that uniquely to one mathematical formulation was impossible that you, you might have several.
And then you still left with the question of what was the actual original intent in the regional mathematical formulation?
You certainly end up with the several and in fact the whole continue, because there are many different ways to write down the same as medical formula, and many more to encode that formula in code.
And of course, not all code comes from mathematical formulas, but for the well engineered systems, for the so called control processers that control things such as engines or generators.
There is a well-engineered symbolic mathematical theory of how they work, and we should be able to discern(分辨) that in code.
This is, what ReMath attempts to do.
right. This is something like embedded processors in the grid.
And there are certain other things you can bring in to kind of rule out 5 candidate mathematical formulations, cause you know what it should look like in this particular engineering category.
That's right.
This aims to help the subject [...] experts.
This aims to put together the specialist in the binary and in the control algorithms.
Or control engineers
Q: When you say binary, what do you mean?
The executable code, as a compiled form of it that finally goes into the memory of the device on controllers and it's operation.
We're only getting started.  I could keep asking questions because what you do fascinates me, and I want to know more and more, but I'm actually gonna suggest that listener to who have the common trigue to go to your program manager webpage on the website, and then to take a tour themselves to get at least some additional taste of all of your programs.
You know, as we come to the end of our time here, I want to get into a couple of just bigger questions.
This is the innovation, ecosystem and technology and society types of questions, what fascinates me about you is that you really have had experience in the three kind of major sectors.
We tend to think about in the innovation ecosystem, right, so you started your career in industry in BBN and spent nearly twenty years in academy at DARPA, and you might return to that at the end of your time here in DARPA.
And then here you are doing government work at DARPA since 2018.
So when you look at those three players, universities and industry and government in the overall innovation ecosystem, specifically when it comes to the to sort of cyber security technology, how do you see each of those players contributing.
It's a great question.
I would say that, of course, the industry looks to deploy product.
Academia explores new ideas and follows publishing trends.
The role of DARPA has been to, at least in the success that I have seen has been to pursue things that could not be immediately made them to product.
Or the industry might not believe could be made into products
and encourage that kind of exploration, when which you could not justify(证明...有理) to your manager, to your shareholders as an industry worker.
You mean, in that case, because there is a sense that there is, there is too much risk to go ahead to do that responsibly in a business context.
But then, if DARPA comes in and has the benefit of managers like you, who can have programs that demonstrate, take the risk down in certain areas, then a company might say, okay, let's take this to a finish line.
That's right.
Whereas with the academia, well, you may have heard the phrase of publish appearash, which means that and academic research or not to have a successful career or any career at all is expected to produce at least several papers a year aimed at a difficult first-tier(第一类) conferences or journals.
Now, those have some idea of which research directions are promising and interesting, but these often fail to encompass(围绕) significant parts of reality, including industrial reality, or even the parts of the industry, does not think about now, has been behind a several DARPA successes that I have experienced personally to define a new direction.
Define a new trend and puts some grand funding behind the trend in order to get academia to listen
Well, this is the need that you might be missing.
This is the cool thing that might, with time create its own first tier publication venue(会场) of journal and conferences.
And there, I believe, DARPA has been greatly successful.
Thinking about this, what a great finish line, what a great result is a DARPA of which is to take a technology.
Neither take the risk down so that someone else will pick it up, in sort of, transition, but a military service or to industry for additional development, sometimes programs just segway to another program to build on what has accomplished in the prior work
when you scanning your own mind, your programs and the many research performers who are working on them who like to come to you now again, say, Sergey, Sergey
Look what I've done. can you mention one or two of the maybe the more mature accomplishments that you think have a good chance of transition and becoming actual technologies in our lifes?
One of the things that really excites me, it is on the SafeDocs program we've been working with the PDF association, which is an industry by the united, unites many stakeholders in the portable document format to produce a machine readable, unambiguous specification of the format.
This is the first time ever that this has been attempted for a major format, with billions of documents out there.
And of course, you cannot reinvent that format for that reason, because people would not take kindly to their documents being simply deemed and compliant and not opening.
But I think we are on our way to reforming how the standards process, the international standards process at the international standardization organization, deals with the information interchange formats and how we might make our electronic documents much more trust worthy
so that we would not actually be told to not click on documents and could rely on computers to securely process the data that comes in a documents and communications in the many sensor sheets that surround us.
Okay, and let you spend one more minute on this PDF example that you bring up, and so that listeners who might not be in this world of increasing security, reducing vulnerabilities as they interact with, say, PDF documents.
What is the security gain that you get by moving toward that kind of standardization that you just mentioned, and the, disambiguation on the part of the platform on which showing up.
How does that increase our security?
Directly and immediately remember the time of your training when starting to use any computing system, when you're told to never click on attachments from people you do not trust
Why is that ?
It's because documents these days are not equivalent of a simple sheet of paper with some passive content that you can read or ignore it [...]
They are sophisticated programs that interact with the software on your computer, make it do things, trigger emergent properties.
Emergent are parts in that software that no one wanted there, no one intended to put there in the first place, and that we could locally really know as the exploit.
So when you talk to not click on documents, well, this is the part of the present that I would like to exclude from the future.
It'll take a lot of effort, but unambiguous definitions of what you expect to find there.
And what is denied and what is expected.
isn't a three piece of it
Super helpful for for someone like me who sees that I don't click, I don't clicks.
Try to make that my practice.
But now I understand that that in some ways that are hedge against some creative person who might have found one of these emergent executable pathways into my computer.
Yeah, which are typically known as vulnerabilities.
But because we don't know all of the vulnerabilities that could be in there, the broad brostroke solution of not clicking on it sort of solves a lot of problems.
But you're saying, we know, that's not really good solution.
Yeah, actually it doesn't work.
Whatever your job is, you're intended to read things.
Edit them, send them on.
I don't think there is any professions these days that doesn't include some kind of form filling or manual reading, or any one of those tasks that do take electronic documents, so you can't just not click.
So I often ask of my, my discussion leaders, who I presume our tech files, because here this is DARPA, right ?
Um.. here's the question. I, I was always like to find out if there are technology that you dreamed about when you were in middle school or later, this don't have to be DARPA technologies at all.
But just, you know, when you just sort of look back in your wish for, you say, oh, if that technology existed I would just love it, are there technologies like that for you?
Of course, I mean ，I am the child of the space exploration age, or the a tail end there're of.(?)
And so flying cars that can go to the moon, a rockets that teenagers could pilot.
If you look back at some of those novels of Heinlein and others, that's what you see.
And we are getting some not the flying cars yet, but certainly spacecraft, and that can land vertically, used to be straight Sci-Fi
till it was not
[Host] right.
We do see that I have to say that the idea of millions of teenagers of
piloting their own rocket is about the most frightening vulnerability I possibly can imagine,
but maybe we can educate the teenagers to operate these things safely,
I just have the image ever I actually do kind of love.
One final question before I show you my gratitude for talking with me.
And that's just, is there something, Sergey, that I should've asked you that I did not or
just something else that on your mind that you think would be adventurous(新奇的) to our listeners.
If I could say one thing on the technology in general, it is that, uh, it is exciting.
But at the same time it brings large and unknown failure modes and vulnerabilities,
getting too enthusiastic about technology to the point of mandating its use is hardly ever a great idea in my book,
you can call me a techno-fobe(排科技主义) or a combined techno-file and techno-fobe (?)
but mandating of the use of any particular technology also means mandating the use of the vulnerabilities that come with it.
And so any such decisions, any sessions enthusiasms should be tampered by the understanding that this is what happens.
[Host] right
And so one way I think about what you just said is that a question that has to be there in the technology development process is
what could possibly go wrong, right ?
And that all we should be part of the practice that is sort of hygiene(保健?) for technology development.
That is true, but I would also take it further.
I would say that listening to rejectionists of any particular technology is underrated(被低估).
They might, in fact, be right in certain ways that a people more enthusiastic about the technologies might not have foreseen(预见)
So we must deal with caution here.
I believe, love that balanced perspective of being excited in a techno feel of sense
but also having that sense of respect and eyes wide open and caution and fear of unintended consequences that
justified a little bit of a techno-fobe component, as well as you move forward.
So that's really, really interesting to hear.
Sergey, we're out of time.
So let me just thank you for helping me understand a bit more about the cyber security and insecurity landscapes.
And I have to say, I am really hardened that people with your expertise and attentions,
which is to say, people exactly like you in particular, I am happy around the case.
It was just a real blast for me to talking to you.
Thank you for having me and it's great to be here.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us, I hope you join us again for the next Voices from DARPA.
Thanks also, to Tom Shotrage for his partnership and producing this program,
for more information about Dr. Sergey Bratus
the programs he and colleagues in the agency's Information Innovation Office,
and many other breaks through technologies DARPA's working on,
visit DARPA.mil
And for links that enable you to download this podcast, go to the Voices from DARPA page on DARPA's website.