Stealth technology, the Internet,GPS in the column of your hand alternative operation technologies, a driver of our, since its founding in one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight, in the midst of the cold war, doubt that offended that research project agency has been a driver of technology.
Welcome to voices a window entitled with core of program managers.
Their job to redefine was possible.
My name is Tyler McQuade since 2013, I've been a program manager in DARPA's.
Defence Sciences' Office, and I'm your DARPA host.
Tyler, I'd like to start out, which is sort of learning a little bit about you as a program manager.
So maybe you could tell us something about your background and how that relates to the kinds of programs you've been developing.
Ivan, I've been a molecular guy, I love molecules I have since I was in high school and even beyond high schools are earlier.
you know, I'm a sort of a, nova junky.
Cosmos, billions and billions of stars.
Well,I was more interested in the billions of molecules.
I've always wanted to be an explorer, but the time I got the age, yeah,I might explore something all the year charted.
the lands that have been charted, and there were no more uncharted land.
So I looked at kind of frontiers that
you couldn't see and molecules fit that look more defined in physics,
'cause you can put it in a bottle all at times, especially in the area that I am very comfortable in organic synthesis.
You can make stuff and see it.
You can test the properties, and you can play with the combination of items that are together.
And in really, it was sort of,
This palette that I could play with.
I really like that.
It was exploring the world in a totally different way,
always been amazed that how just putting together items and certain geometries, certain bonding patterns and can come together in two materials with all kinds of different properties in a skin and bone at the crazy rate.
I mean, you go from having something they can buy to something that explodes to something that makes beautiful colors to something that makes your cookie smell great and taste great events, all chemistry
You're a molecules guy, yeah. They're actually not that many molecules people, like you at DARPA, which is interesting.
So as a wrap of this minority, how are you taking that interesting in the form of programs
in the defense scientist office, one of the things that is going on right now, one of the ziggy's is revolutionizing science.
science but faster, better. and one of the things that is interesting about chemistry, especially when we're talking about the makers, the people who make materials, make small molecules, make medicines.
It is , uh, really slow process.
I really like the idea of reinventing science, and in chemistry, there is a lot of opportunity to reinvent the science.
So let me just ask, when you say we inventing science, maybe you mean the actual process that we were asking questions that we were trying to answer those questions.
Can you be a little more detailed about, what would you have in mind?
Men, chemistry is a tough subject.
We have lots of parameters that we don't often know how are controlling them, but if we did all of the chemistry in much more controlled environment, where the environment was being monitored, we might come up with much, much more reproducible chemistry, which will then mean it can be transportation.
So in other words, if I have a machine that is doing the chemical reaction, recording how it does the net code that record can be sent from one love to another, so you could accelerate the same way to the end.
Internet allows you to accelerate how information was transport, what if you could do that with molecules.
Tyler, this might be a good time to talk a little bit about the two of the programs that you're working on, and what I have in mind is the full effect program, and they Make-It program.
So why don't we start with fold effect, full effects, that's a program, it stands for a full, did non natural with biological function in the photo, fact, program were making polymers that meet natural polymers so that we might biotherapeutics moral bust.
So right now, if you get one of the more modern drugs right now, a good portion of them are made from proteins, and some people like it,I entire bodies.
So, for example, humana or installing those are examples of protein biotherapeutics.
The problems they are not heat stable.
And if something is in heat stable, it's not going to end up in a except.
So our soldiers are a very place, rather than to be most.
Bono's boomer don't have access to the most banks, medicines, as many of them are just gradual, and so we have to transport them back to an environment where you have refrigerators, you have a handling equipment that can allow you to control that the environment around the medicine.
What if you want to make an unnatural?
There are lots of natural fibers that we used to use, and we've replaced them with non natural fivers, because they're more robust.
Do you mean like silk to?
So what if he wanted to take the same?
So the beneficial properties are yet from plastics, and you were emerging with the beneficial properties of the biological balloons, like proteins in DNA.
The full effect program that is a platform.
It's about how we make those in and how we discover them.
So in a way, if you think about all of the possible molecules that one could make the small ones, you know, like, like an aspirin or the below larger ones like these protein based medicines you're talking about, they're really sort of being infinitive to possibilities, like an infinite space that you could possibly search an example which you say here is your trying to develop some tools, even just a few people took to go explore some of the regions of this influenced space.
They just have not been looked at before.
I'm getting on my own track.
Oh, you're so on track.
It gets back to my whole desire to explore that.
I talked about, you know, but it is really about giving researchers a capability to be able to explore these, these universes.
It's almost like a hubble telescope for this particular galaxy or universal regular space.
So that was full of effects.
Young, I'm also interested in the makeup program.
Can you say little bit about what you're doing there Make-It is a platform technology for making small.
And in this particular case, we're trying to do is we're trying to democratize chemistry.
So what if you could have a system that biologists or any scientists came up and type, and the machine figured out how to Make-It, even if there was no recipe available so that the machine would figure out a possible set of ways to make something, and then we'll go about testing each one of those ways and tell it on the solution, and it would log that solution in a cloud or in its data bank.
And now that molecule could be made any time.
In addition, the system would also be able to have to make more of so that initially,I would do really small scale sympathies.
That means milligrams.
And then once it figured out a solution, it would also automatically scale it up.
Can you offer to us a concrete example?
maybe you could think of a, problem or a particular receptor for example on a cell that you might want as a target
Then explain how... The Make-It Framework would go about Interacting with that The receptor in prep solving a medical or other biological problem
Yeah, you know, for example, one very popular target for the heart disease is PCSKnine.
And so there's probably many papers that come out every year.
They describe inhibitors that have been discovered against that target.
The structures are available.
Let's say that I am a researcher, and I want to study some aspect of a complex soil system and having access to the PC inhibitor would be really useful.
But maybe I wanted one selective in a certain way that is commercially available, but somebody is reported now,I might contact that researcher who is made it before.
Maybe they ran out, and it can take them three months to Make-It.
But if I have access to Make-It device,
I could just go type in the structure and have the material, maybe the next day, or at the end of the week.
And in addition to that, I have it memorized.
The machine has kept that in his memory banks, university environment, for example, wants to make that they
typed it in a little bit out that day, because the solution would be, it's a way of saying chemistry has been documented since its inception, especially synthetic chemistry, through what are called experimental.
These are documents that the researcher is using to try to capture what they didn't.
A laboratory to make something, writing it down like a recipe
So a lot of times will leave out that we think are not necessary, but are necessary.
And sometimes we didn't even know there were necessary.
So when another researcher comes in and try to read that cookbook like a experimental, it might take the month to reproduce it, and it may never.
Why should we waste our human effort by not making sure that we document that outcome, that experiment in a way that can guarantee production.
So you're talking about capturing procedural knowledge.
Correct, yes, the Make-It system is not just the artificial intelligence system or a cloud system that's archiving.
It's a machine that's doing the chemistry so that the machine will be reproducible.
You'll be able to recreate that machine in any lab you want, as long as you replicate that machine faithfully(如实地), and it runs the routines that you recorded one lab versus another faithfully, you're going to reproduce chemistry everywhere you want to
one of the things that I find fascinating about DARPA, is that it is perhaps, in its place in the overall technology development ecosystem.
And as a program manager and someone who has been an academy,I think, also an industry.
And now here at DARPA, can you talk to us a little bit about how DARPA might be playing some interesting or perhaps even unique roles in the overall technology ecosystem.
And yeah, it is a very exciting role.
DARPA is that one place where we are thinking about innovation unconstraint(无拘无束), like, where can we go?
in my mind, the way remember doing that is because it fits our mission space.
If you want to create or prevent surprise, it's best to get to that new universe of chemistry sooner rather than later.
And so we take innovations from all of the other funding agencies in other words
they're seeding it, and we look for one wave with the beginning, and we pushed hard and let it across fast
DARPA is critical because we are structuring what I consider to be that crescendo(渐强) investment, as we are trending towards something amazing, and the Internet is an example, and I am really emulating that with, Make-It.
I want to create the Internet of molecules.
How do you change for molecules from one place to another in the same way is a 3D printing concept?
You have a design.
You could put that design on a cloud.
And then if you have 3D printer, you could transfer that design from one place to.
So they are related.
And I have been no, constantly inspired by what dark has done.
Is there a question, tyler, that you wish I had asked you during the discussion that I didn't, even so ask the question yourself and answer, what's my favorite aspect of chemistry?
The answer for most cameras?  What, what's the answer for?
Most cabinet cameras dive, and you know,I love that the structure of molecule relates to the function.
Now I love them.
Yeah, most of my friends media is for the crowd magnets, I guess
everybody likes explosions, but I actually like the smell of organic chemistry, so pretty much amongst all actors like people going to like one flavors are thinking of, maybe it omit chocolate cheap, but actually smelling all of the esters and wondering,I wonder if that's disaster, or that I strength and tell the fluctuations, and also an astronaut refers to a particular chemical motive.
If I recall of my own organization must be part of it.
There's a carbon with the oxygen job, abandon a few other things we don't have to go into the details, except to say that is a particular kind of molecular motivated and variations.
Yeah, classic compounds.
So I,Ireally like the class of compounds that are associated with flavourings, and I don't mean just not a natural flavorings and natural unnaturally a coconut.
It smells the way it does because of chemistry, and that that always just really makes me excited.
So Tyler, I really enjoyed talking with you today about the your programs by chemistry, by dark.
So thanks for being here.
Ivan, it's always a pleasure to be with you, and thanks for having me and really glad to relate my thoughts about chemistry and and thank you listeners for sharing this time with us.
Tune in, next time for another Voice from DARPA.