Sealth Technologies
The Internet, GPS in the palm of your hand. Autonomous operation.
Technology is a driver of our time since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War.
DARPA, Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency has been a driver of Technology
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window at the DARPA's core of program managers
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Dan Green since 2013 I've been a program manager and DARPA's Microsystems technology office
And I'm your DARPA host
Ivan Amato
Dan, tell me a little bit about your background and how it relates to what you hope to accomplish in your time here at DARPA
I came here through a series of fortunate events I got into science from an early age I like physics
I did physics in college
I got into semiconductor physics
So semiconductors are the
Materials that underpin the electronic
in all of our commercial Technologies today
And
Really fell in love with that area
At that point time which was in the in the 90s
When I started getting into electronics and
going out to grad school it was kind of a bad time to be doing electronics, because
There is a lot of maturity
And a lot of
concern about where it was going to go from there because of
established players like Intel or
We're heading there hitting the stride and along came a new material system
Called Gallium Nitride (GaN)
Until I was part of this first wave of engineers that were brought up
Looking at gallium nitride to understanding its properties as it applies to transistor technology
Can you just spend a few seconds talking to us about
What is interesting about different kinds of semiconductors
So when you look at the history of semiconductors
straight, the transistors came out
from the labs of course
after the
the second world war, so it's been around for a long time
And the interesting pieces that
As dominant as silicon is today that was not at all obvious
When they started
And in fact when you look at the
The first transistors they were made of Germanium (锗)
And they look like crazy little contraption(新奇装置)
correct the size of a palm, essentially they jabbed a couple of
wires into this block of material and were able to extrapolate(外推) from that very
very rudimentary(早期) experiment that
Hey we're really onto something here
It's obviously translated
to many billions dollars of
commercial activity now and
The complexity of this we can do things today is
astonishing
Really the key was
Going from Germanium to Silicon and a lot of the technical reasons that
made silicon
work
Relate to the fact that it's just
It warms combinations with other materials called oxide very easily
And so having that oxide layer
Really help control where the electrons flow
The ability to manipulate the the material structure
Is really what separated
Silicon
from the other competitors of that time.
And the interesting peace that happened with the you know
the semiconductors zoo in the 80s and 90s
was the dramatic expansion of the materials that were able to manipulate in that matter
And so we went from
things like Silicon to our notice compound semiconductors where we use combinations of element
to create new material sets
So the first material set that
hit the mainstream is called gallium arsenide (砷化镓)
Instead of being, regular crystal just made of silicon atoms,
it has an alternating pattern of gallium and arsenic
Right and my understanding is going from Silicon to a Compound Semiconductor
like gallium arsenide
was hard enough
that it became a program at DARPA to try to
mature that material make it useful. - Absolutely right
DARPA made an early investment to take
What then was experimental technology of gallium arsenide
That was useful for things like amplifiers and
really scale it up
to make it manufacturable
Because they realize that it was going to enable us to do things
like arrays, phased-array
so what is a phased array phased arrays
Is it is a
A combination of amplifiers in a repeated pattern
So that you can project electromagnetic waves
So that means things like
Radars that go on our
planes and ships
can leverage that capability to see what's around them and to communicate.
And what ended up happening was because of the
the defense interest in maturing that technology
and the ability to bring it to a manufacturable state
A lot of people realize that hey it would be useful for
commercial sector as well.
And so that same gallium arsenide technology that came out of the early DARPA
So-called MIMIC program
In the 90s
I was really what set off the cell phone release
Because it enabled
The amplifiers that let
those small handsets that you carry around with you
to talk to
the cell phone towers.
And that expansion of of the semiconductors zoo we we we started with germanium
We talked about silicon we talked about gallium arsenide
This might be a good time to, sort of, moving to some of the programs that you've been overseeing
absolutely
gallium arsenide was was really exceptional because it showed
How different material properties can be by moving away from to silicon
But by no means did that exhaust the periodic table
And so as people were looking around
They realized
that there's a lot of other options
Late 90s and early 2000s
This was
An individual researcher actually develop the technology to grow high-quality
Gallium nitride material
Gallium nitride materials is special because
It. It offers a wider band gap. So that's a characteristic energy the material
And it enabled
devices to be made which could emit into the Blue
part of the electromagnetic spectrum
which was not available before.
That set off a whole wave in terms of lighting
and so we're saying that today with our pixelated stoplights and and the LEDs that we see now
in the houses
But the correlation that was it enable that material set
to be more widely available
And enable those of us in electronics domain to use it for other purposes
like high power amplifier
Enable us to to look at
Things like more efficient cell phone towers
But also higher power array for
The Navy and the and the Army and airforce
For the sensors and communications and the
electronic warfare equipment that we use everyday.
Right and I know that one of your own passions has been to try to
Look at the strengths of these different kinds of semiconductor materials in and then try to put them together to mix-and-match them
Correct. that might not have been so easy to do before
partly because their crystal structures are a little different and they might
not stick together well
so these are some of the challenges right that
you've been taking on as a program manager.
Part of the interesting piece
with Gallium Nitride is
not so much that it provides all these advantages but then it works at all
It's a very different material set than historical semiconductors
It has a mechanical element that's a part of
The way that it operates more than just the way that it moves electronics around
It has what's known as peers' electric
And so it actually
depends upon being compressed
by the combination materials
in a certain state
to enable the electrons to exist
where we can use them.
So we can mix in a little aluminum for there are gallium and nitrogen
to create a different alloy and we
can grow those crystals right on top of each other
So that they maintain their structure from layer to layer
And a lot of the development that happened in the
early DARPA MIMIC project was enabling those techniques
where we can control that crystal
layering at the atomic scale
which enables us to create
these types of very finely
characterizes and structured devices
over very large area.
So we can create very complex circuits
that are structured at that atomic scale.
So where all this goes from here
Because it has this
Funny characteristic of mechanical and electrical coupling that's different is that
There's a whole swath of degrees of freedom that haven't really makes explore with GaN
So I entered the field just as it was maturing
And worked at a company to help bring one of the initial products
to life in terms of
high power amplifier for the cell phone community
But my time at DARPA has really been about
Where do we go from here in terms of
leveraging all these
hidden attributes of gallium nitride that really haven't been
brought to the barrier yet
So things like scaling the gate lines down to hit the links that we do
And what that that enables us to do is push up higher and higher frequencies
So how do we understand that? well
The
The frequencies that we we commonly encounter for like our cell phone is around 2GHz
And really because the scaling advantages and that we can do with gallium nitride
The higher power density that we can't we can start to realize
The ability to transmit power
Up in the millimeter wave
So that's up
towards
30 to 300 gigahertz
It's the ability to dress that higher frequency range
really opens up a whole part of the electromagnetic spectrum
that we haven't been able to access before.
Why do you want to go there?
Because that will enable things like 5G
in the commercial sector.
There's a lot of activity right now.
That's going to help us all stream video from wherever we want.
But it also enables us to do different things like look at different material properties
As we interrogate what's going on with with different materials with
its different part in electromagnetic spectrum
So we can actually literally see the world in a different way
Because we're using light at different wavelengths
the possibilities of what we can do there are just started to be explored
And the capabilities that we're developing with gallium nitride
are a building block and a tool to help us to get there.
Dan, how would you imagine the technologies
that you are nurturing you spoke speaking a lot about gallium nitride here.
How would image that finding traction
both in national security and civilian settings
So the
technologies were developing with gallium nitride
are going to be very are going to be very important
for national security because
It doesn't enable us to get into these new parts
of the electromagnetic spectrum
So that underpins
all of our capabilities when it comes to things like
communications
or sensing
Coming from the civilian sector I didn't really understand until I worked
with some of the military
is that
we think why do you need to sense things
And
And we know what's down the block when we're walking down the street
But if you're in the Navy and you're on the ship in the middle of Pacific
You're in a very very dark place
And you don't know what's around you in the world
sensing becomes very important
Because you're you're really out in the middle of nowhere
And that's part of the
The piece that's missing I think when we think about this in
context of our everyday lifes
That the military is doing things that are very different
from what we do in the commercial sector.
What we're doing with gallium nitride is enabling the technologies
that will help them with those particular missions
And what will happen at the end of the day is that once we have them
People are creative
And they will find ways to use those pieces
There are more relevant to what we doing
in our everyday lifes.
So what might be some of the larger societal technological in
security context in which your
program in interest reside?
It's a very interesting time right now in electronics
And because
historically the US has had such a dominant position in the development of these technologies
From the initial development of transistor Bell labs
through the
the mass roll out of
PCs from Intel.
And what we've seen is just in the last decade or so
Is the globalization of that technology has
spread around the world.
one of the byproducts of the early going where DARPA funded a lot of these gallium arsenide technologies
that rolled into our defense
defense communications
and sensing technologies
Was that we had a very comfortable
place in the world where we
could make all those components at home
and use them
in very controlled manners for our purposes.
And with this globalization that's taking place
because of the advent of cell phones
and mass consumer electronics
We're seeing now that
All these electronic pieces in these different developments
Are happening all over the world.
And so it really challenges us.
in the way that we
consumer electronics
and the Department of Defense.
Because now we
we don't necessarily have all of those
best components at home because there's a lot of
activity all over the world.
Until there is
there's challenges both understand what pieces
we should develop
And
can continue to own at home
And what pieces we should leverage in that global marketplace.
And how to put the the best of those products together,
so that we can commering competitive.
What you're talkin about here in some ways is the sort of the
technology
ecosystem the engineering ecosystem
innovation ecosystem and makes me think about
where DARPA fits into these very ecosystem
So DARPA really is fantastic and that
It has the ability to go in and make
significant investment
to advanced technologies
Critical
and can really be a difference-maker
For instance, in gallium nitride
I mentioned
The new imports of GaN as it came along
to advancing what we can do in the RF Spectrum
And really that technology was
resound in the world
Because of the LED market place.
But DARPA came along and
made a significant investment
in wide bandgap of semiconductors of which gallium nitride has won
To push the material that
That's base
For the electronics domain
And because of that early investment DARPA
has created capabilities
that are being rolled out now to the services and in
the form of new
radars that are going to the navy and communication systems
that are going around the services
And
It's also dominant
provided the backbone for
industry players that are serving commercial market as well
Dan, can you describe one
science fiction technology either that you read about in the past
you come up on your own you woken up in the middle of the night
with this dream of a technology
that it doesn't exist now but that you really wish
could exist?
This is what we do here cuz I spend time dreaming about different technology so
It's such a fascinating time
because a lot of these things that we formally just dreamed about are
coming to life around us.
The one Comic Book I did read when I was a kid was Iron Man, and so
We now have all these Iron Man movies but
What's fascinating is walking around the building
and seeing how parts of those technologies are trying to make it look
less and less crazy. You started to see
people are actually working on exosuits
people who are working on
how we connect the body to electronics,
how we actually interface with electronics.
So you're talking here about complex and potentially powerful technologies
which means they could lead
To both good and
perhaps troublesome results.
How do you think about the potential consequences of the technology
You're helping to develop?
So I think that's an
interesting question that we do struggle with a lot.
As we continue to expand our capability to
compute
and
project
into the electromagnetic spectrum.
Really raises the ability for us to
to be always on
and always connected.
And it not only did that
erase all the issues that
received today in terms of
having your cell phone on all the time and
being that sense always on
But also this
always aware
So that there's no way to hide things
and so, it becomes a very open and transparent
place to be which has pluses and minuses
in terms of how we operate
as a democracy in the world.
So I think there's a lot of
implications of technology that are yet to be grappled with.
But it's also
a law of physics that technology will advance.
We will continue to explore the world so
It doesn't help us to not try to advance
And see what's what's possible
The whole point of DARPA is to prevent surprise
And really part of our job here is to go out to figure out what's possible
so we can start that process
of understanding it early
Well Dan, I really enjoyed our conversation here today
Thank you, Ivan.
Thanks for listening and tune in next time to hear another Voice from DARPA
For more information about DARPA the program managers
And the breakthrough Technologies they are developing visit us online at darpa.mil