50 Cent
Hi there
Welcome to the -6 podcast
Brought to you by GE Capital under show
Went to the movers and shakers
China's tech industry and discuss how Founders from around the world can draw that stands
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
I'm a managing partner at GTB capital and I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other emerging markets for the last 20 years
And a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule and many Chinese Founders that organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Chinese internet companies Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat groups in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world for a while
You can join these by visiting 96.2 gvtc.com
Hi everyone today I'm very excited
Two hoes are special Ama or ask me anything episode with our managing partner hanstone
Was here with me to answer questions from followers of the 96 pack
So we announces anime a couple weeks ago and caught on our listeners to submit questions and have since they receive a lot of
Great questions on all kinds of topics
So I apologize in advance if we don't get your question since we have limited time here
The first
Just a little bit of background on Hannah
Those of you who regularly listen to our show should know quite a bit about him already but anyways
Igtv he focuses on investments in consumer internet e-commerce and iot sectors across the US China and other
Emerging Markets
He's invested in 11 unicorn companies that over a billion dollars
Including xiaomi
Wish musically now part 2 by dance Airbnb
Songs for little red book OfferUp etcetera
He grew up in Taiwan and move to LA
His worker left in New York Boston Hong Kong Singapore
Shanghai Beijing
And the Bay Area
He's now based in Menlo Park but it's basically on a play every other day so welcome to the show
Thank you Zara
So first I was kind of surprised but also not surprised that around half of all people who submit a question is wrote down
The same question
How do you break into VC
So let's first address this
Burning question that a lot of people seem to have
On their mind
Sure I did not
Starting BC of right off of college
I was very fortunate to
In a class of 1990
Free
So
That was a year. Netscape browser
What's the least
And the world become a very different
Place thereafter
I think Peter Thiel was a couple years ahead of me
In Nigerian was a year behind me
And so that was that was the right time
How to be an internet business
But I didn't know anything about BC back then
I start my career in banking
In New York
And then Hong Kong
Let's spend the next 5 years
Through Hong Kong Taipei in Singapore
Tech-related gross
Basically investing companies that were trying to do country Manufacturing
Semiconductor chip design
Internet was not a big focus at that point in time
And then run around 1999
The group of Ivy Leagues and stuff for graduates got together
2 * 2 startups
One after the other
And both know for intern
And not remind me a lot of love what people are doing about blockchain
Cryptocurrency
Today
It's very similar
And I think if I didn't have that Starbucks.
I probably wouldn't know
I will be
Very interested
Entrepreneurship
Just NASA founder
Better suited as an ambassador
Combining my banking and micro Capital Investments parents
With my appreciation
4 hardest to go to start
How you spell it
So I think if I didn't have died
8 to 10 year experience
Investment
Finance
And as a found
I wouldn't know that busy was the right career for me
But to get into BC I still had to come back to the US
Go to MIT for graduate school
And then join a Bessemer
And it was at Bessemer Tyler Noble
American BC
With appreciation for what would happen
In China so I think I'm very grateful for my ex calling
Forgive me the opportunity
Adding my time in
China
See that
This a market of a bus
About to take off
I made a commitment to my family my wife and I to
Tutu China
And build on my Visa Korea really
In China over the next eight years
18 mm
I think my time at
Dumb
Teeming and also know it
Both were very fortunate
Because the the world for internet users worldwide
Google, Pelion
24 billion
Smartphone
And then
China
Economy really took off
And I made a huge impact on Chinese growth
You know a ton of a star with possum
Back in 2005
So
To get into BC I think one has to have some kind of Consulting with banking background
And ideally some startups.
Management
Experience
So that you have appreciation of
What's a like
Insider startup
What kind of issues. Founders go through
What kind of challenges
Have to overcome
In order to succeed
What kind of lessons
Can we learn from our mistakes that startups inevitably
Will make
We have a sense of pace and rhythm
And I thought appreciation for
Thank you for Consulting analytical skills
New York
My better
Prepare to be a good PC
To what qualities do you look for when you are hiring
People to join the gvt
What I look for
Basically BC's looking for patterns
If you look at number of
Founders
Most startups have succeeded
There is a high correlation
Temperature
And what are they becoming a eunuch
What is Harvard
Or other Ivy Leagues
Versus
Stanford or Berkeley
And the Stanford Berkeley Chihuahua and B.
A pop of the tops
Sports generate most number of a unicorn
BM.
Futon
A university
Indifferent
Cemu
And others
There's a high concentration
So
For VCS
Time to come from one of the top schools that have the network
And exposure
To start up
Welding school
It's become increasingly tough getting to the BC busy
Without having
Prior exposure
2.
New Edition
If you have other language skills
Especially if you come from China
Speak Chinese fluently
And have spent time in China also have some kind of
Banking Consulting background
Plus ideal you some kind of
Exposure to running a startup
Those are all
Recently acquired
To be harmed by one of the top
Bobby Seifer
So the next question is
From two people Richard coward CEO of China emissions as well as
Jacob who described
David the little African American who is moving to China in March
The question is what advice would you give to a foreigner starting a business in China and do you foresee
China being
As attractive as the us as a place to live and work in tap for foreigners
Yeah
Pop the question.
I've heard since I moved
China
Are people coming back
In the time I was
Antenna for 8 years
One more Foreigner
Become interested in
The China model
In China experience
RBC
It's been only you notes GP invested
Alibaba
As early as well come through yet about Edition 270 under $89
And now is a
500 billion dollar market cap company
With information is worth at least another hundred fifty
So when you see companies
Grove. Much
You know something was happening
Fundamentally
In that Society
Internet
And sup
Speaking of such a big impact
To allow this kind of
About equation
So
When you see the conduct
You learn a lot
How to help
Scale over time
And if you have the ability to
Learn quickly
And be willing to help them
That's the best way to create value and we can create value for the founders
You end up creating value for yourself
So if practically speaking if a foreigner wants to move
So China and
Start a company what kind of
Preparations should I make today learn Chinese
Is it that you spoke with any local connection
It is not easy to
About you
On the process
China has caught up
Therefore SF
You need to figure out how to
Something unique
That China doesn't
Experience
If you're hired by a Facebook or a
Google or Amazon
Pick up a lot of product management knowledge
And Engineering skills
Have yuan theater science in
Algorithm
Chinese companies would want
So importantly having that
Harcore CS experience
Or parliamentary experience
Is going to be helpful for you to a body
China
Language skills and you know that
Not having a
Speak my mind
It's not easy
It is important for foreigners
To learn how to speak Chinese
China is this the Talon
Level is so great
In China
There are more than 4.6 million stem graduates a year
There's so many people at work
The basic fundamental skill set
So you don't have something unique
Now to ask you a question whether
Is a China or USA
You got the language scale
I think working China is an absolute must
PSI Chinese models
Have much more
Relevance for emerging markets
In Latin America in Indonesia and India
What is a
Bryson Middle Class loss of organization
High population density improving structure with High-Speed Rail and
And a subway system
So the experience of
China is much more relevant
Much more so than more spread out
Cities in the US
In more advanced
Customer experience
Having that language skills
Having that something special
And then you willing to
Just do it humble and learn a lot
What do someone wonders
I work in China
Not just be successful in China but learn lessons that give him very valuable
For other things.
I would like to argue that having that something special like
Extensive experience of working
In your home country is
Even more valuable than being able to speak Chinese because a lot of people especially Chinese overseas returning these were already bilingual
Chinese in English and they also know
Some Western societies pretty well
So like what is the rationale for hiring
How far to overhang the Chinese overseas returnee like you have to have something that the others don't have
Yeah and also as you know how many companies in China are thinking about going abroad
So
If you will come from him and Market
Chinese companies want to go to what is India or Southeast Asia
Or parts of us
Your knowledge of the local market
As a mainstream user
A product
That understands how local
From China
Overtime will be very bottom
Even for a wedding speak Chinese
Find my URL
If your in the US you need to understand how US market
Misbehave not just in San Francisco New York or
But also how the states
Function how users consumers
And the southwest and the southeast
Are different
The more you understand
Epiphany
Somersby hate the Moor
On the Enterprise side
Knowing how to
Bill product
Help company
He's become more efficient
Better yet get more orders
Becomes very useful
Summit1g Focus career
OT Tech
That's the easiest for you to have
A differentiation in the US
And then eventually go to China
Delphi what you have
Learn
Assuming that
IP protection
To be able to evaluate and do more work
Yeah I dressings at alessa's does no matter what you do just go really deep and do it really well and then you work for
Red-bellied wherever you go
The next question is from Sudan
A software engineer at Google who is considering going back to China to start a car
What made you go to China and what made you come back
Silicon Valley
The question
When I went to China
For me I knew that China is about
To undergrove some kind of changes
As early as 2003
I like the hall the political machine
Handled
Position
And also handled socks
Crisis
So I filled approval Eternal should be stable
At least for next 10 years
For startups do better
Also having taken prison trip to China
This obvious that China needs
Develop more technology
Internally
What are semiconductors
But even more important
There's a chance. Internet
Nashville
Inauthor world
It's very difficult to move it
Expand from City to city or province
Roberts internet
This seems to be a way
Degenerate
National basis
Relative
What wasn't sure back in 2005 for me it was at
Is there a way to monetize all that traffic
The internet
I think. Thank God there is
Alibaba Jack ma now taipei
Which made by business
Possible
Then without a pee noise
I can pay for which one
You can pay for e-commerce
And so.
China
Soupy different
15 / 5
And that's why I decided I'm going to spend the next
10 years my career
In China
Internet space
Nocturnal
Bye 2012-2013
You can tell that
Chinese smartphone penetration is
Is increasing fast
At some point in time
Everybody in China what have a smartphone
So
It is a great Market there's a lot of growth steelhead
But at some point it will reach saturation
Chinese Bismarck
Super useful
For other
Markets in 2011-2012 I saw Alibaba and tencent
Become to make investment in
Lesbian China
I was helping xiaomi
To recruit Hugo Barrett
How to join xiaomi
I'm working with other stomach is active to do so
Income quite interesting to see how
They are similar to
Chinese market
Indian other places
Anoxia xiaomi has International Ice itself very well between 2013
In 2017
So when you see that kind of company I should can go abroad
I started thinking about what is the next 10 years of my life one will be on 2015
And I thought.
For the next 10 years
2015 to 2025
You should be the error for quotation Go Global
. Morton company will go beyond China
And also
Many local Starbucks
Colourpop China
As well so
I know that
If my experience
In China could be applied to other markets
I will do be able to add more value to the ecosystem
Could you more as well
Sow the seed of zhuhai
Okoboji olbia Global BC
It was in my head as early as late 2012
Audi 2013
And I was Fortune
To be able to
Join forces with GDB to build
The next question is from the whole world
Airbnb experiences lead
From Airbnb China
What is the hardest
Decision you've ever made as a investor
I seen a hard decision I ever made was
Going to China in 2005
And then decide to move back in
Talk about it you will just be a Global BC
In 2013
Back in 2005
That you mention I was born in Taiwan
I speak fluent Chinese
But I never live
In China for eczema. Time
I didn't go to college in China
I didn't have a lot of connections
That people grew up with in China
So what value am I going to add
That could be
Helpful to the
Ecosystem that's for me
China
And I realize that
It was my experience
Understanding Japanese history
Alchemist through growth.
Of Korea
Singapore Hong Kong
Taiwan over the 80s and 90s
That's the most valuable tools I can share
What kind of China could be
In an exit in your area
And everything internet
How to get there
So the Hulk
Consumption upgrade new retail
We're twins I foresaw as early as 2015
2005 2006/2007
And I knew that some point
The help
WeChat pay
China 10
Do a lot of stuff
Online offline
In a way that we saw in other Asian countries already
But even bigger
Even better over
So
Having.
Understanding of
How I can add value
I can be helpful to
Founders in China
Give me the confidence.
You know this is not join the war
Tampa 2013 out already
Succeeded in
Don't well in China
Is it really worth risking your career to move to something about a arguably the most competitive market in the world for PCs
To do something completely different
Levees for most people
Mine's, before
That also was a hard decision for me
My kids were young
They could probably benefit from being China for another 6 years
Mandarin chinese better
But I figured I'd for us as a family
To being something about it
What's the fasting
For us to be woke
Build global
Avissi Prosecco
And in Oxford
Could be helpful team in my kiss later
To see how one could be Multicultural
Operating different environments
You have a more Global mindset
So both of them 13
What to do with my career with
La Tapatia
For those of you who have a listen to that
Episode we did with Jenny Lee I'm a highly recommend checking it out because on that episode both Hines and Jenny
Talked about what it was like
For them to move
She tried as a full-time investor without having grown up in Mill in China
That was very instant
These we speak Chinese
We talked about China
Is very easy for everyone assume That We're Men
So how
Well we have done
And how well we build it
Friendships
How about wechat
Support
China something a lot of times
Supposed to
And yet those experience
Help to us to see
If I go to a foreign market Newmarket
How do I be helpful to others
Fathers want to help me
Yeah. Konigsberg on very useful not only in China
Well back in the US
In some Paulo
Inter Carta
Agholor in
Am I bi in
So
It is
Zinc startup
Founders mentality in many ways
Kind of universe
Everyone
No such thing as start up things
He's very lonely you're at midnight
Facing all empty.
And try to figure out what's a plan for
Tomorrow the next month next year and Beyond
It is Well the pressure
So haven't come through startup screen
Myself and I suppose Jenny
We understand how funders think
In that position once
For we know
What to do
They have the Thunders win
If you are helpful to people
Founders Internet space extremely
FaceTime meritocracy
If you are value
And you are willing to help
People want others who want to be helpful to them
If you go on the others with some facts about them
Is very basic human needs
A lot of this is acting that are smarter than the founder
Study can choose and decide
Thanks the basis of Lifestyle business
I think that's the furthest thing from truth
Overtime
The help
OBC
Will be around
Congress are smart and they talk to each other
The next question is from Justin Chon who is the equity investment Analyst at Lloyd George Management in Hong Kong
He says as a young investor I often they can
Mistakes and I try to struggle through and learn from them
I'll be grateful to hear from your experience in dealing with a fill-in Vespa
Or lessons that has shaped you to become a successful venture capital
How did you get through the failure in
How does that
Applies to your process
BC business by nature is a low probability
It's almost like baseball
Inside this is quite a bit of Neurology in baseball
Your
Amazing
In NBC Eva 30% of a company's workout
You are Superstar
And it is a Slowking
Percentage Concept in baseball
Which means I
Each home run
Counts more
Andy
Grand Slam
That brings up four runs to the home base
Come even more
And that's how
You know
If you have to get up unicorns that ends up being
Japan
And so
The things I think every BC need to have mistakes
And skip to the Unicorn
It's very difficult
Walk in and just start picking in
This is such a hard business
The startup
Does being a Founder is very hard to begin with
The chance of success as a Founder is less than 2%
And so
Enough business
Worth
You want to do is sleep
What's the success rate
The odds are against you
So in that situation
In order to
Figure out how to be helpful
Two people
And then learn from mistakes
I think some Investments
The common issues that we faced
Wer
Founders
Did not get along
The level
Little becomes much
Sears
I found this wasn't able to make the pivot as quickly as possible
So you as a VCU part help the founders get better
Had helped him to me but
Go to help them recruit
Somehow Define
Jon Hamm Define partners
Try to help me find buyers
Along the way the more you
The time we spend helping with hunger
The more we learn about what to do or what
Would you come help on the future
One thing I will suggest for both Campisi's 21st
Mo state
Too much money
Do any car
You're much better off
From other people's mistakes
Don't invest too much
But you spend a lot of time with a company to invest
Tecumseh
So that you
Use other people's money
To learn
Butler Natalie
Opportunity
So if it doesn't work out
The Lofts
To the farm or to The Punisher
It's not great
In the process
Without having done that
Bessemer in
Teeming
Had my share of mistakes
But keep operating costs low
And make sure that you know the place at 2
We do put money in
End up making money
Is the way
I survived
The amenity seamless business
Who didn't have the
Right ventricular Leone
And over-committing in the new market
Or new area too soon
And they couldn't recover from them
But the mistakes
To learn how to survive on the battlefield
Is half of
As a follow-up question I think is Avicii there are two major types of mistakes you can make one is
Missing out on a deal the other one is
Making investment
But the company is up as a failure so how do you prevent
Each and which one do you think is
More serious
Different people have different School of thoughts
Missing on a deal
Sounds like a terrible
The Army song
Facebook or I missed out on
Alibaba or Amazon pencil
Json Baidu
It sounds terrible
But it actually
Even if a species
Miss out on love
Cuz there's no more.
So missing on deals
Is not a Muslim
Important
It is important to learn why you miss it
So that you cashed in
Text wife
MI
Career
In China
I want to do but I couldn't
My other colleagues
Sonographer
To do that
Get
You look at the stuff I did too
What is xiaomi you warm up a wall
Or you High Car Rental
Why was I cheating
Or when I meant
HGTV
Airbnb
Poshmark shopping show
Musically you can you name any of them already
I end up doing better and not miss out
As much
After the first
628 years Mike
The hours to Min using
He's coming so missing out stuff early
Is not the end of the world
The key thing
Learn while you listen
How to capture next
Second timer mistakes
That's what I was trying to press in my first question
Which is
Learn the business by now over-committing each. Each of the five deals you do in a funeral prayer
Don't put too much money in
Work with them
MP okay with helping your colleague
I'll Be lyrics
Profolio
The more you learn
About before they manage
The more you know what to avoid when you
Make mistakes
A lot of people see.
ABC business hours
Sourcing and making basket
That is wrong
Wait it's not as difficult
Source deals
Vicks Medical Kit deal for all the time
Is much more to learn after making basket
How to help camp
To scale and overcome their issue
Overtime
If you don't have a company Builder mentality
Peking deals
I think it's very risky
Long run
Hard to do to be a successful
Safest way to become a
Avicii
Is Hive a company Builder mentality
To be willing to help
Profolio
Is Founders milk
Fungus want to pay people
Who care they don't want to be one of your portfolio
I'm asked if I'm a Founder this is everything is to me for my startup
I don't want to go to work BC
I'm just one of his 20 companies
And it doesn't matter which
20 works out well as he was she will win anyway
That is not a good feeling
Thomas
PCS were company builders
Hey Hugo
Your tinsel
Success and attention being synced with a funders will be a lot higher
The next question is from Andrew Jang a product manager at Facebook
What are your thoughts on gen Z in the US versus gen Z in China
And how will this generation ship
Social retail entertainment Etc
How do you recommend
People to study TMZ users in China
To look at new house movie
Republic of Desire
That's not the fantastic movie
And that's alright I going to interview Hall
Next week
The Chelsea users in China affect a lot of pressure
They each have parents
And grandparents
Support
Yeah when I get married. Number * 2
So it is a lot of
Pressure
Overtime
Special living Tier 1 cities
So a lot of users look for it
Escape look for things that can kill time
To get the more hope and we needed help them to
You must figure out a way to
Adjust move out move out to cheer to three cities
So
The Chauncey choosers
A really
Short attention span
They are much more willing to share what they're doing everyday online
Mkconnections online djz users in
Us have some similarity
Half as much
Pressure button
Express himself
The need to get
Instant gratification the need to to
Hopefully not work as hard
Able to enjoy Fame
Good Fortune quickly
Very common in both societies
This was very funny to see those similarities
And overtime I think we'll be making Investments
That could do well in both China and us
With Millennial and gen Z years
Yeah she think increasingly
Generational divide
Between different Generations is even greater than the geographical
Divide
Between the people of the same age but live in different countries
I feel like a lot of their culture and consumption habits are starting to converge based on age
And we seen as a USB
But also across the board
Is as well a lot more similarity
4 people of this
Same h
Across this
Emerging Markets
Big cities ever nice
So the next question is from Kason shoe
Who is the Strategic finance manager at adaro
Loves to GB
Both podcast 96 and found a real talk
The question is what are your thoughts on the enterprise software Market in China will there be equivalence of
Salesforce workday Nestle anytime soon
Usher I think the Condors real talk
It's a
TV podcast hosted by Glenn Solomon
It's an excellent Progress way to buy the interest
Enterprise space
Also is a 32b podcasts Troian a movie
For those who can understand
Chinese
Fantastic job
Talking about startup Inside Story
China I think for
China
As economic growth rate slows down
And ever since I moved back to China
In 2005
Come across great as always
Speed slowing down
China needs to improve efficiency
I'm going to make up for the Lost
Stone Golf Course
So
There will be more need for sauce
For software
The help Desiree efficiencies and Applegate
For many Enterprises
I'm to the cloud
So this is where the US have
A lot of best practice
Chinese classical music and share and learn
So I seen in a long run in China they will be something similar to a Salesforce or similar to a work day
But it'll probably take a bit more time and you have a surf more SMB customers
Olympic Enterprises
Enterprise
Pain
I'm time
Accounts payable office get dropped out
So serving smbt
That you have to order
Therefore they would share their upside with you
It's a
Increase your chance of getting paid sooner and earlier
So we will always looking at
Chaoyang beijing China
Conserva SMB Tech
SMB customers and Enterprises better
I think the consensus is that what
That's slowing down GDP growth and
Rising labor cost
South will definitely
Develop but it's just a matter of
Time when
OHV
Takeoff
So the next question is from
Michael cahoe who is from One Piece work
What do you think will be China's
Internet ecosystems next International
Is Michael Douglas the many Chinese companies are already in Southeast Asia
Alibaba
And inferential
Is affiliate I investors
Asia like tokopedia Pokemon pack
Acquired
Lazada
Tencent investor in C
I was just Karina and shopee
Insult
Many of the TDS investor in grab
And so
Chinese companies already in Southeast Asia
And you look at a top
100 apps
India
Especially the top 20
Many of them almost
The 3rd
If not more are
Somehow China
So more more times, we are definitely
Looking at India
As the next big Market with
Similar population size
Lord gdp per capita in
Having come through experiences with different Chinese models
In cheer wants you to chat with your for cities
Chinese dumplings
These are ready to
Share the experience somehow
In Hindi
I think the best teams that can do that well
End up being
Simon somebody
Who's from China
Amanda cases website
A lot of X Huawei
Senior it manager
Will have living India or latin america or something like that for a long time
But still stay connected what's happening
Space
In China
To end up finding a local partner
Emerging-market
To cooperate
Feel something
Together for the local market
Lamberton China resources experiences
With
No Halo
Of a customer pain points
Miss Emerging Markets
Waiting dots the next Subway formula
For Chinese latest song
Do all these Emerging Markets
Then export Chinese
The next question is from Rose to a communication specialist working with Chinese companies listed in the US
Other than engineering what skill set is most in demand at the companies you invest
In China
It's very obvious he's number one
But increasingly understanding of
For markets
Emerging markets in India and Southwest Asia RSS A+
They got we said earlier
Having a special knowledge
And something what is a customer insights or with
Growth hack Facebook on Instagram
Did you need something
To differentiate yourself
And also the ability to speak English well in Prattville
Are super healthy
Shuffle for nex-5 Foreigner returnees
To be able to evaluate
Chinese camp
The Chinese users
Are increasingly a sophisticated
So how do you communicate
And service
These Chinese users
Gucci Mane a lot
I mean these days JD and Alabama
Deliver
Products to their
Consumers in less than 3 hours
You left it within 5 km
Radius of Hole by 30 minutes
So Chinese users are increasingly
Adam anymore
For Less
So how do you get used to that kind of a speed of
Change speed of iteration
Speed of delivery
Is what every Foreigner expired in
And attorney need to know if you able to adjust to
Do you think that
Marketing and branding is also
Increasing demand because China has always been great
Producing things but less greatest selling
So and
As more and more Chinese domestic brands are starting to
To grow
Do you think
This specific function
Receive a lot of women
Fasting
Building burning China's different building brand in the US
China
Just spending a lot of money
He is not enough
And just come out with the interesting story
Imprint image
It's not enough
As you know it takes a lot of operation
Try not to build a brand
What is xiaomi or haidilao
They both
Very
Experience app
Figuring out how to make the brand cool
A month a lot of
Influencers
Almost a lot of fish oil the heavy key
Users
Whatever it is in China
How to figure out why like why why
With Erica McCoy
You need have ability to Peking
Operation
Of
Ambassadors or volunteers
To incentivize
With the right rapture
For them to help you to build up the brand correctly
So that's something.
Most foreigners don't realize
Someone like a Starbucks or a KFC or McDonald having China long enough
Learn from their previous mistakes
Learn how to localize
Know how do you
To build up a good brand
So
Chinese Wei
With both Western
Brent building know how indeed
Experian
Is absolutely critical
About to succeed
I think go to market in China requires a lot more
Working with the channels
Then in the US
So I in the US we can
I speak of dr2c brazzer director
Consumer button China you literally cannot go direct
The consumer like you have to go through
Timor JDM
Platforms you have to work closely with them
And I feel a lot of the new brands in China as met
Have like dedicated teams that work on tmall just to make sure
They're serving their
Customers well on that specific Channel
I think for most player
That is a good place to get started
But the best player
Kannada
Is depend on
Tmall
Someone like that
I shall me you were
Hadi law or other
Need to be able to
The filter relation
Is the Roxy with a with a
Consumer how do you build your own
Community
So that other people willing to
Speak up for you
Is not easy
I remember 4
In the case of xiaomi
Xiaomi how to show Chico
Some experts
Can paint. They launched
Before they announce the first phone
And I'm not campaign
Beijing
Shut off is 56 phone
That he has ever owned in his entire life
I talked about this
Plus I minus
In many
UI user
They're about a hundred thousand of them
Also participated in
Share their knowledge
Which in turn attracted about 460000 people
To participate
So when I see it
About half a million users talk about what I like about the folks that had
Not like no okay
You can figure out a way to
Being
Pop it to attract people without spending a lot of money on something that I care about
So once you have the
You build a community that's willing to give yours first home
A chance
So how do you get users on on your own in the future is important
But initially leveraging a WeChat leveraging a
Call Bunty mobile
Thank you says alright is
Critical
People do out with a WeChat want to be fingered
So
How do you leverage the papa
What amount of fact
It's something that every small startup
All Uniform Wear
Needs to figure out
In overtime
It would depend on your own ability
And your brand value depreciation
Do PLL something as unique as a body language
Immunity is like theater seats
2.0
The next question is from Tiger Fang
Who is xsober
General manager and now this founder of a startup called cargo which is
Similar to what tribe of Indonesia
There's a lot of talk recently about chuhai entrepreneurs in startups
Copy models from China to emerging market
What are the advantages of Chinese entrepreneurs and Chinese models in places like Indonesia India Latin America versus
Local entrepreneurs and big heavyweights from the US
Call First Wok on Glass Tiger
I think it's a startup
What's this happening well
Yeah that makes a lot of sense
For Indonesia
I think that
The biggest lessons I learned
Back in 2013 what side
China in the span of
Only
10 to 15 years
Rudy leverage Internet to play
Many
National Business
Does it cost money
Suckers for
Home entertainment media
Commerce retail
Gaming
Transportation
Michael Gilligan Sophie
So will you have a
Country.
Leverage internet
Change itself
Fun
2C to 2p
2B 2B 2C
So many different layers are being a
Affected become more
Efficient because of Internet
They are about 300 BC backcountry
Movies from China That's listed
In the US
Another on yourself
How come
All are interrelated
And then the Emoji unicorn
Yeah in the pipeline that's all internet-related as well
So we have all these things to happen
The address Tiffany's from tier one city to cheer for five cities
So all that Biz models of these 500
Many Emerging Markets
I found this, this from Latin America
From Southeast Asia from India
Whatever Publix finally solved their own country
The almost always
Find at least one company in China
New companies West
Something someone
Sure they going to be different
But at the same time
Emerging markets going through a fascist organization
Fast a rising middle class
A lot of problems that people need to solve
Afega Samoa
So it's almost like all those 500 companies in China you can always find something
That will be useful in a local emerging market
And for what tigers doing with a water bottle
Logistics is inefficient
The many drivers
Who are not getting the
Enough
Strike jobs
How to match them
With the right orders
To make them efficient so they can make more money
Beijing time
Pitkin what jobs done
Is a matter of both algorithm in as well as
Anderson local market in order to make a matching possum
The models that China has gone through
UK South Orchard
Becomes quite useful for him
Next question is from Eduardo vasconcelos
Weather Brazilian Stanford grad living in the US and where can a family office
Emerging Market country
Outside of China looks at the Chinese internet ecosystem for inspiration
He or she always has to take China site into
Consideration so that I can adjust expectations
It's about things such as Market size potential
Is upscale etcetera
The question is what are some other unique elements about this Market that you think do not exist in most Emerging Markets
And that I was going to hear from these countries for consider when deciding
Whether Chinese business model platform could work in their country or not
Yes
I don't know I was asked questions
Think
What we always take for granted
And people from outside.
Chinatown garden design inside
The Chinese government historical
I've been quite efficient
How do you say overlap
Last 20 years
To build up an infrastructure
With High-Speed Rail
Subway systems
An internet infrastructure
What makes a possible
For internet business from
PC dust I'll be around
To happen
If the structure is poor it doesn't allow
Fastest rotation of goods
Some people is will be much harder
To build a e-commerce business
In order for Alibaba what is TT maor chitti delivery product
3 hours
In his major cities
With all modern infrastructure of
Transportation is it physically possible
So
I think having a efficient government.
Lie down
Efficient infrastructure
Is extremely critical
And to allow different subnet
The try things with not alot of Regulation
Call me later
It's in second.
It's very easy to shut down
For local government
But you don't allow innovation
Happened what is Spike sharing with scooter sharing and other things
People to try stuff
It's not likely you brought some
In the US
Uber apps did not start
Until 7
Cisco uberX to experiment
And I was 4 years after Uber got started
So
In China
Despite the population the people think that China's government has
RTD and
The quieter you were still allowed
To try sex
So Without Rain
People make fun of
Example mobile
Pandolfo
Data Mountain
Is of assorted bikes
And so forth
Aziz making fun of that
But at the same time without these
Experience the happen
It's very difficult
To come with something something new
So having a government that can lay down infrastructure
I'd be willing to not startups
Experiment are critical for similar models
Was to happen and take off your other
The next question is from Daniel Chen the co-founder of fish up a start of the aims to help people establish and maintain healthy
Hobbit
How do you deal with information overload in the world that's properly
Change it
I love you ask me what's the right sector what
What's a right track
Or tackle issues like how do I adjust to a new country how do I be useful when I go back
All these are very practical tok
Tcole questions
In the vices
Nights before I ask
How do you think how you make
And what a notice is everybody has a different kind of body clock
You need to make a decision after
Imperfect data
Difference for
I think the
Best
If I delete local sports as example
The best
Football player the best stock
2-player the best basketball player baseball player
Baking mix split
The second decision
Extremely quick
You value the value of a quarterback
Because once he has a ball within two seconds you can make Split Decision with for reeds
Who discovered about you
And the build you make decision quickly is
To me almost everything
I noticed all the people take more time to make decisions
And
Usually the qualities
Doesn't improve
With more time pekin
So how do you make
Decision was imperfect about your short. Of time
To me is almost the single most efficient
I'll call you when
Cuz it's summer
For you to succeed from 0 to 100
No matter how smart you are
You might might have maximum number of mistakes
Cuz everybody has any know enough IQ to succeed
Emma Dixon
Martin
Happy WQ
To succeed
As well but at the same time
How do you
Feel comfortable decisions quickly and learn from that
And be able to lift through some of the mistakes that you never broke up before you get the right answer
If you don't make enough mistakes
You cannot get the right answer because if the hypothesis need to be tested before you perfect it
Baby is super smart
Give me something up how to make Christmas
So how do you make decision very quickly I'd love to do them practice
Over 10000 hours
To train yourself to make
Simple decisions officially
So the overtime
If you follow the intuition of how to make
So that overtime dude you're so used to doing that
What pressure comes
You don't get scared
Did you practice for y already
You said with a simple decision first
What opportunity cost is low
Delta. Overtime
It's about time you have to make a big decision
To me I thrive on
I love having
The challenge of bacon
Keep up positions
And I love
Go to bed early
Think about it while sleep
Wake up in the morning when there's no one bother me
I'm sick about those choices again
And when you think hard
What's the point of meditating
For those stuff for 5 hours
Intuitive
It becomes very clear what to do
And this is one aspect of East Asian culture especially Japanese Zen culture
That I like to study
How do you be so calm
And so focused
And block out everything else
To be able to make that split-second decision
And this is why I love watching
Sports
Seahawks key players
When championship
In the most critical man that I'm with him the socks no second left on the clock
How do you so calmly
And nail. Shot to win the game
What hits a baseball hit
To get the Scorpion
Those are the most fun things in life
And if you train yourself
Since College
How to do that well
But I'm usually the certain age
You're naturally know what to do because it becomes second nature
A practical level what are some life
Hacks you used to make sure you consume a vast amount of
Give me the give very
Doctor is as well because you were consumed a lot of information every day and
There's a lot of news out there with how to decide what's worth your time and what's not
For me is I have a develop a sense
Of what is important when
So that I can say hey
2 high back in 2013 what's the train
Remember debating with people
He was at why doesn't make sense
So you asked me how do I know to height is it back in 2013
Just ate entire Chinese bacon
Because either you have that sense
Or you don't
Only if you keep on trying it
You get a write more off of that.
Beautiful but intuitive feel
So I am not good at giving very practical advice
Is based on principles and Eufaula
You pick cotton
Better at
I figured out what it is and is very personal far for everyone
When I first came back to you as soon as we see but if people say you have that work in the US for over 10 years
You're not a woman shop
You don't even know all the Bratz
How do you know you picking the right company
For me it's just if you start the
Societal trends
You know
What should happen
When I first came by
Falafel think that beat Amazon you had to be in a highly differentiated
High margin
Hybrid value
Be got to be loved by you
Broadway
San Francisco LA and so forth
And I disagree I said
Describe the mass markets
I know in China that work
Galaxy users in the us as well
Janus contrarian point of view if you ask me how do I know
It's a matter of understanding what is the landscape
Figure out with a competition is weak
We're figure out where there is underserved Amman
And be able to capitalize up quickly fashion out a people do
So the ability to make decision quickly is play something real
What's going on
Who's winning who's losing who's strong who's not
Where's the opportunity where is the pain pill that starts off yet
Nfocus on it
With the waste to
Make it
More easily accessible
For people who are underserved
So you apply that principle you can find Opportunities anywhere
The next question is from Lawrence clock a business development leader at NBA
Are there instances of new tech entrepreneurs that don't know how to code
Becoming successful in China
Wow
If you're not a p.m.
The most successful
Founding China who's not a colder is obviously Jack Ma
Can you please tell me a joke about today
Becky says alright if someone has an uncanny ability
To build a brand
As a Superuser is super consumer
As someone who is just like love near retail and therefore knows
What is still missing
A lot of Chinese go to Japan Dubai
You know tortoises
He's the one you're behind
Yeah that's amazing
Buy the toothbrush from Japan these brushes are better than American brush to stay
Stop your teeth
We rush
That song is this
Stop products out there
Who just defy the odds
Bacon consumer happy
You don't need ability
To the cold and you just
Not have a sense of what users still want
Add people to
Book with designers
Decide acronym product
They can still be successful
There's still a chance to be the next OC job
In the consumer
Consumption
Yeah I would say that your fear want to be in the entire sector like
You don't have to know how to code but you need to be able to attract
People who are really good at coding
To join you
Because that's like a required aspect of
Doing a startup
Easiest way to
Accrue
Enjoy you
Is he have a busy night
Articulate very clearly
So people gravitate yeah
That's the future
And you know where you going
I'm willing to help you.
The last
Question
I want to post Versace my favorite question from the list
Altaf MD who Airbnb experience manager
From Airbnb China
What motivates you to work at ggb everyday also wondering
Sometimes because you're the most hardworking person I've ever seen and
A lot of people who are in your position with
I didn't need to work so
Mexicali is also laughing
I think that
405 years old
The stories I read that stick in my mind
Worthy's
Either sports figures
Or historical figure
Define
They were on the Martin on the French
But it's up either
Winning it all
With build a team
With all the comradery
To weather together what is winning the championship or
To establish a new title
Christian new Empire
And is *
Journey
Meeting at together
That's extremely gratified
Inspiration
And no matter how tough it is they always find a way to make it work
Is so part of me feel that
I am very fortunate
Reliving your aware number of the neighbors are screwed from a billion 2.5 billion for being on a smartphone
And yet
When I go to Emerging Markets or other places
You mean the US
There places where Tech has to make as much
Positive impact
In
There's a lot of Stewart Title
About how Chinese
The founders or
Chinese feces are
And I just feel that
If we can show
Died being a Global BC or Global founder
You can do a lot more good for
Society
Against all the other Arts
Are people thinking.
It's too complicated you don't need it
Giuseppe happy
C4yourself
You work to live not live to work
I don't like those kind of contrast in those kind of
Darryl Dawkins
I feel that the ability to show it is a different
Way to make impact
To experience life
By making big change
A show.
This is Pop
Because I lost
Is extremely gratifying and satisfying to me
And I hope that my colleagues
Who work long hours
And that work smart at the same time
Work hard and work smart
Field.
There
Doing something
Useful and they bleed
They share the body
This mission to
So is that that's all the questions we have for today and
Thanks to everyone who participated and
We're going to do more of
This kind of interactive sessions in the future so if you have them please join are we try groups or slack Channel and then is 6.
Abc.com
Thanks for letting
Thank you all for your quest
Dell very good
Hu7989
996 Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Play in Beijing in partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo
What's 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across through tampons ggv invests in consumer news
Retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Dollars
Pergola companies include
Airbnb Alibaba
C trip Didi chuxing demo hashicorp Hello by cows keep
Black Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc.
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as lot Channel where we regular share inside
Events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 9 96.3
Gbc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com