Hi there
Welcome to the 9s
Brought to you
Virginia Beach
Co-produced
On the show
We interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
That's was Tech leaders
Weather us
China
My name is Khan song
I'm a manager
Partner at YouTube
And I've been
Start up
Investing in them
In both in US
A China
My name is Sarah Jeong
I meant investment analyst
Ggv capital
Jennifer Moore journalist
Why is the show called 90
Lasix schedule
Chinese founder
Organically adopt
That is
9 a.m. to 9 p.m.
PlayStation
To us
Drive
10 speed
Of Chinese
Many
I'm moving fast
Today we're joined
One of the world
Top expert
An evangelist
AI
Fish intelligence
And
He was a chief Scientist by Baidu
Company XIV
Turkish March
Baidu
Compounded Coursera
B12
I'm 2011-2012
She worked at Google
Where he co-founded
Google bring
Deep learning
Before that
Professor
Where magazine describe Andrew as someone
Who spread the gospel
Thank you and
Will be here with us
Thanks for having me
Let's talk about what are you up to
Custom discussion
About what
What's your latest
Since you left baidu
Can you share with us
What excite you
Good morning is this the idea of building an AI Paula Society I think that AI technology has
Has advanced enough that we see a relatively clear part 2
Making self-driving cars a reality for everyone maybe someday
Giving every child a precise Tutera
Maybe also giving everyone
High-quality low-cost access to healthcare
They radiating every segment of society every major industry will be transformed by a over the neck
Decade
And I think that's all
No one company not even as the Logitech comfort you can do all the work what's up
Let a ibus in all the ways it can be to prove human life
So
I recently announced one of things I'm doing is announcing a new set of courses on Coursera on teeth learning
They try to train out maybe the millions of people me the millions of your listeners.
Neat that could benefit from learning PCI to so use the most creative ways that
I myself would never have prenup
You recently started a project called Deep learning. AI
Could you show us more about what that's about and how that
Effort has been going
Sophie funny.
Treating this new educational content review courses on deep learning
Hosted on Coursera
Oh and I hope will help
Educate puffy millions of people
What's the latest deep learning to so that they can go and invent all the wonderful things
That I can can be invented with deep learning
Cuz you'll be more of it
To see model or two model who
The audience
What US
Yep today we have learned his individual learning is coming to call Sarah to take quizzes on deep learning
And also
Are there also over 500
Companies and governments working directly with Coursera
They tried to educate that were forces or the citizens of these different countries
So I think that's a cool star has been a great
Educational to
To reach lots of individuals as well as
Companies and governments
So Andrew given that your last work at a Chinese checker
I wonder how China figures in your vision for AI
Especially now that we're seeing a lot more research and experts coming out of town
Are you seeing an increase in
Interest from China in your courses and your project
If special the newly-announced government fight in China on a I didn't reason they are in China has always been
I think it's even harder in the last few months
So I planted grass with netezza in Chinese
Supposed a lot of our educational content on their website in China to make it more easy accessible
But I think the China
Ecosystem is just incredible
Globally the two top incentives of innovation for here today are Silicon Valley in Beijing
The office Silicon Valley in Beijing I think
You know calendar London a few other places maybe New York also very good
Not yet seen any other senses with the intensity and Italian than the rapid loss to you
Silicon Valley in Beijing
So we see on Twitter you ask
Recruiting
Osaka
So far and where they
Where the Talent come from
You know since announcing deep learning AI I was surprised at the number of people
Contacted us even before we posted any job positions to try to volunteer or work with us if you're as ways
What building of a team Volta
Help with
Something for doing what you think is what was some new projects that we haven't announced yet
So I hope that's what you've learned. Yeah you can train out many people
That will do wonderful things that maybe someday someone in a village will figure out how to use machine learning to optimize
What's a supplier
Help nature locally and improve
I need water. That's great
There's some AR vertical applications I'm excited about this well so we just
Building a team took off to some of those things now have you seen a lot of applicants coming from
I'm tryna and a lot of Chinese students
For your online courses
Yeah right I'm seeing a lot of interest definitely in the US and in China
Tell work if I said to proceed you say off utilities
I think they I frankly is global almost see a lot of interest in sleeping Valley everything also a lot of interest in India
And if you end of the road
The recent rise of deep learning the recent rise of AI technology
Gives everyone a chance to build
The next generation of companies
One of the things I learned in washing the rise of the internet
Is maybe 20-25 years ago
Was that if you take a shopping mall and go to website for it that does not turn the shopping mall into an internet company
What makes a Trudy internet company is not just where I want you run their website is much deeper than that is what are not
YouTube pervasive a b testing whether or not you're short animation times I should probably everyday route 261
With the rise of a I think that was starting where all sides to figure out what is it that you need to find an AI company how do you unlock
Take your company
Tavares AI capabilities
And I think this gives yeah Rich opportunities both to incompetence as well as such as Google and Baidu
Transform themselves into AI companies
As with a lot of opportunities for
New cities and countries and you companies to arise W maybe the future of eating a organization
He was still in the early days of this exciting wave of the Dollar Man
What are you say
For the first class
You're offering
Michael Cera
You put it all last week
That was over a thousand people
Sign up
The first
24-hours already
Oh that's why on campus Santa Claus
Staz over thousand people of the closer cause this much larger than a thousand what's the number now
Yoda first machine learning course that offer Uncle Sarah had / 1.8 million in Romans so
OverWatch.
Over the last several years have lost five
Interest in the number of people were bringing into the Machinery community
When you look at these
Should have inbound interest
Is the
Have you ever done any analysis
Breakdown by Jack
Graffiti words coming from
Willows Global Buy
How is a concentrator on the
Countries or
So I think the majority of learning machine learning a lot of them come from
The US China India
I'm also a lot from the UK
And I think a lot from Germany as one of her correctly
Is really quite Global Pets
The top three
In the area of a startup
Have you seen
Or through your source to network
Here
The type of a startup
LARPing fun
Today or B
You started
What's kebab
In the end
Nexiq
You know I'm excited about a ice application into a lot of different vertical Industries
So couple Industries assessment
I looking at include Healthcare
Education
That's up to you seen a lot of Industries Destra CIT Revolution
Digitization Revolution
And that Trace data Western enables the AI Revolution to come in and eat today's entry in value
Soap
Maybe 10 years ago in the law of energy say Healthcare
Aulani activities was recorded on a piece of paper that might be found in some filing cabinet
Ohio
That the overtime
Thanks the rise of electronic medical records
Globally
Now is that piece of paper floating around in
I like how it is all very well and all that is now stored in databases is much with digital
I just burped opportunities for AI to come in and learn from down and make predictions entry value
And just as I am
Long time ago your ex
Would have been a physical piece of film today is much more likely to be Digital Image as of the digitization
Healthcare
Creates a lot of opportunities for learning algorithms for AI
And I think the education as well
You know 10 years ago
A lot of sage University education what the professor saying a bunch of warts
The Aether Wildest Dream the students brain
For the most part no digital trace of that
The things the rise of online education such as cerebral
There's not much more Digital Data about what was previously unlock activities in the your student's grade
I want to see species of paper floating all around the world but now some fraction of that
Standard digital realm and now does it take to record
What students are the Whispers questions directly and indirectly
And all that data
Means that
AI now much more than several years ago can I come in to understand the patterns of student Behavior who's there
How to really help students ID both of these examples of Industries
Weather it Revolution
Is well underway and disc
Tri-City Theatre
For the AI Revolution
To also gain momentum
I get there
Data has been created in
What's needed to
Make the
AR Revolution
Impossible
But
Do you see
Startups
Take advantage of that or is more bigger
Zico Baidu
Or Google
Healthcare
Service provider you have a lot of data
Cartoon Network
So you only share that data
With someone
Do you see that
Big companies have a vent
It's over song
In space
Houston startups
Do something different
You know I think that date are is very vertical eyes so
One thing that makes the launch web search engine businesses defensible is they have a theater acid
The tells you if you searching a certain term you're more likely to click on this URL rather than that URL
It's raining so even though you know I thought
Phenomenal
Good sense of how websites technology work
Access to that data I said I would have no idea how to lead a small team to build something competitive but having
Said that I all the web search quickdata is asking you question about whether or not useful
But some other business example
How is website to pick dates are useful for reading x-ray Radiology Imaging useful
For that and so I think that
In other vertical applications where there isn't already a big incumbent
The dominating the market
I think that
Vacations where
Small team beautiful scrappiness which is hard work and sweat Zora or if you punish it's cuz straight to get in a day
Data to start giving momentum
So Andrew Gillum that were in the business of venture capital
I'm wondering if you were a VC investor
AI startups
What were the qualities that you look for it
And what will get you excited about AI starter
What will get you excited
Two one two
At work with a stye
Ndny don't know the starter is going to work is a judgement decision that takes into
Solazzo things
Ranging from
Yeah
Maybe one thing I've used to
I used to tell all of my team's is dad in GNR bosses the customer
Right now y'all set bosses I should not to see you
That's fine to co suzushi much easier than size find a customer and is not one customer over these
Millions or hundreds of millions of people that will go with that feat why don't know what to use your product tray
So Indian I think my bosses since it is usually either
The customer
Santa is a very complex piece of judgment I guess
What are not you the right team that I brought out the technology YouTube channel
Serve the customer in a way that makes sense
Emory
Who yesterday
I heart I hear you speak about
3 years ago
On the different path
How to do machine learning
Deep learning is only one of them
Deep learning
Is cashing a lot of
The wave today
Is the right usage of the R&D dollars going into the area
And you how does an imp
Other
Pass that machine learning
I think that AI technology has many components including
Deep learning albums audio Network
I should love a different
It's a lot of stuff to spend of AI
Having said that I think the thing doesn't dance moves
Rapidly recently is
Given to large part by the rise of dates are the rise of computational power igp compute
You think it also
Innovation
Now because deep learning has advanced so rapidly in the Lost
TSA
This tree is very rich opportunity set this is a lot of stuff can now do if you running late
Speech recognition interactive face recognition
That that that we just didn't know how to do two years ago
Today computers can look at pictures and figure out what's in the picture much better than ever before.
Recognizing faces recognizing animals figure out whether the objects in the picture
Videos
So what does that tree value
I think speech recognition is working for more activity than ever before this is what enables
Product to Amazon Alexa and by Tuesday Heroes Google's OK Google and so on
So you skates is a speech to be invented
To get that
Pakistan to look at
I think that's computers are starting to
Read medical record
The patent is
What if you have a large amount of data typically has labeled data
Then Tiffany out of us letting us
Make predictions or recognize the types of dates are labeled data
NFL football today
Work to be done
Define decree to business use cases if it has into the appropriate business or appropriate
Prada contact
So I think
Not a reason the excitement so much excitement since his auntie because this is the piece of the eye
The most rapidly in the last couple years
Rapid progress
Teresa rich
Set of opportunities.
Keto friendly no one know very few people are trying to tap yet
Incontro siding other pieces of AI technology into some of the bugs were it so you don't need to understand what you saying is like
Light knowledge of sanitation in signing autographs from all those other tooth
I find him useful in a variety of projects yet
But they haven't gone through this step change the way that deep learning has the most couple years so
Even though their option is there
Maybe the set of untapped opportunities there
Might not be as
Why Jesse said upon top of trinities in April by the news
Recently there have been reports of
Potential security issues around AI so there was a
The study that found that voice control assist
Potentially be hijacked by ultrasound commands a human cannot hear
Are you worried about the security issues at all
Fortunately there are many deep learning research is aware of the security issues and so this time around
A lot of us are developing the
Deep learning algorithms together I worth keeping in mind the security of vacation so I think
As we are trust face recognition systems more and more
Researches daroff
Stephanie working on defenses against the attacks other than passing paper
Other than Carnegie Mellon University they showed that
If you wear a certain
Turkish
Shell pattern glasses
Sitka spruce
A face recognition system into thinking your IQ someone else
But fortunately
We've seen enough
Computer security that there now
Hershey top
Computer security researchers and talk utility researchers working together
They try to address these
I would say the solution. Definitely not
Fully developed
We actually don't know what that Solutions are but it's enough research attention on this I feel pretty good about the fall for it
I like to know I remember 2016
When
Deepmind
A contest on
Go play golf against the top player from South Korea
I was five matches
Before the first one
Happen
Most people
Especially in China
Stop. There's no emotion
What what what did you say
Before the first match
And we were surprised at all by
Yeah
The results
I think deep mine has had amazing breakthroughs and getting computers to play games ranging from their work on a tie
Paris
To all the various games I think they've done
Fantastic job show me the results of the morning is really good at playing video games that's what's playing games like go
So you can take that to this
You know in terms of
Michigan urology
I'm really excited by
The work done by a few groups at University of California Berkeley
Elsewhere
Are the pine decide to technology to robotics. Say I personally do not work on
Having computers play video games
But I think that one of those exciting applications of this type of Technology
Is using it
To control robots much better than ever before
Very impressed by some of the work they originated all of UC Berkeley
Peter of yuan circular beans research groups
B16.
Using robotics
Have you seen that kind of
Study or
Efforts elsewhere in other labs
Think that's one more research groups around the world I guess I'll talk to you before selenium for
Temperatures in Canada Acceptance in Germany a few groups in the US
Also a few large corporations are not doing that
Maybe a lot
Fundamental breakthroughs I felt
Took place in Berkeley but it definitely becoming more pop
In terms of applications these technology
Equis are you there a few people Staffing where I can order
I think it's really become quite
Photos were up here I think I still have a seditionist antiviral adjunct faculty
Distanta remains
Has always been there remains one of the top centers of AI technology
And I think I'm
Well pretty multiple universities in Alpha corporate Labs have had a huge impact
Running
Yeah if I hadn't been doing
Tell the world that I was in awe Fitness contract there's no way I would have started an ethical brand Chief right now
SRI dosa
Cardinals here at the top of the statue
So this fortunate struct
Huge application of AIS in self-driving cars
Within the self-driving car ecosystem what do you think are some of the holes in terms of
Arizona people have not devoted enough research or energy to
You know so I guess I'm on the boulder Dr. And then Jenny reusable Dozer varicella
Sylvester in it
I think Dr. Eliezer very exciting, thiruvalla potential
I think that's a
Vehicles will become a reality price sooner than those people think that it's not something to worry about either because
Do you think people will also adapt to it faster than most people currently think they would.
So that's one piece of
The AI future
Excited about
Yeah I remember when I was at undergrad students I started to see
Videos of autonomous driving work
Done to add some Congee Mellon University and then
Over the years by Alta preferably was Stanford's participation in Urban Cowboy
Duffy grandchild inside small
Sebastian thrun Stanford
I think that
Technology timing is important in hindsight I think 10 years ago
Around the Time of the Doctor challenges
Surrounding ecosystem of Technology just wasn't ready to support
Trudy safe and skate of autonomous driving but I think it's only in the last couple years did I fear the technology
Pasta making this not just them aware but making this girl is exactly much clearer now than ever
I think most of it was given
A Rise Above
I know that's extend the availability of stanza
Running
Google's offices
It's been a lot of money investing
This area
And we will probably
Bigger and bigger
You think that is still
All opportunity left
Nu startup
How to do that
Purina USA
I think that dry. AR has a lot of very promising Technologies and approaches
They might be enough room for others in addition to dry the iFit will see
You know I want to see you so dry
Sound Advice
Ready made by students and also my spouse
Self help them out a bit one of they need me there
The tower tarot Simply Amazing
I hate you
Yeah Ameritas 145 is that I have to do anything
That would verify
I think that I helped them out here when dating
Phenomenal Talent up and down so I think they
This is a great thing and also
Did you see opportunities
Worldwide
Beyonce us mark
For sure
That's you travel around the world
Where are the some of the other mark
You see progress so Innovations be made
In autonomous driving
Yeah yeah because we actually have
Foundations of specific government that makes it okay for me to needs to see governments bed
I think that regulations will play it
Throw in the risers on the driving and
Government I think that
Some governments are moving faster than us and the countries that are able to
Get the right regulations in place will will have a nontrivial guyses run epic advantage
The rise of Silas driving
Do you have any advice for US government
Any level with a state-level or Miss
Decibel level
Ocr national level 2
To do more
It sounds like
Innovations
Are happening
Morro Bay
Ecosystem
Nitrous on the starter
An ecosystem evolve government increased
Yeah you know I think we do a lot of smart people on US government
I think that
That's covered your stomach move even faster
Maybe I just ate a lot of governments that there is level since United States as well as internationally have you started
Drive AI so maybe I'll just leave it at that
So would you advise startups in this area to work with big companies or compete against
Yo I think the question is whether or not it's a complex
Strategic calculation for any startup I think that
The great opportunities for startups to go to The Pretender also sometimes wear
Haunting of a large company you could enable a large the smallest on South
To go much faster
So I think it really depends on the details
October 8th
Harley Quinn
What up becomes a doing
Google what's that weigh more than Earth
Weather
Sort of open
Project
When you look at
Different
Big companies trying to do this
Somewhere building
I can get on their own
Somewhere walking with
Do you see one system
Better
The other foot
Yeah it's early days I think I didn't know we were always do the few years and see how the competition plays out so abusive
Let's talk about China
You were born in the UK
And then you move
Hong Kong and Singapore
He came to the US
And you
Baidu
When you look at its what
Kind of innovation
Happening in Asia
Homicide
Impact yourself
Career decisions
Kind of things that your
Working on these days
Haitian background
You know the China
I called a China internet
Community ecosystem
Is almost a totally different world than the US / Global Internet ecosystem
And so I find it really important I find it
Very helpful tips
See what's happening in both ecosystems and to learn from.
System self
I didn't today
One more people realize that a lot of products invented in the US that then later go to China as
Buy Sakura sarada mother idea is that first take off in China
And then your own you only quite a bit later
Make its way over the us so I think that
Beetles that are able to
Really monitor both ecosystems and learn from both
I will just learn faster and see the best ideas much sooner
Within the fear of AI would you think are some areas in which the u.s. is ahead of China and what are some areas where
Where China has a surprisingly over the US
I need the historic for you as well as today did you as husband
Ahead of China in terms of basic Alfred make Innovation cyclical Alta
You know
Detailed very important technology
Conventions I see more of those invented
In the US and China are there China
Really impressed by something
Technology inventions in computer vision for example in China
Dulce out of the big companies or government lab or university lab
What word do you see those
Basic Technology Innovation
Happening in
I think that didn't
China a lot of stuff
Basic research
Is done by the large corporations in also
Some of the universities are doing a pretty good job
Somehow I feel like there are more
Startups in the US that feel a R&D labs and fewest on sales in China if you like basic research
Essential Innovations but maybe
I was I was thinking
Assume right
A lot of innovation
I'm just a few big companies
The capital to pay for the laundry social organizations but some of them nice job
Also want that also more and more
Huawei Maybe
Alibaba and tencent
I feel like Baidu. They are in China
The other companies are definitely working on it
Is taking off
Because China is a society move so quickly
I feel like consumer products seem to have the ability to just go from zero to a hundred much faster in China
The US
And a lot of reasons for this I guess for us to maybe a peanut
Societies of their field market segments have to fight for one of the times you think the US is like a hundred more
Ticket adoption are proud of you to fight one of the time for the
Adoption rules China
You know
Maybe has
700 Moccasin Road I'm on making all of these numbers up
And so things seem able to drop faster in China
Did I see that new products in your business model sometimes take off faster
China and the fact that China is
Motor mobile for society ready for all the people in China
The cell phone was the first competition device rather than in the US would we most of us use a laptop order
Stop cell phone
So that also enables mobile products to take off pretty quickly
So I think is really valuable to you
I want some of the trends in China because
Some of them not not all of them some of the things you see it having China
Might be a Harbinger might be early signal of what might happen in the USA dress well
So the trends that you just mentioned
Sounds like
Large population
I wonder if these also give rise to a lot of lotion
And after China goes
Houses for sale
Adoption
How can I go beyond that and
And actually the world at Universal
I feel like in terms of
AI Power Products this is low-hanging fruit all over the place all. Jones con
Walk around without stumbling on all this
Fruit that's not even though hangers already fall asleep
Resume examples
I mentioned how can education is 240 Kohl's Longmont use a lot of work to do these Health Care
College education products
But he was very clear that
Are there off Healthcare and educational experiences that we could deliver our they just were not possible 2 years ago
Cuz none of us knowing that the technology
Hannity today
You know what the number of great opportunities still vastly exceeds the number of teams that qualified to pursue these off of
I think he has a v a i and business skills
This has many opportunities they could go out there or did I don't think
Yeah. That might not see any competition at least for some time because it just isn't that much a i Talent around
So you work at both Google and
Baidu how do you compare and contrast
National culture
Approach to work and
Hubba hubba 2
Innovate
I think both countries I think both Google and Baidu are gray is very difficult to
I'm headed to because
Ottavio hefei
Very different products very different Samsung 11 also very different products very different
Comfy couches that operate in different countries
I love the super high quality engineering both companies
Just a wonderful keep I got that work with Echo companies
There's one thing I like especially about China which is just a speed of decision-making I feel like
Y'all teams at Baidu
Mount satellite about 1300
He is more like a very small us. Up so so that's one thing that
I think the China internet ecosystem is very good at dissipates a competition is so fast
They tries teams to naturally make decisions very fast as well
Large and small companies in the US
He's like
The pace of decision-making is a bit
Is it not as aggressive and that this pros and cons right when you can take a bit more time to make decision
Maybe the decisions are slightly high quality
And also you know
How is your lifestyle different
When you were at baijiu versus
We work much longer hours
The Bible
I think I pressed seaworth long always pretty much all my life going back to when I was a student so
I don't know that that's very different than the gain in in in in China
Chinese internet companies not just by due to global yalgaar are famous for
Yeah people working very hard
Open 6 days a week
Best auto de PR against massage
You saw you know
I think that
So far a lot of excitement about ARS focus on their tech companies like Google and Baidu
They had a very high technology base to build on and so it was a lot of t-top
And so this is why I do have some of the most phenomenal
Having said that I think about it coming and Padme I will be in other Industries as well
I've even sad if the ultimate impact of AI
What a I need to do
Let's go transform Healthcare LOL Veigar counter medication
Construction and then really all those other industry there are specific non-tech companies in AI that you're excited
Yeah I think I see a lot of starters emerging entering different business verticals
Shenzhen large companies
Set of data that can make the best user
You know I don't know
I think
Other companies really worth more
Digital assets even not
Traditionally considered tech companies
If you have lost data asset
Desperado the accountant Yaki
Piano dolly for Euro fintech
Cody has been adopting a tie
Very rapidly repeat the industry sectors that competes with the data ass
Best position to do this
Yeah we're going to study
A while ago
Comparing the top 10
The market cap
Most valuable
Star listed around the world
10 years ago
Containers to go you have a lot more
Traditional economy.
And the banks
Telecom carriers
Ended
Gospel today
Top 10
7R
Tukwila
Taco riendo
And I was 17
The question to be interesting
Will the next 10 years
How many of these
Industrial offline
Dichotomy company
Culebra jie
Other
T2 mount
The comeback
I'm a lot more fish
Or nah
What are the interesting things that happened in Tech watches in AI is
In the tech world all of us I used to needing to learn new things every 3 years already
Is new technologies invented all the times that we went through
The internet error
Set up to Cloud to mobile and now they are
That's all of it that used to the ground shifting under our feet every 5 years in that I'm using to ship
What's happened in the Lost decade is
Now Tech has infective pretty much every major industry
Guess I'm so Aztec continues to shift every 5 years now everyone needs to ship every 5 years
So the tech World we're kind of used to that we're accustomed to this way of life
I think the other Industries because the pace of change is not driven by this
Say 5 year cycle that Tech has they will need to get used to the pace of change as well
Is Weber is data replace
Oil and credit
Commodity
And how you test data
Determined
How much in a week
Decrease
Yeah yes and then and also you can throw their which is that when you have someone invent said mobile
What's happening cast 10 years ago the iPhone order when someone invents Technologies
Now these fundamental shifts in the tech landscape because all these other industries that using tag
So when the root went went in with a basis of competition always your building a big business
Changes every 5 years then you need a new way of operating
This is one of the
Exit already check-in affecting these other Industries move.
These other Industries also need to change every few years girls exciting times
Football is one of the interesting example is Domino
That they were the
Most
A forward thinker
Adoption of
Internet and mobile
Incognito
Christian behr
Revenue growth and their stock price grow
Everlast
13 years
Parvo
Is a mind-boggling
See how it
Traditional economy company
That
Willing to adopt technology
Straight
Denon
I think these things to move people's market caps
Missouri Credit
You obviously care a lot about you
Jack Ma
Said recently that we
T chart kiss
Computers cannot
I'll do better
One thing about AI is up
Because it moves so fast
When you train someone on a i
Maybe the skills to learn this year will become upset
Sweet in 3D
So how would you advise young people
How to equip in South
In a long time
And how should we approach a
Age of AI
You know I think
Was it
I think that the most valuable skill in the future might be the ability to keep learning because
I took 4 as I think that's a i displacing jobs would be significant but then it may also be someone over Heights OH
Typical us are poison ivy is maybe in the next 20 years
30% of jobs in the US are at risk of Automation and that sounds really scary like 30% how
But the flip side of that is maybe as many as 70% of all your also known as
Slept displacement in the back
We can't find enough people to do it all those jobs we can't find enough
Teachers we can't find enough
Healthcare workers
For some reason we also and we also can't find enough wind turbine technician
So they're Long Beach jobs that
We just can't find enough people to
To do so is much more of a re-skilling retraining issue
Then Humanity has no work left to do kind of problem
He said that
Now that Tech has infected all these other Industries I think that most other Industries weather Industries
Does Pikachu's that you need to learn something new every few years
Technology your business is built on continues to change every few years
Looking back
How did you
Discover
That way I was going to be
Big
Major
Play a role in your life
Tell people outside a I feel like it's Sunday to call
Writing a loss
He is loving
I'm is an EIN cider I feel like they are has been making steady progress exponentially
Real talk about red
The steady progress giraffe is you're up for the Lost movie 20 years and
The thing is
Decide.
I have something to say
Very interesting
Decide to do a skin burn
Semper
I was a freshman
Freshman year in college inside
Hey I want to spin around for a while
I wish I wasn't smart enough
Said I was the one
How did you recognize.
When was living in Singapore my father
Eye doctor
Wava
Was looking into doing a eyewear for automated diagnosis from him
The other Define easier than my career was way back in Singapore
I wanted an internship where I just remembered having to do a lot of photocopying
And
I was definitely
You thinking G it only we could also be at all this photocopying or three maybe I can spend my time doing some
And then when it's not to understand that way I can help us ultimately all the things we did not know that
Want to make a fool then I wont.
Apus
Korean AI pretty much all of my most of my professional life
Moved
Too many places growing up
Would you think we're some of
Challenging
Things about going to new environments especially the move
To the US
So I moved to the US
Start Amy carnegie mellon University in Pittsburgh
When I came here when I was wet every 17 years old
I got time I should probably return to Singapore night when I got my bachelor's degree oven the ResCare does a seven-year-old at that time again
You know my worth to the US was going to be for like quite fine oh yeah
I don't know I think
I really enjoy and I think
People really benefit from seeing multiple organizations red Android
Same time, you better in MIT and groupie and stab fat and gain to see a few different companies
You notice so much knowledge that's treated in the US and so much notice is treated in China
And most people underestimate how much there is in the other community
Although I don't know I think
I don't know maybe that's not totally true ID
People in China enough people in China Rita
What's going on in the US
Vice versa
Still I think
Which of these ecosystems has so much to learn from the other is this the sissies underestimate about different energy to both of them
So I've always been to
Would you enjoy being the most
And what kind of food do you like
I like whatever
Yeah yeah
Yeah I don't even know I feel lost
Now I feel nothing of her food and then now you don't remind my my wife and I we both either all sushi
Pictures of August
What point did you decide that you want to stay in the US
And pursue a career
Sure is that a
PhD and then there are the great us universities
Umit and then Andrew from my advisor Michael Jordan their broccoli and then
After that I thought you know
Tiana position to stand that was that was a great place so I keep on working on and trying to advance a high so I warmed up
Sticking around
Do you see that at different universities.
To Coast
Approach to Innovation or
Encouraging
Startups
Stevia versus very special place I feel like them
If you want to
The fashion industry
If you want to break into film business
And if you want to work in Tech
Does that one place is much better than all the others in the US
Citing Stanford University is in a very special place and
Maybe I json example
Many years ago my students started working on GPU Computing forthethrone are very early reading fluency
Lava Tubes.
Use gpus off a TV running
The reason we want that we are writing a paper I don't think that clever
We had friends in the video right now
And we're just lucky that the right friends and share the right signals and so we said hey let's let's let's do some research on GPU
Computer running
And if we had been living somewhere else other than Silicon Valley I know it whenever I want to
Yeah we would have seen it that early and then they able to do the work to help me through until community
Atenolol examples Italian
Speaking of the right friends who are some people you think
Really helped or mentor to you throughout your career or
You worked I enjoyed working with or
So-called the rightful
Flights
I think by your honesty is too many to the way my mother is afraid of naming if you feed rabbits
But I didn't really fortunate
Dementors was an undergrad
Tanger Mall Michael Corinthos Michael Jordan
Sterisil
And then and then it started all of the Snapchat CS faculty were great I don't even want but they're all trades
And then don't have Coursera
Square a fantastic
Like I'm a video competitors I won't even send for you can look up online who they were
And then yeah and then and then video I thought it was fantastic I think that you were off in this room
Radius property
Technology and Business Leaders in the world
Right I think that talks
A lot of people that have learned a lot from Robin
So I'm curious how did you first meet Robin Lee
So I had a friend the way back
Who is working at
Baidu and
When I told him I want to be able to look at
Using Robin to me
China has a long line
Robin Leach St hours
About what
Holding up to look like
I think I'd let it go
Robin is Ashley Young
Very clear strategic thinking and quite a few times he kind of sees further than a lot of other people so he's really want
I got very much at Meijer
It's a
Impressive to us when we visit
CMU in January
UCI Professor Moore
Lassie movie
Google
Penitentiary
2 a cm
Having
Kind of
Exchange of
Experiences
Makes a lot
More likely
The Fosters Nick
Wave of love
Stanford UC La Cuba movie
Around and
Anthony
Together collaborating different things
I think the Stanford University year has long had a deep connection to a second Audi in fact
Sephiroth you say that you throw
Creating the second out either we all now know today
So I think that
The transfer of knowledge is often a two-way street
Right then
The whole Community benefits
Your everyone is community benefit is true
Are the pieces that communities are ranging from
Basic research and patients is that abuse on a company's a couple sharing with researches
What are the most important Alden Resort
Datasets that then turn house drives to research for it
I feel like Joe Dirt
He's a hundred or maybe a thousand example it exciting things happening today
Almost impossible to summarize interview sentences
It's just
AI has turned into this
Cute engine of opportunity in and then and potential value creation
Podcast this year
Some of the best pack
Not that
Best Minds
Spinach calories
Beechfield
Are working on
And also the
We're hoping that
Elmore University
Operation
Allow Talent
And ideas
To be used
Exchanged
So that
More innovation
Timeout
Four on the next section of the
Podcast
Would ask you a series of rapid-fire
?
An intrapreneur
That you admire the most
And why
Umich Robert earlier
Do you have anyone else
Another executive
One of the best CEOs in America and I
Often listened to his talk
Sometimes my sometimes just on YouTube I feel like I see
Learn a lot from a strategic thinking
I think one of the amazing things about Amazon under Jeff Bezos is Dad
If somehow
Dothan Mall. Let them keep on building up mucus instead of Evil Within this giant company in historically
That's something been very difficult to do and I was on this one of the bed
Where you at by do you made it mandatory for senior Executives to join a book club can you share some titles you guys
I just read that leftmost impression on you
Show us my favorites leaves downtown running very top of the humans
Team read aloud
Sun products
As long as on business strategy
Take a Simpsons writer of innovation
To his new book
Competing against luck
26 books that Malcolm Gladwell
Malcolm Gladwell as love reading history
Book is not on my list currently I really enjoy reading Malcolm Gladwell
Avicii
That's really the two
Building Products
When after use
Most often
The people may have been a
Besides Google
Yeah I read a lot
So there are few
Magazines that I read
Thank you so nice. Enjoy include new hoverboards
Review The Economist Uber business week
Most of eat near Wall Street Journal New York Times
Subscribe to clean a lot of things
So what
Pawcasso videos
I'm not a frequent user of YouTube just occasionally
You have mentioned that when you decide how to spend your time you're up two criteria wanted
Weather
You're doing can change the world and the other is
How much you're learning so which one thing you did that you say
May change the world and what's one thing you did that taught you that
Get out I think that's by offering a set of courses on Coursera
It's not so much me changing the world is me giving you or me giving others the power to change the world sound very faint
And I think in terms of learning new things I think that
As I
Try to apply AI to healthcare I find myself very volatile Healthcare education if I myself
Continue to learn a lot about
Asian Thai fine.
Exciting on and also I was quite happy I got to spend most of this past weekend reading research papers
Wish I hadn't had time to do for a while babe surprising
If you are
You know spend 20 oz / we can reading research paper that you can actually read a lot of research papers
That's something you do for fun
I enjoyed it I can't do it all the time since since I've other things I need to do but I I really enjoy this
For you
What to do
Alpine night
What makes U
Are you excited
Some days
Actually happened to happen someday if I woke up at 5 a.m. and couldn't get back to sleep because I was so excited about work
That's actually happened to me a few times.
The opportunity to change
Thank you so much for
We're coming over and spending time with
Thank you Andrew
Thanks
Thanks for listening
Who does episode of 9/9
By the way
We also produced
Email newsletter
English
Also called night
China
Subscribers
Forward it
And you said.
Original content
An analysis
From Sarah
Striped at nine 6
. GTB
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs
For the last 17 years
From seed
Capri IPO
With 3.8 billion dollars
In capital under management across 8
GTA V invest
Englobal like minded entrepreneurs
In consumer internet
E-commerce
Frontier Tech
In Enterprise
Gdb has invested in over 200 companies
Including Airbnb
Alibaba
The trip
DD
Hello bike
House
Slack
Square
Hotel
Wish
Zappos shoes
Why why and others
With 29 IPOs
17 unicorns
To date
Find out more at gbc.com
Do you have any feedback
Or would like to
Bisimoto
I-96
Mapreduce
Balfron
Abyss partner
Kaiser kuo
The Host
Of the wonderful
Discovery Channel
Political