Hi there
Come to the 9th at 6 podcast brought to you by ggv capital on the show we interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a us China
Cross-border perspective on Stone, managing partner at ggv Capital and I've been working at startup
Invest in them in both in us and China for past 20 years
I meant investment analyst rggb capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96 Chinese Founders have organically it
Adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
To us996 captures intensity Drive in speed
Of Chinese internet companies many of which are moving faster that even their American counterparts
On the show today we have Ashley pong or polini the founder and CEO
CEO of shampoo a mobile platform for young parents in China with kids age 0 to 6 years old
High quality content and tools
Shampoo helps our users navigate Parenthood
Which is a confusing. For many Millennia parents
Selpa literally means Little Steps in Chinese on the show bull parents can take courses on parenting
Enter a parental University
Browse activities to do with their children
And post updates and photos to record their parenting Journey
Chapel now has over 2 million users and is experiencing rapid growth
Before starting Cellfood last year
Ashley Walker
As a consultant
Epicity China for 8 years
And it's been 2 years and ya boo bay
A leading e-commerce company for mom and baby goats in China
Wish you was the VP of strategy and also business assistant
Tennessee Yelp
Show the math bachelor's and master's degree from Devry University in
Journalism
And public policy
And also obtained her MBA
From Stanford GSB in 2011
Shuffle
Is it used to be before the company
I'll call you Jenny Lee
Welcome to the show Ashlee
Callahan
Hi
Good to see you here
Good to see you
Great how did you come up with the idea for shampoo
Was
2 years old
Saddle her highchair
And having
She just has kept us
Throwing her food away
Her dad got really angry because he reminded
Several times that she just
Didn't listen to him at all
Eventually
Her dad
Yelled at her and
It's through her into a dark room
Season my daughter was afraid of Darkness
As always said she
She didn't like her dad
Jaheim
Election in 2000
Cipro ears to correct this mistake
Rochester the fitness
Part also
The intimacy between her dad and her
And actually I've learned a lot
In this process
I think most importantly
Two lessons
First
Both my husband and I
We had to master degrees
Frontier Hall University and Stanford
University
So
Both of us
Is like
We received the best education we're smart
Oh wait still no no
Sing about education
Comes to like educating
Our daughter
Piano better than
Anatomy
Or our parents
Rice
So
Reverb artist
Yeah yeah yeah
I think so because
Very basic mistake
It's because we know
Nothing about parenting
Delete that example I mentioned
The Amendments reasons
It's because my daughter was
At 2
She was at this sensitive period Where
She was testing
The space she was
Experiencing the founder of
Throwing things away
Getting control of something
You know about
Wait we just
Use our adult
View to sink that the sheets she didn't listen to
She was annoying
The Redeemer
Parents should learn about
It's not natural right it's not that
Because you are smart you you have a very good degree that you should naturally know about these it's not
It's something that you really have to
So
This is the first lesson
The second edition is that I actually use many ways to try to bring
Back together
I tried to
Vector my daughter that you should like your dad that
Love you and I actually didn't work if you don't work at all
And he went Rudy
The most important to
Help us is game for the parenting activities that we together with her
So
Play together they actually do things
Together
Can do a lot of things and that is so fun
All these things brings her back
Her dad
Was not that easy
Because you know like
Chinese people tend to
More serious
Or read it
We're not video
Free used to 2
Aldo
Activities or sports or
Hentwi record
DIY kind of saying yes because
What we were raised up we didn't have to
This and do not have that email regine's we have to learn about these things
And I actually spend a lot of time
Researching
Online and learned about
I spend so much time
Exerting all kinds of methods
From the flooring website
And try to find out to the phone way to engage
Wish my teeth
And it was not that easy
Should I study law book series
Because you haven't
Learn about the series before you engage please her
Also I collect ideas
And I have to arrange them
Based on her age
Based on her interest
And I have to teach my family
To do these things because it's not the only my job I have to
Teach her
Dad have
T chart
Her grandparents
How to
Use this interesting found way to re-engage with her
And I realized
If every X have to go
Through these processes
Will be like the bereans too high
A very interesting way
And I could see if it works
On children
Actually
I have some friends
Sending their
Try to my home
And
The children will change
Raising two or three days
If you
Use a right way to engage with
The change very fast
And I stink all the parents should learn about
Have to go through
The pain for a and a complicated process
So
I came up with the idea of shampoo that we can create something
That led the parents
Learn about the Saints
Berkeley
An easy lie
So basically that's how I
Tamales ideas
So it's something that you wish existed when you were a new parents yourself
So yeah when I was new parents
I don't think there's anything
Exist I still remember I searched
Parenting activities with keys of
Free
Elias Tarrytown Baidu
Probably
20 articles
15 of them are the same
And rectify that gave me about
20 ideas
And that's why
Anna Pizza
I think there were only about like 7:08 ideas that attracted me
Result in a picture
Animation to video Genova picture I have to have to read
Imagine
And try to understand what it means from all the wording
And apixaban
And I Try by
NFL
Free so
Situation
Started the whole thing
I was so pissed off I feel like there's no real guidance online
How to engage with your kids
Incontinent
Accompany your keys
Activities
WhatsApp
I just passed
Fall activities
Because I can
Quickly understand that I should do activities
Took me so long
How to actually do what
So I think that's why I told oh my
A user is my team.
Practicing it
Is the most difficult
Because
Really easy to understand the concept
Actually doing it
It is at the following and the thief
I thought they are a lot of snow
Florence
Community sites
About how you should do
You can raise your kids
Especially from people in the same community
Share with each other
Also in there other sites like baby tree we've been around a long time
Yes a lot of content on it
Were they not enough for you
I think the most important thing is that it's not
Systemic
Super Sub or the kind of hunting I mention is basically
It was actually an almost
Naughty this is
Which Apple started
Actually when I was a new mom
Not too much content
And and also even if there was something
It was scattered all are fragmented
Do you have to do a lot of work
To oxidize them
3D
Make some something that you not only you can digest but also you can teach your family
That's actually very difficult
Yes
So you are a millennial parent yourself I wonder what are some characteristics of this generation of
Millennial parents in China
Being a millennial parent in China today is that like as in more difficult than before or is it easier
Very important
Characteristics
Lack of information
For this generous
Old people
Too much information and actually
You don't have enough time
You have to look for the information
Very
Efficiently
I think that's a very
Big difference
So my parents
Generation
There were only
About
A handful of experts talking about
These things and they were just a simple magazines that you could trust
You could get this information and in just a blunt
But now it's
It's Britney
A nesting stats y
The pay for accountant
Is rhydian you trans
In China
All these parents
So much information
Out the air
And they
Mortgage magically more
Authority
Information
3D photo
And also
Information
To be
Very easy to be digested
Sometimes we feel
That's a little bit country
Because normally we would
Information
Exist
For example in books
Rye
Please sistematica
And then maybe courses
School
Diesel
It's too much
It's too heavy for these losers
Good information
Very very efficient way
So that's
Jose
Required
Content provider
To support that
That's why I sing
If you ask the weather
Easier or more challenging to
Raise a child
I think it's very difficult
To say like
When I was young I still remember my mom works 6 days a week
Stayed at home
Mom
Didn't even exist at a time
In China
It's not
Even possible
So most apparent
Just
Jewel their children
Add to their grandparents
I still remember I
I spend a lot of time at
My hometown so
Nowadays
Differently people have more choice
Mm equals 1/2
A lot of things help them break them whole like we don't have to cook now
A lot of time
So maybe it's easier
At the same time
It's getting more and more challenging
My mom actually just studied very
Basic things
Pat Toomey
And she just
She understood saver basic
Principles
And she did very well
I grew up
But now
I think most parents
They're not
Not to join
The train. I was saying
Make a pushing very hard on their children
And pacing
Among
Like a different mother
Yeah and
The tiger mother
It's very difficult to do this because
Cuz everyone is doing this
And
And the competition is getting
More and more fierce
I would say this is the most rich Hannigan
Hardee's
Just understand what you really want for your
Hialeah
What is really good for Dan
And stick to it
Instead of just
Being driven by fomo fear of missing out
Yeah
One term that I frequently see on the shell boo app is quality companionship
This is actually
Kind of opposed to what many Chinese parents are used to do which is
To send their children to various classes and activities
And camps and hope that these activities will shave their children into who they want them to be so why do you think quality
Companionship is so important
First
I think I have a 1 ways a little bit
Knowledge
Education would know that
Parenthood
The faces
For everything
For all the educator
Companionship is the basics
If you
Don't spend time with you
Especially Spell haiku
Time visual kids
There's no way that they
Plus you
Did love you
And a photo
Your guys's
If
That lock
Lacoste
And love
Is missing in the relationship
It's very very difficult for you to
To do anything
And I think a lot of love
Aaron's
Actually
Did you realize how important
They always feel like a
Correcting the child at that moment
Is more important than
NEC
Why sing the so-called Racine
Is more important than maintaining
Relationship with
The first is really The Thundermans
If you ask any
Capers
Or any research
They were
Stephanie
Ethically
I think no one can be better teacher than
The Pirates
What you did at this age
Especially for children
Before
School
Because
For children from 0 to 6
So different
You know like why
Almost all the countries require the children to
Start school to real school
At the age of about six or seven
No earlier than that
Because
Before this age
Children develop so differently
Some shooting
Stars versus trolley
Ross motion
And they survived the relatively slowly
Fine motor
Are very strong and language skill
I'm South children height table at Cosmo
It's no
There's no standard
Orno like
General principle
Said you can
So
At this stage
Really require parents to
Charity
Child
Play song your observations
Play song you're on
Christianity
And also based on your knowledge
Education
So this all comes very naturally
Waze
High quality
Nobody can ever
Ready substitute this
So
It's so important to teach YouTube
Parents
The correct way to engage wizard
Actually
Is Maury fake
You spending time with your
Chide
For about like half an hour maybe
More
Effective than sending them
A school
Special results School
Was very Light commercial
Driven schools
Very limited training teachers
Actually
Should have the
Can do much better
Then
Zeze
So-called
Teach her the damn not even like a serious teacher that you still like her
Employees hired by
A commercial Training Center
And maybe get
Change 4
About 10 days
And started to teach your child
I think all the parents
Should have the comfy
And should have the
Responsibility
You already think that you are the best
For your child
Other state
Quality companionship is something that's relatively new in China
It's a it's a concept thing
That's popular in developed
Country
So I think the fact that you
We are like that's important and want to make the epochal in China
It's very admirable and makes a lot of sense
But as you know many most
Most of the Chinese families
Have to income parents
So it's harder for the mom
It's been a lot of quality time
With there with with with her kiss
What would be your advice
Most families are in that situation
To achieve quality companionship
Yeah I think so
The first is that you really have to find information very
Efficiently
When is it half an hour high quality
Companionship
The time you should spend
Much more than just
Half an hour
Because you have to think about how you should
To do with your tongue
How you feel you have to
Connect Bluetooth
If you do
I understand what game said you you can play with your child or children can initiate a lot of love
Activities in Greensboro
If the parents
Inspiring
I want to play a few ideas
Two children who have to do their homework
Jackson's of time required is much more than the time you spend with your
Your children
Again that's why weight would do shampoo
Because we want to save time for
And we want you
Find Seas
If I can spend very very limited time
For example like
Ava video 1800s just don't like 1 minute
You just been one minute
To learn about
And the activity please select is already
A face down there a gif face down
I even Tara Maids
For your child based on your feedback
Ojc things you have to do for us to do the homework or you find someone to do the homework for you
Amazon concentrate and you play with your
Children
Show
That's the first part
As you come hard I do saying
You have to teach your family
Do this
This maybe not very common in the States but in China
Yeah it's
Vervain normal
I heard a number is it more than 80%
Of children raised in
CDs
Are Ray stop actually buy
So
You really really have to
Educate the whole family
You have to
Mobilizing have to
Metsm
Started as well
It's actually very challenging because
It's difficult work
The elderly's 3D
Open mind
And studying you
Approach
If you ready
Find a way
Ray effect
Safeway to
To make some feel
This is the act
V
Very anxious
This is new with the newest.
Next
Actually very very important
I think
Against
Much more effective than lecturing
This is a choo choo
Your children and also true to your heart your parrot
220 Alder
So
The teacher then and let them
Music
The scientific
And
Systematic way
To engage Boise
Because you cannot just rely on
So
Obviously you have gone through a lot and also
Show me the lot of good knowledge
I don't wish for your family
Complaints for many others
So how do you think about when you design your product
Do you design for the parents duties and for the grandparents as well
Do you how do you organize your information so is easy for
Princess yourself
We're very Hands-On to learn about them
And how do you get more people to share their experience in content
Are you apart from 2
Got started
The first day we adopted a very
Scientific way
Because we walked this
To be
First Delight.
Occasionally
Student varieties Castaways professors
And Stanford and also
Experiments the teacher
Frankenberry from my Jean
Witness Casa framework
The framework
It is very important
That's a rarity Define the product
How you organize
All the counting all the information
And also
Wait wait
Raining a lot of like mobile internet
Design Concepts
Because we know that the users want the information
Information
Easy
And they want
How to share with other people
A special visitor laminate
And it has to be
Very easy
To operate
Write all these things we can buy something together
Cell
It's not just
Of course
It's more of a castle
I shampoo actually offers Bose
Youth weight devices
Parenthood counter
YouTube
The first
The Siri part
Where we will teach the parents
How are the general principles
And then
The activity Park
Where we at
The concrete
Things that you can do with your child
In different areas
Cell
These two parts
Alright
We also have full free content data Paycom
With every single freaking to normal
Online education company
Offer any free count
Because
Mostly 4 for the paint party
Do offer on wall of lothric
For many reasons
First step
We stink
The free content Reedy
Helps the users to
Understand who we are
And what
Principles we
Believe
The users who have used to offer free come
Moc hire conversion
The users
Pure new users
And I think that's actually very
Important
Offer
Actually
A very Broad
Selection
In the Free Company
And we offer relatively Limited
Selection of content
In the paper
Because we think
For free parts
Parents are looking for inspiration
Looking for a diversity
And ideas
There are many ideas
Out there
We just collect all these ideas
And making it easier for them to
Search
For the Peapod wearied
Offer service
It's not just the count
Beauty offer
A lot of service to
Help them
3D packs
Pretty
Do it
But they
Have questions
Come up with questions
I'll help them to
To improve
So
It's not just account
Let me put it this way
If we divide
How industry into several
Community-based
Accountant
Where
People just
The discussion
They discuss the things and the universe
And the information is
Reach
And also
Not very system
Like just the accountant
Approach
Offer pictures
Spell for organized
Accountant
Offer service
And I think we are at the
The search stage
Because we
We ready I think is the most important
Practicing
I keep saying that
Any
Activities that you do is your
Children
Could be very different
How strong you are
Imagination
Because you could sink this is
Boring this book
Boring
Cyn.
You would think of throwing things
Show me a place away is very boring
Back City
For your children
It could be very very far
The actual doing part is right
Important
And that's why
Use a lot of them
Tennessee
Functions to help the
Parents
Who actually Tuesday
And this is awesome
Very important feature of
Community
Nodira Mini
Parent to share their photos with
Ride that store the photos
Oldies
Photos
Are most of the
Most people too
Pictures of the are children
Resolved a story
They just to feel all this you look so cute
Take a picture
But if you look back
I think this is
Especially true
44 Chinese
People
Abusive Luke bag
If you do calves everyday photo
How to say it's cute cute cute
Cute cute cute
There's nothing left
Other than
Do activities with your child
You leave
Photos
The Dred Scott
Will tell you a story every Rick
Tell you a story
And that's why
Parents
Victor Breedlove rides
Many words
Elmira Castle
We used to have
Used to have word limit of law
300 words
And they had
I said to 500
And of one salted and then complete
You can ride however long you want
Play some Pirates really why don't you remember what happened
Avondale
That picture
So
Our
I think Oliver
Rickey Stokes
Different from other
Like just a photo album
It's not just
Nazareth
Video diaries video
Arab
How are you
Accompany your child
To grow up
Obviously to start any company in China you need to pay
Very large Market
I'm in just to get some
Background the early childhood education Market in China is actually huge today
So there are 20 million new babies born in China every year
Montgomery is actually encouraging people to have more babies now
So because we're living in a time when we're really starting to feel the consequences of the one-child policy wishes
Contributed to an aging Society
Is projected that by 2040 24% of China's population will be aged 65 or older
So the Chinese government has actually reversed that decade-long one-child policy and is pursuing a two child policy now
And I even started heading out subsidies and benefits to persuade people to have a second child
And this is why we had ggv felt like the early childhood education Market is
Worth betting on
We could go to the Stamford
China
I guess was the economic Forum with number Summit 2 weekends ago
I have to say no
How does bakers basin from Kickin It is vital to get tickets Adele
Actually I got the news and I almost forgot the
Tickets and I give up because it has another meeting at Shanghai
Too bad
We are probably because
James chairman of secret
Separate ESP alarm PSI PhD from Stanford
Who wrote the book
Asia population policy the China Hut
What does he talk about how
Have you only have one child policy
Makes the China and Asia Society in
Decrease by productivity in
In base foundation for economic growth
So
Side effects of some of his efforts
Now China has a two child policy
Are you seeing the impact
Of that
I something as pasta for your business
Do you see Chinese parents
These days are more willing to have a second child
Or do you see the stuff take some time to
To adjust for that
Because the pace of life
Still very fast in people are very busy
I think it's the definitely
For the industry
People started to
To have more
Keith and when they started we have more keys
StayWell
Feel
Essex people
People with one teeth
RVD
Different from people with several kids
I know we have two and a second one is exponentially more
Yeah exactly
Batteries Plus
Yes oh Daisy actually require
Much more
Cervix much more efficient service
Good for the industry
I cannot focus the like whether Chinese people would have more or less
Children
I think one thing is
Tiffany true
People started to
Raise the child in the more
I would say
Sanlitun
Yeah exactly
So they don't chase for
I think the lesson of this
Parents
Chasing
I chasing for
So cord
Justice
Next school results
These days
They
More and more people have
World
View on
Education
And this definitely
Helps the whole Jenner
You measure the word knowledge
Its impact
Proliferation of mobile Commerce in China
90% of transactions on e-commerce are all done over a smartphone
He also see that WeChat pay is truly popular
People that share share money with each other each other
And so given the given the mobile payments so big in China
11 times the size of
Bouquet Market in the US
Do you see that people are not used
Used to paying for knowledge as well
And therefore more willing user you more than user to Windows pay for premium hunting
Because it's so easy and they see the body
Yeah definitely payment is
Definitely
Some say that
People to
Or not encourage
Enable
M2
Payforit
Pay for the concert
But I think more important
Play it
Estimation
Hamachi
There's just too much
And people
Study to see the value of
Selection
And
See the value of
High quality
So
That's a very good shape
Nu Eve also worked at eCommerce company or me out babe before
How did that experience inform
How you're running shovel today
I think he may yeah
What channels do
Observe
Young Harris
I realize that they are really
Bye
Because the end
Are many companies that
Try to leverage that
Add interest
To to get them to buy
A lot a lot more more than they need
However
The trust you
Because You released there
Not
Christy ring
So
They can buy for once
They can buy under
Certain kind of
Stimulation right empathy
Actually
Do you eventually understand
Who is really healthy
I think trust is this so important
You are sitting by his parents
Really have to
Remember
This is something
That eventually that will help you become
To get into i-Ready
Speaker
Vision
Ura
You can be called a hike way or sea turtle founder
Who what who was educated
Part of Education was done overseas
And I come back to China
Starr companies of staying in the in the US
How do you say your
Experience
With that
GSP and spending time in the US
Help you to
Shape your experience as a
Apparently therefore
As a founder
The early childhood
Bristled boar
My GSB alumni founded miso
When I see networks very very strong
Yeah when I had just an idea I had nothing I have a team and a height of
90 year
Prada animal date they founded
Miso
It is very helpful
More importantly I think Benny's Denver is
It's definitely for me it's a life
Changing expiry
And I got the chance to
To learn
How does
The best education
Philosophy
And miss her
Reading work
I still remember I was so
Surprised
Even innovation
DMV
Can be taught
Can we talk
Stanford
And I do realize
This camp
Talking session
Efficient way
And also
You feel
Like this encourage
Is itchy encouragement
Critical thinking
Analisa Costa
Is Seoul
Different
What's wrong
Education I received
China
And the whole
Project-based approach
Or the
Conversational
Based approach between
The professor is in
The students all these scenes
Sweetie
Open my eyes
Education
So when I'm designing
On courses on shell pool now
I tried to
Autopsies a principal
Oregon
I think they are
Very new to
All the Chinese parents
And you to me
And I see
Think they are
Yeah bring you and a very welcome
To all the new
To all the parents in China
This is Rudy song sing
That's a change
Our
Education
I think the Chinese
Location
Sister
I do think
Everybody understand what
Critical thinking is
A neighborhood
Understand what
Why we shoot
And why we learn
FaceTime saying not
Play Store
Oldies singers
Secret code
3D help
Chinese educator
Yeah we can relate to what you mean it's already got her undergrad degree from Harvard
I did mine at Stanford
Universal hurt innovation
Was in one of the classes I took you my junior junior year
Inbody
Technology and science at de Parma
I'm curious and you do undergrad that you buy in China
And you
Then
Come to a sanfordville NBA
Do you have the best of both worlds you have the College Alumni network from China
Helpful as well as getting exposure
To to Western education critical thinking at Stanford taught you
So do you see
Diastat
The best combo or
Are you seeing that more and more families are having their kids from China
Come to us earlier in for high school
If not for college in the in the US
Before one day Nickelback return to work
How do you think was the
The best combination of us the best
Experiences
This is actually a very different
Difficult question
Because I am
I also like
And my parents now and I have to
MyChart
That's why I asked you this I had a very difficult
Decision
Wizard and when I should send her abroad
For study
Yeah for sure I think
Weather is not a question
I thank God for her
Very important for her
To get a international View and experience
As some stage of her life is really I open
When is epic question
Yeah
I do think there are some things that
Cannot be missing
If you
Walk to
Do
Something in China
And I truly believe that
The future of China
Unlimited
There's so many opportunities
F words for Chinese
Yo
If you
Bebop that part
It's quiet
I would say
I'll order it for Durrett yes not wise to to really give up one of your
One of your biggest
Advantage
So you really have to
Learn about how this Society work
Even
It means that you have to
Follow some of the reviews
You don't
Studio Grace
Brakes and hold my daughter just started her first grade
This September
A local school and she attended a very
Like a foreign style International style kindergarten
And she was raised up
I mean
Waze
All kinds of freedom
Increase in the first week
She said she was shocked and she was
Complaining everyday
You said all the teacher
Doesn't allow us
To talk
At all what they were walking
They don't allow me to go to the bathroom
Before I get the
In a while she stays half these rules this
This is unfair and it is a ridiculous
That's in the public school system
There are so many children there are 800 children
In there school for 1 grapefruit wine
What is a teacher assistant
Don't allow you to go to the playground during the break
Because
So she have to
Chapter goes through these things and so that she understand how this Society work
She will not
Lucchese seems like a foreigner
She's looking at these things as a foreigner now
This is so absurd
After reading that hurt
Experiments
So that's why I sent her to the public
School in action
Surprised surprised about my decision
But me why I'd like to thank the parents
A very important
You have to teach them
How to
Have their own
Opinion cheap theaters
Yasir remine
At least I will tell her
It is still right for her to
To have doubt on these things
So it's important that the parents knows about things
If you eat the parents just a photo what the teacher said
Then maybe
A challenges
If they come to the Future work or come from more International environment
Why does the role of the
The pens are so important
If you know about these you can you can correct them
You kept a lot of the other things
Other than School
So
I do think that very
Basic education
You should still do it
Despite of all these
Elementary School you do Public School
Local school
Junior High School in high school
I don't know yet
Because I'll have to get ready
I think for
Elementary School
The parrot
Make
All the dishes
Junior High and high school the more
Anomor
Yeah I'm worried Vengeance Z10 sync on their own
I think the thing I will do is that what I will
Xposed for
Buspar
And I will
Make more decisions on her
So I can also see you
From now on
Maybe she will
Babysitting
Right
I don't know what things will change
Started to selecting University
Maybe there
Mini train
In Chinese
Dedication
Self
Difficult to say
Now we move to the last part of the interview which is surrounded quick fire questions
The first one is a entrepreneur you admire the most and why
Jack Ma
I have to honestly the he's because I work the immediate wish is
E-commerce
Company yes
So the closer you get
Yazoo the more familiar you getting to the the industry
The more you admire how he
Is able to
Filled up this
Empire
Jamaica, is popular in China without him
E-commerce may take a lot more time
Yeah it's coffee
In China
As a founder of
Company in
And who is managing managing like 70 people now
And iiii
Observe the hall
Mia co-manager when self-employed
Company
And I think the more I admire
Jack
Alaska
Humidity
The system that makes
The whole
Saying work on it
Red up
Company value with a value
Not Justa existed on paper
Like the existing ain't easier
And the other people's mind
I think that's
Very challenging it's not
So easy
It's it's
When you are doing a few are know how difficult it is
Trigger point
What's something you read recently that you recommend
There's a book called
Learning learning
Right side up
Education
Back on track
It's pecan pie
Yeah it's written by Russell at coffee in the Daniel Greenberg
December 8th
Interesting books
Medication
How old is Future
Education would look like
Books to Blue
I've heard it's good will my wife and I have two kids 10 to 6 years old
A book that she mention to me
I've already
So now I make sure I read it
What do you do for fun
Play what is my kids prefer what's your most favorite activity that you do with your
Paddle brush
So many ways to play the Peter walk into a fight
Weber Seafood Lafayette 3D release
How old are anxious older
Stress in the
Ready for
Sounds good
Ask questions are you hiring
And are you hiring locally or hiding from Silicon Valley from Santa
Yes we are always hiring
We are
Looking for
Very good talent to help us to grow up
Especially if you are
You are passionate
Education
Helping the family
Cheetah mobile
Internet
Welcome to order
Pallets
To join us
They're looking for people with education background and Tech background or both
I think both
So if people are interested how can they reach you
You can search on WeChat
Search the account she'll poutine
And leave a message to
Great thank you Ashley
Airline flight 879 89.5
Listening to this episode
I-96 ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
Country with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre IPO
With 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management across state funds GTA V invest in globally-minded on
Entrepreneurs in consumer new retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has in Boston over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollar
Hours for Phila companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip Didi chuxing
Domo hashicorp hellobike cows keep Slack square-toed
Wish sandwich rule white white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as far as China where we regular share insights event
And job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 996. Ggvc
Dot-com Community sister podcast
Thunder we'll talk it is a biweekly show that it's real with unders about the challenges that founders
Is sun-up executive space
And also how they have grown from Top experience by my fellow managing partner at GDP capita
Glenn Solomon office again
Past episodes of the show include Stewart Butterfield from slack Sarah Friar from square and Netflix
Is it from Airbnb you can take a listen by searching founder real talk in any podcast app
On this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us at 996 at gbc.com