Vincent wrestler
Airport
Hi there welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by
GTB capital and co-produced by the sinica podcast
On the show interview movers and shakers of China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a u
China cross-border perspective and the managing partner at GTV capital
Working at startup investing in them in both the US and China for the past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jones an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
6 is the work schedule that many Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is 9 a.m. to 9
RPM 6 days a week
True us996 captures intensity drive and speed of Chinese internet companies
Many of which are moving faster
But even their American counterparts
On the show today we have Bertrand Schmidt the CEO and co-founder of a penny
The leading Global provider of f Market data
It's used by industry leaders all over the world
Customers include Google Snapchat New York Times as well as Chinese companies like tencent by dance in Salem
Ebony's a truly global company
With 450 employees across 13 countries
Person has worked in Mobile internet across the US Europe and Asia
Previously he was an executive at to internet analytic companies that were both acquired
Bertrand grew up in Paris came to the US for MBA at Wharton and then went to Beijing
Where he co-founded a penny in 2010
Welcome to the show Bertrand
Great to be here
So how could you tell us the story the founding story about Annie
I think you had a pretty unconventional path
Most people start their business elsewhere and then expanding to China
But you started out in China
Ebony with space in Beijing for the first four years and then moved to his
Headquarters for San Francisco
What was it like to start a company in China
Yeah I mean it's my bedroom was a typical
Coming from you up experiencing the US and I felt
Juicing Sia.
It's a business trip to China knife
The vagina was going to
To get even be going Tech and smartphones China was already very big
Feature phone
That wasn't seems a new wave and smartphone coming at some point and
I spend that
I know what you said in your panel to setting that in the US and two business about that I didn't know as much energy as Pfeiffer
Stop teenager
I would give out surfing better chance
2 BC
Successful in
Asia Hospital in China but also for my best picky smartphones also going to be begin in Japan and Korea
Amazon Vesta fidget Sandpoint
I'm just here so finding tenants are finding talented engineer
China was already a great place for
What were you doing before
You can do China
So I have been always
The mobile industry I started developing apps
Believe it or not for catch you later
I was 15 so probably 25 years ago
So I always have cheese
Fashion for you know you smoke computer in your pocket
So I transfer everything
Cacciatore
PDS
Leprechauns
What was that disc in interests about
Device in your pocket
I've always been one to be to be side providing software major where I need
Asurion's an energy solution but focus on the performance speed availability mobile
Website
What happened
ISO is the iPhone coming but specially
Yep still
Just was ready solving big issues that we had
I just see we smart
It was difficult to discover
Distribute and monetize content
And I might be speak to you yet still was ready Chinese at
And I'm just see Apple and Google platforms was the first to be ready
What you wanted
Real computer in your pocket
So my text was just informing 2010 to do something to do something about it
And I was excited to sync Xtreme owns a business site
I was trying to understand what was happening
Angie strangest trees uibe industry and I felt like we don't find a lot of
Information about the
So that's how I Penny was stopped at while trying to understand what was happening to Muscat
Trying to fly to stata to developers about what was happening in the market
And we stopped and we saw a free offering first and we're quite amazed how well it was doing
Step by step rebuild
The premium of Raynham.
ICD-10
And Lobster special year
For smartphone in China
That was your show me was founded when we had that co-founder
Lynn
What do you mean Chinese
I don't understand this podcast show earlier
What did you see about China in 20
2009-2010
Not get you to want to go to China
Installed at your deck startup
I've been here since first I mean everyone that feature phones everyone was using SMS
Sofomy smartphones wetware movie table
Price for going to go down
People that would want to have something more powerful the X 3-g was barely there but I wasn't
Very Valentine abilities
To build infrastructure
That's exactly what the fun
As well you need that 3-g
But that was believing it will come
Northwest Mall
When Nathaniel and the 101
Not exactly
So it was that was ready
Republic time is it once I'd already like when I went to China was to
12 people giving mean you don't know just one business card but two business card 3D printer
I've seen two business Guthrie I've never seen outside China
I sent a nice to food today is that China is one of the most
Entrepreneurial country and was one of the country with the most energy
The US you can fit in LG Silicon Valley New York
Outside smells like.
In charge you fees at another you know I usually wear
That's what I like
When you went to China did you know anyone there or speak the language at all
So when I went to China I didn't speak a word like activity
I didn't
Maybe
One of two fans in Shanghai
But I actually stopped at in Beijing I was sucking on moving to
China
And he said it to work with you
Tow company Gomez send me to China
I was up first non-chinese on play in China
And I'll be sweating Beijing so I end up starting in Beijing on
Connected to
So what was that adjustment process
For you like to do encounter any difficulties integrating with the local culture and especially booting a company
Takes a lot of
Yeah
I would say my first 18 months was I was mostly walking for Gomez so in the way I learned about what to do
What not to do in China
Which was an angel
To understand that and I'm happy to $12 each way before starting my own business he gave me time
Time to connect to network
Chris a lot of people
House 2008
Early tonight
To connect pieces of people on
Try to get a sense of
Cuz I decided to stop again a business after the Summer Olympics
Yes so I went I went to the Summer Olympics held
International Expo in Shanghai
Say I Wednesday through Sunday that was coming to China for 6 months
Personal reasons show
But they finally move in January
Differently how can you shut it to Chicana minestrone about keys for find out you have to
White address stop someone else waiting even address the time I was trying to use some
Pocket PC
The funds from Microsoft against Russia value walking map stuff barely walking in Tustin
Just not as easy as enough to that today is pretty patties
Yeah that's what specials are fils Ramones at the time of this year try to launch Chinese
Stop to get to Rome Oasis Resort was
How did you shutting but yeah I got used to it sound so when I was stopping at Penny
I have my network can you people in your house
Get the wrong man
I would say I stopped other business in France and I like to joke once in awhile.
If you can do it in France probably can do it anywhere
Used to be better but I'm using it less so that's
That's bad
But now that I have adult tell my wife
She's from Taiwan
So I'm going to speak more Chinese as well
So you moved the company's headquarters to San Francisco around 4 years ago what goes into that decision and
Do you still have a large team in China and where they working
Yeah well we have more than 150 people in China out of
450R globally shobogenzo biggest of History
Recessive engineering team is still headquartered in China
So that does not change
Laundry hours
I think everyone looks wrong at all so wet when seems that people can also work for Marty I think we are
Elmo focus on what
People than you hoes at the exact time of the office
So that small how we have Edwards at 10
Between search team to ingenuity
I would say
Organization
But different to your team saw a walking holiday
And if we do see 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6
No that's something you don't see in you up
And I'm surprised you don't see much activity in the US
Not as much anymore
Exact
I guess I could use to be more
But not much
So no that's part of United Rihanna
That probably Carreras puppys a place for us
Walking
So how does
I should get for my world business
But size you from the quality of work
Also very good
Some people think that you working hours
Efficient
What do you think
I think it might be true in some companies
But I don't think it's true at that Pennywell really focus on the what people did you go again
Simon's office
So so that's pretty awesome
Acqua di Gio so jobs
So I guess it depends on the
You convenience fish
Different it seems like you can have both fast and
A lot of hours
I still have to work
Outside
Scary combination
Yeah I think so
What is the best Chinese company
How different is it
Anything at the end of the day like 96 and it's more about on my side and then motivation
Just like mere long hours but people charges
Hungrier and they want to work more and if they don't work not as safe to feel
Left Behind if there
Companies moving south
Yeah I seen China and that some of them are cats and I'll do 50 more hungry than usual
She take care of you don't say us sometimes
PlayStation Kia Galpin I'm surprised I've always been hungry
So why some people don't take this but that's what you do
So as a result do you see more Innovations coming out of China due to these competitions
High-end
Like what are some examples of
Innovations that came out of China receiver when it came to T-Mobile
Innovation
Probably because even if it started to be Clayton smartphone a complete move very fast in the way
It was not so hold on by the existing web and internet are presents
People made to move onto the switch very quickly
Nursing UTEP Chinese companies stop to Cindy Franti
Assassin was on Market not just being a mindset of what digit that works in the US and maybe we should do it in China
Developing much more Innovative solution I sync WeChat was Villanova to you how did your therapy anyone else.
America pqq Mattito's
What what dancing did we say
I'm cuckoo and say okay we're going to bed to burn you
App for smartphones that when you took so long for Facebook to go in December
Acquisition
So this is very very impressive on youku.
Line upon line in Japan at the same time
Which I probably started it
So that's what an impressive zhangjiajie has been very impressive
Stop that. See me all times
You better maybe if you take her mobile Kuwait for bike sharing
This is the first
But even if she sees some other companies like
Which one of violence no I mean
That's quite a lot of
Original
Innovation
And I think these past five years are not even talking about show me
Which was a I mean
A grater
I mean the way to lunch menu
New mobile
Company
Did you drive while it's washing
I take things apart I'm from a defendant a new angle
So
In the past few years have been full of
Wielding Ovation in China
Especially in the mobile space.
Craigslist San Jose
It's
Very very impressive I mean I dream about doing space 5 each other
Fabulous Prosecco
I mean
It was not clear with woman
Global company from day one
Back then in 2010-2011
Internal audit board
Don't want to do Starbucks
Only focus on China
But you saw something
What did you see
Yeah I mean my check was I like China isos China as a market potential for stronger
Beltone
Halligan's Eastwood
Toronto weather bet sofa
For me twice
And those sweet videos that's enough space at teaching B2B to Azure 2 to start from one location but you ready
House of Wellness
And quickly and in a way where where you are base is not such relevant where you can sell
Andycine B2B she have a great College
Mosquitoes
As far as you got in there is no reason to be shy about
About that
And also me being a financial night make sense that I was not going to be free
Focus on China Focus type of Market opportunity Global Market
Toronto Pizza. I know very well in B2B
I said
To work pretty well.
So what do you think of the VW space in China in general
Is a lot of people
Sank.
Enterprise
In general is quite behind in China
Compared to more developed more
Yeah I guess he
Probably true I would says you're missing is that from us from a client's perspective I mean how can some
China world class
Loves the same question semi shoes it won't 2000l cayennes for white dress
So from that don't go
We make very little
Flvto
Time in China
Addition key when we symptom of Ozarks.
Watching TV can do right sometimes
Dallas
Opportunities available lots of B2B companies have been shy about going to
China I'm not sure why I remember the old days 10
15 years ago that was
Issue about
Kitchen copied in China I shut the transitional license mother
Add icing specialty resources business model
She's running nothing issue
I'm a bit surprised that he's not going to be global
Pizza companies
I'm sorry felsing going into
Cushing's isb
Chinese companies are big on your veggies that was one of the best
So I think it will come
And maybe I know so you should know you could Argosy availability of cloud computing solution in China
Gelato
Shah B2B tech company you might have more work to do
Go to shabbat
China markets
When you decide to move headquarters from Beijing
Into San Francisco
What's up
Decision purely business
Orsa personal
I know it was purely business
TIG wire
And we sold all Time Force real first time using the store was idg capital in
In China
We got lucky, I knew you shouldn't for a long time and
Has been a great supporter of at what we saw is at
Elmo Natural Market something best of sideways in the US
Cuz I smelled that symptom of
B2B Tech
Global Tech
Angel us
I'm still trying to fight our way as a global company in China trying to find financing was not
Chinese Yuan while it was your fault
Does that mean to us
And we did that
Accessory versus B size in the US but step-by-step result being closed I would be even better for us
22 weather in term of tenant engineering or Coating in China was great but Falls outlet mall
Global mindset
B2B mindset
Does difficult to find Cyrus marketing at people what is mindset and experience
You could find but it would be very rare and maybe even more expensive than San Francisco
So
So yeah at some point we might sit
Something for for me personally
Having being title for
8 years on the ground
Decide to move on
2A California
In 2013
Also because I want to build a morgue
We have office and both here
As well in San Francisco Boswell's
China
You can do so much more together having
Presence in Baltimore
Curious about your experience raising money from Chinese VCS at that time and both times in Birch Run,
Mendez V feel like at that time
Not a lot of Chinese BC's were investing in
Enterprise
Companies are not
Let alone.
Founded by non-chinese on prayers so what was your experience like and was there anything that surprised you
Yeah it was different ear by reaching into space I mean somewhat surprised if he has a phone
How to tighten
Get financing
I think the bigger issue was small
The fact that
Most of our focus and for good reason and b2c China Box
Its fashion
Beaches in China
White balls always arrest
Search for smoke trying to find
Type of investor will understand what
We try to do it
Easy I mean we want people to understand and believe what we do
If it's a stressful damage
It would be a strained relationship at some point Graham
So so far as that was already trying to find out until I'm not so many
We're ready International in mindset and west
Ready to talk in English
But Josephus were Smartphones at the time very
Shoe are in China Beijing thinking about app
An IOS and Android
2010 - 2011
2012 stop
But when we started like a cat
CiCi's Pizza phone number
3 GM
Early fall
People to
To think about
Amazon Associates
Pizza
GMC bed
Woody Hunter China
Summer summer
And
Funny time when you started another When shall we started it wasn't obvious
The smartphone one
Take over
And for both of us to succeed
Almost
A Motorola Arris anoakia all have to fail
And that's in North Hills everywhere inside. Not to bad-mouth Nokia still agree firm
It just not that the war had it seems a lot for you and Shelby to 6
Just send it happened and they having a very
3 year.
Yeah I dream about having discussion with some of his
P ghost player into Mobile space sign
Aswan sensorium to ship a Blackberry to
Nokia Rush
I was like no way these guys are walking dead cuz I don't know it but well not going to sleep all day
I'm not going to invest or precious
Results
My my Julie hunt variant
Cranston West
Messages not on par
If you don't get it.
But I'm not going to
Walking Walking Dead
And I think the Enterprise Market
What stuff
Very tough.
Party tent
Very few
Successful
At all
But I think
Since your success
Construction
Maurices in China are looking at Enterprise security
I think that over time
Giving all that big Chinese internet companies
Grown up
You will you will make some time or Enterprise company that sells services
Solution
Do they speak Chinese in a jar
It's just like
Mus
I totally agree
Bandits it's fun people to
Embossing operate multiple markets
Cuz you see some of the trends happening in one
And you just know it's about time we could happen
Studio the country and vice-versa
And when people just poke someone country
Is very easy to have
Blind spots and nausea
Yes that's 232
That's one thing I love running a penny that 3-wheel bright in certain countries
Around 40% of our business Nisha 14 Americas
What's something you up for
So we have
I mean we sent Market that. So we
I'm all that. We see everything happening in the world at the synapse
But don't say we have the direct contact and touch with all his crayons
Everywhere and that's very exciting
For me to see those
The small differences in
Defense Market
To see one
That can serve as a crystal ball at this for some categories
But what's going to happen in summer in
In some Industries
Addition to some of our clients
Use us Foamposites
What's coming
Price of smelt us when they want to see no grounds what's happening in China and
Japan song
Definitely looking over the last two to three years
Politics is very local
And this a strong push back
Against globalization
In parts of a side part of Europe and Asia
Here in the us as well
But the innovation in Port Orchard
Acknowledge diffusion
It's definitely
Global to Global phenomenon
Ice in politics
I usually
Agrippina story
Hopefully if he doesn't go too fast
But it's
Let's not forget.
Every single
Is going company
Keep doing business
They sold his International
Books-A-Million
I wanted to dig deeper into the reason why China just sleep brought into Mobile so
Quickly
So if you like write a Beijing Subway today at everyone
Glued to their phones
Mobile payment Market in China was 11 times that of the US last
Sphere
And a lot of Chinese companies these days don't even bother to make websites anymore they just have a nap and just a bear
Their website with a QR code and then maybe a WeChat official account but
People just
Or not on desktop.
So what do you think is a reason that
China Star
Jumped into Mobile so quickly
Even more than the US did
He not funny that's actually it was a question that I'm always asking why is he being so slow in the US to get
T-Mobile in Europe
I've been so
Push up because I just go back to he's so convenient to use this device but in your pocket
If we where you are
I seen that thing away from me China is what you chew Avenue
Videos of recent questioning and
I mean obviously the illogical reasons I mean
Home Depot website
And laptop desktop presents
In the USA
Purple shampoo
China beetles
China of course your laptop's internet but
Opal Shimmer shoes
What puts you Smallville
Malden
Each other. We still had balls
700 million
Dust up meaning that users
Yeah but it's not always your on your laptop on your desktop
It might be you or your office while maybe at home but mostly Ralph
The Sidewalk Cafe I sing for me
It's a good experience people moving to gaming in on smartphone so you're not very fast
She's a grocery chain gaming Mobile in Tampa Florida news
How do you spell Celestial King on using accurate was a move home
I have to go to The Sidewalk Cafe I have to pay some extra money and just
I know I can do it from anywhere that's
Pretty obvious
Reason to switch
What was four people in Korea on your car you can play from looking for
It took more time to actually
Move to mobile restroom
Hainan China
There's
Is that more
Subway in High-Speed Rail now
So you spend more time with public transportation
And
Great way to kill time
Is 2
Surf on the smartphone that you compared to the u.s. issue compared to Europe
That's true because you are as mass transportation that be scared but Steve's about not as fast
To move to Tomorrowland and I've seen in France
Puppy dog knows it was a device code mini tell
Long time ago in the
These funds was the first digital
Internet connected
A country in the world we are
Free dominos to access online services India
Every French person that sings at home with it slow down internet adoption in France
Bios
Boss why do you buy your PC screen
You have to pay for it was a 100
A free trip and it was more complex to use so it took three five years
Lost
You know where in France to move to the internet
I think similar phenomenon in European to US where he has his addiction to consult a few home to use your voice
Good enough
But don't say one thing it's not
I mean when you look at some of the big giants you are from the US I mean to us so slow to buy the good
Mobile experience
Damnable expense initially was just
It was done bad people
San Pablo
Talk talk to you she was yes that service was bad so people will not using it
I always go back to that
If you don't provide what you ask him and somebody else is going to do that and you would be trouble so you have to f***
Focus on that time you should be having a lot of European us companies worth
How do you add up my website to make
It's a bit more mobile-friendly it was not like
Let's have a mobile. Watch
Because you received this is our future on West to recognize how we work
Hunting 2015.
Offensive level of service dr. Trivedi
Get better in the US
But since last year 2017 that I fit companies ready get that
Moberly Smalls and I found you say don't put all their resources mobile
Zombie trouble
Image of small companies now
Is this stopping resting on the web
It's okay it's running let's visit
We can have the phone not to invest everything we have on mobile. That's where all the groceries at
That's where all user
A China go cheat March 4th
Bionda China Us in Western Europe
Are you
You said you can certain
Do you see
Other Emerging Markets
Increasing looking more like
Like China
Or us
Yeah and we're insulting countries but we setting many more countries so we have
John Cena
Cheapest countries for 30 plus country recover more
What I would say some developing markets audition chemo like
China
Taking Josh to take Indonesian wedding price by Indonesia
Asia market size small
That India
Yeah I've seen Jazz volume turn off downloading turn off device at 12
Cafecito
These Donald's
Monetization what is more difficult
Can we see a lot of Chinese money in Indonesia
Dies at
I need to use Market
I'll just take a bit more time at all
Yeah I think it
Lot of people try to seniors like China
Bmplus people seem outside
Trinity got a smartphone a smartphone but at some point
What was the worst Liverpool GDP per capita
How is he doing
Monday Night Raw roster
China has issued me.
I need the size of the UK
So there is a big in your own defense and I think Indonesia.
Safari smoke shop
Such a gap
In the inverse sine judgmental cm in China and Vietnam
Highlights coming up
I mean small Market st.
If you keep going with me.
So Chinese companies going
Those are my kids
Can you still see the u.s. first time you see Japan
UC Korea
But I'm expecting a lot of
Dumb TV Investments at download connotation yet
It's from Indonesia 2002
When you get job applicants
Emailing you
Looking for opportunity inside a penny
For those are from the
URS
Or the Bay Area
What's their profile
UCLA
More Chinese people applying for positions ebony
Or more Americans or Europeans
I will see if it's happening July 4th of us position on sweaty Mall us
I mean US citizen or us resident
So we different the the value of a lot of
Depolarization are attached so it's awesome you so differently looking
Very young
Typical of the Bay Area
Tyler Posey
Gennaro's I guess
That's all people
Here
Asking you for
News in China
I always say
No hay very very very happy to have some people function on Tuesday place
Satisfying as a place
New China saline, bet we have that
Patitza
Sometime you spell scientist what's menu Kansas City
Us we see more.
Auction Tucson
We start seeing more and more
Chinese engineers
Impala managers can
Barrier
Pinterest
Either one for Chinese firm
Here in the Bay Area or even
Go back
The last time we saw something like that
Portside
Back in 2000
5 mm sex
In our time
Since then has been
Spend less
But in Alaska
3 years we see that
Picked up again
So if this diffusion of
Western wise Talent
Go into Chinese company
Then
Eylul predicts
Inside Chinese
We could be more global
5 to 10 years from now
As more of these
What's my talent
Spend more time
Jana was one of those things that
We have product management here in Sulphur
Just go out but Solange Mostafa engineering
Shine on your path
So it's not that easy for a big hug you and your folks
Here for engineering
Russian Suicide Squad me some profile
I think for that waves are both
Polish and pull factors
It's getting harder to stay in the US
Because of immigration policies but in China is looking increasingly
And also argue that the phenomenon of Chinese students coming to the US
For college and higher education
I really just took off in the past
Maybe
What are two or three decades
So maybe in the next
Few decades will see a lot more internationalized
Chinese Talon
Butts
That's our bag
That's why we're
Doubling down on us
Noah still growing in China
In the same time
We also be looking at
Opportunities in
Indian giver meaning
Emerging Markets
It's those with darts
Domestic economy
Cut that look up
Us and China
Aspiration in
Increasingly
The Chinese business model
Become more
Done before
Yeah I think what
China's one
Transsexual
Comes that time Galleries at
China you know from far away people sing
It's one big imaginos country
Let me see that even the app space we see different songs by by Tri-Cities but
My phone's at the strength of Chinese app TV shows he's at the at 2 deal
The most successful 1/2
Travel successful dancer frozen meats
I'm Chillin to cheer Force
If you take Japan Korea us Western you up there to deal with mushy but you'll go to lunch
Twin cities weather
Is a symptom of Celsius internal Network
Politics
Petition in term of devices
Petition
Network
BT soap
My buns at the apps that actually don't always expect
Well in developing mark
We're actually Chinese developer some TV shows that build apps that actually scare
So I think that's giving actually very interesting unique advantage
Chinese companies when they go
To any Market because you know how to cover from very where there's love to less-developed
And that's
Pretty unique to China Ganesha take Japanese companies fun sounds
Jeff such usually Hayek's
Petition of
How how young is your phone
Weather for Wednesday
Somebody petite Maxi toddler for him to go in localized just because location of fault is much harder
Hello chiba
China is
Is Big there for a company
Is grow faster
Why what don't
What people miss
Is the nuances
Not because China has a lot of competition
So you have to innovate faster
Because China has
4 different ears
Cities
You deal with differin
Quality of
Networks and users
And tastes so ends up over time
The models
Anapodoton built
Could be more relevant for a wedding
Emerging Markets
Yeah and you're very trusting hansa competition sights
Competition is so intense that the surviving ones over again
Dell'otto popular apps in China started
On the ground with really low tier cities like
Glacier hotel and even QQ start in the internet cafes
I think that's one of our investment thesis here in the US as well so entrepreneurs need to
Learn to make a mass-market product
And not just appeal to people in
So I also monitored the App Store
I'll have any of like Emerging Markets especially Middle East and Southeast Asia
We're starting to see more and more Chinese apps made by Chinese
Making those top ranks
Are you satisfied, you're singing why do you think
Optimistic are you about the ability of Chinese teens to make
Podesta appeal to other emerging
Yeah and maybe he'll I want to or so highlights when initiatives are Chinese government has
What's up
I seen that
I mean we tried actually to measure what was
How Chinese companies were following Sergeant was interesting.
To see that photo capture of Donald
Nike 45% in belt and Road countries to like 55 57% off.
Donald's outside China
Happening in despair Town Road
Country
So I seem to see me some alignment between some level of government policy
What successful Chinese internet companies are doing
So that's probably why I no longer want you to catch that internationalization of
Chinese companies
Following some of these trends
I'm doubling down in some ways and smoke
What is a false
I'm pretty positive because again of what we just discussed at Chinese companies have developed software that
Richie Hawtin
Antenna work at the Funplex
GSF apus
Tiana
And that's what you need in some of these small
If you see another one
Cafe music Google
Facebook
Minka Kelly scrunching some special version of the heart
But you did Transformers not have to do that
Because you don't want to
Straight to the ocean Fidel marketsource
It's better design
Anyway
Have.
Strong results
Actually right now already from Chinese
Prostitute
To keep going up
If you take social for instance
1 subtract Farmers history sheets
What is Veritas
Moviesurf what's up front since he's already established
I don't think it would be easy for WeChat
That's how many more opportunities
Tutuapp something to my mind
1 is a
Wish
And we were fortunate
Tuco be there
Motherboard
And it says
Start of Iowa
Both our first time
Gwen van Meir
Instagram
The other
From China
And then
Google
Respectively
And I'm building a
Leverage
Suppliers from China to sell to Consumers
And there
IHOP
Stop Storage
USM
The other country that jump out
Come by me
Jolly chic
They're hiding in the
Mena countries
Also a
Taobao like business
Model in
The app
Supplies from China
Selling console
And the very low
With 500
Jordan
Number finder
Saudi Arabia
EXO
In addition to have
So
Beat these two companies
Which has operation
Worldwide
According in
Cisco
And then
People in
So those two
Two companies jumped out at me
Next Generation
Global
Tomorrow after you you have earrings
30 countries
Recipe to peking
Beat the u3 all the type that remind me of
Next Generation
Xiaomi puppy Moore Regional
Eastside
You are more
Overtime
Come out
That the three of you
PennDOT
You I wish
Punjabi music
You strike me as
Movie built around
Take advantage
Company
Competitive advantage
Ambition
Become peanut butter go bad
I mean which is a good investment
Zara images
Number one across all Android app
Consistently
Yeah and tell me what they like we send me that's a very salty
Ashanti Body
Let's do eCommerce on mobile
It's more like today let's do something new that is more focused on how you might want
Toy shop
On mobile
And I think it's to put your ass
Most EMP Millsap height ready
Monica music spans that you tried to
From my bowl banana
Amazing
Nook meaning
I walking like that
Pricing versus very good for wish
I did not realize that
I live in
Tencent
Call me since have you lived
Maybe not 10 books
Try guys
Cd2
SF to Shanghai to
Virginia
Look at the wish the guys they also have
When you have a
Hardest
Things overcome in The Bigs
Is competitive
Sustainable
Is having a mole
A cultural DNA
And perspective
Cuz you
You can see the same thing as sub data point
It's a very difficult
Wednesbury provincial
The other wife is
Pause multiple calendar
So.
When you triple the data
You going to have a very differently
Mental framework
I'm very worried
Ya no soy
I believe I've seen that yet
People are just kept
That means you just don't know if no
Always been one country or when
And suddenly one you talked about going for
Set you off but you still remember my first
Company has stopped
Global-minded
It was tough to sing behind you
Beyond York
Anna
What year was already very big across multiple countries already
But yeah is that that's
That's actually quite quite right
Sunday so what icing is coming more and more
People from the
20 searches of Maltese
Abysmal Global antivirus
Experience
I'm just leaving in one region one
So when I look at what you do
II
From the outside
I viewed your stronger
Competitive advantage
Singable
Is your
Troll exposed background
A lot of companies
To schedule
I don't have pizza I'm probably.
She look at the exact
People love
Canada from India
It's a very Global Management Global operation
I'm a very different perspective and I think that's quite.
Sometimes you see companies who
Larvae look nice to One Market sometimes Drive
The Thunder execs
Daddy speak English I mean
To Market so that's
That's surprising to me
Cuz he is going to hell
How do you make divator
I mean team member of San Jose people in DC
Rockets you just don't believe you
When you understand that mean sunrise
Any team that's
Not bad
Decide irse
Copper ceiling
Golf R
The world's movie
If I'm a billionaire
And I users
Mostly
Stopping to
Like to know 3/4
4 billion
Boosie I smart
And the new user
One look different
Then
Some of the market
That
Yeah you should go Global to slow somebody else is going to be so smart
Conveys and said that needs to write for YouTube
What does encourage
All of our audiences spend more time the other markets are there
And we tend to invite guests
We'll have a more Multicultural person
Nothing can replace
Actually spending time
On the ground
As you can read and listen to all you
I think just takes Optical in there
Eva Zarate
She has already.
Corrupted by China
Went to Singapore for a high school went to a hard boss the East Coast
44 college
I did not hear it
In the Bay Area so
The more you talk the more you see
At the border
Mantis you're cute
Yes I'm Simone you can
I think she be on
What you can easily see you see not just like
Maxine Factor
One market
One situation one culture
You can see beyond that you can see the impact office
How people react
I mean
Canada Toronto
Spans
Do you like Star Wars
What's Works in one market Minot working another one
You need to respect
Tips to get out of San Francisco and successful Munchies Locos
Success.
What needs to
Two to beam up
I never forget the first time I saw Kokomo
Imo
Oh my God
What's the weather feature function
But just
Japanese companies to never win
Expanded Beyond Japan
And I had a similar feeling
What's 2007 watching iPhone
What I've seen two years ago with a mug
And but this is much more open
This one by much bigger
So
I think I'm depressed
Fucken help me
Too bad on xiaomi in 2010
Start a event
Yeah I know I have these beliefs
GHIN only 2012
Stupid global company
Users worldwide 2020 in the late 1990s
Tell me a fun are you having connection everywhere I mean
Skype was just starting and barely starting so basically you are missing
Aviation
ATS care globally
But I already first time in 2010.
Classic Shell to be small and Nats game
Did you pay much attention to cryptocurrency or blockchain
Hot topic of the day be
Yeah I look at it from far I'm a bit surprised on one side because I look at it for a long time
I don't know if 6 years plus since it
Stop turn and I'm not sure what happened last year to make
Difference
But I wish I look at your phone
She's very much
Focus on the apps on the wall
I wonder which
Chinese app
Are you most impressed
Spark is you you have access to all these numbers
Yeah I mean I've been myself I'm serious I mean a big user of
WeChat Saint Lucia, I'm very impressed by that but again I must say that
Before you text Mom mobile Corfu
I mean I've been very impressed because
Two Chinese Innovation another sad but that I feel I like that
No people ticklish car so you can go from place to place more efficiently as you know China
Completion issues
So I think this is very I'm not sure how it can scan trying but the market
Equity Fund
What's in China it's all just she's holding I mean you can play the last my tissue like we would go be tonight
It's very interesting for me so I'm going price for Mom
The Thomas format
Best picture
Ofo
Now you know EV cars are coming
Prostitution is being trans a Matic annies food
Chernobyl and apps
And that's very exciting
Because sometimes you see these huge crazy plans
From government to invest
Wrecked and Beyond 617 on sand
Diving lesson bags that's interesting small pictures to it I mean maybe
So that's mommy's very faint
Listing of singleness Chipmunks radio
Get free what
Some people have called WeChat app killing because they have
Medical programs
Where you can do an app with them when the WeChat ecosystem in
Do you think
10 years from now we'll still have screen after screen of apps on our phones
Or do you think it will go towards more consolidation
Amor supera
Yeah
I don't think so I think we'll probably as a Max on CPAP sent to become people live in
Talking about straps for like 5 years
WeChat has been claiming that
Facebook has been trying
I think there is a limit to
People Trust
China is a
Right after India's biggest user of upheaval moms
City Pico Rivera Chinese restaurant using more than 40 apps
Every day every month on his phone
Asobi on the US so
It's not as if we charge King also apps
As you know from your Investments and something very wet
I think she want to see so she Bell apps
Nikolas Cruz out different important
Degeneration or sometimes has a subduction there
But not I don't think pretty beyond that I need so so goes with only so much
She can do research
HTML
5 Yuan
She's getting better from WeChat from
Facebook
You don't have the full access to the
The phone you don't have to
Some capacity
You don't want to just depend on that you got up as and that Patricia
Maybe text you get cheat on his own but once you get them you want to keep them
Flirtations of ego defense would be more for smaller brand smaller apps that don't really want to invest I'm not ready
Tea companies
And believe it's cheaper to just be purely in the WeChat enjoyment and I might make sense
SMS
SMBC
212 East Prospect
Add icing Beyond these guys
It's more of a careful approach I guess on Morley Virginia CPAP suzhou
You like what you see
What advice do you have for non Chinese entrepreneurs who might want to start adventure in China I think a lot of
Not Chinese people these days are interested in getting involved and ecosystem there but are pretty intimidated by
Just the culture there the language and how different everything is
Amy pisani that's what
Cutting Justin Howard Ashanti twice I was excited
Discover new places you could show her very different actually from us and Europe
Ubuntu
I passionately love you stories
So maybe that's why I was I was talking to
Tmall China
I think I don't think people should be so so scared at the same time
It's not easy also so
So I think the best for my Best Buy TVs for
People cool at coffee house painting leaving one or two years in China
How to work with local trash companies I work for
Find companies with
Abortions in China
Cuz once you leave there you learn to be there first
I mean that's also something else
Some people cannot take Heat
You know
But if she already liked it and lock it
She connected and sings and you will stay for more and
It's easier to probably take baby steps are leaving say I'm running a bit of the basics of flavor scene
So that when you are ready to
221 business or Commercial Business
How to do something else
That would be my advice on that money what I did
Making mushroom selling for
Custom for me
To stop stuff in China I have my network
People unusual
Mystics
It's so easy to make me sick
So it's I think about you to do that
And it in China Beijing Shanghai
Since it all quite
How to spend
Time we more than once
You get to know the
And I'll pray the real chine
Restroom
Bess Truman
By myself I spend a year on your tongue I am surprising
I was actually happy to go back in Beijing I fed
Am I best picture of Beijing was multico until Shanghai might be more easy for
Expats but
Looking at TV I'm looking at
If you shampoo Shea Falls a business
I felt that Beijing was a bit so play some uses a great company in Nigeria
Facing specially for expats is my BCT
We just have too much of an international
Viewpoint of China from
Shanghai
Shenzhen
Mezmur
Silicon Valley of
What's your view
Which city
You're mine
Resemble
In the body the most
And Hardware
Of course Sean Jenna butter if using software for me Seymour Beijing internal foot
50%
Investments
Time in China
I mean when I see the company Drive close by
Baidu to Lenovo
Talluto's 10 codes
Anxiety San Jose University
Cityside
I'm bae.
What else I mean it
Tupac
Can white students
Suntan as usual Center of so me as a friend I think he is
Minot City easiest choice
But I singing Beijing you off party mode off meat
Define
The people you need if you're ready to go party.
Show Goldie's chose that just
Walkers for nurses formula
We have a New York
New York off of
Call China albeu
It's always very Global very modern
Lifestyle I would probably prefer
Yes
Okay well go into the final part of the podcast witches
So fat around a quick fire questions first one is a entrepreneur you admire the most and why
So I'm not sure if that is one entrepreneur and meiosis most but I've always been impressed obviously by
Keep it up Suffolk Chief baguettes have a chief but if I go back one of the one I've been very impressed
Sexually don't girls anxieties party Benjamin Franklin
The US for me so amazing
To see someone
Donald Trump
So I mean
He's very special to me and CC coming from Juventus
Cassano's on Galbraith
50 years ago
What's the weather
Twitchy
So much about
I thought you pick someone from the Renaissance period
Or something
Revolution
Benjamin Franklin a society
I mean he's a guy who wants us to the house
To protect yourself again someday
He's a guy with discover out during his
Are you up yet
The different commands
Summit Wellness Center for you could go faster
Show photos of arm Carranza range this is impressive how diverse
Stormy sings about BTS on Tuesdays
People are so specialized on the Visa is no choice
I'm curious how many apps do you have on your
I have more than 500 on my head
Delete Steven Gregory
And what do you do for fun
What do I do for fun I just got the baby girls write now
4 months ago so I'm a very focus is your
Just wondering first one you've been working very hard
Yeah I've been working
See I really hope she would ask Lisa
StreetPass fix even though Asian European Atlanta
So
We speak to her and her mother in French and English
Was she born
San Francisco
What's something that you read recently that you recommend
Good question I really love this book called sapiens I don't know each other out about it so
Sounds like asthma group
Was pretty good
Another one was very good was
Better angels
So usually on but one of the most interesting book
Because it's changing a lot of
Questions
Things people take
For granted a lot of
And that sometimes
Description
That's what happened we said that on these things you should not
Well she's waiting and I'm so impressed by what you want
So I'm now starting with v newest book
Well thank you so much for your time
Thank you my pleasure
Thank you
798 beijing
San Jose International listening to this episode
By the way we also produce a weekly email newsletter in English also called 9 + 6
Roundup of the week's most important happenings in Tech in China
Subscriber some told us it is from formative and fun to read
And you said also features original content and Analysis from Zora and me
Stripe at nine 6. GG bc.com
Venture Capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds GTA V invest in
Globally minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet
E-commerce Frontier tag in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies with 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Orfila companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep slat
Square
Hotel wish
Soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
Podcast or would like to recommend to guess please email us at 996 at Gigi bc.com
This podcast is co-produced Battlefront and business partner Kaiser kuo
The host of the wonderful sinica podcast it covered China's economic political and cultural issue