Hi Nana 6 listeners this is Zara from ggv capital
For those of you on the East Coast I have some special news this week
Hans and I will be doing our second life show in Boston
On Saturday April 7th
We'll be interviewing Joshua Wong
Professor of global economics and management at the MIT Sloan School of Management
Who's the renowned Economist and salt leader
Are you guys trying to relations
Will also be joined by special guest
Are producer Kaiser kuo the host of The Seneca podcast
And former director of international Communications baidu
This event will be free and open to all
The show will begin at 7 p.m. on Saturday April 7th at MIT
Space is limited
And the specific location will be included in the confirmation email
So make sure to register for the event soon
896. GG vici.com
Slash live
Again that's 96. Gbc.com
Flashlight
My dear
Welcome to the 96 podcast brought to you by ggv capital
And co-produced
Basilica podcast
On the show
We interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry
As was Tech leaders
Weather us
China
Cross-border first
My name is Sunstone
I'm a managing partner at ggv Capital
And I've been working at startup
Investing in them
In both the US
In China
For the past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jeong
I need investment analyst igb capital
And a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Who us
996 captures intensity
Drive
And speed
Of Chinese internet company
Many of which are moving faster
But even the American count
On the show today we have bread Bell co-founder and chairman of limebike
Assass growing dockless bike sharing company in the US space in San Mateo
Lime pie was founded in January 2017
And is currently in more than 50 different markets in the US
And have helped users when more than two million trips since it launched
Woodline Bice mobile app you can unlock a signature green bikes
Spie scanning a QR code
And it's dockless meaning. You don't need to worry about parking your bike at a.
All bikes are tracked by GPS
In addition to traditional pedal bikes
And now also provides e-scooters and e-bikes to his users
GTA V participated in limebike series B financing
Which was announced in October 2017
Before founding limebike
Bratz was an investor a full song Kings and capital
And before that helped launch and dude up $0.10 us operation
Extensions first employee outside of China
Welcome to the show Bratz
Thank you for having me here Brad please share with us
Limebike story
Love to hear about it from your perspective.
So where should I start that the ICD the company was founded in January but we started to look at a sector loss
July and the time will svcs svcs
Write out the adult that was the last sector we look at it for our found one
And the first company were looking at it was mobizer
Just giving the connections
Between without are you naturally extended to
Mo bikes Beijing Beijing
Yes that's right
And we'll cross Spotify right. You know throughout my career is always cross-border unicorns Pottery Bassman
Team scores for the opportunity
And when we look at I can Mobic and hopefully I mean lost July they were just got started now launching the market
To be smart
Right back when we fight we were amazed
By the cross
Dada generated by the sociopath
In the house
Stop the war play able to provide
And previously you guys looked at
DD as well as
Air quality in China and also Uber and lifting that's right yeah so you're aware of the right sharing battles
Exactly yes or virus putting me there was the transportation you know you know patience and that shared economy in general
Bozena usne chine
And when we were while we were Amazed by the open mobikes you know progress in China
Add evaluation showed up too quickly and it was all we have are some other concerns
You know unique namik Sandy Auto issues. Associate
Bisimoto right across for the van that we naturally you extended to our search
Into the US that's why it's Europe
Bachelor pad
And we found out the opportunity
Here. He's could be you
Keeping the light off
Public transit
Occasions as well as lack of competition
And deal 6 months into a. We did all kinds of research interview the people and
Yeah companies
Yeah and you know
Trauma investor Prospect
I'm bored you with in Chinese market that's right
As well
Yeah we look at the fsmo dalian the past
Which is stock-based Solutions why they didn't work that well and somewhere we looking for the validation two
Then comes off the market size and and I'm at user demand
And we also look at that it whether there's opportunity and what kind of team
Diabetes necessary to
To pull this off
And we failed to find a good funeral
Team tuivasa
Call Michael at a time was to be a happy Master sitting on the board
Yeah I just like hot spots all the time
So what weed in a frustrated on. End it when we look in the mirror
Yeah and we found a perfect teeth right that has been walking on the cross border
You don't ask back out fed and for myself down to you
Before I found at the event your phone I was at Tenzin which is a starter
Within the big company you asked for 6
Pollo Asado
China and filled out the
You are so precious
From ground up
So I've been doing all that I didn't think that it was so the team were looking for his
The capability
To master do you Hardware design Manufacturing
Vertical integration
The hardware side from China
And the
Capability to really understand the user and Mark
Here you are
And the crossbow.
Ass back that you said
The chi
To success
That's the reason I did always started
Company buy or sell
Annie's assembled a team
Unless
September usually incorporate a company in January
And we thought first launched in the market in June in all the ads
The pilot it was only a hundred
15 x +
And the first Major Market large was it
July
You can see out
Ever since. Even last four months that we did $70 Asians on the hardware you know you normally eat a razor
Software and we launched 17 cities and
And schools
In the last rocket
So there are a lot of people who are skeptical about
White back sure it would work in the US
In China it's not surprising that works because it has a
Huge population and a lot of cities with a lot of urban population and
Not a lot of people have cars
And there a lot of traffic jams so it's natural that bikes will work
But in the US people are more spread out a lot of people live in the suburbs and own cars
So what made you think that this model can work in the US
Yeah that's a really good question so answer you faster and I was right to ultra cleaners God will you look for validations right
I took it off the market size but if there's a real user need
And before we put a tree
And there are things. I think the not well known outside of the industry
That I'd like to share with the audience
Your number one thing is...
Bike
Per capita ownership in SLC in the US is 4 hours
China is a needle well-known for liking evolve bicycles but that was the story
You have to look back
414 yuan 15 years ago
But after 14 years of eighties and nineties
Writing a d or even even in the late 90s early too
Mm nobody really
Use bike as Transportation anymore
End up the bike seat for use personal bike
This house has a
I figured I'd do you know this
Annual sales in China has 26 million
Compared to 1
24.
Ovulation while after you ask
U300
Population by The Vineyards houses
Very comparable but only 150 population
Will be per capita is full as of the ownership scared of behaviors there but daddy is not a
Prada service same as liking China without a bike sure not many people use bike
As a means of trust
Acacia animal
And that's the number one thing your number two. Even look at the population. In China is 1.4 billion
Population and Rafi about 800 million rural areas
Neil Young UIC 300 million population roughly about 40 minutes
And most of them. Live
You already know I'm a big city or small in a small City
Turn off
Dia address
Marquette and then you know that's why top down
Approach should I enema we did also bottom
Bottom up approach will look at it every single match holding out the density two populations without bike-share is different from any other
Services.
He doesn't need to be a 10 million people
You know
Major city
Exactly. Highest-performing
Market we have is South Bend Indiana we just didn on the 2nd
Audacity we launched right only a hundred thousand
Population and
The densities not at high and also
Weather is not that good right there's no fighting culture at all but
Weezer iPod at server
Thaddeus Young
Sometimes it's even
Has more Riders
City Lights
Thaddeus
Studio translates into two things
Thanks really.
Did Last Mile Transportation challenge
That works. We're trying to sell Fiori's universe
And I also the transportation need for anywhere daddy Lavina City War
Venus Motel
Have to get somebody
And on top of that idea out of interested say we can look at it off cuz I be as I mentioned that you asked
Free transportation
He's very like it
You don't compare to a WYD
The two European cities were ancient cities
Fort Apache
Anderson. Much eternal
Unless a soul
Y'all at the house like three hundred bucks lights Ronnie as like 15 metrolite take you to all over the place and you
Daniel lacalle
Yo City like
Say San Francisco
Then we have
I don't know how we do know there's only part
That's running across City and no other alternative
And I figure we also look at it what's the dark base
You know solution even though that the experience was not graded the availability is low
He died be in New York to see if I could still be able to
To generate 10
Risepro bike
Today in their Peak seasons and three rights provided Popeye
You mean the cold weather
And also their huge
Is there as well
And that's a reason
It All Falls Down
Believe there's a
Marketeer and then
Boss we are a little bit fortunate in that way
Six months of diligent for investment turn into a 6 months
Well thought-out file preparation
For Starbucks.
Which is kind of like
Like a rare
You know
Opportunity for us
To think about through a lot of things before we started
Building tools hours question liberal further
In China
Before by Sharon become a phenomenal a lot people doubted up by Sharon could work in China
Cuz you have
The subway you have a high-speed rail you have
A Rideshare already
So why do you need Bike Share on top of that people to ride bikes anymore
420 30 years
Interesting uses Center beside
Since the subway
Lights of being bailed out
In between the subway station
You want go from point A to point B uniform a subway station to go home
We'll go to work
It's too short
To order right here yet I'm too sensitive walking pics too long that's right so by Sharon become
8 common uses
Search for it for that
That was extremely fomo bicondova which number one number two in China
Endeavor discontinued
Then all investment did you just pass me in Skyrim
This is Halloween
It went after tr34 cities
And in those cities
Subway system is not as built and people
Take the bike
Run errands and so forth
Where it's not so far that you need a car but also its
Shower knob whereby can get a job done without having to wait
Is rice share stuff takes time to
Get into those cities
Soaking both
Use existing China for very different reasons and in your expense in in the US
What are the most common usage cases
That you see that's working out well for you in the US
Yeah I think either you are so again. Did that's what we believe that what we've seen you in the market.
The Last Mile Challenge Universal
Try.
And anywhere that's traffic that bike is always with
We got a rotten and we're look when we look at of transportation's. There's three things need to be in place you want to be happy
A viable Transportation means you know affordability is one of the other in the USA as I mentioned
The affordability actually rather difficult
The bus line rods
$5 and the City
All averages subsidized
And 70 leveraged $13 today and you drive your car.
Out of your my lost parking you San Francisco $60
And the Tropicana in the way data Getty and I'll
You don't wait for the
Uber War getting you out of
But the garage that time is
So appalled ability is what picture can provide
Availability is a whole other thing. You don't have to pick time. He will guarantee that you will
Now to be able to get a uber you guaranteed he would not be able to drive you are
Cardinal out of the garage you or whatnot
And India X accessibility
You comes out like the speed
To get your chest
Patience
In the Bible who is the talk Les aflac's
Stability of the dockless bike jerseys
Rotted really easy
Seattle in South Bend
What are the most popular uses case
City is there so different
Write for Seattle. We will see to that Adina commuters is it still wild up there
The peak
Commuting from Bellevue to Downtown Seattle
Mostly from the train and bus stations 30 40% we said we have GPS on each of the bike ride
When we look at the Heat
We will notice. Is starting with m points is very close to the
Or it's a bus stop so that's the number one usage similar to China as well encouragement or two cities
Weathers Auto Supply
Exactly and then this the second part that are for Seattle unique
Dad we have really high usage over the weekend
Add stop people xidan size
Average invite is much longer The Longest Ride we had was 56 miles
Lasik smile 56 Mi it take about eighteen hours and also averaged died for you know our users
Is. The writing pattern is a
That's why I think China is somewhere between you know
200m to 800-meter Translate
25 MI
Practice is always use your daddy is somewhere average artist want
Going to my house and
The many uses write much longer
I think it's a cat out of you reflected in like a
Public Trust
Application in the cities of black. Right even
4-H
3 mile radius
Bikes go faster than driving
The car will be waiting
Vygotsky at the same.
Sabine China. You might take a Subway you might
Take a bath you my
Y'all take a tuk-tuk right
DIY the bought at the taxi ride in China $2 roughly about that
My cell. Ste a different landscape and southbound is very different.
You know and I know so actually I'll give you a better example stylist right Dallas
Is more spread out in
Again every wise Arena air-conditioned car right what we launched there is 110 degrees out there
Jasmine wall of the team ever came back said nobody's gotta ride bikes and nobody would rise by second team came back
Say that's a great Market
When we launching in Dallas
Got the Spidey a high temperature out there this Friday at a car Centric
You know culture there despite the city's very spread out
My utilization in dialysis
Ziva Hyatt at the Owasso usage in Dallas
Dot at Highpoint like beetles
What rides per bike per day the hollows the average distance
Skip one point
21.1 21.2
2 miles and doubt it but the palace light it up like rice more like going to launch a small about
How do you know going to coffee shops or the Enron
From the time in Seattle
A lot of the highest point is like 5:30 p.m. and you know where to go and I are coming in the second highest point is
It's always like that somewhere I'd like a 8 to 8:30 and that's a commuters and $4 is more like love
Lunchtime + light
2 p.m.
And that's deal coffee table and Inn in South Bend. Deepika time we had was that they
They have
Yeah I know Saturday's yes and when there's a game going on we can see you in like six rides provide
Today and that's given. We only have limited
Supplies
Spell we we see you know interesting stories that you wanted to
You keep the pie for themselves is supplies not enough right now to not like
Yeah what happened in China they put a personal lock on a door what not end
The creative one I was saying is that it
They took off the QR code and put it in that pocket this still pay for it but only they have the QR code
Is the Universoul you turned up. Anyone sing we know this. If you don't compare China and US city is Roberta friend is
Yes.
When we say they're 10
20 million population in Beijing today
Walks around Derry NH
I go shopping around here where we
Talk about you know the 800,000 Residence Inn San Francisco everyday.
3 million people
Endowed is a very different thing you know
Compared to USA
Panda China
And then we
4 South Bend
It's at over a hundred about her mm in Residence
And we did a calculation for donut doodle
Golden Steer 300 cities
In the US
At least a hundred thousand
Most of the
Top
Ghost Rider series
Half of $100
That's right and that's how we look at it as well and we look at the other size of the Denver metro area
And then that's why I said downtown
And I would look at that
Well that's all the criteria
Are you look at South Patton Dia initially thought.
DSS Barnwell be saturated or in always a thousand bikes
Now we think that Atlas
Bikes
That will be nice
So you take away the process of Notre Dame in
The game day on Saturdays
What's the normal usage
What will bees were popular
Forest City like Southbend
Assuming there is no
Yeah it was idea Notre Dame we still deliver a doctor do you need birth certificate with
You think that yes it is hope there was
Enough saturation
Melodies. Org
You know somewhere
324 rice prophetic
You translates into
A lot of community
Raichu
Location
Take a meeting
Go to coffee or lunch in Seattle
Could you talk about how you chose
Expanding to the
The cities that you were in right now
So you're in
Yeah you're in Texas Indiana
North Carolina why do you go into these play
What the first and foremost is that our strategy that I didn't know we had a lot of fun
Discussions around that I think the industry Norm for good or for bad right is the LSAT
MCD at 5
Afterwards
And floss. We took it very
Different law
When we look at the Mark have died we sail selfie
Part of the city you know
Part of the company
I'm going to be in better in there at 1 walk
Varicocele
So we choose a rug that. We don't go in without a permit or
Denny translates until you
For the market with launch West
That whoever you bracelet
Technology
Innovation the most
What's today weather
Supporters
That will go YouTube
And for some other City we're in discussion with like almost
Order 300-500 CD that has mansion
Raffia ball
You know thousand to
Universities
It's a move faster
When was slower
Yes I'm off that day at the new Moto is a little bit foreign to them they need to see successful cases
And
Some of them
Got a little bit scared to see in the photos. Parking off bikes party off in China
Public Market education work doing and meanwhile. There are cities
Willing to step forward
Yeah I understand that
They have feet
Your clothes become human
Indicating West
Likes it easy
See
And you decided goal for this
Stevie
You know many of them. I set a goal for the city
B2B like
Carbon emissions
0 by 8
The year is
They're striving for.
Dental more like
Camas
As you are scale so quickly in the in the US
What's a what's a lighter
Do Ralliart
Team 2
Do that
SBC giving even for startups in Silicon Valley
How to copy strike for a
Work lifestyle balance
So how do you get your team to Opry SSG
High-efficiency
Send it.
Yeah I Cynthia you. That's a really good crashes while. It ironically that was
Be at Sarah was talking about that's right that's Park Hazard go tonight at 6
You know I was scheduled I cannot really do Saturday
For our team Subway's we're pretty much alike in 9 to 5 1/2
That's not to p.m. to a.m.
5 1/2 days a week in over the weekend. Although op'ration know what I'd probably
Do more work right
Compared to some other teams
What is we are running a customer-facing
Surveys and dad wants 24/7
Cannot
You know just leave
And the way we do. I think they're just a few things that the kosher on a mission and a vision
For the company has
I've been very clear
And naturally
That it is
Drives that are sea clothing
That the whole team to Worcester
Annie Annie audition. It when we recruited people died we also
Dancing to it so you don't my kind of like a miss a dream or inpatient
For this company is would be the long-lasting great company
And I doubted mean
New Edition to have the great product and services we need to have the
Starting
So we intentionally alert various 2
Choose not
NASA Suite who is the most qualified people from
Who is more like
Obituary
And also has a passion for that
And we do have a lot of ass back to igneel
Repeat until it passed Transportation means together Rhonda but they're still also
You know where will queen and I wear with a reducing the traffic reducing
Conclusions were providing house benefit to the users
And now at the Community Asset
Attractive people.
Apache
And they don't really see that walking over
4 *
They are seeing same as of myself right we're walking towards the equator
And yet. Of course for fast-growing companies right now we still want to keep them to your life I balance and we want them
Be careful
Not exhausted after yoga
Can we do promote to your house see
Your lifestyle in the company and what they officially in order to qualify you know
For the audience. Whoever interested in order to qualify officer
Limebike
You remember remember
Doubted criteria Seether you brought you able to run a half marathon or ride by 400
A hundred miles a hundred miles
That's what we are promoting as a company. Evil live a healthy life and work
Call something in Philippine and passionate about and later we were quote
So you have a pretty bicultural team
UFT members in China and then even many members
If your team here are Chinese
When your
Building a team how do you decide which departments should be staffed by Chinese members versus
Is American member
I offered them by saying your BD team has
A lot of
American members
And what are disadvantages and advantages created by
By having a cross-border
Yes in first of all. It is really
By what erroneous
You know by 8 what are criteria is really simple is what around me
If the road is more better understanding of the users and Market here but understanding off the
Fireman's carry
Danielle we need someone local
Irregardless
Chinese Dad we need someone
Really I just
And on the other hand not even look at some other engineering team
Doubt their role requires
Time to work
Close Lewis
Tell rather than yell put someone
Dardanelle family with
The cultural lag
Which outages
Just natural
We have tried to speed up engineers in China
Because he's working with
On the bike
I'm swimming muscles
Right so most of the hardware L and
Find related firmwares out the time in China
Order software
Especially.
It was. To give us the pass off the
We have a strong
Hardware capability
And also weird that I was overrated
Retarded
Design from
Growing up
War
Number of the American use in your company's I tried to localize them
Can you see where character in Darien CT
Different behavior is on
You know where do you live
But that's how we deciding all
What kind of
Personality Warcraft
Tears where hire for each other
Elations and you heard Toledo
Yuan cross-border team War national team
Global TV
Invite you in. Also looking to and learning from other car
Corporations
Y'all. From the moat even even we can go with you your hundred years back and look at the traditional
Trading Company
Rhonda technology company shipping whatever it is
So we need to what you need to get over someone
Language challenges the minimum wage
Did a culture difference is the way you know of doing things and also
How to align.
All together rally you know to watch for sale
Got it we are all we have
I think the idealist same as like of course
Cross-border aspec outfit
The challenge
Always comes with gravy
Reward if you can overcome
And that's
You know the 9 theater schedule we have is
. literally
Did the US team Hanover
Thule China team at night
Yeah they walk on it
Right on over at their night time exactly is morning here
Yeah I know. He's a lot of advantages to go into equation in terms of Pi Hardware design manufacturer
They're together and functioning
West
Dia software
Here
That gave us a
And we were able to go either way.
Hardware so fast
We're able to
You don't need a software and also you know
Linked out and walking clothes
For you you have been doing passporter activities
Pain management
For for a long time
When did you move back to the to come to the US
Twerk
And how long will you be
In
Doing cross-border management
Before you start it
Limebike
Before you start
Yeah I moved
The over in mm
Breathe
Yeah and but that's for my MBA program
Crisis why was India Arie
Space
Auntie auntie
Plies I wanna be you know
Thank God I wanted to learn
Where is Santa
The reason that I applied
And we think that's who you're not already
Yahoo
Company Murdock
Peaks of otter Yahoo that was the time and I was the only international student Linda off
Official NBA program I was the only one.
Attic apt
For another six
I walking on
Naturally
Working with some
At a time and enjoying the
Tansen Nepal crash
Now that was a
Lego August 2006
Doesn't by unknown company
Publix
Small cap market cap
Write about 5 billion 4 billion
700 million + 5
Yeah but that the stock price was like
$4
Allison but today is 450
Turn in 90 billion dollars that's right
Chaoyang beijing Grill
And even today.
Masswildlife
Company anywhere in the world
Call join. Company take Apple pay
It all and they don't have a structure keep my options right
Yeah everyone think I was crazy
Went to I feel like the same year
Yahoo ask
Guadalajara's company at that time
And isn't that you know what excites me
Is walking on the international ax back of it and why do believe that the
Global vision and the insights plus the local knowledge will be very
Very powerful
So that's a senior really attracts me into the dead taking the DL
Positioning at 10 says I was there for eight years and starting with I was the first employee protest outside of China and feel pretty
Much everything from
Grand.
Audio Tucson
13. I loved
And I was running
44 years
And jump a message
Outback
You know the startup work
Any company that's working the transportation space in the US and was in China
Regulation obviously a huge part of the equation
Yep
Copa 19
Mostly
First generation
How do you
Work with the local government Authority
To see you as an ally
As someone who can put my solution to their problem
And win them over and how were you able to do it so effectively
You such a short period
I think that the first of all.
Outer facing you know you know you know what you're facing image of
The company released
Viento
As a founders
You know I didn't. I also thought I was facing you
Yo how the company is structured how to
Companies
High speed
That's why I asked
Who are the
A company in Echoes water outside
Earlier
That our couple relationship and
ATM. Aldi Nevermore
You know I love
Call person but also to have
Combined as fact
Always adopt
It has the credentials as the
Stations
And they are
The face for the company
Diet for diarrhea
Default
Key to the CDs at 2
Are there speed and meanwhile. A little air pump from company perspective.
The companies
You know you asked
Register to hear headquarter here US ambassadors
You got me so ever seen yes. It all for the company is that
100% Local Company
Is it happened to be
Adiel
Tijuana to Fonda
Which is
Going to get you out at all right
So
I have not experienced in the past dealing with cross-border managed by
And building teams that way
What do you see as the advantage
That makes you guys can be so much better
Here in the in the US
Nat Turner
There's not that many tripe
Datong company or bike sharing bike
With a company
That's expensive so quickly
That's quickly
Republic Services trash
What is a company
Ever in history of
So how do you turn this cross-border angle knowledge
And
Approached
To your foundation makeup
I wish I would have talked about this into you two ways
One of them is
OBD2 protocol
Operations in the transportation business and evolves hardware and the software and services
Slayer tour
And myself
Wallapop not sure about all this knows about it you know
Engineer before
I'm not on front window
Italian China right and I need the the production industry has to be
Expanded form there
Across the itar country right but my background. I'll be watching and observing that's ever see
Since I was a cat
And China has being accumulated
The production capability in the last two decades
Right U turns off like they're high
Scale and low cost and high
High quality production
Onala them almost
How to made
Becomes a mage
Major brand
War becomes a global you know
Prices right
Outdoor Limited
And the reason being that I've spent a lot of time thinking and in the end it looking on.
Just looking at that dad what is missing
The missing too many tooth
Amazing
The brand
Daddy user I resonate with us and then recognize when they're missing Channel
I don't have
Thanks buddy some really deaf
Yandy
It's even challenging
Customer
Switch that relying on acid
The Asti
Artist
Like Walmart like new Costco like
But they cannot easily go there and challenge
Customer
It's kind of a a package
Carrie Wright
It was a sauce. Evil ways to cross-border aspec outfit
Dad we got first we got all the inside
You know off what was working what's not working
What could work
Le Paradis
Smok edible what can
Copied here
And Doctor inside help us a lot
Make decisions even look at them the bike itself right the mobike started
Wiz like it
Literally 6000 RV $1,000 bike
Angelus prayer
Gradually move
Weld on the way to what they have today at almost got it with the other end was like
Make $1 cheap bikes and then move their way up to the mid
LeBron that we started in the middle
That because of the Learning Center
Because we have the ability to manage Del course for the team that has anxiety and reputation
Impulse on both sides that were able to
New recruits will able to gather really high quality
Suppliers of honours to work with
Yeah we have the ability of course rating false
Thanks hands again
A lot
Opt out in when we've done look at it you guys for years. Why don't you
You know what what that translates into right we are leveraging the
Production capability. China
Accumulated
But you know where the Brandon Channel Kung Fu comes from we turned it
The broccoli into a service
Therefore we created
From the service and therefore we owns
The China World War
You are you fat
There's no choice
China Winter Snow Camp
The doubted you give us the capability
Did you eat already
Yeah
Create app
Provide
The products of a
Is that really fits
And on the other hand.
You goes to another angle off
Typing
Pennsylvania
Research and study of learning
About cross-border Scardino University
Back at work till we are to see
Really are us comp
He has made a big
In China market watch repair Market
You know Korea Market or Russian market right
What time Walmart
Coming the other way
As well
And we got to ask. Of Wyatt
What are the reasons that prevented
Do. I think they're many
Your languages were cultural challenges those other things.
Has to be talked about a lot on the softer side but they also the other things like
Decision maker
Process
IHOP
You know we say a
Coach of Defense soap
Dodd RV
Auto management team making a right
Enantia incentivisation Holiday Inn Sand flies.
Going to do something is different
Analyzing back to the manufacturer part is Daddy every success hats. I have
Has packages come with it and you disguised out of you guys mentioned on
When did trying to localize a product has been
Narcissist
The market for Newmarket
Which aspect of a
Culture
You know a spot 280
You will be much more
We just like grown up
Yeah he's just like you. All we ask you to talk about their house today is like
Building a house is much easier
And take much longer
You can put in a basket
And he's still not asking
Analogy same out here. You know applies to like eBay or early days with
Want to go to China that uses that workover company
That we have to charge a Cellars
Like their photos come company
Alibaba
The same thing applies again again the Bean Bean
Successful company and cocoa Supermarket but USA York
Y'all are naturally
Connected better and adulterous Battistelli easier
To copy Louis company to move to Europe has a very different culture that is about March
So I think it's got to be difficult for many of the year
Wow. You're not not to mention that whether they can ask fast as we are but
Jesse Jena weather
Successful
So in China One huge problem that we are saying is that bike sharing companies have
Create a proliferation of bikes that are just
Invading this public spaces in a lot of tiny cities there now littered with colorful bikes everywhere
From sidewalks
The parking laws so building entry
And some Municipal governments have you shoot orders to ban
Bike sharing companies from releasing new bikes
And also the dockless nature of your service means that people can
Practically don't them anywhere so how do you prevent a similar problem from happen
Play in the US
Yeah I took the three
Ways to look at that the first says. As a company that
You know that's one of the reason why we set up a strategy
You will work closely with us City
You stand up like
Galloway Rock
It stopped if I get their wisdom later
Visit Mission Ford account
Ward limebike
Is to drive more bike usage as a
Transportation what percentage of
Traffic but also to make our city Greener healthy area last
That's part of it is
DIA parking
So we walk with
The City Bark closely and also weed
Typically we do is crazy instead of dumping you $100,000 / 9
Got to work till a thousand this month and that gradually increases over time
Buy data
You know and demonstrated aware that the bias and how the weather weekend
And you don't hold onto
Isleworth service Library
That song from Diane
And from the user and I think it's more a puppy at
Location were working with cities
Do. You seem ask Daddy if you have a rental car you could have fuel rocket League
Pocket anywhere
Just because it's red
And there's no difference
Where is a rent
Raise more about education
That guidance
And the third part is on it
Technology side so we will work on you know you Santos
For the user
Do you sound advice.
Apakah more responsibilities as well as we walking on the abortion
No parking you know
Stop sore
Were you eating out guide
Applications
The user behave
No question I have is at
They are
Other startups here
Something similar
Minnesota Twins in China and trying to make
Also what mobile
Thought you're not so expensive
How do you assess
The strength of weak
You are a few
Appears
And
Is there anyone out there.
Impress you
Intense volume process
Walk depends on which angry look at them could it be good to be bad not so much
I think Dad has it as a business what you just read idea healthy competition is always well
And we
You don't see nada from the
Industry perspective or problem Adventure perspective
That's right. Every category
Doubt it will be expanded by the healthy cow
Competition as long as every companies will hold up I exactly and it was a much bigger
A party comes off the appropriate joke
Patience
As long as a child
Popeye the title company
Conditions causing diarrhea
Host the same value
We need. And you'll see where we going and really
Copied by
Teacher that two-division antibody
But not distract
Or not any leaks tracking
Ramadan
Ida healthy at computation unhealthy competition
We Embrace and we welcome all the help
Got it as long as we are you know driving more
Users to ride a bike and
Repetitively do not introduce tiia traffic Grand and Company mission
Just out of Willow for
Who do you think will win the bike sharing War in China
It's a little hard to say I think in China. The other the landscape is very different from you ask
Justia the Unicorn. Makes it will be challenging so the Bike Share
Wolpe the emphasize on the success of the bike shirts different
From here
Which does not support that so you end up in the end
The point
Will use acquisition Channel War
Water usage
Channel 4
It's right before example.
Payment
For example uibe
Appetizing workout
To Rice your
Yanny chin you are in China now that's the fall of the things difference and the second differences.
The bike-share company in China is a little bit
That. Hanzel of a tide
You no way. It cannot do
Mobile payment
Because that's already buy a test at both are you bothering this category try and they cannot really do Rideshare over
What can I do with a decision
They cannot really deal with you no food ordering delivery since there's may try and that's all am I in
They also share the same
UMass art and craft
Iodous acid for imagination
Rising theater
Not necessary outside to outside will be Camp I think they
Options
What choices will be parallel
Create something
Has anyone had someone
Really bad on the other what I see
And and a blue waffle
That's how I made was
And the reason being started we're just suck at you know that when I said
So we are forced to be more innovative
Anodontia came inside on a membership site all the things that never passed speed on YouTube
Analogy that applies here. Instead of a more natural to hate weekend
You know the bike sharing China can't do Mobile payment War
Food delivery is what what not that date their limited on those
Could be from where you know Vape
All about questions
In China Zoo Mansion tencent investor on the space liebeck mobile.
DD's investor in the space they backed oboe
Alibaba is investor in a small company
Which major role.
In the future
Nothing over here
In the US do you see
Big a company coming in sharing their traffic
Bike Shipping Company
Yes or no
And then the second follow-up questions.
If there's becomes don't come in in this space
Is the view as too far away from their equipment
He seems like you could build a business
Who's here
Linebacker build business here
The Heist people delivery
Premium Goods delivery
And other delivery thing
Because you may have some advantage in construction
Natural to a P2P Network
It's an imagination
Work
Blood bank here in the US
Much better than cookie for summer company
China
That's what I believe and that's what I hope for
We could do two deliveries will get back to you out of service categories we could even do mobile payments there just no
Predominant
Players
Space
Given the structure of a company worth
You know what the cap structure that you bastards we're not
Tied to anyone
But I ain't that smart.
And the Ant
On the first question I would
Maya quick answer will be yes I do
Transportation
DSA
Matrix
There's no one means
Cap fitting order
Blackwater use
The partnership
Got to work
You know some kind of
Company that offers them all and then think this case but I
You don't think that it will be more to write your company share you don't traffic or user
To us
I think he's more likely
The other way around
How about people think that
Usbank Walmart bikes and markets too small
Your most natural exit is to
Set resale to a
The Chinese guy that's much bigger
But if you look at history for someone like me 20 in in in China
The end up developing five six seven different businesses
Annies
Kind of
Absentee to each other all increase the
Purchase
Frequency
Of their consumers inside the maven app
Apartments are we inviting you
It's because we thought you can build something that's in multiple a multiple business line
Beyonce's bike-sharing in the usn
That's you know you and I both have done BC
Before
Having the ability talk about having the ability to see data points from
More than one market
How the help you
Do you think through your investment
And now
Operating strategy
Yeah I sent that that part is actually very valuable
What we think about the strategies that will. E
The diagnostic data points or the brass
Soft understanding of the industry
He is very helpful
I'll figure out a strategy that focuses on
And there are many, there are many companies in deposit is not
It all
It's not a sad Italian wrong strategy will went out but they're not a focus enough
Record face
Every single moment of
Start up
Daughter weokie
Resource-constrained
And every single moment that our decisions could make or break the
And we need to
To make sure that we understand what they are
Gotta get it right
So the data points was
Bear Valley fire
And then on the other hand. We described it icing has a nice sharetea, off.
The
Cross-border inside
Help us to
You know we have a little bit crystal ball
To see what happening
In the future and you know this bizmoto has
Invalidating pretty Wily China what you hasn't happened here we are working on that we see some early signs but it's too far away
Conviction
Is coming from
Same as a 20 DM pretty sure when
Started to eat
China repair companies
Is Wilbur Wright as a match baidu
Who started
Yeah there is no aspect
Globovision
And a local s
Audibly benefits a lot of
From that and also matter-of-factly wouldn't you to get out across the entire team
Died last month we took
The entire company
To China and spent a few days Dairy
See what's
Happiny
What has
You're sort of the end result
In China
And how use are utilized
Shifted
The user's Behavior was the densities availability affordability accessibility
And I'm weak
We are invited to your ex
Belvedere II
Yeah sure whizzle our team
What if they haven't seen what has four
Doug mistakes Waterhouse
Be the best practices so we're as a company we're willing to
Even
Revising the team by taking that tire company
Put a job down and go to
Just a few years ago people were talking about C2C or
Copy to China
But now we're starting to share the opposite copy from China wear a lot of entrepreneurs are taking busy
Tomatoes from China
And applying it to the US
And I think dockless bike sharing is an example of that
I wonder what other examples of
Are you from China that you
I've seen recently
They're actually a lot
Across different Industries
I think it's not really you know a
I think General categorisation off like coffee from where to where the year of
Tumi
Is that Lil Bit to generalize
God what I see is that each of the market because stood devolving
Unevenly
Dodger Stadium date
Foster
Define innovation
Yan in this case.
Even today's.
Water
So nobody is leading all the way is a Medicaid services
Core technology
And those are the things do a lot of innovation
You coming from here
Buffalo China.
What three aspects of I've looked in the past decade were
Till YouTube
Case right you'll number one thing is really just me
Is China LeapFrog
You know from the LED light cell mobile environment mobile economy
Yes Deimos Advance because of that I can see here. Are you ask
ASL most advanced country
Adoption off the mobile
Had to pick any what's really slow guy just because of the Legacy.
Who carries
And that's one thing in a second thing that I didn't quite a lot of Innovations
In the past with China because I don't sizing is not enough to support in the
You know you are as I think in your husband I probably see a lot right
Ask Dad he started to say what's your base model 70%
Enough to support Facebook Twitter Google
You know you name it
Topix 708 off 10 are based on Advertising
And the other two
Copy of a peso
We're asking China desk that category just never be big enough there's Baidu yes I love it
You know there's a few more but other than that right
Every company has Dewey Nova
Alibaba
Novation is driven by the industry and therefore hasn't came up with like membership West
You know avocados are Wiz
Free to play games
What is it in the year
And if they're seeing what look at it is
Exactly why the bike-share yeses
Stress off
You know you just
Strength of nature
And that's
Production as Hardware you know
Still all the kinds of things
Yeah he's hot tools
See
China will be like say we are
You don't want much more advanced
Smartwatch
May not Nassar beat a DNA while taking me to watch while but I understand that the science fair
Understanding of data
This case is
The production
What what in the industrial unit capability
Becomes core
Octopus
It's dip the battle is not one who has the
Bass looking
Design off the bike
You know ability to
Scalable high-quality
Low cost
Good enough as a pet
Ablation not necessary to
Peter Ferrari
So you this case this is reflection off the strength of the English
Generalized
What China is innovating
Because of those
Yeah you a c Xenoblade
Because.
You know you still fishing he rebuked
Because coach her here and all. That's how I see it in some of the examples.
Free-to-play game is being one of them's ever since like
Mm
Safe to have 7 years
And that has to be
Gradually becomes a main main track
Quick speech at a wallaby conference data fall like free
Would you play all that I once loved
Is cheap since you charge her $0.10 for item
Value companies Cortez that that's a real comet
In the second, we got inside
Youth small company makes more games
We make $60 box
Speaker inside
We all die
And that's the philosophy in it
But after. We see you
We've seen what happens
Facebook
Pokemon losing
That's why I love a big trap and when we Imagine Dragons people.
Understand what we're doing
You keep that away. Game
Why the game only last 5 minutes
Is that off of our session
And that's a driven by
Diu Novation
China at 12
Xlnt it later on. There are at again
A wish is another example appellate right-of-ways yes
Because they have a kid
Capability access
Chase Burton
Music
Fleas on a
Community
Community operation
Community running this is Sparta
Different from the HDD
Kind of like it
Typical
Can a company ask
And dadaism
Yeah I would say is that
Novation
From China
But I think it will also will talk to companies like Facebook
Or you been
Co-founders
PayPal coinbase
Everybody's looking at a WeChat
Source of inspiration
How that impacts how they roll out
Mobile payment related services
Or
Improving their messaging platform
I'm more ecosystem
Utility app
People are
The smarter people in a valley
More more Progressive in their thinking
Increasing looking at best practice
Naviance
Just that what
History. Morey is a kind of
One-trick Pony
Yell getaway
It's a good thing
Dalian forecast
But meanwhile. If you do see.
Want some really well but I can go pee
Entendido I had a little bit how time you know.
Tried to describe what times I asked you on kazoo variety of things yeah we're like Facebook
Plies
AOL class Yahoo's messenger + Yahoo news + a
Please RN
Restonic came inside and Plaza blah blah blah
Died at someone wanted to squadmate want
Yammy X
Yelp last post made profile your Groupon for sale
Central Bond
Core value
Author uses what they
Do
You make the user
Is life better
That's how we tended to look at
Things that swell
That picture will be the foundation
Doom for switch
But we help them
Their life
From there
So let's go into the final part of this podcast
Which is a quick-fire round of questions
The first one is
An entrepreneur that you admire the most and why
What prison is a maybe a little controversial board is Warren Buffett
That I think. He holds on his value he's being a very
You know in time
His whole life is
Andean
Greedy
Naataanii analyze
Stupid also
Sapporo Japan
And that was the inspiration why I founded
Interesting
Next question something you read recently
The tattoo person
Oh I've read a lot I'm in a household a Tyrese
Vera Bradley
Touched quite a bit
You know on the feedlot philosopher lavaland on the science level and Orlando different things
I think they're
I want to say to both
Started retouchme windiest
It's called a man's search for the light
And it's a very a live account
Commercial about really
What a
Human being
Sustain
Why they can't
In the hole
Glass back outfit
Right and also what
Believe
Those are the scenes
Dad
Supports people
Yeah and Dad and also supports them to
Triode means
Look at what
What has
Said meaning to them
So that is
So you know Moana
Most reliable
Aorta
Cioppino or a veggie
Work so hard
That we don't need to
Honestly smoked
So hard why we devoted ourselves
That's why we
Do you think it's not necessary
Diu no
Like
Hey. That is one book that I would
What I say
Touch me quite a bit
And the other Focus
Not necessary
Touch from the emotion side but more from Orr
Probably everyone Brad
Has
You know right about it
Are the companies I've been doing
Start up quite a bit I started High School
Accounted at one time
Is a 7
Startup I have
Yeah some of them failed write something
Moderate successful O'Neal pays for
What is tuition for my vacations as well as being really good
And
And upon reading. Book
Danielle
That gives him more
New meaning of
Creating a company
How is CO2 produced
Doing things all day
You know
Just make you Financial returns
Are they really just
Keilani for associate
Impact a day
You know here to help a group of uibe
People to
Monster career
Pushing the world forward and the answer is really daddy no
Combination lock
High-end a combination of wall and then becomes another way
Religious
Delete and that's what I have is business is
Sebastian
Best way to
To not only
You know you need to
Friends of families
Thule Society
Hours
And you would have to do that
Danielle Duloxetine
Observation
How do we
Pompeii the ROM
Icon is 3 a free app is
You know what's a ride
Fundamentals
Weston Ryder
Fundations the last part is
The forecast today
Why do we fall
The way I see it is.
You know the fundamentals
Are really
Division
Is what are the salt
Problem word
We're solving
Eastside Realty
So many start of reconcile
The right is a fake
Pekingese
Fake problem to try to solve it doesn't really matter
Yeah you got going to snow are we
Trying to
To do something.
That's valuable are we trying to solve a real things
In the foundation release
The company
You all. It is more on the on the
Listen
Set up a structure wise
Can we have the right setup for the
To be realized
We have the wrong
You Masters if we have the wrong you said
Structure people have the wrong
Culture that you will not work regardless. How great
Yes regardless that would work
Ended lossing the forecast
I think it is more
As a compass
Funny God.
No matter how big a company is right as big ass if you don't Google or Facebook
Tencent
The density of resource
Should focus on
Y'all not only with your focus on winning the battles we need to but also that is a response
Sportway 40
Employees
. their time is
Are many companies account via the
Employees has
You know good life but their time
Is Weston
Start learning Tanakh religion
Next
Question is what is something you believe in that most people may not
The last question
Yeah
Actually a lot
People may not
Your daughter things I don't believe I don't believe in Social
That's one thing I think of diu
If anyone looking to the history
Enough
And looking till
You know what happens in the Humane Society
And in that you know that a lot of salt
Needed work
Kafka
For the era we're living there many of them.
Dusty's not was not true in the past
It may not hopefully the future
Yeah. You want to have
We will I be living catalog
People doing
You know me.
Everyday you work
Wakonda document
It's not right
Whatever
You know I mean political environment
Intrinsic value it is
That's it works for certain. In time doesn't mean that it has a
About to be on that particular
. even even
The society
Good Lovin by some of them does not
Have I do today
And they will just
Keep on doing the same
Closing all time without thinking about it what
It's behind it but I think that's why
Pricing as I optimistically you know ultra-premium
God I
Do believe
Kind of long-term
Lot of people would say they do
But in reality you can look at action they take
Deduct
It takes your car.
U-Haul Valley was a lot of Maureen
Assured
Short term advance
Engaged
Body Darby
So. It I think it's a little bit controversial how to say you be asking anyone nobody will admit it
But I have to charge it from
I think. Do you know that something why I mentioned Warren Buffett
It's a long-term value and also D at the fundamentals of those Valley
You know someone say everyone will say
God damn we've seen.
And then
What will be the third example
I'm something that you believe in our people.
Sky
I do have a lot
And I do believe that the
Diversity this is a little bit difficult to explain that I do believe in diversity
The value of diversity and Dad how decreased
You know I ditional value summer leave immediately could it be
You know the CEO dlc about where you can
Appointed to some of David
Ryan tangible and also it takes time
Yandina human history right we can't even go from like when the time will
Human
Becomes
Walk out the woods and becomes human
And history. That was
Place of cyclical
Controlling there
Any
Society in history task me isolated any society that is not embracing that that was your part of it
Atrophy over time
I pretty much gone
Yeah. That is something that I I believe in but not necessary everyone
The end. That is something that from the history perspective we said that results in from wherever
Lucian
We know the reasons yeah
From the reality
Perspective died we
We cannot already tell you know what's adding value and at some point idea did diversity
Also means uncomfort
Add means.
Uopeople
What Kumar engineered what do you know that where you feel uncomfortable
With thanks. If you're not familiar with
But not the most scary is not a problem to your master or not
How do you spell Moana
And doubt as that uncomfortableness and therefore there are people
Will not embrace
Diversity
But but I will say believing there then you won't be more
You know I'm crazy and tolerance some of the differences but look at it
Topeka Value Place
Not easy
Thank you so much for a for it being here with us
Sound we can wait to see limebike grow
Thank you great to be here at such as fun this conversation we have a lot of similar values and
Makes it easy to work together as partner so I bring we're very fortunate to have a chance to be part of your journey
Thank you
Good afternoon
Thanks for listening to this episode of 996
By the way
We also produce a weekly email newsletter in English
Also called 96
Food restaurant up of the week's most important happenings
Intec in China
Subscriber some tortoise food
Informative
And fun to read
And you said also features original content
Analysis
From Zara
Ami
Stripe at nine 6
. ggbc
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
2p IPO with 3.8 billion dollars in capital under management real estate funds
GTA V invest in globally minded entrepreneurs in consumer internet
E-commerce
Frontier tax in Enterprise
GTA V has invested over 280 companies
With 29 IPOs in 22 unicorns
Pergola companies include
Airbnb
Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing
Domo
Hashicorp hello bike
House
Cheap
Slack
Square
Hotel
Wish
Challenger
White white and others find out more at Gigi bc.com
Do you have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas
Bisimoto
I-96
A gbc.com
This podcast is co-produced
Balfron
Campus partners
Kaiser kuo
The host of the wonderful sinica podcast
It, China's economic
Political
And cultural issues