Vincent wrestler
Hi there
Welcome to the -6 podcast
Brought to you by Gigi Capital under show
Wintergreen movers and shakers
China's tech industry and discuss how Founders from around the world can draw that stands
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
I'm a managing partner at GTB capital and I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other emerging markets for the last 20 years
And a former journalist why is this show called 96
96 is the work schedule and many Chinese Founders that organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Chinese internet companies that produce many growth Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China we organize regular offline events across the world for Apollo
You can join these by visiting 96. Ggvc. Com
Imma show today we have Brian goo
Or cooking tea in Chinese
He's a vice chairman and present
Xpeng Motors
Also known as shell promoters in Chinese
It is a Chinese electric vehicle company
Energy portfolio
The coming designs
M&M factory
What is called internet cars
Which s a i technology
Immigrating to vehicles
Price of Johnnie Expo markers in March
Brian was the chairman
Of a Cyprus investment banking
@jpmorgan
He joined JP Morgan in 2004
And it's hella variety
Leadership
Rose instrumental
In asia-pacific
Is 14 years at JP Morgan
That his team arranged very sizable fundraising deals for Chinese Tech Giants
Including
Most notably Alibis 25 billion dollar US IPO
Before joining JP Morgan Brian worked in the global m&a and Global Healthcare practice of Lehman Brothers in New York
From 1998 to 2004
Before working on Wall Street he was a senior research scientist at the University of Washington Medical School
He holds an MBA from YOLO
A PhD in Biochemistry from University of Washington Medical School and a bachelor's degree in chemistry
The University of Oregon
At Expo Motors
Brian Lisa company's Global strategies Finance fundraising Investments and international partnership
Welcome to the show Brian
Thank you pleasure to be here
So first question is
Shuffle Motors after 20 years in Investment Banking what was the thinking behind joining a car company
Well I think after 20 years banking I definitely was looking for something different than what starting to do
I think I was fortunate to witness the rise of Chinese Industries
What was my tenure at JPMorgan last 14 years
I work with lot of the leading companies
Particularly
Audible.
World class companies
And I think I might
Cease my career
I would love to join a company that could also have the potential to
To be one of the global leaders
I really
Experience the rapid growth inside the company
In Elsa during this
Intrapreneurial rice
Set alarm
And also you know obviously you're joining xpanas
Is is a decision I made looking at both the sector and also look at the
The team and Company
I think you know the
Electric vehicle
Combined with the AI and also the
Thomas driving phenomena
Is a huge game changer and I think brains
Tremendous potential Iowa state from a timing perspective
We're looking at
Explosion happening at the moment
And also obviously
Chapel himself
Play someone I
Known for many years so I really
You know
Identify the way he think about the future and he's
Capabilities as a leader
For our audience
Who may not be as familiar with Expo Motors
What will give me some background on the company
It was co-founded
By Harry Shaw and hotel
Former senior executives
Guangzhou Auto
Is named after its chairman
Rochelle pump
A former Alibaba executive
In the founder of ucweb
Which was also a Tuesday
Before the company
My partner side
Teaching and Jenny
Back to you
Ucweb together we have all known him for almost 10 years
UC bible.say mobile browser company that was
Acquire body type of 13.8 billion dollars
As what's the largest meteor ever in Chinese in the industry at a time
After acquisition shopping became the president of Alibaba mobile
Business group
And later serve as president
$2 and Audi
In August 2017 shopping left
Officially join Motors
August 29
SC off of starter
A lot of outside
Urged on by my colleague
Motors is headquarter
In Guangzhou
It has raised over 1.5 during.
Since this is awesome
In 2014
It's investors
Alibaba
Foxconn
Hell House
Primavera
Morningside
Gdb
So bright how did your first meet cell phone and did you think it makes sense for him
How to join a car company full-time as a former internet except
Velocity was a
Interesting story
Because I mess up on
During an ex
Expedition
Iceland
I was actually a trip put together by
A friend of ours who is also a venture capitalist
And then I think a day
Organize a trip for a number of entrepreneurs
Achoo
Experience
See you in awhile Dennis
Niceland I was the only non intrapreneur in that group
But in a spending 10 days in
I would say soul of the Wild
In Iceland
And I
Stay in cabins
BBQ
I think it gave me a chance to really get to know the individuals for a while
Eyeshadow with one of these
Started forming a bomb
Since that trip was probably four years ago and we ask
In touch for a long time
Yesterday show me
Investment in
Explain Motors I also be following
And
All the way to 2017 When shall come himself
Decided to leave Alibaba
To join Exxon
A truancy of all time
Yes it came to my house
He had a drink in our route
I Hong Kong
And you know he asked me in a without Beach
U-joint cell it took me
A few months to think about it but the more I
Considered the
The opportunity and what I think about you know both the sector the company and individual
I feel this is the musty opportunity for myself so I join
In March
So we all know that China is the world's largest
City Market in Ashley accounted for
For 6% of Global TV sales
4th quarter of 28
And by the end of 2018
Electric vehicles made up 7% of all new vehicle sales
Thanks to a mix of government in March
Enforces the TV Market is now extremely heated with hundreds of startups in the space in China
What do you think differentiates
Expelled from the rest
What are two things you mentioned I definitely agree
I think the first thing is that he he
Presents
One of the sexes
Aldi's Factor
With scale
With explosive growth
And also was
Almost
Certainty that the changes going to happen
So that that's something I agree with your sister
Second
When I think we were just asking this
It's also a competitor
You know you mentioned are hundreds new startup
Joining this
House of movement
I know I think of you know they all cops you not responding startup
Spectabilis tow companies
Existio yams
Trying to do
Alexa vehicle
However I think of what
Cell phone or Exxon doing definitely is a
We're not just focused on making electric vehicle
You know a lot of the Stardust actually
Are people who came from the original OEM
And their vision
Aldi Roanoke
But ideas just to make Maybe
Cheaper or better electric vehicle from a gas engine
I'm because of the unique DNA that she'll pull himself trained to the business
As well as
Type in a unique starting point
In off the venture
Excel Motors actually set out to
Scenic Design
And built not CD but I smart intelligent
Thomas driving
We are one of the very few I would say
Are the startups a she does I'll Hardware
Software
Autonomous driving oil
Are we can leave in a integrated capability
We believe that in order to
To provide the best product
Experience
To deprive ourselves
Customers
You need to own all these three pieces
Gbreb Manufacturing
Supplies for the software
Thomas Drive
And also we do differently from some of the other startups is that
Started
Focusing on Balaji
Sacramento
Auto market
Which is Middle C
Al Price Point
Is actually
Is pubg targeting us the largest
Selling price point segment
Chinese
Passenger.
So you know in like a some of the penis
I think we want our technology to be used and enjoyed by
The mass Market
And I think
Our technology differentiation
In this segment will be
I sleep very bright
A standout
Apache off
Soex phone calls itself an internet car company
Set up a
Evo electric car
Yeah so what is the difference between in my car any electric car
And how does Shopkins background
As an intern executive for a long time
Become a differentiation
Yeah so this is actually a very
Interesting question
So when we launched our these three which is the
.... Car in December
Delivery
For a number of opinion leaders
In Industry to
Here there definition what
I ain't in that car or small car intelligent
Looks like
Everybody
So that means that there's no
Absolute definition with a smart car
It's
But what we plead that make
I'll call carsmart
Can I just be in a someone with a big screen and you can
And also the past some sort of a application features
You really need to get up so early design a vehicle that
And Ashley learn
Respond
And provide you with
Experience
So I think my mind has three elements of a vehicle
Ontology
They need to have in order to
Qualify
To be called
Smart car
What I think you know that
The car self should have a deep learning capability
Suidae in traction
Exchange with driver
Example in our current vehicle that was telling
How we can use voice
To come in the car
The cock and learn your preferences
Your route
Listening to type of songs you like
Are you actually and I have some driving
Patterns inside
Sold car can I sleep
Become smarter and understand you better by spider services in
Ximena productivity
So that's a first degree
Inside of you
The second people reacting to qualify car to be smarter I think
Is the ability to do OTA
I think a lot of cars now claimed that he have
Over-the-air upgrade kit ability
But if you look at them some of those capabilities mainly just to upgrade their
Screen application
But I think I'll be more
To make a call Trudy smart you have to be in much deeper than that
Right now I was saying them with your teeth
ECU electronic control unit
Can be upgraded over the year
And our next model
Even billing
In April we actually anticipate you have 100% of our ecu's to
OT aide
So that's a second thought
And I think the sopot obviously is your Thomas driving kit
So in order to make a Car Smart
He has to be able to
How to learn how to fly the South
Are we actually a very proud
To say that our current selling model G3
Is probably the only domestic
Manufactured volume produced model in corporate self develop
Selale Thomas Drive
And that's something I can
I think I won't make her
Also smartsilk
All those three capabilities I can I think a car
Can be truly called a small intestine bigger
So I wanted to talk about your personal background where did you grow up in
Why did you go to the US for Middle
Clapping sound
I actually I always tell my
Friends
I'm probably the
Il Vicino the lot of shinies that she came from different cities
But my grandfather my father and I are growing same Hospital in Shanghai
So is that
So you mentioned I actually left Shanghai very early my rolling
A year's time I went to the US when I was 12 years old I actually
Spent two years in us for Middle School
And then
I came back to
To China High School
Because I Fall to my mother who's a business daughter the time
So she could have time to China
App to see your sister
After High School I decided to go to the US to college again
So I went back to Oregon to cut my undergrad degrees
And then
Washington to for my PhD
So my
First phase in my Curry always want to be a scientist by study biochemistry
I was fascinated by signs
Obviously because my family
Are all scientists
My mom was Ashley
Camas
So when funny story is that
When I started in Oregon
Before I walked into my first class
They already had me and she said your major is chemistry
Who asked if the kids is for me so I actually
Because my mom's back law so she thought that was the
The best subject to study
So I studied biochemistry and then attack on my PC
I decided that I want to do something different I
Felt that you know the scientific training was
Thanks tithing but I feel like I want to do something that is more
People eating people and Thomas
But I do know what I want to do so I went to
Steuben School
Portraits
70 gal
I got my MBA Palmdale school management
And at Yale like
Got to learn about
I know the finance side of the business
It is east coast.
Not a people focus something came in and asked
Naturally Iceland
Ended up
Joining
Out of business
So
In a few years actually I was
What's in New York
I was at Lemans
My focus has given my background about chemistry
I thought I would definitely make a cookie
Housekeeping
How much I spent probably five-six years focused on Healthcare
UST global companies
Decided to
Return to Asia
+ 2
Really
I saw the opportunity
China
Booming and also I think banking sectors
Transformation
So I decided to
And Joint Chief Morgan
So in China
We started seeing a tradition
Developing
Populace educated
Investment Bank
Underscore find
Professionals joining a top internet companies
Executive
Such a smart allow tencent
Or just high of Alibaba
Horchata
Child of Athena
You join Xbox Auto
It's also could be another example
Obviously in case of Martin and Joe and
Charles
Welcome to Bo
Turn to 10 2nd and Audubon see National Maple Grove
International credibility
What do you see
That's your role
And contribution at the expense to be like
Golang for
And now that you've been there for a year
What are the some of the
Interesting surprises
Or adjustments. You have made
So far
Well I think Martin and Joe and Charles actually they're good friends mine and I really respect what they had
Have accomplished
Thank God they took different type of risks
Awesome
Went into the industry by earlier
Young
Stage Sand Company
Diamond State
Somebody joined Aphrodite on the
But along the way they have
Made
Medicine practice
Hyundai respective businesses
I think that this is definitely something that I would love to do a text to Motors
I believe that Evie is a global
Industry
And then
It's also a cross-section of malt
Disciplines that can patch make it work
Put sample
It's not merely Auto
It's not merely
Technology company
It's not merely operating
Service
Company
It could also have
Financial element
Tu sonrisa
I see it's a very interesting about complexity
And I feel like my background
Being in the banking sector for
70 years
Seeing the development of many different success
Companies
And also understanding the global
Nature of
Dealing with
Partners
Investors
And in the company's active
I believe I can bring
A sense of global
Tooth business
The same time I think
Expand
Addis
Stage of growth
Needs to connect by closely with
Capital markets
And that's an area
Tremendous
Experience
So I think we both in the near-term and the mountain
I would love to contribute to the vast
Gross
Antebellum
Call the company
And also similar to those friends of mine who actually has done success
Spleen in tencent Ali Baba in Encino
I hope one day you know in my contribution kinster
Expand to be one of the global Giants
If I push the point this point little bit further
Operation side
What kind of things would you want
Swimwear Thailand
It's at the international
Partnership
If so what can a partnership is
Is possible
BM. What are the other areas of Interest
You to spend timer
Well I think the first order of business for us is to make sure we are firmly established as one
One of the global
China leaders in the moment
In the EB space all the intelligence
Maybe space we want to have that
In the mind of
Global Investors
The club
I would say
Soul Eaters
And global
Strategic
So that's an area I would love
To spend more time
Cultivate
Establish
Also I think young company which I think I have
Haven't asked you a question
What I see in the young companies
Amanda
Tremendously
Interesting
And a how a young company evolve
You won't know that until you're inside the car
I think there's a tremendous learning power of the executives around me alot of those
Puppy have not
Come through
Large companies before
But they have lot of innovative ideas
Pistos
Good ideas
In a structured manner I think it also takes experience
An organization
And I think that's also an area that I would like to
Make sure we I contribute
Because my background experience in logic
Two companies
I think I also in terms of two
Provide the
The global I was a prospective a lot of things we do
Also can influence the direction of company's business
IOS development
As well as business model us elections
So these are as I think I hope to also
Shape with my involvement
I'm sure that's why I
BB saara
Choose to join him home early on
So now that you've been there for a year
What has a price
Like I said I think
What surprised me most is
How talented and how
You know I would say
How large the potential to learn in a for the young soccer
Does Rami
Because you actually
And you can't unlock company you always felt that
Okay we have seen a lot we know a lot and
We actually
Rakitic them you know how to do things
But you know China I think I specially was
At the talent surrounding us
But they have
Real good
Common sense in business judge
The Ashley has very innovative ideas
And actually you know there
Ability to learn
Also
Tremendously powerful
So I think
What's the price of me most is actually I realize that
You know a lot of time.
Me and I love showing them how to do things
The proper Aldis of the global
Are the
Biscay way in the electric company
Actually I'm learning from
Call Ashley
We can't do more Innovative things
And how we Act
Boys fishing
So I was best
Surprised by my own learning
Example
Noches user is 1.
In a traditional company innovation
You know you look at the ashes
Selling a product
I think I heard there's a lot of the analysis
We have to go through
Inl so that
Standard channels
She actually
APUSH and understand in the market
Almost at Playbook
But I think I know there's a lot of innovative
Measures to react
Put into our business
WhatsApp not in sync
Example
Nobody in the past
Other than
Tesla
Enough people doesn't click and buy automobile
Right and it because it's something
It's a larger purchase item
People want to test
Feel it
Aprotic we actually try to break down
Processed into
To Tupac
We want yesterday
Efficiently levity
Online and internet
So the the traffic
And the peel
And defend based approach
To generate excitement
The same time
We actually are directing that and funneling.
Physical
What should we do it ourselves
Enlarged City
Which is not a thing before
Ian Ashley China
When we actually sell
Automobile
A lot of times I think that you bring and you have exactly who come from
La Jolla company
BMW all from other automatic makers
Ashley
And I was saying
Blown Away by
How Innovative some some of the things that we're doing here
And I think we have results to show for it because if we actually look at
Foot traffic
Coming to our showroom
Tattoo by hour
A product
What is 50% of despotic acid
Convert online
So which is actually a lot more efficient way than rely on
Just regular traffic inside a shopping mall
All the
Physical stores
So I think these are things that we're doing
Hopefully in differential cell
That you have all your own stores
Not
Dealers or channels
Right so I think I for a young company with a product that is
Spell different
And also we want to have a direct connection with our
Customers
Direct stores is on The Rifleman
However if we
Scale-up and if we ask you one penetrate into
TS3 cure for other cities
I think that you cannot be old enough of your cell phone store so we will also explore Partnership if we decide to scale up
So I think we will always be
Looking for the fast
Model maybe it's a
Hybrid
You're too but right now we are focused on building
I spent stores in the large city
I definitely some similarities between your approach and how
Xiaomi
Start selling phones online
And I'm open xiaomi stores
Offline
So it is definitely a In-N-Out
Inspired
Model
Yeah well you know
Shuffle himself
Isometry ISO
Innovating The Truman Show me used
To be Ashley
The chairman of UC
Who sell
You know I can shop on
You snitching has one of the mentors so
Are we if we want to
Received from
A successful model I shall meet which also very Innovative in the way they do business
However I think
As a car
The products by different from a smartphone
Also we need to
Chica model
To make sure that you actually addresses some of the
Pain points for Auto
Assertive
Customers
So that's why we actually a compliment
Nude protest
From my perspective
Seeing call
Bank of China sell clothes online
But they weren't able to open up the stores offline
Can you sell it
And then few years later
Legion
Waco with their selling phones online
And the tribe
Stores offline
And then another few hours later you guys want to do that in auto
Each time
Talents being taken
Hard
And before
Show me something. Even Google fail
And then before you got to do that not many others
Baby besides of Tesla
Each time Chinese founder
Breaking new grounds
Super exciting
Absolutely
Social problems G3 car was released in December 2018 could you talk about what's special about this car and
Husband attraction
Volvo SUV
5 seater beautifully designed
How can show some pictures actually
It's a very sporty look sickly Target
Active
Drivers in large cities
And also
The car is packed with
Technology
This is
Car has the level 2 + autonomous driving features
Which means that they have full has plus some of level three
Teachers in Lusby Samara example
We actually have a full scenario Auto parking.
Betta Fin City compared to everything that's out there on the market
Our car can parking More than 70%
Different type of Parkinson's
In the parking lot and parking areas
Where is that compared to
Even Tesla
I will say poverty is one of the smarter cars
The only can identify probably less than 20%.
So we actually
Provide
A very unique
And targeted
Solution
2 hour driver
Are the car also has the ranch
Procharger
365 km
Which is already I was a sufficient for City use
The car has
Panoramic glass roof
To the model experience it also has one of the larger screens inside
That has a full control
Of the vehicle
Does not have
The traditional vehicles
Futuristic
And also was
Unique about cars that I actually drive our vehicle to work everyday
I don't even touch
I know the screen will control the window I use my in a voice command
So actually
The Voice Change is something that
Sweetie you know how is he different shading
Because we can actually
Select your music
Your lower your window turn on your
Offense or
Just your own
Seats for you and also yet will have also official recognition features was a AI camera
Dashie can monitor your
Whether you are
Distracted
Whether you're tired and you can monitor you
No heartbeat
So there's a lot of these cool intelligent features
Enough
Poor me know the price point that we actually are
Hitting as I mentioned earlier is
Very different
Compared to
Tesla other premium mod
Our cars price between 150000 to 200000
Which is less than half the price
Model sleep most basic model
Anytime around
2000 230
$3,000
Right so I think
We want to provide
A very different shade of younique
Product
Technology
To a segment
Is largest and a fast-growing
What what is the experience of driving
That car
Guanciale
Do you think China is equipped
You have
Like a lot of
People driving
In terms of
For example charge
Driving an EV I think it's
Baggies
Easier then
Other vehicles
No quiere
Go I think I was just three also is very easy to try and it's not
I despise someone
So we don't have the
Super fast acceleration
You know you asked me
Especially in the sodas 0 to 60 km
The reason I think people hesitate
To buy EV
I think the top reason is
I didn't know that
The distant anxiety
Is something that people always site
Which probiotic
Holistic
Charging solution 2 hours
Chivers
Chris Paul
Privai home charging
To whoever that has a bit capability to install home Chargers
I have dedicated parking space so they have to run
She will get them
Freon charge
Second thing is actually have
Our own proprietary supercharging Network
Best built in
Large cities that was selling a vehicle
No supercharging network only provide supercharged which is fast charger that
We designed Without Partners
And Spice
80% above charging for less than 40 minutes
So it's a very fast
Charging time
Likely to
In a pasta
That time in English
How many of those are there
So we have built
Close to 2000 of these charging stations already
We have to have been opposed to 200 by this
End of the year
Solution we have is our vehicle can
Be charged
Any of the third-party charging stations are charging companies or Papi charging.
China's you know is actually
Probably the most advanced systems building all the charging port
The government has already mandated
By 2020 to have close to finally charging piles
The wrong time
So means that you know it is going to have more charges
Pyle Center
The rest of the world combined
So the Chinese government has been closed
Billion dollars
Subsidy
What you said
Support for buildings
Charging station
In the build-out of a new energy vehicle industry
Between inelastic
But recently has been rolling back
Unsub
In some areas
How has this
The growth of
Spending money
Built this industry
Help to support this
And house
The comeback
Subsidies
Have any invite negative impact at all
On the sector
Yeah I think the Chinese government has been very very instrumental
Facilitating the development
Eating
So the subsidy mansion
The infrastructure investment or part of the effort
To really push China to be one of the global leaders
North Dakota
Easy
I think the Chinese dumpling is also thinking about what are the best way to
Supporting this
I need subsidy has been
Puppies
Last five years
Obviously GIF lot of the financial system to
Eevee maker
But the same time I think
Yet I created some Dynamic that encouraged
Lauren
Producers
Design and build products
That's not
The best product
The end of collecting subsidies
Which is not the right thing I need
And try to change the way these appointments be into boy fishing
Me
Example they are a lot of policies that not
Be implemented around Chinese large city
So
Eevee
Can receive
Place much easier than
That's one of them
I would say tribe
Easily
The cost of driving license
Secondly I think they actually
Are pushing the emissions standards
40 yams in
The cast in the world
So the emission standard become almost engine
Ashley
I will say bye
Some measures China's actual already ahead of Euro
Affording Mission standard
Require similar cities
I like YouTube and gas engine cost all together
So that is also some movement.
Pusheen
And also I think the continued investment into infrastructure is something
How to watch Leah
Foster development
So I think that they overall
Tall is lhasa Oprah
Support on the common
Contingency Bastrop
For ED
Young Beauty companies like
Exomotive
Want to make sure we take advantage of these
Support
I got the skill pack of subsidy
It's Sunday felt
By all the players
And we believe that
Ashley favors
Companies like explain why she focused on product design
A unique experience
Technology
Security
So the more
Customers are consumers focused on
The product itself
I think we actually
Getting out
Better
Advantageous
So an alarm
It's good for the industry
Should be one of the
The way that way
Define
G3 SUV
How many orders have been received and how
Delivery
So we started delivering she's three
In December.
I'm in the delivery obviously is a slow ramp-up
Process
If you look at me or another
Companies all went through the same thing
Pixie takes time to
The fact sheets to
Perfect
Supply chain saw
Spaghetti sauce
Specially at low volume
And I think we are going to start a volume delivery by
Later this month
Which is March 2019
We asked him to do
Delivery
Thousands multiple thousands
Arrange the next
A few months
I have daughters we actually have been
You sitting very exciting moments
Downloaders
We have more than
10000p Motors
Our in order
He's already stretched
Volume two
The second half of
And as you mentioned the Expo car is priced very
Competitively
23 - $30,000
Could you talk about why you're targeting this
Younger
Consumer group
Will first look at the Democrats
The Young
Define yam
Between 25 to 35
I think is actually the fastest
Growing
Driving route
And also we believe that age
These fibers
Immortan to
Try new technology new features
Naza maybe the first car
Some of those
I may have
The all the first time
So lot of times I think these people
Can truly enjoy and being bought
Without a clue
I think that's
Why isn't targeting those
Core user
Is OCD
First
Strategy
But again I think I'll once we actually
Can really
Put that precise positioning of a vehicle into the minds of these individuals
What customers that we can expand
The one interesting data point for you is that
If you look at the
The orders
That we have on hand
Given we have three trim levels
The basic form level
Which is without our autonomous driving features
Are we have to
Intelligent ring
Pudding.
And then the cops
Pop and
A 97% of all this Ashley indeed
Intelligent and
The top and
Which means that it's
You know our positioning and I will in a
People come to buy
Shop home cars
Is actually
Coming to us because
Halogen
Technology
So recently Tesla is also
Cut the price of its vehicles
In China significance
Do you think that will happen
First Tesla
Will bring model 3 and model y but I think it will take a little longer
Language is a similar size of our
A few years ago
And also I think
At the current stage
I think the
Are they going to bring to Market still going to be viewed as a
Premium segment vehicles
Even with local production
Play chicken nuggets
Baby Goku
Yet
I think they will be
Additional
So I think it's a vehicle well
Come down in turn price but still I think we're
Above
Pause placement
So I think of that competition yourself we will not feel to correctly
Because we got a second
But I think it's actually a good thing that you have a
Cook Pata, Chinese market that stimulates Chinese
Consumer demand
And anxious love
And sometimes we need high-quality supply chain
To the Chinese
Good for the development
We actually
Sing this is actually a positive
And I think it also given years another saying to the 3 or 4 years
We actually are confident that our technology
You know the user base
The vehicle on Street
We can accomplish
Better Futures more localized
Experiences
Anna, striving
Then Tesla so I think we're very confident that
You Belong With Me
Cheap welders
My last questions around
A different topic around town
Expo Motors
Carly has about 3000
Employees
Yeah this number
As you know in 2018 the company
Alone when you're added
Mm
Employees
74 Summit Rd
Shubble has said recently in Hold Us.
Plants to add
Dada 5000
New employees
I've been able to try to vibrate
Dover High Caliber
Yourself
So can you talk about a child poems
Calastrology
And water differ
Compelling profiles
That you guys are looking forward to add
Tubidy
As you know how many Apple listeners
Listen to our interview of a Chinese company
So hopefully
Everything you said today will be something
They'll help you attract more talents
So we actually have a very diverse
Employee
We have
Employees coming from
Over 200 different companies
So
It is great diversity we also have employees coming from over
OC a dozen different nationalities
And that's growing really fast
Earlier
Obviously you know we are into it
Please
Precinct
The 5000 number you mentioned include
Part-time employees
But still I think it will be a depressive
Animation
We looking for talenti ice cream
Latitudinarian
Right as the company.
Automobile and technology so in Italian
And I'll bring
Celebrity experiences in
The relevant podcast
I think we would love to talk
I would love to
Experience
Applicants in
In driving
In vehicle design
In the powertrain
In
Number of these specific product
The same time we also like to track
Individuals come from
More
Traditional now
Because I think what we are trying to do something
Spotify
So we want
How to bring
Individuals that has
Was New Era tomatoes
Network development disabilities
We want to also
Executive Inn
The functional areas
Legal in finance
And the strategy
I think we should looking for talent across the board
Andis company
Has a berry I was strong
Play Focus culture
Are we we have actually advice pump emphasis
Human cat
One of the key
I would say Ariel
Shuffle
Overseas directly
Is thf
Because he feels like
Having the right infrastructure
Right
Organization structure invite
Is important for a company to grow into much larger scale
So I think that that is something
Are we probably are different from
Other fast-growing Chinese companies
Because our emphasis on human capital
And over this
Construction
I also wanted to ask you a career related question I do have a lot of friends
Investment Bank
To join a tech company
But it doesn't come naturally to allow them do you have any advice for
Aspiring our car and finance professionals
Or trying to
Transition
2 questions
Well they actually quite a few you mustn't Bankers in our company
Myself included obviously now Stratus
We have senior bankers and also
Junior Banker
Well
Will have Finance professional
Who has been
Successful
Investment
Professionals for over 20 years
Largest Wall Street firm
So I think we have a very
I was saying unique
Balance
Companies from
I think it's
That the transition Family Medicine time to fast-growing entrepreneurial company
It's always going to be
Challenging
Because I said different
Maltase
Culture
It's also a focus on different
Priorities
But I think if you are willing to learn
If you actually are
Flexible about
The work schedule intensity
I think
Sorry babe
For y'all
Bankers
I always say
Till the interestings
If I accidentally in the earlier part of my career have experience
Inside a company and see the operation I think I was saved
I make me a much better
Well-rounded
Banker so I think
You know that experience is very valuable
I can give you another story actually and I have breakfast with Josiah
Example
When I joined the
Expungement
Ask him I said well you know you took a lot of risk you joined
Alibaba when it first founded
White Oak Terrace
And she looked at me
You said
I don't think this out of risk enough for me years in Alibaba
Compared to a state ID
So what's a roscato
So at what I'm saying is that for young and old professionals who starting their Bank
Don't be afraid and I'll try the inside of The Inferno company
Experience will be very valuable and used to have time to decide what you want to do later
The only risk
It's not taking any
Brian Madigan
Which is on
I don't think I will be at
Let's go to BC if I didn't have
Start experience
Self
I see a hottie encourage everyone
Follows
If you're in banking or Consulting
Spent three years in a
Text Art of barter companies
You just get more experience
Not be afraid to try.
You would be much better
Volume eight
So now it's jumping to Roundup quick fire questions
So you can just say the first thing that comes to your mind
The first one is who is an entrepreneur you admire the most
Post NY
Jeff Bezos and Jack Ma
Because I think that they not only feel
Bee Company
The weather
The up-and-down of a company then
Always come up with new
Better ideas in better directions for the
I feel like that
Truant preneurship and it's consistent not just one hit wonders
What's a book you read recently that you recommend
I should have read something I recommend to our
Management team is Founders mentality which is a
Book written by pcti thing I think of one of the Consulting companies
It took some analysis on the companies they looked at and
Concluded a number of traits
Dial
Company better which included lot of the
Company
Jose characteristics
He's back to the founders the way up to
What is a habit you have
That you think has changed your life
I think a lot the best thing I learned is not
React too quickly
I think that that's something I learned as a scientist
And then as a banker
I think
LA Times
First reaction may not be the right one always take a pause
And you will
Benefit founded
Slow response
And lastly would you do for fun
I actually look like
Cowboys always fun time but when I do is I usually try to find time to do
Hiking is Hong Kong has a lot of hiking trails
And a group of friends who always liked
To have a night together
And also like
Enjoy Wine and Food so these are fun hobbies
Bright thank you so much for your time
Thank you very much
Is great
Next you were here a short interview with our managing partner tissue.
Cool
Colette Gigi bsms many you see white with our other managing partner Jenny Lee
Ucweb is the mobile browser company founded by Hotel Punk
That was acquired by Alibaba for over a 3.8 billion dollars in 2014
In the largest m&a
Video ever
In tennis history back then
So Justin could you talk about
How you first met shopping and
Persuaded him
To * his next
Adventure Expo Motors
Well actually the history we shall pass on 4th of August
Dates back to
When I first met that out late June
So Legion was
Enjoyed investor in ucweb
And he started to tell me the story about this
That was back in 06
The story about a mobile
Browser
And I was thinking you know feature phone mobile browser
What is that
And I need that made the introduction to one of the CEO of co-founder of the company
You don't fool with so young for at that time
I was brought in
And you know cold out the team and
We shall Paul and he became the CEO of the company
And
Ixd first
Not going full and then later Machop
Shopping with space in Guangzhou
He was really the guy
Delta product for ucweb
So this is kind of interesting cuz
Jenny and I actually got to know Legion and you know that were few deals at that time that leaves you in
Soto
Angel as
The most promising do and he cut off when you don't have power
Setup remote app the deals to Oz and get us to look at it or one of them is why why
Which is spend a lot of time and the other ones you see
So we done subsequently I think that quite a bit of work and
And in 08 we made the investment
Weight 09
Are we made a investment UC
To be fair we are a relatively small while we set up
A cold at the wrong with
It's called the
No clouds Grove venture
At that time
So it WhatsApp all and and his team
And we did
What's a week old at the round
At about $150 valuation at that time
And
So it was an interesting start and
The thing that with you CEO always been that with a feature phone market
How is that
Value is going to evolve by agust D
They made a huge impact in terms of
Going. Not just with China as a browser but he also had
Still outside of China
Anyway the long story short is
That was a time
06 was a time because of you see that's why I met chapeau
As the founder and the key pada person
Bioc
Along the way obviously we stay in touch by
I spend a lot more time with your own food that I spend with him
Having said that I think after the company got acquired by Alibaba I was talking about Jenny and I was
A little involved in
In trying to navigate the the acquisition as well Mojo because
They'll few parties. Just Alibaba involved it was so so by you
Dan Post acquisition Chapel State on a tally
And
That and that was this time that
He called upon Jenny
And say that he know I built this car and incubate at this car
You know I want you guys to come and take a look
So I did so Jenny off me and ran along with rent Guangzhou every saw this whole Market
Stripped out car EV
So he put together a incubator team
All that by Henry
Today's the president of the company Henry hsia
So I was
It was interesting but I didn't I didn't have a lot of
Like driving to hit you up when are you doing this
What time is it no no I'm still at Alibaba
Oh and that didn't
Really gave me a lot of you no conviction or confidence
And how he would want to build this is kind of like
Alpha Project at art
Check for him
That was
Yunnan 2013-2014 by 2016
I start to see
The momentum
Behind the whole momentum behind TVs and
I see that's been a lot more talk about autonomous Drive
And I think that
Smart car
Is a
Is a big future
That's a big potential because
All the
Potential infrastructure Investments that is made by the Chinese government subsidy that's launched by the Chinese government as a juror
I start to think. And I spent a bit of time looking into category matter with Neo and
Way my nephew other players
And I felt like a Child poem If he wants to do this and he go on full-time
You'll be interesting so I spent quite a bit of time talking to him I revisit that his team
If I died right
This time now I drag Jenny along to
To spend a day
Guangzhou meeting of esteem and and so on
I spent probably I will save a few months
Talking to Shopko and say
Are you ready to go full-time are you ready to go food
Because if you are I'm going to
Back injury
And it was this day
That I called him
It was just right after Chinese New Year I'll just around Chinese New Year in February
Fall 2017
I said you'd really need to do this
And so that's
The point in time where
Somehow he's dropped in I'm not sure why because he wants
Yo newborn a second kiss a boy
I got time and you was holding the baby I didn't realize that when I make that call to him
And then I was just grabbing all telling him I was a congratulating him because I do realize that Justice
The bike and
I said you know what you should do that
And that's really turning on and die after he made a decision
Officially jumped in in August 2017
And when
Futon shop
What about chapeau made you have such
Conviction
That if you don't say you're going to bed
You know I think this is the
Tie-dye always give this analogy
Between a feature phone vs smartphone I think
Disa
Fundamental change where you go forum
Just a functional pot out to It's My Party
That that's a lot more
Ideas that has to go into the hole
User environment and the car is not adjust a utility
Anymore
So I thought that somebody like she'll pole with an internet product background
Could be very very powerful
And I know many of such
So call entrepreneur if you will
Web.
To do this
You need a c rock
If you look at me off example
Didn't the founder is a c round trip
So without that she wrote
Entrepreneurship without a bit of Halo
Behind you
It's hard to draw the kind of capital
How to build a cockapoo
You need to elong Musk
Aesir entrepreneur
So
She think you need a bit of a serial entrepreneurship to do this
And I'm not many players are all
Number two
Chi health
I mean he has an interest that's why he incubated this
He has a passion
He loved cars
So that is it
Inter intra so he's not just off the street at Pooh any guy and Sue entrepreneurial and say Hey you go do this
He's somebody who has been doing this and he understand
Cars in Dudley
This is a business giving the Powell capital-intensive it is
You need to be able to put your money where your mouth
So investors not only will follow you they will also follow your money
El Chapo you know given
The exit that you see and so on he has
They not just
The Halo
But ability to say I can put my money where my mouth is
And
You know the capital of long
That's that's
So I need a few reasons I think that's the market Factor that's the
Thank God
He has that Charisma that Halo
Ghettoside office
Pot of gold if you all too well to actually
How about do this and make it work the market opportunities there right China is 26 million you cost every year
Today at Tesla Global he's probably sells
Y'all to 300000 cars
Let's do lots of room
For a second third 4 players
To come up
I will a couple points what you just said I think he's
Definitely right
Comparing
What shop
Cell phone is doing with XP Auto
Similar to coming from Peter from the smartphone
Adventure BC's a game of
Auto recognition
When you see something
Shipt
From Peter from the smartphone as well deal with xiaomi
Elisa impression you are mine
And when you go into a car with a C
Utility wood luxury
Should I go from a dump car
Do a smart car
That experience
It's just remind you of
Different ships that you saw earlier
Both of the investor
Bicycles
And if everything around us going to the cloud
Washing the car where we spend some time on it
Leaving leaving work
Be smarter as well
An alarm has already showed that as possible
In other countries
Do that
Country is Beijing China
In a second
Tikka masala is a Seer entrepreneur
About time to the first time
Maybe a creator
EBay Prada
But he may not be ready when she may not be ready to be a CEO
The company is building a product and
And being a CEO with boobies personal background are two different things
Got exit
It was never the CEO
And you have a
The new baby in your hand everything like what is my legacy
Already have the money
But what am I going to be numbness to my kids
Is someone who cannot follow and get something or someone and I
Myself and it took all the way to the end
Leave a legacy
It's a lot of time to see entrepreneur is driven not my money anymore
Bye-bye
That's extremely powerful motivating factor
What's
I think that's absolutely right I think for
What's y'all Paul's it all he's
Is definitely not about money cuz he's near a well-to-do on its own after you see
So he's driven by
I'm more important mission
Underline Mission and passion for something
For himself
So I think.
Dries for legacy I think that's a good
Way to describe it is really what Propel him
And
You know I had to bought meeting with him recently
And it all ends
Proud of all we have this lunch and you say
You know what I
I woke
I work as hard as I was
They thought harder I was when I wasn't using
So I mean this guy is already
Y'all made it
But yet he's working so hard
And he might be working more than I-96
I'm not I won't be surprised
So Brian join the
Around a year ago
How did you first meet Brian and what do you think
Are some unique value
That he has sprouts
So I met Brian I got the known Brian while he was you know
At the
Investment banking
And his loss
Position was terminated
Stop
JP Morgan
Annies
You know son of
Hat puns with Hume on and off
But why really bring a different set of skill sets
To the organisation
Given his background
His knowledge
Kiss perspective is macro and his ability to communicate
Very very well with
With the outside wall
So I think she'll ponies.
And that's one thing I will say about chapeau I said his Halo
It's important it is not just about attracting you know
Investors full Oasis etra
Batalla
He's able to attract Talent
To join him
And
And Brian joining him is a testimony for
And it's not just Brian he has many other people
Who acts
You know Tesla relax
Paw Commons
Xiaomi has extra
Joining the team
Xenia and professionals is at
So Brian is one of those and I didn't Brian really compliment chaperone in a way
Where you know he is he's
Completely bilingual he understand China very well
He has very strong linkage
To various investors in the community this is a capital-intensive
The game
We need that ability to
Rally the support and the investors behind us to to build the company
And bride please a troll really wow
Ben's interesting that Brian said that now he's flights economy class all the time
When was the banker at JP Morgan
All first class
And making good money
So why is he doing
I just wish things seem more and more
Professional
China
Willing to take. Entrepreneurial ship jump
MP
Be part of a company that sleeping like a
Beseech in human world
Give me something better for society that
There's enough meaning and also
Enough payout at the end
To make it worthwhile
The market is massive
The opportunity is
This is shoot
Outside is there
And we work hard for 3-5 years
You can really make a huge difference a month
Right it's really interesting. Jessica flying
Economy class
David have like
Budget for hotel so he stays in Budget Hotel
Yo for a guy who is made it as a terminal for JP Morgan and
It obviously cheetah
Yallfest class everywhere including in our flights and hotels and travel
To be willing to cut off
Step down and said this is what I'll do
Coming to a company and
Having the desire and Trust
To follow shopping in and do this
I totally thick means a lot and suddenly takes a lot
Not just for himself emotionally bio so you know
Family and everything
I mean he lives
Write this in Hong Kong
Why he walks in Guangzhou
So literally he's fly
I stayed in the hotel where he stayed with his just next to the company like
It is a budget hotel
So it's a sign of commitment and conviction
To the exponent vision
So do you think China's TV or Smart Card Market
Or do you think that you VR smartphone market is inherently localized is it possible for
Nan Chinese
Players to be six
Or do you think
The local players will
In the long run
Well I think
Did this is auto market is not a winner-take-all market
Always say that you know you have Mercedes and Europeans
You have Toyota or Honda
Yeah you are local player so it's a big enough market 26-minute new cars being sold every year
Granted I think the whole Grove Mentor behind new car sales has come down a 17 to 2018
But that's still a lot of
That is a big Market
It's probably the single biggest Market in the world in terms of numbers of car sales
So that's a Pacini D2
To grow their Market share
Today the penetration of Eevee's today's by 3%
And so that's do
Room for
Smart
Smart cars to actually extend itself
I'm less worried about competition
Per say I mean that is definitely the competitive element
But foreign or local the the chances actually fairly equal
And I think China is increasingly trying to open up
It's not limiting foreign players for say so
The market is open to all
And I do think that
Having said that I think that it's important
4 oz
Appreciate the local environment in the local market
I just give you one example
Which is end this I use quite a bit this
Ability to Auto Park
Expo right
The most people when you talk about Auto parking as a feature
The reality is that
Many of the car
Only recognize 10 to 20% of the parking scenarios here in China
So
Out of 10 times that you try to auto part when he wants a two times
You you got
You got the
Auto parking
That that feature is quite useless
So I think Tesla
For wine in a coming to the market and others while trying to come to Market if they want to support that feature
Do you have to localize
2000 aerio.
Cure in China
I was shopping for
For 1
Disable that dress 72 80% off the parking scenario
The Cure till out of 10 times 728 times you could
Easley Auto Parts
Your car that becomes
The true valuable feature versus just a feature that you put on the brochure
So that's it
Localizing to the marketplace
All that you see because China is a very very different driving environments just alright house you guys are where the sister you are
Echo
Pigeon Point Beaufort
We get a call the question
Snus.
It alternates difference in which regulation government rest blah blah blah
And the number one reason
Used company don't do well
It does reality is at
Is it fishing this category
A test that will be welcomed in China
So that's not an issue
At least not
Any more bigger issue than any any Chinese company
But what is different is that
Chinese company to know
And double of Peterbilt he's so strong so good
Extremely fast
To subside Annies
I'm local consumers
12 questions from Richwood
What use your product
And if the profits. Look like for China
Millions of
Tens of hundred many users
Even though you have amazing Grandpa
From from outside
Rigging companies fail to realize why they
You change an Ann Taylor solution
The specific for the Chinese market
And and that's why most reason why
Us companies don't do it
Sew-in for Chinese players there are a lot of
Space as well
What
Made you
Have such strong conviction that X phone
It's the one
First of all I think that each of these companies have
Demerits
The purisolve
The shop only have got married so it's hard for me to
Common but
Baidu fundamentally believe that
This is
A product
Soca kahrizak
Product
It is not
A service business
So
Intensity and skills and knowledge needed to build
Great product is imported
And I think shop home is a
Type of person
He's a product
He's not here to
You know market and
Peach sales and
It all he he is
Pretty focused on
Giving the right product
Experience to the annual
That's why
So
Adding underline yet is
What does it take to
How to build a great car company and I think
Cell phone has what it takes
And that's why I chose to
Factor
That's all we have for today and thanks so much tuition for
Thank you
Airline flight 798 9.4
Thanks for listening to this episode
96 ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
We have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre-ipo
What's 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in costume
Smyrna retail social internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billion.
Dollars
Formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep slat
Square Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at 2
Qvc.com we also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group a slack Channel where we regular
How to share insights events and job opportunities related to attack in China join these groups at 9
Text. G gbc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend a gas please email us I-96
Hepc.com