Hi everyone if you are aspiring
Recurrent highway or a Chinese overseas returnee
We have a special resource for you
We recently compiled a list of
10 Chinese books on Tekken entrepreneur
Chip in China that we recommend all sea turtles
Right before going back
These include books
Sunshine Aztec Giants
Tencent Alibaba JD and
Practical aspects of running a startup in China
Such as growth and marketing
As well as books on General Chinese business
To read the book list
Please follow GPS WeChat official account
By searching ggv capital on WeChat
And the message the word
Sea turtle to that account
We also have a lucky draw for you
If a comment on that article with your story of coming back to
China as a highway before April 10th
You can enter a lottery to win a bundle up
Is 10 bucks
Which will be mailed to you
We look forward to hearing your story
Recent wrestler
Hi there
Welcome to the 96 podcast
Brought to you by GE Capital
On the show
Went to the movers and shakers of China
Tech industry
And discuss how founders
From around the world
I'm fine Aztec ecosystem
My name is Khan song
I'm a managing partner at ggv capital
And I've been working at and investing in startups
Across the US
China and other Emerging Markets
My name is original I'm a marketing manager at ggb Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
96 is the work schedule and many Chinese Founders have organically adopted
That is 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. 6 days a week
Nemesis captured Lincoln City Drive
Speed of Chinese internet companies
Which are produced many growth Miracles over last decade
Also I highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat groups in slack Channel
Where you can connect with like-minded people interested in Tech in China
We organize regular offline events
Across the world for a followers
You can join these by visiting 96.
Gigi bc.com
Hi everyone
On today's show we wanted to talk about the topic of sea turtle
Sorhegui
Which means overseas Chinese returnees
These are people who were born and raised in China
Completed
Higher education outside of China or have worked overseas
And then have returned to China for opportunities
There has been an increasing number of sea turtles in recent years
As China's Tech
Economy boomed and the US immigration policies
Became less friendly
Sephora tallinn
Actually some of the most valuable Chinese tech companies
Honda bike weight
Anniversary every Chinese
Tech company
Has halfway in their leadership
Example includes Robin Li of Baidu
Jing Liu of didi
Call Antoine of pingatore
Jamestown loveseat
Thinking of xiaomi
One scene of May 20th
Jon Hall of Champions
New China Providence
Shower my love shopping shoe
List goes on
Actual interview many of these people
Download previous episodes
Mabel and check this out if you haven't
So sea turtles face both opportunities and challenges when they come back
To try to
And indeed there more internationally minded than Chinese people who have never lived abroad
They speak better English and they can bring back practices from other parts of the world socialist
Silicon Valley
They also faced many challenges
Chief among those is a problem called put UTC or not connected to the energy of the land
So has what is your definition of
Yeah he practice was speaking in China is operates quite differently
From Westworld
So if you are being away from China for 5-10 years
Go back and understand how Grassroots
People are how things get done
That's beyond what's in the official guidebook
That you quite someone who understand what's going on on the line
Ninja blender
So Che Dici is a very common
Complain that we share levied against
Equivoque
Encounter this question a lot from my other boyfriends like how do I
Become more titties she because
What was you have spent so many years abroad when you come back you naturally just
Like have English words pop up when you're speaking Chinese and that might raise the impression that
You're just
Trying to act like
More y'all seahorse
More westernized than the rest when
Just
It's just naturally
The way you're thinking or speaking
So
How do you sing
Practically highways cam
Become more integrated into the local
Chinese
Culturelle
Krowd
You and I both went through that.
Move back to China
In 2005
And back then
I had lived in
No person I was born in Taiwan
I grew up in La winter
Stanford
What's American citizen when I move to China
Did China is not a
Play symbols for Marowak
It is very easy to use
English words
Am I Chinese
Lingo
Every other Sunday
In
Very easy
Juicy Lucy.
In order to become more Chinese I need to do more
Which means including tie
Trains to tear
34 City
You eat all kinds of funny food
Some people remember idioms and old Chinese saying sweet Chinese history books
To be able to recall lessons
Dance from the past
To show that you understand how this line works
Are you know that I tried is about to country with many differences across regions
The more you appreciate China is
A collection of many different cities and regions
And know the difference is the more people respect you
For understanding how to operate in this alarm
Yeah I think that's a really good
Piece of advice because a lot of
Highways
They don't realize how much they have missed out on by not being a
China
For a number of years
Because China develop so fast and has such a vast
Amount
History
So
The people who stay here
Actually absorb a lot just by being here though
You're missing out on
Play if you're just by virtue of not being
It is really easy to
Go to China with the attitude that your Superior you'll see how the West work
You know what's best practice from Silicon Valley
Where New York
And it seem like you're better
But in China since the growth is growing so fast
So much has changed
The group your
Your ability to adjust to that
And in Ingo
Is it very difficult for someone
Pool has been even longer
To be able to keep up
And the differences are so obvious
People have been around in China
That is very hard to win the respect
Can people when you're not sitting in your not understanding
Call appreciate
How amazing this girl has been
So what are some common pitfalls that you have seen Highway entrepreneurs right in two
Besides this Cube race
I think you better look at our portfolio companies
Either as founders
Or as
Managers
People usually think that
The shortest distance between two points
Is a straight line
Butt emoji
Buy infant
Department sort
Different business partners to get something
You got to figure out what everyone's
Imagen de is in
Find a common ground to make that work
Sometimes they could be
Conflicting goals they had a
Figure out a way to
Figure out how to move everyone lawn
Inability to
Treat people nice
Build a relationship without trust
People who talk about business
This is not yours
Jackson butt
You people
Need to do you a favor so you
You do the math papers make a do a favorite back later
All died
Takes work
Bentonite doesn't happen in the business center or in the office
So not respect
China is no different than any other place you have been helping me.
At same time
Channels movies much faster
That's having somebody in New York
Most people don't realize
Chinese companies
10 years ago were small and
White midi 120th of a size
These days
Chinese companies are
Similar in size
Aetna
2% of us counterparts and China is the largest
Internet calling me the world with more consumers anywhere else
So the speed of change the Hobbies companies grow look at bytedance
Example
The work schedule is 5 days a week plus
Wednesday
A weekend
Two week at the month
It is normal
In this work schedule is
Something 9 to 12
So
The pace of change
The pace of growth
How fast
People get irate
It's much quicker
In in Somalia in the New York
We talked about prophecies
Before something gets done then let's go planning
In China is just
Getting it done just do it first and then
Give the problem you fix a uterus move on
So you get more stuff done in short. Time even though the
Buffer
Not as smooth not-so-nice
Better results Yashica more stop talking more efficient
Productivity
You see you if you're willing to spend more time in and not talked about as much angira fast
Difference in style becomes very evident
Within the first week of anybody who come by
Do I think I'm in jail
In terms of the decision making process
Is a lot of
My friends in the valley or in the US
Ask me or should I
Stay at Google or Facebook or Uber or should I go back to
China and if I go back
It's the right time
In terms of his decision-making what do you think should be the
Top consideration
When these potential
Sea turtles are considering
I think it gets harder and harder to come back
Before you go to ready
A lot of
Mainland Chinese students want to go to the US
Work for a few years getting some experience
But it's not a easy in the US to get a lot of experience
English or creative thought
So because
No Chinese companies like Alibaba in a 10-second teaches worth somewhere between 350 billion dollar market
Comparable to Econo Parts in the US
Adidas
It's going to be hard to hard to have a superior position in the Chinese company if you haven't learned a child
In the US
And you actually write faster in Chinese company number four
So I will actually argue that it's important for tencent
Come back to China
Quickly as possible
How to do the work in u.s. for 2-3 years and not worry about what they're missing out
Just come back and acclimate themselves into the scene and climb
Trying to
Become somebody was more senior in the US then come back later
It's not that easy
You can make it work
But the odds of success as she gets smaller
The more time you spend in USA my pen
Because Dad didn't listen to some estate available
Chinese Innovation Chinese
Hillbilly hot tub
Now in the most cutting-edge things
The most interesting
Aspects of a semiconductor technology or AI or machine learning
If you are really smart in the US you have achieved
I love us
Success in the short fighting someone very cutting-edge stuff
Your exception to the rule
You can
Go back to China and I'll come up with something and expect
Carpe
Pick a position
But if you don't
Stay on top of it
Within 2-3 years utility will gota
What do you think
I think there's also the danger of just settling in
So like
A lot of
People in the valley or in the US
Alfred
Stay there for
Three to four years they start to think about things like green cards buying
House
Having a family in the US
What do is just becomes harder and harder
To move around and consider moving to China
So I guess
In the twenties people are the most mobile
In general
And Beijing or China is just such a dynamic
Play the requires a lot of energy
So
I also recommend like friends around me to
Go to China when they're young
You recently moved back to China
How do you spend four years of Harbor
Prior to 3 years in Singapore
And then what used to be the first year in
What's it like for you
Comparing
The difference between Silicon Valley in Beijing
The biggest difference is
It's just everything multi
Surplice decide the amount of
People you need to meet
Information you need to absorb
The deals you're processing
Just the sheer amount of
Stuff that you need to deal with just increases by a lot when you're in Beijing because China is the world
Largest consumer internet
Beijing
It's like one of the most populous
Studies
So it is very energetic and dynamic and exciting
And I also really like this get things done attitude in China
And this focus on execution above everything else
Because if you don't execute faster your competitors will
And forever a new vertical that pops up
It's like several hundred companies competing for market share
The competition is just so brutal
And I feel like one under-appreciated aspect is that there are a lot of opportunities for highways interested in emerging
Markets outside of us in China
So in the past it was more bridging us and China
Bridging China and Emerging Markets because all of these markets
Are looking to China for
Business models and lesson
I see the difference between secretary and us
Typically it
Is a difference of
But for every meeting you have metal Parts in China get usually have double
The number of meetings
This is more people to meet more people wanted me
Then you talk to the point that
More more Founders are coming to China
To learn
We actually notice I asked
Early as 2011-2012
There were a lot of Founders from India the king
These are among the very best in the Bahamas
The bear bear species India
Since then
In 2013-14
We see a lot of Founders Inn
NBC from Southeast Asia
And then fast forward to 2016-2017
Which are seen Founders NBC's from Latin America
Supposed to be Brazil Colombia to Mexico
Come to China
And it's very interesting to see
Other Emerging Markets of sizable domestic markets
Where's the Bryson Middle Class
Lots of organization
Growing economy or Mercury in transition with volatility
Come to China to learn more how Chinese companies
Have deal with those issues
CC shoes and solve something to societal problems
Over the last
And it just being increasingly is China as a place
To some degree Hangzhou City so you just have to go and visit
In order to see how Baidu Audi
Tencent
A WeChat
King Ghidorah xiaomi jadi mate wanted
All these companies
Operate
And it's just fascinating
Start seeing more more Chinese companies
Many of them I mentioned earlier to expand your business
Xian China what is the Russian city Investments
JB's order of operations
And so we are seeing more startups from China
Not having a fresh market be awesome China
Diverting their expense in China to build
A lot of apps
Indian market
So it has become
There's increasingly more needed for Highway to play Roll
So I think the sooner had Way come back to China when they're younger when they don't have that kind of Burden the family in the more they can do
Do I make him back
I also felt that the premium of being a highway in China
Has someone
Decrease / 2
Past few years one because
There's so many of us
They asked the number of Chinese
Students will study abroad increases
Also naturally increases and
Because the immigration policies in the US
Have become less friendly to
Foreign Talent
Alarm were coming back
Today and also because a lot of
It used to be that all at least you graduated from one of the top US schools are you
You have worked at Google Facebook Airbnb you're considered
Automatically
Superior to
Your Chinese equivalent but that's no longer there
The case because you're actually missing out
On a lot of
The local Tampa
How things get done in China in
Don't actually understand the Chinese
Consumer Market
So do you agree that the premium of
Being a highway
Decrease 10
How
We can ask
Leverage our International
Experience
In that context
Yeah that's a great question
If I look at the numbers
Talking to.
Sex
The number of Chinese immigrants in the US
Was only 10000
That's not including the garage
Just Underground
Just lost mother
10 years later in 2016
No number when out by 14x
240 mm
Factor the size of the quietest room
To the group
Back in 2016 there were roughly 300
Thousand
Chinese students in the US
Roughly one-third
More than one-third of all forms
So you hire have that kind of
Pool of
Students to
That was going to work for us
In the US and Emerson
To come back to China
Pacific Tile and pool of a hike weights
But
Cedar Point
Has the premium being Highway going down
Yes
Because like I mentioned earlier
The Chinese way of doing things is do a first
Do you adjust later
Planning is important
But not its importance getting stuff
Done visiting a grown conomy
The market is expanding
Does it matter how you plan
You will know more about the result of Your Action
If you do it first and then adjustment
You can come more productive
Da Wei
Mus
Is market more saturated
That everything you do could be quite destructive to
Vested interest
You have to plan and think harder about what you're doing
In order to get some things done
Is the market is not growing as a
As a whole but China's different
There's so many things
Does Brooklyn
Some of things offline without working
You are better off trying things
Prior hypothesis
The store now
And give feedback normal to move
Ford and adjust
And that way of doing is what people China used to
From schools
From
Working in Workforce for the fur
First few years after college
If you don't have that kind of
Pace
Clock speed
An approach ingrained in you
You going to stick out as a
Sore thumb very very quickly as a haiku
And so
How do you navigate and get stuff done so we can live with your friends or your contacts
Your Professional Network
Yolanda Bass
Quickly get these things done
Python
It becomes very obvious in the first week to their job
That the hike we will operate a much slower
Much less efficiently
Then their counterparts who have been China whole time and didn't leave
So if you go out for a professional degree Stanford or Berkeley
Aldi's close
Sooner and come back the better and when you come back how can you leverage while using outside
Helping Chinese companies expand overseas
Dealing with foreign business partners
These are
Easley area so that when you can speak better English to understand the culture
Are you going to about it
For most of the schools that Chinese many students go to in the US or else Warehouse in China
Your many
Students from other country
How many merchants
Want to learn more about China
So while you're outside as a highway
You should
Gilmore relationship young people
Who are just Americans or other Chinese
People from Southeast Asia from Africa or Middle East
Demorrio Williams engaged
People of other races
Namoura help you to work with them once you go back to China
Just the first thing that people should do
The second thing is
Can I unplug will be more Frank on this
It is not easy is not natural
To figure out
People twerking teens in general
So how do you
You want to buy Ironman
Figure out a way to
Build a team and work well with a team
So that as a team yeah she can get more stuff done then
The collection of individuals
Is something that you get to learn when you assume that Stanford or Berkeley you are Harbor or or other than delete this
Many of the property states are done in teams
And there's many
Extracurricular activities and sports and other things that you can do that working
The more you learn how to work in teams the more you know how to become a leader in things
The more you can effectively can be when you come back to China
As a highway
Those are the two things that's a more General
Specifically
Before you go out
Figure out like what China needs help on
What is machine learning with AI or semiconductor whatever
Areas
If you happen to have a
Interest in.
We are
Outside of China
Learn more about the best practices
So I can come back in a play some Professional Knowledge
That people in China just don't have a haven't had exposed
Those are the three ways I can think about hybrid about it while they're out
And be able to do more when they come
Yes
Stafflinq
So when it comes to younger Highway Founders that have become
Successful searches
Calendar of shabu-shabu and 100 and others
What do you think they did right
I think first of all all these are just very smart
Individual
I did learn extremely quickly
So if they learn
Multiple disciplinary field
Text Keisha and
Technology
Product
Sociology
And just more they see
It helps him to come up with ideas and approaches
Is that a lot of people
If I take
Michelle
Example
When you first went to
She'll die in Shanghai for college
Not the first time he ever took an airplane
Okay on the airplane ride
And that's when he was 18
Fast forward 10 years later it has been to a hundred different countries
Torres transformation
As someone whose
To be at
Who came from the ground
When he was 18
To someone who becomes a hike way 10 years later
Dachshund mix
Remarkable
In his own personal transformation
Epitomizes
Let's kind of transformation
And globalization
How many Chinese
Consumers
In a Tijuana selector tier 2 Market
Sohio
Shoot me
Is aware
What his consumers
Are going through
And be able to relate
Him give him things.
Aspire them to
Want more
With the loading shown with a monkey
She's a Google training
Help them to
Figure out how to take
Using algorithm
Etymology
Solvay traditional epic
Kishin prob
And I said multiple
Disciplinary in nature
And when he started Alicia it wasn't obvious.
Leveraging algorithm alone can solve
The common problem of needles
Devaluing better English
Accent
And know what to say
In interviews and it need a lot of
Life cycle
Why does wasn't as successful with his today so you wasn't obvious that bass
Improvements and changes
Consumers
But he he was
As early as don't you mean by that
To take an approach
Reply to a real problem how to take
Trenton hundreds of millions of Chinese
Consumers in English
It is very interesting, both of them coming from different backgrounds
Leverage your life experiences human way
DYFS it's the wave of the next wave of where Chinatown
So in terms of
Founding startups
What are some areas
Where are you staying
Highways
Have an advantage
Over
Non highways when it comes to either starting companies or working at
Like which
Tracks or vertical should they consider
I seen the most obvious when these days
Is too hot
Chinese companies Go Global
How to say
The
Population dividend mobile internet user dividend
From China
Decreased is already
800 million
Smartphone users in China Auto population of 1.4 billion
You sure do you know there are a hundred million more people could go online but
The book of it has
And the growth has
Slow down
And a lot more apps
Tt4u with your time
As well
So you can still build an interesting consumer companies or apps
In China but a 10 sub.
How come down
Yet China has been through over the last 18 years and throw the history of tgv
Yeah come through for five different generations of
Startups already
Docker knowledge
Acumulador for five generations
Are incredibly useful in other places such as India
. I only start to experience 40 in the last 2 years
This is why you will look at it leaderboard
Up top apps in India
The more than
50%
Come from
China at least as of now
That may not be sustainable. Percentage will definitely go down as an Indian founders
Get a better and smarter and more experienced and then extremely pokeweed which
So for the time being
Highway cam
Definitely
More value in companies from China That's expanding overseas
Many Chinese Founders have not lived in India have lived
Not to be Southeast Asia
So if you have a high-quality who's more familiar with this weekend
How do you make friends while there were studying a friends released
These two regions
We can definitely
Taobao
Ami.
Encourages all
Chinese students or Professionals in the US to actually stay in
In touch with what's going on
In China
There are a lot of resources these days and we have the benefit of
Being able to access not just the English resources but also the Chinese resources
So actually
Spend a lot of time just reading Tech news in Chinese writing Chinese business books history books
Understanding contemporary China and also
The past
Because
Being from Chinese really an advantage
Today is
It's quite lucky to be able to speak
One of the world
Hardest languages
And have the culture Affinity to the world's most populous
Nation and also the largest
Internet economy
So I think there are a lot of opportunities that come with
Having this background
And we should really make the most out of it
By doing something
That's at least really related to China
Are you don't have to be in China but I think even
If
We stay in the US
They're just a lot of opportunities to work on China related
I can see
Type in their 20s
Move to Singapore in
Towards a car. Spend time in Southeast Asia
Or move to
Bangalore
Mumbai
Or even go to Latin America like some Paulo
Mexico City
Because the
Knowledge
The one cats
From
Different all these different WeChat official accounts
All the different Chinese apps out there
About what's happening in China RN
Bible useful
Founders in this Emerging Markets
So the more
Cupquake and play the role of bridge
Between China and Russia world the more value
They can generate
Guess they can watch
Yes
So make friends from Salvador make friends from
Brazil
India I think
Definitely
Any one of the best
Assets of
Going to a
Us college with a lot of diversity is
You got to make friends
What people would that you wouldn't
Have met otherwise
And that's really a huge asset
Like 10 years down the road Maybe not immediately but
In the far future
Maybe you do business with someone
Imagine School
Who knows
I know I was young once
I'm much older today
But I was young once
And very easy to have
How to start a compare with your college buddies
You see how successful
World
Who got what promotion who got a
Salary increase in Sulphur
It's very easy to keep a score
Cuz that's what people used to doing
And everybody is a high-achieving students
In the well in the
Exams
Dwell
In
Successful applications
But one has to think of playing a long game
I even look at my own career the first 10 years
Was a lot of
Things
Dad had a lot of rural movements
But not a lot of vertical
Jumps
The next 10 years
Hi
Did so much more
Because of the preparation for the first 10 years
And it's very difficult find about that
To take a 10 or 20 year review of the
Taqueria
I know that
China's growth
It was one of my Munster
Take the story in the last 20 years
We have found them people knowing from Countryside into cities
That does not like kind of growth
Trying to happen
Anywhere else
Yet
We all
Sync
Igtv definitely know that china's model is
Very exportable to other places
You will be localized he will be changed
You be innovative
But the face that foundation on what about the last 20 years
Are incredibly valuable to Founders who want to make a difference in their own emerging-market over the next 10-20 years
If the highways are patient
And willing to
Engage Reach Out
Learn
Cher
We want to play better
As a as a winning team
You're just so much that can be done
Between China and emerging markets around the world
So I highly encourage everyone to beat
Take a more long-term View
To their career in their life
So in terms of where highways can add value I generally see to Pat's
One is to help Chinese companies
Go Global and the others to help global companies enter China
I think recently I didn't really get the sense that
Helping Chinese companies Go Global is a lot practical passport
Being successful
What way do you think
I think it's
Difficult
For someone
718 San Francisco or London Broil in New York
To understand what's happening China
So helping
International Company
Expanding China
It's not easy
Is very hard to understand China when you're nice
In China
So if I look at it
Our experience working with Airbnb
We have
Being pressed
What how much support
Leadership Airbnb in San Francisco willing to provide
And what a great job
The Army maternity
Blood by tile
I've done over last
Just under one year
I was with
Competition that
Earlier
But it has not been an easy
Yet in Alaska
Step 3 years
You see that
A material portion of
Top apps India come from China
So the ability of Chinese companies
Synapse make a difference oversea Market
In the short-term
Is much greater
So if our hike way I will spend time
You don't have way in the twenties I would spend time helping tennis conmigo broth
UTV action of a lot of resources in programming
For highways or Chinese students
And professionals who are living overseas
Two recently will organize a program called gdb fellows
Which is designed for sea turtles to get re-acclimated
Two Chinese startup ecosystem in business environment
So during a program we have 34 global-minded young leaders
Who came to Beijing and completed a one-week intensive training
Antagonize partnership in China
So R34 fellows were carefully selected from over 400
Qualified app
And they come from
Top institutions from
Around the world
The most well-represented schools were
Harvard Stanford MIT
Itea Berkeley
And many of them are working at Sycamore Valley Tech companies such as Google Facebook
Uber and Apple
And all of them are native speakers of Chinese or equivalent and are fascinated by the rise of
So Chinese internet
Sector over the past decade
So during a program we brought the fellows to visit the
Headquarters of 8
Chinese unicorn internet companies and also heard from
21 Founders or executives
Who shared lessons on what it's like to start and run company
Our speakers came from some of the
Most valuable internet companies in China including
Bytedance
BD xiaomi
Joshua choir show faceplusplus we are bound keep hello chuxing and others
That many of them at Stevie purple wheels
Entering these closed-door sessions.
Speakers shirt not just tip
Tips for success but also
Candid stories of failures
Some pitfalls that they ran into on their startup Journey
So the program is kind of like a lightweight NBA on all things related to China's Tech equals
So hot
You have interacted with some of the fellows what was your
Impression of
Opposed to fellows and what
They took away from
Yeah I think when you laugh
First talked about this idea
We have seen
Fellowship work
That's them for the oldest
Bcfellowship
The catch
Qualify Sanford soon to work in startups
Was the Mayfield Fellowship
What happened in the night
And since then
Does USBC have
Have I started
Fellowship of their kinds
And in China
I think I'm fun
Was the Pioneer for China
In this area
As well
I think when you and I talked about this we increasingly realize that
They're just so many
Who could do more
Henan China release setting
You better have a better way to
Oyster Bar
And since we have the
Buffalo companies
Start doing well
And many of them employee Highway
We thought it would be good
Good way to connect
The two resources
Did I give you an
Terracotta tile a lot of credit
For making this work I'm putting the
This together so kudos to all of you
40gbe I think
Having a chance to
Give a talk
To the shallows
And meet them in person
And have couple of Hour podcast
Just
Confirm that there's a lot of talent
Out there
The cultural
Multidisciplinary
If we can help them
Do more connect with more
People with
Are simple-minded
Wee Sing. Magic
What happened
Ennis be good for society
When more positivity
And creativity
Could happen.
So
Love it
And we are going to
Continue this program in the future I will likely be annual
Programs
In January issue during the winter break of
Major universities
And if you're interested in our future events you can join r96
Community
Visiting 96.3 gvtc.com and all of our events at 8 or should have
Will be announced
Stare
For the first year he has more of a us China
Bent
Heading over time
We highly encourage
Qualify Africa
Apply from Southeast Asia
From India
From different parts of your elbow you in Africa or Middle East
Cuz we want this to be
More global
And how to connect
Qualified
Sideways
How to connect with others from
Different regions
And over time we probably will
Expanded
Encourage each other
Acting groups
Take the time to learn Chinese
So that they can
Participating program like this
And get an accelerator
Apus
To connect with the
Community the world should be more about connection
Connecting
M2 ignored Foster more creativity in product
And in terms of resources
We recently compiled a list of 10 Chinese business books on Tekken entrepreneurship in China
Not that we were coming all sea turtles
Before going back to
The China these include books on China text Ryan
Tencent Alibaba JD and Mate1
Books on practical aspects of running a startup in China such as growth in marketing
As well as books on General Chinese business history
To read the book list please follow jeebies WeChat official account
By searching ggv capital on WeChat
And then messaged a word
Sea turtle to data
We also have a lucky draw for you
If you comment on that article with your story of call me back
The China as a sea turtle
Before April 10th
You can enter a lottery to win a bundle of these
10 bucks
Which will be mailed to you
We look forward to hearing your story
And I also have an article on the list of news outlets and resource
That can help you stay in
Touch with what's going on in check in China
Which out include in a showdown
Excellent thank you
Next episode you're going to hear from two of our fellows themselves
A why they came to the program and what they took away from
Stay tuned and thanks for listening
Thank you all
Airline flight 879 89.5
I-96
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley
Shanghai and Beijing we have been partnering with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed
Capri IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds
Ggv invests in consumer new retail
Social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
Gdb has in Boston over 290 companies
With more than 45 companies valued at over a billion dollars
Formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp
Hello by Adele
House keep Slack
Square
Hotel wish soundtrue white white and others find out more at ggvc. Com
We also highly recommend joining our listeners WeChat group as last Channel
Where we regular share inside
Events and job opportunities related to attack in China
Join these groups at 9 96.3 jvc.com community
You have any feedback on this podcast
Or would like to recommend a gas please email us
I-96
IGG bc.com