Hi everyone we're excited to announce that ggv Capital recently launched a new podcast in Chinese
Called startup Insider or trillion Nemo in Chinese
Which is produced by my colleague Willie base in Beijing
Just like 96
Start Insider features interviews with top Founders in executives
I'm tired of Technology
Imagine a 96 Park house but in Chinese
The first episode with with little to do with the acid
CPS xiaomi and head of the xiaomi cost
If you are Chinese
Speaker I highly recommend checking out this show on Himalaya
You can find it by searching toy name or startup Insider
Recent arrest Monroe County Probation
Hi there
Welcome to the nine at six podcast brought to you by ggv capital on the show we interview movers and shakers
China's tech industry as well as Tech leaders who have a US
China cross-border perspective and the managing partner at GTV capital
And I've been working at startup investing in them in both in US
A China for past 20 years
My name is Sarah Jeong an investment Analyst at ggv Capital and a former journalist
Why is the show called 96
6 is the work schedule than any Chinese Founders have organically adopted that is 9 a.m.
KTM 6 days a week
To us
996 captures intensity Drive in speed of Chinese internet companies many which
Are moving faster they even their American counterparts
Hi everyone on this episode we're going to continue our new series where Hans and I will talk about
A topic of Interest currently
So today we wanted to cover
A phenomenon cultural High which literally means
Going overseas
Ides phenomena of Chinese on printers targeting emerging markets around the world
Soe hunts and I and I didn't igbt
A team has a paying attention to this
Trend
For a long time now
I recently relocated
To the Beijing investment team and I've seen it with my own eyes how
So many of the Stardust we're seeing these days are in this category we're Chinese entrepreneurs
Are going outside of China
Target
Consumers and users in Emerging Markets like southeast Asia India
Russian America in even app
And if you look heavy App Store ranking is Humana Emerging Markets
Many of the top ranking
E-commerce and social apps are actually developed by Chinese
So Hans when did you start
To realize
That's what high or Chinese companies
Going overseas could be a big arch
I'm probably the first DC in the world that coined the phrase
Is too high
That was back in
I think I saw a few things
That happened
It 2012
That made me decide that
This area
Chinese company
Expanding overseas
WSU jobs
Opportunity for next
Three things happen
That get me to send 3 data point
Give me the sunset
This could be a
Emergency
One WeChat came out in 2011
The product is so wealthy
You feel that
Product. At least canx
Respond to rest
Malaysia
Awesome China
And over the next
18 months
You start to hop
Which I was willing
Make a push
Into Taiwan and Southeast Asia
In India what
Your today is doing well in some of these
Including India
70 and a half
That caught my attention
Was a xiaomi
I was part of the xiaomi team that try to
As early investing xiaomi
Need help xiaomi
Kookaburra
To leave Google
Join xiaomi
And this happened in
And we start talking
To go as early as 2012
And
The fact that he was willing to leave
Does head of product for Android
To join xiaomi
Was a seminal event
I think not only for xiaomi
Before Chinese tech industry
Which you have an established Talent
Train overseas
Community Emerging Markets aarhus
Osborne Brazil
Between Chinese company
And do these days
I think his followers
Sina weibo
I'll number is followers on
So that was a second thought was
Chinese handset
Claire can expand
Feel the market
32 point I was in
Adjusting was Alibaba was Act
Always a part of
SoftBank in
Japan
Also looking at
Expansion investment opportunities
In Southeast Asia
Which culminated
With them their investment in the future Act
Lazada
And that wasn't just thought about it until you said other companies have been trying
Odoo e-commerce
And most recently with by 10
Expecting to social networking Beyond China at
So starting in 2012
These few data points
Give me the sun side
The Chinese Interceptor have to come through
Fourth generation of Founders already
The Mount of learning.
Accumulated
And a China is bullying
Countrywood for 5 tier cities
It was really nothing that's happening elsewhere in the world
That doesn't have a similar condition
Somewhere in China already a month
So I thought the Chinese company
When's the tea become more globalized
Anderson
Uncultured
Better half
Skill set
And a requisite knowledge
I'll probably
Skill and build it into
Internet companies
Awesome
So that was the
The key reason why I decide to move
Back to the Bay Area
From Beijing
And have been doing Investments
In this area ever since
Jennifer last few months
Just from talking with a lot of
Other receipts
Some people in the circle ice have a palpable sense that people saying mobile internet
Penetration in China has pretty much reached saturation so it's very
Hard to have that kind of exponential growth that we saw
Maybe a decade ago
And that's another reason
Push a lot of Chinese entrepreneurs
To go outside of China to other markets where Mobile Internet is just starting to take off
I think back in 2013 I get a calculation
Not Chinese
Smartphone users internet users roughly around
300 million
Pcna users with roughly about
600 million
And over the next 5-6 years
Both were we supposed
Situation
And then when the world number you know users
Expendable 3
4 billion
The next 2 billion will have to come also the US and China
Specifically Southeast Asia
India
Naughty America
So it doesn't take a rocket scientist
You know where to pay attention
At some point in the future
This trim
Will come if that's out of 10 is internet founder
Are ready
You take on the Opera
I remember he also said before that you can't imagine Chinese entrepreneurs moving to Jakarta
But it's hard to imagine American Founders kuwada
Go all the way there why do you think that's the
I think you may have the knowledge of what do internet
Space but
It's very difficult to go after Emerging Markets
From your home City
Guess it's time zone differences
And lack of interaction lockup
Field what's happening on the
Street makes you less effect
By remote controlling it
I'm back home
So to be effective
Chinese Founders or American founder
Have to be willing to
Bedtime Emoji mark
A look at where the American Founders are willing to go
What's some people to
RBC Canada
UK
Parts of Western Europe
Australia New Zealand
Tool Essex and even Singapore
Are places that people willing to go
EZ moving family to
It takes a lot more commitment
Ask people to go to Jakarta
2 KL or even two different parts of
I'm tryna get along even South America
Lotto America in Alpha
So just by
Easy takes
To move around
NYX heart of American company
To expand globally
And look for the Chinese founders
You can see people
Working in Southeast Asia living in India
Will you be moving to and traveling to Latin America
He started singing all about doing stuff in Africa
So there more places than the Chinese founders
And teams are willing to go to and move to
And not make Gibson advantage
Compete on the globe
So why do you think
We say that Emerging Markets will look
Palomar lights
China than the US
Us mobile internet
Take selfies
We look at a GDP per capita in India Indonesia is roughly about $3,000
Per person per year
Amy look at gdp per capita for Latin America
New Mexico
And Brazil is roughly about 9000 10000
Per person
15 years ago when we start active investing China
GDP per capita roughly about 3000
And that's kind of where
Indonesia and India
Are today
And look at Chinese that GDP per capita today
Is roughly about 9000
Comparable to Mexico and Brazil
So it's very difficult for emerging-market just
Copy a model from us
And try to
Localizer
Because the stage of development is different for different countries
China spend the first 10 years copy models from
From us
We had to do so much more
Customization innovation
To make it work
For emerging markets
Alibaba
Intensity tennis shoes look like
AOL
Icq messenger
And eBay
But over the first 10 years of Chinese in the history both become very different
Companies instead
Because
Chinese market is very different
Users have different needs
So as a result we feel that Chinese consumers
I've trained the Chinese founders
And companies
To be able to deal with other Emerging Markets better as
At the same time
That the Chinese teams in general or less International lights
That's the European and American team
In general Chinese seems grasp of English
And Hall
Global UI
Is quite different
So
The Chinese things also need to add more Talent
That are more globalized to help them to leverage and I'll let you know if I'm trying to ask
To some extent we also feel that the Chinese company should have woken up in the mistakes made by American come
They should be more willing to make
Minority investor
Or controlling Investments
Into local companies
And help them to become local champions
At the end of the day
If American team or Chinese team are more willing to transfer knowledge they know
And Empower local founders
Do more
That's usually the formula
That works out better
You look at that Chinese companies
Such as
Alibaba
They took investment from Yahoo
They work well with some of Yahoo detective such as that Jerry Yang
And
That helped them to be able to give out a desertion and focus on Innovation more in the whole Market
So if the Chinese company's annual can you want to do that
With local champions in Latin America southeast Asia and India
I think I'm going a long run
That will creep bigger outcome
Together
Emerging Markets across the world are starting to look at Chinese company
Instead of Silicon Valley once for
Inspiration so I think this month alone
We have
Nat or heard of
Dependable of India. Hotel for a southeast Asia the maze
White wine for turkey that means you for India the alley pay
Pay for Africans
51 credit for Brazil etcetera
Just look at
That unicorn
Southeast Asia pretty much all of them are kind of modeled after a Chinese
Tech Giants
Seoul Korea is like tencent
Tokopedia and Lazada are like Alibaba gojackets like
Make wine and grab is like the
And travel OKC
Wuxi trip and a lot of these
Chinese companies have actually invested
Andy's coming
He's as well
So do you think
China offers a much better
Model T replica
Sephora for these markets
What do they need to pay attention to
When they try to draw inspiration
That's exactly right let him know story when I was
Investing in China back in 2011-12
B12
Introduced to a company in India called a stop
And back then they were e-coupon clone
Dad trying to find an Express model
And I talked to them about
Call ball
Tmall and JD
The end up picking
Tmall as a model
Even though I thought about would be a better fit for
And then does not become like a flipped car
They also put a small amount of money answer
Through another fund
Both are personal best
If we park
I sense become so the Amazon Indians
Got sold to Walmart
So
As early as 2011 2012 you started already see
Some of the Emerging Markets
The company is coming to
Chinatown to learn about
What the Chinese companies have done in the PC era
Examples you cited
Where some examples of helping the mobile in Terraria
Go to the PC desktop internet error as well as the mobile internet error
Alesia lhasa 8 years
A lot of Thunders from
Southeast Asia
India coming through China
Twice a year
Sometimes more
And what's amazing is that it's not just now the founders are
Comped even a VC's have
The top be seized from both southeast Asia and India
Have come to Beijing and Shanghai
And sometimes they know our portfolio
Even better
That's some of our peers in China
It's amazing how much you willing to study
In the amount of knowledge they have
Annapolis kind of statistic question we asked
Reminds us a lot about what a Chinese visa
15 years ago
Look at what has happened in the US
Tell me she's a bad business of recognizing patterns
How to recognize
And it's just very
Inches into us
That one is happening 10
15 years ago
Is repeating that these other Market
And what do they have pay attention to
I think that everyone should have cycle of innovation and growth
You still through certain places
Initial phases
Just try to copy the model S work elsewhere
In overtime as the local teams gain more experience in
Confidence is to realize that
Some of the problems that are solving are coming
What's happening in different parts of China
Blessing time they are going to be
Material definition
And so when they are different
How do you apply the differences
Any to your advantage
And Leverage What You Know
Wiz crib something that's more localized
If it's a local market
Stop it,
You look at example of Alibaba
If they just copy eBay and charged
50% Commission
Like eBay did it it will never be
The fact that jackpots will need to make it
Free
So that it can track us more selfish than anywhere else we have more Sellers and more SK use
Anywhere else
It's easier for taobao
Will become more popular that you should know
Watch eBay
And
To come up with a local innovation of an hourly pay
Which function as escort service
Guaranteed out of transactions
Safe secure and
Minimizer disputes
Is also not a great way
Localization
Not without the benefit of having credit card
A PayPal
So these are kind of changes that I'm sure the Indian companies in Southeast Asian companies like America
And that's what will make them successful
When they can do that way
Amy Chinese founder sometimes I sense
This hubris that because something worked
In China course it will work
And all these other Emerging Markets but a lot of
X
The infrastructure is not employed like the mobile payment is not in place where the logistics network is not s
Straw and there's like
What type is not like
There's still a lot of
Differences
So I think that's another
Factor that people need to pay attention
Attention to that
These are the
Marcus even though they're developing fast
There a lot of conditions that are not
Place like they were in China
That's a great obligation 15 years ago Lotto American teams when it comes to China are they show a lot of Hughley as well
Sometimes even today we see that happened to
And they just think that whatever works elsewhere
Around the world
Shells work in China 2
In
Unfortunately some of the Chinese founder
Have the same degree
Overconfidence as well
And when you do that and don't show enough respect
What are the differences in local markets
You're in for a rude awakening
So what
Advice
Do you have four
Chinese
So high
Companies are trying to hire for local talent to understand
These markets better
I think they need to start with hiring
Local Chinese with Latinos comedy parlor
Example if you look at
Shopee in Southeast Asia
Forrest and his partner hired was able to recruit Chris
To join them to wrong shopping
And Chris's
Force himself
Move to Southeast Asia after getting his MBA from Stanford
He was born and raised in tianjin
And you went to Southeast Asia
His wife want to live there
In Singapore so they start a business
In Southeast Asia
And
David Livingstone the gaming
Significance of a pencil
Games of Southeast Asia
When they decide to go out to eat, as well they were able to recruit Chris
Between them and Chris someone who had to work at hazard.
Before and even before that moved to Singapore me with some metals
So he's someone who grew up through the Singapore education system have a lot of friends locally
Missing time still remain quite Chinese in
Disconnect
What's happening
In China
So if you can recruit Allen locally
The undersigned for China and the local market
Then they are able to
Figure out whether the similarities and difference
And be able to make adjustments
Accordingly
So having people who know the local market as well
Pressing time have Chinese roots
Is the first
Kind of executive.
The Chinese company should hire in order to Leverage
And over time you see the people who report to Chris
Nanny McPhee
From Southeast Asia the region
It's so
Overtime you have to localize at local team to understand how local
Consumer taste
Are different
Producing time
You continue leverage Lessons Learned From China
You help you to stay ahead of your competition
Anything that's more of cross-cultural
Then cross-disciplinary and know the differences and similarities in people make the right adjustments
Are the team that most likely will succeed
And what about the other types of
Talent say it like Marcus like India there are not a lot of
Chinese
People who have
Is there a long time
Time ago or less
Right so I think for a company
Places like India
Then is easier to see that a lot of talent from
Huawei ZTE Alibaba
Who have operate a business there I'll be happy Chinese company
NW2 coming out with join startup
Start tackling
Those markets
So if you don't have a receipt as with bigger for long-time the next best thing is probably hired Chinese people
Chinese Executives web off radio
Nemo's Marcus
For 5 to 10 years
To help you get started
The overtime abilities
The local team is critical
If you can do that
On top of the Chinese knowledge you have
Your Chisholm
City will be much higher
Have you said that
The companies I've done well in China
Should I expand to
Southeast Asia tour
Or India on their own
Initially probably
Should try the same time by the time they start going to this weekend they would be
Y'all companies there they want to be
The India or the
Southeast Asia at the local version of what you're doing
So be open to partner
After you compete and get a sense of how they look when Cutters to behave
And how strong they are
It is actually makes sense
Exploring kind of Strategic investment
And be able to partner
Is the more you win the partner I think you think I should go to the pie
Bigger as well
There's a lot of
Howard
Founders of very different
Backgrounds
So there a lot of
Cross-border e-commerce
Companies are trying to
How to Leverage
Chinese supply chain to sell to these
Emerging Markets
But people who understands
Supply chain in China tend not to understand local consumers in
Andy's markets and vice versa
You have two people who are very good at each
Co-founders together
Make him be a very
Powerful
Why didn't one of the
Best investments
What's that I made
Probably wish
When I look at which the co-founders came from Eastern Europe
In China
Mac in Canada
Cooking school and then we're trained professionally in California
And I came out to do what way
So you have people from different parts of the world
Go to Martin allergist so they have a common background
In-N-Out the same time they were willing to
Adult at a local team in Shanghai that we played a role in helping us get started and they were able to hire a lot of
Folks from China to help with
Supply chain
So not. Formula
Seems to be the formula we seen other places
Founders with different back on swimming the partner
We just discussed as willing to work together are more likely the Belmonts
Successful
So I guess this one tip for
Perspective
Entrepreneurs is just to step out of your
Comfort zone and make friends
Other backgrounds perspectives
I think it will always
Playoff NBA
Yes
When we lecture or give talks
Still different NBA
Programs weather is in China where you at
We hollinghurst people
From different disciplines to get to know one.
Example was alright you care for you, so it makes sense for someone
Supply chain expert
To work with somebody who's
Confederate consumer-facing
Areas
In the area of enterprise
We also see
Teams do better at when they have a strong sales person
That knows how to get SMB store topper to Knology
+ someone who is very strong
Software with sass
Dubuque development
Occupy the product and Send The Pain points
Of a people in different of vertigo
When you have teams that have different founders with different discipline
Work well together
Because we went to the same
Score what had to work
Professional
How much is skull tattoos Ybor
Chisholm
So I think as investors were also faced with a
Question
Weather to pick the
The Chinese Founders or the local one so for example there's just start two companies do exactly
I'm saying how would you
But that's usually a very tough choice
In areas of
Different categories what is social networking or gaming
E-commerce
It's difficult
To say
Which one is better than the other
We have some success examples
Fun filled camp
Each of these categories
When coming social networking it's easier to generalize and say
The local team will understand local markets better
Do you mean you see someone like
Bytedance
Hotel and the throwing
That came up with tic toc that's done very well International
With a team that's mostly based in China
Musically
Is not a good example
Miss repeat a lot of local teams in us and Europe
With the Prodigal Son
Define biting
In Shanghai with a lar operation to back it up
So
Even in technology where one would think that local team should win
You can see comfort zone
When it comes to e-commerce
Usopp has a job
Tokopedia is doing well competes against shopee
And a lot of gooey Indie style corn
Let's do which one will win out what is Togepi D'oro jockey
So even eaten Commerce where
I've missed supply chain manager from China
Should be helpful
You can still see the local team compete effectively in
So I think very difficult to analyze
Which camera is better
But it comes on to you
Execution and how fast the Thunders of willing to learn
I see father some tokopedia bukalapak
It's been quite a bit of time in Hangzhou
When was invested by Alibaba not always Best Buy information
Different and learning
So I think the key differentiation is not whether it's a local teamwork
Chinese sing
It's really how fast
The teams learn about what they don't know
What are some examples of successful
Zhuhai company
And what do you think was
The key to theirs
I think the
To accompany its original toy company that has done
Well you can probably say it's a highway
Probably asking is amazing
Booty from a telecom equipment
Player 2 com
Consumer-facing headset
And to be able to be able to Global operation
A lot of that so I consider that you and I have bad
Many of them came out of my way in
ZTE as well
And so you see that they are well-trained
And can do things
Increasingly you look at an internet pure Internet space
One has to say that
You know Tokyo Ghoul has done Tokyo All In
Amazing job with Tik-Tok
In the bike dance
This is just
Impressive company.
Expand beyond beyond beyond China
E Commerce space
I think both the shoppie and wish
Have shown that
If you
Have the building to send local markets
As well as being able to have the
The training
You takes in
Chinese apply to understanding
You can build it
Accessible
E-commerce races wow
So I think these are some of the names that people will watch
For for a long time
You stay all have
What it takes for something
Lastly on xiaomi
Then India has become a fast-growing market for xiaomi in the number one
Indiana
UCA Chinese brand
To do well in a country that historically not as friendly or open
Chinese ideas
Is remarkable
Nothing. A lot of credit goes to mono at xiaomi India
What's an amazing job
A building the brand
That touches hearts
Hundreds of millions of
So how do hard that the right
GM
Put a local market in
Paragon
To really localized the way he or she sees
Respect is an art
Not the science
That sell me some stuff to crack the code for India
In terms of
Picking Market
I think we're seeing a lot of activity
In southeast
Asia India Middle East
Watch America in a little bit of Africa
So each of these different markets
It's have different characteristics so like India is a
The huge Market but the middle class
Sizes of
Smaller in
The Artful is very low
And is very competitive so Middle East has a lot
Higher
Arpu
But the population might be a little bit
Smaller so
And so what do you think
When the Chinese Founders try to
To pick a market
Do they need to
To pay attention to
Write different stages
Requires different kind of company
Maple India the best companies from China can do well
Centipede has a maker
Cuz that's the first thing in deep ocean
We need to buy him to get online
Whether they have a lot of money to spend out of it by the phone or not
It takes time to be able to ramp up disposable income level in order to buy more thing
Be on the phone
So it happens in the stage
Voice authorization
Ecommerce Market is
Less competitive
Compared to India
American players on.
So sweet
Chinese company compete against local players
Some Chinese companies anyway
It's interesting that
All about ohms Lazada
Automaster in
Tokopedia
SO3 of the
Top energy, companies that you know these are all
You know Alibaba related
And it just fascinating
To see the Chinese company doing well in Southeast Asia
Now when you look at which markets are Chinese companies go after
I feel that the argument Marcus out there with both GDP per capita is high enough
Are population-based
Is big enough
And that's actually like America
This is why I think the TD did the right thing to acquire 99 in Brazil
Electrical problems growth Roll on America
I look at Brazil
Rio and Sao Paulo
Are two of the top three cities for Uber
Worldwide outside of China
So. America is actually a market
Where not many Americans are are willing to go
Now you see more European trained Executives there
And she have a vintage
Being there
Local players in local shampoo
So I actually think that America is a market.
You don't see a lot of Chinese companies there today
But you will later because it
Capital is high enough
Annette
7000 to 10000 range
US dollars rate
And also
The population size
Is about 600 million +
With Brazil New Mexico
Stop picking habit
So that's the market. I think we were here about Morganford
Right now going to India into Southeast Asia
It's easier and Middle East is easier from from China
Do you see teams doing that to each of these three three regions
May have its own limitations
India local teams in South East Asia
Learning so quickly
Dottie eventage mod adventures
That Chinese team may have is getting less and less
So for the next five years I see Sully do that India
Still the Middle East
What's the most popular place for Chinese tea
But the upside
May not be as high as
You could have been five years ago
That's the opposite of people missing
Is South America
It takes a lot more hours to
Fly there so he's probably more rewarding
It takes a calculation it takes anywhere between 26 to 30 hours
To go from Beijing
To some Paulo
So it is not easy
Shrimp so you favors the team
The wooden to make that happen
And it's why I admired you so much
Will be able to do that
And intense and also invested in new bank
Yes they invest in you back about the amount
And it's the biggest deal that a Chinese company did invest
Penny Latimer
What's up you start to see more China 2
North America initiatives
Happen especially given Square surface is
With us
Is very typical by any chance company goes through you
We talked about this
Chinese Tech Giant
Sp80 by tencent and the baby Giants
TMD.
Hotel May 20th DD
I think we came to the conclusion that bytedance has the highest chance
Becoming
Internet company with
By offering its own
Just by investing
Steal others do you think that still
Host true I think what they've done.
India with hello is very impressive hello is there a vernacular
Short video app
Sono in English for not English
Speakers in India
And has gained a lot of traction
I just want to keep low profile so I won't talk about them too much
But it did what it doing is very impressive
How to give Pedialyte to credit
For being able to
Make acquisition
In Brazil
And there were shots
Rule Regional
Within North America
Have you both companies
You showing that
Chinese company can expand
Young China Beijing
Five football teams they also have a lot of room for
Improvement and growth
By becoming more
Internationalize
And look alikes
In the queue
I think in general
The tenant seems to have enough skill set
Drive
An experience to internationally while they rely
Is the understanding
Of the local
Marcus and
Hey Stan
Japan is a market we haven't talked about very much
Pod Hotel
In Tik-Tok
Are doing well
In Japan
So over time
Has there more Innovation coming of China
Stephen e Marcus
That's more developed
Like Europe
And that you find there's opportunity
I guess to finish off ggv active
Invest
Chinese Founders targeting overseas
These markets as well as
Local Founders in emerging-market
So
If you are entrepreneur are you have friends while I'm working on this category
We're always open
Our conversations
To like
Sarms
Prodigy
Faces in the sky
Now we have office
In San Francisco
Silicon Valley
Beijing
Shanghai
And soon early next year in Singapore
S5 offices
T-Mobile assets
Office in
India or New York
Or Latin America at some point
You will see that would definitely have teams
Look at all these
Marcos
For us we have investment pieces around for packets
That's Commerce and new retail
Internet services
Shooting social networking
In
Handyman services
Hotel services
Spec transportation
And so forth
Their buckets Enterprise
1/4 bucket is steep Tech Frontier Tech
So any of these four buckets
We rock
Fidelity Investments
Across these regions
We see similarities
An information Arbitrage
And now the sharing not our team
So you have any interest feel free to contact Sarah or myself on WeChat
And we talked about how
Founders should try to meet other people of different backgrounds and
One way of doing that is
To join our night
Sex meetups
Across
Different parts of the world
So you can join the communities at 96.2 gvtc.com
Black community and all of our events and meetups
Will be post
Stood there and we're looking to host a lot more in
Mother parts
What's the world like southeast Asia and
Thank you for listening
Thank you
Airline flight 798
Stop listening
M996
Ggv capital is a multi-stage venture capital firm based in Silicon Valley Shanghai and Beijing
Country with leading technology entrepreneurs for the past 18 years from seed to pre IPO
With 6.2 billion dollars in capital under management across 13 funds ggv invests in consumer
New retail social Digital internet Enterprise cloud and Frontier Tech
GTB has invested over 290 companies with more than 45 companies valued at over a billing.
Dollars
Formula companies include Airbnb Alibaba
C trip
Didi chuxing demo hashicorp hellobike cows keep slat
Square
Hotel wish
Soundtrue white white and others find out more at Gigi vici.com we also highly recommend
Joining our listeners WeChat group as lot China where we regular share insights events and job opportunities
Bass related to talk and try to join these groups at 9 96.3 tvc.com
Watch community
You have any feedback on this podcast or would like to recommend the gas please email us I-96
IGG bc.com